<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 168, folios 86-87</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 168, folios 86-87.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to Joanna Baillee</title>
          <date when="1827">[early October 1827]</date>
          <note type="place">[Brussels]</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 168, folios 86-87</note>
          <note type="recipient">Joanna Baillee</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_168_folios_86-87.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>My dear Mrs Joanna, Mama is at present much the same as usual, but it appears to me that her general state of health is much more comfortable than when she was at this place last year.</p>
      <p>Since Miss Montgomery joined us at Ouchy she has gone through a great deal of suffering and illness indeed which I believe are partly the effects of travelling, and I see no difference whatever in her health from what it was when I last saw her in England. Mrs Henry Siddons and her youngest daughter Elizabeth Siddons who also joined us while we were at Ouchy at the same time with Miss Montgomery was attacked with a very severe illness at Franckfort on the Mein, which detained us some time longer in that town than Mama</p>
      <p>had expected and from the effects of which I do not think that she has ever quite recovered, her daughter Elizabeth who came abroad in a very bad state of health has been exceedingly benefited indeed by her tour, Miss Louisa Chaloner continues to be in comparison to what she was when she left England in very good health indeed.--</p>
      <p>We left Genoa towards the middle of June, we arrived at Turin in a day or two; there I saw all sorts of punch and tumblers and every thing of the sort and I used sometimes to be very much amused in looking at them, I was on the whole pleased with Turin and particularly with the fine view of the Alps seen from thence on a clear day. Towards the end of June we left Turin, crossed Mont Cenis and arrived at Secheron, which is very near Geneva, in a few days. I was not so much struck with the scenery of Mont Cenis as I was with that of the Simplon. We only remained</p>
      <p>at Secheron for two or three days and while Miss Stamp and myself remained at Ouchy. Mama, Miss L Chaloner and also Mr Thomas Noel, who had joined us a few days before we left Genoa made a little excursion up the valley of Chamouny where they were very much delighted with the views they enjoyed of Mont Blanc and the glaciers. We then remained some days after Mama's return at Ouchy and quitted it about the middle of July, we next went through Neuchatel [accent over the "a"] and Berne to Kussnacht [umlaut over the "u"] on the Lake of Lucerne, there Mama left Miss Stamp and myself and went with her friends on a tour of 12 days mont the mountains that she might see the falls of the Aar, the Pont du Diable and some other places which completely answered and even surpassed her expectations. We then went to Zurich and Schaffhausen where we were all disappointed in the falls of the Rhine, as they were</p>
      <p>neither so high nor so broad as we had expected. We went through Stuttgard which I liked better than any other German town I have yet seen, to Franckfort on the Mein where we found the fair going on, but I was very much disappointed in it indeed, it was neither so gay nor so extensive as I had expected. At Franckfort Mr Thomas Noel left us, and pursued his journey to London alone. We left Franckfort toward the end of September and went by the bank of the Rhine to Cologne and from thence we have come by Aix la Chapelle to Brussels where we now are. We shall probably be in England in about a fortnight.</p>
      <p>Your affectionate A A Byron.</p>
      <p>[integral address panel written in a different hand, with postmark stamps and wax seal:</p>
      <p>Angleterre Miss Joanna Baillee Hampstead London]</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
