<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="5">CHAPTER V
PREJUDICES WHICH HAVE RETARDED THE PROGRESS OF GEOLOGY
Prepossessions in regard to the duration of past time—Prejudices arising from our
peculiar position as inhabitants of the land—Of those occasioned by our not
seeing subterranean changes now in progress—All these causes combine to make
the former course of Nature appear different from the present—Objections to
the doctrine, that causes similar in kind and energy to those now acting, have
produced the former changes of the earth's surface, considered.
If we reflect on the history of the progress of geology, as explained
in the preceding chapters, we perceive that there have been great fluctuations
62
of opinion respecting the nature of the causes to which all
former changes of the earth's surface are referable. The first observers
conceived the monuments which the geologist endeavors to decipher
to relate to an original state of the earth, or to a period when there
were causes in activity, distinct, in kind and degree, from those now
constituting the economy of nature. These views were gradually modified,
and some of them entirely abandoned, in proportion as observations
were multiplied, and the signs of former mutations more skilfully
interpreted. Many appearances, which had for a long time been regarded
as indicating mysterious and extraordinary agency, were finally
recognized as the necessary result of the laws now governing the material
world; and the discovery of this unlooked-for conformity has at
length induced some philosophers to infer, that, during the ages contemplated
in geology, there has never been any interruption to the agency
of the same uniform laws of change. The same assemblage of general
causes, they conceive, may have been sufficient to produce, by their
various combinations, the endless diversity of effects, of which the shell
of the earth has preserved the memorials; and, consistently with these
principles, the recurrence of analogous changes is expected by them in
time to come.
Whether we coincide or not in this doctrine, we must admit that the
gradual progress of opinion concerning the succession of phenomena in
very remote eras, resembles, in a singular manner, that which has accompanied
the growing intelligence of every people, in regard to the
economy of nature in their own times. In an early state of advancement,
when a great number of natural appearances are unintelligible,
an eclipse, an earthquake, a flood, or the approach of a comet, with
many other occurrences afterwards found to belong to the regular
course of events, are regarded as prodigies. The same delusion prevails
as to moral phenomena, and many of these are ascribed to the
intervention of demons, ghosts, witches, and other immaterial and
supernatural agents. By degrees, many of the enigmas of the moral
and physical world are explained, and, instead of being due to extrinsic
and irregular causes, they are found to depend on fixed and invariable
laws. The philosopher at last becomes convinced of the undeviating
uniformity of secondary causes; and, guided by his faith in this principle,
he determines the probability of accounts transmitted to him
of former occurrences, and often rejects the fabulous tales of former times,
on the ground of their being irreconcilable with the experience of more
enlightened ages.
Prepossessions in regard to the duration of past time.—As a belief in
the want of conformity in the causes by which the earth's crust has
been modified in ancient and modern periods was, for a long time, universally
prevalent, and that, too, amongst men who were convinced that
the order of nature had been uniform for the last several thousand
years, every circumstance which could have influenced their minds and
given an undue bias to their opinions deserves particular attention.63
Now the reader may easily satisfy himself, that, however undeviating
the course of nature may have been from the earliest epochs, it was
impossible for the first cultivators of geology to come to such a conclusion,
so long as they were under a delusion as to the age of the world,
and the date of the first creation of animate beings. However fantastical
some theories of the sixteenth century may now appear to us,—however
unworthy of men of great talent and sound judgment,—we
may rest assured that, if the same misconception now prevailed in regard
to the memorials of human transactions, it would give rise to a
similar train of absurdities. Let us imagine, for example, that Champollion,
and the French and Tuscan literati lately engaged in exploring the
antiquities of Egypt, had visited that country with a firm belief that the
banks of the Nile were never peopled by the human race before the beginning
of the nineteenth century, and that their faith in this dogma was
as difficult to shake as the opinion of our ancestors that the earth was
never the abode of living beings until the creation of the present continents,
and of the species now existing,—it is easy to perceive what
extravagant systems they would frame, while under the influence of this
delusion, to account for the monuments discovered in Egypt. The
sight of the pyramids, obelisks, colossal statues, and ruined temples,
would fill them with such astonishment, that for a time they would be
as men spell-bound—wholly incapable of reasoning with sobriety. They
might incline at first to refer the construction of such stupendous
works to some superhuman powers of a primeval world. A system
might be invented resembling that so gravely advanced by Manetho,
who relates that a dynasty of gods originally ruled in Egypt, of whom
Vulcan, the first monarch, reigned nine thousand years; after whom
came Hercules and other demigods, who were at last succeeded by
human kings.
When some fanciful speculations of this kind had amused their imaginations
for a time, some vast repository of mummies would be discovered,
and would immediately undeceive those antiquaries who enjoyed
an opportunity of personally examining them; but the prejudices
of others at a distance, who were not eye-witnesses of the whole phenomena,
would not be so easily overcome. The concurrent report of
many travellers would, indeed, render it necessary for them to accommodate
ancient theories to some of the new facts, and much wit and
ingenuity would be required to modify and defend their old positions.
Each new invention would violate a greater number of known analogies;
for if a theory be required to embrace some false principle, it becomes
more visionary in proportion as facts are multiplied, as would be the
case if geometers were now required to form an astronomical system on
the assumption of the immobility of the earth.
Amongst other fanciful conjectures concerning the history of Egypt,
we may suppose some of the following to be started. "As the banks
of the Nile have been so recently colonized for the first time, the curious
substances called mummies could never in reality have belonged to64
men. They may have been generated by some plastic virtue residing
in the interior of the earth, or they may be abortions of Nature produced
by her incipient efforts in the work of creation. For if deformed
beings are sometimes born even now, when the scheme of the universe
is fully developed, many more may have been 'sent before their time,
scarce half made up,' when the planet itself was in the embryo state.
But if these notions appear to derogate from the perfection of the
Divine attributes, and if these mummies be in all their parts true representations
of the human form, may we not refer them to the future
rather than the past?—May we not be looking into the womb of Nature,
and not her grave? May not these images be like the shades of the
unborn in Virgil's Elysium—the archetypes of men not yet called into
existence?"
These speculations, if advocated by eloquent writers, would not fail
to attract many zealous votaries, for they would relieve men from the
painful necessity of renouncing preconceived opinions. Incredible as
such skepticism may appear, it has been rivalled by many systems of
the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, and among others by that of
the learned Falloppio, who regarded the tusks of fossil elephants as
earthy concretions, and the pottery or fragments of vases in the Monte
Testaceo, near Rome, as works of nature, and not of art. But when
one generation had passed away, and another, not compromised to the
support of antiquated dogmas, had succeeded, they would review the
evidence afforded by mummies more impartially, and would no longer
controvert the preliminary question, that human beings had lived in
Egypt before the nineteenth century: so that when a hundred years perhaps
had been lost, the industry and talents of the philosopher would
be at last directed to the elucidation of points of real historical importance.
But the above arguments are aimed against one only of many prejudices
with which the earlier geologists had to contend. Even when
they conceded that the earth had been peopled with animate beings at
an earlier period than was at first supposed, they had no conception that
the quantity of time bore so great a proportion to the historical era as
is now generally conceded. How fatal every error as to the quantity of
time must prove to the introduction of rational views concerning the
state of things in former ages, may be conceived by supposing the annals
of the civil and military transactions of a great nation to be perused
under the impression that they occurred in a period of one hundred instead
of two thousand years. Such a portion of history would immediately
assume the air of a romance; the events would seem devoid of
credibility, and inconsistent with the present course of human affairs.
A crowd of incidents would follow each other in thick succession. Armies
and fleets would appear to be assembled only to be destroyed, and
cities built merely to fall in ruins. There would be the most violent
transitions from foreign or intestine war to periods of profound peace,
and the works effected during the years of disorder or tranquillity would
appear alike superhuman in magnitude.65
He who should study the monuments of the natural world under the
influence of a similar infatuation, must draw a no less exaggerated picture
of the energy and violence of causes, and must experience the
same insurmountable difficulty in reconciling the former and present
state of nature. If we could behold in one view all the volcanic cones
thrown up in Iceland, Italy, Sicily, and other parts of Europe, during
the last five thousand years, and could see the lavas which have flowed
during the same period; the dislocations, subsidences, and elevations
caused during earthquakes; the lands added to various deltas, or devoured
by the sea, together with the effects of devastation by floods,
and imagine that all these events had happened in one year, we must
form most exalted ideas of the activity of the agents, and the suddenness
of the revolutions. Were an equal amount of change to pass before
our eyes in the next year, could we avoid the conclusion that some
great crisis of nature was at hand? If geologists, therefore, have misinterpreted
the signs of a succession of events, so as to conclude that
centuries were implied where the characters imported thousands of
years, and thousands of years where the language of Nature signified
millions, they could not, if they reasoned logically from such false premises,
come to any other conclusion than that the system of the natural
world had undergone a complete revolution.
We should be warranted in ascribing the erection of the great pyramid
to superhuman power, if we were convinced that it was raised in
one day; and if we imagine, in the same manner, a continent or mountain-chain
to have been elevated during an equally small fraction of the
time which was really occupied in upheaving it, we might then be
justified in inferring, that the subterranean movements were once far
more energetic than in our own times. We know that during one
earthquake the coast of Chili may be raised for a hundred miles to the
average height of about three feet. A repetition of two thousand
shocks, of equal violence, might produce a mountain-chain one hundred
miles long, and six thousand feet high. Now, should one or two
only of these convulsions happen in a century, it would be consistent
with the order of events experienced by the Chilians from the earliest
times; but if the whole of them were to occur in the next hundred
years, the entire district must be depopulated, scarcely any animals or
plants could survive, and the surface would be one confused heap of
ruin and desolation.
One consequence of undervaluing greatly the quantity of past time,
is the apparent coincidence which it occasions of events necessarily disconnected,
or which are so unusual, that it would be inconsistent with
all calculation of chances to suppose them to happen at one and the
same time. When the unlooked-for association of such rare phenomena
is witnessed in the present course of nature, it scarcely ever fails to
excite a suspicion of the preternatural in those minds which are not
firmly convinced of the uniform agency of secondary causes;—as if the
death of some individual in whose fate they are interested happens to66
be accompanied by the appearance of a luminous meteor, or a comet, or
the shock of an earthquake. It would be only necessary to multiply
such coincidences indefinitely, and the mind of every philosopher would
be disturbed. Now it would be difficult to exaggerate the number of
physical events, many of them most rare and unconnected in their nature,
which were imagined by the Woodwardian hypothesis to have
happened in the course of a few months; and numerous other examples
might be found of popular geological theories, which require us to imagine
that a long succession of events happened in a brief and almost
momentary period.
Another liability to error, very nearly allied to the former, arises from
the frequent contact of geological monuments referring to very distant
periods of time. We often behold, at one glance, the effects of causes
which have acted at times incalculably remote, and yet there may be no
striking circumstances to mark the occurrence of a great chasm in the
chronological series of Nature's archives. In the vast interval of time
which may really have elapsed between the results of operations thus
compared, the physical condition of the earth may, by slow and insensible
modifications, have become entirely altered; one or more races of
organic beings may have passed away, and yet have left behind, in the
particular region under contemplation, no trace of their existence.
To a mind unconscious of these intermediate events, the passage from
one state of things to another must appear so violent, that the idea of
revolutions in the system inevitably suggests itself. The imagination is
as much perplexed by the deception, as it might be if two distant points
in space were suddenly brought into immediate proximity. Let us
suppose, for a moment, that a philosopher should lie down to sleep in
some arctic wilderness, and then be transferred by a power, such as we
read of in tales of enchantment, to a valley in a tropical country, where,
on awaking, he might find himself surrounded by birds of brilliant plumage,
and all the luxuriance of animal and vegetable forms of which
Nature is so prodigal in those regions. The most reasonable supposition,
perhaps, which he could make, if by the necromancer's art he were
placed in such a situation, would be, that he was dreaming; and if a
geologist form theories under a similar delusion, we cannot expect him
to preserve more consistency in his speculations than in the train of ideas
in an ordinary dream.
It may afford, perhaps, a lively illustration of the principle here insisted
upon, if I recall to the reader's recollection the legend of the Seven
Sleepers. The scene of that popular fable was placed in the two centuries
which elapsed between the reign of the emperor Decius and the
death of Theodosius the younger. In that interval of time (between
the years 249 and 450 of our era) the union of the Roman Empire had
been dissolved, and some of its fairest provinces overrun by the barbarians
of the north. The seat of government had passed from Rome to
Constantinople, and the throne from a pagan persecutor to a succession
of Christian and orthodox princes. The genius of the empire had been67
humbled in the dust, and the altars of Diana and Hercules were on the
point of being transferred to Catholic saints and martyrs. The legend
relates, "that when Decius was still persecuting the Christians, seven
noble youths of Ephesus concealed themselves in a spacious cavern in
the side of an adjacent mountain, where they were doomed to perish
by the tyrant, who gave orders that the entrance should be firmly secured
with a pile of huge stones. They immediately fell into a deep
slumber, which was miraculously prolonged, without injuring the powers
of life, during a period of 187 years. At the end of that time the
slaves of Adolius, to whom the inheritance of the mountain had descended,
removed the stones to supply materials for some rustic edifice: the
light of the sun darted into the cavern, and the Seven Sleepers were
permitted to awake. After a slumber, as they thought, of a few hours,
they were pressed by the calls of hunger, and resolved that Jamblichus,
one of their number, should secretly return to the city to purchase
bread for the use of his companions. The youth could no longer
recognize the once familiar aspect of his native country, and his surprise
was increased by the appearance of a large cross triumphantly erected
over the principal gate of Ephesus. His singular dress and obsolete
language confounded the baker, to whom he offered an ancient medal
of Decius as the current coin of the empire; and Jamblichus, on the
suspicion of a secret treasure, was dragged before the judge. Their
mutual inquiries produced the amazing discovery, that two centuries
were almost elapsed since Jamblichus and his friends had escaped from
the rage of a pagan tyrant."123
This legend was received as authentic throughout the Christian world
before the end of the sixth century, and was afterwards introduced by
Mahomet as a divine revelation into the Koran, and from hence was
adopted and adorned by all the nations from Bengal to Africa who professed
the Mahometan faith. Some vestiges even of a similar tradition
have been discovered in Scandinavia. "This easy and universal belief,"
observes the philosophical historian of the Decline and Fall, "so expressive
of the sense of mankind, may be ascribed to the genuine merit of
the fable itself. We imperceptibly advance from youth to age, without
observing the gradual, but incessant, change of human affairs; and even,
in our larger experience of history, the imagination is accustomed, by a
perpetual series of causes and effects, to unite the most distant revolutions.
But if the interval between two memorable eras could be instantly
annihilated; if it were possible, after a momentary slumber of
two hundred years, to display the new world to the eyes of a spectator
who still retained a lively and recent impression of the old, his surprise
and his reflections would furnish the pleasing subject of a philosophical
romance."124
Prejudices arising from our peculiar position as inhabitants of the
land.—The sources of prejudice hitherto considered may be deemed
68peculiar for the most part to the infancy of the science, but others are
common to the first cultivators of geology and to ourselves, and are all
singularly calculated to produce the same deception, and to strengthen
our belief that the course of nature in the earlier ages differed widely
from that now established. Although these circumstances cannot be
fully explained without assuming some things as proved, which it will
be the object of another part of this work to demonstrate, it may be
well to allude to them briefly in this place.
The first and greatest difficulty, then, consists in an habitual unconsciousness
that our position as observers is essentially unfavorable, when
we endeavor to estimate the nature and magnitude of the changes now
in progress. In consequence of our inattention to this subject, we
are liable to serious mistakes in contrasting the present with former
states of the globe. As dwellers on the land, we inhabit about a fourth
part of the surface; and that portion is almost exclusively a theatre of
decay, and not of reproduction. We know, indeed, that new deposits
are annually formed in seas and lakes, and that every year some new
igneous rocks are produced in the bowels of the earth, but we cannot
watch the progress of their formation; and as they are only present to
our minds by the aid of reflection, it requires an effort both of the reason
and the imagination to appreciate duly their importance. It is, therefore,
not surprising that we estimate very imperfectly the result of operations
thus invisible to us; and that, when analogous results of former
epochs are presented to our inspection, we cannot immediately recognize
the analogy. He who has observed the quarrying of stone from a
rock, and has seen it shipped for some distant port, and then endeavors
to conceive what kind of edifice will be raised by the materials, is in the
same predicament as a geologist, who, while he is confined to the land,
sees the decomposition of rocks, and the transportation of matter by
rivers to the sea, and then endeavors to picture to himself the new strata
which Nature is building beneath the waters.
Prejudices arising from our not seeing subterranean changes.—Nor is
his position less unfavorable when, beholding a volcanic eruption, he
tries to conceive what changes the column of lava has produced, in its
passage upwards, on the intersected strata; or what form the melted
matter may assume at great depths on cooling; or what may be the extent
of the subterranean rivers and reservoirs of liquid matter far beneath
the surface. It should, therefore, be remembered, that the task
imposed on those who study the earth's history requires no ordinary
share of discretion; for we are precluded from collating the corresponding
parts of the system of things as it exists now, and as it existed at
former periods. If we were inhabitants of another element—if the great
ocean were our domain, instead of the narrow limits of the land, our
difficulties would be considerably lessened; while, on the other hand,
there can be little doubt, although the reader may, perhaps, smile at the
bare suggestion of such an idea, that an amphibious being, who should
possess our faculties, would still more easily arrive at sound theoretical69
opinions in geology, since he might behold, on the one hand, the decomposition
of rocks in the atmosphere, or the transportation of matter by
running water; and, on the other, examine the deposition of sediment
in the sea, and the imbedding of animal and vegetable remains in new
strata. He might ascertain, by direct observation, the action of a mountain
torrent, as well as of a marine current; might compare the products
of volcanoes poured out upon the land with those ejected beneath the
waters; and might mark, on the one hand, the growth of the forest,
and, on the other, that of the coral reef. Yet, even with these advantages,
he would be liable to fall into the greatest errors, when endeavoring
to reason on rocks of subterranean origin. He would seek in vain,
within the sphere of his observation, for any direct analogy to the process
of their formation, and would therefore be in danger of attributing
them, wherever they are upraised to view, to some "primeval state of
nature."
But if we may be allowed so far to indulge the imagination, as to
suppose a being entirely confined to the nether world—some "dusky
melancholy sprite," like Umbriel, who could "flit on sooty pinions to
the central earth," but who was never permitted to "sully the fair face
of light," and emerge into the regions of water and of air; and if this
being should busy himself in investigating the structure of the globe, he
might frame theories the exact converse of those usually adopted by
human philosophers. He might infer that the stratified rocks, containing
shells and other organic remains, were the oldest of created things,
belonging to some original and nascent state of the planet. "Of these
masses," he might say, "whether they consist of loose incoherent sand,
soft clay, or solid stone, none have been formed in modern times. Every
year some part of them are broken and shattered by earthquakes, or
melted by volcanic fire; and when they cool down slowly from a state
of fusion, they assume a new and more crystalline form, no longer exhibiting
that stratified disposition and those curious impressions and fantastic
markings, by which they were previously characterized. This
process cannot have been carried on for an indefinite time, for in that
case all the stratified rocks would long ere this have been fused and
crystallized. It is therefore probable that the whole planet once consisted
of these mysterious and curiously bedded formations at a time
when the volcanic fire had not yet been brought into activity. Since
that period there seems to have been a gradual development of heat;
and this augmentation we may expect to continue till the whole globe
shall be in a state of fluidity and incandescence."
Such might be the system of the Gnome at the very time that the
followers of Leibnitz, reasoning on what they saw on the outer surface,
might be teaching the opposite doctrine of gradual refrigeration, and
averring that the earth had begun its career as a fiery comet, and might
be destined hereafter to become a frozen mass. The tenets of the
schools of the nether and of the upper world would be directly opposed
to each other, for both would partake of the prejudices inevitably re70sulting
from the continual contemplation of one class of phenomena to
the exclusion of another. Man observes the annual decomposition of
crystalline and igneous rocks, and may sometimes see their conversion
into stratified deposits; but he cannot witness the reconversion of the
sedimentary into the crystalline by subterranean fire. He is in the habit
of regarding all the sedimentary rocks as more recent than the unstratified,
for the same reason that we may suppose him to fall into the opposite
error if he saw the origin of the igneous class only.
It was not an impossible contingency, that astronomers might have
been placed at some period in a situation much resembling that in which
the geologist seems to stand at present. If the Italians, for example, in
the early part of the twelfth century, had discovered at Amalfi, instead
of the pandects of Justinian, some ancient manuscripts filled with astronomical
observations relating to a period of three thousand years,
and made by some ancient geometers who possessed optical instruments
as perfect as any in modern Europe, they would probably, on consulting
these memorials, have come to a conclusion that there had been a
great revolution in the solar and sidereal systems. "Many primary and
secondary planets," they might say, "are enumerated in these tables,
which exist no longer. Their positions are assigned with such precision
that we may assure ourselves that there is nothing in their place at present
but the blue ether. Where one star is visible to us, these documents
represent several thousands. Some of those which are now
single consisted then of two separate bodies, often distinguished by different
colors, and revolving periodically round a common centre of gravity.
There is nothing analogous to them in the universe at present;
for they were neither fixed stars nor planets, but seem to have stood in
the mutual relation of sun and planet to each other. We must conclude,
therefore, that there has occurred, at no distant period, a tremendous
catastrophe, whereby thousands of worlds have been annihilated
at once, and some heavenly bodies absorbed into the substance of
others."
When such doctrines had prevailed for ages, the discovery of some
of the worlds, supposed to have been lost (the satellites of Jupiter, for
example), by aid of the first rude telescope invented after the revival
of science, would not dissipate the delusion, for the whole burden of
proof would now be thrown on those who insisted on the stability of
the system from a remote period, and these philosophers would be required
to demonstrate the existence of all the worlds said to have been
annihilated.
Such popular prejudices would be most unfavorable to the advancement
of astronomy; for, instead of persevering in the attempt to improve
their instruments, and laboriously to make and record observations,
the greater number would despair of verifying the continued
existence of the heavenly bodies not visible to the naked eye. Instead
of confessing the extent of their ignorance, and striving to remove it by
bringing to light new facts, they would indulge in the more easy and71
indolent employment of framing imaginary theories concerning catastrophes
and mighty revolutions in the system of the universe.
For more than two centuries the shelly strata of the Subapennine hills
afforded matter of speculation to the early geologists of Italy, and few
of them had any suspicion that similar deposits were then forming in
the neighboring sea. They were as unconscious of the continued action
of causes still producing similar effects, as the astronomers, in the case
above supposed, of the existence of certain heavenly bodies still giving
and reflecting light, and performing their movements as of old. Some
imagined that the strata, so rich in organic remains, instead of being
due to secondary agents, had been so created in the beginning of things
by the fiat of the Almighty. Others, as we have seen, ascribed the
imbedded fossil bodies to some plastic power which resided in the earth
in the early ages of the world. In what manner were these dogmas at
length exploded? The fossil relics were carefully compared with their
living analogues, and all doubts as to their organic origin were eventually
dispelled. So, also, in regard to the nature of the containing
beds of mud, sand, and limestone: those parts of the bottom of the sea
were examined where shells are now becoming annually entombed in
new deposits. Donati explored the bed of the Adriatic, and found the
closest resemblance between the strata there forming, and those which
constituted hills above a thousand feet high in various parts of the
Italian peninsula. He ascertained by dredging that living testacea
were there grouped together in precisely the same manner as were
their fossil analogues in the inland strata; and while some of the recent
shells of the Adriatic were becoming incrusted with calcareous rock, he
observed that others had been newly buried in sand and clay, precisely
as fossil shells occur in the Subapennine hills. This discovery of the
identity of modern and ancient submarine operations was not made
without the aid of artificial instruments, which, like the telescope,
brought phenomena into view not otherwise within the sphere of human
observation.
In like manner, the volcanic rocks of the Vicentin had been studied
in the beginning of the last century; but no geologist suspected, before
the time of Arduino, that these were composed of ancient submarine lavas.
During many years of controversy, the popular opinion inclined to a belief
that basalt and rocks of the same class had been precipitated from a
chaotic fluid, or an ocean which rose at successive periods over the continents,
charged with the component elements of the rocks in question.
Few will now dispute that it would have been difficult to invent a theory
more distant from the truth; yet we must cease to wonder that it gained
so many proselytes, when we remember that its claims to probability arose
partly from the very circumstance of its confirming the assumed want of
analogy between geological causes and those now in action. By what train
of investigations were geologists induced at length to reject these views,
and to assent to the igneous origin of the trappean formations? By an72
examination of volcanoes now active, and by comparing their structure
and the composition of their lavas with the ancient trap-rocks.
The establishment, from time to time, of numerous points of identification,
drew at length from geologists a reluctant admission, that there was
more correspondence between the condition of the globe at remote eras
and now, and more uniformity in the laws which have regulated the
changes of its surface, than they at first imagined. If, in this state of the
science, they still despaired of reconciling every class of geological phenomena
to the operations of ordinary causes, even by straining analogy to
the utmost limits of credibility, we might have expected, at least, that the
balance of probability would now have been presumed to incline towards
the close analogy of the ancient and modern causes. But, after repeated
experience of the failure of attempts to speculate on geological monuments,
as belonging to a distinct order of things, new sects continued to persevere
in the principles adopted by their predecessors. They still began, as
each new problem presented itself, whether relating to the animate or inanimate
world, to assume an original and dissimilar order of nature; and
when at length they approximated, or entirely came round to an opposite
opinion, it was always with the feeling, that they were conceding what they
had been justified à priori in deeming improbable. In a word, the same
men who, as natural philosophers, would have been most incredulous respecting
any extraordinary deviations from the known course of nature, if
reported to have happened in their own time, were equally disposed, as geologists,
to expect the proofs of such deviations at every period of the past.
I shall proceed in the following chapters to enumerate some of the principal
difficulties still opposed to the theory of the uniform nature and energy
of the causes which have worked successive changes in the crust of the
earth, and in the condition of its living inhabitants. The discussion of so
important a question on the present occasion may appear premature, but
it is one which naturally arises out of a review of the former history of
the science. It is, of course, impossible to enter into such speculative
topics, without occasionally carrying the novice beyond his depth, and
appealing to facts and conclusions with which he will be unacquainted,
until he has studied some elementary work on geology, but it may be
useful to excite his curiosity, and lead him to study such works by calling
his attention at once to some of the principal points of controversy.125
73
</div></body></text></TEI>