<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Reflections on the Decline of Science in England</title><author>Babbage, Charles (1791-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>B. Fellowes</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="15">
      SECTION 8. OF THE COPLEY MEDALS.
    

      An important distinction exists between scientific communications, which
      seems to have escaped the notice of the Councils of the Royal Society.
      They may contain discoveries of new principles,—of laws of nature
      hitherto unobserved; or they may consist of a register of observations of
      known phenomena, made under new circumstances, or in new and peculiar
      situations on the face of our planet. Both these species of additions to
      our knowledge are important; but their value and their rarity are very
      different in degree. To make and to repeat observations, even with those
      trifling alterations, which it is the fashion in our country (in the
      present day) to dignify with the name of discoveries, requires merely
      inflexible candour in recording precisely the facts which nature has
      presented, and a power of fixing the attention on the instruments
      employed, or phenomena examined,—a talent, which can be much
      improved by proper Instruction, and which is possessed by most persons of
      tolerable abilities and education.* To discover new principles, and to
      detect the undiscovered laws by which nature operates, is another and a
      higher task, and requires intellectual qualifications of a very different
      order: the labour of the one is like that of the computer of an almanac;
      the inquiries of the other resemble more the researches of the
      accomplished analyst, who has invented the formula: by which those
      computations are performed.
    

      [*That the use even of the large astronomical instruments in a national
      observatory, does not require any very profound acquirements, is not an
      opinion which I should have put forth without authority. The
      Astronomer-Royal ought to be the best judge.
    

      On the minutes of the Council of the Royal Society, for April 6, 1826,
      with reference to the Assistants necessary for the two mural circles, we
      find a letter from Mr. Pond on the subject, from which the following
      passage is extracted:
    

      "But to carry on such investigations, I want indefatigable, hard-working,
      and above all, obedient drudges (for so I must call them, although they
      are drudges of a superior order), men who will be contented to pass half
      their day in using their hands and eyes in the mechanical act of
      observing, and the remainder of it in the dull process of calculation."]
    

      Such being the distinction between the merits of these inquiries, some
      difference ought to exist in the nature of any rewards that may be
      proposed for their encouragement. The Royal Society have never marked this
      difference, and consequently those honorary medals which are given to
      observations, gain a value which is due to those that are given for
      discoveries; whilst these latter are diminished in their estimation by
      such an association.
    

      I have stated this distinction, because I think it a just one; but the
      public would have little cause of complaint if this were the only ground
      of objection to the mode of appropriating the Society's medals. The first
      objection to be noticed, is the indistinct manner in which the object for
      which the medals are awarded is sometimes specified. A medal is given to
      A. B. "for his various papers."
    

      There are cases, few perhaps in number, where such a reason may be
      admissible; but it is impossible not to perceive the weakness of those who
      judge these matters legibly written in the phrase, "and for his various
      other communications," which comes in as the frequent tail-piece to these
      awards. With a diffidence in their own powers, which might be more admired
      if it were more frequently expressed, the Council think to escape through
      this loop-hole, should the propriety of their judgment on the main point
      be called in question. Thus, even the discovery which made chemistry a
      science, has attached to it in their award this feeble appendage.
    

      It has been objected to the Royal Society, that their medals have been too
      much confined to a certain set. When the Royal medals were added to their
      patronage, the past distribution of the Copley medals, furnished grounds
      to some of the journals to predict the future possessors of the new ones.
      I shall, doubtless, be told that the Council of the Royal Society are
      persons of such high feeling, that it is impossible to suppose their
      decision could be influenced by any personal motives. As I may not have
      had sufficient opportunities, during the short time I was a member of that
      Council, to enable me to form a fair estimate, I shall avail myself of the
      judgment of one, from whom no one will be inclined to appeal, who knew it
      long and intimately, and who expressed his opinion deliberately and
      solemnly.
    

      The late Dr. Wollaston attached, as a condition to be observed in the
      distribution of the interest of his munificent gift of 2,000L. to the
      Royal Society, the following clause:—"And I hereby empower the said
      President, Council, and Fellows, after my decease, in furtherance of the
      above declared objects of the trust, to apply the said dividends to aid or
      reward any individual or individuals of any country, SAVING ONLY THAT NO
      PERSON BEING A MEMBER OF THE COUNCIL FOR THE TIME BEING, SHALL RECEIVE OR
      PARTAKE OF SUCH REWARD."
    

      Another improvement which might be suggested, is, that it is generally
      inexpedient to vote a medal until the paper which contains the discovery
      is at least read to the Society; perhaps even it might not be quite
      unreasonable to wish that it should have been printed, and consequently
      have been perused by some few of those who have to decide on its merits.
      These trifles have not always been attended to; and even so lately as the
      last year, they escaped the notice of the President and his Council. The
      Society was, however, indebted to the good sense of Mr. Faraday, who
      declined the proffered medal; and thus relieved us from one additional
      charge of precipitancy. [When this hasty adjudication was thus put a stop
      to, one of the members of the Council inquired, whether, as a Copley medal
      must by the will be annually given, some other person might not be found
      deserving of it. To which the Secretary replied, "We do not intend to give
      any this year." All further discussion was thus silenced.]
    

      Perhaps, also, as the Council are on some occasions apt to be oblivious,
      it might be convenient that the President should read, previously to the
      award of any medals or to the decision of any other important subjects,
      the statutes relating to them. He might perhaps propitiate their attention
      to them, by stating, HOW MUCH IT IMPORTETH TO THE CONSISTENCY OF THE
      COUNCIL TO BE ACQUAINTED WITH THE LAWS ON WHICH THEY ARE ABOUT TO DECIDE.
    

      If those who have been conversant with the internal management of the
      Council, would communicate their information, something curious might
      perhaps be learned respecting a few of these medals. Concerning those of
      which I have had good means of information, I shall merely state—of
      three of them—that whatever may have been the official reasons for
      their award, I had ample reasons to convince me of the following being the
      true causes:—
    

      First.—A medal was given to A, at a peculiarly inappropriate time—BECAUSE
      HE HAD NOT HAD ONE BEFORE.
    

      Second.—Subsequently a medal was given to B, in order TO DESTROY THE
      IMPRESSION WHICH THE AWARD OF THE MEDAL TO A HAD MADE ON THE PUBLIC THE
      PRECEDING YEAR.
    

      Third.—A medal was given to C, "BECAUSE WE THINK HE HAS BEEN ILL
      USED."
    

      I will now enter on an examination of one of their awards, which was
      peculiarly injudicious. I allude to that concerning the mode of rendering
      platina malleable. Respecting, as I did, the illustrious philosopher who
      invented the art, and who has left many other claims to the gratitude of
      mankind, I esteem it no disrespect to his memory to place that subject in
      its proper light.
    

      An invention in science or in art, may justly be considered as possessing
      the rights of property in the highest degree. The lands we inherit from
      our fathers, were cultivated ere they were born, and yielded produce
      before they were cultivated. The products of genius are the actual
      creations of the individual; and, after yielding profit or honour to him,
      they remain the permanent endowments of the human race. If the
      institutions of our country, and the opinions of society, support us fully
      in the absolute disposal of our fields, of which we can, by the laws of
      nature, be only the transitory possessors, who shall justly restrict our
      discretion in the disposal of those richer possessions, the products of
      intellectual exertion?
    

      Two courses are open to those individuals who are thus endowed with
      Nature's wealth. They may lock up in their own bosoms the mysteries they
      have penetrated, and by applying their knowledge to the production of some
      substance in demand in commerce, thus minister to the wants or comforts of
      their species, whilst they reap in pecuniary profit the legitimate reward
      of their exertions.
    

      It is open to them, on the other hand, to disclose the secret they have
      torn from Nature, and by allowing mankind to participate with them, to
      claim at once that splendid reputation which is rarely refused to the
      inventors of valuable discoveries in the arts of life.
    

      The two courses are rarely compatible, only indeed when the discoverer,
      having published his process, enters into equal competition with other
      manufacturers.
    

      If an individual adopt the first of these courses, and retaining his
      secret, it perish with him, the world have no right to complain. During
      his life, they profited by his knowledge, and are better off than if the
      philosopher had not existed.
    

      Monopolies, under the name of patents, have been devised to assist and
      reward those who have chosen the line of pecuniary profit. Honorary
      rewards and medals have been the feeble expressions of the sentiments of
      mankind towards those who have preferred the other course. But these have
      been, and should always be, kept completely distinct. [It is a condition
      with the Society of Arts, never to give a reward to any thing for which a
      patent has been, or is to be, taken out.]
    

      Let us now consider the case of platina. A new process was discovered of
      rendering it malleable, and the mere circumstance of so large a quantity
      having been sent into the market, was a positive benefit, of no ordinary
      magnitude, to many of the arts. The discoverer of this valuable process
      selected that course for which no reasonable man could blame him; and from
      some circumstance, or perhaps from accident, he preserved no written
      record of the manipulations. Had Providence appointed for that disorder,
      which terminated too fatally, a more rapid career, all the knowledge he
      had acquired from the long attention he had devoted to the subject, would
      have been lost to mankind. The hand of a friend recorded the directions of
      the expiring philosopher, whose anxiety to render useful even his
      unfinished speculations, proves that the previous omission was most
      probably accidental.
    

      Under such circumstances it was published to the world in the Transactions
      of the Royal Society. But what could induce that body to bestow on it
      their medal? To talk of adding lustre to the name of Wollaston by their
      medal, is to talk idly. They must have done it then as an example, as a
      stimulus to urge future inquiries in the career of discovery. But did they
      wish discoveries to be so endangered?
    

      The discoveries of Professor Mitscherlick, of Berlin, had long been
      considered, by a few members of the Society, as having strong claims on
      one of its honorary rewards; but difficulties had arisen, from so few
      members of the Council having any knowledge of discoveries which had long
      been familiar to Europe. The Council were just on the point of doing
      justice to the merits of the Prussian philosopher, when it was suggested
      that its medal should be given to Dr. Wollaston, and they immediately
      altered their intention, and thus enabled themselves to reserve their
      medal to Professor Mitscherlick for another year; at which period, for
      aught they knew, his discoveries might possess the additional merit of
      having been made prior to the limit allowed by their regulations. That
      medal was, in fact, voted at a meeting, at which no one member present was
      at all conversant with the subjects rewarded. I shall, however, say no
      more on this subject. They erred from feeling, an error so very rare with
      them, that it might be pardoned even for its singularity.
    

      I will, however, add one word to those whose censures have been unjustly
      dealt, to those who have reproached the philosopher for receiving
      pecuniary advantage from his inventions.
    

      Amongst the many and varied contrivances for the demands of science, or
      the arts of life, with which we were enriched by the genius of Wollaston,
      was it too much to allow him to retain, during his fleeting career, one
      out of the multitude, to furnish that: pecuniary supply, without which,
      the man will want food for his body, and the philosopher be destitute of
      tools for his inventions? Had he been, as, from the rank he held in
      science, he certainly would have been in other kingdoms, rich in the
      honours his country could bestow, and receiving from her a reward in some
      measure commensurate with his deserts,—then, indeed, there might
      have been reason for that reproach; but I am convinced that, in such
      circumstances, the philosopher would have balanced, with no "niggard"
      hand, the claims of his country, and would have given to it, unreservedly,
      the produce of his powerful mind.
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>