<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Chambers Robert</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="2">p.
27CONSTITUENT MATERIALS OF
THE EARTH
AND OF THE OTHER BODIES OF
SPACE.
The nebular hypothesis almost
necessarily supposes matter to have originally formed one
mass.  We have seen that the same physical laws preside over
the whole.  Are we also to presume that the constitution of
the whole was uniform?—that is to say, that the whole
consisted of similar elements.  It seems difficult to avoid
coming to this conclusion, at least under the qualification that,
possibly, various bodies, under peculiar circumstances attending
their formation, may contain elements which are wanting, and lack
some which are present in others, or that some may entirely
consist of elements in which others are entirely deficient.
What are elements?  This is a term applied by the chemist
to a certain limited number of substances, (fifty-four or
fifty-five are ascertained,) which, in their combinations, form
all the matters of every kind present in and about our
globe.  They are called elements, or simple substances,
because it has hitherto been found impossible to reduce them into
others, wherefore they are presumed to be the primary bases of
all matters.  It has, indeed, been surmised that these
so-called elements are only modifications of a primordial form of
matter, brought about under certain conditions; but if this
should prove to be the case, it would little affect the view
which we are taking of cosmical arrangements.  Analogy would
lead us to conclude that the combinations of the primordial
matter, forming our so-called elements, are as universal or as
liable to take place everywhere as are the laws of gravitation
and centrifugal force.  We must therefore presume that the
gases, the metals, the earths, and other simple substances,
(besides whatever more of which we have no acquaintance,) exist
or are liable to come into existence under proper conditions, as
well in the astral system, which is thirty-five thousand times
more distant than Sirius, as within the bounds of our own solar
system or our own globe.
Matter, whether it consist of about fifty-five ingredients, or
only one, is liable to infinite varieties of condition under
different circumstances, or, to speak more philosophically, under
different laws.  As a familiar illustration, water, when
subjected to a temperature under 32° Fahrenheit, becomes ice;
raise the temperature to 212°, and it becomes steam,
occupying a vast deal more space than it formerly did.  The
gases, when subjected to pressure, become liquids; for example,
carbonic acid gas, when subjected to a weight equal to a column
of water 1230 feet high, at a temperature of 32°, takes this
form: the other gases require various amounts of pressure for
this transformation, but all appear to be liable to it when the
pressure proper in each case is administered.  Heat is a
power greatly concerned in regulating the volume and other
conditions of matter.  A chemist can reckon with
considerable precision what additional amount of heat would be
required to vaporise all the water of our globe; how much more to
disengage the oxygen which is diffused in nearly a proportion of
one-half throughout its solids; and, finally, how much more would
be required to cause the whole to become vaporiform, which we may
consider as equivalent to its being restored to its original
nebulous state.  He can calculate with equal certainty what
would be the effect of a considerable diminution of the
earth’s temperature—what changes would take place in
each of its component substances, and how much the whole would
shrink in bulk.
The earth and all its various substances have at present a
certain volume in consequence of the temperature which actually
exists.  When, then, we find that its matter and that of the
associate planets was at one time diffused throughout the whole
space, now circumscribed by the orbit of Uranus, we cannot doubt,
after what we know of the power of heat, that the nebulous form
of matter was attended by the condition of a very high
temperature.  The nebulous matter of space, previously to
the formation of stellar and planetary bodies, must have been a
universal Fire Mist, an idea which we can scarcely comprehend,
though the reasons for arriving at it seem irresistible. 
The formation of systems out of this matter implies a change of
some kind with regard to the condition of the heat.  Had
this power continued to act with its full original repulsive
energy, the process of agglomeration by attraction could not have
gone on.  We do not know enough of the laws of heat to
enable us to surmise how the necessary change in this respect was
brought about, but we can trace some of the steps and
consequences of the process.  Uranus would be formed at the
time when the heat of our system’s matter was at the
greatest, Saturn at the next, and so on.  Now this tallies
perfectly with the exceeding diffuseness of the matter of those
elder planets, Saturn being not more dense or heavy than the
substance cork.  It may be that a sufficiency of heat still
remains in those planets to make up for their distance from the
sun, and the consequent smallness of the heat which they derive
from his rays.  And it may equally be, since Mercury is
twice the density of the earth, that its matter exists under a
degree of cold for which that planet’s large enjoyment of
the sun’s rays is no more than a compensation.  Thus
there may be upon the whole a nearly equal experience of heat
amongst all these children of the sun.  Where, meanwhile, is
the heat once diffused through the system over and above what
remains in the planets?  May we not rationally presume it to
have gone to constitute that luminous envelope of the sun, in
which his warmth-giving power is now held to reside?  It
could not be destroyed—it cannot be supposed to have gone
off into space—it must have simply been reserved to
constitute, at the last, a means of sustaining the many
operations of which the planets were destined to be the
theatre.
The tendency of the whole of the preceding considerations is
to bring the conviction that our globe is a specimen of all the
similarly-placed bodies of space, as respects its constituent
matter and the physical and chemical laws governing it, with only
this qualification, that there are possibly shades of
variation with respect to the component materials, and
undoubtedly with respect to the conditions under which the
laws operate, and consequently the effects which they
produce.  Thus, there may be substances here which are not
in some other bodies, and substances here solid may be elsewhere
liquid or vaporiform.  We are the more entitled to draw such
conclusions, seeing that there is nothing at all singular or
special in the astronomical situation of the earth.  It
takes its place third in a series of planets, which series is
only one of numberless other systems forming one group.  It
is strikingly—if I may use such an expression—a
member of a democracy.  Hence, we cannot suppose that there
is any peculiarity about it which does not probably attach to
multitudes of other bodies—in fact, to all that are
analogous to it in respect of cosmical arrangements.
It therefore becomes a point of great interest—what are
the materials of this specimen?  What is the constitutional
character of this object, which may be said to be a sample,
presented to our immediate observation, of those crowds of worlds
which seem to us as the particles of the desert sand-cloud in
number, and to whose profusion there are no conceivable local
limits?
The solids, liquids, and aeriform fluids of our globe are all,
as has been stated, reducible into fifty-five substances hitherto
called elementary.  Six are gases; oxygen, hydrogen, and
nitrogen being the chief.  Forty-two are metals, of which
eleven are remarkable as composing, in combination with oxygen,
certain earths, as magnesia, lime, alumin.  The remaining
six, including carbon, silicon, sulphur, have not any general
appellation.
The gas oxygen is considered as by far the most abundant
substance in our globe.  It constitutes a fifth part of our
atmosphere, a third part of water, and a large proportion of
every kind of rock in the crust of the earth.  Hydrogen,
which forms two-thirds of water, and enters into some mineral
substances, is perhaps next.  Nitrogen, of which the
atmosphere is four-fifths composed, must be considered as an
abundant substance.  The metal silicium, which unites with
oxygen in nearly equal parts to form silica, the basis of nearly
a half of the rocks in the earth’s crust, is, of course, an
important ingredient.  Aluminium, the metallic basis of
alumin, a large material in many rocks, is another abundant
elementary substance.  So, also, is carbon a small
ingredient in the atmosphere, but the chief constituent of animal
and vegetable substances, and of all fossils which ever were in
the latter condition, amongst which coal takes a conspicuous
place.  The familiarly-known metals, as iron, tin, lead,
silver, gold, are elements of comparatively small magnitude in
that exterior part of the earth’s body which we are able to
investigate.
It is remarkable of the simple substances that they are
generally in some compound form.  Thus, oxygen and nitrogen,
though in union they form the aerial envelope of the globe, are
never found separate in nature.  Carbon is pure only in the
diamond.  And the metallic bases of the earths, though the
chemist can disengage them, may well be supposed unlikely to
remain long uncombined, seeing that contact with moisture makes
them burn.  Combination and re-combination are principles
largely pervading nature.  There are few rocks, for example,
that are not composed of at least two varieties of matter, each
of which is again a compound of elementary substances.  What
is still more wonderful with respect to this principle of
combination, all the elementary substances observe certain
mathematical proportions in their unions.  One volume of
them unites with one, two, three, or more volumes of another, any
extra quantity being sure to be left over, if such there should
be.  It is hence supposed that matter is composed of
infinitely minute particles or atoms, each of which belonging to
any one substance, can only (through the operation of some as yet
hidden law) associate with a certain number of the atoms of any
other.  There are also strange predilections amongst
substances for each other’s company.  One will remain
combined in solution with another, till a third is added, when it
will abandon the former and attach itself to the latter.  A
fourth being added, the third will perhaps leave the first, and
join the new comer.
Such is an outline of the information which chemistry gives us
regarding the constituent materials of our globe.  How
infinitely is the knowledge increased in interest, when we
consider the probability of such being the materials of the whole
of the bodies of space, and the laws under which these everywhere
combine, subject only to local and accidental variations!
In considering the cosmogenic arrangements of our globe, our
attention is called in a special degree to the moon.
In the nebular hypothesis, satellites are considered as masses
thrown off from their primaries, exactly as the primaries had
previously been from the sun.  The orbit of any satellite is
also to be regarded as marking the bounds of the mass of the
primary at the time when that satellite was thrown off; its speed
likewise denotes the rapidity of the rotatory motion of the
primary at that particular juncture.  For example, the
outermost of the four satellites of Jupiter revolves round his
body at the distance of 1,180,582 miles, shewing that the planet
was once 3,675,501 miles in circumference, instead of being, as
now, only 89,170 miles in diameter.  This large mass took
rather more than sixteen days six hours and a half (the present
revolutionary period of the outermost satellite) to rotate on its
axis.  The innermost satellite must have been formed when
the planet was reduced to a circumference of 309,075 miles, and
rotated in about forty-two hours and a half.
From similar inferences, we find that the mass of the earth,
at a certain point of time after it was thrown off from the sun,
was no less than 482,000 miles in diameter, being sixty times
what it has since shrunk to.  At that time, the mass must
have taken rather more than twenty-nine and a half days to
rotate, (being the revolutionary period of the moon,) instead of
as now, rather less than twenty-four hours.
The time intervening between the formation of the moon and the
earth’s diminution to its present size, was probably one of
those vast sums in which astronomy deals so largely, but which
the mind altogether fails to grasp.
The observations made upon the surface of the moon by
telescopes, tend strongly to support the hypothesis as to all the
bodies of space being composed of similar matters, subject to
certain variations.  It does not appear that our satellite
is provided with that gaseous envelope which, on earth, performs
so many important functions.  Neither is there any
appearance of water upon the surface; yet that surface is, like
that of our globe, marked by inequalities and the appearance of
volcanic operations.  These inequalities and volcanic
operations are upon a scale far greater than any which now exist
upon the earth’s surface.  Although, from the greater
force of gravitation upon its exterior, the mountains, other
circumstances being equal, might have been expected to be much
smaller than ours, they are, in many instances, equal in height
to nearly the highest of our Andes.  They are generally of
extreme steepness, and sharp of outline, a peculiarity which
might be looked for in a planet deficient in water and
atmosphere, seeing that these are the agents which wear down
ruggedness on the surface of our earth.  The volcanic
operations are on a stupendous scale.  They are the cause of
the bright spots of the moon, while the want of them is what
distinguishes the duller portions, usually but erroneously called
seas.  In some parts, bright volcanic matter, besides
covering one large patch, radiates out in long streams, which
appear studded with subordinate foci of the same kind of
energy.  Other objects of a most remarkable character are
ring mountains, mounts like those of the craters of earthly
volcanoes, surrounded immediately by vast and profound circular
pits, hollowed under the general surface, these again being
surrounded by a circular wall of mountain, rising far above the
central one, and in the inside of which are terraces about the
same height as the inner eminence.  The well-known bright
spot in the south-east quarter, called by astronomers
Tycho, and which can be readily distinguished by the naked
eye, is one of these ring-mountains.  There is one of 200
miles in diameter, with a pit 22,000 feet deep; that is, twice
the height of Ætna.  It is remarkable, that the maps
given by Humboldt of a volcanic district in South America, and
one illustrative of the formerly volcanic district of Auvergne,
in France, present features strikingly like many parts of the
moon’s surface, as seen through a good glass.
These characteristics of the moon forbid the idea that it can
be at present a theatre of life like the earth, and almost seem
to declare that it never can become so.  But we must not
rashly draw any such conclusions.  The moon may be only in
an earlier stage of the progress through which the earth has
already gone.  The elements which seem wanting may be only
in combinations different in those which exist here, and may yet
be developed as we here find them.  Seas may yet fill the
profound hollows of the surface; an atmosphere may spread over
the whole.  Should these events take place, meteorological
phenomena, and all the phenomena of organic life, will commence,
and the moon, like the earth, will become a green and inhabited
world.
It is unavoidably held as a strong proof in favour of any
hypothesis, when all the relative phenomena are in harmony with
it.  This is eminently the case with the nebulous
hypothesis, for here the associated facts cannot be explained on
any other supposition.  We have seen reason to conclude that
the primary condition of matter was that of a diffused mass, in
which the component molecules were probably kept apart through
the efficacy of heat; that portions of this agglomerated into
suns, which threw off planets; that these planets were at first
very much diffused, but gradually contracted by cooling to their
present dimensions.  Now, as to our own globe, there is a
remarkable proof of its having been in a fluid state at the time
when it was finally solidifying, in the fact of its being bulged
at the equator, the very form which a soft revolving body takes,
and must inevitably take, under the influence of centrifugal
force.  This bulging makes the equatorial exceed the polar
diameter as 230 to 229, which has been demonstrated to be
precisely the departure from a correct sphere which might be
predicated from a knowledge of the amount of the mass and the
rate of rotation.  There is an almost equally distinct
memorial of the original high temperature of the materials, in
the store of heat which still exists in the interior.  The
immediate surface of the earth, be it observed, exhibits only the
temperature which might be expected to be imparted to such
materials, by the heat of the sun.  There is a point, very
short way down, but varying in different climes, where all effect
from the sun’s rays ceases.  Then, however, commences
a temperature from an entirely different cause, one which
evidently has its source in the interior of the earth, and which
regularly increases as we descend to greater and greater depths,
the rate of increment being about one degree Fahrenheit for every
sixty feet; and of this high temperature there are other
evidences, in the phenomena of volcanoes and thermal springs, as
well as in what is ascertained with regard to the density of the
entire mass of the earth.  This, it will be remembered, is
four and a half times the weight of water; but the actual weight
of the principal solid substances composing the outer crust is as
two and a half times the weight of water; and this, we know, if
the globe were solid and cold, should increase vastly towards the
centre, water acquiring the density of quicksilver at 362 miles
below the surface, and other things in proportion, and these
densities becoming much greater at greater depths; so that the
entire mass of a cool globe should be of a gravity infinitely
exceeding four and a half times the weight of water.  The
only alternative supposition is, that the central materials are
greatly expanded or diffused by some means; and by what means
could they be so expanded but by heat?  Indeed, the
existence of this central heat, a residuum of that which kept all
matter in a vaporiform chaos at first, is amongst the most solid
discoveries of modern science, [42] and the support
which it gives to Herschel’s explanation of the formation
of worlds is most important.  We shall hereafter see what
appear to be traces of an operation of this heat upon the surface
of the earth in very remote times; an effect, however, which has
long passed entirely away.  The central heat has, for ages,
reached a fixed point, at which it will probably remain for ever,
as the non-conducting quality of the cool crust absolutely
prevents it from suffering any diminution.</div></body></text></TEI>