<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="18">CHAPTER XVIII.
REPRODUCTIVE EFFECTS OF RIVERS—continued.
Deltas formed under the influence of tides—Basin and delta of the Mississippi—Alluvial
plain—River-banks and bluffs—Curves of the river—Natural rafts
and snags—New lakes, and effects of earthquakes—Antiquity of the delta—Delta
of the Ganges and Brahmapootra—Head of the delta and Sunderbunds—Islands
formed and destroyed—Crocodiles—Amount of fluviatile sediment in
the water—Artesian boring at Calcutta—Proofs of subsidence—Age of the
delta—Convergence of deltas—Origin of existing deltas not contemporaneous—Grouping
of strata and stratification in deltas—Conglomerates—Constant interchange
of land and sea.
In the last chapter several examples were given of the deltas of inland
seas, where the influence of the tides is almost imperceptible. We
may next consider those marine or oceanic deltas, where the tides play
an important part in the dispersion of fluviatile sediment, as in the Gulf
of Mexico, where they exert a moderate degree of force, and then in the
Bay of Bengal, where they are extremely powerful. In regard to
estuaries, which Rennel termed "negative deltas," they will be treated
of more properly when our attention is specially turned to the operations
of tides and currents (chapters 20, 21, and 22). In this case,
instead of the land gaining on the sea at the river's mouth, the tides
penetrate far inland beyond the general coast-line.
BASIN AND DELTA OF THE MISSISSIPPI.
Alluvial plain.—The hydrographical basin of the Mississippi displays,
on the grandest scale, the action of running water on the surface of a
vast continent. This magnificent river rises nearly in the forty-ninth
264
parallel of north latitude, and flows to the Gulf of Mexico in the twenty-ninth—a
course, including its meanders, of more than three thousand
miles. It passes from a cold climate, where the hunter obtains his furs
and peltries, traverses the temperate latitudes, and discharges its waters
into the sea in the region of rice, the cotton plant, and the sugar-cane.
From near its mouth at the Balize a steamboat may ascend for 2000
miles with scarcely any perceptible difference in the width of the river.
Several of its tributaries, the Red River, the Arkansas, the Missouri, the
Ohio, and others, would be regarded elsewhere as of the first importance,
and, taken together, are navigable for a distance many times exceeding
that of the main stream. No river affords a more striking illustration
of the law before mentioned, that an augmentation of volume does not
occasion a proportional increase of surface, nay, is even sometimes attended
with a narrowing of the channel. The Mississippi is half a mile
wide at its junction with the Missouri, the latter being also of equal
width; yet the united waters have only, from their confluence to the
mouth of the Ohio, a medial width of about half a mile. The junction
of the Ohio seems also to produce no increase, but rather a decrease,
of surface.356 The St. Francis, White, Arkansas, and Red rivers are
also absorbed by the main stream with scarcely any apparent increase
of its width, although here and there it expands to a breadth of 1½, or
even to 2 miles. On arriving at New Orleans, it is somewhat less than
half a mile wide. Its depth there is very variable, the greatest at high
water being 168 feet. The mean rate at which the whole body of
water flows is variously estimated; according to Mr. Forshey the mean
velocity of the current at the surface, somewhat exceeds 2-1/4 miles an
hour when the water is at a mean height. For 300 miles above New
Orleans the distance measured by the winding river is about twice as
great as the distance in a right line. For the first 100 miles from the
mouth the rate of fall is 1·80 inch per mile, for the second hundred 2
inches, for the third 2·30, for the fourth 2·57.
The alluvial plain of the Mississippi begins to be of great width below
Cape Girardeau, 50 miles above the junction of the Ohio. At this
junction it is about 50 miles broad, south of which it contracts to about
30 miles at Memphis, expands again to 80 miles at the mouth of the
White River, and then, after various contractions and expansions, protrudes
beyond the general coast-line, in a large delta, about 90 miles in
width, from N. E. to S. W. Mr. Forshey estimates the area of the
great plain as above defined at 31,200 square miles, with a circumference
of about 3000 miles, exceeding the area of Ireland. If that part
of this plain which lies below, or to the south of the branching off of
the highest arm, called the Atchafalaya, be termed the delta, it constitutes
less than half of the whole, being 14,000 square British miles in
area. The delta may be said to be bounded on the east, west, and
265
south by the sea; on the north chiefly by the broad valley-plain which
entirely resembles it in character as in origin. The east and west
boundaries of the alluvial region above the head of the delta consists of
cliffs or bluffs, which on the east side of the Mississippi are very abrupt,
and are undermined by the river at many points. They consist, from
Baton Rouge in Louisiana, where they commence, as far north as the
borders of Kentucky, of geological formations newer than the cretaceous,
the lowest being Eocene, and the uppermost consisting of loam, resembling
the loess of the Rhine, and containing freshwater and land
shells almost all of existing species. (See fig. 23.) These recent shells
are associated with the bones of the mastodon, elephant, tapir, mylodon,
horse, ox, and other quadrupeds, most of them of extinct species.
I have endeavored to show in my Second Visit to the United States,
that this extensive formation of loam is either an ancient alluvial plain
or a delta of the great river, formed originally at a lower level, and
since upheaved, and partially denuded.
Fig. 23.
Valley of the Mississippi.
1. Modern alluvium of Mississippi.   2. Loam or Loess.   3.f. Eocene.   4. Cretaceous.
The Mississippi in that part of its course which is below the mouth
of the Ohio, frequently washes the eastern bluffs, but never once comes
in contact with the western. These are composed of similar formations;
but I learn from Mr. Forshey that they rise up more gently
from the alluvial plain (as at a, fig. 23). It is supposed that the
waters are thrown to the eastern side, because all the large tributary
rivers entering from the west have filled that side of the great valley
with their deltas, or with a sloping mass of clay and sand; so that the
opposite bluffs are undermined, and the Mississippi is slowly but incessantly
advancing eastward.357
Curves of the Mississippi.—The river traverses the plain in a meandering
course, describing immense curves. After sweeping round the
half of a circle, it is carried in a rapid current diagonally across the
ordinary direction of its channel, to another curve of similar shape.
Opposite to each of these, there is always a sand-bar, answering, in the
convexity of its form, to the concavity of "the bend," as it is called.358
The river, by continually wearing these curves deep, returns, like many
other streams before described, on its own track, so that a vessel in
some places, after sailing for twenty-five or thirty miles, is brought
round again to within a mile of the place whence it started. When the
waters approach so near to each other, it often happens at high floods
266
that they burst through the small tongue of land, and insulate a portion,
rushing through what is called the "cut-off," so that vessels may pass
from one point to another in half a mile to a distance which it previously
required a voyage of twenty miles to reach. As soon as the river
has excavated the new passage, bars of sand and mud are formed at
the two points of junction with the old bend, which is soon entirely
separated from the main river by a continuous mud-bank covered with
wood. The old bend then becomes a semicircular lake of clear water,
inhabited by large gar-fish, alligators, and wild fowl, which the steamboats
have nearly driven away from the main river. A multitude of
such crescent-shaped lakes, scattered far and wide over the alluvial
plain, the greater number of them to the west, but some of them also
eastward of the Mississippi, bear testimony of the extensive wanderings
of the great stream in former ages. For the last two hundred miles
above its mouth the course of the river is much less winding than
above, there being only in the whole of that distance one great curve,
that called the "English Turn." This great straightness of the stream
is ascribed by Mr. Forshey to the superior tenacity of the banks, which
are more clayey in this region.
Fig. 24.
Section of channel, bank, levees (a and b), and swamps of Mississippi river.
The Mississippi has been incorrectly described by some of the earlier
geographers, as a river running along the top of a long hill, or mound
in a plain. In reality it runs in a valley, from 100 to 200 or more feet
in depth, as a, c, b, fig. 24, its banks forming long strips of land parallel
to the course of the main stream, and to the swamps g, f, and d, e,
lying on each side. These extensive morasses, which are commonly well-wooded,
though often submerged for months continuously, are rarely
more than fifteen feet below the summit level of the banks. The banks
themselves are occasionally overflowed, but are usually above water for
a breadth of about two miles. They follow all the curves of the great
river, and near New Orleans are raised artificially by embankments (or
levees), a b, fig. 24, through which the river when swollen sometimes
cuts a deep channel (or crevasse), inundating the adjoining low lands
and swamps, and not sparing the lower streets of the great city.
The cause of the uniform upward slope of the river-bank above the
adjoining alluvial plain is this: when the waters charged with sediment
pass over the banks in the flood season, their velocity is checked among
the herbage and reeds, and they throw down at once the coarser and
more sandy matter with which they are charged. But the fine particles
of mud are carried farther on, so that at the distance of about two
267
miles, a thin film of fine clay only subsides, forming a stiff unctuous
black soil, which gradually envelops the base of trees growing on the
borders of the swamps.
Waste of the banks.—It has been said of a mountain torrent, that "it
lays down what it will remove, and removes what it has laid down;"
and in like manner the Mississippi, by the continual shifting of its course,
sweeps away, during a great portion of the year, considerable tracts of
alluvium, which were gradually accumulated by the overflow of former
years, and the matter now left during the spring-floods will be at some
future time removed. After the flood season, when the river subsides
within its channel, it acts with destructive force upon the alluvial banks,
softened and diluted by the recent overflow. Several acres at a time,
thickly covered with wood, are precipitated into the stream; and large
portions of the islands are frequently swept away.
"Some years ago," observes Captain Hall, "when the Mississippi was
regularly surveyed, all its islands were numbered, from the confluence
of the Missouri to the sea; but every season makes such revolutions,
not only in the number, but in the magnitude and situation of these
islands, that this enumeration is now almost obsolete. Sometimes large
islands are entirely melted away; at other places they have attached
themselves to the main shore, or, which is the more correct statement,
the interval has been filled up by myriads of logs cemented together by
mud and rubbish."359
Rafts.—One of the most interesting features in the great rivers of this
part of America is the frequent accumulation of what are termed "rafts,"
or masses of floating trees, which have been arrested in their progress
by snags, islands, shoals, or other obstructions, and made to accumulate,
so as to form natural bridges, reaching entirely across the stream. One
of the largest of these was called the raft of the Atchafalaya, an arm of
the Mississippi, which was certainly at some former time the channel of
the Red River, when the latter found its way to the Gulf of Mexico by
a separate course. The Atchafalaya being in a direct line with the
general direction of the Mississippi, catches a large portion of the timber
annually brought down from the north; and the drift-trees collected in
about thirty-eight years previous to 1816 formed a continuous raft, no
less than ten miles in length, 220 yards wide, and eight feet deep. The
whole rose and fell with the water, yet was covered with green bushes
and trees, and its surface enlivened in the autumn by a variety of beautiful
flowers. It went on increasing till about 1835, when some of the
trees upon it had grown to the height of about sixty feet. Steps were
then taken by the State of Louisiana to clear away the whole raft, and
open the navigation, which was effected, not without great labor, in the
space of four years.
The rafts on Red River are equally remarkable: in some parts of its
course, cedar-trees are heaped up by themselves, and in other places,
268
pines. On the rise of the waters in summer hundreds of these are seen,
some with their green leaves still upon them, just as they have fallen
from a neighboring bank, others leafless, broken and worn in their passage
from a far distant tributary: wherever they accumulate on the
edge of a sand-bar they arrest the current, and soon become covered
with sediment. On this mud the young willows and the poplars called
cotton-wood spring up, their boughs still farther retarding the stream,
and as the inundation rises, accelerating the deposition of new soil. The
bank continuing to enlarge, the channel at length becomes so narrow
that a single long tree may reach from side to side, and the remaining
space is then soon choked up by a quantity of other timber.
"Unfortunately for the navigation of the Mississippi," observes Captain
Hall, "some of the largest trunks, after being cast down from the
position on which they grew, get their roots entangled with the bottom
of the river, where they remain anchored, as it were, in the mud. The
force of the current naturally gives their tops a tendency downwards,
and, by its flowing past, soon strips them of their leaves and branches.
These fixtures, called snags, or planters, are extremely dangerous to the
steam-vessels proceeding up the stream, in which they lie like a lance
in rest, concealed beneath the water, with their sharp ends pointed
directly against the bows of the vessels coming up. For the most part
these formidable snags remain so still that they can be detected only by
a slight ripple above them, not perceptible to inexperienced eyes. Sometimes,
however, they vibrate up and down, alternately showing their
heads above the surface and bathing them beneath it."360 So imminent,
until lately, was the danger caused by these obstructions, that almost
all the boats on the Mississippi were constructed on a particular plan,
to guard against fatal accidents; but in the last ten years, by the aid
of the power of steam and the machinery of a snag-boat, as it is called,
the greater number of these trunks of trees have been drawn out of the
mud.361
The prodigious quantity of wood annually drifted down by the Mississippi
and its tributaries, is a subject of geological interest, not merely
as illustrating the manner in which abundance of vegetable matter becomes,
in the ordinary course of nature, imbedded in submarine and estuary
deposits, but as attesting the constant destruction of soil and
transportation of matter to lower levels by the tendency of rivers to
shift their courses. Each of these trees must have required many years,
some of them centuries, to attain their full size; the soil, therefore,
whereon they grew, after remaining undisturbed for long periods, is
ultimately torn up and swept away.
269
It is also found in excavating at New Orleans, even at the depth of
several yards below the level of the sea, that the soil of the delta contains
innumerable trunks of trees, layer above layer, some prostrate, as
if drifted, others broken off near the bottom, but remaining still erect,
and with their roots spreading on all sides, as if in their natural position.
In such situations they appeared to me to indicate a sinking of the
ground, as the trees must formerly have grown in marshes above the
sea-level. In the higher parts of the alluvial plain, for many hundred
miles above the head of the delta, similar stools and roots of trees are
also seen buried in stiff clay at different levels, one above the other, and
exposed to view in the banks at low water. They point clearly to the
successive growth of forests in the extensive swamps of the plain, where
the ground was slowly raised, year after year, by the mud thrown down
during inundations. These roots and stools belong chiefly to the deciduous
cypress (Taxodium distichum), and other swamp-trees, and they
bear testimony to the constant shifting of the course of the great river,
which is always excavating land originally formed at some distance from
its banks.
Formation of lakes in Louisiana..—Another striking feature in the
basin of the Mississippi, illustrative of the changes now in progress, is
the formation by natural causes of great lakes, and the drainage of others.
These are especially frequent in the basin of the Red River in Louisiana,
where the largest of them, called Bistineau, is more than thirty miles
long, and has a medium depth of from fifteen to twenty feet. In the
deepest parts are seen numerous cypress-trees, of all sizes, now dead,
and most of them with their tops broken by the wind, yet standing
erect under water. This tree resists the action of air and water longer
than any other, and, if not submerged throughout the whole year, will
retain life for an extraordinary period. Lake Bistineau, as well as Black
Lake, Cado Lake, Spanish Lake, Natchitoches Lake, and many others,
have been formed, according to Darby, by the gradual elevation of the
bed of Red River, in which the alluvial accumulations have been so great
as to raise its channel, and cause its waters, during the flood season, to
flow up the mouths of many tributaries, and to convert parts of their
courses into lakes. In the autumn, when the level of Red River is again
depressed, the waters rush back, and some lakes become grassy meadows,
with streams meandering through them.362 Thus, there is a periodical
flux and reflux between Red River and some of these basins, which are
merely reservoirs, alternately emptied and filled, like our tide estuaries—with
this difference, that in the one case the land is submerged for several
months continuously, and in the other twice in every twenty-four
hours. It has happened, in several cases, that a raft of timber or a bar
has been thrown by Red River across some of the openings of these
channels, and then the lakes become, like Bistineau, constant repositories
of water. But, even in these cases, their level is liable to annual elevation
270
and depression, because the flood of the main river, when at its
height, passes over the bar; just as, where sand-hills close the entrance
of an estuary on the Norfolk or Suffolk coast, the sea, during some high
tide or storm, has often breached the barrier and inundated again the
interior.
I am informed by Mr. Featherstonhaugh that the plains of the Red
River and the Arkansas are so low and flat, that whenever the Mississippi
rises thirty feet above its ordinary level, those great tributaries are
made to flow back, and inundate a region of vast extent. Both the
streams alluded to contain red sediment, derived from the decomposition
of red porphyry; and since 1833, when there was a great inundation in
the Arkansas, an immense swamp has been formed near the Mammelle
mountain, comprising 30,000 acres, with here and there large lagoons,
where the old bed of the river was situated; in which innumerable trees,
for the most part dead, are seen standing, of cypress, cotton-wood, or
poplar, the triple-thorned acacia, and others, which are of great size.
Their trunks appear as if painted red for about fifteen feet from the
ground; at which height a perfectly level line extends through the
whole forest, marking the rise of the waters during the last
flood.363
But most probably the causes above assigned for the recent origin of
these lakes are not the only ones. Subterranean movements have altered,
so lately as the years 1811-12, the relative levels of various parts of
the basin of the Mississippi, situated 300 miles northeast of Lake Bistineau.
In those years the great valley, from the mouth of the Ohio to
that of the St. Francis, including a tract 300 miles in length, and exceeding
in area the whole basin of the Thames, was convulsed to such a degree,
as to create new islands in the river, and lakes in the alluvial plain.
Some of these were on the left or east bank of the Mississippi, and were
twenty miles in extent; as, for example, those named Reelfoot and Obion
in Tennessee, formed in the channels or valleys of small streams bearing
the same names.364
But the largest area affected by the great convulsion lies eight or ten
miles to the westward of the Mississippi, and inland from the town of
New Madrid, in Missouri. It is called "the sunk country," and is said
271
to extend along the course of the White Water and its tributaries, for a
distance of between seventy and eighty miles north and south, and thirty
miles or more east and west. Throughout this area, innumerable submerged
trees, some standing leafless, others prostrate, are seen; and so
great is the extent of lake and marsh, that an active trade in the skins
of muskrats, mink, otters, and other wild animals, is now carried on
there. In March, 1846, I skirted the borders of the "sunk country"
nearest to New Madrid, passing along the Bayou St. John and Little
Prairie, where dead trees of various kinds, some erect in the water, others
fallen, and strewed in dense masses over the bottom, in the shallows, and
near the shore, were conspicuous. I also beheld countless rents in the
adjoining dry alluvial plains, caused by the movements of the soil in 1811-12,
and still open, though the rains, frost, and river inundations, have
greatly diminished their original depth. I observed, moreover, numerous
circular cavities, called "sunk holes," from ten to thirty yards wide,
and twenty feet or more in depth, which interrupt the general level of
the plain. These were formed by the spouting out of large quantities
of sand and mud during the earthquakes.365
That the prevailing changes of level in the delta and alluvial plain of
the Mississippi have been caused by the subsidence, rather than the upheaval
of land, appears to me established by the fact, that there are no
protuberances of upraised alluvial soil, projecting above the level surface
of the great plain. It is true that the gradual elevation of that plain,
by new accessions of matter, would tend to efface every inequality derived
from this source, but we might certainly have expected to find
more broken ground between the opposite bluffs, had local upthrows of
alluvial strata been of repeated occurrence.
Antiquity of the delta.—The vast size of the alluvial plain both above
and below the head of the delta, or the branching off of the uppermost
arm of the Atchafalaya, has been already alluded to. Its superficial
dimensions, according to Mr. Forshey, exceed 30,000 square miles,
nearly half of which belong to the true delta. The deposits consist
partly of sand originally formed upon or near the banks of the river, and
its tributaries, partly of gravel, swept down the main channel, of which
the position has continually shifted, and partly of fine mud slowly accumulated
in the swamps. The farther we descend the river towards
its mouth, the finer becomes the texture of the sediment. The whole
alluvial formation, from the base of the delta upwards, slopes with a
very gentle inclination, rising about three inches in a mile from the level
of the sea at the Balize, to the height of about 200 feet in a distance of
about 800 miles.
That a large portion of this fluviatile deposit, together with the fluvio-marine
strata now in progress near the Balize, consists of mud and sand
with much vegetable matter intermixed, may be inferred from what has
272
been said of the abundance of drift trees floated down every summer.
These are seen matted together into a net-work around the extensive
mud banks at the extreme mouths of the river. Every one acquainted
with the geography of Louisiana is aware that the most southern part
of the delta forms a long narrow tongue of land protruding for 50 miles
into the Gulf of Mexico, at the end of which are numerous channels of
discharge. This singular promontory consists simply of the river and
its two low, flat banks, covered with reeds, young willows, and poplars.
Its appearance answers precisely to that of the banks far in the interior,
when nothing appears above water during inundations but the higher
part of the sloping glacis or bank. In the one case we have the swamps
or an expanse of freshwater with the tops of trees appearing above, in
the other the bluish green surface of the Gulf of Mexico. An opinion has
very commonly prevailed that this narrow promontory, the newest product
of the river, has gained very rapidly upon the sea, since the foundation
of New Orleans; but after visiting the Balize in 1846, in company
with Dr. Carpenter, and making many inquiries of the pilots, and comparing
the present outline of the coast with the excellent Spanish chart,
published by Charlevoix 120 years before, we came to a different conclusion.
The rate of permanent advance of the new land has been very
slow, not exceeding perhaps one mile in a century. The gain may have
been somewhat more rapid in former years, when the new strip of soil
projected less far into the gulf, since it is now much more exposed to
the action of a strong marine current. The tides also, when the waters
of the river are low, enter into each opening, and scour them out, destroying
the banks of mud and the sand-bars newly formed during the
flood season.
An observation of Darby, in regard to the strata composing part of
this delta, deserves attention. In the steep banks of the Atchafalaya,
before alluded to, the following section, he says, is observable at low
water:—first an upper stratum, consisting invariably of bluish clay,
common to the banks of the Mississippi; below this a stratum of red
ochreous earth, peculiar to Red River, under which the blue clay of the
Mississippi again appears; and this arrangement is constant, proving, as
that geographer remarks, that the waters of the Mississippi and the Red
River occupied alternately, at some former periods, considerable tracts
below their present point of union.366 Such alternations are probably
common in submarine spaces situated between two converging deltas;
for, before the two rivers unite, there must almost always be a certain
period when an intermediate tract will by turns be occupied and abandoned
by the waters of each stream; since it can rarely happen that
the season of highest flood will precisely correspond in each. In the
case of the Red River and Mississippi, which carry off the waters from
countries placed under widely distant latitudes, an exact coincidence in
the time of greatest inundation is very improbable.
273
The antiquity of the delta, or length of the period which has been
occupied in the deposition of so vast a mass of alluvial matter, is a
question which may well excite the curiosity of every geologist. Sufficient
data have not yet been obtained to afford a full and satisfactory
answer to the inquiry, but some approximation may already be made to
the minimum of time required.
When I visited New Orleans, in February, 1846, I found that Dr.
Riddell had made numerous experiments to ascertain the proportion of
sediment contained in the waters of the Mississippi; and he concluded
that the mean annual amount of solid matter was to the water as 1/1245
in weight, or about 1/3000 in volume.367 From the observations of the
same gentleman, and those of Dr. Carpenter and Mr. Forshey, an eminent
engineer, to whom I have before alluded, the average width, depth,
and velocity of the Mississippi, and thence the mean annual discharge
of water were deduced. I assumed 528 feet, or the tenth of a mile,
as the probable thickness of the deposit of mud and sand in the delta;
founding my conjecture chiefly on the depth of the Gulf of Mexico,
between the southern point of Florida and the Balize, which equals on
an average 100 fathoms, and partly on some borings 600 feet deep in
the delta, near Lake Pontchartrain, north of New Orleans, in which the
bottom of the alluvial matter is said not to have been reached. The
area of the delta being about 13,600 square statute miles, and the quantity
of solid matter annually brought down by the river 3,702,758,400
cubic feet, it must have taken 67,000 years for the formation of
the whole; and if the alluvial matter of the plain above be 264 feet
deep, or half that of the delta,368 it must have required 33,500 more
years for its accumulation, even if its area be estimated as only equal
to that of the delta, whereas it is in fact larger. If some deduction be
made from the time here stated, in consequence of the effect of the
drift-wood, which must have aided in filling up more rapidly the space
above alluded to, a far more important allowance must be made on the
other hand, for the loss of matter, owing to the finer particles of mud
274
not settling at the mouths of the river, but being swept out far to sea
during the predominant action of the tides, and the waves in the winter
months, when the current of fresh water is feeble. Yet however vast
the time during which the Mississippi has been transporting its earthy
burden to the ocean, the whole period, though far exceeding, perhaps,
100,000 years, must be insignificant in a geological point of view, since
the bluffs or cliffs, bounding the great valley, and therefore older in
date, and which are from 50 to 250 feet in perpendicular height, consist
in great part of loam containing land, fluviatile, and lacustrine shells
of species still inhabiting the same country. (See fig. 23, p. 265.)
Before we take leave of the great delta, we may derive an instructive
lesson from the reflection that the new deposits already formed, or
now accumulating, whether marine or freshwater, must greatly resemble
in composition, and the general character of their organic remains,
many ancient strata, which enter largely into the earth's structure.
Yet there is no sudden revolution in progress, whether on the land or
in the waters, whether in the animate or the inanimate world. Notwithstanding
the excessive destruction of soil and uprooting of trees,
the region which yields a never-failing supply of drift-wood is densely
clothed with noble forests, and is almost unrivalled in its power of supporting
animal and vegetable life. In spite of the undermining of many
a lofty bluff, and the encroachments of the delta on the sea—in spite
of the earthquake, which rends and fissures the soil, or causes areas
more than sixty miles in length to sink down several yards in a few
months, the general features of the district remain unaltered, or are
merely undergoing a slow and insensible change. Herds of wild deer
graze on the pastures, or browse upon the trees; and if they diminish
in number, it is only where they give way to man and the domestic
animals which follow in his train. The bear, the wolf, the fox, the
panther, and the wild-cat, still maintain themselves in the fastnesses of
the forests of cypress and gum-tree. The racoon and the opossum
are everywhere abundant, while the musk-rat, otter, and mink still
frequent the rivers and lakes, and a few beavers and buffaloes have not
yet been driven from their ancient haunts. The waters teem with aligators,
tortoises, and fish, and their surface is covered with millions of
migratory waterfowl, which perform their annual voyage between the
Canadian lakes and the shores of the Mexican Gulf. The power of
man begins to be sensibly felt, and many parts of the wilderness to be
replaced by towns, orchards, and gardens. The gilded steamboats, like
moving palaces, stem the force of the current, or shoot rapidly down
the descending stream, through the solitudes of the forests and prairies.
Already does the flourishing population of the great valley far
exceed that of the thirteen United States when first they declared their
independence. Such is the state of a continent where trees and stones
are hurried annually by a thousand torrents, from the mountains to the
plains, and where sand and finer matter are swept down by a vast current
to the sea, together with the wreck of countless forests and the
275
bones of animals which perish in the inundations. When these materials
reach the gulf, they do not render the waters unfit for aquatic animals;
but on the contrary, the ocean here swarms with life, as it generally
does where the influx of a great river furnishes a copious supply
of organic and mineral matter. Yet many geologists, when they behold
the spoils of the land heaped in successive strata, and blended confusedly
with the remains of fishes, or interspersed with broken shells and
corals; when they see portions of erect trunks of trees with their roots
still retaining their natural position, and one tier of these preserved
in a fossil state above another, imagine that they are viewing the signs
of a turbulent instead of a tranquil and settled state of the planet.
They read in such phenomena the proof of chaotic disorder and reiterated
catastrophes, instead of indications of a surface as habitable as the
most delicious and fertile districts now tenanted by man.
Fig. 25.
Map of the Delta of the Ganges and Brahmapootra.
As an example of a still larger delta advancing upon the sea in opposition
to more powerful tides, I shall next describe that of the Ganges
and Brahmapootra (or Burrampooter). These, the two principal rivers
of India, descend from the highest mountains in the world, and partially
mingle their waters in the low plains of Hindostan, before reaching
the head of the Bay of Bengal. The Brahmapootra, somewhat the
larger of the two, formerly passed to the east of Dacca, even so lately
as the beginning of the present century, pouring most of its waters into
one of the numerous channels in the delta called "the Megna." By
276
that name the main stream was always spoken of by Rennell and others
in their memoirs on this region. But the main trunk now unites with
an arm of the Ganges considerably higher up, at a point about 100
miles distant from the sea; and it is constantly, according to Dr. Hooker,
working its way westward, having formerly, as may be seen by
ancient maps, moved eastward for a long period.
The area of the delta of the combined rivers, for it is impossible now
to distinguish what belongs to each, is considerably more than double
that of the Nile, even if we exclude from the delta a large extent of
low, flat, alluvial plain, doubtless of fluviatile origin, which stretches
more than 100 miles to the hills west of Calcutta (see map, fig. 25),
and much farther in a northerly direction beyond the head of the great
delta. The head of a delta is that point where the first arm is given off.
Above that point a river receives the waters of tributaries flowing from
higher levels; below it, on the contrary, it gives out portions of its
waters to lower levels, through channels which flow into adjoining
swamps, or which run directly to the sea. The Mississippi, as before
described, has a single head, which originated at an unknown period
when the Red River joined it. In the great delta of Bengal there may
be said to be two heads nearly equidistant from the sea, that of the
Ganges (G, map, fig. 25), about 30 miles below Rajmahal, or 216 statute
miles in a direct line from the sea, and that of the Brahmapootra
(B), below Chirapoonjee, where the river issues from the Khasia mountains,
a distance of 224 miles from the Bay of Bengal.
It will appear, by reference to the map, that the great body of fresh
water derived from the two rivers enters the bay on its eastern side;
and that a large part of the delta bordering on the sea is composed of
a labyrinth of rivers and creeks, all filled with salt water, except those
immediately communicating with the Hoogly, or principal arm of the
Ganges. This tract alone, known by the name of the Woods, or Sunderbunds
(more properly Soonderbuns), a wilderness infested by tigers
and crocodiles, is, according to Rennell, equal in extent to the whole
principality of Wales.369
On the sea-coast there are eight great openings, each of which has
evidently, at some ancient period, served in its turn as the principal
channel of discharge. Although the flux and reflux of the tide extend
even to the heads of the delta when the rivers are low, yet, when they
are periodically swollen by tropical rains, their volume and velocity
counteract the tidal current, so that, except very near the sea, the ebb
and flow become insensible. During the flood season, therefore, the
Ganges and Brahmapootra almost assume in their delta, the character of
rivers entering an inland sea; the movements of the ocean being then
subordinate to the force of the rivers, and only slightly disturbing their
operations. The great gain of the delta in height and area takes place
during the inundations; and, during other seasons of the year, the
277
ocean makes reprisals, scouring out the channels, and sometimes devouring
rich alluvial plains.
Islands formed and destroyed.—Major R. H. Colebrooke, in his
account of the course of the Ganges, relates examples of the rapid
filling up of some of its branches, and the excavation of new channels,
where the number of square miles of soil removed in a short time (the
column of earth being 114 feet high) was truly astonishing. Forty
square miles, or 25,600 acres, are mentioned as having been carried
away, in one place, in the course of a few years.370 The immense transportation
of earthy matter by the Ganges and Brahmapootra is proved
by the great magnitude of the islands formed in their channels during
a period far short of that of a man's life. Some of these, many miles
in extent, have originated in large sand-banks thrown up round the
points at the angular turning of the rivers, and afterwards insulated
by breaches of the streams. Others, formed in the main channel,
are caused by some obstruction at the bottom. A large tree, or a
sunken boat, is sometimes sufficient to check the current, and cause a
deposit of sand, which accumulates till it usurps a considerable portion
of the channel. The river then undermines its banks on each side, to
supply the deficiency in its bed, and the island is afterwards raised by
fresh deposits during every flood. In the great gulf below Luckipour,
formed by the united waters of the Ganges and Megna, some of the
islands, says Rennell, rival in size and fertility the Isle of Wight.
While the river is forming new islands in one part, it is sweeping away
old ones in others. Those newly formed are soon overrun with reeds,
long grass, the Tamarix Indica, and other shrubs, forming impenetrable
thickets, where the tiger, the rhinoceros, the buffalo, deer, and other
wild animals, take shelter. It is easy, therefore, to perceive, that both
animal and vegetable remains may occasionally be precipitated into the
flood, and become imbedded in the sediment which subsides in the delta.
Three or four species of crocodile, of two distinct sub-genera, abound
in the Ganges, and its tributary and contiguous waters; and Mr. H. T.
Colebrooke informed me, that he had seen both forms in places far
inland, many hundred miles from the sea. The Gangetic crocodile, or
Gavial (in correct orthography, Garial), is confined to the fresh water,
living exclusively on fish, but the commoner kinds, called Koomiah and
Muggar, frequent both fresh and salt, being much larger and fiercer in
salt and brackish water.371 These animals swarm in the brackish water
along the line of sand-banks, where the advance of the delta is most
rapid. Hundreds of them are seen together in the creeks of the delta,
278
or basking in the sun on the shoals without. They will attack men
and cattle, destroying the natives when bathing, and tame and wild
animals which come to drink. "I have not unfrequently," says Mr.
Colebrooke, "been witness to the horrid spectacle of a floating corpse
seized by a crocodile with such avidity, that he half emerged above the
water with his prey in his mouth." The geologist will not fail to observe
how peculiarly the habits and distribution of these saurians expose
them to become imbedded in the horizontal strata of fine mud, which
are annually deposited over many hundred square miles in the Bay of
Bengal. The inhabitants of the land, which happen to be drowned or
thrown into the water, are usually devoured by these voracious reptiles;
but we may suppose the remains of the saurians themselves to be continually
entombed in the new formations. The number, also, of bodies
of the poorer class of Hindoos thrown annually into the Ganges is so
great, that some of their bones or skeletons can hardly fail to be occasionally
enveloped in fluviatile mud.
It sometimes happens, at the season when the periodical flood is at
its height, that a strong gale of wind, conspiring with a high springtide,
checks the descending current of the river, and gives rise to most
destructive inundations. From this cause, in 1763, the waters at Luckipour
rose six feet above their ordinary level, and the inhabitants of a considerable
district, with their houses and cattle, were totally swept away.
The population of all oceanic deltas are particularly exposed to suffer
by such catastrophes, recurring at considerable intervals of time; and
we may safely assume that such tragical events have happened again
and again since the Gangetic delta was inhabited by man. If human
experience and forethought cannot always guard against these calamities,
still less can the inferior animals avoid them; and the monuments
of such disastrous inundations must be looked for in great abundance in
strata of all ages, if the surface of our planet has always been governed
by the same laws. When we reflect on the general order and tranquillity
that reigns in the rich and populous delta of Bengal, notwithstanding
the havoc occasionally committed by the depredations of the ocean,
we perceive how unnecessary it is to attribute the imbedding of successive
races of animals in older strata to extraordinary energy in the
causes of decay and reproduction in the infancy of our planet, or to those
general catastrophes and sudden revolutions so often resorted to.
Deposits in the delta.—The quantity of mud held in suspension by
the waters of the Ganges and Brahmapootra is found, as might be expected,
to exceed that of any of the rivers alluded to in this or the preceding
chapters; for, in the first place, their feeders flow from mountains
of unrivalled altitude, and do not clear themselves in any lakes,
as does the Rhine in the Lake of Constance, or the Rhone in that of Geneva.
And, secondly, their whole course is nearer the equator than that
of the Mississippi, or any great river, respecting which careful experiments
have been made, to determine the quantity of its water and
earthy contents. The fall of rain, moreover, as we have before seen, is
279
excessive on the southern flanks of the first range of mountains which
rise from the plains of Hindostan, and still more remarkable is the quantity
sometimes poured down in one day. (See above, p. 200.) The
sea, where the Ganges and Brahmapootra discharge their main stream at
the flood season, only recovers its transparency at the distance of from
60 to 100 miles from the delta; and we may take for granted that the
current continues to transport the finer particles much farther south
than where the surface water first becomes clear. The general slope,
therefore, of the new strata must be extremely gentle. According to
the best charts, there is a gradual deepening from four to about sixty
fathoms, as we proceed from the base of the delta to the distance of
about one hundred miles into the Bay of Bengal. At some few points
seventy, or even one hundred, fathoms are obtained at that distance.
One remarkable exception, however, occurs to the regularity of the
shape of the bottom. Opposite the middle of the delta, at the distance
of thirty or forty miles from the coast, a deep submarine valley occurs,
called the "swatch of no ground," about fifteen miles in diameter,
where soundings of 180, and even 300, fathoms fail to reach the
bottom. (See map, p. 275.) This phenomenon is the more extraordinary,
since the depression runs north to within five miles of the line of
shoals; and not only do the waters charged with sediment pass over
it continually, but, during the monsoons, the sea, loaded with mud and
sand, is beaten back in that direction towards the delta. As the mud
is known to extend for eighty miles farther into the gulf, an enormous
thickness of matter must have been deposited in "the swatch." We
may conclude, therefore, either that the original depth of this part of
the Bay of Bengal was excessive, or that subsidences have occurred in
modern times. The latter conjecture is the less improbable, as the
whole area of the delta has been convulsed in the historical era by
earthquakes, and actual subsidences have taken place in the neighboring
coast of Chittagong, while "the swatch" lies not far from the volcanic
band which connects Sumatra, Barren Island, and Ramree.372
Opposite the mouth of the Hoogly river, and immediately south of
Saugor Island, four miles from the nearest land of the delta, a new islet
was formed about twenty years ago, called Edmonstone Island, on the
centre of which a beacon was erected as a landmark in 1817. In 1818
the island had become two miles long and half a mile broad, and was
covered with vegetation and shrubs. Some houses were then built upon
it, and in 1820 it was used as a pilot station. The severe gale of 1823
divided it into two parts, and so reduced its size as to leave the beacon
standing out in the sea, where, after remaining seven years, it was washed
away. The islet in 1836 had been converted by successive storms into
a sand-bank, half a mile long, on which a sea-mark was placed.
Although there is evidence of gain at some points, the general progress
of the coast is very slow; for the tides, when the river water is
low, are actively employed in removing alluvial matter. In the Sunderbunds
280
the usual rise and fall of the tides is no more than eight feet,
but, on the east side of the delta, Dr. Hooker observed, in the winter of
1851, a rise of from sixty to eighty feet, producing among the islands at
the mouths of the Megna and Fenny rivers, a lofty wave or "bore" as
they ascend, and causing the river water to be ponded back, and then
to sweep down with great violence when the tide ebbs. The bay for
forty miles south of Chittagong is so fresh that neither algæ nor mangroves
will grow in it. We may, therefore, conceive how effective may
be the current formed by so great a volume of water in dispersing fine
mud over a wide area. Its power is sometimes augmented by the
agitation of the bay during hurricanes in the month of May. The new
superficial strata consists entirely of fine sand and mud; such, at least,
are the only materials which are exposed to view in regular beds on the
banks of the numerous creeks. Neither here or higher up the Ganges,
could Dr. Hooker discover any land or freshwater shells in sections of
the banks, which in the plains higher up sometimes form cliffs eighty
feet in height at low water. In like manner I have stated373 that I was
unable to find any buried shells in the delta or modern river cliffs of
the Mississippi.
No substance so coarse as gravel occurs in any part of the delta of
the Ganges and Brahmapootra, nor nearer the sea than 400 miles. Yet
it is remarkable that the boring of an Artesian well at Fort William,
near Calcutta, in the years 1835-1840, displayed, at the depth of 120
feet, clay and sand with pebbles. This boring was carried to a depth
of 481 feet below the level of Calcutta, and the geological section obtained
in the operation has been recorded with great care. Under the
surface soil, at a depth of about ten feet, they came to a stiff blue clay
about forty feet in thickness; below which was sandy clay, containing
in its lower portion abundance of decayed vegetable matter, which at
the bottom assumed the character of a stratum of black peat two feet
thick. This peaty mass was considered as a clear indication (like the
"dirt-bed" of Portland) of an ancient terrestrial surface, with a forest
or Sunderbund vegetation. Logs and branches of a red-colored wood
occur both above and immediately below the peat, so little altered that
Dr. Wallich was able to identify them with the Soondri tree, Heritiera
littoralis, one of the most prevalent forms, at the base of the delta. Dr.
Falconer tells me that similar peat has been met with at other points
round Calcutta at the depth of nine feet and twenty-five feet. It
appears, therefore, that there has been a sinking down of what was
originally land in this region, to the amount of seventy feet or more perpendicular;
for Calcutta is only a few feet above the level of the sea,
and the successive peat-beds seem to imply that the subsidence of the
ground was gradual or interrupted by several pauses. Below the vegetable
mass they entered upon a stratum of yellowish clay about ten feet
thick, containing horizontal layers of kunkar (or kankar), a nodular, concretionary,
argillaceous limestone, met with abundantly at greater or
281
less depths in all parts of the valley of the Ganges, over many thousand
square miles, and always presenting the same characters, even at a distance
of one thousand miles north of Calcutta. Some of this kunkar is
said to be of very recent origin in deposits formed by river inundations
near Saharanpoor. After penetrating 120 feet, they found loam containing
water-worn fragments of mica-slate and other kinds of rock,
which the current of the Ganges can no longer transport to this region.
In the various beds pierced through below, consisting of clay, marl,
and friable sandstone, with kunkar here and there intermixed, no organic
remains of decidedly marine origin were met with. Too positive a conclusion
ought not, it is true, to be drawn from such a fact, when we
consider the narrow bore of the auger and its effect in crushing shells
and bones. Nevertheless, it is worthy of remark, that the only fossils
obtained in a recognizable state were of a fluviatile or terrestrial character.
Thus, at the depth of 350 feet, the bony shell of a tortoise, or
trionyx, a freshwater genus, was found in sand, resembling the living
species of Bengal. From the same stratum, also, they drew up the lower
half of the humerus of a ruminant, at first referred to a hyæna. It was
the size and shape, says Dr. Falconer, of the shoulder-bone of the Cervus
porcinus, or common hog-deer, of India. At the depth of 380 feet,
clay with fragments of lacustrine shells was incumbent on what appears
clearly to have been another "dirt-bed," or stratum of decayed wood,
implying a period of repose of some duration, and a forest-covered land,
which must have subsided 300 feet, to admit of the subsequent superposition
of the overlying deposits. It has been conjectured that, at
the time when this area supported trees, the land extended much farther
out into the Bay of Bengal than now, and that in later times the
Ganges, while enlarging its delta, has been only recovering lost ground
from the sea.
At the depth of about 400 feet below the surface, an abrupt change
was observed in the character of the strata, which were composed in
great part of sand, shingle, and boulders, the only fossils observed being
the vertebræ of a crocodile, shell of a trionyx, and fragments of wood
very little altered, and similar to that buried in beds far above. These
gravelly beds constituted the bottom of the section at the depth of 481
feet, when the operations were discontinued, in consequence of an accident
which happened to the auger.
The occurrence of pebbles at the depths of 120 and 400 feet implies
an important change in the geographical condition of the region around
or near Calcutta. The fall of the river, or the general slope of the alluvial
plain may have been formerly greater; or, before a general and perhaps
unequal subsidence, hills once nearer the present base of the delta
may have risen several hundred feet, forming islands in the bay, which
may have sunk gradually, and become buried under fluviatile sediment.
Antiquity of the delta.—It would be a matter of no small scientific interest,
if experiments were made to enable us to determine, with some
degree of accuracy, the mean quantity of earthy matter discharged
annually282
into the sea by the united waters of the Ganges and Brahmapootra.
The Rev. Mr. Everest instituted, in 1831-2, a series of observations
on the earthy matter brought down by the Ganges, at Ghazepoor,
500 miles from the sea. He found that, in 1831, the number of cubic
feet of water discharged by the river per second at that place was,
during the


Rains (4 months)
494,208

Winter (5 months)
71,200

Hot weather (3 months)
36,330


so that we may state in round numbers that 500,000 cubic feet per
second flow down during the four months of the flood season, from
June to September, and less than 60,000 per second during the remaining
eight months.
The average quantity of solid matter suspended in the water during
the rains was, by weight, 1/428th part; but as the water is about one-half
the specific gravity of the dried mud, the solid matter discharged is
1/856th part in bulk, or 577 cubic feet per second. This gives a total of
6,082,041,600 cubic feet for the discharge in the 122 days of the rain.
The proportion of sediment in the waters at other seasons was comparatively
insignificant, the total amount during the five winter months being
only 247,881,600 cubic feet, and during the three months of hot weather
38,154,240 cubic feet. The total annual discharge, then, would be
6,368,077,440 cubic feet.
This quantity of mud would in one year raise a surface of 228½
square miles, or a square space, each side of which should measure 15
miles, a height of one foot. To give some idea of the magnitude of this
result, we will assume that the specific gravity of the dried mud is only
one-half that of granite (it would, however, be more); in that case, the
earthy matter discharged in a year would equal 3,184,038,720 cubic
feet of granite. Now about 12½ cubic feet of granite weigh one ton;
and it is computed that the great Pyramid of Egypt, if it were a solid
mass of granite, would weigh about 600,000,000 tons. The mass of
matter, therefore, carried down annually would, according to this estimate,
more than equal in weight and bulk forty-two of the great pyramids
of Egypt, and that borne down in the four months of the rains
would equal forty pyramids. But if, without any conjecture as to what
may have been the specific gravity of the mud, we attend merely to the
weight of solid matter actually proved by Mr. Everest to have been
contained in the water, we find that the number of tons weight which
passed down in the 122 days of the rainy season was 339,413,760,
which would give the weight of fifty-six pyramids and a half; and in
the whole year 355,361,464 tons, or nearly the weight of sixty pyramids.
The base of the great Pyramid of Egypt covers eleven acres, and its
perpendicular height is about five hundred feet. It is scarcely possible
to present any picture to the mind which will convey an adequate conception
of the mighty scale of this operation, so tranquilly and almost
insensibly carried on by the Ganges, as it glides through its alluvial
283
plain, even at a distance of 500 miles from the sea. It may, however,
be stated, that if a fleet of more than eighty Indiamen, each freighted
with about 1400 tons' weight of mud, were to sail down the river every
hour of every day and night for four months continuously, they would
only transport from the higher country to the sea a mass of solid matter
equal to that borne down by the Ganges, even in this part of its course,
in the four months of the flood season. Or the exertions of a fleet of
about 2000 such ships going down daily with the same burden, and
discharging it into the gulf, would be no more than equivalent to the
operations of the great river.
The most voluminous current of lava which has flowed from Etna
within historical times was that of 1669. Ferrara, after correcting
Borelli's estimate, calculated the quantity of cubic yards of lava in this
current at 140,000,000. Now, this would not equal in bulk one-fifth
of the sedimentary matter which is carried down in a single year by the
Ganges, past Ghazepoor, according to the estimate above explained; so
that it would require five grand eruptions of Etna to transfer a mass of
lava from the subterranean regions to the surface, equal in volume to
the mud carried down in one year to that place.
Captain R. Strachey, of the Bengal Engineers, has remarked to me,
not only that Ghazepoor, where Mr. Everest's observations were made,
is 500 miles from the sea, but that the Ganges has not been joined there
by its most important feeders. These drain upon the whole 750 miles
of the Himalaya, and no more than 150 miles of that mountain-chain
have sent their contributions to the main trunk at Ghazepoor. Below
that place, the Ganges is joined by the Gogra, Gunduk, Khosee, and
Teesta from the north, to say nothing of the Sone flowing from the
south, one of the largest of the rivers which rise in the table-land of
central India. (See map, fig. 25, p. 275.) Moreover the remaining 600
miles of the Himalaya comprise that eastern portion of the basin where
the rains are heaviest. (See above, p. 200.) The quantity of water
therefore carried down to the sea may probably be four or five times as
much as that which passes Ghazepoor.
The Brahmapootra, according to Major Wilcox,374 in the month of
January, when it is near its minimum, discharges 150,000 cubic feet of
water per second at Gwalpara, not many miles above the head of its
delta. Taking the proportions observed at Ghazepoor at the different
seasons as a guide, the probable average discharge of the Brahmapootra
for the whole year may be estimated at about the same as that of the
Ganges. Assuming this; and secondly, in order to avoid the risk of
exaggeration, that the proportion of sediment in their waters is about a
third less than Mr. Everest's estimate, the mud borne down to the Bay
of Bengal in one year would equal 40,000 millions of cubic feet, or between
six and seven times as much as that brought down to Ghazepoor,
according to Mr. Everest's calculations in 1831, and ten times as much
as that conveyed annually by the Mississippi to the Gulf of Mexico.
284
Captain Strachey estimates the annually inundated portion of the
delta at 250 miles in length by 80 in breadth, making an area of 20,000
square miles. The space south of this in the bay, where sediment is
thrown down, may be 300 miles from E. to W. by 150 N. and S., or
45,000 square miles, which, added to the former, gives a surface of
65,000 square miles, over which the sediment is spread out by the two
rivers. Suppose then the solid matter to amount to 40,000 millions of
cubic feet per annum, the deposit, he observes, must be continued for
forty-five years and three-tenths to raise the whole area a height of one
foot, or 13,600 years to raise it 300 feet; and this, as we have seen, is
much less than the thickness of the fluviatile strata actually penetrated,
(and the bottom not reached) by the auger at Calcutta.
Nevertheless we can by no means deduce from these data alone, what
will be the future rate of advance of the delta, nor even predict whether
the land will gain on the sea, or remain stationary. At the end of
13,000 years the bay may be less shallow than now, provided a moderate
depression, corresponding to that experienced in part of Greenland
for many centuries shall take place (see chap. 30). A subsidence quite
insensible to the inhabitants of Bengal, not exceeding two feet three
inches in a century, would be more than sufficient to counterbalance all
the efforts of the two mighty rivers to extend the limits of their delta.
We have seen that the Artesian borings at Calcutta attest, what the vast
depth of the "swatch" may also in all likelihood indicate, that the antagonist
force of subsidence has predominated for ages over the influx of
fluviatile mud, preventing it from raising the plains of Bengal, or from
filling up a larger portion of the bay.
CONCLUDING REMARKS ON DELTAS.
Convergence of deltas.—If we possessed an accurate series of maps
of the Adriatic for many thousand years, our retrospect would, without
doubt, carry us gradually back to the time when the number of rivers
descending from the mountains into that gulf by independent deltas was
far greater in number. The deltas of the Po and the Adige, for instance,
would separate themselves within the recent era, as, in all probability,
would those of the Isonzo and the Torre. If, on the other hand, we
speculate on future changes, we may anticipate the period when the
number of deltas will greatly diminish; for the Po cannot continue to
encroach at the rate of a mile in a hundred years, and other rivers to
gain as much in six or seven centuries upon the shallow gulf, without
new junctions occurring from time to time; so that Eridanus, "the king
of rivers," will continually boast a greater number of tributaries. The
Ganges and the Brahmapootra have perhaps become partially confluent
in the same delta within the historical, or at least within the human era;
and the date of the junction of the Red River and the Mississippi would,
in all likelihood, have been known, if America had not been so recently
discovered. The union of the Tigris and the Euphrates must undoubtedly
have been one of the modern geographical changes of our Earth,
285
for Col. Rawlinson informs me that the delta of those rivers has advanced
two miles in the last sixty years, and is supposed to have encroached
about forty miles upon the Gulf of Persia in the course of the last twenty-five
centuries.
When the deltas of rivers, having many mouths, converge, a partial
union at first takes place by the confluence of some one or more of their
arms; but it is not until the main trunks are connected above the head
of the common delta, that a complete intermixture of their joint waters
and sediment takes place. The union, therefore, of the Po and Adige,
and of the Ganges and Brahmapootra, is still incomplete. If we reflect
on the geographical extent of surface drained by rivers such as now enter
the Bay of Bengal, and then consider how complete the blending
together of the greater part of their transported matter has already become,
and throughout how vast a delta it is spread by numerous arms,
we no longer feel so much surprise at the area occupied by some ancient
formations of homogeneous mineral composition. But our surprise will
be still farther lessened, when we afterwards inquire (ch. 21) into the
action of tides and currents in disseminating sediment.
Age of existing deltas.—If we could take for granted, that the relative
level of land and sea had remained stationary ever since all the existing
deltas began to be formed—could we assume that their growth
commenced at one and the same instant when the present continents
acquired their actual shape—we might understand the language of
geologists who speak of "the epoch of existing continents." They endeavor
to calculate the age of deltas from this imaginary fixed period;
and they calculate the gain of new land upon the sea, at the mouths of
rivers, as having begun everywhere simultaneously. But the more we
study the history of deltas, the more we become convinced that upward
and downward movements of the land and contiguous bed of the sea
have exerted, and continue to exert, an influence on the physical geography
of many hydrographical basins, on a scale comparable in magnitude
or importance to the amount of fluviatile deposition effected in an
equal lapse of time. In the basin of the Mississippi, for example, proofs
both of descending and ascending movements to a vertical amount of
several hundred feet can be shown to have taken place since the existing
species of land and freshwater shells lived in that region.375
The deltas also of the Po and Ganges have each, as we have seen (p.
257), when probed by the Artesian auger, borne testimony to a gradual
subsidence of land to the extent of several hundred feet—old terrestrial
surfaces, turf, peat, forest-land, and "dirt-beds," having been pierced at
various depths. The changes of level at the mouth of the Indus in
Cutch (see below, chap. 27), and those of New Madrid in the valley of
the Mississippi (see p. 270, and chap. 27), are equally instructive, as
demonstrating unceasing fluctuations in the levels of those areas into
which running water is transporting sediment. If, therefore, the exact
286
age of all modern deltas could be known, it is scarcely probable that
we should find any two of them in the world to have coincided in date,
or in the time when their earliest deposits originated.
Grouping of strata in deltas.—The changes which have taken place
in deltas, even within the times of history, may suggest many important
considerations in regard to the manner in which subaqueous sediment is
distributed. With the exception of some cases hereafter to be noticed,
there are some general laws of arrangement which must evidently hold
good in almost all the lakes and seas now filling up. If a lake, for example,
be encircled on two sides by lofty mountains, receiving from
them many rivers and torrents of different sizes, and if it be bounded
on the other sides, where the surplus waters issue, by a comparatively
low country, it is not difficult to define some of the leading geological
features which must characterize the lacustrine formation, when this
basin shall have been gradually converted into dry land by the influx of
sediment. The strata would be divisible into two principal groups: the
older comprising those deposits which originated on the side adjoining
the mountains, where numerous deltas first began to form; and the
newer group consisting of beds deposited in the more central parts of
the basin, and towards the side farthest from the mountains. The following
characters would form the principal marks of distinction between
the strata in each series:—The more ancient system would be composed,
for the most part, of coarser materials, containing many beds of pebbles
and sand, often of great thickness, and sometimes dipping at a considerable
angle. These, with associated beds of finer ingredients, would, if
traced round the borders of the basin, be seen to vary greatly in color
and mineral composition, and would also be very irregular in thickness.
The beds, on the contrary, in the newer group, would consist of finer
particles, and would be horizontal, or very slightly inclined. Their
color and mineral composition would be very homogeneous throughout
large areas, and would differ from almost all the separate beds in the
older series.
The following causes would produce the diversity here alluded to between
the two great members of such lacustrine formations:—When
the rivers and torrents first reach the edge of the lake, the detritus
washed down by them from the adjoining heights sinks at once into
deep water, all the heavier pebbles and sand subsiding near the shore.
The finer mud is carried somewhat farther out, but not to the distance
of many miles, for the greater part may be seen, as, for example, where
the Rhone enters the Lake of Geneva, to fall down in clouds to the
bottom, not far from the river's mouth. Thus alluvial tracts are soon
formed at the mouths of every torrent and river, and many of these in
the course of ages become of considerable extent. Pebbles and sand
are then transported farther from the mountains; but in their passage
they decrease in size by attrition, and are in part converted into mud
and sand. At length some of the numerous deltas, which are all directed
towards a common centre, approach near to each other; those
287
of adjoining torrents become united, and each is merged, in its turn, in
the delta of the largest river, which advances most rapidly into the lake,
and renders all the minor streams, one after the other, its tributaries.
The various mineral ingredients of all are thus blended together into
one homogeneous mixture, and the sediment is poured out from a common
channel into the lake.
As the average size of the transported particles decreases, while the
force and volume of the main river augments, the newer deposits are
diffused continually over a wider area, and are consequently more horizontal
than the older. When at first there were many independent
deltas near the borders of the basin, their separate deposits differed entirely
from each other; one may have been charged, like the Arve
where it joins the Rhone, with white sand and sediment derived from
granite—another may have been black, like many streams in the Tyrol,
flowing from the waste of decomposing rocks of dark slate—a third
may have been colored by ochreous sediment, like the Red River in
Louisiana—a fourth, like the Elsa in Tuscany, may have held much
carbonate of lime in solution. At first they would each form distinct
deposits of sand, gravel, limestone, marl, or other materials; but, after
their junction, new chemical combinations and a distinct color would be
the result, and the particles, having been conveyed ten, twenty, or a
greater number of miles over alluvial plains, would become finer.
In those deltas where the tides and strong marine currents interfere,
the above description would only be applicable, with certain modifications.
If a series of earthquakes accompany the growth of a delta, and
change the levels of the land from time to time, as in the region where
the Indus now enters the sea, the phenomena will depart still more
widely from the ordinary type. If, after a protracted period of rest, a
delta sinks down, pebbles may be borne along in shallow water near the
foot of the boundary hills, so as to form conglomerates overlying the
fine mud previously thrown into deeper water in the same area.
Causes of stratification in deltas.—The stratified arrangement, which
is observed to prevail so generally in aqueous deposits, is most frequently
due to variations in the velocity of running water, which cannot
sweep along particles of more than a certain size and weight when
moving at a given rate. Hence, as the force of the stream augments or
decreases, the materials thrown down in successive layers at particular
places are rudely sorted, according to their dimensions, form, and specific
gravity. Where this cause has not operated, as where sand, mud,
and fragments of rock are conveyed by a glacier, a confused heap of
rubbish devoid of all stratification is produced.
Natural divisions are also occasioned in deltas, by the interval of time
which separates annually the deposition of matter during the periodical
rains, or melting of snow upon the mountains. The deposit of each
year may acquire some degree of consistency before that of the succeeding
year is superimposed. A variety of circumstances also give rise
annually, or sometimes from day to day, to slight variations in color,
288
fineness of the particles, and other characters, by which alternations of
strata distinct in texture and mineral ingredients must be produced.
Thus, for example, at one period of the year, drift-wood may be carried
down, and, at another, mud, as was before stated to be the case in the
delta of the Mississippi; or at one time, when the volume and velocity
of the stream are greatest, pebbles and sand may be spread over a certain
area, over which, when the waters are low, fine matter or chemical
precipitates are formed. During inundations, the turbid current of
fresh water often repels the sea for many miles; but when the river
is low, salt water again occupies the same space. When two deltas are
converging, the intermediate space is often, for reasons before explained,
alternately the receptacle of different sediments derived from the converging
streams (see p. 272). The one is, perhaps, charged with calcareous,
the other with argillaceous matter; or one sweeps down sand
and pebbles, the other impalpable mud. These differences may be
repeated with considerable regularity, until a thickness of hundreds of
feet of alternating beds is accumulated. The multiplication, also, of
shells and corals in particular spots, and for limited periods, gives rise
occasionally to lines of separation, and divides a mass which might
otherwise be homogeneous into distinct strata.
An examination of the shell marl now forming in the Scotch lakes, or
the sediment termed "warp," which subsides from the muddy water of
the Humber and other rivers, shows that recent deposits are often composed
of a great number of extremely thin layers, either even or slightly
undulating, and preserving a general parallelism to the planes of stratification.
Sometimes, however, the laminæ in modern strata are disposed
diagonally at a considerable angle, which appears to take place
where there are conflicting movements in the waters. In January, 1829,
I visited, in company with Professor L. A. Necker, of Geneva, the confluence
of the Rhone and Arve, when those rivers were very low, and
were cutting channels through the vast heaps of débris thrown down
from the waters of the Arve in the preceding spring. One of the sandbanks
which had formed, in the spring of 1828, where the opposing
currents of the two rivers neutralized each other, and caused a retardation
in the motion, had been undermined; and the following is an exact
representation of the arrangement of laminæ exposed in a vertical section.
The length of the portion here seen is about twelve feet, and the
height five. The strata A A consist of irregular alternations of pebbles
and sand in undulating beds: below these are seams of very fine sand
B B, some as thin as paper, others about a quarter of an inch thick. The
strata C C are composed of layers of fine greenish-gray sand as thin as
paper. Some of the inclined beds will be seen to be thicker at their
upper, others at their lower extremity, the inclination of some being
very considerable. These layers must have accumulated one on the
other by lateral apposition, probably when one of the rivers was very
gradually increasing or diminishing in velocity, so that the point of
greatest retardation caused by their conflicting currents shifted slowly,
289
allowing the sediment to be thrown down in successive layers on a
sloping bank. The same phenomenon is exhibited in older strata of all
ages.376
Fig. 26.
Section of a sand-bank in the bed of the Arve at its confluence with the Rhone, showing the
stratification of deposits where currents meet.
If the bed of a lake or of the sea be sinking, whether at a uniform or
an unequal rate, or oscillating in level during the deposition of sediment,
these movements will give rise to a different class of phenomena, as, for
example, to repeated alternations of shallow-water and deep-water deposits,
each with peculiar organic remains, or to frequent repetitions of
similar beds, formed at a uniform depth, and inclosing the same organic
remains, and to other results too complicated and varied to admit of
enumeration here.
Formation of conglomerates.—Along the base of the Maritime Alps,
between Toulon and Genoa, the rivers, with few exceptions, are now
forming strata of conglomerate and sand. Their channels are often several
miles in breadth, some of them being dry, and the rest easily forded
for nearly eight months in the year, whereas during the melting of the
snow they are swollen, and a great transportation of mud and pebbles
takes place. In order to keep open the main road from France to Italy,
now carried along the sea-coast, it is necessary to remove annually great
masses of shingle brought down during the flood season. A portion of
the pebbles are seen in some localities, as near Nice, to form beds of
shingle along the shore, but the greater part are swept into a deep sea.
The small progress made by the deltas of minor rivers on this coast
need not surprise us, when we recollect that there is sometimes a depth
of two thousand feet at a few hundred yards from the beach, as near
Nice. Similar observations might be made respecting a large proportion
of the rivers in Sicily, and among others, respecting that which,
immediately north of the port of Messina, hurries annually vast masses
of granitic pebbles into the sea.
Constant interchange of land and sea.—I may here conclude my remarks
on deltas, observing that, imperfect as is our information of the
changes which they have undergone within the last three thousand
years, they are sufficient to show how constant an interchange of sea
290
and land is taking place on the face of our globe. In the Mediterranean
alone, many flourishing inland towns, and a still greater number of ports,
now stand where the sea rolled its waves since the era of the early civilization
of Europe. If we could compare with equal accuracy the ancient
and actual state of all the islands and continents, we should probably
discover that millions of our race are now supported by lands situated
where deep seas prevailed in earlier ages. In many districts not
yet occupied by man, land animals and forests now abound where ships
once sailed; and, on the other hand, we shall find, on inquiry, that inroads
of the ocean have been no less considerable. When to these revolutions,
produced by aqueous causes, we add analogous changes
wrought by igneous agency, we shall, perhaps, acknowledge the justice
of the conclusion of Aristotle, who declared that the whole land and
sea on our globe periodically changed places.377
</div></body></text></TEI>