<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="34">

CHAPTER IX.
Of the Establishment of the Law of Universal Gravitation.


THE doctrine of universal gravitation is a feature of so
much importance in the history of science that we shall not
pass it by without a few remarks on the nature and evidence
of the doctrine.
1. To a certain extent the doctrine of the attraction of
bodies according to the law of the inverse square of the
distance, exhibits in its progress among men the same
general features which we have noticed in the history of the
laws of motion. This doctrine was maintained à priori
on the ground of its simplicity, and was asserted
positively, even before it was clearly
understood:—notwithstanding this anticipation, its
establishment on the ground of facts was a task of vast
labour and sagacity:—when it had been so established in a
general way, there occurred at later periods, an occasional
suspicion that it might be approximately true only:—these
suspicions led to further researches, which showed the rule
to be rigorously exact:—and at present there are
mathematicians who maintain, not only that it is true, but
that it is a necessary property of matter. A very few words
on each of these points will suffice.
2. I have shown in the History of Science41, that
the attraction of the sun according to the inverse square of
the distance, had been divined by Bullialdus, Hooke, Halley,
and others, before it was proved by Newton. Probably the
reason which suggested this conjecture was, that gravity
might be considered 273 as a sort of emanation; and that
thus, like light or any other effect diffused from a center,
it must follow the law just stated, the efficacy of the
force being weakened in receding from the center, exactly in
proportion to the space through which it is diffused. It
cannot be denied that such a view appears to be strongly
recommended by analogy.</div></body></text></TEI>