<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="98">CHAPTER V.
Chemistry of Gases.—Black.
Cavendish.
THE study of the properties of
aëriform substances, or Pneumatic Chemistry, as it was called,
occupied the chemists of the eighteenth century, and was the main
occasion of the great advances which the science made at that period.
The most material general truths which came into view in the course of
these researches, were, that gases were to be numbered among the
constituent elements of solid and fluid bodies; and that, in these, as
in all other cases of composition, the compound was equal to the sum
of its elements. The latter proposition, indeed, cannot be looked upon
as a discovery, for it had been frequently acknowledged, though little
applied; in fact, it could not be referred to with any advantage, till
the aëriform elements, as well as others, were taken into the account.
As soon as this was done, it produced a revolution in chemistry.
[2nd Ed.] [Though the view of the mode in which gaseous elements
become fixed in bodies and determine their properties, had great
additional light thrown upon it by Dr. Black’s discoveries, as we
shall see, the notion that solid bodies involve such gaseous elements
was not new at that period. Mr. Vernon Harcourt has shown16 that Newton and Boyle admitted into
their speculations airs of various kinds, capable of fixation in
bodies. I have, in the succeeding chapter (chap.
vi.), spoken of the views of Rey, Hooke, and Mayow, connected with
the function of airs in chemistry, and forming a prelude to the Oxygen
Theory.]
16 Phil. Mag. 1846.
Notwithstanding these preludes, the credit of the first great step
in pneumatic chemistry is, with justice, assigned to Dr. Black,
afterwards professor at Edinburgh, but a young man of the age of
twenty-four at the time when he made his discovery.17 He found that the difference between
caustic lime and common limestone arose from this, that the latter
substance consists of the former, combined with a certain air, which,
being thus fixed in the solid body, he called fixed air
(carbonic 273 acid
gas). He found, too, that magnesia, caustic potash, and caustic soda,
would combine with the same air, with similar results. This discovery
consisted, of course, in a new interpretation of observed changes.
Alkalies appeared to be made caustic by contact with quicklime: at
first Black imagined that they underwent this change by acquiring
igneous matter from the quicklime; but when he perceived that the lime
gained, not lost, in magnitude as it became mild, he rightly supposed
that the alkalies were rendered caustic by imparting their air to the
lime. This discovery was announced in Black’s inaugural dissertation,
pronounced in 1755, on the occasion of his taking his degree of Doctor
in the University of Edinburgh.
17 Thomson’s Hist. Chem. i.
317.
The chemistry of airs was pursued by other experimenters. The
Honorable Henry Cavendish, about 1765, invented an apparatus, in which
aërial fluids are confined by water, so that they can be managed and
examined. This hydro-pneumatic apparatus, or as it is sometimes
called, the pneumatic trough, from that time was one of the
most indispensable parts of the chemist’s apparatus. Cavendish,18 in 1766, showed the identity of the
properties of fixed air derived from various sources; and pointed out
the peculiar qualities of inflammable air (afterwards called
hydrogen gas), which, being nine times lighter than common air, soon
attracted general notice by its employment for raising balloons. The
promise of discovery which this subject now offered, attracted the
confident and busy mind of Priestley, whose Experiments and
Observations on different kinds of Air appeared in 1744–79.
In these volumes, he describes an extraordinary number of trials of
various kinds; the results of which were, the discovery of new kinds
of air, namely, phlogisticated air (azotic gas), nitrous
air (nitrous gas), and dephlogisticated air (oxygen
gas).
18 Phil. Trans. 1766.
But the discovery of new substances, though valuable in supplying
chemistry with materials, was not so important as discoveries
respecting their modes of composition. Among such discoveries, that of
Cavendish, published in the Philosophical Transactions for
1784, and disclosing the composition of water by the union of two
gases, oxygen and hydrogen, must be considered as holding a most
distinguished place. He states,19 that his
“experiments were made principally with a view to find out the cause
of the diminution which common air is well known to suffer, by all the
various ways in which it is phlogisticated.” And, after describing
various unsuccessful attempts, he finds 274 that when inflammable air is used in
this phlogistication (or burning), the diminution of the common air is
accompanied by the formation of a dew in the apparatus.20 And thus he infers21 that “almost
all the inflammable air, and one-fifth of the common air, are turned
into pure water.”
19 Phil. Trans. 1784, p.
119.
20 Phil. Trans. 1784, p.
128.
21 Ib. p. 129.
Lavoisier, to whose researches this result was, as we shall soon
see, very important, was employed in a similar attempt at the same
time (1783), and had already succeeded,22 when he learned
from Dr. Blagden, who was present at the experiment, that Cavendish
had made the discovery a few months sooner. Monge had, about the same
time, made the same experiments, and communicated the result to
Lavoisier and Laplace immediately afterwards. The synthesis was soon
confirmed by a corresponding analysis. Indeed the discovery
undoubtedly lay in the direct path of chemical research at the time.
It was of great consequence in the view it gave of experiments in
composition; for the small quantity of water produced in many such
processes, had been quite overlooked; though, as it now appeared, this
water offered the key to the whole interpretation of the change.
22 A. P. 1781, p. 472
Though some objections to Mr. Cavendish’s view were offered by
Kirwan,23 on the whole they were generally
received with assent and admiration. But the bearing of these
discoveries upon the new theory of Lavoisier, who rejected phlogiston,
was so close, that we cannot further trace the history of the subject
without proceeding immediately to that theory.
23 P. T. 1784, p. 154.
[2nd Ed.] [I have elsewhere stated,24—with
reference to recent attempts to deprive Cavendish of the credit of his
discovery of the composition of water, and to transfer it to
Watt,—that Watt not only did not anticipate, but did not fully
appreciate the discovery of Cavendish and Lavoisier; and I have
expressed my concurrence with Mr. Vernon Harcourt’s views, when he
says,25 that “Cavendish pared off from the
current hypotheses their theory of combustion, and their affinities of
imponderable for ponderable matter, as complicating chemical with
physical considerations; and he then corrected and adjusted them with
admirable skill to the actual phenomena, not binding the facts to the
theory, but adapting the theory to the facts.”
24 Philosophy, b. vi. c.
4.
25 Address to the British
Association, 1839.
I conceive that the discussion which the subject has recently
received, has left no doubt on the mind of any one who has perused the
275 documents, that
Cavendish is justly entitled to the honor of this discovery, which in
his own time was never contested. The publication of his Journals of
Experiments26 shows that he succeeded in establishing
the point in question in July, 1781. His experiments are referred to
in an abstract of a paper of Priestley’s, made by Dr. Maty, the
secretary of the Royal Society, in June, 1783. In June, 1783, also,
Dr. Blagden communicated the result of Cavendish’s experiments to
Lavoisier, at Paris. Watt’s letter, containing his hypothesis that
“water is composed of dephlogisticated air and phlogiston deprived of
part of their latent or elementary heat; and that phlogisticated or
pure air is composed of water deprived of its phlogiston and united to
elementary heat and light,” was not read till Nov. 1783; and even if
it could have suggested such an experiment as Cavendish’s (which does
not appear likely), is proved, by the dates, to have had no share in
doing so.
26 Appendix to Mr. V.
Harcourt’s Address
Mr. Cavendish’s experiment was suggested by an experiment in which
Warltire, a lecturer on chemistry at Birmingham, exploded a mixture of
hydrogen and common air in a close vessel, in order to determine
whether heat were ponderable.]
</div></body></text></TEI>