<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="3">NATURE OF THE ARGUMENT.
 THE notions we acquire of contrivance and design arise from comparing our
 observations on the works of other beings with the intentions of which we are
 conscious in our own undertakings. We take the highest and best of human faculties,
 and, exalting them in our imagination to an unlimited extent, endeavour to attain
 an imperfect conception of that Infinite Power which created every thing around
 us. In pursuing this course, it is evident that we are liable to impress upon
 the
[page] 24
 notion of Deity thus shadowed out,
 many traces of those imperfections in our own limited faculties which are best
 known to those who have most deeply cultivated them. It is also evident that
 all those discoveries which arm human reason with new power, and all additions
 to our acquaintance with the material world, must from time to time render a
 revision of that notion necessary. The present seems to be a fit occasion for
 such a revision. Many excellent and religious persons not deeply versed in what
 they mistakenly call "human knowledge" but which is in truth the interpretation
 of those laws that God himself has impressed on his creation, have endeavoured
 to discover proofs of design in a multitude of apparent adaptations of means
 to ends, and have represented the Deity as perpetually interfering, to alter
 for a time the laws he had previously ordained; thus by implication denying
 to him the possession
[page] 25
 of that foresight which is the
 highest attribute of omnipotence. Minds of this order, insensible of the existence
 of that combining and generalising faculty which gives to human intellect its
 greatest development, and tied down by the trammels of their peculiar pursuits,
 have in their mistaken zeal not erceived their own unfitness for the mighty
 task, and have ventured to represent the Creator of the universe as fettered
 by the same infirmities as those by which their own limited faculties are subjugated.
 To causes of this kind must in some measure be attributed an opinion which has
 been industriously spread, that minds highly imbued with mathematical knowledge
 are disqualified, by the possession of that knowledge, and by the habits of
 mind produced during its acquisition, from rightly appreciating the works of
 the Creator. At periods and in countries in which the knowledge of the priests
 exceeded that of the people, science has always been held up by the
[page] 26
 former class as an object of regard,
 and its crafty possessors have too frequently defiled its purity by employing
 their knowledge for the delusion of the people. On the other hand, at times
 and in countries in which the knowledge of the people has advanced beyond that
 of the priesthood, the ministers of the temple have too often been afraid of
 the advance of knowledge, and have threatened with the displeasure of the Almighty
 those engaged in employing the faculties he has bestowed on the study of the
 works he has created. At the present period, when knowledge is so universally
 spread that neither class is far in advance of the other,—when every subject
 is submitted to unbounded discussion,—when it is at length fully acknowledged
 that truth alone can stand unshaken by perennial attacks, and that error, though
 for centuries triumphant, must fall at last, and leave behind no ashes from
 which it may revive, the authority of names has but little weight: facts and
 arguments are the basis of
[page] 27
 creeds, and convictions so arrived
 at are the more deeply seated, and the more enduring, because they are not the 
 wild fancies of passion or of impulse, but the deliberate results of reason
 and reflection. It is a condition of our race that we must ever wade through
 error in our advance towards truth; and it may even be said that in many cases
 we exhaust almost every variety of error before we attain the desired goal.
 But those truths, once reached by such a course, are always most highly valued; and when, in addition to this, they have been exposed to every variety of
 attack which splendid talents quickened into energy by the keen perception of
 personal interests can suggest,—when they have revived undying from unmerited
 neglect; when the anathema of spiritual, and the arm of secular power have been
 found as impotent in suppressing, as arguments were in refuting them, then they
 are indeed irresistible. Thus tried and
[page] 28
 thus triumphant in the fiercest
 warfare of intellectual strife, even the temporary interests and furious passions
 which urge on the contest, contribute in no small measure to establish their
 value, and thus to render these truths the permanent heritage of our race. Viewed
 in this light, the propagation of an error, although it may be unfavourable
 or fatal to the temporary interest of an individual, can never be long injurious
 to the cause of truth. It may, at a particular period, retard its progress for
 a while, but it repays the transitory injury by a benefit as permanent as the
 duration of the truth to which it was opposed. These reflections are offered
 for the purpose of proving that the toleration of the fullest discussion is
 most advantageous to truth. They are not offered as the apology for error;
 and whilst it is admitted that every person who wilfully puts forward arguments
 the soundness of which he doubts, incurs a deep responsibility, it is some satisfaction
 to
[page] 29
 reflect that the delay likely to
 be thus occasioned to the great cause can be but small; and that those who
 in sincerity of heart maintain arguments which a more advanced state of knowledge
 shall prove to be erroneous, may yet ultimately contribute, by their very publication,
 to the speedier establishment of truth.
[page] 30</div></body></text></TEI>