<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="39">
CHAPTER VII.

On Final Causes.

We have pointed out a great number of instances
where the mode in which the arrangements of nature
produce their effect, suggests, as we conceive,
the belief that this effect is to be considered as the
end and purpose of these arrangements. The impression
which thus arises, of design and intention
exercised in the formation of the world, or of the
reality of Final Causes, operates on men’s minds so
generally, and increases so constantly on every additional
examination of the phenomena of the universe,
that we cannot but suppose such a belief to
have a deep and stable foundation. And we conceive
that in several of the comparatively few cases
in which such a belief has been rejected, the averseness
to it has arisen from the influence of some of
the causes mentioned in the last chapter; the exclusive
pursuit, namely, of particular trains and modes
of reasoning, till the mind becomes less capable of
forming the conceptions and making the exertions
which are requisite for the apprehension of truths
not included among its usual subjects of thought.
[258]
1. This seems to be the case with those who maintain
that purpose and design cannot be inferred or
deduced from the arrangements which we see around
us by any process of reasoning. We can reason
from effects to causes, say such writers, only in cases
where we know something of the nature of the cause.
We can infer from the works of men, the existence
of design and purpose, because we know, from past
observation, what kind of works human design and
purpose can produce. But the universe, considered
as the work of God, cannot be compared with any
corresponding work, or judged of by any analogy
with known examples. How then can we, in this
case, they ask, infer design and purpose in the artist
of the universe? On what principles, on what axioms,
can we proceed, which shall include this necessarily
singular instance, and thus give legitimacy and validity
to our reasonings?
What has already been said on the subject of the
two different processes by which we obtain principles,
and by which we reason from them, will suggest
the reply to these questions. When we collect
design and purpose from the arrangements of the
universe, we do not arrive at our conclusion by a
train of deductive reasoning, but by the conviction
which such combinations as we perceive immediately
and directly impress upon the mind. “Design
must have had a designer.” But such a principle
can be of no avail to one whom the contemplation
or the description of the world does not impress with
the perception of design. It is not, therefore, at the
end, but at the beginning of our syllogisms, not
among remote conclusions, but among original principles,
that we must place the truth, that such arrangements,
manifestations, and proceedings as we
behold about us imply a Being endowed with consciousness,
design, and will, from whom they proceed.
This is inevitably the mode in which such a conviction
is acquired; and that it is so, we may the
more readily believe, when we consider that it is the[259]
case with the design and will which we ascribe to
man, no less than in that which we believe to exist
in God. At first sight we might perhaps be tempted
to say, that we infer design and purpose from the
works of man in one case, because we have known
these attributes in other cases produce effects in some
measure similar. But to this we must reply, by asking
how we come to know the existence of human
design and purpose at first, and at all? What we
see around us are certain appearances, things, successions
of events; how come we ever to ascribe to
other men the thought and will of which we are conscious
ourselves? How do we come to believe that
there are other men? How are we led to elevate,
in our conceptions, some of the objects which we
perceive into persons? No doubt their actions, their
words induce us to do this. We see that the manifestations
which we observe must be so understood,

and not otherwise. We feel that such actions, such
events must be connected by consciousness and
personality; that the actions are not the actions of
things, but of persons; not necessary and without
significance, like the falling of a stone, but voluntary
and with purpose like what we do ourselves. But
this is not a result of reasoning: we do not infer this
from any similar case which we have known; since
we are now speaking of the first conception of a will
and purpose different from our own. In arriving at
such knowledge, we are aided only by our own consciousness
of what thought, purpose, will, are: and
possessing this regulative principle, we so decipher
and interpret the complex appearances which surround
us, that we receive irresistibly the persuasion
of the existence of other men, with thought and will
and purpose like our own. And just in the same
manner, when we examine attentively the adjustment
of the parts of the human frame to each other
and to the elements, the relation of the properties of
the earth to those of its inhabitants, or of the physical
to the moral nature of man, the thought must[260]
arise and cling to our perceptions, however little it
be encouraged, that this system, every where so full
of wonderful combinations, suited to the preservation,
and well-being of living creatures, is also the expression
of the intention, wisdom, and goodness of a personal
creator and governor.
We conceive then that it is so far from being an
unsatisfactory or unphilosophical process by which
we collect the existence of a Deity from the works
of creation, that the process corresponds most closely
with that on which rests the most steadfast of our
convictions, next to that of our own existence, the
belief of the existence of other human beings. If
any one ever went so far in scepticism as to doubt
the existence of any other person than himself, he
might, so far as the argument from final causes is
concerned, reject the being of God as well as that of
man; but, without dwelling on the possibility of such
fantasies, when we consider how impossible it is for
men in general not to attribute personality, purpose,
thought, will to each other, in virtue of certain combinations
of appearances and actions, we must deem
them most consistent and reasonable in attributing
also personality and purpose to God, in virtue of the
whole assemblage of appearances and actions which
constitute the universe, full as it is of combinations
from which such a suggestion springs. The vividness,
the constancy of the belief of a wise and good
Being, thus governing the world, may be different in
different men, according to their habit of directing
their thoughts to the subject; but such a belief is
undoubtedly capable of becoming lively and steadfast
in the highest degree. It has been entertained and
cherished by enlightened and well-regulated minds
in all ages; and has been, at least since the rise of
Christianity, not only the belief, but a pervading
and ruling principle of action of many men, and of
whole communities. The idea may be rendered
more faint by turning the mind away from it, and
perhaps by indulging too exclusively in abstract and[261]
general speculations. It grows stronger by an actual
study of the details of the creation; and, as regards
the practical consequences of such a belief, by a
habit of referring our actions and hopes to such a
Governor. In this way it is capable of becoming as
real and fixed an impression as that of a human
friend and master; and all that we can learn, by
observing the course of men’s feelings and actions,
tends to convince us, that this belief of the being
and presence and government of God, leads to the
most elevated and beneficial frame of mind of which
man is capable.
2. How natural and almost inevitable is this persuasion
of the reality of Final Causes and consequent
belief in the personality of the Deity, we may gather
by observing how constantly it recurs to the
thoughts, even of those who, in consequence of
such peculiarities of mental discipline as have been
described, have repelled and resisted the impression.
Thus, Laplace, of whom we have already spoken,
as one of the greatest mathematicians of modern
times, expresses his conviction that the supposed evidence
of final causes will disappear as our knowledge
advances, and that they only seem to exist in
those cases where our ignorance leaves room for
such a mistake. “Let us run over,” he says, “the
history of the progress of the human mind and its
errors: we shall perpetually see final causes pushed
away to the bounds of its knowledge. These causes,
which Newton removed to the limits of the solar
system, were not long ago conceived to obtain in
the atmosphere, and employed in explaining meteors:
they are, therefore, in the eyes of the philosopher
nothing more than the expression of the ignorance
in which we are of the real causes.”
We may observe that we have endeavoured to
give a very different, and, as we believe, a far truer
view of the effect which philosophy has produced on
our knowledge of final causes. We have shown,
we trust, that the notion of design and end is transferred[262]
by the researches of science, not from the
domain of our knowledge to that of our ignorance,
but merely from the region of facts to that of laws.
We hold that, in this form, final causes in the atmosphere
are still to be conceived to obtain, no less
than in an earlier state of meteorological knowledge;
and that Newton was right, when he believed that
he had established their reality in the solar system,
not expelled them from it.
But our more peculiar business at present is to
observe that Laplace himself, in describing the arrangements
by which the stability of the solar system
is secured, uses language which shows how irresistibly
these arrangements suggest an adaptation to
its preservation as an end. If in his expressions we
were to substitute the Deity for the abstraction
“nature” which he employs, his reflection would
coincide with that which the most religious philosopher
would entertain. “It seems that ‘God’ has
ordered every thing in the heavens to ensure the duration
of the planetary system, by views similar to
those which He appears to us so admirably to follow
upon the earth, for the preservation of animals and
the perpetuity of species.[40] This consideration alone
would explain the disposition of the system, if it
were not the business of the geometer to go further.”
It may be possible for the geometer to go further;
but he must be strangely blinded by his peculiar pursuits,
if, when he has discovered the mode in which
these views are answered, he supposes himself to
have obtained a proof that there are no views at all.
It would be as if the savage, who had marvelled at
the steady working of the steam engine, should cease
to consider it a work of art, as soon as the self-regulating[263]
part of the mechanism had been explained
to him.
The unsuccessful struggle in which those persons
engage, who attempt to throw off the impression of
design in the creation, appears in an amusing manner
through the simplicity of the ancient Roman
poet of this school. Lucretius maintains that the
eye was not made for seeing, nor the ear for hearing.
But the terms in which he recommends this
doctrine show how hard he knew it to be for men to
entertain such an opinion. His advice is,—</div></body></text></TEI>