<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="62">

BOOK IX.

THE PHILOSOPHY OF BIOLOGY.

CHAPTER I.
Analogy of Biology With Other Sciences.



1. IN
the History of the Sciences, after treating of
the Sciences of Classification, we proceeded to
what are there termed the Organical Sciences, including
in this term Physiology and Comparative Anatomy.
A peculiar feature in this group of sciences is that
they involve the notion of living things. The notion
of Life, however vague and obscure it may be in men’s
minds, is apprehended as a peculiar Idea, not resolvable into any other Ideas, such, for instance, as Matter
and Motion. The separation between living creatures
and inert matter, between organized and unorganized
beings, is conceived as a positive and insurmountable
barrier. The two classes of objects are considered as
of a distinct kind, produced and preserved by different
forces. Whether the Idea of Life is really thus original and fundamental, and whether, if so, it be one
Idea only, or involve several, it must be the province
of true philosophy to determine. What we shall here
offer may be considered as an attempt to contribute
something to the determination of these questions;
but we shall perhaps be able to make it appear that
science is at present only in the course of its progress
towards a complete solution of such problems.
Since the main feature of those sciences of which
we have now to examine the philosophy is, that they 170 involve the Idea of Life, it would be desirable to have
them designated by a name expressive of that circumstance. The word Physiology, by which they have
most commonly been described, means the Science of
Nature; and though it would be easy to explain, by
reference to history, the train of thought by which the
word was latterly restricted to Living Nature, it is plain
that the name is, etymologically speaking, loose and
improper. The term Biology, which means exactly
what we wish to express, the Science of Life, has often
been used, and has of late become not uncommon
among good winters. I shall therefore venture to employ it, in most cases, rather than the word Physiology.
2. As I have already intimated, one main inquiry
belonging to the Philosophy of Biology, is concerning
the Fundamental Idea or Ideas which the science involves. If we look back at the course and the results
of our disquisitions respecting other sciences in this
work, and assume, as we may philosophically do, that
there will be some general analogy between those
sciences and this, in their development and progress,
we shall be enabled to anticipate in some measure the
nature of the view which we shall now have to take.
We have seen that in other subjects the Fundamental
Ideas on which science depended, and the Conceptions
derived from these, were at first vague, obscure, and
confused;—that by gradual steps, by a constant union
of thought and observation, these conceptions become
more and more clear, more and more definite;—and
that when they approached complete distinctness and
precision, there were made great positive discoveries
into which these conceptions entered; and thus the
new precision of thought was fixed and perpetuated
in some conspicuous and lasting truths. Thus we
have seen how the first confused mechanical conceptions (Force, and the like,) were, from time to time,
growing clearer, down to the epoch of Newton;—how true conceptions of Genera and of wider classes,
gradually unfolded themselves among the botanists of
the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries;—how the
idea of Substance became steady enough to govern the 171 theories of chemists only at the epoch of Lavoisier;—how the Idea of Polarity, although often used by physicists and chemists, is even now somewhat vague and
indistinct in the minds of the greater part of speculators. In like manner we may expect to find that the
Idea of Life, if indeed that be the governing Idea of
the Science which treats of Living Things, will be
found to have been gradually approaching towards a
distinct and definite form among the physiologists of all
ages up to the present day. And if this be the case, it
may not be considered superfluous, with reference to
so interesting a subject, if we employ some space in
tracing historically the steps of this progress;—the
changes by which the originally loose notion of Life, or
of Vital Powers, became more nearly an Idea suited to
the purposes of science.
3. But we may safely carry this analogy between
Biology and other sciences somewhat further. We
have seen, in other sciences, that while men in their
speculations were thus tending towards a certain peculiar Idea, but before they as yet saw clearly that it was
peculiar and independent, they naturally and inevitably clothed their speculations in conceptions borrowed
from some other extraneous idea. And the unsatisfactoriness of all such attempts, and the necessary consequence of this, a constant alteration and succession
of such inappropriate hypotheses, were indications and
aids of the progress which was going on towards a more
genuine form of the science. For instance, we have
seen that in chemistry, so long as men refused to recognize a peculiar and distinct kind of power in the
Affinity which binds together the elements of bodies,
they framed to themselves a series of hypotheses, each
constructed according to the prevalent ideas of the
time, by which they tried to represent the relation of
the compound to the ingredients:—first, supposing
that the elements bestowed upon the whole qualities
resembling their own:—then giving up this supposition, and imagining that the properties of the body
depended upon the shape of the component particles;—then, as their view expanded, assuming that it was 172 not the shape, but the mechanical forces of the particles which gave the body its attributes;—and finally
acquiescing in, or rather reluctantly admitting, the
idea of Affinity, conceived as a peculiar power, different not only from material contact, but from any mechanical or dynamical attraction.
Now we cannot but think it very natural, if we find
that the history of Biology offers a series of occurrences
of the same nature. The notions of Life in general,
or of any Vital Functions or Vital Forces in particular,
are obviously very loose and vague as they exist in the
minds of most men. The discrepancies and controversies respecting the definitions of all such terms,
which are found in all works on physiology, afford us
abundant evidence that these notions are not, at least
not generally, apprehended with complete clearness
and steadiness. We shall therefore find approaches
and advances, intermediate steps, gradually leading
up to the greatest degree of distinctness which has yet
been attained. And in those stages of imperfect
apprehension in which the notions of Life and of Vital
Powers are still too loose and unformed to be applied
independently, we may expect to find them supported
and embodied by means of hypotheses borrowed from
other subjects, and thus, made so distinct and substantial as to supply at least a temporary possibility of
scientific reasoning upon the laws of life.
4. For example, if we suppose that men begin to
speculate upon the properties of living things, not
acknowledging a peculiar Vital Power, but making
use successively of the knowledge supplied by the study
of other subjects, we may easily imagine a series of
hypotheses along which they would pass.
They would probably, first, in this as in other
sciences, have their thoughts occupied by vague and
mystical notions in which material and spiritual agency,
natural and supernatural events, were mixed together
without discrimination, and without any clear notion
at all. But as they acquired a more genuine perception of the nature of knowledge, they would naturally
try to explain vital motions and processes by means of 173 such forces as they had learnt the existence of from
other sciences. They might first have a mechanical
hypothesis, in which the mechanical Forces of the solids
and fluids which compose organized bodies should be
referred to, as the most important influences in the
process of life. They might then attend to the actions
which the fluids exercise in virtue of their Affinity,
and might thus form a chemical theory. When they
had proved the insufficience of these hypotheses, borrowed from the powers which matter exhibits in other
cases, they might think themselves authorized to
assume some peculiar power or agency, still material,
and thus they would have the hypothesis of a Vital
Fluid. And if they were driven to reject this, they
might think that there was no resource but to assume
an immaterial principle of life, and thus they would
arrive at the doctrine of an Animal Soul.
Now, through the cycle of hypotheses which we
have thus supposed, physiology has actually passed.
The conclusions to which the most philosophical minds
have been led by a survey of this progress is, that by
the failure of all these theories, men have exhausted
this path of inquiry, and shown that scientific truth is
to be sought in some other manner. But before I
proceed further to illustrate this result, it will be
proper, as I have already stated, to exhibit historically
the various hypotheses which I have described. In
doing this I shall principally follow the History of
Medicine of Sprengel. It is only by taking for my
guide a physiologist of acknowledged science and judgment, that I can hope, on such a subject, to avoid
errours of detail. I proceed now to give in succession
an account of the Mystical, the Iatrochemical, the
Iatromathematical, and the Vital-Fluid Schools; and
finally of the Psychical School, who hold the Vital
Powers to be derived from the Soul (Psyche).</div></body></text></TEI>