<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="73">

CHAPTER V.
Of the Conception of a First Cause.



1. AT
the end of the last chapter but one, we were
led to this result,—that we cannot, in any
of the Palætiological Sciences, ascend to a beginning
which is of the same nature as the existing cause of
events, and which depends upon causes that are still in
operation. Philosophers never have demonstrated, and
probably never will be able to demonstrate, what
was the original condition of the solar system, of the
earth, of the vegetable and animal worlds, of languages,
of arts. On all these subjects the course of investigation, followed backwards as far as our materials allow
us to pursue it, ends at last in an impenetrable gloom.
We strain our eyes in vain when we try, by our natural
faculties, to discern an origin.
2. Yet speculative men have been constantly employed in attempts to arrive at that which thus seems
to be placed out of their reach. The Origin of
Languages, the Origin of the present Distribution of
Plants and Animals, the Origin of the Earth, have
been common subjects of diligent and persevering
inquiry. Indeed inquiries respecting such subjects
have been, at least till lately, the usual form which
Palætiological researches have assumed. Cosmogony,
the Origin of the World, of which, in such speculations,
the earth was considered as a principal part, has been
a favourite study both of ancient and of modern
times: and most of the attempts at Geology previous
to the present period have been Cosmogonies or Geogonies, rather than that more genuine science which
we have endeavoured to delineate. Again: Glossology,
though now an extensive body of solid knowledge, was 317 mainly brought into being by inquiries concerning the
Original Language spoken by men; and the nature of
the first separation and diffusion of languages, the first
peopling of the earth by man and by animals, were
long sought after with ardent curiosity, although of
course with reference to the authority of the Scriptures,
as well as the evidence of natural phenomena. Indeed
the interest of such inquiries even yet is far from being
extinguished. The disposition to explore the past in
the hope of finding, by the light of natural reasoning
as well as by the aid of revelation, the origin of the
present course of things, appears to be unconquerable.
‘What was the beginning?’ is a question which the
human race cannot desist from perpetually asking.
And no failure in obtaining a satisfactory answer can
prevent inquisitive spirits from again and again repeating the inquiry, although the blank abyss into which
it is uttered does not even return an echo.
3. What, then, is the reason of an attempt so pertinacious yet so fruitless? By what motive are we impelled thus constantly to seek what we can never find?
Why are the errour of our conjectures, the futility of
our reasonings, the precariousness of our interpretations, over and over again proved to us in vain? Why
is it impossible for us to acquiesce in our ignorance
and to relinquish the inquiry? Why cannot we content ourselves with examining those links of the chain
of causes which are nearest to us,—those in which the
connexion is intelligible and clear; instead of fixing
our attention upon those remote portions where we
can no longer estimate its coherence? In short, why
did not men from the first take for the subject of their
speculations the Course of Nature rather than the
Origin of Things?
To this we reply, that in doing what they have thus
done, in seeking what they have sought, men are impelled by an intellectual necessity. They cannot conceive a Series of connected occurrences without a Commencement; they cannot help supposing a cause for
the Whole, as well as a cause for each part; they cannot be satisfied with a succession of causes without 318 assuming a First Cause. Such an assumption is necessarily impressed upon our minds by our contemplation
of a series of causes and effects; that there must be a
First Cause, is accepted by all intelligent reasoners as
an Axiom: and like other Axioms, its truth is necessarily implied in the Idea which it involves.
4. The evidence of this axiom may be illustrated in
several ways. In the first place, the axiom is assumed
in the argument usually offered to prove the existence
of the Deity. Since, it is said, the world now exists,
and since nothing cannot produce something, something must have existed from eternity. This Something is the First Cause: it is God.
Now what I have to remark here is this:—the conclusiveness of this argument, as a proof of the existence
of one independent, immutable Deity, depends entirely
upon the assumption of the axiom above stated. The
World, a series of causes and effects, exists: therefore
there must be, not only this series of causes and effects,
but also a First Cause. It will be easily seen, that
without the axiom, that in every series of causes and
effects there must be a First Cause, the reasoning is
altogether inconclusive.
5. Or to put the matter otherwise: The argument
for the existence of the Deity was stated thus: Something exists, therefore something must have existed
from eternity. ‘Granted,’ the opponent might say;
‘but this something which has existed from eternity,
why may it not be this very series of causes and effects
which is now going on, and which appears to contain
in itself no indication of beginning or end?’ And
thus, without the assumption of the necessity of a
First Cause, the force of the argument may be resisted.
6. But, it may be asked, how do those who have
written to prove the existence of the Deity reply to
such an objection as the one just stated? It is natural
to suppose that, on a subject so interesting and so long
discussed, all the obvious arguments with their replies,
have been fully brought into view. What is the result in this case? 319
The principal modes of replying to the above objection, that the series of causes and effects which now
exists, may have existed from eternity, appear to be
these.
In the first place, our minds cannot be satisfied with
a series of successive, dependent, causes and effects,
without something first and independent. We pass
from effect to cause, and from that to a higher cause,
in search of something on which the mind can rest;
but if we can do nothing but repeat this process, there
is no use in it. We move our limbs, but make no
advance. Our question is not answered, but evaded.
The mind cannot acquiesce in the destiny thus presented to it, of being referred from event to event,
from object to object, along an interminable vista of
causation and time. Now this mode of stating the
reply,—to say that the mind cannot thus be satisfied,
appears to be equivalent to saying that the mind is
conscious of a Principle, in virtue of which such a view
as this must be rejected;—the mind takes refuge in
the assumption of a First Cause, from an employment
inconsistent with its own nature.
7. Or again, we may avoid the objection, by putting the argument for the existence of a Deity in this
form: The series of causes and effects which we call
the world, or the course of nature, may be considered as
a whole, and this whole must have a cause of its existence. The whole collection of objects and events may
be comprehended as a single effect, and of this effect
there must be a cause. This Cause of the Universe
must be superior to, and independent of the special
events, which, happening in time, make up the universe of which He is the cause. He must exist and
exercise causation, before these events can begin: He
must be the First Cause.
Although the argument is here somewhat modified
in form, the substance is the same as before. For the
assumption that we may consider the whole series of
causes and effects as a single effect, is equivalent to the
assumption that besides partial causes we must have a
First Cause. And thus the Idea of a First Cause, and 320 the axiom which asserts its necessity, are recognized in
the usual argumentation on this subject.
8. This Idea of a First Cause, and the principle
involved in the Idea, have been the subject of discussion in another manner. As we have already said,
we assume as an axiom that a First Cause must exist;
and we assert that God, the First Cause, exists eternal and immutable, by the necessity which the axiom
implies. Hence God is said to exist necessarily;—to
be a necessarily existing being. And when this necessary existence of God had been spoken of, it soon began
to be contemplated as a sufficient reason, and as an absolute demonstration of His existence; without any
need of referring to the world as an effect, in order to
arrive at God as the cause. And thus men conceived
that they had obtained a proof of the existence of the
Deity, à priori, from Ideas, as well as à posteriori,
from Effects.
9. Thus, Thomas Aquinas employs this reasoning to prove the eternity of God29: ‘Oportet ponere
aliquod primum necessarium quod est per se ipsum
necessarium; et hoc est Deus, cum sit prima causa
ut dictum est: igitur Deus æternus est, cum omne
necessarium per se sit æternum.’ It is true that the
schoolmen never professed to be able to prove the
existence of the Deity à priori: but they made use
of this conception of necessary existence in a manner
which approached very near to such an attempt. Thus
Suarez30 discusses the question, ‘Utrum aliquo modo
possit à priori demonstrari Deum esse.’ And resolves
the question in this manner: ‘Ad hunc ergo modum
dicendum est: Demonstrato à posteriori Deum esse
ens necessarium et a se, ex hoc attributo posse à
priori demonstrari præter illud non posse esse aliud
ens necessarium et a se, et consequenter demonstrari
Deum esse.’</div></body></text></TEI>