<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="16"> 

CHAPTER VI.
General Rules for the Construction of the Conception.


Aphorism XXXVIII.
The Construction of the Conception very often includes, in
a great measure, the Determination of the Magnitudes.
Aphorism XXXIX.
When a series of progressive numbers is given as the
result of observation, it may generally be reduced to law by
combinations of arithmetical and geometrical progressions.
Aphorism XL.
A true formula for a progressive series of numbers cannot
commonly be obtained from a narrow range of observations.
Aphorism XLI.
Recurrent series of numbers must, in most cases, be expressed
by circular formulæ.
Aphorism XLII.
The true construction of the conception is frequently suggested
by some hypothesis; and in these cases, the hypothesis
may be useful, though containing superfluous parts.

1. IN
speaking of the discovery of laws of nature,
those which depend upon quantity, as number,
space, and the like, are most prominent and most easily
conceived, and therefore in speaking of such researches,
we shall often use language which applies peculiarly to 196
the cases in which quantities numerically measurable
are concerned, leaving it for a subsequent task to extend
our principles to ideas of other kinds.
Hence we may at present consider the Construction
of a Conception which shall include and connect the
facts, as being the construction of a Mathematical Formula,
coinciding with the numerical expression of the
facts; and we have to consider how this process can be
facilitated, it being supposed that we have already before
us the numerical measures given by observation.
2. We may remark, however, that the construction
of the right Formula for any such case, and the determination
of the Coefficients of such formula, which we
have spoken of as two separate steps, are in practice
almost necessarily simultaneous; for the near coincidence
of the results of the theoretical rule with the
observed facts confirms at the same time the Formula
and its Coefficients. In this case also, the mode of
arriving at truth is to try various hypotheses;—to
modify the hypotheses so as to approximate to the
facts, and to multiply the facts so as to test the hypotheses.
The Independent Variable, and the Formula which
we would try, being once selected, mathematicians have
devised certain special and technical processes by which
the value of the coefficients may be determined. These
we shall treat of in the next Chapter; but in the mean
time we may note, in a more general manner, the mode
in which, in physical researches, the proper formula
may be obtained.
3. A person somewhat versed in mathematics, having before
him a series of numbers, will generally be
able to devise a formula which approaches near to
those numbers. If, for instance, the series is constantly
progressive, he will be able to see whether it
more nearly resembles an arithmetical or a geometrical
progression. For example, MM. Dulong and Petit, in
their investigation of the law of cooling of bodies,
obtained the following series of measures. A thermometer,
made hot, was placed in an enclosure of which
the temperature was 0 degrees, and the rapidity of 197
cooling of the thermometer was noted for many temperatures.
It was found that


For the temperature 240the rapidity of cooling was10·69
〃220〃8·81
〃200〃7·40
〃180〃6·10
〃160〃4·89
〃140〃3·88

and so on. Now this series of numbers manifestly increases
with greater rapidity as we proceed from the
lower to the higher parts of the scale. The numbers
do not, however, form a geometrical series, as we may
easily ascertain. But if we were to take the differences
of the successive terms we should find them to be—
1·88, 1·41, 1·30, 1·21, 1·01, &c.
and these numbers are very nearly the terms of a geometric
series. For if we divide each term by the succeeding one,
we find these numbers,
1·33, 1·09, 1·07, 1·20, 1·27,
in which there does not appear to be any constant tendency
to diminish or increase. And we shall find that
a geometrical series in which the ratio is 1·165, may be
made to approach very near to this series, the deviations
from it being only such as may be accounted for
by conceiving them as errours of observation. In this
manner a certain formula26
is obtained, giving results 198
which very nearly coincide with the observed facts, as
may be seen in the margin.</div></body></text></TEI>