<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="63">CHAPTER II.
Discovery of the Law of Refraction.
WE have seen in the former part of this history that the Greeks had formed
a tolerably clear conception of the refraction as well as the
reflection of the rays of light; and that Ptolemy had measured the
amount of refraction of glass and water at various angles. If we give
the names of the angle of incidence and the angle of
refraction respectively to the angles which a ray of light makes
with the line perpendicular to surface of glass or water (or any other
medium) within and without the medium, Ptolemy had observed that the
angle of refraction is always less than the angle of incidence. He had
supposed it to be less in a given proportion, but this opinion is
false; and was afterwards rightly denied by the Arabian mathematician
Alhazen. The optical views which occur in the work of Alhazen are far
sounder than those of his predecessors; and the book may be regarded
as the most considerable monument which we have of the scientific
genius of the Arabians; for it appears, for the most part, not to be
borrowed from Greek authorities. The author not only asserts (lib.
vii.), that refraction takes place towards the perpendicular, and
refers to experiment for the truth of this: and that the quantities of
the refraction differ according to the magnitudes of the angles which
the directions of the incidental rays (primæ lineæ) make with
the perpendiculars to the surface; but he also says distinctly and
decidedly that the angles of refraction do not follow the proportion
of the angles of incidence.
[2nd Ed.] [There appears to be good ground to assent to the
assertion of Alhazen’s originality, made by his editor Risner, who
says, “Euclideum hic vel Ptolemaicum nihil fere est.” Besides the
doctrine of reflection and refraction of light, the Arabian author
gives a description of the eye. He distinguishes three fluids,
humor aqueus, crystallinus, vitreus, and four
coats of the eye, tunica adherens, cornea, uvea,
tunica reti similis. He distinguishes also three kinds of
vision: “Visibile percipitur aut solo visu, aut visu et syllogismo,
aut visu et anticipatâ notione.” He has several propositions relating
to what we sometimes call the Philosophy of Vision: for instance this:
“E visibili sæpius viso remanet in anima generalis notio,” &c.]
55
The assertion, that the angles of refraction are not proportional
to the angles of incidence, was an important remark; and if it had
been steadily kept in mind, the next thing to be done with regard to
refraction was to go on experimenting and conjecturing till the true
law of refraction was discovered; and in the mean time to apply the
principle as far as it was known. Alhazen, though he gives directions
for making experimental measures of refraction, does not give any
Table of the results of such experiments, as Ptolemy had done.
Vitello, a Pole, who in the 13th century published an extensive work
upon Optics, does give such a table; and asserts it to be deduced from
experiment, as I have already said (vol. i.).
But this assertion is still liable to doubt in consequence of the
table containing impossible observations.
[2nd Ed.] [As I have already stated, Vitello asserts that his
Tables were derived from his own observations. Their near agreement
with those of Ptolemy does not make this improbable: for where the
observations were only made to half a degree, there was not much room
for observers to differ. It is not unlikely that the observations of
refraction out of air into water and glass, and out of water into
glass, were actually made; while the impossible values which accompany
them, of the refraction out of water and glass into air, and out of
glass into water, were calculated, and calculated from an erroneous
rule.]
The principle that a ray refracted in glass or water is turned
towards the perpendicular, without knowing the exact law of
refraction, enabled mathematicians to trace the effects of transparent
bodies in various cases. Thus in Roger Bacon’s works we find a
tolerably distinct explanation of the effect of a convex glass; and in
the work of Vitello the effect of refraction at the two surfaces of a
glass globe is clearly traceable.
Notwithstanding Alhazen’s assertion of the contrary, the opinion
was still current among mathematicians that the angle of refraction
was proportional to the angle of incidence. But when Kepler’s
attention was drawn to the subject, he saw that this was plainly
inconsistent with the observations of Vitello for large angles; and he
convinced himself by his own experiments that the true law was
something different from the one commonly supposed. The discovery of
this true law excited in him an eager curiosity; and this point had
the more interest for him in consequence of the introduction of a
correction for atmospheric refraction into astronomical calculations,
which had been made by Tycho, and of the invention of the telescope.
In 56 his
Supplement to Vitello, published in 1604, Kepler attempts to
reduce to a rule the measured quantities of refraction. The reader who
recollects what we have already narrated, the manner in which Kepler
attempted to reduce to law the astronomical observations of
Tycho,—devising an almost endless variety of possible formulæ,
tracing their consequences with undaunted industry, and relating, with
a vivacious garrulity, his disappointments and his hopes,—will
not be surprised to find that he proceeded in the same manner with
regard to the Tables of Observed Refractions. He tried a variety of
constructions by triangles, conic sections, &c., without being
able to satisfy himself; and he at last3 is obliged to
content himself with an approximate rule, which makes the refraction
partly proportional to the angle of incidence, and partly, to the
secant of that angle. In this way he satisfies the observed
refractions within a difference of less than half a degree each way.
When we consider how simple the law of refraction is, (that the ratio
of the sines of the angles of incidence and refraction is constant for
the same medium,) it appears strange that a person attempting to
discover it, and drawing triangles for the purpose, should fail; but
this lot of missing what afterwards seems to have been obvious, is a
common one in the pursuit of truth.
3 L. U. K. Life of Kepler, p.
115.
The person who did discover the Law of the Sines, was Willebrord
Snell, about 1621; but the law was first published by Descartes, who
had seen Snell’s papers.4 Descartes does not acknowledge this law
to have been first detected by another; and after his manner, instead
of establishing its reality by reference to experiment, he pretends to
prove à priori that it must be true,5 comparing, for
this purpose, the particles of light to balls striking a substance
which accelerates them.
4 Huyghens, Dioptrica, p.
2.
5 Diopt. p. 53.
[2nd Ed.] [Huyghens says of Snell’s papers, “Quæ et nos vidimus
aliquando, et Cartesium quoque vidisse accepimus, et hinc fortasse
mensuram illam quæ in sinibus consistit elicuerit.” Isaac Vossius,
De Lucis Naturâ et Proprietate, says that he also had seen this
law in Snell’s unpublished optical Treatise. The same writer says,
“Quod itaque (Cartesius) habet, refractionum momenta non exigenda esse
ad angulos sed ad lineas, id tuo Snellio, acceptum ferre debuisset,
cujus nomen more solito dissimulavit.” “Cartesius got his law
from Snell, and in his usual way, concealed it.” 57
Huyghens’ assertion, that Snell did not attend to the
proportion of the sines, is very captious; and becomes absurdly so,
when it is made to mean that Snell did not know the law of
the sines. It is not denied that Snell knew the true law, or that the
true law is the law of the sines. Snell does not use the
trigonometrical term sine, but he expresses the law in a
geometrical form more simply. Even if he had attended to the
law of the sines, he might reasonably have preferred his own way of
stating it.
James Gregory also independently discovered the true law of
refraction; and, in publishing it, states that he had learnt that it
had already been published by Descartes.]
But though Descartes does not, in this instance, produce any good
claims to the character of an inductive philosopher, he showed
considerable skill in tracing the consequences of the principle when
once adopted. In particular we must consider him as the genuine author
of the explanation of the rainbow. It is true that Fleischer6
and Kepler had previously ascribed this phenomenon to the rays of
sunlight which, falling on drops of rain, are refracted into each
drop, reflected at its inner surface, and refracted out again: Antonio
de Dominis had found that a glass globe of water, when placed in a
particular position with respect to the eye, exhibited bright colors;
and had hence explained the circular form of the bow, which, indeed,
Aristotle had done before.7 But none of these writers had shown why
there was a narrow bright circle of a definite diameter; for the drops
which send rays to the eye after two refractions and a reflection,
occupy a much wider space in the heavens. Descartes assigned the
reason for this in the most satisfactory manner,8 by showing that
the rays which, after two refractions and a reflection, come to the
eye at an angle of about forty-one degrees with their original
direction, are far more dense than those in any other position. He
showed, in the same manner, that the existence and position of the
secondary bow resulted from the same laws. This is the complete
and adequate account of the state of things, so far as the brightness
of the bows only is concerned; the explanation of the colors belongs
to the next article of our survey.
6 Mont. i. 701.
7 Meteorol. iii. 3.
8 Meteorum, cap. viii. p.
196.
The explanation of the rainbow and of its magnitude, afforded by
Snell’s law of sines, was perhaps one of the leading points in the
verification of the law. The principle, being once established, was
applied, by the aid of mathematical reasoning, to atmospheric
refractions, 58
optical instruments, diacaustic curves, (that is, the curves of
intense light produced by refraction,) and to various other cases; and
was, of course, tested and confirmed by such applications. It was,
however, impossible to pursue these applications far, without a due
knowledge of the laws by which, in such cases, colors are produced. To
these we now proceed.
[2nd Ed.] [I have omitted many interesting parts of the history of
Optics about this period, because I was concerned with the
inductive discovery of laws, rather than with mathematical
deductions from such laws when established, or
applications of them in the form of instruments. I might
otherwise have noticed the discovery of Spectacle Glasses, of the
Telescope, of the Microscope, of the Camera Obscura, and the
mathematical explanation of these and other phenomena, as given by
Kepler and others. I might also have noticed the progress of knowledge
respecting the Eye and Vision. We have seen
that Alhazen described the structure of the eye. The operation of the
parts was gradually made out. Baptista Porta compares the eye to his
Camera Obscura (Magia Naturalis, 1579). Scheiner, in his
Oculus, published 1652, completed the Theory of the Eye. And
Kepler discussed some of the questions even now often agitated; as the
causes and conditions of our seeing objects single with two eyes, and
erect with inverted images.]
</div></body></text></TEI>