<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 166, folios 154-155</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 166, folios 154-155.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1843">undated (estimated from box 166 date range)</date>
          <note type="place">[no place]</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 166, folios 154-155</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_166_folios_154-155.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Thursdy. 1/2 past 9 o'clock</p>
      <p>Dearest. What a kind kind mate ou is. Your sweetest letter (just received) has almost made me cry. It is so wise, &amp; yet so tender.</p>
      <p>I am going on more comfortably than I expected. The head improves every 6 hours; &amp; Locock was so impressed with the change when he paid his yesterdays second visit the last thing at night, that he did not administer the dose of Laudanum which he had come expressly to give me himself, (that he might apportion the quantity precisely to the state).</p>
      <p>This morning it (the pate) is lighter &amp; clearer than I have</p>
      <p>been used to feel it of late.</p>
      <p>I think there is no likelihood whatever of more bleeding having to be appealed to; unless by some mismanagement or indiscretions.</p>
      <p>The Hen was here last evening, &amp; wrote the enclosed for you.</p>
      <p>Your uncle's letter to me is, to say the very least, not a little cordial. It goes further in its tone that way, than mine to him did; showing evidently that he eagerly seized the door held open to him.</p>
      <p>Tell Lord Worsley, with my Compliments, that I hope I shall have the pleasure of making his acquaintance this spring, &amp; regret my absence; &amp; that I am very</p>
      <p>jealous of his having been riding Tag-Rag whom I prize as the greatest treasure.--</p>
      <p>My dear, I hope ou won't let people ride that horse. I suppose ou satisfied ou-self first that Lord W-- is a very good rider. But remember Mr Austen's accident with Tam.</p>
      <p>Give that message to Lord W--. It will amuse him that the Avis is so chary of her animal.</p>
      <p>You shall hear by post again.</p>
      <p>Miss Boutell with me, &amp; the greatest comfort. She sleeps in your room.</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
