<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="3">CHAPTER III.
HISTORY OF THE PROGRESS OF GEOLOGY—continued.
Arabian writers of the tenth century—Avicenna—Omar—Cosmogony of the
Koran—Kazwini—Early Italian writers—Leonardo da Vinci—Fracastoro—Controversy
as to the real nature of fossils—Attributed to the Mosaic deluge—
Palissy—Steno—Scilla—Quirini—Boyle—Lister—Leibnitz—Hooke's Theory
of Elevation by Earthquakes—Of lost species of animals—Ray—Physico-theological
writers—Woodward's Diluvial Theory—Burnet—Whiston—Vallisneri—Lazzaro
Moro—Generelli—Buffon—His theory condemned by the Sorbonne as
unorthodox—His declaration—Targioni—Arduino—Michell—Catcott—Raspe
Fuchsel—Fortis—Testa—Whitehurst—Pallas—Saussure.
Arabian writers.—After the decline of the Roman empire, the cultivation
of physical science was first revived with some success by the
Saracens, about the middle of the eighth century of our era. The
works of the most eminent classic writers were purchased at great expense
from the Christians, and translated into Arabic; and Al Mamûn,
son of the famous Harûn-al-Rashid, the contemporary of Charlemagne,
received with marks of distinction, at his court at Bagdad, astronomers
and men of learning from different countries. This caliph, and some of
his successors, encountered much opposition and jealousy from the doctors
of the Mahometan law, who wished the Moslems to confine their
studies to the Koran, dreading the effects of the diffusion of a taste for
the physical sciences.32
Avicenna.—Almost all the works of the early Arabian writers are
lost. Amongst those of the tenth century, of which fragments are now
extant, is a short treatise, "On the Formation and Classification of
Minerals," by Avicenna, a physician, in whose arrangement there is considerable
merit. The second chapter, "On the Cause of Mountains," is
remarkable; for mountains, he says, are formed, some by essential,
others by accidental causes. In illustration of the essential, he instances
"a violent earthquake, by which land is elevated, and becomes a
mountain;" of the accidental, the principal, he says, is excavation by
water, whereby cavities are produced, and adjoining lands made to stand
out and form eminences.33
Omar—Cosmogony of the Koran.—In the same century, also, Omar,
surnamed "El Aalem," or "The Learned," wrote a work on "The Retreat
of the Sea." It appears that on comparing the charts of his own
time with those made by the Indian and Persian astronomers two thousand
years before, he had satisfied himself that important changes had
taken place since the times of history in the form of the coasts of Asia,
18and that the extension of the sea had been greater at some former periods.
He was confirmed in this opinion by the numerous salt springs
and marshes in the interior of Asia,—a phenomenon from which Pallas,
in more recent times, has drawn the same inference.
Von Hoff has suggested, with great probability, that the changes in
the level of the Caspian (some of which there is reason to believe have
happened within the historical era), and the geological appearances in
that district, indicating the desertion by that sea of its ancient bed, had
probably led Omar to his theory of a general subsidence. But whatever
may have been the proofs relied on, his system was declared contradictory
to certain passages in the Koran, and he was called upon
publicly to recant his errors; to avoid which persecution he went into
voluntary banishment from Samarkand.34
The cosmological opinions expressed in the Koran are few, and
merely introduced incidentally: so that it is not easy to understand
how they could have interfered so seriously with free discussion on the
former changes of the globe. The Prophet declares that the earth was
created in two days, and the mountains were then placed on it; and
during these, and two additional days, the inhabitants of the earth were
formed; and in two more the seven heavens.35 There is no more detail
of circumstances; and the deluge, which is also mentioned, is discussed
with equal brevity. The waters are represented to have poured
out of an oven; a strange fable, said to be borrowed from the Persian
Magi, who represented them as issuing from the oven of an old woman.36
All men were drowned, save Noah and his family; and then God said,
"O earth, swallow up thy waters; and thou, O heaven, withhold thy
rain;" and immediately the waters abated.37
We may suppose Omar to have represented the desertion of the land
by the sea to have been gradual, and that his hypothesis required a
greater lapse of ages than was consistent with Moslem orthodoxy; for
it is to be inferred from the Koran, that man and this planet were created
at the same time; and although Mahomet did not limit expressly
the antiquity of the human race, yet he gave an implied sanction to the
Mosaic chronology, by the veneration expressed by him for the Hebrew
Patriarchs.38
19A manuscript work, entitled the "Wonders of Nature," is preserved
in the Royal Library at Paris, by an Arabian writer, Mohammed
Kazwini, who flourished in the seventh century of the Hegira, or at
the close of the thirteenth century of our era.39 Besides several curious
remarks on aerolites, earthquakes, and the successive changes of position
which the land and sea have undergone, we meet with the following
beautiful passage which is given as the narrative of Kidhz, an allegorical
personage:—"I passed one day by a very ancient and wonderfully
populous city, and asked one of its inhabitants how long it had
been founded. 'It is indeed a mighty city,' replied he; 'we know
not how long it has existed, and our ancestors were on this subject
as ignorant as ourselves.' Five centuries afterwards, as I passed by
the same place, I could not perceive the slightest vestige of the city.
I demanded of a peasant, who was gathering herbs upon its former
site, how long it had been destroyed. 'In sooth a strange question!'
replied he. 'The ground here has never been different from what you
now behold it.'—'Was there not of old,' said I, 'a splendid city here?'—'Never,'
answered he, 'so far as we have seen, and never did our
fathers speak to us of any such.' On my return there 500 years afterwards,
I found the sea in the same place, and on its shores were a party
of fishermen, of whom I inquired how long the land had been covered
by the waters? 'Is this a question,' said they, 'for a man like
you? this spot has always been what it is now.' I again returned,
500 years afterwards, and the sea had disappeared; I inquired of a
man who stood alone upon the spot, how long ago this change had
taken place, and he gave me the same answer as I had received before.
Lastly, on coming back again after an equal lapse of time, I found
there a flourishing city, more populous and more rich in beautiful buildings,
than the city I had seen the first time, and when I would fain
have informed myself concerning its origin, the inhabitants answered
me, 'Its rise is lost in remote antiquity: we are ignorant how long it has
existed, and our fathers were on this subject as ignorant as ourselves.'"
Early Italian writers.—It was not till the earlier part of the sixteenth
century that geological phenomena began to attract the attention
of the Christian nations. At that period a very animated controversy
sprang up in Italy, concerning the true nature and origin of marine
shells, and other organized fossils, found abundantly in the strata of the
peninsula. The celebrated painter Leonardo da Vinci, who in his youth
had planned and executed some navigable canals in the north of Italy,
was one of the first who applied sound reasoning to these subjects.
The mud of rivers, he said, had covered and penetrated into the interior
of fossil shells at a time when these were still at the bottom of the sea
near the coast. "They tell us that these shells were formed in the
20hills by the influence of the stars; but I ask where in the hills are the
stars now forming shells of distinct ages and species? and how can the
stars explain the origin of gravel, occurring at different heights and
composed of pebbles rounded as if by the motion of running water; or
in what manner can such a cause account for the petrifaction in the
same places of various leaves, sea-weeds, and marine-crabs?"40
The excavations made in 1517, for repairing the city of Verona,
brought to light a multitude of curious petrifactions, and furnished
matter for speculation to different authors, and among the rest to
Fracastoro,41 who declared his opinion, that fossil shells had all belonged
to living animals, which had formerly lived and multiplied where there
exuviæ are now found. He exposed the absurdity of having recourse
to a certain "plastic force," which it was said had power to fashion
stones into organic forms; and with no less cogent arguments, demonstrated
the futility of attributing the situation of the shells in question
to the Mosaic deluge, a theory obstinately defended by some. That
inundation, he observed, was too transient; it consisted principally of
fluviatile waters; and if it had transported shells to great distances,
must have strewed them over the surface, not buried them at vast
depths in the interior of mountains. His clear exposition of the evidence
would have terminated the discussion forever, if the passions of
mankind had not been enlisted in the dispute; and even though doubts
should for a time have remained in some minds, they would speedily
have been removed by the fresh information obtained almost immediately
afterwards, respecting the structure of fossil remains, and of
their living analogues.
But the clear and philosophical views of Fracastoro were disregarded,
and the talent and argumentative powers of the learned were
doomed for three centuries to be wasted in the discussion of these two
simple and preliminary questions: first, whether fossil remains had
ever belonged to living creatures; and, secondly, whether, if this be
admitted, all the phenomena could not be explained by the deluge of
Noah. It had been the general belief of the Christian world down to
the period now under consideration, that the origin of this planet was
not more remote than a few thousand years; and that since the creation
the deluge was the only great catastrophe by which considerable
change had been wrought on the earth's surface. On the other hand,
the opinion was scarcely less general, that the final dissolution of our
system was an event to be looked for at no distant period. The era, it
is true, of the expected millennium had passed away; and for five
hundred years after the fatal hour when the annihilation of the planet
21had been looked for, the monks remained in undisturbed enjoyment of
rich grants of land bequeathed to them by pious donors, who, in the
preamble of deeds beginning "appropinquante mundi termino"——"appropinquante
magno judicii die," left lasting monuments of the
popular delusion.42
But although in the sixteenth century it had become necessary to
interpret certain prophecies respecting the millennium more liberally,
and to assign a more distant date to the future conflagration of the
world, we find, in the speculations of the early geologists, perpetual
allusion to such an approaching catastrophe; while in all that regarded
the antiquity of the earth, no modification whatever of the opinions of
the dark ages had been effected. Considerable alarm was at first excited
when the attempt was made to invalidate, by physical proofs, an
article of faith so generally received; but there was sufficient spirit of
toleration and candor amongst the Italian ecclesiastics, to allow the subject
to be canvassed with much freedom. They even entered warmly
into the controversy themselves, often favoring different sides of the
question; and however much we may deplore the loss of time and labor
devoted to the defence of untenable positions, it must be conceded that
they displayed far less polemic bitterness than certain writers who followed
them "beyond the Alps," two centuries and a half later.
CONTROVERSY AS TO THE REAL NATURE OF FOSSIL ORGANIC REMAINS.
Mattioli—Falloppio.—The system of scholastic disputations, encouraged
in the universities of the middle ages, had unfortunately
trained men to habits of indefinite argumentation; and they often preferred
absurd and extravagant propositions, because greater skill was
required to maintain them; the end and object of these intellectual
combats being victory, and not truth. No theory could be so far-fetched
or fantastical as not to attract some followers, provided it fell
in with popular notions; and as cosmogonists were not at all restricted,
in building their systems, to the agency of known causes, the opponents
of Fracastoro met his arguments by feigning imaginary causes, which
differed from each other rather in name than in substance. Andrea
Mattioli, for instance, an eminent botanist, the illustrator of Dioscorides,
embraced the notion of Agricola, a skilful German miner, that a certain
"materia pinguis," or "fatty matter," set into fermentation by heat,
gave birth to fossil organic shapes. Yet Mattioli had come to the conclusion,
from his own observations, that porous bodies, such as bones
and shells, might be converted into stone, as being permeable to what
he termed the "lapidifying juice." In like manner, Falloppio of Padua
conceived that petrified shells were generated by fermentation in the
spots where they are found, or that they had in some cases acquired
22their form from "the tumultuous movements of terrestrial exhalations."
Although celebrated as a professor of anatomy, he taught that certain
tusks of elephants, dug up in his time in Apulia, were mere earthy concretions;
and, consistently with these principles, he even went so far as
to consider it probable, that the vases of Monte Testaceo at Rome were
natural impressions stamped in the soil.43 In the same spirit, Mercati,
who published, in 1574, faithful figures of the fossil shells preserved by
Pope Sixtus V. in the Museum of the Vatican, expressed an opinion that
they were mere stones, which had assumed their peculiar configuration
from the influence of the heavenly bodies; and Olivi of Cremona, who
described the fossil remains of a rich museum at Verona, was satisfied
with considering them as mere "sports of nature."
Some of the fanciful notions of those times were deemed less unreasonable,
as being somewhat in harmony with the Aristotelian theory
of spontaneous generation, then taught in all the schools.44 For men
who had been taught in early youth, that a large proportion of living
animals and plants was formed from the fortuitous concourse of atoms,
or had sprung from the corruption of organic matter, might easily persuade
themselves that organic shapes, often imperfectly preserved in
the interior of solid rocks, owed their existence to causes equally obscure
and mysterious.
Cardano, 1552.—But there were not wanting some who, during the
progress of this century, expressed more sound and sober opinions. The
title of a work of Cardano's, published in 1552, "De Subtilitate" (corresponding
to what would now be called Transcendental Philosophy),
would lead us to expect, in the chapter on minerals, many far-fetched
theories characteristic of that age; but when treating of petrified shells,
he decided that they clearly indicated the former sojourn of the sea
upon the mountains.45
Cesalpino—Majoli, 1597.—Cesalpino, a celebrated botanist, conceived
that fossil shells had been left on the land by the retiring sea,
and had concreted into stone during the consolidation of the soil;46 and
in the following year (1597), Simeone Majoli47 went still farther; and,
coinciding for the most part with the views of Cesalpino, suggested that
the shells and submarine matter of the Veronese, and other districts,
might have been cast up upon the land by volcanic explosions, like
those which gave rise, in 1538, to Monte Nuovo, near Puzzuoli. This
hint seems to have been the first imperfect attempt to connect the position
of fossil shells with the agency of volcanoes, a system afterwards more
fully developed by Hooke, Lazzaro Moro, Hutton, and other writers.
Two years afterwards, Imperati advocated the animal origin of fossilized
shells, yet admitted that stones could vegetate by force of "an
internal principle;" and, as evidence of this, he referred to the teeth of
fish and spines of echini found petrified.48
23Palissy, 1580.—Palissy, a French writer on "The Origin of Springs
from Rain-water," and of other scientific works, undertook, in 1580, to
combat the notions of many of his contemporaries in Italy, that petrified
shells had all been deposited by the universal deluge. "He was the
first," said Fontenelle, when, in the French Academy, he pronounced
his eulogy, nearly a century and a half later, "who dared assert," in
Paris, that fossil remains of testacea and fish had once belonged to marine
animals.
Fabio Colonna.—To enumerate the multitude of Italian writers, who
advanced various hypotheses, all equally fantastical, in the early part of
the seventeenth century, would be unprofitably tedious; but Fabio Colonna
deserves to be distinguished; for, although he gave way to the
dogma, that all fossil remains were to be referred to the deluge of Noah,
he resisted the absurd theory of Stelluti, who taught that fossil wood
and ammonites were mere clay, altered into such forms by sulphureous
waters and subterranean heat; and he pointed out the different states
of shells buried in the strata, distinguishing between, first, the mere
mould or impression; second, the cast or nucleus; and, thirdly, the
remains of the shell itself. He had also the merit of being the first to
point out that some of the fossils had belonged to marine and some to
terrestrial testacea.49
Steno, 1669.—But the most remarkable work of that period was
published by Steno, a Dane, once professor of anatomy at Padua, and
who afterwards resided many years at the court of the Grand Duke of
Tuscany. His treatise bears the quaint title of "De Solido intra Solidum
naturaltier contento (1669)," by which the author intended to
express, "On Gems, Crystals, and organic Petrifactions inclosed within
solid Rocks." This work attests the priority of the Italian school in
geological research; exemplifying at the same time the powerful obstacles
opposed, in that age, to the general reception of enlarged views in
the science. It was still a favorite dogma, that the fossil remains of
shells and marine creatures were not of animal origin; an opinion adhered
to by many from their extreme reluctance to believe, that the
earth could have been inhabited by living beings before a great part of
the existing mountains were formed. In reference to this controversy,
Steno had dissected a shark recently taken from the Mediterranean, and
had demonstrated that its teeth and bones were identical with many
fossils found in Tuscany. He had also compared the shells discovered
in the Italian strata with living species, pointed out their resemblance,
and traced the various gradations from shells merely calcined, or which
had only lost their animal gluten, to those petrifactions in which there
was a perfect substitution of stony matter. In his division of mineral
masses, he insisted on the secondary origin of those deposits in which
the spoils of animals or fragments of older rocks were inclosed. He
distinguished between marine formations and those of a fluviatile character,
24the last containing reeds, grasses, or the trunks and branches of
trees. He argued in favor of the original horizontality of sedimentary
deposits, attributing their present inclined and vertical position sometimes
to the escape of subterranean vapors heaving the crust of the
earth from below upwards, and sometimes to the falling in of masses
overlying subterranean cavities.
He declared that he had obtained proof that Tuscany must successively
have acquired six distinct configurations, having been twice covered
by water, twice laid dry with a level, and twice with an irregular
and uneven surface.50 He displayed great anxiety to reconcile his new
views with Scripture, for which purpose he pointed to certain rocks as
having been formed before the existence of animals and plants: selecting
unfortunately as examples certain formations of limestone and sandstone
in his own country, now known to contain, though sparingly, the
remains of animals and plants,—strata which do not even rank as the
oldest part of our secondary series. Steno suggested that Moses, when
speaking of the loftiest mountains as having been covered by the deluge,
meant merely the loftiest of the hills then existing, which may not have
been very high. The diluvian waters, he supposed, may have issued
from the interior of the earth into which they had retired, when in the
beginning the land was separated from the sea. These, and other
hypotheses on the same subject, are not calculated to enhance the value
of the treatise, and could scarcely fail to detract from the authority of
those opinions which were sound and legitimate deductions from fact
and observation. They have served, nevertheless, as the germs of many
popular theories of later times, and in an expanded form have been put
forth as original inventions by some of our contemporaries.
Scilla, 1670.—Scilla, a Sicilian painter, published, in 1670, a treatise,
in Latin, on the fossils of Calabria, illustrated by good engravings.
This work proves the continued ascendancy of dogmas often refuted;
for we find the wit and eloquence of the author chiefly directed against
the obstinate incredulity of naturalists as to the organic nature of fossil
shells.51 Like many eminent naturalists of his day, Scilla gave way to the
popular persuasion, that all fossil shells were the effects and proofs of the
Mosaic deluge. It may be doubted whether he was perfectly sincere,
and some of his contemporaries who took the same course were certainly
not so. But so eager were they to root out what they justly considered
an absurd prejudice respecting the nature of organized fossils, that they
seem to have been ready to make any concessions, in order to establish
this preliminary point. Such a compromising policy was short-sighted,
since it was to little purpose that the nature of the documents should at
25length be correctly understood, if men were to be prevented from deducing
fair conclusions from them.
Diluvial Theory.—The theologians who now entered the field in
Italy, Germany, France, and England, were innumerable; and henceforward,
they who refused to subscribe to the position, that all marine
organic remains were proofs of the Mosaic deluge, were exposed to the
imputation of disbelieving the whole of the sacred writings. Scarcely
any step had been made in approximating to sound theories since the
time of Fracastoro, more than a hundred years having been lost, in
writing down the dogma that organized fossils were mere sports of
nature. An additional period of a century and a half was now destined
to be consumed in exploding the hypothesis, that organized fossils had
all been buried in the solid strata by Noah's flood. Never did a theoretical
fallacy, in any branch of science, interfere more seriously with
accurate observation and the systematic classification of facts. In recent
times, we may attribute our rapid progress chiefly to the careful
determination of the order of succession in mineral masses, by means of
their different organic contents, and their regular superposition. But
the old diluvialists were induced by their system to confound all the
groups of strata together instead of discriminating,—to refer all appearances
to one cause and to one brief period, not to a variety of causes
acting throughout a long succession of epochs. They saw the phenomena
only as they desired to see them, sometimes misrepresenting facts,
and at other times deducing false conclusions from correct data. Under
the influence of such prejudices, three centuries were of as little avail as
a few years in our own times, when we are no longer required to propel
the vessel against the force of an adverse current.
It may be well, therefore, to forewarn the reader, that in tracing the
history of geology from the close of the seventeenth to the end of the
eighteenth century, he must expect to be occupied with accounts of the
retardation, as well as of the advance, of the science. It will be necessary
to point out the frequent revival of exploded errors, and the relapse
from sound to the most absurd opinions; and to dwell on futile
reasoning and visionary hypothesis, because some of the most extravagant
systems were invented or controverted by men of acknowledged
talent. In short, a sketch of the progress of geology is the history of
a constant and violent struggle of new opinions against doctrines sanctioned
by the implicit faith of many generations, and supposed to rest
on scriptural authority. The inquiry, therefore, although highly interesting
to one who studies the philosophy of the human mind, is too
often barren of instruction to him who searches for truths in physical
science.
Quirini, 1676.—Quirini, in 1676,52 contended, in opposition to Scilla,
that the diluvian waters could not have conveyed heavy bodies to the
summit of mountains, since the agitation of the sea never (as Boyle had
26demonstrated) extended to great depths;53 and still less could the testacea,
as some pretended, have lived in these diluvian waters; for "the
duration of the flood was brief, and the heavy rains must have destroyed
the saltness of the sea!" He was the first writer who ventured to maintain
that the universality of the Mosaic cataclysm ought not to be insisted
upon. As to the nature of petrified shells, he conceived that as
earthy particles united in the sea to form the shells of mollusca, the
same crystallizing process might be effected on the land; and that, in
the latter case, the germs of the animals might have been disseminated
through the substance of the rocks, and afterwards developed by virtue
of humidity. Visionary as was this doctrine, it gained many proselytes
even amongst the more sober reasoners of Italy and Germany; for it
conceded that the position of fossil bodies could not be accounted for by
the diluvial theory.
Plot—Lister, 1678.—In the mean time, the doctrine that fossil shells
had never belonged to real animals maintained its ground in England,
where the agitation of the question began at a much later period. Dr.
Plot, in his "Natural History of Oxfordshire" (1677), attributed to a
"plastic virtue latent in the earth" the origin of fossil shells and fishes;
and Lister, to his accurate account of British shells, in 1678, added the
fossil species, under the appellation of turbinated and bivalve stones.
"Either," said he, "these were terriginous, or, if otherwise, the animals
they so exactly represent have become extinct." This writer appears to
have been the first who was aware of the continuity over large districts
of the principal groups of strata in the British series, and who proposed
the construction of regular geological maps.54
Leibnitz, 1680.—The great mathematician Leibnitz published his
"Protogœa" in 1680. He imagined this planet to have been originally
a burning luminous mass, which ever since its creation has been undergoing
refrigeration. When the outer crust had cooled down sufficiently
to allow the vapors to be condensed, they fell, and formed a universal
ocean, covering the loftiest mountains, and investing the whole globe.
The crust, as it consolidated from a state of fusion, assumed a vesicular
and cavernous structure; and being rent in some places, allowed the
water to rush into the subterranean hollows, whereby the level of the
primeval ocean was lowered. The breaking in of these vast caverns is
supposed to have given rise to the dislocated and deranged position of
the strata "which Steno had described," and the same disruptions communicated
27
violent movements to the incumbent waters, whence great
inundations ensued. The waters, after they had been thus agitated,
deposited their sedimentary matter during intervals of quiescence, and
hence the various stony and earthy strata. "We may recognize, therefore,"
says Leibnitz, "a double origin of primitive masses, the one by
refrigeration from igneous fusion, the other by concretion from aqueous
solution."55 By the repetition of similar causes (the disruption of the
crust and consequent floods), alternations of new strata were produced,
until at length these causes were reduced to a condition of quiescent
equilibrium, and a more permanent state of things was established.56
Hooke, 1688.—The "Posthumous Works of Robert Hooke, M. D.,"
well known as a great mathematician and natural philosopher, appeared
in 1705, containing "A Discourse of Earthquakes," which, we are informed
by his editor, was written in 1668, but revised at subsequent
periods.57 Hooke frequently refers to the best Italian and English
authors who wrote before his time on geological subjects; but there
are no passages in his works implying that he participated in the enlarged
views of Steno and Lister, or of his contemporary, Woodward,
in regard to the geographical extent of certain groups of strata. His
treatise, however, is the most philosophical production of that age, in
regard to the causes of former changes in the organic and inorganic
kingdoms of nature.
"However trivial a thing," he says, "a rotten shell may appear to
some, yet these monuments of nature are more certain tokens of antiquity
than coins or medals, since the best of those may be counterfeited
or made by art and design, as may also books, manuscripts, and
inscriptions, as all the learned are now sufficiently satisfied has often
been actually practised," &c.; "and though it must be granted that it
is very difficult to read them (the records of nature) and to raise a
chronology out of them, and to state the intervals of the time wherein
such or such catastrophes and mutations have happened, yet it is not
impossible."58
Respecting the extinction of species, Hooke was aware that the
fossil ammonites, nautili, and many other shells and fossil skeletons
found in England, were of different species from any then known; but
he doubted whether the species had become extinct, observing that the
knowledge of naturalists of all the marine species, especially those inhabiting
the deep sea, was very deficient. In some parts of his writings,
28
however, he leans to the opinion that species had been lost; and in
speculating on this subject, he even suggests that there might be some
connection between the disappearance of certain kinds of animals and
plants, and the changes wrought by earthquakes in former ages. Some
species, he observes, with great sagacity, are "peculiar to certain places,
and not to be found elsewhere. If, then, such a place had been swallowed
up, it is not improbable but that those animate beings may have
been destroyed with it; and this may be true both of aerial and aquatic
animals; for those animated bodies, whether vegetables or animals,
which were naturally nourished or refreshed by the air, would be destroyed
by the water," &c.59 Turtles, he adds, and such large ammonites
as are found in Portland, seem to have been the productions of
hotter countries; and it is necessary to suppose that England once lay
under the sea within the torrid zone! To explain this and similar phenomena,
he indulges in a variety of speculations concerning changes in
the position of the axis of the earth's rotation, "a shifting of the earth's
centre of gravity, analogous to the revolutions of the magnetic pole,"
&c. None of these conjectures, however, are proposed dogmatically,
but rather in the hope of promoting fresh inquiries and experiments.
In opposition to the prejudices of his age, we find him arguing
against the idea that nature had formed fossil bodies "for no other end
than to play the mimic in the mineral kingdom;"—maintaining that
figured stones were "really the several bodies they represent, or the
mouldings of them petrified," and not, as some have imagined, 'a lusus
naturæ,' sporting herself in the needless formation of useless beings."60
It was objected to Hooke, that his doctrine of the extinction of
species derogated from the wisdom and power of the omnipotent Creator;
but he answered, that, as individuals die, there may be some termination
to the duration of a species; and his opinions, he declared,
were not repugnant to Holy Writ: for the Scriptures taught that our
system was degenerating, and tending to its final dissolution; "and as,
when that shall happen, all the species will be lost, why not some at
one time and some at another?"61
But his principal object was to account for the manner in which shells
29
had been conveyed into the higher parts of "the Alps, Apennines, and
Pyrenean hills, and the interior of continents in general." These and
other appearances, he said, might have been brought about by earthquakes,
"which have turned plains into mountains, and mountains into
plains, seas into land, and land into seas, made rivers where there were
none before, and swallowed up others that formerly were, &c., &c.; and
which, since the creation of the world, have wrought many great changes
on the superficial parts of the earth, and have been the instruments of
placing shells, bones, plants, fishes, and the like, in those places where,
with much astonishment, we find them."62 This doctrine, it is true, had
been laid down in terms almost equally explicit by Strabo, to explain
the occurrence of fossil shells in the interior of continents, and to that
geographer, and other writers of antiquity, Hooke frequently refers; but
the revival and development of the system was an important step in the
progress of modern science.
Hooke enumerated all the examples known to him of subterranean
disturbance, from "the sad catastrophe of Sodom and Gomorrah," down
to the Chilian earthquake of 1646. The elevating of the bottom of the
sea, the sinking and submersion of the land, and most of the inequalities
of the earth's surface, might, he said, be accounted for by the agency
of these subterranean causes. He mentions that the coast near Naples
was raised during the eruption of Monte Nuovo; and that, in 1591, land
rose in the island of St. Michael, during an eruption: and although it
would be more difficult, he says, to prove, he does not doubt but that
there had been as many earthquakes in the parts of the earth under the
ocean, as in the parts of the dry land; in confirmation of which, he
mentions the immeasurable depth of the sea near some volcanoes. To
attest the extent of simultaneous subterranean movements, he refers to
an earthquake in the West Indies, in the year 1690, where the space of
earth raised, or "struck upwards," by the shock, exceeded, he affirms,
the length of the Alps and Pyrenees.
Hooke's diluvial Theory.—As Hooke declared the favorite hypothesis
of the day, "that marine fossil bodies were to be referred to Noah's
flood," to be wholly untenable, he appears to have felt himself called
upon to substitute a diluvial theory of his own, and thus he became involved
in countless difficulties and contradictions. "During the great
catastrophe," he said, "there might have been a changing of that part
which was before dry land into sea by sinking, and of that which was
sea into dry land by raising, and marine bodies might have been buried
in sediment beneath the ocean, in the interval between the creation and
the deluge."63 Then follows a disquisition on the separation of the land
from the waters, mentioned in Genesis; during which operation some
places of the shell of the earth were forced outwards, and others pressed
downwards or inwards, &c. His diluvial hypothesis very much resembled
that of Steno, and was entirely opposed to the fundamental
30
principles professed by him, that he would explain the former changes
of the earth in a more natural manner than others had done. When,
in despite of this declaration, he required a former "crisis of nature,"
and taught that earthquakes had become debilitated, and that the Alps,
Andes, and other chains, had been lifted up in a few months, he was
compelled to assume so rapid a rate of change, that his machinery appeared
scarcely less extravagant than that of his most fanciful predecessors.
For this reason, perhaps, his whole theory of earthquakes met
with undeserved neglect.
Ray, 1692.—One of his contemporaries, the celebrated naturalist,
Ray, participated in the same desire to explain geological phenomena
by reference to causes less hypothetical than those usually resorted to.64
In his essay on "Chaos and Creation," he proposed a system, agreeing
in its outline, and in many of its details, with that of Hooke; but his
knowledge of natural history enabled him to elucidate the subject with
various original observations. Earthquakes, he suggested, might have
been the second causes employed at the creation, in separating the land
from the waters, and in gathering the waters together into one place.
He mentions, like Hooke, the earthquake of 1646, which had violently
shaken the Andes for some hundreds of leagues, and made many alterations
therein. In assigning a cause for the general deluge, he preferred
a change in the earth's centre of gravity to the introduction of earthquakes.
Some unknown cause, he said, might have forced the subterranean
waters outwards, as was, perhaps, indicated by "the breaking
up of the fountains of the great deep."
Ray was one of the first of our writers who enlarged upon the effects
of running water upon the land, and of the encroachment of the sea
upon the shores. So important did he consider the agency of these
causes, that he saw in them an indication of the tendency of our system
to its final dissolution; and he wondered why the earth did not proceed
more rapidly towards a general submersion beneath the sea, when so
much matter was carried down by rivers, or undermined in the sea-cliffs.
We perceive clearly from his writings, that the gradual decline of our
system, and its future consummation by fire, was held to be as necessary
an article of faith by the orthodox, as was the recent origin of our planet.
His discourses, like those of Hooke, are highly interesting, as attesting
the familiar association in the minds of philosophers, in the age of Newton,
of questions in physics and divinity. Ray gave an unequivocal proof
of the sincerity of his mind, by sacrificing his preferment in the church,
rather than take an oath against the Covenanters, which he could not
reconcile with his conscience. His reputation, moreover, in the scientific
world placed him high above the temptation of courting popularity, by
pandering to the physico-theological taste of his age. It is, therefore,
31
curious to meet with so many citations from the Christian fathers and
prophets in his essays on physical science—to find him in one page proceeding,
by the strict rules of induction, to explain the former changes
of the globe, and in the next gravely entertaining the question, whether
the sun and stars, and the whole heavens, shall be annihilated, together
with the earth, at the era of the grand conflagration.
Woodward, 1695.—Among the contemporaries of Hooke and Ray,
Woodward, a professor of medicine, had acquired the most extensive
information respecting the geological structure of the crust of the earth.
He had examined many parts of the British strata with minute attention;
and his systematic collection of specimens, bequeathed to the
University of Cambridge, and still preserved there as arranged by him,
shows how far he had advanced in ascertaining the order of superposition.
From the great number of facts collected by him, we might have
expected his theoretical views to be more sound and enlarged than
those of his contemporaries; but in his anxiety to accommodate all observed
phenomena to the scriptural account of the Creation and Deluge,
he arrived at most erroneous results. He conceived "the whole terrestrial
globe to have been taken to pieces and dissolved at the flood, and
the strata to have settled down from this promiscuous mass as any earthy
sediment from a fluid."65 In corroboration of these views he insisted
upon the fact, that "marine bodies are lodged in the strata according
to the order of their gravity, the heavier shells in stone, the lighter in
chalk, and so of the rest."66 Ray immediately exposed the unfounded
nature of this assertion, remarking truly that fossil bodies "are often
mingled, heavy with light, in the same stratum;" and he even went so
far as to say, that Woodward "must have invented the phenomena for
the sake of confirming his bold and strange hypothesis"67—a strong expression
from the pen of a contemporary.
Burnet, 1690.—At the same time Burnet published his "Theory of
the Earth."68 The title is most characteristic of the age,—"The Sacred
Theory of the Earth; containing an Account of the Original of the
Earth, and of all the general Changes which it hath already undergone,
or is to undergo, till the Consummation of all Things." Even Milton
had scarcely ventured in his poem to indulge his imagination so freely
in painting scenes of the Creation and Deluge, Paradise and Chaos.
He explained why the primeval earth enjoyed a perpetual spring before
the flood! showed how the crust of the globe was fissured by "the
sun's rays," so that it burst, and thus the diluvial waters were let loose
from a supposed central abyss. Not satisfied with these themes, he
derived from the books of the inspired writers, and even from heathen
authorities, prophetic views of the future revolutions of the globe, gave
a most terrific description of the general conflagration, and proved that
32
a new heaven and a new earth will rise out of a second chaos—after
which will follow the blessed millennium.
The reader should be informed, that, according to the opinion of many
respectable writers of that age, there was good scriptural ground for
presuming that the garden bestowed upon our first parents was not on
the earth itself, but above the clouds, in the middle region between our
planet and the moon. Burnet approaches with becoming gravity the
discussion of so important a topic. He was willing to concede that the
geographical position of Paradise was not in Mesopotamia, yet he maintained
that it was upon the earth, and in the southern hemisphere, near the
equinoctial line. Butler selected this conceit as a fair mark for his satire,
when, amongst the numerous accomplishments of Hudibras, he says,—

"He knew the seat of Paradise,
Could tell in what degree it lies;
And, as he was disposed, could prove it
Below the moon, or else above it."

Yet the same monarch, who is said never to have slept without Butler's
poem under his pillow, was so great an admirer and patron of Burnet's
book, that he ordered it to be translated from the Latin into English.
The style of the "Sacred Theory" was eloquent, and the book displayed
powers of invention of no ordinary stamp. It was, in fact, a
fine historical romance, as Buffon afterwards declared; but it was
treated as a work of profound science in the time of its author, and was
panegyrized by Addison in a Latin ode, while Steele praised it in the
"Spectator."
Whiston, 1696.—Another production of the same school, and equally
characteristic of the time, was that of Whiston, entitled, "A New
Theory of the Earth; wherein the Creation of the world in Six Days,
the Universal Deluge, and the General Conflagration, as laid down in
the Holy Scriptures, are shown to be perfectly agreeable to Reason and
Philosophy." He was at first a follower of Burnet; but his faith in
the infallibility of that writer was shaken by the declared opinion of
Newton, that there was every presumption in astronomy against any
former change in the inclination of the earth's axis. This was a leading
dogma in Burnet's system, though not original, for it was borrowed
from an Italian, Alessandro degli Alessandri, who had suggested it in
the beginning of the fifteenth century, to account for the former occupation
of the present continents by the sea. La Place has since strengthened
the arguments of Newton, against the probability of any former
revolution of this kind.
The remarkable comet of 1680 was fresh in the memory of every
one when Whiston first began his cosmological studies; and the principal
novelty of his speculations consisted in attributing the deluge to the
near approach to the earth of one of these erratic bodies. Having
ascribed an increase of the waters to this source, he adopted Woodward's
33
theory, supposing all stratified deposits to have resulted from
the "chaotic sediment of the flood." Whiston was one of the first who
ventured to propose that the text of Genesis should be interpreted differently
from its ordinary acceptation, so that the doctrine of the earth
having existed long previous to the creation of man might no longer be
regarded as unorthodox. He had the art to throw an air of plausibility
over the most improbable parts of his theory, and seemed to be proceeding
in the most sober manner, and, by the aid of mathematical demonstration,
to the establishment of his various propositions. Locke
pronounced a panegyric on his theory, commending him for having explained
so many wonderful and before inexplicable things. His book,
as well as Burnet's, was attacked and refuted by Keill.69 Like all who
introduced purely hypothetical causes to account for natural phenomena,
Whiston retarded the progress of truth, diverting men from the
investigation of the laws of sublunary nature, and inducing them to
waste time in speculations on the power of comets to drag the waters
of the ocean over the land—on the condensation of the vapors of their
tails into water, and other matters equally edifying.
Hutchinson, 1724.—John Hutchinson, who had been employed by
Woodward in making his collection of fossils, published afterwards, in
1724, the first part of his "Moses's Principia," wherein he ridiculed
Woodward's hypothesis. He and his numerous followers were accustomed
to declaim loudly against human learning; and they maintained
that the Hebrew Scriptures, when rightly translated, comprised a perfect
system of natural philosophy, for which reason they objected to the
Newtonian theory of gravitation.
Celsius.—Andrea Celsius, the Swedish astronomer, published about
this time his remarks on the gradual diminution and sinking of the
waters in the Baltic, to which I shall have occasion to advert more particularly
in the sequel (ch. 29).
Scheuchzer, 1708.—In Germany, in the mean time, Scheuchzer published
his "Complaint and Vindication of the Fishes" (1708), "Piscium
Querelæ et Vindiciæ," a work of zoological merit, in which he gave
some good plates and descriptions of fossil fish. Among other conclusions
he labored to prove that the earth had been remodelled at the
deluge. Pluche, also, in 1732, wrote to the same effect; while Holbach,
in 1753, after considering the various attempts to refer all the ancient
formations to the flood of Noah, exposed the inadequacy of this
cause.
Italian Geologists—Vallisneri.—I return with pleasure to the geologists
of Italy, who preceded, as has been already shown, the naturalists
of other countries in their investigations into the ancient history of
the earth, and who still maintained a decided pre-eminence. They refuted
and ridiculed the physico-theological systems of Burnet, Whiston,
34
and Woodward;70 while Vallisneri,71 in his comments on the Woodwardian
theory, remarked how much the interests of religion, as well as those
of sound philosophy, had suffered by perpetually mixing up the sacred
writings with questions in physical science. The works of this author
were rich in original observations. He attempted the first general
sketch of the marine deposits of Italy, their geographical extent, and
most characteristic organic remains. In his treatise "On the Origin of
Springs," he explained their dependence on the order, and often on the
dislocations, of the strata, and reasoned philosophically against the
opinions of those who regarded the disordered state of the earth's crust
as exhibiting signs of the wrath of God for the sins of man. He found
himself under the necessity of contending, in his preliminary chapter,
against St. Jerome, and four other principal interpreters of Scripture,
besides several professors of divinity, "that springs did not flow by subterranean
siphons and cavities from the sea upwards, losing their saltness
in the passage," for this theory had been made to rest on the infallible
testimony of Holy Writ.
Although reluctant to generalize on the rich materials accumulated
in his travels, Vallisneri had been so much struck with the remarkable
continuity of the more recent marine strata, from one end of Italy to the
other, that he came to the conclusion that the ocean formerly extended
over the whole earth, and after abiding there for a long time, had gradually
subsided. This opinion, however untenable, was a great step beyond
Woodward's diluvian hypothesis, against which Vallisneri, and
after him all the Tuscan geologists, uniformly contended, while it was
warmly supported by the members of the Institute of Bologna.72
Among others of that day, Spada, a priest of Grezzana, in 1737,
wrote to prove that the petrified marine bodies near Verona were not
diluvian.73 Mattani drew a similar inference from the shells of Volterra
and other places; while Costantini, on the other hand, whose observations
on the valley of the Brenta and other districts were not without
value, undertook to vindicate the truth of the deluge, as also to prove
that Italy had been peopled by the descendants of Japhet.74
Moro, 1740.—Lazzaro Moro, in his work (published in 1740) "On the
Marine Bodies which are found in the Mountains,"75 attempted to apply
the theory of earthquakes, as expounded by Strabo, Pliny, and
other ancient authors, with whom he was familiar, to the geological
phenomena described by Vallisneri.76 His attention was awakened to
35
the elevating power of subterranean forces by a remarkable phenomenon
which happened in his own time, and which had also been noticed by
Vallisneri in his letters. A new island rose in 1707 from deep water in
the Gulf of Santorin, in the Mediterranean, during continued shocks of
an earthquake, and, increasing rapidly in size, grew in less than a month
to be half a mile in circumference, and about twenty-five feet above
high-water mark. It was soon afterwards covered by volcanic ejections,
but, when first examined, it was found to be a white rock, bearing on
its surface living oysters and crustacea. In order to ridicule the various
theories then in vogue, Moro ingeniously supposes the arrival on
this new island of a party of naturalists ignorant of its recent origin.
One immediately points to the marine shells, as proofs of the universal
deluge; another argues that they demonstrate the former residence of
the sea upon the mountains; a third dismisses them as mere sports of
nature; while a fourth affirms that they were born and nourished
within the rock in ancient caverns, into which salt water had been raised
in the shape of vapor by the action of subterranean heat.
Moro pointed with great judgment to the faults and dislocations of
the strata described by Vallisneri, in the Alps and other chains, in confirmation
of his doctrine, that the continents had been heaved up by
subterranean movements. He objected, on solid grounds, to the hypothesis
of Burnet and of Woodward; yet he ventured so far to disregard
the protest of Vallisneri, as to undertake the adaptation of every part of
his own system to the Mosaic account of the creation. On the third
day, he said, the globe was everywhere covered to the same depth by
fresh water; and when it pleased the Supreme Being that the dry land
should appear, volcanic explosions broke up the smooth and regular
surface of the earth composed of primary rocks. These rose in mountain
masses above the waves, and allowed melted metals and salts to
ascend through fissures. The sea gradually acquired its saltness from
volcanic exhalations, and, while it became more circumscribed in area,
increased in depth. Sand and ashes ejected by volcanoes were regularly
disposed along the bottom of the ocean, and formed the secondary
strata, which in their turn were lifted up by earthquakes. We need
not follow this author in tracing the progress of the creation of vegetables
and animals on the other days of creation; but, upon the whole, it
may be remarked, that few of the old cosmological theories had been
conceived with so little violation of known analogies.
Generelli's illustrations of Moro, 1749.—The style of Moro was extremely
prolix, and, like Hutton, who, at a later period, advanced many
of the same views, he stood in need of an illustrator. The Scotch geologist
was hardly more fortunate in the advocacy of Playfair, than was
Moro in numbering amongst his admirers Cirillo Generelli, who, nine
36
years afterwards, delivered at a sitting of Academicians at Cremona a
spirited exposition of his theory. This learned Carmelitan friar does not
pretend to have been an original observer, but he had studied sufficiently
to enable him to confirm the opinions of Moro by arguments from other
writers; and his selection of the doctrines then best established is so
judicious, that a brief abstract of them cannot fail to be acceptable, as
illustrating the state of geology in Europe, and in Italy in particular,
before the middle of the last century.
The bowels of the earth, says he, have carefully preserved the memorials
of past events, and this truth the marine productions so frequent
in the hills attest. From the reflections of Lazzaro Moro, we may assure
ourselves that these are the effects of earthquakes in past times,
which have changed vast spaces of sea into terra firma, and inhabited
lands into seas. In this, more than in any other department of physics,
are observations and experiments indispensable, and we must diligently
consider facts. The land is known, wherever we make excavations, to
be composed of different strata or soils placed one above the other, some
of sand, some of rock, some of chalk, others of marl, coal, pummice,
gypsum, lime, and the rest. These ingredients are sometimes pure, and
sometimes confusedly intermixed. Within are often imprisoned different
marine fishes, like dried mummies, and more frequently shells, crustacea,
corals, plants, &c., not only in Italy, but in France, Germany,
England, Africa, Asia, and America;—sometimes in the lowest, sometimes
in the loftiest beds of the earth, some upon the mountains, some
in deep mines, others near the sea, and others hundreds of miles distant
from it. Woodward conjectured that these marine bodies might be
found everywhere; but there are rocks in which none of them occur,
as is sufficiently attested by Vallisneri and Marsilli. The remains of
fossil animals consist chiefly of their more solid parts, and the most
rocky strata must have been soft when such exuviæ were inclosed in
them. Vegetable productions are found in different states of maturity,
indicating that they were imbedded in different seasons. Elephants,
elks, and other terrestrial quadrupeds, have been found in England and
elsewhere, in superficial strata, never covered by the sea. Alternations
are rare, yet not without example, of marine strata, with those which
contain marshy and terrestrial productions. Marine animals are arranged
in the subterraneous beds with admirable order, in distinct
groups, oysters here, dentalia or corals there, &c., as now, according to
Marsilli,77 on the shores of the Adriatic. We must abandon the doctrine,
once so popular, which denies that organized fossils were derived
from living beings, and we cannot account for their present position by
the ancient theory of Strabo, nor by that of Leibnitz, nor by the universal
deluge, as explained by Woodward and others; "nor is it reasonable
to call the Deity capriciously upon the stage, and to make him
work miracles for the sake of confirming our preconceived
37
hypothesis."—"I hold in utter abomination, most learned Academicians! those
systems which are built with their foundations in the air, and cannot be
propped up without a miracle; and I undertake, with the assistance of
Moro, to explain to you how these marine animals were transported
into the mountains by natural causes."78
A brief abstract then follows of Moro's theory, by which, says Generelli,
we may explain all the phenomena, as Vallisneri so ardently desired,
"without violence, without fictions, without hypothesis, without
miracles."79 The Carmelitan then proceeds to struggle against an obvious
objection to Moro's system, considered as a method of explaining
the revolutions of the earth, naturally. If earthquakes have been the
agents of such mighty changes, how does it happen that their effects
since the times of history have been so inconsiderable? This same difficulty
had, as we have seen, presented itself to Hooke, half a century
before, and forced him to resort to a former "crisis of nature:" but
Generelli defended his position by showing how numerous were the
accounts of eruptions and earthquakes, of new islands, and of elevations
and subsidences of land, and yet how much greater a number of
like events must have been unattested and unrecorded during the last
six thousand years. He also appealed to Vallisneri as an authority to
prove that the mineral masses containing shells, bore, upon the whole,
but a small proportion to those rocks which were destitute of organic
remains; and the latter, says the learned monk, might have been created
as they now exist, in the beginning.
Generelli then describes the continual waste of mountains and continents,
by the action of rivers and torrents, and concludes with these
eloquent and original observations:—"Is it possible that this waste
should have continued for six thousand, and perhaps a greater number
of years, and that the mountains should remain so great, unless their
ruins have been repaired? Is it credible that the Author of Nature
should have founded the world upon such laws, as that the dry land
should forever be growing smaller, and at last become wholly submerged
beneath the waters? Is it credible that, amid so many created
things, the mountains alone should daily diminish in number and bulk,
without there being any repair of their losses? This would be contrary
to that order of Providence which is seen to reign in all other things in
the universe. Wherefore I deem it just to conclude, that the same
cause which, in the beginning of time, raised mountains from the abyss,
has down to the present day continued to produce others, in order to
restore from time to time the losses of all such as sink down in different
places, or are rent asunder, or in other way suffer disintegration. If
this be admitted, we can easily understand why there should now be
38
found upon many mountains so great a number of crustacea and other
marine animals."
In the above extract, I have not merely enumerated the opinions and
facts which are confirmed by recent observation, suppressing all that
has since proved to be erroneous, but have given a faithful abridgment
of the entire treatise, with the omission only of Moro's hypothesis, which
Generelli adopted, with all its faults and excellences. The reader will
therefore remark, that although this admirable essay embraces so large
a portion of the principal objects of geological research, it makes no
allusion to the extinction of certain classes of animals; and it is evident
that no opinions on this head had, at that time, gained a firm footing in
Italy. That Lister and other English naturalists should long before
have declared in favor of the loss of species, while Scilla and most of
his countrymen hesitated, was perhaps natural, since the Italian museums
were filled with fossil shells belonging to species of which a great
portion did actually exist in the Mediterranean; whereas the English
collectors could obtain no recent species from such of their own strata
as were then explored.
The weakest point in Moro's system consisted in deriving all the stratified
rocks from volcanic ejections; an absurdity which his opponents
took care to expose, especially Vito Amici.80 Moro seems to have been
misled by his anxious desire to represent the formation of secondary
rocks as having occupied an extremely short period, while at the same
time he wished to employ known agents in nature. To imagine torrents,
rivers, currents, partial floods, and all the operations of moving
water, to have gone on exerting an energy many thousand times greater
than at present, would have appeared preposterous and incredible, and
would have required a hundred violent hypotheses; but we are so unacquainted
with the true sources of subterranean disturbances, that their
former violence may in theory be multiplied indefinitely, without its
being possible to prove the same manifest contradiction or absurdity in
the conjecture. For this reason, perhaps, Moro preferred to derive the
materials of the strata from volcanic ejections, rather than from transportation
by running water.
Marsilli.—Marsilli, whose work is alluded to by Generelli, had been
prompted to institute inquiries into the bed of the Adriatic, by discovering,
in the territory of Parma (what Spada had observed near Verona,
and Schiavo in Sicily), that fossil shells were not scattered through the
rocks at random, but disposed in regular order, according to certain
genera and species.
Vitaliano Donati, 1750.—But with a view of throwing further light
upon these questions, Donati, in 1750, undertook a more extensive investigation
of the Adriatic, and discovered, by numerous soundings, that deposits
of sand, marl, and tufaceous incrustations, most strictly analogous
to those of the Subapennine hills, were in the act of accumulating there.
39
He ascertained that there were no shells in some of the submarine
tracts, while in other places they lived together in families, particularly
the genera Arca, Pecten, Venus, Murex, and some others. He also
states that in divers localities he found a mass composed of corals,
shells, and crustaceous bodies of different species, confusedly blended
with earth, sand, and gravel. At the depth of a foot or more, the
organic substances were entirely petrified and reduced to marble; at
less than a foot from the surface, they approached nearer to their natural
state; while at the surface they were alive, or, if dead, in a good
state of preservation.
Baldassari.—A contemporary naturalist, Baldassari, had shown that
the organic remains in the tertiary marls of the Siennese territory were
grouped in families, in a manner precisely similar to that above alluded
to by Donati.
Buffon, 1749.—Buffon first made known his theoretical views concerning
the former changes of the earth, in his Natural History, published
in 1749. He adopted the theory of an original volcanic nucleus,
together with the universal ocean of Leibnitz. By this aqueous envelope
the highest mountains were once covered. Marine currents then
acted violently, and formed horizontal strata, by washing away solid
matter in some parts, and depositing it in others; they also excavated
deep submarine valleys. The level of the ocean was then depressed by
the entrance of a part of its waters into subterranean caverns, and thus
some land was left dry. Buffon seems not to have profited, like Leibnitz
and Moro, by the observations of Steno, or he could not have imagined
that the strata were generally horizontal, and that those which
contain organic remains had never been disturbed since the era of their
formation. He was conscious of the great power annually exerted by
rivers and marine currents in transporting earthy materials to lower
levels, and he even contemplated the period when they would destroy
all the present continents. Although in geology he was not an original
observer, his genius enabled him to render his hypothesis attractive;
and by the eloquence of his style, and the boldness of his speculations,
he awakened curiosity, and provoked a spirit of inquiry amongst his
countrymen.
Soon after the publication of his "Natural History," in which was
included his "Theory of the Earth," he received an official letter (dated
January, 1751) from the Sorbonne, or Faculty of Theology in Paris,
informing him that fourteen propositions in his works "were reprehensible,
and contrary to the creed of the church." The first of these obnoxious
passages, and the only one relating to geology, was as follows:—"The
waters of the sea have produced the mountains and valleys of the
land—the waters of the heavens, reducing all to a level, will at last deliver
the whole land over to the sea, and the sea successively prevailing
over the land, will leave dry new continents like those which we inhabit."
Buffon was invited by the College, in very courteous terms, to
send in an explanation, or rather a recantation of his unorthodox opinions.
40
To this he submitted; and a general assembly of the Faculty
having approved of his "Declaration," he was required to publish it in
his next work. The document begins with these words:—"I declare
that I had no intention to contradict the text of Scripture; that I believe
most firmly all therein related about the creation, both as to order
of time and matter of fact; and I abandon every thing in my book respecting
the foundation of the earth, and, generally, all which may be
contrary to the narration of Moses."81
The grand principle which Buffon was called upon to renounce was
simply this,—that the present mountains and valleys of the earth are
due to secondary causes, and that the same causes will in time destroy
all the continents, hills, and valleys, and reproduce others like them.
Now, whatever may be the defects of many of his views, it is no longer
controverted that the present continents are of secondary origin. The
doctrine is as firmly established as the earth's rotation on its axis; and
that the land now elevated above the level of the sea will not endure
forever, is an opinion which gains ground daily, in proportion as we
enlarge our experience of the changes now in progress.
Targioni, 1751.—Targioni, in his voluminous "Travels in Tuscany,
1751 and 1754," labored to fill up the sketch of the geology of that
region left by Steno sixty years before. Notwithstanding a want of
arrangement and condensation in his memoirs, they contained a rich
store of faithful observations. He has not indulged in many general
views, but in regard to the origin of valleys, he was opposed to the
theory of Buffon, who attributed them principally to submarine currents.
The Tuscan naturalist labored to show that both the larger and smaller
valleys of the Apennines were excavated by rivers and floods, caused
by the bursting of the barriers of lakes, after the retreat of the ocean.
He also maintained that the elephants and other quadrupeds, so frequent
in the lacustrine and alluvial deposits of Italy, had inhabited that
peninsula; and had not been transported thither, as some had conceived,
by Hannibal or the Romans, nor by what they were pleased to term
"a catastrophe of nature."
Lehman, 1756.—In the year 1756 the treatise of Lehman, a German
mineralogist, and director of the Prussian mines, appeared, who also
divided mountains into three classes: the first, those formed with the
world, and prior to the creation of animals, and which contained no
fragments of other rocks; the second class, those which resulted from
the partial destruction of the primary rocks by a general revolution;
and a third class, resulting from local revolutions, and in part from the
deluge of Noah.
A French translation of this work appeared in 1759, in the preface
of which, the translator displays very enlightened views respecting the
operations of earthquakes, as well as of the aqueous causes.82
41Gesner, 1758.—In this year Gesner, the botanist, of Zurich, published
an excellent treatise on petrifactions, and the changes of the
earth which they testify.83 After a detailed enumeration of the various
classes of fossils of the animal and vegetable kingdoms, and remarks on
the different states in which they are found petrified, he considers the
geological phenomena connected with them; observing, that some, like
those of Œningen, resembled the testacea, fish, and plants indigenous
in the neighboring region;84 while some, such as ammonites, gryphites,
belemnites, and other shells, are either of unknown species, or found
only in the Indian and other distant seas. In order to elucidate the
structure of the earth, he gives sections, from Verenius, Buffon, and
others, obtained in digging wells; distinguishes between horizontal and
inclined strata; and, in speculating on the causes of these appearances,
mentions Donati's examination of the bed of the Adriatic; the filling
up of lakes and seas by sediment; the imbedding of shells now in progress;
and many known effects of earthquakes, such as the sinking
down of districts, or the heaving up of the bed of the sea, so as to form
new islands, and lay dry strata containing petrifactions. The ocean, he
says, deserts its shores in many countries, as on the borders of the
Baltic; but the rate of recession has been so slow in the last 2000
years, that to allow the Apennines, whose summits are filled with marine
shells, to emerge to their present height, would have required about
80,000 years,—a lapse of time ten times greater, or more, than the age
of the universe. We must therefore refer the phenomenon to the command
of the Deity, related by Moses, that "the waters should be
gathered together in one place, and the dry land appear." Gesner
adopted the views of Leibnitz, to account for the retreat of the primeval
ocean: his essay displays much erudition; and the opinions of preceding
writers of Italy, Germany, and England, are commented upon with
fairness and discrimination.
Arduino, 1759.—In the year following, Arduino,85 in his memoirs on
the mountains of Padua, Vicenza, and Verona, deduced, from original
observations, the distinction of rocks into primary, secondary, and tertiary,
and showed that in those districts there had been a succession of
submarine volcanic eruptions.
Michell, 1760.—In the following year (1760) the Rev. John Michell,
Woodwardian Professor of Mineralogy at Cambridge, published in the
Philosophical Transactions, an Essay on the Cause and Phenomena of
Earthquakes.86 His attention had been drawn to this subject by the
42
great earthquake of Lisbon in 1755. He advanced many original and
philosophical views respecting the propagation of subterranean movements,
and the caverns and fissures wherein steam might be generated.
In order to point out the application of his theory to the structure of
the globe, he was led to describe the arrangement and disturbance of
the strata, their usual horizontality in low countries, and their contortions
and fractured state in the neighborhood of mountain chains. He also explained,
with surprising accuracy, the relations of the central ridges of
older rocks to the "long narrow slips of similar earth, stones, and minerals,"
which are parallel to these ridges. In his generalizations, derived
in great part from his own observations on the geological structure of
Yorkshire, he anticipated many of the views more fully developed by
later naturalists.
Catcott, 1761.—Michell's papers were entirely free from all physico-theological
disquisitions, but some of his contemporaries were still earnestly
engaged in defending or impugning the Woodwardian hypothesis.
We find many of these writings referred to by Catcott, a Hutchinsonian,
who published a "Treatise on the Deluge" in 1761. He labored particularly
to refute an explanation offered by his contemporary, Bishop
Clayton, of the Mosaic writings. That prelate had declared that the
deluge "could not be literally true, save in respect to that part where
Noah lived before the flood." Catcott insisted on the universality of
the deluge, and referred to traditions of inundations mentioned by ancient
writers, or by travellers, in the East Indies, China, South America,
and other countries. This part of his book is valuable, although it is
not easy to see what bearing the traditions have, if admitted to be authentic,
on the Bishop's argument, since no evidence is adduced to prove
that the catastrophes were contemporaneous events, while some of them
are expressly represented by ancient authors to have occurred in succession.
Fortis—Odoardi, 1761.—The doctrines of Arduino, above adverted
to, were afterwards confirmed by Fortis and Desmarest, in their travels
in the same country; and they, as well as Baldassari, labored to complete
the history of the Subapennine strata. In the work of Odoardi,87
there was also a clear argument in favor of the distinct ages of the older
Apennine strata, and the Subapennine formations of more recent origin.
He pointed out that the strata of these two groups were unconformable,
and must have been the deposits of different seas at distant
periods of time.
Raspe, 1763.—A history of the new islands, by Raspe, a Hanoverian,
43
appeared in 1763, in Latin.88 In this work, all the authentic accounts
of earthquakes which had produced permanent changes on the
solid parts of the earth were collected together and examined with judicious
criticism. The best systems which had been proposed concerning
the ancient history of the globe, both by ancient and modern writers,
are reviewed; and the merits and defects of the doctrines of Hooke,
Ray, Moro, Buffon, and others, fairly estimated. Great admiration is
expressed for the hypothesis of Hooke, and his explanation of the origin
of the strata is shown to have been more correct than Moro's, while their
theory of the effects of earthquakes was the same. Raspe had not seen
Michell's memoirs, and his views concerning the geological structure of
the earth were perhaps less enlarged; yet he was able to add many
additional arguments in favor of Hook's theory, and to render it, as he
said, a nearer approach to what Hooke would have written had he lived
in later times. As to the periods wherein all the earthquakes happened,
to which we owe the elevation of various parts of our continents and
islands, Raspe says he pretends not to assign their duration, still less to
defend Hooke's suggestion, that the convulsions almost all took place
during the deluge of Noah. He adverts to the apparent indications of
the former tropical heat of the climate of Europe, and the changes in
the species of animals and plants, as among the most obscure and difficult
problems in geology. In regard to the islands raised from the sea,
within the times of history or tradition, he declares that some of them
were composed of strata containing organic remains, and that they were
not, as Buffon had asserted, made of mere volcanic matter. His work
concludes with an eloquent exhortation to naturalists to examine the isles
which rose, in 1707, in the Grecian Archipelago, and, in 1720, in the Azores,
and not to neglect such splendid opportunities of studying nature "in
the act of parturition." That Hooke's writings should have been neglected
for more than half a century, was matter of astonishment to
Raspe; but it is still more wonderful that his own luminous exposition
of that theory should, for more than another half century, have excited
so little interest.
Fuchsel, 1762 and 1773.—Fuchsel, a German physician, published,
in 1762, a geological description of the country between the Thuringerwald
and the Hartz, and a memoir on the environs of Rudelstadt;89 and
afterwards, in 1773, a theoretical work on the ancient history of the
earth and of man.90 He had evidently advanced considerably beyond
his predecessor Lehman, and was aware of the distinctness, both as to
position and fossil contents, of several groups of strata of different ages,
corresponding to the secondary formations now recognized by geologists
44
in various parts of Germany. He supposed the European continents to
have remained covered by the sea until the formation of the marine strata,
called in Germany "muschelkalk," at the same time that the terrestrial
plants of many European deposits, attested the existence of dry land
which bordered the ancient sea; land which, therefore, must have occupied
the place of the present ocean. The pre-existing continent had
been gradually swallowed up by the sea, different parts having subsided
in succession into subterranean caverns. All the sedimentary strata
were originally horizontal, and their present state of derangement must
be referred to subsequent oscillations of the ground.
As there were plants and animals in the ancient periods, so also there
must have been men, but they did not all descend from one pair, but
were created at various points on the earth's surface; and the number
of these distinct birth-places was as great as are the original languages
of nations.
In the writings of Fuchsel we see a strong desire manifested to explain
geological phenomena as far as possible by reference to the agency
of known causes; and although some of his speculations were fanciful,
his views coincide much more nearly with those now generally adopted,
than the theories afterwards promulgated by Werner and his followers.
Brander, 1766.—Gustavus Brander published, in 1766, his "Fossilia
Hantoniensia," containing excellent figures of fossil shells from the more
modern (or Eocene) marine strata of Hampshire. "Various opinions,"
he says in the preface, "had been entertained concerning the time when
and how these bodies became deposited. Some there are who conceive
that it might have been effected in a wonderful length of time by a
gradual changing and shifting of the sea," &c. But the most common
cause assigned is that of "the deluge." This conjecture, he says, even
if the universality of the flood be not called in question, is purely hypothetical.
In his opinion, fossil animals and testacea were, for the most
part, of unknown species; and of such as were known, the living analogues
now belonged to southern latitudes.
Soldani, 1780.—Soldani applied successfully his knowledge of zoology
to illustrate the history of stratified masses. He explained that microscopic
testacea and zoophytes inhabited the depths of the Mediterranean;
and that the fossil species were, in like manner, found in those deposits
wherein the fineness of their particles, and the absence of pebbles, implied
that they were accumulated in a deep sea, or far from shore. This
author first remarked the alternation of marine and freshwater strata in
the Paris basin.91
Fortis—Testa, 1793.—A lively controversy arose between Fortis and
another Italian naturalist, Testa, concerning the fish of Monte Bolca, in
1793. Their letters,92 written with great spirit and elegance, show that
they were aware that a large proportion of the Subapennine shells were
45
identical with living species, and some of them with species now living
in the torrid zone. Fortis proposed a somewhat fanciful conjecture, that
when the volcanoes of the Vicentin were burning, the waters of the Adriatic
had a higher temperature; and in this manner, he said, the shells
of warmer regions may once have peopled their own seas. But Testa
was disposed to think that these species of testacea were still common
to their own and to equinoctial seas; for many, he said, once supposed
to be confined to hotter regions, had been afterwards discovered in the
Mediterranean.93
Cortesi—Spallanzani—Wallerius—Whitehurst.—While these Italian
naturalists, together with Cortesi and Spallanzani, were busily engaged
in pointing out the analogy between the deposits of modern and
ancient seas, and the habits and arrangement of their organic inhabitants,
and while some progress was making, in the same country, in
investigating the ancient and modern volcanic rocks, some of the most
original observers among the English and German writers, Whitehurst94
and Wallerius, were wasting their strength in contending, according to
the old Woodwardian hypothesis, that all the strata were formed by
Noah's deluge. But Whitehurst's description of the rocks of Derbyshire
was most faithful; and he atoned for false theoretical views, by
providing data for their refutation.
Pallas—Saussure.—Towards the close of the eighteenth century, the
idea of distinguishing the mineral masses on our globe into separate
groups, and studying their relations, began to be generally diffused.
Pallas and Saussure were among the most celebrated whose labors contributed
to this end. After an attentive examination of the two great
mountain chains of Siberia, Pallas announced the result, that the granitic
rocks were in the middle, the schistose at their sides, and the limestones
again on the outside of these; and this he conceived would
prove a general law in the formation of all chains composed chiefly of
primary rocks.95
In his "Travels in Russia," in 1793 and 1794, he made many geological
observations on the recent strata near the Wolga and the Caspian,
and adduced proofs of the greater extent of the latter sea at no
distant era in the earth's history. His memoir on the fossil bones of
Siberia attracted attention to some of the most remarkable phenomena
in geology. He stated that he had found a rhinoceros entire in the frozen
soil, with its skin and flesh: an elephant, found afterwards in a mass
46
of ice on the shore of the North Sea, removed all doubt as to the accuracy
of so wonderful a discovery.96
The subjects relating to natural history which engaged the attention
of Pallas, were too multifarious to admit of his devoting a large share
of his labors exclusively to geology. Saussure, on the other hand, employed
the chief portion of his time in studying the structure of the
Alps and Jura, and he provided valuable data for those who followed
him. He did not pretend to deduce any general system from his numerous
and interesting observations; and the few theoretical opinions which
escaped from him, seem, like those of Pallas, to have been chiefly derived
from the cosmological speculations of preceding writers.
</div></body></text></TEI>