<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="10">

CHAPTER I.
Of the Pure Sciences.



1. ALL
external objects and events which we can contemplate
are viewed as having relations of Space, Time, and Number;
and are subject to the general conditions which these Ideas
impose, as well as to the particular laws which belong to
each class of objects and occurrences. The special laws of
nature, considered under the various aspects which
constitute the different sciences, are obtained by a mixed
reference to Experience and to the Fundamental Ideas of each
science. But besides the sciences thus formed by the aid of
special experience, the conditions which flow from those
more comprehensive ideas first mentioned, Space, Time, and
Number, constitute a body of science, applicable to objects
and changes of all kinds, and deduced without recurrence
being had to any observation in particular. These sciences,
thus unfolded out of ideas alone, unmixed with any reference
to the phenomena of matter, are hence termed Pure
Sciences. The principal sciences of this class are Geometry,
Theoretical Arithmetic, and Algebra considered in its most
general sense, as the investigation of the relations of
space and number by means of general symbols.
2. These Pure Sciences were not included in our survey of
the history of the sciences, because they are not
inductive sciences. Their progress has not
consisted in collecting laws from phenomena, true theories
from observed facts, and more general from more limited
laws; but in tracing the consequences of the ideas
themselves, and in detecting the most general and intimate
analogies and connexions which prevail 89 among such
conceptions as are derivable from the ideas. These sciences
have no principles besides definitions and axioms, and no
process of proof but deduction; this process, however,
assuming here a most remarkable character; and exhibiting a
combination of simplicity and complexity, of rigour and
generality, quite unparalleled in other subjects.
3. The universality of the truths, and the rigour of the
demonstrations of these pure sciences, attracted attention
in the earliest times; and it was perceived that they
offered an exercise and a discipline of the intellectual
faculties, in a form peculiarly free from admixture of
extraneous elements. They were strenuously cultivated by the
Greeks, both with a view to such a discipline, and from the
love of speculative truth which prevailed among that people:
and the name mathematics, by which they are
designated, indicates this their character of
disciplinal studies.
4. As has already been said, the ideas which these sciences
involve extend to all the objects and changes which we
observe in the external world; and hence the consideration
of mathematical relations forms a large portion of many of
the sciences which treat of the phenomena and laws of
external nature, as Astronomy, Optics, and Mechanics. Such
sciences are hence often termed Mixed Mathematics,
the relations of space and number being, in these branches
of knowledge, combined with principles collected from
special observation; while Geometry, Algebra, and the like
subjects, which involve no result of experience, are called
Pure Mathematics.
5. Space, time, and number, may be conceived as
forms by which the knowledge derived from our
sensations is moulded, and which are independent of the
differences in the matter of our knowledge, arising from the
sensations themselves. Hence the sciences which have these
ideas for their subject may be termed Formal
Sciences. In this point of view, they are distinguished
from sciences in which, besides these mere formal laws by
which appearances are corrected, we endeavour to apply to
the phenomena the idea of cause, 90 or some of the other
ideas which penetrate further into the principles of nature.
We have thus, in the History, distinguished Formal Astronomy
and Formal Optics from Physical Astronomy and Physical
Optics.
We now proceed to our examination of the Ideas which
constitute the foundation of these formal or pure
mathematical sciences, beginning with the Idea of Space.</div></body></text></TEI>