<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="130">CHAPTER VIII.
The Doctrine of Final Causes in
Physiology.

Sect. 1.—Assertion of the Principle
of Unity of Plan.
WE have repeatedly seen, in
the course of our historical view of Physiology, that those who have
studied the structure of animals and plants, have had a conviction
forced upon them, that the organs are constructed and combined in
subservience to the life and functions of the whole. The parts have a
purpose, as well as a law;—we can trace Final
Causes, as well as Laws of Causation. This principle is peculiar to
physiology; and it might naturally be expected that, in the progress
of the science, it would come under special consideration. This
accordingly has happened; and the principle has been drawn 483 into a prominent
position by the struggle of two antagonistic schools of physiologists.
On the one hand, it has been maintained that this doctrine of final
causes is altogether unphilosophical, and requires to be replaced by a
more comprehensive and profound principle: on the other hand, it is
asserted that the doctrine is not only true, but that, in our own
time, it has been fixed and developed so as to become the instrument
of some of the most important discoveries which have been made. Of the
views of these two schools we must endeavor to give some account.
The disciples of the former of the two schools express their tenets
by the phrases unity of plan, unity of
composition; and the more detailed developement of these
doctrines has been termed the Theory of Analogies, by Geoffroy
Saint-Hilaire, who claims this theory as his own creation. According
to this theory, the structure and functions of animals are to be
studied by the guidance of their analogy only; our attention is to be
turned, not to the fitness of the organization for any end of life or
action, but to its resemblance to other organizations by which it is
gradually derived from the original type.
According to the rival view of this subject, we must not assume,
and cannot establish, that the plan of all animals is the same, or
their composition similar. The existence of a single and universal
system of analogies in the construction of all animals is entirely
unproved, and therefore cannot be made our guide in the study of their
properties. On the other hand, the plan of the animal, the purpose of
its organization in the support of its life, the necessity of the
functions to its existence, are truths which are irresistibly
apparent, and which may therefore be safely taken as the bases of our
reasonings. This view has been put forward as the doctrine of the
conditions of existence: it may also be described as the
principle of a purpose in organization; the structure being
considered as having the function for its end. We must say a few words
on each of these views.
It had been pointed out by Cuvier, as we have seen in the last chapter, that the animal kingdom may be divided
into four great branches; in each of which the plan of the
animal is different, namely, vertebrata, articulata,
mollusca, radiata. Now the question naturally occurs, is
there really no resemblance of construction in these different
classes? It was maintained by some, that there is such a resemblance.
In 1820,105 M. Audouin, a young naturalist of
Paris, 484
endeavored to fill up the chasm which separates insects from other
animals; and by examining carefully the portions which compose the
solid frame-work of insects, and following them through their various
transformations in different classes, he conceived that he found
relations of position and function, and often of number and form,
which might be compared with the relations of the parts of the
skeleton in vertebrate animals. He thought that the first segment of
an insect, the head,106 represents one of the three vertebræ
which, according to Spix and others, compose the vertebrate head: the
second segment of the insects, (the prothorax of Audouin,) is,
according to M. Geoffroy, the second vertebra of the head of the
vertebrata, and so on. Upon this speculation Cuvier107 does not give any decided opinion;
observing only, that even if false, it leads to active thought and
useful research.
105 Cuv. Hist. Sc. Nat. iii.
422.
106 Ib. 437.
107 Cuv. Hist. Sc. Nat. iii.
441.
But when an attempt was further made to identify the plan of
another branch of the animal world, the mollusca, with that of the
vertebrata, the radical opposition between such views and those of
Cuvier, broke out into an animated controversy.
Two French anatomists, MM. Laurencet and Meyranx, presented to the
Academy of Sciences, in 1830, a Memoir containing their views on the
organization of molluscous animals; and on the sepia or cuttle-fish in
particular, as one of the most complete examples of such animals.
These creatures, indeed, though thus placed in the same division with
shell-fish of the most defective organization and obscure structure,
are far from being scantily organized. They have a brain,108 often eyes, and these, in the animals
of this class, (cephalopoda) are more complicated than in any
vertebrates;109 they have sometimes ears, salivary
glands, multiple stomachs, a considerable liver, a bile, a complete
double circulation, provided with auricles and ventricles; in short,
their vital activity is vigorous, and their senses are distinct.
108 Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire denies
this. Principes de Phil. Zoologique discutés en 1830, p.
68.
109 Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire,
Principes de Phil. Zoologique discutés en 1830, p. 55.
But still, though this organization, in the abundance and diversity
of its parts, approaches that of vertebrate animals, it had not been
considered as composed in the same manner, or arranged in the same
order, Cuvier had always maintained that the plan of molluscs is not a
continuation of the plan of vertebrates. 485
MM. Laurencet and Meyranx, on the contrary, conceived that the
sepia might be reduced to the type of a vertebrate creature, by
considering the back-bone of the latter bent double backwards, so as
to bring the root of the tail to the nape of the neck; the parts thus
brought into contact being supposed to coalesce. By this mode of
conception, these anatomists held that the viscera were placed in the
same connexion as in the vertebrate type, and the functions exercised
in an analogous manner.
To decide on the reality of the analogy thus asserted, clearly
belonged to the jurisdiction of the most eminent anatomists and
physiologists. The Memoir was committed to Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire and
Latreille, two eminent zoologists, in order to be reported on. Their
report was extremely favorable; and went almost to the length of
adopting the views of the authors.
Cuvier expressed some dissatisfaction with this report on its being
read;110 and a short time afterwards,111 represented Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire as
having asserted that the new views of Laurencet and Meyranx refuted
completely the notion of the great interval which exists between
molluscous and vertebrate animals. Geoffroy protested against such an
interpretation of his expressions; but it soon appeared, by the
controversial character which the discussions on this and several
other subjects assumed, that a real opposition of opinions was in
action.
110 Princ. de Phil. Zool.
discutés en 1830, p. 36.
111 p. 50.
Without attempting to explain the exact views of Geoffroy, (we may,
perhaps, venture to say that they are hardly yet generally understood
with sufficient distinctness to justify the mere historian of science
in attempting such an explanation,) their general tendency may be
sufficiently collected from what has been said; and from the phrases
in which his views are conveyed.112 The
principle of connexions, the elective affinities of organic elements,
the equilibrization of organs;—such are the designations of
the leading doctrines which are unfolded in the preliminary discourse
of his Anatomical Philosophy. Elective affinities of organic
elements are the forces by which the vital structures and varied forms
of living things are produced; and the principles of connexion and
equilibrium of these forces in the various parts of the organization
prescribe limits and conditions to the variety and developement of
such forms.
112 Phil. Zool. 15.
The character and tendency of this philosophy will be, I think,
486 much more
clear, if we consider what it excludes and denies. It rejects
altogether all conception of a plan and purpose in the organs of
animals, as a principle which has determined their forms, or can be of
use in directing our reasonings. “I take care,” says Geoffroy, “not to
ascribe to God any intention.”113 And when
Cuvier speaks of the combination of organs in such order that they may
be in consistence with the part which the animal has to play
in nature; his rival rejoins,114 I “know
nothing of animals which have to play a part in nature.” Such
a notion is, he holds, unphilosophical and dangerous. It is an abuse
of final causes which makes the cause to be engendered by the effect.
And to illustrate still further his own view, he says, “I have read concerning
fishes, that because they live in a medium which resists more than
air, their motive forces are calculated so as to give them the power
of progression under those circumstances. By this mode of reasoning,
you would say of a man who makes use of crutches, that he was
originally destined to the misfortune of having a leg paralysed or
amputated.”
113 “Je me garde de prêter à Dieu
aucune intention.” Phil. Zool. 10.
114 “Je ne connais point d’animal
qui doive jouer un rôle dans la nature.” p.
65.
How far this doctrine of unity in the plan in animals, is
admissible or probable in physiology when kept within proper limits,
that is, when not put in opposition to the doctrine of a purpose
involved in the plan of animals, I do not pretend even to conjecture.
The question is one which appears to be at present deeply occupying
the minds of the most learned and profound physiologists; and such
persons alone, adding to their knowledge and zeal, judicial sagacity
and impartiality, can tell us what is the general tendency of the best
researches on this subject.115 But when the
anatomist expresses such opinions, and defends them by such
illustrations as those which I have just quoted,116 we perceive
that he quits the entrenchments of his superior science, in which he
might 487 have
remained unassailable so long as the question was a professional one;
and the discussion is open to those who possess no peculiar knowledge
of anatomy. We shall, therefore, venture to say a few words upon
it.
115 So far as this doctrine is
generally accepted among the best physiologists, we cannot doubt the
propriety of Meckel’s remark, (Comparative Anatomy, 1821, Pref.
p. xi.) that it cannot be truly asserted either to be new, or to be
peculiarly due to Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire.
116 It is hardly worth while
answering such illustrations, but I may remark, that the one quoted
above, irrelevant and unbecoming as it is, tells altogether against
its author. The fact that the wooden leg is of the same length as the
other, proves, and would satisfy the most incredulous man, that it was
intended for walking.
Sect. 2.—Estimate of the Doctrine of Unity of
Plan.
It has been so often
repeated, and so generally allowed in modern times, that Final Causes
ought not to be made our guides in natural philosophy, that a
prejudice has been established against the introduction of any views
to which this designation can be applied, into physical speculations.
Yet, in fact, the assumption of an end or purpose in the structure of
organized beings, appears to be an intellectual habit which no efforts
can cast off. It has prevailed from the earliest to the latest ages of
zoological research; appears to be fastened upon us alike by our
ignorance and our knowledge; and has been formally accepted by so many
great anatomists, that we cannot feel any scruple in believing the
rejection of it to be the superstition of a false philosophy, and a
result of the exaggeration of other principles which are supposed
capable of superseding its use. And the doctrine of unity of plan of
all animals, and the other principles associated with this doctrine,
so far as they exclude the conviction of an intelligible scheme and a
discoverable end, in the organization of animals, appear to be utterly
erroneous. I will offer a few reasons for an opinion which may appear
presumptuous in a writer who has only a general knowledge of the
subject.
1. In the first place, it appears to me that the argumentation on
the case in question, the Sepia, does by no means turn out to the
advantage of the new hypothesis. The arguments in support of the
hypothetical view of the structure of this mollusc were, that by this
view the relative position of the parts was explained, and
confirmations which had appeared altogether anomalous, were reduced to
rule; for example, the beak, which had been supposed to be in a
position the reverse of all other beaks, was shown, by the assumed
posture, to have its upper mandible longer than the lower, and thus to
be regularly placed. “But,” says Cuvier,117 “supposing
the posture, in order that the side on which the funnel of the sepia
is folded should be the back of the animal, considered as similar to a
vertebrate, the brain with 488 regard to the beak, and the œsophagus
with regard to the liver, should have positions corresponding to those
in vertebrates; but the positions of these organs are exactly contrary
to the hypothesis. How, then, can you say,” he asks, “that the
cephalopods and vertebrates have identity of composition,
unity of composition, without using words in a sense entirely
different from their common meaning?”
117 G. S. H. Phil. Zool. p.
70.
This argument appears to be exactly of the kind on which the value
of the hypothesis must depend.118 It is,
therefore, interesting to see the reply made to it by the theorist. It
is this: “I admit the facts here stated, but I deny that they lead to
the notion of a different sort of animal composition. Molluscous
animals had been placed too high in the zoological scale; but if they
are only the embryos of its lower stages, if they are only beings in
which far fewer organs come into play, it does not follow that the
organs are destitute of the relations which the power of successive
generations may demand. The organ A will be in an unusual relation
with the organ C, if B has not been produced;—if a stoppage of
the developement has fallen upon this latter organ, and has thus
prevented its production. And thus,” he says, “we see how we may have
different arrangements, and divers constructions as they appear to the
eye.”
118 I do not dwell on other
arguments which were employed. It was given as a circumstance
suggesting the supposed posture of the type, that in this way the back
was colored, and the belly was white. On this Cuvier observes
(Phil. Zool. pp. 93, 68), “I must say, that I do not know any
naturalist so ignorant as to suppose that the back is determined by
its dark color, or even by its position when the animal is in motion;
they all know that the badger has a black belly and a white back; that
an infinity of other animals, especially among insects, are in the
same case; and that many fishes swim on their side, or with their
belly upwards.”
It seems to me that such a concession as this entirely destroys the
theory which it attempts to defend; for what arrangement does the
principle of unity of composition exclude, if it admits
unusual, that is, various arrangements of some organs, accompanied by
the total absence of others? Or how does this differ from Cuvier’s
mode of stating the conclusion, except in the introduction of certain
arbitrary hypotheses of developement and stoppage? “I reduce the
facts,” Cuvier says, “to their true expression, by saying that
Cephalopods have several organs which are common to them and
vertebrates, and which discharge the same offices; but that these
organs are in them differently distributed, and often constructed in a
different manner; 489 and they are accompanied by several
other organs which vertebrates have not; while these on the other hand
have several which are wanting in cephalopods.”
We shall see afterwards the general principles which Cuvier himself
considered as the best guides in these reasonings. But I will first
add a few words on the disposition of the school now under
consideration, to reject all assumption of an end.
2. That the parts of the bodies of animals are made in order to
discharge their respective offices, is a conviction which we cannot
believe to be otherwise than an irremovable principle of the
philosophy of organization, when we see the manner in which it has
constantly forced itself upon the minds of zoologists and anatomists
in all ages; not only as an inference, but as a guide whose
indications they could not help following. I have already noticed
expressions of this conviction in some of the principal persons who
occur in the history of physiology, as Galen and Harvey. I might add
many more, but I will content myself with adducing a contemporary of
Geoffroy’s whose testimony is the more remarkable, because he
obviously shares with his countryman in the common prejudice against
the use of final causes. “I consider,” he says, in speaking of the
provisions for the reproduction of animals,119 “with the
great Bacon, the philosophy of final causes as sterile; but I have
elsewhere acknowledged that it was very difficult for the most
cautious man never to have recourse to them in his explanations.”
After the survey which we have had to take of the history of
physiology, we cannot but see that the assumption of final causes in
this branch of science is so far from being sterile, that it has had a
large share in every discovery which is included in the existing mass
of real knowledge. The use of every organ has been discovered by
starting from the assumption that it must have some use. The
doctrine of the circulation of the blood was, as we have seen, clearly
and professedly due to the persuasion of a purpose in the circulatory
apparatus. The study of comparative anatomy is the study of the
adaption of animal structures to their purposes. And we shall soon
have to show that this conception of final causes has, in our own
times, been so far from barren, that it has, in the hands of Cuvier
and others, enabled us to become intimately acquainted with vast
departments of zoology to which we have no other mode of access. It
has placed before us in a complete state, 490 animals, of which, for thousands of
years, only a few fragments have existed, and which differ widely from
all existing animals; and it has given birth, or at least has given
the greatest part of its importance and interest, to a science which
forms one of the brightest parts of the modern progress of knowledge.
It is, therefore, very far from being a vague and empty assertion,
when we say that final causes are a real and indestructible element in
zoological philosophy; and that the exclusion of them, as attempted by
the school of which we speak, is a fundamental and most mischievous
error.
119 Cabanis, Rapports du Physique
et du Morale de l’Homme, i. 299.
3. Thus, though the physiologist may persuade himself that he ought
not to refer to final causes, we find that, practically, he cannot
help doing this; and that the event shows that his practical habit is
right and well-founded. But he may still cling to the speculative
difficulties and doubts in which such subjects may be involved by à
priori considerations. He may say, as Saint-Hilaire does say,120 “I ascribe no intention to God, for I
mistrust the feeble powers of my reason. I observe facts merely, and
go no further. I only pretend to the character of the historian of
what is.” “I cannot make Nature an intelligent being who does
nothing in vain, who acts by the shortest mode, who does all for the
best.”
120 Phil. Zool. p. 10.
I am not going to enter at any length into this subject, which,
thus considered, is metaphysical and theological, rather than
physiological. If any one maintain, as some have maintained, that no
manifestation of means apparently used for ends in nature, can prove
the existence of design in the Author of nature, this is not the place
to refute such an opinion in its general form. But I think it may be
worth while to show, that even those who incline to such an opinion,
still cannot resist the necessity which compels men to assume, in
organized beings, the existence of an end.
Among the philosophers who have referred our conviction of the
being of God to our moral nature, and have denied the possibility of
demonstration on mere physical grounds, Kant is perhaps the most
eminent. Yet he has asserted the reality of such a principle of
physiology as we are now maintaining in the most emphatic manner.
Indeed, this assumption of an end makes his very definition of an
organized being. “An organized product of nature is that in which all
the parts are mutually ends and means.”121 And this, he
says, is a universal and necessary maxim. He adds, “It is well known
that the 491
anatomizers of plants and animals, in order to investigate their
structure, and to obtain an insight into the grounds why and to what
end such parts, why such a situation and connexion of the parts, and
exactly such an internal form, come before them, assume, as
indispensably necessary, this maxim, that in such a creature nothing
is in vain, and proceed upon it in the same way in which in
general natural philosophy we proceed upon the principle that
nothing happens by chance. In fact, they can as little free
themselves from this teleological principle as from the general
physical one; for as, on omitting the latter, no experience would be
possible, so on omitting the former principle, no clue could exist for
the observation of a kind of natural objects which can be considered
teleologically under the conception of natural ends.”
121 Urtheilskraft, p.
296.
Even if the reader should not follow the reasoning of this
celebrated philosopher, he will still have no difficulty in seeing
that he asserts, in the most distinct manner, that which is denied by
the author whom we have before quoted, the propriety and necessity of
assuming the existence of an end as our guide in the study of animal
organization.
4. It appears to me, therefore, that whether we judge from the
arguments, the results, the practice of physiologists, their
speculative opinions, or those of the philosophers of a wider field,
we are led to the same conviction, that in the organized world we may
and must adopt the belief that organization exists for its purpose,
and that the apprehension of the purpose may guide us in seeing the
meaning of the organization. And I now proceed to show how this
principle has been brought into additional clearness and use by
Cuvier.
In doing this, I may, perhaps, be allowed to make a reflection of a
kind somewhat different from the preceding remarks, though suggested
by them. In another work,122 I endeavored
to show that those who have been discoverers in science have generally
had minds, the disposition of which was to believe in an intelligent
Maker of the universe; and that the scientific speculations which
produced an opposite tendency, were generally those which, though they
might deal familiarly with known physical truths, and conjecture
boldly with regard to the unknown, did not add to the number of solid
generalizations. In order to judge whether this remark is distinctly
applicable in the case now considered, I should have to estimate
Cuvier in comparison with other physiologists of his time, which I do
not presume to do. But I may 492 observe, that he is allowed by all to
have established, on an indestructible basis, many of the most
important generalizations which zoology now contains; and the
principal defect which his critics have pointed out, has been, that he
did not generalize still more widely and boldly. It appears,
therefore, that he cannot but be placed among the great discoverers in
the studies which he pursued; and this being the case, those who look
with pleasure on the tendency of the thoughts of the greatest men to
an Intelligence far higher than their own, most be gratified to find
that he was an example of this tendency; and that the acknowledgement
of a creative purpose, as well as a creative power, not only entered
into his belief but made an indispensable and prominent part of his
philosophy.
122 Bridgewater Treatise, B.
iii. c. vii. and viii. On Inductive Habits of Thought, and on
Deductive Habits of Thought.
Sect. 3.—Establishment and Application of the
Principle of the Conditions of Existence of
Animals.—Cuvier.
We have now to describe more
in detail the doctrine which Cuvier maintained in opposition to such
opinions as we have been speaking of; and which, in his way of
applying it, we look upon as a material advance in physiological
knowledge, and therefore give to it a distinct place in our history.
“Zoology has,” he says,123 in the outset of his Règne
Animal, “a principle of reasoning which is peculiar to it, and
which it employs with advantage on many occasions: this is the
principle of the Conditions of Existence, vulgarly the
principle of Final Causes. As nothing can exist if it do not
combine all the conditions which render its existence possible, the
different parts of each being must be co-ordinated in such a manner as
to render the total being possible, not only in itself, but in its
relations to those which surround it; and the analysis of these
conditions often leads to general laws, as clearly demonstrated as
those which result from calculation or from experience.”
123 Règne An. p. 6.
This is the enunciation of his leading principle in general terms.
To our ascribing it to him, some may object on the ground of its being
self-evident in its nature,124 and having
been very anciently applied. But to this we reply, that the principle
must be considered as a real discovery in the hands of him who first
shows how to make it an instrument of other discoveries. It is true,
in other cases as well as in this, that some vague apprehension, of
true general principles, such as à 493 priori considerations can supply,
has long preceded the knowledge of them as real and verified laws. In
such a way it was seen, before Newton, that the motions of the planets
must result from attraction; and so, before Dufay and Franklin, it was
held that electrical actions must result from a fluid. Cuvier’s merit
consisted, not in seeing that an animal cannot exist without combining
all the conditions of its existence; but in perceiving that this truth
may be taken as a guide in our researches concerning
animals;—that the mode of their existence may be collected from
one part of their structure, and then applied to interpret or detect
another part. He went on the supposition not only that animal forms
have some plan, some purpose, but that they have an
intelligible plan, a discoverable purpose. He proceeded in his
investigations like the decipherer of a manuscript, who makes out his
alphabet from one part of the context, and then applies it to read the
rest. The proof that his principle was something very different from
an identical proposition, is to be found in the fact, that it enabled
him to understand and arrange the structures of animals with
unprecedented clearness and completeness of order; and to restore the
forms of the extinct animals which are found in the rocks of the
earth, in a manner which has been universally assented to as
irresistibly convincing. These results cannot flow from a trifling or
barren principle; and they show us that if we are disposed to form
such a judgment of Cuvier’s doctrine, it must be because we do not
fully apprehend its import.
124 Swainson. Study of Nat.
Hist. p. 85.
To illustrate this, we need only quote the statement which he
makes, and the uses to which he applies it. Thus in the Introduction
to his great work on Fossil Remains he says, “Every organized
being forms an entire system of its own, all the parts of which
mutually correspond, and concur to produce a certain definite purpose
by reciprocal reaction, or by combining to the same end. Hence none of
these separate parts can change their forms without a corresponding
change in the other parts of the same animal; and consequently each of
these parts, taken separately, indicates all the other parts to which
it has belonged. Thus, if the viscera of an animal are so organized as
only to be fitted for the digestion of recent flesh, it is also
requisite that the jaws should be so constructed as to fit them for
devouring prey; the claws must be constructed for seizing it and
tearing it to pieces; the teeth for cutting and dividing its flesh;
the entire system of the limbs or organs of motion for pursuing and
overtaking it; and the organs of sense for discovering it at a
distance. Nature must also have endowed the brain of the animal with
instincts sufficient for concealing itself and for laying plans to
494 catch its
necessary victims.”125 By such considerations he has been
able to reconstruct the whole of many animals of which parts only were
given;—a positive result, which shows both the reality and the
value of the truth on which he wrought.
125 Theory of the Earth, p.
90.
Another great example, equally showing the immense importance of
this principle in Cuvier’s hands, is the reform which, by means of it,
he introduced into the classification of animals. Here again we may
quote the view he himself has given126 of the
character of his own improvements. In studying the physiology of the
natural classes of vertebrate animals, he found, he says, “in the
respective quantity of their respiration, the reason of the quantity
of their motion, and consequently of the kind of locomotion. This,
again, furnishes the reason for the forms of their skeletons and
muscles; and the energy of their senses, and the force of their
digestion, are in a necessary proportion to the same quantity. Thus a
division which had till then been established, like that of
vegetables, only upon observation, was found to rest upon causes
appreciable, and applicable to other cases.” Accordingly, he applied
this view to invertebrates;—examined the modifications which
take place in their organs of circulation, respiration, and sensation;
and having calculated the necessary results of these modifications, he
deduced from it a new division of those animals, in which they are
arranged according to their true relations.
126 Hist. Sc. Nat. i.
293.
Such have been some of the results of the principle of the
Conditions of Existence, as applied by its great assertor.
It is clear, indeed, that such a principle could acquire its
practical value only in the hands of a person intimately acquainted
with anatomical details, with the functions of the organs, and with
their variety in different animals. It is only by means of such
nutriment that the embryo truth could be developed into a vast tree of
science. But it is not the less clear, that Cuvier’s immense knowledge
and great powers of thought led to their results, only by being
employed under the guidance of this master-principle: and, therefore,
we may justly consider it as the distinctive feature of his
speculations, and follow it with a gratified eye, as the thread of
gold which runs through, connects, and enriches his zoological
researches:—gives them a deeper interest and a higher value than
can belong to any view of the organical sciences, in which the very
essence of organization is kept out of sight. 495
The real philosopher, who knows that all the kinds of truth are
intimately connected, and that all the best hopes and encouragements
which are granted to our nature must be consistent with truth, will be
satisfied and confirmed, rather than surprised and disturbed, thus to
find the Natural Sciences leading him to the borders of a higher
region. To him it will appear natural and reasonable, that after
journeying so long among the beautiful and orderly laws by which the
universe is governed, we find ourselves at last approaching to a
Source of order and law, and intellectual beauty:—that, after
venturing into the region of life and feeling and will, we are led to
believe the Fountain of life and will not to be itself unintelligent
and dead, but to be a living Mind, a Power which aims as well as acts.
To us this doctrine appears like the natural cadence of the tones to
which we have so long been listening; and without such a final strain
our ears would have been left craving and unsatisfied. We have been
lingering long amid the harmonies of law and symmetry, constancy and
development; and these notes, though their music was sweet and deep,
must too often have sounded to the ear of our moral nature, as vague
and unmeaning melodies, floating in the air around us, but conveying
no definite thought, moulded into no intelligible announcement. But
one passage which we have again and again caught by snatches, though
sometimes interrupted and lost, at last swells in our ears full,
clear, and decided; and the religious “Hymn in honor of the Creator,”
to which Galen so gladly lent his voice, and in which the best
physiologists of succeeding times have ever joined, is filled into a
richer and deeper harmony by the greatest philosophers of these later
days, and will roll on hereafter the “perpetual song” of the temple of
science.
~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~


BOOK XVIII.

THE PALÆTIOLOGICAL SCIENCES.

HISTORY OF GEOLOGY.

Di quibus imperium est animarum, Umbræque
silentes,
Et Chaos, et Phlegethon, loca nocte silentia
late,
Sit mihi fas audita loqui; sit, numine
vestro
Pandere res alta terrâ et caligine mersas.
Virgil. Æn. vi.
264.

Ye Mighty Ones, who sway the Souls that go
Amid the marvels of the world below!
Ye, silent Shades, who sit and hear around!
Chaos! and Streams that burn beneath the
ground!
All, all forgive, if by your converse
stirred,
My lips shall utter what my ears have
heard;
If I shall speak of things of doubtful
birth,
Deep sunk in darkness, as deep sunk in
earth.

</div></body></text></TEI>