<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol II</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1796</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="4">ADDITIONS.


ADDITION I.

At the end of the article Canities, in Class I. 2. 2. 11. please to add the
  following:

As mechanical injury from a percussion, or a wound, or a caustic, is
  liable to occasion the hair of the part to become grey; so I suspect the
  compression of parts against each other of some animals in the womb is
  liable to render the hair of those parts of a lighter colour; as seems
  often to occur in black cats and dogs. A small terrier bitch now stands
  by me, which is black on all those parts, which were external, when she
  was wrapped up in the uterus, teres atque rotunda; and those parts white,
  which were most constantly pressed together; and those parts tawny, which
  were generally but less constantly pressed together. Thus the hair of the
  back from the forehead to the end of the tail is black, as well as that
  of the sides, and external parts of the legs, both before and behind.
As in the uterus the chin of the whelp is bent down, and lies in
  contact with the fore part of the neck and breast; the tail is applied
  close against the division of the thighs behind; the inside of the hinder
  thighs are pressed close to the sides of the belly, all these parts have
  white hairs.
The fore-legs in the uterus lie on each side of the face; so that the
  feet cover part of the temples, and compress the prominent part of the
  upper eye-brows, but are so placed as to defend the eye-balls from
  pressure; it is curious to observe, that the hair of the sides of the
  face, and of the prominent upper eye-brows, are tawny, and of the inside
  of the feet and legs, which covered them; for as this posture admitted of
  more change in the latter weeks of gestation, the colour of these parts
  is not so far removed from black, as of those parts, where the contact or
  compression was more uniform.
Where this uterine compression of parts has not been so great as to
  render the hair white in other animals, it frequently happens, that the
  extremities of the body are white, as the feet, and noses, and tips of
  the ears of dogs and cats and horses, where the circulation is naturally
  weaker; whence it would seem, that the capillary glands, which form the
  hair, are impeded in the first instance by compression, and in the last
  by the debility of the circulation in them. See Class I. 1. 2. 15.
This day, August 8th, 1794, I have seen a negro, who was born (as he
  reports) of black parents, both father and mother, at Kingston in
  Jamaica, who has many large white blotches on the skin of his limbs and
  body; which I thought felt not so soft to the finger, as the black parts.
  He has a white divergent blaze from the summit of his nose to the vertex
  of his head; the upper part of which, where it extends on the hairy
  scalp, has thick curled hair, like the other part of his head, but quite
  white. By these marks I supposed him to be the same black, who is
  described, when only two years old, in the Transactions of the American
  Philosophical Society, Vol. II. page 292, where a female one is likewise
  described with nearly similar marks.
The joining of the frontal bones, and the bregma, having been later
  than that of the other sutures of the cranium, probably gave cause to the
  whiteness of the hair on these parts by delaying or impeding its
  growth.
ADDITION II.
The following extract from a letter of Dr. Beddoes on hydrocephalus
  internus, I esteem a valuable addition to the article on that subject at
  Class I. 2. 3. 12.

"Master L——, aged 9 years, became suddenly ill in the
  night about a week before I saw him. On the day before the attack, he had
  taken opening medicines, and had bathed afterwards. He had complained of
  violently acute pain in his head, shrieked frequently, ground his teeth
  hard, could not bear to have his head raised from the pillow, and was
  torpid or deaf. His tongue was white, pulse 110 in the evening and full.
  As yet the pupil of the eye was irritable, and he had no strabismus. He
  had been bled with leeches about the head, and blistered. I directed
  mercurial inunction, and calomel from 3 to 6 grains to be taken at first
  every six, and afterwards every three hours. This plan produced no
  sensible effect, and the patient died on the 18th day after the seizure.
  He had convulsion fits two days preceding his death, and the well-known
  symptoms of hydrocephalus internus all made their appearance. From what I
  had seen and read of this disease, I believed it to belong to
  inflammations, and at an earlier period I should be tempted to bleed as
  largely as for pneumonia. The fluid found after death in the ventricules
  of the brain I impute to debility of the absorbents induced by
  inflammation. My reasons are briefly these; 1. The acuteness of the pain.
  2. The state of the pulse. In the above case for the first 9 or 10 days
  it did not exceed 110, and was full and strong.
3. To find out whether any febrile alternations took place, Master
  L.'s feet were frequently felt, and they were found at times cold, and at
  other times of a dry heat. I have many times seen this disease, but the
  patients were too young, or too far advanced, to inform me, whether they
  had chillness succeeded by heat at its onset. 4. The disorders to which
  the young are more peculiarly liable afford a presumption, that
  hydrocephalus internus is an inflammatory disease; and this is confirmed
  by the regularity of the period, within which it finishes its course. And
  lastly, does it not happen more frequently than is suspected from
  external injury?
I have just now been well informed, that Dr. Rush has lately cured
  five out of six patients by copious bleedings. I relate here the reasons
  for an opinion without pretending to a discovery. Something like this
  doctrine may be found in certain modern publications, but it is delivered
  in that vague and diffuse style, which I trust your example will banish
  from medical literature."


Clifton, near Bristol,
July 28, 1795.



To this idea of Dr. Beddoes may be added, that the hydrocele generally
  succeeds an injury, and consequent inflammation of the bag, which
  contains it. And that other dropsies, which principally attend
  inebriates, are consequent to too great action of the mucous membranes by
  the stimulus of beer, wine, and spirits. And lastly, that as these cases
  of hydrocephalus end so fatally, a new mode of treating them is much to
  be desired, and deserves to be seriously attended to.
ADDITION III. On Vertigo.
To be placed after the additional Note at the end of Vol. I. on
this Subject.
Having reperused the ingenious Essay of Dr. Wells on Single Vision,
  and his additional observations in the Gentleman's Magazine on the
  apparent retrogression of objects in vertigo, I am induced to believe,
  that this apparent retrogression of objects is not always owing to the
  same cause.
When a person revolves with his eyes closed, till he becomes
  vertiginous, and then stands still without opening them, he seems for a
  while to go forward in the same direction. This hallucination of his
  ideas cannot be owing to ocular spectra, because, as Dr. Wells observes,
  no such can have been formed; but it must arise from a similar
  continuance or repetition of ideas belonging to the sense of touch,
  instead of to the sense of vision; and should therefore be called a
  tangible, not a visual, vertigo. In common language this belief of
  continuing to revolve for some time, after he stands still, when a person
  has turned round for a minute in the dark, would be called a deception of
  imagination.
Now at this time if he opens his eyes upon a gilt book, placed with
  other books on a shelf about the height of his eye, the gilt book seems
  to recede in the contrary direction; though his eyes are at this time
  kept quite still, as well as the gilt book. For if his eyes were not kept
  still, other books would fall on them in succession; which, when I
  repeatedly made the experiment, did not occur; and which thus evinces,
  that no motion of the eyes is the cause of the apparent retrocession of
  the gilt book. Why then does it happen?—Certainly from an
  hallucination of ideas, or in common language the deception of
  imagination.
The vertiginous person still imagines, that he continues to revolve
  forwards, after he has opened his eyes; and in consequence that the
  objects, which his eyes happen to fall upon, are revolving backward; as
  they would appear to do, if he was actually turning round with his eyes
  open. For he has been accustomed to observe the motions of bodies,
  whether apparent or real, so much more frequently by the eye than by the
  touch; that the present belief of his gyration, occasioned by the
  hallucinations of the sense of touch, is attended with ideas of such
  imagined motions of visible objects, as have always accompanied his
  former gyrations, and have thus been associated with the muscular actions
  and perceptions of touch, which occurred at the same time.
When the remains of colours are seen in the eye, they are termed
  ocular spectra; when remaining sounds are heard in the ear, they may be
  called auricular murmurs; but when the remaining motions, or ideas, of
  the sense of touch continue, as in this vertigo of a blindfolded person,
  they have acquired no name, but may be termed evanescent titillations, or
  tangible hallucinations.
Whence I conclude, that vertigo may have for its cause either the
  ocular spectra of the sense of vision, when a person revolves with his
  eyes open; or the auricular murmurs of the sense of hearing, if he is
  revolved near a cascade; or the evanescent titillations of the sense of
  touch, if he revolves blindfold. All these I should wish to call
  vanishing ideas, or sensual motions, of those organs of sense; which,
  ideas, or sensual motions, have lately been associated in a circle, and
  therefore for a time continue to be excited. And what are the ideas of
  colours, when they are excited by imagination or memory, but the
  repetition of finer ocular spectra? What the idea of sounds, but the
  repetition of finer auricular murmurs? And what the ideas of tangible
  objects, but the repetition of finer evanescent titillations?
The tangible, and the auricular, and the visual vertigo, are all
  perceived by many people for a day or two after long travelling in a boat
  or coach; the motions of the vessel, or vehicle, or of the surrounding
  objects, and the noise of the wheels and oars, occur at intervals of
  reverie, or at the commencement of sleep. See Sect. XX. 5. These ideas,
  or sensual motions, of sight, of hearing, and of touch, are succeeded by
  the same effects as the ocular spectra, the auricular murmurs, and the
  evanescent titillations above mentioned; that is, by a kind of vertigo,
  and cannot in that respect be distinguished from them. Which is a further
  confirmation of the truth of the doctrine delivered in Sect. III. of this
  work, that the colours remaining in the eyes, which are termed ocular
  spectra, are ideas, or sensual motions, belonging to the sense of vision,
  which for too long a time continue their activity.
ADDITION IV. Of Voluntary Motions.
A correspondent acquaints me, that he finds difficulty in
  understanding how the convulsions of the limbs in epilepsy can be induced
  by voluntary exertions. This I suspect first to have arisen from the
  double meaning of the words "involuntary motions;" which are sometimes
  used for those motions, which are performed without the interference of
  volition, as the pulsations of the heart and arteries; and at other times
  for those actions, which occur, where two counter volitions oppose each
  other, and the stronger prevails; as in endeavouring to suppress
  laughter, and to stop the shudderings, when exposed to cold. Thus when
  the poet writes,


———video meliora, proboque,
Deteriora sequor.——


The stronger volition actuates the system, but not without the
  counteraction of unavailing smaller ones; which constitute
  deliberation.
A second difficulty may have arisen from the confined use of the words
  "to will," which in common discourse generally mean to choose after
  deliberation; and hence our will or volition is supposed to be always in
  our own power. But the will or voluntary power, acts always from motive,
  as explained in Sect. XXXIV. 1. and in Class IV. 1. 3. 2. and III. 2. 1. 12. which motive can frequently
  be examined previous to action, and balanced against opposite motives,
  which is called deliberation; at other times the motive is so powerful as
  immediately to excite the sensorial power of volition into action,
  without a previous balancing of opposite motives, or counter volitions.
  The former of these volitions is exercised in the common purposes of
  life, and the latter in the exertions of epilepsy and insanity.
It is difficult to think without words, which however all those
  must do, who discover new truths by reasoning; and still more difficult,
  when the words in common use deceive us by their twofold meanings, or by
  the inaccuracy of the ideas, which they suggest.
ADDITION V. Of Figure.
I feel myself much obliged by the accurate attention given to the
  first volume of Zoonomia, and by the ingenious criticisms bestowed on it,
  by the learned writers of that article both in the Analytical and English
  Reviews. Some circumstances, in which their sentiments do not accord with
  those expressed in the work, I intend to reconsider, and to explain
  further at some future time. One thing, in which both these gentlemen
  seem to dissent from me, I shall now mention, it is concerning the
  manner, in which we acquire the idea of figure; a circumstance of great
  importance in the knowledge of our intellect, as it shews the cause of
  the accuracy of our ideas of motion, time, space, number, and of the
  mathematical sciences, which are concerned in the mensurations or
  proportions of figure.
This I imagine may have in part arisen from the prepossession, which
  has almost universally prevailed, that ideas are immaterial beings, and
  therefore possess no properties in common with solid matter. Which I
  suppose to be a fanciful hypothesis, like the stories of ghosts and
  apparitions, which have so long amused, and still amuse, the credulous
  without any foundation in nature.
The existence of our own bodies, and of their solidity, and of their
  figure, and of their motions, is taken for granted in my account of
  ideas; because the ideas themselves are believed to consist of motions or
  configurations of solid fibres; and the question now proposed is, how we
  become acquainted with the figures of bodies external to our organs of
  sense? Which I can only repeat from what is mentioned in Sect. XIV. 2. 2.
  that if part of an organ of sense be stimulated into action, as of the
  sense of touch, that part so stimulated into action must possess figure,
  which must be similar to the figure of the body, which stimulates it.
Another previous prepossession of the mind, which may have rendered
  the manner of our acquiring the knowledge of figure less intelligible,
  may have arisen from the common opinion of the perceiving faculty
  residing in the head; whereas our daily experience shews, that our
  perception (which consists of an idea, and of the pleasure or pain it
  occasions) exists principally in the organ of sense, which is stimulated
  into action; as every one, who burns his finger in the candle, must be
  bold to deny.
When an ivory triangle is pressed on the palm of the hand, the figure
  of the surface of the part of the organ of touch thus compressed is a
  triangle, resembling in figure the figure of the external body, which
  compresses it. The action of the stimulated fibres, which constitute the
  idea of hardness and of figure, remains in this part of the sensorium,
  which forms the sense of touch; but the sensorial motion, which
  constitutes pleasure or pain, and which is excited in consequence of
  these fibrous motions of the organ of sense, is propagated to the central
  parts of the sensorium, or to the whole of it; though this generally
  occurs in less degree of energy, than it exists in the stimulated organ
  of sense; as in the instance above mentioned of burning a finger in the
  candle.
Some, who have espoused the doctrine of the immateriality of ideas,
  have seriously doubted the existence of a material world, with which only
  our senses acquaint us; and yet have assented to the existence of spirit,
  with which our senses cannot acquaint us; and have finally allowed, that
  all our knowledge is derived through the medium of our senses! They
  forget, that if the spirit of animation had no properties in common with
  matter, it could neither affect nor be affected by the material body. But
  the knowledge of our own material existence being granted, which I
  suspect few rational persons will seriously deny, the existence of a
  material external world follows in course; as our perceptions, when we
  are awake and not insane, are distinguished from those excited by
  sensation, as in our dreams, and from those excited by volition or by
  association as in insanity and reverie, by the power we have of comparing
  the present perceptions of one sense with those of another, as explained
  in Sect. XIV. 2. 5. And also by comparing the tribes of ideas, which the
  symbols of pictures, or of languages, suggest to us, by intuitive analogy
  with our previous experience, that is, with the common course of nature.
  See Class III. 2. 2. 3. on
  Credulity.
ADDITION VI.
Please to add the following in page 14, after line 20.
Cold and hot Fit.
As the torpor, with which a fit of fever commences, is sometimes owing
  to defect of stimulus, as in going into the cold-bath; and sometimes to a
  previous exhaustion of the sensorial power by the action of some violent
  stimulus, as after coming out of a hot room into cold air; a longer time
  must elapse, before there can be a sufficient accumulation of sensorial
  power to produce a hot fit in one case than in the other. Because in the
  latter case the quantity of sensorial power previously expended must be
  supplied, before an accumulation can begin.
The cold paroxysm commences, when the torpor of a part becomes so
  great, and its motions in consequence so slow or feeble, as not to excite
  the sensorial power of association; which in health contributes to move
  the rest of the system, which is catenated with it. And the hot fit
  commences by the accumulation of the sensorial power of irritation of the
  part first affected, either so as to counteract its deficient stimulus,
  or its previous waste of sensorial power; and it becomes general by the
  accumulation of the sensorial power of association; which is excited by
  the renovated actions of the part first affected; or becomes so great as
  to overbalance the deficient excitement of it. On all these accounts the
  hot fit cannot be supposed to bear any proportion to the cold one in
  length of time, though the latter may be the consequence of the former.
  See Suppl. I. 16. 8.
ADDITION VII. On Warmth.
To be added at the end of the Species Sudor Calidus, in Class I. 1. 2. 3.
When the heat of the body in weak patients in fevers is increased by
  the stimulus of the points of flannel, a greater consequent debility
  succeeds, than when it is produced by the warmth of fire; as in the
  former the heat is in part owing to the increased activity of the skin,
  and consequent expenditure of sensorial power; whereas in the latter case
  it is in part owing to the influx of the fluid matter of heat.
So the warmth produced by equitation, or by rubbing the body and limbs
  with a smooth brush or hand, as is done after bathing in some parts of
  the East, does not expend nearly so much sensorial power, as when the
  warmth is produced by the locomotion of the whole weight of the body by
  muscular action, as in walking, or running, or swimming. Whence the
  warmth of a fire is to be preferred to flannel shirts for weak people,
  and the agitation of a horse to exercise on foot. And I suppose those,
  who are unfortunately lost in snow, who are on foot, are liable to perish
  sooner by being exhausted by their muscular exertions; and might
  frequently preserve themselves by lying on the ground, and covering
  themselves with snow, before they were too much exhausted by fatigue. See
  Botan. Garden, Vol. II. the note on Barometz.
ADDITION VIII. Puerperal Fever.
To be added to Class II. 1. 6. 16.
A very interesting account of the puerperal fever, which was epidemic
  at Aberdeen, has been lately published by Dr. Alexander Gordon.
  (Robinson, London.) In several dissections of those, who died of this
  disease, purulent matter was found in the cavity of the abdomen; which he
  ascribes to an erysipelatous inflammation of the periton�um, as its
  principal seat, and of its productions, as the omentum, mesentery, and
  periton�al coat of the intestines.
He believes, that it was infectious, and that the contagion was always
  carried by the accoucheur or the nurse from one lying-in woman to
  another.
The disease began with violent unremitting pain of the abdomen on the
  day of delivery, or the next day, with shuddering, and very quick pulse,
  often 140 in a minute. In this situation, if he saw the patient within 12
  or 24 hours of her seizure, he took away from 16 to 24 ounces of blood,
  which was always sizy. He then immediately gave a cathartic consisting of
  three grains of calomel, and 40 grains of powder of jalap. After this had
  operated, he gave an opiate at night; and continued the purging and the
  opiate for several days.
He asserts, that almost all those, whom he was permitted to treat in
  this manner early in the disease, recovered to the number of 50; and that
  almost all the rest died. But that when two or three days were elapsed,
  the patient became too weak for this method; and the matter was already
  formed, which destroyed them. Except that he saw two patients, who
  recovered after discharging a large quantity of matter at the navel. And
  a few, who were relieved by the appearance of external erysipelas on the
  extremities.
This disease, consisting of an erysipelatous inflammation, may
  occasion the great debility sooner to occur than in inflammation of the
  uterus; which latter is neither erysipelatous, I suppose, nor contagious.
  And the success of Dr. Gordon's practice seems to correspond with that of
  Dr. Rush in the contagious fever or plague at Philadelphia; which
  appeared to be much assisted by early evacuations. One case I saw some
  time ago, where violent unceasing pain of the whole abdomen occurred a
  few hours after delivery, with quick pulse; which ceased after the
  patient had twice lost about eight ounces of blood, and had taken a
  moderate cathartic with calomel.
This case induces me to think, that it might be safer and equally
  efficacious, to take less blood at first, than Dr. Gordon mentions, and
  to repeat the operation in a few hours, if the continuance of the
  symptoms should require it. And the same in respect to the cathartic,
  which might perhaps be given in less quantity, and repeated every two or
  three hours.
Nor should I wish to give an opiate after the first venesection and
  cathartic; as I suspect that this might be injurious, except those
  evacuations had emptied the vessels so much, that the stimulus of the
  opiate should act only by increasing the absorption of the new vessels or
  fluids produced on the surfaces of the inflamed membranes. In other
  inflammations of the bowels, and in acute rheumatism, I have seen the
  disease much prolonged, and I believe sometimes rendered fatal, by the
  too early administration of opiates, either along with cathartics, or at
  their intervals; while a small dose of opium given after sufficient
  evacuations produces absorption only by its stimulus, and much
  contributes to the cure of the patient. We may have visible testimony of
  this effect of opium, when a solution of it is put into an inflamed eye;
  if it be thus used previous to sufficient evacuation, it increases the
  inflammation; if it be used after sufficient evacuation, it increases
  absorption only, and clears the eye in a very small time.
I cannot omit observing, from considering these circumstances, how
  unwise is the common practice of giving an opiate to every woman
  immediately after her delivery, which must often have been of dangerous
  consequence.
END OF THE SECOND PART.

</div></body></text></TEI>