<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="72">CHAPTER XI.
Epoch of Young and Fresnel.

Sect. 1.—Introduction.
THE man whose name must occupy
the most distinguished place in the history of Physical Optics, in
consequence of what he did in reviving and establishing the undulatory
theory of light, is Dr. Thomas Young. He was born in 1773, at
Milverton in Somersetshire, of Quaker parents; and after
distinguishing himself during youth by the variety and accuracy of his
attainments, he settled in London as a physician in 1801; but
continued to give much of his attention to general science. His
optical theory, for a long time, made few proselytes; and several
years afterwards, Auguste Fresnel, an eminent French mathematician, an
engineer officer, took up similar views, proved their truth, and
traced their consequences, by a series of labors almost independent of
those of Dr. Young. It was not till the theory was thus re-echoed from
another land, that it was able to take any strong hold on the
attention of the countrymen of its earlier promulgator.
The theory of undulations, like that of universal gravitation, may
be divided into several successive steps of generalization. In both
cases, all these steps were made by the same persons; but there is
this difference:—all the parts of the law of universal
gravitation were worked out in one burst of inspiration by its author,
and published at one time;—in the doctrine of light, on the
other hand, the different steps of the advance were made and published
at separate times, with intervals between. We see the theory in a
narrower form, and in detached portions, before the widest
generalizations and principles of unity are reached; we see the
authors struggling with the difficulties before we see them
successful. They appear to us as men like ourselves, liable to
perplexity and failure, instead of coming before us, as Newton does in
the history of Physical Astronomy, as the irresistible and almost
supernatural hero of a philosophical romance. 93
The main subdivisions of the great advance in physical optics, of
which we have now to give an account, are the following:—
1. The explanation of the periodical colors of thin plates,
thick plates, fringed shadows, striated surfaces, and other phenomena
of the same kind, by means of the doctrine of the interference
of undulations.
2. The explanation of the phenomena of double refraction by
the propagation of undulations in a medium of which the optical
elasticity is different in different directions.
3. The conception of polarization as the result of the
vibrations being transverse; and the consequent explanation of
the production of polarization, and the necessary connexion between
polarization and double refraction, on mechanical principles.
4. The explanation of the phenomena of dipolarization, by
means of the interference of the resolved parts of the
vibrations after double refraction.
The history of each of these discoveries will be given separately
to a certain extent; by which means the force of proof arising from
their combination will be more apparent.
Sect. 2.—Explanation of the
Periodical Colors of Thin Plates and Shadows by the Undulatory
Theory.
The explanation of periodical
colors by the principle of interference of vibrations, was the first
step which Young made in his confirmation of the undulatory theory. In
a paper on Sound and Light, dated Emmanuel College, Cambridge, 9th
July, 1799, and read before the Royal Society in January following, he
appears to incline strongly to the Huyghenian theory; not however
offering any new facts or calculations in its favor, but pointing out
the great difficulties of the Newtonian hypothesis. But in a paper
read before the Royal Society, November 12, 1801, he says, “A further
consideration of the colors of thin plates has converted that
prepossession which I before entertained for the undulatory theory of
light, into a very strong conviction of its truth and efficiency; a
conviction which has since been most strikingly confirmed by an
analysis of the colors of striated surfaces.” He here states the
general principle of interferences in the form of a proposition.
(Prop. viii.) “When two undulations from different origins coincide
either perfectly or very nearly in direction, their joint effect is a
combination of the motions belonging to them.” He explains, by the
help of this proposition, the colors which were observed in Coventry’s
94 micrometers, in
which instrument lines were drawn on glass at a distance of 1⁄500th of
an inch. The interference of the undulations of the rays reflected
from the two sides of these fine lines, produced periodical colors. In
the same manner, he accounts for the colors of thin plates, by the
interference of the light partially reflected from the two surfaces of
the plates. We have already seen that Hooke
had long before suggested the same explanation; and Young says at the
end of his paper, “It was not till I had satisfied myself respecting
all these phenomena, that I found in Hooke’s Micrographia a
passage which might have led me earlier to a similar opinion.” He also
quotes from Newton many passages which assume the existence of an
ether; of which, as we have already seen,
Newton suggests the necessity in these very phenomena, though he would
apply it in combination with the emission of material light. In July,
1802, Young explained, on the same principle, some facts in indistinct
vision, and other similar appearances. And in 1803,75 he speaks more positively still. “In
making,” he says, “some experiments on the fringes of colors
accompanying shadows, I have found so simple and so demonstrative a
proof of the general law of interference of two portions of light,
which I have already endeavored to establish, that I think it right to
lay before the Royal Society a short statement of the facts which
appear to me to be thus decisive.” The two papers just mentioned
certainly ought to have convinced all scientific men of the truth of
the doctrine thus urged; for the number and exactness of the
explanations is very remarkable. They include the colored fringes
which are seen with the shadows of fibres; the colors produced by a
dew between two pieces of glass, which, according to the theory,
should appear when the thickness of the plate is six times
that of thin plates, and which do so; the changes resulting from the
employment of other fluids than water; the effect of inclining the
plates; also the fringes and bands which accompany shadows, the
phenomena observed by Grimaldi, Newton, Maraldi, and others, and
hitherto never at all reduced to rule. Young observes, very justly,
“whatever may be thought of the theory, we have got a simple and
general law” of the phenomena. He moreover calculated the length of an
undulation from the measurements of fringes of shadows, as he had done
before from the colors of thin plates; and found a very close
accordance of the results of the various cases with one another.
75 Phil. Trans. Memoir, read
Nov. 24.
95 There is one
difficulty, and one inaccuracy, in Young’s views at this period, which
it may be proper to note. The difficulty was, that he found it
necessary to suppose that light, when reflected at a rarer medium, is
retarded by half an undulation. This assumption, though often urged at
a later period as an argument against the theory, was fully justified
as the mechanical principles of the subject were unfolded; and the
necessity of it was clear to Young from the first. On the strength of
this, says he, “I ventured to predict, that if the reflections were of
the same kind, made at the surfaces of a thin plate, of a density
intermediate between the densities of the mediums surrounding it, the
central spot would be white; and I have now the pleasure of stating,
that I have fully verified this prediction by interposing a drop of
oil of sassafras between a prism of flint-glass and a lens of
crown-glass.”
The inaccuracy of his calculations consisted in his considering the
external fringe of shadows to be produced by the interference of a ray
reflected from the edge of the object, with a ray
which passes clear of it; instead of supposing all the parts
of the wave of light to corroborate or interfere with one another. The
mathematical treatment of the question on the latter hypothesis was by
no means easy. Young was a mathematician of considerable power in the
solution of the problems which came before him: though his methods
possessed none of the analytical elegance which, in his time, had
become general in France. But it does not appear that he ever solved
the problem of undulations as applied to fringes, with its true
conditions. He did, however, rectify his conceptions of the nature of
the interference; and we may add, that the numerical error of the
consequences of the defective hypothesis is not such as to prevent
their confirming the undulatory theory.76
76 I may mention, in addition to the
applications which Young made of the principle of interferences, his
Eriometer, an instrument invented for the purpose of measuring
the thickness of the fibres of wood; and the explanation of the
supernumerary bands of the rainbow. These explanations involve
calculations founded on the length of an undulation of light, and were
confirmed by experiment, as far as experiment went.
But though this theory was thus so powerfully recommended by
experiment and calculation, it met with little favor in the scientific
world. Perhaps this will be in some measure accounted for, when we
come, in the next chapter, to speak of the mode
of its reception by 96 the supposed judges of science and
letters. Its author went on laboring at the completion and application
of the theory in other parts of the subject; but his extraordinary
success in unravelling the complex phenomena of which we have been
speaking, appears to have excited none of the notice and admiration
which properly belonged to it, till Fresnel’s Memoir On
Diffraction was delivered to the Institute, in October, 1815.
MM. Arago and Poinsot were commissioned to make a report upon this
Memoir; and the former of these philosophers threw himself upon the
subject with a zeal and intelligence which peculiarly belonged to him.
He verified the laws announced by Fresnel: “laws,” he says, “which
appear to be destined to make an epoch in science.” He then cast a
rapid glance at the history of the subject, and recognized, at once,
the place which Young occupied in it. Grimaldi, Newton, Maraldi, he
states, had observed the facts, and tried in vain to reduce them to
rule or cause. “Such77 was the state of our knowledge on this
difficult question, when Dr. Thomas Young made the very remarkable
experiment which is described in the Philosophical Transactions
for 1803;” namely, that to obliterate all the bands within the shadow,
we need only stop the ray which is going to graze, or has grazed, one
border of the object. To this, Arago added the important observation,
that the same obliteration takes place, if we stop the ray, with a
transparent plate; except the plate be very thin, in which case the
bands are displaced, and not extinguished. “Fresnel,” says he,
“guessed the effect which a thin plate would produce, when I had told
him of the effect of a thick glass.” Fresnel himself declares78 that he was not, at the time, aware of
Young’s previous labors. After stating nearly the same reasonings
concerning fringes which Young had put forward in 1801, he adds, “it
is therefore the meeting, the actual crossing of the rays, which
produces the fringes. This consequence, which is only, so to speak,
the translation of the phenomena, seems to me entirely opposed to the
hypothesis of emission, and confirms the system which makes light
consist in the vibrations of a peculiar fluid.” And thus the Principle
of Interferences, and the theory of undulations, so far as that
principle depends upon the theory, was a second time established by
Fresnel in France, fourteen years after it had been discovered, fully
proved, and repeatedly published by Young in England.
77 An. Chim. 1815, Febr.
78 Ib. tom. xvii. p. 402.
97 In this Memoir
of Fresnel’s, he takes very nearly the same course as Young had done;
considering the interference of the direct light with that reflected
at the edge, as the cause of the external fringes; and he observes,
that in this reflection it is necessary to suppose half an undulation
lost: but a few years later, he considered the propagation of
undulations in a more true and general manner, and obtained the
solution of this difficulty of the half-undulation. His more complete
Memoir on Diffraction was delivered to the Institute of France,
July 29, 1818; and had the prize awarded it in 1819:79 but by the delays which at that period
occurred in the publication of the Parisian Academical
Transactions, it was not published80 till 1826, when
the theory was no longer generally doubtful or unknown in the
scientific world. In this Memoir, Fresnel observes, that we must
consider the effect of every portion of a wave of light upon
a distant point, and must, on this principle, find the illumination
produced by any number of such waves together. Hence, in general, the
process of integration is requisite; and though the integrals which
here offer themselves are of a new and difficult kind, he succeeded in
making the calculation for the cases in which he experimented. His
Table of the Correspondences of Theory and Observation,81 is very remarkable for the closeness of
the agreement; the errors being generally less than one hundredth of
the whole, in the distances of the black bands. He justly adds, “A
more striking agreement could not be expected between experiment and
theory. If we compare the smallness of the differences with the extent
of the breadths measured; and if we remark the great variations which
a and b (the distance of the object from the luminous
point and from the screen) have received in the different
observations, we shall find it difficult not to regard the integral
which has led us to these results as the faithful expression of the
law of the phenomena.”
79 Ann. Chim. May, 1819.
80 Mém. Inst. for
1821–2.
81 Mém. Inst. p.
420–424.
A mathematical theory, applied, with this success, to a variety of
cases of very different kinds, could not now fail to take strong hold
of the attention of mathematicians; and accordingly, from this time,
the undulatory doctrine of diffraction has been generally assented to,
and the mathematical difficulties which it involves, have been duly
studied and struggled with.
Among the remarkable applications of the undulatory doctrine to
diffraction, we may notice those of Joseph Fraunhofer, a 98 mathematical optician
of Munich. He made a great number of experiments on the shadows
produced by small holes, and groups of small holes, very near each
other. These were published82 in his New Modifications of
Light, in 1823. The greater part of this Memoir is employed in
tracing the laws of phenomena of the extremely complex and splendid
appearances which he obtained; but at the conclusion he observes, “It
is remarkable that the laws of the reciprocal influence and of the
diffraction of the rays, can be deduced from the principles of the
undulatory theory: knowing the conditions, we may, by means of an
extremely simple equation, determine the extent of a luminous wave for
each of the different colors; and in every case, the calculation
corresponds with observation.” This mention of “an extremely simple
equation,” appears to imply that he employed only Young’s and
Fresnel’s earlier mode of calculating interferences, by considering
two portions of light, and not the method of integration. Both from
the late period at which they were published, and from the absence of
mathematical details, Fraunhofer’s labors had not any strong influence
on the establishment of the undulatory theory; although they are
excellent verifications of it, both from the goodness of the
observations, and the complexity and beauty of the phenomena.
82 In Schumacher’s Astronomische
Abhandlungen, in French; earlier in German.
We have now to consider the progress of the undulatory theory in
another of its departments, according to the division already
stated.
Sect. 3.—Explanation of Double Refraction by the
Undulatory Theory.
We have traced the history of
the undulatory theory applied to diffraction, into the period when
Young came to have Fresnel for his fellow-laborer. But in the mean
time, Young had considered the theory in its reference to other
phenomena, and especially to those of double refraction.
In this case, indeed, Huyghens’s explanation of the facts of
Iceland spar, by means of spheroidal undulations, was so complete, and
had been so fully confirmed by the measurements of Haüy and Wollaston,
that little remained to be done, except to connect the Huyghenian
hypothesis with the mechanical views belonging to the theory, and to
extend his law to other cases. The former part of this task Young
executed, by remarking that we may conceive the elasticity of
the 99 crystal, on
which the velocity of propagation of the luminiferous undulation
depends, to be different, in the direction of the crystallographic
axis, and in the direction of the planes at right angles to this axis;
and from such a difference, he deduces the existence of spheroidal
undulations. This suggestion appeared in the Quarterly Review
for November, 1809, in a critique upon an attempt of Laplace to
account for the same phenomena. Laplace had proposed to reduce the
double refraction of such crystals as Iceland spar, to his favorite
machinery of forces which are sensible at small distances only. The
peculiar forces which produce the effect in this case, he conceives to
emanate from the crystallographic axis: so that the velocity of light
within the crystal will depend only on the situation of the ray with
respect to this axis. But the establishment of this condition is, as
Young observes, the main difficulty of the problem. How are we to
conceive refracting forces, independent of the surface of the
refracting medium, and regulated only by a certain internal line?
Moreover, the law of force which Laplace was obliged to assume,
namely, that it varied as the square of the sine of the angle which
the ray made with the axis, could hardly be reconciled with mechanical
principles. In the critique just mentioned, Young appears to feel that
the undulatory theory, and perhaps he himself, had not received
justice at the hands of men of science; he complains that a person so
eminent in the world of science as Laplace then was, should employ his
influence in propagating error, and should disregard the extraordinary
confirmations which the Huyghenian theory had recently received.
The extension of this view, of the different elasticity of crystals
in different directions, to other than uniaxal crystals, was a more
complex and difficult problem. The general notion was perhaps obvious,
after what Young had done; but its application and verification
involved mathematical calculations of great generality, and required
also very exact experiments. In fact, this application was not made
till Fresnel, a pupil of the Polytechnic School, brought the resources
of the modern analysis to bear upon the problem;—till the
phenomena of dipolarized light presented the properties of biaxal
crystals in a vast variety of forms;—and till the theory
received its grand impulse by the combination of the explanation of
polarization with the explanation of double refraction. To the history
of this last-mentioned great step we now proceed. 100
Sect. 4.—Explanation of Polarization by the
Undulatory Theory.
Even while the only phenomena
of polarization which were known were those which affect the
two images in Iceland spar, the difficulty which these facts seemed at
first to throw in the way of the undulatory theory was felt and
acknowledged by Young. Malus’s discovery of polarization by reflection
increased the difficulty, and this Young did not attempt to conceal.
In his review of the papers containing this discovery83 he says, “The discovery related in
these papers appears to us to be by far the most important and
interesting which has been made in France concerning the properties of
light, at least since the time of Huyghens; and it is so much the more
deserving of notice, as it greatly influences the general balance of
evidence in the comparison of the undulatory and projectile theories
of the nature of light.” He then proceeds to point out the main
features in this comparison, claiming justly a great advantage for the
theory of undulations on the two points we have been considering, the
phenomena of diffraction and of double refraction. And he adds, with
reference to the embarrassment introduced by polarization, that we are
not to expect the course of scientific discovery to run smooth and
uninterrupted; but that we are to lay our account with partial
obscurity and seeming contradiction, which we may hope that time and
enlarged research will dissipate. And thus he steadfastly held, with
no blind prejudice, but with unshaken confidence, his great
philosophical trust, the fortunes of the undulatory theory. It is
here, after the difficulties of polarization had come into view, and
before their solution had been discovered, that we may place the
darkest time of the history of the theory; and at this period Young
was alone in the field.
83 Quart. Rev. May, 1810.
It does not appear that the light dawned upon him for some years.
In the mean time, Young found that his theory would explain
dipolarized colors; and he had the satisfaction to see Fresnel
re-discover, and M. Arago adopt, his views on diffraction. He became
engaged in friendly intercourse with the latter philosopher, who
visited him in England in 1816. On January the 12th, 1817, in writing
to this gentleman, among other remarks on the subject of optics, he
says, “I have also been reflecting on the possibility of giving an
imperfect explanation of the affection of light which constitutes
polarization, 101
without departing from the genuine doctrine of undulation.” He then
proceeds to suggest the possibility of “a transverse
vibration, propagated in the direction of the radius, the motions of
the particles being in a certain constant direction with respect to
that radius; and this,” he adds, “is polarization.” From his
further explanation of his views, it appears that he conceived the
motions of the particles to be oblique to the direction of the ray,
and not perpendicular, as the theory was afterwards framed; but still,
here was the essential condition for the explanation of the facts of
polarization,—the transverse nature of the vibrations. This idea
at once made it possible to conceive how the rays of light could have
sides; for the direction in which the vibration was transverse
to the ray, might be marked by peculiar properties. And after the idea
was once started, it was comparatively easy for men like Young and
Fresnel to pursue and modify it till it assumed its true and distinct
form.
We may judge of the difficulty of taking firmly hold of the
conception of transverse vibrations of the ether, as those which
constitute light, by observing how long the great philosophers of whom
we are speaking lingered within reach of it, before they ventured to
grasp it. Fresnel says, in 1821, “When M. Arago and I had remarked (in
1816) that two rays polarized at right angles always give the same
quantity of light by their union, I thought this might be explained by
supposing the vibrations to be transverse, and to be at right angles
when the rays are polarized at right angles. But this supposition was
so contrary to the received ideas on the nature of the vibrations of
elastic fluids,” that Fresnel hesitated to adopt it till he could
reconcile it better to his mechanical notions. “Mr. Young, more bold
in his conjectures, and less confiding in the views of geometers,
published it before me, though perhaps he thought it after me.” And M.
Arago was afterwards wont to relate84 that when he and
Fresnel had obtained their joint experimental results of the
non-interference of oppositely-polarized pencils, and when Fresnel
pointed out that transverse vibrations were the only possible
translation of this fact into the undulatory theory, he himself
protested that he had not courage to publish such a conception; and
accordingly, the second part of the Memoir was published in Fresnel’s
name alone. What renders this more remarkable is, that it occurred
when M. Arago had in his possession the very letter of Young, in which
he proposed the same suggestion.
84 I take the liberty of stating this
from personal knowledge.
102 Young’s
first published statement of the doctrine of transverse vibrations was
given in the explanation of the phenomena of dipolarization, of which
we shall have to speak in the next Section. But
the primary and immense value of this conception, as a step in the
progress of the undulatory theory, was the connexion which it
established between polarization and double refraction; for it held
forth a promise of accounting for polarization, if any conditions
could be found which might determine what was the direction of the
transverse vibrations. The analysis of these conditions is, in a great
measure, the work of Fresnel; a task performed with profound
philosophical sagacity and great mathematical skill.
Since the double refraction of uniaxal crystals could be explained
by undulations of the form of a spheroid, it was perhaps not difficult
to conjecture that the undulations of biaxal crystals would be
accounted for by undulations of the form of an ellipsoid, which
differs from the spheroid in having its three axes unequal, instead of
two only; and consequently has that very relation to the other, in
respect of symmetry, which the crystalline and optical phenomena have.
Or, again, instead of supposing two different degrees of elasticity in
different directions, we may suppose three such different degrees in
directions at right angles to each other. This kind of generalization
was tolerably obvious to a practised mathematician.
But what shall call into play all these elasticities at once, and
produce waves governed by each of them? And what shall explain the
different polarization of the rays which these separate waves carry
with them? These were difficult questions, to the solution of which
mathematical calculation had hitherto been unable to offer any
aid.
It was here that the conception of transverse vibrations came in,
like a beam of sunlight, to disclose the possibility of a mechanical
connexion of all these facts. If transverse vibrations, travelling
through a uniform medium, come to a medium not uniform, but
constituted so that the elasticity shall be different in different
directions, in the manner we have described, what will be the course
and condition of the waves in the second medium? Will the effects of
such waves agree with the phenomena of doubly-refracted light in
biaxal crystals? Here was a problem, striking to the mathematician for
its generality and difficulty, and of deep interest to the physical
philosopher, because the fate of a great theory depended upon its
solution.
The solution, obtained by great mathematical skill, was laid before
the French Institute by Fresnel in November, 1821, and was carried
103 further in two
Memoirs presented in 1822. Its import is very curious. The undulations
which, coming from a distant centre, fall upon such a medium as we
have described, are, it appears from the principles of mechanics,
propagated in a manner quite different from anything which had been
anticipated. The “surface of the waves” (that is, the surface which
would bound undulations diverging from a point), is a very complex,
yet symmetrical curve surface; which, in the case of uniaxal crystals,
resolves itself into a sphere and a spheroid; but which, in general,
forms a continuous double envelope of the central point to which it
belongs, intersecting itself and returning into itself. The directions
of the rays are determined by this curve surface in biaxal crystals,
as in uniaxal crystals they are determined by the sphere and the
spheroid; and the result is, that in biaxal crystals, both
rays suffer extraordinary refraction according to determinate
laws. And the positions of the planes of polarization of the two rays
follow from the same investigation; the plane of polarization in every
case being supposed to be that which is perpendicular to the
transverse vibrations. Now it appeared that the polarization of the
two rays, as determined by Fresnel’s theory, would be in directions,
not indeed exactly accordant with the law deduced by M. Biot from
experiment, but deviating so little from those directions, that there
could be small doubt that the empirical formula was wrong, and the
theoretical one right.
The theory was further confirmed by an experiment showing that, in
a biaxal crystal (topaz), neither of the rays was refracted according
to the ordinary law, though it had hitherto been supposed that one of
them was so; a natural inaccuracy, since the error was small.85 Thus this beautiful theory corrected,
while it explained, the best of the observations which had previously
been made; and offered itself to mathematicians with an almost
irresistible power of conviction. The explanation of laws so strange
and diverse as those of double refraction and polarization, by the
same general and symmetrical theory, could not result from anything
but the truth of the theory.
85 An. Ch. xxviii. p.
264.
“Long,” says Fresnel,86 “before I had conceived this theory, I
had convinced myself by a pure contemplation of the facts, that it was
not possible to discover the true explanation of double refraction,
without explaining, at the same time, the phenomena of polarization,
which always goes along with it; and accordingly, it was after having
found 104 what mode
of vibration constituted polarization, that I caught sight of the
mechanical causes of double refraction.”
86 Sur la Double Réf., Mém.
Inst. 1826, p. 174.
Having thus got possession of the principle of the mechanism of
polarization, Fresnel proceeded to apply it to the other cases of
polarized light, with a rapidity and sagacity which reminds us of the
spirit in which Newton traced out the consequences of the principle of
universal gravitation. In the execution of his task, indeed, Fresnel
was forced upon several precarious assumptions, which make, even yet,
a wide difference between the theory of gravitation and that of light.
But the mode in which these were confirmed by experiment, compels us
to admire the happy apparent boldness of the calculator.
The subject of polarization by reflection was one of those
which seemed most untractable; but, by means of various artifices and
conjectures, it was broken up and subdued. Fresnel began with the
simplest case, the reflection of light polarized in the plane of
reflection; which he solved by means of the laws of collision of
elastic bodies. He then took the reflection of light polarized
perpendicularly to this plane; and here, adding to the general
mechanical principles a hypothetical assumption, that the
communication of the resolved motion parallel to the refracting
surface, takes place according to the laws of elastic bodies, he
obtains his formula. These results were capable of comparison with
experiment; and the comparison, when made by M. Arago, confirmed the
formulæ. They accounted, too, for Sir D. Brewster’s law concerning the
polarizing angle (see Chap. vi.); and this
could not but be looked upon as a striking evidence of their having
some real foundation. Another artifice which MM. Fresnel and Arago
employed, in order to trace the effect of reflection upon common
light, was to use a ray polarized in a plane making half a right angle
with the plane of reflection; for the quantities of the oppositely87 polarized light in such an incident ray
are equal, as they are in common light; but the relative quantities of
the oppositely polarized light in the reflected ray are indicated by
the new plane of polarization; and thus these relative quantities
become known for the case of common light. The results thus obtained
were also confirmed by facts; and in this manner, all that was
doubtful in the process of Fresnel’s reasoning, seemed to be
authorized by its application to real cases.
87 It will be recollected all along,
that oppositely polarized rays are those which are polarized
in two planes perpendicular to each other. See above, chap. vi.
105 These
investigations were published88 in 1821. In
succeeding years, Fresnel undertook to extend the application of his
formulæ to a case in which they ceased to have a meaning, or, in the
language of mathematicians, became imaginary; namely, to the
case of internal reflection at the surface of a transparent body. It
may seem strange to those who are not mathematicians, but it is
undoubtedly true, that in many cases in which the solution of a
problem directs impossible arithmetical or algebraical operations to
be performed, these directions may be so interpreted as to point out a
true solution of the question. Such an interpretation Fresnel
attempted89 in the case of which we now speak; and
the result at which he arrived was, that the reflection of light
through a rhomb of glass of a certain form (since called Fresnel’s
rhomb, would produce a polarization of a kind altogether different
from those which his theory had previously considered, namely, that
kind which we have spoken of as circular polarization. The
complete confirmation of this curious and unexpected result by trial,
is another of the extraordinary triumphs which have distinguished the
history of the theory at every step since the commencement of
Fresnel’s labors.
88 An. Chim. t. xvii.
89 Bullet. des Sc. Feb.
1823.
But anything further which has been done in this way, may be
treated of more properly in relating the verification of the theory.
And we have still to speak of the most numerous and varied class of
facts to which rival theories of light were applied, and of the
establishment of the undulatory doctrine in reference to that
department; I mean the phenomena of depolarized, or rather, as I have
already said, dipolarized light.
Sect. 5.—Explanation of
Dipolarization by the Undulatory Theory.
When Arago, in 1811, had
discovered the colors produced by polarized light passing through
certain crystals,90 it was natural that attempts should be
made to reduce them to theory. M. Biot, animated by the success of
Malus in detecting the laws of double refraction, and Young, knowing
the resources of his own theory, were the first persons to enter upon
this undertaking. M. Biot’s theory, though in the end displaced by its
rival, is well worth notice in the history of the subject. It was what
he called the doctrine of moveable polarization. He conceived
that when the molecules of light pass through 106 thin crystalline plates, the plane of
polarization undergoes an oscillation which carries it backwards and
forwards through a certain angle, namely, twice the angle contained
between the original plane of polarization and the principal section
of the crystal. The intervals which this oscillation occupies are
lengths of the path of the ray, very minute, and different for
different colors, like Newton’s fits of easy transmission; on which
model, indeed, the new theory was evidently framed.91 The colors produced in the phenomena of
dipolarization really do depend, in a periodical manner, on the length
of the path of the light through the crystal, and a theory such as M.
Biot’s was capable of being modified, and was modified, so as to
include the leading features of the facts as then known; but many of
its conditions being founded on special circumstances in the
experiments, and not on the real conditions of nature, there were in
it several incongruities, as well as the general defect of its being
an arbitrary and unconnected hypothesis.
90 See chap.
ix.
91 See MM. Arago and Biot’s Memoirs,
Mém. Inst. for 1811; the whole volume for 1812 is a Memoir of
M. Biot’s (published 1814); also Mém. Inst. for 1817; M. Biot’s
Mem. read in 1818, published in 1819 and for 1818.
Young’s mode of accounting for the brilliant phenomena of
dipolarization appeared in the Quarterly Review for 1814. After
noticing the discoveries of MM. Arago, Brewster, and Biot, he adds,
“We have no doubt that the surprise of these gentlemen will be as
great as our own satisfaction in finding that they are perfectly
reducible, like other causes of recurrent colors, to the general laws
of the interference of light which have been established in this
country;” giving a reference to his former statements. The results are
then explained by the interference of the ordinary and extraordinary
ray. But, as M. Arago properly observes, in his account of this
matter,92 “It must, however, be added that Dr.
Young had not explained either in what circumstances the interference
of the rays can take place, nor why we see no colors unless the
crystallized plates are exposed to light previously polarized.” The
explanation of these circumstances depends on the laws of interference
of polarized light which MM. Arago and Fresnel established in 1816.
They then proved, by direct experiment, that when polarized light was
treated so as to bring into view the most marked phenomena of
interference, namely, the bands of shadows; pencils of light which
have a common origin, and which are polarized in the parallel planes,
interfere completely, while those which are 107 polarized in opposite (that is,
perpendicular,) planes do not interfere at all.93 Taking these
principles into the account, Fresnel explained very completely, by
means of the interference of undulations, all the circumstances of
colors produced by crystallized plates; showing the necessity of the
polarization in the first instance; the dipolarizing
effect of the crystal; and the office of the analysing plate,
by which certain portions of each of the two rays in the crystal are
made to interfere and produce color. This he did, as he says,94 without being aware, till Arago told
him, that Young had, to some extent, anticipated him.
92 Enc. Brit. Supp. art.
Polarization.
93 Ann. Chim. tom. x.
94 Ib. tom. xvii. p. 402.
When we look at the history of the emission-theory of light, we see
exactly what we may consider as the natural course of things in the
career of a false theory. Such a theory may, to a certain extent,
explain the phenomena which it was at first contrived to meet; but
every new class of facts requires a new supposition,—an addition
to the machinery; and as observation goes on, these incoherent
appendages accumulate, till they overwhelm and upset the original
frame-work. Such was the history of the hypothesis of solid epicycles;
such has been the history of the hypothesis of the material emission
of light. In its simple form, it explained reflection and refraction;
but the colors of thin plates added to it the hypothesis of fits of
easy transmission and reflection; the phenomena of diffraction further
invested the particles with complex hypothetical laws of attraction
and repulsion; polarization gave them sides; double refraction
subjected them to peculiar forces emanating from the axes of crystals;
finally, dipolarization loaded them with the complex and unconnected
contrivance of moveable polarization; and even when all this had been
assumed, additional mechanism was wanting. There is here no unexpected
success, no happy coincidence, no convergence of principles from
remote quarters; the philosopher builds the machine, but its parts do
not fit; they hold together only while he presses them: this is not
the character of truth.
In the undulatory theory, on the other hand, all tends to unity and
simplicity. We explain reflection and refraction by undulations; when
we come to thin plates, the requisite “fits” are already involved in
our fundamental hypothesis, for they are the length of an undulation;
the phenomena of diffraction also require such intervals; and the
intervals thus required agree exactly with the others in magnitude,
108 so that no new
property is needed. Polarization for a moment checks us; but not long;
for the direction of our vibrations is hitherto arbitrary;—we
allow polarization to decide it. Having done this for the sake of
polarization, we find that it also answers an entirely different
purpose, that of giving the law of double refraction. Truth may give
rise to such a coincidence; falsehood cannot. But the phenomena become
more numerous, more various, more strange; no matter: the Theory is
equal to them all. It makes not a single new physical hypothesis; but
out of its original stock of principles it educes the counterpart of
all that observation shows. It accounts for, explains, simplifies, the
most entangled cases; corrects known laws and facts; predicts and
discloses unknown ones; becomes the guide of its former teacher,
Observation; and, enlightened by mechanical conceptions, acquires an
insight which pierces through shape and color to force and cause.
We thus reach the philosophical moral of this history, so
important in reference to our purpose; and here we shall close the
account of the discovery and promulgation of the undulatory theory.
Any further steps in its development and extension, may with propriety
be noticed in the ensuing chapters, respecting its reception and
verification.
[2nd Ed.] [In the Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences, B.
xi. ch. iii. Sect. 11, I have spoken of the Consilience of
Inductions as one of the characters of scientific truth. We have
several striking instances of such consilience in the history of the
undulatory theory. The phenomena of fringes of shadows and colored
bands in crystals jump together in the Theory of Vibrations.
The phenomena of polarization and double refraction jump
together in the Theory of Crystalline Vibrations. The phenomena
of polarization and of the interference of polarized rays jump
together in the Theory of Transverse Vibrations.
The proof of what is above said of the undulatory theory is
contained in the previous history. This theory has “accounted for,
explained, and simplified the most entangled cases;” as the cases of
fringes of shadows; shadows of gratings; colored bands in biaxal
crystals, and in quartz. There are no optical phenomena more entangled
than these. It has “corrected experimental laws,” as in the case of M.
Biot’s law of the direction of polarization in biaxal crystals. It has
done this, “without making any new physical hypothesis;” for the
transverse direction of vibrations, the different optical elasticities
of crystals in different directions, and (if it be adopted) the
hypothesis of finite 109 intervals of the particles (see chap. x. and hereafter, chap.
xiii.), are only limitations of what was indefinite in the earlier
form of the hypothesis. And so far as the properties of visible
radiant light are concerned, I do not think it at all too much to say,
as M. Schwerd has said, that “the undulation theory accounts for the
phenomena as completely as the theory of gravitation does for the
facts of the solar system.”
This we might say, even if some facts were not yet fully explained;
for there were till very lately, if there are not still, such
unexplained facts with regard to the theory of gravitation, presented
to us by the solar system. With regard to the undulatory theory, these
exceptions are, I think, disappearing quite as rapidly and as
completely as in the case of gravitation. It is to be observed that no
presumption against the theory can with any show of reason be
collected from the cases in which classes of phenomena remain
unexplained, the theory having never been applied to them by any
mathematician capable of tracing its results correctly. The history of
the theory of gravitation may show us abundantly how necessary it is
to bear in mind this caution; and the results of the undulatory theory
cannot be traced without great mathematical skill and great labor, any
more than those of gravitation.
This remark applies to such cases as that of the transverse
fringes of grooved surfaces. The general phenomena of these cases
are perfectly explained by the theory. But there is an interruption in
the light in an oblique direction, which has not yet been explained;
but looking at what has been done in other cases, it is impossible to
doubt that this phenomenon depends upon the results of certain
integrations, and would be explained if these were rightly
performed.
The phenomena of crystallized surfaces, and especially their
effects upon the plane of polarization, were examined by Sir D.
Brewster, and laws of the phenomena made out by him with his usual
skill and sagacity. For a time these were unexplained by the theory.
But recently Mr. Mac Cullagh has traced the consequences of the theory
in this case,95 and obtained a law which represents
with much exactness, Sir D. Brewster’s observation.
95 Prof. Lloyd’s Report, Brit.
Assoc. 1834, p. 374.
The phenomena which Sir D. Brewster, in 1837, called a new
property of light, (certain appearances of the spectrum when the
pupil of the eye is half covered with a thin glass or crystal,) have
been explained by Mr. Airy in the Phil. Trans. for 1840.
Mr. Airy’s explanation of the phenomena termed by Sir D. 110 Brewster a new
property of light, is completed in the Philosophical
Magazine for November, 1846. It is there shown that a dependence
of the breadth of the bands upon the aperture of the pupil, which had
been supposed to result from the theory, and which does not appear in
the experiment, did really result from certain limited conditions of
the hypothesis, which conditions do not belong to the experiment; and
that when the problem is solved without those limitations, the
discrepance of theory and observation vanishes; so that, as Mr. Airy
says, “this very remarkable experiment, which long appeared
inexplicable, seems destined to give one of the strongest
confirmations to the Undulatory Theory.”
I may remark also that there is no force in the objection which has
been urged against the admirers of the undulatory theory, that by the
fulness of their assent to it, they discourage further researches
which may contradict or confirm it. We must, in this point of view
also, look at the course of the theory of gravitation and its results.
The acceptance of that theory did not prevent mathematicians and
observers from attending to the apparent exceptions, but on the
contrary, stimulated them to calculate and to observe with additional
zeal, and still does so. The acceleration of the Moon, the mutual
disturbances of Jupiter and Saturn, the motions of Jupiter’s
Satellites, the effect of the Earth’s oblateness on the Moon’s motion,
the motions of the Moon about her own centre, and many other
phenomena, were studied with the greater attention, because
the general theory was deemed so convincing: and the same cause makes
the remaining exceptions objects of intense interest to astronomers
and mathematicians. The mathematicians and optical experimenters who
accept the undulatory theory, will of course follow out their
conviction in the same manner. Accordingly, this has been done and is
still doing, as in Mr. Airy’s mathematical investigation of the effect
of an annular aperture; Mr. Earnshaw’s, of the effect of a triangular
aperture; Mr. Talbot’s explanation of the effect of interposing a film
of mica between a part of the pupil and the pure spectrum, so nearly
approaching to the phenomena which have been spoken of as a new
Polarity of Light; besides other labors of eminent mathematicians,
elsewhere mentioned in these pages.
The phenomena of the absorption of light have no especial
bearing upon the undulatory theory. There is not much difficulty in
explaining the possibility of absorption upon the theory.
When the light is absorbed, it ceases to belong to the theory. 111
For, as I have said, the theory professes only to explain the
phenomena of radiant visible light. We know very well that
light has other bearings and properties. It produces chemical effects.
The optical polarity of crystals is connected with the chemical
polarity of their constitution. The natural colors of bodies, too, are
connected with their chemical constitution. Light is also connected
with heat. The undulatory theory does not undertake to explain these
properties and their connexion. If it did, it would be a Theory of
Heat and of Chemical Composition, as well as a Theory of Light.
Dr. Faraday’s recent experiments have shown that the magnetic
polarity is directly connected with that optical polarity by which the
plane of polarization is affected. When the lines of magnetic force
pass through certain transparent bodies, they communicate to them a
certain kind of circular polarizing power; yet different from the
circular polarizing power of quartz, and certain fluids mentioned in
chapter ix.
Perhaps I may be allowed to refer to this discovery as a further
illustration of the views I have offered in the Philosophy of the
Inductive Sciences respecting the Connexion of Co-existent
Polarities. (B. v. Chap. ii.)]
</div></body></text></TEI>