<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="31">

CHAPTER VI.
Of the Establishment of the Principles of Statics.


1. Object of the Chapter.—In the present and the
succeeding chapters we have to show how the general axioms
of Causation enable us to construct the science of
Mechanics. We have to consider these axioms as moulding
themselves, in the first place, into certain fundamental
mechanical principles, which are of evident and necessary
truth in virtue of their dependence upon the general axioms
of Causation; and thus as forming a foundation for the whole
structure of the science;—a system of truths no less
necessary than the fundamental principles, because derived
from these by rigorous demonstration.
This account of the construction of the science of
Mechanics, however generally treated, cannot be otherwise
than technical in its details, and will probably be
imperfectly understood by any one not acquainted with
Mechanics as a mathematical science.
I cannot omit this portion of my survey without rendering my
work incomplete; but I may remark that the main purpose of
it is to prove, in a more particular manner, what I have
already declared in general, that there are, in Mechanics no
less than in Geometry, fundamental principles of axiomatic
evidence and necessity;—that these principles derive their
axiomatic character from the Idea which they involve,
namely, the Idea of Cause;—and that through the combination
of principles of this kind, the whole science of Mechanics,
including its most complex and remote results, exists as a
body of solid and universal truths. 213
2. Statics and Dynamics.—We must first turn our
attention to a technical distinction of Mechanics into two
portions, according as the forces about which we reason
produce rest, or motion; the former portion is termed
Statics, the latter Dynamics. If a stone fall,
or a weight put a machine in motion, the problem belongs to
Dynamics; but if the stone rest upon the ground, or a weight
be merely supported by a machine, without being raised
higher, the question is one of Statics.
3. Equilibrium.—In Statics, forces balance
each other, or keep each other in equilibrium. And
forces which directly balance each other, or keep each other
in equilibrium, are necessarily and manifestly equal. If we
see two boys pull at two ends of a rope so that neither of
them in the smallest degree prevails over the other, we have
a case in which two forces are in equilibrium. The two
forces are evidently equal, and are a statical
exemplification of action and reaction, such as are spoken
of in the third axiom concerning causes. Now the same
exemplification occurs in every case of equilibrium. No
point or body can be kept at rest except in virtue of
opposing forces acting upon it; and these forces must always
be equal in their opposite effect. When a stone lies on the
floor, the weight of the stone downwards is opposed and
balanced by an equal pressure of the floor upwards. If the
stone rests on a slope, its tendency to slide is
counteracted by some equal and opposite force, arising, it
may be, from the resistance which the sloping ground opposes
to any motion along its surface. Every case of rest is a
case of equilibrium: every case of equilibrium is a case of
equal and opposite forces.
The most complex frame-work on which weights are supported,
as the roof of a building, or the cordage of a machine, are
still examples of equilibrium. In such cases we may have
many forces all combining to balance each other; and the
equilibrium will depend on various conditions of direction
and magnitude among the forces. And in order to understand
what are these conditions, we must ask, in the first place,
what 214 we understand by the magnitude of such
forces;—what is the measure of statical forces.
4. Measure of Statical Forces.—At first we might
expect, perhaps, that since statical forces come under the
general notion of Cause, the mode of measuring them would be
derived from the second axiom of Causation, that causes are
measured by their effects. But we find that the application
of this axiom is controlled by the limitation which we
noticed, after stating that axiom; namely, the condition
that the causes shall be capable of addition. Further, as we
have seen, a statical force produces no other effect than
this, that it balances some other statical force; and hence
the measure of statical forces is necessarily dependent upon
their balancing, that is, upon the equality of action and
reaction.
That statical forces are capable of addition is
involved in our conception of such forces. When two men pull
at a rope in the same direction, the forces which they exert
are added together. When two heavy bodies are put into a
basket suspended by a string, their weights are added, and
the sum is supported by the string.
Combining these considerations, it will appear that the
measure of statical forces is necessarily given at once by
the fundamental principle of the equality of action and
reaction. Since two opposite forces which balance each other
are equal, each force is measured by that which it balances;
and since forces are capable of addition, a force of any
magnitude is measured by adding together a proper number of
such equal forces. Thus a heavy body which, appended to some
certain elastic branch of a tree, would bend it down through
one inch, may be taken as a unit of weight. Then if we
remove this first body, and find a second heavy body which
will also bend the branch through the same space, this is
also a unit of weight; and in like manner we might go on to
a third and a fourth equal body; and adding together the
two, or the three, or the four heavy bodies, we have a force
twice, or three times, or four times the unit of weight. And
with 215 such a collection of heavy bodies, or
weights, we can readily measure all other forces; for
the same principle of the equality of action and reaction
leads at once to this maxim, that any statical force is
measured by the weight which it would support.
As has been said, it might at first have been supposed that
we should have to apply, in this case, the axiom that causes
are measured by their effects in another manner; that thus,
if that body were a unit of weight which bent the bough of a
tree through one inch, that body would be
two units which bent it through two
inches, and so on. But, as we have already stated, the
measures of weight must be subject to this condition, that
they are susceptible of being added: and therefore we cannot
take the deflexion of the bough for our measure, till we
have ascertained, that which experience alone can teach us,
that under the burden of two equal weights, the deflexion
will be twice as great as it is with one weight, which is
not true, or at least is neither obviously nor necessarily
true. In this, as in all other cases, although causes must
be measured by their effects, we learn from experience only
how the effects are to be interpreted, so as to give a true
and consistent measure.
With regard, however, to the measure of statical force, and
of weight, no difficulty really occurred to philosophers
from the time when they first began to speculate on such
subjects; for it was easily seen that if we take any uniform
material, as wood, or stone, or iron, portions of this which
are geometrically equal, must also be equal in statical
effect; since this was implied in the very hypothesis of a
uniform material And a body ten times as large as another of
the same substance, will be of ten times the weight. But
before men could establish by reasoning the conditions under
which weights would be in equilibrium, some other principles
were needed in addition to the mere measure of forces. The
principles introduced for this purpose still resulted from
the conception of equal action and reaction; but it required
no small clearness of thought to select them rightly, and to
employ them 216 successfully. This, however, was done, to
a certain extent, by the Greeks; and the treatise of
Archimedes On the Center of Gravity, is founded on
principles which may still be considered as the genuine
basis of statical reasoning. I shall make a few remarks on
the most important principle among those which Archimedes
thus employs.
5. The Center of Gravity.—The most important of the
principles which enter into the demonstration of Archimedes
is this: that “Every body has a center of gravity;” meaning
by the center of gravity, a point at which the whole matter
of the body may be supposed to be collected, to all intents
and purposes of statical reasoning. This principle has been
put in various forms by succeeding writers: for instance, it
has been thought sufficient to assume a case much simpler
than the general one; and to assert that two equal
bodies have their center of gravity in the point midway
between them. It is to be observed, that this assertion not
only implies that the two bodies will balance upon a
support placed at that midway point, but also, that they
will exercise, upon such a support, a pressure equal to
their sum; for this point being the center of gravity,
the whole matter of the two bodies may be conceived to be
collected there, and therefore the whole weight will press
there. And thus the principle in question amounts to this,
that when two equal heavy bodies are supported on the
middle point between them, the pressure upon the support is
equal to the sum of the weights of the bodies.
A clear understanding of the nature and grounds of this
principle is of great consequence: for in it we have the
foundation of a large portion of the science of Mechanics.
And if this principle can be shown to be necessarily true,
in virtue of our Fundamental Ideas, we can hardly doubt that
there exist many other truths of the same kind, and that no
sound view of the evidence and extent of human knowledge can
be obtained, so long as we mistake the nature of these, its
first principles. 217
The above principle, that the pressure on the support is
equal to the sum of the bodies supported, is often stated as
an axiom in the outset of books on Mechanics. And this
appears to be the true place and character of this
principle, in accordance with the reasonings which we have
already urged. The axiom depends upon our conception of
action and reaction. That the two weights are supported,
implies that the supporting force must be equal to the force
or weight supported.
In order further to show the foundation of this principle,
we may ask the question:—If it be not an axiom, deriving
its truth from the fundamental conception of equal action
and reaction, which equilibrium always implies, what is the
origin of its certainty? The principle is never for an
instant denied or questioned: it is taken for granted, even
before it is stated. No one will doubt that it is not only
true, but true with the same rigour and universality as the
axioms of Geometry. Will it be said, that it is borrowed
from experience? Experience could never prove a principle to
be universally and rigorously true. Moreover, when from
experience we prove a proposition to possess great exactness
and generality, we approach by degrees to this proof: the
conviction becomes stronger, the truth more secure, as we
accumulate trials. But nothing of this kind is the case in
the instance before us. There is no gradation from less to
greater certainty;—no hesitation which precedes confidence.
From the first, we know that the axiom is exactly and
certainly true. In order to be convinced of it, we do not
require many trials, but merely a clear understanding of the
assertion itself.
But in fact, not only are trials not necessary to the proof,
but they do not strengthen it. Probably no one ever made a
trial for the purpose of showing that the pressure upon the
support is equal to the sum of the two weights. Certainly no
person with clear mechanical conceptions ever wanted such a
trial to convince him of the truth; or thought the truth
clearer after the trial had been made. If to such a person,
an 218 experiment were shown which seemed to contradict
the principle, his conclusion would be, not that the
principle was doubtful, but that the apparatus was out of
order. Nothing can be less like collecting truth from
experience than this.
We maintain, then, that this equality of mechanical action
and reaction, is one of the principles which do not flow
from, but regulate our experience. To this principle, the
facts which we observe must conform; and we cannot help
interpreting them in such a manner that they shall be
exemplifications of the principle. A mechanical pressure not
accompanied by an equal and opposite pressure, can no more
be given by experience, than two unequal right angles. With
the supposition of such inequalities, space ceases to be
space, force ceases to be force, matter ceases to be matter.
And this equality of action and reaction, considered in the
case in which two bodies are connected so as to act on a
single support, leads to the axiom which we have stated
above, and which is one of the main foundations of the
science of Mechanics.
[2d ed.] [To the doctrine that mechanical principles, such
as the one here under consideration (that the pressure on
the point of support is equal to the sum of the weights),
are derived from our Ideas, and do not flow from but
regulate our experience, objections are naturally made by
those who assert all our knowledge to be derived from
experience. How, they ask, can we know the properties of
pressures, levers and the like, except from experience? What
but experience can possibly inform us that a force applied
transversely to a lever will have any tendency to turn the
lever on its center? This cannot be, except we suppose in
the lever tenacity, rigidity and the like, which are
qualities known only by experience. And it is obvious that
this line of argument might be carried on through the whole
subject.
My answer to this objection is a remark of the same kind as
one which I have made respecting the Ideas of Space, Time,
and Number, in the last Book. The mind, in apprehending
events as causes 219 and effects, is governed by Laws of
its own Activity; and these Laws govern the results of the
mind’s action; and make these results conform to the Axioms
of Causation. But this activity of the mind is awakened and
developed by being exercised; and in dealing with the
examples of cause and effect here spoken of, (namely,
pressure and resistance, force and motion,) the mind’s
activity is necessarily governed also by the bodily powers
of perception and action. We are human beings only in so far
as we have existed in space and time; and of our human
faculties, developed by our existence in space and time,
space and time are necessary conditions. In like manner, we
are human beings only in so far as we have bodies, and
bodily organs; and our bodies necessarily imply material
objects external to us. And hence our human faculties,
developed by our bodily existence in a material world, have
the conditions of matter for their necessary Laws. I have
already said (chap. v.) that our conception of Force arises
with our consciousness of our own muscular exertions;—that
Force cannot be conceived without Resistance to exercise
itself upon;—and that this resistance is supplied by
Matter. And thus the conception of Matter, and of the most
general modes in which Matter receives, resists, and
transmits force, are parts of our constitution which, though
awakened and unfolded by our being in a material world, are
not distinguishable from the original structure of the mind.
I do not ascribe to the mind innate Ideas—Ideas
which it would have, even if it had no intercourse with the
world of space, time, and matter; because we cannot imagine
a mind in such a state. But I attempt to point out and
classify those Conditions of all Experience, to which the
intercourse of all minds with the material world has
necessarily given rise in all. Truths thus
necessarily acquired in the course of all experience, cannot
be said to be learnt from experience, in the same
sense in which particular facts, at definite times, are
learnt from experience—learnt by some persons and not by
others—learnt with more or less of certainty. These latter
special truths of 220 experience will be
very important subjects of our consideration; but our whole
chance of discussing them with any profit depends upon our
keeping them distinct from the necessary and universal
conditions of experience. Here, as everywhere, we must
keep in view the fundamental antithesis of Ideas and Facts.]
6. Oblique Forces.—By the aid of the above axiom and
a few others, the Greeks made some progress in the science
of Statics. But after a short advance, they arrived at
another difficulty, that of Oblique Forces, which they never
overcame; and which no mathematician mastered till modern
times. The unpublished manuscripts of Leonardo da Vinci,
written in the fifteenth century, and the works of Stevinus
and Galileo, in the sixteenth, are the places in which we
find the first solid grounds of reasoning on the subject of
forces acting obliquely to each other. And from that period,
mathematicians, having thus become possessed of all the
mechanical principles which are requisite in problems
respecting equilibrium, soon framed a complete science of
Statics. Succeeding writers presented this science in forms
variously modified; for it was found, in Mechanics as in
Geometry, that various propositions might be taken as the
starting points; and that the collection of truths which it
was the mechanician’s business to include in his course,
might thus be traversed by various routes, each path
offering a series of satisfactory demonstrations. The
fundamental conceptions of force and resistance, like those
of space and number, could be contemplated under different
aspects, each of which might be made the basis of axioms, or
of principles employed as axioms. Hence the grounds of the
truth of Statics may be stated in various ways; and it would
be a task of some length to examine all these completely,
and to trace them to their Fundamental Ideas. This I shall
not undertake here to do; but the philosophical importance
of the subject makes it proper to offer a few remarks on
some of the main principles involved in the different modes
of presenting Statics as a rigorously demonstrated science. 221
7. A Force may be supposed to act at any Point of its
Direction.—It has been stated in the history of
Mechanics12, that Leonardo da Vinci and Galileo obtained
the true measure of the effect of oblique forces, by
reasonings which were, in substance, the same. The principle
of these reasonings is that expressed at the head of this
paragraph; and when we have a little accustomed ourselves to
contemplate our conceptions of force, and its action on
matter, in an abstract manner, we shall have no difficulty
in assenting to the principle in this general form. But it
may, perhaps, be more obvious at first in a special case.</div></body></text></TEI>