<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="73">CHAPTER XII.
Sequel to the Epoch of Young and Fresnel. Reception
of the Undulatory Theory.
WHEN Young, in 1800, published
his assertion of the Principle of Interferences, as the true theory of
optical phenomena, the condition of England was not very favorable to
a fair appreciation of the value of the new opinion. The men of
science were strongly pre-occupied in favor of the doctrine of
emission, not only from a national interest in Newton’s glory, and a
natural reverence for his authority, but also from deference towards
the geometers of France, who were looked up to as our masters in the
application of mathematics to physics, and who were understood to be
Newtonians in this as in other subjects. A general tendency to an
atomic philosophy, which had begun to appear from the time of Newton,
operated powerfully; and 112 the hypothesis of emission was so easily
conceived, that, when recommended by high authority, it easily became
popular; while the hypothesis of luminiferous undulations, unavoidably
difficult to comprehend, even by the aid of steady thought, was
neglected, and all but forgotten.
Yet the reception which Young’s opinions met with was more harsh
than he might have expected, even taking into account all these
considerations. But there was in England no visible body of men,
fitted by their knowledge and character to pronounce judgment on such
a question, or to give the proper impulse and bias to public opinion.
The Royal Society, for instance, had not, for a long time, by custom
or institution, possessed or aimed at such functions. The writers of
“Reviews” alone, self-constituted and secret tribunals, claimed this
kind of authority. Among these publications, by far the most
distinguished about this period was the Edinburgh Review; and,
including among its contributors men of eminent science and great
talents, employing also a robust and poignant style of writing (often
certainly in a very unfair manner), it naturally exercised great
influence. On abstruse doctrines, intelligible to few persons, more
than on other subjects, the opinions and feelings expressed in a
Review must be those of the individual reviewer. The criticism on some
of Young’s early papers on optics was written by Mr. (afterwards Lord)
Brougham, who, as we have seen, had experimented on diffraction,
following the Newtonian view, that of inflexion. Mr. Brougham was
perhaps at this time young enough96 to be somewhat
intoxicated with the appearance of judicial authority in matters of
science, which his office of anonymous reviewer gave him: and even in
middle-life, he was sometimes considered to be prone to indulge
himself in severe and sarcastic expressions. In January, 1803, was
published97 his critique on Dr. Young’s Bakerian
Lecture, On the Theory of Light and Colors, in which lecture
the doctrine of undulations and the law of interferences was
maintained. This critique was an uninterrupted strain of blame and
rebuke. “This paper,” the reviewer said, “contains nothing which
deserves the name either of experiment or discovery.” He charged the
writer with “dangerous relaxations of the principles of physical
logic.” “We wish,” he cried, “to recall philosophers to the strict and
severe methods of investigation,” describing them as those pointed out
by Bacon, Newton, and the like. Finally, Dr. Young’s speculations
113 were spoken of
as a hypothesis, which is a mere work of fancy; and the critic added,
“we cannot conclude our review without entreating the attention of the
Royal Society, which has admitted of late so many hasty and
unsubstantial papers into its Transactions;” which habit he
urged them to reform. The same aversion to the undulatory theory
appears soon after in another article by the same reviewer, on the
subject of Wollaston’s measures of the refraction of Iceland spar; he
says, “We are much disappointed to find that so acute and ingenious an
experimentalist should have adopted the wild optical theory of
vibrations.” The reviewer showed ignorance as well as prejudice in the
course of his remarks; and Young drew up an answer, which was ably
written, but being published separately had little circulation. We can
hardly doubt that these Edinburgh reviews had their effect in
confirming the general disposition to reject the undulatory
theory.
96 His age was twenty-four.
97 Edin. Review, vol. i. p.
450.
We may add, however, that Young’s mode of presenting his opinions
was not the most likely to win them favor; for his mathematical
reasonings placed them out of the reach of popular readers, while the
want of symmetry and system in his symbolical calculations, deprived
them of attractiveness for the mathematician. He himself gave a very
just criticism of his own style of writing, in speaking on another of
his works:98 “The mathematical reasoning, for want
of mathematical symbols, was not understood, even by tolerable
mathematicians. From a dislike of the affectation of algebraical
formality which he had observed in some foreign authors, he was led
into something like an affectation of simplicity, which was equally
inconvenient to a scientific reader.”
98 See Life of Young, p.
54.
Young appears to have been aware of his own deficiency in the power
of drawing public favor, or even notice, to his discoveries. In 1802,
Davy writes to a friend, “Have you seen the theory of my colleague,
Dr. Young, on the undulations of an ethereal medium as the cause of
light? It is not likely to be a popular hypothesis, after what has
been said by Newton concerning it. He would be very much flattered if
you could offer any observations upon it, whether for or against
it.” Young naturally felt confident in his power of refuting
objections, and wanted only the opportunity of a public combat.
Dr. Brewster, who was, at this period, enriching optical knowledge
with so vast a train of new phenomena and laws, shared the general
aversion to the undulatory theory, which, indeed, he hardly overcame
114 thirty years
later. Dr. Wollaston was a person whose character led him to look long
at the laws of phenomena, before he attempted to determine their
causes; and it does not appear that he had decided the claims of the
rival theories in his own mind. Herschel (I now speak of the son) had
at first the general mathematical prejudice in favor of the emission
doctrine. Even when he had himself studied and extended the laws of
dipolarized phenomena, he translated them into the language of the
theory of moveable polarization. In 1819, he refers to, and corrects,
this theory; and says, it is now “relieved from every difficulty, and
entitled to rank with the fits of easy transmission and reflection as
a general and simple physical law;” a just judgment, but one which now
conveys less of praise than he then intended. At a later period, he
remarked that we cannot be certain that if the theory of emission had
been as much cultivated as that of undulation, it might not have been
as successful; an opinion which was certainly untenable after the fair
trial of the two theories in the case of diffraction, and extravagant
after Fresnel’s beautiful explanation of double refraction and
polarization. Even in 1827, in a Treatise on Light, published
in the Encyclopædia Metropolitana, he gives a section to the
calculations of the Newtonian theory; and appears to consider the
rivalry of the theories as still subsisting. But yet he there speaks
with a proper appreciation of the advantages of the new doctrine.
After tracing the prelude to it, he says, “But the unpursued
speculations of Newton, and the opinions of Hooke, however distinct,
must not be put in competition, and, indeed, ought scarcely to be
mentioned, with the elegant, simple, and comprehensive theory of
Young,—a theory which, if not founded in nature, is certainly
one of the happiest fictions that the genius of man ever invented to
grasp together natural phenomena, which, at their first discovery,
seemed in irreconcileable opposition to it. It is, in fact, in all its
applications and details, one succession of felicities;
insomuch, that we may almost be induced to say, if it be not true, it
deserves to be so.”
In France, Young’s theory was little noticed or known, except
perhaps by M. Arago, till it was revived by Fresnel. And though
Fresnel’s assertion of the undulatory theory was not so rudely
received as Young’s had been, it met with no small opposition from the
older mathematicians, and made its way slowly to the notice and
comprehension of men of science. M. Arago would perhaps have at once
adopted the conception of transverse vibrations, when it was suggested
by his fellow-laborer, Fresnel, if it had not been that he was a
member of the 115
Institute, and had to bear the brunt of the war, in the frequent
discussions on the undulatory theory; to which theory Laplace, and
other leading members, were so vehemently opposed, that they would not
even listen with toleration to the arguments in its favor. I do not
know how far influences of this kind might operate in producing the
delays which took place in the publication of Fresnel’s papers. We
have seen that he arrived at the conception
of transverse vibrations in 1816, as the true key to the understanding
of polarization. In 1817 and 1818, in a memoir read to the Institute,
he analysed and explained the perplexing phenomena of quartz, which he
ascribed to a circular polarization. This memoir had not been
printed, nor any extract from it inserted in the scientific journals,
in 1822, when he confirmed his views by further experiments.99 His remarkable memoir, which solved the
extraordinary and capital problem of the connexion of double
refraction and crystallization, though written in 1821, was not
published till 1827. He appears by this time to have sought other
channels of publication. In 1822, he gave,100 in the
Annales de Chimie et de Physique, an explanation of refraction
on the principles of the undulatory theory; alleging, as the reason
for doing so, that the theory was still little known. And in
succeeding years there appeared in the same work, his theory of
reflection. His memoir on this subject (Mémoire sur la Loi des
Modifications que la Réflexion imprime à la Lumière Polarisée,)
was read to the Academy of Sciences in 1823. But the original paper was
mislaid, and, for a time, supposed to be lost; it has since been
recovered among the papers of M. Fourier, and printed in the eleventh
volume of the Memoirs of the Academy.101 Some of the
speculations to which he refers, as communicated to the Academy, have
never yet appeared.102
99 Hersch. Light, p. 539.
100 Ann. de Chim. 1822, tom.
xxi. p. 235.
101 Lloyd. Report on Optics,
p. 363. (Fourth Rep. of Brit. Ass.)
102 Ib. p. 316, note.
Still Fresnel’s labors were, from the first, duly appreciated by
some of the most eminent of his countrymen. His Memoir on
Diffraction was, as we have seen, crowned in 1819: and, in 1822, a
Report upon his Memoir on Double Refraction was drawn up by a
commission consisting of MM. Ampère, Fourier, and Arago. In this
report103 Fresnel’s theory is spoken of as
confirmed by the most delicate tests. The reporters add, respecting
his “theoretical ideas on the particular kind of undulations which,
according to him, constitute light,” that “it would be impossible for
them to pronounce at present a decided 116 judgment,” but that “they have not
thought it right to delay any longer making known a work of which the
difficulty is attested by the fruitless efforts of the most skilful
philosophers, and in which are exhibited in the same brilliant degree,
the talent for experiment and the spirit of invention.”
103 Ann. Chim. tom. xx. p.
343.
In the meantime, however, a controversy between the theory of
undulations and the theory of moveable polarization which M. Biot had
proposed with a view of accounting for the colors produced by
dipolarizing crystals, had occurred among the French men of science.
It is clear that in some main features the two theories coincide; the
intervals of interference in the one theory being represented by the
intervals of the oscillations in the other. But these intervals in M.
Biot’s explanations were arbitrary hypotheses, suggested by these very
facts themselves; in Fresnel’s theory, they were essential parts of
the general scheme. M. Biot, indeed, does not appear to have been
averse from a coalition; for he allowed104 to Fresnel
that “the theory of undulations took the phenomena at a higher point
and carried them further.” And M. Biot could hardly have dissented
from M. Arago’s account of the matter, that Fresnel’s views
“linked together”105 the
oscillations of moveable polarization. But Fresnel, whose hypothesis
was all of one piece, could give up no part of it, although he allowed
the usefulness of M. Biot’s formulæ. Yet M. Biot’s speculations fell
in better with the views of the leading mathematicians of Paris. We
may consider as evidence of the favor with which they were looked
upon, the large space they occupy in the volumes of the Academy for
1811, 1812, 1817, and 1818. In 1812, the entire volume is filled with
a memoir of M. Biot’s on the subject of moveable polarization. This
doctrine also had some advantage in coming early before the world in a
didactic form, in his Traité de Physique, which was published
in 1816, and was the most complete treatise on general physics which
had appeared up to that time. In this and others of this author’s
writings, he expresses facts so entirely in the terms of his own
hypothesis, that it is difficult to separate the two. In the sequel M.
Arago was the most prominent of M. Biot’s opponents; and in his report
upon Fresnel’s memoir on the colors of crystalline plates, he exposed
the weaknesses of the theory of moveable polarization with some
severity. The details of this controversy need not occupy us; but we
may observe that this may be considered as the last struggle 117 in favor of the
theory of emission among mathematicians of eminence. After this crisis
of the war, the theory of moveable polarization lost its ground; and
the explanations of the undulatory theory, and the calculations
belonging to it, being published in the Annales de Chimie et de
Physique, of which M. Arago was one of the conductors, soon
diffused it over Europe.
104 Ann. Chim. tom. xvii. p.
251.
105 “Nouait”.
It was probably in consequence of the delays to which we have
referred, in the publication of Fresnel’s memoirs, that as late as
December, 1826, the Imperial Academy at St Petersburg proposed, as one
of their prize-questions for the two following years, this,—“To
deliver the optical system of waves from all the objections which have
(as it appears) with justice been urged against it, and to apply it to
the polarization and double refraction of light.” In the programme to
this announcement, Fresnel’s researches on the subject are not alluded
to, though his memoir on diffraction is noticed; they were, therefore,
probably not known to the Russian Academy.
Young was always looked upon as a person of marvellous variety of
attainments and extent of knowledge; but during his life he hardly
held that elevated place among great discoverers which posterity will
probably assign him. In 1802, he was constituted Foreign Secretary of
the Royal Society, an office which he held during life; in 1827 he was
elected one of the eight Foreign Members of the Institute of France;
perhaps the greatest honor which men of science usually receive. The
fortune of his life in some other respects was of a mingled
complexion. His profession of a physician occupied, sufficiently to
fetter, without rewarding him; while he was Lecturer at the Royal
Institution, he was, in his lectures, too profound to be popular; and
his office of Superintendent of the Nautical Almanac subjected
him to much minute labor, and many petulant attacks of pamphleteers.
On the other hand, he had a leading part in the discovery of the
long-sought key to the Egyptian hieroglyphics; and thus the age which
was marked by two great discoveries, one in science and one in
literature, owed them both in a great measure to him. Dr. Young died
in 1829, when he had scarcely completed his fifty-sixth year. Fresnel
was snatched from science still more prematurely, dying, in 1827, at
the early age of thirty-nine.
We need not say that both these great philosophers possessed, in an
eminent degree, the leading characteristics of the discoverer’s mind,
perfect clearness of view, rich fertility of invention, and intense
love of knowledge. We cannot read without great interest a letter of
118 Fresnel to
Young,106 in November, 1824: “For a long time
that sensibility, or that vanity, which people call love of glory, is
much blunted in me. I labor much less to catch the suffrages of the
public, than to obtain an inward approval which has always been the
sweetest reward of my efforts. Without doubt I have often wanted the
spur of vanity to excite me to pursue my researches in moments of
disgust and discouragement. But all the compliments which I have
received from MM. Arago, De Laplace, or Biot, never gave me so much
pleasure as the discovery of a theoretical truth, or the confirmation
of a calculation by experiment.”
106 I was able to give this, and some
other extracts, from the then unedited correspondence of Young and
Fresnel, by the kindness of (the Dean of Ely) Professor Peacock, of
Trinity College, Cambridge, whose Life of Dr. Young has since been
published.
Though Young and Fresnel were in years the contemporaries of many
who are now alive, we must consider ourselves as standing towards them
in the relation of posterity. The Epoch of Induction in Optics is
past; we have now to trace the Verification and Application of the
true theory.
</div></body></text></TEI>