<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="45">CHAPTER V.
Progress in the Middle Ages.

Thomas Aquinas.
Aquinas wrote (besides the
Summa mentioned in the text) a Commentary
on the Physics of Aristotle: Commentaria in Aristotelis Libros
Physicorum, Venice, 1492. This work is of course of no scientific
value; and the commentary consists of empty permutations of abstract
terms, similar to those which constitute the main substance of the
text in Aristotle’s physical speculations. There is, however, an
attempt to give a more technical form to the propositions and their
demonstrations. As specimens of these, I may mention that in Book vi.
c. 2, we have a demonstration that when bodies move, the time and the
magnitude (that is, the space described), are divided similarly; with
many like propositions. And in Book viii. we have such propositions as
this (c. 10): “Demonstration that a finite mover (movens)
cannot move anything in an infinite time.” This is illustrated by a
diagram in which two hands are represented as engaged in moving a
whole sphere, and one hand in moving a hemisphere.
This mode of representing force, in diagrams illustrative of
mechanical reasonings, by human hands pushing, pulling, and the like,
is still employed in elementary books. Probably this is the first
example of such a mode of representation.
Roger Bacon.
This writer, a contemporary of Thomas
Aquinas, exhibits to us a kind of knowledge, speculation, and opinion,
so different from that of any known person near his time, that he
deserves especial notice here; 513 and I shall transfer to this place the
account which I have given of him in the Philosophy. I do this
the more willingly because I regard the existence of such a work as
the Opus Majus at that period as a problem which has never yet
been solved. Also I may add, that the scheme of the Contents of this
work which I have given, deserves, as I conceive, more notice than it
has yet received.
“Roger Bacon was born in 1214, near Ilchester, in Somersetshire, of
an old family. In his youth he was a student at Oxford, and made
extraordinary progress in all branches of learning. He then went to
the University of Paris, as was at that time the custom of learned
Englishmen, and there received the degree of Doctor of Theology. At
the persuasion of Robert Grostête, bishop of Lincoln, he entered the
brotherhood of Franciscans in Oxford, and gave himself up to study
with extraordinary fervor. He was termed by his brother monks
Doctor Mirabilis. We know from his own works, as well as from
the traditions concerning him, that he possessed an intimate
acquaintance with all the science of his time which could be acquired
from books; and that he had made many remarkable advances by means of
his own experimental labors. He was acquainted with Arabic, as well as
with the other languages common in his time. In the title of his
works, we find the whole range of science and philosophy, Mathematics
and Mechanics, Optics, Astronomy, Geography, Chronology, Chemistry,
Magic, Music, Medicine, Grammar, Logics, Metaphysics, Ethics, and
Theology; and judging from those which are published, these works are
full of sound and exact knowledge. He is, with good reason, supposed
to have discovered, or to have had some knowledge of, several of the
most remarkable inventions which were made generally known soon
afterwards; as gunpowder, lenses, burning specula, telescopes, clocks,
the correction of the calendar, and the explanation of the
rainbow.
“Thus possessing, in the acquirements and habits of his own mind,
abundant examples of the nature of knowledge and of the process of
invention, Roger Bacon felt also a deep interest in the growth and
progress of science, a spirit of inquiry respecting the causes which
produced or prevented its advance, and a fervent hope and trust in its
future destinies; and these feelings impelled him to speculate
worthily and wisely respecting a Reform of the Method of
Philosophizing. The manuscripts of his works have existed for nearly
six hundred years in many of the libraries of Europe, and especially
in those of England; and for a long period the very imperfect portions
of them which were 514 generally known, left the character and
attainments of the author shrouded in a kind of mysterious obscurity.
About a century ago, however, his Opus Majus was published5
by Dr. S. Jebb, principally from a manuscript in the library of
Trinity College, Dublin; and this contained most or all of the
separate works which were previously known to the public, along with
others still more peculiar and characteristic. We are thus able to
judge of Roger Bacon’s knowledge and of his views, and they are in
every way well worthy our attention.
5 Fratris Rogeri Bacon Ordinis
Minorum Opus Majus ad Clementem Quartum, Pontificem Romanum, ex
MS. Codice Dubliniensi cum aliis quibusdam collato nunc primum
edidit S. Jebb, M.D. Londini, 1733.
“The Opus Majus is addressed to Pope Clement the Fourth,
whom Bacon had known when he was legate in England as Cardinal-bishop
of Sabina, and who admired the talents of the monk, and pitied him for
the persecutions to which he was exposed. On his elevation to the
papal chair, this account of Bacon’s labours and views was sent, at
the earnest request of the pontiff. Besides the Opus Majus, he
wrote two others, the Opus Minus and Opus Tertium; which
were also sent to the pope, as the author says,6 ‘on account of the
danger of roads, and the possible loss of the work.’ These works still
exist unpublished, in the Cottonian and other libraries.
6 Opus Majus, Præf.
“The Opus Majus is a work equally wonderful with regard to
its general scheme, and to the special treatises with which the
outlines of the plan are filled up. The professed object of the work
is to urge the necessity of a reform in the mode of philosophizing, to
set forth the reasons why knowledge had not made a greater progress,
to draw back attention to the sources of knowledge which had been
unwisely neglected, to discover other sources which were yet almost
untouched, and to animate men in the undertaking, by a prospect of the
vast advantages which it offered. In the developement of this plan,
all the leading portions of science are expounded in the most complete
shape which they had at that time assumed; and improvements of a very
wide and striking kind are proposed in some of the principal of these
departments. Even if the work had had no leading purpose, it would
have been highly valuable as a treasure of the most solid knowledge
and soundest speculations of the time; even if it had contained no
such details, it would have been a work most remarkable for its
general views and scope. It may be considered as, at the same time,
the Encyclopedia and the Novum Organon of the thirteenth
century. 515
“Since this work is thus so important in the history of Inductive
Philosophy I shall give, in a Note, a view7 of its divisions
and contents. But I must now endeavor to point out more especially the
way in which the various principles, which the reform of scientific
method involved, are here brought into view.
7 Contents of Roger Bacon’s Opus
Majus:







Part I.
On the four causes of human
ignorance:—Authority, Custom, Popular Opinion, and the Pride of
supposed Knowledge.
Part II.
On the source of perfect wisdom in the
Sacred Scripture.
Part III.
On the Usefulness of Grammar.
Part IV. On the Usefulness
of Mathematics.
(1.) The Necessity of
Mathematics in Human Things (published separately as the Specula
Mathematica).
(2.) The Necessity of
Mathematics in Divine Things.—1°. This study has occupied holy
men: 2°. Geography: 3°. Chronology: 4°. Cycles; the Golden Number,
&c.: 5°. Natural Phenomena, as the Rainbow: 6°. Arithmetic: 7°.
Music.
(3.) The Necessity of
Mathematics in Ecclesiastical Things. 1°. The Certification of Faith:
2°. The Correction of the Calendar.
(4.) The Necessity of
Mathematics in the State.—1°. Of Climates: 2°. Hydrography: 3°.
Geography: 4°. Astrology.
Part V. On Perspective
(published separately as Perspectiva).
(1.) The organs of vision.
(2.) Vision in straight lines.
(3.) Vision reflected and
refracted.
(4.) De multiplicatione
specierum (on the propagation of the impressions of light, heat,
&c.)
Part VI. On Experimental
Science.
“One of the first points to be noticed for this purpose, is the
resistance to authority; and at the stage of philosophical history
with which we here have to do, this means resistance to the authority
of Aristotle, as adopted and interpreted by the Doctors of the
Schools. Bacon’s work8 is divided into Six Parts; and of these
Parts, the First is, Of the four universal Causes of all Human
Ignorance. The causes thus enumerated9 are:—the
force of unworthy authority;—traditionary habit;—the
imperfection of the undisciplined senses;—and the disposition to
conceal our ignorance and to make an ostentatious show of our
knowledge. These influences involve every man, occupy every condition.
They prevent our obtaining the most useful and large and fair
doctrines of wisdom, the secrets of all sciences and arts. He then
proceeds to argue, from the testimony of philosophers themselves, that
the authority of antiquity, and especially of Aristotle, is not
infallible. ‘We find10 their books full of doubts,
obscurities, and perplexities. They 516 scarce agree with each other in one
empty question or one worthless sophism, or one operation of science,
as one man agrees with another in the practical operations of
medicine, surgery, and the like arts of secular men. Indeed,’ he
adds,11 ‘not only the philosophers, but the
saints have fallen into errors which they have afterwards retracted,’
and this he instances in Augustin, Jerome, and others. He gives an
admirable sketch of the progress of philosophy from the Ionic School
to Aristotle; of whom he speaks with great applause. ‘Yet,’ he adds,
‘those who came after him corrected him in some things, and added many
things to his works, and shall go on adding to the end of the world.’
Aristotle, he adds, is now called peculiarly12 the Philosopher,
‘yet there was a time when his philosophy was silent and unregarded,
either on account of the rarity of copies of his works, or their
difficulty, or from envy; till after the time of Mahomet, when
Avicenna and Averroes, and others, recalled this philosophy into the
full light of exposition. And although the Logic and some other works
were translated by Boethius from the Greek, yet the philosophy of
Aristotle first received a quick increase among the Latins at the time
of Michael Scot; who, in the year of our Lord 1230, appeared, bringing
with him portions of the books of Aristotle on Natural Philosophy and
Mathematics. And yet a small part only of the works of this author is
translated, and a still smaller part is in the hands of common
students.’ He adds further13 (in the Third Part of the Opus
Majus, which is a Dissertation on Language) that the translations
which are current of these writings, are very bad and imperfect. With
these views, he is moved to express himself somewhat impatiently14 respecting these works: ‘If I had,’ he
says, ‘power over the works of Aristotle, I would have them all burnt;
for it is only a loss of time to study in them, and a course of error,
and a multiplication of ignorance beyond expression.’ ‘The common herd
of students,’ he says, ‘with their heads, have no principle by which
they can be excited to any worthy employment; and hence they mope and
make asses of themselves over their bad translations, and lose their
time, and trouble, and money.’
8 Op. Maj. p. 1.
9 Ib. p. 2.
10 Ib. p. 10.
11 Op. Maj. p. 36.
12 Autonomaticè.
13 Op. Maj. p. 46.
14 See Pref. to Jebb’s edition.
The passages there quoted, however, are not extracts from the Opus
Majus, but (apparently) from the Opus Minus (MS.
Cott. Tib. c. 5). “Si haberem potestatem supra libros Aristotelis,
ego facerem omnes cremari; quia non est nisi temporis amissio studere
in illis, et causa erroris, et multiplicatio ignorantiæ ultra id quod
valeat explicari. . . . Vulgus studentum cum capitibus suis non habet
unde excitetur ad aliquid dignum, et ideo languet et asininat
circa male translata, et tempus et studium amittit in omnibus et
expensas.”
517 “The
remedies which he recommends for these evils, are, in the first place,
the study of that only perfect wisdom which is to be found in the
Sacred Scripture;15 in the next place, the study of
mathematics and the use of experiment.16 By the aid of
these methods, Bacon anticipates the most splendid progress for human
knowledge. He takes up the strain of hope and confidence which we have
noticed as so peculiar in the Roman writers; and quotes some of the
passages of Seneca which we adduced in illustration of
this:—that the attempts in science were at first rude and
imperfect, and were afterwards improved;—that the day will come,
when what is still unknown shall be brought to light by the progress
of time and the labors of a longer period;—that one age does not
suffice for inquiries so wide and various;—that the people of
future times shall know many things unknown to us;—and that the
time shall arrive when posterity will wonder that we overlooked what
was so obvious. Bacon himself adds anticipations more peculiarly in
the spirit of his own time. ‘We have seen,’ he says, at the end of the
work, ‘how Aristotle, by the ways which wisdom teaches, could give to
Alexander the empire of the world. And this the Church ought to take
into consideration against the infidels and rebels, that there may be
a sparing of Christian blood, and especially on account of the
troubles that shall come to pass in the days of Antichrist; which by
the grace of God it would be easy to obviate, if prelates and princes
would encourage study, and join in searching out the secrets of nature
and art.’
15 Part ii.
16 Parts iv. v. and vi.
“It may not be improper to observe here that this belief in the
appointed progress of knowledge, is not combined with any overweening
belief in the unbounded and independent power of the human intellect.
On the contrary, one of the lessons which Bacon draws from the state
and prospects of knowledge, is the duty of faith and humility. ‘To
him,’ he says,17 ‘who denies the truth of the faith
because he is unable to understand it, I will propose in reply the
course of nature, and as we have seen it in examples.’ And after
giving some instances, he adds, ‘These, and the like, ought to move
men and to excite them to the reception of divine truths. For if, in
the vilest objects of creation, truths are found, before which the
inward pride of man must bow, and believe though it cannot understand,
how much more should man humble his mind before the glorious truths of
God!’ He had before said:18 ‘Man is incapable of perfect wisdom in
this life; it is hard for 518 him to ascend towards perfection, easy
to glide downwards to falsehoods and vanities: let him then not boast
of his wisdom, or extol his knowledge. What he knows is little and
worthless, in respect of that which he believes without knowing; and
still less, in respect of that which he is ignorant of. He is mad who
thinks highly of his wisdom; he most mad, who exhibits it as something
to be wondered at.’ He adds, as another reason for humility, that he
has proved by trial, he could teach in one year, to a poor boy, the
marrow of all that the most diligent person could acquire in forty
years’ laborious and expensive study.
17 Op. Maj. p. 476.
18 Ib. p. 15.
“To proceed somewhat more in detail with regard to Roger Bacon’s
views of a Reform in Scientific Inquiry, we may observe that by making
Mathematics and Experiment the two great points of his recommendation,
he directed his improvement to the two essential parts of all
knowledge, Ideas and Facts, and thus took the course which the most
enlightened philosophy would have suggested. He did not urge the
prosecution of experiment, to the comparative neglect of the existing
mathematical sciences and conceptions; a fault which there is some
ground for ascribing to his great namesake and successor Francis
Bacon: still less did he content himself with a mere protest against
the authority of the schools, and a vague demand for change, which was
almost all that was done by those who put themselves forward as
reformers in the intermediate time. Roger Bacon holds his way steadily
between the two poles of human knowledge; which, as we have seen, it
is far from easy to do. ‘There are two modes of knowing,’ says he;19 ‘by argument, and by experiment.
Argument concludes a question; but it does not make us feel certain,
or acquiesce in the contemplation of truth, except the truth be also
found to be so by experience.’ It is not easy to express more
decidedly the clearly-seen union of exact conceptions with certain
facts, which, as we have explained, constitutes real knowledge.
19 Op. Maj. p. 445; see also p.
448. “Scientiæ aliæ sciunt sua principia invenire per experimenta, sed
conclusiones per argumenta facta ex principiis inventis. Si vero
debeant habere experientiam conclusionum suarum particularem et
completam, tunc oportet quod habeant per adjutorium istius scientiæ
nobilis (experimentalis).”
“One large division of the Opus Majus is ‘On the Usefulness
of Mathematics,’ which is shown by a copious enumeration of existing
branches of knowledge, as Chronology, Geography, the Calendar and (in
a separate Part) Optics. There is a chapter,20 in which it is
proved 519 by
reason, that all science requires mathematics. And the arguments which
are used to establish this doctrine, show a most just appreciation of
the office of mathematics in science. They are such as
follows:—That other sciences use examples taken from mathematics
as the most evident:—That mathematical knowledge is, as it were,
innate to us, on which point he refers to the well-known dialogue of
Plato, as quoted by Cicero:—That this science, being the
easiest, offers the best introduction to the more
difficult:—That in mathematics, things as known to us are
identical with things as known to nature:—That we can here
entirely avoid doubt and error, and obtain certainty and
truth:—That mathematics is prior to other sciences in nature,
because it takes cognizance of quantity, which is apprehended by
intuition (intuitu intellectus). ‘Moreover,’ he adds,21 ‘there have been found famous men, as
Robert, bishop of Lincoln, and Brother Adam Marshman (de Marisco), and
many others, who by the power of mathematics have been able to explain
the causes of things; as may be seen in the writings of these men, for
instance, concerning the Rainbow and Comets, and the generation of
heat, and climates, and the celestial bodies.’
20 Ib. p. 60.
21 Op. Maj. p. 64.
“But undoubtedly the most remarkable portion of the Opus
Majus is the Sixth and last Part, which is entitled ‘De Scientia
experimentali.’ It is indeed an extraordinary circumstance to find a
writer of the thirteenth century, not only recognizing experiment as
one source of knowledge, but urging its claims as something far more
important than men had yet been aware of, exemplifying its value by
striking and just examples, and speaking of its authority with a
dignity of diction which sounds like a foremurmur of the Baconian
sentences uttered nearly four hundred years later. Yet this is the
character of what we here find.22 ‘Experimental
science, the sole mistress of speculative sciences, has three great
Prerogatives among other parts of knowledge: First she tests by
experiment the noblest conclusions of all other sciences: Next she
discovers respecting the notions which other sciences deal with,
magnificent truths to which these sciences of themselves can by no
means attain: her Third dignity is, that she by her own power and
without respect of other sciences, investigates the secrets of
nature.’
22 “Veritates magnificas in terminis
aliarum scientiarum in quas per nullam viam possunt illæ scientiæ, hæc
sola scientiarum domina speculativarum, potest dare.”—Op.
Maj. p. 465.
520 “The
examples which Bacon gives of these ‘Prerogatives’ are very curious,
exhibiting, among some error and credulity, sound and clear views. His
leading example of the First Prerogative is the Rainbow, of which the
cause, as given by Aristotle, is tested by reference to experiment
with a skill which is, even to us now, truly admirable. The examples
of the Second Prerogative are three—first, the art of
making an artificial sphere which shall move with the heavens by
natural influences, which Bacon trusts may be done, though astronomy
herself cannot do it—’et tunc,’ he says, ‘thesaurum unius regis
valeret hoc instrumentum;’—secondly, the art of
prolonging life, which experiment may teach, though medicine has no
means of securing it except by regimen;23—thirdly, the art of making
gold finer than fine gold, which goes beyond the power of alchemy. The
Third Prerogative of experimental science, arts independent of the
received sciences, is exemplified in many curious examples, many of
them whimsical traditions. Thus it is said that the character of a
people may be altered by altering the air.24 Alexander, it
seems, applied to Aristotle to know whether he should exterminate
certain nations which he had discovered, as being irreclaimably
barbarous; to which the philosopher replied, ‘If you can alter their
air, permit them to live; if not, put them to death.’ In this part, we
find the suggestion that the fire-works made by children, of
saltpetre, might lead to the invention of a formidable military
weapon.
23 One of the ingredients of a
preparation here mentioned, is the flesh of a dragon, which, it
appears, is used as food by the Ethiopians. The mode of preparing this
food cannot fail to amuse the reader. “Where there are good flying
dragons, by the art which they possess, they draw them out of their
dens, and have bridles and saddles in readiness, and they ride upon
them, and make them bound about in the air in a violent manner, that
the hardness and toughness of the flesh may be reduced, as boars are
hunted and bulls are baited before they are killed for
eating.”—Op. Maj. p. 470.
24 Op. Maj. p. 472.
“It could not be expected that Roger Bacon, at a time when
experimental science hardly existed, could give any precepts
for the discovery of truth by experiment. But nothing can be a better
example of the method of such investigation, than his inquiry
concerning the cause of the Rainbow. Neither Aristotle, nor Avicenna,
nor Seneca, he says, have given us any clear knowledge of this matter,
but experimental science can do so. Let the experimenter
(experimentator) consider the cases in which he finds the same
colors, as the hexagonal crystals from Ireland and India; by looking
into these he will see colors like those of the rainbow. Many think
that this arises from some 521 special virtue of these stones and their
hexagonal figure; let therefore the experimenter go on, and he will
find the same in other transparent stones, in dark ones as well as in
light-colored. He will find the same effect also in other forms than
the hexagon, if they be furrowed in the surface, as the Irish crystals
are. Let him consider too, that he sees the same colors in the drops
which are dashed from oars in the sunshine;—and in the spray
thrown by a mill wheel;—and in the dew drops which lie on the
grass in a meadow on a summer morning;—and if a man takes water
in his mouth and projects it on one side into a sunbeam;—and if
in an oil lamp hanging in the air, the rays fall in certain positions
upon the surface of the oil;—and in many other ways, are colors
produced. We have here a collection of instances, which are almost all
examples of the same kind as the phenomenon under consideration; and
by the help of a principle collected by induction from these facts,
the colors of the rainbow were afterwards really explained.
“With regard to the form and other circumstances of the bow he is
still more precise. He bids us measure the height of the bow and of
the sun, to show that the centre of the bow is exactly opposite to the
sun. He explains the circular form of the bow,—its being
independent of the form of the cloud, its moving when we move, its
flying when we follow,—by its consisting of the reflections from
a vast number of minute drops. He does not, indeed, trace the course
of the rays through the drop, or account for the precise magnitude
which the bow assumes; but he approaches to the verge of this part of
the explanation; and must be considered as having given a most happy
example of experimental inquiry into nature, at a time when such
examples were exceedingly scanty. In this respect, he was more
fortunate than Francis Bacon, as we shall hereafter see.
“We know but little of the biography of Roger Bacon, but we have
every reason to believe that his influence upon his age was not great.
He was suspected of magic, and is said to have been put into close
confinement in consequence of this charge. In his work he speaks of
Astrology, as a science well worth cultivating. ‘But,’ says he,
‘Theologians and Decretists, not being learned in such matters, and
seeing that evil as well as good may be done, neglect and abhor such
things, and reckon them among Magic Arts.’ We have already seen, that
at the very time when Bacon was thus raising his voice against the
habit of blindly following authority, and seeking for all science in
Aristotle, Thomas Aquinas was employed in fashioning Aristotle’s
tenets into that fixed form in which they became the great impediment
to the 522 progress
of knowledge. It would seem, indeed, that something of a struggle
between the progressive and stationary powers of the human mind was
going on at this time. Bacon himself says,25 ‘Never was there
so great an appearance of wisdom, nor so much exercise of study in so
many Faculties, in so many regions, as for this last forty years.
Doctors are dispersed everywhere, in every castle, in every burgh, and
especially by the students of two Orders, (he means the Franciscans
and Dominicans, who were almost the only religious orders that
distinguished themselves by an application to study,26) which has not happened except for
about forty years. And yet there was never so much ignorance, so much
error.’ And in the part of his work which refers to Mathematics, he
says of that study,27 that it is the door and the key of the
sciences; and that the neglect of it for thirty or forty years has
entirely ruined the studies of the Latins. According to these
statements, some change, disastrous to the fortunes of science, must
have taken place about 1230, soon after the foundation of the
Dominican and Franciscan Orders.28 Nor can we doubt
that the adoption of the Aristotelian philosophy by these two Orders,
in the form in which the Angelical Doctor had systematized it, was one
of the events which most tended to defer, for three centuries, the
reform which Roger Bacon urged as a matter of crying necessity in his
own time.”
25 Quoted by Jebb, Pref. to Op.
Maj.
26 Mosheim, Hist. iii.
161.
27 Op. Maj. p. 57.
28 Mosheim, iii. 161.
It is worthy of remark that in the Opus Majus of Roger
Bacon, as afterwards in the Novum Organon of Francis Bacon, we
have certain features of experimental research pointed out
conspicuously as Prærogativæ: although in the former, this term
is employed to designate the superiority of experimental science in
general to the science of the schools; in the latter work, the term is
applied to certain classes of experiments as superior to others.


BOOK V.

FORMAL ASTRONOMY.
</div></body></text></TEI>