<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol I</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1794</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="12">SECT. XII.
OF STIMULUS, SENSORIAL EXERTION, AND FIBROUS CONTRACTION.

I. Of fibrous contraction. 1. Two particles of a fibre cannot approach
  without the intervention of something, as in magnetism, electricity,
  elasticity. Spirit of life is not electric ether. Galvani's
  experiments. 2. Contraction of a
  fibre. 3. Relaxation succeeds. 4. Successive contractions, with intervals.
  Quick pulse from debility, from paucity of blood. Weak contractions
  performed in less time, and with shorter intervals. 5. Last situation of the fibres continues
  after contraction. 6. Contraction
  greater than usual induces pleasure or pain. 7. Mobility of the fibres uniform. Quantity
  of sensorial power fluctuates. Constitutes excitability. II. Of sensorial exertion. 1. Animal motion includes stimulus, sensorial
  power, and contractile fibres. The sensorial faculties act separately or
  conjointly. Stimulus of four kinds. Strength and weakness defined.
  Sensorial power perpetually exhausted and renewed. Weakness from defect
  of stimulus. From defect of sensorial power, the direct and indirect
  debility of Dr. Brown. Why we become warm in Buxton bath after a time,
  and see well after a time in a darkish room. Fibres may act violently, or
  with their whole force, and yet feebly. Great exertion in inflammation
  explained. Great muscular force of some insane people. 2. Occasional accumulation of sensorial power
  in muscles subject to constant stimulus. In animals sleeping in winter.
  In eggs, seeds, schirrous tumours, tendons, bones. 3. Great exertion introduces pleasure or
  pain. Inflammation. Libration of the system between torpor and activity.
  Fever-fits. 4. Desire and aversion
  introduced. Excess of volition cures fevers. III. Of repeated stimulus. 1. A stimulus repeated too frequently looses
  effect. As opium, wine, grief. Hence old age. Opium and aloes in small
  doses. 2. A stimulus not repeated too
  frequently does not lose effect. Perpetual movement of the vital
  organs. 3. A stimulus repeated at
  uniform times produces greater effect. Irritation combined with
  association. 4. A stimulus repeated
  frequently and uniformly may be withdrawn, and the action of the organ
  will continue. Hence the bark cures agues, and strengthens weak
  constitutions. 5. Defect of stimulus
  repeated at certain intervals causes fever-fits. 6. Stimulus long applied ceases to act a
  second time. 7. If a stimulus excites
  sensation in an organ not usually excited into sensation, inflammation is
  produced. IV. Of stimulus greater than
  natural. 1. A stimulus greater than
  natural diminishes the quantity of sensorial power in general. 2. In particular organs. 3. Induces the organ into spasmodic
  actions. 4. Induces the antagonist
  fibres into action. 5. Induces the
  organ into convulsive or fixed spasms. 6.
  Produces paralysis of the organ. V. Of
  stimulus less than natural. 1. Stimulus
  less than natural occasions accumulation of sensorial power in
  general. 2. In particular organs,
  flushing of the face in a frosty morning. In fibres subject to perpetual
  stimulus only. Quantity of sensorial power inversely as the stimulus.
3. Induces pain. As of cold, hunger,
  head-ach. 4. Induces more feeble and
  frequent contraction. As in low fevers. Which are frequently owing to
  deficiency of sensorial power rather than to deficiency of stimulus.
5. Inverts successive trains of motion.
  Inverts ideas. 6. Induces paralysis
  and death. VI. Cure of increased exertion.
  1. Natural cure of exhaustion of sensorial
  power. 2. Decrease the irritations.
  Venesection. Cold. Abstinence. 3.
  Prevent the previous cold fit. Opium. Bark. Warmth. Anger.
  Surprise. 4. Excite some other part of
  the system. Opium and warm bath relieve pains both from defect and from
  excess of stimulus. 5. First increase
  the stimulus above, and then decrease it beneath the natural
  quantity. VII. Cure of decreased exertion.
  1. Natural cure by accumulation of
  sensorial power. Ague-fits. Syncope. 2.
  Increase the stimulation, by wine, opium, given so as not to
  intoxicate. Cheerful ideas. 3. Change
  the kinds of stimulus. 4. Stimulate
  the associated organs. Blisters of use in heart-burn, and cold
  extremities. 5. Decrease the
  stimulation for a time, cold bath. 6.
  Decrease the stimulation below natural, and then increase it above
  natural. Bark after emetics. Opium after venesection. Practice of
  Sydenham in chlorosis. 7. Prevent
  unnecessary expenditure of sensorial power. Decumbent posture, silence,
  darkness. Pulse quickened by rising out of bed. 8. To the greatest degree of quiescence apply
  the least stimulus. Otherwise paralysis or inflammation of the organ
  ensues. Gin, wine, blisters, destroy by too great stimulation in fevers
  with debility. Intoxication in the slightest degree succeeded by
  debility. Golden rule for determining the best degree of stimulus in low
  fevers. Another golden rule for determining the quantity of spirit which
  those, who are debilitated by drinking it, may safely omit.

I. Of fibrous contraction.
1. If two particles of iron lie near each
  other without motion, and afterwards approach each other; it is
  reasonable to conclude that something besides the iron particles is the
  cause of their approximation; this invisible something is termed
  magnetism. In the same manner, if the particles, which compose an animal
  muscle, do not touch each other in the relaxed state of the muscle, and
  are brought into contact during the contraction of the muscle, it is
  reasonable to conclude, that some other agent is the cause of this new
  approximation. For nothing can act, where it does not exist; for to act
  includes to exist; and therefore the particles of the muscular fibre
  (which in its state of relaxation are supposed not to touch) cannot
  affect each other without the influence of some intermediate agent; this
  agent is here termed the spirit of animation, or sensorial power, but may
  with equal propriety be termed the power, which causes contraction; or
  may be called by any other name, which the reader may choose to affix to
  it.
The contraction of a muscular fibre may be compared to the following
  electric experiment, which is here mentioned not as a philosophical
  analogy, but as an illustration or simile to facilitate the conception of
  a difficult subject. Let twenty very small Leyden phials properly coated
  be hung in a row by fine silk threads at a small distance from each
  other; let the internal charge of one phial be positive, and of the other
  negative alternately, if a communication be made from the internal
  surface of the first to the external surface of the last in the row, they
  will all of them instantly approach each other, and thus shorten a line
  that might connect them like a muscular fibre. See Botanic Garden, p. 1.
  Canto I. 1. 202, note on Gymnotus.
The attractions of electricity or of magnetism do not apply
  philosophically to the illustration of the contraction of animal fibres,
  since the force of those attractions increases in some proportion
  inversely as the distance, but in muscular motion there appears no
  difference in velocity or strength during the beginning or end of the
  contraction, but what may be clearly ascribed to the varying mechanic
  advantage in the approximation of one bone to another. Nor can muscular
  motion be assimilated with greater plausibility to the attraction of
  cohesion or elasticity; for in bending a steel spring, as a small sword,
  a less force is required to bend it the first inch than the second; and
  the second than the third; the particles of steel on the convex side of
  the bent spring endeavouring to restore themselves more powerfully the
  further they are drawn from each other. See Botanic Garden, P. I. addit.
  Note XVIII.
I am aware that this may be explained another way, by supposing the
  elasticity of the spring to depend more on the compression of the
  particles on the concave side than on the extension of them on the convex
  side; and by supposing the elasticity of the elastic gum to depend more
  on the resistance to the lateral compression of its particles than to the
  longitudinal extension of them. Nevertheless in muscular contraction, as
  above observed, there appears no difference in the velocity or force of
  it at its commencement or at its termination; from whence we must
  conclude that animal contraction is governed by laws of its own, and not
  by those of mechanics, chemistry, magnetism, or electricity.
On these accounts I do not think the experiments conclusive, which
  were lately published by Galvani, Volta, and others, to shew a similitude
  between the spirit of animation, which contracts the muscular fibres, and
  the electric fluid. Since the electric fluid may act only as a more
  potent stimulus exciting the muscular fibres into action, and not by
  supplying them with a new quantity of the spirit of life. Thus in a
  recent hemiplegia I have frequently observed, when the patient yawned and
  stretched himself, that the paralytic limbs moved also, though they were
  totally disobedient to the will. And when he was electrified by passing
  shocks from the affected hand to the affected foot, a motion of the
  paralytic limbs was also produced. Now as in the act of yawning the
  muscles of the paralytic limbs were excited into action by the stimulus
  of the irksomeness of a continued posture, and not by any additional
  quantity of the spirit of life; so we may conclude, that the passage of
  the electric fluid, which produced a similar effect, acted only as a
  stimulus, and not by supplying any addition of sensorial power.
If nevertheless this theory should ever become established, a stimulus
  must be called an eductor of vital ether; which stimulus may consist of
  sensation or volition, as in the electric eel, as well as in the appulses
  of external bodies; and by drawing off the charges of vital fluid may
  occasion the contraction or motions of the muscular fibres, and organs of
  sense.
2. The immediate effect of the action of
  the spirit of animation or sensorial power on the fibrous parts of the
  body, whether it acts in the mode of irritation, sensation, volition, or
  association, is a contraction of the animal fibre, according to the
  second law of animal causation. Sect. IV. Thus the
  stimulus of the blood induces the contraction of the heart; the agreeable
  taste of a strawberry produces the contraction of the muscles of
  deglutition; the effort of the will contracts the muscles, which move the
  limbs in walking; and by association other muscles of the trunk are
  brought into contraction to preserve the balance of the body. The fibrous
  extremities of the organs of sense have been shewn, by the ocular spectra
  in Sect. III. to suffer similar contraction by
  each of the above modes of excitation; and by their configurations to
  constitute our ideas.
3. After animal fibres have for some time
  been excited into contraction, a relaxation succeeds, even though the
  exciting cause continues to act. In respect to the irritative motions
  this is exemplified in the peristaltic contractions of the bowels; which
  cease and are renewed alternately, though the stimulus of the aliment
  continues to be uniformly applied; in the sensitive motions, as in
  strangury, tenesmus, and parturition, the alternate contractions and
  relaxations of the muscles exist, though the stimulus is perpetual. In
  our voluntary exertions it is experienced, as no one can hang long by the
  hands, however vehemently he wills so to do; and in the associate motions
  the constant change of our attitudes evinces the necessity of relaxation
  to those muscles, which have been long in action.
This relaxation of a muscle after its contraction, even though the
  stimulus continues to be applied, appears to arise from the expenditure
  or diminution of the spirit of animation previously resident in the
  muscle, according to the second law of animal causation in Sect. IV. In those constitutions, which are termed weak,
  the spirit of animation becomes sooner exhausted, and tremulous motions
  are produced, as in the hands of infirm people, when they lift a cup to
  their mouths. This quicker exhaustion of the spirit of animation is
  probably owing to a less quantity of it residing in the acting fibres,
  which therefore more frequently require a supply from the nerves, which
  belong to them.
4. If the sensorial power continues to act,
  whether it acts in the mode of irritation, sensation, volition, or
  association, a new contraction of the animal fibre succeeds after a
  certain interval; which interval is of shorter continuance in weak people
  than in strong ones. This is exemplified in the shaking of the hands of
  weak people, when they attempt to write. In a manuscript epistle of one
  of my correspondents, which is written in a small hand, I observed from
  four to six zigzags in the perpendicular stroke of every letter, which
  shews that both the contractions of the fingers, and intervals between
  them, must have been performed in very short periods of time.
The times of contraction of the muscles of enfeebled people being
  less, and the intervals between those contractions being less also,
  accounts for the quick pulse in fevers with debility, and in dying
  animals. The shortness of the intervals between one contraction and
  another in weak constitutions, is probably owing to the general
  deficiency of the quantity of the spirit of animation, and that therefore
  there is a less quantity of it to be received at each interval of the
  activity of the fibres. Hence in repeated motions, as of the fingers in
  performing on the harpsichord, it would at first sight appear, that
  swiftness and strength were incompatible; nevertheless the single
  contraction of a muscle is performed with greater velocity as well as
  with greater force by vigorous constitutions, as in throwing a
  javelin.
There is however another circumstance, which may often contribute to
  cause the quickness of the pulse in nervous fevers, as in animals
  bleeding to death in the slaughter-house; which is the deficient quantity
  of blood; whence the heart is but half distended, and in consequence
  sooner contracts. See Sect. XXXII. 2.
  1.
For we must not confound frequency of repetition with quickness of
  motion, or the number of pulsations with the velocity, with which the
  fibres, which constitute the coats of the arteries, contract themselves.
  For where the frequency of the pulsations is but seventy-five in a
  minute, as in health; the contracting fibres, which constitute the sides
  of the arteries, may move through a greater space in a given time, than
  where the frequency of pulsation is one hundred and fifty in a minute, as
  in some fevers with great debility. For if in those fevers the arteries
  do not expand themselves in their diastole to more than half the usual
  diameter of their diastole in health, the fibres which constitute their
  coats, will move through a less space in a minute than in health, though
  they make two pulsations for one.
Suppose the diameter of the artery during its systole to be one line,
  and that the diameter of the same artery during its diastole is in health
  is four lines, and in a fever with, great debility only two lines. It
  follows, that the arterial fibres contract in health from a circle of
  twelve lines in circumference to a circle of three lines in
  circumference, that is they move through a space of nine lines in length.
  While the arterial fibres in the fever with debility would twice contract
  from a circle of six lines to a circle of three lines; that is while they
  move through a space equal to six lines. Hence though the frequency of
  pulsation in fever be greater as two to one, yet the velocity of
  contraction in health is greater as nine to six, or as three to two.
On the contrary in inflammatory diseases with strength, as in the
  pleurisy, the velocity of the contracting sides of the arteries is much
  greater than in health, for if we suppose the number of pulsations in a
  pleurisy to be half as much more than in health, that is as one hundred
  and twenty to eighty, (which is about what generally happens in
  inflammatory diseases) and if the diameter of the artery in diastole be
  one third greater than in health, which I believe is near the truth, the
  result will be, that the velocity of the contractile sides of the
  arteries will be in a pleurisy as two and a half to one, compared to the
  velocity of their contraction in a state of health, for if the
  circumference of the systole of the artery be three lines, and the
  diastole in health be twelve lines in circumference, and in a pleurisy
  eighteen lines; and secondly, if the artery pulsates thrice in the
  diseased state for twice in the healthy one, it follows, that the
  velocity of contraction in the diseased state to that in the healthy
  state will be forty-five to eighteen, or as two and a half to one.
From hence it would appear, that if we had a criterion to determine
  the velocity of the arterial contractions, it would at the same time give
  us their strength, and thus be of more service in distinguishing
  diseases, than the knowledge of their frequency. As such a criterion
  cannot be had, the frequency of pulsation, the age of the patient being
  allowed for, will in some measure assist us to distinguish arterial
  strength from arterial debility, since in inflammatory diseases with
  strength the frequency seldom exceeds one hundred and eighteen or one
  hundred and twenty pulsations in a minute; unless under peculiar
  circumstance, as the great additional stimuli of wine or of external
  heat.
5. After a muscle or organ of sense has
  been excited into contraction, and the sensorial power ceases to act, the
  last situation or configuration of it continues; unless it be disturbed
  by the action of some antagonist fibres, or other extraneous power. Thus
  in weak or languid people, wherever they throw their limbs on their bed
  or sofa, there they lie, till another exertion changes their attitude;
  hence one kind of ocular spectra seems to be produced after looking at
  bright objects; thus when a fire-stick is whirled round in the night,
  there appears in the eye a complete circle of fire; the action or
  configuration of one part of the retina not ceasing before the return of
  the whirling fire.
Thus if any one looks at the setting sun for a short time, and then
  covers his closed eyes with his hand, he will for many seconds of time
  perceive the image of the sun on his retina. A similar image of all other
  bodies would remain some time in the eye, but is effaced by the eternal
  change of the motions of the extremity of this nerve in our attention to
  other objects. See Sect. XVIII. 5. on Sleep.
  Hence the dark spots, and other ocular spectra, are more frequently
  attended to, and remain longer in the eyes of weak people, as after
  violent exercise, intoxication, or want of sleep.
6. A contraction of the fibres somewhat
  greater than usual introduces pleasurable sensation into the system,
  according to the fourth law of animal causation. Hence the pleasure in
  the beginning of drunkenness is owing to the increased action of the
  system from the stimulus of vinous spirit or of opium. If the
  contractions be still greater in energy or duration, painful sensations
  are introduced, as in consequence of great heat, or caustic applications,
  or fatigue.
If any part of the system, which is used to perpetual activity, as the
  stomach, or heart, or the fine vessels of the skin, acts for a time with
  less energy, another kind of painful sensation ensues, which is called
  hunger, or faintness, or cold. This occurs in a less degree in the
  locomotive muscles, and is called wearysomeness. In the two former kinds
  of sensation there is an expenditure of sensorial power, in these latter
  there is an accumulation of it.
7. We have used the words exertion of
  sensorial power as a general term to express either irritation,
  sensation, volition, or association; that is, to express the activity or
  motion of the spirit of animation, at the time it produces the
  contractions of the fibrous parts of the system. It may be supposed that
  there may exist a greater or less mobility of the fibrous parts of our
  system, or a propensity to be stimulated into contraction by the greater
  or less quantity or energy of the spirit of animation; and that hence if
  the exertion of the sensorial power be in its natural state, and the
  mobility of the fibres be increased, the same quantity of fibrous
  contraction will be caused, as if the mobility of the fibres continues in
  its natural state, and the sensorial exertion be increased.
Thus it may be conceived, that in diseases accompanied with strength,
  as in inflammatory fevers with arterial strength, that the cause of
  greater fibrous contraction, may exist in the increased mobility of the
  fibres, whose contractions are thence both more forceable and more
  frequent. And that in diseases attended with debility, as in nervous
  fevers, where the fibrous contractions are weaker, and more frequent, it
  may be conceived that the cause consists in a decrease of mobility of the
  fibres; and that those weak constitutions, which are attended with cold
  extremities and large pupils of the eyes, may possess less mobility of
  the contractile fibres, as well as less quantity of exertion of the
  spirit of animation.
In answer to this mode of reasoning it may be sufficient to observe,
  that the contractile fibres consist of inert matter, and when the
  sensorial power is withdrawn, as in death, they possess no power of
  motion at all, but remain in their last state, whether of contraction or
  relaxation, and must thence derive the whole of this property from the
  spirit of animation. At the same time it is not improbable, that the
  moving fibres of strong people may possess a capability of receiving or
  containing a greater quantity of the spirit of animation than those of
  weak people.
In every contraction of a fibre there is an expenditure of the
  sensorial power, or spirit of animation; and where the exertion of this
  sensorial power has been for some time increased, and the muscles or
  organs of sense have in consequence acted with greater energy, its
  propensity to activity is proportionally lessened; which is to be
  ascribed to the exhaustion or diminution of its quantity. On the
  contrary, where there has been less fibrous contraction than usual for a
  certain time, the sensorial power or spirit of animation becomes
  accumulated in the inactive part of the system. Hence vigour succeeds
  rest, and hence the propensity to action of all our organs of sense and
  muscles is in a state of perpetual fluctuation. The irritability for
  instance of the retina, that is, its quantity of sensorial power, varies
  every moment according to the brightness or obscurity of the object last
  beheld compared with the present one. The same occurs to our sense of
  heat, and to every part of our system, which is capable of being excited
  into action.
When this variation of the exertion of the sensorial power becomes
  much and permanently above or beneath the natural quantity, it becomes a
  disease. If the irritative motions be too great or too little, it shews
  that the stimulus of external things affect this sensorial power too
  violently or too inertly. If the sensitive motions be too great or too
  little, the cause arises from the deficient or exuberant quantity of
  sensation produced in consequence of the motions of the muscular fibres
  or organs of sense; if the voluntary actions are diseased the cause is to
  be looked for in the quantity of volition produced in consequence of the
  desire or aversion occasioned by the painful or pleasurable sensations
  above mentioned. And the diseases of associations probably depend on the
  greater or less quantity of the other three sensorial powers by which
  they were formed.
From whence it appears that the propensity to action, whether it be
  called irritability, sensibility, voluntarity, or associability, is only
  another mode of expression for the quantity of sensorial power residing
  in the organ to be excited. And that on the contrary the words
  inirritability and insensibility, together with inaptitude to voluntary
  and associate motions, are synonymous with deficiency of the quantity of
  sensorial power, or of the spirit of animation, residing in the organs to
  be excited.
II. Of sensorial Exertion.
1. There are three circumstances to be
  attended to in the production of animal motions, 1st. The stimulus. 2d.
  The sensorial power. 3d. The contractile fibre. 1st. A stimulus, external
  to the organ, originally induces into action the sensorial faculty termed
  irritation; this produces the contraction of the fibres, which, if it be
  perceived at all, introduces pleasure or pain; which in their active
  state are termed sensation; which is another sensorial faculty, and
  occasionally produces contraction of the fibres; this pleasure or pain is
  therefore to be considered as another stimulus, which may either act
  alone or in conjunction with the former faculty of the sensorium termed
  irritation.
This new stimulus of pleasure or pain either induces into action the
  sensorial faculty termed sensation, which then produces the contraction
  of the fibres; or it introduces desire or aversion, which excite into
  action another sensorial faculty, termed volition, and may therefore be
  considered as another stimulus, which either alone or in conjunction with
  one or both of the two former faculties of the sensorium produces the
  contraction of animal fibres. There is another sensorial power, that of
  association, which perpetually, in conjunction with one or more of the
  above, and frequently singly, produces the contraction of animal fibres,
  and which is itself excited into action by the previous motions of
  contracting fibres.
Now as the sensorial power, termed irritation, residing in any
  particular fibres, is excited into exertion by the stimulus of external
  bodies acting on those fibres; the sensorial power, termed sensation,
  residing in any particular fibres is excited into exertion by the
  stimulus of pleasure or pain acting on those fibres; the sensorial power,
  termed volition, residing in any particular fibres is excited into
  exertion by the stimulus of desire or aversion; and the sensorial power,
  termed association, residing in any particular fibres, is excited into
  action by the stimulus of other fibrous motions, which had frequently
  preceded them. The word stimulus may therefore be used without
  impropriety of language, for any of these four causes, which excite the
  four sensorial powers into exertion. For though the immediate cause of
  volition has generally been termed a motive; and that of
  irritation only has generally obtained the name of stimulus; yet
  as the immediate cause, which excites the sensorial powers of sensation,
  or of association into exertion, have obtained no general name, we shall
  use the word stimulus for them all.
Hence the quantity of motion produced in any particular part of the
  animal system will be as the quantity of stimulus and the quantity of
  sensorial power, or spirit of animation, residing in the contracting
  fibres. Where both these quantities are great, strength is
  produced, when that word is applied to the motions of animal bodies.
  Where either of them is deficient, weakness is produced, as
  applied to the motions of animal bodies.
Now as the sensorial power, or spirit of animation, is perpetually
  exhausted by the expenditure of it in fibrous contractions, and is
  perpetually renewed by the secretion or production of it in the brain and
  spinal marrow, the quantity of animal strength must be in a perpetual
  state of fluctuation on this account; and if to this be added the
  unceasing variation of all the four kinds of stimulus above described,
  which produce the exertions of the sensorial powers, the ceaseless
  vicissitude of animal strength becomes easily comprehended.
If the quantity of sensorial power remains the same, and the quantity
  of stimulus be lessened, a weakness of the fibrous contractions ensues,
  which may be denominated debility from defect of stimulus. If the
  quantity of stimulus remains the same, and the quantity of sensorial
  power be lessened, another kind of weakness ensues, which may be termed
  debility from defect of sensorial power; the former of these is
  called by Dr. Brown, in his Elements of Medicine, direct debility, and
  the latter indirect debility. The coincidence of some parts of this work
  with correspondent deductions in the Brunonian Elementa Medicina, a work
  (with some exceptions) of great genius, must be considered as
  confirmations of the truth of the theory, as they were probably arrived
  at by different trains of reasoning.
Thus in those who have been exposed to cold and hunger there is a
  deficiency of stimulus. While in nervous fever there is a deficiency of
  sensorial power. And in habitual drunkards, in a morning before their
  usual potation, there is a deficiency both of stimulus and of sensorial
  power. While, on the other hand, in the beginning of intoxication there
  is an excess of stimulus; in the hot-ach, after the hands have been
  immersed in snow, there is a redundancy of sensorial power; and in
  inflammatory diseases with arterial strength, there is an excess of
  both.
Hence if the sensorial power be lessened, while the quantity of
  stimulus remains the same as in nervous fever, the frequency of
  repetition of the arterial contractions may continue, but their force in
  respect to removing obstacles, as in promoting the circulation of the
  blood, or the velocity of each contraction, will be diminished, that is,
  the animal strength will be lessened. And secondly, if the quantity of
  sensorial power be lessened, and the stimulus be increased to a certain
  degree, as in giving opium in nervous fevers, the arterial contractions
  may be performed more frequently than natural, yet with less
  strength.
And thirdly, if the sensorial power continues the same in respect to
  quantity, and the stimulus be somewhat diminished, as in going into a
  darkish room, or into a coldish bath, suppose of about eighty degrees of
  heat, as Buxton-bath, a temporary weakness of the affected fibres is
  induced, till an accumulation of sensorial power gradually succeeds, and
  counterbalances the deficiency of stimulus, and then the bath ceases to
  feel cold, and the room ceases to appear dark; because the fibres of the
  subcutaneous vessels, or of the organs of sense, act with their usual
  energy.
A set of muscular fibres may thus be stimulated into violent exertion,
  that is, they may act frequently, and with their whole sensorial power,
  but may nevertheless not act strongly; because the quantity of their
  sensorial power was originally small, or was previously exhausted. Hence
  a stimulus may be great, and the irritation in consequence act with its
  full force, as in the hot paroxysms of nervous fever; but if the
  sensorial power, termed irritation, be small in quantity, the force of
  the fibrous contractions, and the times of their continuance in their
  contracted state, will be proportionally small.
In the same manner in the hot paroxysm of putrid fevers, which are
  shewn in Sect. XXXIII. to be inflammatory
  fevers with arterial debility, the sensorial power termed sensation is
  exerted with great activity, yet the fibrous contractions, which produce
  the circulation of the blood, are performed without strength, because the
  quantity of sensorial power then residing in that part of the system is
  small.
Thus in irritative fever with arterial strength, that is, with excess
  of spirit of animation, the quantity of exertion during the hot part of
  the paroxysm is to be estimated from the quantity of stimulus, and the
  quantity of sensorial power. While in sensitive (or inflammatory) fever
  with arterial strength, that is, with excess of spirit of animation, the
  violent and forcible actions of the vascular system during the hot part
  of the paroxysm are induced by the exertions of two sensorial powers,
  which are excited by two kinds of stimulus. These are the sensorial power
  of irritation excited by the stimulus of bodies external to the moving
  fibres, and the sensorial power of sensation excited by the pain in
  consequence of the increased contractions of those moving fibres.
And in insane people in some cases the force of their muscular actions
  will be in proportion to the quantity of sensorial power, which they
  possess, and the quantity of the stimulus of desire or aversion, which
  excites their volition into action. At the same time in other cases the
  stimulus of pain or pleasure, and the stimulus of external bodies, may
  excite into action the sensorial powers of sensation and irritation, and
  thus add greater force to their muscular actions.
2. The application of the stimulus, whether
  that stimulus be some quality of external bodies, or pleasure or pain, or
  desire or aversion, or a link of association, excites the correspondent
  sensorial power into action, and this causes the contraction of the
  fibre. On the contraction of the fibre a part of the spirit of animation
  becomes expended, and the fibre ceases to contract, though the stimulus
  continues to be applied; till in a certain time the fibre having received
  a supply of sensorial power is ready to contract again, if the stimulus
  continues to be applied. If the stimulus on the contrary be withdrawn,
  the same quantity of quiescent sensorial power becomes resident in the
  fibre as before its contraction; as appears from the readiness for action
  of the large locomotive muscles of the body in a short time after common
  exertion.
But in those muscular fibres, which are subject to constant stimulus,
  as the arteries, glands, and capillary vessels, another phenomenon
  occurs, if their accustomed stimulus be withdrawn; which is, that the
  sensorial power becomes accumulated in the contractile fibres, owing to
  the want of its being perpetually expended, or carried away, by their
  usual unremitted contractions. And on this account those muscular fibres
  become afterwards excitable into their natural actions by a much weaker
  stimulus; or into unnatural violence of action by their accustomed
  stimulus, as is seen in the hot fits of intermittent fevers, which are in
  consequence of the previous cold ones. Thus the minute vessels of the
  skin are constantly stimulated by the fluid matter of heat; if the
  quantity of this stimulus of heat be a while diminished, as in covering
  the hands with snow, the vessels cease to act, as appears from the
  paleness of the skin; if this cold application of snow be continued but a
  short time, the sensorial power, which had habitually been supplied to
  the fibres, becomes now accumulated in them, owing to the want of its
  being expended by their accustomed contractions. And thence a less
  stimulus of heat will now excite them into violent contractions.
If the quiescence of fibres, which had previously been subject to
  perpetual stimulus, continues a longer time; or their accustomed stimulus
  be more completely withdrawn; the accumulation of sensorial power becomes
  still greater, as in those exposed to cold and hunger; pain is produced,
  and the organ gradually dies from the chemical changes, which take place
  in it; or it is at a great distance of time restored to action by
  stimulus applied with great caution in small quantity, as happens to some
  larger animals and to many insects, which during the winter months lie
  benumbed with cold, and are said to sleep, and to persons apparently
  drowned, or apparently frozen to death. Snails have been said to revive
  by throwing them into water after having been many years shut up in the
  cabinets of the curious; and eggs and seeds in general are restored to
  life after many months of torpor by the stimulus of warmth and
  moisture.
The inflammation of schirrous tumours, which have long existed in a
  state of inaction, is a process of this kind; as well as the sensibility
  acquired by inflamed tendons and bones, which had at their formation a
  similar sensibility, which had so long lain dormant in their uninflamed
  state.
3. If after long quiescence from defect of
  stimulus the fibres, which had previously been habituated to perpetual
  stimulus, are again exposed to but their usual quantity of it; as in
  those who have suffered the extremes of cold or hunger; a violent
  exertion of the affected organ commences, owing, as above explained, to
  the great accumulation of sensorial power. This violent exertion not only
  diminishes the accumulated spirit of animation, but at the same time
  induces pleasure or pain into the system, which, whether it be succeeded
  by inflammation or not, becomes an additional stimulus, and acting along
  with the former one, produces still greater exertions; and thus reduces
  the sensorial power in the contracting fibres beneath its natural
  quantity.
When the spirit of animation is thus exhausted by useless exertions,
  the organ becomes torpid or unexcitable into action, and a second fit of
  quiescence succeeds that of abundant activity. During this second fit of
  quiescence the sensorial power becomes again accumulated, and another fit
  of exertion follows in train. These vicissitudes of exertion and inertion
  of the arterial system constitute the paroxysms of remittent fevers; or
  intermittent ones, when there is an interval of the natural action of the
  arteries between the exacerbations.
In these paroxysms of fevers, which consist of the libration of the
  arterial system between the extremes of exertion and quiescence, either
  the fits become less and less violent from the contractile fibres
  becoming coming less excitable to the stimulus by habit, that is, by
  becoming accustomed to it, as explained below XII. 3. 1. or the whole sensorial power becomes
  exhausted, and the arteries cease to beat, and the patient dies in the
  cold part of the paroxysm. Or secondly, so much pain is introduced into
  the system by the violent contractions of the fibres, that inflammation
  arises, which prevents future cold fits by expending a part of the
  sensorial power in the extension of old vessels or the production of new
  ones; and thus preventing the too great accumulation or exertion of it in
  other parts of the system; or which by the great increase of stimulus
  excites into great action the whole glandular system as well as the
  arterial, and thence a greater quantity of sensorial power is produced in
  the brain, and thus its exhaustion in any peculiar part of the system
  ceases to be affected.
4. Or thirdly, in consequence of the
  painful or pleasurable sensation above mentioned, desire and aversion are
  introduced, and inordinate volition succeeds; which by its own exertions
  expends so much of the spirit of animation, that the two other sensorial
  faculties, or irritation and sensation, act so much more feebly; that the
  paroxysms of fever, or that libration between the extremes of exertion
  and inactivity of the arterial system, gradually subsides. On this
  account a temporary insanity is a favourable sign in fevers, as I have
  had some opportunities of observing.
III. Of repeated Stimulus.
1. When a stimulus is repeated more
  frequently than the expenditure of sensorial power can be renewed in the
  acting organ, the effect of the stimulus becomes gradually diminished.
  Thus if two grains of opium be swallowed by a person unused to so strong
  a stimulus, all the vascular systems in the body act with greater energy,
  all the secretions and the absorption from those secreted fluids are
  increased in quantity; and pleasure or pain are introduced into the
  system, which adds an additional stimulus to that already too great.
  After some hours the sensorial power becomes diminished in quantity,
  expended by the great activity of the system; and thence, when the
  stimulus of the opium is withdrawn, the fibres will not obey their usual
  degree of natural stimulus, and a consequent torpor or quiescence
  succeeds, as is experienced by drunkards, who on the day after a great
  excess of spirituous potation feel indigestion, head-ach, and general
  debility.
In this fit of torpor or quiescence of a part or of the whole of the
  system, an accumulation of the sensorial power in the affected fibres is
  formed, and occasions a second paroxysm of exertion by the application
  only of the natural stimulus, and thus a libration of the sensorial
  exertion between one excess and the other continues for two or three
  days, where the stimulus was violent in degree; and for weeks in some
  fevers, from the stimulus of contagious matter.
But if a second dose of opium be exhibited before the fibres have
  regained their natural quantity of sensorial power, its effect will be
  much less than the former, because the spirit of animation or sensorial
  power is in part exhausted by the previous excess of exertion. Hence all
  medicines repeated too frequently gradually lose their effect, as opium
  and wine. Many things of disagreeable taste at first cease to be
  disagreeable by frequent repetition, as tobacco; grief and pain gradually
  diminish, and at length cease altogether, and hence life itself becomes
  tolerable.
Besides the temporary diminution of the spirit of animation or
  sensorial power, which is naturally stationary or resident in every
  living fibre, by a single exhibition of a powerful stimulus, the
  contractile fibres themselves, by the perpetual application of a new
  quantity of stimulus, before they have regained their natural quantity of
  sensorial power, appear to suffer in their capability of receiving so
  much as the natural quantity of sensorial power; and hence a permanent
  deficiency of spirit of animation takes place, however long the stimulus
  may have been withdrawn. On this cause depends the permanent debility of
  those, who have been addicted to intoxication, the general weakness of
  old age, and the natural debility or inirritability of those, who have
  pale skins and large pupils of their eyes.
There is a curious phenomenon belongs to this place, which has always
  appeared difficult of solution; and that is, that opium or aloes may be
  exhibited in small doses at first, and gradually increased to very large
  ones without producing stupor or diarrhœa. In this case, though the
  opium and aloes are given in such small doses as not to produce
  intoxication or catharsis, yet they are exhibited in quantities
  sufficient in some degree to exhaust the sensorial power, and hence a
  stronger and a stronger dose is required; otherwise the medicine would
  soon cease to act at all.
On the contrary, if the opium or aloes be exhibited in a large dose at
  first, so as to produce intoxication or diarrhœa; after a few
  repetitions the quantity of either of them may be diminished, and they
  will still produce this effect. For the more powerful stimulus dissevers
  the progressive catenations of animal motions, described in Sect. XVII. and introduces a new link between them;
  whence every repetition strengthens this new association or catenation,
  and the stimulus may be gradually decreased, or be nearly withdrawn, and
  yet the effect shall continue; because the sensorial power of association
  or catenation being united with the stimulus, increases in energy with
  every repetition of the catenated circle; and it is by these means that
  all the irritative associations of motions are originally produced.
2. When a stimulus is repeated at such
  distant intervals of time, that the natural quantity of sensorial power
  becomes completely restored in the acting fibres, it will act with the
  same energy as when first applied. Hence those who have lately accustomed
  themselves to large doses of opium by beginning with small ones, and
  gradually increasing them, and repeating them frequently, as mentioned in
  the preceding paragraph; if they intermit the use of it for a few days
  only, must begin again with as small doses as they took at first,
  otherwise they will experience the inconveniences of intoxication.
On this circumstance depend the constant unfailing effects of the
  various kinds of stimulus, which excite into action all the vascular
  systems in the body; the arterial, venous, absorbent, and glandular
  vessels, are brought into perpetual unwearied action by the fluids, which
  are adapted to stimulate them; but these have the sensorial power of
  association added to that of irritation, and even in some degree that of
  sensation, and even of volition, as will be spoken of in their places;
  and life itself is thus carried on by the production of sensorial power
  being equal to its waste or expenditure in the perpetual movement of the
  vascular organization.
3. When a stimulus is repeated at uniform
  intervals of time with such distances between them, that the expenditure
  of sensorial power in the acting fibres becomes completely renewed, the
  effect is produced with greater facility or energy. For the sensorial
  power of association is combined with the sensorial power of irritation,
  or, in common language, the acquired habit assists the power of the
  stimulus.
This circumstance not only obtains in the annual and diurnal
  catenations of animal motions explained in Sect. XXXVI. but in every less circle of actions or
  ideas, as in the burthen of a song, or the iterations of a dance; and
  constitutes the pleasure we receive from repetition and imitation; as
  treated of in Sect. XXII. 2.
4. When a stimulus has been many times
  repeated at uniform intervals, so as to produce the complete action of
  the organ, it may then be gradually diminished, or totally withdrawn, and
  the action of the organ will continue. For the sensorial power of
  association becomes united with that of irritation, and by frequent
  repetition becomes at length of sufficient energy to carry on the new
  link in the circle of actions, without the irritation which at first
  introduced it.
Hence, when the bark is given at stated intervals for the cure of
  intermittent fevers, if sixty grains of it be given every three hours for
  the twenty-four hours preceding the expected paroxysm, so as to stimulate
  the defective part of the system into action, and by that means to
  prevent the torpor or quiescence of the fibres, which constitutes the
  cold fit; much less than half the quantity, given before the time at
  which another paroxysm of quiescence would have taken place, will be
  sufficient to prevent it; because now the sensorial power, termed
  association, acts in a twofold manner. First, in respect to the period of
  the catenation in which the cold fit was produced, which is now
  dissevered by the stronger stimulus of the first doses of the bark; and,
  secondly, because each dose of bark being repeated at periodical times,
  has its effect increased by the sensorial faculty of association being
  combined with that of irritation.
Now, when sixty grains of Peruvian bark are taken twice a day, suppose
  at ten o'clock and at six, for a fortnight, the irritation excited by
  this additional stimulus becomes a part of the diurnal circle of actions,
  and will at length carry on the increased action of the system without
  the assistance of the stimulus of the bark. On this theory the bitter
  medicines, chalybeates, and opiates in appropriated doses, exhibited for
  a fortnight, give permanent strength to pale feeble children, and other
  weak constitutions.
5. When a defect of stimulus, as of heat,
  recurs at certain diurnal intervals, which induces some torpor or
  quiescence of a part of the system, the diurnal catenation of actions
  becomes disordered, and a new association with this link of torpid action
  is formed; on the next period the quantity of quiescence will be
  increased, suppose the same defect of stimulus to recur, because now the
  new association conspires with the defective irritation in introducing
  the torpid action of this part of the diurnal catenation. In this manner
  many fever-fits commence, where the patient is for some days indisposed
  at certain hours, before the cold paroxysm of fever is completely formed.
  See Sect. XVII. 3. 3. on Catenation of
  Animal Motions.
6. If a stimulus, which at first excited
  the affected organ into so great exertion as to produce sensation, be
  continued for a certain time, it will cease to produce sensation both
  then and when repeated, though the irritative motions in consequence of
  it may continue or be re-excited.
Many catenations of irritative motions were at first succeeded by
  sensation, as the apparent motions of objects when we walk past them, and
  probably the vital motions themselves in the early state of our
  existence. But as those sensations were followed by no movements of the
  system in consequence of them, they gradually ceased to be produced, not
  being joined to any succeeding link of catenation. Hence contagious
  matter, which has for some weeks stimulated the system into great and
  permanent sensation, ceases afterwards to produce general sensation, or
  inflammation, though it may still induce topical irritations. See Sect.
  XXXIII. 2. 8. XIX.
  9.
Our absorbent system then seems to receive those contagious matters,
  which it has before experienced, in the same manner as it imbibes common
  moisture or other fluids; that is, without being thrown into so violent
  action as to produce sensation; the consequence of which is an increase
  of daily energy or activity, till inflammation and its consequences
  succeed.
7. If a stimulus excites an organ into such
  violent contractions as to produce sensation, the motions of which organ
  had not usually produced sensation, this new sensorial power, added to
  the irritation occasioned by the stimulus, increases the activity of the
  organ. And if this activity be catenated with the diurnal circle of
  actions, an increasing inflammation is produced; as in the evening
  paroxysms of small-pox, and other fevers with inflammation. And hence
  schirrous tumours, tendons and membranes, and probably the arteries
  themselves become inflamed, when they are strongly stimulated.
IV. Of Stimulus greater than natural.
1. A quantity of stimulus greater than
  natural, producing an increased exertion of sensorial power, whether that
  exertion be in the mode of irritation, sensation, volition, or
  association, diminishes the general quantity of it. This fact is
  observable in the progress of intoxication, as the increased quantity or
  energy of the irritative motions, owing to the stimulus of vinous spirit,
  introduces much pleasurable sensation into the system, and much exertion
  of muscular or sensual motions in consequence of this increased
  sensation; the voluntary motions, and even the associate ones, become
  much impaired or diminished; and delirium and staggering succeed. See
  Sect. XXI. on Drunkenness. And hence the great
  prostration of the strength of the locomotive muscles in some fevers, is
  owing to the exhaustion of sensorial power by the increased action of the
  arterial system.
In like manner a stimulus greater than natural, applied to a part of
  the system, increases the exertion of sensorial power in that part, and
  diminishes it in some other part. As in the commencement of scarlet
  fever, it is usual to see great redness and heat on the faces and breasts
  of children, while at the same time their feet are colder than natural;
  partial heats are observable in other fevers with debility, and are
  generally attended with torpor or quiescence of some other part of the
  system. But these partial exertions of sensorial power are sometimes
  attended with increased partial exertions in other parts of the system,
  which sympathize with them, as the flushing of the face after a full
  meal. Both these therefore are to be ascribed to sympathetic
  associations, explained in Sect. XXXV. and not
  to general exhaustion or accumulation of sensorial power.
2. A quantity of stimulus greater than
  natural, producing an increased exertion of sensorial power in any
  particular organ, diminishes the quantity of it in that organ. This
  appears from the contractions of animal fibres being not so easily
  excited by a less stimulus after the organ has been subjected to a
  greater. Thus after looking at any luminous object of a small size, as at
  the setting sun, for a short time, so as not much to fatigue the eye,
  this part of the retina becomes less sensible to smaller quantities of
  light; hence when the eyes are turned on other less luminous parts of the
  sky, a dark spot is seen resembling the shape of the sun, or other
  luminous object which we last behold. See Sect. XL.
  No. 2.
Thus we are some time before we can distinguish objects in an obscure
  room after coming from bright day-light, though the iris presently
  contracts itself. We are not able to hear weak sounds after loud ones.
  And the stomachs of those who have been much habituated to the stronger
  stimulus of fermented or spirituous liquors, are not excited into due
  action by weaker ones.
3. A quantity of stimulus something greater
  than the last mentioned, or longer continued, induces the organ into
  spasmodic action, which ceases and recurs alternately. Thus on looking
  for a time on the setting sun, so as not greatly to fatigue the sight, a
  yellow spectrum is seen when the eyes are closed and covered, which
  continues for a time, and then disappears and recurs repeatedly before it
  entirely vanishes. See Sect. XL. No. 5. Thus the
  action of vomiting ceases and is renewed by intervals, although the
  emetic drug is thrown up with the first effort. A tenesmus continues by
  intervals some time after the exclusion of acrid excrement; and the
  pulsations of the heart of a viper are said to continue some time after
  it is cleared from its blood.
In these cases the violent contractions of the fibres produce pain
  according to law 4; and this pain constitutes an additional kind or
  quantity of excitement, which again induces the fibres into contraction,
  and which painful excitement is again renewed, and again induces
  contractions of the fibres with gradually diminishing effect.
4. A quantity of stimulus greater than that
  last mentioned, or longer continued, induces the antagonist muscles into
  spasmodic action. This is beautifully illustrated by the ocular spectra
  described in Sect. XL. No. 6. to which the
  reader is referred. From those experiments there is reason to conclude
  that the fatigued part of the retina throws itself into a contrary mode
  of action like oscitation or pandiculation, as soon as the stimulus,
  which has fatigued it, is withdrawn; but that it still remains liable to
  be excited into action by any other colours except the colour with which
  it has been fatigued. Thus the yawning and stretching the limbs after a
  continued action or attitude seems occasioned by the antagonist muscles
  being stimulated by their extension during the contractions of those in
  action, or in the situation in which that action last left them.
5. A quantity of stimulus greater than the
  last, or longer continued, induces variety of convulsions or fixed spasms
  either of the affected organ or of the moving fibres in the other parts
  of the body. In respect to the spectra in the eye, this is well
  illustrated in No. 7 and 8, of Sect. XL. Epileptic convulsions, as the
  emprosthotonos and opisthotonos, with the cramp of the calf of the leg,
  locked jaw, and other cataleptic fits, appear to originate from pain, as
  some of these patients scream aloud before the convulsion takes place;
  which seems at first to be an effort to relieve painful sensation, and
  afterwards an effort to prevent it.
In these cases the violent contractions of the fibres produce so much
  pain, as to constitute a perpetual excitement; and that in so great a
  degree as to allow but small intervals of relaxation of the contracting
  fibres as in convulsions, or no intervals at all as in fixed spasms.
6. A quantity of stimulus greater than the
  last, or longer continued, produces a paralysis of the organ. In many
  cases this paralysis is only a temporary effect, as on looking long on a
  small area of bright red silk placed on a sheet of white paper on the
  floor in a strong light, the red silk gradually becomes paler, and at
  length disappears; which evinces that a part of the retina, by being
  violently excited, becomes for a time unaffected by the stimulus of that
  colour. Thus cathartic medicines, opiates, poisons, contagious matter,
  cease to influence our system after it has been habituated to the use of
  them, except by the exhibition of increased quantities of them; our
  fibres not only become unaffected by stimuli, by which they have
  previously been violently irritated, as by the matter of the small-pox or
  measles; but they also become unaffected by sensation, where the violent
  exertions, which disabled them, were in consequence of too great quantity
  of sensation. And lastly the fibres, which become disobedient to
  volition, are probably disabled by their too violent exertions in
  consequence of too great a quantity of volition.
After every exertion of our fibres a temporary paralysis succeeds,
  whence the intervals of all muscular contractions, as mentioned in No. 3
  and 4 of this Section; the immediate cause of these more permanent kinds
  of paralysis is probably owing in the same manner to the too great
  exhaustion of the spirit of animation in the affected part; so that a
  stronger stimulus is required, or one of a different kind from that,
  which occasioned those too violent contractions, to again excite the
  affected organ into activity; and if a stronger stimulus could be
  applied, it must again induce paralysis.
For these powerful stimuli excite pain at the same time, that they
  produce irritation; and this pain not only excites fibrous motions by its
  stimulus, but it also produces volition; and thus all these stimuli
  acting at the same time, and sometimes with the addition of their
  associations, produce so great exertion as to expend the whole of the
  sensorial power in the affected fibres.
V. Of Stimulus less than natural.
1. A quantity of stimulus less than
  natural, producing a decreased exertion of sensorial power, occasions an
  accumulation of the general quantity of it. This circumstance is
  observable in the hemiplagia, in which the patients are perpetually
  moving the muscles, which are unaffected. On this account we awake with
  greater vigour after sleep, because during so many hours, the great usual
  expenditure of sensorial power in the performance of voluntary actions,
  and in the exertions of our organs of sense, in consequence of the
  irritations occasioned by external objects had been suspended, and a
  consequent accumulation had taken place.
In like manner the exertion of the sensorial power less than natural
  in one part of the system, is liable to produce an increase of the
  exertion of it in some other part. Thus by the action of vomiting, in
  which the natural exertion of the motions of the stomach are destroyed or
  diminished, an increased absorption of the pulmonary and cellular
  lymphatics is produced, as is known by the increased absorption of the
  fluid deposited in them in dropsical cases. But these partial quiescences
  of sensorial power are also sometimes attended with other partial
  quiescences, which sympathize with them, as cold and pale extremities
  from hunger. These therefore are to be ascribed to the associations of
  sympathy explained in Sect. XXXV. and not to the
  general accumulation of sensorial power.
2. A quantity of stimulus less than
  natural, applied to fibres previously accustomed to perpetual stimulus,
  is succeeded by accumulation of sensorial power in the affected organ.
  The truth of this proposition is evinced, because a stimulus less than
  natural, if it be somewhat greater than that above mentioned, will excite
  the organ so circumstanced into violent activity. Thus on a frosty day
  with wind, the face of a person exposed to the wind is at first pale and
  shrunk; but on turning the face from the wind, it becomes soon of a glow
  with warmth and flushing. The glow of the skin in emerging from the
  cold-bath is owing to the same cause.
It does not appear, that an accumulation of sensorial power above the
  natural quantity is acquired by those muscles, which are not subject to
  perpetual stimulus, as the locomotive muscles: these, after the greatest
  fatigue, only acquire by rest their usual aptitude to motion; whereas the
  vascular system, as the heart and arteries, after a short quiescence, are
  thrown into violent action by their natural quantity of stimulus.
Nevertheless by this accumulation of sensorial power during the
  application of decreased stimulus, and by the exhaustion of it during the
  action of increased stimulus, it is wisely provided, that the actions of
  the vascular muscles and organs of sense are not much deranged by small
  variations of stimulus; as the quantity of sensorial power becomes in
  some measure inversely as the quantity of stimulus.
3. A quantity of stimulus less than that
  mentioned above, and continued for some time, induces pain in the
  affected organ, as the pain of cold in the hands, when they are immersed
  in snow, is owing to a deficiency of the stimulation of heat. Hunger is a
  pain from the deficiency of the stimulation of food. Pain in the back at
  the commencement of ague-fits, and the head-achs which attend feeble
  people, are pains from defect of stimulus, and are hence relieved by
  opium, essential oils, spirit of wine.
As the pains, which originate from defect of stimulus, only occur in
  those parts of the system, which have been previously subjected to
  perpetual stimulus; and as an accumulation of sensorial power is produced
  in the quiescent organ along with the pain, as in cold or hunger, there
  is reason to believe, that the pain is owing to the accumulation of
  sensorial power. For, in the locomotive muscles, in the retina of the
  eye, and other organs of senses, no pain occurs from the absence of
  stimulus, nor any great accumulation of sensorial power beyond their
  natural quantity, since these organs have not been used to a perpetual
  supply of it. There is indeed a greater accumulation occurs in the organ
  of vision after its quiescence, because it is subject to more constant
  stimulus.
4. A certain quantity of stimulus less than
  natural induces the moving organ into feebler and more frequent
  contractions, as mentioned in No. I. 4. of
  this Section. For each contraction moving through a less space, or with
  less force, that is, with less expenditure of the spirit of animation, is
  sooner relaxed, and the spirit of animation derived at each interval into
  the acting fibres being less, these intervals likewise become shorter.
  Hence the tremours of the hands of people accustomed to vinous spirit,
  till they take their usual stimulus; hence the quick pulse in fevers
  attended with debility, which is greater than in fevers attended with
  strength; in the latter the pulse seldom beats above 120 times in a
  minute, in the former it frequently exceeds 140.
It must be observed, that in this and the two following articles the
  decreased action of the system is probably more frequently occasioned by
  deficiency in the quantity of sensorial power, than in the quantity of
  stimulus. Thus those feeble constitutions which have large pupils of
  their eyes, and all who labour under nervous fevers, seem to owe their
  want of natural quantity of activity in the system to the deficiency of
  sensorial power; since, as far as can be seen, they frequently possess
  the natural quantity of stimulus.
5. A certain quantity of stimulus, less
  than that above mentioned, inverts the order of successive fibrous
  contractions; as in vomiting the vermicular motions of the stomach and
  duodenum are inverted, and their contents ejected, which is probably
  owing to the exhaustion of the spirit of animation in the acting muscles
  by a previous excessive stimulus, as by the root of ipecacuanha, and the
  consequent defect of sensorial power. The same retrograde motions affect
  the whole intestinal canal in ileus; and the œsophagus in globus
  hystericus. See this further explained in Sect. XXIX. No. 11. on Retrograde Motions.
I must observe, also, that something similar happens in the production
  of our ideas, or sensual motions, when they are too weakly excited; when
  any one is thinking intensely about one thing, and carelessly conversing
  about another, he is liable to use the word of a contrary meaning to that
  which he designed, as cold weather for hot weather, summer for
  winter.
6. A certain quantity of stimulus, less
  than that above mentioned, is succeeded by paralysis, first of the
  voluntary and sensitive motions, and afterwards of those of irritation,
  and of association, which constitutes death.
VI. Cure of increased Exertion.
1. The cure, which nature has provided for
  the increased exertion of any part of the system, consists in the
  consequent expenditure of the sensorial power. But as a greater torpor
  follows this exhaustion of sensorial power, as explained in the next
  paragraph, and a greater exertion succeeds this torpor, the constitution
  frequently sinks under these increasing librations between exertion and
  quiescence; till at length complete quiescence, that is, death, closes
  the scene.
For, during the great exertion of the system in the hot fit of fever,
  an increase of stimulus is produced from the greater momentum of the
  blood, the greater distention of the heart and arteries, and the
  increased production of heat, by the violent actions of the system
  occasioned by this augmentation of stimulus, the sensorial power becomes
  diminished in a few hours much beneath its natural quantity, the vessels
  at length cease to obey even these great degrees of stimulus, as shewn in
  Sect. XL. 9. 1. and a torpor of the whole or
  of a part of the system ensues.
Now as this second cold fit commences with a greater deficiency of
  sensorial power, it is also attended with a greater deficiency of
  stimulus than in the preceding cold fit, that is, with less momentum of
  blood, less distention of the heart. On this account the second cold fit
  becomes more violent and of longer duration than the first; and as a
  greater accumulation of sensorial power must be produced before the
  system of vessels will again obey the diminished stimulus, it follows,
  that the second hot fit of fever will be more violent than the former
  one. And that unless some other causes counteract either the violent
  exertions in the hot fit, or the great torpor in the cold fit, life will
  at length be extinguished by the expenditure of the whole of the
  sensorial power. And from hence it appears, that the true means of curing
  fevers must be such as decrease the action of the system in the hot fit,
  and increase it in the cold fit; that is, such as prevent the too great
  diminution of sensorial power in the hot fit, and the too great
  accumulation of it in the cold one.
2. Where the exertion of the sensorial
  powers is much increased, as in the hot fits of fever or inflammation,
  the following are the usual means of relieving it. Decrease the
  irritations by blood-letting, and other evacuations; by cold water taken
  into the stomach, or injected as an enema, or used externally; by cold
  air breathed into the lungs, and diffused over the skin; with food of
  less stimulus than the patient has been accustomed to.
3. As a cold fit, or paroxysm of inactivity
  of some parts of the system, generally precedes the hot fit, or paroxysm
  of exertion, by which the sensorial power becomes accumulated, this cold
  paroxysm should be prevented by stimulant medicines and diet, as wine,
  opium, bark, warmth, cheerfulness, anger, surprise.
4. Excite into greater action some other
  part of the system, by which means the spirit of animation may be in part
  expended, and thence the inordinate actions of the diseased part may be
  lessened. Hence when a part of the skin acts violently, as of the face in
  the eruption of the small-pox, if the feet be cold they should be
  covered. Hence the use of a blister applied near a topical inflammation.
  Hence opium and warm bath relieve pains both from excess and defect of
  stimulus.
5. First increase the general stimulation
  above its natural quantity, which may in some degree exhaust the spirit
  of animation, and then decrease the stimulation beneath its natural
  quantity. Hence after sudorific medicines and warm air, the application
  of refrigerants may have greater effect, if they could be administered
  without danger of producing too great torpor of some part of the system;
  as frequently happens to people in health from coming out of a warm room
  into the cold air, by which a topical inflammation in consequence of
  torpor of the mucous membrane of the nostril is produced, and is termed a
  cold in the head.
VII. Cure of decreased Exertion.
1. Where the exertion of the sensorial
  powers is much decreased, as in the cold fits of fever, a gradual
  accumulation of the spirit of animation takes place; as occurs in all
  cases where inactivity or torpor of a part of the system exists; this
  accumulation of sensorial power increases, till stimuli less than natural
  are sufficient to throw it into action, then the cold fit ceases; and
  from the action of the natural stimuli a hot one succeeds with increased
  activity of the whole system.
So in fainting fits, or syncope, there is a temporary deficiency of
  sensorial exertion, and a consequent quiescence of a great part of the
  system. This quiescence continues, till the sensorial power becomes again
  accumulated in the torpid organs; and then the usual diurnal stimuli
  excite the revivescent parts again into action; but as this kind of
  quiescence continues but a short time compared to the cold paroxysm of an
  ague, and less affects the circulatory system, a less superabundancy of
  exertion succeeds in the organs previously torpid, and a less excess of
  arterial activity. See Sect. XXXIV. 1.
  6.
2. In the diseases occasioned by a defect
  of sensorial exertion, as in cold fits of ague, hysteric complaint, and
  nervous fever, the following means are those commonly used. 1. Increase
  the stimulation above its natural quantity for some weeks, till a new
  habit of more energetic contraction of the fibres is established. This is
  to be done by wine, opium, bark, steel, given at exact periods, and in
  appropriate quantities; for if these medicines be given in such quantity,
  as to induce the least degree of intoxication, a debility succeeds from
  the useless exhaustion of spirit of animation in consequence of too great
  exertion of the muscles or organs of sense. To these irritative stimuli
  should be added the sensitive ones of cheerful ideas, hope,
  affection.
3. Change the kinds of stimulus. The habits
  acquired by the constitution depend on such nice circumstances, that when
  one kind of stimulus ceases to excite the sensorial power into the
  quantity of exertion necessary to health, it is often sufficient to
  change the stimulus for another apparently similar in quantity and
  quality. Thus when wine ceases to stimulate the constitution, opium in
  appropriate doses supplies the defect; and the contrary. This is also
  observed in the effects of cathartic medicines, when one loses its power,
  another, apparently less efficacious, will succeed. Hence a change of
  diet, drink, and stimulating medicines, is often advantageous in diseases
  of debility.
4. Stimulate the organs, whose motions are
  associated with the torpid parts of the system. The actions of the minute
  vessels of the various parts of the external skin are not only associated
  with each other, but are strongly associated with those of some of the
  internal membranes, and particularly of the stomach. Hence when the
  exertion of the stomach is less than natural, and indigestion and
  heartburn succeed, nothing so certainly removes these symptoms as the
  stimulus of a blister on the back. The coldness of the extremities, as of
  the nose, ears, or fingers, are hence the best indication for the
  successful application of blisters.
5. Decrease the stimulus for a time. By
  lessening the quantity of heat for a minute or two by going into the cold
  bath, a great accumulation of sensorial power is produced; for not only
  the minute vessels of the whole external skin for a time become inactive,
  as appears by their paleness; but the minute vessels of the lungs lose
  much of their activity also by concert with those of the skin, as appears
  from the difficulty of breathing at first going into cold water. On
  emerging from the bath the sensorial power is thrown into great exertion
  by the stimulus of the common degree of the warmth of the atmosphere, and
  a great production of animal heat is the consequence. The longer a person
  continues in the cold bath the greater must be the present inertion of a
  great part of the system, and in consequence a greater accumulation of
  sensorial power. Whence M. Pom� recommends some melancholy patients to be
  kept from two to six hours in spring-water, and in baths still
  colder.
6. Decrease the stimulus for a time below
  the natural, and then increase it above natural. The effect of this
  process, improperly used, is seen in giving much food, or applying much
  warmth, to those who have been previously exposed to great hunger, or to
  great cold. The accumulated sensorial power is thrown into so violent
  exertion, that inflammations and mortifications supervene, and death
  closes the catastrophe. In many diseases this method is the most
  successful; hence the bark in agues produces more certain effect after
  the previous exhibition of emetics. In diseases attended with violent
  pain, opium has double the effect, if venesection and a cathartic have
  been previously used. On this seems to have been founded the successful
  practice of Sydenham, who used venesection and a cathartic in chlorosis
  before the exhibition of the bark, steel, and opiates.
7. Prevent any unnecessary expenditure of
  sensorial power. Hence in fevers with debility, a decumbent posture is
  preferred, with silence, little light, and such a quantity of heat as may
  prevent any chill sensation, or any coldness of the extremities. The
  pulse of patients in fevers with debility increases in frequency above
  ten pulsations in a minute on their rising out of bed. For the
  expenditure of sensorial power to preserve an erect posture of the body
  adds to the general deficiency of it, and thus affects the
  circulation.
8. The longer in time and the greater in
  degree the quiescence or inertion of an organ has been, so that it still
  retains life or excitability, the less stimulus should at first be
  applied to it. The quantity of stimulation is a matter of great nicety to
  determine, where the torpor or quiescence of the fibres has been
  experienced in a great degree, or for a considerable time, as in cold
  fits of the ague, in continued fevers with great debility, or in people
  famished at sea, or perishing with cold. In the two last cases, very
  minute quantities of food should be first supplied, and very few
  additional degrees of heat. In the two former cases, but little stimulus
  of wine or medicine, above what they had been lately accustomed to,
  should be exhibited, and this at frequent and stated intervals, so that
  the effect of one quantity may be observed before the exhibition of
  another.
If these circumstances are not attended to, as the sensorial power
  becomes accumulated in the quiescent fibres, an inordinate exertion takes
  place by the increase of stimulus acting on the accumulated quantity of
  sensorial power, and either the paralysis, or death of the contractile
  fibres ensues, from the total expenditure of the sensorial power in the
  affected organ, owing to this increase of exertion, like the debility
  after intoxication. Or, secondly, the violent exertions above mentioned
  produce painful sensation, which becomes a new stimulus, and by thus
  producing inflammation, and increasing the activity of the fibres already
  too great, sooner exhausts the whole of the sensorial power in the acting
  organ, and mortification, that is, the death of the part, supervenes.
Hence there have been many instances of people, whose limbs have been
  long benumbed by exposure to cold, who have lost them by mortification on
  their being too hastily brought to the fire; and of others, who were
  nearly famished at sea, who have died soon after having taken not more
  than an usual meal of food. I have heard of two well-attested instances
  of patients in the cold fit of ague, who have died from the exhibition of
  gin and vinegar, by the inflammation which ensued. And in many fevers
  attended with debility, the unlimited use of wine, and the wanton
  application of blisters, I believe, has destroyed numbers by the debility
  consequent to too great stimulation, that is, by the exhaustion of the
  sensorial power by its inordinate exertion.
Wherever the least degree of intoxication exists, a proportional
  debility is the consequence; but there is a golden rule by which the
  necessary and useful quantity of stimulus in fevers with debility may be
  ascertained. When wine or beer are exhibited either alone or diluted with
  water, if the pulse becomes slower the stimulus is of a proper quantity;
  and should be repeated every two or three hours, or when the pulse again
  becomes quicker.
In the chronical debility brought on by drinking spirituous or
  fermented liquors, there is another golden rule by which I have
  successfully directed the quantity of spirit which they may safely
  lessen, for there is no other means by which they can recover their
  health. It should be premised, that where the power of digestion in these
  patients is totally destroyed, there is not much reason to expect a
  return to healthful vigour.
I have directed several of these patients to omit one fourth part of
  the quantity of vinous spirit they have been lately accustomed to, and if
  in a fortnight their appetite increases, they are advised to omit another
  fourth part; but if they perceive that their digestion becomes impaired
  from the want of this quantity of spirituous potation, they are advised
  to continue as they are, and rather bear the ills they have, than risk
  the encounter of greater. At the same time flesh-meat with or without
  spice is recommended, with Peruvian bark and steel in small quantities
  between their meals, and half a grain of opium or a grain, with five or
  eight grains of rhubarb at night.

</div></body></text></TEI>