<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 166, folios 207-209</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 166, folios 207-209.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1843">undated (estimated from box 166 date range)</date>
          <note type="place">St. James' Square</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 166, folios 207-209</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_166_folios_207-209.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>St James' Sqre Satdy. 6 o'clock.</p>
      <p>You may like to have a few lines more, altho' I did write by parcel today.</p>
      <p>I have never seen my Mother worse I think, &amp; am very anxious about her. Her pulse is one of high fever. She does not wish to see any adviser, but she has let me send the Cupper to her, which is the chief thing, if she will but allow him to take as</p>
      <p>much as would do her good. If I find she has not, I really shall be quite angry, after all her experience.-- Miss Murray (who has imbibed a horror of bleeding from that clever quack Dr Dickson), has been with her, croaking about the danger of it.</p>
      <p>But on the other hand, Miss Montgomery cries out to her, Bleed, bleed, bleed; &amp; so do I. So I hope she will be wise.</p>
      <p>I am very much less well certainly this day. Dr. L-- (who yesterday did</p>
      <p>not see me), found my pulse too full this morning, &amp; is obliged to pull me down again a little; &amp; I do not feel at all comfortable.</p>
      <p>What an odd animal the Bird is; so anti-feverish, notwithstanding all this full tendency of another kind.</p>
      <p>I hope to give you a better account again on Monday Morning. My wish is to go down, (unless I see some good reason for staying), that afternoon; to pass a few days at Ockham, &amp; then to come here again. I</p>
      <p>tell you, my Dear, my wishes &amp; intentions, as far as I know them myself.</p>
      <p>I find I require my Doctor's aid much, just at present. It is difficult for me to judge when or not I require Laudanum for instance, or certain medicines, &amp; how much or how little.</p>
      <p>I believe my being less well today is chiefly owing to a blunder I made yesterday in a matter of this kind; in which I used my best judgment &amp; was not to blame, but really unable to form a proper opinion. (He had</p>
      <p>been called out of Town).</p>
      <p>Now don't (pray) fancy that I want to be tied to an M. D for the rest of my life. I merely speak of the present week or two; (possibly month or two, but I do not venture to extend my anticipations so far even as that). When one is completely out of order, it is then not so very easy to get right again. This you will understand. Avis' own unprofessional knowledge &amp; watching &amp; experience may be very sufficient to keep right right, but by no means to put</p>
      <p>wrong right.</p>
      <p>I have been a most insolent Thrush, &amp; have got some books in the Crow's name, from the Royal Society.--</p>
      <p>I hope, my Dear, ou is tolerably happy; tho' ou poor thing, ou has neither a Thrush, a Hen, nor young.</p>
      <p>I think I am tolerably attentive in writing to you.</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
