<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="17">CHAPTER III.
Of the Mysticism of the Middle Ages.
IT has been already several
times hinted, that a new and peculiar element was introduced into the
Greek philosophy which occupied the attention of the Alexandrian
school; and that this element tinged a large portion of the
speculations of succeeding ages. We may speak of this peculiar element
as Mysticism; for, from the notion usually conveyed by this
term, the reader will easily apprehend the general character of the
tendency now spoken of; and especially when he sees its effect pointed
out in various subjects. Thus, instead of referring the events of the
external world to space and time, to sensible connection and
causation, men attempted to reduce such occurrences under spiritual
and supersensual relations and dependencies; they referred them to
superior intelligences, to theological conditions, to past and future
events in the moral world, to states of mind and feelings, to the
creatures of an imaginary mythology or demonology. And thus their
physical Science became Magic, their Astronomy became Astrology, the
study of the Composition of bodies became Alchemy, Mathematics became
the contemplation of the Spiritual Relations of number and figure, and
Philosophy became Theosophy.
The examination of this feature in the history of the human mind is
important for us, in consequence of its influence upon the employments
and the thoughts of the times now under our notice. This tendency
materially affected both men’s speculations and their labours in the
pursuit of knowledge. By its direct operation, it gave rise to the
newer Platonic philosophy among the Greeks, and to corresponding
doctrines among the Arabians; and by calling into a prominent place
astrology, alchemy, and magic, it long occupied most of the real
observers of the material world. In this manner it delayed and impeded
the progress of true science; for we shall see reason to believe that
human knowledge lost more by the perversion of men’s minds and the
misdirection of their efforts, than it gained by any increase of zeal
arising from the peculiar hopes and objects of the mystics.
It is not our purpose to attempt any general view of the progress
and fortunes of the various forms of Mystical Philosophy; but only to
exhibit some of its characters, in so far as they illustrate those
212 tendencies of
thought which accompanied the retrogradation of inductive science. And
of these, the leading feature which demands our notice is that already
alluded to; namely, the practice of referring things and events, not
to clear and distinct relations, obviously applicable to such
cases;—not to general rules capable of direct verification; but
to notions vague, distant, and vast, which we cannot bring into
contact with facts, because they belong to a different region from the
facts; as when we connect natural events with moral or historical
causes, or seek spiritual meanings in the properties of number and
figure. Thus the character of Mysticism is, that it refers
particulars, not to generalizations homogeneous and immediate, but to
such as are heterogeneous and remote; to which we must add, that the
process of this reference is not a calm act of the intellect, but is
accompanied with a glow of enthusiastic feeling.
1. Neoplatonic Theosophy.—The Newer Platonism
is the first example of this Mystical Philosophy which I shall
consider. The main points which here require our notice are, the
doctrine of an Intellectual World resulting from the act of the Divine
Mind, as the only reality; and the aspiration after the union of the
human soul with this Divine Mind, as the object of human existence.
The “Ideas” of Plato were Forms of our knowledge; but among the
Neoplatonists they became really existing, indeed the only really
existing, Objects; and the inaccessible scheme of the universe which
these ideas constitute, was offered as the great subject of
philosophical contemplation. The desire of the human mind to approach
towards its Creator and Preserver, and to obtain a spiritual access to
Him, leads to an employment of the thoughts which is well worth the
notice of the religious philosopher; but such an effort, even when
founded on revelation and well regulated, is not a means of advance in
physics; and when it is the mere result of natural enthusiasm, it may
easily obtain such a place in men’s minds as to unfit them for the
successful prosecution of natural philosophy. The temper, therefore,
which introduces such supernatural communion into the general course
of its speculations, may be properly treated as mystical, and as one
of the causes of the decline of science in the Stationary Period. The
Neoplatonic philosophy requires our notice as one of the most
remarkable forms of this Mysticism.
Though Ammonius Saccas, who flourished at the end of the second
century, is looked upon as the beginner of the Neoplatonists, his
disciple Plotinus is, in reality, the great founder of the school,
both by his 213
works, which still remain to us, and by the enthusiasm which his
character and manners inspired among his followers. He lived a life of
meditation, gentleness, and self-denial, and died in the second year
of the reign of Claudius (a. d. 270). His
disciple, Porphyry, has given us a Life of him, from which we may see
how well his habitual manners were suited to make his doctrines
impressive. “Plotinus, the philosopher of our time,” Porphyry thus
begins his biography, “appeared like a person ashamed that he was in
the body. In consequence of this disposition, he could not bear to
talk concerning his family, or his parents, or his country. He would
not allow himself to be represented by a painter or statuary; and
once, when Aurelius entreated him to permit a likeness of him to be
taken, he said, ‘Is it not enough for us to carry this image in which
nature has enclosed us, but we must also try to leave a more durable
image of this image, as if it were so great a sight?’ And he retained
the same temper to the last. When he was dying, he said, ‘I am trying
to bring the divinity which is in us to the divinity which is in the
universe.’” He was looked upon by his successors with extraordinary
admiration and reverence; and his disciple Porphyry collected from his
lips, or from fragmental notes, the six Enneads of his
doctrines (that is, parts each consisting of nine Books), which
he arranged and annotated.
We have no difficulty in finding in this remarkable work examples
of mystical speculation. The Intelligible World of realities or
essences corresponds to the world of sense40 in the classes
of things which it includes. To the Intelligible World, man’s mind
ascends, by a triple road which Plotinus figuratively calls that of
the Musician, the Lover, the Philosopher.41 The activity of
the human soul is identified by analogy with the motion of the
heavens. “This activity is about a middle point, and thus it is
circular; but a middle point is not the same in body and in the soul:
in that, the middle point is local; in this, it is that on which the
rest depends. There is, however, an analogy; for as in one case, so in
the other, there must be a middle point, and as the sphere revolves
about its centre, the soul revolves about God through its
affections.”
40 vi. Ennead, iii. 1.
41 ii. E. ii. 2.
The conclusion of the work is,42 as might be
supposed, upon the approach to, union with, and fruition of God. The
author refers again to the analogy between the movements of the soul
and those of the heavens. “We move round him like a choral dance; even
when we 214 look
from him we revolve about him: we do not always look at him, but when
we do, we have satisfaction and rest, and the harmony which belongs to
that divine movement. In this movement, the mind beholds the fountain
of life, the fountain of mind, the origin of being, the cause of good,
the root of the soul.”43 “There will be a time when this vision
shall be continual; the mind being no more interrupted, nor suffering
any perturbation from the body. Yet that which beholds is not that
which is disturbed; and when this vision becomes dim, it does not
obscure the knowledge which resides in demonstration, and faith, and
reasoning; but the vision itself is not reason, but greater than
reason, and before reason.”44
42 vi. Enn. ix. 8.
43 vi. Enn. ix. 9.
44 vi. Enn. ix. 10.
The fifth book of the third Ennead has for its subject the Dæmon
which belongs to each man. It is entitled “Concerning Love;” and the
doctrine appears to be, that the Love, or common source of the
passions which is in each man’s mind, is “the Dæmon which they say
accompanies each man.”45 These dæmons were, however (at least by
later writers), invested with a visible aspect and with a personal
character, including a resemblance of human passions and motives. It
is curious thus to see an untenable and visionary generalization
falling back into the domain of the senses and the fancy, after a vain
attempt to support itself in the region of the reason. This
imagination soon produced pretensions to the power of making these
dæmons or genii visible; and the Treatise on the Mysteries of the
Egyptians, which is attributed to Iamblichus, gives an account of the
secret ceremonies, the mysterious words, the sacrifices and
expiations, by which this was to be done.
45 Ficinus, Comm. in v. Enn.
iii.
It is unnecessary for us to dwell on the progress of this school;
to point out the growth of the Theurgy which thus arose; or to
describe the attempts to claim a high antiquity for this system, and
to make Orpheus, the poet, the first promulgator of its doctrines. The
system, like all mystical systems, assumed the character rather of
religion than of a theory. The opinions of its disciples materially
influenced their lives. It gave the world the spectacle of an austere
morality, a devotional exaltation, combined with the grossest
superstitions of Paganism. The successors of Iamblichus appeared
rather to hold a priesthood, than the chair of a philosophical
school.46 They were persecuted by Constantine and
Constantius, as opponents of Christianity. Sopater, a 215 Syrian philosopher of
this school, was beheaded by the former emperor on a charge that he
had bound the winds by the power of magic.47 But Julian, who
shortly after succeeded to the purple, embraced with ardor the
opinions of Iamblichus. Proclus (who died a.
d. 487) was one of the greatest of the teachers of this
school;48 and was, both in his life and
doctrines, a worthy successor of Plotinus, Porphyry, and Iamblichus.
We possess a biography, or rather a panegyric of him, by his disciple
Marinus, in which he is exhibited as a representation of the ideal
perfection of the philosophic character, according to the views of the
Neoplatonists. His virtues are arranged as physical, moral,
purificatory, theoretic, and theurgic. Even in his boyhood, Apollo and
Minerva visited him in his dreams: he studied oratory at Alexandria,
but it was at Athens that Plutarch and Lysianus initiated him in the
mysteries of the New Platonists. He received a kind of consecration at
the hands of the daughter of Plutarch, the celebrated Asclepigenia,
who introduced him to the traditions of the Chaldeans, and the
practices of theurgy; he was also admitted to the mysteries of
Eleusis. He became celebrated for his knowledge and eloquence; but
especially for his skill in the supernatural arts which were connected
with the doctrines of his sect. He appears before us rather as a
hierophant than a philosopher. A large portion of his life was spent
in evocations, purifications, fastings, prayers, hymns, intercourse
with apparitions, and with the gods, and in the celebration of the
festivals of Paganism, especially those which were held in honor of
the Mother of the Gods. His religious admiration extended to all forms
of mythology. The philosopher, said he, is not the priest of a single
religion, but of all the religions of the world. Accordingly, he
composed hymns in honor of all the divinities of Greece, Rome, Egypt,
Arabia;—Christianity alone was excluded from his favor.
46 Deg. iii. 407
47 Gibbon, iii. 352.
48 Deg. iii. 419.
The reader will find an interesting view of the School of
Alexandria, in M. Barthelemy Saint-Hilaire’s Rapport on the
Mémoires sent to the Academy of Moral and Political Sciences at
Paris, in consequence of its having, in 1841, proposed this as the
subject of a prize, which was awarded in 1844. M. Saint-Hilaire has
prefixed to this Rapport a dissertation on the Mysticism of
that school. He, however, uses the term Mysticism in a wider
sense than my purpose, which regarded mainly the bearing of the
doctrines of this school upon the progress of the Inductive Sciences,
has led me to do. Although he finds much to 216 admire in the Alexandrian philosophy, he
declares that they were incapable of treating scientific questions.
The extent to which this is true is well illustrated by the extract
which he gives from Plotinus, on the question, “Why objects appear
smaller in proportion as they are more distant.” Plotinus denies that
the reason of this is that the angles of vision become smaller. His
reason for this denial is curious enough. If it were so, he says, how
could the heaven appear smaller than it is, since it occupies the
whole of the visual angle?
2. Mystical Arithmetic.—It is unnecessary further to
exemplify, from Proclus, the general mystical character of the school
and time to which he belonged; but we may notice more specially one of
the forms of this mysticism, which very frequently offers itself to
our notice, especially in him; and which we may call Mystical
Arithmetic. Like all the kinds of Mysticism, this consists in the
attempt to connect our conceptions of external objects by general and
inappropriate notions of goodness, perfection, and relation to the
divine essence and government; instead of referring such conceptions
to those appropriate ideas, which, by due attention, become perfectly
distinct, and capable of being positively applied and verified. The
subject which is thus dealt with, in the doctrines of which we now
speak, is Number; a notion which tempts men into these visionary
speculations more naturally than any other. For number is really
applicable to moral notions—to emotions and feelings, and to
their objects—as well as to the things of the material world.
Moreover, by the discovery of the principle of musical concords, it
had been found, probably most unexpectedly, that numerical relations
were closely connected with sounds which could hardly be distinguished
from the expression of thought and feeling; and a suspicion might
easily arise, that the universe, both of matter and of thought, might
contain many general and abstract truths of some analogous kind. The
relations of number have so wide a bearing, that the ramifications of
such a suspicion could not easily be exhausted, supposing men willing
to follow them into darkness and vagueness; which it is precisely the
mystical tendency to do. Accordingly, this kind of speculation
appeared very early, and showed itself first among the Pythagoreans,
as we might have expected, from the attention which they gave to the
theory of harmony: and this, as well as some other of the doctrines of
the Pythagorean philosophy, was adopted by the later Platonists, and,
indeed, by Plato himself, whose speculations concerning number have
decidedly a mystical character. The mere mathematical relations of
numbers,—as odd and even, perfect and imperfect, 217 abundant and
defective,—were, by a willing submission to an enthusiastic
bias, connected with the notions of good and beauty, which were
suggested by the terms expressing their relations; and principles
resulting from such a connection were woven into a wide and complex
system. It is not necessary to dwell long on this subject; the mere
titles of the works which treated of it show its nature. Archytas49 is said to have written a treatise on
the number ten: Telaugé, the daughter of Pythagoras, wrote on
the number four. This number, indeed, which was known by the
name of the Tetractys, was very celebrated in the school of
Pythagoras. It is mentioned in the “Golden Verses,” which are ascribed
to him: the pupil is conjured to be virtuous,


Ναὶ μὰ τὸν ἁμετέρᾳ ψυχᾷ παραδόντα
τετρακτὺν
Παγὰν ἀεννάου φύσεως . . . .
By him who stampt The Four upon the
mind,—
The Four, the fount of nature’s endless
stream.

49 Mont. ii. 123.
In Plato’s works, we have evidence of a similar belief in religious
relations of Number; and in the new Platonists, this doctrine was
established as a system. Proclus, of whom we have been speaking,
founds his philosophy, in a great measure, on the relation of Unity
and Multiple; from this, he is led to represent the causality of the
Divine Mind by three Triads of abstractions; and in the development of
one part of this system, the number seven is introduced.50 “The intelligible and intellectual gods
produce all things triadically; for the monads in these latter are
divided according to number; and what the monad was in the former, the
number is in these latter. And the intellectual gods produce all
things hebdomically; for they evolve the intelligible, and at the same
time intellectual triads, into intellectual hebdomads, and expand
their contracted powers into intellectual variety.” Seven is what is
called by arithmeticians a prime number, that is, it cannot be
produced by the multiplication of other numbers. In the language of
the New Platonists, the number seven is said to be a virgin, and
without a mother, and it is therefore sacred to Minerva. The number
six is a perfect number, and is consecrated to Venus.
50 Procl. v. 3, Taylor’s
translation.
The relations of space were dealt with in like manner, the
Geometrical properties being associated with such physical and
metaphysical notions as vague thought and lively feeling could anyhow
connect with them. We may consider, as an example of this,51 Plato’s opinion 218 concerning the
particles of the four elements. He gave to each kind of particle one
of the five regular solids, about which the geometrical speculations
of himself and his pupils had been employed. The particles of fire
were pyramids, because they are sharp, and tend upwards; those of
earth are cubes, because they are stable, and fill space; the
particles of air are octahedral, as most nearly resembling those of
fire; those of water are the icositetrahedron, as most nearly
spherical. The dodecahedron is the figure of the element of the
heavens, and shows its influence in other things, as in the twelve
signs of the zodiac. In such examples we see how loosely space and
number are combined or confounded by these mystical visionaries.
51 Stanley, Hist. Phil.
These numerical dreams of ancient philosophers have been imitated
by modern writers; for instance, by Peter Bungo and Kircher, who have
written De Mysteriis Numerorum. Bungo treats of the mystical
properties of each of the numbers in order, at great length. And such
speculations have influenced astronomical theories. In the first
edition of the Alphonsine Tables,52 the precession
was represented by making the first point of Aries move, in a period
of 7000 years, through a circle of which the radius was 18 degrees,
while the circle moved round the ecliptic in 49,000 years; and these
numbers, 7000 and 49,000, were chosen probably by Jewish calculators,
or with reference to Jewish Sabbatarian notions.
52 Montucla, i. 511.
3. Astrology.—Of all the forms which mysticism
assumed, none was cultivated more assiduously than astrology. Although
this art prevailed most universally and powerfully during the
stationary period, its existence, even as a detailed technical system,
goes back to a very early age. It probably had its origin in the East;
it is universally ascribed to the Babylonians and Chaldeans; the name
Chaldean was, at Rome, synonymous with mathematicus, or
astrologer; and we read repeatedly that this class of persons were
expelled from Italy by a decree of the senate, both during the times
of the republic and of the empire.53 The recurrence
of this act of legislation shows that it was not effectual: “It is a
class of men,” says Tacitus, “which, in our city, will always be
prohibited, and will always exist.” In Greece, it does not appear that
the state showed any hostility to the professors of this art. They
undertook, it would seem, then, as at a later period, to determine the
course of a man’s character and life from the configuration of the
stars at the moment of his birth. We do not possess any of the 219 speculations of the
early astrologers; and we cannot therefore be certain that the notions
which operated in men’s minds when the art had its birth, agreed with
the views on which it was afterwards defended, when it became a matter
of controversy. But it appears probable, that, though it was at later
periods supported by physical analogies, it was originally suggested
by mythological belief. The Greeks spoke of the influences or
effluxes (ἀπόῤῥοιας) which proceeded from the stars; but the
Chaldeans had probably thought rather of the powers which they
exercised as deities. In whatever manner the sun, moon, and
planets came to be identified with gods and goddesses, it is clear
that the characters ascribed to these gods and goddesses regulate the
virtues and powers of the stars which bear their names. This
association, so manifestly visionary, was retained, amplified, and
pursued, in an enthusiastic spirit, instead of being rejected for more
distinct and substantial connections; and a pretended science was thus
formed, which bears the obvious stamp of mysticism.
53 Tacit. Ann. ii. 32. xii. 52.
Hist. I. 22, II. 62.
That common sense of mankind which teaches them that theoretical
opinions are to be calmly tried by their consequences and their
accordance with facts, appears to have counteracted the prevalence of
astrology in the better times of the human mind. Eudoxus, as we are
informed by Cicero,54 rejected the pretensions of the
Chaldeans; and Cicero himself reasons against them with arguments as
sensible and intelligent as could be adduced by a writer of the
present day; such as the different fortunes and characters of persons
born at the same time; and the failure of the predictions, in the case
of Pompey, Crassus, Cæsar, to whom the astrologers had foretold
glorious old age and peaceful death. He also employs an argument which
the reader would perhaps not expect from him,—the very great
remoteness of the planets as compared with the distance of the moon.
“What contagion can reach us,” he asks, “from a distance almost
infinite?”
54 Cic. de Div. ii. 42.
Pliny argues on the same side, and with some of the same
arguments.55 “Homer,” he says, “tells us that Hector
and Polydamus were born the same night;—men of such different
fortune. And every hour, in every part of the world, are born lords
and slaves, kings and beggars.”
55 Hist. Nat. vii. 49.
The impression made by these arguments is marked in an anecdote
told concerning Publius Nigidius Figulus, a Roman of the time of
Julius Cæsar, whom Lucan mentions as a celebrated astrologer. It is
220 said, that when
an opponent of the art urged as an objection the different fates of
persons born in two successive instants, Nigidius bade him make two
contiguous marks on a potter’s wheel, which was revolving rapidly near
them. On stopping the wheel, the two marks were found to be really far
removed from each other; and Nigidius is said to have received the
name of Figulus (the potter), in remembrance of this story, His
argument, says St. Augustine, who gives us the narrative, was as
fragile as the ware which the wheel manufactured.
As the darkening times of the Roman empire advanced, even the
stronger minds seem to have lost the clear energy which was requisite
to throw off this delusion. Seneca appears to take the influence of
the planets for granted; and even Tacitus56 seems to
hesitate. “For my own part,” says he, “I doubt; but certainly the
majority of mankind cannot be weaned from the opinion, that, at the
birth of each man, his future destiny is fixed; though some things may
fall out differently from the predictions, by the ignorance of those
who profess the art; and that thus the art is unjustly blamed,
confirmed as it is by noted examples in all ages.” The occasion which
gives rise to these reflections of the historian is the mention of
Thrasyllus, the favorite astrologer of the Emperor Tiberius, whose
skill is exemplified in the following narrative. Those who were
brought to Tiberius on any important matter, were admitted to an
interview in an apartment situated on a lofty cliff in the island of
Capreæ. They reached this place by a narrow path, accompanied by a
single freedman of great bodily strength; and on their return, if the
emperor had conceived any doubts of their trustworthiness, a single
blow buried the secret and its victim in the ocean below. After
Thrasyllus had, in this retreat, stated the results of his art as they
concerned the emperor, Tiberius asked him whether he had calculated
how long he himself had to live. The astrologer examined the aspect of
the stars, and while he did this, as the narrative states, showed
hesitation, alarm, increasing terror, and at last declared that, “the
present hour was for him critical, perhaps fatal.” Tiberius embraced
him, and told him “he was right in supposing he had been in danger,
but that he should escape it;” and made him thenceforth his
confidential counsellor.
56 Ann. vi. 22.
The belief in the power of astrological prediction which thus
obtained dominion over the minds of men of literary cultivation and
practical energy, naturally had a more complete sway among the
speculative 221 but
unstable minds of the later philosophical schools of Alexandria,
Athens, and Rome. We have a treatise on astrology by Proclus, which
will serve to exemplify the mystical principle in this form. It
appears as a commentary on a work on the same subject called
“Tetrabiblos,” ascribed to Ptolemy; though we may reasonably doubt
whether the author of the “Megale Syntaxis” was also the writer of the
astrological work. A few notices of the commentary of Proclus will
suffice.57 The science is defended by urging how
powerful we know the physical effects of the heavenly bodies to be.
“The sun regulates all things on earth;—the birth of animals,
the growth of fruits, the flowing of waters, the change of health,
according to the seasons: he produces heat, moisture, dryness, cold,
according to his approach to our zenith. The moon, which is the
nearest of all bodies to the earth, gives out much influence;
and all things, animate and inanimate, sympathize with her: rivers
increase and diminish according to her light; the advance of the sea,
and its recess, are regulated by her rising and setting; and along
with her, fruits and animals wax and wane, either wholly or in part.”
It is easy to see that by pursuing this train of associations (some
real and some imaginary) very vaguely and very enthusiastically, the
connections which astrology supposes would receive a kind of
countenance. Proclus then proceeds to state58 the doctrines of
the science. “The sun,” he says, “is productive of heat and dryness;
this power is moderate in its nature, but is more perceived than that
of the other luminaries, from his magnitude, and from the change of
seasons. The nature of the moon is for the most part moist; for being
the nearest to the earth, she receives the vapors which rise from
moist bodies, and thus she causes bodies to soften and rot. But by the
illumination she receives from the sun, she partakes in a moderate
degree of heat. Saturn is cold and dry, being most distant both from
the heating power of the sun, and the moist vapors of the earth. His
cold, however, is most prevalent, his dryness is more moderate. Both
he and the rest receive additional powers from the configurations
which they make with respect to the sun and moon.” In the same manner
it is remarked that Mars is dry and caustic, from his fiery nature,
which, indeed, his color shows. Jupiter is well compounded of warm and
moist, as is Venus. Mercury is variable in his character. From these
notions were derived others concerning the beneficial or hurtful
effect of these stars. Heat and 222 moisture are generative and creative
elements; hence the ancients, says Proclus, deemed Jupiter, and Venus,
and the Moon to have a good power; Saturn and Mercury, on the other
hand, had an evil nature.
57 I. 2.
58 I. 4.
Other distinctions of the character of the stars are enumerated,
equally visionary, and suggested by the most fanciful connections.
Some are masculine, and some feminine: the Moon and Venus are of the
latter kind. This appears to be merely a mythological or etymological
association. Some are diurnal, some nocturnal: the Moon and Venus are
of the latter kind, the Sun and Jupiter of the former; Saturn and Mars
are both.
The fixed stars, also, and especially those of the zodiac, had
especial influences and subjects assigned to them. In particular, each
sign was supposed to preside over a particular part of the body; thus
Aries had the head assigned to it, Taurus the neck, and so on.
The most important part of the sky in the astrologer’s
consideration, was that sign of the zodiac which rose at the moment of
the child’s birth; this was, properly speaking, the horoscope,
the ascendant, or the first house; the whole circuit of
the heavens being divided into twelve houses, in which life and
death, marriage and children, riches and honors, friends and enemies,
were distributed.
We need not attempt to trace the progress of this science. It
prevailed extensively among the Arabians, as we might expect from the
character of that nation. Albumasar, of Balkh in Khorasan, who
flourished in the ninth century, who was one of their greatest
astronomers, was also a great astrologer; and his work on the latter
subject, “De Magnis Conjunctionibus, Annorum Revolutionibus ac eorum
Perfectionibus,” was long celebrated in Europe. Aboazen Haly (the
writer of a treatise “De Judiciis Astrorum”), who lived in Spain in
the thirteenth century, was one of the classical authors on this
subject.
It will easily be supposed that when this apotelesmatic or
judicial astrology obtained firm possession of men’s minds, it
would be pursued into innumerable subtle distinctions and extravagant
conceits; and the more so, as experience could offer little or no
check to such exercises of fancy and subtlety. For the correction of
rules of astrological divination by comparison with known events,
though pretended to by many professors of the art, was far too vague
and fallible a guidance to be of any real advantage. Even in what has
been called Natural Astrology, the dependence of the weather on the
heavenly bodies, it is easy to see what a vast accumulation of
well-observed facts is requisite to establish 223 any true rule; and it is well known how
long, in spite of facts, false and groundless rules (as the dependence
of the weather on the moon) may keep their hold on men’s minds. When
the facts are such loose and many-sided things as human characters,
passions, and happiness, it was hardly to be expected that even the
most powerful minds should be able to find a footing sufficiently
firm, to enable them to resist the impression of a theory constructed
of sweeping and bold assertions, and filled out into a complete system
of details. Accordingly, the connection of the stars with human
persons and actions was, for a long period, undisputed. The vague,
obscure, and heterogeneous character of such a connection, and its
unfitness for any really scientific reasoning, could, of course, never
be got rid of; and the bewildering feeling of earnestness and
solemnity, with which the connection of the heavens with man was
contemplated, never died away. In other respects, however, the
astrologers fell into a servile commentatorial spirit; and employed
themselves in annotating and illustrating the works of their
predecessors to a considerable extent, before the revival of true
science.
It may be mentioned, that astrology has long been, and probably is,
an art held in great esteem and admiration among other eastern nations
besides the Mohammedans; for instance, the Jews, the Indians, the
Siamese, and the Chinese. The prevalence of vague, visionary, and
barren notions among these nations, cannot surprise us; for with
regard to them we have no evidence, as with regard to Europeans we
have, that they are capable, on subjects of physical speculation, of
originating sound and rational general principles. The Arts may have
had their birth in all parts of the globe; but it is only Europe, at
particular favored periods of its history, which has ever produced
Sciences.
We are, however, now speaking of a long period, during which this
productive energy was interrupted and suspended. During this period
Europe descended, in intellectual character, to the level at which the
other parts of the world have always stood. Her Science was then a
mixture of Art and Mysticism; we have considered several forms of this
Mysticism, but there are two others which must not pass unnoticed,
Alchemy and Magic.
We may observe, before we proceed, that the deep and settled
influence which Astrology had obtained among them, appears perhaps
most strongly in the circumstance, that the most vigorous and
clear-sighted minds which were concerned in the revival of science,
did not, for a long period, shake off the persuasion that there was,
in this art, some element of truth. Roger Bacon, Cardan, Kepler, Tycho
Brahe, 224 Francis
Bacon, are examples of this. These, or most of them, rejected all the
more obvious and extravagant absurdities with which the subject had
been loaded; but still conceived that some real and valuable truth
remained when all these were removed. Thus Campanella,59 whom we shall have to speak of as one of the first opponents of
Aristotle, wrote an “Astrology purified from all the Superstitions of
the Jews and Arabians, and treated physiologically.”
59 Bacon, De Aug. iii. 4.
4. Alchemy.—Like other kinds of Mysticism, Alchemy
seems to have grown out of the notions of moral, personal, and
mythological qualities, which men associated with terms, of which the
primary application was to physical properties. This is the form in
which the subject is presented to us in the earliest writings which we
possess on the subject of chemistry;—those of Geber60 of Seville, who is supposed to have
lived in the eighth or ninth century. The very titles of Geber’s works
show the notions on which this pretended science proceeds. They are,
“Of the Search of Perfection;” “Of the Sum of Perfection, or of the
Perfect Magistery;” “Of the Invention of Verity, or Perfection.” The
basis of this phraseology is the distinction of metals into more or
less perfect; gold being the most perfect, as being the most
valuable, most beautiful, most pure, most durable; silver the next;
and so on. The “Search of Perfection” was, therefore, the attempt to
convert other metals into gold; and doctrines were adopted which
represented the metals as all compounded of the same elements, so that
this was theoretically possible. But the mystical trains of
association were pursued much further than this; gold and silver were
held to be the most noble of metals; gold was their King, and silver
their Queen. Mythological associations were called in aid of these
fancies, as had been done in astrology. Gold was Sol, silver was Luna,
the moon; copper, iron, tin, lead, were assigned to Venus, Mars,
Jupiter, Saturn. The processes of mixture and heat were spoken of as
personal actions and relations, struggles and victories. Some elements
were conquerors, some conquered; there existed preparations which
possessed the power of changing the whole of a body into a substance
of another kind: these were called magisteries.61 When gold and quicksilver are combined,
the king and the queen are married, to produce children of their own
kind. It will easily be conceived, that when chemical operations were
described in phraseology of this sort, the enthusiasm of the 225 fancy would be added
to that of the hopes, and observation would not be permitted to
correct the delusion, or to suggest sounder and more rational
views.
60 Thomson’s Hist. of Chem. i.
117.
61 Boyle, Thomson’s Hist. Ch.
i. 25. Carolus Musitanus.
The exaggeration of the vague notion of perfection and power in the
object of the alchemist’s search, was carried further still. The same
preparation which possessed the faculty of turning baser metals into
gold, was imagined to be also a universal medicine, to have the gift
of curing or preventing diseases, prolonging life, producing bodily
strength and beauty: the philosophers’ stone was finally
invested with every desirable efficacy which the fancy of the
“philosophers” could devise.
It has been usual to say that Alchemy was the mother of Chemistry;
and that men would never have made the experiments on which the real
science is founded, if they had not been animated by the hopes and the
energy which the delusive art inspired. To judge whether this is truly
said, we must be able to estimate the degree of interest which men
feel in purely speculative truth, and in the real and substantial
improvement of art to which it leads. Since the fall of Alchemy, and
the progress of real Chemistry, these motives have been powerful
enough to engage in the study of the science, a body far larger than
the Alchemists ever were, and no less zealous. There is no apparent
reason why the result should not have been the same, if the progress
of true science had begun sooner. Astronomy was long cultivated
without the bribe of Astrology. But, perhaps, we may justly say
this;—that, in the stationary period, men’s minds were so far
enfeebled and degraded, that pure speculative truth had not its full
effect upon them; and the mystical pursuits in which some dim and
disfigured images of truth were sought with avidity, were among the
provisions by which the human soul, even when sunk below its best
condition, is perpetually directed to something above the mere objects
of sense and appetite;—a contrivance of compensation, as it
were, in the intellectual and spiritual constitution of man.
5. Magic.—Magical Arts, so far as they were believed
in by those who professed to practise them, and so far as they have a
bearing in science, stand on the same footing as astrology; and,
indeed, a close alliance has generally been maintained between the two
pursuits. Incapacity and indisposition to perceive natural and
philosophical causation, an enthusiastic imagination, and such a faith
as can devise and maintain supernatural and spiritual connexions, are
the elements of this, as of other forms of Mysticism. And thus, that
temper which led men to aim at the magician’s supposed authority over
the elements, 226
is an additional exemplification of those habits of thought which
prevented the progress of real science, and the acquisition of that
command over nature which is founded on science, during the interval
now before us.
But there is another aspect under which the opinions connected with
this pursuit may serve to illustrate the mental character of the
Stationary Period.
The tendency, during the middle ages, to attribute the character of
Magician to almost all persons eminent for great speculative or
practical knowledge, is a feature of those times, which shows how
extensive and complete was the inability to apprehend the nature of
real science. In cultivated and enlightened periods, such as those of
ancient Greece, or modern Europe, knowledge is wished for and admired,
even by those who least possess it: but in dark and degraded periods,
superior knowledge is a butt for hatred and fear. In the one case,
men’s eyes are open; their thoughts are clear; and, however high the
philosopher may be raised above the multitude, they can catch glimpses
of the intervening path, and see that it is free to all, and that
elevation is the reward of energy and labor. In the other case, the
crowd are not only ignorant, but spiritless; they have lost the
pleasure in knowledge, the appetite for it, and the feeling of dignity
which it gives: there is no sympathy which connects them with the
learned man: they see him above them, but know not how he is raised or
supported: he becomes an object of aversion and envy, of vague
suspicion and terror; and these emotions are embodied and confirmed by
association with the fancies and dogmas of superstition. To consider
superior knowledge as Magic, and Magic as a detestable and criminal
employment, was the form which these feelings of dislike assumed; and
at one period in the history of Europe, almost every one who had
gained any eminent literary fame, was spoken of as a magician.
Naudæus, a learned Frenchman, in the seventeenth century, wrote “An
Apology for all the Wise Men who have been unjustly reported
Magicians, from the Creation to the present Age.” The list of persons
whom he thus thinks it necessary to protect, are of various classes
and ages. Alkindi, Geber, Artephius, Thebit, Raymund Lully, Arnold de
Villâ Novâ, Peter of Apono, and Paracelsus, had incurred the black
suspicion as physicians or alchemists. Thomas Aquinas, Roger Bacon,
Michael Scott, Picus of Mirandula, and Trithemius, had not escaped it,
though ministers of religion. Even dignitaries, such as Robert
Grosteste, Bishop of Lincoln, Albertus Magnus, Bishop of Ratisbon,
227 Popes Sylvester
the Second, and Gregory the Seventh, had been involved in the wide
calumny. In the same way in which the vulgar confounded the eminent
learning and knowledge which had appeared in recent times, with skill
in dark and supernatural arts, they converted into wizards all the
best-known names in the rolls of fame; as Aristotle, Solomon, Joseph,
Pythagoras; and, finally, the poet Virgil was a powerful and skilful
necromancer, and this fancy was exemplified by many strange stories of
his achievements and practices.
The various results of the tendency of the human mind to mysticism,
which we have here noticed, form prominent features in the
intellectual character of the world, for a long course of centuries.
The theosophy and theurgy of the Neoplatonists, the mystical
arithmetic of the Pythagoreans and their successors, the predictions
of the astrologers, the pretences of alchemy and magic, represent, not
unfairly, the general character and disposition of men’s thoughts,
with reference to philosophy and science. That there were stronger
minds, which threw off in a greater or less degree this train of
delusive and unsubstantial ideas, is true; as, on the other hand,
Mysticism, among the vulgar or the foolish, often went to an extent of
extravagance and superstition, of which I have not attempted to convey
any conception. The lesson which the preceding survey teaches us is,
that during the Stationary Period, Mysticism, in its various forms,
was a leading character, both of the common mind, and of the
speculations of the most intelligent and profound reasoners; and that
this Mysticism was the opposite of that habit of thought which we have
stated Science to require; namely, clear Ideas, distinctly employed to
connect well-ascertained Facts; inasmuch as the Ideas in which it
dealt were vague and unstable, and the temper in which they were
contemplated was an urgent and aspiring enthusiasm, which could not
submit to a calm conference with experience upon even terms. The
fervor of thought in some degree supplied the place of reason in
producing belief; but opinions so obtained had no enduring value; they
did not exhibit a permanent record of old truths, nor a firm
foundation for new. Experience collected her stores in vain, or ceased
to collect them, when she had only to pour them into the flimsy folds
of the lap of Mysticism; who was, in truth, so much absorbed in
looking for the treasures which were to fall from the skies, that she
heeded little how scantily she obtained, or how loosely she held, such
riches as might be found near her. 228</div></body></text></TEI>