<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="138">CHAPTER VII.
Progress of Physical Geology.

Sect. 1.—Object and Distinctions of
Physical Geology.
BEING, in consequence of the
steps which we have attempted to describe, in possession of two
sciences, one of which traces the laws of action of known causes, and
the other describes the phenomena which the earth’s surface presents,
we are now prepared to examine how far the attempts to refer the facts
to their causes have been successful: we are ready to enter upon the
consideration of Theoretical or Physical Geology, as, by
analogy with Physical Astronomy, we may term this branch of
speculation.
The distinction of this from other portions of our knowledge is
sufficiently evident. In former times, Geology was always associated
with Mineralogy, and sometimes confounded with it; but the mistake of
such an arrangement must be clear, from what has been said. Geology is
connected with Mineralogy, only so far as the latter science
classifies a large portion of the objects which Geology employs as
evidence of its statements. To confound the two is the same error as
it would be to treat philosophical history as identical with the
knowledge of medals. Geology procures evidence of her conclusions
wherever she can; from minerals or from seas; from inorganic or from
organic bodies; from the ground or from the skies. The geologist’s
business is to learn the past history of the earth; and he is no more
limited to one or a few kinds of documents, as his sources of
information, than is the historian of man, in the execution of a
similar task.
Physical Geology, of which I now speak, may not be always easily
separable from Descriptive Geology: in fact, they have generally been
combined, for few have been content to describe, without attempting in
some measure to explain. Indeed, if they had done so, it is 580 probable that their
labors would have been far less zealous, and their expositions far
less impressive. We by no means regret, therefore, the mixture of
these two kinds of knowledge, which has so often occurred; but still,
it is our business to separate them. The works of astronomers before
the rise of sound physical astronomy, were full of theories, but these
were advantageous, not prejudicial, to the progress of the
science.
Geological theories have been abundant and various; but yet our
history of them must be brief. For our object is, as must be borne in
mind, to exhibit these, only so far as they are steps discoverably
tending to the true theory of the earth: and in most of them
we do not trace this character. Or rather, the portions of the labors
of geologists which do merit this praise, belong to the two preceding
divisions of the subject, and have been treated of there.
The history of Physical Geology, considered as the advance towards
a science as real and stable as those which we have already treated of
(and this is the form in which we ought to trace it), hitherto
consists of few steps. We hardly know whether the progress is begun.
The history of Physical Astronomy almost commences with Newton, and
few persons will venture to assert that the Newton of Geology has yet
appeared.
Still, some examination of the attempts which have been made is
requisite, in order to explain and justify the view which the analogy
of scientific history leads us to take, of the state of the subject.
Though far from intending to give even a sketch of all past geological
speculations, I must notice some of the forms such speculations have
at different times assumed.
Sect. 2.—Of Fanciful Geological Opinions.
Real and permanent geological
knowledge, like all other physical knowledge, can be obtained only by
inductions of classification and law from many clearly seen phenomena.
The labor of the most active, the talent of the most intelligent, are
requisite for such a purpose. But far less than this is sufficient to
put in busy operation the inventive and capricious fancy. A few
appearances hastily seen, and arbitrarily interpreted, are enough to
give rise to a wondrous tale of the past, full of strange events and
supernatural agencies. The mythology and early poetry of nations
afford sufficient evidence of man’s love of the wonderful, and of his
inventive powers, in early stages of intellectual development. The
scientific faculty, on the other hand, 581 and especially that part of it which is
requisite for the induction of laws from facts, emerges slowly and
with difficulty from the crowd of adverse influences, even under the
most favorable circumstances. We have seen that in the ancient world,
the Greeks alone showed themselves to possess this talent; and what
they thus attained to, amounted only to a few sound doctrines in
astronomy, and one or two extremely imperfect truths in mechanics,
optics, and music, which their successors were unable to retain. No
other nation, till we come to the dawn of a better day in modern
Europe, made any positive step at all in sound physical speculation.
Empty dreams or useless exhibitions of ingenuity, formed the whole of
their essays at such knowledge.
It must, therefore, independently of positive evidence, be
considered as extremely improbable, that any of these nations should,
at an early period, have arrived, by observation and induction, at
wide general truths, such as the philosophers of modern times have
only satisfied themselves of by long and patient labor and thought. If
resemblances should be discovered between the assertions of ancient
writers and the discoveries of modern science, the probability in all
cases, the certainty in most, is that these are accidental
coincidences;—that the ancient opinion is no anticipation of the
modern discovery, but is one guess among many, not a whit the more
valuable because its expression agrees with a truth. The author of the
guess could not intend the truth, because his mind was not prepared to
comprehend it. Those of the ancients who spoke of the harmony
which binds all things together, could not mean the Newtonian
gravitation, because they had never been led to conceive an attractive
force, governed by definite mathematical laws in its quantity and
operation.
In agreement with these views, we must, I conceive, estimate the
opinions which we find among the ancients, respecting the changes
which the earth’s surface has undergone. These opinions, when they are
at all of a general kind, are arbitrary fictions of the fancy, showing
man’s love of generality indeed, but indulging it without that expense
of labor and thought which alone can render it legitimate.
We might, therefore, pass by all the traditions and speculations of
Oriental, Egyptian, and Greek cosmogony, as extraneous to our subject.
But since these have recently been spoken of, as conclusions
collected, however vaguely, from observed facts,95 we may make a
remark or two upon them.
95 Lyell, B. i. c. ii. p. 8. (4th
ed.)
582 The notion
of a series of creations and destructions of worlds, which appears in
the sacred volume of the Hindoos, which formed part of the
traditionary lore of Egypt, and which was afterwards adopted into the
poetry and philosophy of Greece, must be considered as a mythological,
not a physical, doctrine. When this doctrine was dwelt upon, men’s
thoughts were directed, not to the terrestrial facts which it seemed
to explain, but to the attributes of the deities which it illustrated.
The conception of a Supreme power, impelling and guiding the progress
of events, which is permanent among all perpetual change, and regular
among all seeming chance, was readily entertained by contemplative and
enthusiastic minds; and when natural phenomena were referred to this
doctrine, it was rather for the purpose of fastening its
impressiveness upon the senses, than in the way of giving to it
authority and support. Hence we perceive that in the exposition of
this doctrine, an attempt was always made to fill and elevate the mind
with the notions of marvellous events, and of infinite times, in which
vast cycles of order recurred. The “great year,” in which all
celestial phenomena come round, offered itself as capable of being
calculated; and a similar great year was readily assumed for
terrestrial and human events. Hence there were to be brought round by
great cycles, not only deluges and conflagrations which were to
destroy and renovate the earth, but also the series of historical
occurrences. Not only the sea and land were to recommence their
alternations, but there was to be another Argo, which should carry
warriors on the first sea-foray,96 and another
succession of heroic wars. Looking at the passages of ancient authors
which refer to terrestrial changes in this view, we shall see that
they are addressed almost entirely to the love of the marvellous and
the infinite, and cannot with propriety be taken as indications of a
spirit of physical philosophy. For example, if we turn to the
celebrated passage in Ovid,97 where
Pythagoras is represented as asserting that land becomes sea, and sea
land, and many other changes which geologists have verified, we find
that these observations are associated with many fables, as being
matter of exactly the same kind;—the fountain of Ammon which was
cold by day and warm by night;98—the
waters of Salmacis which effeminate men;—the Clitorian spring
which makes them loathe wine;—the Simplegades islands which were
once moveable;—the Tritonian lake which covered men’s bodies
with feathers;—and many similar marvels. And the general purport
of 583 the whole
is, to countenance the doctrine of the metempsychosis, and the
Pythagorean injunction of not eating animal food. It is clear, I
think, that facts so introduced must be considered as having been
contemplated rather in the spirit of poetry than of science.
96 Virg. Eclog. 4.
97 Met. Lib. xv.
98 V. 309, &c.
We must estimate in the same manner, the very remarkable passage
brought to light by M. Elie de Beaumont,99 from the
Arabian writer, Kazwiri; in which we have a representation of the same
spot of ground, as being, at successive intervals of five hundred
years, a city, a sea, a desert, and again a city. This invention is
adduced, I conceive, rather to feed the appetite of wonder, than to
fix it upon any reality: as the title of his book, The Marvels of
Nature obviously intimates.
99 Ann. des Sc. Nat. xxv.
380.
The speculations of Aristotle, concerning the exchanges of land and
sea which take place in long periods, are not formed in exactly the
same spirit, but they are hardly more substantial; and seem to be
quite as arbitrary, since they are not confirmed by any examples and
proofs. After stating,100 that the same spots of the earth are
not always land and always water, he gives the reason. “The principle
and cause of this is,” he says, “that the inner parts of the earth,
like the bodies of plants and animals, have their ages of vigor and of
decline; but in plants and animals all the parts are in vigor, and all
grow old, at once: in the earth different parts arrive at maturity at
different times by the operation of cold and heat: they grow and decay
on account of the sun and the revolution of the stars, and thus the
parts of the earth acquire different power, so that for a certain time
they remain moist, and then become dry and old: and then other places
are revivified, and become partially watery.” We are, I conceive,
doing no injustice to such speculations by classing them among
fanciful geological opinions.
100 Meteorol. i. 14.
We must also, I conceive, range in the same division another class
of writers of much more modern times;—I mean those who have
trained their geology by interpretations of Scripture. I have already
endeavored to show that such an attempt is a perversion of the purpose
of a divine communication, and cannot lead to any physical truth. I do
not here speak of geological speculations in which the Mosaic account
of the deluge has been referred to; for whatever errors may have been
committed on that subject, it would be as absurd to disregard the most
ancient historical record, in attempting to trace back the history of
the earth, as it would be, gratuitously to reject any other 584 source of
information. But the interpretations of the account of the creation
have gone further beyond the limits of sound philosophy: and when we
look at the arbitrary and fantastical inventions by which a few
phrases of the writings of Moses have been moulded into complete
systems, we cannot doubt that these interpretations belong to the
present Section.
I shall not attempt to criticize, nor even to enumerate, these
Scriptural Geologies,—Sacred Theories of the Earth, as
Burnet termed his. Ray, Woodward, Whiston, and many other persons to
whom science has considerable obligations, were involved, by the
speculative habits of their times, in these essays; and they have been
resumed by persons of considerable talent and some knowledge, on
various occasions up to the present day; but the more geology has been
studied on its own proper evidence, the more have geologists seen the
unprofitable character of such labors.
I proceed now to the next step in the progress of Theoretical
Geology.
Sect. 3.—Of Premature Geological
Theories.
While we were giving our
account of Descriptive Geology, the attentive reader would perceive
that we did, in fact, state several steps in the advance towards
general knowledge; but when, in those cases, the theoretical aspect of
such discoveries softened into an appearance of mere classification,
the occurrence was assigned to the history of Descriptive rather than
of Theoretical Geology. Of such a kind was the establishment, by a
long and vehement controversy, of the fact, that the impressions in
rocks are really the traces of ancient living things; such, again,
were the division of rocks into Primitive, Secondary, Tertiary; the
ascertainment of the orderly succession of organic remains: the
consequent fixation of a standard series of formations and strata; the
establishment of the igneous nature of trap rocks; and the like. These
are geological truths which are assumed and implied in the very
language which geology uses; thus showing how in this, as in all other
sciences, the succeeding steps involve the preceding. But in the
history of geological theory, we have to consider the wider attempts
to combine the facts, and to assign them to their causes.
The close of the last century produced two antagonist theories of
this kind, which long maintained a fierce and doubtful
struggle;—that of Werner and that of Hutton: the one termed
Neptunian, from its 585 ascribing the phenomena of the earth’s
surface mainly to aqueous agency; the other Plutonian or
Vulcanian, because it employed the force of subterraneous fire
as its principal machinery. The circumstance which is most worthy of
notice in these remarkable essays is, the endeavor to give, by means
of such materials as the authors possessed, a complete and simple
account of all the facts of the earth’s history. The Saxon professor,
proceeding on the examination of a small district in Germany,
maintained the existence of a chaotic fluid, from which a series of
universal formations had been precipitated, the position of the strata
being broken up by the falling in of subterraneous cavities, in the
intervals between these depositions. The Scotch philosopher, who had
observed in England and Scotland, thought himself justified in
declaring that the existing causes were sufficient to spread new
strata on the bottom of the ocean, and that they are consolidated,
elevated, and fractured by volcanic heat, so as to give rise to new
continents.
It will hardly be now denied that all that is to remain as
permanent science in each of these systems must be proved by the
examination of many cases and limited by many conditions and
circumstances. Theories so wide and simple, were consistent only with
a comparatively scanty collection of facts, and belong to the early
stage of geological knowledge. In the progress of the science, the
“theory” of each part of the earth must come out of the examination of
that part, combined with all that is well established, concerning all
the rest; and a general theory must result from the comparison of all
such partial theoretical views. Any attempt to snatch it before its
time must fail; and therefore we may venture at present to designate
general theories, like those of Hutton and Werner, as
premature.
This, indeed, is the sentiment of most of the good geologists of
the present day. The time for such general systems, and for the fierce
wars to which the opposition of such generalities gives rise, is
probably now past for ever; and geology will not again witness such a
controversy as that of the Wernerian and Huttonian schools.

.  . . . . .  As when
two black clouds
With heaven’s artillery fraught, come rattling
on
Over the Caspian: then stand front to
front,
Hovering a space, till winds the signal
blow
To join their dark encounter in mid-air.
So frowned the mighty combatants, that hell
Grew darker at their frown; so matched they
stood:
For never but once more was either like
To meet so great a foe.

586 The main points really affecting the progress of sound theoretical
geology, will find a place in one of the two next Sections.
[2nd Ed.] [I think I do no injustice to Dr. Hutton in describing
his theory of the earth as premature. Prof. Playfair’s elegant
work, Illustrations of the Huttonian Theory (1802,) so justly
admired, contains many doctrines which the more mature geology of
modern times rejects; such as the igneous origin of chalk-flints,
siliceous pudding stone, and the like; the universal formation of
river-beds by the rivers themselves; and other points. With regard to
this last-mentioned question, I think all who have read Deluc’s
Geologie (1810) will deem his refutation of Playfair
complete.
But though Hutton’s theory was premature, as well as Werner’s, the
former had a far greater value as an important step on the road to
truth. Many of its boldest hypotheses and generalizations have become
a part of the general creed of geologists; and its publication is
perhaps the greatest event which has yet occurred in the progress of
Physical Geology.]
</div></body></text></TEI>