<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="11">

BOOK III.

THE GREEK ASTRONOMY.

INTRODUCTION.
THE mathematical opinions of
Plato respecting the philosophy of nature, and especially respecting
what we commonly call “the heavenly bodies,” the Sun, Moon, and
Planets, were founded upon the view which I have already described:
namely, that it is the business of philosophy to aim at a truth higher
than observation can teach; and to solve problems which the phenomena
of the universe only suggest. And though the students of nature in
more recent times have learnt that this is too presumptuous a notion
of human knowledge, yet the very boldness and hopefulness which it
involved impelled men in the pursuit of truth, with more vigor than a
more timorous temper could have done; and the belief that there must
be, in nature, mathematical laws more exact than experience could
discover, stimulated men often to discover true laws, though often
also to invent false laws. Plato’s writings, supplying examples of
both these processes, belong to the Prelude of true Astronomy, as well
as to the errors of false philosophy. We may find specimens of both
kinds in those parts of his Dialogues to which we have referred in the
preceding Book of our History.
To Plato’s merits in preparing the way for the Theory of Epicycles,
I have already referred in Chapter ii. of
this Book. I conceive that he had a great share in that which is an
important step in every discovery, the proposing distinctly the
problem to be solved; which was, in this case, as he states it, To
account for the apparent movements of the planets by a combination of
two circular motions for each:—the motion of identity, and the
motion of difference. (Tim. 39, a.) In
the tenth Book of the Republic, quoted in our text, the spindle
which Destiny or Necessity holds between her knees, and on which are
rings, by means of which the planets revolve round it as an axis, is a
step towards the conception of the problem, as the construction of a
machine.
It will not be thought surprising that Plato expected that 504 Astronomy, when
further advanced, would be able to render an account of many things
for which she has not accounted even to this day. Thus, in the passage
in the seventh Book of the Republic, he says that the
philosopher requires a reason for the proportion of the day to the
month, and the month to the year, deeper and more substantial than
mere observation can give. Yet Astronomy has not yet shown us any
reason why the proportion of the times of the earth’s rotation on its
axis, the moon’s revolution round the earth, and the earth’s
revolution round the sun, might not have been made by the Creator
quite different from what they are. But in thus asking Mathematical
Astronomy for reasons which she cannot give, Plato was only doing what
a great astronomical discoverer, Kepler, did at a later period. One of
the questions which Kepler especially wished to have answered was, why
there are five planets, and why at such particular distances from the
sun? And it is still more curious that he thought he had found the
reason of these things, in the relations of those Five Regular Solids
which, as we have seen, Plato was desirous of
introducing into the philosophy of the universe. We have Kepler’s
account of this, his imaginary discovery, in the Mysterium
Cosmographicum, published in 1596, as stated in our History, Book
v. Chap. iv. Sect. 2.
Kepler regards the law which thus determines the number and
magnitude of the planetary orbits by means of the five regular solids
as a discovery no less remarkable and certain than the Three Laws
which give his name its imperishable place in the history of
astronomy.
We are not on this account to think that there is no steady
criterion of the difference between imaginary and real discoveries in
science. As discovery becomes possible by the liberty of guessing, it
becomes real by allowing observation constantly and authoritatively to
determine the value of guesses. Kepler added to Plato’s boldness of
fancy his own patient and candid habit of testing his fancies by a
rigorous and laborious comparison with the phenomena; and thus his
discoveries led to those of Newton. 505
CHAPTER I.
Earliest Stages of Astronomy.

The Globular Form of the
Earth.
THERE are parts of Plato’s
writings which have been adduced as bearing upon the subsequent
progress of science; and especially upon the globular form of the
earth, and the other views which led to the discovery of America. In
the Timæus we read of a great continent lying in the Ocean west
of the Pillars of Hercules, which Plato calls Atlantis. He
makes the personage in his Dialogue who speaks of this put it forward
as an Egyptian tradition. M. H. Martin, who has discussed what has
been written respecting the Atlantis of Plato, and has given therein a
dissertation rich in erudition and of the most lively interest,
conceives that Plato’s notions on this subject arose from his
combining his conviction of the spherical form of the earth, with
interpretations of Homer, and perhaps with traditions which were
current in Egypt (Etudes sur le Timée, Note xiii. § ix.). He
does not consider that the belief in Plato’s Atlantis had any share in
the discoveries of Columbus.
It may perhaps surprise modern readers who have a difficulty in
getting rid of the persuasion that there is a natural direction
upwards and a natural direction downwards, to learn that
both Plato and Aristotle, and of course other philosophers also, had
completely overcome this difficulty. They were quite ready to allow
and to conceive that down meant nothing but towards some
centre, and up, the opposite direction. (Aristotle has,
besides, an ingenious notion that while heavy bodies, as earth and
water, tend to the centre, and light bodies, as fire, tend from the
centre, the fifth element, of which the heavenly bodies are composed,
tends to move round the centre.)
Plato explains this in the most decided manner in the Timæus
(62, c). “It is quite erroneous to suppose
that there are two opposite regions in the universe, one above and the
other below; and that heavy things naturally tend to the latter place.
The heavens are spherical, and every thing tends to the centre; and
thus above and below have no real meaning. If there be a
solid globe in the middle, 506 and if a person walk round it, he will
become the antipodes to himself, and the direction which is up
at one time will be down at another.”
The notion of antipodes, the inhabitants of the part of the
globe of the earth opposite to ourselves, was very familiar. Thus in
Cicero’s Academic Questions (ii. 39) one of the speakers says,
“Etiam dicitis esse e regione nobis, e contraria parte terræ, qui
adversis vestigiis stant contra nostra vestigia, quos Antipodas
vocatis.” See also Tusc. Disp. i. 28 and v. 24.
The Heliocentric System among the
Ancients.
As the more clear-sighted of the ancients had overcome the natural
prejudice of believing that there is an absolute up and
down, so had they also overcome the natural prejudice of
believing that the earth is at rest. Cicero says (Acad. Quest.
ii. 39), “Hicetas of Syracuse, as Theophrastus tells us, thinks that
the heavens, the sun, the moon, the stars, do not move; and that
nothing does move but the earth. The earth revolves about her axis
with immense velocity; and thus the same effect is produced as if the
earth were at rest and the heavens moved; and this, he says, Plato
teaches in the Timæus, though somewhat obscurely.” Of course
the assertion that the moon and planets do not move, was meant of the
diurnal motion only. The passage referred to in the Timæus
seems to be this (40, c)—“As to the
Earth, which is our nurse, and which clings to the axis which
stretches through the universe, God made her the producer and
preserver of day and night.” The word εἱλλομένην, which I have
translated clings to, some translate revolves; and an
extensive controversy has prevailed, both in ancient and modern times
(beginning with Aristotle), whether Plato did or did not believe in
the rotation of the earth on her axis. (See M. Cousin’s Note on the
Timæus, and M. Henri Martin’s Dissertation, Note xxxvii., in
his Etudes sur le Timée.) The result of this discussion seems
to be that, in the Timæus, the Earth is supposed to be at rest.
It is however related by Plutarch (Platonic Questions, viii.
1), that Plato in his old age repented of having given to the Earth
the place in the centre of the universe which did not belong to
it.
In describing the Prelude to the Epoch of Copernicus (Book v. Chap. i.), I have spoken of Philolaus, one of
the followers of Pythagoras, who lived at the time of Socrates, as
having held the doctrine that the earth revolves about the sun. This
has been a current 507 opinion;—so current, indeed, that
the Abbé Bouillaud, or Bullialdus, as we more commonly call him, gave
the title of Philolaus to the defence of Copernicus which he
published in 1639; and Chiaramonti, an Aristotelian, published his
answer under the title of Antiphilolaus. In 1645 Bullialdus
published his Astronomia Philolaica, which was another
exposition of the heliocentric doctrine.
Yet notwithstanding this general belief, it appears to be tolerably
certain that Philolaus did not hold the doctrine of the earth’s motion
round the sun. (M. H. Martin, Etudes sur le Timée, 1841, Note
xxxvii. Sect. i.; and Bœckh, De vera Indole Astronomiæ
Philolaicæ, 1810.) In the system of Philolaus, the earth revolved
about the central fire; but this central fire was not the
sun. The Sun, along with the moon and planets, revolved in circles
external to the earth. The Earth had the Antichthon or
Counter-Earth between it and the centre; and revolving round
this centre in one day, the Antichthon, being always between it and
the centre, was, during a portion of the revolution, interposed
between the Earth and the Sun, and thus made night; while the Sun, by
his proper motion, produced the changes of the year.
When men were willing to suppose the earth to be in motion, in
order to account for the recurrence of day and night, it is curious
that they did not see that the revolution of a spherical earth about
an axis passing through its centre was a scheme both simple and quite
satisfactory. Yet the illumination of a globular earth by a distant
sun, and the circumstances and phenomena thence resulting, appear to
have been conceived in a very confused manner by many persons. Thus
Tacitus (Agric. xii.), after stating that he has heard that in
the northern part of the island of Britain, the night disappears in
the height of summer, says, as his account of this phenomenon, that
“the extreme parts of the earth are low and level, and do not throw
their shadow upwards; so that the shade of night falls below the sky
and the stars.” But, as a little consideration will show, it is the
globular form of the earth, and not the level character of the
country, which produces this effect.
It is not in any degree probable that Pythagoras taught that the
Earth revolves round the Sun, or that it rotates on its own axis. Nor
did Plato hold either of these motions of the Earth. They got so far
as to believe in the Spherical Form of the Earth; and this was
apparently such an effort that the human mind made a pause before
going any further. “It required,” says M. H. Martin, “a great struggle
for 508 men to free
themselves from the prejudices of the senses, and to interpret their
testimony in such a manner as to conceive the sphericity of the earth.
It is natural that they should have stopped at this point, before
putting the earth in motion in space.”
Some of the expressions which have been understood, as describing a
system in which the Sun is the centre of motion, do really
imply merely the Sun is the middle term of the series of
heavenly bodies which revolve round the earth: the series being Moon,
Mercury, Venus, Sun, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn. This is the case, for
instance, in a passage of Cicero’s Vision of Scipio, which has
been supposed to imply, (as I have stated in
the History,) that Mercury and Venus revolve about the Sun.
But though the doctrine of the diurnal rotation and annual
revolution of the earth is not the doctrine of Pythagoras, or of
Philolaus, or of Plato, it was nevertheless held by some of the
philosophers of antiquity. The testimony of Archimedes that this
doctrine was held by his contemporary Aristarchus of Samos, is
unquestionable  and there is no reason to doubt Plutarch’s assertion
that Seleucus further enforced it.
It is curious that Copernicus appears not to have known anything of
the opinions of Aristarchus and Seleucus, which were really
anticipations of his doctrine; and to have derived his notion from
passages which, as I have been showing, contain no such doctrine. He
says, in his Dedication to Pope Paul III., “I found in Cicero that
Nicetas [or Hicetas] held that the earth was in motion: and in
Plutarch I found that some others had been of that opinion: and his
words I will transcribe that any one may read them: ‘Philosophers in
general hold that the earth is at rest. But Philolaus the Pythagorean
teaches that it moves round the central fire in an oblique circle, in
the same direction as the Sun and the Moon. Heraclides of Pontus and
Ecphantus the Pythagorean give the earth a motion, but not a motion of
translation; they make it revolve like a wheel about its own centre
from west to east.’” This last opinion was a correct assertion of the
diurnal motion.
The Eclipse of Thales.
“The Eclipse of Thales” is so remarkable a
point in the history of astronomy, and has been the subject of so much
discussion among astronomers, that it ought to be more especially
noticed. The original 509 record is in the first Book of
Herodotus’s History (chap. lxxiv.) He says that there was a war
between the Lydians and the Medes; and after various turns of fortune,
“in the sixth year a conflict took place; and on the battle being
joined, it happened that the day suddenly became night. And this
change, Thales of Miletus had predicted to them, definitely naming
this year, in which the event really took place. The Lydians and the
Medes, when they saw day turned into night, ceased from fighting; and
both sides were desirous of peace.” Probably this prediction was
founded upon the Chaldean period of eighteen years, of which I have
spoken in Section 11. It is probable, as I
have already said, that this period was discovered by noticing the
recurrence of eclipses. It is to be observed that Thales predicted
only the year of the eclipse, not the day or the month. In fact, the
exact prediction of the circumstances of an eclipse of the sun is a
very difficult problem; much more difficult, it may be remarked, than
the prediction of the circumstance of an eclipse of the moon.
Now that the Theory of the Moon is brought so far towards
completeness, astronomers are able to calculate backwards the eclipses
of the sun which have taken place in former times; and the question
has been much discussed in what year this Eclipse of Thales really
occurred. The Memoir of Mr. Airy, the Astronomer Royal, on this
subject, in the Phil. Trans. for 1853, gives an account of the
modern examinations of this subject. Mr. Airy starts from the
assumption that the eclipse must have been one decidedly total; the
difference between such a one and an eclipse only nearly
total being very marked. A total eclipse alone was likely to produce
so strong an effect on the minds of the combatants. Mr. Airy concludes
from his calculations that the eclipse predicted by Thales took place
b. c. 585.
Ancient eclipses of the Moon and Sun, if they can be identified,
are of great value for modern astronomy; for in the long interval of
between two and three thousand years which separates them from our
time, those of the inequalities, that is, accelerations or
retardations of the Moon’s motion, which go on increasing
constantly,4 accumulate to a large amount; so that
the actual time and circumstances of the eclipse give astronomers the
means of determining what the rate of these accelerations or
retardations has been. Accordingly Mr. Airy has discussed, as even
more important than the eclipse of Thales, an eclipse which Diodorus
relates to have happened during an expedition of 510 Agathocles, the ruler
of Sicily, and which is hence known as the Eclipse of Agathocles. He
determines it to have occurred b. c. 310.</div></body></text></TEI>