<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="29">CHAPTER  III.
Sequel to the Epoch of Galileo.—Period of
Verification and Deduction.
THE evidence on which Galileo
rested the truth of the Laws of Motion which he asserted, was, as we
have seen, the simplicity of the laws themselves, and the agreement of
their consequences with facts; proper allowances being made for
disturbing causes. His successors took up and continued the task of
making repeated comparisons of the theory with practice, till no doubt
remained of the exactness of the fundamental doctrines: they also
employed themselves in simplifying, as much as possible, the mode of
stating these doctrines, and in tracing their consequences in various
problems by the aid of mathematical reasoning. These employments led
to the publication of various Treatises on Falling Bodies, Inclined
Planes, Pendulums, Projectiles, Spouting Fluids, which occupied a
great part of the seventeenth century.
The authors of these treatises may be considered as the School of
Galileo. Several of them were, indeed, his pupils or personal friends.
Castelli was his disciple and astronomical assistant at Florence, and
afterwards his correspondent. Torricelli was at first a pupil of
Castelli, but became the inmate and amanuensis of Galileo in 1641, and
succeeded him in his situation at the court of Florence on his death,
which took place a few months afterwards. Viviani formed one of his
family during the three last years of his life; and surviving him and
his contemporaries (for Viviani lived even into the eighteenth
century), has a manifest pleasure and pride in calling himself the
last of the disciples of Galileo. Gassendi, an eminent French
mathematician and professor, visited him in 1628; and it shows us the
extent of his reputation when we find Milton referring thus to his
travels in Italy:24 “There it was that I found and visited
the famous Galileo, grown old, a prisoner in the Inquisition, for
thinking in astronomy otherwise than the Franciscan and Dominican
licensers thought.”
24 Speech for the Liberty of
Unlicensed Printing.
Besides the above writers, we may mention, as persons who pursued
and illustrated Galileo’s doctrines, Borelli, who was professor at
Florence and Pisa; Mersenne, the correspondent of Descartes, who was
341 professor at
Paris; Wallis, who was appointed Savilian professor at Oxford in 1649,
his predecessor being ejected by the parliamentary commissioners. It
is not necessary for us to trace the progress of purely mathematical
inventions, which constitute a great part of the works of these
authors; but a few circumstances may be mentioned.
The question of the proof of the Second Law of Motion was, from the
first, identified with the controversy respecting the truth of the
Copernican System; for this law supplied the true answer to the most
formidable of the objections against the motion of the earth; namely,
that if the earth were moving, bodies which were dropt from an
elevated object would be left behind by the place from which they
fell. This argument was reproduced in various forms by the opponents
of the new doctrine; and the answers to the argument, though they
belong to the history of Astronomy, and form part of the Sequel to the
Epoch of Copernicus, belong more peculiarly to the history of
Mechanics, and are events in the sequel to the Discoveries of Galileo.
So far, indeed, as the mechanical controversy was concerned, the
advocates of the Second Law of Motion appealed, very triumphantly, to
experiment. Gassendi made many experiments on this subject publicly,
of which an account is given in his Epistolæ tres de Motu Impresso
a Motore Translato25 It appeared in these experiments, that
bodies let fall downwards, or cast upwards, forwards, or backwards,
from a ship, or chariot, or man, whether at rest, or in any degree of
motion, had always the same motion relatively to the motor.
In the application of this principle to the system of the world,
indeed, Gassendi and other philosophers of his time were greatly
hampered; for the deference which religious scruples required, did not
allow them to say that the earth really moved, but only that the
physical reasons against its motion were invalid. This restriction
enabled Riccioli and other writers on the geocentric side to involve
the subject in metaphysical difficulties; but the conviction of men
was not permanently shaken by these, and the Second Law of Motion was
soon assumed as unquestioned.
25 Mont. ii. 199.
The Laws of the Motion of Falling Bodies, as assigned by Galileo,
were confirmed by the reasonings of Gassendi and Fermat, and the
experiments of Riccioli and Grimaldi; and the effect of resistance was
pointed out by Mersenne and Dechales. The parabolic motion of
Projectiles was more especially illustrated by experiments on the jet
which spouts from an orifice in a vessel full of fluid. This mode of
experimenting 342
is well adapted to attract notice, since the curve described, which is
transient and invisible in the case of a single projectile, becomes
permanent and visible when we have a continuous stream. The doctrine
of the motions of fluids has always been zealously cultivated by the
Italians. Castelli’s treatise, Della Misura dell’ Acque
Corrente (1638), is the first work on this subject, and Montucla
with justice calls him “the creator of a new branch of hydraulics;”26 although he mistakenly supposed the
velocity of efflux to be as the depth of the orifice from the surface.
Mersenne
and Torricelli also pursued this subject, and after them, many
others.
26 Mont. ii. 201.
Galileo’s belief in the near approximation of the curve described
by a cannon-ball or musket-ball to the theoretical parabola, was
somewhat too obsequiously adopted by succeeding practical writers on
artillery. They underrated, as he had done, the effect of the
resistance of the air, which is in effect so great as entirely to
change the form and properties of the curve. Notwithstanding this, the
parabolic theory was employed, as in Anderson’s Art of Gunnery
(1674); and Blondel, in his Art de jeter les Bombes (1688), not
only calculated Tables on this supposition, but attempted to answer
the objections which had been made respecting the form of the curve
described. It was not till a later period (1740), when Robins made a
series of careful and sagacious experiments on artillery, and when
some of the most eminent mathematicians calculated the curve, taking
into account the resistance, that the Theory of Projectiles could be
said to be verified in fact.
The Third Law of Motion was still in some confusion when Galileo
died, as we have seen. The next great step made in the school of
Galileo was the determination of the Laws of the motions of bodies in
their Direct Impact, so far as this impact affects the motion of
translation. The difficulties of the problem of Percussion arose, in
part, from the heterogeneous nature of Pressure (of a body at rest),
and Momentum (of a body in motion); and, in part, from mixing together
the effects of percussion on the parts of a body, as, for instance,
cutting, bruising, and breaking, with its effect in moving the
whole.
The former difficulty had been seen with some clearness by Galileo
himself. In a posthumous addition to his Mechanical Dialogues,
he says, “There are two kinds of resistance in a movable body, one
internal, as when we say it is more difficult to lift a weight of a
thousand pounds than a weight of a hundred; another respecting space,
as 343 when we say
that it requires more force to throw a stone one hundred paces than
fifty.”27 Reasoning upon this difference, he
comes to the conclusion that “the Momentum of percussion is infinite,
since there is no resistance, however great, which is not overcome by
a force of percussion, however small.”28 He further
explains this by observing that the resistance to percussion must
occupy some portion of time, although this portion may be insensible.
This correct mode of removing the apparent incongruity of continuous
and instantaneous force, was a material step in the solution of the
problem.
27 Op. iii. 210.
28 iii. 211.
The Laws of the mutual Impact of bodies were erroneously given by
Descartes in his Principia; and appear to have been first
correctly stated by Wren, Wallis, and Huyghens, who about the same
time (1669) sent papers to the Royal Society of London on the subject.
In these solutions, we perceive that men were gradually coming to
apprehend the Third Law of Motion in its most general sense; namely,
that the Momentum (which is proportional to the Mass of the body and
its Velocity jointly) may be taken for the measure of the effect; so
that this Momentum is as much diminished in the striking body by the
resistance it experiences, as it is increased in the body struck by
the Impact. This was sometimes expressed by saying that “the Quantity
of Motion remains unaltered,” Quantity of Motion being used as
synonymous with Momentum. Newton expressed it by saying that
“Action and Reaction are equal and opposite,” which is still one of
the most familiar modes of expressing the Third Law of Motion.
In this mode of stating the Law, we see an example of a propensity
which has prevailed very generally among mathematicians; namely, a
disposition to present the fundamental laws of rest and of motion as
if they were equally manifest, and, indeed, identical. The close
analogy and connection which exists between the principles of
equilibrium and of motion, often led men to confound the evidence of
the two; and this confusion introduced an ambiguity in the use of
words, as we have seen in the case of Momentum, Force, and others. The
same may be said of Action and Reaction, which have both
a statical and a dynamical signification. And by this means, the most
general statements of the laws of motion are made to coincide with the
most general statical propositions. For instance, Newton deduced from
his principles the conclusion, that by the mutual action of bodies,
the motion of their centre of gravity cannot be affected. Marriotte,
in his Traité de la 344 Percussion (1684), had asserted
this proposition for the case of direct impact. But by the reasoners
of Newton’s time, the dynamical proposition, that the motion of the
centre of gravity is not altered by the actual free motion and impact
of bodies, was associated with the statical proposition, that when
bodies are in equilibrium, the centre of gravity cannot be made to
ascend or descend by the virtual motions of the bodies. This
latter is a proposition which was assumed as self-evident by
Torricelli; but which may more philosophically be proved from
elementary statical principles.
This disposition to identify the elementary laws of equilibrium and
of motion, led men to think too slightingly of the ancient solid and
sufficient foundation of Statics, the doctrine of the lever. When the
progress of thought had opened men’s minds to a more general view of
the subject, it was considered as a blemish in the science to found it
on the properties of one particular machine. Descartes says in his
Letters, that “it is ridiculous to prove the pulley by means of the
lever.” And Varignon was led by similar reflections to the project of
his Nouvelle Mécanique, in which the whole of statics should be
founded on the composition of forces. This project was published in
1687; but the work did not appear till 1725, after the death of the
author. Though the attempt to reduce the equilibrium of all machines
to the composition of forces, is philosophical and meritorious, the
attempt to reduce the composition of Pressures to the composition of
Motions, with which Varignon’s work is occupied, was a
retrograde step in the subject, so far as the progress of distinct
mechanical ideas was concerned.
Thus, at the period at which we have now arrived, the Principles of
Elementary Mechanics were generally known and accepted; and there was
in the minds of mathematicians a prevalent tendency to reduce them to
the most simple and comprehensive form of which they admitted. The
execution of this simplification and extension, which we term the
generalization of the laws, is so important an event, that though it
forms part of the natural sequel of Galileo, we shall treat of it in a
separate chapter. But we must first bring up
the history of the mechanics of fluids to the corresponding point.
345</div></body></text></TEI>