<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="25">

CHAPTER XVI.
IDEA OF NUMBER.

1. Number the simplest and most universal Idea.


Amongst all the ideas we have, as there is none suggested to the mind by more
ways, so there is none more simple, than that of UNITY, or one: it has no
shadow of variety or composition in it: every object our senses are employed
about; every idea in our understandings; every thought of our minds, brings
this idea along with it. And therefore it is the most intimate to our thoughts,
as well as it is, in its agreement to all other things, the most universal idea
we have. For number applies itself to men, angels, actions, thoughts;
everything that either doth exist or can be imagined.


2. Its Modes made by Addition.


By repeating this idea in our minds, and adding the repetitions together, we
come by the COMPLEX ideas of the MODES of it. Thus, by adding one to one, we
have the complex idea of a couple; by putting twelve units together we have the
complex idea of a dozen; and so of a score or a million, or any other number.


3. Each Mode distinct.


The SIMPLE MODES of NUMBER are of all other the most distinct; every the least
variation, which is an unit, making each combination as clearly different from
that which approacheth nearest to it, as the most remote; two being as distinct
from one, as two hundred; and the idea of two as distinct from the idea of
three, as the magnitude of the whole earth is from that of a mite. This is not
so in other simple modes, in which it is not so easy, nor perhaps possible for
us to distinguish betwixt two approaching ideas, which yet are really
different. For who will undertake to find a difference between the white of
this paper and that of the next degree to it: or can form distinct ideas of
every the least excess in extension?


4. Therefore Demonstrations in Numbers the most precise.


The clearness and distinctness of each mode of number from all others, even
those that approach nearest, makes me apt to think that demonstrations in
numbers, if they are not more evident and exact than in extension, yet they are
more general in their use, and more determinate in their application. Because
the ideas of numbers are more precise and distinguishable than in extension;
where every equality and excess are not so easy to be observed or measured;
because our thoughts cannot in space arrive at any determined smallness beyond
which it cannot go, as an unit; and therefore the quantity or proportion of any
the least excess cannot be discovered; which is clear otherwise in number,
where, as has been said, 91 is as distinguishable from 90 as from 9000, though
91 be the next immediate excess to 90. But it is not so in extension, where,
whatsoever is more than just a foot or an inch, is not distinguishable from the
standard of a foot or an inch; and in lines which appear of an equal length,
one may be longer than the other by innumerable parts: nor can any one assign
an angle, which shall be the next biggest to a right one.


5. Names necessary to Numbers.


By the repeating, as has been said, the idea of an unit, and joining it to
another unit, we make thereof one collective idea, marked by the name two. And
whosoever can do this, and proceed on, still adding one more to the last
collective idea which he had of any number, and gave a name to it, may count,
or have ideas, for several collections of units, distinguished one from
another, as far as he hath a series of names for following numbers, and a
memory to retain that series, with their several names: all numeration being
but still the adding of one unit more, and giving to the whole together, as
comprehended in one idea, a new or distinct name or sign, whereby to know it
from those before and after, and distinguish it from every smaller or greater
multitude of units. So that he that can add one to one, and so to two, and so
go on with his tale, taking still with him the distinct names belonging to
every progression; and so again, by subtracting an unit from each collection,
retreat and lessen them, is capable of all the ideas of numbers within the
compass of his language, or for which he hath names, though not perhaps of
more. For, the several simple modes of numbers being in our minds but so many
combinations of units, which have no variety, nor are capable of any other
difference but more or less, names or marks for each distinct combination seem
more necessary than in any other sort of ideas. For, without such names or
marks, we can hardly well make use of numbers in reckoning, especially where
the combination is made up of any great multitude of units; which put together,
without a name or mark to distinguish that precise collection, will hardly be
kept from being a heap in confusion.


6. Another reason for the necessity of names to numbers.


This I think to be the reason why some Americans I have spoken with, (who were
otherwise of quick and rational parts enough,) could not, as we do, by any
means count to 1000; nor had any distinct idea of that number, though they
could reckon very well to 20. Because their language being scanty, and
accommodated only to the few necessaries of a needy, simple life, unacquainted
either with trade or mathematics, had no words in it to stand for 1000; so that
when they were discoursed with of those greater numbers, they would show the
hairs of their head, to express a great multitude, which they could not number;
which inability, I suppose, proceeded from their want of names. The
Tououpinambos had no names for numbers above 5; any number beyond that they
made out by showing their fingers, and the fingers of others who were present.
And I doubt not but we ourselves might distinctly number in words a great deal
further than we usually do, would we find out but some fit denominations to
signify them by; whereas, in the way we take now to name them, by millions of
millions of millions, &c., it is hard to go beyond eighteen, or at most,
four and twenty, decimal progressions, without confusion. But to show how much
distinct names conduce to our well reckoning, or having useful ideas of
numbers, let us see all these following figures in one continued line, as the
marks of one number: v. g.


Nonillions. 857324


Octillions. 162486


Septillions. 345896


Sextillions. 437918


Quintrillions. 423147


Quartrillions. 248106


Trillions. 235421


Billions. 261734


Millions. 368149


Units. 623137


The ordinary way of naming this number in English, will be the often repeating
of millions, of millions, of millions, of millions, of millions, of millions,
of millions, of millions, (which is the denomination of the second six
figures). In which way, it will be very hard to have any distinguishing notions
of this number. But whether, by giving every six figures a new and orderly
denomination, these, and perhaps a great many more figures in progression,
might not easily be counted distinctly, and ideas of them both got more easily
to ourselves, and more plainly signified to others, I leave it to be
considered. This I mention only to show how necessary distinct names are to
numbering, without pretending to introduce new ones of my invention.


7. Why Children number not earlier.


Thus children, either for want of names to mark the several progressions of
numbers, or not having yet the faculty to collect scattered ideas into complex
ones, and range them in a regular order, and so retain them in their memories,
as is necessary to reckoning, do not begin to number very early, nor proceed in
it very far or steadily, till a good while after they are well furnished with
good store of other ideas: and one may often observe them discourse and reason
pretty well, and have very clear conceptions of several other things, before
they can tell twenty. And some, through the default of their memories, who
cannot retain the several combinations of numbers, with their names, annexed in
their distinct orders, and the dependence of so long a train of numeral
progressions, and their relation one to another, are not able all their
lifetime to reckon, or regularly go over any moderate series of numbers. For he
that will count twenty, or have any idea of that number, must know that
nineteen went before, with the distinct name or sign of every one of them, as
they stand marked in their order; for wherever this fails, a gap is made, the
chain breaks, and the progress in numbering can go no further. So that to
reckon right, it is required, (1) That the mind distinguish carefully two
ideas, which are different one from another only by the addition or subtraction
of ONE unit: (2) That it retain in memory the names or marks of the several
combinations, from an unit to that number; and that not confusedly, and at
random, but in that exact order that the numbers follow one another. In either
of which, if it trips, the whole business of numbering will be disturbed, and
there will remain only the confused idea of multitude, but the ideas necessary
to distinct numeration will not be attained to.


8. Number measures all Measurables.


This further is observable in number, that it is that which the mind makes use
of in measuring all things that by us are measurable, which principally are
EXPANSION and DURATION; and our idea of infinity, even when applied to those,
seems to be nothing but the infinity of number. For what else are our ideas of
Eternity and Immensity, but the repeated additions of certain ideas of imagined
parts of duration and expansion, with the infinity of number; in which we can
come to no end of addition? For such an inexhaustible stock, number (of all
other our ideas) most clearly furnishes us with, as is obvious to every one.
For let a man collect into one sum as great a number as he pleases, this
multitude how great soever, lessens not one jot the power of adding to it, or
brings him any nearer the end of the inexhaustible stock of number; where still
there remains as much to be added, as if none were taken out. And this ENDLESS
ADDITION or ADDIBILITY (if any one like the word better) of numbers, so
apparent to the mind, is that, I think, which gives us the clearest and most
distinct idea of infinity: of which more in the following chapter.


</div></body></text></TEI>