<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Vestiges of the Natural History of Creation</title><author>Chambers, Robert (1802-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="16">p.
277EARLY HISTORY OF MANKIND.
The human race is known to consist
of numerous nations, displaying considerable differences of
external form and colour, and speaking in general different
languages.  This has been the case since the commencement of
written record.  It is also ascertained that the external
peculiarities of particular nations do not rapidly change. 
There is rather a tendency to a persistency of type in all lines
of descent, insomuch that a subordinate admixture of various type
is usually obliterated in a few generations.  Numerous as
the varieties are, they have all been found classifiable under
five leading ones:—1.  The Caucasian or Indo-European,
which extends from India into Europe and Northern Africa;
2.  The Mongolian, which occupies Northern and Eastern Asia;
3.  The Malayan, which extends from the Ultra-Gangetic
Peninsula into the numerous islands of the South Sea and Pacific;
4.  The Negro, chiefly confined to Africa; 5.  The
aboriginal American.  Each of these is distinguished by
certain general features of so marked a kind, as to give rise to
a supposition that they have had distinct or independent
origins.  Of these peculiarities, colour is the most
conspicuous: the Caucasians are generally white, the Mongolians
yellow, the Negroes black, and the Americans red.  The
opposition of two of these in particular, white and black, is so
striking, that of them, at least, it seems almost necessary to
suppose separate origins.  Of late years, however, the whole
of this question has been subjected to a rigorous investigation,
and it has been successfully shewn that the human race might have
had one origin, for anything that can be inferred from external
peculiarities.
It appears from this inquiry, [278] that colour and
other physiological characters are of a more superficial and
accidental nature than was at one time supposed.  One fact
is at the very first extremely startling, that there are nations,
such as the inhabitants of Hindostan, known to be one in descent,
which nevertheless contain groups of people of almost all shades
of colour, and likewise discrepant in other of those important
features on which much stress has been laid.  Some other
facts, which I may state in brief terms, are scarcely less
remarkable.  In Africa, there are Negro nations,—that
is, nations of intensely black complexion, as the Jolofs,
Mandingoes, and Kafirs, whose features and limbs are as elegant
as those of the best European nations.  While we have no
proof of Negro races becoming white in the course of generations,
the converse may be held as established, for there are Arab and
Jewish families of ancient settlement in Northern Africa, who
have become as black as the other inhabitants.  There are
also facts which seem to shew the possibility of a natural
transition by generation from the black to the white complexion,
and from the white to the black.  True whites (apart from
Albinoes) are not unfrequently born among the Negroes, and the
tendency to this singularity is transmitted in families. 
There is, at least, one authentic instance of a set of perfectly
black children being born to an Arab couple, in whose ancestry no
such blood had intermingled.  This occurred in the valley of
the Jordan, where it is remarkable that the Arab population in
general have flatter features, darker skins, and coarser hair,
than any other tribes of the same nation. [280]
The style of living is ascertained to have a powerful effect
in modifying the human figure in the course of generations, and
this even in its osseous structure.  About two hundred years
ago, a number of people were driven by a barbarous policy from
the counties of Antrim and Down, in Ireland, towards the
sea-coast, where they have ever since been settled, but in
unusually miserable circumstances, even for Ireland; and the
consequence is, that they exhibit peculiar features of the most
repulsive kind, projecting jaws with large open mouths, depressed
noses, high cheek bones, and bow legs, together with an extremely
diminutive stature.  These, with an abnormal slenderness of
the limbs, are the outward marks of a low and barbarous condition
all over the world; it is particularly seen in the Australian
aborigines.  On the other hand, the beauty of the higher
ranks in England is very remarkable, being, in the main, as
clearly a result of good external conditions. 
“Coarse, unwholesome, and ill-prepared food,” says
Buffon, “makes the human race degenerate.  All those
people who live miserably are ugly and ill-made.  Even in
France, the country people are not so beautiful as those who live
in towns; and I have often remarked that in those villages where
the people are richer and better fed than in others, the men are
likewise more handsome, and have better
countenances.”  He might have added, that elegant and
commodious dwellings, cleanly habits, comfortable clothing, and
being exposed to the open air only as much as health requires,
cooperate with food in increasing the elegance of a race of human
beings.
Subject only to these modifying agencies, there is, as has
been said, a remarkable persistency in national features and
forms, insomuch that a single individual thrown into a family
different from himself is absorbed in it, and all trace of him
lost after a few generations.  But while there is such a
persistency to ordinary observation, it would also appear that
nature has a power of producing new varieties, though this is
only done rarely.  Such novelties of type abound in the
vegetable world, are seen more rarely in the animal circle, and
perhaps are least frequent of occurrence in our own race. 
There is a noted instance in the production, on a New England
farm, of a variety of sheep with unusually short legs, which was
kept up by breeding, on account of the convenience in that
country of having sheep which are unable to jump over low
fences.  The starting and main taming a breed of
cattle, that is, a variety marked by some desirable peculiarity,
are familiar to a large class of persons.  It appears only
necessary, when a variety has been thus produced, that a union
should take place between individuals similarly characterized, in
order to establish it.  Early in the last century, a man
named Lambert, was born in Suffolk, with semi-horny excrescences
of about half an inch long, thickly growing all over his
body.  The peculiarity was transmitted to his children, and
was last heard of in a third generation.  The peculiarity of
six fingers on the hand and six toes on the feet, appears in like
manner in families which have no record or tradition of such a
peculiarity having affected them at any former period, and it is
then sometimes seen to descend through several generations. 
It was Mr. Lawrence’s opinion, that a pair, in which both
parties were so distinguished, might be the progenitors of a new
variety of the race who would be thus marked in all future
time.  It is not easy to surmise the causes which operate in
producing such varieties.  Perhaps they are simply types in
nature, possible to be realized under certain appropriate
conditions, but which conditions are such as altogether to
elude notice.  I might cite as examples of such possible
types, the rise of whites amongst the Negroes, the occurrence of
the family of black children in the valley of the Jordan, and the
comparatively frequent birth of red-haired children amongst not
only the Mongolian and Malayan families, but amongst the
Negroes.  We are ignorant of the laws of variety-production;
but we see it going on as a principle in nature, and it is
obviously favourable to the supposition that all the great
families of men are of one stock.
The tendency of the modern study of the languages of nations
is to the same point.  The last fifty years have seen this
study elevated to the character of a science, and the light which
it throws upon the history of mankind is of a most remarkable
nature.
Following a natural analogy, philologists have thrown the
earth’s languages into a kind of classification: a number
bearing a considerable resemblance to each other, and in general
geographically near, are styled a group or
sub-family; several groups, again, are associated as a
family, with regard to more general features of
resemblance.  Six families are spoken of.
The Indo-European family nearly coincides in geographical
limits with those which have been assigned to that variety of
mankind which generally shews a fair complexion, called the
Caucasian variety.  It may be said to commence in India, and
thence to stretch through Persia into Europe, the whole of which
it occupies, excepting Hungary, the Basque provinces of Spain,
and Finland.  Its sub-families are the Sanskrit, or ancient
language of India, the Persian, the Slavonic, Celtic, Gothic, and
Pelasgian.  The Slavonic includes the modern languages of
Russia and Poland.  Under the Gothic, are (1) the
Scandinavian tongues, the Norske, Swedish, and Danish; and (2)
the Teutonic, to which belong the modern German, the Dutch, and
our own Anglo-Saxon.  I give the name of Pelasgian to the
group scattered along the north shores of the Mediterranean, the
Greek and Latin, including the modifications of the latter under
the names of Italian, Spanish, &c.  The Celtic was from
two to three thousand years ago, the speech of a considerable
tribe dwelling in Western Europe; but these have since been
driven before superior nations into a few corners, and are now
only to be found in the highlands of Scotland, Ireland, Wales,
Cornwall, and certain parts of France.  The Gaelic of
Scotland, Erse of Ireland, and the Welsh, are the only living
branches of this sub-family of languages.
The resemblances amongst languages are of two
kinds,—identity of words, and identity of grammatical
forms; the latter being now generally considered as the most
important towards the argument.  When we inquire into the
first kind of affinity among the languages of the Indo-European
family, we are surprised at the great number of common terms
which exist amongst them, and these referring to such primary
ideas, as to leave no doubt of their having all been derived from
a common source.  Colonel Vans Kennedy presents nine hundred
words common to the Sanskrit and other languages of the same
family.  In the Sanskrit and Persian, we find several which
require no sort of translation to an English reader, as
pader, mader, sunu, dokhter,
brader, mand, vidhava; likewise
asthi, a bone, (Greek, ostoun;) denta, a
tooth, (Latin, dens, dentis;) eyeumen, the
eye; brouwa, the eye-brow, (German, braue;)
nasa, the nose; karu, the hand, (Gr. cheir;)
genu, the knee, (Lat. genu;) ped, the foot,
(Lat. pes, pedis;) hrti, the heart;
jecur, the liver, (Lat. jecur;) stara, a
star; gela, cold, (Lat. gelu, ice;) aghni,
fire, (Lat. ignis;) dhara, the earth, (Lat.
terra, Gaelic, tir;) arrivi, a river;
nau, a ship, (Gr. naus, Lat. navis;)
ghau, a cow; sarpam, a serpent.
The inferences from these verbal coincidences were confirmed
in a striking manner when Bopp and others investigated the
grammatical structure of this family of languages.  Dr.
Wiseman pronounces that the great philologist just named,
“by a minute and sagacious analysis of the Sanskrit verb,
compared with the conjugational system of the other members of
this family, left no doubt of their intimate and positive
affinity.”  It was now discovered that the peculiar
terminations or inflections by which persons are expressed
throughout the verbs of nearly the whole of these languages, have
their foundations in pronouns; the pronoun was simply placed at
the end, and thus became an inflexion.  “By an
analysis of the Sanskrit pronouns, the elements of those existing
in all the other languages were cleared of their anomalies; the
verb substantive, which in Latin is composed of fragments
referable to two distinct roots, here found both existing in
regular form; the Greek conjugations, with all their complicated
machinery of middle voice, augments, and reduplications, were
here found and illustrated in a variety of ways, which a few
years ago would have appeared chimerical.  Even our own
language may sometimes receive light from the study of distant
members of our family.  Where, for instance, are we to seek
for the root of our comparative better?  Certainly
not in its positive, good, nor in the Teutonic dialects in which
the same anomaly exists.  But in the Persian we have
precisely the same comparative, behter, with exactly the
same signification, regularly formed from its positive
beh, good.” [287]
The second great family is the Syro-Phœnician,
comprising the Hebrew, Syro-Chaldaic, Arabic, and Gheez or
Abyssinian, being localized principally in the countries to the
west and south of the Mediterranean.  Beyond them, again, is
the African family, which, as far as research has gone, seems to
be in like manner marked by common features, both verbal and
grammatical.  The fourth is the Polynesian family, extending
from Madagascar on the west through all the Indian Archipelago,
besides taking in the Malayan dialect from the continent of
India, and comprehending Australia and the islands of the western
portion of the Pacific.  This family, however, bears such an
affinity to that next to be described, that Dr. Leyden and some
others do not give it a distinct place as a family of
languages.
The fifth family is the Chinese, embracing a large part of
China, and most of the regions of Central and Northern
Asia.  The leading features of the Chinese are, its
consisting altogether of monosyllables, and being destitute of
all grammatical forms, except certain arrangements and
accentuations, which vary the sense of particular words.  It
is also deficient in some of the consonants most conspicuous in
other languages, b, d, r, v, and z; so that this people can
scarcely pronounce our speech in such a way as to be
intelligible: for example, the word Christus they call
Kuliss-ut-oo-suh.  The Chinese, strange to say,
though they early attained to a remarkable degree of
civilization, and have preceded the Europeans in many of the most
important inventions, have a language which resembles that of
children, or deaf and dumb people.  The sentence of short,
simple, unconnected words, in which an infant amongst us attempts
to express some of its wants and its ideas—the equally
broken and difficult terms which the deaf and dumb express by
signs, as the following passage of the Lord’s
Prayer:—“Our Father, heaven in, wish your name
respect, wish your soul’s kingdom providence arrive, wish
your will do heaven earth equality,” &c.—these
are like the discourse of the refined people of the so-called
Celestial Empire.  An attempt was made by the Abbé
Sicard to teach the deaf and dumb grammatical signs; but they
persisted in restricting themselves to the simple signs of ideas,
leaving the structure undetermined by any but the natural order
of connexion.  Such is exactly the condition of the Chinese
language.
Crossing the Pacific, we come to the last great family in the
languages of the aboriginal Americans, which have all of them
features in common, proving them to constitute a group by
themselves, without any regard to the very different degrees of
civilization which these nations had attained at the time of the
discovery.  The common resemblance is in the grammatical
structure as well as in words, and the grammatical structure of
this family is of a very peculiar and complicated kind.  The
general character in this respect has caused the term
Polysynthetic to be applied to the American languages.  A
long many-syllabled word is used by the rude Algonquins and
Delawares to express a whole sentence: for example, a woman of
the latter nation, playing with a little dog or cat, would
perhaps be heard saying, “kuligatschis,”
meaning, “give me your pretty little paw;” the word,
on examination, is found to be made up in this manner: k,
the second personal pronoun; uli, part of the word wulet,
pretty; gat, part of the word wichgat, signifying a leg or
paw; schis, conveying the idea of littleness.  In the
same tongue, a youth is called pilape, a word compounded from the
first part of pilsit, innocent, and the latter part of lenape, a
man.  Thus, it will be observed, a number of parts of words
are taken and thrown together, by a process which has been
happily termed agglutination, so as to form one word,
conveying a complicated idea.  There is also an elaborate
system of inflection; in nouns, for instance, there is one kind
of inflection to express the presence or absence of vitality, and
another to express number.  The genius of the language has
been described as accumulative: it “tends rather to add
syllables or letters, making farther distinctions in objects
already before the mind, than to introduce new words.” [291]  Yet it has also been shewn very
distinctly, that these languages are based in words of one
syllable, like those of the Chinese and Polynesian families; all
the primary ideas are thus expressed: the elaborate system of
inflection and agglutination is shewn to be simply a farther
development of the language-forming principle, as it may be
called—or the Chinese system may be described as an
arrestment of this principle at a particular early point. 
It has been fully shewn, that between the structure of the
American and other families, sufficient affinities exist to make
a common origin or early connexion extremely likely.  The
verbal affinities are also very considerable.  Humboldt
says, “In eighty-three American languages examined by
Messrs. Barton and Vater, one hundred and seventy words have been
found, the roots of which appear to be the same; and it is easy
to perceive that this analogy is not accidental, since it does
not rest merely upon imitative harmony, or on that conformity of
organs which produces almost a perfect identity in the first
sounds articulated by children.  Of these one hundred and
seventy words which have this connexion, three-fifths resemble
the Manchou, the Tongouse, the Mongal, and the Samoyed; and
two-fifths, the Celtic and Tchoud, the Biscayan, the Coptic, and
Congo languages.  These words have been found by comparing
the whole of the American languages with the whole of those of
the Old World; for hitherto we are acquainted with no American
idiom which seems to have an exclusive correspondence with any of
the Asiatic, African, or European tongues.” [293]  Humboldt and others considered
these words as brought into America by recent immigrants; an idea
resting on no proof, and which seems at once refuted by the
common words being chiefly those which represent primary ideas;
besides, we now know, what was not formerly perceived or
admitted, that there are great affinities of structure
also.  I may here refer to a curious mathematical
calculation by Dr. Thomas Young, to the effect, that if three
words coincide in two different languages, it is ten to one they
must be derived in both cases from some parent language, or
introduced in some other manner.  “Six words would
give more,” he says, “than seventeen hundred to one,
and eight near 100,000, so that in these cases the evidence would
be little short of absolute certainty.”  He instances
the following words to shew a connexion between the ancient
Egyptian and the Biscayan:—


 

Biscayan.

Egyptian.



New

Beria

Beri.



A dog

Ora

Whor.



Little

Gutchi

Kudchi.



Bread

Ognia

Oik.



A wolf

Otgsa

Ounsh.



Seven

Shashpi

Shashf.



Now, as there are, according to Humboldt, one hundred and
seventy words in common between the languages of the new and old
continents, and many of these are expressive of the most
primitive ideas, there is, by Dr. Young’s calculation,
overpowering proof of the original connexion of the American and
other human families.
This completes the slight outline which I have been able to
give, of the evidence for the various races of men being
descended from one stock.  It cannot be considered as
conclusive, and there are many eminent persons who deem the
opposite idea the more probable; but I must say that, without the
least regard to any other kind of evidence, that which physiology
and philology present seems to me decidedly favourable to the
idea of a single origin.
Assuming that the human race is one, we are next called
upon to inquire in what part of the earth it may most probably be
supposed to have originated.  One obvious mode of
approximating to a solution of this question is to trace backward
the lines in which the principal tribes appear to have migrated,
and to see if these converge nearly to a point.  It is very
remarkable that the lines do converge, and are concentrated about
the region of Hindostan.  The language, religion, modes of
reckoning time, and some other peculiar ideas of the Americans,
are now believed to refer their origin to North-Eastern
Asia.  Trace them farther back in the same direction, and we
come to the north of India.  The history of the Celts and
Teutones represents them as coming from the east, the one after
the other, successive waves of a tide of population flowing
towards the north-west of Europe: this line being also traced
back, rests finally at the same place.  So does the line of
Iranian population, which has peopled the east and south shores
of the Mediterranean, Syria, Arabia, and Egypt.  The Malay
variety, again, rests its limit in one direction on the borders
of India.  Standing on that point, it is easy to see how the
human family, originating there, might spread out in different
directions, passing into varieties of aspect and of language as
they spread, the Malay variety proceeding towards the Oceanic
region, the Mongolians to the east and north, and sending off the
red men as a sub-variety, the European population going off to
the north-westward, and the Syrian, Arabian, and Egyptian,
towards the countries which they are known to have so long
occupied.  The Negro alone is here unaccounted for; and of
that race it may fairly be said, that it is the one most likely
to have had an independent origin, seeing that it is a type so
peculiar in an inveterate black colour, and so mean in
development.  But it is not necessary to presume such an
origin for it, as much good argument might be employed to shew
that it is only a deteriorated offshoot of the general
stock.  Our view of the probable original seat of man agrees
with the ancient traditions of the race.  There is one among
the Hindoos which places the cradle of the human family in
Thibet; another makes Ceylon the residence of the first
man.  Our view is also in harmony with the hypothesis
detailed in the chapter before the last.  According to that
theory, we should expect man to have originated where the highest
species of the quadrumana are to be found.  Now these are
unquestionably found in the Indian Archipelago.
After all, it may be regarded as still an open question,
whether mankind is of one or many origins.  The first human
generation may have consisted of many pairs, though situated at
one place, and these may have been considerably different from
each other in external characters.  And we are equally bound
to admit, though this does not as yet seem to have occurred to
any other speculator, that there may have been different lines
and sources of origination, geographically apart, but which all
resulted uniformly in the production of a being, one in species,
although variously marked.
It has of late years been a favourite notion with many, that
the human race was at first in a highly civilized state, and that
barbarism was a second condition.  This idea probably took
its origin in a wish to support certain interpretations of the
Mosaic record, and it has never yet been propounded by any writer
who seemed to have a due sense of the value of science in this
class of investigations.  The principal argument for it is,
that we see many examples of nations falling away from
civilization into barbarism, while in some regions of the earth,
the history of which we do not clearly know, there are remains of
works of art far superior to any which the present unenlightened
inhabitants could have produced.  It is to be readily
admitted that such decadences are common; but do they necessarily
prove that there has been anything like a regular and constant
decline into the present state, from a state more generally
refined?  May not these be only instances of local failures
and suppressions of the principle of civilization, where it had
begun to take root amongst a people generally barbarous?  It
is, at least, as legitimate to draw this inference from the facts
which are known.  But it is also alleged that we know of no
such thing as civilization being ever self-originated.  It
is always seen to be imparted from one people to another. 
Hence, of course, we must infer that civilization at the first
could only have been of supernatural origin.  This argument
appears to be founded on false premises, for civilization does
sometimes rise in a manner clearly independent amongst a horde of
people generally barbarous.  A striking instance is
described in the laborious work of Mr. Catlin on the
North-American tribes.  Far placed among those which inhabit
the vast region of the north-west, and quite beyond the reach of
any influence from the whites, he found a small tribe living in a
fortified village, where they cultivated the arts of manufacture,
realized comforts and luxuries, and had attained to a remarkable
refinement of manners, insomuch as to be generally called the
polite and friendly Mandans.  They were also more than
usually elegant in their persons, and of every variety of
complexion between that of their compatriots and a pure
white.  Up to the time of Mr. Catlin’s visit, these
people had been able to defend themselves and their possessions
against the roving bands which surrounded them on all sides; but,
soon after, they were attacked by small-pox, which cut them all
off except a small party, whom their enemies rushed in upon and
destroyed to a man.  What is this but a repetition on a
small scale of phenomena with which ancient history familiarizes
us—a nation rising in arts and elegances amidst barbarous
neighbours, but at length overpowered by the rude majority,
leaving only a Tadmor or a Luxor as a monument of itself to
beautify the waste?  What can we suppose the nation which
built Palenque and Copan to have been but only a Mandan tribe,
which chanced to have made its way farther along the path of
civilization and the arts, before the barbarians broke in upon
it?  The flame essayed to rise in many parts of the earth;
but there were always considerable chances against it, and down
it accordingly went, times without number; but there was always a
vitality in it, nevertheless, and a tendency to progress, and at
length it seems to have attained a strength against which the
powers of barbarism can never more prevail.  The state of
our knowledge of uncivilized nations is very apt to make us fall
into error on this subject.  They are generally supposed to
be all at one point in barbarism, which is far from being the
case, for in the midst of every great region of uncivilized men,
such as North America, there are nations partially refined. 
The Jolofs, Mandingoes, and Kafirs, are African examples, where a
natural and independent origin for the improvement which exists
is as unavoidably to be presumed as in the case of the
Mandans.
The most conclusive argument against the original civilization
of mankind is to be found in the fact that we do not now see
civilization existing anywhere except in certain conditions
altogether different from any we can suppose to have
existed at the commencement of our race.  To have
civilization, it is necessary that a people should be numerous
and closely placed; that they should be fixed in their
habitations, and safe from violent external and internal
disturbance; that a considerable number of them should be exempt
from the necessity of drudging for immediate subsistence. 
Feeling themselves at ease about the first necessities of their
nature, including self-preservation, and daily subjected to that
intellectual excitement which society produces, men begin to
manifest what is called civilization; but never in rude and
shelterless circumstances, or when widely scattered.  Even
men who have been civilized, when transferred to a wide
wilderness, where each has to work hard and isolatedly for the
first requisites of life, soon shew a retrogression to barbarism:
witness the plains of Australia, as well as the backwoods of
Canada and the prairies of Texas.  Fixity of residence and
thickening of population are perhaps the prime requisites for
civilization, and hence it will be found that all civilizations
as yet known have taken place in regions physically
limited.  That of Egypt arose in a narrow valley hemmed in
by deserts on both sides.  That of Greece took its rise in a
small peninsula bounded on the only land side by mountains. 
Etruria and Rome were naturally limited regions. 
Civilizations have taken place at both the eastern and western
extremities of the elder continent—China and Japan, on the
one hand; Germany, Holland, Britain, France, on the
other—while the great unmarked tract between contains
nations decidedly less advanced.  Why is this, but because
the sea, in both cases, has imposed limits to further migration,
and caused the population to settle and condense—the
conditions most necessary for social improvement. [302]  Even the simple case of the
Mandans affords an illustration of this principle, for Mr. Catlin
expressly, though without the least regard to theory, attributes
their improvement to the fact of their being a small tribe,
obliged, by fear of their more numerous enemies, to settle in
a permanent village, so fortified as to ensure their
preservation.  “By this means,” says he,
“they have advanced farther in the arts of manufacture, and
have supplied their lodges more abundantly with the comforts and
even luxuries of life than any Indian nation I know of.  The
consequence of this,” he adds, “is that the tribe
have taken many steps ahead of other tribes in manners and
refinements.”  These conditions can only be
regarded as natural laws affecting civilization, and it might not
be difficult, taking them into account, to predict of any newly
settled country its social destiny.  An island like Van
Dieman’s land might fairly be expected to go on more
rapidly to good manners and sound institutions than a wide region
like Australia.  The United States might be expected to make
no great way in civilization till they be fully peopled to the
Pacific; and it might not be unreasonable to expect that, when
that even has occurred, the greatest civilizations of that vast
territory will be found in the peninsula of California and the
narrow stripe of country beyond the Rocky Mountains.  This,
however, is a digression.  To return: it is also necessary
for a civilization that at least a portion of the community
should be placed above mean and engrossing toils. 
Man’s mind becomes subdued, like the dyer’s hand, to
that it works in.  In rude and difficult circumstances we
unavoidably become rude, because then only the inferior and
harsher faculties of our nature are called into existence. 
When, on the contrary, there is leisure and abundance, the
self-seeking and self-preserving instincts are allowed to rest,
the gentler and more generous sentiments are evoked, and man
becomes that courteous and chivalric being which he is found to
be amongst the upper classes of almost all civilized
countries.  These, then, may be said to be the chief natural
laws concerned in the moral phenomenon of civilization.  If
I am right in so considering them, it will of course be readily
admitted that the earliest families of the human race, although
they might be simple and innocent, could not have been in
anything like a civilized state, seeing that the conditions
necessary for that state could not have then existed.  Let
us only for a moment consider some of the things requisite for
their being civilized,—namely, a set of elegant homes ready
furnished for their reception, fields ready cultivated to yield
them food without labour, stores of luxurious appliances of all
kinds, a complete social enginery for the securing of life and
property,—and we shall turn from the whole conceit as one
worthy only of the philosophers of Utopia.
Yet, as has been remarked, the earliest families might be
simple and innocent, while at the same time unskilled and
ignorant, and obliged to live merely upon such substances as they
could readily procure.  The traditions of all nations refer
to such a state as that in which mankind were at first: perhaps
it is not so much a tradition as an idea which the human mind
naturally inclines to form respecting the fathers of the race;
but nothing that we see of mankind absolutely forbids our
entertaining this idea, while there are some considerations
rather favourable to it.  A few families, in a state of
nature, living near each other, in a country supplying the means
of livelihood abundantly, are generally simple and innocent;
their instinctive and perceptive faculties are also apt to be
very active, although the higher intellect may be dormant. 
If we therefore presume India to have been the cradle of our
race, they might at first exemplify a sort of golden age; but it
could not be of long continuance.  The very first movements
from the primal seat would be attended with degradation, nor
could there be any tendency to true civilization till groups had
settled and thickened in particular seats physically limited.
The probability may now be assumed that the human race sprung
from one stock, which was at first in a state of simplicity, if
not barbarism.  As yet we have not seen very distinctly how
the various branches of the family, as they parted off, and took
up separate ground, became marked by external features so
peculiar.  Why are the Africans black, and generally marked
by coarse features and ungainly forms?  Why are the
Mongolians generally yellow, the Americans red, the Caucasians
white?  Why the flat features of the Chinese, the small
stature of the Laps, the soft round forms of the English, the
lank features of their descendants, the Americans?  All of
these phenomena appear, in a word, to be explicable on the ground
of development.  We have already seen that various
leading animal forms represent stages in the embryotic progress
of the highest—the human being.  Our brain goes
through the various stages of a fish’s, a reptile’s,
and a mammifer’s brain, and finally becomes human. 
There is more than this, for, after completing the animal
transformations, it passes through the characters in which it
appears, in the Negro, Malay, American, and Mongolian nations,
and finally is Caucasian.  The face partakes of these
alterations.  “One of the earliest points in which
ossification commences is the lower jaw.  This bone is
consequently sooner completed than the other bones of the head,
and acquires a predominance, which, as is well known, it never
loses in the Negro.  During the soft pliant state of the
bones of the skull, the oblong form which they naturally assume,
approaches nearly the permanent shape of the Americans.  At
birth, the flattened face, and broad smooth forehead of the
infant, the position of the eyes rather towards the side of the
head, and the widened space between, represent the Mongolian
form; while it is only as the child advances to maturity, that
the oval face, the arched forehead, and the marked features of
the true Caucasian, become perfectly developed.” [307a]  The leading characters,
in short, of the various races of mankind, are
simply representations of particular stages in the development of
the highest or Caucasian type.  The Negro exhibits
permanently the imperfect brain, projecting lower jaw, and
slender bent limbs, of a Caucasian child, some considerable time
before the period of its birth.  The aboriginal American
represents the same child nearer birth.  The Mongolian is an
arrested infant newly born.  And so forth.  All this is
as respects form; [307b] but whence
colour?  This might be supposed to have depended on climatal
agencies only; but it has been shewn by overpowering evidence to
be independent of these.  In further considering the matter,
we are met by the very remarkable fact that colour is deepest in
the least perfectly developed type, next in the Malay, next in
the American, next in the Mongolian, the very order in which the
degrees of development are ranged.  May not colour,
then, depend upon development also?  We do
not, indeed, see that a Caucasian fœtus at the stage which
the African represents is anything like black; neither is a
Caucasian child yellow, like the Mongolian.  There may,
nevertheless, be a character of skin at a certain stage of
development which is predisposed to a particular colour when it
is presented as the envelope of a mature being.  Development
being arrested at so immature a stage in the case of the Negro,
the skin may take on the colour as an unavoidable consequence of
its imperfect organization.  It is favourable to this view,
that Negro infants are not deeply black at first, but only
acquire the full colour tint after exposure for some time to the
atmosphere.  Another consideration in its favour is that
there is a likelihood of peculiarities of form and colour, since
they are so coincident, depending on one set of phenomena. 
If it be admitted as true, there can be no difficulty in
accounting for all the varieties of mankind.  They are
simply the result of so many advances and retrogressions in the
developing power of the human mothers, these advances and
retrogressions being, as we have formerly seen, the immediate
effect of external conditions in nutrition, hardship, &c., [309] and also, perhaps, to some extent, of
the suitableness and unsuitableness of marriages, for it is found
that parents too nearly related tend to produce offspring of the
Mongolian type,—that is, persons who in maturity still are
a kind of children.  According to this view, the greater
part of the human race must be considered as having lapsed or
declined from the original type.  In the Caucasian or
Indo-European family alone has the primitive organization been
improved upon.  The Mongolian, Malay, American, and Negro,
comprehending perhaps five-sixths of mankind, are
degenerate.  Strange that the great plan should admit of
failures and aberrations of such portentous magnitude!  But
pause and reflect; take time into consideration: the past history
of mankind may be, to what is to come, but as a day.  Look
at the progress even now making over the barbaric parts of the
earth by the best examples of the Caucasian type, promising not
only to fill up the waste places, but to supersede the imperfect
nations already existing.  Who can tell what progress may be
made, even in a single century, towards reversing the proportions
of the perfect and imperfect types? and who can tell but that the
time during which the mean types have lasted, long as it appears,
may yet be thrown entirely into the shade by the time during
which the best types will remain predominant?
We have seen that the traces of a common origin in all
languages afford a ground of presumption for the unity of the
human race.  They establish a still stronger probability
that mankind had not yet begun to disperse before they were
possessed of a means of communicating their ideas by conventional
sounds—in short, speech.  This is a gift so peculiar
to man, and in itself so remarkable, that there is a great
inclination to surmise a miraculous origin for it, although there
is no proper ground, or even support, for such an idea in
Scripture, while it is clearly opposed to everything else that we
know with regard to the providential arrangements for the
creation of our race.  Here, as in many other cases, a
little observation of nature might have saved much vain
discussion.  The real character of language itself has not
been thoroughly understood.  Language, in its most
comprehensive sense, is the communication of ideas by whatever
means.  Ideas can be communicated by looks, gestures, and
signs of various other kinds, as well as by speech.  The
inferior animals possess some of those means of communicating
ideas, and they have likewise a silent and unobservable mode of
their own, the nature of which is a complete mystery to us,
though we are assured of its reality by its effects.  Now,
as the inferior animals were all in being before man, there was
language upon earth long ere the history of our race
commenced.  The only additional fact in the history of
language, which was produced by our creation, was the rise of a
new mode of expression—namely, that by sound-signs
produced by the vocal organs.  In other words, speech was
the only novelty in this respect attending the creation of the
human race.  No doubt it was an addition of great
importance, for, in comparison with it, the other natural modes
of communicating ideas sink into insignificance.  Still, the
main and fundamental phenomenon, language, as the communication
of ideas, was no new gift of the Creator to man; and in speech
itself, when we judge of it as a natural fact, we see only a
result of some of those superior endowments of which so many
others have fallen to our lot through the medium of an improved
or advanced organization.
The first and most obvious natural endowment concerned in
speech is that peculiar organization of the larynx, trachea, and
mouth, which enables us to produce the various sounds required in
the case.  Man started at first with this organization ready
for use, a constitution of the atmosphere adapted for the sounds
which that organization was calculated to produce, and, lastly,
but not leastly, as will afterwards be more particularly shewn, a
mental power within, prompting to, and giving directions for, the
expression of ideas.  Such an arrangement of mutually
adapted things was as likely to produce sounds as an Eolian harp
placed in a draught is to produce tones.  It was unavoidable
that human beings so organized, and in such a relation to
external nature, should utter sounds, and also come to attach to
these conventional meanings, thus forming the elements of spoken
language.  The great difficulty which has been felt was to
account for man going in this respect beyond the inferior
animals.  There could have been no such difficulty if
speculators in this class of subjects had looked into physiology
for an account of the superior vocal organization of man, and had
they possessed a true science of mind to shew man possessing a
faculty for the expression of ideas which is only rudimental in
the lower animals.  Another difficulty has been in the
consideration that, if men were at first utterly untutored and
barbarous, they could scarcely be in a condition to form or
employ language—an instrument which it requires the fullest
powers of thought to analyse and speculate upon.  But this
difficulty also vanishes upon reflection—for, in the first
place, we are not bound to suppose the fathers of our race early
attaining to great proficiency in language, and, in the second,
language itself seems to be amongst the things least difficult to
be acquired, if we can form any judgment from what we see in
children, most of whom have, by three years of age, while their
information and judgment are still as nothing, mastered and
familiarized themselves with a quantity of words, infinitely
exceeding in proportion what they acquire in the course of any
subsequent similar portion of time.
Discussions as to which parts of speech were first formed, and
the processes by which grammatical structure and inflections took
their rise, appear in a great measure needless, after the matter
has been placed in this light.  The mental powers could
readily connect particular arbitrary sounds with particular
ideas, whether those ideas were nouns, verbs, or
interjections.  As the words of all languages can be traced
back into roots which are monosyllables, we may presume these
sounds to have all been monosyllabic accordingly.  The
clustering of two or more together to express a compound idea,
and the formation of inflections by additional syllables
expressive of pronouns and such prepositions as of, by, and to,
are processes which would or might occur as matters of course,
being simple results of a mental power called into action, and
partly directed, by external necessities.  This power,
however, as we find it in very different degrees of endowment in
individuals, so would it be in different degrees of endowment in
nations, or branches of the human family.  Hence we find the
formation of words and the process of their composition and
grammatical arrangement, in very different stages of development
in different races.  The Chinese have a language composed of
a limited number of monosyllables, which they multiply in use by
mere variations of accent, and which they have never yet attained
the power of clustering or inflecting; the language of this
immense nation—the third part of the human race—may
be said to be in the condition of infancy.  The aboriginal
Americans, so inferior in civilization, have, on the other hand,
a language of the most elaborately composite kind, perhaps even
exceeding, in this respect, the languages of the most refined
European nations.  These are but a few out of many facts
tending to shew that language is in a great measure independent
of civilization, as far as its advance and development are
concerned.  Do they not also help to prove that cultivated
intellect is not necessary for the origination of language?
Facts daily presented to our observation afford equally simple
reasons for the almost infinite diversification of
language.  It is invariably found that, wherever society is
at once dense and refined, language tends to be uniform
throughout the whole population, and to undergo few changes in
the course of time.  Wherever, on the contrary, we have a
scattered and barbarous people, we have great diversities, and
comparatively rapid alterations of language.  Insomuch that,
while English, French, and German are each spoken with little
variation by many millions, there are islands in the Indian
archipelago, probably not inhabited by one million, but in which
there are hundreds of languages, as diverse as are English,
French, and German.  It is easy to see how this should
be.  There are peculiarities in the vocal organization of
every person, tending to produce peculiarities of pronunciation;
for example, it has been stated that each child in a family of
six gave the monosyllable, fly, in a different manner, (eye, fy,
ly, &c.) until, when the organs were more advanced, correct
example induced the proper pronunciation of this and similar
words.  Such departures from orthoepy are only to be checked
by the power of such example; but this is a power not always
present, or not always of sufficient strength.  The able and
self-devoted Robert Moffat, in his work on South Africa, states,
without the least regard to hypothesis, that amongst the people
of the towns of that great region, “the purity and harmony
of language is kept up by their pitchos or public meetings, by
their festivals and ceremonies, as well as by their songs and
their constant intercourse.  With the isolated villages of
the desert it is far otherwise.  They have no such meetings;
they are compelled to traverse the wilds, often to a great
distance from their native village.  On such occasions,
fathers and mothers, and all who can bear a burden, often set out
for weeks at a time, and leave their children to the care of two
or three infirm old people.  The infant progeny, some of
whom are beginning to lisp, while others can just master a whole
sentence, and those still farther advanced, romping and playing
together, the children of nature, through the live-long day,
become habituated to a language of their own.  The
more voluble condescend to the less precocious, and thus, from
this infant Babel, proceeds a dialect composed of a host of
mongrel words and phrases, joined together without rule, and
in the course of a generation the entire character of the
language is changed.” [317]  I have been
told, that in like manner the children of the Manchester factory
workers, left for a great part of the day, in large assemblages,
under the care of perhaps a single elderly person, and spending
the time in amusements, are found to make a great deal of new
language.  I have seen children in other circumstances amuse
themselves by concocting and throwing into the family circulation
entirely new words; and I believe I am running little risk of
contradiction when I say that there is scarcely a family, even
amongst the middle classes of this country, who have not some
peculiarities of pronunciation and syntax, which have originated
amongst themselves, it is hardly possible to say how.  All
these things being considered, it is easy to understand how
mankind have come at length to possess between three and four
thousand languages, all different at least as much as French,
German, and English, though, as has been shewn, the traces of a
common origin are observable in them all.
What has been said on the question whether mankind were
originally barbarous or civilized, will have prepared the reader
for understanding how the arts and sciences, and the rudiments of
civilization itself, took their rise amongst men.  The only
source of fallacious views on this subject is the so frequent
observation of arts, sciences, and social modes, forms, and
ideas, being not indigenous where we see them now flourishing,
but known to have been derived elsewhere: thus Rome borrowed from
Greece, Greece from Egypt, and Egypt itself, lost in the mists of
historic antiquity, is now supposed to have obtained the light of
knowledge from some still earlier scene of intellectual
culture.  This has caused to many a great difficulty in
supposing a natural or spontaneous origin for civilization and
the attendant arts.  But, in the first place, several stages
of derivation are no conclusive argument against there having
been an originality at some earlier stage.  In the second,
such observers have not looked far enough, for, if they had, they
could have seen various instances of civilizations which it is
impossible, with any plausibility, to trace back to a common
origin with others; such are those of China and America. 
They would also have seen civilization springing up, as it were,
like oases amongst the arid plains of barbarism, as in the case
of the Mandans.  A still more attentive study of the subject
would have shewn, amongst living men, the very psychological
procedure on which the origination of civilization and the arts
and sciences depended.
These things, like language, are simply the effects of the
spontaneous working of certain mental faculties, each in relation
to the things of the external world on which it was intended by
creative Providence to be exercised.  The monkeys
themselves, without instruction from any quarter, learn to use
sticks in fighting, and some build houses—an act which
cannot in their case be considered as one of instinct, but of
intelligence.  Such being the case, there is no necessary
difficulty in supposing how man, with his superior mental
organization, (a brain five times heavier,) was able, in his
primitive state, without instruction, to turn many things in
nature to his use, and commence, in short, the circle of the
domestic arts.  He appears, in the most unfavourable
circumstances, to be able to provide himself with some sort of
dwelling, to make weapons, and to practise some simple kind of
cookery.  But, granting, it will be said, that he can go
thus far, how does he ever proceed farther unprompted, seeing
that many nations remain fixed for ever at this point, and seem
unable to take one step in advance?  It is perfectly true
that there is such a fixation in many nations; but, on the other
hand, all nations are not alike in mental organization, and
another point has been established, that only when some
favourable circumstances have settled a people in one place, do
arts and social arrangements get leave to flourish.  If we
were to limit our view to humbly endowed nations, or the common
class of minds in those called civilized, we should see
absolutely no conceivable power for the origination of new ideas
and devices.  But let us look at the inventive class of
minds which stand out amongst their fellows—the men who,
with little prompting or none, conceive new ideas in science,
arts, morals—and we can be at no loss to understand how and
whence have arisen the elements of that civilization which
history traces from country to country throughout the course of
centuries.  See a Pascal, reproducing the
Alexandrian’s problems at fifteen; a Ferguson, making
clocks from the suggestions of his own brain, while tending
cattle on a Morayshire heath; a boy Lawrence, in an inn on the
Bath road, producing, without a master, drawings which the
educated could not but admire; or look at Solon and Confucius,
devising sage laws, and breathing the accents of all but divine
wisdom, for their barbarous fellow-countrymen, three thousand
years ago—and the whole mystery is solved at once. 
Amongst the arrangements of Providence is one for the production
of original, inventive, and aspiring minds, which, when
circumstances are not decidedly unfavourable, strike out new
ideas for the benefit of their fellow-creatures, or put upon them
a lasting impress of their own superior sentiments. 
Nations, improved by these means, become in turn foci for
the diffusion of light over the adjacent regions of
barbarism—their very passions helping to this end, for
nothing can be more clear than that ambitious aggression has led
to the civilization of many countries.  Such is the process
which seems to form the destined means for bringing mankind from
the darkness of barbarism to the day of knowledge and mechanical
and social improvement.  Even the noble art of letters is
but, as Dr. Adam Fergusson has remarked, “a natural produce
of the human mind, which will rise spontaneously, wherever men
are happily placed;” original alike amongst the ancient
Egyptians and the dimly monumented Toltecans of Yucatan. 
“Banish,” says Dr. Gall, “music, poetry,
painting, sculpture, architecture, all the arts and sciences, and
let your Homers, Raphaels, Michael Angelos, Glucks, and Canovas,
be forgotten, yet let men of genius of every description spring
up, and poetry, music, painting, architecture, sculpture, and all
the arts and sciences will again shine out in all their
glory.  Twice within the records of history has the human
race traversed the great circle of its entire destiny, and twice
has the rudeness of barbarism been followed by a higher degree of
refinement.  It is a great mistake to suppose one people to
have proceeded from another on account of their conformity of
manners, customs, and arts.  The swallow of Paris builds its
nest like the swallow of Vienna, but does it thence follow that
the former sprung from the latter?  With the same causes we
have the same effects; with the same organization we have the
manifestation of the same powers.”</div></body></text></TEI>