<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="21">
CHAPTER V.
Analysis of the Process of Induction.
Aphorism XXXIV.
The Process of Induction may be resolved into three steps;
the Selection of the Idea, the Construction of the Conception,
and the Determination of the Magnitudes.
Aphorism XXXV.
These three steps correspond to the determination of the
Independent Variable, the Formula, and the Coefficients,
in mathematical investigations; or to the Argument, the
Law, and the Numerical Data, in a Table of an astronomical
or other Inequality.
Aphorism XXXVI.
The Selection of the Idea depends mainly upon inventive
sagacity: which operates by suggesting and trying various
hypotheses. Some inquirers try erroneous hypotheses; and
thus, exhausting the forms of errour, form the Prelude to
Discovery.
Aphorism XXXVII.
The following Rules may be given, in order to the selection
of the Idea for purposes of Induction:—the Idea and the
Facts must be homogeneous; and the Rule must be tested
by the Facts.
Sect. I.—The Three Steps of Induction.
1. WHEN
facts have been decomposed and phenomena measured,
the philosopher endeavours to combine them into general laws,
by the aid of 187 Ideas and Conceptions; these being
illustrated and regulated by such means as we have spoken of in the last
two chapters. In this task, of gathering laws of nature
from observed facts, as we have already
said24, the natural
sagacity of gifted minds is the power by which
the greater part of the successful results have been
obtained; and this power will probably always be more
efficacious than any Method can be. Still there are
certain methods of procedure which may, in such investigations,
give us no inconsiderable aid, and these I
shall endeavour to expound.
24 B. ii. c. vi.
2. For this purpose, I remark that the Colligation
of ascertained Facts into general Propositions may be
considered as containing three steps, which I shall
term the Selection of the Idea, the Construction of the
Conception, and the Determination of the Magnitudes.
It will be recollected that by the word Idea,
(or Fundamental Idea,) used in a peculiar sense, I mean certain
wide and general fields of intelligible relation, such as
Space, Number, Cause, Likeness; while by Conception
I denote more special modifications of these ideas, as a
circle, a square number, a uniform force, a like form of
flower. Now in order to establish any law by reference
to facts, we must select the true Idea and the true
Conception. For example; when Hipparchus
found25
that the distance of the bright star Spica Virginis from
the equinoxial point had increased by two degrees in
about two hundred years, and desired to reduce this
change to a law, he had first to assign, if possible, the
idea on which it depended;—whether it was regulated
for instance, by space, or by time; whether it was determined
by the positions of other stars at each moment, or went on
progressively with the lapse of ages.
And when there was found reason to select time as the
regulative idea of this change, it was then to be determined
how the change went on with the time;—whether uniformly,
or in some other manner: the conception, or the rule
of the progression, was to be 188 rightly constructed.
Finally, it being ascertained that
the change did go on uniformly, the question then
occurred what was its amount:—whether exactly a
degree in a century, or more, or less, and how much:
and thus the determination of the magnitude completed
the discovery of the law of phenomena respecting this star.
25 Hist. Ind. Sc. b. iii. c. iv. sect. 3.
3. Steps similar to these three may be discerned
in all other discoveries of laws of nature. Thus, in
investigating the laws of the motions of the sun, moon
or planets, we find that these motions may be resolved,
besides a uniform motion, into a series of partial motions,
or Inequalities; and for each of these Inequalities,
we have to learn upon what it directly depends, whether
upon the progress of time only, or upon some configuration
of the heavenly bodies in space; then, we have
to ascertain its law; and finally, we have to determine
what is its amount. In the case of such Inequalities,
the fundamental element on which the Inequality depends,
is called by mathematicians the Argument. And
when the Inequality has been fully reduced to known
rules, and expressed in the form of a Table, the Argument
is the fundamental Series of Numbers which
stands in the margin of the Table, and by means of
which we refer to the other Numbers which express
the Inequality. Thus, in order to obtain from a Solar
Table the Inequality of the sun’s annual motion, the
Argument is the Number which expresses the day of
the year; the Inequalities for each day being (in the
Table) ranged in a line corresponding to the days.
Moreover, the Argument of an Inequality being assumed
to be known, we must, in order to calculate the
Table, that is, in order to exhibit the law of nature,
know also the Law of the Inequality, and its Amount.
And the investigation of these three things, the Argument,
the Law, and the Amount of the Inequality,
represents the three steps above described, the
Selection of the Idea, the Construction of the Conception,
and the Determination of the Magnitude.
4. In a great body of cases, mathematical language
and calculation are used to express the
connexion 189 between
the general law and the special facts. And when
this is done, the three steps above described may be
spoken of as the Selection of the Independent Variable,
the Construction of the Formula, and the Determination
of the Coefficients. It may be worth our while to
attend to an exemplification of this. Suppose then,
that, in such observations as we have just spoken of,
namely, the shifting of a star from its place in the
heavens by an unknown law, astronomers had, at the
end of three successive years, found that the star had
removed by 3, by 8, and by 15 minutes from its original place.
Suppose it to be ascertained also, by
methods of which we shall hereafter treat, that this
change depends upon the time; we must then take the
time, (which we may denote by the symbol t,) for the
independent variable. But though the star changes
its place with the time, the change is not proportional
to the time; for its motion which is only 3 minutes in
the first year, is 5 minutes in the second year, and 7
in the third. But it is not difficult for a person a little
versed in mathematics to perceive that the series 3, 8,
15, may be obtained by means of two terms, one of
which is proportional to the time, and the other to the
square of the time; that is, it is expressed by the formula at + btt.
The question then occurs, what are the
values of the coefficients a and b;
and a little examination of the case shows us that a must be 2,
and b, 1: so that the formula is 2t + tt.
Indeed if we add together the series 2, 4, 6, which expresses a change
proportional to the time, and 1, 4, 9, which is proportional
to the square of the time, we obtain the series
3, 8, 15, which is the series of numbers given by observation.
And thus the three steps which give us the
Idea, the Conception, and the Magnitudes; or the
Argument, the Law, and the Amount, of the change;
give us the Independent Variable, the Formula, and
the Coefficients, respectively.
We now proceed to offer some suggestions of methods
by which each of these steps may be in some degree
promoted. 190
Sect. II.—Of the
Selection of the Fundamental Idea.
5. When we turn our thoughts upon any assemblage of
facts, with a view of collecting from them
some connexion or law, the most important step, and
at the same time that in which rules can least aid us, is
the Selection of the Idea by which they are to be
collected. So long as this idea has not been detected,
all seems to be hopeless confusion or insulated facts;
when the connecting idea has been caught sight of, we
constantly regard the facts with reference to their
connexion, and wonder that it should be possible for
any one to consider them in any other point of view.
Thus the different seasons, and the various aspects
of the heavenly bodies, might at first appear to be
direct manifestations from some superior power, which
man could not even understand: but it was soon found
that the ideas of time and space, of motion and recurrence,
would give coherency to many of the phenomena. Yet this
took place by successive steps. Eclipses,
for a long period, seemed to follow no law; and being
very remarkable events, continued to be deemed the
indications of a supernatural will, after the common
motions of the heavens were seen to be governed by
relations of time and space. At length, however, the
Chaldeans discovered that, after a period of eighteen
years, similar sets of eclipses recur; and, thus selecting
the idea of time, simply, as that to which these events
were to be referred, they were able to reduce them to
rule; and from that time, eclipses were recognized as
parts of a regular order of things. We may, in the
same manner, consider any other course of events, and
may enquire by what idea they are bound together.
For example, if we take the weather, years peculiarly
wet or dry, hot and cold, productive and unproductive,
follow each other in a manner which, at first sight at
least, seems utterly lawless and irregular. Now can we
in any way discover some rule and order in these
occurrences? Is there, for example, in these events,
as in eclipses, a certain cycle of years, after which like 191
seasons come round again? or does the weather depend
upon the force of some extraneous body—for instance,
the moon—and follow in some way her aspects? or
would the most proper way of investigating this subject
be to consider the effect of the moisture and heat of
various tracts of the earth’s surface upon the ambient
air? It is at our choice to try these and other modes
of obtaining a science of the weather: that is, we may
refer the phenomena to the idea of time, introducing
the conception of a cycle;—or to the idea of external
force, by the conception of the moon’s action;—or to the
idea of mutual action, introducing the conceptions of
thermotical and atmological agencies, operating between
different regions of earth, water, and air.
6. It may be asked, How are we to decide in such
alternatives? How are we to select the one right idea
out of several conceivable ones? To which we can only
reply, that this must be done by trying which will
succeed. If there really exist a cycle of the weather, as
well as of eclipses, this must be established by comparing
the asserted cycle with a good register of the seasons,
of sufficient extent. Or if the moon really influence
the meteorological conditions of the air, the asserted
influence must be compared with the observed facts,
and so accepted or rejected. When Hipparchus had
observed the increase of longitude of the stars, the idea
of a motion of the celestial sphere suggested itself as
the explanation of the change; but this thought was
verified only by observing several stars.
It was conceivable that each star should have an independent
motion, governed by time only, or by other circumstances,
instead of being regulated by its place in the
sphere; and this possibility could be rejected by trial
alone. In like manner, the original opinion of the
composition of bodies supposed the compounds to derive
their properties from the elements according to the law
of likeness; but this opinion was overturned by a
thousand facts; and thus the really applicable Idea
of Chemical Composition was introduced in modern
times. In what has already been said on the History
of Ideas, we have seen how each science was in a state 192
of confusion and darkness till the right idea was introduced.
7. No general method of evolving such ideas can be
given. Such events appear to result from a peculiar
sagacity and felicity of mind;—never without labour,
never without preparation;—yet with no constant dependence
upon preparation, or upon labour, or even
entirely upon personal endowments. Newton explained
the colours which refraction produces, by referring
each colour to a peculiar angle of refraction,
thus introducing the right idea. But when the same philosopher
tried to explain the colours produced by diffraction, he
erred, by attempting to apply the same idea, (the course
of a single ray,) instead of applying the truer idea, of
the interference of two rays. Newton gave a wrong
rule for the double refraction of Iceland spar, by
making the refraction depend on the edges of the rhombohedron:
Huyghens, more happy, introduced the
idea of the axis of symmetry of the solid, and thus was
able to give the true law of the phenomena.
8. Although the selected idea is proved to be the
right one, only when the true law of nature is established
by means of it, yet it often happens that there
prevails a settled conviction respecting the relation
which must afford the key to the phenomena, before
the selection has been confirmed by the laws to which
it leads. Even before the empirical laws of the tides
were made out, it was not doubtful that these laws
depended upon the places and motions of the sun and
moon. We know that the crystalline form of a body
must depend upon its chemical composition, though
we are as yet unable to assign the law of this dependence.
Indeed in most cases of great discoveries, the right
idea to which the facts were to be referred, was selected
by many philosophers, before the decisive demonstration
that it was the right idea, was given by the
discoverer. Thus Newton showed that the motions of
the planets might be explained by means of a central
force in the sun: but though he established, he did not
first select the idea involved in the conception of a 193
central force. The idea had already been sufficiently
pointed out, dimly by Kepler, more clearly by Borelli,
Huyghens, Wren, and Hooke. Indeed this anticipation of
the true idea is always a principal part of that
which, in the History of the Sciences, we have termed
the Prelude of a Discovery. The two steps of proposing
a philosophical problem, and of solving it, are, as
we have elsewhere said, both important, and are often
performed by different persons. The former step is, in
fact, the Selection of the Idea. In explaining any
change, we have to discover first the Argument, and
then the Law of the change. The selection of the
Argument is the step of which we here speak; and is
that in which inventiveness of mind and justness of
thought are mainly shown.
9. Although, as we have said, we can give few precise directions
for this cardinal process, the Selection of
the Idea, in speculating on phenomena, yet there is
one Rule which may have its use: it is this:—The idea
and the facts must be homogeneous: the elementary
Conceptions, into which the facts have been decomposed,
must be of the same nature as the Idea by
which we attempt to collect them into laws. Thus, if
facts have been observed and measured by reference to
space, they must be bound together by the idea of
space: if we would obtain a knowledge of mechanical
forces in the solar system, we must observe mechanical
phenomena. Kepler erred against this rule in his
attempts at obtaining physical laws of the system; for
the facts which he took were the velocities, not the
changes of velocity, which are really the mechanical
facts. Again, there has been a transgression of this
Rule committed by all chemical philosophers who have
attempted to assign the relative position of the elementary
particles of bodies in their component molecules. For their
purpose has been to discover the
relations of the particles in space; and yet they have
neglected the only facts in the constitution of bodies
which have a reference to space—namely, crystalline
form, and optical properties. No progress can be made
in the theory of the elementary structure of bodies, 194
without making these classes of facts the main basis of
our speculations.
10. The only other Rule which I have to offer on
this subject, is that which I have already given:—the
Idea must be tested by the facts. It must be tried by
applying to the facts the conceptions which are derived
from the idea, and not accepted till some of these succeed
in giving the law of the phenomena. The justice
of the suggestion cannot be known otherwise than by
making the trial. If we can discover a true law by
employing any conceptions, the idea from which these
conceptions are derived is the right one; nor can there
be any proof of its rightness so complete and satisfactory,
as that we are by it led to a solid and permanent
truth.
This, however, can hardly be termed a Rule; for
when we would know, to conjecture and to try the
truth of our conjecture by a comparison with the facts,
is the natural and obvious dictate of common sense.
Supposing the Idea which we adopt, or which we
would try, to be now fixed upon, we still have before
us the range of many Conceptions derived from it;
many Formulæ may be devised depending on the same
Independent Variable, and we must now consider how
our selection among these is to be made.
</div></body></text></TEI>