<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="4">
NOVUM ORGANON RENOVATUM.
The name Organon was applied to the works of
Aristotle which treated of Logic, that is, of the method
of establishing and proving knowledge, and of refuting
errour, by means of Syllogisms. Francis Bacon, holding
that this method was insufficient and futile for
the augmentation of real and useful knowledge, published
his Novum Organon, in which he proposed for
that purpose methods from which he promised a better
success. Since his time real and useful knowledge has
made great progress, and many Sciences have been
greatly extended or newly constructed; so that even
if Bacon’s method had been the right one, and had
been complete as far as the progress of Science up to
his time could direct it, there would be room for the
revision and improvement of the methods of arriving
at scientific knowledge.
Inasmuch as we have gone through the Histories
of the principal Sciences, from the earliest up to the
present time, in a previous work, and have also traced
the History of Scientific Ideas in another work, it
may perhaps be regarded as not too presumptuous if
we attempt this revision and improvement of the
methods by which Sciences must rise and grow.
This 4
is our task in the present volume; and to mark the
reference of this undertaking to the work of Bacon, we
name our book Novum Organon Renovatum.
Bacon has delivered his precepts in Aphorisms,
some of them stated nakedly, others expanded into
dissertations. The general results at which we have
arrived by tracing the history of Scientific Ideas are
the groundwork of such Precepts as we have to give:
and I shall therefore begin by summing up these
results in Aphorisms, referring to the former work
for the historical proof that these Aphorisms are true.
</div></body></text></TEI>