<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="42">

CHAPTER XXXIII.
OF THE ASSOCIATION OF IDEAS.

1. Something unreasonable in most Men.


There is scarce any one that does not observe something that seems odd to him,
and is in itself really extravagant, in the opinions, reasonings, and actions
of other men. The least flaw of this kind, if at all different from his own,
every one is quick-sighted enough to espy in another, and will by the authority
of reason forwardly condemn; though he be guilty of much greater
unreasonableness in his own tenets and conduct, which he never perceives, and
will very hardly, if at all, be convinced of.


2. Not wholly from Self-love.


This proceeds not wholly from self-love, though that has often a great hand in
it. Men of fair minds, and not given up to the overweening of self-flattery,
are frequently guilty of it; and in many cases one with amazement hears the
arguings, and is astonished at the obstinacy of a worthy man, who yields not to
the evidence of reason, though laid before him as clear as daylight.


3. Not from Education.


This sort of unreasonableness is usually imputed to education and prejudice,
and for the most part truly enough, though that reaches not the bottom of the
disease, nor shows distinctly enough whence it rises, or wherein it lies.
Education is often rightly assigned for the cause, and prejudice is a good
general name for the thing itself: but yet, I think, he ought to look a little
further, who would trace this sort of madness to the root it springs from, and
so explain it, as to show whence this flaw has its original in very sober and
rational minds, and wherein it consists.


4. A Degree of Madness found in most Men.


I shall be pardoned for calling it by so harsh a name as madness, when it is
considered that opposition to reason deserves that name, and is really madness;
and there is scarce a man so free from it, but that if he should always, on all
occasions, argue or do as in some cases he constantly does, would not be
thought fitter for Bedlam than civil conversation. I do not here mean when he
is under the power of an unruly passion, but in the steady calm course of his
life. That which will yet more apologize for this harsh name, and ungrateful
imputation on the greatest part of mankind, is, that, inquiring a little by the
bye into the nature of madness, (b. ii. ch. xi., Section 13,) I found it to
spring from the very same root, and to depend on the very same cause we are
here speaking of. This consideration of the thing itself, at a time when I
thought not the least on the subject which I am now treating of, suggested it
to me. And if this be a weakness to which all men are so liable, if this be a
taint which so universally infects mankind, the greater care should be taken to
lay it open under its due name, thereby to excite the greater care in its
prevention and cure.


5. From a wrong Connexion of Ideas.


Some of our ideas have a NATURAL correspondence and connexion one with another:
it is the office and excellency of our reason to trace these, and hold them
together in that union and correspondence which is founded in their peculiar
beings. Besides this, there is another connexion of ideas wholly owing to
CHANCE or CUSTOM. Ideas that in themselves are not all of kin, come to be so
united in some men’s minds, that it is very hard to separate them; they always
keep in company, and the one no sooner at any time comes into the
understanding, but its associate appears with it; and if they are more than two
which are thus united, the whole gang, always inseparable, show themselves
together.


6. This Connexion made by custom.


This strong combination of ideas, not allied by nature, the mind makes in
itself either voluntarily or by chance; and hence it comes in different men to
be very different, according to their different inclinations, education,
interests, &c. CUSTOM settles habits of thinking in the understanding, as
well as of determining in the will, and of motions in the body: all which seems
to be but trains of motions in the animal spirits, which, once set a going,
continue in the same steps they have been used to; which, by often treading,
are worn into a smooth path, and the motion in it becomes easy, and as it were
natural. As far as we can comprehend thinking, thus ideas seem to be produced
in our minds; or, if they are not, this may serve to explain their following
one another in an habitual train, when once they are put into their track, as
well as it does to explain such motions of the body. A musician used to any
tune will find that, let it but once begin in his head, the ideas of the
several notes of it will follow one another orderly in his understanding,
without any care or attention, as regularly as his fingers move orderly over
the keys of the organ to play out the tune he has begun, though his unattentive
thoughts be elsewhere a wandering. Whether the natural cause of these ideas, as
well as of that regular dancing of his fingers be the motion of his animal
spirits, I will not determine, how probable soever, by this instance, it
appears to be so: but this may help us a little to conceive of intellectual
habits, and of the tying together of ideas.


7. Some Antipathies an Effect of it.


That there are such associations of them made by custom, in the minds of most
men, I think nobody will question, who has well considered himself or others;
and to this, perhaps, might be justly attributed most of the sympathies and
antipathies observable in men, which work as strongly, and produce as regular
effects as if they were natural; and are therefore called so, though they at
first had no other original but the accidental connexion of two ideas, which
either the strength of the first impression, or future indulgence so united,
that they always afterwards kept company together in that man’s mind, as if
they were but one idea. I say most of the antipathies, I do not say all; for
some of them are truly natural, depend upon our original constitution, and are
born with us; but a great part of those which are counted natural, would have
been known to be from unheeded, though perhaps early, impressions, or wanton
fancies at first, which would have been acknowledged the original of them, if
they had been warily observed. A grown person surfeiting with honey no sooner
hears the name of it, but his fancy immediately carries sickness and qualms to
his stomach, and he cannot bear the very idea of it; other ideas of dislike,
and sickness, and vomiting, presently accompany it, and he is disturbed; but he
knows from whence to date this weakness, and can tell how he got this
indisposition. Had this happened to him by an over-dose of honey when a child,
all the same effects would have followed; but the cause would have been
mistaken, and the antipathy counted natural.


8. Influence of association to be watched educating young children.


I mention this, not out of any great necessity there is in this present
argument to distinguish nicely between natural and acquired antipathies; but I
take notice of it for another purpose, viz. that those who have children, or
the charge of their education, would think it worth their while diligently to
watch, and carefully to prevent the undue connexion of ideas in the minds of
young people. This is the time most susceptible of lasting impressions; and
though those relating to the health of the body are by discreet people minded
and fenced against, yet I am apt to doubt, that those which relate more
peculiarly to the mind, and terminate in the understanding or passions, have
been much less heeded than the thing deserves: nay, those relating purely to
the understanding, have, as I suspect, been by most men wholly overlooked.


9. Wrong connexion of ideas a great Cause of Errors.


This wrong connexion in our minds of ideas in themselves loose and independent
of one another, has such an influence, and is of so great force to set us awry
in our actions, as well moral as natural, passions, reasonings, and notions
themselves, that perhaps there is not any one thing that deserves more to be
looked after.


10. As instance.


The ideas of goblins and sprites have really no more to do with darkness than
light: yet let but a foolish maid inculcate these often on the mind of a child,
and raise them there together, possibly he shall never be able to separate them
again so long as he lives, but darkness shall ever afterwards bring with it
those frightful ideas, and they shall be so joined, that he can no more bear
the one than the other.


11. Another instance.


A man receives a sensible injury from another, thinks on the man and that
action over and over, and by ruminating on them strongly, or much, in his mind,
so cements those two ideas together, that he makes them almost one; never
thinks on the man, but the pain and displeasure he suffered comes into his mind
with it, so that he scarce distinguishes them, but has as much an aversion for
the one as the other. Thus hatreds are often begotten from slight and innocent
occasions, and quarrels propagated and continued in the world.


12. A third instance.


A man has suffered pain or sickness in any place; he saw his friend die in such
a room: though these have in nature nothing to do one with another, yet when
the idea of the place occurs to his mind, it brings (the impression being once
made) that of the pain and displeasure with it: he confounds them in his mind,
and can as little bear the one as the other.


13. Why Time cures some Disorders in the Mind, which Reason cannot cure.


When this combination is settled, and while it lasts, it is not in the power of
reason to help us, and relieve us from the effects of it. Ideas in our minds,
when they are there, will operate according to their natures and circumstances.
And here we see the cause why time cures certain affections, which reason,
though in the right, and allowed to be so, has not power over, nor is able
against them to prevail with those who are apt to hearken to it in other cases.
The death of a child that was the daily delight of its mother’s eyes, and joy
of her soul, rends from her heart the whole comfort of her life, and gives her
all the torment imaginable: use the consolations of reason in this case, and
you were as good preach ease to one on the rack, and hope to allay, by rational
discourses, the pain of his joints tearing asunder. Till time has by disuse
separated the sense of that enjoyment and its loss, from the idea of the child
returning to her memory, all representations, though ever so reasonable, are in
vain; and therefore some in whom the union between these ideas is never
dissolved, spend their lives in mourning, and carry an incurable sorrow to
their graves.


14. Another instance of the Effect of the Association of Ideas.


A friend of mine knew one perfectly cured of madness by a very harsh and
offensive operation. The gentleman who was thus recovered, with great sense of
gratitude and acknowledgment owned the cure all his life after, as the greatest
obligation he could have received; but, whatever gratitude and reason suggested
to him, he could never bear the sight of the operator: that image brought back
with it the idea of that agony which he suffered from his hands, which was too
mighty and intolerable for him to endure.


15. More instances.


Many children, imputing the pain they endured at school to their books they
were corrected for, so join those ideas together, that a book becomes their
aversion, and they are never reconciled to the study and use of them all their
lives after; and thus reading becomes a torment to them, which otherwise
possibly they might have made the great pleasure of their lives. There are
rooms convenient enough, that some men cannot study in, and fashions of
vessels, which, though ever so clean and commodious, they cannot drink out of,
and that by reason of some accidental ideas which are annexed to them, and make
them offensive; and who is there that hath not observed some man to flag at the
appearance, or in the company of some certain person not otherwise superior to
him, but because, having once on some occasion got the ascendant, the idea of
authority and distance goes along with that of the person, and he that has been
thus subjected, is not able to separate them.


16. A curious instance.


Instances of this kind are so plentiful everywhere, that if I add one more, it
is only for the pleasant oddness of it. It is of a young gentleman, who, having
learnt to dance, and that to great perfection, there happened to stand an old
trunk in the room where he learnt. The idea of this remarkable piece of
household stuff had so mixed itself with the turns and steps of all his dances,
that though in that chamber he could dance excellently well, yet it was only
whilst that trunk was there; nor could he perform well in any other place,
unless that or some such other trunk had its due position in the room. If this
story shall be suspected to be dressed up with some comical circumstances, a
little beyond precise nature, I answer for myself that I had it some years
since from a very sober and worthy man, upon his own knowledge, as I report it;
and I dare say there are very few inquisitive persons who read this, who have
not met with accounts, if not examples, of this nature, that may parallel, or
at least justify this.


17. Influence of Association on intellectual Habits.


Intellectual habits and defects this way contracted, are not less frequent and
powerful, though less observed. Let the ideas of being and matter be strongly
joined, either by education or much thought; whilst these are still combined in
the mind, what notions, what reasonings, will there be about separate spirits?
Let custom from the very childhood have joined figure and shape to the idea of
God, and what absurdities will that mind be liable to about the Deity? Let the
idea of infallibility be inseparably joined to any person, and these two
constantly together possess the mind; and then one body in two places at once,
shall unexamined be swallowed for a certain truth, by an implicit faith,
whenever that imagined infallible person dictates and demands assent without
inquiry.


18. Observable in the opposition between different Sects of philosophy and of
religion.


Some such wrong and unnatural combinations of ideas will be found to establish
the irreconcilable opposition between different sects of philosophy and
religion; for we cannot imagine every one of their followers to impose wilfully
on himself, and knowingly refuse truth offered by plain reason. Interest,
though it does a great deal in the case, yet cannot be thought to work whole
societies of men to so universal a perverseness, as that every one of them to a
man should knowingly maintain falsehood: some at least must be allowed to do
what all pretend to, i.e. to pursue truth sincerely; and therefore there must
be something that blinds their understandings, and makes them not see the
falsehood of what they embrace for real truth. That which thus captivates their
reasons, and leads men of sincerity blindfold from common sense, will, when
examined, be found to be what we are speaking of: some independent ideas, of no
alliance to one another, are, by education, custom, and the constant din of
their party, so coupled in their minds, that they always appear there together;
and they can no more separate them in their thoughts than if they were but one
idea, and they operate as if they were so. This gives sense to jargon,
demonstration to absurdities, and consistency to nonsense, and is the
foundation of the greatest, I had almost said of all the errors in the world;
or, if it does not reach so far, it is at least the most dangerous one, since,
so far as it obtains, it hinders men from seeing and examining. When two
things, in themselves disjoined, appear to the sight constantly united; if the
eye sees these things riveted which are loose, where will you begin to rectify
the mistakes that follow in two ideas that they have been accustomed so to join
in their minds as to substitute one for the other, and, as I am apt to think,
often without perceiving it themselves? This, whilst they are under the deceit
of it, makes them incapable of conviction, and they applaud themselves as
zealous champions for truth, when indeed they are contending for error; and the
confusion of two different ideas, which a customary connexion of them in their
minds hath to them made in effect but one, fills their heads with false views,
and their reasonings with false consequences.


19. Conclusion.


Having thus given an account of the original, sorts, and extent of our IDEAS,
with several other considerations about these (I know not whether I may say)
instruments, or materials of our knowledge, the method I at first proposed to
myself would now require that I should immediately proceed to show, what use
the understanding makes of them, and what KNOWLEDGE we have by them. This was
that which, in the first general view I had of this subject, was all that I
thought I should have to do: but, upon a nearer approach, I find that there is
so close a connexion between ideas and WORDS, and our abstract ideas and
general words have so constant a relation one to another, that it is impossible
to speak clearly and distinctly of our knowledge, which all consists in
propositions, without considering, first, the nature, use, and signification of
Language; which, therefore, must be the business of the next Book.

END OF VOLUME I
</div></body></text></TEI>