<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="2"> 

CHAPTER III.
Of Facts as the Materials of Science.


Aphorism IV.
Facts are the materials of science, but all Facts involve
Ideas. Since in observing Facts, we cannot exclude Ideas,
we must, for the purposes of science, take care that the Ideas
are clear and rigorously applied.
Aphorism V.
The last Aphorism leads to such Rules as the following:—That
Facts, for the purposes of material science, must involve
Conceptions of the Intellect only, and not Emotions:—That
Facts must be observed with reference to our most exact conceptions,
Number, Place, Figure, Motion:—That they must
also be observed with reference to any other exact conceptions
which the phenomena suggest, as Force, in mechanical phenomena,
Concord, in musical.
Aphorism VI.
The resolution of complex Facts into precise and measured
partial Facts, we call the Decomposition of Facts. This
process is requisite for the progress of science, but does not
necessarily lead to progress.

1. WE
have now to examine how Science is built
up by the combination of Facts. In doing this,
we suppose that we have already attained a supply of
definite and certain Facts, free from obscurity and doubt.
We must, therefore, first consider under what conditions
Facts can assume this character.
When we inquire what Facts are to be made the
materials of Science, perhaps the answer which we 51
should most commonly receive would be, that they
must be True Facts, as distinguished from any mere
inferences or opinions of our own. We should probably be told
that we must be careful in such a case to
consider as Facts, only what we really observe;—that
we must assert only what we see; and believe nothing
except upon the testimony of our senses.
But such maxims are far from being easy to apply,
as a little examination will convince us.
2. It has been explained, in preceding works,
that all perception of external objects and occurrences
involves an active as well as a passive process
of the mind;—includes not only Sensations, but also
Ideas by which Sensations are bound together, and
have a unity given to them. From this it follows, that
there is a difficulty in separating in our perceptions
what we receive from without, and what we ourselves
contribute from within;—what we perceive, and what
we infer. In many cases, this difficulty is obvious to
all: as, for example, when we witness the performances
of a juggler or a ventriloquist. In these instances, we
imagine ourselves to see and to hear what certainly we
do not see and hear. The performer takes advantage
of the habits by which our minds supply interruptions
and infer connexions; and by giving us fallacious
indications, he leads us to perceive as an actual fact, what
does not happen at all. In these cases, it is evident
that we ourselves assist in making the fact; for we
make one which does not really exist. In other cases,
though the fact which we perceive be true, we can
easily see that a large portion of the perception is our
own act; as when, from the sight of a bird of prey we
infer a carcase, or when we read a half-obliterated inscription.
In the latter case, the mind supplies the
meaning, and perhaps half the letters; yet we do not
hesitate to say that we actually read the inscription.
Thus, in many cases, our own inferences and interpretations
enter into our facts. But this happens in
many instances in which it is at first sight less obvious.
When any one has seen an oak-tree blown down by a
strong gust of wind, he does not think of the occurrence 52
any otherwise than as a Fact of which he is assured by
his senses. Yet by what sense does he perceive the
Force which he thus supposes the wind to exert? By
what sense does he distinguish an Oak-tree from all
other trees? It is clear upon reflexion, that in such
a case, his own mind supplies the conception of extraneous
impulse and pressure, by which he thus interprets the motions
observed, and the distinction of
different kinds of trees, according to which he thus
names the one under his notice. The Idea of Force,
and the idea of definite Resemblances and Differences,
are thus combined with the impressions on our senses,
and form an undistinguished portion of that which we
consider as the Fact. And it is evident that we can in
no other way perceive Force, than by seeing motion;
and cannot give a Name to any object, without not
only seeing a difference of single objects, but supposing
a difference of classes of objects. When we speak as
if we saw impulse and attraction, things and classes,
we really see only objects of various forms and colours,
more or less numerous, variously combined. But do
we really perceive so much as this? When we see the
form, the size, the number, the motion of objects, are
these really mere impressions on our senses, unmodified
by any contribution or operation of the mind
itself? A very little attention will suffice to convince
us that this is not the case. When we see a windmill
turning, it may happen, as we have elsewhere
noticed3,
that we mistake the direction in which the sails turn:
when we look at certain diagrams, they may appear
either convex or concave: when we see the moon first
in the horizon and afterwards high up in the sky, we
judge her to be much larger in the former than in the
latter position, although to the eye she subtends the
same angle. And in these cases and the like, it has
been seen that the errour and confusion which we thus
incur arise from the mixture of acts of the mind itself
with impressions on the senses. But such acts are, as
we have also seen, inseparable portions of the process 53
of perception. A certain activity of the mind is involved,
not only in seeing objects erroneously, but in
seeing them at all. With regard to solid objects, this
is generally acknowledged. When we seem to see an
edifice occupying space in all dimensions, we really see
only a representation of it as it appears referred by
perspective to a surface. The inference of the solid
form is an operation of our own, alike when we look at
a reality and when we look at a picture. But we may
go further. Is plane Figure really a mere Sensation?
If we look at a decagon, do we see at once that it has
ten sides, or is it not necessary for us to count them:
and is not counting an act of the mind? All objects
are seen in space; all objects are seen as one or many:
but are not the Idea of Space and the Idea of Number
requisite in order that we may thus apprehend what
we see? That these Ideas of Space and Number involve a
connexion derived from the mind, and not from
the senses, appears, as we have already seen, from this,
that those Ideas afford us the materials of universal
and necessary truths:—such truths as the senses cannot
possibly supply. And thus, even the perception of
such facts as the size, shape, and number of objects,
cannot be said to be impressions of sense, distinct from
all acts of mind, and cannot be expected to be free
from errour on the ground of their being mere observed
Facts.</div></body></text></TEI>