<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="81">CHAPTER 1.
Discovery of Laws of Electric Phenomena.
WE have already seen what was
the state of this branch of knowledge at the beginning of the
seventeenth century; and the advances made by Gilbert. We must now
notice the additions which it subsequently received, and especially
those which led to the discovery of general laws, and the
establishment of the theory; events of this kind being those of which
we have more peculiarly to trace the conditions and causes. Among the
facts which we have thus especially to attend to, are the electric
attractions of small bodies by amber and other substances when rubbed.
Boyle, who repeated and extended the experiments of Gilbert, does not
appear to have arrived at any new general notions; but Otto Guericke
of Magdeburg, about the same time, made a very material step, by
discovering that there was an electric force of repulsion as well as
of attraction. He found that when a globe of sulphur had attracted a
feather, it afterwards repelled it, till the feather had been in
contact with some other body. This, when verified under a due
generality of circumstances, forms a capital fact in our present
subject. Hawkesbee, who wrote in 1709 (Physico-Mechanical
Experiments) also observed various of the effects of attraction
and repulsion upon threads hanging loosely. But the person who appears
to have first fully seized the general law of these facts, is 194 Dufay, whose
experiments appear in the Memoirs of the French Academy, in 1733,
1734, and 1737.5 “I discovered,” he says, “a very simple
principle, which accounts for a great part of the irregularities, and,
if I may use the term, the caprices that seem to accompany most of the
experiments in electricity. This principle is, that electric bodies
attract all those that are not so, and repel them as soon as they are
become electric by the vicinity or contact of the electric body. . . .
Upon applying this principle to various experiments of electricity,
any one will be surprised at the number of obscure and puzzling facts
which it clears up.” By the help of this principle, he endeavors to
explain several of Hawkesbee’s experiments.
5 Priestley’s History of
Electricity, p. 45, and the Memoirs quoted.
A little anterior to Dufay’s experiments were those of Grey, who,
in 1729, discovered the properties of conductors. He found that
the attraction and repulsion which appear in electric bodies are
exhibited also by other bodies in contact with the electric. In this
manner he found that an ivory ball, connected with a glass tube by a
stick, a wire, or a packthread, attracted and repelled a feather, as
the glass itself would have done. He was then led to try to extend
this communication to considerable distances, first by ascending to an
upper window and hanging down his ball, and, afterwards, by carrying
the string horizontally supported on loops. As his success was
complete in the former case, he was perplexed by failure in the
latter; but when he supported the string by loops of silk instead of
hempen cords, he found it again become a conductor of electricity.
This he ascribed at first to the smaller thickness of the silk, which
did not carry off so much of the electric virtue; but from this
explanation he was again driven, by finding that wires of brass still
thinner than the silk destroyed the effect. Thus Grey perceived that
the efficacy of the support depended on its being silk, and he soon
found other substances which answered the same purpose. The
difference, in fact, depended on the supporting substance being
electric, and therefore not itself a conductor; for it soon appeared
from such experiments, and especially6 from those made
by Dufay, that substances might be divided into electrics per
se, and non-electrics, or conductors. These terms
were introduced by Desaguliers,7 and gave a
permanent currency to the results of the labors of Grey and
others.
6 Mém. Acad. Par. 1734.
7 Priestley, p. 66.
Another very important discovery belonging to this period is, that
195 of the two
kinds of electricity. This also was made by Dufay. “Chance,” says he,
“has thrown in my way another principle more universal and remarkable
than the preceding one, and which casts a new light upon the subject
of electricity. The principle is, that there are two distinct kinds of
electricity, very different from one another; one of which I call
vitreous, the other resinous, electricity. The first is
that of glass, gems, hair, wool, &c.; the second is that of amber,
gum-lac, silk, &c. The characteristic of these two electricities
is, that they repel themselves and attract each other.” This discovery
does not, however, appear to have drawn so much attention as it
deserved. It was published in 1735; (in the Memoirs of the Academy
for 1733;) and yet in 1747, Franklin and his friends at
Philadelphia, who had been supplied with electrical apparatus and
information by persons in England well acquainted with the then
present state of the subject, imagined that they were making
observations unknown to European science, when they were led to assert
two conditions of bodies, which were in fact the opposite
electricities of Dufay, though the American experimenters referred
them to a single element, of which electrized bodies might have either
excess or defect. “Hence,” Franklin says, “have arisen some new terms
among us: we say B,” who receives a spark from glass, “and bodies in
like circumstances, is electrized positively; A,” who
communicates his electricity to glass, “negatively; or rather B
is electrized plus, A minus.” Dr. (afterwards Sir
William) Watson had, about the same time, arrived at the same
conclusions, which he expresses by saying that the electricity of A
was more rare, and that of B more dense, than it
naturally would have been.8 But that which gave the main importance
to this doctrine was its application to some remarkable experiments,
of which we must now speak.
8 Priestley, p. 115.
Electric action is accompanied, in many cases, by light and a
crackling sound. Otto Guericke9 observes that his
sulphur-globe, when rubbed in a dark place, gave faint flashes, such
as take place when sugar is crushed. And shortly after, a light was
observed at the surface of the mercury in the barometer, when shaken,
which was explained at first by Bernoulli, on the then prevalent
Cartesian principles; but, afterwards, more truly by Hawkesbee, as an
electrical phenomenon. Wall, in 1708, found sparks produced by rubbing
amber, and Hawkesbee observed the light and the snapping, as he
calls it, under various modifications. But the electric spark from a
living body, which, as 196 Priestley says,10 “makes a
principal part of the diversion of gentlemen and ladies who come to
see experiments in electricity,” was first observed by Dufay and the
Abbé Nollet. Nollet says11 he “shall never forget the surprise
which the first electric spark ever drawn from the human body excited,
both in M. Dufay and in himself.” The drawing of a spark from the
human body was practised in various forms, one of which was familiarly
known as the “electrical kiss.” Other exhibitions of electrical light
were the electrical star, electrical rain, and the like.
9 Experimenta Magdeburgica,
1672, lib. iv. cap. 15.
10 P. p. 47.
11 Priestley, p. 47. Nollet,
Leçons de Physique, vol.  vi. p. 408.
As electricians determined more exactly the conditions of
electrical action, they succeeded in rendering more intense those
sudden actions which the spark accompanies, and thus produced the
electric shock. This was especially done in the Leyden
phial. This apparatus received its name, while the discovery of
its property was attributed to Cunæus, a native of Leyden, who, in
1746, handling a vessel containing water in communication with the
electrical machine, and happening thus to bring the inside and the
outside into connexion, received a sudden shock in his arms and
breast. It appears, however,12 that a shock
had been received under nearly the same circumstances in 1746, by Von
Kleist, a German prelate, at Camin, in Pomerania. The strangeness of
this occurrence, and the suddenness of the blow, much exaggerated the
estimate which men formed of its force. Muschenbroek, after taking one
shock, declared he would not take a second for the kingdom of France;
though Boze, with a more magnanimous spirit, wished13 that he might die by such a stroke, and
have the circumstances of the experiment recorded in the Memoirs of
the Academy. But we may easily imagine what a new fame and interest
this discovery gave to the subject of electricity. It was repeated in
all parts of the world, with various modifications: and the shock was
passed through a line of several persons holding hands; Nollet, in the
presence of the king of France, sent it through a circle of 180 men of
the guards, and along a line of men and wires of 900 toises;14 and experiments of the same kind were
made in England, principally under the direction of Watson, on a scale
so large as to excite the admiration of Muschenbroek; who says, in a
letter to Watson, “Magnificentissimis tuis experimentis superasti
conatus omnium.” The result was, that the transmission of electricity
through a length of 12,000 feet was, to sense, instantaneous.
12 Fischer, v. 490.
13 Fischer, p. 84.
14 Ibid. v. 512.
197 The
essential circumstances of the electric shock were gradually
unravelled. Watson found that it did not increase in proportion either
to the contents of the phial or the size of the globe by which the
electricity was excited; that the outside coating of the glass (which,
in the first form of the experiment, was only a film of water), and
its contents, might be varied in different ways. To Franklin is due
the merit of clearly pointing out most of the circumstances on which
the efficacy of the Leyden phial depends. He showed, in 1747,15 that the inside of the bottle is
electrized positively, the outside negatively; and that the shock is
produced by the restoration of the equilibrium, when the outside and
inside are brought into communication suddenly. But in order to
complete this discovery, it remained to be shown that the electric
matter was collected entirely at the surface of the glass, and that
the opposite electricities on the two opposite sides of the glass were
accumulated by their mutual attraction. Monnier the younger discovered
that the electricity which bodies can receive, depends upon their
surface rather than their mass, and Franklin16 soon found that
“the whole force of the bottle, and power of giving a shock, is in the
glass itself.” This they proved by decanting the water out of an
electrized into another bottle, when it appeared that the second
bottle did not become electric, but the first remained so. Thus it was
found “that the non-electrics, in contact with the glass, served only
to unite the force of the several parts.”
15 Letters, p. 13.
16 Letters, iv. Sect.
16.
So far as the effect of the coating of the Leyden phial is
concerned, this was satisfactory and complete: but Franklin was not
equally successful in tracing the action of the electric matter upon
itself, in virtue of which it is accumulated in the phial; indeed, he
appears to have ascribed the effect to some property of the glass. The
mode of describing this action varied, accordingly as two electric
fluids were supposed (with Dufay,) or one, which was the view
taken by Franklin. On this latter supposition the parts of the
electric fluid repel each other, and the excess in one surface of the
glass expels the fluid from the other surface. This kind of action,
however, came into much clearer view in the experiments of Canton,
Wilcke, and Æpinus. It was principally manifested in the attractions
and repulsions which objects exert when they are in the neighborhood
of electrized bodies; or in the electrical atmosphere, using
the phraseology of the time. At present we say that bodies are
electrized by induction, when they are 198 thus made electric by the electric
attraction and repulsion of other bodies. Canton’s experiments were
communicated to the Royal Society in 1753, and show that the
electricity on each body acts upon the electricity of another body, at
a distance, with a repulsive energy. Wilcke, in like manner, showed
that parts of non-electrics, plunged in electric atmospheres, acquire
an electricity opposite to that of such atmospheres. And Æpinus
devised a method of examining the nature of the electricity at any
part of the surface of a body, by means of which he ascertained its
distribution, and found that it agreed with such a law of
self-repulsion. His attempt to give mathematical precision to this
induction was one of the most important steps towards electrical
theory, and must be spoken of shortly, in that point of view. But in
the mean time we may observe, that this doctrine was applied to the
explanation of the Leyden jar; and the explanation was confirmed by
charging a plate of air, and obtaining a shock from it, in a manner
which the theory pointed out.
Before we proceed to the history of the theory, we must mention
some other of the laws of phenomena which were noticed, and which
theory was expected to explain. Among the most celebrated of these,
were the effect of sharp points in conductors, and the phenomena of
electricity in the atmosphere. The former of these circumstances was
one of the first which Franklin observed as remarkable. It was found
that the points of needles and the like throw off and draw off the
electric virtue; thus a bodkin, directed towards an electrized ball,
at six or eight inches’ distance, destroyed its electric action. The
latter subject, involving the consideration of thunder and lightning,
and of many other meteorological phenomena, excited great interest.
The comparison of the electric spark to lightning had very early been
made; but it was only when the discharge had been rendered more
powerful in the Leyden jar, that the comparison of the effects became
very plausible. Franklin, about 1750, had offered a few somewhat vague
conjectures17 respecting the existence of electricity
in the clouds; but it was not till Wilcke and Æpinus had obtained
clear notions of the effect of electric matter at a distance, that the
real condition of the clouds could be well understood. In 1752,
however,18 D’Alibard, and other French
philosophers, were desirous of verifying Franklin’s conjecture of the
analogy of thunder and electricity. This they did by erecting a
pointed iron rod, forty feet high, 199 at Marli: the rod was found capable of
giving out electrical sparks when a thunder-cloud passed over the
place. This was repeated in various parts of Europe, and Franklin
suggested that a communication with the clouds might be formed by
means of a kite. By these, and similar means, the electricity of the
atmosphere was studied by Canton in England, Mazeas in France,
Beccaria in Italy, and others elsewhere. These essays soon led to a
fatal accident, the death of Richman at Petersburg, while he was, on
Aug. 6th, 1753, observing the electricity collected from an
approaching thunder-cloud, by means of a rod which he called an
electrical gnomon: a globe of blue fire was seen to leap from the rod
to the head of the unfortunate professor, who was thus struck
dead.
17 Letter v.
18 Franklin, p. 107.
[2nd Ed.] [As an important application of the doctrines of
electricity, I may mention the contrivances employed to protect ships
from the effects of lightning. The use of conductors in such cases is
attended with peculiar difficulties. In 1780 the French began to turn
their attention to this subject, and Le Roi was sent to Brest and the
various sea-ports of France for that purpose. Chains temporarily
applied in the rigging had been previously suggested, but he
endeavored to place, he says, such conductors in ships as might be
fixed and durable. He devised certain long linked rods, which led from
a point in the mast-head along a part of the rigging, or in divided
stages along the masts, and were fixed to plates of metal in the
ship’s sides communicating with the sea. But these were either unable
to stand the working of the rigging, or otherwise inconvenient, and
were finally abandoned.19
19 See Le Roi’s Memoir in the
Hist. Acad. Sc. for 1790.
The conductor commonly used in the English Navy, till recently,
consisted of a flexible copper chain, tied, when occasion required, to
the mast-head, and reaching down into the sea; a contrivance
recommended by Dr. Watson in 1762. But notwithstanding this
precaution, the shipping suffered greatly from the effects of
lightning.
Mr. Snow Harris (now Sir William Snow Harris), whose electrical
labors are noticed above, proposed to the
Admiralty, in 1820, a plan which combined the conditions of
ship-conductors, so desirable, yet so difficult to
secure:—namely, that they should be permanently fixed, and
sufficiently large, and yet should in no way interfere with the motion
of the rigging, or with the sliding masts. The method which he
proposed was to make the masts themselves conductors of electricity,
200 by
incorporating with them, in a peculiar way, two laminæ of
sheet-copper, uniting these with the metallic masses in the hull by
other laminæ, and giving the whole a free communication with the sea.
This method was tried experimentally, both on models and to a large
extent in the navy itself; and a Commission appointed to examine the
result reported themselves highly satisfied with Mr. Harris’s plan,
and strongly recommended that it should be fully carried out in the
Navy.20]
20 See Mr. Snow Harris’s paper in
Phil. Mag. March, 1841.
It is not here necessary to trace the study of atmospheric
electricity any further: and we must now endeavor to see how these
phenomena and laws of phenomena which we have related, were worked up
into consistent theories; for though many experimental observations
and measures were made after this time, they were guided by the
theory, and may be considered as having rather discharged the office
of confirming than of suggesting it.
We may observe also that we have now described the period of most
extensive activity and interest in electrical researches. These
naturally occurred while the general notions and laws of the phenomena
were becoming, and were not yet become, fixed and clear. At such a
period, a large and popular circle of spectators and amateurs feel
themselves nearly upon a level, in the value of their trials and
speculations, with more profound thinkers: at a later period, when the
subject is become a science, that is, a study in which all must be
left far behind who do not come to it with disciplined, informed, and
logical minds, the cultivators are far more few, and the shout of
applause less tumultuous and less loud. We may add, too, that the
experiments, which are the most striking to the senses, lose much of
their impressiveness with their novelty. Electricity, to be now
studied rightly, must be reasoned upon mathematically; how slowly such
a mode of study makes its way, we shall see in the progress of the
theory, which we must now proceed to narrate.
[2nd Ed.] [A new mode of producing electricity has excited much
notice lately. In October, 1840, one of the workmen in attendance upon
a boiler belonging to the Newcastle and Durham Railway, reported that
the boiler was full of fire; the fact  being, that when he placed his
hand near it an electrical spark was given out. This drew the
attention of Mr. Armstrong and Mr. Pattinson, who made the
circumstance publicly known.21 Mr. Armstrong
pursued the investigation 201 with great zeal, and after various
conjectures was able to announce22 that the
electricity was excited at the point where the steam is subject to
friction in its emission. He found too that he could produce a like
effect by the emission of condensed air. Following out his views, he
was able to construct, for the Polytechnic Institution in London, a
“Hydro-electric Machine,” of greater power than any electrical machine
previously made. Dr. Faraday took up the investigation as the subject
of the Eighteenth Series of his Researches, sent to the Royal
Society, Jan. 26, 1842; and in this he illustrated, with his usual
command of copious and luminous experiments, a like view;—that
the electricity is produced by the friction of the particles of the
water carried along by the steam. And thus this is a new manifestation of
that electricity, which, to distinguish it from voltaic electricity,
is sometimes called Friction Electricity or Machine
Electricity. Dr. Faraday has, however, in the course of this
investigation, brought to light several new electrical relations of
bodies.]
21 Phil. Mag. Oct 1840.
22 Phil. Mag. Jan. 1848, dated
Dec. 9, 1841.
</div></body></text></TEI>