<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="72">

CHAPTER IV.
Of the Relation of Tradition to Palætiology.


1. Importance of Tradition.—Since the Palætiological Sciences have it for their business to study
the train of past events produced by natural causes
down to the present time, the knowledge concerning such events which is supplied by the remembrance and records of man, in whatever form, must
have an important bearing upon these sciences. All
changes in the condition and extent of land and
sea, which have taken place within man’s observation,
all effects of deluges, sea-waves, rivers, springs, volcanoes, earthquakes, and the like, which come within the
reach of human history, have a strong interest for the
palætiologist. Nor is he less concerned in all recorded instances of the modification of the forms and
habits of plants and animals, by the operations of man,
or by transfer from one land to another. And when
we come to the Palætiology of Language, of Art, of
Civilization, we find our subject still more closely connected with history; for in truth these are historical,
no less than palætiological investigations. But, confining ourselves at present to the material sciences, we
may observe that though the importance of the information which tradition gives us, in the sciences now
under our consideration, as, for instance, geology, has
long been tacitly recognised; yet it is only recently
that geologists have employed themselves in collecting
their historical facts upon such a scale and with such
comprehensive views as are required by the interest
and use of collections of this kind. The Essay of Von 298 Hoff19, On the Natural Alterations in the Surface of the
Earth which are proved by Tradition, was the work
which first opened the eyes of geologists to the extent
and importance of this kind of investigation. Since
that time the same path of research has been pursued
with great perseverance by others, especially by Sir
C. Lyell; and is now justly considered as an essential
portion of Geology.</div></body></text></TEI>