<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="12">

CHAPTER III.
Of some Peculiarities of the Idea of Space.



1. SOME
of the Ideas which we shall have to examine involve
conceptions of certain relations of objects, as the idea of
Cause and of Likeness; and may appear to be suggested by
experience, enabling us to abstract this general relation
from particular cases. But it will be seen that Space is not
such a general conception of a relation. For we do not speak
of Spaces as we speak of Causes and Likenesses, but
of Space. And when we speak of spaces, we understand
by the expression, parts of one and the same identical
everywhere-extended Space. We conceive a universal Space;
which is not made up of these partial spaces as its
component parts, for it would remain if these were taken
away; and these cannot be conceived without presupposing
absolute space. Absolute Space is essentially one; and the
complication which exists in it, and the conception of
various spaces, depends merely upon boundaries. Space must,
therefore, be, as we have said, not a general conception
abstracted from particulars, but a universal mode of
representation, altogether independent of experience.
2. Space is infinite. We represent it to ourselves as an
infinitely great magnitude. Such an idea as that of Likeness
or Cause, is, no doubt, found in an infinite number of
particular cases, and so far includes these cases. But these
ideas do not include an infinite number of cases as parts of
an infinite whole. When we say that all bodies and partial
spaces exist in infinite space, we use an expression which
is not applied in the same sense to any cases except those
of Space and Time. 96
3. What is here said may appear to be a denial of the real
existence of space. It must be observed, however, that we do
not deny, but distinctly assert, the existence of space as a
real and necessary condition of all objects perceived; and
that we not only allow that objects are seen external to us,
but we found upon the fact of their being so seen, our view
of the nature of space. If, however, it be said that we deny
the reality of space as an object or thing, this is true.
Nor does it appear easy to maintain that space exists as a
thing, when it is considered that this thing is infinite in
all its dimensions; and, moreover, that it is a thing,
which, being nothing in itself, exists only that other
things may exist in it. And those who maintain the real
existence of space, must also maintain the real existence of
time in the same sense. Now two infinite things, thus really
existing, and yet existing only as other things exist in
them, are notions so extravagant that we are driven to some
other mode of explaining the state of the matter.
4. Thus space is not an object of which we perceive the
properties, but a form of our perception; not a thing which
affects our senses, but an idea to which we conform the
impressions of sense. And its peculiarities appear to depend
upon this, that it is not only a form of sensation, but of
intuition; that in reference to space, we not only
perceive but contemplate objects. We see objects in
space, side by side, exterior to each other; space, and
objects in so far as they occupy space, have parts exterior
to other parts; and have the whole thus made up by the
juxtaposition of parts. This mode of apprehension belongs
only to the ideas of space and time. Space and Time are made
up of parts, but Cause and Likeness are not apprehended as
made up of parts. And the term intuition (in its
rigorous sense) is applicable only to that mode of
contemplation in which we thus look at objects as made up of
parts, and apprehend the relations of those parts at the
same time and by the same act by which we apprehend the
objects themselves.
5. As we have said, space limited by boundaries
97 gives rise to various conceptions which we have often
to consider. Thus limited, space assumes form or
figure; and the variety of conceptions thus brought
under our notice is infinite. We have every possible form of
line, straight line, and curve; and of curves an endless
number;—circles, parabolas, hyperbolas, spirals, helices.
We have plane surfaces of various shapes,—parallelograms,
polygons, ellipses; and we have solid figures,—cubes,
cones, cylinders, spheres, spheroids, and so on. All these
have their various properties, depending on the relations of
their boundaries; and the investigation of their properties
forms the business of the science of Geometry.
6. Space has three dimensions, or directions in which it may
be measured; it cannot have more or fewer. The simplest
measurement is that of a straight line, which has length
alone. A surface has both length and breadth: and solid
space has length, breadth, and thickness or depth. The
origin of such a difference of dimensions will be seen if we
reflect that each portion of space has a boundary, and is
extended both in the direction in which its
boundary extends, and also in a direction from its
boundary; for otherwise it would not be a boundary. A point
has no dimensions. A line has but one dimension,—the
distance from its boundary, or its length. A plane,
bounded by a straight line, has the dimension which belongs
to this line, and also has another dimension arising from
the distance of its parts from this boundary line; and this
may be called breadth. A solid, bounded by a plane,
has the dimensions which this plane has; and has also a
third dimension, which we may call height or
depth, as we consider the solid extended above or
below the plane; or thickness, if we omit all
consideration of up and down. And no space can have any
dimensions which are not resoluble into these three.
We may now proceed to consider the mode in which the idea of
space is employed in the formation of Geometry.</div></body></text></TEI>