<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Chambers Robert</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="5">p. 66ERA OF
THE OLD RED SANDSTONE—
FISHES ABUNDANT.
We advance to a new chapter in this
marvellous history—the era of the Old Red Sandstone
System.  This term has been recently applied to a series
of strata, of enormous thickness in the whole mass, largely
developed in Herefordshire, Shropshire, Worcestershire, and South
Wales; also in the counties of Fife, Forfar, Moray, Cromarty, and
Caithness; and in Russia and North America, if not in many other
parts of the world.  The particular strata forming the
system are somewhat different in different countries; but there
is a general character to the extent of these being a mixture of
flagstones, marly rocks, and sandstones, usually of a laminous
structure, with conglomerates.  There is also a schist
shewing the presence of bitumen; a remarkable new ingredient,
since it is a vegetable production.  In the conglomerates,
of great extent and thickness, which form, in at least one
district, the basis or leading feature of the system, inclosing
water-worn fragments of quartz and other rocks, we have evidence
of the seas of that period having been subjected to a violent and
long-continued agitation, probably from volcanic causes. 
The upper members of the series bear the appearance of having
been deposited in comparatively tranquil seas.  The English
specimens of this system shew a remarkable freedom from those
disturbances which result in the interjection of trap; and they
are thus defective in mineral ores.  In some parts of
England the old red sandstone system has been stated as 10,000
feet in thickness.
In this era, the forms of life which existed in the Silurian
are continued: we have the same orders of marine creatures,
zoophyta, polypiaria, conchifera, crustacea; but to these are
added numerous fishes, some of which are of most extraordinary
and surprising forms.  Several of the strata are crowded
with remains of fish, shewing that the seas in which those beds
were deposited had swarmed with that class of inhabitants. 
The investigation of this system is recent; but already [68] M. Agassiz has ascertained about twenty
genera, and thrice the number of species.  And it is
remarkable that the Silurian fishes are here only represented in
genera; the whole of the species of that era had already
passed away.  Even throughout the sub-groups of the system
itself, the species are changed; and these are phenomena observed
throughout all the subsequent systems or geological eras;
apparently arguing that, during the deposition of all the rocks,
a gradual change of physical conditions was constantly going
on.  A varying temperature, or even a varying depth of sea,
would at present be attended with similar changes in marine life;
and by analogy we are entitled to assume that such variations in
the ancient seas might be amongst the causes of that constant
change of genera and species in the inhabitants of those seas to
which the organic contents of the rocks bear witness.
Some of the fossils of this system,—the cephalaspis,
coccosteus, pterichthys, holoptychius—are, in form and
structure, entirely different from any fishes now existing, only
the sturgeon family having any trace of affinity to them in any
respect.  They seem to form a sort of connecting link
between the crustacea and true fishes.
The cephalaspis may be considered as making the
smallest advance from the crustacean character; it very much
resembles in form the asaphus of lower formations, having a
longish tail-like body inserted within the cusp of a large
crescent-shaped head, somewhat like a saddler’s
cutting-knife.  The body is covered with strong plates of
bone, enamelled, and the head was protected on the upper side
with one large plate, as with a buckler—hence the name,
implying buckler-head.  A range of small fins conveys
the idea of its having been as weak in motion as it is strong in
structure.  The coccosteus may be said to mark the
next advance to fish creation.  The outline of its body is
of the form of a short thick coffin, rounded, covered with strong
bony plates, and terminating in a long tail, which seems to have
been the sole organ of motion.  It is very remarkable, that,
while the tail establishes this creature among the vertebrata and
the fishes, its mouth has been opened vertically, like those of
the crustaceans, but which is contrary to the mode of vertebrata
generally.  This seems a pretty strong mark of the link
character of the coccosteus between these two great departments
of the animal kingdom.  The pterichthys has also
strong bony plates over its body, arranged much like those of a
tortoise, and has a long tail; but its most remarkable feature,
and that which has suggested its name, is a pair of long and
narrow wing-like appendages attached to the shoulders, which the
creature is supposed to have erected for its defence when
attacked by an enemy.
The holoptychius is of a flat oval form, furnished with
fins, and ending in a long tail; the whole body covered with
strong plates which overlap each other, and the head forming only
a slight rounded projection from the general figure.  The
specimens in the lower beds are not above the size of a flounder;
but in the higher strata, to judge by the size of the scales or
plates which have been found, the creature attained a
comparatively monstrous size.
The other fishes of the system,—the osteolepis,
glyptolepis, dipterus, &c., are, in general outline, much
like fishes still existing, but their organization has,
nevertheless, some striking peculiarities.  They have been
entirely covered with bony scales or plates, enamelled
externally; their spines are tipped with bone, and, as one
striking and unvarying feature, the tail is only finned on the
lower side.  The internal skeleton, of which no traces have
been preserved, is presumed to have been cartilaginous. 
They therefore unite the character of cartilaginous fishes with a
character peculiar to themselves, and in which we see pretty
clear vestiges of the pre-existent crustaceous form.
With regard to the link character of these animals, some
curious facts are mentioned.  It appears that in the
imperfect condition of the vertebral column, and the inferior
situation of the mouth in the pterichthys, coccosteus, &c.,
there is an analogy to the form of the dorsal cord and position
of the mouth in the embryo of perfect fishes.  The one-sided
form of the tail in the osteolepis &c. finds a similar
analogy in the form of the tail in the embryo of the
salmon.  It is not premature to remark how broadly these
facts seem to hint at a parity of law affecting the progress of
general creation, and the progress of an individual fœtus
of one of the more perfect animals.
It is equally ascertained of the types of being prevalent in
the old red, as of those of the preceding system, that they are
uniform in the corresponding strata of distant parts of the
earth; for instance, Russia and North America.
In the old red sandstone, the marine plants, of which faint
traces are observable in the Silurians, continue to appear. 
It would seem as if less change took place in the vegetation than
in the animals of those early seas; and for this, as Mr. Miller
has remarked, it is easy to imagine reasons.  For example,
an infusion of lime into the sea would destroy animal life, but
be favourable to vegetation.
As yet there were no land animals or plants, and for this the
presumable reason is, that no dry land as yet existed.  We
are not left to make this inference solely from the absence of
land animals and plants; in the arrangement of the primary
(stratified) rocks, we have further evidence of it.  That
these rocks were formed in a generally horizontal position, we
are as well assured as that they were formed at the bottom of
seas.  But they are always found greatly inclined in
position, tilted up against the slopes of the granitic masses
which are beneath them in geological order, though often shooting
up to a higher point in the atmosphere.  No doubt can be
entertained that these granitic masses, forming our principal
mountain ranges, have been protruded from below, or, at least,
thrust much further up, since the deposition of the
primary rocks.  The protrusion was what tilted up the
primary rocks; and the inference is, of course, unavoidable, that
these mountains have risen chiefly, at least, since the primary
rocks were laid down.  It is remarkable that, while the
primary rocks thus incline towards granitic nuclei or axes, the
strata higher in the series rest against these again, generally
at a less inclination, or none at all, shewing that these strata
were laid down after the swelling mountain eminences had, by
their protrusion, tilted up the primary strata.  And thus it
may be said an era of local upthrowing of the primitive and
(perhaps) central matter of our planet, is established as
happening about the close of the primary strata, and beginning of
the next ensuing system.  It may be called the Era of the
Oldest Mountains, or, more boldly, of the formation of the
detached portions of dry land over the hitherto watery surface of
the globe—an important part of the designs of Providence,
for which the time was now apparently come.  It may be
remarked, that volcanic disturbances and protrusions of trap took
place throughout the whole period of the deposition of the
primary rocks; but they were upon a comparatively limited scale,
and probably all took place under water.  It was only now
that the central granitic masses of the great mountain ranges
were thrown up, carrying up with them broken edges of the primary
strata; a process which seems to have had this difference from
the other, that it was the effect of a more tremendous force
exerted at a lower depth in the earth, and generally acting in
lines pervading a considerable portion of the earth’s
surface.  We shall by-and-by see that the protrusion of some
of the mountain ranges was not completed, or did not stop, at
that period.  There is no part of geological science more
clear than that which refers to the ages of mountains.  It
is as certain that the Grampian mountains of Scotland are older
than the Alps and Apennines, as it is that civilization had
visited Italy, and had enabled her to subdue the world, while
Scotland was the residence of “roving
barbarians.”  The Pyrenees, Carpathians, and other
ranges of continental Europe, are all younger than the Grampians,
or even the insignificant Mendip Hills of southern England. 
Stratification tells this tale as plainly as Livy tells the
history of the Roman republic.  It tells us—to use the
words of Professor Philips—that at the time when the
Grampians sent streams and detritus to straits where now the
valleys of the Forth and Clyde meet, the greater part of Europe
was a wide ocean.
The last three systems—called, in England, the Cumbrian,
Silurian, and Devonian, and collectively the palæozoic
rocks, from their containing the remains of the earliest
inhabitants of the globe—are of vast thickness; in England,
not much less than 30,000 feet, or nearly six miles.  In
other parts of the world, as we have seen, the earliest of these
systems alone is of much greater depth—arguing an enormous
profundity in the ocean in which they were formed.</div></body></text></TEI>