<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="57">

BOOK VIII.


THE PHILOSOPHY OF THE CLASSIFICATORY
SCIENCES.

CHAPTER I.
The Idea of Likeness as Governing the Use of Common Names.

1. Object of the Chapter.—Not only the Classificatory Sciences, but the application of names to things
in the rudest and most unscientific manner, depends
upon our apprehending them as like each other. We
must therefore endeavour to trace the influence and
operation of the Idea of Likeness in the common use
of language, before we speak of the conditions under
which it acquires its utmost exactness and efficacy.
It will be my object to show in this, as in previous
cases, that the impressions of sense are apprehended
by acts of the mind; and that these mental acts necessarily imply certain relations which may be made the
subjects of speculative reasoning. We shall have, if
we can, to seize and bring into clear view the principles which the relation of like and unlike involves, and
the mode in which these principles have been developed.
2. Unity of the Individual.—But before we can
attend to several things as like or unlike, we must be
able to apprehend each of these by itself as one thing. 96 It may at first sight perhaps appear that this apprehension results immediately from the impressions on
our senses, without any act of our thoughts. A very
little attention, however, enables us to see that thus to
single out special objects requires a mental operation
as well as a sensation. How, for example, without an
exertion of mental activity, can we see one tree, in a
forest where there are many? We have, spread before us, a collection of colours and forms, green and
brown, dark and light, irregular and straight: this is
all that sensation gives or can give. But we associate
one brown trunk with one portion of the green mass,
excluding the rest, although the neighbouring leaves
are both nearer in contiguity and more similar in
appearance than is the stem. We thus have before us
one tree; but this unity is given by the mind itself.
We see the green and the brown, but we must make
the tree before we can see it.
That this composition of our sensations so as to
form one thing implies an act of our own, will perhaps
be more readily allowed, if we once more turn our
attention to the manner in which we sometimes attempt
to imitate and record the objects of sight, by drawing.
When we do this, as we have already observed, we
mark this unity of each object, by drawing a line to
separate the parts which we include from those which
we exclude;—an Outline. This line corresponds to
nothing which we see; the beginner in drawing has
great difficulty in discerning it; he has in fact to make
it. It is, as has been said by a painter of our own
time1, a fiction: but it is a fiction employed to mark
a real act of the mind; to designate the singleness of
the object in our conception. As we have said elsewhere, we see lines, but especially outlines, by mentally drawing them ourselves.</div></body></text></TEI>