<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="30">
CHAPTER XI.

The Laws of Motion.

We shall now make a few remarks on the general
Laws of Motion by which all mechanical 
effects take place. Are we to consider these as instituted
laws? and if so, can we point out any of the reasons
which we may suppose to have led to the selection
of those laws which really exist?
The observations formerly made concerning the
inevitable narrowness and imperfection of our conclusions
on such subjects, apply here, even more
strongly than in the case of the law of gravitation.
We can hardly conceive matter divested of these
laws; and we cannot perceive or trace a millionth
part of the effects which they produce. We cannot,
therefore, expect to go far in pointing out the advantages
of these laws such as they now obtain.
It would be easy to show that the fundamental
laws of motion, in whatever form we state them,
possess a very preeminent simplicity, compared with
almost all others, which we might imagine as existing.
This simplicity has indeed produced an effect
on men’s minds which, though delusive, appears to[179]
be very natural; several writers have treated these
laws as self-evident, and necessarily flowing from
the nature of our conceptions. We conceive that
this is an erroneous view, and that these laws are
known to us to be what they are, by experience
only; that they might, so far as we can discern,
have been any others. They appear therefore to be
selected for their fitness to answer their purposes;
and we may, perhaps, be able to point out some instances
in which this fitness is apparent to us.
Newton, and many English philosophers, teach the
existence of three separate fundamental laws of motion,
while most of the eminent mathematicians of
France reduce these to two, the law of inertia and
the law that force is proportioned to velocity. As
an example of the views which we wish to illustrate,
we may take the law of inertia, which is identical
with Newton’s first Law of Motion. This law asserts,
that a body at rest continues at rest, and that
a body in motion goes on moving with its velocity
and direction unchanged, except so far as it is acted
on by extraneous forces.[24]
We conceive that this law, simple and universal
as it is, cannot be shown to be necessarily true. It
might be difficult to discuss this point in general
terms with any clearness; but let us take the only
example which we know of a motion absolutely uniform,
in consequence of the absence of any force to
accelerate or retard it;—this motion is the rotation
of the earth on its axis.
1. It is scarcely possible that discussions on such[180]
subjects should not have a repulsive and scholastic
aspect, and appear like disputes about words rather
than things. For mechanical writers have exercised
all their ingenuity so to circumscribe their notions
and so to define their terms that these fundamental
truths should be expressed in the simplest manner:
the consequence of which has been, that they have
been made to assume the appearance rather of identical
assertions than of general facts of experience.
But in order to avoid this inconvenience, as far as
may be, let us take the first law of motion as exemplified
in a particular case, the rotation of the earth.
Of all the motions with which we are acquainted
this is alone invariable. Each day, measured by the
passages of the stars, is so precisely of the same
length that, according to Laplace’s calculations, it is
impossible that a difference of hundredth of a second
of time should have obtained between the length of
the day in the earliest ages and at the present time.
Now why is this? How is this very remarkable uniformity
preserved in this particular phenomenon,
while all the other motions of the system are subject
to inequalities? How is it that in the celestial machine
no retardation takes place by the lapse of time,
as would be the case in any machine which it would
be possible for human powers to construct? The answer
is, that in the earth’s revolution on her axis no
cause operates to retard the speed, like the imperfection
of materials, the friction of supports, the resistance
of the ambient medium; impediments which
cannot, in any human mechanism, however perfect,
be completely annihilated. But here we are led to
ask again, why should the speed continue the same
when not affected by an extraneous cause? Why
should it not languish and decay of itself by the mere
lapse of time? That it might do so, involves no contradiction,
for it was the common, though erroneous,
belief of all mechanical speculators, to the time of
Galileo. We can conceive velocity to diminish in
proceeding from a certain point of time, as easily as[181]
we can conceive force to diminish in proceeding
from a certain point of space, which in attractive
forces really occurs. But, it is sometimes said, the
motion (that is the velocity) must continue the same
from one instant to another, for there is nothing to
change it. This appears to be taking refuge in
words. We may call the velocity, that is the speed
of a body, its motion; but we cannot, by giving it
this name, make it a thing which has any à priori
claim to permanence, much less any self-evident constancy.
Why must the speed of a body, left to itself,
continue the same, any more than its temperature?
Hot bodies grow cooler of themselves, why should
not quick bodies go slower of themselves? Why must
a body describe one thousand feet in the next second
because it has described one thousand feet in the
last? Nothing but experience, under proper circumstances,
can inform us whether bodies, abstracting
from external agency, do move according to such a
rule. We find that they do so, we learn that all
diminution of their speed which ever takes place, can
be traced to external causes. Contrary to all that
men had guessed, motion appears to be of itself endless
and unwearied. In order to account for the unalterable
permanence of the length of our day, all
that is requisite is to show that there is no let or
hindrance in the way of the earth’s rotation;—no resisting
medium or alteration of size,—she “spinning
sleeps” on her axle, as the poet expresses it, and may
go on sleeping with the same regularity for ever, so
far as the experimental properties of motion are concerned.
Such is the necessary consequence of the first law
of motion; but the law itself has no necessary existence,
so far as we can see. It was discovered only
after various perplexities and false conjectures of
speculators on mechanics. We have learnt that it
is so, but we have not learnt, nor can any one undertake
to teach us, that it must have been so. For
aught we can tell, it is one among a thousand equally[182]
possible laws, which might have regulated the motions
of bodies.
2. But though we have thus no reason to consider
this as the only possible law, we have good reason
to consider it as the best, or at least as possessing all
that we can conceive of advantage. It is the simplest
conceivable of such laws. If the velocity had
been compelled to change with the time, there must
have been a law of the change, and the kind and
amount of this change must have been determined
by its dependence on the time and other conditions.
This, though quite supposable, would undoubtedly
have been more complex than the present state of
things. And though complexity does not appear to
embarrass the operations of the laws of nature, and
is admitted, without scruple, when there is reason for
it, simplicity is the usual character of such laws, and
appears to have been a ground of selection in the
formation of the universe, as it is a mark of beauty
to us in our contemplation of it.
But there is a still stronger apparent reason for the
selection of this law of the preservation of motion.
If the case had been otherwise, the universe must
necessarily in the course of ages have been reduced
to a state of rest, or at least to a state not sensibly
differing from it. If the earth’s motion, round its
axis, had slackened by a very small quantity, for instance,
by a hundredth of a second in a revolution,
and in this proportion continued, the day would have
been already lengthened by six hours in the six
thousand years which have elapsed since the history
of the world began; and if we suppose a longer period
to precede or to follow, the day might be increased
to a month or to any length. All the adaptations
which depend on the length of the day would
consequently be deranged. But this would not be
all; for the same law of motion is equally requisite
for the preservation of the annual motion of the
earth. If her motion were retarded by the establishment
of any other law instead of the existing one,[183]
she would wheel nearer and nearer to the sun at
every revolution, and at last reach the centre, like a
falling hoop. The same would happen to the other
planets; and the whole solar system would, in the
course of a certain period, be gathered into a heap
of matter without life or motion. In the present
state of things on the other hand, the system, as we
have already explained, is, by a combination of remarkable
provisions, calculated for an almost indefinite
existence, of undiminished fitness for its purposes.
There are, therefore, manifest reasons, why, of all
laws which could occupy the place of the first law
of motion, the one which now obtains is the only one
consistent with the durability and uniformity of the
system;—the one, therefore, which we may naturally
conceive to be selected by a wise contriver. And as,
along with this, it has appeared that we have no sort
of right to attribute the establishment of this law to
any thing but selection, we have here a striking evidence,
to lead us to a perception of that Divine
mind, by which means so simple are made to answer
purposes so extensive and so beneficial.
</div></body></text></TEI>