<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="37">CHAPTER XXXVII.
LAWS WHICH REGULATE THE GEOGRAPHICAL DISTRIBUTION OF SPECIES.
Analogy of climate not attended with identity of species—Botanical geography—Stations—Habitations—Distinct
provinces of indigenous plants—Vegetation
of islands—Marine vegetation—In what manner plants become diffused—Effects
of wind, rivers, marine currents—Agency of animals—Many seeds
pass through the stomachs of animals and birds undigested—Agency of man
in the dispersion of plants, both voluntary and involuntary—Its analogy to
that of the inferior animals.
Next to determining the question whether species have a real existence,
the consideration of the laws which regulate their geographical distribution
is a subject of primary importance to the geologist. It is only by
studying these laws with attention, by observing the positions which
groups of species occupy at present, and inquiring how these may be
varied in the course of time by migrations, by changes in physical geography,
and other causes, that we can hope to learn whether the duration
of species be limited, or in what manner the state of the animate world
is affected by the endless vicissitudes of the inanimate.
Different regions inhabited by distinct species.—That different regions
of the globe are inhabited by entirely distinct animals and plants, is a
fact which has been familiar to all naturalists since Buffon first pointed
out the want of specific identity between the land quadrupeds of America
and those of the Old World. The same phenomenon has, in later times,
been forced in a striking manner upon our attention, by the examination
of New Holland, where the indigenous species of animals and plants were
found to be, almost without exception, distinct from those known in other
parts of the world.
But the extent of this parcelling out of the globe amongst different
nations, as they have been termed, of plants and animals—the universality
of a phenomenon so extraordinary and unexpected, may be considered as
one of the most interesting facts clearly established by the advance of
modern science.
Scarcely fourteen hundred species of plants appear to have been known
and described by the Greeks, Romans, and Arabians. At present, more
than three thousand species are enumerated, as natives of our own island.841
In other parts of the world there have been now collected (1846) upwards
of 100,000 species, specimens of which are preserved in European herbariums.
It was not to be supposed, therefore, that the ancients should
have acquired any correct notions respecting what may be called the
geography of plants, although the influence of climate on the character
of the vegetation could hardly have escaped their observation.
613
Antecedently to investigation, there was no reason for presuming that
the vegetable productions, growing wild in the eastern hemisphere,
should be unlike those of the western, in the same latitude; nor that
the plants of the Cape of Good Hope should be unlike those of the
south of Europe; situations where the climate is little dissimilar. The
contrary supposition would have seemed more probable, and we might
have anticipated an almost perfect identity in the animals and plants
which inhabit corresponding parallels of latitude. The discovery, therefore,
that each separate region of the globe, both of the land and water,
is occupied by distinct groups of species, and that most of the exceptions
to this general rule may be referred to disseminating causes now in
operation, is eminently calculated to excite curiosity, and to stimulate
us to seek some hypothesis respecting the first introduction of species
which may be reconcileable with such phenomena.
Botanical geography.—A comparison of the plants of different regions
of the globe affords results more to be depended upon in the present state
of our knowledge than those relating to the animal kingdom, because
the science of botany is more advanced, and probably comprehends a
great proportion of the total number of the vegetable productions of the
whole earth. Humboldt, in several eloquent passages of his Personal
Narrative, was among the first to promulgate philosophical views on this
subject. Every hemisphere, says this traveller, produces plants of different
species; and it is not by the diversity of climates that we can attempt
to explain why equinoctial Africa has no Laurinæ, and the New World
no Heaths; why the Calceolariæ are found only in the southern hemisphere;
why the birds of the continent of India glow with colors less
splendid than the birds of the hot parts of America: finally, why the
tiger is peculiar to Asia, and the ornithorhynchus to New Holland.842
"We can conceive," he adds, "that a small number of the families of
plants, for instance, the Musaceæ and the Palms, cannot belong to very
cold regions, on account of their internal structure and the importance of
certain organs; but we cannot explain why no one of the family of
Melastomas vegetates north of the parallel of thirty degrees; or why no
rose-tree belongs to the southern hemisphere. Analogy of climates is
often found in the two continents without identity of productions."843
The luminous essay of De Candolle on "Botanical Geography" presents
us with the fruits of his own researches and those of Humboldt,
Brown, and other eminent botanists, so arranged, that the principal phenomena
of the distribution of plants are exhibited in connexion with the
causes to which they are chiefly referrible.844 "It might not, perhaps, be
difficult," observes this writer, "to find two points, in the United States
and in Europe, or in Equinoctial America and Africa, which present
all the same circumstances: as, for example, the same temperature,
614
the same height above the sea, a similar soil, an equal dose of
humidity; yet nearly all, perhaps all, the plants in these two similar
localities shall be distinct. A certain degree of analogy, indeed, of
aspect, and even of structure, might very possibly be discoverable between
the plants of the two localities in question; but the species would in
general be different. Circumstances, therefore, different from those which
now determine the stations, have had an influence on the habitations of
plants."
Stations and habitations of plants.—As I shall frequently have occasion
to speak of the stations and habitations of plants in the technical
sense in which the terms are used in the above passage, I may remind
the geologist that station indicates the peculiar nature of the locality where
each species is accustomed to grow, and has reference to climate, soil,
humidity, light, elevation above the sea, and other analogous circumstances;
whereas, by habitation is meant a general indication of the
country where a plant grows wild. Thus the station of a plant may be a
salt-marsh, a hill-side, the bed of the sea, or a stagnant pool. Its habitation
may be Europe, North America, or New Holland, between the
tropics. The study of stations has been styled the topography, that of
habitations the geography, of botany. The terms thus defined, express
each a distinct class of ideas, which have been often confounded together,
and which are equally applicable in zoology.
In farther illustration of the principle above alluded to, that difference
of longitude, independently of any influence of temperature, is accompanied
by a great, and sometimes a complete, diversity in the species of
plants, De Candolle observes, that, out of 2891 species of phænogamous
plants described by Pursh, in the United States, there are only 385 which
are found in northern or temperate Europe. MM. Humboldt and Bonpland,
in all their travels through equinoctial America, found only
twenty-four
species (these being all Cyperaceæ and Gramineæ) common to America
and any part of the Old World. They collected, it is true, chiefly
on the mountains, or the proportion would have been larger; for Dr. J.
Hooker informs me that many tropical plants of the New World are
identical with African species. Nevertheless, the general discordance of
these Floras is very striking. On comparing New Holland with Europe,
Mr. Brown ascertained that, out of 4100 species, discovered in Australia,
there were only 166 common to Europe, and of this small number there
were some few which may have been transported thither by man. Almost
all of the 166 species were cryptogamic, and the rest consist, in
nearly every case, of phænogamous plants which also inhabit intervening
regions.
But what is still more remarkable, in the more widely separated parts
of the ancient continent, notwithstanding the existence of an uninterrupted
land-communication, the diversity in the specific character of the
respective vegetations is almost as striking. Thus there is found one
assemblage of species in China, another in the countries bordering the
Black Sea and the Caspian, a third in those surrounding the Mediterranean,
615
a fourth in the great platforms of Siberia and Tartary, and so
forth.
The distinctness of the groups of indigenous plants, in the same parallel
of latitude, is greatest where continents are disjoined by a wide expanse
of ocean. In the northern hemisphere, near the pole, where the extremities
of Europe, Asia, and America unite or approach near to one another,
a considerable number of the same species of plants are found, common
to the three continents. But it has been remarked, that these plants,
which are thus so widely diffused in the arctic regions, are also found in
the chain of the Aleutian islands, which stretch almost across from America
to Asia, and which may probably have served as the channel of communication
for the partial blending of the Floras of the adjoining regions.
It has, indeed, been observed to be a general rule, that plants found at
two points very remote from each other occur also in places intermediate.
Dr. J. Hooker informs me that in high latitudes in the southern ocean,
in spite of the great extent of the sea, Floras of widely disconnected islands
contain many species in common. Perhaps icebergs, transporting to vast
distances not only stones, but soil with the seeds of plants, may explain
this unusually wide diffusion of insular plants.
In islands very distant from continents the total number of plants is
comparatively small; but a large proportion of the species are such as
occur nowhere else. In so far as the Flora of such islands is not peculiar
to them, it contains, in general, species common to the nearest main
lands.845 The islands of the great southern ocean exemplify these rules;
the easternmost containing more American, and the western more Indian
plants.846 Madeira and Teneriffe contain many species, and even entire
genera, peculiar to them; but they have also plants in common with
Portugal, Spain, the Azores, and the north-west coast of Africa.847
In the Canaries, out of 533 species of phænogamous plants, it is said
that 310 are peculiar to these islands, and the rest identical with those
of the African continent; but in the Flora of St. Helena, which is so far
distant even from the western shores of Africa, there have been found,
out of thirty native species of the phænogamous class, only one or two
which are to be found in any other part of the globe. On the other
hand, of sixty cryptogamic plants, collected by Dr. J. Hooker in the same
island, twelve only were peculiar.
The natural history of the Galapagos archipelago, described by Mr.
Darwin, affords another very instructive illustration of the laws governing
the geographical distribution of plants and animals in islands. This
group consists of ten principal islands, situated in the Pacific Ocean, under
the equator, about 600 miles westward of the coast of South America.
As they are all formed of volcanic rocks, many of the craters, of which
there are about 2000 in number, having a very fresh aspect, we may
616
regard the whole as much more modern in origin than the mass of the
adjoining continent; yet neither has the Flora nor Fauna been derived from
South America, but consist of species for the most part indigenous, yet
stamped with a character decidedly South American.
What is still more singular, there is a difference between the species
inhabiting the different islands. Of flowering plants, for example, there
are 185 species at present known, and forty cryptogamic, making together
225. One hundred of the former class are new species, probably confined
to this archipelago; and of the rest, ten at least have been introduced by
man. Of twenty-one species of Compositæ, all but one are peculiar, and
they belong to twelve genera, no less than ten of which genera are confined
to the Galapagos. Dr. Hooker observes, that the type of this Flora
has an undoubted relation to that of the western side of South America,
and he detects in it no affinity with that of the numerous islands scattered
over other parts of the Pacific. So in regard to the birds, reptiles,
land-shells, and insects, this archipelago, standing as it does in the Pacific
Ocean, is zoologically part of America. Although each small island is
not more than fifty or sixty miles apart, and most of them are in sight of
each other, formed of precisely the same rocks, rising nearly to an equal
height, and placed under a similar climate, they are tenanted each by a
different set of beings, the tortoises, mocking-thrushes, finches, beetles,
scarcely any of them ever ranging over the whole, and often not even
common to any two of the islands.
"The archipelago," says Mr. Darwin, "is a little world within itself, or
rather a satellite attached to America; whence it has derived a few stray
colonists, and has received the general character of its indigenous productions.
One is astonished," he adds, "at the amount of creative force
displayed on so many small, barren, and rocky islands, and still more so,
at its diverse, yet analogous action on points so near each other. I have
said that the Galapagos archipelago might be called a satellite attached
to America, but it should rather be called a group of satellites physically
similar, organically distinct, yet intimately related to each other, and all
related in a marked, though much lesser degree, to the great American
continent."848
Number of botanical provinces.—De Candolle has enumerated twenty
great botanical provinces inhabited by indigenous or aboriginal plants;
and although many of these contain a variety of species which are common
to several others, and sometimes to places very remote, yet the lines
of demarcation are, upon the whole, astonishingly well defined.849 Nor is
it likely that the bearing of the evidence on which these general views
are founded will ever be materially affected, since they are already confirmed
by the examination of nearly one hundred thousand species of
plants.
617
The entire change of opinion which the contemplation of those phenomena
has brought about is worthy of remark. The first travellers were
persuaded that they should find, in distant regions, the plants of their own
country, and they took a pleasure in giving them the same names. It
was some time before this illusion was dissipated; but so fully sensible did
botanists at last become of the extreme smallness of the number of phænogamous
plants common to different continents, that the ancient Floras
fell into disrepute. All grew diffident of the pretended identifications;
and we now find that every naturalist is inclined to examine each supposed
exception with scrupulous severity.850 If they admit the fact, they begin
to speculate on the mode whereby the seeds may have been transported
from one country into the other, or enquire on which of two continents
the plant was indigenous, assuming that a species, like an individual,
cannot have two birthplaces.
Marine vegetation.—The marine vegetation is divisible into different
systems, like those prevailing on the land; but they are much fewer, as
we might have expected, the temperature of the ocean being more uniform
than that of the atmosphere, and consequently the dispersion of species
from one zone to another being less frequently checked by the intervention
of uncongenial climates. The proportion also of land to sea throughout
the globe being small, the migration of marine plants is not so often
stopped by barriers of land, as is that of the terrestrial species by the
ocean. The number of hydrophytes, as they are termed, is very considerable,
and their stations are found to be infinitely more varied than could
have been anticipated; for while some plants are covered and uncovered
daily by the tide, others live at the depth of several hundred feet. Among
the known provinces of Algæ, we may mention, 1st, The north circumpolar,
from lat 60° N. to the pole; 2dly, The North Atlantic or the
region of Fucus proper and Delesseriæ, extending from lat. 40° N. to lat.
60° N.; 3dly, That of the Mediterranean, which may be regarded as a
sub-region of the fourth or warmer temperate zone of the Atlantic, between
lat. 23° N. and lat. 40° N.; 5thly, The Tropical Atlantic, in which Sargassum,
Rhodomelia, Corallinea, and Siphonia abound; 6thly, The South
Atlantic, where the Fucus reappears; 7thly, The Antarctic American,
comprehending from Chili to Cape Horn, the Falkland Islands, and thence
round the world south of latitude 50° S.; 8thly, The Australian and New
Zealand, which is very peculiar, being characterized, among other generic
forms, by Cystoseiriæ and Fuceæ; 9thly, The Indian Ocean and Red Sea;
and, 10thly, The Chinese and Japanese seas.851 In addition to the above
provinces, there are several others not yet well determined in the Pacific
Ocean and elsewhere. There are, however, many species which range
through several of these geographical regions of subaqueous vegetation,
being common to very remote countries; as, for example, to the coasts of
618
Europe and the United States, and others, to Cape Horn and Van Diemen's
Land, the same plants extending also for the most part to the New Zealand
sea. Of the species strictly antarctic (excluding the New Zealand
and Tasmanian groups) Dr. Hooker has identified not less than a fifth part
of the whole with British Algæ! Yet is there a much smaller proportion
of cosmopolite species among the Algæ than among the terrestrial cellular
plants, such as lichens, mosses, and Hepaticæ.
It must always be borne in mind, that the distinctness alluded to between
the provinces, whether of subaqueous or terrestrial plants, relates
strictly to species, and not to forms. In regard to the numerical preponderance
of certain forms, and many peculiarities of internal structure,
there is usually a marked agreement in the vegetable productions of districts
placed in corresponding latitudes, and under similar physical circumstances,
however remote their position. Thus there are innumerable
points of analogy between the vegetation of the Brazils, equinoctial Africa,
and India; and there are also points of difference wherein the plants of
these regions are distinguishable from all extra-tropical groups. But there
is a very small proportion of the entire number of species common to the
three continents. The same may be said, if we compare the plants of the
United States with that of the middle of Europe; the species are distinct,
but the forms are often so analogous, as to have been styled "geographical
representatives." There are very few species of phænogamous plants, says
Dr. J. Hooker, common to Van Diemen's Land, New Zealand, and Fuegia,
but a great many genera, and some of them are confined to those three
distant regions of the southern hemisphere, being in many instances each
severally represented by a single species. The same naturalist also
observes that the southern temperate as well as the antarctic regions,
possess each of them representatives of some of the genera of the analogous
climates of the opposite hemisphere; but very few of the species are identical
unless they be such as are equally diffused over other countries, or
which inhabit the Andes, by the aid of which they have evidently effected
their passage southwards.
Manner in which plants become diffused.—Winds.—Let us now consider
what means of diffusion, independently of the agency of man, are
possessed by plants, whereby, in the course of ages, they may be enabled
to stray from one of the botanical provinces above mentioned to another,
and to establish new colonies at a great distance from their birthplace.
The principal of the inanimate agents provided by nature for scattering
the seeds of plants over the globe, are the movements of the atmosphere
and of the ocean, and the constant flow of water from the mountains to
the sea. To begin with the winds: a great number of seeds, are furnished
with downy and feathery appendages, enabling them, when ripe, to float
in the air, and to be wafted easily to great distances by the most gentle
breeze. Other plants are fitted for dispersion by means of an attached
wing, as in the case of the fir tree, so that they are caught up by the wind
as they fall from the cone, and are carried to a distance. Amongst the
619
comparatively small number of plants known to Linnæus, no less than 138
genera are enumerated as having winged seeds.
As winds often prevail for days, weeks, or even months together, in the
same direction, these means of transportation may sometimes be without
limits; and even the heavier grains may be borne through considerable
spaces, in a very short time, during ordinary tempests; for strong gales,
which can sweep along grains of sand, often move at the rate of about
forty miles an hour, and if the storm be very violent, at the rate of fifty-six
miles.852 The hurricanes of tropical regions, which root up trees and
throw down buildings, sweep along at the rate of ninety miles an hour;
so that, for however short a time they prevail, they may carry even the
heavier fruits and seeds over friths and seas of considerable width, and
doubtless are often the means of introducing into islands the vegetation
of adjoining continents. Whirlwinds are also instrumental in bearing
along heavy vegetable substances to considerable distances. Slight ones
may frequently be observed in our fields, in summer carrying up haycocks
into the air, and then letting fall small tufts of hay far and wide over
the country; but they are sometimes so powerful as to dry up lakes and
ponds, and to break off the boughs of trees, and carry them up in a
whirling column of air.
Franklin tells us, in one of his letters, that he saw, in Maryland, a
whirlwind which began by taking up the dust which lay in the road, in
the form of a sugar loaf with the pointed end downwards, and soon after
grew to the height of forty or fifty feet, being twenty or thirty in diameter.
It advanced in a direction contrary to the wind; and although the
rotary motion of the column was surprisingly rapid, its onward progress
was sufficiently slow to allow a man to keep pace with it on foot. Franklin
followed it on horseback, accompanied by his son, for three quarters
of a mile, and saw it enter a wood, where it twisted and turned round
large trees with surprising force. These were carried up in a spiral line,
and were seen flying in the air, together with boughs and innumerable
leaves, which, from their height, appeared reduced to the apparent size
of flies. As this cause operates at different intervals of time throughout
a great portion of the earth's surface, it may be the means of bearing not
only plants but insects, land testacea and their eggs, with many other species
of animals, to points which they could never otherwise have reached,
and from which they may then begin to propagate themselves again as
from a new centre.
Distribution of cryptogamous plants.—It has been found that a great
numerical proportion of the exceptions to the limitation of species to
certain quarters of the globe occur in the various tribes of cryptogamic
plants. Linnæus observed that, as the germs of plants of this class, such
as mosses, fungi, and lichens, consist of an impalpable powder, the particles
of which are scarcely visible to the naked eye, there is no difficulty
to account for their being dispersed throughout the atmosphere, and carried
to every point of the globe, where there is a station fitted for them.
620
Lichens in particular ascend to great elevations, sometimes growing two
thousand feet above the line of perpetual snow, at the utmost limits
of vegetation, and where the mean temperature is nearly at the freezing
point. This elevated position must contribute greatly to facilitate the
dispersion of those buoyant particles of which their fructification consists.853
Some have inferred, from the springing up of mushrooms whenever
particular soils and decomposed organic matter are mixed together, that
the production of fungi is accidental, and not analogous to that of perfect
plants. But Fries, whose authority on these questions is entitled to the
highest respect, has shown the fallacy of this argument in favor of the
old doctrine of equivocal generation. "The sporules of fungi," says this
naturalist, "are so infinite, that in a single individual of Reticularia
maxima, I have counted above ten millions, and so subtile as to be
scarcely visible, often resembling thin smoke; so light that they may be
raised perhaps by evaporation into the atmosphere, and dispersed in so
many ways by the attraction of the sun, by insects, wind, elasticity, adhesion,
&c., that it is difficult to conceive a place from which they may
be excluded."854
The club-moss called Lycopodium cernuum affords a striking example
of a cryptogamous plant universally distributed over all equinoctial countries.
It scarcely ever passes beyond the northern tropic, except in one
instance, where it appears around the hot-springs in the Azores, although
it is neither an inhabitant of the Canaries nor Madeira. Doubtless its
microscopic sporules are everywhere present, ready to germinate on any
spot where they can enjoy throughout the year the proper quantity of
warmth, moisture, light, and other conditions essential to the species.
Almost every lichen brought home from the southern hemisphere by
the antarctic expedition under Sir James Ross, amounting to no less than
200 species, was ascertained to be also an inhabitant of the northern
hemisphere, and almost all of them European.
Agency of rivers and currents.—In considering, in the next place, the
instrumentality of the aqueous agents of dispersion, I cannot do better
than cite the words of one of our ablest botanical writers. "The mountain
stream or torrent," observes Keith, "washes down to the valley the
seeds which may accidentally fall into it, or which it may happen to
sweep from its banks when it suddenly overflows them. The broad and
majestic river, winding along the extensive plain, and traversing the continents
of the world, conveys to the distance of many hundreds of miles
the seeds that may have vegetated at its source. Thus the southern
shores of the Baltic are visited by seeds which grew in the interior of
Germany, and the western shores of the Atlantic by seeds that have been
generated in the interior of America."855 Fruits, moreover, indigenous to
America and the West Indies, such as that of the Mimosa scandens, the
cashewnut and others, have been known to be drifted across the Atlantic
621
by the Gulf stream, on the western coasts of Europe, in such a state
that they might have vegetated had the climate and soil been favourable.
Among these the Guilandina Bonduc, a leguminous plant, is particularly
mentioned, as having been raised from a seed found on the west coast of
Ireland.856
Sir Hans Sloane states, that several kinds of beans cast ashore on the
Orkney Isles, and Ireland, but none of which appear to have naturalized
themselves, are derived from trees which grow in the West Indies, and
many of them in Jamaica. He conjectures that they might have been
conveyed by rivers into the sea, and then by the Gulf stream to greater
distances, in the same manner as the sea-weed called Lenticula marina,
or Sargasso, which grows on the rocks about Jamaica, is known to be
"carried by the winds and current towards the coast of Florida, and thence
into the North American ocean, where it lies very thick on the surface
of the sea."857
The absence of liquid matter in the composition of seeds renders them
comparatively insensible to heat and cold, so that they may be carried
without detriment through climates where the plants themselves would
instantly perish. Such is their power of resisting the effects of heat, that
Spallanzani mentions some seeds that germinated after having been boiled
in water.858 Sir John Herschel informs me that he has sown at the
Cape of Good Hope the seeds of the Acacia lophanta after they had
remained for twelve hours in water of 140° Fahrenheit, and they germinated
far more rapidly than unboiled seeds. He also states that an eminent
botanist, Baron Ludwig, could not get the seeds of a species of cedar
to grow at the Cape till they were thoroughly boiled.
When therefore, a strong gale, after blowing violently off the land for
a time, dies away, and the seeds alight upon the surface of the waters, or
wherever the ocean, by eating away the sea-cliffs, throws down into its
waves plants which would never otherwise reach the shores, the tides and
currents become active instruments in assisting the dissemination of
almost all classes of the vegetable kingdom. The pandanus and many
other plants have been distributed in this way over the islands of the
Pacific. I have before called attention (p. 618.) to the interesting fact
that one-fifth of all the algæ found in the antarctic regions in 1841-3, by
Dr. J. Hooker, were of species common to the British seas. He has
suggested that cold currents which prevail from Cape Horn to the equator,
and are there met by other cold water, may by their direct influence, as
well as by their temperature, facilitate the passage of antarctic species to
the Arctic Ocean. In like manner the migration of certain marine animals
from the southern to the northern hemisphere may have been brought
about by the same cause.
In a collection of six hundred plants from the neighborhood of the
river Zaire, in Africa, Mr. Brown found that thirteen species were also
622
met with on the opposite shores of Guiana and Brazil. He remarked
that most of these plants were found only on the lower parts of the river
Zaire, and were chiefly such as produced seeds capable of retaining their
vitality a long time in the currents of the ocean. Dr. J. Hooker informs
me that after an examination of a great many insular floras, he has found
that no one of the large natural orders is so rich in species common to
other countries, as the Leguminosæ. The seeds in this order, which comprises
the largest proportion of widely diffused littoral species, are better
adapted than those of any other plants for water-carriage.
The migration of plants aided by islands.—Islands, moreover, and
even the smallest rocks, play an important part in aiding such migrations;
for when seeds alight upon them from the atmosphere, or are
thrown up by the surf, they often vegetate, and supply the winds and
waves with a repetition of new and uninjured crops of fruit and seeds.
These may afterwards pursue their course through the atmosphere, or
along the surface of the sea, in the same direction. The number of plants
found at any given time on an islet affords us no test whatever of the
extent to which it may have co-operated towards this end, since a variety
of species may first thrive there and then perish, and be followed by other
chance-comers like themselves. If neither St. Helena nor Ascension have
promoted the botanical intercourse between the Old and New Worlds,
we may easily account for the fact by remembering that they are not
only extremely minute and isolated spots, but are also bounded by lofty
and precipitous shores without beaches, where the seeds of foreign species
could readily establish themselves.
Currents and winds in the arctic regions drift along icebergs covered
with an alluvial soil, on which herbs and pine-saplings are seen growing,
which may often continue to vegetate on some distant shore where the
ice-island is stranded.
Dispersion of marine plants.—With respect to marine vegetation, the
seeds, being in their native element, may remain immersed in water without
injury for indefinite periods, so that there is no difficulty in conceiving
the diffusion of species wherever uncongenial climates, contrary currents,
and other causes do not interfere. All are familiar with the sight of the
floating sea-weed,


"Flung from the rock on ocean's foam to sail,
Where'er the surge may sweep, the tempest's breath prevail."


Remarkable accumulations of that species of sea-weed generally known
as gulf-weed, or sargasso, occur on each side of the equator in the Atlantic,
Pacific, and Indian Oceans. Columbus and other navigators, who first
encountered these banks of algæ in the Northern Atlantic, compared them
to vast inundated meadows, and state that they retarded the progress of
their vessels. The most extensive bank is a little west of the meridian
of Fayal, one of the Azores, between latitudes 35° and 36°: violent
north-winds sometimes prevail in this space, and drive the sea-weed to
623
low latitudes, as far as the 24th or even the 20th degree.859 Along the
northern edge of the Gulf stream Dr. Hooker found Fucus nodosus, and
F. serratus, which he traced all the way from lat. 36° N. to England.
The hollow pod-like receptacle in which the seeds of many algæ are
lodged, and the filaments attached to the seed-vessels of others, seem
intended to give buoyancy; and I may observe that these hydrophytes
are in general proliferous, so that the smallest fragment of a branch can
be developed into a perfect plant. The seeds, moreover, of the greater
number of species are enveloped with a mucous matter like that which
surrounds the eggs of some fish, and which not only protects them from
injury, but serves to attach them to floating bodies or to rocks.
Agency of animals in the distribution of plants.—But we have as yet
considered part only of the fertile resources of nature for conveying seeds
to a distance from their place of growth. The various tribes of animals
are busily engaged in furthering an object whence they derive such important
advantages. Sometimes an express provision is found in the
structure of seeds to enable them to adhere firmly by prickles, hooks, and
hairs, to the coats of animals, or feathers of the winged tribe, to which
they remain attached for weeks, or even months, and are borne along into
every region whither birds or quadrupeds may migrate. Linnæus enumerates
fifty genera of plants, and the number now known to botanists is
much greater, which are armed with hooks, by which, when ripe, they
adhere to the coats of animals. Most of these vegetables, he remarks,
require a soil enriched with dung. Few have failed to mark the locks of
wool hanging on the thorn-bushes, wherever the sheep pass, and it is probable
that the wolf or lion never give-chase to herbivorous animals without
being unconsciously subservient to this part of the vegetable economy.
A deer has strayed from the herd when browsing on some rich pasture,
when he is suddenly alarmed by the approach of his foe. He instantly
takes to flight, dashing through many a thicket, and swimming across
many a river and lake. The seeds of the herbs and shrubs which have
adhered to his smoking flanks are washed off again by the waters. The
thorny spray is torn off, and fixes itself in its hairy coat, until brushed off
again in other thickets and copses. Even on the spot where the victim
is devoured many of the seeds which he had swallowed immediately
before the chase may be left on the ground uninjured, and ready to spring
up in a new soil.
The passage, indeed, of undigested seeds through the stomachs of animals
is one of the most efficient causes of the dissemination of plants, and
is of all others, perhaps, the most likely to be overlooked. Few are
ignorant that a portion of the oats eaten by a horse preserve their germinating
faculty in the dung. The fact of their being still nutritious is
not lost on the sagacious rook. To many, says Linnæus, it seems extraordinary,
and something of a prodigy, that when a field is well tilled and
sown with the best wheat, it frequently produces darnel or the wild oat,
624
especially if it be manured with new dung; they do not consider that
the fertility of the smaller seeds is not destroyed in the stomachs of
animals.860
Agency of birds.—Some birds of the order Passeres devour the seeds
of plants in great quantities, which they eject again in very distant places,
without destroying its faculty of vegetation: thus a flight of larks will fill
the cleanest field with a great quantity of various kinds of plants, as the
melilot trefoil (Medicago lupulina), and others whose seeds are so heavy
that the wind is not able to scatter them to any distance.861 In like manner,
the blackbird and misselthrush, when they devour berries in too great
quantities, are known to consign them to the earth undigested in their
excrement.862
Pulpy fruits serve quadrupeds and birds as food, while their seeds, often
hard and indigestible, pass uninjured through the intestines, and are deposited
far from their original place of growth in a condition peculiarly
fit for vegetation.863 So well are the farmers, in some parts of England,
aware of this fact, that when they desire to raise a quickset hedge in the
shortest possible time, they feed turkeys with the haws of the common
white-thorn (Cratægus Oxyacantha), and then sow the stones which are
ejected in their excrement, whereby they gain an entire year in the growth
of the plant.864 Birds, when they pluck cherries, sloes, and haws, fly away
with them to some convenient place; and when they have devoured the
fruit, drop the stone into the ground. Captain Cook, in his account of
the volcanic island of Tanna, one of the New Hebrides, which he visited
in his second voyage, makes the following interesting
observation:—"Mr.
Forster, in his botanical excursion this day, shot a pigeon, in the craw of
which was a wild nutmeg."865 It is easy, therefore, to perceive, that birds
in their migrations to great distances, and even across seas, may transport
seeds to new isles and continents.
The sudden deaths to which great numbers of frugivorous birds are
annually exposed must not be omitted as auxiliary to the transportation of
seeds to new habitations. When the sea retires from the shore, and
leaves fruits and seeds on the beach, or in the mud of estuaries, it might,
by the returning tide, wash them away again, or destroy them by long
immersion; but when they are gathered by land birds which frequent the
sea side, or by waders and water-fowl, they are often borne inland; and
if the bird to whose crop they have been consigned is killed, they may be
left to grow up far from the sea. Let such an accident happen but once
in a century, or a thousand years, it will be sufficient to spread many of
the plants from one continent to another; for in estimating the activity
of these causes, we must not consider whether they act slowly in relation
625
to the period of our observation, but in reference to the duration of species
in general.
Let us trace the operation of this cause in connection with others. A
tempestuous wind bears the seeds of a plant many miles through the air,
and then delivers them to the ocean; the oceanic current drifts them to
a distant continent; by the fall of the tide they become the food of numerous
birds, and one of these is seized by a hawk or eagle, which, soaring
across hill and dale to a place of retreat, leaves, after devouring its prey,
the unpalatable seeds to spring up and flourish in a new soil.
The machinery before adverted to, is so capable of disseminating seeds
over almost unbounded spaces, that were we more intimately acquainted
with the economy of nature, we might probably explain all the instances
which occur of the aberration of plants to great distances from their native
countries. The real difficulty which must present itself to every one who
contemplates the present geographical distribution of species, is the small
number of exceptions to the rule of the non-intermixture of different groups
of plants. Why have they not, supposing them to have been ever so distinct
originally, become more blended and confounded together in the
lapse of ages?
Agency of man in the dispersion of plants.—But in addition to all the
agents already enumerated as instrumental in diffusing plants over the
globe, we have still to consider man—one of the most important of all.
He transports with him, into every region, the vegetables which he cultivates
for his wants, and is the involuntary means of spreading a still
greater number which are useless to him, or even noxious. "When the
introduction of cultivated plants," says De Candolle, "is of recent date,
there is no difficulty in tracing their origin; but when it is of high antiquity,
we are often ignorant of the true country of the plants on which
we feed. No one contests the American origin of the maize or the potatoe;
nor the origin, in the Old World, of the coffee-tree, and of wheat.
But there are certain objects of culture, of very ancient date, between the
tropics, such for example as the banana, of which the origin cannot be
verified. Armies, in modern times, have been known to carry, in all directions,
grain and cultivated vegetables from one extremity of Europe to
the other; and thus have shown us how, in more ancient times, the conquests
of Alexander, the distant expeditions of the Romans, and afterwards
the crusades, may have transported many plants from one part of the
world to the other."866
But, besides the plants used in agriculture, the numbers which have
been naturalized by accident, or which man has spread unintentionally,
is considerable. One of our old authors, Josselyn, gives a catalogue of
such plants as had, in his time, sprung up in the colony since the English
planted and kept cattle in New England. They were two-and-twenty in
number. The common nettle was the first which the settlers noticed;
and the plantain was called by the Indians "Englishman's foot," as if it
sprung from their footsteps.867
626
"We have introduced every where," observes De Candolle, "some
weeds which grow among our various kinds of wheat, and which have
been received, perhaps, originally from Asia along with them. Thus,
together with the Barbary wheat, the inhabitants of the south of Europe
have sown, for many ages, the plants of Algiers and Tunis. With the
wools and cottons of the East, or of Barbary, there are often brought into
France the grains of exotic plants, some of which naturalize themselves.
Of this I will cite a striking example. There is, at the gate of Montpellier,
a meadow set apart for drying foreign wool, after it has been washed.
There hardly passes a year without foreign plants being found naturalized
in this drying-ground. I have gathered there Centaurea parviflora,
Psoralea palæstina, and Hypericum crispum." This fact is not only
illustrative of the aid which man lends inadvertently to the propagation
of plants, but it also demonstrates the multiplicity of seeds which are
borne about in the woolly and hairy coats of wild animals.
The same botanist mentions instances of plants naturalized in seaports
by the ballast of ships; and several examples of others which have spread
through Europe from botanical gardens, so as to have become more common
than many indigenous species.
It is scarcely a century, says Linnæus, since the Canadian erigeron, or
flea-bane, was brought from America to the botanical garden at Paris;
and already the seeds have been carried by the winds so that it is diffused
over France, the British islands, Italy, Sicily, Holland, and Germany.868
Several others are mentioned by the Swedish naturalist, as having been
dispersed by similar means. The common thorn-apple (Datura Stramonium),
observes Willdenow, now grows as a noxious weed throughout
all Europe, with the exception of Sweden, Lapland and Russia. It came
from the East Indies and Abyssinia to us, and was thus universally spread
by certain quacks, who used its seeds as an emetic.869 The same plant is
now abundant throughout the greater part of the United States, along
road-sides and about farm-yards. The yellow monkey-flower, Mimulus
luteus, a plant from the north-west region of America, has now established
itself in various parts of England, and is spreading rapidly.
In hot and ill-cultivated countries, such naturalization takes place more
easily. Thus the Chenopodium ambrosioides, sown by Mr. Burchell on a
point of St. Helena, multiplied so fast in four years as to become one of
the commonest weeds in the island, and it has maintained its ground ever
since 1845.870
The most remarkable proof, says De Candolle, of the extent to which
man is unconsciously the instrument of dispersing and naturalizing species,
is found in the fact, that in New Holland, America, and the Cape
of Good Hope, the aboriginal European species exceed in number all the
others which have come from any distant regions; so that, in this instance,
the influence of man has surpassed that of all the other causes which tend
627
to disseminate plants to remote districts. Of nearly 1600 British flowering
plants, it is supposed that about 300 species are naturalized; but a
large proportion of these would perish with the discontinuance of agriculture.
Although we are but slightly acquainted, as yet, with the extent of our
instrumentality in naturalizing species, yet the facts ascertained afford no
small reason to suspect that the number which we introduce unintentionally
exceeds all those transported by design. Nor is it unnatural to suppose
that the functions, which the inferior beings, extirpated by man, once
discharged in the economy of nature, should devolve upon the human
race. If we drive many birds of passage from different countries, we are
probably required to fulfil their office of carrying seeds, eggs of fish, insects,
mollusks, and other creatures, to distant regions: if we extirpate quadrupeds,
we must replace them not merely as consumers of the animal and
vegetable substances which they devour, but as disseminators of plants,
and of the inferior classes of the animal kingdom. I do not mean to
insinuate that the very same changes which man brings about, would have
taken place by means of the agency of other species, but merely that he
supersedes a certain number of agents; and so far as he disperses plants
unintentionally, or against his will, his intervention is strictly analogous
to that of the species so extirpated.
I may observe, moreover, that if, at former periods, the animals inhabiting
any given district have been partially altered by the extinction of
some species, and the introduction of others, whether by new creations or
by immigration, a change must have taken place in regard to the particular
plants conveyed about with them to foreign countries. As, for
example, when one set of migratory birds is substituted for another, the
countries from and to which seeds are transported are immediately changed.
Vicissitudes, therefore, analogous to those which man has occasioned,
may have previously attended the springing up of new relations between
species in the vegetable and animal worlds.
It may also be remarked, that if man is the most active agent in enlarging,
so also is he in circumscribing the geographical boundaries of
particular plants. He promotes the migration of some, he retards that
of other species; so that, while in many respects he appears to be exerting
his power to blend and confound the various provinces of indigenous
species, he is, in other ways, instrumental in obstructing the fusion into
one group of the inhabitants of contiguous provinces.
Thus, for example, when two botanical regions exist in the same great
continent, such as the European region, comprehending the central parts
of Europe, and those surrounding the Mediterranean, and the Oriental
region, as it has been termed, embracing the countries adjoining the Black
Sea and the Caspian, the interposition between these of thousands of
square miles of cultivated lands, opposes a new and powerful barrier against
the mutual interchange of indigenous plants. Botanists are well aware
that garden plants naturalize and diffuse themselves with great facility in
comparatively unreclaimed countries, but spread themselves slowly and
628
with difficulty in districts highly cultivated. There are many obvious
causes for this difference; by drainage and culture the natural variety of
stations is diminished, and those stray individuals by which the passage
of a species from one fit station to another is effected, are no sooner detected
by the agriculturist, than they are uprooted as weeds. The larger
shrubs and trees, in particular, can scarcely ever escape observation, when
they have attained a certain size, and will rarely fail to be cut down if
unprofitable.
The same observations are applicable to the interchange of the insects,
birds, and quadrupeds of two regions situated like those above alluded to.
No beasts of prey are permitted to make their way across the intervening
arable tracts. Many birds, and hundreds of insects, which would have
found some palatable food amongst the various herbs and trees of the
primeval wilderness, are unable to subsist on the olive, the vine, the wheat,
and a few trees and grasses favored by man. In addition, therefore, to
his direct intervention, man, in this case, operates indirectly to impede
the dissemination of plants, by intercepting the migration of animals,
many of which would otherwise have been active in transporting seeds
from one province to another.
Whether, in the vegetable kingdom, the influence of man will tend,
after a considerable lapse of ages, to render the geographical range of
species in general more extended, as De Candolle seems to anticipate, or
whether the compensating agency above alluded to will not counterbalance
the exceptions caused by our naturalizations, admits at least of some
doubt. In the attempt to form an estimate on this subject, we must be
careful not to underrate, or almost overlook, as some appear to have done,
the influence of man in checking the diffusion of plants, and restricting
their distribution to narrower limits.

629</div></body></text></TEI>