<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="22">

ATMOLOGY.

CHAPTER III.
The Relation of Vapor and Air.

Sect. 1.—The Boylean Law of the Air’s
Elasticity.
IN the Sixth Book (Chap. iv.
Sect. 1.) we have already seen how the
conception on the laws of fluid equilibrium was, by Pascal and others,
extended to air, as well as water. But though air presses and is
pressed as water presses and is pressed, pressure produces upon air an
effect which it does not, in any obvious degree, produce upon water.
Air which is pressed is also compressed, or made to occupy a
smaller space; and is consequently also made more dense, or
condensed; and on the other hand, when the pressure upon a
portion of air is diminished, the air expands or is rarefied. These
broad facts are evident. They are expressed in a general way by saying
that air is an elastic fluid, yielding in a certain degree to
pressure, and recovering its previous dimensions when the pressure is
removed.
But when men had reached this point, the questions obviously
offered themselves, in what degree and according to what law air
yields to pressure; when it is compressed, what relation does the
density bear to the pressure? The use which had been made of tubes
containing columns of mercury, by which the pressure of portions of
air was varied and measured, suggested obvious modes of devising
experiments by which this question might be answered. Such experiments
accordingly were made by Boyle about 1650; and the result at which he
arrived was, that when air is thus compressed, the density is as the
pressure. Thus if the pressure of the atmosphere in its common state
be equivalent to 30 inches of mercury, as shown by the barometer; if
air included in a tube be pressed by 30 additional inches of 164 mercury, its density
will be doubled, the air being compressed into one half the space. If
the pressure be increased threefold, the density is also trebled; and
so on. The same law was soon afterwards (in 1676) proved
experimentally by Mariotte. And this law of the air’s elasticity, that
the density is as the pressure, is sometimes called the Boylean
Law, and sometimes the Law of Boyle and Mariotte.
Air retains its aerial character permanently; but there are other
aerial substances which appear as such, and then disappear or change
into some other condition. Such are termed vapors. And the
discovery of their true relation to air was the result of a long
course of researches and speculations.
[2nd Ed.] [It was found by M. Cagniard de la Tour (in 1823), that
at a certain temperature, a liquid, under sufficient pressure, becomes
clear transparent vapor or gas, having the same bulk as the liquid.
This condition Dr. Faraday calls the Cagniard de la Tour state,
(the Tourian state?) It was also discovered by Dr. Faraday that
carbonic-acid gas, and many other gases, which were long conceived to
be permanently elastic, are really reducible to a liquid state by
pressure.39 And in 1835, M. Thilorier found the
means of reducing liquid carbonic acid to a solid form, by means of
the cold produced in evaporation. More recently Dr. Faraday has added
several substances usually gaseous to the list of those which could
previously be shown in the liquid state, and has reduced others,
including ammonia, nitrous oxide, and sulphuretted hydrogen, to a
solid consistency.40 After these discoveries, we may, I
think, reasonably doubt whether all bodies are not capable of existing
in the three consistencies of solid, liquid, and air.</div></body></text></TEI>