<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="57">CHAPTER III.
Problem of the Propagation of Sound.
WE have seen that the ancient
philosophers, for the most part, held that sound was transmitted, as
well as produced, by some motion of the air, without defining what
kind of motion this was; that some writers, however, applied to it a
very happy similitude, the expansive motion of the circular waves
produced by throwing a stone into still water; but that
notwithstanding, some rejected this mode of conception, as, for
instance, Bacon, who ascribed the transmission of sound to certain
“spiritual species.”
Though it was an obvious thought to ascribe the motion of sound to
some motion of air; to conceive what kind of motion could and did
produce this effect, must have been a matter of grave perplexity at
the time of which we are speaking; and is far from easy to most
persons even now. We may judge of the difficulty of forming this
conception, when we recollect that John Bernoulli the younger12 declared, that he could not understand
Newton’s proposition on this subject. The difficulty consists in this;
that the movement of the parts of air, in which sound consists,
travels along, but that the parts 33 of air themselves do not so travel.
Accordingly Otto Guericke,13 the inventor of the air-pump, asks,
“How can sound be conveyed by the motion of the air? when we find that
it is better conveyed through air that is still, than when there is a
wind.” We may observe, however, that he was partly misled by finding,
as he thought, that a bell could be heard in the vacuum of his
air-pump; a result which arose, probably, from some imperfection in
his apparatus.
12 Prize Dis. on Light,
1736.
13 De Vac. Spat. p. 138.
Attempts were made to determine, by experiment, the circumstances
of the motion of sound; and especially its velocity. Gassendi14 was one of the first who did this. He
employed fire-arms for the purpose, and thus found the velocity to be
1473 Paris feet in a second. Roberval found a velocity so small (560
feet) that it threw uncertainty upon the rest, and affected Newton’s
reasonings subsequently.15 Cassini, Huyghens, Picard, Römer, found
a velocity of 1172 Paris feet, which is more accurate than the former.
Gassendi had been surprised to find that the velocity with which
sounds travel, is the same whether they are loud or gentle.
14 Fischer, Gesch. d. Physik.
vol. i. 171.
15 Newt. Prin. B. ii. P. 50,
Schol.
The explanation of this constant velocity of sound, and of its
amount, was one of the problems of which a solution was given in the
Great Charter of modern science, Newton’s Principia (1687).
There, for the first time, were explained the real nature of the
motions and mutual action of the parts of the air through which sound
is transmitted. It was shown16 that a body
vibrating in an elastic medium, will propagate pulses through
the medium; that is, the parts of the medium will move forwards and
backwards, and this motion will affect successively those parts which
are at a greater and greater distance from the origin of motion. The
parts, in going forwards, produce condensation; in returning to their
first places, they allow extension; and the play of the elasticities
developed by these expansions and contractions, supplies the forces
which continue to propagate the motion.
16 Newt. Prin. B. ii. P.
43.
The idea of such a motion as this, is, as we have said, far from
easy to apprehend distinctly: but a distinct apprehension of it is a
step essential to the physical part of the sciences now under notice;
for it is by means of such pulses, or undulations, that
not only sound, but light, and probably heat, are propagated. We
constantly meet with evidence of the difficulty which men have in
conceiving this undulatory motion, and in separating it from a local
motion of the medium as a 34 mass. For instance, it is not easy at
first to conceive the waters of a great river flowing constantly
down towards the sea, while waves are rolling up the
very same part of the stream; and while the great elevation, which
makes the tide, is travelling from the sea perhaps with a velocity of
fifty miles an hour. The motion of such a wave, or elevation, is
distinct from any stream, and is of the nature of undulations in
general. The parts of the fluid stir for a short time and for a small
distance, so as to accumulate themselves on a neighboring part, and
then retire to their former place; and this movement affects the parts
in the order of their places. Perhaps if the reader looks at a field
of standing corn when gusts of wind are sweeping over it in visible
waves, he will have his conception of this matter aided; for he will
see that here, where each ear of grain is anchored by its stalk, there
can be no permanent local motion of the substance, but only a
successive stooping and rising of the separate straws, producing
hollows and waves, closer and laxer strips of the crowded ears.
Newton had, moreover, to consider the mechanical consequences which
such condensations and rarefactions of the elastic medium, air, would
produce in the parts of the fluid itself. Employing known laws of the
elasticity of air, he showed, in a very remarkable proposition,17 the law according to which the
particles of air might vibrate. We may observe, that in this solution,
as in that of the vibrating string already mentioned, a rule was
exhibited according to which the particles might oscillate,
but not the law to which they must conform. It was proved
that, by taking the motion of each particle to be perfectly similar to
that of a pendulum, the forces, developed by contraction and
expansion, were precisely such as the motion required; but it was not
shown that no other type of oscillation would give rise to the same
accordance of force and motion. Newton’s reasoning also gave a
determination of the speed of propagation of the pulses: it appeared
that sound ought to travel with the velocity which a body would
acquire by falling freely through half the height of a homogeneous
atmosphere; “the height of a homogeneous atmosphere” being the
height which the air must have, in order to produce, at the earth’s
surface, the actual atmospheric pressure, supposing no diminution of
density to take place in ascending. This height is about 29,000 feet;
and hence it followed that the velocity was 968 feet. This velocity is
really considerably less than that of sound; but at the time of which
35 we speak, no
accurate measure had been established; and Newton persuaded himself,
by experiments made in the cloister of Trinity College, his residence,
that his calculation was not far from the fact. When, afterwards, more
exact experiments showed the velocity to be 1142 English feet, Newton
attempted to explain the difference by various considerations, none of
which were adequate to the purpose;—as, the dimensions of the
solid particles of which the fluid air consists;—or the vapors
which are mixed with it. Other writers offered other suggestions; but
the true solution of the difficulty was reserved for a period
considerably subsequent.
17 Princ. B. ii. P. 48.
Newton’s calculation of the motion of sound, though logically
incomplete, was the great step in the solution of the problem; for
mathematicians could not but presume that his result was not
restricted to the hypothesis on which he had obtained it; and the
extension of the solution required only mere ordinary talents. The
logical defect of his solution was assailed, as might have been
expected. Cranmer (professor at Geneva), in 1741, conceived that he
was destroying the conclusiveness of Newton’s reasoning, by showing
that it applied equally to other modes of oscillation. This, indeed,
contradicted the enunciation of the 48th Prop. of the Second Book of
the Principia; but it confirmed and extended all the general
results of the demonstration; for it left even the velocity of sound
unaltered, and thus showed that the velocity did not depend
mechanically on the type of the oscillation. But the satisfactory
establishment of this physical generalization was to be supplied from
the vast generalizations of analysis, which mathematicians were now
becoming able to deal with. Accordingly this task was performed by the
great master of analytical generalization, Lagrange, in 1759, when, at
the age of twenty-three, he and two friends published the first volume
of the Turin Memoirs. Euler, as his manner was, at once
perceived the merit of the new solution, and pursued the subject on
the views thus suggested. Various analytical improvements and
extensions were introduced into the solution by the two great
mathematicians; but none of these at all altered the formula by which
the velocity of sound was expressed; and the discrepancy between
calculation and observation, about one-sixth of the whole, which had
perplexed Newton, remained still unaccounted for.
The merit of satisfactorily explaining this
discrepancy belongs to Laplace. He was the first to remark18 that the common law of the 36 changes of elasticity
in the air, as dependent on its compression, cannot be applied to
those rapid vibrations in which sound consists, since the sudden
compression produces a degree of heat which additionally increases the
elasticity. The ratio of this increase depended on the experiments by
which the relation of heat and air is established. Laplace, in 1816,
published19 the theorem on which the correction
depends. On applying it, the calculated velocity of sound agreed very
closely with the best antecedent experiments, and was confirmed by
more exact ones instituted for that purpose.
18 Méc. Cél. t. v. l. xii. p.
96.
19 Ann. Phys. et Chim. t. iii.
p. 288.
This step completes the solution of the problem of the propagation
of sound, as a mathematical induction, obtained from, and verified by,
facts. Most of the discussions concerning points of analysis to which
the investigations on this subject gave rise, as, for instance, the
admissibility of discontinuous functions into the solutions of
partial differential equations, belong to the history of pure
mathematics. Those which really concern the physical theory of sound
may be referred to the problem of the motion of air in tubes, to which
we shall soon have to proceed; but we must first
speak of another form which the problem of vibrating strings
assumed.
It deserves to be noticed that the ultimate result of the study of
the undulations of fluids seems to show that the comparison of the
motion of air in the diffusion of sound with the motion of circular
waves from a centre in water, which is mentioned at the beginning of
this chapter, though pertinent in a certain way, is not exact. It
appears by Mr. Scott’s recent investigations concerning waves,20 that the circular waves are oscillating
waves of the Second order, and are gregarious. The sound-wave
seems rather to resemble the great solitary Wave of Translation of the
First order, of which we have already spoken in Book vi. chapter vi.
20 Brit. Ass. Reports for 1844,
p. 361.
</div></body></text></TEI>