<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="84">CHAPTER II.
Progress of Magnetic Theory.
Theory of Magnetic
Action.—The assumption of a fluid, as a mode of
explaining the phenomena, was far less obvious in magnetic than in
electric cases, yet it was soon arrived at. After the usual philosophy
of the middle ages, the “forms” of Aquinas, the “efflux” of Cusanus,
the “vapors” of Costæus, and the like, which are recorded by
Gilbert,10 we have his own theory, which he also
expresses by ascribing the effects to a “formal efficiency;”—a
“form of primary globes; the proper entity and existence of
their homogeneous parts, which we may call a primary and radical and
astral form;”—of which forms there is one in the sun, one
in the moon, one in the earth, the latter being the magnetic
virtue.
10 Gilb. lib. ii. c. 3, 4
Without attempting to analyse the precise import of these
expressions, we may proceed to Descartes’s explanation of magnetic
phenomena. The mode in which he presents this subject11 is, perhaps, the 221 most persuasive of
his physical attempts. If a magnet be placed among iron filings, these
arrange themselves in curved lines, which proceed from one pole of the
magnet to the other. It was not difficult to conceive these to be the
traces of currents of ethereal matter which circulate through the
magnet, and which are thus rendered sensible even to the eye. When
phenomena could not be explained by means of one vortex, several were
introduced. Three Memoirs on Magnetism, written on such principles,
had the prize adjudged12 by the French Academy of Sciences in
1746.
11 Prin. Phil. pars c. iv.
146.
12 Coulomb, 1789, p. 482.
But the Cartesian philosophy gradually declined; and it was not
difficult to show that the magnetic curves, as well as other
phenomena, would, in fact, result from the attraction and repulsion of
two poles. The analogy of magnetism with electricity was so strong and
clear, that similar theories were naturally proposed for the two sets
of facts; the distinction of bodies into conductors and electrics in
the one case, corresponding to the distinction of soft and hard steel,
in their relations to magnetism. Æpinus published a theory of
magnetism and electricity at the same time (1759); and the former
theory, like the latter, explained the phenomena of the opposite poles
as results of the excess and defect of a magnetic “fluid,” which was
dislodged and accumulated in the ends of the body, by the repulsion of
its own particles, and by the attraction of iron or steel, as in the
case of induced electricity. The Æpinian theory of magnetism, as of
electricity, was recast by Coulomb, and presented in a new shape, with
two fluids instead of one. But before this theory was reduced to
calculation, it was obviously desirable, in the first place, to
determine the law of force.
In magnetic, as in electric action, the determination of the law of
attraction of the particles was attended at first with some
difficulty, because the action which a finite magnet exerts is a
compound result of the attractions and repulsions of many points.
Newton had imagined the attractive force of magnetism to be inversely
as the cube of the distance; but Mayer in 1760, and Lambert a few
years later, asserted the law to be, in this as in other forces, the
inverse square. Coulomb has the merit of having first clearly
confirmed this law, by the use of his torsion-balance.13 He established, at the same time, other
very important facts, for instance, “that the directive magnetic
force, which the earth exerts upon a needle, is a constant quantity,
parallel 222 to the
magnetic meridian, and passing through the same point of the needle
whatever be its position.” This was the more important, because it was
necessary, in the first place, to allow for the effect of the
terrestrial force, before the mutual action of the magnets could be
extricated from the phenomena.14 Coulomb then
proceeded to correct the theory of magnetism.
13 Mem. A. P. 1784, 2d Mem. p.
593.
14 p. 603.
Coulomb’s reform of the Æpinian theory, in the case of magnetism,
as in that of electricity, substituted two fluids (an austral
and a boreal fluid,) for the single fluid; and in this way
removed the necessity under which Æpinus found himself, of supposing
all the particles of iron and steel and other magnetic bodies to have
a peculiar repulsion for each other, exactly equal to their attraction
for the magnetic fluid. But in the case of magnetism, another
modification was necessary. It was impossible to suppose here, as in
the electrical phenomena, that one of the fluids was accumulated on
one extremity of a body, and the other fluid on the other extremity;
for though this might appear, at first sight, to be the case in a
magnetic needle, it was found that when the needle was cut into two
halves, the half in which the austral fluid had seemed to predominate,
acquired immediately a boreal pole opposite to its austral pole, and a
similar effect followed in the other half. The same is true, into
however many parts the magnetic body be cut. The way in which Coulomb
modified the theory so as to reconcile it with such facts, is simple
and satisfactory. He supposes15 the magnetic
body to be made up of “molecules or integral parts,” or, as they were
afterwards called by M. Poisson, “magnetic elements.” In each of these
elements, (which are extremely minute,) the fluids can be separated,
so that each element has an austral and a boreal pole; but the austral
pole of an element which is adjacent to the boreal pole of the next,
neutralizes, or nearly neutralizes, its effect; so that the sensible
magnetism appears only towards the extremities of the body, as it
would do if the fluids could permeate the body freely. We shall have
exactly the same result, as to sensible magnetic force, on the one
supposition and on the other, as Coulomb showed.16
15 Mem. A. P. 1789, p.
488.
16 Mem. A. P. p. 492.
The theory, thus freed from manifest incongruities, was to be
reduced to calculation, and compared with experiment; this was done in
Coulomb’s Seventh Memoir.17 The difficulties of calculation in
this, as in the electric problem, could not be entirely surmounted by
the analysis of Coulomb; but by various artifices, he obtained
theoretically the 223 relative amount of magnetism at several
points of a needle,18 and the proposition that the directive
force of the earth on similar needles saturated with magnetism, was as
the cube of their dimensions; conclusions which agreed with
experiment.
17 A. P. 1789.
18 p. 485.
The agreement thus obtained was sufficient to give a great
probability to the theory; but an improvement of the methods of
calculation and a repetition of experiments, was, in this as in other
cases, desirable, as a confirmation of the labors of the original
theorist. These requisites, in the course of time, were supplied. The
researches of Laplace and Legendre on the figure of the earth had (as
we have already stated,) introduced some very
peculiar analytical artifices, applicable to the attractions of
spheroids; and these methods were employed by M. Biot in 1811, to show
that on an elliptical spheroid, the thickness of the fluid in the
direction of the radius would be as the distance from the centre.19 But the subject was taken up in a more
complete manner in 1824 by M. Poisson, who obtained general
expressions for the attractions or repulsions of a body of any form
whatever, magnetized by influence, upon a given point; and in the case
of spherical bodies was able completely to solve the equations which
determine these forces.20
19 Bull. des Sc. No. li.
20 A. P. for 1821 and 2,
published 1826.
Previously to these theoretical investigations, Mr. Barlow had made
a series of experiments on the effect of an iron sphere upon a compass
needle; and had obtained empirical formulæ for the amount of the
deviation of the needle, according to its dependence upon the position
and magnitude of the sphere. He afterwards deduced the same formulæ
from a theory which was, in fact, identical with that of Coulomb, but
which he considered as different, in that it supposed the magnetic
fluids to be entirely collected at the surface of the sphere. He had
indeed found, by experiment, that the surface was the only part in
which there was any sensible magnetism; and that a thin shell of iron
would produce the same effect as a solid ball of the same
diameter.
But this was, in fact, a most complete verification of Coulomb’s
theory. For though that theory did not suppose the magnetism to be
collected solely at the surface, as Mr. Barlow found it, it followed
from the theory, that the sensible magnetic intensity assumed
the same distribution (namely, a surface distribution,) as if the
fluids could permeate the whole body, instead of the “magnetic
elements” only. Coulomb, indeed, had not expressly noticed the result,
that the sensible 224 magnetism would be confined to the
surface of bodies; but he had found that, in a long needle, the
magnetic fluid might be supposed to be concentrated very near the
extremities, just as it is in a long electric body. The theoretical
confirmation of this rule among the other consequences of the
theory,—that the sensible magnetism would be collected at the
surface,—was one of the results of Poisson’s analysis. For it
appeared that if the sum of the electric elements of the body was
equal to the whole body, there would be no difference between the
action of a solid sphere and very thin shell.
We may, then, consider the Coulombian theory to be fully
established and verified, as a representation of the laws of
magnetical phenomena. We may add, as a remarkable and valuable example
of an ulterior step in the course of sciences, the application of the
laws of the distribution of magnetism to the purposes of navigation.
It had been found that the mass of iron which exists in a ship
produces a deviation in the direction of the compass-needle, which was
termed “local attraction,” and which rendered the compass an erroneous
guide. Mr. Barlow proposed to correct this by a plate of iron placed
near the compass; the plate being of comparatively small mass, but, in
consequence of its expanded form, and its proximity to the needle, of
equivalent effect to the disturbing cause.
[2nd Ed.] [This proposed arrangement was not successful, because as
the ship turns into different positions, it may be considered as
revolving round a vertical axis; and as this does not coincide with
the magnetic axis, the relative magnetic position of the disturbing
parts of the ship, and of the correcting plate, will be altered, so
that they will not continue to counteract each other. In high magnetic
latitudes the correcting plate was used with success.
But when iron ships became common, a correction of the effect of
the iron upon the ship’s compass in the general case became necessary.
Mr. Airy devised the means of making this correction. By placing a
magnet and a mass of iron in certain positions relative to the
compass, the effect of the rest of the iron in the ship is completely
counteracted in all positions.21] ~Additional
material in the 3rd edition.~
21 See Phil. Trans.
1836.
But we have still to trace the progress of the theory of
terrestrial magnetism.
Theory of Terrestrial
Magnetism.—Gilbert had begun a plausible course of
speculation on this point. “We must reject,” he says,22 “in 225 the first place, that vulgar opinion of
recent writers concerning magnetic mountains, or a certain magnetic
rock, or an imaginary pole at a certain distance from the pole of the
earth.” For, he adds, “we learn by experience, that there is no such
fixed pole or term in the earth for the variation.” Gilbert describes
the whole earth as a magnetic globe, and attributes the variation to
the irregular form of its protuberances, the solid parts only being
magnetic. It was not easy to confirm or refute this opinion, but other
hypotheses were tried by various writers; for instance, Halley had
imagined, from the forms of the lines of equal variation, that there
must be four magnetic poles; but Euler23 showed that the
“Halleian lines” would, for the most part, result from the supposition
of two magnetic poles, and assigned their position so as to represent
pretty well the known state of the variation all over the world in
1744. But the variation was not the only phenomenon which required to
be taken into account; the dip at different places, and also the
intensity of the force, were to be considered. We have already mentioned M. de Humboldt’s collection of
observations of the dip. These were examined by M. Biot, with the view
of reducing them to the action of two poles in the supposed
terrestrial magnetic axis. Having, at first, made the distance of
these poles from the centre of the earth indefinite, he found that his
formulæ agreed more and more nearly with the observations, as the
poles were brought nearer; and that fact and theory coincided
tolerably well when both poles were at the centre. In 1809,24 Krafft simplified this result, by
showing that, on this supposition, the tangent of the dip was twice
the tangent of the latitude of the place as measured from the magnetic
equator. But M. Hansteen, who has devoted to the subject of
terrestrial magnetism a great amount of labor and skill, has shown
that, taking together all the observations which we possess, we are
compelled to suppose four magnetic poles; two near the north pole, and
two near the south pole, of the terrestrial globe; and that these
poles, no two of which are exactly opposite each other, are all in
motion, with different velocities, some moving to the east and some to
the west. This curious collection of facts awaits the hand of future
theorists, when the ripeness of time shall invite them to the
task.
22 Lib. iv. c. 1. De
Variatione.
23 Ac. Berlin, 1757.
24 Enc. Met. p. 742.
[2nd Ed.] [I had thus written in the first edition. The theorist
who was needed to reduce this accumulation of facts to their laws,
226 had already
laid his powerful hand upon them; namely, M. Gauss, a mathematician
not inferior to any of the great men who completed the theory of
gravitation. And institutions had been established for extending the
collection of the facts pertaining to it, on a scale which elevates
Magnetism into a companionship with Astronomy. M. Hansteen’s
Magnetismus der Erde was published in 1819. His conclusions
respecting the position of the four magnetic “poles” excited so much
interest in his own country, that the Norwegian Storthing, or
parliament, by a unanimous vote, provided funds for a magnetic
expedition which he was to conduct along the north of Europe and Asia;
and this they did at the very time when they refused to make a grant
to the king for building a palace at Christiania. The expedition was
made in 1828–30, and verified Hansteen’s anticipations as to the
existence of a region of magnetic convergence in Siberia, which he
considered as indicating a “pole” to the north of that country. M.
Erman also travelled round the earth at the same time, making magnetic
observations.
About the same time another magnetical phenomenon attracted
attention. Besides the general motion of the magnetic poles, and the
diurnal movements of the needle, it was found that small and irregular
disturbances take place in its position, which M. de Humboldt termed
magnetic storms. And that which excited a strong interest on
this subject was the discovery that these magnetic storms, seen only
by philosophers who watch the needle with microscopic exactness, rage
simultaneously over large tracts of the surface of our globe. This was
detected about 1825 by a comparison of the observations of M. Arago at
Paris with simultaneous observations of M. Kupffer at Kasan in Russia,
distant more than 47 degrees of longitude.
At the instance of M. de Humboldt, the Imperial Academy of Russia
adopted with zeal the prosecution of this inquiry, and formed a chain
of magnetic stations across the whole of the Russian empire. Magnetic
observations were established at Petersburg and at Kasan, and
corresponding observations were made at Moscow, at Nicolaieff in the
Crimea, and Barnaoul and Nertchinsk in Siberia, at Sitka in Russian
America, and even at Pekin. To these magnetic stations the Russian
government afterwards added, Catharineburg in Russia Proper,
Helsingfors in Finland, Teflis in Georgia. A comparison of the results
obtained at four of these stations made by MM. de Humboldt and Dove,
in the year 1830, showed that the magnetic disturbances were
simultaneous, and were for the most parallel in their progress. 227
Important steps in the prosecution of this subject were soon after
made by M. Gauss, the great mathematician of Göttingen. He contrived
instruments and modes of observation far more perfect than any before
employed, and organized a system of comparative observations
throughout Europe. In 1835, stations for this purpose were established
at Altona, Augsburg, Berlin, Breda, Breslau, Copenhagen, Dublin,
Freiberg, Göttingen, Greenwich, Hanover, Leipsic, Marburg, Milan,
Munich, Petersburg, Stockholm, and Upsala. At these places, six times
in the year, observations were taken simultaneously, at intervals of
five minutes for 24 hours. The Results of the Magnetic
Association (Resultaten des Magnetischen Vereins) were published
by MM. Gauss and Weber, beginning in 1836.
British physicists did not at first take any leading part in these
plans. But in 1836, Baron Humboldt, who by his long labors and
important discoveries in this subject might be considered as
peculiarly entitled to urge its claims, addressed a letter to the Duke
of Sussex, then President of the Royal Society, asking for the
co-operation of this country in so large and hopeful a scheme for the
promotion of science. The Royal Society willingly entertained this
appeal; and the progress of the cause was still further promoted when
it was zealously taken up by the British Association for the
Advancement of Science, assembled at Newcastle in 1838. The
Association there expressed its strong interest in the German system
of magnetic observations; and at the instigation of this body, and of
the Royal Society, four complete magnetical observatories were
established by the British government, at Toronto, St. Helena, the
Cape of Good Hope, and Van Diemen’s Land. The munificence of the
Directors of the East India Company founded and furnished an equal
number at Simla (in the Himalayah), Madras, Bombay, and Sincapore. Sir
Thomas Brisbane added another at his own expense at Kelso, in
Scotland. Besides this, the government sent out a naval expedition to
make discoveries (magnetic among others), in the Antarctic regions,
under the command of Sir James Ross. Other states lent their
assistance also, and founded or reorganized their magnetic
observatories. Besides those already mentioned, one was established by
the French government at Algiers; one by the Belgian, at Brussels; two
by Austria, at Prague and Milan; one by Prussia, at Breslau; one by
Bavaria, at Munich; one by Spain, at Cadiz; there are two in the
United States, at Philadelphia and Cambridge; one at Cairo, founded by
the Pasha of Egypt; and in India, one at Trevandrum, established by
the Rajah of Travancore; and one by 228 the King of Oude, at Lucknow. At all
these distant stations the same plan was followed out, by observations
strictly simultaneous, made according to the same methods, with the
same instrumental means. Such a scheme, combining world-wide extent
with the singleness of action of an individual mind, is hitherto
without parallel.
At first, the British stations were established for three years
only; but it was thought advisable to extend this period three years
longer, to end in 1845. And when the termination of that period
arrived, a discussion was held among the magneticians themselves,
whether it was better to continue the observations still, or to
examine and compare the vast mass of observations already collected,
so as to see to what results and improvements of methods they pointed.
This question was argued at the meeting of the British Association at
Cambridge in that year; and the conference ended in the magneticians
requesting to have the observations continued, at some of the
observatories for an indefinite period, at others, till the year 1848.
In the mean time the Antarctic expedition had brought back a rich
store of observations, fitted to disclose the magnetic condition of
those regions which it had explored. These were discussed,
and their results exhibited, in the Philosophical Transactions
for 1843, by Col. Sabine, who had himself at various periods, made
magnetic observations in the Arctic regions, and in several remote
parts of the globe, and had always been a zealous laborer in this
fruitful field. The general mass of the observations was placed under
the management of Professor Lloyd, of Dublin, who has enriched the
science of magnetism with several valuable instruments and methods,
and who, along with Col. Sabine, made a magnetic survey of the British
Isles in 1835 and 1836.
I do not dwell upon magnetic surveys of various countries made by
many excellent observers; as MM. Quetelet, Forbes, Fox, Bache and
others.
The facts observed at each station were, the intensity of
the magnetic force; the declination of the needle from the
meridian, sometimes called the variation; and its
inclination to the horizon, the dip;—or at least,
some elements equivalent to these. The values of these elements at any
given time, if known, can be expressed by charts of the earth’s
surface, on which are drawn the isodynamic, isogonal,
and isoclinal curves. The second of these kinds of charts
contain the “Halleian lines” spoken of in a previous page. Moreover the magnetic elements at each
place are to be observed in such a 229 manner as to determine both their
periodical variations (the changes which occur in the period of
a day, and of a year), the secular changes, as the gradual
increase or diminution of the declination at the same place for many
years; and the irregular fluctuations which, as we have said, are
simultaneous over a large part, or the whole, of the earth’s
surface.
When these Facts have been ascertained over the whole extent of the
earth’s surface, we shall still have to inquire what is the Cause of
the changes in the forces which these phenomena disclose. But as a
basis for all speculation on that subject, we must know the law of the
phenomena, and of the forces which immediately produce them. I have
already said that Euler tried to account for
the Halleian lines by means of two magnetic “poles,” but that
M. Hansteen conceived it necessary to assume four. But an
entirely new light has been thrown upon this subject by the beautiful
investigations of Gauss, in his Theory of Terrestrial
Magnetism, published in 1839. He remarks that the term “poles,” as
used by his predecessors, involves an assumption arbitrary, and, as it
is now found, false; namely, that certain definite points, two, four,
or more, acting according to the laws of ordinary magnetical poles,
will explain the phenomena. He starts from a more comprehensive
assumption, that magnetism is distributed throughout the mass of the
earth in an unknown manner. On this assumption he obtains a function
V, by the differentials of which the elements of the magnetic
force at any point will be expressed. This function V is well
known in physical astronomy, and is obtained by summing all the
elements of magnetic force in each particle, each multiplied by the
reciprocal of its distance; or as we may express it, by taking the sum
of each element and its proximity jointly. Hence it has been
proposed25 to term this function the “integral
proximity” of the attracting mass.26 By using the
most refined 230
mathematical artifices for deducing the values of V and its
differentials in converging series, he is able to derive the
coefficients of these series from the observed magnetic elements at
certain places, and hence, to calculate them for all places. The
comparison of the calculation with the observed results is, of course,
the test of the truth of the theory.
25 Quart. Rev. No. 131, p.
283.
26 The function V is of constant
occurrence in investigations respecting attractions. It is introduced
by Laplace in his investigations respecting the attractions of
spheroids, Méc. Cél. Livr. iii. Art. 4.
Mr. Green and Professor Mac Cullagh have proposed to term this
function the Potential of the system; but this term (though
suggested, I suppose, by analogy with the substantive
Exponential), does not appear convenient in its form. On the
other hand, the term Integral Proximity does not indicate that
which gives the function its peculiar claim to distinction; namely,
that its differentials express the power or attraction of the system.
Perhaps Integral Potentiality, or Integral Attractivity,
would be a term combining the recommendations of both the
others.
The degree of convergence of the series depends upon the unknown
distribution of magnetism within the earth. “If we could venture to
assume,” says M. Gauss, “that the members have a sensible influence
only as far as the fourth order, complete observations from eight
points would be sufficient, theoretically considered, for the
determination of the coefficients.” And under certain limitations,
making this assumption, as the best we can do at present, M. Gauss
obtains from eight places, 24 coefficients (each supplying three
elements), and hence calculates the magnetic elements (intensity,
variation and dip) at 91 places in all parts of the earth. He finds
his calculations approach the observed values with a degree of
exactness which appears to be quite convincing as to the general truth
of his results; especially taking into account how entirely unlimited
is his original hypothesis.
It is one of the most curious results of this investigation that
according to the most simple meaning which we can give to the term
“pole” the earth has only two magnetic poles; that is, two
points where the direction of the magnetic force is vertical. And thus
the isogonal curves may be looked upon as deformations
of the curves deduced by Euler from the supposition of two poles, the
deformation arising from this, that the earth does not contain a
single definite magnet, but irregularly diffused magnetical elements,
which still have collectively a distinct resemblance to a single
magnet. And instead of Hansteen’s Siberian pole, we have a Siberian
region in which the needles converge; but if the apparent convergence
be pursued it nowhere comes to a point; and the like is the case in
the Antarctic region. When the 24 Gaussian elements at any time are
known the magnetic condition of the globe is known, just as the
mechanical condition of the solar system is known, when we know the
elements of the orbits of the satellites and planets and the mass of
each. And the comparison of this magnetic condition of the globe at
distant periods of time cannot fail to supply materials for future
researches and speculations with regard to the agencies by which the
condition of the earth is determined. The condition of which we here
speak must necessarily be its mechanico-chemical condition,
being expressed, as it will be, in terms of the mechanico-chemical
sciences. The 231
investigations I have been describing belong to the mechanical side of
the subject: but when philosophers have to consider the causes of the
secular changes which are found to occur in this mechanical condition,
they cannot fail to be driven to electrical, that is, chemical
agencies and laws.
I can only allude to Gauss’s investigations respecting the
Absolute Measure of the Earth’s Magnetic Force. To determine
the ratio of the magnetic force of the earth to that of a known
magnet, Poisson proposed to observe the time of vibration of a second
magnet. The method of Gauss, now universally adopted, consists in
observing the position of equilibrium of the second magnet when
deflected by the first.
The manner in which the business of magnetic observation has been
taken up by the governments of our time makes this by far the greatest
scientific undertaking which the world has ever seen. The result will
be that we shall obtain in a few years a knowledge of the magnetic
constitution of the earth which otherwise it might have required
centuries to accumulate. The secular magnetic changes must still
require a long time to reduce to their laws of phenomena, except
observation be anticipated or assisted by some happy discovery as to
the cause of these changes. But besides the special gain to magnetic
science by this great plan of joint action among the nations of the
earth, there is thereby a beginning made in the recognition and
execution of the duty of forwarding science in general by national
exertions. For at most of the magnetic observatories, meteorological
observations are also carried on; and such observations, being far
more extensive, systematic, and permanent than those which have
usually been made, can hardly fail to produce important additions to
science. But at any rate they do for science that which nations can
do, and individuals cannot; and they seek for scientific truths in a
manner suitable to the respect now professed for science and to the
progress which its methods have made. Nor are we to overlook the
effect of such observations as means of training men in the pursuit of
science. “There is amongst us,” says one of the magnetic observers, “a
growing recognition of the importance, both for science and for
practical life, of forming exact observers of nature. Hitherto
astronomy alone has afforded a very partial opportunity for the
formation of fine observers, of which few could avail themselves.
Experience has shown that magnetic observations may serve as excellent
training schools in this respect.”27]
27 Letter of W. Weber.
Brit. Assoc. Rep. 1845, p. 17.
232 The various
other circumstances which terrestrial magnetism exhibits,—the
diurnal and annual changes of the position of the
compass-needle;—the larger secular change which affects it in
the course of years;—the difference of intensity at different
places, and other facts, have naturally occupied philosophers with the
attempt to determine, both the laws of the phenomena and their causes.
But these attempts necessarily depend, not upon laws of statical
magnetism, such as they have been explained above; but upon the laws
by which the production and intensity of magnetism in different cases
are regulated;—laws which belong to a different province, and
are related to a different set of principles. Thus, for example, we
have not attempted to explain the discovery of the laws by which heat
influences magnetism; and therefore we cannot now give an account of
those theories of the facts relating to terrestrial magnetism, which
depend upon the influence of temperature. The conditions of excitation
of magnetism are best studied by comparing this force with other cases
where the same effects are produced by very different apparent
agencies; such as galvanic and thermo-electricity. To the history of
these we shall presently proceed.
Conclusion.—The hypothesis of magnetic fluids, as
physical realities, was never widely or strongly embraced, as that of
electric fluids was. For though the hypothesis accounted, to a
remarkable degree of exactness, for large classes of the phenomena,
the presence of a material fluid was not indicated by facts of a
different kind, such as the spark, the discharge from points, the
shock, and its mechanical effects. Thus the belief of a peculiar
magnetic fluid or fluids was not forced upon men’s minds; and the
doctrine above stated was probably entertained by most of its
adherents, chiefly as a means of expressing the laws of phenomena in
their elementary form.
One other observation occurs here. We have seen that the
supposition of a fluid moveable from one part of bodies to another,
and capable of accumulation in different parts of the surface,
appeared at first to be as distinctly authorized by magnetic as by
electric phenomena; and yet that it afterwards appeared, by
calculation, that this must be considered as a derivative result; no
real transfer of fluid taking place except within the limits of the
insensible particles of the body. Without attempting to found a
formula of philosophizing on this circumstance, we may observe, that
this occurrence, like the disproof of heat as a material fluid, shows
the possibility of an hypothesis which shall very exactly satisfy many
phenomena, and yet be incomplete: it 233 shows, too, the necessity of bringing
facts of all kinds to bear on the hypothesis; thus, in this case it
was requisite to take into account the facts of junction and
separation of magnetic bodies, as well as their attractions and
repulsions.
If we have seen reason to doubt the doctrine of electric fluids as
physical realities, we cannot help pronouncing upon the magnetic
fluids as having still more insecure claims to a material existence,
even on the grounds just stated. But we may add considerations still
more decisive; for at a further stage of discovery, as we shall see,
magnetic and electric action were found to be connected in the closest
manner, so as to lead to the persuasion of their being different
effects of one common cause. After those discoveries, no philosopher
would dream of assuming electric fluids and magnetic fluids as two
distinct material agents. Yet even now the nature of the dependence of
magnetism upon any other cause is extremely difficult to conceive. But
till we have noticed some of the discoveries to which we have alluded,
we cannot even speculate about that dependence. We now, therefore,
proceed to sketch the history of these discoveries. ~Additional
material in the 3rd edition.~


BOOK XIII.

MECHANICO-CHEMICAL SCIENCES.
(CONTINUED.)

HISTORY OF GALVANISM,
OR
VOLTAIC ELECTRICITY.

Percusssæ gelido trepidant sub pectore
fibræ,
Et nova desuetis subrepens vita medullis
Miscetur morti: tunc omnis palpitat artus
Tenduntur nervi; nec se tellure cadaver
Paullatim per membra levat; terrâque repulsum
est
Erectumque simul.
Lucan. vi.
752.

The form which lay before inert and dead,
Sudden a piercing thrill of change
o’erspread;
Returning life gleams in the stony face,
The fibres quiver and the sinews brace,
Move the stiff limbs;—nor did the body
rise
With tempered strength which genial life
supplies,
But upright starting, its full stature
held,
As though the earth the supine corse
repelled.

</div></body></text></TEI>