<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="24">CHAPTER XXIV.
VOLCANIC DISTRICT OF NAPLES—continued.
Dimensions and structure of the cone of Vesuvius—Fluidity and motion of lava—Dikes—Alluviums
called "aqueous lavas"—Origin and composition of the
matter enveloping Herculaneum and Pompeii—Condition and contents of the
buried cities—Small number of skeletons—State of preservation of animal and
vegetable substances—Rolls of papyrus—Stabiæ—Torre del
Greco—Concluding
remarks on the Campanian volcanoes.
Structure of the cone of Vesuvius.—Between the end of the eighteenth
century and the year 1822, the great crater of Vesuvius had been
gradually filled by lava boiling up from below, and by scoriæ falling
from the explosions of minor mouths which were formed at intervals on
its bottom and sides. In place of a regular cavity, therefore, there
was a rough and rocky plain, covered with blocks of lava and scoriæ,
and cut by numerous fissures, from which clouds of vapor were evolved.
But this state of things was totally changed by the eruption of October,
1822, when violent explosions, during the space of more than
twenty days, broke up and threw out all this accumulated mass, so as
to leave an immense gulf or chasm, of an irregular, but somewhat elliptical
shape, about three miles in circumference when measured along
the very sinuous and irregular line of its extreme margin, but somewhat
less than three quarters of a mile in its longest diameter, which was directed
from N. E. to S. W.518 The depth of this tremendous abyss has
been variously estimated; for from the hour of its formation it increased
daily by the dilapidation of its sides. It measured, at first, according
to the account of some authors, two thousand feet in depth from the
extreme part of the existing summit;519 but Mr. Scrope, when he saw it,
soon after the eruption, estimated its depth at less than half that
amount. More than eight hundred feet of the cone was carried away
by the explosions, so that the mountain was reduced in height from
about 4200 to 3400 feet.520
As we ascend the sloping sides, the volcano appears a mass of loose
materials—a mere heap of rubbish, thrown together without the slightest
order; but on arriving at the brim of the crater, and obtaining a
view of the interior, we are agreeably surprised to discover that the
conformation of the whole displays in every part the most perfect symmetry
and arrangement. The materials are disposed in regular strata,
slightly undulating, appearing, when viewed in front, to be disposed in
horizontal planes. But, as we make the circuit of the edge of the crater,
376
and observe the cliffs by which it is encircled projecting or receding
in salient or retiring angles, we behold transverse sections of the currents
of lava and beds of sand and scoriæ, and recognize their true dip. We
then discover that they incline outwards from the axis of the cone, at
angles varying from 30° to 40°. The whole cone, in fact, is composed
of a number of concentric coatings of alternating lavas, sand, and scoriæ.
Every shower of ashes which has fallen from above, and every
stream of lava descending from the lips of the crater, have conformed
to the outward surface of the hill, so that one conical envelope may be
said to have been successively folded round another, until the aggregation
of the whole mountain was completed. The marked separation
into distinct beds results from the different colors and degrees of coarseness
in the sands, scoriæ, and lava, and the alternation of these with
each other. The greatest difficulty, on the first view, is to conceive
how so much regularity can be produced, notwithstanding the unequal
distribution of sand and scoriæ, driven by prevailing winds in particular
eruptions, and the small breadth of each sheet of lava as it first flows
out from the crater.
But, on a closer examination, we find that the appearance of extreme
uniformity is delusive; for when a number of beds thin out gradually,
and at different points, the eye does not without difficulty recognize
the termination of any one stratum, but usually supposes it continuous
with some other, which at a short distance may lie precisely in the
same plane. The slight undulations, moreover, produced by inequalities
on the sides of the hill on which the successive layers were
moulded, assist the deception. As countless beds of sand and scoriæ
constitute the greater part of the whole mass, these may sometimes
mantle continuously round the whole cone; and even lava streams may
be of considerable breadth when first they overflow, and since, in some
eruptions, a considerable part of the upper portion of the cone breaks
down at once, may form a sheet extending as far as the space which
the eye usually takes in, in a single section.
The high inclination of some of the beds, and the firm union of the
particles even where there is evidently no cement, is another striking
feature in the volcanic tuffs and breccias, which seems at first not very
easy of explanation. But the last great eruption afforded ample illustration
of the manner in which these strata are formed. Fragments of
lava, scoriæ, pumice, and sand, when they fall at slight distances from the
summit, are only half cooled down from a state of fusion, and are afterwards
acted upon by the heat from within, and by fumeroles or small
crevices in the cone through which hot vapors are disengaged. Thus
heated, the ejected fragments cohere together strongly; and the whole
mass acquires such consistency in a few days, that fragments cannot be
detached without a smart blow of the hammer. At the same time sand
and scoriæ, ejected to a greater distance, remain incoherent.521
377
Sir William Hamilton, in his description of the eruption of 1779,
says that jets of liquid lava, mixed with stones and scoriæ, were thrown
up to the height of at least ten thousand feet, having the appearance of
a column of fire.522 Some of these were directed by the winds towards
Ottajano, and some of them falling almost perpendicularly, still red-hot
and liquid, on Vesuvius, covered its whole cone, part of the mountain
of Somma, and the valley between them. The falling matter being
nearly as vividly inflamed as that which was continually issuing fresh
from the crater, formed with it one complete body of fire, which could
not be less than two miles and a half in breadth, and of the extraordinary
height above mentioned, casting a heat to the distance of at least
six miles round it. Dr. Clarke, also, in his account of the eruption of
1793, says that millions of red-hot stones were shot into the air full
half the height of the cone itself, and then bending, fell all round in a
fine arch. On another occasion he says that, as they fell, they covered
nearly half the cone with fire.
The same author has also described the different appearance of the
lava at its source, and at some distance from it, when it had descended
into the plains below. At the point where it issued, in 1793, from an
arched chasm in the side of the mountain, the vivid torrent rushed
with the velocity of a flood. It was in perfect fusion, unattended with
any scoriæ on its surface, or any gross materials not in a state of complete
solution. It flowed with the translucency of honey, "in regular
channels, cut finer than art can imitate, and glowing with all the splendor
of the sun."—"Sir William Hamilton," he continues, "had conceived
that no stones thrown upon a current of lava would make any
impression. I was soon convinced of the contrary. Light bodies,
indeed, of five, ten, and fifteen pounds' weight, made little or no impression
even at the source; but bodies of sixty, seventy, and eighty
pounds were seen to form a kind of bed on the surface of the lava, and
float away with it. A stone of three hundred weight, that had been
thrown out by the crater, lay near the source of the current of lava: I
raised it upon one end, and then let it fall in upon the liquid lava;
when it gradually sunk beneath the surface, and disappeared. If I
wished to describe the manner in which it acted upon the lava, I should
say that it was like a loaf of bread thrown into a bowl of very thick
honey, which gradually involves itself in the heavy liquid, and then
slowly sinks to the bottom.
"The lava, at a small distance from its source, acquires a darker tint
upon its surface, is less easily acted upon, and, as the stream widens,
the surface, having lost its state of perfect solution, grows harder and
harder, and cracks into innumerable fragments of very porous matter,
to which they give the name of scoriæ, and the appearance of which
has led many to suppose that it proceeded thus from the mountain.
There is, however, no truth in this. All lava, at its first exit from its
378
native volcano, flows out in a liquid state, and all equally in fusion.
The appearance of the scoriæ is to be attributed only to the action of
the external air, and not to any difference in the materials which compose
it, since any lava whatever, separated from its channel, and exposed
to the action of the external air, immediately cracks, becomes
porous, and alters its form. As we proceeded downwards, this became
more and more evident; and the same lava which at its original source
flowed in perfect solution, undivided, and free from incumbrances of
any kind, a little farther down had its surface loaded with scoriæ in
such a manner, that, upon its arrival at the bottom of the mountain,
the whole current resembled nothing so much as a heap of unconnected
cinders from an iron-foundry." In another place he says that "the rivers
of lava in the plain resembled a vast heap of cinders, or the scoriæ of
an iron-foundry, rolling slowly along, and falling with a rattling noise
over one another."523 Von Buch, who was in company with MM. de
Humboldt and Gay-Lussac, describes the lava of 1805 (the most fluid
on record) as shooting suddenly before their eyes from top to bottom
of the cone in one single instant. Professor J. D. Forbes remarks that
the length of the slope of the cone proper being about 1300 feet, this
motion must correspond to a velocity of many hundred feet in a few
seconds, without interpreting Von Buch's expression literally. The
same lava, when it reached the level road at Torre del Greco, moved at
the rate of only eighteen inches per minute, or three-tenths of an inch
per second.524 "Although common lava," observes Professor Forbes,
"is nearly as liquid as melted iron, when it issues from the orifice of the
crater, its fluidity rapidly diminishes, and as it becomes more and more
burdened by the consolidated slag through which it has to force its
way, its velocity of motion diminishes in an almost inconceivable degree;
and at length, when it ceases to present the slightest external trace of
fluidity, its movement can only be ascertained by careful and repeated
observations, just as in the case of a glacier."525
It appears that the intensity of the light and heat of the lava varies
considerably at different periods of the same eruption, as in that of
Vesuvius in 1819 and 1820, when Sir H. Davy remarked different
degrees of vividness in the white heat at the point where the lava
originated.526
When the expressions "flame" and "smoke" are used in describing
volcanic appearances, they must generally be understood in a figurative
sense. We are informed, indeed, by M. Abich, that he distinctly saw,
in the eruption of Vesuvius in 1834, the flame of burning
hydrogen;527
but what is usually mistaken for flame consists of vapor or scoriæ, and
impalpable dust illuminated by that vivid light which is emitted from
the crater below, where the lava is said to glow with the splendor of
379
the sun. The clouds of apparent smoke are formed either of aqueous
and other vapor, or of finely comminuted scoriæ.
Dikes in the recent cone, how formed.—The inclined strata before
mentioned which dip outwards in all directions from the axis of the
cone of Vesuvius, are intersected by veins or dikes of compact lava, for
the most part in a vertical position. In 1828 these were seen to be
about seven in number, some of them not less than four or five hundred
feet in height, and thinning out before they reached the uppermost part
of the cone. Being harder than the beds through which they pass,
they have decomposed less rapidly, and therefore stand out in relief.
When I visited Vesuvius, in November, 1828, I was prevented from
descending into the crater by the constant ejections then thrown out;
so that I got sight of three only of the dikes; but Signor Monticelli had
previously had drawings made of the whole, which he showed me. The
dikes which I saw were on that side of the cone which is encircled by
Somma. The eruption before mentioned, of 1828, began in March, and
in the November following the ejected matter had filled up nearly one-third
of the deep abyss formed at the close of the eruption of 1822. In
November I found a single black cone at the bottom of the crater continually
throwing out scoriæ, while on the exterior of the cone I observed
the lava of 1822, which had flowed out six years before, not yet
cool, and still evolving much heat and vapor from crevices.
Hoffmann, in 1832, saw on the north side of Vesuvius, near the
peak called Palo, a great many parallel bands of lava, some from six to
eight feet thick, alternating with scoriæ and conglomerate. These beds,
he says, were cut through by many dikes, some of them five feet broad.
They resemble those of Somma, the stone being composed of grains of
leucite and augite.528
There can be no doubt that the dikes above mentioned have been
produced by the filling up of open fissures with liquid lava; but of the
date of their formation we know nothing farther than that they are all
subsequent to the year 79, and, relatively speaking, that they are more
modern than all the lavas and scoriæ which they intersect. A considerable
number of the upper strata are not traversed by them. That the
earthquakes, which almost invariably precede eruptions, occasion rents
in the mass, is well known; and, in 1822, three months before the lava
flowed out, open fissures, evolving hot vapors, were numerous. It is
clear that such rents must be ejected with melted matter when the column
of lava rises, so that the origin of the dikes is easily explained, as
also the great solidity and crystalline nature of the rock composing them,
which has been formed by lava cooling slowly under great pressure.
It has been suggested that the frequent rending of volcanic cones
during eruptions may be connected with the gradual and successive
upheaval of the whole mass in such a manner as to increase the inclination
of the beds composing the cone; and in accordance with the
380
hypothesis before proposed for the origin of Monte Nuovo, Von Buch
supposes that the present cone of Vesuvius was formed in the year 79,
not by eruption, but by upheaval. It was not produced by the repeated
superposition of scoriæ and lava cast out or flowing from a central
source, but by the uplifting of strata previously horizontal. The
entire cone rose at once, such as we now see it, from the interior and
middle of Somma, and has since received no accession of height, but, on
the contrary, has ever since been diminishing in elevation.529
Although I consider this hypothesis of Von Buch to be quite untenable,
I may mention some facts which may at first sight seem to favor it.
These are recorded by M. Abich in his account of the Vesuvian eruptions
of 1833 and 1834, a work illustrated by excellent engravings of
the volcanic phenomena which he witnessed.530 It appears that, in the
year 1834, the great crater of Vesuvius had been filled up nearly to the
top with lava, which had consolidated and formed a level and unbroken
plain, except that a small cone thrown up by the ejection of scoriæ rose
in the middle of it like an island in a lake. At length this plain of lava
was broken by a fissure which passed from N. E. to S. W., and along
this line a great number of minute cones emitting vapor were formed.
The first act of formation of these minor cones is said to have consisted
of a partial upheaval of beds of lava previously horizontal, and which
had been rendered flexible by the heat and tension of elastic fluids,
which, rising from below, escaped from the centre of each new monticule.
There would be considerable analogy between this mode of origin
and that ascribed by Von Buch to Vesuvius and Somma, if the
dimensions of the upraised masses were not on so different a scale, and
if it was safe to reason from the inflation of bladders of half-fused lava,
from fifteen to twenty-five feet in height, to mountains attaining an altitude
of several thousand feet, and having their component strata strengthened
by intersecting dikes of solid lava.
At the same time M. Abich mentions, that when, in August, 1834,
a great subsidence took place in the platform of lava within the great
crater, so that the structure of the central cone was laid open, it was
seen to have been evidently formed, not by upheaval, but by the fall
of cinders and scoriæ which had been thrown out during successive
eruptions.531
Previous to the year 79, Vesuvius appears, from the description of
its figure given by Strabo, to have been a truncated cone, having a level
and even outline as seen from a distance. That it had a crater on its
summit, we may infer from a passage in Plutarch, on which Dr. Daubeny
has judiciously commented in his treatise on volcanoes.532 The walls
of the crater were evidently entire, except on one side, where there was
a single narrow breach. When Spartacus, in the year 72, encamped his
381
gladiators in this hollow, Clodius, the prætor, besieged him there, keeping
the single outlet carefully guarded, and then let down his soldiers
by scaling-ladders over the steep precipices which surrounded the crater,
at the bottom of which the insurgents were encamped. On the
side towards the sea, the walls of this original cavity, which must have
been three miles in diameter, have been destroyed, and Brieslak was the
first to announce the opinion, that this destruction happened during the
tremendous eruption which occurred in 79, when the new cone, now
called Vesuvius, was thrown up, which stands encircled on three sides
by the ruins of the ancient cone, called Monte Somma.
Fig. 45.
Supposed section of Vesuvius and Somma.
a, Monte Somma, or the remains of the ancient cone of Vesuvius.
b, The Pedamentina, a terrace-like projection, encircling the base of the recent cone of Vesuvius
on the south side.
c, Atrio del Cavallo.533
d, e, Crater left by eruption of 1822.
f, Small cone thrown up in 1828, at the bottom of the great crater.
g, g, Dikes intersecting Somma.
h, h, Dikes intersecting the recent cone of Vesuvius.
In the annexed diagram (fig. 45) it will be seen that on the side of
Vesuvius opposite to that where a portion of the ancient cone of Somma
(a) still remains, is a projection (b) called the Pedamentina, which some
have supposed to be part of the circumference of the ancient crater
broken down towards the sea, and over the edge of which the lavas of
the modern Vesuvius have poured; the axis of the present cone of Vesuvius
being, according to Visconti, precisely equidistant from the
escarpment of Somma and the Pedamentina.
In the same diagram I have represented the slanting beds of the cone
of Vesuvius as becoming horizontal in the Atrio del Cavallo (at c),
where the base of the new cone meets the precipitous escarpment of
Somma; for when the lava flows down to this point, as happened in
1822, its descending course is arrested, and it then runs in another
direction along this small valley, circling round the base of the cone.
Sand and scoriæ, also, blown by the winds, collect at the base of the
cone, and are then swept away by torrents; so that there is always
here a flatish plain, as represented. In the same manner, the small
382
interior cone (f) must be composed of sloping beds, terminating in a
horizontal plain; for, while this monticule was gradually gaining height
by successive ejections of lava and scoriæ, in 1828, it was always surrounded
by a flat pool of semi-fluid lava, into which scoriæ and sand
were thrown.
In the steep simicircular escarpment of Somma, which faces the
modern Vesuvius, we see a great number of sheets of lava inclined at
an angle of about 26°. They alternate with scoriæ, and are intersected
by numerous dikes, which, like the sheets of lava, are composed chiefly
of augite, with crystals of leucite, but the rock in the dikes is more
compact, having cooled and consolidated under greater pressure. Some
of the dikes cut through and shift others, so that they have evidently
been formed during successive eruptions. While the higher region of
Somma is made up of these igneous products, there appear on its flanks,
for some depth from the surface, as seen in a ravine called the "Fossa
Grande," beds of white pumiceous tuff, resembling the tuff which, at
Pausilippo, and other places, near Naples, contain shells of living
Mediterranean species. It is supposed by Pilla, Von Buch, and others,
that the tufaceous beds, which rise in Somma to more than half the
height of that mountain, are, in like manner, of submarine origin, because
a few sea-shells have been found in them, here and there, together
with serpulæ of recent species attached to included blocks of
limestone.534
It is contended, therefore, that as these strata were once accumulated
beneath the sea, they may have been subjected as they rose to such an
upward movement as may have given rise to a conical hill; and this
hypothesis, it is said, acquires confirmation from the fact, that the sheets
of lava near the summit of Somma are so compact and crystalline, and
of such breadth individually, as would not have been the case had they
run down a steep slope. They must, therefore, have consolidated on a
nearly level surface, and have been subsequently uplifted into their present
inclined position.
Unfortunately there are no sections of sufficient depth and continuity
on the flanks of Somma, to reveal to us clearly the relations of the
lava, scoriæ, and associated dikes, forming the highest part of the
mountain, with the marine tuffs observed on its declivity. Both
may, perhaps, have been produced contemporaneously when Somma
raised its head, like Stromboli, above the sea, its sides and base being
then submerged. Such a state of things may be indicated by a fact
noticed by Von Buch, namely, that the pumiceous beds of Naples,
when they approach Somma, contain fragments of the peculiar leucitic
lava proper to that mountain, which are not found in the same tuff at a
greater distance.535 Portions, therefore, of this lava were either thrown
383
out by explosions, or torn off by the waves, during the deposition of the
pumiceous strata beneath the sea.
We have as yet but a scanty acquaintance with the laws which regulate
the flow of lava beneath water, or the arrangement of scoriæ and
volcanic dust on the sides of a submarine cone. There can, however,
be little doubt that showers of ejected matter may settle on a steep
slope, and may include shells and the remains of aquatic animals, which
flourish in the intervals between eruptions. Lava under the pressure of
water would be less porous; but, as Dr. Daubeny suggests, it may
retain its fluidity longer than in the open air; for the rapidity with
which heated bodies are cooled by being plunged into water arises
chiefly from the conversion of the lower portions of water into steam,
which steam absorbing much heat, immediately ascends, and is reconverted
into water. But under the pressure of a deep ocean, the heat
of the lava would be carried off more slowly, and only by the circulation
of ascending and descending currents of water, those portions nearest
the source of heat becoming specifically light, and consequently displacing
the water above. This kind of circulation would take place
with much less rapidity than in the atmosphere, inasmuch as the expansion
of water by equal increments of heat is less considerable than
that of air.536
We learn from the valuable observations made by Mr. Dana on the
active volcanoes of the Sandwich Islands, that large sheets of compact
basaltic lava have been poured out of craters at the top or near the summits
of flattened domes higher than Etna, as in the case of Mount Loa
for example, where a copious stream two miles broad and twenty-five
miles long proceeded from an opening 13,000 feet above the level of the
sea. The usual slope of these sheets of lava is between 5° and 10°;
but Mr. Dana convinced himself that, owing to the suddenness with which
they cool in the air, some lavas may occasionally form on slopes equalling
25°, and still preserve a considerable compactness of texture. It is even
proved, he says, from what he saw in the great lateral crater of Kilauea,
on the flanks of Mount Loa, that a mass of such melted rock may consolidate
at an inclination of 30°, and be continuous for 300 or 400 feet.
Such masses are narrow, he admits, "but if the source had been more
generous, they would have had a greater breadth, and by a succession
of ejections overspreading each cooled layer, a considerable thickness
might have been attained."537 The same author has also shown, as before
mentioned, that in the "cinder cones" of the Sandwich Islands, the
strata have an original inclination of between 35° and 40°.538
Mr. Scrope, writing in 1827, attributed the formation of a volcanic
cone chiefly to matter ejected from a central orifice, but partly to the
injection of lava into dikes, and "to that force of gaseous expansion, the
384
intensity of which, in the central parts of the cone, is attested by local
earthquakes, which so often accompany eruptions.539 It is the opinion
of MM. Von Buch, De Beaumont, and Dufrénoy, that the sheets of
lava on Somma are so uniform and compact, that their original inclination
did not exceed four or five degrees, and that four-fifths, therefore,
of their present slope is due to their having been subsequently tilted
and upraised. Notwithstanding the light thrown by M. de Beaumont
on the laws regulating the flow and consolidation of lava, I do not conceive
that these laws are as yet sufficiently determined to warrant us in
assigning so much of the inclined position of the beds of Somma to the
subsequent rending and dislocation of the cone. Even if this were admitted,
it is far more in harmony with the usual mode of development
of volcanic forces to suppose the movement which modified the shape of
the cone to have been intermittent and gradual, and not to have consisted
of a single effort, or one sudden and violent convulsion.540
Vesuvian lavas.—The lavas of Somma are characterized by containing
disseminated crystals of leucite (called, by the French, amphigène),
a mineral said to be very rare in the modern lavas of Vesuvius, which
are in general much more scoriaceous and less crystalline than those of
Somma.541
At the fortress near Torre del Greco a section is exposed, fifteen feet
in height, of a current which ran into the sea; and it evinces, especially
in the lower part, a decided tendency to divide into rude columns. A
still more striking example may be seen to the west of Torre del Annunziata,
near Forte Scassato, where the mass is laid open to the depth
of twenty feet. In both these cases, however, the rock may rather be
said to be divided into numerous perpendicular fissures, than to be prismatic,
although the same picturesque effect is produced. In the lava-currents
of Central France (those of the Vivarais, in particular), the
uppermost portion, often forty feet or more in thickness, is an amorphous
mass passing downwards into lava irregularly prismatic; and under this
there is a foundation of regular and vertical columns; but these lavas
are often one hundred feet or more in thickness. We can scarcely expect
to discover the same phenomenon in the shallow currents of Vesuvius,
where the lowest part has cooled more rapidly, although it may
be looked for in modern streams in Iceland, which exceed even those of
ancient France in volume.
Mr. Scrope mentions that, in the cliffs encircling the modern crater
of Vesuvius, he saw many currents offering a columnar division, and some
almost as regularly prismatic as any ranges of the older basalts; and
he adds, that in some the spheroidal concretionary structure, on a large
scale, was equally conspicuous.542 Brieslak543 also informs us that, in the
385
siliceous lava of 1737, which contains augite, leucite, and crystals of
felspar, he found very regular prisms in a quarry near Torre del Greco;
an observation confirmed by modern authorities.544
Effects of decomposition on lavas.—The decomposition of some of the
felspathic lavas, either by simple weathering, or by gaseous emanations,
converts them from a hard to a soft clayey state, so that they no longer
retain the smallest resemblance to rocks cooled down from a state of
fusion. The exhalations of sulphuretted hydrogen and muriatic acid,
which are disengaged continually from the Solfatara, also produce curious
changes on the trachyte of that nearly extinct volcano: the rock is
bleached, and becomes porous, fissile, and honey-combed, till at length
it crumbles into a white siliceous powder.545 Numerous globular concretions,
composed of concentric laminæ, are also formed by the same
vapors in this decomposed rock.546
Vesuvian minerals.—A great variety of minerals are found in the
lavas of Vesuvius and Somma; augite, leucite, felspar, mica, olivine,
and sulphur are most abundant. It is an extraordinary fact, that in an
area of three square miles round Vesuvius, a greater number of simple
minerals have been found than in any spot of the same dimensions on
the surface of the globe. Häuy enumerated only 380 species of simple
minerals as known to him; and no less than eighty-two had been found
on Vesuvius and in the tuffs on the flanks of Somma before the end of
the year 1828.547 Many of these are peculiar to that locality. Some
mineralogists have conjectured that the greater part of these were not
of Vesuvian origin, but thrown up in fragments from some older formation,
through which the gaseous explosions burst. But none of the
older rocks in Italy, or elsewhere, contain such an assemblage of mineral
products; and the hypothesis seems to have been prompted by a
disinclination to admit that, in times so recent in the earth's history,
the laboratory of nature could have been so prolific in the creation of
new and rare compounds. Had Vesuvius been a volcano of high antiquity,
formed when nature


Wanton'd as in her prime, and play'd at will
Her virgin fancies,


it would have been readily admitted that these, or a much greater variety
of substances, had been sublimed in the crevices of lava, just as
several new earthy and metallic compounds are known to have been
produced by fumeroles, since the eruption of 1822.
Mass enveloping Herculaneum and Pompeii.—In addition to the
ejections which fall on the cone, and that much greater mass which
finds its way gradually to the neighboring sea, there is a third portion,
often of no inconsiderable thickness, composed of alluviums, spread over
the valleys and plains at small distances from the volcano. Aqueous
386
vapors are evolved copiously from volcanic craters during eruptions,
and often for a long time subsequently to the discharge of scoriæ and
lava: these vapors are condensed in the cold atmosphere surrounding
the high volcanic peak, and heavy rains are thus caused. The floods
thus occasioned, sweep along the impalpable dust and light scoriæ, till
a current of mud is produced, which is called in Campania "lava d'
acqua," and is often more dreaded than an igneous stream (lava di fuoco),
from the greater velocity with which it moves. So late as the 27th
of October, 1822, one of these alluviums descended the cone of Vesuvius,
and, after overspreading much cultivated soil, flowed suddenly
into the villages of St. Sebastian and Massa, where, filling the streets
and interior of some of the houses, it suffocated seven persons. It will,
therefore, happen very frequently that, towards the base of a volcanic
cone, alternations will be found of lava, alluvium, and showers of
ashes.
To which of these two latter divisions the mass enveloping Herculaneum
and Pompeii should be referred, has been a question of the keenest
controversy; but the discussion might have been shortened, if the
combatants had reflected that, whether volcanic sand and ashes were
conveyed to the towns by running water, or through the air, during an
eruption, the interior of buildings, so long as the roofs remain entire,
together with all underground vaults and cellars, could be filled only
by an alluvium. We learn from history, that a heavy shower of sand,
pumice, and lapilli, sufficiently great to render Pompeii and Herculaneum
uninhabitable, fell for eight successive days and nights in the year
79, accompanied by violent rains.548 We ought, therefore, to find a very
close resemblance between the strata covering these towns and those
composing the minor cones of the Phlegræan Fields, accumulated rapidly,
like Monte Nuovo, during a continued shower of ejected matter;
with this difference however, that the strata incumbent on the cities
would be horizontal, whereas those on the cones are highly inclined;
and that large angular fragments of rock, which are thrown out near the
vent, would be wanting at a distance where small lapilli only can be
found. Accordingly, with these exceptions, no identity can be more
perfect than the form, and distribution of the matter at the base of
Monte Nuovo, as laid open by the encroaching sea, and the appearance
of the beds superimposed on Pompeii. That city is covered with numerous
alternations of different horizontal beds of tuff and lapilli, for the
most part thin, and subdivided into very fine layers. I observed the
following section near the amphitheatre, in November, 1828—(descending
series):—
387


 
Feet
Inches.

1. Black sparkling sand from the eruption of 1822,
containing minute regularly formed crystals of augite and tourmaline
0
2½

2. Vegetable mould
3
0

3. Brown incoherent tuff, full of pisolitic globules
in layers, from half an inch to three inches in thickness
1
6

4. Small scoriæ and white lapilli
0
3

5. Brown earthy tuff, with numerous pisolitic globules
0
9

6. Brown earthy tuff, with lapilli divided into layers
4
0

7. Layer of whitish lapilli
0
1

8. Gray solid tuff
0
3

9. Pumice and white lapilli
0
3

 
 ——
——

 
10
3½

 
 ——
——


Many of the ashes in these beds are vitrified, and harsh to the touch.
Crystals of leucite, both fresh and farinaceous, have been found intermixed.549
The depth of the bed of ashes above the houses is variable,
but seldom exceeds twelve or fourteen feet, and it is said that the higher
part of the amphitheatre always projected above the surface; though if
this were the case, it seems inexplicable that the city should never have
been discovered till the year 1750. It will be observed in the above
section that two of the brown, half-consolidated tuffs are filled with small
pisolitic globules. This circumstance is not alluded to in the animated
controversy which the Royal Academy of Naples maintained with one
of their members, Signor Lippi, as to the origin of the strata incumbent
on Pompeii. The mode of aggregation of these globules has been fully
explained by Mr. Scrope, who saw them formed in great numbers in
1822, by rain falling during the eruption on fine volcanic sand, and sometimes
also produced like hail in the air, by the mutual attraction of the
minutest particles of fine damp sand. Their occurrence, therefore, agrees
remarkably well with the account of heavy rain, and showers of sand and
ashes recorded in history.550
Lippi entitled his work, "Fù il fuoco o l' acqua che sotterò Pompei ed
Ercolano?"551 and he contended that neither were the two cities destroyed
in the year 79, nor by a volcanic eruption, but purely by the agency of
water charged with transported matter. His letters, wherein he endeavored
to dispense, as far as possible, with igneous agency, even at the
foot of the volcano, were dedicated, with great propriety, to Werner,
and afford an amusing illustration of the polemic style in which geological
writers of that day indulged themselves. His arguments were partly
of an historical nature, derived from the silence of contemporary historians,
respecting the fate of the cities, which, as we have already stated,
is most remarkable, and partly drawn from physical proofs. He pointed
out with great clearness the resemblance of the tufaceous matter in the
vaults and cellars at Herculaneum and Pompeii to aqueous alluviums,
and its distinctness from ejections which had fallen through the air.
Nothing, he observes, but moist pasty matter could have received the
impression of a woman's breast, which was found in a vault at Pompeii,
388
or have given the cast of a statue discovered in the theatre at Herculaneum.
It was objected to him, that the heat of the tuff in Herculaneum
and Pompeii was proved by the carbonization of the timber, corn, papyrus-rolls,
and other vegetable substances there discovered; but Lippi
replied with truth, that the papyri would have been burnt up if they
had come in contact with fire, and that their being only carbonized was
a clear demonstration of their having been enveloped, like fossil wood,
in a sediment deposited from water. The Academicians, in their report
on his pamphlet, assert, that when the amphitheatre was first cleared
out, the matter was arranged on the steps in a succession of concave
layers, accommodating themselves to the interior form of the building,
just as snow would lie if it had fallen there. This observation is highly
interesting, and points to the difference between the stratification of ashes
in an open building and of mud derived from the same in the interior of
edifices and cellars. Nor ought we to call the allegation in question,
because it could not be substantiated at the time of the controversy after
the matter had been all removed; although Lippi took advantage of
this removal, and met the argument of his antagonists by requiring them
to prove the fact. There is decisive evidence that no stream of lava has
ever reached Pompeii since it was first built, although the foundations
of the town stand upon the old leucitic lava of Somma; several streams
of which, with tuff interposed, had been cut through in excavations.
Infusorial beds covering Pompeii.—A most singular and unexpected
discovery has been recently made (1844-5) by Professor Ehrenberg,
respecting the remote origin of many of the layers of ashes and pumice
enveloping Pompeii. They are, he says, in great part, of organic and
freshwater origin, consisting of the siliceous cases of microscopic infusoria.
What is still more surprising, this fact proves to be by no means
an isolated or solitary example of an intimate relation between organic
life and the results of volcanic activity. On the Rhine, several beds of
tuff and pumiceous conglomerate, resembling the mass incumbent upon
Pompeii and closely connected with extinct volcanoes, are now ascertained
to be made up to a great extent of the siliceous cases of infusoria
(or Diatomaceæ), invisible to the naked eye, and often half
fused.552 No
less than 94 distinct species have already been detected in one mass of
this kind, more than 150 feet thick, at Hochsimmer, on the left bank of
the Rhine, near the Laacher-see. Some of these Rhenish infusorial
accumulations appear to have fallen in showers, others to have been
poured out of lake-craters in the form of mud, as in the Brohl valley.
In Mexico, Peru, the Isle of France, and several other volcanic regions,
analogous phenomena have been observed, and everywhere the species
of infusoria belong to freshwater and terrestrial genera, except in the
case of the Patagonian pumiceous tuffs, specimens of which, brought
389
home by Mr. Darwin, are found to contain the remains of marine animalcules.
In various kinds of pumice ejected by volcanoes, the microscope
has revealed to Professor Ehrenberg the siliceous cases of infusoria
often half obliterated by the action of heat, and the fine dust thrown out
into the air during eruptions, is sometimes referable to these most minute
organic substances, brought up from considerable depths, and sometimes
mingled with small particles of vegetable matter.
In what manner did the solid coverings of these most minute plants
and animalcules, which can only originate and increase at the surface
of the earth, sink down and penetrate into subterranean cavities, so as
to be ejected from the volcanic orifices? We have of late years become
familiar with the fact, in the process of boring Artesian wells, that the
seeds of plants, the remains of insects, and even small fish, with other
organic bodies, are carried in an uninjured state by the underground
circulation of waters, to the depth of many hundred feet. With still
greater facility in a volcanic region we may conjecture, that water and
mud full of invisible infusoria may be sucked down, from time to time,
into subterranean rents and hollows in cavernous lava which has been
permeated by gases, or in rocks dislocated by earthquakes. It often
happens that a lake which has endured for centuries in a volcanic crater,
disappears suddenly on the approach of a new eruption. Violent
shocks agitate the surrounding region, and ponds, rivers, and wells are
dried up. Large cavities far below may thus become filled with fen-mud
chiefly composed of the more indestructible and siliceous portions
of infusoria, destined perhaps to be one day ejected in a fragmentary or
half-fused state, yet without the obliteration of all traces of organic
structure.553
Herculaneum.—It was remarked that no lava has flowed over the
site of Pompeii, since that city was built, but with Herculaneum the
case is different. Although the substance which fills the interior of the
houses and the vaults must have been introduced in a state of mud, like
that found in similar situations in Pompeii; yet the superincumbent
mass differs wholly in composition and thickness. Herculaneum was
situated several miles nearer to the volcano, and has, therefore, been always
more exposed to be covered, not only by showers of ashes, but by
alluviums and streams of lava. Accordingly, masses of both have
390
accumulated on each other above the city, to a depth of nowhere less than
70, and in many places of 112 feet.554
The tuff which envelops the buildings consists of comminuted volcanic
ashes, mixed with pumice. A mask imbedded in this matrix has
left a cast, the sharpness of which was compared by Hamilton to those
in plaster of Paris; nor was the mask in the least degree scorched, as
if it had been imbedded in heated matter. This tuff is porous; and,
when first excavated, is soft and easily worked, but acquires a considerable
degree of induration on exposure to the air. Above this lowest
stratum is placed, according to Hamilton, "the matter of six eruptions,"
each separated from the other by veins of good soil. In these soils
Lippi states that he collected a considerable number of land shells—an
observation which is no doubt correct; for many snails burrow in soft
soils, and some Italian species descend, when they hybernate, to the
depth of five feet and more from the surface. Della Torre also informs
us that there is in one part of this superimposed mass a bed of true
siliceous lava (lava di pietra dura); and, as no such current is believed
to have flowed till near one thousand years after the destruction of Herculaneum,
we must conclude, that the origin of a large part of the covering
of Herculaneum was long subsequent to the first inhumation of
the place. That city, as well as Pompeii, was a seaport. Herculaneum
is still very near the shore, but a tract of land, a mile in length, intervenes
between the borders of the Bay of Naples and Pompeii. In both
cases the gain of land is due to the filling up of the bed of the sea with
volcanic matter, and not to elevation by earthquakes, for there has been
no change in the relative level of land and sea. Pompeii stood on a
slight eminence composed of the lavas of the ancient Vesuvius, and
flights of steps led down to the water's edge. The lowermost of these
steps are said to be still on an exact level with the sea.
Condition and contents of the buried cities.—After these observations
on the nature of the strata enveloping and surrounding the cities, we
may proceed to consider their internal condition and contents, so far at
least as they offer facts of geological interest. Notwithstanding the
much greater depth at which Herculaneum was buried, it was discovered
before Pompeii, by the accidental circumstance of a well being
sunk, in 1713, which came right down upon the theatre, where the statues
of Hercules and Cleopatra were soon found. Whether this city or
Pompeii, both of them founded by Greek colonies, was the more considerable,
is not yet determined; but both are mentioned by ancient
authors as among the seven most flourishing cities in Campania. The
walls of Pompeii were three miles in circumference; but we have, as
yet, no certain knowledge of the dimensions of Herculaneum. In the
latter place the theatre alone is open for inspection; the Forum, Temple
of Jupiter, and other buildings, having been filled up with rubbish as
the workmen proceeded, owing to the difficulty of removing it from so
391
great a depth below ground. Even the theatre is only seen by torchlight,
and the most interesting information, perhaps, which the geologist
obtains there, is the continual formation of stalactite in the galleries cut
through the tuff; for there is a constant percolation of water charged
with carbonate of lime mixed with a small portion of magnesia. Such
mineral waters must, in the course of time, create great changes in
many rocks; especially in lavas, the pores of which they may fill with
calcareous spar, so as to convert them into amygdaloids. Some geologists,
therefore, are unreasonable when they expect that volcanic rocks
of remote eras should accord precisely with those of modern date;
since it is obvious that many of those produced in our own time will
not long retain the same aspect and internal composition.
Both at Herculaneum and Pompeii, temples have been found with
inscriptions commemorating the rebuilding of the edifices after they had
been thrown down by an earthquake.555 This earthquake happened in
the reign of Nero, sixteen years before the cities were overwhelmed. In
Pompeii, one-fourth of which is now laid open to the day, both the
public and private buildings bear testimony to the catastrophe. The
walls are rent, and in many places traversed by fissures still open.
Columns are lying on the ground only half hewn from huge blocks of
travertin, and the temple for which they were designed is seen half
repaired. In some few places the pavement had sunk in, but in general
it was undisturbed, consisting of large irregular flags of lava joined
neatly together, in which the carriage wheels have often worn ruts an
inch and a half deep. In the wider streets, the ruts are numerous and
irregular; in the narrower, there are only two, one on each side, which
are very conspicuous. It is impossible not to look with some interest
even on these ruts, which were worn by chariot wheels more than
seventeen centuries ago; and, independently of their antiquity, it is
remarkable to see such deep incisions so continuous in a stone of great
hardness.
Small number of skeletons.—A very small number of skeletons have
been discovered in either city; and it is clear that most of the inhabitants
not only found time to escape, but also to carry with them the
principal part of their valuable effects. In the barracks at Pompeii
were the skeletons of two soldiers chained to the stocks, and in the
vaults of a country-house in the suburbs were the skeletons of seventeen
persons, who appear to have fled there to escape from the shower
of ashes. They were found inclosed in an indurated tuff, and in this
matrix was preserved a perfect cast of a woman, perhaps the mistress
of the house, with an infant in her arms. Although her form was imprinted
on the rock, nothing but the bones remained. To these a chain
of gold was suspended, and on the fingers of the skeletons were rings
with jewels. Against the sides of the same vault was ranged a long
line of earthen amphoræ.
392
The writings scribbled by the soldiers on the walls of their barracks,
and the names of the owners of each house written over the doors, are
still perfectly legible. The colors of fresco paintings on the stuccoed
walls in the interior of buildings are almost as vivid as if they were just
finished. There are public fountains decorated with shells laid out in
patterns in the same fashion as those now seen in the town of Naples;
and in the room of a painter, who was perhaps a naturalist, a large collection
of shells was found, comprising a great variety of Mediterranean
species, in as good a state of preservation as if they had remained for
the same number of years in a museum. A comparison of these
remains, with those found so generally in a fossil state would not assist
us in obtaining the least insight into the time required to produce a certain
degree of decomposition or mineralization; for, although under
favorable circumstances much greater alteration might doubtless have
been brought about in a shorter period, yet the example before us shows
that an inhumation of seventeen centuries may sometimes effect nothing
towards the reduction of shells to the state in which fossils are usually
found.
The wooden beams in the houses at Herculaneum are black on the
exterior, but, when cleft open, they appear to be almost in the state of
ordinary wood, and the progress made by the whole mass towards the
state of lignite is scarcely appreciable. Some animal and vegetable
substances of more perishable kinds have of course suffered much
change and decay, yet the state of preservation of these is truly remarkable.
Fishing-nets are very abundant in both cities, often quite
entire; and their number at Pompeii is the more interesting from the
sea being now, as we stated, a mile distant. Linen has been found at
Herculaneum, with the texture well defined; and in a fruiterer's shop
in that city were discovered vessels full of almonds, chestnuts, walnuts,
and fruit of the "carubiere," all distinctly recognizable from their
shape. A loaf, also, still retaining its form, was found in a baker's
shop, with his name stamped upon it. On the counter of an apothecary
was a box of pills converted into a fine earthy substance; and by
the side of it a small cylindrical roll evidently prepared to be cut into
pills. By the side of these was a jar containing medicinal herbs. In
1827, moist olives were found in a square glass-case, and "caviare," or
roe of a fish, in a state of wonderful preservation. An examination of
these curious condiments has been published by Covelli of Naples, and
they are preserved hermetically sealed in the museum there.556
Papyri.—There is a marked difference in the condition and appearance
of the animal and vegetable substances found at Pompeii and
Herculaneum; those of Pompeii being penetrated by a gray pulverulent
tuff, those in Herculaneum seeming to have been first enveloped
by a paste which consolidated round them, and then allowed them to
become slowly carbonized. Some of the rolls of papyrus at Pompeii
393
still retain their form; but the writing, and indeed almost all the vegetable
matter, appear to have vanished, and to have been replaced by
volcanic tuff somewhat pulverulent. At Herculaneum the earthy matter
has scarcely ever penetrated; and the vegetable substance of the
papyrus has become a thin friable black matter, almost resembling in
appearance the tinder which remains when stiff paper has been burnt,
in which the letters may still be sometimes traced. The small bundles
of papyri, composed of five or six rolls tied up together, had sometimes
lain horizontally, and were pressed in that direction, but sometimes
they had been placed in a vertical position. Small tickets were attached
to each bundle, on which the title of the work was inscribed.
In one case only have the sheets been found with writing on both sides
of the pages. So numerous are the obliterations and corrections, that
many must have been original manuscripts. The variety of handwritings
is quite extraordinary: nearly all are written in Greek, but there
are a few in Latin. They were almost all found in a suburban villa in
the library of one private individual; and the titles of four hundred of
those least injured, which have been read, are found to be unimportant
works, but all entirely new, chiefly relating to music, rhetoric, and
cookery. There are two volumes of Epicurus "On Nature," and the
others are mostly by writers of the same school, only one fragment
having been discovered, by an opponent of the Epicurean system,
Chrysippus.557
Probability of future discoveries of MSS.—In the opinion of some
antiquaries, not one-hundredth part of the city has yet been explored:
and the quarters hitherto cleared out at a great expense, are those
where there was the least probability of discovering manuscripts. As
Italy could already boast her splendid Roman amphitheatres and Greek
temples, it was a matter of secondary interest to add to their number
those in the dark and dripping galleries of Herculaneum; and having
so many of the masterpieces of ancient art, we could have dispensed
with the inferior busts and statues which could alone have been expected
to reward our researches in the ruins of a provincial town.
But from the moment that it was ascertained that rolls of papyrus preserved
in this city could still be deciphered, every exertion ought to
have been steadily and exclusively directed towards the discovery of
other libraries. Private dwellings should have been searched, before
so much labor and expense were consumed in examining public edifices.
A small portion of that zeal and enlightened spirit which
prompted the late French and Tuscan expedition to Egypt might long
ere this, in a country nearer home, have snatched from oblivion some
of the lost works of the Augustan age, or of eminent Greek historians
and philosophers. A single roll of papyrus might have disclosed more
394
matter of intense interest than all that was ever written in hieroglyphics.
Stabiæ.—Besides the cities already mentioned, Stabiæ, a small town
about six miles from Vesuvius, and near the site of the modern Castel-a-Mare
(see map of volcanic district of Naples), was overwhelmed during
the eruption of 79. Pliny mentions that, when his uncle was there, he
was obliged to make his escape, so great was the quantity of falling
stones and ashes. In the ruins of this place, a few skeletons have been
found buried in volcanic ejections, together with some antiquities of no
great value, and rolls of papyrus, which, like those of Pompeii, were
illegible.
Torre del Greco overflowed by lava.—Of the towns hitherto mentioned,
Herculaneum alone has been overflowed by a stream of melted
matter; but this did not, as we have seen, enter or injure the buildings,
which were previously enveloped or covered over with tuff. But burning
torrents have often taken their course through the streets of Torre
del Greco, and consumed or inclosed a large portion of the town in
solid rock. It seems probable that the destruction of three thousand
of its inhabitants in 1631, which some accounts attribute to boiling water,
was principally due to one of those alluvial floods which we before
mentioned: but, in 1737, the lava itself flowed through the eastern
side of the town, and afterwards reached the sea; and, in 1794, another
current, rolling over the western side, filled the streets and houses, and
killed more than four hundred persons. The main street is now quarried
through this lava, which supplied building stones for new houses erected
where others had been annihilated. The church was half buried in a
rocky mass, but the upper portion served as the foundation of a new
edifice.
The number of the population at present is estimated at fifteen thousand;
and a satisfactory answer may readily be returned to those who
inquire how the inhabitants can be so "inattentive to the voice of time
and the warnings of nature,"558 as to rebuild their dwellings on a spot so
often devastated. No neighboring site unoccupied by a town, or which
would not be equally insecure, combines the same advantages of proximity
to the capital, to the sea, and to the rich lands on the flanks of
Vesuvius. If the present population were exiled, they would immediately
be replaced by another, for the same reason that the Maremma
of Tuscany and the Campagna di Roma will never be depopulated,
although the malaria fever commits more havoc in a few years than the
Vesuvian lavas in as many centuries. The district around Naples supplies
one amongst innumerable examples, that those regions where the
surface is most frequently renewed, and where the renovation is accompanied,
at different intervals of time, by partial destruction of animal
and vegetable life, may nevertheless be amongst the most habitable and
delightful on our globe.
395
I have already made a similar remark when speaking of tracts where
aqueous causes are now most active; and the observation applies as
well to parts of the surface which are the abode of aquatic animals, as
to those which support terrestrial species. The sloping sides of Vesuvius
give nourishment to a vigorous and healthy population of about
eighty thousand souls; and the surrounding hills and plains, together
with several of the adjoining isles, owe the fertility of their soil to matter
ejected by prior eruptions. Had the fundamental limestone of the
Apennines remained uncovered throughout the whole area, the country
could not have sustained a twentieth part of its present inhabitants. This
will be apparent to every geologist who has marked the change in the
agricultural character of the soil the moment he has passed the utmost
boundary of the volcanic ejections, as when, for example, at the distance
of about seven miles from Vesuvius, he leaves the plain and
ascends the declivity of the Sorrentine Hills.
Yet, favored as this region has been by Nature from time immemorial,
the signs of the changes imprinted on it during the period that it has
served as the habitation of man may appear in after-ages to indicate
a series of unparalleled disasters. Let us suppose that at some future
time the Mediterranean should form a gulf of the great ocean, and that
the waves and tidal current should encroach on the shores of Campania,
as it now advances upon the eastern coast of England; the geologist will
then behold the towns already buried, and many more which will evidently
be entombed hereafter, laid open in the steep cliffs, where he
will discover buildings superimposed above each other, with thick intervening
strata of tuff or lava—some unscathed by fire, like those of
Herculaneum and Pompeii; others half melted down, as in Torre del
Greco; and many shattered and thrown about in strange confusion, as
in Tripergola, beneath Monte Nuovo. Among the ruins will be seen
skeletons of men, and impressions of the human form stamped in solid
rocks of tuff. Nor will the signs of earthquakes be wanting. The pavement
of part of the Domitian Way, and the temple of the Nymphs, submerged
at high tide, will be uncovered at low water, the columns remaining
erect and uninjured. Other temples which had once sunk down,
like that of Serapis, will be found to have been upraised again by subsequent
movements. If they who study these phenomena, and speculate
on their causes, assume that there were periods when the laws of
Nature or the whole course of natural events differed greatly from those
observed in their own time, they will scarcely hesitate to refer the wonderful
monuments in question to those primeval ages. When they consider
the numerous proofs of reiterated catastrophes to which the region
was subject, they may, perhaps, commiserate the unhappy fate of beings
condemned to inhabit a planet during its nascent and chaotic state, and
feel grateful that their favored race has escaped such scenes of anarchy
and misrule.
Yet what was the real condition of Campania during those years of
dire convulsion? "A climate where heaven's breath smells sweet and
396
wooingly—a vigorous and luxuriant nature unparalleled in its productions—a
coast which was once the fairy-land of poets, and the favorite
retreat of great men. Even the tyrants of the creation loved this alluring
region, spared it, adorned it, lived in it, died in it."559 The inhabitants,
indeed, have enjoyed no immunity from the calamities which are
the lot of mankind; but the principal evils which they have suffered
must be attributed to moral, not to physical, causes—to disastrous
events over which man might have exercised a control, rather than to
the inevitable catastrophes which result from subterranean agency.
When Spartacus encamped his army of ten thousand gladiators in the
old extinct crater of Vesuvius, the volcano was more justly a subject of
terror to Campania, than it has ever been since the rekindling of its fires.
</div></body></text></TEI>