<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="34">CHAPTER XXXIV.
TRANSMUTATION OF SPECIES—Continued.
Recapitulation of the arguments in favor of the theory of transmutation of
species—Their insufficiency—Causes of difficulty in discriminating species—Some
varieties possibly more distinct than certain individuals of distinct species—Variability
in a species consistent with a belief that the limits of deviation
are fixed—No facts of transmutation authenticated—Varieties of the
Dog—the Dog and Wolf distinct species—Mummies of various animals from
Egypt identical in character with living individuals—Seeds and plants from
the Egyptian tombs—Modifications produced in plants by agriculture and
gardening.
The theory of the transmutation of species, considered in the last
chapter, has met with some degree of favor from many naturalists,
from their desire to dispense, as far as possible, with the repeated intervention
of a First Cause, as often as geological monuments attest the
successive appearance of new races of animals and plants, and the extinction
of those pre-existing. But, independently of a predisposition
to account, if possible, for a series of changes in the organic world by
the regular action of secondary causes, we have seen that in truth
many perplexing difficulties present themselves to one who attempts to
establish the nature and reality of the specific character. And if once
there appears ground of reasonable doubt, in regard to the constancy of
species, the amount of transformation which they are capable of undergoing
may seem to resolve itself into a mere question of the quantity
of time assigned to the past duration of animate existence.
Before entering upon the reasons which may be adduced for rejecting
Lamarck's hypothesis, I shall recapitulate, in a few words, the phenomena,
and the whole train of thought, by which I conceive it to have
been suggested, and which have gained for this and analogous theories,
both in ancient and modern times, a considerable number of votaries.
In the first place, the various groups into which plants and animals
may be thrown seem almost invariably, to a beginner, to be so natural,
that he is usually convinced at first, as was Linnæus to the last, "that
genera are as much founded in nature as the species which compose
them."800 When by examining the numerous intermediate gradations
the student finds all lines of demarcation to be in most instances obliterated,
even where they at first appeared most distinct, he grows
more and more sceptical as to the real existence of genera, and finally
regards them as mere arbitrary and artificial signs, invented, like those
579
which serve to distinguish the heavenly constellations, for the convenience
of classification, and having as little pretensions to reality.
Doubts are then engendered in his mind as to whether species may
not also be equally unreal. The student is probably first struck with
the phenomenon, that some individuals are made to deviate widely
from the ordinary type by the force of peculiar circumstances, and
with the still more extraordinary fact, that the newly acquired peculiarities
are faithfully transmitted to the offspring. How far, he asks,
may such variations extend in the course of indefinite periods of
time, and during great vicissitudes in the physical condition of the
globe? His growing incertitude is at first checked by the reflection
that nature has forbidden the intermixture of the descendants of
distinct original stocks, or has, at least, entailed sterility on their
offspring, thereby preventing their being confounded together, and
pointing out that a multitude of distinct types must have been created
in the beginning, and must have remained pure and uncorrupted to
this day.
Relying on this general law, he endeavors to solve each difficult problem
by direct experiment, until he is again astounded by the phenomenon
of a prolific hybrid, and still more by an example of a
hybrid perpetuating itself throughout several generations in the vegetable
world. He then feels himself reduced to the dilemma of choosing
between two alternatives; either to reject the test, or to declare that
the two species, from the union of which the fruitful progeny has
sprung, were mere varieties. If he prefer the latter, he is compelled
to question the reality of the distinctness of all other supposed species
which differ no more than the parents of such prolific hybrids; for
although he may not be enabled immediately to procure, in all such
instances, a fruitful offspring; yet experiments show, that after repeated
failures, the union of two recognized species may at last, under very
favorable circumstances, give birth to a fertile progeny. Such circumstances,
therefore, the naturalist may conceive to have occurred again
and again, in the course of a great lapse of ages.
His first opinions are now fairly unsettled, and every stay at which he
has caught has given way one after another; he is in danger of
falling into any new and visionary doctrine which may be presented to
him; for he now regards every part of the animate creation as void of
stability, and in a state of continual flux. In this mood he encounters
the Geologist, who relates to him how there have been endless vicissitudes
in the shape and structure of organic beings in former ages—how
the approach to the present system of things has been gradual—that
there has been a progressive development of organization subservient
to the purposes of life, from the most simple to the most
complex state—that the appearance of man is the last phenomenon in
a long succession of events—and, finally, that a series of physical revolutions
can be traced in the inorganic world, coeval and co-extensive
with those of organic nature.
580
These views seem immediately to confirm all his preconceived doubts
as to the stability of the specific character, and he begins to think there
may exist an inseparable connection between a series of changes in
the inanimate world, and the capability of the species to be indefinitely
modified by the influence of external circumstances. Henceforth his
speculations know no definite bounds; he gives the rein to conjecture,
and fancies that the outward form, internal structure, instinctive faculties,
nay, that reason itself may have been gradually developed from
some of the simplest states of existence—that all animals, that man
himself, and the irrational beings, may have had one common origin;
that all may be parts of one continuous and progressive scheme of
development, from the most imperfect to the more complex; in fine, he
renounces his belief in the high genealogy of his species, and looks forward,
as if in compensation, to the future perfectibility of man in his
physical, intellectual, and moral attributes.
Let us now proceed to consider what is defective in evidence, and
what fallacious in reasoning, in the grounds of these strange conclusions.
Blumenbach judiciously observes, that "no general rule can be
laid down for determining the distinctness of species, as there is no particular
class of characters which can serve as a criterion. In each
case we must be guided by analogy and probability." The multitude,
in fact, and complexity of the proofs to be weighed is so great, that we
can only hope to obtain presumptive evidence, and we must, therefore,
be the more careful to derive our general views as much as possible
from those observations where the chances of deception are least.
We must be on our guard not to tread in the footsteps of the naturalists
of the middle ages, who believed the doctrine of spontaneous
generation to be applicable to all those parts of the animal and vegetable
kingdoms which they least understood, in direct contradiction to the
analogy of all the parts best known to them; and who, when at length
they found that insects and cryptogamous plants were also propagated
from eggs or seeds, still persisted in retaining their old prejudices
respecting the infusory animalcules and other minute beings, the generation
of which had not then been demonstrated by the microscope to
be governed by the same laws.
Lamarck has, indeed, attempted to raise an argument in favor of his
system, out of the very confusion which has arisen in the study of some
orders of animals and plants, in consequence of the slight shades of
difference which separate the new species discovered within the last
half century. That the embarrassment of those who attempt to classify
and distinguish the new acquisitions, poured in such multitudes into
our museums, should increase with the augmentation of their number,
is quite natural; since to obviate this, it is not enough that our powers
of discrimination should keep pace with the increase of the objects, but
we ought to possess greater opportunities of studying each animal and
plant in all stages of its growth, and to know profoundly their history,
their habits, and physiological characters, throughout several generations;
581
for, in proportion as the series of known animals grows more complete
none can doubt there is a nearer approximation to a graduated scale
of being; and thus the most closely allied species will be found to
possess a greater number of characters in common.
Causes of the difficulty of discriminating species.—But, in point of
fact, our new acquisitions consist, more and more as we advance, of
specimens brought from foreign and often very distant and barbarous
countries. A large proportion have never even been seen alive by
scientific inquirers. Instead of having specimens of the young, the
adult, and the aged individuals of each sex, and possessing means of
investigating the anatomical structure, the peculiar habits, and instincts
of each, what is usually the state of our information? A single specimen,
perhaps, of a dried plant, or a stuffed bird or quadruped; a shell,
without the soft parts of the animal; an insect in one stage of its numerous
transformations;—these are the scanty and imperfect data which
the naturalist possesses. Such information may enable us to separate
species which stand at a considerable distance from each other; but we
have no right to expect any thing but difficulty and ambiguity, if we
attempt, from such imperfect opportunities, to obtain distinctive marks
for defining the characters of species which are closely related.
If Lamarck could introduce so much certainty and precision into the
classification of several thousand species of recent and fossil shells, notwithstanding
the extreme remoteness of the organization of these animals
from the type of those vertebrated species which are best known,
and in the absence of so many of the living inhabitants of shells, we are
led to form an exalted conception of the degree of exactness to which
specific distinctions are capable of being carried, rather than to call in
question their reality.
When our data are so defective, the most acute naturalist must expect
to be sometimes at fault, and, like the novice, to overlook essential
points of difference, passing unconsciously from one species to another,
until, like one who is borne along in a current, he is astonished on
looking back, at observing that he has reached a point so remote from
that whence he set out.
It is by no means improbable, that, when the series of species of
certain genera is very full, they may be found to differ less widely from
each other than do the mere varieties or races of certain species. If
such a fact could be established, it would, undoubtedly, diminish the
chance of our obtaining certainty in our results; but it would by no
means overthrow our confidence in the reality of species.
Some mere varieties possibly more distinct than certain individuals
of distinct species.—It is almost necessary, indeed, to suppose that varieties
will differ in some cases more decidedly than some species, if we
admit that there is a graduated scale of being, and assume that the following
laws prevail in the economy of the animate creation:—first,
that the organization of individuals is capable of being modified to a
limited extent, by the force of external causes; secondly, that these
582
modifications are, to a certain extent, transmissible to their offspring;
thirdly, that there are fixed limits, beyond which the descendants from
common parents can never deviate from a certain type; fourthly, that
each species springs from one original stock, and can never be permanently
confounded by intermixing with the progeny of any other stock;
fifthly, that each species shall endure for a considerable period of time.
Now, let us assume, for the present, these rules hypothetically, and see
what consequences may naturally be expected to result from them.
We must suppose that when the Author of Nature creates an animal
or plant, all the possible circumstances in which its descendants are
destined to live are foreseen, and that an organization is conferred upon
it which will enable the species to perpetuate itself and survive under all
the varying circumstances to which it must be inevitably exposed.
Now, the range of variation of circumstances will differ essentially in
almost every case. Let us take, for example, any one of the most influential
conditions of existence, such as temperature. In some extensive
districts near the equator, the thermometer might never vary, throughout
several thousand centuries, for more than 20° Fahrenheit; so that
if a plant or animal be provided with an organization fitting it to endure
such a range, it may continue on the globe for that immense period,
although every individual might be liable at once to be cut off by the
least possible excess of heat or cold beyond the determinate degree. But
if a species be placed in one of the temperate zones, and have a constitution
conferred on it capable of supporting a similar range of temperature
only, it will inevitably perish before a single year has passed away.
Humboldt has shown that, at Cumana, within the tropics, there is a
difference of only 4° Fahr. between the temperature of the warmest and
coldest months; whereas, in the temperate zones, the annual variation
amounts to about 60°, and the extreme range of the thermometer in
Canada is not less than 90°.
The same remark might be applied to any other condition, as food,
for example; it may be foreseen that the supply will be regular throughout
indefinite periods in one part of the world, and in another very precarious
and fluctuating both in kind and quantity. Different qualifications
may be required for enabling species to live for a considerable time
under circumstances so changeable. If, then, temperature and food be
among those external causes which, according to certain laws of animal
and vegetable physiology, modify the organization, form, or faculties, of
individuals, we instantly perceive that the degrees of variability from a
common standard must differ widely in the two cases above supposed;
since there is a necessity of accommodating a species in one case to a
much greater latitude of circumstances than in the other.
If it be a law, for instance, that scanty sustenance should check those
individuals in their growth which are enabled to accommodate themselves
to privations of this kind, and that a parent, prevented in this
manner from attaining the size proper to its species, should produce a
dwarfish offspring, a stunted race will arise, as is remarkably exemplified
583
in some varieties of the horse and dog. The difference of stature in
some races of dogs, when compared to others, is as one to five in linear
dimensions, making a difference of a hundred-fold in volume.801 Now,
there is a good reason to believe that species in general are by no means
susceptible of existing under a diversity of circumstances, which may
give rise to such a disparity in size, and, consequently, there will be a
multitude of distinct species, of which no two adult individuals can ever
depart so widely from a certain standard of dimensions as the mere varieties
of certain other species—the dog, for instance. Now, we have
only to suppose that what is true of size, may also hold in regard to
color and many other attributes; and it will at once follow, that the
degree of possible discordance between varieties of the same species
may, in certain cases, exceed the utmost disparity which can arise between
two individuals of many distinct species.
The same remarks may hold true in regard to instincts; for, if it
be foreseen that one species will have to encounter a great variety
of foes, it may be necessary to arm it with great cunning and
circumspection, or with courage or other qualities capable of developing
themselves on certain occasions; such, for example, as those migratory
instincts which are so remarkably exhibited at particular periods, after
they have remained dormant for many generations. The history and
habits of one variety of such a species may often differ more considerably
from some other than those of many distinct species which have no
such latitude of accommodation to circumstances.
Extent of known variability in species.—Lamarck has somewhat
mis-stated the idea commonly entertained of a species; for it is not
true that naturalists in general assume that the organisation of an
animal or plant remains absolutely constant, and that it can never
vary in any of its parts.802 All must be aware that circumstances
influence the habits, and that the habits may alter the state of the
parts and organs; but the difference of opinion relates to the extent
to which these modifications of the habits and organs of a particular
species may be carried.
Now, let us first inquire what positive facts can be adduced in the
history of known species, to establish a great and permanent amount
of change in the form, structure, or instinct of individuals descending
from some common stock. The best authenticated examples of the
extent to which species can be made to vary may be looked for in
the history of domesticated animals and cultivated plants. It usually
happens, that those species, both of the animal and vegetable kingdom,
which have the greatest pliability of organisation, those which
are most capable of accommodating themselves to a great variety of
new circumstances, are most serviceable to man. These only can
be carried by him into different climates, and can have their properties
or instincts variously diversified by differences of nourishment
584
and habits. If the resources of a species be so limited, and its habits
and faculties be of such a confined and local character, that it can
only flourish in a few particular spots, it can rarely be of great
utility.
We may consider, therefore, that in the domestication of animals
and the cultivation of plants, mankind have first selected those species
which have the most flexible frames and constitutions, and have then
been engaged for ages in conducting a series of experiments, with
much patience and at great cost, to ascertain what may be the greatest
possible deviation from a common type which can be elicited in these
extreme cases.
Varieties of the dog—no transmutation.—The modifications produced
in the different races of dogs exhibit the influence of man
in the most striking point of view. These animals have been
transported into every climate and placed in every variety of circumstances;
they have been made, as a modern naturalist observes, the
servant, the companion, the guardian, and the intimate friend of
man, and the power of a superior genius has had a wonderful influence
not only on their forms, but on their manners and intelligence.803
Different races have undergone remarkable changes in the quantity
and color of their clothing; the dogs of Guinea are almost naked, while
those of the arctic circle are covered with a warm coat both of hair and
wool, which enables them to bear the most intense cold without
inconvenience. There are differences also of another kind no less
remarkable, as in size, the length of their muzzles, and the convexity of
their foreheads.
But, if we look for some of those essential changes which would
be required to lend even the semblance of a foundation for the theory
of Lamarck, respecting the growth of new organs and the gradual
obliteration of others, we find nothing of the kind. For, in all these
varieties of the dog, says Cuvier, the relation of the bones with each
other remains essentially the same; the form of the teeth never
changes in any perceptible degree, except that, in some individuals,
one additional false grinder occasionally appears, sometimes on the one
side, and sometimes on the other.804 The greatest departure from a
common type—and it constitutes the maximum of variation as yet
known in the animal kingdom—is exemplified in those races of
dogs which have a supernumerary toe on the hind foot with the corresponding
tarsal bones; a variety analogous to one presented by six-fingered
families of the human race.805
Lamarck has thrown out as a conjecture, that the wolf may
have been the original of the dog; and eminent naturalists are still
divided in opinion on this subject. It seems now admitted that both
species agree in the period of gestation, and Mr. Owen has been unable
585
to confirm the alleged difference in the structure of a part of the intestinal
canal.806 Mr. Bell inclines to the opinion that all the various races
of dogs have descended from one common stock, of which the wolf is
the original source.
It is well known that the horse, the ox, the boar, and other domestic
animals which have been introduced into South America, and have run
wild in many parts, have entirely lost all marks of domesticity, and have
reverted to the original characters of their species. But dogs have also
become wild in Cuba, Hayti, and in all the Caribbean islands. In the
course of the seventeenth century, they hunted in packs from twelve to
fifty, or more, in number, and fearlessly attacked herds of wild boars
and other animals. It is natural, therefore, to inquire to what form
they reverted? Now, they are said by many travellers to have resembled
very nearly the shepherd's dog; but it is certain that they were
never turned into wolves. They were extremely savage, and their
ravages appear to have been as much dreaded as those of wolves; but
when any of their whelps were caught, and brought from the woods to
the towns, they grew up in the most perfect submission to man.807
Many examples might be adduced to prove that the extent to which
the alteration of species can be pushed in the domestic state depends
on the original capacity of the species to admit of variation. The horse
has been as long domesticated as the dog, yet its different races depart
much less widely from a common type; the ass has been still less
changed, the camel scarcely at all; yet these species have probably
been subjected to the influence of domestication as long as the horse.
Mummies of animals in Egyptian tombs identical with species still
living.—As the advocates of the theory of transmutation trust much to
the slow and insensible changes which time may work, they are accustomed
to lament the absence of accurate descriptions, and figures of
particular animals and plants, handed down from the earliest periods of
history, such as might have afforded data for comparing the condition
of species, at two periods considerably remote. But, fortunately, we
are in some measure independent of such evidence: for, by a singular
accident, the priests of Egypt have bequeathed to us, in their cemeteries,
that information which the museums and works of the Greek philosophers
have failed to transmit.
For the careful investigation of these documents, we are greatly
indebted to the skill and diligence of those naturalists who accompanied
the French armies during their brief occupation of Egypt: that
conquest of four years, from which we may date the improvement of the
modern Egyptians in the arts and sciences, and the rapid progress which
has been made of late in our knowledge of the arts and sciences of their
remote predecessors. Instead of wasting their whole time, as so many
preceding travellers had done, in exclusively collecting human mummies,
586
M. Geoffrey and his associates examined diligently, and sent home
great numbers of embalmed bodies of consecrated animals, such as the
bull, the dog, the cat, the ape, the ichneumon, the crocodile, and
the ibis.
To those who have never been accustomed to connect the facts of
Natural History with philosophical speculations, who have never raised
their conceptions of the end and import of such studies beyond the mere
admiration of isolated and beautiful objects, or the exertion of skill in
detecting specific differences, it will seem incredible that amidst the din
of arms, and the stirring excitement of political movements, so much
enthusiasm could have been felt in regard to these precious remains.
In the official report drawn up by the Professors of the Museum at
Paris, on the value of these objects, there are some eloquent passages,
which may appear extravagant, unless we reflect how fully these naturalists
could appreciate the bearing of the facts thus brought to light on
the past history of the globe.
"It seems," say they, "as if the superstition of the ancient Egyptians
had been inspired by Nature, with a view of transmitting to after ages
a monument of her history. That extraordinary and eccentric people,
by embalming with so much care the brutes which were the objects of
their stupid adoration, have left us in their secret grottoes, cabinets of
zoology almost complete. The climate has conspired with the art of
embalming to preserve the bodies from corruption, and we can now assure
ourselves by our own eyes what was the state of a great number of
species three thousand years ago. We can scarcely restrain the transports
of our imagination, on beholding thus preserved, with their
minutest bones, with the smallest portions of their skin, and in every
particular most perfectly recognizable, many an animal, which at Thebes
or Memphis, two or three thousand years ago, had its own priests
and altars."808
Among the Egyptian mummies thus procured were not only those of
numerous wild quadrupeds, birds, and reptiles; but what was perhaps
of still higher importance in deciding the great question under discussion,
there were the mummies of domestic animals, among which those
above mentioned, the bull, the dog, and the cat, were frequent. Now,
such was the conformity of the whole of these species to those now
living, that there was no more difference, says Cuvier, between them
than between the human mummies and the embalmed bodies of
men of the present day. Yet some of these animals have since that
period been transported by man to almost every climate, and forced to
accommodate their habits to the greatest variety of circumstances. The
cat, for example, has been carried over the whole earth, and within the
last three centuries, has been naturalized in every part of the new world,—from
the cold regions of Canada to the tropical plains of Guiana;
587
yet it has scarcely undergone any perceptible mutation, and is still the
same animal which was held sacred by the Egyptians.
Of the ox, undoubtedly, there are many very distinct races; but the
bull Apis, which was led in solemn processions by the Egyptian priests,
did not differ from some of those now living. The black cattle that
have run wild in America, where there were many peculiarities in the climate
not to be found, perhaps, in any part of the old world, and where
scarcely a single plant on which they fed was of precisely the same
species, instead of altering their form and habits, have actually reverted
to the exact likeness of the aboriginal wild cattle of Europe.
In answer to the arguments drawn from the Egyptian mummies,
Lamarck said they were identical with their living descendants in the
same country, because the climate and physical geography of the banks
of the Nile have remained unaltered for the last thirty centuries. But
why, it may be asked, have other individuals of these species retained
the same characters in many different quarters of the globe, where the
climate and many other conditions are so varied?
Seeds and plants from the Egyptian tombs.—The evidence derived
from the Egyptian monuments was not confined to the animal kingdom;
the fruits, seeds, and other portions of twenty different plants, were
faithfully preserved in the same manner; and among these the common
wheat was procured by Delille, from closed vessels in the sepulchres
of the kings, the grain of which retained not only their form
but even their color; so effectual has proved the process of embalming
with bitumen in a dry and equable climate. No difference could be
detected between this wheat and that which now grows in the East
and elsewhere; and in regard to the barley, I am informed by Mr.
Brown, the celebrated botanist, that its identity with the grain of our
own times can be tested by the closest comparison. On examining, for
example, one of the seeds from Mr. Sam's Egyptian collection in the
British Museum, it is found that "the structure of the husks or that
part of the flower which is persistent, agrees precisely with the barley of
the present day, in having one perfect flower and the filiform rudiments
of a second." Some naturalists believe that the perfect identification
of the ancient Egyptian cerealia with the varieties now cultivated has
been carried still further, by sowing the seeds taken out of the catacombs,
and raising plants from them; but we want more evidence of
this fact. Certain it is, that when the experiment was recently made
in the botanic garden at Kew, with 100 seeds of wheat, barley, and
lentils, from the Egyptian collection before mentioned of the British
Museum, not one of them would germinate.809
588
Native country of the common wheat.—And here I may observe that
there is an obvious answer to Lamarck's objection, that the botanist cannot
point out a country where the common wheat grows wild, unless in
places where it may have been derived from neighboring
cultivation.810
All naturalists are well aware that the geographical distribution of a
great number of species is extremely limited; that it was to be expected
that every useful plant should first be cultivated successfully in
the country where it was indigenous; and that, probably, every station
which it partially occupied, when growing wild, would be selected by
the agriculturist as best suited to it when artificially increased. Palestine
has been conjectured, by a late writer on the cerealia, to have been
the original habitation of wheat and barley; a supposition which is
rendered the more plausible by Hebrew and Egyptian traditions, and
by tracing the migrations of the worship of Ceres, as indicative of the
migrations of the plant.811
If we are to infer that some one of the wild grasses has been transformed
into the common wheat, and that some animal of the genus
Canis, still unreclaimed, has been metamorphosed into the dog, merely
because we cannot find the domestic dog, or the cultivated wheat, in a
state of nature, we may be next called upon to make similar admissions
in regard to the camel; for it seems very doubtful whether any race of
this species of quadruped is now wild.
Changes in plants produced by cultivation.—But if agriculture, it
will be said, does not supply examples of extraordinary changes of
form and organization, the horticulturist can, at least, appeal to facts
which may confound the preceding train of reasoning. The crab has
been transformed into the apple; the sloe into the plum; flowers
have changed their color, and become double; and these new characters
can be perpetuated by seed; a bitter plant, with wavy sea-green
leaves, has been taken from the sea-side, where it grew like wild charlock;
has been transplanted into the garden, lost its saltness, and has
been metamorphosed into two distinct vegetables, as unlike each other
as is each to the parent plant—the red cabbage and the cauliflower.
These, and a multitude of analogous facts, are undoubtedly among the
wonders of nature, and attest more strongly, perhaps, the extent to
which species may be modified, than any examples derived from the
animal kingdom. But in these cases we find that we soon reach certain
limits, beyond which we are unable to cause the individuals descending
from the same stock to vary; while, on the other hand, it is easy
to show that these extraordinary varieties could seldom arise, and could
never be perpetuated in a wild state for many generations, under any
imaginable combination of accidents. They may be regarded as extreme
589
cases, brought about by human interference, and not as phenomena
which indicate a capability of indefinite modification in the
natural world.
The propagation of a plant by buds or grafts, and by cuttings, is
obviously a mode which nature does not employ; and this multiplication,
as well as that produced by roots and layers, seems merely to
operate as an extension of the life of an individual, and not as a reproduction
of the species such as happens by seed. All plants increased
by grafts or layers retain precisely the peculiar qualities of the individual
to which they owe their origin, and, like an individual, they have
only a determinate existence; in some cases longer, and in others
shorter.812 It seems now admitted by horticulturists, that none of our
garden varieties of fruit are entitled to be considered strictly permanent,
but that they wear out after a time;813 and we are thus compelled to resort
again to seeds; in which case there is so decided a tendency in the
seedlings to revert to the original type, that our utmost skill is sometimes
baffled in attempting to recover the desired variety.
Varieties of the cabbage.—The different races of cabbages afford, as
was admitted, an astonishing example of deviation from a common
type; but we can scarcely conceive them to have originated, much
less to have lasted for several generations, without the intervention of
man. It is only by strong manures that these varieties have been obtained,
and in poorer soils they instantly degenerate. If, therefore, we
suppose in a state of nature the seed of the wild Brassica oleracea to
have been wafted from the sea-side to some spot enriched by the dung
of animals, and to have there become a cauliflower, it would soon diffuse
its seed to some comparatively sterile soils around, and the offspring
would relapse to the likeness of the parent stock.
But if we go so far as to imagine the soil, in the spot first occupied,
to be constantly manured by herds of wild animals, so as to continue
as rich as that of a garden, still the variety could not be maintained;
because we know that each of these races is prone to fecundate others,
and gardeners are compelled to exert the utmost diligence to prevent
cross-breeds. The intermixture of the pollen of varieties growing in
the poorer soil around would soon destroy the peculiar characters of
the race which occupied the highly manured tract; for, if these accidents
so continually happen, in spite of our care, among the culinary
varieties, it is easy to see how soon this cause might obliterate every
marked singularity in a wild state.
Besides, it is well known that, although the pampered races which
we rear in our gardens for use or ornament may often be perpetuated
by seed, yet they rarely produce seed in such abundance, or so prolific
in quality, as wild individuals; so that if the care of man were withdrawn,
the most fertile variety would always, in the end, prevail over
the more sterile.
590Similar remarks may be applied to the double flowers, which present
such strange anomalies to the botanist. The ovarium, in such cases, is
frequently abortive; and the seeds, when prolific, are generally much
fewer than where the flowers are single.
Changes caused by soil.—Some curious experiments, recently made
on the production of blue instead of red flowers in the Hydrangea
hortensis, illustrate the immediate effect of certain soils on the colors
of the calyx and petals. In garden-mould or compost, the flowers are
invariably red; in some kinds of bog-earth they are blue; and the same
change is always produced by a particular sort of yellow loam.
Varieties of the primrose.—Linnæus was of opinion that the primrose,
oxlip, cowslip, and polyanthus, were only varieties of the same
species. The majority of the modern botanists, on the contrary, consider
them to be distinct, although some conceived that the oxlip might
be a cross between the cowslip and the primrose. Mr. Herbert has
lately recorded the following experiment:—"I raised from the natural
seed of one umbel of a highly manured red cowslip a primrose, a
cowslip, oxlips of the usual and other colors, a black polyanthus, a
hose-in-hose cowslip, and a natural primrose bearing its flower on a
polyanthus stalk. From the seed of that very hose-in-hose cowslip
I have since raised a hose-in-hose primrose. I therefore consider all
these to be only local varieties, depending upon soil and situation."814
Professor Henslow, of Cambridge, has since confirmed this experiment
of Mr. Herbert; so that we have an example, not only of the remarkable
varieties which the florist can obtain from a common stock, but of
the distinctness of analogous races found in a wild state.815
On what particular ingredient, or quality in the earth, these changes
depend, has not yet been ascertained.816 But gardeners are well aware
that particular plants, when placed under the influence of certain circumstances,
are changed in various ways, according to the species; and
as often as the experiments are repeated, similar results are obtained.
The nature of these results, however, depends upon the species, and
they are, therefore, part of the specific character; they exhibit the
same phenomena, again and again, and indicate certain fixed and invariable
relations between the physiological peculiarities of the plant,
and the influence of certain external agents. They afford no ground
for questioning the instability of species, but rather the contrary;
they present us with a class of phenomena, which, when they are more
thoroughly understood, may afford some of the best tests for identifying
species, and proving that the attributes originally conferred endure so
long as any issue of the original stock remains upon the earth.

591</div></body></text></TEI>