<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 166, folios 101-104</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 166, folios 101-104.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1844">11 August [1844]</date>
          <note type="place">38 Bedford Square, Brighton</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 166, folios 101-104</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_166_folios_101-104.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>38. Bedford Sqre Brighton Sunday Evening 11th August</p>
      <p>Dearest W. Miserable sufferings prevented my writing to you by yesterday morning's post. I had put off preparing a letter for you on the Friday Night, because I had no good to tell since I had written on that morning. Yesterday morning I was asleep, resting after a bad night. I am now really quite recovering, thro' perseverance in the plans &amp; habits requisite: The daily batheing is beginning to take the same mighty effects it did before. My teeth sufferings have seriously injured my, not only from their direct effects, but from my being wholly unable now to masticate anything properly.</p>
      <p>My stomach &amp; general health were becoming severely affected by this circumstance, until Dr King directed me to have all my food pounded, &amp; to take it at 4 or 5 times a day (instead of in regular meals), by small quantities at a time. I believe it may be some months before I shall be able to chew in a proper manner. My mouth is in a lamentably helpless state, but now free from pain, thro' the remedies applied.</p>
      <p>I have a letter from E. Duppa, announcing to me his intended marriage to Miss Long, daughter of the member for Witts. He is staying there,</p>
      <p>12 miles from Chippenham. I read the place Rood Ashton, Trowbridge. He will marry in about 6 weeks.</p>
      <p>He writes of course very happily, &amp; expresses ardent desires that I may like his lady.</p>
      <p>As to the ropes: I intended a part for my bed- -room; but I wish I had seen to it, for you cannot know which is which, &amp; all about them, as I can.</p>
      <p>I really was so overwhelmed that I think I scarcely deserve blame in the matter. You will know how I have been pressed of late. As my health, &amp; also my habit of attending to practical matters (which, like all other subjects, do demand habit &amp; experience, in order to affect Multum in parvo)</p>
      <p>as these two requisites , you will find I have a head &amp; a corner of time for overlooking everything a little, &amp; forgetting nothing. But if you are unreasonable and impatient with me meanwhile, you will tend to retard my improvement in these respects.</p>
      <p>As to the ropes, Mr Chiosso assured me that they are of one particular &amp; patent manufacture, &amp; that it is exceedingly important to obtain them of that quality. Pray therefore consider properly about it, &amp; do not run any risks. Had you furnished me with the measures, I should have procured the ropes long ago.</p>
      <p>Dr Carpenter understands a good deal about gymnastics I think. You might consult</p>
      <p>him. If you like to send me the measures, I will still settle about it. What will you do? I am anxious to know. I am just as eager &amp; interested in the matter as ever, only lately I have been really taken away from attending to it. I am very sorry, since it has evidently so vexed you. It annoys me beyond measure to hurt you in anything, when I am conscious of doing so; &amp; I have become aware that I have often given you pain I had no idea of.--</p>
      <p>I have nothing very lively or interesting to communicate. The main thing just now is for me to get better, after all my pain &amp; sufferings. I can as yet settle no plans, nor think of anything much but the good</p>
      <p>&amp; evil of the day itself.</p>
      <p>Pray however think with pleasure of a poor gentle affectionate Bird, who thinks of her Mate with much tenderness &amp; interest; a real speckled Thrush!--</p>
      <p>How is Jack? I hear a portentous tale of his having once torn off a man's arm (&amp; killed the man's dog on the spot). The man had knocked down a woman, &amp; was robbing her. Jack was honorably taken (as a necessary person among the witnesses) before the Steyning magistrates. I am assured Jack is a dreadful man to all ill-disposed persons.</p>
      <p>I receive good accounts from my Mother, who says "direct P. O. Chittenham."</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
