<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="42">CHAPTER XLII.
EXTINCTION OF SPECIES.—INFLUENCE OF INORGANIC CAUSES.
Powers of diffusion indispensable, that each species may maintain its ground—How
changes in physical geography affect the distribution of species—Rate
of the change of species due to this cause cannot be uniform—Every change
in the physical geography of large regions tends to the extinction of species—Effects
of a general alteration of climate on the migration of species—Gradual
refrigeration would cause species in the northern and southern
hemispheres to become distinct—Elevation of temperature the reverse—Effects
on the condition of species which must result from inorganic changes
inconsistent with the theory of transmutation.
Powers of diffusion indispensable, that each species may maintain its
ground.—Having shown in the last chapter, how considerably the
numerical increase or the extension of the geographical range of any
one species must derange the numbers and distribution of others, let us
now direct our attention to the influence which the inorganic causes
described in the second book are continually exerting on the habitations
of species.
So great is the instability of the earth's surface, that if nature were
not continually engaged in the task of sowing seeds and colonizing
animals, the depopulation of a certain portion of the habitable sea and
land would in a few years be considerable. Whenever a river transports
sediment into a lake or sea, so as materially to diminish its depth, the
aquatic animals and plants which delight in deep water are expelled:
the tract, however, is not allowed to remain useless; but is soon peopled
by species which require more light and heat, and thrive where the
water is shallow. Every addition made to the land by the encroachment
of the delta of a river banishes many subaqueous species from
their native abodes; but the new-formed plain is not permitted to lie
unoccupied, being instantly covered with terrestrial vegetation. The
ocean devours continuous lines of sea-coasts, and precipitates forests or
rich pasture land into the waves: but this space is not lost to the
animate creation; for shells and sea-weeds soon adhere to the new-made
cliffs, and numerous fish people the channel which the current has
scooped out for itself. No sooner has a volcanic island been thrown
up than some lichens begin to grow upon it, and it is sometimes clothed
with verdure while smoke and ashes are still occasionally thrown from
the crater. The cocoa, pandanus, and mangrove take root upon the
coral reef before it has fairly risen above the waves. The burning
stream of lava that descends from Etna rolls through the stately forest,
and converts to ashes every tree and herb which stands in its way; but
the black strip of land thus desolated is covered again in the course of
time, with oaks, pines, and chestnuts, as luxuriant as those which the
fiery torrent swept away.
690
Every flood and landslip, every wave which a hurricane or earthquake
throws upon the shore, every shower of volcanic dust and ashes
which buries a country far and wide to the depth of many feet, every
advance of the sand-flood, every conversion of salt water into fresh
when rivers alter their main channel of discharge, every permanent
variation in the rise or fall of tides in an estuary—these and countless
other causes displace, in the course of a few centuries, certain plants
and animals from stations which they previously occupied. If, therefore,
the Author of nature had not been prodigal of those numerous
contrivances, before alluded to, for spreading all classes of organic
beings over the earth—if he had not ordained that the fluctuations of
the animate and inanimate creation should be in perfect harmony with
each other, it is evident that considerable spaces, now the most habitable
on the globe, would soon be as devoid of life as are the Alpine
snows, or the dark abysses of the ocean, or the moving sands of the
Sahara.
The powers, then, of migration and diffusion conferred on animals
and plants are indispensable to enable them to maintain their ground,
and would be necessary, even though it were never intended that a
species should gradually extend its geographical range. But a facility
of shifting their quarters being once given, it cannot fail to happen that
the inhabitants of one province should occasionally penetrate into some
other; since the strongest of those barriers which I before described as
separating distinct regions are all liable to be thrown down, one after
the other, during the vicissitudes of the earth's surface.
How changes in physical Geography affect the distribution of species.—The
numbers and distribution of particular species are affected in
two ways, by changes in the physical geography of the earth:—First,
these changes promote or retard the migrations of species; secondly,
they alter the physical conditions of the localities which species inhabit.
If the ocean should gradually wear its way through an isthmus, like
that of Suez, it would open a passage for the intermixture of the aquatic
tribes of two seas previously disjoined, and would, at the same time,
close a free communication which the terrestrial plants and animals of
two continents had before enjoyed. These would be, perhaps, the most
important consequences, in regard to the distribution of species, which
would result from the breach made by the sea in such a spot; but
there would be others of a distinct nature, such as the conversion of a
certain tract of land, which formed the isthmus, into sea. This space,
previously occupied by terrestrial plants and animals, would be immediately
delivered over to the aquatic; a local revolution which might
have happened in innumerable other parts of the globe, without being
attended by any alteration in the blending together of species of two
distinct provinces.
Rate of change of species cannot be uniform.—This observation leads
me to point out one of the most interesting conclusions to which we
are led by the contemplation of the vicissitudes of the inanimate world
691
in relation to those of the animate. It is clear that, if the agency of
inorganic causes be uniform, as I have supposed, they must operate
very irregularly on the state of organic beings, so that the rate according
to which these will change in particular regions will not be equal in
equal periods of time.
I am not about to advocate the doctrine of general catastrophes
recurring at certain intervals, as in the ancient Oriental cosmogonies, nor
do I doubt that, if very considerable periods of equal duration could be
compared one with another, the rate of change in the living, as well as
in the inorganic world, might be nearly uniform; but if we regard each
of the causes separately, which we know to be at present the most
instrumental in remodelling the state of the surface, we shall find that we
must expect each to be in action for thousands of years, without producing
any extensive alterations in the habitable surface, and then to give rise,
during a very brief period, to important revolutions.
Illustration derived from subsidences.—I shall illustrate this principle
by a few of the most remarkable examples which present themselves. In
the course of the last century, as we have seen, a considerable number of
instances are recorded of the solid surface, whether covered by water or
not, having been permanently sunk or upraised by subterranean movements.
Most of these convulsions are only accompanied by temporary
fluctuations in the state of limited districts, and a continued repetition of
these events for thousands of years might not produce any decided change
in the state of many of those great zoological or botanical provinces of
which I have sketched the boundaries.
When, for example, large parts of the ocean and even of inland seas
are a thousand fathoms or upwards in depth, it is a matter of no moment
to the animate creation that vast tracts should be heaved up many fathoms
at certain intervals, or should subside to the same amount. Neither can
any material revolution be produced in South America either in the terrestrial
or the marine plants or animals by a series of shocks on the coast
of Chili, each of which, like that of Penco, in 1751, should uplift the
coast about twenty-five feet. Nor if the ground sinks fifty feet at a time,
as in the harbor of Port Royal, in Jamaica, in 1692, will such alterations
of level work any general fluctuations in the state of organic beings
inhabiting the West Indian Islands, or the Caribbean Sea.
It is only when the subterranean powers, by shifting gradually the
points where their principal force is developed, happen to strike upon
some particular region where a slight change of level immediately affects
the distribution of land and water, or the state of the climate, or the
barriers between distinct groups of species over extensive areas, that the
rate of fluctuation becomes accelerated, and may, in the course of a few
years or centuries, work mightier changes than had been experienced in
myriads of antecedent years.
Thus, for example, a repetition of subsidences causing the narrow
isthmus of Panama to sink down a few hundred feet, would, in a few
centuries, bring about a great revolution in the state of the animate creation
692
in the western hemisphere. Thousands of aquatic species would pass,
for the first time, from the Caribbean Sea into the Pacific; and thousands
of others, before peculiar to the Pacific Ocean, would make their way
into the Caribbean Sea, the Gulf of Mexico, and the Atlantic. A considerable
modification would probably be occasioned by the same event
in the direction or volume of the Gulf stream, and thereby the temperature
of the sea and the contiguous lands might be altered as far as the
influence of that current extends. A change of climate might thus be
produced in the ocean from Florida to Spitzbergen, and in many countries
of North America, Europe, and Greenland. Not merely the heat, but
the quantity of rain which falls, would be altered in certain districts, so
that many species would be excluded from tracts where they before
flourished: others would be reduced in number; and some would thrive
more and multiply. The seeds also and the fruits of plants would no
longer be drifted in precisely the same directions, nor the eggs of aquatic
animals; neither would species be any longer impeded in their migrations
towards particular stations before shut out from them by their inability
to cross the mighty current.
Let us take another example from a part of the globe which is at
present liable to suffer by earthquakes, namely, the low sandy tract which
intervenes between the sea of Azof and the Caspian. If there should
occur a sinking down to a trifling amount, and such ravines should be
formed as might be produced by a few earthquakes, not more considerable
than have fallen within our limited observation during the last 150
years, the waters of the Sea of Azof would pour rapidly into the Caspian,
which, according to the measurements lately made by the Academy of
St. Petersburg, is 84 feet below the level of the Black Sea.984 The Sea
of Azof would immediately borrow from the Black Sea, that sea again
from the Mediterranean, and the Mediterranean from the Atlantic, so that
an inexhaustible current would pour down into the low tracts of Asia
bordering the Caspian, by which all the sandy salt steppes adjacent to
that sea would be inundated. An area of several thousand square leagues,
now below the level of the Mediterranean, would be converted from land
into sea.
Illustration derived from the elevation of land.—Let us next imagine
a few cases of the elevation of land of small extent at certain critical
points, as, for example, in the shallowest part of the Straits of Gibraltar,
where the deepest soundings from the African to the European side give
only 220 fathoms. In proportion as this submarine barrier of rock was
upheaved, the whole channel would be contracted in width and depth,
and the volume of water which the current constantly flowing from the
Atlantic pours into the Mediterranean would be lessened. But the loss
of the inland sea by evaporation would remain the same; so that being
no longer able to draw on the ocean for a supply sufficient to restore its
equilibrium, it must sink, and leave dry a certain portion of land around
693
its borders. The current which now flows constantly out of the Black
Sea into the Mediterranean would then rush in more rapidly, and the
level of the Mediterranean would be thereby prevented from falling so
low; but the level of the Black Sea would, for the same reason, sink; so
that when, by a continued series of elevatory movements, the Straits of
Gibraltar had become completely closed up, we might expect large and
level sandy steppes to surround both the Black Sea and Mediterranean,
like those occurring at present on the skirts of the Caspian and the Lake
of Aral. The geographical range of hundreds of aquatic species would be
thereby circumscribed, and that of hundreds of terrestrial plants and
animals extended.
A line of submarine volcanos crossing the channel of some strait, and
gradually choking it up with ashes and lava, might produce a new barrier
as effectually as a series of earthquakes; especially if thermal springs,
charged with carbonate of lime, silica, and other mineral ingredients,
should promote the rapid multiplication of corals and shells, and cement
them together with solid matter precipitated during the intervals between
eruptions. Suppose in this manner a stoppage to be caused of the Bahama
channel between the bank of that name and the coast of Florida.
This insignificant revolution, confined to a mere spot in the bottom of
the ocean, would, by diverting the main current of the Gulf stream, give
rise to extensive changes in the climate and distribution of animals and
plants inhabiting the northern hemisphere.
Illustration from the formation of new islands.—A repetition of elevatory
movements of earthquakes might continue over an area as extensive
as Europe, for thousands of ages, at the bottom of the ocean, in certain
regions, and produce no visible effects; whereas, if they should operate
in some shallow parts of the Pacific, amid the coral archipelagos,
they would soon give birth to a new continent. Hundreds of volcanic
islands may be thrown up, and become covered with vegetation, without
causing more than local fluctuations in the animate world; but if a chain
like the Aleutian archipelago, or the Kurile Isles, run for a distance of
many hundred miles, so as to form an almost uninterrupted communication
between two continents, or two distant islands, the migrations of
plants, birds, insects, and even of some quadrupeds, may cause, in a short
time, an extraordinary series of revolutions tending to augment the range
of some animals and plants, and to limit that of others. A new archipelago
might be formed in the Mediterranean, the Bay of Biscay, and a
thousand other places, and might produce less important events than one
rock which should rise up between Australia and Java, so placed that
winds and currents might cause an interchange of the plants, insects,
and birds.
From the wearing through of an isthmus.—If we turn from the igneous
to the aqueous agents, we find the same tendency to an irregular
rate of change, naturally connected with the strictest uniformity in the
energy of those causes. When the sea, for example, gradually encroaches
upon both sides of a narrow isthmus, as that of Sleswick, separating the
694
North Sea from the Baltic, where, as before stated, the cliffs on both the
opposite coasts are wasting away985, no material alteration results for
thousands of years, save only that there is a progressive conversion of a
small strip of land into water. A few feet only, or a few yards, are annually
removed; but if, at last, the partition should be broken down, and
the tides of the ocean should enter by a direct passage into the inland sea,
instead of going by a circuitous route through the Cattegat, a body of
salt water would sweep up as far as the Gulfs of Bothnia and Finland,
the waters of which are now brackish, or almost fresh; and this revolution
would be attended by the local annihilation of many species.
Similar consequences must have resulted on a small scale, when the
sea opened its way through the Isthmus of Staveren in the thirteenth
century, forming a union between an inland lake and the ocean, and
opening, in the course of one century, a shallow strait, more than half as
wide as the narrowest part of that which divides England from France.
Changes in physical geography which must occasion extinction of species.—It
will almost seem superfluous, after I have thus traced the important
modifications in the condition of living beings which flow from changes
of trifling extent, to argue that entire revolutions might be brought
about, if the climate and physical geography of the whole globe were
greatly altered. It has been stated, that species are in general local, some
being confined to extremely small spots, and depending for their existence
on a combination of causes, which, if they are to be met with elsewhere,
occur only in some very remote region. Hence it must happen that,
when the nature of these localities is changed, the species will perish;
for it will rarely happen that the cause which alters the character
of the district will afford new facilities to the species to establish itself
elsewhere.
African deserts.—If we attribute the origin of a great part of the desert
of Africa to the gradual progress of moving sands driven eastward by the
westerly winds, we may safely infer that a variety of species must have been
annihilated by this cause alone. The sand-flood has been inundating, from
time immemorial, some of the rich lands on the west of the Nile; and
we have only to multiply this effect a sufficient number of times in order
to understand how, in the lapse of ages, a whole group of terrestrial animals
and plants may become extinct.
The African desert, without including Bornou and Darfour, extends,
according to the calculation of Humboldt, over 194,000 square leagues;
an area nearly three times as great as that of France. In a small portion
of so vast a space, we may infer from analogy that there were many
peculiar species of plants and animals which must have been banished by
the sand, and their habitations invaded by the camel, and by birds and
insects formed for the arid sands.
There is evidently nothing in the nature of the catastrophe to favor
the escape of the former inhabitants to some adjoining province; nothing
695
to weaken, in the bordering lands, that powerful barrier against emigration—pre-occupancy.
Nor, even if the exclusion of a certain group of
species from a given tract were compensated by an extension of their
range over a new country, would that circumstance tend to the conservation
of species in general; for the extirpation would merely then be
transferred to the region so invaded. If it be imagined, for example, that
the aboriginal quadrupeds, birds, and other animals of Africa, emigrated
in consequence of the advance of drift-sand, and colonized Arabia, the
indigenous Arabian species must have given way before them, and have
been reduced in number or destroyed.
Let us next suppose that, in some central or more elevated parts of the
great African desert, the upheaving power of subterranean movements
should be exerted throughout an immense series of ages, accompanied, at
certain intervals, by volcanic eruptions, such as gave rise at once, in 1755,
to a mountain 1600 feet high, on the Mexican plateau. When the continued
repetition of these events had caused a mountain-chain, it is
obvious that a complete transformation in the state of the climate would
be brought about throughout a vast area.
We may imagine the summits of the new chain to rise so high as to
be covered, like Mount Atlas, for several thousand feet, with snow, during
a great part of the year. The melting of these snows, during the greatest
heat, would cause the rivers to swell in the season when the greatest
drought now prevails; the waters, moreover, derived from this source,
would always be of lower temperature than the surrounding atmosphere,
and would thus contribute to cool the climate. During the numerous
earthquakes and volcanic eruptions supposed to accompany the gradual
formation of the chain, there would be many floods caused by the bursting
of temporary lakes, and by the melting of snows by lava. These
inundations might deposit alluvial matter far and wide over the original
sands, as the country assumed varied shapes, and was modified again and
again by the moving power from below, and the aqueous erosion of the
surface above. At length the Sahara might be fertilized, irrigated by rivers
and streamlets intersecting it in every direction, and covered by jungle
and morasses; so that the animals and plants which now people Northern
Africa would disappear, and the region would gradually become fitted
for the reception of a population of species perfectly dissimilar in their
forms, habits, and organization.
There are always some peculiar and characteristic features in the physical
geography of each large division of the globe; and on these
peculiarities the state of animal and vegetable life is dependent. If,
therefore, we admit incessant fluctuations in the physical geography, we
must, at the same time, concede the successive extinction of terrestrial
and aquatic species to be part of the economy of our system. When
some great class of stations is in excess in certain latitudes, as, for example,
in wide savannahs, arid sands, lofty mountains, or inland seas, we find a
corresponding development of species adapted for such circumstances.
In North America, where there is a chain of vast inland lakes of fresh
696
water, we find an extraordinary abundance and variety of aquatic birds,
fresh-water fish, testacea, and small amphibious reptiles, fitted for such a
climate. The greater part of these would perish if the lakes were
destroyed,—an event that might be brought about by some of the least
of those important revolutions contemplated in geology. It might
happen that no fresh-water lakes of corresponding magnitude might then
exist on the globe; or that, if they occurred elsewhere, they might be
situated in New Holland, Southern Africa, Eastern Asia, or some region
so distant as to be quite inaccessible to the North American species; or
they might be situated within the tropics, in a climate uninhabitable by
creatures fitted for a temperate zone; or, finally, we may presume that
they would be pre-occupied by indigenous tribes.
A vivid description has been given by Mr. Darwin and Sir W. Parish
of the great droughts which have sometimes visited the Pampas of South
America, for three or four years in succession, during which an incredible
number of wild animals, cattle, horses, and birds, have perished from
want of food and water. Several hundred thousand animals were drowned
in the Parana alone, having rushed into the river to drink, and being
too much exhausted by hunger to escape.986 Such droughts are often
attended in South America and other hot climates by wide-spreading
conflagrations, caused by lightning, which fires the dried grass and brush-wood.
Thus quadrupeds, birds, insects, and other creatures, are destroyed
by myriads. How many species, both of the animal and vegetable world,
which once flourished in the country between the valley of the Parana
and the Straits of Magellan, may not have been annihilated, since the first
drought or first conflagration began!
To pursue this train of reasoning farther is unnecessary; the geologist
has only to reflect on what has been said of the habitations and stations
of organic beings in general, and to consider them in relation to those
effects which were contemplated in the second book, as resulting from
the igneous and aqueous causes now in action, and he will immediately
perceive that, amidst the vicissitudes of the earth's surface, species cannot
be immortal, but must perish, one after the other, like the individuals
which compose them. There is no possibility of escaping from this conclusion,
without resorting to some hypothesis as violent as that of
Lamarck, who imagined, as we have before seen, that species are each of
them endowed with indefinite powers of modifying their organization, in
conformity to the endless changes of circumstances to which they are
exposed.
Effects of a general Alteration in Climate on the Distribution of Species.
Some of the effects which must attend every general alteration of climate
are sufficiently peculiar to claim a separate consideration before
concluding the present chapter.
697
I have before stated that, during seasons of extraordinary severity,
many northern birds, and in some countries many quadrupeds, migrate
southwards. If these cold seasons were to become frequent, in consequence
of a gradual and general refrigeration of the atmosphere, such
migrations would be more and more regular, until, at length, many
animals, now confined to the arctic regions, would become the tenants
of the temperate zone; while the inhabitants of the temperate zone would
approach nearer to the equator. At the same time, many species previously
established on high mountains would begin to descend, in every
latitude, towards the middle regions; and those which were confined to
the flanks of mountains would make their way into the plains. Analogous
changes would also take place in the vegetable kingdom.
If, on the contrary, the heat of the atmosphere be on the increase, the
plants and animals of low grounds would ascend to higher levels, the
equatorial species would migrate into the temperate zone, and those of
the temperate into the arctic circle.
But although some species might thus be preserved, every great change
of climate must be fatal to many which can find no place of retreat when
their original habitations become unfit for them. For if the general temperature
be on the rise, then there is no cooler region whither the polar
species can take refuge; if it be on the decline, then the animals and
plants previously established between the tropics have no resource. Suppose
the general heat of the atmosphere to increase, so that even the
arctic region became too warm for the musk-ox, and rein-deer, it is clear
that they must perish; so if the torrid zone should lose so much of its
heat, by the progressive refrigeration of the earth's surface, as to be an
unfit habitation for apes, boas, bamboos, and palms, these tribes of animals
and plants, or, at least; most of the species now belonging to them,
would become extinct, for there would be no warmer latitudes for their
reception.
It will follow, therefore, that as often as the climates of the globe are
passing from the extreme of heat to that of cold—from the summer to
the winter of the great year before alluded to987—the migratory movement
will be directed constantly from the poles towards the equator; and for
this reason the species inhabiting parallel latitudes, in the northern and
southern hemispheres, must become widely different. For I assume, on
grounds before explained, that the original stock of each species is introduced
into one spot of the earth only, and, consequently, no species can
be at once indigenous in the arctic and antarctic circles.
But when, on the contrary, a series of changes in the physical geography
of the globe, or any other supposed cause, occasions an elevation of
the general temperature,—when there is a passage from the winter to one
of the vernal or summer seasons of the great cycle of climate,—then the
order of the migratory movement is inverted. The different species of
animals and plants direct their course from the equator towards the poles;
698
and the northern and southern hemispheres may become peopled to a
certain limited extent by identical species.
I say limited, because we cannot speculate on the entire transposition
of a group of animals and plants from tropical to polar latitudes, or the
reverse, as a probable or even possible event. We may believe the mean
annual temperature of one zone to be transferable to another, but we
know that the same climate cannot be so transferred. Whatever be the
general temperature of the earth's surface, comparative equability of heat
will characterize the tropical regions; while great periodical variations
will belong to the temperate, and still more to the polar latitudes. These,
and many other peculiarities connected with heat and light, depend on
fixed astronomical causes, such as the motion of the earth and its position
in relation to the sun, and not on those fluctuations of its surface which
may influence the general temperature.
Among many obstacles to such extensive transference of habitations,
we must not forget the immense lapse of time required, according to the
hypothesis before suggested, to bring about a considerable change in
climate. During a period so vast, the other cause of extirpation, before
enumerated, would exert so powerful an influence as to prevent all, save
a very few hardy species, from passing from equatorial to polar regions,
or from the tropics to the pole.988
But the power of accommodation to new circumstances is great in
certain species, and might enable many to pass from one zone to another,
if the mean annual heat of the atmosphere and the ocean were greatly
altered. To the marine tribes, especially, such a passage would be possible;
for they are less impeded in their migrations by barriers of land,
than are the terrestrial by the ocean. Add to this, that the temperature
of the ocean is much more uniform than that of the atmosphere investing
the land; so that we may easily suppose that most of the testacea, fish,
and other classes, might pass from the equatorial into the temperate
regions, if the mean temperature of those regions were transposed, although
a second expatriation of these species of tropical origin into the arctic and
antarctic circles would probably be impossible.
Let us now consider more particularly the effect of vicissitudes of
climate in causing one species to give way before the increasing numbers
of some other.
When temperature forms the barrier which arrests the progress of an
animal or plant in a particular direction, the individuals are fewer and
less vigorous as they approach the extreme confines of the geographical
range of the species. But these stragglers are ready to multiply rapidly
on the slightest increase or diminution of heat that may be favorable
to them, just as particular insects increase during a hot summer, and
certain plants and animals gain ground after a series of congenial
seasons.
In almost every district, especially if it be mountainous, there are a
699
variety of species the limits of whose habitations are conterminous, some
being unable to proceed farther without encountering too much heat,
others too much cold. Individuals, which are thus on the borders of the
regions proper to their respective species, are like the outposts of hostile
armies, ready to profit by every slight change of circumstances in their
favor, and to advance upon the ground occupied by their neighbors
and opponents.
The proximity of distinct climates produced by the inequalities of the
earth's surface, brings species possessing very different constitutions into
such immediate contact, that their naturalizations are very speedy whenever
opportunities of advancing present themselves. Many insects and
plants, for example, are common to low plains within the arctic circle,
and to lofty mountains in Scotland and other parts of Europe. If the
climate, therefore, of the polar regions were transferred to our own latitudes,
the species in question would immediately descend from these elevated
stations to overrun the low grounds. Invasions of this kind, attended
by the expulsion of the pre-occupants, are almost instantaneous,
because the change of temperature not only places the one species in a
more favorable position, but renders the others sickly and almost incapable
of defence.
These changes inconsistent with the theory of transmutation.—Lamarck,
when speculating on the transmutation of species, supposed every modification
in organization and instinct to be brought about slowly and insensibly
in an indefinite lapse of ages. But he does not appear to have
sufficiently considered how much every alteration in the physical condition
of the habitable surface changes the relations of a great number of co-existing
species, and that some of these would be ready instantly to avail
themselves of the slightest change in their favor, and to multiply to the
injury of others. Even if we thought it possible that the palm or the
elephant, which now flourish in equatorial regions, could ever learn to
bear the variable seasons of our temperate zone, or the rigors of an
arctic winter, we might with no less confidence affirm, that they must
perish before they had time to become habituated to such new circumstances.
That they would be displaced by other species as often as the
climate varied, may be inferred from the data before explained respecting
the local extermination of species produced by the multiplication of
others.
Suppose the climate of the highest part of the woody zone of Etna to
be transferred to the sea-shore of the base of the mountain, no botanist
would anticipate that the olive, lemon-tree, and prickly pear (Cactus
Opuntia) would be able to contend with the oak and chestnut, which
would begin forthwith to descend to a lower level; or that these last
would be able to stand their ground against the pine, which would also,
in the space of a few years, begin to occupy a lower position. We might
form some kind of estimate of the time which might be required for the
migrations of these plants; whereas we have no data for concluding that
any number of thousands of years would be sufficient for one step in the
700
pretended metamorphosis of one species into another, possessing distinct
attributes and qualities.
This argument is applicable not merely to climate, but to any other
cause of mutation. However slowly a lake may be converted into a
marsh, or a marsh into a meadow, it is evident that before the lacustrine
plants can acquire the power of living in marshes, or the marsh-plants
of living in a less humid soil, other species, already existing in the region,
and fitted for these several stations, will intrude and keep possession of
the ground. So, if a tract of salt water becomes fresh by passing through
every intermediate degree of brackishness, still the marine mollusks will
never be permitted to be gradually metamorphosed into fluviatile species;
because long before any such transformation can take place by slow and
insensible degrees, other tribes, already formed to delight in brackish or
fresh water, will avail themselves of the change in the fluid, and will,
each in their turn, monopolize the space.
It is idle, therefore, to dispute about the abstract possibility of the
conversion of one species into another, when there are known causes so
much more active in their nature, which must always intervene and prevent
the actual accomplishment of such conversions. A faint image of
the certain doom of a species less fitted to struggle with some new condition
in a region which it previously inhabited, and where it has to contend
with a more vigorous species, is presented by the extirpation of savage
tribes of men by the advancing colony of some civilized nation. In
this case the contest is merely between two different races—two varieties,
moreover, of a species which exceeds all others in its aptitude to accommodate
its habits to the most extraordinary variations of circumstances.
Yet few future events are more certain than the speedy extermination of
the Indians of North America and the savages of New Holland in the
course of a few centuries, when these tribes will be remembered only in
poetry or history.

Concluding remarks.—We often hear astonishment expressed at the
disappearance from the earth in times comparatively modern of many
small as well as large animals, the remains of which have been found in
a fossil state, under circumstances implying that neither any great geographical
revolution, nor the exterminating influence of man has intervened
to account for their extinction. But in all such cases we should
inquire whether we are sufficiently acquainted with the numerous and
complicated conditions on which the perpetuation of each species depends,
to entitle us to wonder if it should be suddenly cut off.
Mr. Darwin, when calling attention to the fact that the horse, megatherium,
megalonyx, and many contemporary Mammalia, had perished
in South America after that continent had acquired its present configuration,
and when, if we may judge by the Testacea, the climate very
nearly resembled the present, observes, "that in the living creation one
species is often extremely rare in a given region, while another of the
same genus and with closely allied habits is exceedingly common. A
701
zoologist familiar with such phenomena, if asked to explain them, usually
replies, that some slight difference in climate, food, or the number
of its enemies, must determine the relative strength of the two species
in question, although we may be unable to point out the precise manner
of the action of the check. We are, therefore, driven to the conclusion,
that causes generally quite inappreciable by us determine whether
a given species shall be abundant or scanty in numbers. Why,
then, should we feel astonishment if the rarity is occasionally carried a
step farther,—to extinction?"989
</div></body></text></TEI>