<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="101">CHAPTER VIII.
Theory of Definite, Reciprocal, and Multiple
Proportions.

Sect. 1.—Prelude to the Atomic
Theory, and its Publication by Dalton.
THE general laws of chemical
combination announced by Mr. Dalton are truths of the highest
importance in the science, and are now nowhere contested; but the view
of matter as constituted of atoms, which he has employed in
conveying those laws, and in expressing his opinion of their cause, is
neither so important nor so certain. In the place which I here assign
to his discovery, as one of the great events of the history of
chemistry, I speak only of the law of phenomena, the rules
which govern the quantities in which elements combine.
This law may be considered as consisting of three parts, according
to the above description of it;—that elements combine in
definite proportions;—that these determining
proportions operate reciprocally;—and that when,
between the same elements, several combining proportions occur, they
are related as multiples.
That elements combine in certain definite proportions of quantity,
and in no other, was implied, as soon as it was supposed that chemical
compounds had any definite properties. Those who first attempted to
establish regular formulæ44 for the constitution of salts,
minerals, and 286
other compounds, assumed, as the basis of this process, that the
elements in different specimens had the same proportion. Wenzel, in
1777, published his Lehre von der Verwandschaft der Körper; or,
Doctrine of the Affinities of Bodies; in which he gave many
good and accurate analyses. His work, it is said, never grew into
general notice. Berthollet, as we have already stated, maintained that chemical
compounds were not definite; but this controversy took place at a
later period. It ended in the establishment of the doctrine, that
there is, for each combination, only one proportion of the elements,
or at most only two or three.
44 Thomson, Hist. Chem. vol.
ii. p. 279.
Not only did Wenzel, by his very attempt, presume the first law of
chemical composition, the definiteness of the proportions, but he was
also led, by his results, to the second rule, that they are
reciprocal. For he found that when two neutral salts
decompose each other, the resulting salts are also neutral. The
neutral character of the salts shows that they are definite compounds;
and when the two elements of the one salt, P and s, are
presented to those of the other, B and n, if P be
in such quantity as to combine definitely with n, B will
also combine definitely with s.45
45 I am told that Wenzel (whose book
I have not seen), though he adduces many cases in which double
decomposition gives neutral salts, does not express the proposition in
a general form, nor use letters in expressing it.
Views similar to those of Wenzel were also published by Jeremiah
Benjamin Richter46 in 1792, in his Anfangsgründe der
Stöchyometrie, oder Messkunst Chymischer Elemente, (Principles
of the Measure of Chemical Elements) in which he took the law,
just stated, of reciprocal proportions, as the basis of his
researches, and determined the numerical quantities of the common
bases and acids which would saturate each other. It is clear that, by
these steps, the two first of our three rules may be considered as
fully developed. The change of general views which was at this time
going on, probably prevented chemists from feeling so much interest as
they might have done otherwise, in these details; the French and
English chemists, in particular, were fully employed with their own
researches and controversies.
46 Thomson, Hist. Chem. vol.
ii. p. 283.
Thus the rules which had already been published by Wenzel and
Richter had attracted so little notice, that we can hardly consider
Mr. Dalton as having been anticipated by those writers, when, in 1803,
he began to communicate his views on the chemical constitution of
287 bodies; these
views being such as to include both these two rules in their most
general form, and further, the rule, at that time still more new to
chemists, of multiple proportions. He conceived bodies as
composed of atoms of their constituent elements, grouped, either one
and one, or one and two, or one and three, and so on. Thus, if
C represent an atom of carbon and O one of oxygen, O
C will be an atom of carbonic oxide, and O C O an
atom of carbonic acid; and hence it follows, that while both
these bodies have a definite quantity of oxygen to a given quantity of
carbon, in the latter substance this quantity is double of
what it is in the former.
The consideration of bodies as consisting of compound atoms, each
of these being composed of elementary atoms, naturally led to this law
of multiple proportions. In this mode of viewing bodies, Mr. Dalton
had been preceded (unknown to himself) by Mr. Higgins, who, in 1789,
published47 his Comparative View of the
Phlogistic and Antiphlogistic Theories. He there says,48 “That in volatile vitriolic acid, a
single ultimate particle of sulphur is united only to a single
particle of dephlogisticated air; and that in perfect vitriolic acid,
every single particle of sulphur is united to two of dephlogisticated
air, being the quantity necessary to saturation;” and he reasons in
the same manner concerning the constitution of water, and the
compounds of nitrogen and oxygen. These observations of Higgins were,
however, made casually, and not followed out, and cannot affect
Dalton’s claim to original merit.
47 Turner’s Chem. p.
217.
48 P. 36 and 37.
Mr. Dalton’s generalization was first suggested49 during his examination of olefiant gas
and carburetted hydrogen gas; and was asserted generally, on the
strength of a few facts, being, as it were, irresistibly recommended
by the clearness and simplicity which the notion possessed. Mr. Dalton
himself represented the compound atoms of bodies by symbols, which
professed to exhibit the arrangement of the elementary atoms in space
as well as their numerical proportion; and he attached great
importance to this part of his scheme. It is clear, however, that this
part of his doctrine is not essential to that numerical comparison of
the law with facts, on which its establishment rests. These
hypothetical configurations of atoms have no value till they are
confirmed by corresponding facts, such as the optical or crystalline
properties of bodies may perhaps one day furnish.
49 Thomson, vol. ii. p. 291. 288
Sect. 2.—Reception and Confirmation of the Atomic
Theory.
In order to give a sketch of
the progress of the Atomic Theory into general reception, we cannot do
better than borrow our information mainly from Dr. Thomson, who was
one of the earliest converts and most effective promulgators of the
doctrine. Mr. Dalton, at the time when he conceived his theory, was a
teacher of mathematics at Manchester, in circumstances which might
have been considered narrow, if he himself had been less simple in his
manner of life, and less moderate in his worldly views. His
experiments were generally made with apparatus of which the simplicity
and cheapness corresponded to the rest of his habits. In 1804, he was
already in possession of his atomic theory, and explained it to Dr.
Thomson, who visited him at that time. It was made known to the
chemical world in Dr. Thomson’s Chemistry, in 1807; and in
Dalton’s own System of Chemistry (1808) the leading ideas of it
were very briefly stated. Dr. Wollaston’s memoir, “on superacid and
subacid salts,” which appeared in the Philosophical
Transactions for 1808, did much to secure this theory a place in
the estimation of chemists. Here the author states, that he had
observed, in various salts, the quantities of acid combined with the
base in the neutral and in the superacid salts to be as one to two:
and he says that, thinking it likely this law might obtain generally
in such compounds, it was his design to have pursued this subject,
with the hope of discovering the cause to which so regular a relation
may be ascribed. But he adds, that this appears to be superfluous
after the publication of Dalton’s theory by Dr. Thomson, since all
such facts are but special cases of the general law. We cannot but
remark here, that the scrupulous timidity of Wollaston was probably
the only impediment to his anticipating Dalton in the publication of
the rule of multiple proportions; and the forwardness to generalize,
which belongs to the character of the latter, justly secured him, in
this instance, the name of the discoverer of this law. The rest of the
English chemists soon followed Wollaston and Thomson, though Davy for
some time resisted. They objected, indeed, to Dalton’s assumption of
atoms, and, to avoid this hypothetical step, Wollaston used the phrase
chemical equivalents, and Davy the word proportions, for
the numbers which expressed Dalton’s atomic weights. We may, however,
venture to say that the term “atom” is the most convenient, and it
need not be understood as claiming our assent to the hypothesis of
indivisible molecules. 289
As Wollaston and Dalton were thus arriving independently at the
same result in England, other chemists, in other countries, were,
unknown to each other, travelling towards the same point.
In 1807, Berzelius,50 intending to publish a system of
chemistry, went through several works little read, and among others
the treatises of Richter. He was astonished, he tells us, at the light
which was there thrown upon composition and decomposition, and which
had never been turned to profit. He was led to a long train of
experimental research, and, when he received information of Dalton’s
ideas concerning multiple proportions, he found, in his own collection
of analyses, a full confirmation of this theory.
50 Berz. Chem. B. iii. p.
27.
Some of the Germans, indeed, appear discontented with the partition
of reputation which has taken place with respect to the Theory of
Definite Proportions. One51 of them says, “Dalton has only done
this;—he has wrapt up the good Richter (whom he knew; compare
Schweigger, T, older series, vol. x., p. 381;) in a ragged suit,
patched together of atoms; and now poor Richter comes back to his own
country in such a garb, like Ulysses, and is not recognized.” It is to
be recollected, however, that Richter says nothing of multiple
proportions.
51 Marx. Gesch. der Cryst. p.
202.
The general doctrine of the atomic theory is now firmly established
over the whole of the chemical world. There remain still several
controverted points, as, for instance, whether the atomic weights of
all elements are exact multiples of the atomic weight of hydrogen. Dr.
Prout advanced several instances in which this appeared to be true,
and Dr. Thomson has asserted the law to be of universal application.
But, on the other hand, Berzelius and Dr. Turner declare that this
hypothesis is at variance with the results of the best analyses. Such
controverted points do not belong to our history, which treats only of
the progress of scientific truths already recognized by all competent
judges.
Though Dalton’s discovery was soon generally employed, and
universally spoken of with admiration, it did not bring to him
anything but barren praise, and he continued in the humble employment
of which we have spoken, when his fame had filled Europe, and his name
become a household word in the laboratory. After some years he was
appointed a corresponding member of the Institute of France; which may
be considered as a European recognition of the importance 290 of what he had done;
and, in 1826, two medals for the encouragement of science having been
placed at the disposal of the Royal Society by the King of England,
one of them was assigned to Dalton, “for his development of the atomic
theory.” In 1833, at the meeting of the British Association for the
Advancement of Science, which was held in Cambridge, it was announced
that the King had bestowed upon him a pension of 150l.; at the
preceding meeting at Oxford, that university had conferred upon him
the degree of Doctor of Laws, a step the more remarkable, since he
belonged to the sect of Quakers. At all the meetings of the British
Association he has been present, and has always been surrounded by the
reverence and admiration of all who feel any sympathy with the
progress of science. May he long remain among us thus to remind us of
the vast advance which Chemistry owes to him!
[2nd Ed.] [Soon after I wrote these expressions of hope, the period
of Dalton’s sojourn among us terminated. He died on the 27th of July,
1844, aged 78.
His fellow-townsmen, the inhabitants of Manchester, who had so long
taken a pride in his residence among them, soon after his death came
to a determination to perpetuate his memory by establishing in his
honor a Professor of Chemistry at Manchester.]
Sect. 3.—The Theory of
Volumes.—Gay-Lussac.
The atomic theory, at the
very epoch of its introduction into France, received a modification in
virtue of a curious discovery then made. Soon after the publication of
Dalton’s system, Gay-Lussac and Humboldt found a rule for the
combination of substances, which includes that of Dalton as far as it
goes, but extends to combinations of gases only. This law is the
theory of volumes; namely, that gases unite together by
volume in very simple and definite proportions. Thus water is
composed exactly of 100 measures of oxygen and 200 measures of
hydrogen. And since these simple ratios 1 and 1, 1 and 2, 1 and 3,
alone prevail in such combinations, it may easily be shown that laws
like Dalton’s law of multiple proportions, must obtain in such cases
as he considered.
[2nd Ed.] [M. Schröder, of Mannheim, has endeavored to extend to
solids a law in some degree resembling Gay-Lussac’s law of the volumes
of gases. According to him, the volumes of the chemical equivalents
291 of simple
substances and their compounds are as whole numbers.52 MM. Kopp, Playfair, and Joule have
labored in the same field.]
52 Die molecular-volume der
Chemischen Verbindungen in festen und flüssingen Zustande,
1843.
I cannot now attempt to trace other bearings and developments of
this remarkable discovery. I hasten on to the last generalization of
chemistry; which presents to us chemical forces under a new aspect,
and brings us back to the point from which we departed in commencing
the history of this science.
</div></body></text></TEI>