<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Chambers Robert</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="12">p.
145GENERAL CONSIDERATIONS
RESPECTING
THE ORIGIN OF THE ANIMATED TRIBES.
Thus concludes the wondrous chapter
of the earth’s history which is told by geology.  It
takes up our globe at the period when its original incandescent
state had nearly ceased; conducts it through what we have every
reason to believe were vast, or at least very considerable,
spaces of time, in the course of which many superficial changes
took place, and vegetable and animal life was gradually
developed; and drops it just at the point when man was apparently
about to enter on the scene.  The compilation of such a
history, from materials of so extraordinary a character, and the
powerful nature of the evidence which these materials afford, are
calculated to excite our admiration, and the result must be
allowed to exalt the dignity of science, as a product of
man’s industry and his reason.
If there is any thing more than another impressed on our minds
by the course of the geological history, it is, that the same
laws and conditions of nature now apparent to us have existed
throughout the whole time, though the operation of some of these
laws may now be less conspicuous than in the early ages, from
some of the conditions having come to a settlement and a
close.  That seas have flowed and ebbed, and winds disturbed
their surfaces, in the time of the secondary rocks, we have proof
on the yet preserved surfaces of the sands which constituted
margins of the seas in those days.  Even the fall of
wind-slanted rain is evidenced on the same tablets.  The
washing down of detached matter from elevated grounds, which we
see rivers constantly engaged in at the present time, and which
is daily shallowing the seas adjacent to their mouths, only
appears to have proceeded on a greater scale in earlier
epochs.  The volcanic subterranean force, which we see
belching forth lavas on the sides of mountains, and throwing up
new elevations by land and sea, was only more powerfully
operative in distant ages.  To turn to organic nature,
vegetation seems to have proceeded then exactly as now.  The
very alternations of the seasons has been read in unmistakable
characters in sections of the trees of those days, precisely as
it might be read in a section of a tree cut down yesterday. 
The system of prey amongst animals flourished throughout the
whole of the pre-human period; and the adaptation of all plants
and animals to their respective spheres of existence was as
perfect in those early ages as it is still.
But, as has been observed, the operation of the laws may be
modified by conditions.  At one early age, if there was any
dry land at all, it was perhaps enveloped in an atmosphere unfit
for the existence of terrestrial animals, and which had to go
though some changes before that condition was altered.  In
the carbonigenous era, dry land seems to have consisted only of
clusters of islands, and the temperature was much above what now
obtains at the same places.  Volcanic forces, and perhaps
also the disintegrating power, seem to have been on the decrease
since the first, or we have at least long enjoyed an exemption
from such paroxysms of the former, as appear to have prevailed at
the close of the coal formation in England and throughout the
tertiary era.  The surface has also undergone a gradual
progress by which it has become always more and more variegated,
and thereby fitted for the residence of a higher class of
animals.
In pursuing the progress of the development of both plants and
animals upon the globe, we have seen an advance in both cases,
along the line leading to the higher forms of organization. 
Amongst plants, we have first sea-weeds, afterwards land plants;
and amongst these the simpler (cellular and cryptogamic) before
the more complex.  In the department of zoology, we see
zoophytes, radiata, mollusca, articulata, existing for ages
before there were any higher forms.  The first step forward
gives fishes, the humblest class of the vertebrata; and,
moreover, the earliest fishes partake of the character of the
next lowest sub-kingdom, the articulata.  Afterwards come
land animals, of which the first are reptiles, universally
allowed to be the type next in advance from fishes, and to be
connected with these by the links of an insensible
gradation.  From reptiles we advance to birds, and thence to
mammalia, which are commenced by marsupialia, acknowledgedly low
forms in their class.  That there is thus a progress of some
kind, the most superficial glance at the geological history is
sufficient to convince us.  Indeed the doctrine of the
gradation of animal forms has received a remarkable support from
the discoveries of this science, as several types formerly
wanting to a completion of the series have been found in a fossil
state. [149]
It is scarcely less evident, from the geological record, that
the progress of organic life has observed some correspondence
with the progress of physical conditions on the surface.  We
do not know for certain that the sea, at the time when it
supported radiated, molluscous, and articulated families, was
incapable of supporting fishes; but causes for such a limitation
are far from inconceivable.  The huge saurians appear to
have been precisely adapted to the low muddy coasts and sea
margins of the time when they flourished.  Marsupials appear
at the time when the surface was generally in that flat,
imperfectly variegated state in which we find Australia, the
region where they now live in the greatest abundance, and one
which has no higher native mammalian type.  Finally, it was
not till the land and sea had come into their present relations,
and the former, in its principal continents, had acquired the
irregularity of surface necessary for man, that man
appeared.  We have likewise seen reason for supposing that
land animals could not have lived before the carbonigenous era,
owing to the great charge of carbonic acid gas presumed to have
been contained in the atmosphere down to that time.  The
surplus of this having gone, as M. Brogniart suggests, to form
the vegetation, whose ruins became coal, and the air being thus
brought to its present state, land animals immediately
appeared.  So also, sea-plants were at first the only
specimens of vegetation, because there appears to have been no
place where other plants could be produced or supported. 
Land vegetation followed, at first simple, afterwards complex,
probably in conformity with an advance of the conditions required
by the higher class of plants.  In short, we see everywhere
throughout the geological history, strong traces of a parallel
advance of the physical conditions and the organic forms.
In examining the fossils of the lower marine creation, with a
reference to the kind of rock in connexion, with which they are
found, it is observed that some strata are attended by a much
greater abundance of both species and individuals than
others.  They abound most in calcareous rocks, which is
precisely what might be expected, since lime is necessary for the
formation of the shells of the mollusks and articulata, and the
hard substance of the crinoidea and corals; next in the
carboniferous series; next in the tertiary; next in the new red
sandstone; next in slates; and lastly, least of all, in the
primary rocks. [151]  This may have been the case
without regard to the origination of new species, but more
probably it was otherwise; or why, for instance, should the
polypiferous zoophyta be found almost exclusively in the
limestones?  There are, indeed, abundant appearances as if,
throughout all the changes of the surface, the various kinds of
organic life invariably pressed in, immediately on the
specially suitable conditions arising, so that no place which
could support any form of organic being might be left for any
length of time unoccupied.  Nor is it less remarkable how
various species are withdrawn from the earth, when the proper
conditions for their particular existence are changed.  The
trilobite, of which fifty species existed during the earlier
formations, was extirpated before the secondary had commenced,
and appeared no more.  The ammonite does not appear above
the chalk.  The species, and even genera of all the early
radiata and mollusks were exchanged for others long ago. 
Not one species of any creature which flourished before the
tertiary (Ehrenberg’s infusoria excepted) now exists; and
of the mammalia which arose during that series, many forms are
altogether gone, while of others we have now only kindred
species.  Thus to find not only frequent additions to the
previously existing forms, but frequent withdrawals of forms
which had apparently become inappropriate—a constant
shifting as well as advance—is a fact calculated very
forcibly to arrest attention.
A candid consideration of all these circumstances can scarcely
fail to introduce into our minds a somewhat different idea of
organic creation from what has hitherto been generally
entertained.  That God created animated beings, as well as
the terraqueous theatre of their being, is a fact so powerfully
evidenced, and so universally received, that I at once take it
for granted.  But in the particulars of this so highly
supported idea, we surely here see cause for some
re-consideration.  It may now be inquired,—In what way
was the creation of animated beings effected?  The ordinary
notion may, I think, be not unjustly described as
this,—that the Almighty author produced the progenitors of
all existing species by some sort of personal or immediate
exertion.  But how does this notion comport with what we
have seen of the gradual advance of species, from the humblest to
the highest?  How can we suppose an immediate exertion of
this creative power at one time to produce zoophytes, another
time to add a few marine mollusks, another to bring in one or two
conchifers, again to produce crustaceous fishes, again perfect
fishes, and so on to the end?  This would surely be to take
a very mean view of the Creative Power—to, in short,
anthropomorphize it, or reduce it to some such character as that
borne by the ordinary proceedings of mankind.  And yet this
would be unavoidable; for that the organic creation was thus
progressive through a long space of time, rests on evidence which
nothing can overturn or gainsay.  Some other idea must then
be come to with regard to the mode in which the Divine
Author proceeded in the organic creation.  Let us seek in
the history of the earth’s formation for a new suggestion
on this point.  We have seen powerful evidence, that the
construction of this globe and its associates, and inferentially
that of all the other globes of space, was the result, not of any
immediate or personal exertion on the part of the Deity, but of
natural laws which are expressions of his will.  What is to
hinder our supposing that the organic creation is also a result
of natural laws, which are in like manner an expression of his
will?  More than this, the fact of the cosmical arrangements
being an effect of natural laws is a powerful argument for the
organic arrangements being so likewise, for how can we suppose
that the august Being who brought all these countless worlds into
form by the simple establishment of a natural principle flowing
from his mind, was to interfere personally and specially on every
occasion when a new shell-fish or reptile was to be ushered into
existence on one of these worlds?  Surely this idea
is too ridiculous to be for a moment entertained.
It will be objected that the ordinary conceptions of Christian
nations on this subject are directly derived from Scripture, or,
at least, are in conformity with it.  If they were clearly
and unequivocally supported by Scripture, it may readily be
allowed that there would be a strong objection to the reception
of any opposite hypothesis.  But the fact is, however
startling the present announcement of it may be, that the first
chapter of the Mosaic record is not only not in harmony with the
ordinary ideas of mankind respecting cosmical and organic
creation, but is opposed to them, and only in accordance with the
views here taken.  When we carefully peruse it with awakened
minds, we find that all the procedure is represented primarily
and pre-eminently as flowing from commands and expressions of
will, not from direct acts.  Let there be
light—let there be a firmament—let the dry land
appear—let the earth bring forth grass, the herb, the
tree—let the waters bring forth the moving creature that
hath life—let the earth bring forth the living creature
after his kind—these are the terms in which the principal
acts are described.  The additional expressions,—God
made the firmament—God made the beast of the earth,
&c., occur subordinately, and only in a few instances; they
do not necessarily convey a different idea of the mode of
creation, and indeed only appear as alternative phrases, in the
usual duplicative manner of Eastern narrative.  Keeping this
in view, the words used in a subsequent place, “God
formed man in his own image,” cannot well be
understood as implying any more than what was implied
before,—namely, that man was produced in consequence of an
expression of the Divine will to that effect.  Thus, the
scriptural objection quickly vanishes, and the prevalent ideas
about the organic creation appear only as a mistaken inference
from the text, formed at a time when man’s ignorance
prevented him from drawing therefrom a just conclusion.  At
the same time, I freely own that I do not think it right to
adduce the Mosaic record, either in objection to, or support of
any natural hypothesis, and this for many reasons, but
particularly for this, that there is not the least appearance of
an intention in that book to give philosophically exact views of
nature.
To a reasonable mind the Divine attributes must appear, not
diminished or reduced in any way, by supposing a creation by law,
but infinitely exalted.  It is the narrowest of all views of
the Deity, and characteristic of a humble class of intellects, to
suppose him acting constantly in particular ways for particular
occasions.  It, for one thing, greatly detracts from his
foresight, the most undeniable of all the attributes of
Omnipotence.  It lowers him towards the level of our own
humble intellects.  Much more worthy of him it surely is, to
suppose that all things have been commissioned by him from the
first, though neither is he absent from a particle of the current
of natural affairs in one sense, seeing that the whole system is
continually supported by his providence.  Even in human
affairs, if I may be allowed to adopt a familiar illustration,
there is a constant progress from specific action for particular
occasions, to arrangements which, once established, shall
continue to answer for a great multitude of occasions.  Such
plans the enlightened readily form for themselves, and conceive
as being adopted by all who have to attend to a multitude of
affairs, while the ignorant suppose every act of the greatest
public functionary to be the result of some special consideration
and care on his part alone.  Are we to suppose the Deity
adopting plans which harmonize only with the modes of procedure
of the less enlightened of our race?  Those who would object
to the hypothesis of a creation by the intervention of law, do
not perhaps consider how powerful an argument in favour of the
existence of God is lost by rejecting this doctrine.  When
all is seen to be the result of law, the idea of an Almighty
Author becomes irresistible, for the creation of a law for an
endless series of phenomena—an act of intelligence above
all else that we can conceive—could have no other
imaginable source, and tells, moreover, as powerfully for a
sustaining as for an originating power.  On this point a
remark of Dr. Buckland seems applicable: “If the properties
adopted by the elements at the moment of their creation adapted
them beforehand to the infinity of complicated useful purposes
which they have already answered, and may have still farther to
answer, under many dispensations of the material world, such an
aboriginal constitution, so far from superseding an intelligent
agent, would only exalt our conceptions of the consummate skill
and power that could comprehend such an infinity of future uses
under future systems, in the original groundwork of his
creation.”
A late writer, in a work embracing a vast amount of
miscellaneous knowledge, but written in a dogmatic style, argues
at great length for the doctrine of more immediate exertions on
the part of the Deity in the works of his creation.  One of
the most striking of his illustrations is as
follows:—“The coral polypi, united by a common animal
bond, construct a defined form in stone; many kinds construct
many forms.  An allotted instinct may permit each polypus to
construct its own cell, but there is no superintending one to
direct the pattern, nor can the workers unite by consultation for
such an end.  There is no recipient for an instinct by which
the pattern might be constructed.  It is God alone,
therefore, who is the architect; and for this end, consequently,
he must dispose of every new polypus required to continue the
pattern, in a new and peculiar position, which the animal could
not have discovered by itself.  Yet more, millions of these
blind workers unite their works to form an island, which is also
wrought out according to a constant general pattern, and of a
very peculiar nature, though the separate coral works are
numerously diverse.  Still less, then, here is an instinct
possible.  The Great Architect himself must execute what he
planned, in each case equally.  He uses these little and
senseless animals as hands; but they are hands which himself must
direct.  He must direct each one everywhere, and therefore
he is ever acting.” [159]  This is a
most notable example of a dangerous kind of reasoning.  It
is now believed that corals have a general life and sensation
throughout the whole mass, residing in the nervous tissue which
envelops them; consequently, there is nothing more wonderful in
their determinate general forms than in those of other
animals.
It may here be remarked that there is in our doctrine that
harmony in all the associated phenomena which generally marks
great truths.  First, it agrees, as we have seen, with the
idea of planet-creation by natural law.  Secondly, upon this
supposition, all that geology tells us of the succession of
species appears natural and intelligible.  Organic life
presses in, as has been remarked, wherever there was room
and encouragement for it, the forms being always such as suited
the circumstances, and in a certain relation to them, as, for
example, where the limestone-forming seas produced an abundance
of corals, crinoidea, and shell-fish.  Admitting for a
moment a re-origination of species after a cataclysm, as has been
surmised by some geologists, though the hypothesis is always
becoming less and less tenable, it harmonizes with nothing so
well as the idea of a creation by law.  The more solitary
commencements of species, which would have been the most
inconceivably paltry exercise for an immediately creative power,
are sufficiently worthy of one operating by laws.
It is also to be observed, that the thing to be accounted for
is not merely the origination of organic being upon this little
planet, third of a series which is but one of hundreds of
thousands of series, the whole of which again form but one
portion of an apparently infinite globe-peopled space, where all
seems analogous.  We have to suppose, that every one of
these numberless globes is either a theatre of organic being, or
in the way of becoming so.  This is a conclusion which every
addition to our knowledge makes only the more irresistible. 
Is it conceivable, as a fitting mode of exercise for creative
intelligence, that it should be constantly moving from one sphere
to another, to form and plant the various species which may be
required in each situation at particular times?  Is such an
idea accordant with our general conception of the dignity, not to
speak of the power, of the Great Author?  Yet such is the
notion which we must form, if we adhere to the doctrine of
special exercise.  Let us see, on the other hand, how the
doctrine of a creation by law agrees with this expanded view of
the organic world.
Unprepared as most men may be for such an announcement, there
can be no doubt that we are able, in this limited sphere, to form
some satisfactory conclusions as to the plants and animals of
those other spheres which move at such immense distances from
us.  Suppose that the first persons of an early nation who
made a ship and ventured to sea in it, observed, as they sailed
along, a set of objects which they had never before
seen—namely, a fleet of other ships—would they not
have been justified in supposing that those ships were occupied,
like their own, by human beings possessing hands to row and
steer, eyes to watch the signs of the weather, intelligence to
guide them from one place to another—in short, beings in
all respects like themselves, or only shewing such differences as
they knew to be producible by difference of climate and habits of
life.  Precisely in this manner we can speculate on the
inhabitants of remote spheres.  We see that matter has
originally been diffused in one mass, of which the spheres are
portions.  Consequently, inorganic matter must be presumed
to be everywhere the same, although probably with differences in
the proportions of ingredients in different globes, and also some
difference of conditions.  Out of a certain number of the
elements of inorganic matter are composed organic bodies, both
vegetable and animal; such must be the rule in Jupiter and in
Sirius, as it is here.  We, therefore, are all but certain
that herbaceous and ligneous fibre, that flesh and blood, are the
constituents of the organic beings of all those spheres which are
as yet seats of life.  Gravitation we see to be an
all-pervading principle: therefore there must be a relation
between the spheres and their respective organic occupants, by
virtue of which they are fixed, as far as necessary, on the
surface.  Such a relation, of course, involves details as to
the density and elasticity of structure, as well as size, of the
organic tenants, in proportion to the gravity of the respective
planets—peculiarities, however, which may quite well
consist with the idea of a universality of general types, to
which we are about to come.  Electricity we also see to be
universal; if, therefore, it be a principle concerned in life and
in mental action, as science strongly suggests, life and mental
action must everywhere be of one general character.  We come
to comparatively a matter of detail, when we advert to heat and
light; yet it is important to consider that these are universal
agents, and that, as they bear marked relations to organic life
and structure on earth, they may be presumed to do so in other
spheres also.  The considerations as to light are
particularly interesting, for, on our globe, the structure of one
important organ, almost universally distributed in the animal
kingdom, is in direct and precise relation to it.  Where
there is light there will be eyes, and these, in other spheres,
will be the same in all respects as the eyes of tellurian
animals, with only such differences as may be necessary to accord
with minor peculiarities of condition and of situation.  It
is but a small stretch of the argument to suppose that, one
conspicuous organ of a large portion of our animal kingdom being
thus universal, a parity in all the other organs—species
for species, class for class, kingdom for kingdom—is highly
likely, and that thus the inhabitants of all the other globes of
space bear not only a general, but a particular resemblance to
those of our own.
Assuming that organic beings are thus spread over all space,
the idea of their having all come into existence by the operation
of laws everywhere applicable, is only conformable to that
principle, acknowledged to be so generally visible in the affairs
of Providence, to have all done by the employment of the smallest
possible amount of means.  Thus, as one set of laws produced
all orbs and their motions and geognostic arrangements, so one
set of laws overspread them all with life.  The whole
productive or creative arrangements are therefore in perfect
unity.</div></body></text></TEI>