<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol I</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1794</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="2">SECT. II.
EXPLANATIONS AND DEFINITIONS.

I. Outline of the animal
  economy.—II. 1. Of the sensorium. 2. Of the brain and nervous medulla. 3. A nerve. 4.
  A muscular fibre. 5. The immediate
  organs of sense. 6. The external organs
  of sense. 7. An idea or sensual
  motion. 8. Perception. 9. Sensation. 10. Recollection and suggestion. 11. Habit, causation, association,
  catenation. 12. Reflex ideas. 13. Stimulus defined.




As some explanations and definitions will be necessary in the
  prosecution of the work, the reader is troubled with them in this place,
  and is intreated to keep them in his mind as he proceeds, and to take
  them for granted, till an apt opportunity occurs to evince their truth;
  to which I shall premise a very short outline of the animal economy.



I.—1. The
  nervous system has its origin from the brain, and is distributed to every
  part of the body. Those nerves, which serve the senses, principally arise
  from that part of the brain, which is lodged in the head; and those,
  which serve the purposes of muscular motion, principally arise from that
  part of the brain, which is lodged in the neck and back, and which is
  erroneously called the spinal marrow. The ultimate fibrils of these
  nerves terminate in the immediate organs of sense and muscular fibres,
  and if a ligature be put on any part of their passage from the head or
  spine, all motion and perception cease in the parts beneath the
  ligature.
2. The longitudinal muscular fibres compose
  the locomotive muscles, whose contractions move the bones of the limbs
  and trunk, to which their extremities are attached. The annular or spiral
  muscular fibres compose the vascular muscles, which constitute the
  intestinal canal, the arteries, veins, glands, and absorbent vessels.
3. The immediate organs of sense, as the
  retina of the eye, probably consist of moving fibrils, with a power of
  contraction similar to that of the larger muscles above described.
4. The cellular membrane consists of cells,
  which resemble those of a sponge, communicating with each other, and
  connecting together all the other parts of the body.
5. The arterial system consists of the
  aortal and the pulmonary artery, which are attended through their whole
  course with their correspondent veins. The pulmonary artery receives the
  blood from the right chamber of the heart, and carries it to the minute
  extensive ramifications of the lungs, where it is exposed to the action
  of the air on a surface equal to that of the whole external skin, through
  the thin moist coats of those vessels, which are spread on the air-cells,
  which constitute the minute terminal ramifications of the wind-pipe. Here
  the blood changes its colour from a dark red to a bright scarlet. It is
  then collected by the branches of the pulmonary vein, and conveyed to the
  left chamber of the heart.
6. The aorta is another large artery, which
  receives the blood from the left chamber of the heart, after it has been
  thus aerated in the lungs, and conveys it by ascending and descending
  branches to every other part of the system; the extremities of this
  artery terminate either in glands, as the salivary glands, lacrymal
  glands, &c. or in capillary vessels, which are probably less
  involuted glands; in these some fluid, as saliva, tears, perspiration,
  are separated from the blood; and the remainder of the blood is absorbed
  or drank up by branches of veins correspondent to the branches of the
  artery; which are furnished with valves to prevent its return; and is
  thus carried back, after having again changed its colour to a dark red,
  to the right chamber of the heart. The circulation of the blood in the
  liver differs from this general system; for the veins which drink up the
  refluent blood from those arteries, which are spread on the bowels and
  mesentery, unite into a trunk in the liver, and form a kind of artery,
  which is branched into the whole substance of the liver, and is called
  the vena portarum; and from which the bile is separated by the numerous
  hepatic glands, which constitute that viscus.
7. The glands may be divided into three
  systems, the convoluted glands, such as those above described, which
  separate bile, tears, saliva, &c. Secondly, the glands without
  convolution, as the capillary vessels, which unite the terminations of
  the arteries and veins; and separate both the mucus, which lubricates the
  cellular membrane, and the perspirable matter, which preserves the skin
  moist and flexible. And thirdly, the whole absorbent system, consisting
  of the lacteals, which open their mouths into the stomach and intestines,
  and of the lymphatics, which open their mouths on the external surface of
  the body, and on the internal linings of all the cells of the cellular
  membrane, and other cavities of the body.
These lacteal and lymphatic vessels are furnished with numerous valves
  to prevent the return of the fluids, which they absorb, and terminate in
  glands, called lymphatic glands, and may hence be considered as long
  necks or mouths belonging to these glands. To these they convey the chyle
  and mucus, with a part of the perspirable matter, and atmospheric
  moisture; all which, after having passed through these glands, and having
  suffered some change in them, are carried forward into the blood, and
  supply perpetual nourishment to the system, or replace its hourly
  waste.
8. The stomach and intestinal canal have a
  constant vermicular motion, which carries forwards their contents, after
  the lacteals have drank up the chyle from them; and which is excited into
  action by the stimulus of the aliment we swallow, but which becomes
  occasionally inverted or retrograde, as in vomiting, and in the iliac
  passion.
II. 1. The word
  sensorium in the following pages is designed to express not only
  the medullary part of the brain, spinal marrow, nerves, organs of sense,
  and of the muscles; but also at the same time that living principle, or
  spirit of animation, which resides throughout the body, without being
  cognizable to our senses, except by its effects. The changes which
  occasionally take place in the sensorium, as during the exertions of
  volition, or the sensations of pleasure or pain, are termed sensorial
  motions.
2. The similarity of the texture of the
  brain to that of the pancreas, and some other glands of the body, has
  induced the inquirers into this subject to believe, that a fluid, perhaps
  much more subtile than the electric aura, is separated from the blood by
  that organ for the purposes of motion and sensation. When we recollect,
  that the electric fluid itself is actually accumulated and given out
  voluntarily by the torpedo and the gymnotus electricus, that an electric
  shock will frequently stimulate into motion a paralytic limb, and lastly
  that it needs no perceptible tubes to convey it, this opinion seems not
  without probability; and the singular figure of the brain and nervous
  system seems well adapted to distribute it over every part of the
  body.
For the medullary substance of the brain not only occupies the
  cavities of the head and spine, but passes along the innumerable
  ramifications of the nerves to the various muscles and organs of sense.
  In these it lays aside its coverings, and is intermixed with the slender
  fibres, which constitute those muscles and organs of sense. Thus all
  these distant ramifications of the sensorium are united at one of their
  extremities, that is, in the head and spine; and thus these central parts
  of the sensorium constitute a communication between all the organs of
  sense and muscles.
3. A nerve is a continuation of the
  medullary substance of the brain from the head or spine towards the other
  parts of the body, wrapped in its proper membrane.
4. The muscular fibres are moving
  organs intermixed with that medullary substance, which is continued along
  the nerves, as mentioned above. They are indued with the power of
  contraction, and are again elongated either by antagonist muscles, by
  circulating fluids, or by elastic ligaments. So the muscles on one side
  of the forearm bend the fingers by means of their tendons, and those on
  the other side of the fore-arm extend them again. The arteries are
  distended by the circulating blood; and in the necks of quadrupeds there
  is a strong elastic ligament, which assists the muscles, which elevate
  the head, to keep it in its horizontal position, and to raise it after it
  has been depressed.
5. The immediate organs of sense
  consist in like manner of moving fibres enveloped in the medullary
  substance above mentioned; and are erroneously supposed to be simply an
  expansion of the nervous medulla, as the retina of the eye, and the rete
  mucosum of the skin, which are the immediate organs of vision, and of
  touch. Hence when we speak of the contractions of the fibrous parts of
  the body, we shall mean both the contractions of the muscles, and those
  of the immediate organs of sense. These fibrous motions are thus
  distinguished from the sensorial motions above mentioned.
6. The external organs of sense are
  the coverings of the immediate organs of sense, and are mechanically
  adapted for the reception or transmission of peculiar bodies, or of their
  qualities, as the cornea and humours of the eye, the tympanum of the ear,
  the cuticle of the fingers and tongue.
7. The word idea has various meanings
  in the writers of metaphysic: it is here used simply for those notions of
  external things, which our organs of sense bring us acquainted with
  originally; and is defined a contraction, or motion, or configuration, of
  the fibres, which constitute the immediate organ of sense; which will be
  explained at large in another part of the work. Synonymous with the word
  idea, we shall sometimes use the words sensual motion in
  contradistinction to muscular motion.
8. The word perception includes both
  the action of the organ of sense in consequence of the impact of external
  objects, and our attention to that action; that is, it expresses both the
  motion of the organ of sense, or idea, and the pain or pleasure that
  succeeds or accompanies it.
9. The pleasure or pain which necessarily
  accompanies all those perceptions or ideas which we attend to, either
  gradually subsides, or is succeeded by other fibrous motions. In the
  latter case it is termed sensation, as explained in Sect. V. 2, and VI. 2.—The
  reader is intreated to keep this in his mind, that through all this
  treatise the word sensation is used to express pleasure or pain only in
  its active state, by whatever means it is introduced into the system,
  without any reference to the stimulation of external objects.
10. The vulgar use of the word
  memory is too unlimited for our purpose: those ideas which we
  voluntarily recall are here termed ideas of recollection, as when
  we will to repeat the alphabet backwards. And those ideas which are
  suggested to us by preceding ideas are here termed ideas of
  suggestion, as whilst we repeat the alphabet in the usual order;
  when by habits previously acquired B is suggested by A, and C by B,
  without any effort of deliberation.
11. The word association properly
  signifies a society or convention of things in some respects similar to
  each other. We never say in common language, that the effect is
  associated with the cause, though they necessarily accompany or succeed
  each other. Thus the contractions of our muscles and organs of sense may
  be said to be associated together, but cannot with propriety be said to
  be associated with irritations, or with volition, or with sensation;
  because they are caused by them, as mentioned in Sect. IV. When fibrous contractions succeed other fibrous
  contractions, the connection is termed association; when fibrous
  contractions succeed sensorial motions, the connection is termed
  causation; when fibrous and sensorial motions reciprocally
  introduce each other in progressive trains or tribes, it is termed
  catenation of animal motions. All these connections are said to be
  produced by habit; that is, by frequent repetition.
12. It may be proper to observe, that by
  the unavoidable idiom of our language the ideas of perception, of
  recollection, or of imagination, in the plural number signify the ideas
  belonging to perception, to recollection, or to imagination; whilst the
  idea of perception, of recollection, or of imagination, in the singular
  number is used for what is termed "a reflex idea of any of those
  operations of the sensorium."
13. By the word stimulus is not only
  meant the application of external bodies to our organs of sense and
  muscular fibres, which excites into action the sensorial power termed
  irritation; but also pleasure or pain, when they excite into action the
  sensorial power termed sensation; and desire or aversion, when they
  excite into action the power of volition; and lastly, the fibrous
  contractions which precede association; as is further explained in Sect.
  XII. 2. 1.

</div></body></text></TEI>