<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="93">CHAPTER IX.
Transition to Chemical Science.
THE preceding train of
generalization may justly appear extensive, and of itself well worthy
of admiration. Yet we are to consider all that has there been
established as only one-half of the science to which it
belongs,—one limb of the colossal form of Chemistry. We 257 have ascertained, we
will suppose, the laws of Electric Polarity; but we have then to ask,
What is the relation of this Polarity to Chemical Composition? This
was the great problem which, constantly present to the minds of
electro-chemical inquirers, drew them on, with the promise of some
deep and comprehensive insight into the mechanism of nature. Long
tasks of research, though only subsidiary to this, were cheerfully
undertaken. Thus Faraday37 describes himself as compelled to set
about satisfying himself of the identity of common, animal, and
voltaic electricity, as “the decision of a doubtful point which
interfered with the extension of his views, and destroyed the
strictness of reasoning.” Having established this identity, he
proceeded with his grand undertaking of electro-chemical research.
37 Dec. 1832. Researches,
266.
The connexion of electrical currents with chemical action, though
kept out of sight in the account we have hitherto given, was never
forgotten by the experimenters; for, in fact, the modes in which
electrical currents were excited, were chemical actions;—the
action of acids and metals on each other in the voltaic trough, or in
some other form. The dependence of the electrical effect on these
chemical actions, and still more, the chemical actions produced by the
agency of the poles of the circuit, had been carefully studied; and we
must now relate with what success.
But in what terms shall we present this narration? We have spoken
of chemical actions,—but what kind of actions are these?
Decomposition; the resolution of compounds into their
ingredients; the separation of acids from bases; the
reduction of bodies to simple elements. These names open to us
a new drama; they are words which belong to a different set of
relations of things, a different train of scientific inductions, a
different system of generalizations, from any with which we have
hitherto been concerned. We must learn to understand these phrases,
before we can advance in our history of human knowledge.
And how are we to learn the meaning of this collection of words? In
what other language shall it be explained? In what terms shall we
define these new expressions? To this we are compelled to reply, that
we cannot translate these terms into any ordinary language;—that
we cannot define them in any terms already familiar to us. Here, as in
all other branches of knowledge, the meaning of words is to be sought
in the progress of thought; the history of science is our 258 dictionary; the steps
of scientific induction are our definitions. It is only by going back
through the successful researches of men respecting the composition
and elements of bodies, that we can learn in what sense such terms
must be understood, so as to convey real knowledge. In order that they
may have a meaning for us, we must inquire what meaning they had in
the minds of the authors of our discoveries.
And thus we cannot advance a step, till we have brought up our
history of Chemistry to the level of our history of
Electricity;—till we have studied the progress of the
analytical, as well as the mechanical sciences. We are compelled to
pause and look backwards here; just as happened in the history of
astronomy, when we arrived at the brink of the great mechanical
inductions of Newton, and found that we must trace the history of
Mechanics, before we could proceed to mechanical Astronomy. The terms
“force, attraction, inertia, momentum,” sent us back into preceding
centuries then, just as the terms “composition” and “element” send us
back now.
Nor is it to a small extent that we have thus to double back upon
our past advance. Next to Astronomy, Chemistry is one of the most
ancient of sciences;—the field of the earliest attempts of man
to command and understand nature. It has held men for centuries by a
kind of fascination; and innumerable and endless are the various
labors, the failures and successes, the speculations and conclusions,
the strange pretences and fantastical dreams, of those who have
pursued it. To exhibit all these, or give any account of them, would
be impossible; and for our design, it would not be pertinent. To
extract from the mass that which is to our purpose, is difficult; but
the attempt must be made. We must endeavor to analyse the history of
Chemistry, so far as it has tended towards the establishment of
general principles. We shall thus obtain a sight of generalizations of
a new kind, and shall prepare ourselves for others of a higher
order.


BOOK XIV.

THE ANALYTICAL SCIENCE.

HISTORY OF CHEMISTRY.

.  .  .  .  .  . 
.  Soon had his crew
Opened into the hill a spacious wound,
And digged out ribs of gold  .  . 
.  .
Anon out of the earth a fabric huge
Rose like an exhalation, with the sound
Of dulcet symphonies and voices sweet,
Built like a temple.
Milton. Paradise
Lost, i.   

</div></body></text></TEI>