<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="89">CHAPTER V.
Discovery of the Laws of Electro-magnetic
Action.
ON attempting to analyse the
electro-magnetic phenomena observed by Oersted and others into their
simplest forms, they appeared, at least at first sight, to be
different from any mechanical actions which had yet been observed. It
seemed as if the conducting wire exerted on the pole of the magnet a
force which was not attractive or repulsive, but
transverse;—not tending to draw the point acted on
nearer, or to push it further off, in the line which reached from the
acting point, but urging it to move at right angles to this line. The
forces appeared to be such as Kepler had dreamt of in the infancy of
mechanical conceptions; rather than such as those of which Newton had
established the existence in the solar system, and such as he, and all
his successors, had supposed to be the only kinds of force which exist
in nature. The north pole of the needle moved as if it were impelled
by a vortex revolving round the wire in one direction, while the south
pole seemed to be driven by an opposite vortex. The case seemed novel,
and almost paradoxical.
It was soon established by experiments, made in a great variety of
forms, that the mechanical action was really of this transverse kind.
And a curious result was obtained, which a little while before would
have been considered as altogether incredible;—that this force
would cause a constant and rapid revolution of either of the bodies
about the other;—of the conducting wire about the magnet, or of
the magnet about the conducting wire. This was effected by Mr. Faraday
in 1821.
The laws which regulated the intensity of this force, with
reference to the distance and position of the bodies, now naturally
came to be examined. MM. Biot and Savart in France, and Mr. Barlow in
England, instituted such measures; and satisfied themselves that the
elementary force followed the law of magnitude of all known elementary
forces, in being inversely as the square of the distance; although, in
its direction, it was so entirely different from other forces. But the
investigation of the laws of phenomena of the subject was too
closely connected with the choice of a mechanical theory, to be
established 246
previously and independently, as had been done in astronomy. The
experiments gave complex results, and the analysis of these into their
elementary actions was almost an indispensable step in order to
disentangle their laws. We must, therefore, state the progress of this
analysis.
</div></body></text></TEI>