<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Humboldt Alexander</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1814</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="13">CHAPTER 1.14.
EARTHQUAKES AT CARACAS.
CONNECTION OF THOSE PHENOMENA WITH THE VOLCANIC ERUPTIONS
  OF THE WEST INDIA ISLANDS.
On the evening of the 7th of February we took our departure from
Caracas. Since the period of our visit to that place, tremendous
earthquakes have changed the surface of the soil. The city, which I
have described, has disappeared; and on the same spot, on the
ground fissured in various directions, another city is now slowly
rising. The heaps of ruins, which were the grave of a numerous
population, are becoming anew the habitation of men. In retracing
changes of so general an interest, I shall be led to notice events
which took place long after my return to Europe. I shall pass over
in silence the popular commotions which have taken place, and the
modifications which society has undergone. Modern nations, careful
of their own remembrances, snatch from oblivion the history of
human revolutions, which is, in fact, the history of ardent
passions and inveterate hatred. It is not the same with respect to
the revolutions of the physical world. These are described with
least accuracy when they happen to be contemporary with civil
dissensions. Earthquakes and eruptions of volcanoes strike the
imagination by the evils which are their necessary consequence.
Tradition seizes on whatever is vague and marvellous; and amid
great public calamities, as in private misfortunes, man seems to
shun that light which leads us to discover the real causes of
events, and to understand the circumstances by which they are
attended.
I have recorded in this work all I have been able to collect, and
on the accuracy of which I can rely, respecting the earthquake of
the 26th of March, 1812. By that catastrophe the town of Caracas
was destroyed, and more than twenty thousand persons perished
throughout the extent of the province of Venezuela. The intercourse
which I have kept up with persons of all classes has enabled me to
compare the description given by many eye-witnesses, and to
interrogate them on objects that may throw light on physical
science in general. The traveller, as the historian of nature,
should verify the dates of great catastrophes, examine their
connection and their mutual relations, and should mark in the rapid
course of ages, in the continual progress of successive changes,
those fixed points with which other catastrophes may one day be
compared. All epochs are proximate to each other in the immensity
of time comprehended in the history of nature. Years which have
passed away seem but a few instants; and the physical descriptions
of a country, even when they offer subjects of no very powerful and
general interest, have at least the advantage of never becoming
old. Similar considerations, no doubt, led M. de la Condamine to
describe in his Voyage a l'Equateur, the memorable eruptions of the
volcano of Cotopaxi,* which took place long after his departure
from Quito. (* Those of the 30th of November, 1744, and of the 3rd
of September, 1750.) I feel the less hesitation in following the
example of that celebrated traveller, as the events I am about to
relate will help to elucidate the theory of volcanic reaction, or
the influence of a system of volcanoes on a vast space of
circumjacent territory.
At the time when M. Bonpland and myself visited the provinces of
New Andalusia, New Barcelona, and Caracas, it was generally
believed that the most eastern parts of those coasts were
especially exposed to the destructive effects of earthquakes. The
inhabitants of Cumana dreaded the valley of Caracas, on account of
its damp and variable climate, and its gloomy and misty sky; whilst
the inhabitants of the temperate valley regarded Cumana as a town
whose inhabitants incessantly inhaled a burning atmosphere, and
whose soil was periodically agitated by violent commotions.
Unmindful of the overthrow of Riobamba and other very elevated
towns, and not aware that the peninsula of Araya, composed of
mica-slate, shares the commotions of the calcareous coast of
Cumana, well-informed persons imagined they discerned security in
the structure of the primitive rocks of Caracas, as well as in the
elevated situation of this valley. Religious ceremonies celebrated
at La Guayra, and even in the capital, in the middle of the night,*
doubtless called to mind the fact that the province of Venezuela
had been subject at intervals to earthquakes; but dangers of rare
occurrence are slightly feared. (* For instance, the nocturnal
procession of the 21st of October, instituted in commemoration of
the great earthquake which took place on that day of the month, at
one o'clock in the morning, in 1778. Other very violent shocks were
those of 1641, 1703, and 1802.) However, in the year 1811, fatal
experience destroyed the illusion of theory and of popular opinion.
Caracas, situated in the mountains, three degrees west of Cumana,
and five degrees west of the volcanoes of the Caribbee islands, has
suffered greater shocks than were ever experienced on the coast of
Paria or New Andalusia.
At my arrival in Terra Firma, I was struck with the connection
between the destruction of Cumana on the 14th of December, 1797,
and the eruption of the volcanoes in the smaller West India
Islands. This connection was again manifest in the destruction of
Caracas on the 26th of March, 1812. The volcano of Guadaloupe
seemed in 1797 to have exercised a reaction on the coasts of
Cumana. Fifteen years later, it was a volcano situated nearer the
continent (that of St. Vincent), which appeared to have extended
its influence as far as Caracas and the banks of Apure. Possibly,
at both those periods, the centre of the explosion was, at an
immense depth, equally distant from the regions towards which the
motion was propagated at the surface of the globe.
From the beginning of 1811 to 1813, a vast superficies of the
earth,* (* Between latitudes 5 and 36 degrees north, and 31 and 91
degrees west longitude from Paris.) bound by the meridian of the
Azores, the valley of the Ohio, the Cordilleras of New Grenada, the
coasts of Venezuela, and the volcanoes of the smaller West India
Islands, was shaken throughout its whole extent, by commotions
which may be attributed to subterranean fires. The following series
of phenomena seems to indicate communications at enormous
distances. On the 30th of January, 1811, a submarine volcano broke
out near the island of St. Michael, one of the Azores. At a place
where the sea was sixty fathoms deep, a rock made its appearance
above the surface of the waters. The heaving-up of the softened
crust of the globe appears to have preceded the eruption of flame
at the crater, as had already been observed at the volcanoes of
Jorullo in Mexico, and on the appearance of the little island of
Kameni, near Santorino. The new islet of the Azores was at first a
mere shoal; but on the 15th of June, an eruption, which lasted six
days, enlarged its extent, and carried it progressively to the
height of fifty toises above the surface of the sea. This new land,
of which captain Tillard took possession in the name of the British
government, giving it the name of Sabrina Island, was nine hundred
toises in diameter. It has again, it seems, been swallowed up by
the ocean. This is the third time that submarine volcanoes have
presented this extraordinary spectacle near the island of St.
Michael; and, as if the eruptions of these volcanoes were subject
to periodical recurrence, owing to a certain accumulation of
elastic fluids, the island raised up has appeared at intervals of
ninety-one or ninety-two years.* (* Malte-Brun, Geographie
Universelle. There is, however, some doubt respecting the eruption
of 1628, to which some accounts assign the date of 1638. The rising
always happened near the island of St. Michael, though not
identically on the same spot. It is remarkable that the small
island of 1720 reached the same elevation as the island of Sabrina
in 1811.)
At the time of the appearance of the new island of Sabrina, the
smaller West India Islands, situated eight hundred leagues
south-west of the Azores, experienced frequent earthquakes. More
than two hundred shocks were felt from the month of May 1811, to
April 1812, at St. Vincent; one of the three islands in which there
are still active volcanoes. The commotion was not circumscribed to
the insular portion of eastern America; and from the 16th of
December, 1811, till the year 1813, the earth was almost
incessantly agitated in the valleys of the Mississippi, the
Arkansas river, and the Ohio. The oscillations were more feeble on
the east of the Alleghanies, than to the west of these mountains,
in Tennessee and Kentucky. They were accompanied by a great
subterranean noise, proceeding from the south-west. In some places
between New Madrid and Little Prairie, as at the Saline, north of
Cincinnati, in latitude 37 degrees 45 minutes, shocks were felt
every day, nay almost every hour, during several months. The whole
of these phenomena continued from the 16th of December 1811, till
the year 1813. The commotion, confined at first to the south, in
the valley of the lower Mississippi, appeared to advance slowly
northward.
Precisely at the period when this long series of earthquakes
commenced in the Transalleghanian States (in the month of December
1811), the town of Caracas felt the first shock in calm and serene
weather. This coincidence of phenomena was probably not accidental;
for it must be borne in mind that, notwithstanding the distance
which separates these countries, the low grounds of Louisiana and
the coasts of Venezuela and Cumana belong to the same basin, that
of the Gulf of Mexico. When we consider geologically the basin of
the Caribbean Sea, and of the Gulf of Mexico, we find it bounded on
the south by the coast-chain of Venezuela and the Cordilleras of
Merida and Pamplona; on the east by the mountains of the West India
Islands, and the Alleghanies; on the west by the Andes of Mexico,
and the Rocky Mountains; and on the north by the very
inconsiderable elevations which separate the Canadian lakes from
the rivers which flow into the Mississippi. More than two-thirds of
this basin are covered with water. It is bordered by two ranges of
active volcanoes; on the east, in the Carribee Islands, between
latitudes 13 and 16 degrees; and on the west in the Cordilleras of
Nicaragua, Guatimala, and Mexico, between latitudes 11 and 20
degrees. When we reflect that the great earthquake at Lisbon, of
the 1st of November, 1755, was felt almost simultaneously on the
coasts of Sweden, at lake Ontario, and at the island of Martinique,
it may not seem unreasonable to suppose, that all this basin of the
West Indies, from Cumana and Caracas as far as the plains of
Louisiana, should be simultaneously agitated by commotions
proceeding from the same centre of action.
It is an opinion very generally prevalent on the coasts of Terra
Firma, that earthquakes become more frequent when electric
explosions have been during some years rare. It is supposed to have
been observed, at Cumana and at Caracas, that the rains were less
frequently attended with thunder from the year 1792; and the total
destruction of Cumana in 1797, as well as the commotions felt in
1800, 1801, and 1802, at Maracaibo, Porto Cabello, and Caracas,
have not failed to be attributed to an accumulation of electricity
in the interior of the earth. Persons who have lived long in New
Andalusia, or in the low regions of Peru, will admit that the
period most to be dreaded for the frequency of earthquakes is the
beginning of the rainy season, which, however, is also the season
of thunder-storms. The atmosphere and the state of the surface of
the globe seem to exercise an influence unknown to us on the
changes which take place at great depths; and I am inclined to
think that the connection which it is supposed has been traced
between the absence of thunder-storms and the frequency of
earthquakes, is rather a physical hypothesis framed by the
half-learned of the country than the result of long experience. The
coincidence of certain phenomena may be favoured by chance. The
extraordinary commotions felt almost continually during the space
of two years on the banks of the Mississippi and the Ohio, and
which corresponded in 1812 with those of the valley of Caracas,
were preceded at Louisiana by a year almost exempt from
thunder-storms. The public mind was again struck with this
phenomenon. We cannot be surprised that there should be in the
native land of Franklin a great readiness to receive explanations
founded on the theory of electricity.
The shock felt at Caracas in the month of December 1811, was the
only one which preceded the terrible catastrophe of the 26th of
March, 1812. The inhabitants of Terra Firma were alike ignorant of
the agitations of the volcano in the island of St. Vincent, and of
those felt in the basin of the Mississippi, where, on the 7th and
8th of February, 1812, the earth was day and night in perpetual
oscillation. A great drought prevailed at this period in the
province of Venezuela. Not a single drop of rain had fallen at
Caracas or in the country to the distance of ninety leagues round,
during five months preceding the destruction of the capital. The
26th of March was a remarkably hot day. The air was calm, and the
sky unclouded. It was Ascension-day, and a great portion of the
population was assembled in the churches. Nothing seemed to presage
the calamities of the day. At seven minutes after four in the
afternoon the first shock was felt. It was sufficiently forcible to
make the bells of the churches toll; and it lasted five or six
seconds. During that interval the ground was in a continual
undulating movement, and seemed to heave up like a boiling liquid.
The danger was thought to be past, when a tremendous subterranean
noise was heard, resembling the rolling of thunder, but louder and
of longer continuance than that heard within the tropics in the
time of storms. This noise preceded a perpendicular motion of three
or four seconds, followed by an undulatory movement somewhat
longer. The shocks were in opposite directions, proceeding from
north to south, and from east to west. Nothing could resist the
perpendicular movement and the transverse undulations. The town of
Caracas was entirely overthrown, and between nine and ten thousand
of the inhabitants were buried under the ruins of the houses and
churches. The procession of Ascension-day had not yet begun to pass
through the streets, but the crowd was so great within the churches
that nearly three or four thousand persons were crushed by the fall
of the roofs. The explosion was most violent towards the north, in
that part of the town situated nearest the mountain of Avila and
the Silla. The churches of la Trinidad and Alta Gracia, which were
more than one hundred and fifty feet high, and the naves of which
were supported by pillars of twelve or fifteen feet diameter, were
reduced to a mass of ruins scarcely exceeding five or six feet in
elevation. The sinking of the ruins has been so considerable that
there now scarcely remain any vestiges of pillars or columns. The
barracks, called el Quartel de San Carlos, situated north of the
church of la Trinidad, on the road from the custom-house of La
Pastora, almost entirely disappeared. A regiment of troops of the
line, under arms, and in readiness to join the procession, was,
with the exception of a few men, buried beneath the ruins of the
barracks. Nine-tenths of the fine city of Caracas were entirely
destroyed. The walls of some houses not thrown down, as those in
the street San Juan, near the Capuchin Hospital, were cracked in
such a manner as to render them uninhabitable. The effects of the
earthquake were somewhat less violent in the western and southern
parts of the city, between the principal square and the ravine of
Caraguata. There, the cathedral, supported by enormous buttresses,
remains standing.
It is computed that nine or ten thousand persons were killed in the
city of Caracas, exclusive of those who, being dangerously wounded,
perished several months after, for want of food and proper care.
The night of the Festival of the Ascension witnessed an awful scene
of desolation and distress. The thick cloud of dust which, rising
above the ruins, darkened the sky like a fog, had settled on the
ground. No commotion was felt, and never was a night more calm or
more serene. The moon, then nearly at the full, illumined the
rounded domes of the Silla, and the aspect of the sky formed a
perfect contrast to that of the earth, which was covered with the
bodies of the dead, and heaped with ruins. Mothers were seen
bearing in their arms their children, whom they hoped to recall to
life. Desolate families were wandering through the city, seeking a
brother, a husband, or a friend, of whose fate they were ignorant,
and whom they believed to be lost in the crowd. The people pressed
along the streets, which could be traced only by long lines of
ruins.
All the calamities experienced in the great catastrophes of Lisbon,
Messina, Lima, and Riobamba were renewed at Caracas on the fatal
26th of March, 1812. Wounded persons, buried beneath the ruins,
were heard imploring by their cries the help of the passers-by, and
nearly two thousand were dug out. Never was pity more tenderly
evinced; never was it more ingeniously active than in the efforts
employed to save the miserable victims whose groans reached the
ear. Implements for digging and clearing away the ruins were
entirely wanting; and the people were obliged to use their bare
hands, to disinter the living. The wounded, as well as the invalids
who had escaped from the hospitals, were laid on the banks of the
small river Guayra, where there was no shelter but the foliage of
trees. Beds, linen to dress the wounds, instruments of surgery,
medicines, every object of the most urgent necessity, was buried in
the ruins. Everything, even food, was wanting; and for the space of
several days water became scarce in the interior of the city. The
commotion had rent the pipes of the fountains; and the falling in
of the earth had choked up the springs that supplied them. To
procure water it was necessary to go down to the river Guayra,
which was considerably swelled; and even when the water was
obtained vessels for conveying it were wanting.
There was a duty to be fulfilled to the dead, enjoined at once by
piety and the dread of infection. It being impossible to inter so
many thousand bodies, half-buried under the ruins, commissioners
were appointed to burn them: and for this purpose funeral piles
were erected between the heaps of ruins. This ceremony lasted
several days. Amidst so many public calamities, the people devoted
themselves to those religious duties which they thought best fitted
to appease the wrath of heaven. Some, assembling in processions,
sang funeral hymns; others, in a state of distraction, made their
confessions aloud in the streets. In Caracas was then repeated what
had been remarked in the province of Quito, after the tremendous
earthquake of 1797; a number of marriages were contracted between
persons who had neglected for many years to sanction their union by
the sacerdotal benediction. Children found parents, by whom they
had never till then been acknowledged; restitutions were promised
by persons who had never been accused of fraud; and families who
had long been at enmity were drawn together by the tie of common
calamity. But if this feeling seemed to calm the passions of some,
and open the heart to pity, it had a contrary effect on others,
rendering them more rigorous and inhuman. In great calamities
vulgar minds evince less of goodness than of energy. Misfortune
acts in the same manner as the pursuits of literature and the study
of nature; the happy influence of which is felt only by a few,
giving more ardour to sentiment, more elevation to the thoughts,
and increased benevolence to the disposition.
Shocks as violent as those which in about the space of a minute*
overthrew the city of Caracas, could not be confined to a small
portion of the continent. (* The duration of the earthquake, that
is to say the whole of the movements of undulation and rising
(undulacion y trepidacion), which occasioned the horrible
catastrophe of the 26th of March, 1812, was estimated by some at 50
seconds, by others at 1 minute 12 seconds.) Their fatal effects
extended as far as the provinces of Venezuela, Varinas, and
Maracaibo, along the coast; and especially to the inland mountains.
La Guayra, Mayquetia, Antimano, Baruta, La Vega, San Felipe, and
Merida, were almost entirely destroyed. The number of the dead
exceeded four or five thousand at La Guayra, and at the town of San
Felipe, near the copper-mines of Aroa. It would appear that on a
line running east-north-east and west-south-west from La Guayra and
Caracas to the lofty mountains of Niquitao and Merida, the violence
of the earthquake was principally directed. It was felt in the
kingdom of New Grenada from the branches of the high Sierra de
Santa Martha* (* As far as Villa de Los Remedios, and even to
Carthagena.) as far as Santa Fe de Bogota and Honda, on the banks
of the Magdalena, one hundred and eighty leagues from Caracas. It
was everywhere more violent in the Cordilleras of gneiss and
mica-slate, or immediately at their base, than in the plains; and
this difference was particularly striking in the savannahs of
Varinas and Casanara.* (* This is easily explained according to the
system of those geologists who are of opinion that all chains of
mountains, volcanic and not volcanic, have been formed by being
raised up, as if through crevices.) In the valleys of Aragua,
between Caracas and the town of San Felipe, the commotions were
very slight; and La Victoria, Maracay, and Valencia, scarcely
suffered at all, notwithstanding their proximity to the capital. At
Valecillo, a few leagues from Valencia, the yawning earth threw out
such an immense quantity of water, that it formed a new torrent.
The same phenomenon took place near Porto-Cabello.* (* It is
asserted that, in the mountains of Aroa, the ground, immediately
after the great shocks, was found covered with a very fine and
white earth, which appeared to have been projected through
crevices.) On the other hand, the lake of Maracaybo diminished
sensibly. At Coro no commotion was felt, though the town is
situated on the coast, between other towns which suffered from the
earthquake. Fishermen, who had passed the day of the 26th of March
in the island of Orchila, thirty leagues north-east of La Guayra,
felt no shock. These differences in the direction and propagation
of the shock, are probably owing to the peculiar position of the
stony strata.
Having thus traced the effects of the earthquake to the west of
Caracas, as far as the snowy mountains of Santa Martha, and the
table-land of Santa Fe de Bogota, we will proceed to consider their
action on the country eastward of the capital. The commotions were
very violent beyond Caurimare, in the valley of Capaya, where they
extended as far as the meridian of Cape Codera: but it is extremely
remarkable that they were very feeble on the coasts of Nueva
Barcelona, Cumana, and Paria; though these coasts are the
continuation of the shore of La Guayra, and were formerly known to
have been often agitated by subterranean commotions. Admitting that
the destruction of the four towns of Caracas, La Guayra, San
Felipe, and Merida, may be attributed to a volcanic focus situated
under or near the island of St. Vincent, we may conceive that the
motion might have been propagated from north-east to south-west in
a line passing through the islands of Los Hermanos, near
Blanquilla, without touching the coasts of Araya, Cumana, and Nueva
Barcelona. This propagation of the shock might even have taken
place without any commotion having been felt at the intermediate
points on the surface of the globe (the Hermanos Islands for
instance). This phenomenon is frequently remarked at Peru and
Mexico, in earthquakes which have followed during ages a fixed
direction. The inhabitants of the Andes say, speaking of an
intermediary tract of ground, not affected by the general
commotion, "that it forms a bridge" (que hace puente): as if they
mean to indicate by this expression that the undulations are
propagated at an immense depth under an inert rock.
At Caracas, fifteen or eighteen hours after the great catastrophe,
the earth was tranquil. The night, as has already been observed,
was fine and calm; and the commotions did not recommence till after
the 27th. They were then attended by a very loud and long continued
subterranean noise (bramido). The inhabitants of the destroyed city
wandered into the country; but the villages and farms having
suffered as much as the town, they could find no shelter till they
were beyond the mountains of los Teques, in the valleys of Aragua,
and in the llanos or savannahs. No less than fifteen oscillations
were felt in one day. On the 5th of April there was almost as
violent an earthquake as that which overthrew the capital. During
several hours the ground was in a state of perpetual undulation.
Large heaps of earth fell in the mountains; and enormous masses of
rock were detached from the Silla of Caracas. It was even asserted,
and this opinion prevails still in the country, that the two domes
of the Silla sunk fifty or sixty toises; but this statement is not
founded on any measurement. I am informed that, in like manner, in
the province of Quito, the people, at every period of great
commotions, imagine that the volcano of Tunguragua diminishes in
height. It has been affirmed, in many published accounts of the
destruction of Caracas, that the mountain of the Silla is an
extinguished volcano; that a great quantity of volcanic substances
are found on the road from La Guayra to Caracas; that the rocks do
not present any regular stratification; and that everything bears
the stamp of the action of fire. It has even been stated that
twelve years prior to the great catastrophe, M. Bonpland and myself
had, from our own observations, considered the Silla as a very
dangerous neighbour to the city of Caracas, because the mountain
contained a great quantity of sulphur, and the commotions must come
from the north-east. It is seldom that observers of nature have to
justify themselves for an accomplished prediction; but I think it
my duty to oppose ideas which are too easily adopted on the LOCAL
CAUSES of earthquakes.
In all places where the soil has been incessantly agitated for
whole months, as at Jamaica in 1693, Lisbon in 1755, Cumana in
1766, and Piedmont in 1808, a volcano is expected to open. People
forget that we must seek the focus or centre of action, far from
the surface of the earth; that, according to undeniable evidence,
the undulations are propagated almost at the same instant across
seas of immense depth, at the distance of a thousand leagues; and
that the greatest commotions take place not at the foot of active
volcanoes, but in chains of mountains composed of the most
heterogeneous rocks. In our geognostical observation of the country
round Caracas we found gneiss, and mica-slate containing beds of
primitive limestone. The strata are scarcely more fractured or
irregularly inclined than near Freyburg in Saxony, or wherever
mountains of primitive formation rise abruptly to great heights. I
found at Caracas neither basalt nor dorolite, nor even trachytes or
trap-porphyries; nor in general any trace of an extinguished
volcano, unless we choose to regard the diabases of primitive
grunstein, contained in gneiss, as masses of lava, which have
filled up fissures. These diabases are the same as those of
Bohemia, Saxony, and Franconia;* (* These grunsteins are found in
Bohemia, near Pilsen, in granite; in Saxony, in the mica-slates of
Scheenberg; in Franconia, between Steeben and Lauenstein, in
transition-slates.) and whatever opinion may be entertained
respecting the ancient causes of the oxidation of the globe at its
surface, all those primitive mountains, which contain a mixture of
hornblende and feldspar, either in veins or in balls with
concentric layers, will not, I presume, be called volcanic
formations. Mont Blanc and Mont d'Or will not be ranged in one and
the same class. Even the partisans of the Huttonian or volcanic
theory make a distinction between the lavas melted under the mere
pressure of the atmosphere at the surface of the globe, and those
layers formed by fire beneath the immense weight of the ocean and
superincumbent rocks. They would not confound Auvergne and the
granitic valley of Caracas in the same denomination; that of a
country of extinct volcanoes.
I never could have pronounced the opinion, that the Silla and the
Cerro de Avila, mountains of gneiss and mica-slate, were in
dangerous proximity to the city of Caracas because they contained a
great quantity of pyrites in subordinate beds of primitive
limestone. But I remember having said, during my stay at Caracas,
that the eastern extremity of Terra Firma appeared, since the great
earthquake of Quito, in a state of agitation, which warranted
apprehension that the province of Venezuela would gradually be
exposed to violent commotions. I added, that when a country had
been long subject to frequent shocks, new subterranean
communications seemed to open with neighbouring countries; and that
the volcanoes of the West India Islands, lying in the direction of
the Silla, north-east of the city, were perhaps the vents, at the
time of an eruption, for those elastic fluids which cause
earthquakes on the coasts of the continent. These considerations,
founded on local knowledge of the place, and on simple analogies,
are very far from a prediction justified by the course of physical
events.
On the 30th of April, 1812, whilst violent commotions were felt
simultaneously in the valley of the Mississippi, in the island of
St. Vincent, and in the province of Venezuela, a subterranean noise
resembling frequent discharges of large cannon was heard at
Caracas, at Calabozo (situated in the midst of the steppes), and on
the borders of the Rio Apure, over a superficies of four thousand
square leagues. This noise began at two in the morning. It was
accompanied by no shock; and it is very remarkable, that it was as
loud on the coast as at the distance of eighty leagues inland. It
was everywhere believed to be transmitted through the air; and was
so far from being thought a subterranean noise, that in several
places, preparations were made for defence against an enemy, who
seemed to be advancing with heavy artillery. Senor Palacio,
crossing the Rio Apure below the Orivante, near the junction of the
Rio Nula, was told by the inhabitants, that the firing of cannon
had been heard distinctly at the western extremity of the province
of Varinas, as well as at the port of La Guayra to the north of the
chain of the coast.
The day on which the inhabitants of Terra Firma were alarmed by a
subterranean noise was that of the great eruption of the volcano in
the island of St. Vincent. That mountain, near five hundred toises
high, had not thrown out lava since the year 1718. Scarcely was any
smoke perceived to issue from it, when, in the month of May 1811,
frequent shocks announced that the volcanic fire was either
rekindled, or directed anew to that part of the West Indies. The
first eruption did not take place till the 27th of April, 1812, at
noon. It was merely an ejection of ashes, but attended with a
tremendous noise. On the 30th, the lava overflowed the brink of the
crater, and, after a course of four hours, reached the sea. The
sound of the explosion is described as resembling that of alternate
discharges of very large cannon and musketry; and it is worthy of
remark, that it seemed much louder to persons out at sea, and at a
great distance from land, than to those within sight of land, and
near the burning volcano.
The distance in a straight line from the volcano of St. Vincent to
the Rio Apure, near the mouth of the Nula, is two hundred and ten
leagues.* (* Where the contrary is not expressly stated, nautical
leagues of twenty to a degree, or two thousand eight hundred and
fifty-five toises, are always to be understood.) The explosions
were consequently heard at a distance equal to that between
Vesuvius and Paris. This phenomenon, in conjunction with a great
number of facts observed in the Cordilleras of the Andes, shows
that the sphere of the subterranean activity of a volcano is much
more extensive than we should be disposed to admit, if we judged
merely from the small changes effected at the surface of the globe.
The detonations heard during whole days together in the New World,
eighty, one hundred, or even two hundred leagues distant from a
crater, do not reach us by the propagation of the sound through the
air; they are transmitted by the earth, perhaps in the very place
where we happen to be. If the eruptions of the volcano of St.
Vincent, Cotopaxi, or Tunguragua, resounded from afar, like a
cannon of immense magnitude, the noise ought to increase in the
inverse ratio of the distance: but observations prove, that this
augmentation does not take place. I must further observe, that M.
Bonpland and I, going from Guayaquil to the coast of Mexico,
crossed latitudes in the Pacific, where the crew of our ship were
dismayed by a hollow sound coming from the depth of the ocean, and
transmitted by the waters. At that time a new eruption of Cotopaxi
took place, but we were as far distant from the volcano, as Etna
from the city of Naples. The little town of Honda, on the banks of
the Magdalena, is not less than one hundred and forty-five leagues*
(* This is the distance from Vesuvius to Mont Blanc.) from
Cotopaxi; and yet, in the great explosions of this volcano, in
1744, a subterranean noise was heard at Honda, and supposed to be
discharges of heavy artillery. The monks of San Francisco spread a
report that the town of Carthagena was besieged and bombarded by
the English; and the intelligence was believed throughout the
country. Now the volcano of Cotopaxi is a cone, more than one
thousand eight hundred toises above the basin of Honda, and it
rises from a table-land, the elevation of which is more than one
thousand five hundred toises above the valley of the Magdalena. In
all the colossal mountains of Quito, of the province of los Pastos,
and of Popayan, crevices and valleys without number intervene. It
cannot be admitted, under these circumstances, that the noise was
transmitted through the air, or over the surface of the globe, and
that it came from the point at which the cone and crater of
Cotapaxi are situated. It appears probable, that the more elevated
part of the kingdom of Quito and the neighbouring Cordilleras, far
from being a group of distinct volcanoes, constitute a single
swollen mass, an enormous volcanic wall, stretching from south to
north, and the crest of which presents a superficies of more than
six hundred square leagues. Cotopaxi, Tunguragua, Antisana, and
Pichincha, are on this same raised ground. They have different
names, but they are merely separate summits of the same volcanic
mass. The fire issues sometimes from one, sometimes from another of
these summits. The obstructed craters appear to be extinguished
volcanoes; but we may presume, that, while Cotopaxi or Tunguragua
have only one or two eruptions in the course of a century, the fire
is not less continually active under the town of Quito, under
Pichincha and Imbabura.
Advancing northward we find, between the volcano of Cotopaxi and
the town of Honda, two other systems of volcanic mountains, those
of los Pastos and of Popayan. The connection between these systems
was manifested in the Andes by a phenomenon which I have already
had occasion to notice, in speaking of the last destruction of
Cumana. In the month of November 1796 a thick column of smoke began
to issue from the volcano of Pasto, west of the town of that name,
and near the valley of Rio Guaytara. The mouths of the volcano are
lateral, and situated on its western declivity, yet during three
successive months the column of smoke rose so much higher than the
ridge of the mountain that it was constantly visible to the
inhabitants of the town of Pasto. They described to us their
astonishment when, on the 4th of February, 1797, they observed the
smoke disappear in an instant, whilst no shock whatever was felt.
At that very moment, sixty-five leagues southward, between
Chimborazo, Tunguragua, and the Altar (Capac-Urcu), the town of
Riobamba was overthrown by the most terrible earthquake on record.
Is it possible to doubt, from this coincidence of phenomena, that
the vapours issuing from the small apertures or ventanillas of the
volcano of Pasto had an influence on the pressure of those elastic
fluids which convulsed the earth in the kingdom of Quito, and
destroyed in a few minutes thirty or forty thousand inhabitants?
To explain these great effects of volcanic reactions, and to prove
that the group or system of the volcanoes of the West India Islands
may sometimes shake the continent, I have cited the Cordillera of
the Andes. Geological reasoning can be supported only by the
analogy of facts which are recent, and consequently well
authenticated: and in what other region of the globe could we find
greater and more varied volcanic phenomena than in that double
chain of mountains heaved up by fire? in that land where nature has
covered every mountain and every valley with her marvels? If we
consider a burning crater only as an isolated phenomenon, if we be
satisfied with merely examining the mass of stony substances which
it has thrown up, the volcanic action at the surface of the globe
will appear neither very powerful nor very extensive. But the image
of this action becomes enlarged in the mind when we study the
relations which link together volcanoes of the same group; for
instance, those of Naples and Sicily, of the Canary Islands,* of
the Azores, of the Caribbee islands of Mexico, of Guatimala, and of
the table-land of Quito; when we examine either the reactions of
these different systems of volcanoes on one another, or the
distance at which, by subterranean communication, they
simultaneously convulse the earth. (I have already observed
(Chapter 1.2) that the whole group of the Canary Islands rises, as
we may say, above one and the same submarine volcano. Since the
sixteenth century, the fire of this volcano has burst forth
alternately in Palma, Teneriffe, and Lancerote. Auvergne presents a
whole system of volcanoes, the action of which has now ceased; but
in the middle of a system of active volcanoes, for instance, in
that of Quito, we must not consider as an extinguished volcano a
mountain, the crater of which is obstructed, and through which the
subterraneous fire has not issued for ages. Etna, the Aeolian
Isles, Vesuvius, and Epomeo; the peak of Teyde, Palma, and
Lancerote; St. Michael, La Caldiera of Fayal, and Pico; St.
Vincent, St. Lucia, and Guadaloupe; Orizava, Popocatepetl, Jorullo,
and La Colima; Bombacho, the volcano of Grenada, Telica, Momotombo,
Isalco, and the volcano of Guatimala; Cotopaxi, Tunguragua,
Pichincha, Antisana, and Sangai, belong to the same system of
burning volcanoes; they are generally ranged in rows, as if they
had issued from a crevice, or vein not filled up; and, it is very
remarkable, that their position is in some parts in the general
direction of the Cordilleras, and in others in a contrary
direction.)
The study of volcanoes may be divided into two distinct branches;
one, simply mineralogical, is directed to the examination of the
stony strata, altered or produced by the action of fire; from the
formation of the trachytes or trap-porphyries, of basalts,
phonolites, and dolerites, to the most recent lavas: the other
branch, less accessible and more neglected, comprehends the
physical relations which link volcanoes together, the influence of
one volcanic system on another, the connection existing between the
action of burning mountains and the commotions which agitate the
earth at great distances, and during long intervals, in the same
direction. This study cannot progress till the various epochs of
simultaneous action, the direction, the extent, and the force of
the convulsions are carefully noted; till we have attentively
observed their progressive advance to regions which they had not
previously reached; and the coincidence between distant volcanic
eruptions and those noises which the inhabitants of the Andes very
expressively term subterraneous thunders, or roarings.* (* Bramidos
y truenos subterraneos.) All these objects are comprehended in the
domain of the history of nature.
Though the narrow circle within which all certain traditions are
confined, does not present any of those general revolutions which
have heaved up the Cordilleras and buried myriads of pelagian
animals; yet Nature, acting under our eyes, nevertheless exhibits
violent though partial changes, the study of which may throw light
on the most remote epochs. In the interior of the earth those
mysterious powers exist, the effects of which are manifested at the
surface by the production of vapours, of incandescent scoriae, of
new volcanic rocks and thermal springs, by the appearance of new
islands and mountains, by commotions propagated with the rapidity
of an electric shock, finally by those subterranean thunders,*
heard during whole months, without shaking the earth, in regions
far distant from active volcanoes. (* In the town of Guanaxuato, in
Mexico, these thunders lasted from the 9th of January till the 12th
of February, 1784. Guanaxuato is situated forty leagues north of
the volcano of Jorullo, and sixty leagues north west of the volcano
of Popocatepetl. In places nearer these two volcanoes, three
leagues distant from Guanaxuato, the subterranean thunders were not
heard. The noise was circumscribed within a very narrow space, in
the region of a primitive schist, which approaches a
transition-schist, containing the richest silver mines of the known
world, and on which rest trap-porphyries, slates, and diabasis
(grunstein.))
In proportion as equinoctial America shall increase in culture and
population, and the system of volcanoes of the central table-land
of Mexico, of the Caribbee Islands, of Popayan, of los Pastos, and
Quito, shall be more attentively observed, the connection of
eruptions and of earthquakes, which precede and sometimes accompany
those eruptions, will be more generally recognized. The volcanoes
just mentioned, particularly those of the Andes, which rise above
the enormous height of two thousand five hundred toises, present
great advantages for observation. The periods of their eruptions
are singularly regular. They remain thirty or forty years without
emitting scoriae, ashes, or even vapours. I could not perceive the
smallest trace of smoke on the summit of Tunguragua or Cotopaxi. A
gust of vapour issuing from the crater of Mount Vesuvius scarcely
attracts the attention of the inhabitants of Naples, accustomed to
the movements of that little volcano, which throws out scoriae
sometimes during two or three years successively. Thence it becomes
difficult to judge whether the emission of scoriae may have been
more frequent at the time when an earthquake has been felt in the
Apennines. On the ridge of the Cordilleras everything assumes a
more decided character. An eruption of ashes, which lasts only a
few minutes, is often followed by a calm of ten years. In such
circumstances it is easy to mark the periods, and to observe the
coincidence of phenomena.
If, as there appears to be little reason to doubt, that the
destruction of Cumana in 1797, and of Caracas in 1812, indicate the
influence of the volcanoes of the West India Islands* on the
commotions felt on the coasts of Terra Firma, it may be desirable,
before we close this chapter, to take a cursory view of this
Mediterranean archipelago.
(* The following is the series of the phenomena:—
27th of September, 1796. Eruption in the West India Islands.
(Volcano of Guadaloupe).
November, 1796. The volcano of Pasto began to emit smoke.
14th of December, 1796. Destruction of Cumana.
4th of February, 1797. Destruction of Riobamba.
30th of January, 1811. Appearance of Sabrina Island, in the Azores.
The island enlarged very considerably on the 15th of June, 1811.
May, 1811. Commencement of the earthquakes in the island of St.

Vincent, which lasted till May 1812.

16th of December, 1811. Commencement of the commotions in the
valley of the Mississippi and the Ohio, which lasted till 1813.
December, 1811. Earthquake at Caracas.
26th of March, 1811. Destruction of Caracas. Earthquakes, which
continued till 1813.
30th of April, 1811. Eruption of the volcano in St. Vincent; and
the same day subterranean noises at Caracas, and on the banks of
the Apure.)
The volcanic islands form one-fifth of that great arc extending
from the coast of Paria to the peninsula of Florida. Running from
south to north, they close the Caribbean Sea on the eastern side,
while the greater West India Islands appear like the remains of a
group of primitive mountains, the summit of which seems to have
been between Cape Abacou, Point Morant, and the Copper Mountains,
in that part where the islands of St. Domingo, Cuba, and Jamaica,
are nearest to each other. Considering the basin of the Atlantic as
an immense valley* which separates the two continents, and where,
from 20 degrees south to 30 degrees north, the salient angles
(Brazil and Senegambia) correspond to the receding angles (the gulf
of Guinea and the Caribbean Sea), we are led to think that the
latter sea owes its formation to the action of currents, which,
like the current of rotation now existing, have flowed from east to
west; and have given the southern coast of Porto Rico, St. Domingo,
and the island of Cuba their uniform configuration. (* The valley
is narrowest (300 leagues) between Cape St. Roque and Sierra Leone.
Proceeding toward the north along the Coasts of the New Continent,
from its pyramidal extremity, or the Straits of Magellan, we
imagine we recognise the effects of a repulsion directed first
toward the north-east, then toward the north-west, and finally
again to the north-east.) This supposition of an oceanic irruption
has been the source of two other hypotheses on the origin of the
smaller West India Islands. Some geologists admit that the
uninterrupted chain of islands from Trinidad to Florida exhibits
the remains of an ancient chain of mountains. They connect this
chain sometimes with the granite of French Guiana, sometimes with
the calcareous mountains of Pari. Others, struck with the
difference of geological constitution between the primitive
mountains of the Greater and the volcanic cones of the Lesser
Antilles, consider the latter as having risen from the bottom of
the sea.
If we recollect that volcanic upheavings, when they take place
through elongated crevices, usually take a straight direction, we
shall find it difficult to judge from the disposition of the
craters alone, whether the volcanoes have belonged to the same
chain, or have always been isolated. Supposing an irruption of the
ocean to take place either into the eastern part of the island of
Java* (* Raffles, History of Java, 1817, pages 23-28. The principal
line of the volcanoes of Java, on a distance of 160 leagues, runs
from west to east, through the mountains of Gagak, Gede,
Tankuban-Prahu, Ungarang Merapi, Lawu, Wilis, Arjuna, Dasar, and
Tashem.) or into the Cordilleras of Guatimala and Nicaragua, where
so many burning mountains form but one chain, that chain would be
divided into several islands, and would perfectly resemble the
Caribbean Archipelago. The union of primitive formations and
volcanic rocks in the same range of mountain is not extraordinary;
it is very distinctly seen in my geological sections of the
Cordillera of the Andes. The trachytes and basalts of Popayan are
separated from the system of the volcanoes of Quito by the
mica-slates of Almaguer; the volcanoes of Quito from the trachytes
of Assuay by the gneiss of Condorasta and Guasunto. There does not
exist a real chain of mountains running south-east and north-west
from Oyapoc to the mouths of the Orinoco, and of which the smaller
West India Islands might be a northern prolongation. The granites
of Guiana, as well as the hornblende-slates, which I saw near
Angostura, on the banks of the Lower Orinoco, belong to the
mountains of Pacaraimo and of Parime, stretching from west to east,
* (From the cataracts of Atures towards the Essequibo River. This
chain of Pacaraimo divides the waters of the Carony from those of
the Rio Parime, or Rio de Aguas Blancas.) in the interior of the
continent, and not in a direction parallel with the coast, between
the mouths of the river Amazon and the Orinoco. But though we find
no chain of mountains at the north-east extremity of Terra Firma,
having the same direction as the archipelago of the smaller West
India Islands, it does not therefore follow that the volcanic
mountains of the archipelago may not have belonged originally to
the continent, and formed a part of the littoral chain of Caracas
and Cumana.* (* Among many such examples which the structure of the
globe displays, we shall mention only the inflexion at a right
angle formed by the Higher Alps towards the maritime Alps, in
Europe; and the Belour-Tagh, which joins transversely the Mouz-Tagh
and the Himalaya, in Asia. Amid the prejudices which impede the
progress of mineralogical geography, we may reckon, 1st, the
supposition of a perfect uniformity of direction in the chains of
mountains; 2nd, the hypothesis of the continuity of all chains;
3rd, the supposition that the highest summits determine the
direction of a central chain; 4th, the idea that, in all places
where great rivers take rise, we may suppose the existence of great
tablelands, or very high mountains.)
In opposing the objections of some celebrated naturalists, I am far
from maintaining the ancient contiguity of all the smaller West
India Islands. I am rather inclined to consider them as islands
heaved up by fire, and ranged in that regular line, of which we
find striking examples in so many volcanic hills in Auvergne, in
Mexico, and in Peru. The geological constitution of the Archipelago
appears, from the little we know respecting it, to be very similar
to that of the Azores and the Canary Islands. Primitive formations
are nowhere seen above ground; we find only what belongs
unquestionably to volcanoes: feldspar-lava, dolerite, basalt,
conglomerated scoriae, tufa, and pumice-stone. Among the limestone
formations we must distinguish those which are essentially
subordinate to volcanic tufas* from those which appear to be the
work of madrepores and other zoophytes. (* We have noticed some of
the above, following Von Buch, at Lancerote, and at Fortaventura,
in the system of the Canary Islands. Among the smaller islands of
the West Indies, the following islets are entirely calcareous,
according to M. Cortes: Mariegalante, La Desirade, the Grande Terre
of Guadaloupe, and the Grenadillas. According to the observations
of that naturalist, Curacoa and Buenos Ayres present only
calcareous formations. M. Cortes divides the West India Islands
into, 1st, those containing at once primitive, secondary, and
volcanic formations, like the greater islands; 2nd, those entirely
calcareous, (or at least so considered) as Mariegalante and
Curacoa; 3rd, those at once volcanic and calcareous, as Antigua,
St. Bartholomew, St. Martin, and St. Thomas; 4th, those which have
volcanic rocks only, as St. Vincent, St. Lucia, and St. Eustache.)
The latter, according to M. Moreau de Jonnes, seem to lie on shoals
of a volcanic nature. Those mountains, which present traces of the
action of fire more or less recent, and some of which reach nearly
nine hundred toises of elevation, are all situated on the western
skirt of the smaller West India Islands.* (* Journal des Mines,
tome 3 page 59. In order to exhibit in one point of view the whole
system of the volcanoes of the smaller West India Islands, I will
here trace the direction of the islands from south to north.—Grenada,
an ancient crater, filled with water; boiling springs;
basalts between St. George and Goave.—St. Vincent, a burning
volcano.—St. Lucia, a very active solfatara, named Oualibou, two
or three hundred toises high; jets of hot water, by which small
basins are periodically filled.—Martinique, three great
extinguished volcanoes; Vauclin, the Paps of Carbet, which are
perhaps the most elevated summits of the smaller islands, and
Montagne Pelee. (The height of this last mountain is probably 800
toises; according to Leblond it is 670 toises; according to
Dupuget, 736 toises. Between Vauclin and the feldspar-lavas of the
Paps of Carbet is found, as M. Moreau de Jonnes asserts, in a neck
of land, a region of early basalt called La Roche Carree). Thermal
waters of Precheur and Lameutin.—Dominica, completely
volcanic.—Guadaloupe, an active volcano, the height of which,
according to Leboucher, is 799 toises; according to Amie, 850
toises.—Montserrat, a solfatara; fine porphyritic lavas with large
crystals of feldspar and hornblende near Galloway, according to Mr.
Nugent.—Nevis, a solfatara.—St. Christopher's, a solfatara at
Mount Misery.—St. Eustache, a crater of an extinguished volcano,
surrounded by pumice-stone. (Trinidad, which is traversed by a
chain of primitive slate, appears to have anciently formed a part
of the littoral chain of Cumana, and not of the system of the
mountains of the Caribbee Islands.)) Each island is not the effect
of one single heaving-up: most of them appear to consist of
isolated masses which have been progressively united together. The
matter has not been emitted from one crater, but from several; so
that a single island of small extent contains a whole system of
volcanoes, regions purely basaltic, and others covered with recent
lavas. The volcanoes still burning are those of St. Vincent, St.
Lucia, and Guadaloupe. The first threw out lava in 1718 and 1812;
in the second there is a continual formation of sulphur by the
condensation of vapours, which issue from the crevices of an
ancient crater. The last eruption of the volcano of Guadaloupe took
place in 1797. The Solfatara of St. Christopher's was still burning
in 1692. At Martinique, Vauclin, Montagne Pelee, and the crater
surrounded by the five Paps of Carbet, must be considered as three
extinguished volcanoes. The effects of thunder have been often
confounded in that place with subterranean fire. No good
observation has confirmed the supposed eruption of the 22nd of
January, 1792. The group of volcanoes in the Caribbee Islands
resembles that of the volcanoes of Quito and Los Pastos; craters
with which the subterranean fire does not appear to communicate are
ranged on the same line with burning craters, and alternate with
them.
Notwithstanding the intimate connection manifested in the action of
the volcanoes of the smaller West India Islands and the earthquakes
of Terra Firma, it often happens that shocks felt in the volcanic
archipelago are not propagated to the island of Trinidad, or to the
coasts of Caracas and Cumana. This phenomenon is in no way
surprising: even in the Caribbees the commotions are often confined
to one place. The great eruption of the volcano in St. Vincent's
did not occasion an earthquake at Martinique or Guadaloupe. Loud
explosions were heard there as well as at Venezuela, but the ground
was not convulsed.
These explosions must not be confounded with the rolling noise
which everywhere precedes the slightest commotions; they are often
heard on the banks of the Orinoco, and (as we were assured by
persons living on the spot) between the Rio Arauca and Cuchivero.
Father Morello relates that at the Mission of Cabruta the
subterranean noise so much resembles discharges of small cannon
(pedreros) that it has seemed as if a battle were being fought at a
distance. On the 21st of October, 1766, the day of the terrible
earthquake which desolated the province of New Andalusia, the
ground was simultaneously shaken at Cumana, at Caracas, at
Maracaybo, and on the banks of the Casanare, the Meta, the Orinoco,
and the Ventuario. Father Gili has described these commotions at
the Mission of Encaramada, a country entirely granitic, where they
were accompanied by loud explosions. Great fallings-in of the earth
took place in the mountain Paurari, and near the rock Aravacoto a
small island disappeared in the Orinoco. The undulatory motion
continued during a whole hour. This seemed the first signal of
those violent commotions which shook the coasts of Cumana and
Cariaco for more than ten months. It might be supposed that men
living in woods, with no other shelter than huts of reeds and
palm-leaves, could have little to dread from earthquakes. But at
Erevato and Caura, where these phenomena are of rare occurrence,
they terrify the Indians, frighten the beasts of the forests, and
impel the crocodiles to quit the waters for the shore. Nearer the
sea, where shocks are frequent, far from being dreaded by the
inhabitants, they are regarded with satisfaction as the prognostics
of a wet and fertile year.
In this dissertation on the earthquakes of Terra Firma and on the
volcanoes of the neighbouring archipelago of the West India
Islands, I have pursued the plan of first relating a number of
particular facts, and then considering them in one general point of
view. Everything announces in the interior of the globe the
operation of active powers, which, by mutual reaction, balance and
modify one another. The greater our ignorance of the causes of
these undulatory movements, these evolutions of heat, these
formations of elastic fluids, the more it becomes the duty of
persons who apply themselves to the study of physical science to
examine the relations which these phenomena so uniformly present at
great distances apart. It is only by considering these various
relations under a general point of view, and tracing them over a
great extent of the surface of the globe, through formations of
rocks the most different, that we are led to abandon the
supposition of trifling local causes, strata of pyrites, or of
ignited coal.* (* See "Views of Nature"—On the structure and
action of volcanoes in different parts of the world, page 353
(Bohn's edition); also "Cosmos" pages 199-225 (Bohn's edition).)
The following is the series of phenomena remarked on the northern
coasts of Cumana, Nueva Barcelona, and Caracas; and presumed to be
connected with the causes which produce earthquakes and eruptions
of lava. We shall begin with the most eastern extremity, the island
of Trinidad; which seems rather to belong to the shore of the
continent than to the system of the mountains of the West India
Islands.
1. The pit which throws up asphaltum in the bay of Mayaro, on the
eastern coast of the island of Trinidad, southward of Point
Guataro. This is the mine of chapapote or mineral tar of the
country. I was assured that in the months of March and June the
eruptions are often attended with violent explosions, smoke, and
flames. Almost on the same parallel, and also in the sea, but
westward of the island (near Punta de la Brea, and to the south of
the port of Naparaimo), we find a similar vent. On the neighbouring
coast, in a clayey ground, appears the celebrated lake of asphaltum
(Laguna de la Brea), a marsh, the waters of which have the same
temperature as the atmosphere. The small cones situated at the
south-western extremity of the island, between Point Icacos and the
Rio Erin, appear to have some analogy with the volcanoes of air and
mud which I met with at Turbaco in the kingdom of New Grenada. I
mention these situations of asphaltum on account of the remarkable
circumstances peculiar to them in these regions; for I am not
unaware that naphtha, petroleum, and asphaltum are found equally in
volcanic and secondary regions,* and even more frequently in the
latter. (* The inflammable emanations of Pietra Mala, (consisting
of hydrogen gas containing naphtha in a state of suspension) issue
from the Alpine limestone, which may be traced from Covigliano to
Raticofa, and which lies on ancient sandstone near Scarica l'Asino.
Under this sandstone (old red sandstone) we find black transition
limestone and the grauwack (quartzose psammite) of Florence.)
Petroleum is found floating on the sea thirty leagues north of
Trinidad, around the island of Grenada, which contains an
extinguished crater and basalts.
2. Hot Springs of Irapa, at the north-eastern extremity of New
Andalusia, between Rio Caribe, Soro, and Yaguarapayo.
3. Air-volcano, or Salce, of Cumacatar, to the south of San Jose
and Carupano, near the northern coast of the continent, between La
Montana de Paria and the town of Cariaco. Almost constant
explosions are felt in a clayey soil, which is affirmed to be
impregnated with sulphur. Hot sulphureous waters gush out with such
violence that the ground is agitated by very sensible shocks. It is
said that flames have been frequently seen issuing out since the
great earthquake of 1797. These facts are well worthy of being
examined.
4. Petroleum-spring of the Buen Pastor, near Rio Areo. Large masses
of sulphur have been found in clayey soils at Guayuta, as in the
valley of San Bonifacio, and near the junction of the Rio Pao with
the Orinoco.
5. The Hot Waters (Aguas Calientes) south of the Rio Azul, and the
Hollow Ground of Cariaco, which, at the time of the great
earthquake of Cumana, threw up sulphuretted water and viscous
petroleum.
6. Hot waters of the gulf of Cariaco.
7. Petroleum-spring in the same gulf, near Maniquarez. It issues
from mica-slate.
8. Flames issuing from the earth, near Cumana, on the banks of the
Manzanares, and at Mariguitar, on the southern coast of the gulf of
Cariaco, at the time of the great earthquake of 1797.
9. Igneous phenomena of the mountain of Cuchivano, near Cumanacoa.
10. Petroleum-spring gushing from a shoal to the north of the
Caracas Islands. The smell of this spring warns ships of the danger
of this shoal, on which there is only one fathom of water.
11. Thermal springs of the mountain of the Brigantine, near Nueva
Barcelona. Temperature 43.2 degrees (centigrade).
12. Thermal springs of Provisor, near San Diego, in the province of
New Barcelona.
13. Thermal springs of Onoto, between Turmero and Maracay, in the
valleys of Aragua, west of Caracas.
14. Thermal springs of Mariara, in the same valleys. Temperature
58.9 degrees.
15. Thermal springs of Las Trincheras, between Porto Cabello and
Valencia, issuing from granite like those of Mariara, and forming a
river of warm water (Rio de Aguas Calientes). Temperature 90.4
degrees.
16. Boiling springs of the Sierra Nevada of Merida.
17. Aperture of Mena, on the borders of Lake Maracaybo. It throws
up asphaltum, and is said to emit gaseous emanations, which ignite
spontaneously, and are seen at a great distance.
These are the springs of petroleum and of thermal waters, the
igneous meteors, and the ejections of muddy substances attended
with explosions, of which I acquired a knowledge in the vast
provinces of Venezuela, whilst travelling over a space of two
hundred leagues from east to west. These various phenomena have
occasioned great excitement among the inhabitants since the
catastrophes of 1797 and 1812: yet they present nothing which
constitutes a volcano, in the sense hitherto attributed to that
word. If the apertures, which throw up vapours and water with
violent noise, be sometimes called volcancitos, it is only by such
of the inhabitants as persuade themselves that volcanoes must
necessarily exist in countries so frequently exposed to
earthquakes. Advancing from the burning crater of St. Vincent in
the directions of south, west and south-west, first by the chain of
the Caribbee Islands, then by the littoral chain of Cumana and
Venezuela, and finally by the Cordilleras of New Grenada, along a
distance of three hundred and eighty leagues, we find no active
volcano before we arrive at Purace, near Popayan. The total absence
of apertures, through which melted substances can issue, in that
part of the continent, which stretches eastward of the Cordillera
of the Andes, and eastward of the Rocky Mountains, is a most
remarkable geological fact.
In this chapter we have examined the great commotions which from
time to time convulse the stony crust of the globe, and scatter
desolation in regions favoured by the most precious gifts of
nature. An uninterrupted calm prevails in the upper atmosphere;
but, to use an expression of Franklin, more ingenious than
accurate, thunder often rolls in the subterranean atmosphere,
amidst that mixture of elastic fluids, the impetuous movements of
which are frequently felt at the surface of the earth. The
destruction of so many populous cities presents a picture of the
greatest calamities which afflict mankind. A people struggling for
independence are suddenly exposed to the want of subsistence, and
of all the necessaries of life. Famished and without shelter, the
inhabitants are dispersed through the country, and numbers who have
escaped from the ruin of their dwellings are swept away by disease.
Far from strengthening mutual confidence among the citizens, the
feeling of misfortune destroys it; physical calamities augment
civil discord; nor does the aspect of a country bathed in tears and
blood appease the fury of the victorious party.
After the recital of so many calamities, the mind is soothed by
turning to consolatory remembrances. When the great catastrophe of
Caracas was known in the United States, the Congress, assembled at
Washington, unanimously decreed that five ships laden with flour
should be sent to the coast of Venezuela; their cargoes to be
distributed among the most needy of the inhabitants. The generous
contribution was received with the warmest gratitude; and this
solemn act of a free people, this mark of national interest, of
which the advanced civilization of the Old World affords but few
examples, seemed to be a valuable pledge of the mutual sympathy
which ought for ever to unite the nations of North and South
America.</div></body></text></TEI>