<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="54">INTRODUCTION.
The Secondary Mechanical Sciences.
IN the sciences of Mechanics
and Physical Astronomy, Motion and Force are the direct and primary
objects of our attention. But there is another class of sciences in
which we endeavor to reduce phenomena, not evidently mechanical, to a
known dependence upon mechanical properties and laws. In the cases to
which I refer, the facts do not present themselves to the senses as
modifications of position and motion, but as secondary
qualities, which are found to be in some way derived from those
primary attributes. Also, in these cases the phenomena are reduced to
their mechanical laws and causes in a secondary manner; namely, by
treating them as the operation of a medium interposed between
the object and the organ of sense. These, then, we may call
Secondary Mechanical Sciences. The sciences of this kind which
require our notice are those which treat of the sensible qualities,
Sound, Light, and Heat; that is. Acoustics, Optics, and
Thermotics.
It will be recollected that our object is not by any means to give
a full statement of all the additions which have been successively
made to our knowledge on the subjects under review, or a complete list
of the persons by whom such additions have been made; but to present a
view of the progress of each of those branches of knowledge as a
theoretical science;—to point out the Epochs of the
discovery of those general principles which reduce many facts to one
theory; and to note all that is most characteristic and instructive in
the circumstances and persons which bear upon such Epochs. A history
of any science, written with such objects, will not need to be long;
but it will fail in its purpose altogether, if it do not distinctly
exhibit some well-marked and prominent features. 24
We begin our account of the Secondary Mechanical Sciences with
Acoustics, because the progress towards right theoretical views, was,
in fact, made much earlier in the science of Sound, than in those of
Light and of Heat; and also, because a clear comprehension of the
theory to which we are led in this case, is the best preparation for
the difficulties (by no means inconsiderable) of the reasonings of
theorists on the other subjects.
</div></body></text></TEI>