<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="7">CHAPTER V.
Charles was now nine years of age. His mother and
myself had delighted ourselves with observing and forwarding
the opening of his infant mind, and had hitherto been[46]
contented with the assistance of a neighbouring priest by
way of preceptor. But, as he was our only son, we were
desirous that he should obtain every advantage of education.
We were neither of us illiterate; but, in the course of
twenty-three years, which had elapsed since I was myself of
Charles’s age, the progress of literature and the literary
passion in Europe had been astonishingly great, and I was
anxious that he should realise in his own person every
benefit which the fortunate and illustrious period of human
affairs in which he began to exist seemed to hold out to
him. Beside, there was an impetuosity and forwardness in
his character, that seemed ill to brook the profound solitude
and retirement in which his mother and I were contented
to live. His case demanded companions of his own
age, a little world of fellow-beings, with whom he might
engage in their petty business and cares, with whose passions
his own might jostle or might sympathise, who might
kindle his emulation, and open to him the field of fraternal
associations and amity.
There was, however, a considerable difficulty attendant
on this question. The schools of real literature in France,
where languages were properly taught, and science might
be acquired, were at this time exceedingly few. The
nearest university was that of Toulouse, at the distance of
twenty-six leagues. This was, practically speaking, as far
from us as Paris itself. Was then our darling child to be
torn from his parents, from all he was accustomed to see,
and all by whom he was loved, to be planted in the midst
of strangers, to have his mind excited to observation, and
the spirit of generous contention roused, at the risk of
suppressing the tender affections of his soul, and the sentiments
of duty, reliance, and love? There seemed, however,
to be no alternative. It was necessary that a temporary
separation should take place. Intellectual improvement was
a point by all means to be pursued; and we must direct
our efforts to keep alive along with it those winning qualities,
and that softness of heart, which had hitherto rendered
Charles so eminently our delight. Such were our
fond speculations and projects for the future.
It was at length determined that I should proceed along[47]
with him to Paris. I could there observe upon the spot
the state of the university, and the means of learning that
existed in the metropolis; and could consult with some of
those eminent luminaries with whom I had become acquainted
at the house of the Marquis de Damville. Marguerite
declined accompanying me upon this occasion. Her
father was dead: she could not think of quitting her daughters
for any considerable time; and our nuptial engagement
of residing always in the country gave her a repugnance to
the removing with her whole family to Paris. It was left
probable that she might come to me when the business was
settled, if at that time it was determined to leave her son at
the capital; and that she might then reconduct me to the
place, which had been the scene of all my happiness, but
which I was destined never to revisit in peace.
Preliminaries being at length fully adjusted in the manner
that appeared suitable to the importance of the occasion,
I set off for the metropolis of my country, which I had seen
only once, and that for a very short period, in the course
of ten years. That visit had been produced by a very melancholy
circumstance, the death of the Marquis de Damville.
Marguerite and myself had then been summoned,
and arrived at his hotel but a few days before he expired.
Though extremely weakened by the mortal disease under
which he laboured, he retained all the faculties of his mind,
and conversed with us in the most affectionate and endearing
terms. He congratulated us upon our mutual felicity;
nor could the situation in which we found him, upon the
brink of an everlasting oblivion of all earthly things, abate
the sincerity and fervour of his delight. He thanked me
for my carriage and conduct as a husband, which, he said,
might with propriety be held up as a model to the human
species. He applauded himself for that mingled discernment
and determination, which, as he affirmed, had so
opportunely secured my virtue and his daughter’s happiness.
He trusted that I was now sufficiently weaned from those
habits which had formerly given him so much alarm. At
the same time he conjured me, by every motive that an
overflowing enthusiasm could suggest, to persist in my good
resolutions, and never to change that residence, where I[48]
had found every degree of delight of which the human
mind is in its present condition susceptible. “Do not,” said
he, “be drawn aside by ambition; do not be dazzled by the
glitter of idle pomp and decoration; do not enter the remotest
circle of the vortex of dissipation! Live in the
midst of your family; cultivate domestic affection; be the
solace and joy of your wife; watch for the present and
future welfare of your children; and be assured that you
will then be found no contemptible or unbeneficial member
of the community at large!”
Such were the last advices of the Marquis de Damville.
Excellent man! how ill were your lessons remembered!
how ill your kindness remunerated! He died in the sixth
year of our marriage. The serious impression which this
event produced in my mind gave me small inclination to
enter into any species of society, and disposed me to quit
Paris as soon as every respect had been paid to the obsequies
of the deceased.
Upon my arrival in the metropolis on the present occasion,
I immediately sought to renew my acquaintance with
those amiable and eminent persons, who had for the most
part constituted the circle of the Marquis de Damville.
They received me with that interest and attention that I
have usually found attendant on a cultivated mind. The
pleasure was considerable, that resulted from meeting them
thus again, after ten years’ cessation of intercourse. A few
of them, indeed, were dead, and others dispersed by various
accidents in different parts of France or of Europe. The
greater part, however, I still found in that celebrated city,
which might well be considered as the metropolis of the
civilised world. The king had early been distinguished by
his love of letters and the arts; and added years, while
they abated in his mind the eagerness of ambition and glory,
gave new strength to his more cultivated propensities. The
liberality of his conduct, and the polished ease that characterised
his manners, produced a general predilection in
favour of the capital in which he resided.
I found all my former friends matured and improved by
the silent influence of time. Their knowledge was increased;
their views rendered wider; their conversation[49]
was more amusing and instructive, their manners more
bland and unaffected. But, if their characters had experienced
revolution, mine was more materially changed. I
had before encountered them with all the heat and presumption
of youth, with no views so much present to my
mind as those of chivalry and a factitious honour, with no
experience but that of a camp. I was impetuous, volatile,
and dissipated. I had not rested long enough upon any one
of the flowers of intellect to extract its honey; and my
mind was kept in a state of preternatural agitation by the
passions of a gamester. It was now become cool, moderate,
and tranquil. The society of Marguerite had contributed
much to the improvement of my character; I had lived in
no idle and brutish solitude, but in the midst of contemplation
and letters; and I had the passions of a husband
and a father, in the extremest degree attached to his family.
These passions will be found, perhaps, to be the true school
of humanity: the man, whose situation continually exercises
in him the softest and most amiable charities of our nature,
will almost infallibly surpass his brethren in kindness to
sympathise with, and promptness to relieve, the distresses
of others.
Will it be accounted strange that, in Paris, surrounded
by persons of various knowledge and liberal benevolence, I
found myself under the influence of other feelings, than any
I had lately experienced? I was like a man who had suffered
long calamity in a famished vessel or a town besieged,
and is immediately after introduced into the midst of luxury,
to a table loaded with the most costly dainties. Every viand
has to his apprehension an exquisite relish, and every wine
a delicious flavour, that he never perceived in them before.
Let no one infer that my love for Marguerite was diminished;
it has already sufficiently appeared in the course of
my narrative, that no happiness could be more consummate
than mine was with this admirable woman. Had I been
called upon to choose for the seat of my future life, between
my paternal château in the Bordelois, with Marguerite to
grace my abode, on the one hand; and all the gratifications
that Paris could afford, on the other, I should not have
hesitated even for an instant. But the mind of man is[50]
made capacious of various pleasures; and a person of sound
and uncorrupted judgment will perhaps always enjoy with
emotion the delights which for a long time before he had
not encountered, however enviable his content may have
been under their absence. I delighted to converse with
the men of genius and refinement with whom Paris at this
time abounded. It was a feast of soul of which I had
rarely partaken in my rural retreat. I delighted to combine
excellence with number, and, to a considerable degree at
least, variety of intercourse with sentiments of regard and
friendship. In these select societies I found no cold suppressions
and reserve. Their members were brethren in
disposition, similar in their pursuits, and congenial in their
sentiments. When any one spoke, it was that the person
to whom he addressed himself might apprehend what was
passing in his thoughts. They participated with sincerity
and a liberal mind in each other’s feelings, whether of gay
delight or melancholy disappointment.
Thus situated, I forgot for a time my engagements with
Marguerite. The scenes of St. Leon, its fields, its walks,
its woods and its streams, faded from my mind. I forgot
the pleasure with which I had viewed my children sporting
on the green, and the delicious, rural suppers which I had
so often partaken with my wife beneath my vines and my
fig-trees at the period of the setting sun. When I set out
for Paris, these images had dwelt upon my mind, and saddened
my fancy. At every stage I felt myself removed
still further from the scene where my treasures and my
affections were deposited. But, shortly after, new scenes
and new employments engaged my thoughts. The pleasures
which I sought but weakly at first, every time they
were tasted increased my partiality for them. I seemed for
a time to be under the influence of an oblivion of my former
life. Thus circumstanced, the folly which had so deep a
root in my character, took hold of me. I hired a magnificent
hotel, and entertained at my own expense those persons
in whose society I principally delighted. My circles
became more numerous than those of the Marquis de Damville,
and were conducted in a very different style of splendour
and profusion. I corresponded with Marguerite; but[51]
I continually found some new pretext for lengthening my
stay; and she on her part, though the kindest and most
indulgent of women, became seriously alarmed and unhappy.
As my parties were more numerous than those of the
Marquis de Damville had been, they were more mixed.
Among others, I occasionally associated with some of those
noblemen who had been the companions of my former dissipation
and gaming. An obvious consequence resulted
from this. Parties of play were occasionally proposed to
me. I resisted—I yielded. My first compliances were
timid, hesitating, and painful. I recollected the lessons
and exhortations of my excellent father-in-law. At length,
however, my alarms abated. I reproached myself with the
want of an honourable confidence in my own firmness, and
the cowardice of supposing that I was not to be trusted with
the direction of my conduct.
One evening I ventured beyond the cautious limits I had
at first prescribed myself, and won a considerable sum.
This incident produced a strong impression upon me, and
filled my mind with tumult and agitation. There was a
secret that I had concealed almost from myself, but which
now recurred to me with tenfold violence. I was living
beyond the means I had to discharge my expenses. My
propensity of this sort seemed to be fatal and irresistible.
My marriage with Marguerite had occurred opportunely, to
heal the breaches I had at that time made in my fortune,
and to take from me the consciousness of embarrassments
which I should otherwise have deeply felt. The death of
the Marquis, however deplorable in other respects, happened
at a period when the spirit of profusion and magnificence
which characterised me had again involved my affairs in
considerable difficulty. It might be supposed that these two
cases of experience would have sufficed to extirpate my
folly; but they had rather the contrary effect. In each of
them the event was such as to prevent extravagance and
thoughtlessness from producing their genuine results; and,
of consequence, they appeared less criminal and mischievous
in my eyes than otherwise they probably would have appeared.
I rather increased than diminished my establishment[52]
upon the death of my father-in-law. I had no reasonable
prospect of any property hereafter to descend to me,
that should exonerate me from the consequences of further
prodigality. But I did not advert to this. I saw myself
surrounded by my children; they were the delight and solace
of my life; and yet I was needless of their interests.
Sometimes I resolved upon a more rigid economy: but
economy is a principle that does not easily lay hold of any
but a heart framed to receive it. It is a business of attentive
and vigilant detail. It easily escapes the mind, amidst
the impetuosity of the passions, the obstinacy of rooted
propensities, and the seduction of long established habits.
Marguerite, indeed, did not share with me in these follies;
the simplicity and ingenuousness of her mind were such,
that she would have been as happy in a cottage as a palace;
but, though she did not partake my vices, an ill-judged
forbearance and tenderness for my feelings did not permit
her effectually to counteract them. This is, perhaps, the
only defect of character I am able to impute to her.
After I had won the sum to which I have alluded, I
retired to my hotel full of anxious thoughts. It produced
upon me, in some degree, the same effect as ordinarily belongs
to a great calamity. I lay all night sleepless and
disturbed. Ruin and despair presented themselves to my
mind in a thousand forms. Heedless prodigality and dilapidated
revenues passed in review before me. I counted
the years of my life. I had completed the thirty-second
year of my age: this was scarcely half the probable duration
of human existence. How was I to support the remaining
period, a period little assorted to difficulties and expedients;
and which, in the close of it, seems imperiously to call for
every indulgence? Hitherto, an interval of four or five
years had repeatedly sufficed to involve me in serious embarrassment.
My children were growing up around me;
my family was likely to become still larger; as my offspring
increased in years, their demands upon my revenues would
be more considerable. Were these demands to be slighted?
Were my daughters, nay, was the heir of my rank and my
name, to be committed to the compassion of the world,
unprovided and forlorn? What a cheerless prospect! What[53]
a gloomy and disconsolate hue did these ideas spread upon
that future, which the health of the human mind requires
to have gilded with the beams of hope and expectation? I
had already tried the expedient of economy; and I had
uniformly found this inestimable and only sheet-anchor of
prudence gliding from my deluded grasp. Could I promise
myself better success in future? There seemed to be something
in my habits, whether of inattention, ostentation, or
inconsistency, that baffled the strongest motives by which
parsimony and frugality can be enforced.
Why did these thoughts importunately recur to me in
the present moment? They were the suggestions of a malignant
genius,—thoughts, the destination of which was
to lead me into a gulf of misery and guilt! While I was
going on in a regular train of expense, while I was scooping
the mine that was to swallow me and my hopes together,
I had the art to keep these reflections at bay. Now
that I had met with an unexpected piece of good fortune,
they rushed upon me with irresistible violence. Unfortunate
coincidence! Miserable,—rather let me say, guilty, abandoned
miscreant!
As soon as I rose in the morning, I went to the closet
where, the evening before, I had deposited my recent acquisitions.
I spread out the gold before me. I gazed
upon it with intentness. My eyes, a moment after, rolled
in vacancy. I traversed the apartment with impatient steps.
All the demon seemed to make his descent upon my soul.
This was the first time that I had ever felt the struggle of
conscious guilt and dishonour. I was far indeed from anticipating
that species of guilt, and that species of ruin,
which soon after overwhelmed me. My mind did not once
recur to the possibility of any serious mischief. I dwelt
only, as gamesters perhaps usually do, upon the alternative
between acquisition and no acquisition. I did not take into
the account the ungovernableness of my own passions. I
assumed it as unquestionable, that I could stop when I
pleased. The thoughts that tortured me were, in the first
place, those of a sanguine and unexperienced adventurer in
a lottery, whose mind rests not for a moment upon the sum
he has risked, but who, having in fancy the principal prize[54]
already in his possession, and having distributed it to various
objects and purposes, sometimes fearfully recurs to the possibility
of his disappointment, and anticipates with terror
what will be his situation, if deprived of this imaginary
wealth. I had now, for the first time, opened my eyes to
the real state of my affairs, and I clung with proportionable
vehemence to this plank which was to bear me from the
storm. In the second place, I felt, though darkly and unwillingly,
the immorality of my conception. To game may,
in some instances, not be in diametrical opposition to liberality
of mind; but he who games for the express purpose
of improving his circumstances must be an idiot, if he does
not sometimes recollect that the money lost may be as serious
a mischief to his neighbour, as the money gained can
possibly be a benefit to himself. It is past a question, that
he who thus turns his amusement into his business loses
the dignity of a man of honour, and puts himself upon a
level with the most avaricious and usurious merchant.
Though I was far from having digested a specific plan
of enriching myself by these discreditable means, yet the
very tumult of my thoughts operated strongly to lead me
once more to the gaming-table. I was in no humour to
busy myself with my own thoughts; the calmness of literary
discussion, and the polished interchange of wit, which had
lately so much delighted me, had now no attraction for my
heart; the turbulence of a scene of high play alone had
power to distract my attention from the storm within. I
won a second time. I felt the rapidity and intenseness of
my contemplations still further accelerated. I will not over
again detail what they were. Suffice it to say, that my
hopes became more ardent, my conception of the necessity
of this resource more impressive, and my alarm lest this
last expedient should fail me more tormenting.
The next time I lost half as much as the sum of my
winnings. I then proceeded for several days in a nearly
regular alternation of gain and loss. This, as soon as the
fact unavoidably forced itself upon my mind, only served
to render my thoughts more desperate. No, exclaimed I,
it was not for this that I entered upon so tormenting a
pursuit. It is not for this that I have deserted the learned
societies which were lately my delight, and committed myself[55]
to a sea of disquiet and anxiety. I came not here, like
a boy, for amusement; or, like one who has been bred in
the lap of ignorance and wealth, to seek a relief from the
burden of existence, and to find a stimulus to animate my
torpid spirits. Am I then to be for ever baffled? Am I to
cultivate a tract of land, which is to present me nothing in
return but unvaried barenness? Am I continually to wind up
my passions, and new-string my attention in vain? Am I
a mere instrument to be played upon by endless hopes and
fears and tormenting wishes? Am I to be the sport of
events, the fool of promise, always agitated with near approaching
good, yet always deluded?
This frame of mind led me on insensibly to the most
extravagant adventures. It threw me in the first place into
the hands of notorious gamblers. Men of real property
shrunk from the stakes I proposed; as, though they were
in some degree infected with the venom of gaming, their
infection was not so deep as mine, nor with my desperation
of thought. The players with whom I engaged were for
the most part well known to every one but myself, not to
be able to pay the sums they played for, if they lost; nay,
this fact might be said in some sense to be known to me as
well as the rest, though I obstinately steeled myself against
the recollection of it. One evening I won of one of these
persons a very large sum, for which I suffered him to play
with me upon honour. The consequence was simple. The
next morning he took his departure from Paris, and I heard
of him no more.
Before this, however, the tide of success had set strongly
against me. I had sustained some serious vicissitudes;
and, while I was playing with the wretch I have just mentioned,
my eagerness increased as my good luck began, and
I flattered myself that I should now avenge myself of fortune
for some of her late unkindnesses. My anguish—why
should I call the thing by a disproportionate and
trivial appellation?—my agony—was by so much the
greater, when I found that this person, the very individual
who had already stripped me of considerable sums, had
disappeared, and left me without the smallest benefit from
my imaginary winnings.
[56]
No man who has not felt, can possibly image to himself
the tortures of a gamester, of a gamester like me, who
played for the improvement of his fortune, who played with
the recollection of a wife and children dearer to him than
the blood that bubbled through the arteries of his heart,
who might be said, like the savages of ancient Germany, to
make these relations the stake for which he threw, who
saw all my own happiness and all theirs through the long
vista of life, depending on the turn of a card! Hell is but
the chimera of priests, to bubble idiots and cowards. What
have they invented, to come into competition with what
I felt! Their alternate interchange of flames and ice
is but a feeble image of the eternal varieties of hope and
fear. All bodily racks and torments are nothing compared
with certain states of the human mind. The gamester
would be the most pitiable, if he were not the most despicable
creature that exists. Arrange ten bits of painted
paper in a certain order, and he is ready to go wild with
the extravagance of his joy. He is only restrained by
some remains of shame, from dancing about the room, and
displaying the vileness of his spirit by every sort of freak
and absurdity. At another time, when his hopes have
been gradually worked up into a paroxysm, an unexpected
turn arrives, and he is made the most miserable of men.
Never shall I cease to recollect the sensation I have repeatedly
felt, in the instantaneous sinking of the spirits, the
conscious fire that spread over my visage, the anger in my
eye, the burning dryness of my throat, the sentiment that
in a moment was ready to overwhelm with curses the cards,
the stake, my own existence, and all mankind. How every
malignant and insufferable passion seemed to rush upon my
soul! What nights of dreadful solitude and despair did I
repeatedly pass during the progress of my ruin! It was the
night of the soul! My mind was wrapped in a gloom that
could not be pierced! My heart was oppressed with a
weight that no power human or divine was equal to
remove! My eyelids seemed to press downward with an
invincible burden! My eyeballs were ready to start and
crack their sockets! I lay motionless, the victim of ineffable
horror! The whole endless night seemed to be[57]
filled with one vast, appalling, immovable idea! It was a
stupor, more insupportable and tremendous than the
utmost whirl of pain, or the fiercest agony of exquisite perception!
One day that my mind was in a state of excessive anguish
and remorse (I had already contrived by this infernal
means to dispossess myself of the half of my property),
my son came unexpectedly into my chamber. For some
time I had scarcely ever seen him: such is a gamester!
All the night, while he slept, I was engaged in these haunts
of demons. All the day, while he was awake, and studying
with his masters, or amusing himself, I was in my bed-chamber,
endeavouring to court a few broken hours of sleep.
When, notwithstanding the opposition of our habits, I had
the opportunity of seeing him, I rather shunned to use,
than sought to embrace it. The sight of him had a savour
of bitterness in it, that more than balanced all the solace of
natural affection. It brought before me the image of his
mother and his sisters; it presented to my soul a frightful
tale of deserted duties; it was more galling and envenomed
than the sting of scorpions.
Starting at the sound of the opening door, I called out
abruptly, and with some harshness, “Who is there? What
do you want?”
“It is I, sir,” replied the boy; “it is Charles, come to
pay his duty to you!”
“I do not want you now; you should not come, but
when you know I am at leisure,” answered I somewhat
disturbed.
“Very well, sir; very well: I am going.” As he spoke
his voice seemed suffocated with tears. He was on the
point of shutting the door, and leaving me to myself.
“Charles!” said I, not well knowing what it was I intended
to do.
He returned.
“Come here, my dear boy!”
I took his hand, I drew him between my knees, I hid
my face in his neck, I shook with the violence of my emotion.
“Go, go, boy: you perceive I cannot talk to you.”
[58]
I pushed him gently from me.
“Papa!” cried he, “I do not like to leave you. I
know I am but a boy, and can be but of little use to you.
If mamma were with you, I would not be troublesome. I
should cry when I saw you were grieved, but I would ask
no questions, and would leave you, because you desired it.
I hope you have not had any bad news?”
“No, my boy, no. Come to me to-morrow, and I will
be at leisure, and will talk a great deal to you.”
“Ah, papa, to-morrow! Every day that I did not see
you, I thought it would be to-morrow! And there was one
to-morrow, and another to-morrow, and so many, that it
seemed as if you had forgotten to speak to me at all.”
“Why, Charles, you do not doubt my word? I tell
you that to-morrow you shall see me as long as you please.”
“Well, well, I will wait! But do then let it be all day!
I will not go to college, and it shall be a holiday. Papa, I
do not like my lessons half so well as I did, since I have
neither you nor mamma that I can tell what they are
about.”
“Good-bye, Charles! Be a good boy! remember to-morrow!
Good-bye!”
“Papa! now I am sure you look a good deal better than
you did at first. Let me tell you something about the
lesson I read this morning. It was a story of Zaleucus
the Locrian, who put out one of his own eyes, that he
might preserve eye-sight to his son.”
This artless story, thus innocently introduced, cut me to
the soul. I started in my chair, and hid my face upon the
table.
“Papa, what is the matter? Indeed you frighten me!”
“Zaleucus was a father! What then am I?”
“Yes, Zaleucus was very good indeed! But, do you
know, his son was very naughty. It was his disobedience
and wickedness that made him liable to such a punishment.
I would not for the world be like Zaleucus’s son. I hope,
papa, you will never suffer from my wilfulness. You shall
not, papa, indeed, indeed!”
I caught the boy in my arms. “No, you are very good!
you are too good! I cannot bear it!”
[59]
“Well, papa, I wish I were able to show you that I
love you as well as ever Zaleucus loved his son!”
I was melted with the ingenuousness of the boy’s expression.
I quitted him. I paced up and down the
room. Suddenly, as if by paroxysm of insanity, I seized
my child by the arm, I seated myself, I drew him towards
me, I put my eye upon him.
“Boy, how dare you talk to me of Zaleucus? Do you
mean to insinuate a reproach? Do I not discharge a father’s
duty? If I do not, know, urchin, I will not be insulted
by my child!”
The boy was astonished. He burst into tears, and was
silent.
I was moved by his evident distress. “No, child, you
have no father. I am afraid you have not. You do not
know my baseness. You do not know that I am the deadliest
foe you have in the world.”
“Dear papa, do not talk thus! Do not I know that you
are the best of men? Do not I love you and mamma
better than every body else put together?”
“Well, Charles,” cried I, endeavouring to compose myself,
“we will talk no more now. Did not I tell you, you
should not come to me but when you knew it was a proper
time? I hope you will never have reason to hate me.”
“I never will hate you, papa, do to me what you will!”
He saw I wished to be alone, and left me.
</div></body></text></TEI>