<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="69">CHAPTER VIII.
Attempts to discover the Laws of other
Phenomena.
THE phenomena which result
from optical combinations, even of a comparatively simple nature, are
extremely complex. The theory which is now known accounts for these
results with the most curious exactness, and points out the laws which
pervade the apparent confusion; but without this key to the
appearances, it was scarcely possible that any rule or order should be
detected. The undertaking was of 79 the same kind as it would have been, to
discover all the inequalities of the moon’s motion without the aid of
the doctrine of gravity. We will enumerate some of the phenomena which
thus employed and perplexed the cultivators of optics.
The fringes of shadows were one of the most curious and noted of
such classes of facts. These were first remarked by Grimaldi50 (1665), and referred by him to a
property of light which he called Diffraction. When shadows are
made in a dark room, by light admitted through a very small hole,
these appearances are very conspicuous and beautiful. Hooke, in 1672,
communicated similar observations to the Royal Society, as “a new
property of light not mentioned by any optical writer before;” by
which we see that he had not heard of Grimaldi’s experiments. Newton,
in his Opticks, treats of the same phenomena, which he ascribes
to the inflexion of the rays of light. He asks (Qu. 3), “Are
not the rays of light, in passing by the edges and sides of bodies,
bent several times backward and forward with a motion like that of an
eel? And do not the three fringes of colored light in shadows arise
from three such bendings?” It is remarkable that Newton should not
have noticed, that it is impossible, in this way, to account for the
facts, or even to express their laws; since the light which produces
the fringes must, on this theory, be propagated, even after it leaves
the neighborhood of the opake body, in curves, and not in straight
lines. Accordingly, all who have taken up Newton’s notion of
inflexion, have inevitably failed in giving anything like an
intelligible and coherent character to these phenomena. This is, for
example, the case with Mr. (now Lord) Brougham’s attempts in the
Philosophical Transactions for 1796. The same may be said of
other experimenters, as Mairan51 and Du Four,52 who attempted to explain the facts by
supposing an atmosphere about the opake body. Several authors, as
Maraldi,53 and Comparetti,54 repeated or
varied these experiments in different ways.
50 Physico-Mathesis, de Lumine,
Coloribus et Iride. Bologna, 1665.
51 Ac. Par. 1738.
52 Mémoires Présentés, vol.
v.
53 Ac. Par. 1723.
54 Observationes Opticæ de Luce
Inflexâ et Coloribus. Padua, 1787.
Newton had noticed certain rings of color produced by a glass
speculum, which he called “colors of thick plates,” and which he
attempted to connect with the colors of thin plates. His reasoning is
by no means satisfactory; but it was of use, by pointing out this as a
case in which his “fits” (the small periods, or cycles in the rays of
light, of 80 which
we have spoken) continued to occur for a considerable length of the
ray. But other persons, attempting to repeat his experiments,
confounded with them extraneous phenomena of other kinds; as the Duc
de Chaulnes, who spread muslin before his mirror,55 and Dr.
Herschel, who scattered hair-powder before his.56 The colors
produced by the muslin were those belonging to shadows of
gratings, afterwards examined more successfully by Fraunhofer,
when in possession of the theory. We may mention here also the colors
which appear on finely-striated surfaces, and on mother-of-pearl,
feathers, and similar substances. These had been examined by various
persons (as Boyle, Mazeas, Lord Brougham), but could still, at this
period, be only looked upon as insulated and lawless facts.
55 Ac. Par. 1755.
56 Phil. Trans. 1807.
</div></body></text></TEI>