<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="16">
      SECTION 9. OF THE FAIRCHILD LECTURE.
    

      Mr. Fairchild left by will twenty-five pounds to the Royal Society. This
      was increased by several subscriptions, and 100L. 3 per cent. South Sea
      Annuities was purchased, the interest of which was to be devoted annually
      to pay for a sermon to be preached at St.Leonard's, Shoreditch.
    

      Few members of the Society, perhaps, are aware, either of the bequest or
      of its annual payment. I shall merely observe, that for five years, from
      1800 to 1804, it was regularly given to Mr. Ascough; and that for
      twenty-six years past, it has been as regularly given to the Rev. Mr.
      Ellis.
    

      The annual amount is too trifling to stimulate to any extraordinary
      exertions; yet, small as it is, it might, if properly applied, be
      productive of much advantage to religion, and of great honour to the
      Society. For this purpose, it would be desirable that it should be
      delivered at some church or chapel, more likely to be attended by members
      of the Royal Society. Notice of it should be given at the place of worship
      appointed, at least a week previous to its delivery, and at the two
      preceding weekly meetings of the Royal Society. The name of the gentleman
      nominated for that year, and the church at which the sermon is to be
      preached, should be stated.
    

      With this publicity attending it, and by a judicious selection of the
      first two or three gentlemen appointed to deliver it, it would soon be
      esteemed an honour to be invited to compose such a lecture, and the
      Society might always find in its numerous list of members or aspirants,
      persons well qualified to fulfil a task as beneficial for the promotion of
      true religion, as it ever must be for the interest of science. I am
      tempted to believe that such a course would call forth exertions of the
      most valuable character, as well as give additional circulation to what is
      already done on that subject.
    

      The geological speculations which have been adduced, perhaps with too much
      haste by some, as according with the Mosaic history, and by others, as
      inconsistent with its truth, would, if this subject had been attentively
      considered, have been allowed to remain until the fullest and freest
      inquiry had irrevocably fixed their claim to the character of indisputable
      facts. But, I will not press this subject further on my reader's
      attention, lest he should think I am myself delivering the lecture. All
      that I could have said on this point has been so much more ably stated by
      one whose enlightened view of geological science has taken away some
      difficulties from its cultivators, and, I hope, removed a stumbling-block
      from many respectable individuals, that I should only weaken by adding to
      the argument. [I allude to the critique of Dr. Ure's Geology in the
      British Review, for July, 1829; an Essay, equally worthy of a philosopher
      and a Christian.]
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>