<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="27">

CHAPTER II.
Of the Idea of Cause.



1. WE
see in the world around us a constant succession of
causes and effects connected with each other. The laws of
this connexion we learn in a great measure from experience,
by observation of the occurrences which present themselves
to our notice, succeeding one another. But in doing this,
and in attending to this succession of appearances, of which
we are aware by means of our senses, we supply from our own
minds the Idea of Cause. This Idea, as we have already shown
with respect to other Ideas, is not derived from experience,
but has its origin in the mind itself;—is introduced into
our experience by the active, and not by the passive part of
our nature.
By Cause we mean some quality, power, or efficacy, by which
a state of things produces a succeeding state. Thus the
motion of bodies from rest is produced by a cause which we
call Force: and in the particular case in which
bodies fall to the earth, this force is termed
Gravity. In these cases, the Conceptions of Force and
Gravity receive their meaning from the Idea of Cause which
they involve: for Force is conceived as the Cause of Motion.
That this Idea of Cause is not derived from experience, we
prove (as in former cases) by this consideration: that we
can make assertions, involving this idea, which are
rigorously necessary and universal; whereas knowledge
derived from experience can only be true as far as
experience goes, and can never contain in itself any
evidence whatever of its necessity. We assert that ‘Every
event must have a cause:’ and this proposition we know to be
true, not only probably, and generally, and as far as we can
see: 174 but we cannot suppose it to be false in any
single instance. We are as certain of it as of the truths of
arithmetic or geometry. We cannot doubt that it must apply
to all events past and future, in every part of the
universe, just as truly as to those occurrences which we
have ourselves observed. What causes produce what
effects;—what is the cause of any particular event;—what
will be the effect of any peculiar process;—these are
points on which experience may enlighten us. Observation and
experience may be requisite, to enable us to judge
respecting such matters. But that every event has
some cause, Experience cannot prove any more than
she can disprove. She can add nothing to the evidence of the
truth, however often she may exemplify it. This doctrine,
then, cannot have been acquired by her teaching; and the
Idea of Cause, which the doctrine involves, and on which it
depends, cannot have come into our minds from the region of
observation.
2. That we do, in fact, apply the Idea of Cause in a more
extensive manner than could be justified, if it were derived
from experience only, is easily shown. For from the
principle that everything must have a cause, we not only
reason concerning the succession of the events which occur
in the progress of the world, and which form the course of
experience; but we infer that the world itself must have a
cause;—that the chain of events connected by common
causation, must have a First Cause of a nature different
from the events themselves. This we are entitled to do, if
our Idea of Cause be independent of, and superior to,
experience: but if we have no Idea of Cause except such as
we gather from experience, this reasoning is altogether
baseless and unmeaning.
3. Again; by the use of our powers of observation, we are
aware of a succession of appearances and events. But none of
our senses or powers of external observation can detect in
these appearances the power or quality which we call Cause.
Cause is that which connects one event with another; but no
sense or perception discloses to us, or can disclose, any
connexion 175 among the events which we observe. We see
that one occurrence follows another, but we can never see
anything which shows that one occurrence must
follow another. We have already noticed1, that this
truth has been urged by metaphysicians in modern times, and
generally assented to by those who examine carefully the
connexion of their own thoughts. The arguments are, indeed,
obvious enough. One ball strikes another and causes it to
move forwards. But by what compulsion? Where is the
necessity? If the mind can see any circumstance in this case
which makes the result inevitable, let this circumstance be
pointed out. But, in fact, there is no such discoverable
necessity; for we can conceive this event not to take place
at all. The struck ball may stand still, for aught we can
see. ‘But the laws of motion will not allow it to do so.’
Doubtless they will not. But the laws of motion are learnt
from experience, and therefore can prove no necessity. Why
should not the laws of motion be other than they are? Are
they necessarily true? That they are necessarily such as do
actually regulate the impact of bodies, is at least no
obvious truth; and therefore this necessity cannot be, in
common minds, the ground of connecting the impact of one
ball with the motion of another. And assuredly, if this
fail, no other ground of such necessary connexion can be
shown. In this case, then, the events are not seen to be
necessarily connected. But if this case, where one ball
moves another by impulse, be not an instance of events
exhibiting a necessary connexion, we shall look in vain for
any example of such a connexion. There is, then, no case in
which events can be observed to be necessarily connected:
our idea of causation, which implies that the event is
necessarily connected with the cause, cannot be derived from
observation.</div></body></text></TEI>