<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ninth Bridgewater Treatise</title><author>Babbage, Charles (1791-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="25">ON THE NATURE OF A SUPERINTENDING PROVIDENCE.
 SOME of the readers of the former edition of this work, whilst they have admitted
 the exalted view of the Creator, which arises from considering his will as the
 development of laws of unbounded generality, have expressed regret that those
 views appeared to them, in some measure, to imply that we are less immediately the objects of his protecting care, — that he seems thus less constantly
 and less directly, our watchful Guardian and Protector.
[page] 142
 This difficulty ultimately resolves
 itself into that of the reconciling foreknowledge with freewill. Without, however,
 entering at present on that abstruse discussion, there are some reflections
 which may at least afford partial reply to the objection stated above. In
 reverting to the first origin of our knowledge of the motives and feelings of
 those around us, we must necessarily look into our own hearts. When we exercise
 that feeling which is called kindness or benevolence, we are conscious that
 we make some exertion, or some sacrifice, to add to the happiness of another
 person, without ourselves expecting to derive any advantage in return. When
 we observe other persons making similar exertions or sacrifices, and when we
 can discover no possibility of their deriving advantage from them, except that
 interior feeling of happiness which always arises from the exercise of such
 good offices, we conclude that they are actuated by the same feeling of kindness
 or benevolence.
[page] 143
 In the first case we are conscious
 of the existence of that feeling within our own bosoms; in the second we infer
 that it exists in others, from the similarity of human actions under the same
 apparent circumstances. The reasoning which leads us to ascribe the attribute
 of benevolence to the Creator, is of precisely the same kind, although the infinity
 of this, as of his other attributes, can bear no comparison to the finite extent
 of those of other beings. Since however it is by such reasoning only that we
 attain the knowledge of them, so, if there arise a question about the comparative
 amount of any of those attributes when exerted in one way rather than in another,
 we must apply to such cases the same reasoning. The inference from which
 the objection has arisen, is that the superintendence of Providence is remote,
 not immediate; the answer that I shall endeavour to make to it is, that
[page] 144
 the value of benevolence is not
 diminished by the distance of time at which its exertion arises. In order to
 examine this question of immediate or remote superintendence, let us imagine
 a case occurring amongst our fellow-creatures, and let us endeavour to ascertain
 the conclusion we should form with regard to it. Let us suppose the wealthy
 resident near a small village, returning from the neighbouring town, to have
 observed from a distance that the bridge across a rapid stream has been carried
 away by a flood, and that the blind postman who makes his daily journey along
 the causeway to the neighbouring town, unconscious of what has happened, is
 just approaching the torrent. Setting spurs to his horse, he dashes forward,
 and clearing the broken bridge, has just time to alight and patch the postman
 on the verge of destruction.
[page] 145
 Such conduct is an example of kindness
 or benevolence, and would receive the praise it justly merits. Let us now suppose
 another village,—another stream,—and another postman starting, like the former
 one, at an early hour, before the villagers are abroad. We will imagine too
 the wealthy resident near this other village to have been out on the preceding
 day amongst the distant mountains, from which the torrent which passes the village
 is fed; and that observing the quantity of rain which has fallen in those parts,
 he foresees that the resulting flood will in all probability destroy the bridge
 across that stream; and knowing from his experience that several hours must
 elapse before the rain which falls in the mountains produces its full effect
 on the stream in his neighbourhood, he sends off one of his attendants in time
 to reach the broken bridge just before the moment when the stream
[page] 146
would be crossed by the unsuspecting traveller, who is thus saved from death.
Undoubtedly this is benevolence. And although we may not infer, that the benevolence in the latter, was greater than in the former case, yet it cannot for a moment be maintained to be less. In fact, the first case was one of benevolence excited by feeling; in the second it was benevolence called forth by reflection, and aided and reduced to action by reasoning founded upon knowledge. The sportsman in the mountains who thus reasoned, would not have been less active had he been on the spot at the dangerous moment. But he who by his personal exertion preserved the blind man, although of an equally benevolent heart, might not have possessed the knowledge available for the safety of the postman, had he been at a distance from the spot on which his effort was successful.
[page] 147
Two inferences are connected with this imagined case.
1st, That the benevolence which organizes beforehand contrivances for the advantage or security of its objects, is at least as high as that which acts from the impulse of immediate feeling.
2d, That the benevolence which is guided by knowledge, even though, as a feeling, it may not be superior in intensity, is often of far more value to those who are its subjects.
Such are the decisions we should arrive at respecting human feelings and human knowledge; and applying the same principles instead of looking with any feelings of doubt or apprehension at the distance of time at which it may have pleased the Creator to have organized our protection from danger, we ought, when once convinced of his benevolence, to discover
[page] 148
 in that very distance, proof of
 his higher knowledge and higher power, and with every addition to those attributes,
 to feel ourselves under still more potent and unintermitted watchfulness.
[page] 149</div></body></text></TEI>