<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="115">CHAPTER I.
Imaginary Knowledge of Plants.
THE apprehension of such
differences and resemblances as those by which we group together and
discriminate the various kinds of plants and animals, and the
appropriation of words to mark and convey the resulting notions, must
be presupposed, as essential to the very beginning of human knowledge.
In whatever manner we imagine man to be placed on the earth by his
Creator, these processes must be conceived to be, as our Scriptures
represent them, contemporaneous with the first exertion of reason, and
the first use of speech. If we were to indulge ourselves in framing a
hypothetical account of the origin of language, we should probably
assume as the first-formed words, those which depend on the visible
likeness or unlikeness of objects; and should arrange as of subsequent
formation, those terms which imply, in the mind, acts of wider
combination and higher abstraction. At any rate, it is certain that
the names of the kinds of vegetables and animals are very abundant
even in the most uncivilized stages of man’s career. Thus we are
informed1 that the inhabitants of New Zealand have
a distinct name of every tree and plant in their island, of which
there are six or seven hundred or more different kinds. In the
accounts of the rudest tribes, in the earliest legends, poetry, and
literature of nations, pines and oaks, roses and violets, the olive
and the vine, and the thousand other productions of the earth, have a
place, and are spoken of in a manner which assumes, that in such kinds
of natural objects, permanent and infallible distinctions had been
observed and universally recognized.
1 Yate’s New Zealand, p.
238.
For a long period, it was not suspected that any ambiguity or
confusion could arise from the use of such terms; and when such
inconveniences did occur, (as even in early times they did,) men were
far from divining that the proper remedy was the construction of a
science of classification. The loose and insecure terms of the
language of common life retained their place in botany, long after
their 359 defects
were severely felt: for instance, the vague and unscientific
distinction of vegetables into trees, shrubs, and
herbs, kept its ground till the time of Linnæus.
While it was thus imagined that the identification of a plant, by
means of its name, might properly be trusted to the common uncultured
faculties of the mind, and to what we may call the instinct of
language, all the attention and study which were bestowed on such
objects, were naturally employed in learning and thinking upon such
circumstances respecting them as were supplied by any of the common
channels through which knowledge and opinion flow into men’s
minds.
The reader need hardly be reminded that in the earlier periods of
man’s mental culture, he acquires those opinions on which he loves to
dwell, not by the exercise of observation subordinate to reason; but,
far more, by his fancy and his emotions, his love of the marvellous,
his hopes and fears. It cannot surprise us, therefore, that the
earliest lore concerning plants which we discover in the records of
the past, consists of mythological legends, marvellous relations, and
extraordinary medicinal qualities. To the lively fancy of the Greeks,
the Narcissus, which bends its head over the stream, was originally a
youth who in such an attitude became enamored of his own beauty: the
hyacinth,2 on whose petals the notes of grief were
traced (a i, a i), recorded the sorrow of
Apollo for the death of his favorite Hyacinthus: the beautiful lotus
of India,3 which floats with its splendid flower on
the surface of the water, is the chosen seat of the goddess Lackshmi,
the daughter of Ocean.4 In Egypt, too,5 Osiris swam on a
lotus-leaf and Harpocrates was cradled in one. The lotus-eaters of
Homer lost immediately their love of home. Every one knows how easy it
would be to accumulate such tales of wonder or religion.
2 Lilium martagon.

Ipse suos gemitus foliis inscribit et a i, a i,
Flos habet inscriptum funestaque litera ducta
est.—Ovid.

3 Nelumbium speciosum. ~Correction to
text in the 3rd edition, bottom of
page.~
4 Sprengel, Geschichte der
Botanik, i. 27.
5 Ib. i. 28.
Those who attended to the effects of plants, might discover in them
some medicinal properties, and might easily imagine more; and when the
love of the marvellous was added to the hope of health, it is easy to
believe that men would be very credulous. We need not dwell upon the
examples of this. In Pliny’s Introduction to that book of his 360 Natural History which
treats of the medicinal virtues of plants, he says,6
“Antiquity was so much struck with the properties of herbs, that it
affirmed things incredible. Xanthus, the historian, says, that a man
killed by a dragon, will be restored to life by an herb which he calls
balin; and that Thylo, when killed by a dragon, was recovered
by the same plant. Democritus asserted, and Theophrastus believed,
that there was an herb, at the touch of which, the wedge which the
woodman had driven into a tree would leap out again. Though we cannot
credit these stories, most persons believe that almost anything might
be effected by means of herbs, if their virtues were fully known.” How
far from a reasonable estimate of the reality of such virtues were the
persons who entertained this belief we may judge from the many
superstitious observances which they associated with the gathering and
using of medicinal plants. Theophrastus speaks of these;7
“The drug-sellers and the rhizotomists (root-cutters) tell us,” he
says, “some things which may be true, but other things which are
merely solemn quackery;8 thus they direct us to gather some
plants, standing from the wind, and with our bodies anointed; some by
night, some by day, some before the sun falls on them. So far there
may be something in their rules. But others are too fantastical and
far fetched. It is, perhaps, not absurd to use a prayer in plucking a
plant; but they go further than this. We are to draw a sword three
times round the mandragora, and to cut it looking to the west: again,
to dance round it, and to use obscene language, as they say those who
sow cumin should utter blasphemies. Again, we are to draw a line round
the black hellebore, standing to the east and praying; and to avoid an
eagle either on the right or on the left; for, say they, ‘if an eagle
be near, the cutter will die in a year.’”
6 Lib. xxv. 5.
7 De Plantis, ix. 9.
8 Ἐπιτραγῳδοῦντες.
This extract may serve to show the extent to which these
imaginations were prevalent, and the manner in which they were looked
upon by Theophrastus, our first great botanical author. And we may now
consider that we have given sufficient attention to these fables and
superstitions, which have no place in the history of the progress of
real knowledge, except to show the strange chaos of wild fancies and
legends out of which it had to emerge. We proceed to trace the history
of the knowledge of plants. 361</div></body></text></TEI>