<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="16">CHAPTER II.
The Commentatorial Spirit of the Middle
Ages.
WE have already noticed, that,
after the first great achievements of the founders of sound
speculation, in the different departments of human knowledge, had
attracted the interest and admiration which those who became
acquainted with them could not but give to them, there appeared a
disposition among men to lean on the authority of some of these
teachers;—to study the opinions of others as the only mode of
forming their own;—to read nature through books;—to attend
to what had been already thought and said, rather than to what really
is and happens. This tendency of men’s minds requires our particular
consideration. Its manifestations were very important, and highly
characteristic of the stationary period; it gave, in a great degree, a
peculiar bias and direction to the intellectual activity of many
centuries; and the kind of labor with which speculative men were
occupied in consequence of this bias, took the place of that
examination of realities which must be their employment, in order that
real knowledge may make any decided progress.
In some subjects, indeed, as, for instance, in the domains of
morals, poetry, and the arts, whose aim is the production of beauty,
this opposition between the study of former opinion and present
reality, may not be so distinct; inasmuch as it may be said by some,
that, in these subjects, opinions are realities; that the thoughts and
feelings which 202
prevail in men’s minds are the material upon which we must work, the
particulars from which we are to generalize, the instruments which we
are to use; and that, therefore, to reject the study of antiquity, or
even its authority, would be to show ourselves ignorant of the extent
and mutual bearing of the elements with which we have to
deal;—would be to cut asunder that which we ought to unite into
a vital whole. Yet even in the provinces of history and poetry, the
poverty and servility of men’s minds during the middle ages, are shown
by indications so strong as to be truly remarkable; for instance, in
the efforts of the antiquarians of almost every European country to
assimilate the early history of their own state to the poet’s account
of the foundation of Rome, by bringing from the sack of Troy, Brutus
to England, Bavo to Flanders, and so on. But however this may be, our
business at present is, to trace the varying spirit of the
physical philosophy of different ages; trusting that,
hereafter, this prefatory study will enable us to throw some light
upon the other parts of philosophy. And in physics the case
undoubtedly was, that the labor of observation, which is one of the
two great elements of the progress of knowledge, was in a great
measure superseded by the collection, the analysis, the explanation,
of previous authors and opinions; experimenters were replaced by
commentators; criticism took the place of induction; and instead of
great discoverers we had learned men.
1. Natural Bias to Authority.—It is very evident that,
in such a bias of men’s studies, there is something very natural;
however strained and technical this erudition may have been, the
propensities on which it depends are very general, and are easily
seen. Deference to the authority of thoughtful and sagacious men, a
disposition which men in general neither reject nor think they ought
to reject in practical matters, naturally clings to them, even in
speculation. It is a satisfaction to us to suppose that there are, or
have been, minds of transcendent powers, of wide and wise views,
superior to the common errors and blindness of our nature. The
pleasure of admiration, and the repose of confidence, are inducements
to such a belief. There are also other reasons why we willingly
believe that there are in philosophy great teachers, so profound and
sagacious, that, in order to arrive at truth, we have only to learn
their thoughts, to understand their writings. There is a peculiar
interest which men feel in dealing with the thoughts of their
fellow-men, rather than with brute matter. Matter feels and excites no
sympathies: in seeking for mere laws of nature, there is nothing of
mental intercourse with the great spirits of the past, as there is in
203 studying
Aristotle or Plato. Moreover, a large portion of this employment is of
a kind the most agreeable to most speculative minds; it consists in
tracing the consequences of assumed principles: it is deductive like
geometry: and the principles of the teachers being known, and being
undisputed, the deduction and application of their results is an
obvious, self-satisfying, and inexhaustible exercise of ingenuity.
These causes, and probably others, make criticism and commentation
flourish, when invention begins to fail, oppressed and bewildered by
the acquisitions it has already made; and when the vigor and hope of
men’s minds are enfeebled by civil and political changes.
Accordingly,20 the Alexandrian school was eminently
characterized by a spirit of erudition, of literary criticism, of
interpretation, of imitation. These practices, which reigned first in
their full vigor in “the Museum,” are likely to be, at all times, the
leading propensities of similar academical institutions.
20 Degerando, Hist. des Syst. de
Philos. iii. p. 134.
How natural it is to select a great writer as a paramount
authority, and to ascribe to him extraordinary profundity and
sagacity, we may see, in the manner in which the Greeks looked upon
Homer; and the fancy which detected in his poems traces of the origin
of all arts and sciences, has, as we know, found favor even in modern
times. To pass over earlier instances of this feeling, we may observe,
that Strabo begins his Geography by saying that he agrees with
Hipparchus, who had declared Homer to be the first author of our
geographical knowledge; and he does not confine the application of
this assertion to the various and curious topographical information
which the Iliad and Odyssey contain, concerning the countries
surrounding the Mediterranean; but in phrases which, to most persons,
might appear the mere play of a poetical fancy, or a casual selection
of circumstances, he finds unquestionable evidence of a correct
knowledge of general geographical truths. Thus,21 when Homer
speaks of the sun “rising from the soft and deep-flowing ocean,” of
his “splendid blaze plunging in the ocean;” of the northern
constellation
“Alone unwashen by the ocean wave;”
and of Jupiter, “who goes to the ocean to feast with
the blameless Ethiopians;” Strabo is satisfied from these passages
that Homer knew the dry land to be surrounded with water: and he
reasons in like manner with respect to other points of geography.
21 Strabo, i. p. 5.
204 2.
Character of Commentators.—The spirit of commentation, as
has already been suggested, turns to questions of taste, of
metaphysics, of morals, with far more avidity than to physics.
Accordingly, critics and grammarians were peculiarly the growth of
this school; and, though the commentators sometimes chose works of
mathematical or physical science for their subject (as Proclus, who
commented on Euclid’s Geometry, and Simplicius, on Aristotle’s
Physics), these commentaries were, in fact, rather metaphysical than
mathematical. It does not appear that the commentators have, in any
instance, illustrated the author by bringing his assertions of facts
to the test of experiment. Thus, when Simplicius comments on the
passage concerning a vacuum, which we formerly
adduced, he notices the argument which went upon the assertion, that a
vessel full of ashes would contain as much water as an empty vessel;
and he mentions various opinions of different authors, but no trial of
the fact. Eudemus had said, that the ashes contained something hot, as
quicklime does, and that by means of this, a part of the water was
evaporated; others supposed the water to be condensed, and so on.22
22 Simplicius, p. 170.
The Commentator’s professed object is to explain, to enforce, to
illustrate doctrines assumed as true. He endeavors to adapt the work
on which he employs himself to the state of information and of opinion
in his own time; to elucidate obscurities and technicalities; to
supply steps omitted in the reasoning; but he does not seek to obtain
additional truths or new generalizations. He undertakes only to give
what is virtually contained in his author; to develop, but not to
create. He is a cultivator of the thoughts of others: his labor is not
spent on a field of his own; he ploughs but to enrich the granary of
another man. Thus he does not work as a freeman, but as one in a
servile condition; or rather, his is a menial, and not a productive
service: his office is to adorn the appearance of his master, not to
increase his wealth.
Yet though the Commentator’s employment is thus subordinate and
dependent, he is easily led to attribute to it the greatest importance
and dignity. To elucidate good books is, indeed, a useful task; and
when those who undertake this work execute it well, it would be most
unreasonable to find fault with them for not doing more. But the
critic, long and earnestly employed on one author, may easily
underrate the relative value of other kinds of mental exertion. He may
205 ascribe too
large dimensions to that which occupies the whole of his own field of
vision. Thus he may come to consider such study as the highest aim,
and best evidence of human genius. To understand Aristotle, or Plato,
may appear to him to comprise all that is possible of profundity and
acuteness. And when he has travelled over a portion of their domain,
and satisfied himself that of this he too is master, he may look with
complacency at the circuit he has made, and speak of it as a labor of
vast effort and difficulty. We may quote, as an expression of this
temper, the language of Sir Henry Savile, in concluding a course of
lectures on Euclid, delivered at Oxford.23 “By the grace of
God, gentlemen hearers, I have performed my promise; I have redeemed
my pledge. I have explained, according to my ability, the definitions,
postulates, axioms, and first eight propositions of the
Elements of Euclid. Here, sinking under the weight of years, I lay
down my art and my instruments.”
23 Exolvi per Dei gratiam, Domini
auditores, promissum; liberavi fldem meam; explicavi pro meo modulo,
definitiones, petitiones, communes sententias, et octo priores
propositiones Elementorum Euclidis. Hic, annis fessus, cyclos
artemque repono.
We here speak of the peculiar province of the Commentator; for
undoubtedly, in many instances, a commentary on a received author has
been made the vehicle of conveying systems and doctrines entirely
different from those of the author himself; as, for instance, when the
New Platonists wrote, taking Plato for their text. The labors of
learned men in the stationary period, which came under this
description, belong to another class.
3. Greek Commentators on Aristotle.—The commentators
or disciples of the great philosophers did not assume at once their
servile character. At first their object was to supply and correct, as
well as to explain their teacher. Thus among the earlier commentators
of Aristotle, Theophrastus invented five moods of syllogism in the
first figure, in addition to the four invented by Aristotle, and
stated with additional accuracy the rules of hypothetical syllogisms.
He also not only collected much information concerning animals, and
natural events, which Aristotle had omitted, but often differed with
his master; as, for instance, concerning the saltness of the sea:
this, which the Stagirite attributed to the effect of the evaporation
produced by the sun’s rays, was ascribed by Theophrastus to beds of
salt at the bottom. Porphyry,24 who flourished
in the third century, wrote a book on the Predicables, which
was found to be so suitable a complement 206 to the Predicaments or Categories
of Aristotle, that it was usually prefixed to that treatise; and the
two have been used as an elementary work together, up to modern times.
The Predicables are the five steps which the gradations of generality
and particularity introduce;—genus, species,
difference, individual, accident:—the
Categories are the ten heads under which assertions or predications
may be arranged:—substance, quantity,
relation, quality, place, time,
position, habit, action, passion.
24 Buhle, Arist. i. 284.
At a later period, the Aristotelian commentators became more
servile, and followed the author step by step, explaining, according
to their views, his expressions and doctrines; often, indeed, with
extreme prolixity, expanding his clauses into sentences, and his
sentences into paragraphs. Alexander Aphrodisiensis, who lived at the
end of the second century, is of this class; “sometimes useful,” as
one of the recent editors of Aristotle says;25 “but by the
prolixity of his interpretation, by his perverse itch for himself
discussing the argument expounded by Aristotle, for defending his
opinions, and for refuting or reconciling those of others, he rather
obscures than enlightens.” At various times, also, some of the
commentators, and especially those of the Alexandrian school,
endeavored to reconcile, or combined without reconciling, opposing
doctrines of the great philosophers of the earlier times. Simplicius,
for instance, and, indeed, a great number of the Alexandrian
Philosophers,26 as Alexander, Ammonius, and others,
employed themselves in the futile task of reconciling the doctrines of
the Pythagoreans, of the Eleatics, of Plato, and of the Stoics, with
those of Aristotle. Boethius27 entertained the
design of translating into Latin the whole of Aristotle’s and Plato’s
works, and of showing their agreement; a gigantic plan, which he never
executed. Others employed themselves in disentangling the confusion
which such attempts produced, as John the Grammarian, surnamed
Philoponus, “the Labor-loving;” who, towards the end of the seventh
century, maintained that Aristotle was entirely misunderstood by
Porphyry and Proclus,28 who had pretended to incorporate his
doctrines into those of the New Platonic school, or even to reconcile
him with Plato himself on the subject of ideas. Others,
again, wrote Epitomes, Compounds, Abstracts; and endeavored to throw
the works of the philosopher into some simpler and more obviously
regular form, as John of Damascus, in 207 the middle of the eighth century, who
made abstracts of some of Aristotle’s works, and introduced the study
of the author into theological education. These two writers lived
under the patronage of the Arabs; the former was favored by Amrou, the
conqueror of Egypt; the latter was at first secretary to the Caliph,
but afterwards withdrew to a monastery.29
25 Ib. i. 288.
26 Ib. i. 311.
27 Degerando, Hist. des Syst.
iv. 100.
28 Ib. iv. 155.
29 Deg. iv. 150.
At this period the Arabians became the fosterers and patrons of
philosophy, rather than the Greeks. Justinian had, by an edict, closed
the school of Athens, the last of the schools of heathen philosophy.
Leo, the Isaurian, who was a zealous Iconoclast, abolished also the
schools where general knowledge had been taught, in combination with
Christianity,30 yet the line of the Aristotelian
commentators was continued, though feebly, to the later ages of the
Greek empire. Anna Comnena31 mentions a Eustratus who employed
himself upon the dialectic and moral treatises, and whom she does not
hesitate to elevate above the Stoics and Platonists, for his talent in
philosophical discussions. Nicephorus Blemmydes wrote logical and
physical epitomes for the use of John Ducas; George Pachymerus
composed an epitome of the philosophy of Aristotle, and a compend of
his logic; Theodore Metochytes, who was famous in his time alike for
his eloquence and his learning, has left a paraphrase of the books of
Aristotle on Physics, on the Soul, the Heavens,32 &c.
Fabricius states that this writer has a chapter, the object of which
is to prove, that all philosophers, and Aristotle and Plato in
particular, have disdained the authority of their predecessors. He
could hardly help remarking in how different a spirit philosophy had
been pursued since their time.
30 Ib. iv. 163.
31 Ib. 167.
32 Ib. 168.
4. Greek Commentators of Plato and others.—I have
spoken principally of the commentators of Aristotle, for he was the
great subject of the commentators proper; and though the name of his
rival, Plato, was graced by a list of attendants, hardly less
numerous, these, the Neoplatonists, as they are called, had introduced
new elements into the doctrines of their nominal master, to such an
extent that they must be placed in a different class. We may observe
here, however, how, in this school as in the Peripatetic, the race of
commentators multiplied itself. Porphyry, who commented on Aristotle,
was commented on by Ammonius; Plotinus’s Enneads were commented on by
Proclus and Dexippus. Psellus33 the elder was a
paraphrast of 208
Aristotle; Psellus the younger, in the eleventh century, attempted to
restore the New Platonic school. The former of these two writers had
for his pupils two men, the emperor Leo, surnamed the Philosopher, and
Photius the patriarch, who exerted themselves to restore the study of
literature at Constantinople. We still possess the Collection of
Extracts of Photius, which, like that of Stobæus and others, shows the
tendency of the age to compilations, abstracts, and
epitomes,—the extinction of philosophical vitality.
33 Deg. iv. 169.
5. Arabian Commentators of Aristotle.—The reader might
perhaps have expected, that when the philosophy of the Greeks was
carried among a new race of intellects, of a different national
character and condition, the train of this servile tradition would
have been broken; that some new thoughts would have started forth;
that some new direction, some new impulse, would have been given to
the search for truth. It might have been anticipated that we should
have had schools among the Arabians which should rival the
Peripatetic, Academic, and Stoic among the Greeks;—that they
would preoccupy the ground on which Copernicus and Galileo, Lavoisier
and Linnæus, won their fame;—that they would make the next great
steps in the progressive sciences. Nothing of this, however, happened.
The Arabians cannot claim, in science or philosophy, any really great
names; they produced no men and no discoveries which have materially
influenced the course and destinies of human knowledge; they tamely
adopted the intellectual servitude of the nation which they conquered
by their arms; they joined themselves at once to the string of slaves
who were dragging the car of Aristotle and Plotinus. Nor, perhaps, on
a little further reflection, shall we be surprised at this want of
vigor and productive power, in this period of apparent national youth.
The Arabians had not been duly prepared rightly to enjoy and use the
treasures of which they became possessed. They had, like most
uncivilized nations, been passionately fond of their indigenous
poetry; their imagination had been awakened, but their rational powers
and speculative tendencies were still torpid. They received the Greek
philosophy without having passed through those gradations of ardent
curiosity and keen research, of obscurity brightening into clearness,
of doubt succeeded by the joy of discovery, by which the Greek mind
had been enlarged and exercised. Nor had the Arabians ever enjoyed, as
the Greeks had, the individual consciousness, the independent
volition, the intellectual freedom, arising from the freedom of
political institutions. They had not felt the contagious mental
activity of a small city,—the elation arising from the general
209 sympathy in
speculative pursuits diffused through an intelligent and acute
audience; in short, they had not had a national education such as
fitted the Greeks to be disciples of Plato and Hipparchus. Hence,
their new literary wealth rather encumbered and enslaved, than
enriched and strengthened them: in their want of taste for
intellectual freedom, they were glad to give themselves up to the
guidance of Aristotle and other dogmatists. Their military habits had
accustomed them to look to a leader; their reverence for the book of
their law had prepared them to accept a philosophical Koran also. Thus
the Arabians, though they never translated the Greek poetry,
translated, and merely translated, the Greek philosophy; they followed
the Greek philosophers without deviation, or, at least, without any
philosophical deviations. They became for the most part
Aristotelians;—studied not only Aristotle, but the commentators
of Aristotle; and themselves swelled the vast and unprofitable
herd.
The philosophical works of Aristotle had, in some measure, made
their way in the East, before the growth of the Saracen power. In the
sixth century, a Syrian, Uranus,34 encouraged by
the love of philosophy manifested by Cosroes, had translated some of
the writings of the Stagirite; about the same time, Sergius had given
some translations in Syriac. In the seventh century, Jacob of Edessa
translated into this language the Dialectics, and added Notes to the
work. Such labors became numerous; and the first Arabic translations
of Aristotle were formed upon these Persian or Syriac texts. In this
succession of transfusions, some mistakes must inevitably have been
introduced.
34 Deg. iv. 196.
The Arabian interpreters of Aristotle, like a large portion of the
Alexandrian ones, gave to the philosopher a tinge of opinions borrowed
from another source, of which I shall have to speak under the head of
Mysticism. But they are, for the most part, sufficiently strong
examples of the peculiar spirit of commentation, to make it fitting to
notice them here. At the head of them stands35 Alkindi, who
appears to have lived at the court of Almamon, and who wrote
commentaries on the Organon of Aristotle. But Alfarabi was the glory
of the school of Bagdad; his knowledge included mathematics,
astronomy, medicine, and philosophy. Born in an elevated rank, and
possessed of a rich patrimony, he led an austere life, and devoted
himself altogether to study and meditation. He employed himself
particularly in unfolding the import of Aristotle’s treatise On the
Soul.36 Avicenna (Ebn Sina) 210 was at once the
Hippocrates and the Aristotle of the Arabians; and certainly the most
extraordinary man that the nation produced. In the course of an
unfortunate and stormy life, occupied by politics and by pleasures, he
produced works which were long revered as a sort of code of science.
In particular, his writings on medicine, though they contain little
besides a compilation of Hippocrates and Galen, took the place of
both, even in the universities of Europe; and were studied as models
at Paris and Montpelier, till the end of the seventeenth century, at
which period they fell into an almost complete oblivion. Avicenna is
conceived, by some modern writers,37 to have shown
some power of original thinking in his representations of the
Aristotelian Logic and Metaphysics. Averroes (Ebn Roshd) of Cordova,
was the most illustrious of the Spanish Aristotelians, and became the
guide of the schoolmen,38 being placed by them on a level with
Aristotle himself, or above him. He translated Aristotle from the
first Syriac version, not being able to read the Greek text. He
aspired to, and retained for centuries, the title of the
Commentator; and he deserves this title by the servility with
which he maintains that Aristotle39 carried the
sciences to the highest possible degree, measured their whole extent,
and fixed their ultimate and permanent boundaries; although his works
are conceived to exhibit a trace of the New Platonism. Some of his
writings are directed against an Arabian skeptic, of the name of
Algazel, whom we have already noticed.
35 Ib. iv. 187.
36 Ib. iv. 205.
37 Deg. iv. 206.
38 Ib. iv. 247. Averroes died a. d. 1206.
39 Ib. iv. 248.
When the schoolmen had adopted the supremacy of Aristotle to the
extent in which Averroes maintained it, their philosophy went further
than a system of mere commentation, and became a system of dogmatism;
we must, therefore, in another chapter, say a
few words more of the Aristotelians in this point of view, before we
proceed to the revival of science; but we must previously consider
some other features in the character of the Stationary Period. 211</div></body></text></TEI>