<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="71">

CHAPTER III.
Of the Doctrine of Catastrophes and the Doctrine of Uniformity.


1. Doctrine of Catastrophes.—I have already shown,
in the History of Geology, that the attempts to frame
a theory of the earth have brought into view two completely opposite opinions:—one, which represents the
course of nature as uniform through all ages, the
causes which produce change having had the same
intensity in former times which they have at the present day;—the other opinion, which sees, in the present condition of things, evidences of catastrophes;—changes of a more sweeping kind, and produced by
more powerful agencies than those which occur in recent times. Geologists who held the latter opinion,
maintained that the forces which have elevated the
Alps or the Andes to their present height could not
have been any forces which are now in action: they
pointed to vast masses of strata hundreds of miles long,
thousands of feet thick, thrown into highly-inclined
positions, fractured, dislocated, crushed: they remarked
that upon the shattered edges of such strata they found
enormous accumulations of fragments and rubbish,
rounded by the action of water, so as to denote ages
of violent aqueous action: they conceived that they
saw instances in which whole mountains of rock in a
state of igneous fusion, must have burst the earth’s crust
from below: they found that in the course of the revolutions by which one stratum of rock was placed
upon another, the whole collection of animal species
which tenanted the earth and the seas had been removed, and a new set of living things introduced in
its place: finally, they found, above all the strata, 285 vast masses of sand and gravel containing bones of
animals, and apparently the work of a mighty deluge.
With all these proofs before their eyes, they thought
it impossible not to judge that the agents of change by
which the world was urged from one condition to
another till it reached its present state must have been
more violent, more powerful, than any which we see at
work around us. They conceived that the evidence of
‘catastrophes’ was irresistible.
2. Doctrine of Uniformity.—I need not here repeat the narrative (given in the History14) of the
process by which this formidable array of proofs was,
in the minds of some eminent geologists, weakened,
and at last overcome. This was done by showing that
the sudden breaks in the succession of strata were
apparent only, the discontinuity of the series which
occurred in one country being removed by terms
interposed in another locality:—by urging that the
total effect produced by existing causes, taking into
account the accumulated result of long periods, is far
greater than a casual speculator would think possible:—by making it appear that there are in many parts of
the world evidences of a slow and imperceptible rising
of the land since it was the habitation of now existing species:—by proving that it is not universally
true that the strata separated in time by supposed
catastrophes contain distinct species of animals:—by
pointing out the limited fields of the supposed diluvial
action:—and finally, by remarking that though the
creation of species is a mystery, the extinction of
species is going on in our own day. Hypotheses were
suggested, too, by which it was conceived that the
change of climate might be explained, which, as the
consideration of the fossil remains seemed to show,
must have taken place between the ancient and the
modern times. In this manner the whole evidence of
catastrophes was explained away: the notion of a
series of paroxysms of violence in the causes of change
was represented as a delusion arising from our 286 contemplating short periods only, in the action of present
causes: length of time was called in to take the place
of intensity of force: and it was declared that Geology
need not despair of accounting for the revolutions of
the earth, as Astronomy accounts for the revolutions
of the heavens, by the universal action of causes
which are close at hand to us, operating through time
and space without variation or decay.</div></body></text></TEI>