<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="11">CHAPTER XI.
ON THE SUPPOSED FORMER INTENSITY OF THE IGNEOUS FORCES.
Volcanic action at successive geological periods—Plutonic rocks of different ages—Gradual
development of subterranean movements—Faults—Doctrine of the
sudden upheaval of parallel mountain-chains—Objections to the proof of the
suddenness of the upheaval, and the contemporaneousness of parallel chains—Trains
of active volcanoes not parallel—As large tracts of land are rising or
sinking slowly, so narrow zones of land may be pushed up gradually to great
heights—Bending of strata by lateral pressure—Adequacy of the volcanic
power to effect this without paroxysmal convulsions.
When reasoning on the intensity of volcanic action at former periods,
as well as on the power of moving water, already treated of, geologists
have been ever prone to represent Nature as having been prodigal of
violence and parsimonious of time. Now, although it is less easy to
determine the relative ages of the volcanic than of the fossiliferous formations,
it is undeniable that igneous rocks have been produced at all
geological periods, or as often as we find distinct deposits marked by
peculiar animal and vegetable remains. It can be shown that rocks
commonly called trappean have been injected into fissures, and ejected
at the surface, both before and during the deposition of the Carboniferous
series, and at the time when the Magnesian Limestone, and
when the Upper New Red Sandstone were formed, or when the Lias,
Oolite, Green Sand, Chalk, and the several tertiary groups newer than
the chalk, originated in succession. Nor is this all: distinct volcanic
products may be referred to the subordinate divisions of each period,
such as the Carboniferous, as in the county of Fife, in Scotland, where
certain masses of contemporaneous trap are associated with the Lower,
others with the Upper Coal measures. And if one of these masses is
more minutely examined, we find it to consist of the products of a great
many successive outbursts, by which scoriæ and lava were again and
again emitted, and afterwards consolidated, then fissured, and finally
traversed by melted matter, constituting what are called dikes.239 As
we enlarge, therefore, our knowledge of the ancient rocks formed by
161
subterranean heat, we find ourselves compelled to regard them as the
aggregate effects of innumerable eruptions, each of which may have
been comparable in violence to those now experienced in volcanic
regions.
It may indeed be said that we have as yet no data for estimating the
relative volume of matter simultaneously in a state of fusion at two
given periods, as if we were to compare the columnar basalt of Staffa
and its environs with the lava poured out in Iceland in 1783; but for
this very reason it would be rash and unphilosophical to assume an excess
of ancient as contrasted with modern outpourings of melted matter
at particular periods of time.240 It would be still more presumptuous to
take for granted that the more deep-seated effects of subterranean heat
surpassed at remote eras the corresponding effects of internal heat in
our own times. Certain porphyries and granites, and all the rocks commonly
called plutonic, are now generally supposed to have resulted from
the slow cooling of materials fused and solidified under great pressure;
and we cannot doubt that beneath existing volcanoes there are large
spaces filled with melted stone, which must for centuries remain in an
incandescent state, and then cool and become hard and crystalline when
the subterranean heat shall be exhausted. That lakes of lava are continuous
for hundreds of miles beneath the Chilian Andes, seems established
by observations made in the year 1835.241
Now, wherever the fluid contents of such reservoirs are poured out
successively from craters in the open air, or at the bottom of the sea,
the matter so ejected may afford evidence by its arrangement of having
originated at different periods; but if the subterranean residue after the
withdrawal of the heat be converted into crystalline or plutonic rock,
the entire mass may seem to have been formed at once, however countless
the ages required for its fusion and subsequent refrigeration. As
the idea that all the granite in the earth's crust was produced simultaneously,
and in a primitive state of the planet, has now been universally
abandoned; so the suggestion above adverted to, may put us on our
guard against too readily adopting another opinion, namely, that each
large mass of granite was generated in a brief period of time.
Modern writers indeed, of authority, seem more and more agreed that
in the case of granitic rocks, the passage from a liquid or pasty to a
solid and crystalline state must have been an extremely gradual process.
The doctrine so much insisted upon formerly, that crystalline rocks,
such as granite, gneiss, mica-schist, quartzite, and others were produced
in the greatest abundance in the earlier ages of the planet, and that
their formation has ceased altogether in our own times, will be controverted
in the next chapter.
Gradual development of subterranean movements.—The extreme violence
of the subterranean forces in remote ages has been often inferred
from the facts that the older rocks are more fractured and dislocated
162
than the newer. But what other result could we have anticipated if the
quantity of movement had been always equal in equal periods of time?
Time must, in that case, multiply the derangement of strata in the ratio
of their antiquity. Indeed the numerous exceptions to the above rule
which we find in nature, present at first sight the only objection to the
hypothesis of uniformity. For the more ancient formations remain in
many places horizontal, while in others much newer strata are curved
and vertical. This apparent anomaly, however, will be seen in the next
chapter to depend on the irregular manner in which the volcanic and
subterranean agency affect different parts of the earth in succession, being
often renewed again and again in certain areas, while others remain
during the whole time at rest.
That the more impressive effects of subterranean power, such as the
upheaval of mountain-chains, may have been due to multiplied convulsions
of moderate intensity rather than to a few paroxysmal explosions,
will appear the less improbable when the gradual and intermittent development
of volcanic eruptions in times past is once established. It is
now very generally conceded that these eruptions have their source in
the same causes as those which give rise to the permanent elevation and
sinking of land; the admission, therefore, that one of the two volcanic
or subterranean processes has gone on gradually, draws with it the conclusion
that the effects of the other have been elaborated by successive
and gradual efforts.
Faults.—The same reasoning is applicable to great faults, or those
striking instances of the upthrow or downthrow of large masses of rock,
which have been thought by some to imply tremendous catastrophes
wholly foreign to the ordinary course of nature. Thus we have in
England faults, in which the vertical displacement is between 600 and
3000 feet, and the horizontal extent thirty miles or more, the width of
the fissures since filled up with rubbish varying from ten to fifty feet.
But when we inquire into the proofs of the mass having risen or fallen
suddenly on the one side of these great rents, several hundreds or thousands
of feet above or below the rock with which it was once continuous
on the other side, we find the evidence defective. There are grooves, it
is said, and scratches on the rubbed and polished walls, which have
often one common direction, favoring the theory that the movement was
accomplished by a single stroke, and not by a series of interrupted movements.
But, in fact, the striæ are not always parallel in such cases, but
often irregular, and sometimes the stones and earth which are in the middle
of the fault, or fissure, have been polished and striated by friction in
different directions, showing that there have been slidings subsequent to
the first introduction of the fragmentary matter. Nor should we forget
that the last movement must always tend to obliterate the signs of previous
trituration, so that neither its instantaneousness nor the uniformity
of its direction can be inferred from the parallelism of the striæ that
have been last produced.
When rocks have been once fractured, and freedom of motion communicated
163
to detached portions of them, these will naturally continue
to yield in the same direction, if the process of upheaval or of undermining
be repeated again and again. The incumbent mass will always
give way along the lines of least resistance, or where it was formerly
rent asunder. Probably, the effects of reiterated movement, whether
upward or downward, in a fault, may be undistinguishable from those
of a single and instantaneous rise or subsidence; and the same may be
said of the rising or falling of continental masses, such as Sweden or
Greenland, which we know to take place slowly and insensibly.
Doctrine of the sudden upheaval of parallel mountain-chains.—The
doctrine of the suddenness of many former revolutions in the physical
geography of the globe has been thought by some to derive additional
confirmation from a theory respecting the origin of mountain-chains, advanced
in 1833 by a distinguished geologist, M. Elie de Beaumont. In
several essays on this subject, the last published in 1852, he has attempted
to establish two points; first, that a variety of independent
chains of mountains have been thrown up suddenly at particular periods;
and, secondly, that the contemporaneous chains thus thrown up, preserve
a parallelism the one to the other.
These opinions, and others by which they are accompanied, are so
adverse to the method of interpreting the history of geological changes
which I have recommended in this work, that I am desirous of explaining
the grounds of my dissent, a course which I feel myself the more
called upon to adopt, as the generalizations alluded to are those of a
skilful writer, and an original observer of great talent and experience.
I shall begin, therefore, by giving a brief summary of the principal propositions
laid down in the works above referred to.242
1st. M. de Beaumont supposes "that in the history of the earth
there have been long periods of comparative repose, during which the
deposition of sedimentary matter has gone on in regular continuity; and
there have also been short periods of paroxysmal violence, during which
that continuity was broken.
"2dly. At each of these periods of violence or 'revolution,' in the
state of the earth's surface, a great number of mountain-chains have
been formed suddenly.
"3dly. The chains thrown up by a particular revolution have one
uniform direction, being parallel to each other within a few degrees of
the compass, even when situated in remote regions; whilst the chains
thrown up at different periods have, for the most part, different directions.
"4thly. Each 'revolution,' or 'great convulsion,' has fallen in with
the date of another geological phenomenon; namely, 'the passage from
164
one independent sedimentary formation to another,' characterized by a
considerable difference in 'organic types.'
"5thly. There has been a recurrence of these paroxysmal movements
from the remotest geological periods; and they may still be reproduced,
and the repose in which we live may hereafter be broken by the sudden
upthrow of another system of parallel chains of mountains.
"6thly. The origin of these chains depends not on partial volcanic
action, or a reiteration of ordinary earthquakes, but on the secular refrigeration
of the entire planet. For the whole globe, with the exception
of a thin envelope, much thinner in proportion than the shell to an
egg, is a fused mass, kept fluid by heat, but constantly cooling and
contracting its dimensions. The external crust does not gradually collapse
and accommodate itself century after century to the shrunken
nucleus, subsiding as often as there is a slight failure of support, but it
is sustained throughout whole geological periods, so as to become partially
separated from the nucleus, until at last it gives way suddenly,
cracking and falling in along determinate lines of fracture. During such
a crisis the rocks are subjected to great lateral pressure, the unyielding
ones are crushed, and the pliant strata bent, and are forced to pack
themselves more closely into a smaller space, having no longer the
same room to spread themselves out horizontally. At the same time,
a large portion of the mass is squeezed upwards, because it is in the
upward direction only that the excess in size of the envelope, as compared
to the contracted nucleus, can find relief. This excess produces
one or more of those folds or wrinkles in the earth's crust which we call
mountain-chains.
"Lastly, some chains are comparatively modern; such as the Alps,
which were partly upheaved after the middle tertiary period. The
elevation of the Andes was much more recent, and was accompanied by
the simultaneous outburst for the first time of 270 of the principal volcanoes
now active.243
"The agitation of the waters of the ocean caused by this convulsion
probably occasioned that transient and general deluge which is noticed
in the traditions of so many nations."244
Several of the topics enumerated in the above summary, such as the
cause of interruptions in the sedimentary series, will be discussed in the
thirteenth chapter, and I shall now confine myself to what I conceive
to be the insufficiency of the proofs adduced in favor of the suddenness
of the upthrow, and the contemporaneousness of the origin of the parallel
chains referred to. At the same time I may remark, that the great
body of facts collected together by M. de Beaumont will always form
a most valuable addition to our knowledge, tending as they do to confirm
the doctrine that different mountain-chains have been formed in
succession, and, as Werner first pointed out, that there are certain determinate
lines of direction or strike in the strata of various countries.
165The following may serve as an analysis of the evidence on which
the theory above stated depends. "We observe," says M. de Beaumont,
"when we attentively examine nearly all mountain-chains, that
the most recent rocks extend horizontally up to the foot of such chains,
as we should expect would be the case if they were deposited in seas
or lakes, of which these mountains have partly formed the shores;
whilst the other sedimentary beds, tilted up, and more or less contorted,
on the flanks of the mountains, rise in certain points even to their highest
crests."245 There are, therefore, in and adjacent to each chain, two
classes of sedimentary rocks, the ancient and inclined beds, and the
newer or horizontal. It is evident that the first appearance of the chain
itself was an event "intermediate between the period when the beds
now upraised were deposited, and the period when the strata were produced
horizontally at its feet."
Fig. 11.
Thus the chain A assumed its present position after the deposition
of the strata b, which have undergone great movements, and before
the deposition of the group c, in which the strata have not suffered
derangement.
Fig. 12.
If we then discover another chain B, in which we find not only the
formation b, but the group c also, disturbed and thrown on its edges,
we may infer that the latter chain is of subsequent date to A; for B
must have been elevated after the deposition of c, and before that of
the group d; whereas A had originated before the strata c were formed.
It is then argued, that in order to ascertain whether other mountain
ranges are of contemporaneous date with A and B, or are referable to
distinct periods, we have only to inquire whether the inclined and undisturbed
sets of strata in each range correspond with or differ from
those in the typical chain A and B.
Now all this reasoning is perfectly correct, so long as the period of
time required for the deposition of the strata b and c is not made identical
166
in duration with the period of time during which the animals and
plants found fossil in b and c may have flourished; for the latter, that
is to say, the duration of certain groups of species, may have greatly
exceeded, and probably did greatly exceed, the former, or the time
required for the accumulation of certain local deposits, such as b and c
(figs. 11 and 12). In order, moreover, to render the reasoning correct,
due latitude must be given to the term contemporaneous; for
this term must be understood to allude, not to a moment of time, but
to the interval, whether brief or protracted, which elapsed between
two events, namely, between the accumulation of the inclined and that
of the horizontal strata.
But, unfortunately, no attempt has been made in the treatises under
review to avoid this manifest source of confusion, and hence the very
terms of each proposition are equivocal; and the possible length of
some of the intervals is so vast, that to affirm that all the chains raised
in such intervals were contemporaneous is an abuse of language.
In order to illustrate this argument, I shall select the Pyrenees as an
example. Originally M. E. de Beaumont spoke of this range of mountains
as having been uplifted suddenly (à un seul jet), but he has since
conceded that in this chain, in spite of the general unity and simplicity
of its structure, six, if not seven, systems of dislocation of different dates
can be recognized.246 In reference, however, to the latest, and by far
the most important of these convulsions, the chain is said to have attained
its present elevation at a certain epoch in the earth's history,
namely, between the deposition of the chalk, or rocks of about that
age, and that of certain tertiary formations "as old as the plastic clay;"
for the chalk is seen in vertical, curved, and distorted beds on the flanks
of the chain, as the beds b, fig. 11, while the tertiary formations rest
upon them in horizontal strata at its base, as c, ibid.
The proof, then, of the extreme suddenness of the convulsion is supposed
to be the shortness of the time which intervened between the
formation of the chalk and the origin of certain tertiary strata.247 Even
if the interval were deducible within these limits, it might comprise an
indefinite lapse of time. In strictness of reasoning, however, the author
cannot exclude the Cretaceous or Tertiary periods from the possible
duration of the interval during which the elevation may have taken
place. For, in the first place, it cannot be assumed that the movement
of upheaval took place after the close of the Cretaceous period;
we can merely say, that it occurred after the deposition of certain
strata of that period; secondly, although it were true that the event
happened before the formation of all the tertiary strata now at the base
of the Pyrenees, it would by no means follow that it preceded the
whole Tertiary epoch.
The age of the strata, both of the inclined and horizontal series, may
167
have been accurately determined by M. De Beaumont, and still the upheaving
of the Pyrenees may have been going on before the animals of
the Chalk period, such as are found fossil in England, had ceased to exist,
or when the Maestricht beds were in progress, or during the indefinite
ages which may have elapsed between the extinction of the Maestricht
animals and the introduction of the Eocene tribes, or during the
Eocene epoch, or the rise may have been going on throughout one, or
several, or all of these periods.
It would be a purely gratuitous assumption to say that the inclined
cretaceous strata (b, fig. 11.) on the flanks of the Pyrenees, were the
very last which were deposited during the Cretaceous period, or that,
as soon as they were upheaved, all or nearly all the species of animals
and plants now found fossil in them were suddenly exterminated; yet,
unless this can be affirmed, we cannot say that the Pyrenees were not
upheaved during the Cretaceous period. Consequently, another range
of mountains, at the base of which cretaceous rocks may lie in horizontal
stratification, may have been elevated, like the chain A, fig. 12, during
some part of the same great period.
There are mountains in Sicily two or three thousand feet high, the
tops of which are composed of limestone, in which a large proportion of
the fossil shells agree specifically with those now inhabiting the Mediterranean.
Here, as in many other countries, the deposits now in progress
in the sea must inclose shells and other fossils specifically identical
with those of the rocks constituting the contiguous land. So there are
islands in the Pacific where a mass of dead coral has emerged to a considerable
altitude, while other portions of the mass remain beneath the
sea, still increasing by the growth of living zoophytes and shells. The
chalk of the Pyrenees, therefore, may at a remote period have been
raised to an elevation of several thousand feet, while the species found
fossil in the same chalk still continued to be represented in the fauna of
the neighboring ocean. In a word, we cannot assume that the origin of
a new range of mountains caused the Cretaceous period to cease, and
served as the prelude to a new order of things in the animate creation.
To illustrate the grave objections above advanced, against the theory
considered in the present chapter, let us suppose, that in some country
three styles of architecture had prevailed in succession, each for a period
of one thousand years; first the Greek, then the Roman, and then the
Gothic; and that a tremendous earthquake was known to have occurred
in the same district during one of the three periods—a convulsion of
such violence as to have levelled to the ground all the buildings then
standing. If an antiquary, desirous of discovering the date of the catastrophe,
should first arrive at a city where several Greek temples were
lying in ruins and half engulphed in the earth, while many Gothic edifices
were standing uninjured, could he determine on these data the era
of the shock? Could he even exclude any one of the three periods,
and decide that it must have happened during one of the other two?
Certainly not. He could merely affirm that it happened at some period
168
after the introduction of the Greek style, and before the Gothic had
fallen into disuse. Should he pretend to define the date of the convulsion
with greater precision, and decide that the earthquake must have
occurred after the Greek and before the Gothic period, that is to say,
when the Roman style was in use, the fallacy in his reasoning would be
too palpable to escape detection for a moment.
Yet such is the nature of the erroneous induction which I am now
exposing. For as, in the example above proposed, the erection of a
particular edifice is perfectly distinct from the period of architecture in
which it may have been raised, so is the deposition of chalk, or any
other set of strata, from the geological epochs characterized by certain
fossils to which they may belong.
It is almost superfluous to enter into any farther analysis of the theory
of parallelism, because the whole force of the argument depends on the
accuracy of the data by which the contemporaneous or
non-contemporaneous
date of the elevation of two independent chains can be demonstrated.
In every case, this evidence, as stated by M. de Beaumont, is
equivocal, because he has not included in the possible interval of time
between the depositions of the deranged and the horizontal formations,
part of the periods to which each of those classes of formations are referable.
Even if all the geological facts, therefore, adduced by the author
were true and unquestionable, yet the conclusion that certain chains
were or were not simultaneously upraised is by no means a legitimate
consequence.
In the third volume of my first edition of the Principles, which appeared
in April, 1833, I controverted the views of M. de Beaumont,
then just published, in the same terms as I have now restated them.
At that time I took for granted that the chronological date of the newest
rocks entering into the disturbed series of the Pyrenees had been
correctly ascertained. It now appears, however, that some of the most
modern of those disturbed strata belong to the nummulitic formation,
which are regarded by the majority of geologists as Eocene or older
tertiary, an opinion not assented to by M. E. de Beaumont, and which
I cannot discuss here without being led into too long a digression.248
Perhaps a more striking illustration of the difficulties we encounter,
when we attempt to apply the theory under consideration even to the
best known European countries, is afforded by what is called "The System
of the Longmynds." This small chain, situated in Shropshire, is
the third of the typical systems to which M. E. de Beaumont compares
other mountain ranges corresponding in strike and structure. The date
assigned to its upheaval is "after the unfossiliferous greywacke, or Cambrian
strata, and before the Silurian." But Sir R. I. Murchison had
shown in 1838, in his "Silurian System," and the British government
surveyors, since that time, in their sections (about 1845), that the Longmynds
and other chains of similar composition in North Wales are post-Silurian.
169
In all of them fossiliferous beds of the lower Silurian formation,
or Llandeilo flags are highly inclined, and often vertical. In one
limited region the Caradoc sandstone, a member of the lower Silurian,
rests unconformably on the denuded edges of the inferior (or Llandeilo)
member of the same group; whilst in some cases both of these sets of
strata are upturned. When, therefore, so grave an error is detected in
regard to the age of a typical chain, we are entitled to inquire with surprise,
by what means nine other parallel chains in France, Germany,
and Sweden, assumed to be "ante-Silurian," have been made to agree
precisely in date with the Longmynds? If they are correctly represented
as having been all deposited before the deposition of the Silurian
strata, they cannot be contemporaneous with the Longmynds, and they
only prove how little reliance can be placed on parallelism as a test of
simultaneousness of upheaval. But in truth it is impossible, for reasons
already given, to demonstrate that each of those nine chains coincide in
date with one another, any more than with the Longmynds.
The reader will see in the sequel (chap. 31249) that Mr. Hopkins has
inferred from astronomical calculations, that the solid crust of the earth
cannot be less than 800 or 1000 miles thick, and may be more. Even
if it be solid to the depth of 100 miles, such a thickness would be inconsistent
with M. E. de Beaumont's hypothesis, which requires a shell
not more than thirty miles thick, or even less. Mr. Hopkins admits
that the exterior of the planet, though solid as a whole, may contain
within it vast lakes or seas of lava. If so, the gradual fusion of rocks,
and the expansive power of heat exerted for ages, as well as the subsequent
contraction of the same during slow refrigeration, may perhaps
account for the origin of mountain-chains, for these, as Dolomieu has
remarked, are "far less important, proportionally speaking, than the inequalities
on the surface of an egg-shell, which to the eye appears
smooth." A "centripetal force" affecting the whole planet as it cools,
seems a mightier cause than is required to produce wrinkles of such
insignificant size.
In pursuing his investigations, M. E. de Beaumont has of late greatly
multiplied the number of successive periods of instantaneous upheaval,
admitting at the same time that occasionally new lines of upthrow have
taken the direction of older ones.250 These admissions render his views
much more in harmony with the principles advocated in this work, but
they impair the practical utility of parallelism considered as a chronological
test; for no rule is laid down for limiting the interval, whether in
time or space, which may separate two parallel lines of upheaval of
different dates.251
170
Among the various propositions above laid down (p. 164), it will be
seen that the sudden rise of the Andes is spoken of as a modern event,
but Mr. Darwin has brought together ample data in proof of the local
persistency of volcanic action throughout a long succession of geological
periods, beginning with times antecedent to the deposition of the oolitic
and cretaceous formations of Chili, and continuing to the historical
epoch. It appears that some of the parallel ridges which compose the
Cordilleras, instead of being contemporaneous, were successively and
slowly upheaved at widely different epochs. The whole range, after
twice subsiding some thousands of feet, was brought up again by a slow
movement in mass, during the era of the Eocene tertiary formations,
after which the whole sank down once more several hundred feet, to be
again uplifted to its present level by a slow and often interrupted movement.252
In a portion of this latter period the "Pampean mud" was
formed, in which the Megatherium mylodon and other extinct quadrupeds
are buried. This mud contains in it recent species of shells, some
of them proper to brackish water, and is believed by Mr. Darwin to be
an estuary or delta deposit. M. A. d'Orbigny, however, has advanced
an hypothesis referred to by M. E. de Beaumont, that the agitation and
displacement of the waters of the ocean, caused by the elevation of the
Andes, gave rise to a deluge, of which this Pampean mud, which rises
sometimes to the height of 12,000 feet, is the result and monument.253
In studying many chains of mountains, we find that the strike or line
of outcrop of continuous sets of strata, and the general direction of the
chain, may be far from rectilinear. Curves forming angles of 20° or 30°
may be found in the same range as in the Alleghanies; just as trains
of active volcanoes and the zones throughout which modern earthquakes
occur are often linear, without running in straight lines. Nor are all of
these, though contemporaneous or belonging to our own epoch, by any
means parallel, but some at right angles, the one to the other.
Slow upheaval and subsidence.—Recent observations have disclosed
to us the wonderful fact, that not only the west coast of South
America, but also other large areas, some of them several thousand
miles in circumference, such as Scandinavia, and certain archipelagoes in
the Pacific, are slowly and insensibly rising; while other regions, such
as Greenland, and parts of the Pacific and Indian Oceans, in which
atolls or circular coral islands abound, are as gradually sinking. That
all the existing continents and submarine abysses may have originated
in movements of this kind, continued throughout incalculable periods of
time, is undeniable, and the denudation which the dry land appears
everywhere to have suffered, favors the idea that it was raised from
the deep by a succession of upward movements, prolonged throughout
indefinite periods. For the action of waves and currents on land slowly
emerging from the deep, affords the only power by which we can conceive
171
so many deep valleys and wide spaces to have been denuded as
those which are unquestionably the effects of running water.
But perhaps it may be said that there is no analogy between the slow
upheaval of broad plains or table-lands, and the manner in which we
must presume all mountain-chains, with their inclined strata, to have
originated. It seems, however, that the Andes have been rising century
after century, at the rate of several feet, while the Pampas on the
east have been raised only a few inches in the same time. Crossing
from the Atlantic to the Pacific, in a line passing through Mendoza,
Mr. Darwin traversed a plain 800 miles broad, the eastern part of
which has emerged from beneath the sea at a very modern period.
The slope from the Atlantic is at first very gentle, then greater, until
the traveller finds, on reaching Mendoza, that he has gained, almost insensibly,
a height of 4000 feet. The mountainous district then begins
suddenly, and its breadth from Mendoza to the shores of the Pacific is
120 miles, the average height of the principal chain being from 15,000
to 16,000 feet, without including some prominent peaks, which ascend
much higher. Now all we require, to explain the origin of the principal
inequalities of level here described, is to imagine, first, a zone of more
violent movement to the west of Mendoza, and, secondly, to the east of
that place, an upheaving force, which died away gradually as it approached
the Atlantic. In short, we are only called upon to conceive,
that the region of the Andes was pushed up four feet in the same period
in which the Pampas near Mendoza rose one foot, and the plains
near the shores of the Atlantic one inch. In Europe we have learnt
that the land at the North Cape ascends about five feet in a century,
while farther to the south the movements diminish in quantity first to a
foot, and then, at Stockholm, to three inches in a century, while at certain
points still farther south there is no movement.
But in what manner, it is asked, can we account for the great lateral
pressure which has been exerted not only in the Andes, Alps, and other
chains, but also on the strata of many low and nearly level countries?
Do not the folding and fracture of the beds, the anticlinal and synclinal
ridges and troughs, as they are called, and the vertical, and even sometimes
the inverted position of the beds, imply an abruptness and intensity
in the disturbing force wholly different in kind and energy to that
which now rends the rocks during ordinary earthquakes? I shall treat
more fully in the sequel (end of chap. 32) of the probable subterranean
sources, whether of upward or downward movement, and of great lateral
pressure; but it may be well briefly to state in this place that in our
own times, as, for example, in Chili, in 1822, the volcanic force has
overcome the resistance, and permanently uplifted a country of such
vast extent that the weight and volume of the Andes must be insignificant
in comparison, even if we indulge the most moderate conjectures as
to the thickness of the earth's crust above the volcanic foci.
To assume that any set of strata with which we are acquainted are
made up of such cohesive and unyielding materials, as to be able to
172
resist a power of such stupendous energy, if its direction, instead of
being vertical, happened to be oblique or horizontal, would be extremely
rash. But if they could yield to a sideway thrust, even in a slight degree,
they would become squeezed and folded to any amount if subjected
for a sufficient number of times to the repeated action of the
same force. We can scarcely doubt that a mass of rock several miles
thick was uplifted in Chili in 1822 and 1835, and that a much greater
volume of solid matter is upheaved wherever the rise of the land is very
gradual, as in Scandinavia, the development of heat being probably, in
that region, at a greater distance from the surface. If continents,
rocked, shaken, and fissured, like the western region of South America,
or very gently elevated, like Norway and Sweden, do not acquire in a
few days or hours an additional height of several thousand feet, this
can arise from no lack of mechanical force in the subterranean moving
cause, but simply because the antagonist power, or the strength, toughness,
and density of the earth's crust is insufficient to resist, so long, as
to allow the volcanic energy an indefinite time to accumulate. Instead
of the explosive charge augmenting in quantity for countless ages, it
finds relief continuously, or by a succession of shocks of moderate violence,
so as never to burst or blow up the covering of incumbent rock
in one grand paroxysmal convulsion. Even in its most energetic efforts
it displays an intermittent and mitigated intensity, being never permitted
to lay a whole continent in ruins. Hence the numerous eruptions
of lava from the same vent, or chain of vents, and the recurrence of
similar earthquakes for thousands of years along certain areas or zones
of country. Hence the numerous monuments of the successive ejection
and injection of melted matter in ancient geological epochs, and the fissures
formed in distinct ages, and often widened and filled at different
eras.
Among the causes of lateral pressure, the expansion by heat of large
masses of solid stone intervening between others which have a different
degree of expansibility, or which happen not to have their temperature
raised at the same time, may play an important part. But as we know
that rocks have so often sunk down thousands of feet below their original
level, we can hardly doubt that much of the bending of pliant
strata, and the packing of the same into smaller spaces, has frequently
been occasioned by subsidence. Whether the failure of support be
produced by the melting of porous rocks, which, when fluid, and subjected
to great pressure, may occupy less room than before, or which,
by passing from a pasty to a crystalline condition, may, as in the case
of granite, according to the experiments of Deville, suffer a contraction
of 10 per cent., or whether the sinking be due to the subtraction of
lava driven elsewhere to some volcanic orifice, and there forced outwards,
or whether it be brought on by the shrinking of solid and stony
masses during refrigeration, or by the condensation of gases, or any
other imaginable cause, we have no reason to incline to the idea that
the consequent geological changes are brought about so suddenly, as
173
that large parts of continents are swallowed up at once in unfathomable
subterranean abysses. If cavities be formed, they will be enlarged
gradually, and as gradually filled. We read, indeed, accounts of engulphed
cities and areas of limited extent which have sunk down many
yards at once; but we have as yet no authentic records of the sudden
disappearance of mountains, or the submergence or emergence of great
islands. On the other hand, the creeps in coal mines254 demonstrate
that gravitation begins to act as soon as a moderate quantity of matter
is removed even at a great depth. The roof sinks in, or the floor of the
mine rises, and the bent strata often assume as regularly a curved and
crumpled arrangement as that observed on a grander scale in mountain-chains.
The absence, indeed, of chaotic disorder, and the regularity
of the plications in geological formations of high antiquity, although
not unfrequently adduced to prove the unity and instantaneousness
of the disturbing force, might with far greater propriety be brought
forward as an argument in favor of the successive application of some
irresistible but moderated force, such as that which can elevate or depress
a continent.
In conclusion, I may observe that one of the soundest objections to
the theory of the sudden upthrow or downthrow of mountain-chains is
this, that it provides us with too much force of one kind, namely, that
of subterranean movement, while it deprives us of another kind of mechanical
force, namely, that exerted by the waves and currents of the
ocean, which the geologist requires for the denudation of land during its
slow upheaval or depression. It may be safely affirmed that the quantity
of igneous and aqueous action,—of volcanic eruption and denudation,—of
subterranean movement and sedimentary deposition,—not
only of past ages, but of one geological epoch, or even the fraction of
an epoch, has exceeded immeasurably all the fluctuations of the inorganic
world which have been witnessed by man. But we have still to
inquire whether the time to which each chapter or page or paragraph
of the earth's autobiography relates, was not equally immense when
contrasted with a brief era of 3000 or 5000 years. The real point on
which the whole controversy turns, is the relative amount of work done
by mechanical force in given quantities of time, past and present. Before
we can determine the relative intensity of the force employed, we
must have some fixed standard by which to measure the time expended
in its development at two distinct periods. It is not the magnitude of
the effects, however gigantic their proportions, which can inform us in
the slightest degree whether the operation was sudden or gradual, insensible
or paroxysmal. It must be shown that a slow process could
never in any series of ages give rise to the same results.
The advocate of paroxysmal energy might assume a uniform and
fixed rate of variation in times past and present for the animate world,
that is to say, for the dying-out and coming-in of species, and then endeavor
174
to prove that the changes of the inanimate world have not gone
on in a corresponding ratio. But the adoption of such a standard of
comparison would lead, I suspect, to a theory by no means favorable to
the pristine intensity of natural causes. That the present state of the
organic world is not stationary, can be fairly inferred from the fact, that
some species are known to have become extinct in the course even of
the last three centuries, and that the exterminating causes always in
activity, both on the land and in the waters, are very numerous; also,
because man himself is an extremely modern creation; and we may
therefore reasonably suppose that some of the mammalia now contemporary
with man, as well as a variety of species of inferior classes, may
have been recently introduced into the earth, to supply the places of
plants and animals which have from time to time disappeared. But
granting that some such secular variation in the zoological and botanical
worlds is going on, and is by no means wholly inappreciable to the
naturalist, still it is certainly far less manifest than the revolution always
in progress in the inorganic world. Every year some volcanic eruptions
take place, and a rude estimate might be made of the number of cubic
feet of lava and scoriæ poured or cast out of various craters. The
amount of mud and sand deposited in deltas, and the advance of new
land upon the sea, or the annual retreat of wasting sea-cliffs, are changes
the minimum amount of which might be roughly estimated. The quantity
of land raised above or depressed below the level of the sea might
also be computed, and the change arising from such movements in a
century might be conjectured. Suppose the average rise of the land in
some parts of Scandinavia to be as much as five feet in a hundred years,
the present sea-coast might be uplifted 700 feet in fourteen thousand
years; but we should have no reason to anticipate, from any zoological
data hitherto acquired, that the molluscous fauna of the northern seas
would in that lapse of years undergo any sensible amount of variation.
We discover sea-beaches in Norway 700 feet high, in which the shells
are identical with those now inhabiting the German Ocean; for the rise
of land in Scandinavia, however insensible to the inhabitants, has evidently
been rapid when compared to the rate of contemporaneous change
in the testaceous fauna of the German Ocean. Were we to wait therefore
until the mollusca shall have undergone as much fluctuation as
they underwent between the period of the Lias and the Upper Oolite
formations; or between the Oolite and Chalk, nay, even between any
two of eight subdivisions of the Eocene series, what stupendous revolutions
in physical geography ought we not to expect, and how many
mountain-chains might not be produced by the repetition of shocks of
moderate violence, or by movements not even perceptible by man!
Or, if we turn from the mollusca to the vegetable kingdom, and ask
the botanist how many earthquakes and volcanic eruptions might be
expected, and how much the relative level of land and sea might be
altered, or how far the principal deltas will encroach upon the ocean,
or the sea-cliffs recede from the present shores, before the species of
175
European forest-trees will die out, he would reply that such alterations
in the inanimate world might be multiplied indefinitely before he should
have reason to anticipate, by reference to any known data, that the existing
species of trees in our forests would disappear and give place to
others. In a word, the movement of the inorganic world is obvious and
palpable, and might be likened to the minute-hand of a clock, the progress
of which can be seen and heard, whereas the fluctuations of the
living creation are nearly invisible, and resemble the motion of the hour-hand
of a timepiece. It is only by watching it attentively for some
time, and comparing its relative position after an interval, that we can
prove the reality of its motion.255
</div></body></text></TEI>