<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="19"> 

CHAPTER IX.
Of the Application of Inductive Truths.


Aphorism LIII.
When the theory of any subject is established, the observations
and experiments which are made in applying the
science to use and to instruction, supply a perpetual verification
of the theory.
Aphorism LIV.
Such observations and experiments, when numerous and
accurate, supply also corrections of the constants involved
in the theory; and sometimes, (by the Method of Residues,)
additions to the theory.
Aphorism LV.
It is worth considering, whether a continued and connected
system of observation and calculation, like that of
astronomy, might not be employed with advantage in improving
our knowledge of other subjects; as Tides, Currents,
Winds, Clouds, Rain, Terrestrial Magnetism, Aurora Borealis,
Composition of Crystals, and many other subjects.
Aphorism LVI.
An extension of a well-established theory to the explanation
of new facts excites admiration as a discovery; but it is a
discovery of a lower order than the theory itself.
Aphorism LVII.
The practical inventions which are most important in
Art may be either unimportant parts of Science, or results
not explained by Science. 234
Aphorism LVIII.
In modern times, in many departments. Art is constantly
guided, governed and advanced by Science.
Aphorism LIX.
Recently several New Arts have been invented, which may
be regarded as notable verifications of the anticipations of
material benefits to be derived to man from the progress of
Science.

1. BY the
application of inductive truths, we here
mean, according to the arrangement given in
chap. I. of this book, those steps, which in the natural
order of science, follow the discovery of each truth.
These steps are, the verification of the discovery by additional
experiments and reasonings, and its extension
to new cases, not contemplated by the original discoverer.
These processes occupy that period, which,
in the history of each great discovery, we have termed
the Sequel of the epoch; as the collection of facts, and
the elucidation of conceptions, form its Prelude.
2. It is not necessary to dwell at length on the
processes of the Verification of Discoveries. When the
Law of Nature is once stated, it is far easier to devise
and execute experiments which prove it, than it was
to discern the evidence before. The truth becomes
one of the standard doctrines of the science to which it
belongs, and is verified by all who study or who teach
the science experimentally. The leading doctrines of
Chemistry are constantly exemplified by each chemist
in his Laboratory; and an amount of verification is
thus obtained of which books give no adequate conception.
In Astronomy, we have a still stronger example
of the process of verifying discoveries. Ever since the
science assumed a systematic form, there have been
Observatories, in which the consequences of the theory
were habitually compared with the results of observation.
And to facilitate this comparison, Tables of
great extent have been calculated, with immense labour,
from each theory, showing the place which the 235
theory assigned to the heavenly bodies at successive
times; and thus, as it were, challenging nature to
deny the truth of the discovery. In this way, as I
have elsewhere stated, the continued prevalence of an
errour in the systematic parts of astronomy is
impossible49.
An errour, if it arise, makes its way into the
tables, into the ephemeris, into the observer’s nightly
list, or his sheet of reductions; the evidence of sense
flies in its face in a thousand Observatories; the
discrepancy is traced to its source, and soon disappears
for ever.</div></body></text></TEI>