<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="28">
CHAPTER IX.

Mechanical Laws.

In the preceding observations we have supposed
the laws, by which different kinds of matter act and
are acted upon, to be already in existence; and have
endeavoured to point out evidences of design and
adaptation, displayed in the selection and arrangement
of these materials of the universe. These materials
are, it has appeared, supplied in such measures
and disposed in such forms, that by means of their
properties and laws the business of the world goes
on harmoniously and beneficially. But a further
question occurs: how came matter to have such
properties and laws? Are these also to be considered
as things of selection and institution? And if so, can
we trace the reasons why the laws were established[164]
in their present form; why the properties which matter
actually possesses were established and bestowed
and bestowed upon it? We have already attempted,
in a previous part of this work, to point out some of
the advantages which are secured by the existing
laws of heat, light and moisture. Can we, in the
same manner, point out the benefits which arise from
the present constitution of those laws of matter which
are mainly concerned in the production of cosmical
phenomena?
It will readily be perceived that the discussion of
this point must necessarily require some effort of abstract
thought. The laws and properties of which
we have here to speak, the laws of motion and the
universal properties of matter, are so closely interwoven
with our conceptions of the external world,
that we have great difficulty in conceiving them not
to exist, or to exist other than they are. When we
press or lift a stone, we can hardly imagine that it
could, by possibility, do otherwise than resist our
effort by its hardness and by its heaviness, qualities
so familiar to us: when we throw it, it seems inevitable
that its motion should depend on the impulse we
give, just as we find that it invariably does.
Nor is it easy to say how far it is really possible to
suppose the fundamental attributes of matter to be
different from what they are. If we, in our thoughts,
attempt to divest matter of its powers of resisting
and moving, it ceases to be matter, according to our
conceptions, and we can no longer reason upon it
with any distinctness. And yet it is certain that we
can conceive the laws of hardness and weight and
motion to be quite different from what they are, and
can point out some of the consequences which would
result from such difference. The properties of matter,
even the most fundamental and universal ones,
do not obtain by any absolute necessity, resembling
that which belongs to the properties of geometry. A
line touching a circle is necessarily perpendicular to
a line drawn to the centre through the point touched;[165]
for it may be shown that the contrary involves
a contradiction. But there is no contradiction in
supposing that a body’s motion should naturally
diminish, or that its weight should increase in removing
further from the earth’s centre.
Thus the properties of matter and the laws of motion
are what we find them, not by virtue of any internal
necessity which we can understand. The
study of such laws and properties may therefore disclose
to us the character of that external agency by
which we conceive them to have been determined to
be what they are; and this must be the same agency
by which all other parts of the constitution of the
universe were appointed and ordered.
But we can hardly expect, with regard to such
subjects, that we shall be able to obtain any complete
or adequate view of the reasons why these general
laws are so selected, and so established. These laws
are the universal basis of all operations which go on,
at any moment, in every part of space, with regard
to every particle of matter, organic and inorganic.
All other laws and properties must have a reference
to these, and must be influenced by them; both such
as men have already discovered, and the far greater
number which remain still unknown. The general
economy and mutual relations of all parts of the universe,
must be subordinate to the laws of motion and
matter of which we here speak. We can easily suppose
that the various processes of nature, and the
dependencies of various creatures, are affected in the
most comprehensive manner by these laws;—are
simplified by their simplicity, made consistent by
their universality; rendered regular by their symmetry.
We can easily suppose that in this way there may
be the most profound and admirable reasons for the
existence of the present universal properties of matter,
which we cannot apprehend in consequence of
the limited nature of our knowledge, and of our faculties.
For, compared with the whole extent of the
universe, the whole aggregate of things and relations[166]
and connexions which exist in it, our knowledge is
most narrow and partial, most shallow and superficial.
We cannot suppose, therefore, that the reasons
which we discover for the present form of the
laws of nature go nearly to the full extent, or to the
bottom of the reasons, which a more complete and
profound insight would enable us to perceive. To
do justice to such reasons, would require nothing less
than a perfect acquaintance with the whole constitution
of every part of creation; a knowledge which
man has not, and, so far as we can conceive, never
can have.
We are certain, therefore, that our views, with
regard to this part of our subject, must be imperfect
and limited. Yet still man has some knowledge with
regard to various portions of nature; and with regard
to those most general and comparatively simple
facts to which we now refer, his knowledge is more
comprehensive, and goes deeper than it does in any
other province. We conceive, therefore, that we
shall not be engaged in any rash or presumptuous
attempt, if we endeavour to point out some of the
advantages which are secured by the present constitution
of some of the general mechanical laws of nature;
and to suggest the persuasion of that purpose
and wise design, which the selection of such laws
will thus appear to imply.
</div></body></text></TEI>