<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="8">
CHAPTER III.
Of Facts as the Materials of Science.
Aphorism IV.
Facts are the materials of science, but all Facts involve
Ideas. Since in observing Facts, we cannot exclude Ideas,
we must, for the purposes of science, take care that the Ideas
are clear and rigorously applied.
Aphorism V.
The last Aphorism leads to such Rules as the following:—That
Facts, for the purposes of material science, must involve
Conceptions of the Intellect only, and not Emotions:—That
Facts must be observed with reference to our most exact conceptions,
Number, Place, Figure, Motion:—That they must
also be observed with reference to any other exact conceptions
which the phenomena suggest, as Force, in mechanical phenomena,
Concord, in musical.
Aphorism VI.
The resolution of complex Facts into precise and measured
partial Facts, we call the Decomposition of Facts. This
process is requisite for the progress of science, but does not
necessarily lead to progress.
1. WE
have now to examine how Science is built
up by the combination of Facts. In doing this,
we suppose that we have already attained a supply of
definite and certain Facts, free from obscurity and doubt.
We must, therefore, first consider under what conditions
Facts can assume this character.
When we inquire what Facts are to be made the
materials of Science, perhaps the answer which we 51
should most commonly receive would be, that they
must be True Facts, as distinguished from any mere
inferences or opinions of our own. We should probably be told
that we must be careful in such a case to
consider as Facts, only what we really observe;—that
we must assert only what we see; and believe nothing
except upon the testimony of our senses.
But such maxims are far from being easy to apply,
as a little examination will convince us.
2. It has been explained, in preceding works,
that all perception of external objects and occurrences
involves an active as well as a passive process
of the mind;—includes not only Sensations, but also
Ideas by which Sensations are bound together, and
have a unity given to them. From this it follows, that
there is a difficulty in separating in our perceptions
what we receive from without, and what we ourselves
contribute from within;—what we perceive, and what
we infer. In many cases, this difficulty is obvious to
all: as, for example, when we witness the performances
of a juggler or a ventriloquist. In these instances, we
imagine ourselves to see and to hear what certainly we
do not see and hear. The performer takes advantage
of the habits by which our minds supply interruptions
and infer connexions; and by giving us fallacious
indications, he leads us to perceive as an actual fact, what
does not happen at all. In these cases, it is evident
that we ourselves assist in making the fact; for we
make one which does not really exist. In other cases,
though the fact which we perceive be true, we can
easily see that a large portion of the perception is our
own act; as when, from the sight of a bird of prey we
infer a carcase, or when we read a half-obliterated inscription.
In the latter case, the mind supplies the
meaning, and perhaps half the letters; yet we do not
hesitate to say that we actually read the inscription.
Thus, in many cases, our own inferences and interpretations
enter into our facts. But this happens in
many instances in which it is at first sight less obvious.
When any one has seen an oak-tree blown down by a
strong gust of wind, he does not think of the occurrence 52
any otherwise than as a Fact of which he is assured by
his senses. Yet by what sense does he perceive the
Force which he thus supposes the wind to exert? By
what sense does he distinguish an Oak-tree from all
other trees? It is clear upon reflexion, that in such
a case, his own mind supplies the conception of extraneous
impulse and pressure, by which he thus interprets the motions
observed, and the distinction of
different kinds of trees, according to which he thus
names the one under his notice. The Idea of Force,
and the idea of definite Resemblances and Differences,
are thus combined with the impressions on our senses,
and form an undistinguished portion of that which we
consider as the Fact. And it is evident that we can in
no other way perceive Force, than by seeing motion;
and cannot give a Name to any object, without not
only seeing a difference of single objects, but supposing
a difference of classes of objects. When we speak as
if we saw impulse and attraction, things and classes,
we really see only objects of various forms and colours,
more or less numerous, variously combined. But do
we really perceive so much as this? When we see the
form, the size, the number, the motion of objects, are
these really mere impressions on our senses, unmodified
by any contribution or operation of the mind
itself? A very little attention will suffice to convince
us that this is not the case. When we see a windmill
turning, it may happen, as we have elsewhere
noticed3,
that we mistake the direction in which the sails turn:
when we look at certain diagrams, they may appear
either convex or concave: when we see the moon first
in the horizon and afterwards high up in the sky, we
judge her to be much larger in the former than in the
latter position, although to the eye she subtends the
same angle. And in these cases and the like, it has
been seen that the errour and confusion which we thus
incur arise from the mixture of acts of the mind itself
with impressions on the senses. But such acts are, as
we have also seen, inseparable portions of the process 53
of perception. A certain activity of the mind is involved,
not only in seeing objects erroneously, but in
seeing them at all. With regard to solid objects, this
is generally acknowledged. When we seem to see an
edifice occupying space in all dimensions, we really see
only a representation of it as it appears referred by
perspective to a surface. The inference of the solid
form is an operation of our own, alike when we look at
a reality and when we look at a picture. But we may
go further. Is plane Figure really a mere Sensation?
If we look at a decagon, do we see at once that it has
ten sides, or is it not necessary for us to count them:
and is not counting an act of the mind? All objects
are seen in space; all objects are seen as one or many:
but are not the Idea of Space and the Idea of Number
requisite in order that we may thus apprehend what
we see? That these Ideas of Space and Number involve a
connexion derived from the mind, and not from
the senses, appears, as we have already seen, from this,
that those Ideas afford us the materials of universal
and necessary truths:—such truths as the senses cannot
possibly supply. And thus, even the perception of
such facts as the size, shape, and number of objects,
cannot be said to be impressions of sense, distinct from
all acts of mind, and cannot be expected to be free
from errour on the ground of their being mere observed
Facts.
3 History of Ideas, B. ii. c. vi. s. 6.
Thus the difficulty which we have been illustrating,
of distinguishing Facts from inferences and from
interpretations of facts, is not only great, but amounts to an
impossibility. The separation at which we aimed in
the outset of this discussion, and which was supposed
to be necessary in order to obtain a firm groundwork
for science, is found to be unattainable. We cannot
obtain a sure basis of Facts, by rejecting all inferences
and judgments of our own, for such inferences and
judgments form an unavoidable element in all Facts.
We cannot exclude our Ideas from our Perceptions,
for our Perceptions involve our Ideas.
3. But still, it cannot be doubted that in selecting
the Facts which are to form the foundation of Science, 54
we must reduce them to their most simple and certain
form; and must reject everything from which doubt or
errour may arise. Now since this, it appears, cannot
be done, by rejecting the Ideas which all Facts involve,
in what manner are we to conform to the obvious maxim,
that the Facts which form the basis of
Science must be perfectly definite and certain?
The analysis of facts into Ideas and Sensations,
which we have so often referred to, suggests the answer
to this inquiry. We are not able, nor need we
endeavour, to exclude Ideas from our Facts; but we
may be able to discern, with perfect distinctness, the
Ideas which we include. We cannot observe any phenomena
without applying to them such Ideas as Space
and Number, Cause and Resemblance, and usually,
several others; but we may avoid applying these Ideas
in a wavering or obscure manner, and confounding
Ideas with one another. We cannot read any of the
inscriptions which nature presents to us, without
interpreting them by means of some language which we
ourselves are accustomed to speak; but we may make
it our business to acquaint ourselves perfectly with the
language which we thus employ, and to interpret it
according to the rigorous rules of grammar and analogy.
This maxim, that when Facts are employed as the
basis of Science, we must distinguish clearly the Ideas
which they involve, and must apply these in a distinct
and rigorous manner, will be found to be a more precise
guide than we might perhaps at first expect. We
may notice one or two Rules which flow from it.
4. In the first place. Facts, when used as the materials
of physical Science, must be referred to Conceptions
of the Intellect only, all emotions of fear, admiration,
and the like, being rejected or subdued. Thus,
the observations of phenomena which are related as
portents and prodigies, striking terrour and boding
evil, are of no value for purposes of science. The tales
of armies seen warring in the sky, the sound of arms
heard from the clouds, fiery dragons, chariots, swords
seen in the air, may refer to meteorological phenomena;
but the records of phenomena observed in the 55
state of mind which these descriptions imply can be
of no scientific value. We cannot make the poets our
observers.
Armorum sonitum toto Germania cœlo
Audiit; insolitis tremuerunt motibus Alpes.
Vox quoque per lucos vulgo exaudita silentes
Ingens; et simulacra modis pallentia miris
Visa sub obscurum noctis: pecudesque locutæ.
The mixture of fancy and emotion with the observation
of facts has often disfigured them to an extent which
is too familiar to all to need illustration. We have an
example of this result, in the manner in which Comets
are described in the treatises of the middle ages. In
such works, these bodies are regularly distributed into
several classes, accordingly as they assume the form of
a sword, of a spear, of a cross, and so on. When such
resemblances had become matters of interest, the
impressions of the senses were governed, not by the
rigorous conceptions of form and colour, but by these
assumed images; and under these circumstances, we can
attach little value to the statement of what was seen.
In all such phenomena, the reference of the objects
to the exact Ideas of Space, Number, Position, Motion,
and the like, is the first step of Science: and accordingly,
this reference was established at an early period
in those sciences which made an early progress, as, for
instance, Astronomy. Yet even in astronomy there
appears to have been a period when the predominant
conceptions of men in regarding the heavens and the
stars pointed to mythical story and supernatural influence,
rather than to mere relations of space, time,
and motion: and of this primeval condition of those
who gazed at the stars, we seem to have remnants in
the Constellations, in the mythological Names of the
Planets, and in the early prevalence of Astrology. It
was only at a later period, when men had begun to
measure the places, or at least to count the revolutions
of the stars, that Astronomy had its birth.
5. And thus we are led to another Rule:—that in
collecting Facts which are to be made the basis of 56
Science, the Facts are to be observed, as far as possible,
with reference to place, figure,
number, motion, and the
like Conceptions; which, depending upon the Ideas of
Space and Time, are the most universal, exact, and
simple of our conceptions. It was by early attention to
these relations in the case of the heavenly bodies, that
the ancients formed the science of Astronomy: it was
by not making precise observations of this kind in the
case of terrestrial bodies, that they failed in framing a
science of the Mechanics of Motion. They succeeded
in Optics as far as they made observations of this nature;
but when they ceased to trace the geometrical
paths of rays in the actual experiment, they ceased to
go forwards in the knowledge of this subject.
6. But we may state a further Rule:—that though
these relations of Time and Space are highly important
in almost all Facts, we are not to confine ourselves to
these: but are to consider the phenomena with reference
to other Conceptions also: it being always understood
that these conceptions are to be made as exact and
rigorous as those of geometry and number. Thus the
science of Harmonics arose from considering sounds
with reference to Concords and Discords; the science
of Mechanics arose from not only observing motions as
they take place in Time and Space, but further, referring
them to Force as their Cause. And in like manner, other
sciences depend upon other Ideas, which, as
I have endeavoured to show, are not less fundamental
than those of Time and Space; and like them, capable
of leading to rigorous consequences.
7. Thus the Facts which we assume as the basis of
Science are to be freed from all the mists which
imagination and passion throw round them; and to be
separated into those elementary Facts which exhibit
simple and evident relations of Time, or Space, or
Cause, or some other Ideas equally clear. We resolve
the complex appearances which nature offers to us,
and the mixed and manifold modes of looking at these
appearances which rise in our thoughts, into limited,
definite, and clearly-understood portions. This process
we may term the Decomposition of Facts. It is the 57
beginning of exact knowledge,—the first step in the
formation of all Science. This Decomposition of Facts
into Elementary Facts, clearly understood and surely
ascertained, must precede all discovery of the laws of
nature.
8. But though this step is necessary, it is not infallibly
sufficient. It by no means follows that when we
have thus decomposed Facts into Elementary Truths
of observation, we shall soon be able to combine these,
so as to obtain Truths of a higher and more speculative
kind. We have examples which show us how
far this is from being a necessary consequence of the
former step. Observations of the weather, made and
recorded for many years, have not led to any general
truths, forming a science of Meteorology: and although
great numerical precision has been given to such
observations by means of barometers, thermometers, and
other instruments, still, no general laws regulating the
cycles of change of such phenomena have yet been
discovered. In like manner the faces of crystals, and
the sides of the polygons which these crystals form,
were counted, and thus numerical facts were obtained,
perfectly true and definite, but still of no value for
purposes of science. And when it was discovered
what Element of the form of crystals it was important
to observe and measure, namely, the Angle made by
two faces with each other, this discovery was a step of
a higher order, and did not belong to that department,
of mere exact observation of manifest Facts,
with which we are here concerned.
9. When the Complex Facts which nature offers to
us are thus decomposed into Simple Facts, the
decomposition, in general, leads to the introduction of Terms
and Phrases, more or less technical, by which these
Simple Facts are described. When Astronomy was
thus made a science of measurement, the things measured
were soon described as Hours, and Days, and
Cycles, Altitude and Declination,
Phases and Aspects.
In the same manner, in Music, the concords had names
assigned them, as Diapente, Diatessaron, Diapason; in
studying Optics, the Rays of light were spoken of as 58
having their course altered by Reflexion and Refraction;
and when useful observations began to be made
in Mechanics, the observers spoke of Force, Pressure,
Momentum, Inertia, and the like.
10. When we take phenomena in which the leading Idea is
Resemblance, and resolve them into precise
component Facts, we obtain some kind of Classification;
as, for instance, when we lay down certain Rules
by which particular trees, or particular animals are to
be known. This is the earliest form of Natural History;
and the Classification which it involves is that
which corresponds, nearly or exactly, with the usual
Names of the objects thus classified.
11. Thus the first attempts to render observation
certain and exact, lead to a decomposition of the obvious
facts into Elementary Facts, connected by the
Ideas of Space, Time, Number, Cause, Likeness, and
others: and into a Classification of the Simple Facts;
a classification more or less just, and marked by Names
either common or technical. Elementary Facts, and
Individual Objects, thus observed and classified, form
the materials of Science; and any improvement in
Classification or Nomenclature, or any discovery of a
Connexion among the materials thus accumulated,
leads us fairly within the precincts of Science. We
must now, therefore, consider the manner in which
Science is built up of such materials;—the process by
which they are brought into their places, and the
texture of the bond which unites and cements them.
</div></body></text></TEI>