<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="39">INTRODUCTION.
THERE is a difficulty in
writing for popular readers a History of the Inductive Sciences,
arising from this;—that the sympathy of such readers goes most
readily and naturally along the course which leads to false science
and to failure. Men, in the outset of their attempts at knowledge, are
prone to rush from a few hasty observations of facts to some wide and
comprehensive principles; and then, to frame a system on these
principles. This is the opposite of the method by which the Sciences
have really and historically been conducted; namely, the method of a
gradual and cautious ascent from observation to principles of limited
generality, and from them to others more general. This latter, the
true Scientific Method, is Induction, and has led to the
Inductive Sciences. The other, the spontaneous and delusive
course, has been termed by Francis Bacon, who first clearly pointed
out the distinction, and warned men of the error, Anticipation.
The hopelessness of this course is the great lesson of his philosophy;
but by this course proceeded all the earlier attempts of the Greek
philosophers to obtain a knowledge of the Universe.
Laborious observation, narrow and modest inference, caution, slow
and gradual advance, limited knowledge, are all unwelcome efforts and
restraints to the mind of man, when his speculative spirit is once
roused: yet these are the necessary conditions of all advance in the
Inductive Sciences. Hence, as I have said, it is difficult to win the
sympathy of popular readers to the true history of these sciences. The
career of bold systems and fanciful pretences of knowledge is more
entertaining and striking. Not only so, but the bold guesses and
fanciful reasonings of men unchecked by doubt or fear of failure are
often presented as the dictates of Common Sense;—as the
plain, unsophisticated, unforced reason of man, acting according to no
artificial rules, but following its own natural course. Such Common
Sense, while it 490
complacently plumes itself on its clear-sightedness in rejecting
arbitrary systems of others, is no less arbitrary in its own
arguments, and often no less fanciful in its inventions, than those
whom it condemns.
We cannot take a better representative of the Common Sense of the
ancient Greeks than Socrates: and we find that his Common Sense,
judging with such admirable sagacity and acuteness respecting moral
and practical matters, offered, when he applied it to physical
questions, examples of the unconscious assumptions and fanciful
reasonings which, as we have said, Common Sense on such subjects
commonly involves.
Socrates, Xenophon tells us (Memorabilia, iv. 7),
recommended his friends not to study astronomy, so as to pursue it
into scientific details. This was practical advice: but he proceeded
further to speak of the palpable mistakes made by those who had
carried such studies farthest. Anaxagoras, for instance, he said, held
that the Sun was a Fire:—he did not consider that men can look
at a fire, but they cannot look at the Sun; they become dark by the
Sun shining upon them, but not so by the fire. He did not consider
that no plants can grow well except they have sunshine, but if they
are exposed to the fire they are spoiled. Again, when he said that the
Sun was a stone red-hot, he did not consider that a stone heated by
the fire is not luminous, and soon cools, but the Sun is always
luminous and always hot.
We may easily conceive how a disciple of Anaxagoras would reply to
these arguments. He would say, for example, as we should probably say
at present, that if there were a mass of matter so large and so hot as
Anaxagoras supposed the Sun to be, its light might be as great and its
heat as permanent as the heat and light of the Sun are, as yet, known
to be. In this case the arguments of Socrates are at any rate no
better than the doctrine of Anaxagoras.


BOOK I.

THE GREEK SCHOOL PHILOSOPHY.
</div></body></text></TEI>