<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="20">

NOTE TO CHAPTER X.


I have in the last ten chapters described Space, Time, and
Number by various expressions, all intended to point out
their office as exemplifying the Ideal Element of human
knowledge. I have called them Fundamental Ideas;
Forms of Perception; Forms of Intuition; and
perhaps other names. I might add yet other phrases. I might
say that the properties of Space, Time, and Number are
Laws of the Mind’s Activity in apprehending what is.
For the mind cannot apprehend any thing or event except
conformably to the properties of space, time, and number. It
is not only that it does not, but it can not: and this
impossibility shows that the law is a law of the mind, and
not of objects extraneous to the mind.
It is usual for some of those who reject the doctrines here
presented to say that the axioms of geometry, and of other
sciences, are obtained by Induction from facts constantly
presented by experience. But I do not see how Induction can
prove that a proposition must be true. The only
intelligible usage of the word Induction appears to
me to be, that in which it is applied to a proposition
which, being separable from the facts in our apprehension,
and being compared with them, is seen to agree with them.
But in the cases now spoken of, the proposition is not
separable from the facts. We cannot infer by induction that
two straight lines cannot inclose a space, because we cannot
contemplate special cases of two lines inclosing a space, in
which it remains to be determined whether or not the
proposition, that both are straight, is true.
I do not deny that the activity of the mind by which it
perceives objects and events as related according to the
laws of space, time, and number, is awakened and developed
by being constantly exercised; and that we cannot imagine a
stage of human existence in which the powers have not been
awakened and 146 developed by such exercise. In this way,
experience and observation are necessary conditions and
prerequisites of our apprehension of geometrical (and other)
axioms. We cannot see the truth of these axioms without some
experience, because we cannot see any thing, or be human
beings, without some experience. This might be expressed by
saying that such truths are acquired necessarily in the
course of all experience; but I think it is very
undesirable to apply, to such a case, the word
Induction, of which it is so important to us to keep
the scientific meaning free from confusion. Induction cannot
give demonstrative proofs, as I have already stated in Book
1. C. i. sect. 3, and therefore cannot be the ground of
necessary truths.
Another expression which may be used to describe the
Fundamental Ideas here spoken of is suggested by the
language of a very profound and acute Review of the former
edition. The Reviewer holds that we pass from special
experiences to universal truths in virtue of ‘the inductive
propensity—the irresistible impulse of the mind to
generalize ad infinitum.’ I have already given
reasons why I cannot adopt the former expression; but I do
not see why space, time, number, cause, and the rest, may
not be termed different forms of the impulse of
the mind to generalize. But if we put together all the
Fundamental Ideas as results of the Generalizing Impulse, we
must still separate them as different modes of action of
that Impulse, showing themselves in various characteristic
ways in the axioms and modes of reasoning which belong to
different sciences. The Generalizing Impulse in one case
proceeds according to the Idea of Space; in another,
according to the Idea of Mechanical Cause; and so in other
subjects.</div></body></text></TEI>