<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Sketch of the Analytical Engine with Notes by the Translator</title><author>Menabrea, Luigi; Lovelace, Ada</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1843</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="7">
NOTE E.—Page 19.
[Pg 46]
This example has evidently been chosen on account of its brevity and
simplicity, with a view merely to explain the manner in which
the engine would proceed in the case of an analytical calculation
containing variables, rather than to illustrate the extent of its
powers to solve cases of a difficult and complex nature. The equations
of page 14 are in fact a more complicated problem than the present one.
We have not subjoined any diagram of its development for this new
example, as we did for the former one, because this is unnecessary
after the full application already made of those diagrams to the
illustration of M. Menabrea’s excellent tables.
It may be remarked that a slight discrepancy exists between the formulæ

given in the Memoir as the data for calculation, and the
results of the calculation as developed in the last division of
the table which accompanies it. To agree perfectly with this latter,
the data should have been given as

The following is a more complicated example of the manner in which the
engine would compute a trigonometrical function containing variables.
To multiply

Let the resulting products be represented under the general form


This trigonometrical series is not only in itself very appropriate
for illustrating the processes of the engine, but is likewise of much
practical interest from its frequent use in astronomical computations.
Before proceeding further with it, we shall point out that there are
three very distinct classes of ways in which it may be desired to
deduce numerical values from any analytical formula.
First. We may wish to find the collective, numerical value of the
whole formula, without any reference to the quantities of
which that formula is a function, or to the particular mode of their
combination and distribution, of which the formula is the result and
representative. Values of this kind are of a strictly arithmetical
nature in the most limited sense of the term, and retain no trace
whatever of the processes through which they have been deduced. In
fact, any one such numerical value may have been attained from an
infinite variety of data, or of problems. The values for 
and  in the two equations (see Note D.), come under this class of
numerical results.
Secondly. We may propose to compute the collective numerical value of
each term of a formula, or of a series, and to keep these results
[Pg 47]
separate. The engine must in such a case appropriate as many columns to
results as there are terms to compute.
Thirdly. It may be desired to compute the numerical value of various
subdivisions of each term, and to keep all these results
separate. It may be required, for instance, to compute each coefficient
separately from its variable, in which particular case the engine must
appropriate two result-columns to every term that contains
both a variable and coefficient.
There are many ways in which it may be desired in special cases to
distribute and keep separate the numerical values of different parts of
an algebraical formula; and the power of effecting such distributions
to any extent is essential to the algebraical character of
the Analytical Engine. Many persons who are not conversant with
mathematical studies, imagine that because the business of the engine
is to give its results in numerical notation, the nature
of its processes must consequently be arithmetical and
numerical, rather than algebraical and analytical.
This is an error. The engine can arrange and combine its numerical
quantities exactly as if they were letters or any other
general symbols; and in fact it might bring out its results in
algebraical notation, were provisions made accordingly. It might
develope three sets of results simultaneously, viz. symbolic
results (as already alluded to in Notes A. and B.); numerical
results (its chief and primary object); and algebraical results
in literal notation, This latter however has not been deemed
a necessary or desirable addition to its powers, partly because the
necessary arrangements for effecting it would increase the complexity
and extent of the mechanism to a degree that would not be commensurate
with the advantages, where the main object of the invention is to
translate into numerical language general formulæ of analysis already
known to us, or whose laws of formation are known to us. But it would
be a mistake to suppose that because its results are given
in the notation of a more restricted science, its processes
are therefore restricted to those of that science. The object of the
engine is in fact to give the utmost practical efficiency to the
resources of numerical interpretations of the higher science of
analysis, while it uses the processes and combinations of this latter.
To return to the trigonometrical series. We shall only consider
the four first terms of the factor
(),
since this will be sufficient to show the method. We propose to
obtain separately the numerical value of each coefficient
, , &c. of (1.). The direct
multiplication of the two factors gives

a result which would stand thus on the engine:—






























[Pg 48]






























()
()
()



The variable belonging to each coefficient is written below it,
as we have done in the diagram, by way of memorandum. The only
further reduction which is at first apparently possible in the
preceding result, would be the addition of  to
 (in which case  should
be effaced from ). The whole operations from the
beginning would then be—


First Series of
Operations.
Second Series of
Operations.
Third Series, which contains
only one (final) operation.





















We do not enter into the same detail of every step of the
processes as in the examples of Notes D. and G., thinking it
unnecessary and tedious to do so. The reader will remember the meaning
and use of the upper and lower indices, &c., as before explained.
To proceed: we know that

Consequently, a slight examination of the second line of (2.) will show
that by making the proper substitutions, (2.) will become








































These coefficients should respectively appear on

We shall perceive, if we inspect the particular arrangement of the
results in (2.) on the Result-columns as represented in the diagram,
that, in order to effect this transformation, each successive
coefficient upon , , &c.
(beginning with ), must through means of proper
cards be divided by two[25]; and that one of the halves thus[Pg 49] obtained
must be added to the coefficient on the Variable which precedes
it by ten columns, and the other half to the coefficient on the
Variable which precedes it by twelve columns; ,
, &c. themselves becoming zeros during the process.
This series of operations may be thus expressed:—
Fourth Series.[26]



The calculation of the coefficients , ,
&c. of (1.), would now be completed, and they would stand ranged in
order on , , &c. It will be
remarked, that from the moment the fourth series of operations is
ordered, the Variables , ,
&c. cease to be Result-Variables, and become mere
Working-Variables.
The substitution made by the engine of the processes in the second
side of (3.) for those in the first side, is an excellent illustration
of the manner in which we may arbitrarily order it to substitute any
function, number, or process, at pleasure, for any other function,
number or process, on the occurrence of a specified contingency.
We will now suppose that we desire to go a step further, and to obtain
the numerical value of each complete term of the product (1.),
that is of each coefficient and variable united, which for the
()th term would be .
We must for this purpose place the variables themselves on another
set of columns, , , &c., and
then order their successive multiplication by ,
, &c., each for each. There would thus be a
final series of operations as follows:—
Fifth and Final Series of Operations.

(N.B. that  being intended to receive the
coefficient on  which has no variable, will
only have  inscribed on it, preparatory to
commencing the fifth series of operations.)
From the moment that the fifth and final series of operations is
ordered, the Variables , , &c.
then in their turn cease to be Result-Variables and become mere
[Pg 50]
Working-Variables; , , &c.
being now the recipients of the ultimate results.
We should observe, that if the variables , ,
, &c. are furnished, they would be placed directly upon
, , &c., like any other data.
If not, a separate computation might be entered upon in a separate
part of the engine, in order to calculate them, and place them on
, &c.
We have now explained how the engine might compute (1.) in the most
direct manner, supposing we knew nothing about the general term
of the resulting series. But the engine would in reality set to work
very differently, whenever (as in this case) we do know the law
for the general term.
The two first terms of (1.) are

and the general term for all after these is

which is the coefficient of the ( term. The engine would
calculate the two first terms by means of a separate set of suitable
Operation-cards, and would then need another set for the third term;
which last set of Operation-cards would calculate all the succeeding
terms ad infinitum; merely requiring certain new Variable-cards
for each term to direct the operations to act on the proper columns.
The following would be the successive sets of operations for computing
the coefficients of  terms—

Or we might represent them as follows, according to the numerical order
of the operations:—

The brackets, it should be understood, point out the relation in
which the operations may be grouped, while the comma marks
succession. The symbol + might be used for this latter purpose,
but this would be liable to produce confusion, as + is also necessarily
used to represent one class of the actual operations which are the
subject of that succession. In accordance with this meaning attached to
the comma, care must be taken when any one group of operations recurs
more than once, as is represented above by  (11 ... 15), not to
insert a comma after the number or letter prefixed to that group.
,(11 ... 15) would stand for an operation  followed
by the group of operations (11 ... 15); instead of denoting the
number of groups which are to follow each other.
Wherever a general term exists, there will be a recurring
group of operations, as in the above example. Both for brevity and
for distinctness, a recurring group is called a cycle.
A cycle of operations, then, must be understood to signify any
set of operations which is repeated more than once.
It is equally a cycle, whether it be repeated twice
only, or an indefinite number of times; for it is the fact of a
repetition occurring at all that constitutes it such. In many
cases of analysis there is a recurring group of one or more
[Pg 51]
cycles; that is, a cycle of a cycle, or a cycle of
cycles. For instance: suppose we wish to divide a series by a
series,

it being required that the result shall be developed, like the dividend
and the divisor, in successive powers of . A little consideration
of (1.), and of the steps through which algebraical division is
effected, will show that (if the denominator be supposed to consist
of  terms) the first partial quotient will be completed by the
following operations:—

that the second partial quotient will be completed by an exactly
similar set of operations, which acts on the remainder obtained by
the first set, instead of on the original dividend. The whole of the
processes therefore that have been gone through, by the time the
second partial quotient has been obtained, will be,—

which is a cycle that includes a cycle, or a cycle of the second order.
The operations for the complete division, supposing we propose
to obtain  terms of the series constituting the quotient, will
be,—

It is of course to be remembered that the process of algebraical
division in reality continues ad infinitum, except in the few
exceptional cases which admit of an exact quotient being obtained. The
number  in the formula (4.), is always that of the number of terms
we propose to ourselves to obtain; and the th partial quotient is
the coefficient of the ()th power of .
There are some cases which entail cycles of cycles of cycles, to
an indefinite extent. Such cases are usually very complicated, and they
are of extreme interest when considered with reference to the engine.
The algebraical development in a series, of the th function of any
given function, is of this nature. Let it be proposed to obtain the
th function of

We should premise that we suppose the reader to understand what is
meant by an th function. We suppose him likewise to comprehend
distinctly the difference between developing an th
function algebraically, and merely calculating an th
function arithmetically. If he does not, the following will
be by no means very intelligible; but we have not space to give any
preliminary explanations. To proceed: the law, according to which the
successive functions of (5.) are to be developed, must of course first
be fixed on. This law may be of very various kinds. We may propose to
obtain our results in successive powers of , in which case
the general form would be

[Pg 52]
or in successive powers of  itself, the index of the function we
are ultimately to obtain, in which case the general form would be

and  would only enter in the coefficients. Again, other functions
of  or of  instead of powers, might be selected. It
might be in addition proposed, that the coefficients themselves should
be arranged according to given functions of a certain quantity. Another
mode would be to make equations arbitrarily amongst the coefficients
only, in which case the several functions, according to either of
which it might be possible to develop the th function of (5.),
would have to be determined from the combined consideration of these
equations and of (5.) itself.
The algebraical nature of the engine (so strongly insisted
on in a previous part of this Note) would enable it to follow out
any of these various modes indifferently; just as we recently showed
that it can distribute and separate the numerical results of any one
prescribed series of processes, in a perfectly arbitrary manner. Were
it otherwise, the engine could merely compute the arithmetical
th function, a result which, like any other purely
arithmetical results, would be simply a collective number, bearing no
traces of the data or the processes which had led to it.
Secondly, the law of development for the th function being
selected, the next step would obviously be to develope (5.) itself,
according to this law. This result would be the first function, and
would be obtained by a determinate series of processes. These in
most cases would include amongst them one or more cycles of
operations.
The third step (which would consist of the various processes necessary
for effecting the actual substitution of the series constituting
the first function, for the variable itself) might
proceed in either of two ways. It might make the substitution either
wherever  occurs in the original (5.), or it might similarly make
it wherever  occurs in the first function itself which is the
equivalent of (5.). In some cases the former mode might be best, and in
others the latter.
Whichever is adopted, it must be understood that the result is to
appear arranged in a series following the law originally prescribed
for the development of the th function. This result constitutes
the second function; with which we are to proceed exactly as we did
with the first function, in order to obtain the third function; and
so on,  times, to obtain the th function. We easily
perceive that since every successive function is arranged in a series
following the same law, there would (after the first
function is obtained) be a cycle, of a cycle, of a cycle,
&c. of operations[27], one, two, three, up to  times, in order
to get the th function. We say, after the first function is
obtained, because (for reasons on which we cannot here enter) the
first function might in many cases be developed through a set
[Pg 53]
of processes peculiar to itself, and not recurring for the remaining
functions.
We have given but a very slight sketch, of the principal general
steps which would be requisite for obtaining an th function of
such a formula as (5.). The question is so exceedingly complicated,
that perhaps few persons can be expected to follow, to their own
satisfaction, so brief and general a statement as we are here
restricted to on this subject. Still it is a very important case as
regards the engine, and suggests ideas peculiar to itself, which we
should regret to pass wholly without allusion. Nothing could be more
interesting than to follow out, in every detail, the solution by the
engine of such a case as the above; but the time, space and labour this
would necessitate, could only suit a very extensive work.
To return to the subject of cycles of operations: some of the
notation of the integral calculus lends itself very aptly to express
them: (2.) might be thus written:—

where  stands for the variable; ( for the function of
the variable, that is, for ; and the limits are from 1 to
, or from 0 to , each increment being equal to unity.
Similarly, (4.) would be,—

the limits of  being from 1 to , or from 0 to ,

Perhaps it may be thought that this notation is merely a circuitous way
of expressing what was more simply and as effectually expressed before;
and, in the above example, there may be some truth in this. But there
is another description of cycles which can only effectually be
expressed, in a condensed form, by the preceding notation. We shall
call them varying cycles. They are of frequent occurrence, and
include successive cycles of operations of the following nature:—

where each cycle contains the same group of operations, but in which
the number of repetitions of the group varies according to a fixed
rate, with every cycle. (9.) can be well expressed as follows:—

Independent of the intrinsic advantages which we thus perceive to
result in certain cases from this use of the notation of the integral
calculus, there are likewise considerations which make it interesting,
from the connections and relations involved in this new application.
It has been observed in some of the former Notes, that the processes
used in analysis form a logical system of much higher generality
than the applications to number merely. Thus, when we read over any
algebraical formula, considering it exclusively with reference to the
processes of the engine, and putting aside for the moment its abstract
signification as to the relations of quantity, the symbols +, x, &c.,
in reality represent (as their immediate and proximate effect, when the
formula is applied to the engine) that a certain prism which is a part
[Pg 54]
of the mechanism (see Note C.), turns a new face, and thus presents
a new card to act on the bundles of levers of the engine; the new
card being perforated with holes, which are arranged according to the
peculiarities of the operation of addition, or of multiplication, &c.
Again, the numbers in the preceding formula (8.), each of them
really represents one of these very pieces of card that are hung over
the prism.
Now in the use made in the formulæ (7.). (8.) and (10.), of the
notation of the integral calculus, we have glimpses of a similar new
application of the language of the higher mathematics. ,
in reality, here indicates that when a certain number of cards have
acted in succession, the prism over which they revolve must rotate
backwards, so as to bring those cards into their former position;
and the limits 1 to , 1 to  &c., regulate how often this
backward rotation is to be repeated.
A.A.L.</div></body></text></TEI>