<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="60">CHAPTER VI.
Problem of Different Modes of Vibration of Bodies in
General.
NOT only the objects of which
we have spoken hitherto, strings and pipes, but almost all bodies are
capable of vibration. Bells, gongs, tuning-forks, are examples of
solid bodies; drums and tambourines, of membranes; if we run a wet
finger along the edge of a glass goblet, we throw the fluid which it
contains into a regular vibration; and the various character which
sounds possess according to the room in which they are uttered, shows
that large masses of air have peculiar modes of vibration. Vibrations
are generally accompanied by sound, and they may, therefore, be
considered as acoustical phenomena, especially as the sound is one of
the most decisive facts in indicating the mode of vibration. Moreover,
every body of this kind can vibrate in many different ways, the
vibrating segments being divided by Nodal Lines and Surfaces of
various form and number. The mode of vibration, selected by the body
in each case, is determined by the way in which it is held, the way in
which it is set in vibration, and the like circumstances.
The general problem of such vibrations includes the discovery and
classification of the phenomena; the detection of their formal laws;
and, finally, the explanation of these on mechanical principles. We
must speak very briefly of what has been done in these ways. The facts
which indicate Nodal Lines had been remarked by Galileo, on the
sounding board of a musical instrument; and Hooke had proposed to
observe the vibrations of a bell by strewing flour upon it. But it was
Chladni, a German philosopher, who enriched acoustics with the
discovery of the vast variety of symmetrical figures of Nodal Lines,
which are exhibited on plates of regular forms, when 42 made to sound. His
first investigations on this subject, Entdeckungen über die Theorie
des Klangs, were published 1787; and in 1802 and 1817 he added
other discoveries. In these works he not only related a vast number of
new and curious facts, but in some measure reduced some of them to
order and law. For instance, he has traced all the vibrations of
square plates to a resemblance with those forms of vibration in which
Nodal Lines are parallel to one side of the square, and those in which
they are parallel to another side; and he has established a notation
for the modes of vibration founded on this classification. Thus,
5–2 denotes a form in which there are five nodal lines parallel
to one side, and two to another; or a form which can be traced to a
disfigurement of such a standard type. Savart pursued this subject
still further; and traced, by actual observation, the forms of the
Nodal Surfaces which divide solid bodies, and masses of air, when in a
state of vibration.
The dependence of such vibrations upon their physical cause,
namely, the elasticity of the substance, we can conceive in a general
way; but the mathematical theory of such cases is, as might be
supposed, very difficult, even if we confine ourselves to the obvious
question of the mechanical possibility of these different modes of
vibration, and leave out of consideration their dependence upon the
mode of excitation. The transverse vibrations of elastic rods, plates,
and rings, had been considered by Euler in 1779; but his calculation
concerning plates had foretold only a small part of the curious
phenomena observed by Chladni;37 and the several
notes which, according to his calculation, the same ring ought to
give, were not in agreement with experiment.38 Indeed,
researches of this kind, as conducted by Euler, and other authors,39 rather were, and were intended for,
examples of analytical skill, than explanations of physical facts.
James Bernoulli, after the publication of Chladni’s experiments in
1787, attempted to solve the problem for plates, by treating a plate
as a collection of fibres; but, as Chladni observes, the justice of
this mode of conception is disproved, by the disagreement of the
results with experiment.
37 Fischer, vi. 587.
38 Ib. vi. 596.
39 See Chladni, p. 474.
The Institute of France, which had approved of Chladni’s labours,
proposed, in 1809, the problem now before us as a prize-question:40—“To give the mathematical theory
of the vibrations of elastic 43 surfaces, and to compare it with
experiment.” Only one memoir was sent in as a candidate for the prize;
and this was not crowned, though honorable mention was made of it.41 The formulæ of James Bernoulli were,
according to M. Poisson’s statement, defective, in consequence of his
not taking into account the normal force which acts at the exterior
boundary of the plate.42 The author of the anonymous memoir
corrected this error, and calculated the note corresponding to various
figures of the nodal lines; and he found an agreement with experiment
sufficient to justify his theory. He had not, however, proved his
fundamental equation, which M. Poisson demonstrated in a Memoir, read
in 1814.43 At a more recent period also, MM.
Poisson and Cauchy (as well as a lady, Mlle. Sophie Germain) have
applied to this problem the artifices of the most improved analysis.
M. Poisson44 determined the relation of the notes
given by the longitudinal and the transverse vibrations of a rod; and
solved the problem of vibrating circular plates when the nodal lines
are concentric circles. In both these cases, the numerical agreement
of his results with experience, seemed to confirm the justice of his
fundamental views.45 He proceeds upon the hypothesis, that
elastic bodies are composed of separate particles held together by the
attractive forces which they exert upon each other, and distended by
the repulsive force of heat. M. Cauchy46 has also
calculated the transverse, longitudinal, and rotatory vibrations of
elastic rods, and has obtained results agreeing closely with
experiment through a considerable list of comparisons. The combined
authority of two profound analysts, as MM. Poisson and Cauchy are,
leads us to believe that, for the simpler cases of the vibrations of
elastic bodies, Mathematics has executed her task; but most of the
more complex cases remain as yet unsubdued.
40 See Chladni, p. 357.
41 Poisson’s Mém. in Ac. Sc.
1812, p. 169.
42 Ib. p. 220.
43 Ib. 1812, p. 2.
44 Ib. t. viii. 1829.
45 An. Chim. tom. xxxvi. 1827,
p. 90.
46 Exercices de Mathématique,
iii. and iv.
The two brothers, Ernest and William Weber, made many curious
observations on undulations, which are contained in their
Wellenlehre, (Doctrine of Waves,) published at Leipsig in 1825.
They were led to suppose, (as Young had suggested at an earlier
period,) that Chladni’s figures of nodal lines in plates were to be
accounted for by the superposition of undulations.47 Mr. Wheatstone48 has undertaken to account for Chladni’s
figures of vibrating square plates by this 44 superposition of two or
more simple and obviously allowable modes of nodal division, which
have the same time of vibration. He assumes, for this purpose, certain
“primary figures,” containing only parallel nodal lines; and
by combining these, first in twos, and then in fours, he obtains most
of Chladni’s observed figures, and accounts for their transitions and
deviations from regularity.
47 Wellenlehre, p. 474.
48 Phil. Trans. 1833, p.
593.
The principle of the superposition of vibrations is so solidly
established as a mechanical truth, that we may consider an acoustical
problem as satisfactorily disposed of when it is reduced to that
principle, as well as when it is solved by analytical mechanics: but
at the same time we may recollect, that the right application and
limitation of this law involves no small difficulty; and in this case,
as in all advances in physical science, we cannot but wish to have the
new ground which has been gained, gone over by some other person in
some other manner; and thus secured to us as a permanent
possession.
Savart’s Laws.—In what has preceded, the vibrations of
bodies have been referred to certain general classes, the separation
of which was suggested by observation; for example, the
transverse, longitudinal, and rotatory,49 vibrations of rods. The transverse
vibrations, in which the rod goes backwards and forwards across the
line of its length, were the only ones noticed by the earlier
acousticians: the others were principally brought into notice by
Chladni. As we have already seen in the preceding pages, this
classification serves to express important laws; as, for instance, a
law obtained by M. Poisson which gives the relation of the notes
produced by the transverse and longitudinal vibrations of a rod. But
this distinction was employed by M. Felix Savart to express laws of a
more general kind; and then, as often happens in the progress of
science, by pursuing these laws to a higher point of generality, the
distinction again seemed to vanish. A very few words will explain
these steps.
49 Vibrations tournantes.
It was long ago known that vibrations may be communicated by
contact. The distinction of transverse and longitudinal vibrations
being established, Savart found that if one rod touched another
perpendicularly, the longitudinal vibrations of the first occasion
transverse vibrations in the second, and vice versâ. This is
the more remarkable, since the two sets of vibrations are not equal in
rapidity, and therefore cannot sympathize in any obvious manner.50 Savart found himself 45 able to generalize this
proposition, and to assert that in any combination of rods, strings,
and laminæ, at right angles to each other, the longitudinal and
transverse vibrations affect respectively the rods in the one and
other direction,51 so that when the horizontal rods, for
example, vibrate in the one way, the vertical rods vibrate in the
other.
50 An. Chim. 1819, tom. xiv. p.
138.
51 An. Chim. p. 152.
This law was thus expressed in terms of that classification of
vibrations of which we have spoken. Yet we easily see that we may
express it in a more general manner, without referring to that
classification, by saying, that vibrations are communicated so as
always to be parallel to their original direction. And by following it
out in this shape by means of experiment, M. Savart was led, a short
time afterwards, to deny that there is any essential distinction in
these different kinds of vibration. “We are thus led,” he says52 in 1822, “to consider normal
[transverse] vibrations as only one circumstance in a more general
motion common to all bodies, analogous to tangential
[longitudinal and rotatory] vibrations; that is, as produced by small
molecular oscillations, and differently modified according to
the direction which it affects, relatively to the dimensions of the
vibrating body.”
52 Ib. t. xxv. p. 33.
These “inductions,” as he properly calls them, are supported by a
great mass of ingenious experiments; and may be considered as well
established, when they are limited to molecular oscillations,
employing this phrase in the sense in which it is understood in the
above statement; and also when they are confined to bodies in which
the play of elasticity is not interrupted by parts more rigid than the
rest, as the sound-post of a violin.53 And before I
quit the subject, I may notice a consequence which M. Savart has
deduced from his views, and which, at first sight, appears to overturn
most of the earlier doctrines respecting vibrating bodies. It was
formerly held that tense strings and elastic rods could vibrate only
in a determinate series of modes of division, with no intermediate
steps. But M. Savart maintains,54 on the contrary,
that they produce sounds which are gradually transformed into one
another, by indefinite intermediate degrees. The reader may naturally
ask, what is the solution of this apparent 46 contradiction between the earliest and the
latest discoveries in acoustics. And the answer must be, that these
intermediate modes of vibration are complex in their nature, and
difficult to produce; and that those which were formerly believed to
be the only possible vibrating conditions, are so eminent above all
the rest by their features, their simplicity, and their facility, that
we may still, for common purposes, consider them as a class apart;
although for the sake of reaching a general theorem, we may associate
them with the general mass of cases of molecular vibrations. And thus
we have no exception here, as we can have none in any case, to our
maxim, that what formed part of the early discoveries of science,
forms part of its latest systems.
53 For the suggestion of the necessity
of this limitation I am indebted to Mr. Willis.
54 An. Chim. 1826, t. xxxii. p.
384.
We have thus surveyed the progress of the science of sound up to
recent times, with respect both to the discovery of laws of phenomena,
and the reduction of these to their mechanical causes. The former
branch of the science has necessarily been inductively pursued; and
therefore has been more peculiarly the subject of our attention. And
this consideration will explain why we have not dwelt more upon the
deductive labors of the great analysts who have treated of this
problem.
To those who are acquainted with the high and deserved fame which
the labors of D’Alembert, Euler, Lagrange, and others, upon this
subject, enjoy among mathematicians, it may seem as if we had not
given them their due prominence in our sketch. But it is to be
recollected here, as we have already observed in the case of
hydrodynamics, that even when the general principles are uncontested,
mere mathematical deductions from them do not belong to the history of
physical science, except when they point out laws which are
intermediate between the general principle and the individual facts,
and which observation may confirm.
The business of constructing any science may be figured as the task
of forming a road on which our reason can travel through a certain
province of the external world. We have to throw a bridge which may
lead from the chambers of our own thoughts, from our speculative
principles, to the distant shore of material facts. But in all cases
the abyss is too wide to be crossed, except we can find some
intermediate points on which the piers of our structure may rest. Mere
facts, without connexion or law, are only the rude stones hewn from
the opposite bank, of which our arches may, at some time, be built.
But mere hypothetical mathematical calculations are only plans of
projected structures; and those plans which exhibit only one vast
47 and single arch,
or which suppose no support but that which our own position supplies,
will assuredly never become realities. We must have a firm basis of
intermediate generalizations in order to frame a continuous and stable
edifice.
In the subject before us, we have no want of such points of
intermediate support, although they are in many instances irregularly
distributed and obscurely seen. The number of observed laws and
relations of the phenomena of sound, is already very great; and though
the time may be distant, there seems to be no reason to despair of one
day uniting them by clear ideas of mechanical causation, and thus of
making acoustics a perfect secondary mechanical science.
The historical sketch just given includes only such parts of
acoustics as have been in some degree reduced to general laws and
physical causes; and thus excludes much that is usually treated of
under that head. Moreover, many of the numerical calculations
connected with sound belong to its agreeable effect upon the ear; as
the properties of the various systems of Temperament. These are
parts of Theoretical Music, not of Acoustics; of the Philosophy of the
Fine Arts, not of Physical Science; and may be referred to in a future
portion of this work, so far as they bear upon our object.
The science of Acoustics may, however, properly consider other
differences of sound than those of acute and grave,—for
instance, the articulate differences, or those by which the
various letters are formed. Some progress has been made in reducing
this part of the subject to general rules; for though Kempelen’s
“talking machine” was only a work of art, Mr. Willis’s machine,55 which exhibits the relation among the
vowels, gives us a law such as forms a step in science. We may,
however, consider this instrument as a phthongometer, or
measure of vowel quality; and in that point of view we shall have to
refer to it again when we come to speak of such measures.
55 On the Vowel Sounds, and on Reed
Organ-pipes. Camb. Trans. iii. 237.
~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~


BOOK IX.

SECONDARY MECHANICAL SCIENCES.
(CONTINUED)

HISTORY OF OPTICS,
FORMAL AND PHYSICAL.

Ω Διὸς ὑψιμέλαθρον ἔχων κράτος αἰὲν ἀτειρὲς
Ἄστρων, Ἠελίου τε, Σεληναίης τε μέρισμα
Πανδαμάτωρ, πυρίπνου, πᾶσιν ζωοῖσιν ἔναυσμα
Ὑψιφάνης ἌIϴΗΡ, κόσμου στοιχεῖον, ἄριστον·
Ἀγλαὸν ὦ βλάστημα, σελασφόρον, ἀστεροφεγγὲς
Κικλήσκων λίτομαι σε, κεκραμένον εὔδιον
εἶναι.
Orpheus.
Hymn.  

O thou who fillest the palaces of Jove;
Who flowest round moon, and sun, and stars
above;
Pervading, bright, life-giving element,
Supernal Ether, fair and
excellent;
Fountain of hope and joy, of light and day,
We own at length thy tranquil, steady sway.
</div></body></text></TEI>