<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="50">

CHAPTER IV.
Application of the Idea of Substance in Chemistry.


1. A Body is Equal to the Sum of its Elements.—From the earliest periods of chemistry the balance has
been familiarly used to determine the proportions of
the ingredients and of the compound; and soon after
the middle of the last century, this practice was so
studiously followed, that Wenzel and Richter were
thereby led to the doctrine of Definite Proportions.
But yet the full value and significance of the balance,
as an indispensable instrument in chemical researches,
was not understood till the gaseous, as well as solid
and fluid ingredients were taken into the account.
When this was done, it was found that the principle,
that the whole is equal to the sum of its parts, of
which, as we have seen, the necessary truth, in such
cases, flows from the idea of substance, could be applied
in the most rigorous manner. And conversely, it was
found that by the use of the balance, the chemist
could decide, in doubtful cases, which was a whole, and
which were parts.
For chemistry considers all the changes which belong
to her province as compositions and decompositions of
elements; but still the question may occur, whether an
observed change be the one or the other. How can we
distinguish whether the process which we contemplate
be composition or decomposition?—whether the new
body be formed by addition of a new, or subtraction of
an old element? Again; in the case of decomposition,
we may inquire, What are the ultimate limits of our
analysis? If we decompound bodies into others more
and more simple, how far can we carry this succession 40 of processes? How far can we proceed in the road of
analysis? And in our actual course, what evidence
have we that our progress, as far as it has gone, has
carried us from the more complex to the more simple?
To this we reply, that the criterion which enables
us to distinguish, decidedly and finally, whether our
process have been a mere analysis of the proposed body
into its ingredients, or a synthesis of some of them with
some new element, is the principle stated above, that
the weight of the whole is equal to the weight of
all the parts. And no process of chemical analysis or
synthesis can be considered complete till it has been
verified by this fact;—by finding that the weight of the
compound is the weight of its supposed ingredients; or,
that if there be an element which we think we have
detached from the whole, its loss is betrayed by a corresponding diminution of weight.
I have already noticed what an important part this
principle has played in the great chemical controversy
which ended in the establishment of the oxygen theory.
The calcination of a metal was decided to be the union
of oxygen with the metal, and not the separation of
phlogiston from it, because it was found that in the process of calcination, the weight of the metal increased,
and increased exactly as much as the weight of ambient
air diminished. When oxygen and hydrogen were exploded together, and a small quantity of water was
produced, it was held that this was really a synthesis
of water, because, when very great care was taken
with the process, the weight of the water which resulted
was equal to the weight of the gases which disappeared.
2. Lavoisier.—It was when gases came to be considered as entering largely into the composition of
liquid and solid bodies, that extreme accuracy in weighing was seen to be so necessary to the true understanding of chemical processes. It was in this manner
discovered by Lavoisier and his contemporaries that
oxygen constitutes a large ingredient of calcined metals,
of acids, and of water. A countryman of Lavoisier30 41 has not only given most just praise to that great philosopher for having constantly tested all his processes
by a careful and skilful use of the balance, but has also
claimed for him the merit of having introduced the
maxim, that in chemical operations nothing is created
and nothing lost. But I think it is impossible to
deny that this maxim is assumed in all the attempts at
analysis made by his contemporaries, as well as by him.
This maxim is indeed included in any clear notion of
analysis: it could not be the result of the researches of
any one chemist, but was the governing principle of
the reasonings of all. Lavoisier, however, employed
this principle with peculiar assiduity and skill. In
applying it, he does not confine himself to mere additions and subtractions of the quantities of ingredients;
but often obtains his results by more complex processes. In one of his investigations he says, ‘I may
consider the ingredients which are brought together,
and the result which is obtained as an algebraical equation; and if I successively suppose each of the quantities of this equation to be unknown, I can obtain its
value from the rest: and thus I can rectify the experiment by the calculation, and the calculation by the experiment. I have often taken advantage of this
method, in order to correct the first results of my experiments, and to direct me in repeating them with
proper precautions.’</div></body></text></TEI>