<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 165, folios 98-104</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 165, folios 98-104.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1838">10 March [1838]</date>
          <note type="place">Ockham</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 165, folios 98-104</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_165_folios_98-104.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Ockham Saturday 1/2 pst 3 10th March</p>
      <p>My Dearest W. I have just been extremely annoyed with a very inexcusable negligence of Thyer's. I told him on Wednesday night most particularly to send on the Thursday Morning for the plants to Dr Somerville's. I was very minute in my directions &amp; even settled which man was to go. Of course</p>
      <p>I concluded they had come, &amp; went into the garden today to settle where they should be put.-- Think of my annoyance at finding they had been entirely neglected! Thyer is out, but as soon as he comes in I mean to insist on his making an arrangement at his own expense, for getting a letter of mine sent to Dr S (there being no post to Town today), &amp; having the plants down for Monday.--</p>
      <p>Now I must tell you more about Dr Locock. I am to take this zinc preparation for many weeks to come. He was well satisfied with the first effects of it, which he wished to observe. I am likewise to add tincture of Hops to my nightly glass of ale.-- Good as the riding is for my general health, he has positively prohibited it during from 10 days to a fortnight out of</p>
      <p>every 4 weeks, though he prescribes it for the rest of the time.-- This prohibition is connected with matters you will guess at.-- There appears to be a doubt whether all the have healed since my last confinement, &amp; he thinks some internal applications will be requisite. It is quite clear he says that there is something wrong about the monthly concerns, &amp; that</p>
      <p>it requires a good deal of attention. I am to write to him after this next time, &amp; to write down certain observations respecting what takes place. He is much pleased with the improvement in my appearance, &amp; in many essential points, &amp; says that time will under proper measures &amp; precautions effect the whole that remains to be done.--</p>
      <p>He gave me the whole</p>
      <p>history of the causes of Lady [Storemont's?] death, which are most curious &amp; extraordinary. You shall hear when you return. He entered into some very interesting anatomical details on the subject. There was an examination by Lord Mansfield's orders, to Lord [Storemont's?] great satisfaction.-- Nothing could have saved her.--</p>
      <p>I shall begin a little of the much I have to say about the</p>
      <p>arrangments in St. James' Sqre. First of all, I intend going again in about 10 days or fortnight, for a night or two, as I have much I still wish to settle.-- I have taken on myself to order wardrobe cupboards to be put up in the large nursery. It was essential this should be settled previous to</p>
      <p>measuring for the carpet. I spoke myself to the clerk of the works about it, &amp; took Thyer into counsel too, as to the how &amp; where.-- I proposed its being painted the colour of the walls, but was told this would soil directly, &amp; that of oak was best, to which I agreed. The carpet I selected, after very minute enquiries about their relative merits, was</p>
      <p>the first Kidderminster we saw, which on the whole I think best as well as prettiest.</p>
      <p>The wash-stand for my dressing-room is to be of perfectly white statuary marble, the woodwork of rose-wood, to which I found on enquiring. There is not objection on ground of .--</p>
      <p>We found that any marble but white would agree ill with the chimney-piece</p>
      <p>&amp; that the white would look much the most beautiful.-- My dressing-table is to be what they call a toilette;-- that is white muslin drapery over a colour which will be that of the curtains, whatever I fix on for them.--</p>
      <p>They are to show me drawings for the drapery &amp; looking glass, &amp; meantime to make the common deal table which will frame-work to it, &amp; is</p>
      <p>to fit the window.--</p>
      <p>I went to Minter's, &amp; had the green cut velvet brought to me in St James Sqre, that I might be sure it matched properly on comparing it with the walls &amp; furniture. I found it admirable.-- I am going to make an alteration in your order about my invalid sofa. Instead of a sacking cover quilted</p>
      <p>in, I mean to have leather,-- green leather to match that I have selected for the Louis Quatorze table. This is Hester's suggestion, &amp; I think admirable. You know it wears everlastingly, &amp; if used in a confinement, would then of course have stuff covers over it.--</p>
      <p>I find Minter can alter at triffling expense the only fault in my wheel-chair, by</p>
      <p>adding little leather splash-boards to the arms, which will keep my cloaks from all injury.-- So we must take it to Town by &amp; bye, to have this done.--</p>
      <p>I am afraid you will say I do much better about arranging &amp; ordering, without you than with you, &amp; perhaps I am then less confused &amp; from having no one to depend on.--</p>
      <p>I saw Lord Byron for a short time yesterday. He called not knowing I was there, to see the horse. I was glad of it, having just heard from the Hen of Marianne Coulson's most desperate illness, with influenza fever.-- She has been at death's door, taken ill the very day before they were to have set out for Town to consult Locock about her other ailments. They say she is now just out of danger. I could write you much more.-- Ou Birdie</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
