<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Vestiges of the Natural History of Creation</title><author>Chambers, Robert (1802-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="19">p. 387NOTE
CONCLUSORY.
Thus ends a book, composed in
solitude, and almost without the cognizance of a single human
being, for the sole purpose (or as nearly so as may be) of
improving the knowledge of mankind, and through that medium their
happiness.  For reasons which need not be specified, the
author’s name is retained in its original obscurity, and,
in all probability, will never be generally known.  I do not
expect that any word of praise which the work may elicit shall
ever be responded to by me; or that any word of censure shall
ever be parried or deprecated.  It goes forth to take its
chance of instant oblivion, or of a long and active course of
usefulness in the world.  Neither contingency can be of any
importance to me, beyond the regret or the satisfaction which may
be imparted by my sense of a lost or a realized benefit to my
fellow-creatures.  The book, as far as I am aware, is the
first attempt to connect the natural sciences into a history of
creation.  The idea is a bold one, and there are many
circumstances of time and place to render its boldness more than
usually conspicuous.  But I believe my doctrines to be in
the main true; I believe all truth to be valuable, and its
dissemination a blessing.  At the same time, I hold myself
duly sensible of the common liability to error, but am certain
that no error in this line has the least chance of being allowed
to injure the public mind.  Therefore I publish.  My
views, if correct, will most assuredly stand, and may sooner or
later prove beneficial; if otherwise, they will as surely pass
out of notice without doing any harm.
My sincere desire in the composition of the book was to give
the true view of the history of nature, with as little
disturbance as possible to existing beliefs, whether
philosophical or religious.  I have made little reference to
any doctrines of the latter kind which may be thought
inconsistent with mine, because to do so would have been to enter
upon questions for the settlement of which our knowledge is not
yet ripe.  Let the reconciliation of whatever is true in my
views with whatever is true in other systems come about in the
fulness of calm and careful inquiry.  I cannot but here
remind the reader of what Dr. Wiseman has shewn so strikingly in
his lectures, how different new philosophic doctrines are apt to
appear after we have become somewhat familiar with them. 
Geology at first seems inconsistent with the authority of the
Mosaic record.  A storm of unreasoning indignation rises
against its teachers.  In time, its truths, being found
quite irresistible, are admitted, and mankind continue to regard
the Scriptures with the same respect as before.  So also
with several other sciences.  Now the only objection that
can be made on such ground to this book, is, that it brings
forward some new hypotheses, at first sight, like geology, not in
perfect harmony with that record, and arranges all the rest into
a system which partakes of the same character.  But may not
the sacred text, on a liberal interpretation, or with the benefit
of new light reflected from nature, or derived from learning, be
shewn to be as much in harmony with the novelties of this volume
as it has been with geology and natural philosophy?  What is
there in the laws of organic creation more startling to the
candid theologian than in the Copernican system or the natural
formation of strata?  And if the whole series of facts is
true, why should we shrink from inferences legitimately flowing
from it?  Is it not a wiser course, since reconciliation has
come in so many instances, still to hope for it, still to go on
with our new truths, trusting that they also will in time be
found harmonious with all others?  Thus we avoid the damage
which the very appearance of an opposition to natural truth is
calculated to inflict on any system presumed to require such
support.  Thus we give, as is meet, a respectful reception
to what is revealed through the medium of nature, at the same
time that we fully reserve our reverence for all we have been
accustomed to hold sacred, not one tittle of which it may
ultimately be found necessary to alter.</div></body></text></TEI>