<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="11">CHAPTER II.
Prelude to the Inductive Epoch of
Hipparchus.
WITHOUT pretending that we
have exhausted the consequences of the elementary discoveries which we
have enumerated, we now proceed to consider the nature and
circumstances of the next great discovery which makes an Epoch in the
history of Astronomy; and this we shall find to be the Theory of
Epicycles and Eccentrics. Before, however, we relate the establishment
of this theory, we must, according to the general plan we have marked
out, notice some of the conjectures and attempts by which it was
preceded, and the growing acquaintance with facts, which made the want
of such an explanation felt.
In the steps previously made in astronomical knowledge, no
ingenuity had been required to devise the view which was adopted. The
motions of the stars and sun were most naturally and almost
irresistibly conceived as the results of motion in a revolving sphere;
the indications of position which we obtain from different places on
the earth’s surface, when clearly combined, obviously imply a globular
shape. In these cases, the first conjectures, the supposition of the
simplest form, of the most uniform motion, required no
after-correction. But this manifest simplicity, this easy and obvious
explanation, did not apply to the movement of all the heavenly bodies.
The Planets, the “wandering stars,” could not be so easily understood;
the motion of each, as Cicero says, “undergoing very remarkable
changes in its course, going before and behind, quicker and slower,
appearing in the evening, but gradually lost there, and emerging again
in the morning.”55 A continued attention to these stars
would, however, 139
detect a kind of intricate regularity in their motions, which might
naturally be described as “a dance.” The Chaldeans are stated by
Diodorus56 to have observed assiduously the
risings and settings of the planets, from the top of the temple of
Belus. By doing this, they would find the times in which the forward
and backward movements of Saturn, Jupiter, and Mars recur; and also
the time in which they come round to the same part of the heavens.57 Venus and Mercury never recede far from
the sun, and the intervals which elapse while either of them leaves
its greatest distance from the sun and returns again to the greatest
distance on the same side, would easily be observed.
55 Cic. de Nat. D. lib. ii. p.
450. “Ea quæ Saturni stella dicitur, φαίνωνque a Græcis nominatur, quæ
a terra abest plurimum, xxx fere annis cursum suum conficit; in quo
cursu multa mirabiliter efficiens, tum antecedendo, tum retardando,
tum vespertinis temporibus delitescendo, tum matutinis se rursum
aperiendo, nihil immutat sempiternis sæculorum ætatibus, quin eadem
iisdem temporibus efficiat.” And so of the other planets.
56 A. A. i. p. 4.
57 Plin. H. N. ii. p.
204.
Probably the manner in which the motions of the
planets were originally reduced to rule was something like the
following:—In about 30 of our years, Saturn goes 29 times
through his Anomaly, that is, the succession of varied motions
by which he sometimes goes forwards and sometimes backwards among the
stars. During this time, he goes once round the heavens, and returns
nearly to the same place. This is the cycle of his apparent
motions.
Perhaps the eastern nations contented themselves with thus
referring these motions to cycles of time, so as to determine their
recurrence. Something of this kind was done at an early period, as we
have seen.
But the Greeks soon attempted to frame to themselves a sensible
image of the mechanism by which these complex motions were produced;
nor did they find this difficult. Venus, for instance, who, upon the
whole, moves from west to east among the stars, is seen, at certain
intervals, to return or move retrograde a short way back from
east to west, then to become for a short time stationary, then
to turn again and resume her direct motion westward, and so on.
Now this can be explained by supposing that she is placed in the rim
of a wheel, which is turned edgeways to us, and of which the centre
turns round in the heavens from west to east, while the wheel,
carrying the planet in its motion, moves round its own centre. In this
way the motion of the wheel about its centre, would, in some
situations, counterbalance the general motion of the centre, and make
the planet retrograde, while, on the whole, the westerly motion would
prevail. Just as if we suppose that a person, holding a lamp in his
hand in the dark, and at a 140 distance, so that the lamp alone is
visible, should run on turning himself round; we should see the light
sometimes stationary, sometimes retrograde, but on the whole
progressive.
A mechanism of this kind was imagined for each of the planets, and
the wheels of which we have spoken were in the end called
Epicycles.
The application of such mechanism to the planets appears to have
arisen in Greece about the time of Aristotle. In the works of Plato we
find a strong taste for this kind of mechanical speculation. In the
tenth book of the “Polity,” we have the apologue of Alcinus the
Pamphylian, who, being supposed to be killed in battle, revived when
he was placed on the funeral pyre, and related what he had seen during
his trance. Among other revelations, he beheld the machinery by which
all the celestial bodies revolve. The axis of these revolutions is the
adamantine distaff which Destiny holds between her knees; on this are
fixed, by means of different sockets, flat rings, by which the planets
are carried. The order and magnitude of these spindles are minutely
detailed. Also, in the “Epilogue to the Laws” (Epinomis), he
again describes the various movements of the sky, so as to show a
distinct acquaintance with the general character of the planetary
motions; and, after speaking of the Egyptians and Syrians as the
original cultivators of such knowledge, he adds some very remarkable
exhortations to his countrymen to prosecute the subject. “Whatever we
Greeks,” he says, “receive from the barbarians, we improve and
perfect; there is good hope and promise, therefore, that Greeks will
carry this knowledge far beyond that which was introduced from
abroad.” To this task, however, he looks with a due appreciation of
the qualities and preparation which it requires. “An astronomer must
be,” he says, “the wisest of men; his mind must be duly disciplined in
youth; especially is mathematical study necessary; both an
acquaintance with the doctrine of number, and also with that other
branch of mathematics, which, closely connected as it is with the
science of the heavens, we very absurdly call
geometry, the measurement of the earth.”58
58 Epinomis, pp. 988,
990.
Those anticipations were very remarkably verified in the subsequent
career of the Greek Astronomy.
The theory, once suggested, probably made rapid progress.
Simplicius59 relates, that Eudoxus of Cnidus
introduced the hypothesis of revolving circles or spheres. Calippus of
Cyzicus, having visited 141 Polemarchus, an intimate friend of
Eudoxus, they went together to Athens, and communicated to Aristotle
the invention of Eudoxus, and with his help improved and corrected
it.
59 Lib. ii. de Cœlo.
Bullialdus, p. 18.
Probably at first this hypothesis was applied only to account for
the general phenomena of the progressions, retrogradations, and
stations of the planet; but it was soon found that the motions of the
sun and moon, and the circular motions of the planets, which the
hypothesis supposed, had other anomalies or irregularities,
which made a further extension of the hypothesis necessary.
The defect of uniformity in these motions of the sun and moon,
though less apparent than in the planets, is easily detected, as soon
as men endeavor to obtain any accuracy in their observations. We have
already stated (Chap. I.) that the Chaldeans
were in possession of a period of about eighteen years, which they
used in the calculation of eclipses, and which might have been
discovered by close observation of the moon’s motions; although it was
probably rather hit upon by noting the recurrence of eclipses. The
moon moves in a manner which is not reducible to regularity without
considerable care and time. If we trace her path among the stars, we
find that, like the path of the sun, it is oblique to the equator, but
it does not, like that of the sun, pass over the same stars in
successive revolutions. Thus its latitude, or distance from the
equator, has a cycle different from its revolution among the stars;
and its Nodes, or the points where it cuts the equator, are
perpetually changing their position. In addition to this, the moon’s
motion in her own path is not uniform; in the course of each lunation,
she moves alternately slower and quicker, passing gradually through
the intermediate degrees of velocity; and goes through the cycle of
these changes in something less than a month; this is called a
revolution of Anomaly. When the moon has gone through a
complete number of revolutions of Anomaly, and has, in the same time,
returned to the same position with regard to the sun, and also with
regard to her Nodes, her motions with respect to the sun will
thenceforth be the same as at the first, and all the circumstances on
which lunar eclipses depend being the same, the eclipses will occur in
the same order. In 6585⅓ days there are 239 revolutions of anomaly,
241 revolutions with regard to one of the Nodes, and, as we have said,
223 lunations or revolutions with regard to the sun. Hence this Period
will bring about a succession of the same lunar eclipses.
If the Chaldeans observed the moon’s motion among the stars with
any considerable accuracy, so as to detect this period by that means,
142 they could
hardly avoid discovering the anomaly or unequal motion of the moon;
for in every revolution, her daily progression in the heavens varies
from about twenty-two to twenty-six times her own diameter. But there
is not, in their knowledge of this Period, any evidence that they had
measured the amount of this variation; and Delambre60 is probably right in attributing all
such observations to the Greeks.
60 Astronomie Ancienne, i.
212.
The sun’s motion would also be seen to be irregular as soon as men
had any exact mode of determining the lengths of the four seasons, by
means of the passage of the sun through the equinoctial and solstitial
points. For spring, summer, autumn, and winter, which would each
consist of an equal number of days if the motions were uniform, are,
in fact, found to be unequal in length.
It was not very difficult to see that the mechanism of epicycles
might be applied so as to explain irregularities of this kind. A wheel
travelling round the earth, while it revolved upon its centre, might
produce the effect of making the sun or moon fixed in its rim go
sometimes faster and sometimes slower in appearance, just in the same
way as the same suppositions would account for a planet going
sometimes forwards and sometimes backwards: the epicycles of the sun
and moon would, for this purpose, be less than those of the planets.
Accordingly, it is probable that, at the time of Plato and Aristotle,
philosophers were already endeavoring to apply the hypothesis to these
cases, though it does not appear that any one fully succeeded before
Hipparchus.
The problem which was thus present to the minds of astronomers, and
which Plato is said to have proposed to them in a distinct form, was,
“To reconcile the celestial phenomena by the combination of equable
circular motions.” That the circular motions should be equable as well
as circular, was a condition, which, if it had been merely tried at
first, as the most simple and definite conjecture, would have deserved
praise. But this condition, which is, in reality, inconsistent with
nature, was, in the sequel, adhered to with a pertinacity which
introduced endless complexity into the system. The history of this
assumption is one of the most marked instances of that love of
simplicity and symmetry which is the source of all general truths,
though it so often produces and perpetuates error. At present we can
easily see how fancifully the notion of simplicity and perfection was
interpreted, in the arguments by which the opinion was defended, that
the 143 real
motions of the heavenly bodies must be circular and uniform. The
Pythagoreans, as well as the Platonists, maintained this dogma.
According to Geminus, “They supposed the motions of the sun, and the
moon, and the five planets, to be circular and equable: for they would
not allow of such disorder among divine and eternal things, as that
they should sometimes move quicker, and sometimes slower, and
sometimes stand still; for no one would tolerate such anomaly in the
movements, even of a man, who was decent and orderly. The occasions of
life, however, are often reasons for men going quicker or slower, but
in the incorruptible nature of the stars, it is not possible that any
cause can be alleged of quickness and slowness. Whereupon they
propounded this question, how the phenomena might be represented by
equable and circular motions.”
These conjectures and assumptions led naturally to the
establishment of the various parts of the Theory of Epicycles. It is
probable that this theory was adopted with respect to the Planets at
or before the time of Plato. And Aristotle gives us an account of the
system thus devised.61 “Eudoxus,” he says, “attributed four
spheres to each Planet: the first revolved with the fixed stars (and
this produced the diurnal motion); the second gave the planet a motion
along the ecliptic (the mean motion in longitude); the third had its
axis perpendicular62 to the ecliptic (and this gave the
inequality of each planetary motion, really arising from its special
motion about the sun); the fourth produced the oblique motion
transverse to this (the motion in latitude).” He is also said to have
attributed a motion in latitude and a corresponding sphere to the Sun
as well as to the Moon, of which it is difficult to understand the
meaning, if Aristotle has reported rightly of the theory; for it would
be absurd to ascribe to Eudoxus a knowledge of the motions by which
the sun deviates from the ecliptic. Calippus conceived that two
additional spheres must be given to the sun and to the moon, in order
to explain the phenomena: probably he was aware of the inequalities of
the motions of these luminaries. He also proposed an additional sphere
for each planet, to account, we may suppose, for the results of the
eccentricity of the orbits.
61 Metaph. xi. 8.
62 Aristotle says “has its poles in
the ecliptic,” but this must be a mistake of his. He professes merely
to receive these opinions from the mathematical astronomers, “ἐκ τῆς
οἰκειοτάτης φιλοσοφίας τῶν μαθηματικῶν.”
The hypothesis, in this form, does not appear to have been reduced
to measure, and was, moreover, unnecessarily complex. The resolution
144 of the oblique
motion of the moon into two separate motions, by Eudoxus, was not the
simplest way of conceiving it; and Calippus imagined the connection of
these spheres in some way which made it necessary nearly to double
their number; in this manner his system had no less than 55
spheres.
Such was the progress which the Idea of the hypothesis of
epicycles had made in men’s minds, previously to the establishment of
the theory by Hipparchus. There had also been a preparation for this
step, on the other side, by the collection of Facts. We know
that observations of the Eclipses of the Moon were made by the
Chaldeans 367 b. c. at Babylon, and were known
to the Greeks; for Hipparchus and Ptolemy founded their Theory of the
Moon on these observations. Perhaps we cannot consider, as equally
certain, the story that, at the time of Alexander’s conquest, the
Chaldeans possessed a series of observations, which went back 1903
years, and which Aristotle caused Callisthenes to bring to him in
Greece. All the Greek observations which are of any value, begin with
the school of Alexandria. Aristyllus and Timocharis appear, by the
citations of Hipparchus, to have observed the Places of Stars and
Planets, and the Times of the Solstices, at various periods from b. c. 295 to b. c. 269.
Without their observations, indeed, it would not have been easy for
Hipparchus to establish either the Theory of the Sun or the Precession
of the Equinoxes.
In order that observations at distant intervals may be compared
with each other, they must be referred to some common era. The
Chaldeans dated by the era of Nabonassar, which commenced 749 b. c. The Greek observations were referred to the
Calippic periods of 76 years, of which the first began 331 b. c. These are the dates used by Hipparchus and
Ptolemy. 145</div></body></text></TEI>