<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="1"> 

CHAPTER II.
Of the Explication of Conceptions.


Aphorism II.
The Explication of Conceptions, as requisite for the progress
of science, has been effected by means of discussions and
controversies among scientists; often by debates concerning
definitions; these controversies have frequently led to the
establishment of a Definition; but along with the Definition,
a corresponding Proposition has always been expressed or
implied. The essential requisite for the advance of science
is the clearness of the Conception, not the establishment of a
Definition. The construction of an exact Definition is often
very difficult. The requisite conditions of clear Conceptions
may often be expressed by Axioms as well as by Definitions.
Aphorism III.
Conceptions, for purposes of science, must be appropriate
as well as clear: that is, they must be modifications of that
Fundamental Idea, by which the phenomena can really be interpreted.
This maxim may warn us from errour, though
it may not lead to discovery. Discovery depends upon the
previous cultivation or natural clearness of the appropriate
Idea, and therefore no discovery is the work of accident.
Sect. I.—Historical Progress of the Explication of Conceptions.

1. WE have given the appellation of Ideas to certain
comprehensive forms of thought,—as
space, number, cause, composition, resemblance,—which
we apply to the phenomena which we contemplate.
But the special modifications of these ideas which are 31
exemplified in particular facts, we have termed Conceptions;
as a circle, a square number, an accelerating
force, a neutral combination of elements, a genus.
Such Conceptions involve in themselves certain necessary and
universal relations derived from the Ideas
just enumerated; and these relations are an indispensable
portion of the texture of our knowledge. But to
determine the contents and limits of this portion of
our knowledge, requires an examination of the Ideas
and Conceptions from which it proceeds. The Conceptions must
be, as it were, carefully unfolded, so as
to bring into clear view the elements of truth with
which they are marked from their ideal origin. This
is one of the processes by which our knowledge is extended
and made more exact; and this I shall describe
as the Explication of Conceptions.
In the several Books of the History of Ideas we
have discussed a great many of the Fundamental Ideas
of the most important existing sciences. We have, in
those Books, abundant exemplifications of the process
now under our consideration. We shall here add a
few general remarks, suggested by the survey which
we have thus made.
2. Such discussions as those in which we have been
engaged concerning our fundamental Ideas, have been
the course by which, historically speaking, those Conceptions
which the existing sciences involve have been
rendered so clear as to be fit elements of exact knowledge.
Thus, the disputes concerning the various kinds
and measures of Force were an important part of the
progress of the science of Mechanics. The struggles by
which philosophers attained a right general conception
of plane, of circular, of elliptical Polarization, were
some of the most difficult steps in the modern discoveries
of Optics. A Conception of the Atomic Constitution
of bodies, such as shall include what we know,
and assume nothing more, is even now a matter of
conflict among Chemists. The debates by which, in
recent times, the Conceptions of Species and Genera
have been rendered more exact, have improved the
science of Botany: the imperfection of the science of 32
Mineralogy arises in a great measure from the circumstance,
that in that subject, the Conception of a Species
is not yet fixed. In Physiology, what a vast advance
would that philosopher make, who should establish a
precise, tenable, and consistent Conception of Life!
Thus discussions and speculations concerning the
import of very abstract and general terms and notions,
may be, and in reality have been, far from useless and
barren. Such discussions arose from the desire of men
to impress their opinions on others, but they had the
effect of making the opinions much more clear and distinct.
In trying to make others understand them, they
learnt to understand themselves. Their speculations
were begun in twilight, and ended in the full brilliance
of day. It was not easily and at once, without expenditure
of labour or time, that men arrived at those
notions which now form the elements of our knowledge;
on the contrary, we have, in the history of
science, seen how hard, discoverers, and the forerunners
of discoverers, have had to struggle with the indistinctness
and obscurity of the intellect, before they could
advance to the critical point at which truth became
clearly visible. And so long as, in this advance, some
speculators were more forward than others, there was
a natural and inevitable ground of difference of opinion,
of argumentation, of wrangling. But the tendency of all
such controversy is to diffuse truth and to
dispel errour. Truth is consistent, and can bear the
tug of war; Errour is incoherent, and falls to pieces
in the struggle. True Conceptions can endure the
sun, and become clearer as a fuller light is obtained;
confused and inconsistent notions vanish like visionary
spectres at the break of a brighter day. And thus
all the controversies concerning such Conceptions as
science involves, have ever ended in the establishment
of the side on which the truth was found.
3. Indeed, so complete has been the victory of
truth in most of these instances, that at present we
can hardly imagine the struggle to have been necessary.
The very essence of these triumphs is that they
lead us to regard the views we reject as not only false, 33
but inconceivable. And hence we are led rather to
look back upon the vanquished with contempt than
upon the victors with gratitude. We now despise those
who, in the Copernican controversy, could not conceive
the apparent motion of the sun on the heliocentric
hypothesis;—or those who, in opposition to Galileo,
thought that a uniform force might be that which
generated a velocity proportional to the space;—or
those who held there was something absurd in Newton’s
doctrine of the different refrangibility of differently
coloured rays;—or those who imagined that
when elements combine, their sensible qualities must
be manifest in the compound;—or those who were
reluctant to give up the distinction of vegetables into
herbs, shrubs, and trees. We cannot help thinking that
men must have been singularly dull of comprehension,
to find a difficulty in admitting what is to us so plain
and simple. We have a latent persuasion that we in
their place should have been wiser and more clear-sighted;—that
we should have taken the right side,
and given our assent at once to the truth.
4. Yet in reality, such a persuasion is a mere delusion.
The persons who, in such instances as the above,
were on the losing side, were very far, in most cases,
from being persons more prejudiced, or stupid, or narrow-minded,
than the greater part of mankind now
are; and the cause for which they fought was far
from being a manifestly bad one, till it had been so
decided by the result of the war. It is the peculiar
character of scientific contests, that what is only an
epigram with regard to other warfare is a truth in
this;—They who are defeated are really in the wrong.
But they may, nevertheless, be men of great subtilty,
sagacity, and genius; and we nourish a very foolish
self-complacency when we suppose that we are their
superiors. That this is so, is proved by recollecting
that many of those who have made very great discoveries
have laboured under the imperfection of thought
which was the obstacle to the next step in knowledge.
Though Kepler detected with great acuteness the
Numerical Laws of the solar system, he laboured in 34
vain to conceive the very simplest of the Laws of
Motion by which the paths of the planets are governed.
Though Priestley made some important steps in chemistry,
he could not bring his mind to admit the doctrine
of a general Principle of Oxidation. How many ingenious
men in the last century rejected the Newtonian Attraction
as an impossible chimera! How
many more, equally intelligent, have, in the same manner,
in our own time, rejected, I do not now mean as
false, but as inconceivable, the doctrine of Luminiferous
Undulations! To err in this way is the lot, not
only of men in general, but of men of great endowments,
and very sincere love of truth.
5. And those who liberate themselves from such
perplexities, and who thus go on in advance of their
age in such matters, owe their superiority in no small
degree to such discussions and controversies as those
to which we now refer. In such controversies, the
Conceptions in question are turned in all directions,
examined on all sides; the strength and the weakness
of the maxims which men apply to them are fully tested;
the light of the brightest minds is diffused to other
minds. Inconsistency is unfolded into self-contradiction;
axioms are built up into a system of necessary
truths; and ready exemplifications are accumulated of
that which is to be proved or disproved, concerning
the ideas which are the basis of the controversy.
The History of Mechanics from the time of Kepler
to that of Lagrange, is perhaps the best exemplification
of the mode in which the progress of a science
depends upon such disputes and speculations as give
clearness and generality to its elementary conceptions.
This, it is to be recollected, is the kind of progress of
which we are now speaking; and this is the principal
feature in the portion of scientific history which we
have mentioned. For almost all that was to be done
by reference to observation, was executed by Galileo
and his disciples. What remained was the task of
generalization and simplification. And this was promoted
in no small degree by the various controversies
which took place within that period concerning 35 mechanical
conceptions:—as, for example, the question
concerning the measure of the Force of Percussion;—the
war of the Vis Viva;—the controversy of the
Center of Oscillation;—of the independence of Statics and
Dynamics;—of the principle of Least Action;—of the
evidence of the Laws of Motion;—and of the number
of Laws really distinct. None of these discussions was
without its influence in giving generality and clearness
to the mechanical ideas of mathematicians: and therefore,
though remote from general apprehension, and
dealing with very abstract notions, they were of eminent
use in the perfecting the science of Mechanics.
Similar controversies concerning fundamental notions,
those, for example, which Galileo himself had to maintain,
were no less useful in the formation of the science
of Hydrostatics. And the like struggles and conflicts,
whether they take the form of controversies between
several persons, or only operate in the efforts and
fluctuations of the discoverer’s mind, are always requisite,
before the conceptions acquire that clearness which
makes them flt to appear in the enunciation of scientific
truth. This, then, was one object of the History
of Ideas;—to bring under the reader’s notice the main
elements of the controversies which have thus had so
important a share in the formation of the existing
body of science, and the decisions on the controverted
points to which the mature examination of the subject
has led; and thus to give an abundant exhibition of
that step which we term the Explication of Conceptions.
Sect. II.—Use of Definitions.
6. The result of such controversies as we have
been speaking of, often appears to be summed up in a
Definition; and the controversy itself has often assumed
the form of a battle of definitions. For example, the
inquiry concerning the Laws of Falling
Bodies led to the question whether the proper Definition
of a uniform force is, that it generates a velocity
proportional to the space from rest, or to the time.
The controversy of the Vis Viva was, what was the 36
proper Definition of the measure of force. A principal
question in the classification of minerals is, what is
the Definition of a mineral species. Physiologists have
endeavoured to throw light on their subject, by
Defining organization, or some similar term.
7. It is very important for us to observe, that
these controversies have never been questions of insulated
and arbitrary Definitions, as men seem often
tempted to suppose them to have been. In all cases
there is a tacit assumption of some Proposition which
is to be expressed by means of the Definition, and
which gives it its importance. The dispute concerning
the Definition thus acquires a real value, and becomes
a question concerning true and false. Thus in the discussion
of the question, What is a Uniform Force? it
was taken for granted that ‘gravity is a uniform
force:’—in the debate of the Vis Viva, it was assumed
that ‘in the mutual action of bodies the whole effect
of the force is unchanged:’—in the zoological definition
of Species, (that it consists of individuals which have,
or may have, sprung from the same parents,) it is presumed
that ‘individuals so related resemble each other
more than those which are excluded by such a definition;’ or
perhaps, that ‘species so defined have permanent and definite
differences.’ A definition of Organization, or of any other
term, which was not employed to express some principle,
would be of no value.
The establishment, therefore, of a right Definition
of a Term may be a useful step in the Explication of
our Conceptions; but this will be the case then only
when we have under our consideration some Proposition
in which the Term is employed. For then the
question really is, how the Conception shall be understood
and defined in order that the Proposition may be
true.
8. The establishment of a Proposition requires an
attention to observed Facts, and can never be rightly
derived from our Conceptions alone. We must hereafter
consider the necessity which exists that the Facts
should be rightly bound together, as well as that our
Conceptions should be clearly employed, in order to 37
lead us to real knowledge. But we may observe here
that, in such cases at least as we are now considering,
the two processes are co-ordinate. To unfold our Conceptions
by the means of Definitions, has never been
serviceable to science, except when it has been associated
with an immediate use of the Definitions. The
endeavour to define a uniform Force was combined
with the assertion that ‘gravity is a uniform force:’
the attempt to define Accelerating Force was immediately
followed by the doctrine that ‘accelerating
forces may be compounded:’ the process of defining
Momentum was connected with the principle that
‘momenta gained and lost are equal:’ naturalists would
have given in vain the Definition of Species which we
have quoted, if they had not also given the ‘characters’
of species so separated. Definition and Proposition
are the two handles of the instrument by which we
apprehend truth; the former is of no use without the
latter. Definition may be the best mode of explaining
our Conception, but that which alone makes it worth
while to explain it in any mode, is the opportunity of
using it in the expression of Truth. When a Definition
is propounded to us as a useful step in knowledge,
we are always entitled to ask what Principle it
serves to enunciate. If there be no answer to this inquiry,
we define and give clearness to our conceptions
in vain. While we labour at such a task, we do but
light up a vacant room;—we sharpen a knife with
which we have nothing to cut;—we take exact aim,
while we load our artillery with blank cartridge;—we
apply strict rules of grammar to sentences which
have no meaning.
If, on the other hand, we have under our consideration
a proposition probably established, every step
which we can make in giving distinctness and exactness
to the Terms which this proposition involves, is
an important step towards scientific truth. In such
cases, any improvement in our Definition is a real
advance in the explication of our Conception. The
clearness of our impressions casts a light upon the
Ideas which we contemplate and convey to others. 38
9. But though Definition may be subservient to a
right explication of our conceptions, it is not essential
to that process. It is absolutely necessary to every
advance in our knowledge, that those by whom such
advances are made should possess clearly the conceptions
which they employ: but it is by no means necessary that
they should unfold these conceptions in the
words of a formal Definition. It is easily seen, by
examining the course of Galileo’s discoveries, that he
had a distinct conception of the Moving Force which
urges bodies downwards upon an inclined plane, while
he still hesitated whether to call it Momentum, Energy,
Impetus, or Force, and did not venture to offer
a Definition of the thing which was the subject of his
thoughts. The Conception of Polarization was clear
in the minds of many optical speculators, from the
time of Huyghens and Newton to that of Young and
Fresnel. This Conception we have defined to be
‘Opposite properties depending upon opposite positions;’
but this notion was, by the discoverers, though constantly
assumed and expressed by means of superfluous
hypotheses, never clothed in definite language. And
in the mean time, it was the custom, among subordinate
writers on the same subjects, to say, that the
term Polarization had no definite meaning, and was
merely an expression of our ignorance. The Definition
which was offered by Haüy and others of a Mineralogical
Species;—‘The same elements combined in the
same proportions, with the same fundamental form;’—was
false, inasmuch as it was incapable of being rigorously
applied to any one case; but this defect did not
prevent the philosophers who propounded such a Definition
from making many valuable additions to mineralogical
knowledge, in the way of identifying some
species and distinguishing others. The right Conception
which they possessed in their minds prevented
their being misled by their own very erroneous Definition.
The want of any precise Definitions of Strata,
and Formations, and Epochs, among geologists, has
not prevented the discussions which they have carried
on upon such subjects from being highly serviceable 39
in the promotion of geological knowledge. For however
much the apparent vagueness of these terms
might leave their arguments open to cavil, there was a
general understanding prevalent among the most intelligent
cultivators of the science, as to what was
meant in such expressions; and this common understanding
sufficed to determine what evidence should
be considered conclusive and what inconclusive, in
these inquiries. And thus the distinctness of Conception,
which is a real requisite of scientific progress,
existed in the minds of the inquirers, although Definitions,
which are a partial and accidental evidence
of this distinctness, had not yet been hit upon. The
Idea had been developed in men’s minds, although a
clothing of words had not been contrived for it, nor,
perhaps, the necessity of such a vehicle felt: and thus
that essential condition of the progress of knowledge,
of which we are here speaking, existed; while it was
left to the succeeding speculators to put this unwritten
Rule in the form of a verbal Statute.
10. Men are often prone to consider it as a thoughtless
omission of an essential circumstance, and as a
neglect which involves some blame, when knowledge
thus assumes a form in which Definitions, or rather
Conceptions, are implied but are not expressed. But in
such a judgment, they assume that to be a matter of
choice requiring attention only, which is in fact as
difficult and precarious as any other portion of the task
of discovery. To define, so that our Definition shall
have any scientific value, requires no small portion of
that sagacity by which truth is detected. As we have
already said, Definitions and Propositions are co-ordinate
in their use and in their origin. In many cases,
perhaps in most, the Proposition which contains a
scientific truth, is apprehended with confidence, but
with some vagueness and vacillation, before it is put in
a positive, distinct, and definite form.—It is thus known
to be true, before it can be enunciated in terms each of
which is rigorously defined. The business of Definition is
part of the business of discovery. When it has
been clearly seen what ought to be our Definition, it 40
must be pretty well known what truth we have to
state. The Definition, as well as the discovery, supposes
a decided step in our knowledge to have been
made. The writers on Logic in the middle ages, made
Definition the last stage in the progress of knowledge;
and in this arrangement at least, the history of science,
and the philosophy derived from the history, confirm
their speculative views. If the Explication of our
Conceptions ever assume the form of a Definition, this
will come to pass, not as an arbitrary process, or as a
matter of course, but as the mark of one of those happy
efforts of sagacity to which all the successive advances
of our knowledge are owing.
Sect. III.—Use of Axioms.
11. Our Conceptions, then, even when they become
so clear as the progress of knowledge requires, are not
adequately expressed, or necessarily expressed at all, by
means of Definitions. We may ask, then, whether there
is any other mode of expression in which we may look
for the evidence and exposition of that peculiar exactness
of thought which the formation of Science demands.
And in answer to this inquiry, we may refer to the
discussions respecting many of the Fundamental Ideas
of the sciences contained in our History of such Ideas.
It has there been seen that these Ideas involve many
elementary truths which enter into the texture of our
knowledge, introducing into it connexions and relations
of the most important kind, although these elementary
truths cannot be deduced from any verbal definition of
the idea. It has been seen that these elementary truths
may often be enunciated by means of Axioms, stated in
addition to, or in preference to, Definitions. For example,
the Idea of Cause, which forms the basis of the
science of Mechanics, makes its appearance in our elementary
mechanical reasonings, not as a Definition, but by
means of the Axioms that ‘Causes are measured by
their effects,’ and that ‘Reaction is equal and opposite
to action.’ Such axioms, tacitly assumed or 41 occasionally
stated, as maxims of acknowledged validity,
belong to all the Ideas which form the foundations of
the sciences, and are constantly employed in the reasoning
and speculations of those who think clearly on
such subjects. It may often be a task of some difficulty
to detect and enunciate in words the Principles
which are thus, perhaps silently and unconsciously,
taken for granted by those who have a share in the
establishment of scientific truth: but inasmuch as
these Principles are an essential element in our knowledge,
it is very important to our present purpose
to separate them from the associated materials, and
to trace them to their origin. This accordingly I
attempted to do, with regard to a considerable number
of the most prominent of such Ideas, in the History.
The reader will there find many of these Ideas
resolved into Axioms and Principles by means of
which their effect upon the elementary reasonings of
the various sciences may be expressed. That Work
is intended to form, in some measure, a representation
of the Ideal Side of our physical knowledge;—a Table
of those contents of our Conceptions which are not
received directly from facts;—an exhibition of Rules
to which we know that truth must conform.
Sect. IV.—Clear and appropriate Ideas.
12. In order, however, that we may see the necessary
cogency of these rules, we must possess, clearly and
steadily, the Ideas from which the rules flow. In order
to perceive the necessary relations of the Circles of the
Sphere, we must possess clearly the Idea of Solid
Space:—in order that we may see the demonstration of
the composition of forces, we must have the Idea of
Cause moulded into a distinct Conception of Statical
Force. This is that Clearness of Ideas which we
stipulate for in any one’s mind, as the first essential
condition of his making any new step in the discovery of
truth. And we now see what answer we are able to
give, if we are asked for a Criterion of this Clearness of 42
Idea. The Criterion is, that the person shall see the
necessity of the Axioms belonging to each Idea;—shall
accept them in such a manner as to perceive the cogency
of the reasonings founded upon them. Thus, a person
has a clear Idea of Space who follows the reasonings of
geometry and fully apprehends their conclusiveness.
The Explication of Conceptions, which we are speaking
of as an essential part of real knowledge, is the process
by which we bring the Clearness of our Ideas to bear
upon the Formation of our knowledge. And this is
done, as we have now seen, not always, nor generally,
nor principally, by laying down a Definition of the
Conception; but by acquiring such a possession of it
in our minds as enables, indeed compels us, to admit,
along with the Conception, all the Axioms and Principles
which it necessarily implies, and by which it
produces its effect upon our reasonings.
13. But in order that we may make any real advance
in the discovery of truth, our Ideas must not only be
clear, they must also be appropriate. Each science has
for its basis a different class of Ideas; and the steps
which constitute the progress of one science can never
be made by employing the Ideas of another kind of
science. No genuine advance could ever be obtained
in Mechanics by applying to the subject the Ideas of
Space and Time merely:—no advance in Chemistry, by
the use of mere Mechanical Conceptions:—no discovery
in Physiology, by referring facts to mere Chemical and
Mechanical Principles. Mechanics must involve the
Conception of Force;—Chemistry, the Conception of
Elementary Composition;—Physiology, the Conception
of Vital Powers. Each science must advance by means
of its appropriate Conceptions. Each has its own field,
which extends as far as its principles can be applied. I
have already noted the separation of several of these
fields by the divisions of the Books of the History of Ideas.
The Mechanical, the Secondary Mechanical, the Chemical, the
Classificatory, the Biological Sciences form so
many great Provinces in the Kingdom of knowledge,
each in a great measure possessing its own peculiar
fundamental principles. Every attempt to build up a 43
new science by the application of principles which
belong to an old one, will lead to frivolous and barren
speculations.
This truth has been exemplified in all the instances
in which subtle speculative men have failed in their
attempts to frame new sciences, and especially in the
essays of the ancient schools of philosophy in Greece,
as has already been stated in the History of Science.
Aristotle and his followers endeavoured in vain to
account for the mechanical relation of forces in the
lever by applying the inappropriate geometrical conceptions
of the properties of the circle:—they speculated to no
purpose about the elementary composition
of bodies, because they assumed the inappropriate
conception of likeness between the elements and the
compound, instead of the genuine notion of elements
merely determining the qualities of the compound. And
in like manner, in modern times, we have seen, in the
history of the fundamental ideas of the physiological
sciences, how all the inappropriate mechanical and
chemical and other ideas which were applied in succession
to the subject failed in bringing into view any
genuine physiological truth.
14. That the real cause of the failure in the instances
above mentioned lay in the Conceptions, is
plain. It was not ignorance of the facts which in
these cases prevented the discovery of the truth. Aristotle
was as well acquainted with the fact of the proportion
of the weights which balance on a Lever as Archimedes
was, although Archimedes alone gave the true mechanical
reason for the proportion.
With regard to the doctrine of the Four Elements
indeed, the inapplicability of the conception of
composition of qualities, required, perhaps, to be proved by
some reference to facts. But this conception was
devised at first, and accepted by succeeding times, in a
blind and gratuitous manner, which could hardly have
happened if men had been awake to the necessary
condition of our knowledge;—that the conceptions
which we introduce into our doctrines are not arbitrary
or accidental notions, but certain peculiar modes of 44
apprehension strictly determined by the subject of our
speculations.
15. It may, however, be said that this injunction
that we are to employ appropriate Conceptions only in
the formation of our knowledge, cannot be of practical
use, because we can only determine what Ideas are
appropriate, by finding that they truly combine the
facts. And this is to a certain extent true. Scientific
discovery must ever depend upon some happy thought,
of which we cannot trace the origin;—some fortunate
cast of intellect, rising above all rules. No maxims
can be given which inevitably lead to discovery. No
precepts will elevate a man of ordinary endowments
to the level of a man of genius: nor will an inquirer
of truly inventive mind need to come to the teacher
of inductive philosophy to learn how to exercise the
faculties which nature has given him. Such persons
as Kepler or Fresnel, or Brewster, will have their
powers of discovering truth little augmented by any
injunctions respecting Distinct and Appropriate Ideas;
and such men may very naturally question the utility
of rules altogether.
16. But yet the opinions which such persons may
entertain, will not lead us to doubt concerning the
value of the attempts to analyse and methodize the
process of discovery. Who would attend to Kepler if
he had maintained that the speculations of Francis
Bacon were worthless? Notwithstanding what has
been said, we may venture to assert that the Maxim
which points out the necessity of Ideas appropriate
as well as clear, for the purpose of discovering truth, is
not without its use. It may, at least, have a value as
a caution or prohibition, and may thus turn us away
from labours certain to be fruitless. We have already
seen, in the History of Ideas, that this maxim, if duly
attended to, would have at once condemned, as wrongly
directed, the speculations of physiologists of the
mathematical, mechanical, chemical, and vital-fluid schools;
since the Ideas which the teachers of these schools
introduce, cannot suffice for the purposes of physiology,
which seeks truths respecting the vital powers. Again, 45
it is clear from similar considerations that no definition
of a mineralogical species by chemical characters alone
can answer the end of science, since we seek to make
mineralogy, not an analytical but a classificatory science1.
Even before the appropriate conception is matured in
men’s minds so that they see clearly what it is, they
may still have light enough to see what it is not.</div></body></text></TEI>