<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="37">CHAPTER XXXV.
From St. Leon I proceeded to the kingdom of Hungary.
To complete this journey I must pass through near twenty
degrees of longitude. But that was a trivial consideration:
what I most desired was to gain a new situation, and enter
upon an untried scene. I had determined in my next experiment
upon the endowments of the stranger, to make no
half-formed efforts, and to suffer no mischiefs that drew
their source from my own irresolution. I determined, as
I have said, to forestall all opposition by my firmness, and
to silence all objectors by the display of a more than princely
magnificence. I thought it therefore eligible to remove to
a scene, where no encounter with any one I had ever known
might abash me, and no relation of any adventure I had ever
met should follow me. The change of my figure, it is true,
would render an encounter of this sort of little moment to
my liberty or my reputation; but I was a new man, and
I was desirous to engross and to feel the benefits that attend
upon novelty.
There was another motive however secretly working at
my heart, of a grander and more exalted cast, that made
me prefer Hungary to all the countries of the earth. Hungary
had been now, for upwards of a century, the great
frontier of the Christian world,—the theatre upon which
the followers of Mahomet contended against the followers of
Jesus for destruction and for empire. My mind had from
time to time brooded over this picture in the solitude and
forlornness of my dungeon. I ruminated on all the calamities
of Hungary, from the battle of Warna in 1444, to the
battle of Mohacz in 1526; in both of which this generous
nation had unsuccessfully achieved prodigies of valour, and,
even by their defeats, had protracted the date of their own
independence, and co-operated for the defence of the population
and arts of Europe against a barbarous and blood-delighting
foe. My thoughts dwelt with rapturous admiration
upon the exploits of the heroic Huniades and his
greater son. In the course of my many-coloured experience[369]
I had seen something of war, and was not totally unacquainted
with its never-failing consequences. Meditating as
I had done in the dungeons of the inquisition, if ever I recovered
my personal liberty and my freedom of action, a
journey into Hungary, my imagination had grown familiar
with captured towns and smoking villages; with the gallant
soldier stretched lifeless on the plain, and the defenceless
mother and her offspring brutally insulted and massacred;
with fields laid waste, and a people lifting up their hands
for bread. Determined as I was to open at once all the
stores of my wealth, I thought I could not find a nobler
scene for its display. I resolved to pour the entire stream
of my riches, like a mighty river, to fertilise these wasted
plains, and revive their fainting inhabitants. Thus proceeding,
should I not have a right to expect to find myself
guarded by the faithful love of a people who would be indebted
to my beneficence for every breath they drew?
This was the proper scene in which for the possessor of the
philosopher’s stone to take up his abode. He who could
feel his ambition satisfied in a more straitened field would,
by so doing, prove himself unworthy of the mighty blessing.
Nothing occurred to me in my journey of importance
enough to obtain a place in this history. When I arrived,
I found the condition of the inhabitants even more wretched
than the lawlessness of my imagination had represented it.
In the battle of Mohacz the last of the line of their native
sovereigns, together with the flower of his nobility, had
fallen a victim to the merciless plague of war. What survived
of eminent persons in the state assembled soon after in
national diet, and elected, as they had been accustomed to
do, one of the most illustrious among themselves to preside
over the councils and to conduct the battles of their country.
But the princes of the house of Austria, ever on the
watch for the aggrandisement of their family, seized the
opportunity of their disastrous situation to enslave the
Hungarians to their sceptre. Charles the Fifth caused his
brother Ferdinand, whose consort was only sister to the
deceased monarch, to advance his claim to the vacant throne,
and to enter the country with an imperial army. The native[370]
and elected sovereign found himself, in the weakened
condition of his realm, unable to resist the Austrian arms,
and was finally driven to the desperate expedient of calling
in the Turk to his assistance. From this time, for now
upwards of thirty years, the kingdom had been a prey to
two foreign invaders, alternately taking and retaking her
most considerable towns, and distributing with the strictest
impartiality the miseries of war to her devoted inhabitants.
Solyman the Magnificent, the present Ottoman emperor, in
no long time threw off the mask; and, like his rival Ferdinand,
professed to fight only for the enlargement of his
own dominions; while the claims, the liberties, the constitution,
and the prosperity of Hungary, were alike trodden
under foot in the protracted and sanguinary struggle.
At the period at which I entered this unfortunate realm,
the Turk was in possession of Buda, Gran, Temeswar, and
many of the most considerable cities; and Ferdinand, who
had now succeeded Charles in the imperial dignity, had
been obliged to withdraw the seat of the national government
from the first of these towns, the ancient metropolis,
to the comparatively insignificant city of Presburg. The
war between the two parties had more than once been interrupted;
not indeed by the more stable accommodations of a
treaty of peace, but by a truce variously concluded for the
terms of six or of eight years. Short as was the period
assigned to the suspension of arms, it was never suffered to
reach its natural termination; but, after the interval of one
or two summers, hostilities did not fail to break out again,
with aggravated symptoms of resentment and animosity.
The warfare that was now carried on had more in it of passion
than vigour: it was of little moment to the interest of
either of the princes under whose banners it was conducted;
but it was not on that account the less, but rather the more,
vexatious and distressing to the Hungarian people. It
obeyed no rule; it operated in every direction; no place,
no province, no town,—neither the church nor the palace,
neither the cottage nor the castle,—could assure safety to
those who sought its protection. A flying party, which was
to-day in the west, would almost the next day make its
appearance in the eastern extremity of the kingdom. Arts[371]
were neglected; civilisation was destroyed; the stern and
haughty baron, free from restraint, would sally from his
castle, sometimes in pursuit of plunder, sometimes of private
resentment and revenge; the starving peasantry gladly
enlisted in the band of a ferocious partisan for bread; the
gangs of robbers, which the vigilant policy of better times
had almost annihilated, rose again in importance, and
swelled into regiments; and, while they assumed at pleasure
the denomination of adherents to Ferdinand or to Solyman,
perpetrated every species of excess with impunity.
When a reflecting spectator surveys a country in a condition
like this, he is tempted to wonder that the inhabitants still
retain the courage to bestow on their fields any sort of cultivation,
and that the licensed or the unlicensed robber still
finds something over which to extend the fangs of his
rapacity.
I had not long passed the gates of Vienna, before I began
to observe the symptoms of that, which I had come
from the Pyrenees and the Garonne to visit. The farther
I advanced, the more melancholy was the scene I beheld.
The country in some places entirely deserted; villages laid
in ashes; cities reduced to the dimensions and insignificance
of villages; fields fertilised or made rank with the
manure of human blood; the roads broken up; the erections
of human ingenuity almost obliterated; mills thrown
down; rivers choked up and rendered stagnant; a few
solitary plots of cultivation scattered amidst the mighty
waste. The inhabitants I saw, appeared terrified, sickly,
dejected, and despairing; there was scarcely one who earlier
or later had not lost a father or a brother, whose wife had
not been made the victim of brutal lust, or who had not
seen his children butchered before his face. Persons of
the more opulent classes could not travel the country in
safety, without being armed and associated in companies
and caravans. I was myself obliged to obtain the protection
of parties of soldiers, who from time to time happened
to be marching in the route I pursued. The savage neglect
into which every thing was declining, produced in
repeated instances a contagious air and pestilential diseases;
while dearth and famine unrelentingly haunted the steps[372]
of those whom the sword and the pestilence had spared.
Such is war: such are the evils nations willingly plunge
into, or are compelled to endure, to pamper the senseless
luxury or pride of a Ferdinand and a Solyman!
I proceeded, as I had originally determined to do, to
Buda, the metropolis of the kingdom. It was in the hands
of the Turk. It was of little importance to me whether
the monarch of the soil were a Mahometan or a Christian;
my mind was engrossed by considerations of a very different
magnitude. I came to relieve and assist, to the utmost
of my power, the inhabitants of the country in the extremity
of their distress.
I had not proceeded thus far, without bestowing a certain
strictness of reflection on the subject. I easily saw that,
if I would confer a substantial benefit on this unfortunate
nation, I had scarcely any other means for the purpose,
than that of reviving among them a spirit of industry. I
was aware that, in the strictness of the term, money was
not wealth; that it could be neither eaten nor drunk; that
it would not of itself either clothe the naked or shelter the
houseless; and that it was unable, but by a circuitous
operation, to increase the quantity of provisions or commodities
that the country afforded. It was my business
therefore not to proceed idly in the distribution of gold,
but to meditate seriously my plan of operations.
I fixed myself in a spacious and beautiful mansion in
the capital. This in the present distressed and depopulated
condition of Hungary, it was not difficult to procure.
The house I selected had for centuries been the principal
residence of the illustrious family of Ragotski; but the
present representative of that family, after having seen his
sons, one after another, killed in the battles of his country,
and his estates ruined by military depredation, had found
himself compelled to fly in his old age, and had taken refuge
with a distant branch of the same house in the great
duchy of Lithuania. It was not necessary for me to
proceed to any great extent in the first instance in the manufacture
of my wealth; I had every facility for adding
to my store from time to time as circumstances should
demand.
[373]
I determined to open my operations with the article of
building. There was sufficient need of it. One half of
the houses, through most of the districts of Lower, or
Western Hungary in particular, were ruined and untenantable.
I did not begin with erecting palaces; I felt that
the first claimants in the present emergency were the peasant
and the cultivator. I was more desirous that the
rustic than the prince should be well lodged and accommodated,
provided with the means of rest after fatigue,
and secured against the invasion of ungenial seasons.
My reasons for beginning with building were these:—It
was my purpose to stimulate and revive the industry of the
nation: I was desirous of doing this with the least practicable
violence upon the inclinations and freedom of the inhabitants.
Had I required of those to whom I addressed
myself, that they should fertilise the earth, the seeds with
which it should be impregnated might be wanting: I should
have a nice balance to adjust between what was necessary
for immediate subsistence, and what might be applied as
the basis of future; a point better left to its spontaneous
level: I might be impeded and controlled by a thousand
circumstances and at every step. But the materials of
building are to be found in every country; no seasons can
impair, no malignity of man can annihilate them. Wherever
there are quarries, there is stone; wherever there is
clay, there are the means of manufacturing bricks. I was
anxious to leave the rest of the great process of human
accommodation to its course. While I employed labourers,
and paid them their wages, there would be, in the mildest
and most salutary mode, a continual influx of money into
the market. The increase of the precious metals would
give new alacrity to the operations of traffic; the buyers
would come forward with double confidence; the venders
would be eager to meet the activity and spirit of the demand.
Ardour and hope would revisit the human mind;
and the industry I created, and the accommodations of one
kind at least to which I gave birth, would inoculate the
other departments of the community with a similar industry.
I came into Hungary in the spring of 1560; the[374]
season was favourable to seeding and cultivation; I seemed
to enter on my undertaking with the happiest auspices.
Some time however must necessarily elapse between the
period of impregnating the soil, and that of the future harvest.
Though I laid it down therefore as a law to myself,
to commit the least practicable violence upon the genuine
action of human society in pursuit of the means of subsistence,
I thought proper in a certain degree to engage in
the importation of corn from Poland, Silesia, and other
neighbouring countries. This seemed an eligible measure,
if it were only that I might show others the way, and excite
them by my example. I procured agents; I extended
my concerns in various directions over the navigable rivers;
I formed magazines. It would have been contrary to the
genius of my undertaking, either to make a gratuitous distribution
of what I purchased, or to sell it at such low
prices as to drive other speculators, whose spirit of enterprise
might happily co-operate with mine, out of the market.
However indifferent I might feel to the receipt of
pecuniary compensation, it was necessary that, in the concerns
of barter and trade, I should assume the exterior of
a merchant.
Nor did I wholly confine my exertions within the occupations
of an architect and a corn-dealer. These, or
rather the former of the two, I regarded as my true and
genuine province; but I did not so far enslave myself to
my own maxims, as to negative in all instances the direct
demands of want. I was not anxious to convert a nation
or an army of men into my personal adherents and retainers:
I was rather desirous to avoid this as a dangerous
source of obloquy. I did not therefore always decline, by
pretended loans to assist other men to employ labourers as
well as myself, to act upon their own designs, and prosecute
their own fortune. The cries of the poor man, the widow,
and the orphan, were sometimes too importunate, and too
well justified by their unquestionable necessities, to allow
me to withhold from them my alms. In a few instances
I conveyed my supplies anonymously to persons, whose
dignity of birth or whose proud independence would have
been too grievously wounded if they had known their benefactor.[375]
I was cautious and apprehensive as to the direct
dispensing of money, but not entirely bent against it; I
regarded it as a precarious, but in some cases a necessary
interference.
The impulse which, by these various measures, I was
fortunate enough to generate, seemed to have the effect, so
far at least as the sphere of my activity extended, to revive
the almost expiring life of the country. Dejection and
hopeless indolence, when I commenced my operations, were
written in every face; the miserable inhabitants crawled
along the roads or the street, their hands idly relaxed by
their side, and their slow and painful steps scarcely supporting
their lifeless trunk. When my plan became known,
and I had already in a few instances reduced my maxims
into practice, it was as if the mellow and spirit-stirring
blast of a trumpet had wakened their sleeping souls. Their
eyes lightened with intelligence; the tear of anguish was
wiped from their faded cheeks; the smile of hope slowly
expelled, and faintly succeeded to, the bitter expression of
despair. Busy and active thoughts gave new motion to
their limbs and quickness to their steps; the labourer was
seen hastening from place to place; the sound of the hammer,
the saw, and the various tools of the workman, was
to be heard from every side.
The conduct I pursued necessarily fixed upon me a considerable
portion of public attention. I was a foreigner,
destitute of connections, and having no previous acquaintance
with any individual in the country. I was in appearance
a mere boy, a young man in all the flower and
bloom of adolescence, and who must be supposed to have
just entered into possession of his patrimony. These things
tended to increase the public wonder, and to render the
mystery of my proceedings more perplexing and obscure.
In the age of genial warmth and melting softness, I did
not appear accessible to those passions which haunt the
days, and too often undermine the virtues, of youth. Youth
is the season of benevolence; but benevolence is rarely, as
seemed to be my case, the only fruit that youth is found
to produce. There was a maturity and a justness of adaptation
in my plans, not less foreign from what those who[376]
surrounded me would have expected me to display. The
apparent disinterestedness and modesty of my proceedings
were not lost upon the spectators. The consequence of all
this was, that the sieur de Chatillon, such was the name I
at this time assumed, was regarded as a phenomenon which
could not be too much admired, or too loudly extolled.
Wherever I appeared, the people followed me with their
gratitude and blessings; ballads were written in my praise;
the very children were taught with their infant tongues to
lisp the virtues of the saviour of Hungary. My doors
were besieged; my steps were watched; I could move no
where without public observation. I was importuned with
petitions without end; yet, if any petitioner showed himself
presumptuous and intrusive, the whole multitude of
bystanders was ready to repress his indiscretion, and teach
him the respect that was due to their generous benefactor,
who never refused any thing, but what it would be improper
and injurious to grant.
Such was the treatment I experienced in Buda and the
neighbouring districts. Whether I looked within or without,
I was equally presented with incitements to self-approbation.
I sent forth labour, accompanied with her best
and loveliest companions, plenty and health, congratulation
and contentment, to scatter blessings through the land. I
felt that I was prompted to this conduct by none of the
motives of vulgar ambition. I desired neither lordships
nor estates, neither elevation of rank, nor extension of prerogative.
Sufficient to myself, if I effected the happiness
of the people, and they confessed me their benefactor, my
every passion would then be gratified. The utmost boundary
of my personal wishes proceeded no farther than this,
that I might be honoured and loved. What I desired, I
obtained; the youth I had procured to myself through the
medium of the opus magnum, was like what we are told
of the youth of Job:—“When I went out through the
gate of the city, the young men saw me and hid themselves,
and the aged arose and stood up; the nobles refrained from
talking, and the princes laid their hands upon their mouths.
When the ear heard me, then it blessed me; and when
the eye saw me, it gave witness to my actions.”
[377]
Here it may be thought I had ascended to that sphere
which it was fit the possessor of the philosopher’s stone
should fill, and reaped the rewards to which a man thus
endowed ought to be forward to entitle himself. Nor will
I affirm that I was insensible to the gratifications of my
present situation. Though I sought to escape from the
applause that pursued me, yet there is something in the
nature of the human mind, that makes it impossible for us
to hear it without complacence. It was not however a
boisterous and obtrusive acclamation that satisfied me. A
certain inwrought modesty of nature made me listen to
noisy commendations with a sentiment of shame. They
seemed to be more than any thing I had done could deserve;
or they seemed to be in a tone from which the
delicacy of a virtuous mind shrinks back displeased. They
were so obstreperous, as to take from me the power of
hearing the sweeter verdict of my own conscience. No;
it was the unbidden tear that glistened in the eye of my
beneficiaries; the tongue that faltered beneath the essays
of gratitude; the overwhelmed heart that had no power to
express itself; the hand of the parent that was stretched
out to his children, and dumbly said, These, these shall
thank you!—it was these things, that I felt within as the
balsam of my life, and the ambrosia of heaven.
</div></body></text></TEI>