<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="43">CHAPTER XLIII.
EXTINCTION AND CREATION OF SPECIES.
Theory of the successive extinction of species consistent with a limited geographical
distribution—Opinions of botanists respecting the centres from which
plants have been diffused—Whether there are grounds for inferring that the
loss, from time to time, of certain animals and plants, is compensated by the
introduction of new species?—Whether any evidence of such new creations
could be expected within the historical era?—The question whether the existing
species have been created in succession must be decided by geological
monuments.
Successive Extinction of Species consistent with their limited Geographical
Distribution.
In the preceding chapters I have pointed out the strict dependence
of each species of animal and plant on certain physical conditions in
the state of the earth's surface, and on the number and attributes of
other organic beings inhabiting the same region. I have also endeavored
to show that all these conditions are in a state of continual
fluctuation, the igneous and aqueous agents remodelling, from time
to time, the physical geography of the globe, and the migrations of
species causing new relations to spring up successively between different
organic beings. I have deduced as a corollary, that the species existing
at any particular period, must, in the course of ages, become extinct
one after the other. "They must die out," to borrow an emphatical
expression from Buffon, "because Time fights against them."
If the views which I have taken are just, there will be no difficulty in
explaining why the habitations of so many species are now restrained
within exceedingly narrow limits. Every local revolution, such as
those contemplated in the preceding chapter, tends to circumscribe the
range of some species, while it enlarges that of others; and if we are
702
led to infer that new species originate in one spot only, each must
require time to diffuse itself over a wide area. It will follow, therefore,
from the adoption of this hypothesis, that the recent origin of
some species, and the high antiquity of others, are equally consistent
with the general fact of their limited distribution; some being local,
because they have not existed long enough to admit of their wide
dissemination; others, because circumstances in the animate or inanimate
world have occurred to restrict the range which they may once
have obtained. As a general rule, however, species, common to many
distant provinces, or those now found to inhabit very distant parts of
the globe, are to be regarded as the most ancient. Numerically speaking,
they may not perhaps be largely represented, but their wide diffusion
shows that they have had a long time to spread themselves, and
have been able to survive many important revolutions in physical
geography.
After so much evidence has been brought to light by the geologist,
of land and sea having changed places in various regions since the
existing species were in being, we can feel no surprise that the zoologist
and botanist have hitherto found it difficult to refer the geographical
distribution of species to any clear and determinate principles, since
they have usually speculated on the phenomena, upon the assumption
that the physical geography of the globe had undergone no material
alteration since the introduction of the species now living. So long as
this assumption was made, the facts relating to the geography of plants
and animals appeared capricious in the extreme, and by many the subject
was pronounced to be so full of mystery and anomalies, that the
establishment of a satisfactory theory was hopeless.990
Centres from which plants have been diffused.—Some botanists conceived,
in accordance with the hypothesis of Wildenow, that mountains
were the centres of creation from which the plants now inhabiting large
continents have radiated; to which De Candolle and others, with much
reason, objected, that mountains, on the contrary, are often the barriers
between two provinces of distinct vegetation. The geologist who is
acquainted with the extensive modifications which the surface of the
703
earth has undergone in very recent geological epochs, may be able, perhaps,
to reconcile both these theories in their application to different
regions.
A lofty range of mountains, which is so ancient as to date from a
period when the species of animals and plants differed from those now
living, will naturally form a barrier between contiguous provinces; but a
chain which has been raised, in great part, within the epoch of existing
species, and around which new lands have arisen from the sea within
that period, will be a centre of peculiar vegetation.
"In France," observes De Candolle, "the Alps and Cevennes prevent
a great number of the plants of the south from spreading themselves to
the northward; but it has been remarked that some species have made
their way through the gorges of these chains, and are found on their
northern sides, principally in those places where they are lower and more
interrupted."991 Now the chains here alluded to have probably been of
considerable height ever since the era when the existing vegetation began
to appear, and were it not for the deep fissures which divide them, they
might have caused much more abrupt terminations to the extension of
distinct assemblages of species.
Parts of the Italian peninsula, on the other hand, have gained a considerable
portion of their present height since a majority of the marine
species now inhabiting the Mediterranean, and probably, also, since the
terrestrial plants of the same region were in being. Large tracts of land
have been added, both on the Adriatic and Mediterranean side, to what
originally constituted a much narrower range of mountains, if not a chain
of islands running nearly north and south, like Corsica and Sardinia. It
may therefore be presumed that the Apennines have been a centre whence
species have diffused themselves over the contiguous lower and newer
regions. In this and all analogous situations, the doctrine of Wildenow,
that species have radiated from the mountains as from centres, may be
well founded.
Introduction of New Species.
If the reader should infer, from the facts laid before him in the preceding
chapters, that the successive extinction of animals and plants may
be part of the constant and regular course of nature, he will naturally
inquire whether there are any means provided for the repair of these
losses? Is it part of the economy of our system that the habitable globe
should, to a certain extent, become depopulated both in the ocean and
on the land; or that the variety of species should diminish until some
new era arrives when a new and extraordinary effort of creative energy
is to be displayed? Or is it possible that new species can be called into
being from time to time, and yet that so astonishing a phenomenon can
escape the observation of naturalists?
704
Humboldt has characterized these subjects as among the mysteries
which natural science cannot reach; and he observes that the investigation
of the origin of beings does not belong to zoological or botanical
geography. To geology, however, these topics do strictly appertain; and
this science is chiefly interested in inquiries into the state of the animate
creation as it now exists, with a view of pointing out its relations to antecedent
periods when its condition was different.
Before offering any hypothesis towards the solution of so difficult a
problem, let us consider what kind of evidence we ought to expect, in
the present state of science, of the first appearance of new animals or
plants, if we could imagine the successive creation of species to constitute,
like their gradual extinction, a regular part of the economy of nature.
In the first place it is obviously more easy to prove that a species,
once numerously represented in a given district, has ceased to be, than
that some other which did not pre-exist has made its appearance—assuming
always, for reasons before stated, that single stocks only of each
animal and plant are originally created, and that individuals of new
species do not suddenly start up in many different places at once.
So imperfect has the science of natural history remained down to our
own times, that, within the memory of persons now living, the numbers
of known animals and plants have been doubled, or even quadrupled, in
many classes. New and often conspicuous species are annually discovered
in parts of the old continent, long inhabited by the most civilized
nations. Conscious, therefore, of the limited extent of our information,
we always infer, when such discoveries are made, that the beings in
question had previously eluded our research; or had at least existed elsewhere,
and only migrated at a recent period into the territories where we
now find them. It is difficult, even in contemplation, to anticipate the
time when we shall be entitled to make any other hypothesis in regard
to all the marine tribes, and to by far the greater number of the terrestrial;—such
as birds, which possess such unlimited powers of migration;
insects, which, besides the variability of each species in number, are also
so capable of being diffused to vast distances; and cryptogamous plants,
to which, as to many other classes, both of the animal and vegetable
kingdom, similar observations are applicable.
What kind of evidence of new creations could be expected?—What kind
of proofs, therefore, could we reasonably expect to find of the origin at a
particular period of a new species?
Perhaps it may be said in reply that, within the last two or three centuries,
some forest tree or new quadruped might have been observed to
appear suddenly in those parts, of England or France which had been
most thoroughly investigated;—that naturalists might have been able to
show that no such living being inhabited any other region of the globe,
and that there was no tradition of anything similar having before been
observed in the district where it had made its appearance.
Now, although this objection may seem plausible, yet its force will be
found to depend entirely on the rate of fluctuation which we suppose to
705
prevail in the animate world, and on the proportion which such conspicuous
subjects of the animal and vegetable kingdoms bear to those which
are less known and escape our observation. There are, perhaps, more than
a million species of plants and animals, exclusive of the microscopic and
infusory animalcules, now inhabiting the terraqueous globe. The terrestrial
plants may amount, says De Candolle, to somewhere between 110,000
and 120,000;992 but the data on which this conjecture is founded are considered
by many botanists to be vague and unsatisfactory. Sprengel only
enumerated, in 1827, about 31,000 known phænogamous, and 6000
cryptogamous plants; but that naturalist omitted many, perhaps 7000
phænogamous, and 1000 cryptogamous species. Mr. Lindley, in a letter
to the author in 1836, expressed his opinion that it would be rash to
speculate on the existence of more than 80,000 phænogamous, and 10,000
cryptogamous plants. "If we take," he says, in a letter to the author on
this subject, "37,000 as the number of published phænogamous species,
and then add, for the undiscovered species in Asia and New Holland,
15,000, in Africa 10,000, and in America 18,000, we have 80,000 species;
and if 7000 be the number of published cryptogamous plants, and
we allow 3000 for the undiscovered species (making 10,000), there would
then be, on the whole, 90,000 species." But since that period one catalogue,
as I learn from Dr. J. Hooker, contains a list of the names of 78,000
phænogamous plants which had been published before 1841.
It was supposed by Linnæus that there were four or five species of
insects in the world for each phænogamous plant: but if we may judge from
the relative proportion of the two classes in Great Britain, the number of
insects must be still greater; for the total number of British insects,
"according to the last census," is about 12,500;993 whereas there are only
1500 phænogamous plants indigenous to our island. As the insects are
much more numerous in hot countries than in our temperate latitudes, it
seems difficult to avoid the conclusion that there are more than half a
million species in the world.
The number of known mammifers, when Temminck wrote, exceeded
800, and Mr. Waterhouse informs me that more than 1200 are now
(1850) ascertained to exist. Baron Cuvier estimated the amount of known
fishes at 6000; and Mr. G. Gray, in his "Genera of Birds," enumerates
8000 species. We have still to add the reptiles, and all the invertebrated
animals, exclusive of insects. It remains, in a great degree, mere matter
of conjecture what proportion the aquatic tribes may bear to the denizens
of the land; but the habitable surface beneath the waters can hardly be
estimated at less than double that of the continents and islands, even
admitting that a very considerable area is destitute of life, in consequence
of great depth, cold, darkness, and other circumstances. In the late polar
expedition it was found that, in some regions, as in Baffin's Bay, there
were marine animals inhabiting the bottom at great depths, where the
temperature of the water was below the freezing point. That there is
706
life at much greater profundities in warmer regions may be confidently
inferred.
The ocean teems with life—the class of Polyps alone are conjectured
by Lamarck to be as strong in individuals as insects. Every tropical reef
is described as covered with Corals and Sponges, and swarming with
Crustacea, Echini, and Testacea; while almost every tide-washed rock in
the world is carpeted with Fuci, and supports some Corallines, Actiniæ,
and Mollusca. There are innumerable forms in the seas of the warmer
zones, which have scarcely begun to attract the attention of the naturalist;
and there are parasitic animals without number, three or four of which
are sometimes appropriated to one genus, as to the whale (Balæna), for
example. Even though we concede, therefore, that the geographical range
of marine species is more extensive in general than that of the terrestrial (the
temperature of the sea being more uniform, and the land impeding less
the migrations of the oceanic than the ocean those of the terrestrial species),
yet it seems probable that the aquatic tribes far exceed in number
the inhabitants of the land.
Without insisting on this point, it may be safe to assume, that, exclusive
of microscopic beings, there are between one and two millions of
species now inhabiting the terraqueous globe; so that if only one of these
were to become extinct annually, and one new one were to be every year
called into being, much more than a million of years might be required
to bring about a complete revolution in organic life.
I am not hazarding at present any hypothesis as to the probable rate
of change; but none will deny that when the annual birth and the annual
death of one species on the globe is proposed as a mere speculation, this
at least is to imagine no slight degree of instability in the animate creation.
If we divide the surface of the earth into twenty regions of equal
area, one of these might comprehend a space of land and water about
equal in dimensions to Europe, and might contain a twentieth part of the
million of species which may be assumed to exist in the animal kingdom.
In this region one species only would, according to the rate of mortality
before assumed, perish in twenty years, or only five out of fifty thousand
in the course of a century. But as a considerable proportion of the whole
would belong to the aquatic classes, with which we have a very imperfect
acquaintance, we must exclude them from our consideration; and if they
constitute half of the entire number, then one species only might be lost
in forty years among the terrestrial tribes. Now the Mammalia, whether
terrestrial or aquatic, bear so small a proportion to other classes of animals,
forming less, perhaps, than one thousandth part of the whole, that
if the longevity of species in the different orders were equal, a vast period
must elapse before it would come to the turn of this conspicuous class to
lose one of their number. If one species only of the whole animal kingdom
died out in forty years, no more than one mammifer might disappear
in 40,000 years in a region of the dimensions of Europe.
It is easy, therefore, to see, that in a small portion of such an area,
in countries, for example, of the size of England and France, periods of
707
much greater duration must elapse before it would be possible to authenticate
the first appearance of one of the larger plants and animals, assuming
the annual birth and death of one species to be the rate of vicissitude
in the animate creation throughout the world.
The observations of naturalists upon living species may, in the course
of future centuries, accumulate positive data, from which an insight into
the laws which govern this part of our terrestrial system may be derived;
but, in the present deficiency of historical records, we have traced up the
subject to that point where geological monuments alone are capable of
leading us on to the discovery of ulterior truths. To these, therefore, we
must appeal, carefully examining the strata of recent formation wherein
the remains of living species, both animal and vegetable, are known to
occur. We must study these strata in strict reference to their chronological
order, as deduced from their superposition, and other relations. From
these sources we may learn which of the species, now our contemporaries,
have survived the greatest revolutions of the earth's surface; which of
them have co-existed with the greatest number of animals and plants
now extinct; and which have made their appearance only when the animate
world had nearly attained its present condition.
From such data we may be enabled to infer, whether species have been
called into existence in succession, or all at one period; whether singly,
or by groups simultaneously; whether the antiquity of man be as high
as that of any of the inferior beings which now share the planet
with him, or whether the human species is one of the most recent of the
whole.
To some of these questions we can even now return a satisfactory
answer; and with regard to the rest, we have some data to guide conjecture,
and to enable us to speculate with advantage: but in order to be
fully qualified to enter upon such discussions the reader must study the
ample body of materials amassed by the industry of modern geologists.

708</div></body></text></TEI>