<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Vestiges of the Natural History of Creation</title><author>Chambers, Robert (1802-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="20">FOOTNOTES.
[3]  By Mr. Henderson, Professor of
Astronomy in the Edinburgh University, and Lieutenant
Meadows.
[5]  Made by M. Argelander, late
director of the Observatory at Abo.
[6]  Professor Mossotti, on the
Constitution of the Sidereal System, of which the Sun forms a
part.—London, Edinburgh, and Dublin
Philosophical Magazine, February, 1843.
[9]  The orbitual revolutions of the
satellites of Uranus have not as yet been clearly scanned. 
It has been thought that their path is retrograde compared with
the rest.  Perhaps this may be owing to a
bouleversement of the primary, for the inclination of its
equator to the ecliptic is admitted to be unusually high; but the
subject is altogether so obscure, that nothing can be founded on
it.
[12]  Astronomy, Lardner’s
Cyclopædia.
[17]  M. Compte combined
Huygens’s theorems for the measure of centrifugal force
with the law of gravitation, and thus formed a simple fundamental
equation between the duration of the rotation of what he calls
the producing star, and the distance of the star produced. 
The constants of this equation were the radius of the central
star, and the intensity of gravity at its surface, which is a
direct consequence of its mass.  It leads directly to the
third law of Kepler, which thus becomes susceptible of being
conceived à priori in a cosmogonical point of
view.  M. Compte first applied it to the moon, and found, to
his great delight, that the periodic time of that satellite
agrees within an hour or two with the duration which the
revolution of the earth ought to have had at the time when the
lunar distance formed the limit of the earth’s
atmosphere.  He found the coincidence less exact, but still
very striking in every other case.  In those of the planets
he obtained for the duration of the corresponding solar rotations
a value always a little less than their actual periodic
times.  “It is remarkable,” says he, “that
this difference, though increasing as the planet is more distant,
preserves very nearly the same relation to the corresponding
periodic time, of which it commonly forms the forty-fifth
part,”—shewing, we may suppose, that only some small
elements of the question had been overlooked by the
calculator.  The defect changes to an excess in the
different systems of the satellites, where it is proportionally
greater than in the planets, and unequal in the different
systems.  “From the whole of these comparisons,”
says he, “I deduced the following general
result:—Supposing the mathematical limit of the solar
atmosphere successively extended to the regions where the
different planets are now found, the duration of the sun’s
rotation was, at each of these epochs, sensibly equal to that of
the actual sidereal revolution of the corresponding planet; and
the same is true for each planetary atmosphere in relation to the
different satellites.”—Cours de Philosophie
Positif.
[42]  The researches on this subject
were conducted chiefly by the late Baron Fourier, perpetual
secretary to the Academy of Sciences of Paris.  See his
Théorie Analytique de la Chaleur.  1822.
[52]  Delabeche’s Geological
Researches.
[60]  In the Cumbrian limestone occur
“calamoporæ, lithodendra, cyathophylla, and
orbicula.”—Philips.  The asaphus and
trinucleus (crustacea) have been found respectively in the slate
rocks of Wales, and the limestone beds of the grawacke group in
Bohemia.  That fragments of crinoidea, though of no
determinate species, occur in this system, we have the authority
of Mr. Murchison.—Silurian System, p. 710.
[62]  Such as amphioxus and myxene.
[64]  Miller’s “New Walks
in an Old Field.”
[68]  June, 1842.
[84a]  The principal families are named
sphenopteris, neuropteris, and pecopteris.
[84b]  A specimen from Bengal, in the
staircase of the British Museum, is forty-five feet high.
[93]  “Some of the most
considerable dislocations of the border of the coal fields of
Coalbrookdale and Dudley happened after the deposition of a part
of the new red sandstone; but it is certain that those of
Somersetshire and Gloucestershire were completed before the date
of that rock.”—Philips.
[97]  The immediate effects of the slow
respiration of the reptilia are, a low temperature in their
bodies, and a slow consumption of food.  Requiring little
oxygen, they could have existed in an atmosphere containing a
less proportion of that gas to carbonic acid gas than what now
obtains.
[99]  The order to which frogs and
toads belong.
[103]  Dr. Buckland, quoting an article
by Professor Hitchcock, in the American Journal of Science and
Arts, 1836.
[108a]  Murchison’s Silurian
System, p. 583.
[108b] Buckland.
[110]  In some instances, these fossils
are found with the contents of the stomach faithfully preserved,
and even with pieces of the external skin.  The pellets
ejected by them (coprolites) are found in vast numbers,
each generally enclosed in a nodule of ironstone, and sometimes
shewing remains of the fishes which had formed their food.
[114]  De la Beche’s Geological
Researches, p. 344.
[127]  Thick-skinned animals. 
This term has been given by Cuvier to an order in which the hog,
elephant, horse, and rhinoceros are included.
[149]  Intervals in the series were
numerous in the department of the pachydermata; many of these
gaps are now filled up from the extinct genera found in the
tertiary formation.
[151]  See paper by Professor Edward
Forbes, read to the British Association, 1839.
[159]  Macculloch on the Attributes of
the Deity, iii. 569.
[166]  “A glass tube is to be
bent into a syphon, and placed with the curve downwards, and in
the bend is to be placed a small portion of mercury, not
sufficient to close the connexion between the two legs; a
solution of nitrate of silver is then to be introduced until it
rises in both limbs of the tube.  The precipitation of the
mercury, in the form of an Arbor Dianæ, will then take
place, slowly, only when the syphon is placed in a plane
perpendicular to the magnetic meridian; but if it be placed in a
plane coinciding with the magnetic meridian, the action is rapid,
and the crystallization particularly beautiful, taking place
principally in that branch of the syphon towards the north. 
If the syphon be placed in a plane perpendicular to the magnetic
meridian, and a strong magnet brought near it, the precipitation
will commence in a short time, and be most copious in the branch
of the syphon nearest to the south pole of the magnet.”
[169a]  Fatty matter has also been
formed in the laboratory.  The process consisted in passing
a mixture of carbonic acid, pure hydrogen, and carburetted
hydrogen, in the proportion of one measure of the first, twenty
of the second, and ten of the third, through a red-hot tube.
[169b]  Supplement to the Atomic
Theory.
[170]  Carpenter on Life; Todd’s
Cyclopædia of Physiology.
[171]  Carpenter’s Report on the
results obtained by the Microscope in the Study of Anatomy and
Physiology, 1843.
[172]  See Dr. Martin Barry on
Fissiparous Generation; Jameson’s Journal, Oct. 1843. 
Appearances precisely similar have been detected in the germs of
the crustacea.
[175]  Mr. Leonard Horner and Sir David
Brewster, on a substance resembling shell.—Philosophical
Transactions, 1836.
[179a]  Dr. Allen Thomson, in the
article Generation, in Todd’s Cyclopædia of
Anatomy and Physiology.
[179b]  The term aboriginal is here
suggested, as more correct than spontaneous, the one hitherto
generally used.
[182]  Article “Zoophytes,”
Encyclopædia Britannica, 7th edition.
[187]  See a pamphlet circulated by Mr.
Weekes, in 1842.
[195]  Daubenton established the rule,
that all the viviparous quadrupeds have seven vertebræ in
the neck.
[201]  Lord’s Popular
Physiology.  It is to Tiedemann that we chiefly owe these
curious observations; but ground was first broken in this branch
of physiological science by Dr. John Hunter.
[204]  When I formed this idea, I was
not aware of one which seems faintly to foreshadow
it—namely, Socrates’s doctrine, afterwards dilated on
by Plato, that “previous to the existence of the world, and
beyond its present limits, there existed certain archetypes, the
embodiment (if we may use such a word) of general ideas; and that
these archetypes were models, in imitation of which all
particular beings were created.”
[208]  The numbers 1, 3, 6, 10, 15, 21,
28, &c. are formed by adding the successive terms of the
series of natural numbers thus:


1

= 1



1+2

= 3



1+2+3

= 6



l+2+3+4

= 10, &c.



They are called triangular numbers, because a number of points
corresponding to any term can always be placed in the form of a
triangle; for instance—


.

.
..

.
..
...

.
..
...
....



1

3

6

10



[215]  Kirby and Spence.
[221]  See an article by Dr.
Weissenborn, in the New Series of “Magazine of Natural
History,” vol. i. p. 574.
[224]  “It is a fact of the
highest interest and moment that as the brain of every tribe of
animals appears to pass, during its development, in succession
through the types of all those below it, so the brain of man
passes through the types of those of every tribe in the
creation.  It represents, accordingly, before the second
month of utero-gestation, that of an avertebrated animal; at the
second month, that of an osseous fish; at the third, that of a
turtle; at the fourth, that of a bird; at the fifth, that of one
of the rodentia; at the sixth, that of one of the ruminantia; at
the seventh, that of one of the digitigrada; at the eighth, that
of one of the quadrumana; till at length, at the ninth, it
compasses the brain of Man!  It is hardly necessary to say,
that all this is only an approximation to the truth; since
neither is the brain of all osseous fishes, of all turtles, of
all birds, nor of all the species of any one of the above order
of mammals, by any means precisely the same, nor does the brain
of the human fœtus at any time precisely resemble, perhaps,
that of any individual whatever among the lower animals. 
Nevertheless, it may be said to represent, at each of the
above-mentioned periods, the aggregate, as it were, of the brains
of each of the tribes stated; consisting as it does, about the
second month, chiefly of the mesial parts of the cerebellum, the
corpora quadrigemina, thalami optici, rudiments of the
hemispheres of the cerebrum and corpora striata; and receiving in
succession, at the third, the rudiments of the lobes of the
cerebrum; at the fourth, those of the fornix, corpus callosum,
and septum lucidum; at the fifth, the tubor annulare, and so
forth; the posterior lobes of the cerebrum increasing from before
to behind, so as to cover the thalami optici about the fourth
month, the corpora quadrigemina about the sixth, and the
cerebellum about the seventh.  This, then, is another
example of an increase in the complexity of an organ succeeding
its centralization; as if Nature, having first piled up her
materials in one spot, delighted afterwards to employ her
abundance, not so much in enlarging old parts as in forming new
ones upon the old foundations, and thus adding to the complexity
of a fabric, the rudimental structure of which is in all animals
equally simple.”—Fletcher’s Rudiments of
Physiology.
[226]  Project Gutenberg note: the
table in the book is very wide.  Since it won’t fit
within the normal Gutenberg margins, and cannot be reproduced
typographically, the rows of the table have been broken out as
follows.—DP.
Table shows: scale of animal kingdom (the numbers indicate
orders); order of animals in; ascending series of rocks;
fœtal human brain resembles, in
(The numbers indicate orders)
Rocks: 1. Gneiss and Mica Slate system
Fœtal: 1st month, that of an avertebrated animal;
Scale: Radiata (1, 2, 3, 4, 5)
Order: Zoophyta, Polypiaria
Rocks: 2. Clay Slate and Grawacke system
Fœtal: 1st month, that of an avertebrated animal;
Scale: Mollusca (6, 7, 8, 9, 10,
11)
Order: Conchifera, Double-shelled Mollusks
Rocks: 3. Silurian system
Fœtal: 1st month, that of an avertebrated animal;
Scale: Articulata Annelida
(12, 13, 14)
Rocks: 3. Silurian system
Fœtal: 1st month, that of an avertebrated animal;
Scale: Articulata Crustacea
(15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20)
Order: Crustacea, Annelida, Crustaceous Fishes
Rocks: 3. Silurian system
Fœtal: 1st month, that of an avertebrated animal;
Scale: Articulata Arachnida
& Insecta (21–31)
Order: Crustaceous Fishes
Rocks: 4. Old Red Sandstone
Fœtal: 1st month, that of an avertebrated animal;
Scale: Vertebrata Pisces
(32, 33, 34, 35, 36)
Order: True Fishes
Rocks: 5. Carboniferous formation
Fœtal: 2nd month, that of a fish;
Scale: Vertebrata Reptilia
(37, 38, 39, 40)
Order: Piscine Saurians (ichthyosaurus, &c.),
Pterodactyles, Crocodiles, Tortoises, Batrachians
Rocks: 6. New Red Sandstone
Fœtal: 3rd month, that of a turtle;
Scale: Vertebrata Aves (41,
42, 43, 44, 45, 46)
Order: Birds
Rocks: 6. New Red Sandstone
Fœtal: 4th month, that of a bird;
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
47 Cetacea
Order: (Bone of a marsupial animal)
Rocks: 7. Oolite
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
48 Ruminantia
Order: (Bone of a marsupial animal)
Rocks: 8. Cretaceous formation
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
49 Pachydermata
Order: Pachydermata (tapirs, horses, &c.)
Rocks: 9. Lower Eocene
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
50 Edentata
Order: Pachydermata (tapirs, horses, &c.)
Rocks: 9. Lower Eocene
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
51 Rodentia
Order: Rodentia (dormouse, squirrel, &c.)
Rocks: 9. Lower Eocene
Fœtal: 5th month, that of a rodent;
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
52 Marsupialia
Order: Marsupialia (racoon, opossum, &c.)
Rocks: 9. Lower Eocene
Fœtal: 6th month, that of a ruminant;
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
53 Amphibia
Order: Marsupialia (racoon, opossum, &c.)
Rocks: 9. Lower Eocene
Fœtal: 6th month, that of a ruminant;
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
54 Digitigrada
Order: Digitigrada (genette, fox, wolf, &c.)
Rocks: 10. Miocene
Fœtal: 7th month, that of a digitigrade animal;
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
55 Plantigrada
Order: Plantigrada (bear)
Rocks: 10. Miocene
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
55 Plantigrada
Order: Cetacea (lamantins, seals, whales)
Rocks: 10. Miocene
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
56 Insectivora
Order: Edentata (sloths, &c.)
Rocks: 11. Pliocene
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
56 Insectivora
Order: Ruminantia (oxen, deer, &c.)
Rocks: 11. Pliocene
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
57 Cheiroptera
Rocks: 11. Pliocene
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
58 Quadrumana
Order: Quadrumana (monkeys)
Rocks: 11. Pliocene
Fœtal: 8th month, that of the quadrumana;
Scale: Vertebrata Mammalia:
59 Bimana
Order: Bimana (man)
Rocks: 12. Superficial deposits
Fœtal: 9th month, attains full human character;
[229]  Some poor people having taken up
their abode in the cells under the fortifications of Lisle, the
proportion of defective infants produced by them became so great,
that it was deemed necessary to issue an order commanding these
cells to be shut up.
[232]  These affinities and analogies
are explained in the next chapter.
[239a]  Corresponding to the articulata
of Cuvier.
[239b]  A new sub-kingdom, made out of
part of the radiata of Cuvier.
[239c]  This is a newly applied term,
the reasons for which will be explained in the sequel.
[242]  This is preferred to
grallatorial, as more comprehensively descriptive.  There is
the same need for a substitute for rasorial, which is only
applicable to birds.
[246]  Distribution and Classification
of Animals, p. 248.
[255]  Researches, 4th edition, i.
95.
[257]  Prichard.
[266]  Mr. Swainson’s arguments
about the entireness of the circle simiadæ are only too
rigid, for fossil geology has since added new genera to this
group and the cebidæ, and there may be still farther
additions.
[270]  See Wilson’s American
Ornithology; article, Fishing Crow.
[274]  Project Gutenberg note: in the
diagram the triangles extending from the 1,2,3,4 and the a,b,c,d
meet at the same point—the line from the 1,2,3,4 being at
around 45° and the line from the a,b,c,d being at around
60°.  Despite what the text says there is no line
labelled 5 in the diagram.—DP.
[278]  See Dr. Prichard’s
Researches into the Physical History of Man.
[280]  Buckingham’s Travels among
the Arabs.  This fact is the more valuable to the argument,
as having been set down with no regard to any kind of
hypothesis.
[287]  Wiseman’s Lectures on the
Connexion between Science and Revealed Religion, i. 44.  The
Celtic has been established as a member or group of the
Indo-European family, by the work of Dr. Prichard, on the
Eastern Origin of the Celtic Nations. 
“First,” says Dr. Wiseman, “he has examined the
lexical resemblances, and shewn that the primary and most simple
words are the same in both, as well as the numerals and
elementary verbal roots.  Then follows a minute analysis of
the verb, directed to shew its analogies with other languages,
and they are such as manifest no casual coincidence, but an
internal structure radically the same.  The verb
substantive, which is minutely analysed, presents more striking
analogies to the Persian verb than perhaps any other language of
the family.  But Celtic is not thus become a mere member of
this confederacy, but has brought to it most important aid; for,
from it alone can be satisfactorily explained some of the
conjugational endings in the other languages.  For instance,
the third person plural of the Latin, Persian, Greek, and
Sanscrit ends in nt, nd, ντι, ντο,
nti, or nt.  Now, supposing, with most grammarians, that the
inflexions arose from the pronouns of the respective persons, it
is only in Celtic that we find a pronoun that can explain this
termination; for there, too, the same person ends in nt, and thus
corresponds exactly, as do the others, with its pronoun,
hwynt, or ynt.”
[291]  Schoolcraft.
[293]  Views of the Cordilleras.
[302]  The problem of Chinese
civilization, such as it is—so puzzling when we consider
that they are only, as will be presently seen, the child race of
mankind—is solved when we look to geographical position
producing fixity of residence and density of population.
[307a]  Lord’s Popular
Physiology, explaining observations by M. Serres.
[307b]  Conformably to this view, the
beard, that peculiar attribute of maturity, is scanty in the
Mongolian, and scarcely exists in the Americans and Negroes.
[309]  Of this we have perhaps an
illustration in the peculiarities which distinguish the Arabs
residing in the valley of the Jordan.  They have flatter
features, darker skins, and coarser hair than other tribes of
their nation; and we have seen one instance of a thoroughly Negro
family being born to an ordinary couple.  It may be presumed
that the conditions of the life of these people tend to arrest
development.  We thus see how an offshoot of the human
family migrating at an early period into Africa, might in time,
from subjection to similar influences, become Negroes.
[317]  Missionary Scenes and Labours in
South Africa.
[326]  “Is not God the first
cause of matter as well as of mind?  Do not the first
attributes of matter lie as inscrutable in the bosom of
God—of its first author—as those of mind?  Has
not even matter confessedly received from God the power of
experiencing, in consequence of impressions from the earlier
modifications of matter, certain consciousnesses called
sensations of the same?  Is not, therefore, the wonder of
matter also receiving the consciousnesses of other matter called
ideas of the mind a wonder more flowing out of and in analogy
with all former wonders, than would be, on the contrary, the
wonder of this faculty of the mind not flowing out of any
faculties of matter?  Is it not a wonder which, so far from
destroying our hopes of immortality, can establish that doctrine
on a train of inferences and inductions more firmly established
and more connected with each other than the former belief can be,
as soon as we have proved that matter is not perishable, but is
only liable to successive combinations and decombinations.
“Can we look farther back one way into the first origin
of matter than we can look forward the other way into the last
developments of mind?  Can we say that God has not in matter
itself laid the seeds of every faculty of mind, rather than that
he has made the first principle of mind entirely distinct from
that of matter?  Cannot the first cause of all we see and
know have fraught matter itself, from its very
beginning, with all the attributes necessary to develop
into mind, as well as he can have from the first made the
attributes of mind wholly different from those of matter, only in
order afterwards, by an imperceptible and incomprehensible link,
to join the two together?
“ * * [The decombination of the matter on which mind
rests] is this a reason why mind must be annihilated?  Is
the temporary reverting of the mind, and of the sense out of
which that mind developes, to their original component elements,
a reason for thinking that they cannot again at another later
period, and in another higher globe, be again recombined, and
with more splendour than before? * * The New Testament does not
after death here promise us a soul hereafter unconnected with
matter, and which has no connexion with our present mind—a
soul independent of time and space.  That is a fanciful
idea, not founded on its expressions, when taken in their just
and real meaning.  On the contrary, it promises us a mind
like the present, founded on time and space; since it is, like
the present, to hold a certain situation in time, and a certain
locality in space.  But it promises a mind situated in
portions of time and of space different from the present; a mind
composed of elements of matter more extended, more perfect, and
more glorious: a mind which, formed of materials supplied by
different globes, is consequently able to see farther into the
past, and to think farther into the future, than any mind here
existing: a mind which, freed from the partial and uneven
combination incidental to it on this globe, will be exempt from
the changes for evil to which, on the present globe, mind as well
as matter is liable, and will only thenceforth experience the
changes for the better which matter, more justly poised, will
alone continue to experience: a mind which, no longer fearing the
death, the total decomposition, to which it is subject on this
globe, will thenceforth continue last and
immortal.”—Hope, on the
Origin and Prospects of Man, 1831.
[331]  Dublin Review, Aug. 1840. 
The Guarantee Society has since been established, and is likely
to become a useful and prosperous institution.
[333]  The ray, which is considered the
lowest in the scale of fishes, or next to the crustaceans, gives
the first faint representation of a brain in certain scanty and
medullary masses, which appear as merely composed of enlarged
origins of the nerves.
[335]  If mental action is electric,
the proverbial quickness of thought—that is, the quickness
of the transmission of sensation and will—may be presumed
to have been brought to an exact measurement.  The speed of
light has long been known to be about 192,000 miles per second,
and the experiments of Wheatstone have shewn that the electric
agent travels (if I may so speak) at the same rate, thus shewing
a likelihood that one law rules the movements of all the
“imponderable bodies.”  Mental action may
accordingly be presumed to have a rapidity equal to one hundred
and ninety-two thousand miles in the second—a rate
evidently far beyond what is necessary to make the design and
execution of any of our ordinary muscular movements apparently
identical in point of time, which they are.
[346]  Phrenological Journal, xv.
338.
[347]  A pampered lap-dog, living where
there is another of its own species, will hide any nice morsel
which it cannot eat, under a rug, or in some other by-place,
designing to enjoy it afterwards.  I have seen children do
the same thing.
</div></body></text></TEI>