<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="38">
CHAPTER VI.

On Deductive Habits;
or, on the Impression produced
on Men’s Minds by tracing the consequences of ascertained
Laws.

The opinion illustrated in the last chapter, that
the advances which men make in science tend to impress
upon them the reality of the Divine government
of the world, has often been controverted.[244]
Complaints have been made, and especially of late
years, that the growth of piety has not always been
commensurate with the growth of knowledge, in the
minds of those who make nature their study. Views
of an irreligious character have been entertained, it
is sometimes said, by persons eminently well instructed
in all the discoveries of modern times, no
less than by the superficial and ignorant. Those
who have been supposed to deny or to doubt the existence,
the providence, the attributes of God, have
in many cases been men of considerable eminence
and celebrity for their attainments in science. The
opinion that this is the case, appears to be extensively
diffused, and this persuasion has probably often
produced inquietude and grief in the breasts of pious
and benevolent men.
This opinion, concerning the want of religious
convictions among those who have made natural
philosophy their leading pursuit, has probably gone
far beyond the limits of the real fact. But if we
allow that there are any strong cases to countenance
such an opinion, it may be worth our while to consider
how far they admit of any satisfactory explanation.
The fact appears at first sight to be at variance
with the view we have given of the impression
produced by scientific discovery; and it is moreover
always a matter of uneasiness and regret, to have
men of eminent talents and knowledge opposed to
doctrines which we consider as important truths.
We conceive that an explanation of such cases,
if they should occur, may be found in a very curious
and important circumstance belonging to the
process by which our physical sciences are formed.
The first discovery of new general truths, and the
developement of these truths when once obtained,
are two operations extremely different; imply different
mental habits, and may easily be associated with
different views and convictions on points out of the
reach of scientific demonstration. There would
therefore be nothing surprising, or inconsistent with[245]
what we have maintained above, if it should appear
that while original discoverers of laws of nature are
peculiarly led, as we have seen, to believe the existence
of a supreme intelligence and purpose; the
far greater number of cultivators of science, whose
employment it is to learn from others these general
laws, and to trace, combine, and apply their consequences,
should have no clearness of conviction or
security from error on this subject, beyond what belongs
to persons of any other class.
This will, perhaps, become somewhat more evident
by considering a little more closely the distinction
of the two operations of discovery and developement,
of which we have spoken above, and the
tendency which the habitual prosecution of them
may be expected to produce in the thoughts and
views of the student.
We have already endeavoured in some measure to
describe that which takes place when a new law of
nature is discovered. A number of facts in which,
before, order and connexion did not appear at all, or
appeared by partial and contradictory glimpses, are
brought into a point of view in which order and connexion
become their essential character. It is seen
that each fact is but a different manifestation of the
same principle; that each particular is that which it
is, in virtue of the same general truth. The inscription
is deciphered; the enigma is guessed; the principle
is understood; the truth is enunciated.
When this step is once made, it becomes possible
to deduce from the truth thus established, a train of
consequences often in no small degree long and complex.
The process of making these inferences may
properly be described by the word Deduction, while
the very different process by which a new principle
is collected from an assemblage of facts, has been
termed Induction; the truths so obtained and their
consequences constitute the results of the Inductive
Philosophy; which is frequently and rightly described
as a science which ascends from particular facts to[246]
general principles, and then descends again from
these general principles to particular applications and
exemplifications.
While the great and important labours by which
science is really advanced consist in the successive
steps of the inductive ascent in the discovery of new
laws perpetually more and more general; by far the
greater part of our books of physical science unavoidably
consists in deductive reasoning, exhibiting
the consequences and applications of the laws which
have been discovered; and the greater part of writers
upon science have their minds employed in this process
of deduction and application.
This is true of many of those who are considered,
and justly, as distinguished and profound philosophers.
In the mechanical philosophy, that science
which applies the properties of matter and the
laws of motion to the explanation of the phenomena
of the world, this is peculiarly the case. The laws,
when once discovered, occupy little room in their
statement, and when no longer contested, are not
felt to need a lengthened proof. But their consequences
require far more room and far more intellectual
labour. If we take, for example, the laws of
motion and the law of universal gravitation, we can
express in a few lines, that which, when developed,
represents and explains an innumerable mass of natural
phenomena. But here the course of developement
is necessarily so long, the reasoning contains
so many steps, the considerations on which it rests
are so minute and refined, the complication of cases
and of consequences is so vast, and even the involution
arising from the properties of space and number
so serious, that the most consummate subtlety, the
most active invention, the most tenacious power of
inference, the widest spirit of combination, must be
tasked and tasked severely, in order to solve the
problems which belong to this portion of science.
And the persons who have been employed on these
problems, and who have brought to them the high[247]
and admirable qualities which such an office requires,
have justly excited in a very eminent degree the admiration
which mankind feel for great intellectual
powers. Their names occupy a distinguished place in
literary history; and probably there are no scientific
reputations of the last century higher, and none more
merited, than those earned by the great mathematicians
who have laboured with such wonderful success
in unfolding the mechanism of the heavens; such
for instance as D’Alembert, Clairault, Euler, Lagrange,
Laplace.
But it is still important to recollect, that the mental
employments of men, while they are occupied in
this portion of the task of the formation of science,
are altogether different from that which takes place
in the mind of a discoverer, who, for the first time,
seizes the principle which connects phenomena before
unexplained, and thus adds another original
truth to our knowledge of the universe. In explaining,
as the great mathematicians just mentioned have
done, the phenomena of the solar system by means
of the law of universal gravitation, the conclusions
at which they arrived were really included in the
truth of the law itself, whatever skill and sagacity it
might require to develope and extricate them from
the general principle. But when Newton conceived
and established the law itself, he added to our knowledge
something which was not contained in any
truth previously known, nor deducible from it by any
course of mere reasoning. And the same distinction,
in all other cases, obtains, between these processes
which establish the principles, generally few and
simple, on which our sciences rest, and those reasonings
and calculations, founded on the principles
thus obtained, which constitute by far the larger portion
of the common treatises on the most complete of
the sciences now cultivated.
Since the difference is so great between the process
of inductive generalization of physical facts, and
that of mathematical deduction of consequences, it is[248]
not surprising that the two processes should imply
different mental powers and habits. However rare
the mathematical talent, in its highest excellence,
may be, it is far more common, if we are to judge
from the history of science, than the genius which
divines the general laws of nature. We have several
good mathematicians in every age; we have few
great discoverers in the whole history of our species.
The distinction being thus clearly established between
original discovery and derivative speculation,
between the ascent to principles and the descent from
them, we have further to observe, that the habitual
and exclusive prosecution of the latter process may
sometimes exercise an unfavourable effect on the
mind of the student, and may make him less fitted
and ready to apprehend and accept truths different
from those with which his reasonings are concerned.
We conceive, for example, that a person labours
under gross error, who believes the phenomena of
the world to be altogether produced by mechanical
causes, and who excludes from his view all reference
to an intelligent First Cause and Governor. But we
conceive that reasons may be shown which make it
more probable that error of such a kind should find
a place in the mind of a person of deductive, than of
inductive habits;—of a mere mathematician or logician,
than of one who studies the facts of the natural
world and detects their laws.
The person whose mind is employed in reducing
to law and order and intelligible cause the complex
facts of the material world, is compelled to look beyond
the present state of his knowledge, and to turn
his thoughts to the existence of principles higher than
those which he yet possesses. He has seen occasions
when facts that at first seemed incoherent and anomalous,
were reduced to rule and connexion; and
when limited rules were discovered to be included in
some rule of superior generality. He knows that all
facts and appearances, all partial laws, however confused[249]
and casual they at present seem, must still, in
reality, have this same kind of bearing and dependence;—must
be bound together by some undiscovered
principle of order;—must proceed from some cause
working by most steady rules;—must be included in
some wide and fruitful general truth. He cannot
therefore consider any principles which he has already
obtained, as the ultimate and sufficient reason
of that which he sees. There must be some higher
principle, some ulterior reason. The effort and struggle
by which he endeavours to extend his view, makes
him feel that there is a region of truth not included
in his present physical knowledge; the very imperfection
of the light in which he works his way, suggests
to him that there must be a source of clearer
illumination at a distance from him.
We must allow that it is scarcely possible to describe
in a manner free from some vagueness and
obscurity, the effect thus produced upon the mind by
the efforts which it makes to reduce natural phenomena
to general laws. But we trust it will still be
allowed that there is no difficulty in seeing clearly
that a different influence may result from this process,
and from the process of deductive reasoning
which forms the main employment of the mathematical
cultivators and systematic expositors of physical
science in modern times. Such persons are not
led by their pursuits to any thing beyond the general
principles, which form the basis of their explanations
and applications. They acquiesce in these; they
make these their ultimate grounds of truth; and they
are entirely employed in unfolding the particular
truths which are involved in the general truth.
Their thoughts dwell little upon the possibility of the
laws of nature being other than we find them to be,
or on the reasons why they are not so; and still less
on those facts and phenomena which philosophers
have not yet reduced to any rule; which are lawless to
us, though we know that, in reality, they are governed
by some principle of order and harmony. On the[250]
contrary, by assuming perpetually the existing laws
as the basis of their reasoning, without question or
doubt, and by employing such language that these
laws can be expressed in the simplest and briefest
form, they are led to think and believe as if these
laws were necessarily and inevitably what they are.
Some mathematicians indeed have maintained that
the highest laws of nature with which we are acquainted,
the laws of motion and the law of universal
gravitation, are not only necessarily true, but are
even self-evident and certain à priori, like the truths
of geometry. And though the mathematical cultivator
of the science of mechanics may not adopt this
as his speculative opinion, he may still be so far influenced
by the tendency from which it springs, as
to rest in the mechanical laws of the universe as ultimate
and all-sufficient principles, without seeing in
them any evidence of their having been selected and
ordained, and thus without ascending from the world
to the thought of an Intelligent Ruler. He may thus
substitute for the Deity certain axioms and first principles,
as the cause of all. And the follower of Newton
may run into the error with which he is sometimes
charged, of thrusting some mechanic cause
into the place of God, if he do not raise his views,
as his master did, to some higher cause, to some
source of all forces, laws, and principles.
When, therefore, we consider the mathematicians
who are employed in successfully applying the mechanical
philosophy, as men well deserving of honour
from those who take an interest in the progress of science,
we do rightly; but it is still to be recollected, that
in doing this they are not carrying us to any higher
point of view in the knowledge of nature than we had
attained before: they are only unfolding the consequences,
which were already virtually in our possession,
because they were implied in principles already
discovered:—they are adding to our knowledge of
effects, but not to our knowledge of causes:—they
are not making any advance in that progress of[251]
which Newton spoke, and in which he made so vast
a stride, in which “every step made brings us nearer
to the knowledge of the first cause, and is on that
account highly to be valued.” And as in this advance
they have no peculiar privileges or advantages,
their errors of opinion concerning it, if they
err, are no more to be wondered at, than those of
common men; and need as little disturb or distress
us, as if those who committed them had confined
themselves to the study of arithmetic or of geometry.
If we can console and tranquillize ourselves concerning
the defective or perverted views of religious
truth entertained by any of our fellow men, we need
find no additional difficulty in doing so when those
who are mistaken are great mathematicians, who
have added to the riches and elegance of the mechanical
philosophy. And if we are seeking for extraneous
grounds of trust and comfort on this subject,
we may find them in the reflection;—that, whatever
may be the opinions of those who assume the causes
and laws of that philosophy and reason from them, the
views of those admirable and ever-honoured men who
first caught sight of these laws and causes, impressed
them with the belief that this is “the fabric of a great
and good God;” that “it is man’s duty to pour out
his soul in praise of the Creator;” and that all this
beautiful system must be referred to “a first cause,
which is certainly not mechanical.”
2. We may thus, with the greatest propriety, deny
to the mechanical philosophers and mathematicians
of recent times any authority with regard to their
views of the administration of the universe; we have
no reason whatever to expect from their speculations
any help, when we attempt to ascend to the first
cause and supreme ruler of the universe. But we
might perhaps go further, and assert that they are
in some respects less likely than men employed in
other pursuits, to make any clear advance towards
such a subject of speculation. Persons whose thoughts
are thus entirely occupied in deduction are apt to[252]
forget that this is, after all, only one employment of
the reason among more; only one mode of arriving
at truth, needing to have its deficiencies completed
by another. Deductive reasoners, those who cultivate
science, of whatever kind, by means of mathematical
and logical processes alone, may acquire
an exaggerated feeling of the amount and value of
their labours. Such employments, from the clearness
of the notions involved in them, the irresistible
concatenation of truths which they unfold, the subtlety
which they require, and their entire success in
that which they attempt, possess a peculiar fascination
for the intellect. Those who pursue such studies
have generally a contempt and impatience of the
pretensions of all those other portions of our knowledge,
where from the nature of the case, or the
small progress hitherto made in their cultivation, a
more vague and loose kind of reasoning seems to be
adopted. Now if this feeling be carried so far as to
make the reasoner suppose that these mathematical
and logical processes can lead him to all the knowledge
and all the certainty which we need, it is
clearly a delusive feeling. For it is confessed on all
hands, that all which mathematics or which logic
can do, is to develope and extract those truths, as
conclusions, which were in reality involved in the
principles on which our reasonings proceeded.[38]
And this being allowed, we cannot but ask how we
obtain these principles? from what other source of
knowledge we derive the original truths which we
thus pursue into detail? since it is manifest that such
principles cannot be derived from the proper stores
of mathematics or logic. These methods can generate
no new truth; and all the grounds and elements[253]
of the knowledge which, through them, we can acquire,
must necessarily come from some extraneous
source. It is certain, therefore, that the mathematician
and the logician must derive from some process
different from their own, the substance and
material of all our knowledge, whether physical or
metaphysical, physiological or moral. This process,
by which we acquire our first principles, (without
pretending here to analyse it,) is obviously the general
course of human experience, and the natural
exercise of the understanding; our intercourse with
matter and with men, and the consequent growth in
our minds of convictions and conceptions such as
our reason can deal with, either by her systematic
or unsystematic methods of procedure. Supplies
from this vast and inexhaustible source of original
truths are requisite, to give any value whatever to
the results of our deductive processes, whether mathematical
or logical; while on the other hand, there
are many branches of our knowledge, in which we
possess a large share of original and derivative convictions
and truths, but where it is nevertheless at
present quite impossible to erect our knowledge into
a complete system;—to state our primary and independent
truths, and to show how on these all the rest
depend by the rules of art. If the mathematician is
repelled from speculations on morals or politics, on
the beautiful or the right, because the reasonings
which they involve have not mathematical precision
and conclusiveness, he will remain destitute of much
of the most valuable knowledge which man can acquire.
And if he attempts to mend the matter by
giving to treatises on morals, or politics, or criticism,
a form and a phraseology borrowed from the very
few tolerably complete physical sciences which exist,
it will be found that he is compelled to distort and
damage the most important truths, so as to deprive
them of their true shape and import, in order to force
them into their places in his artificial system.
If therefore, as we have said, the mathematical[254]
philosopher dwells in his own bright and pleasant
land of deductive reasoning, till he turns with disgust
from all the speculations, necessarily less clear and
conclusive, in which his imagination, his practical
faculties, his moral sense, his capacity of religious
hope and belief, are to be called into action, he becomes,
more than common men, liable to miss the
road to truths of extreme consequence.
This is so obvious, that charges are frequently
brought against the study of mathematics, as unfitting
men for those occupations which depend upon our
common instinctive convictions and feelings, upon
the unsystematic exercise of the understanding with
regard to common relations and common occurrences.
Bonaparte observed of Laplace, when he
was placed in a public office of considerable importance,
that he did not discharge it in so judicious and
clear sighted a manner as his high intellectual fame
might lead most persons to expect.[39] “He sought,”
that great judge of character said, “subtleties in
every subject, and carried into his official employments
the spirit of the method of infinitely small
quantities,” by which the mathematician solves his
more abstruse problems. And the complaint that
mathematical studies make men insensible to moral
evidence and to poetical beauties, is so often repeated
as to show that some opposition of tendency is
commonly perceived between that exercise of the intellect
which mathematics requires and those processes
which go on in our minds when moral character
or imaginative beauty is the subject of our contemplation.
[255]
Thus, while we acknowledge all the beauty and
all the value of the mathematical reasonings by
which the consequences of our general laws are deduced,
we may yet consider it possible that a philosopher,
whose mind has been mainly employed, and
his intellectual habits determined, by this process of
deduction, may possess, in a feeble and imperfect degree
only, some of those faculties by which truth is
attained, and especially those truths which regard
our relation to that mind, the origin of all law, the
source of first principles, which must be immeasurably
elevated above all derivative truths. It would,
therefore, be far from surprising, if there should be
found, among the great authors of the developements
of the mechanical philosophy, some who had refused
to refer the phenomena of the universe to a supreme
mind, purpose, and will. And though this world be,
to a believer in the Being and government of God, a
matter of sorrow and pain, it need not excite more
surprise than if the same were true of a person of
the most ordinary endowments, when it is recollected
in what a disproportionate manner the various
faculties of such a philosopher may have been cultivated.
And our apprehensions of injury to mankind
from the influence of such examples will diminish,
when we consider, that those mathematicians
whose minds have been less partially exercised,
the great discoverers of the truths which others
apply, the philosophers who have looked upwards as
well as downwards, to the unknown as well as to
the known, to ulterior as well as proximate principles,
have never rested in this narrow and barren
doctrine; but have perpetually looked forwards, beyond
mere material laws and causes, to a First
Cause of the moral and material world, to which
each advance in philosophy might bring them nearer,
though it must ever remain indefinitely beyond their
reach.
It scarcely needs, perhaps, to be noticed, that what
we here represent as the possible source of error is,[256]
not the perfection of the mathematical habits of the
mind, but the deficiency of the habit of apprehending
truth of other kinds;—not a clear insight into the
mathematical consequences of principles, but a want
of a clear view of the nature and foundation of
principles;—not the talent for generalizing geometrical
or mechanical relations, but the tendency to
erect such relations into ultimate truths and efficient
causes. The most consummate mathematical skill
may accompany and be auxiliary to the most earnest
piety, as it often has been. And an entire command
of the conceptions and processes of mathematics is
not only consistent with, but is the necessary condition
and principal instrument of every important
step in the discovery of physical principles. Newton
was eminent above the philosophers of his time, in
no one talent so much as in the power of mathematical
deduction. When he had caught sight of the law
of universal gravitation, he traced it to its consequences
with a rapidity, a dexterity, a beauty of
mathematical reasoning which no other person could
approach; so that on this account, if there had been
no other, the establishment of the general law was
possible to him alone. He still stands at the head of
mathematicians as well as of philosophical discoverers.
But it never appeared to him, as it may have
appeared to some mathematicians who have employed
themselves on his discoveries, that the general
law was an ultimate and sufficient principle: that
the point to which he had hung his chain of deduction
was the highest point in the universe. Lagrange,
a modern mathematician of transcendent genius, was
in the habit of saying, in his aspirations after future
fame, that Newton was fortunate in having had the
system of the world for his problem, since its theory
could be discovered once only. But Newton himself
appears to have had no such persuasion that the
problem he had solved was unique and final: he
laboured to reduce gravity to some higher law, and
the forces of other physical operations to an analogy[257]
with those of gravity, and declared that all these
were but steps in our advance towards a first cause.
Between us and this first cause, the source of the
universe and of its laws, we cannot doubt that there
intervene many successive steps of possible discovery
and generalization, not less wide and striking than
the discovery of universal gravitation: but it is still
more certain that no extent or success of physical
investigation can carry us to any point which is not
at an immeasurable distance from an adequate knowledge
of Him.
</div></body></text></TEI>