<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="15">

CHAPTER VI.
Of the Perception of Space.



1. ACCORDING
to the views above explained, certain of the
impressions of our senses convey to us the perception of
objects as existing in space; inasmuch as by the
constitution of our minds we cannot receive those
impressions otherwise than in a certain form, involving such
a manner of existence. But the question deserves to be
asked, What are the impressions of sense by which
we thus become acquainted with space and its relations? And
as we have seen that this idea of space implies an act of
the mind as well as an impression on the sense, what
manifestations do we find of this activity of the mind, in
our observation of the external world?
It is evident that sight and touch are the senses by which
the relations of space are perceived, principally or
entirely. It does not appear that an odour, or a feeling of
warmth or cold, would, independently of experience, suggest
to us the conception of a space surrounding us. But when we
see objects, we see that they are extended and
occupy space; when we touch them, we feel that they
are in a space in which we also are. We have before our eyes
any object, for instance, a board covered with geometrical
diagrams; and we distinctly perceive, by vision, those lines
of which the relations are the subjects of our mathematical
reasoning. Again, we see before us a solid object, a cubical
box for instance; we see that it is within reach; we stretch
out the hand and perceive by the touch that it has sides,
edges, corners, which we had already perceived by vision. 118
2. Probably most persons do not generally apprehend that
there is any material difference in these two cases;—that
there are any different acts of mind concerned in perceiving
by sight a mathematical diagram upon paper, and a solid cube
lying on a table. Yet it is not difficult to show that, in
the latter case at least, the perception of the shape of the
object is not immediate. A very little attention teaches us
that there is an act of judgment as well as a mere
impression of sense requisite, in order that we may see any
solid object. For there is no visible appearance which is
inseparably connected with solidity. If a picture of a cube
be rightly drawn, in perspective and skilfully shaded, the
impression upon the sense is the same as if it were a real
cube. The picture may be mistaken for a solid object. But it
is clear that, in this case, the solidity is given to the
object by an act of mental judgment. All that is seen is
outline and shade, figures and colours on a flat board. The
solid angles and edges, the relation of the faces of the
figure by which they form a cube, are matters of inference.
This, which is evident in the case of the pictured cube, is
true in all vision whatever. We see a scene before us on
which are various figures and colours, but the eye cannot
see more. It sees length and breadth, but no third
dimension. In order to know that there are solids, we must
infer as well as see. And this we do readily and constantly;
so familiarly, indeed, that we do not perceive the
operation. Yet we may detect this latent process in many
ways; for instance, by attending to cases in which the habit
of drawing such inferences misleads us. Most persons have
experienced this delusion in looking at a scene in a
theatre, and especially that kind of scene which is called a
diorama, when the interior of a building is
represented. In these cases, the perspective representations
of the various members of the architecture and decoration
impress us almost irresistibly with the conviction that we
have before us a space of great extent and complex form,
instead of a flat painted canvass. Here, at least, the space
is our own creation; but yet here, it is 119 manifestly
created by the same act of thought as if we were really in
the palace or the cathedral of which the halls and aisles
thus seem to inclose us. And the act by which we thus create
space of three dimensions out of visible extent of length
and breadth, is constantly and imperceptibly going on. We
are perpetually interpreting in this manner the language of
the visible world. From the appearances of things which we
directly see, we are constantly inferring that which we
cannot directly see,—their distance from us, and the
position of their parts.
3. The characters which we thus interpret are various. They
are, for instance, the visible forms, colours, and shades of
the parts, understood according to the maxims of
perspective; (for of perspective every one has a practical
knowledge, as every one has of grammar;) the effort by which
we fix both our eyes on the same object, and adjust each eye
to distinct vision; and the like. The right interpretation
of the information which such circumstances give us
respecting the true forms and distances of things, is
gradually learned; the lesson being begun in our earliest
infancy, and inculcated upon us every hour during which we
use our eyes. The completeness with which the lesson is
mastered is truly admirable; for we forget that our
conclusion is obtained indirectly, and mistake a judgment on
evidence for an intuitive perception. We see the breadth of
the street, as clearly and readily as we see the house on
the other side of it; and we see the house to be square,
however obliquely it be presented to us. This, however, by
no means throws any doubt or difficulty on the doctrine that
in all these cases we do interpret and infer. The rapidity
of the process, and the unconsciousness of the effort, are
not more remarkable in this case than they are when we
understand the meaning of the speech which we hear, or of
the book which we read. In these latter cases we merely hear
noises or see black marks; but we make, out of these
elements, thought and feeling, without being aware of the
act by which we do so. And by an exactly similar process we
see a variously-coloured 120 expanse, and collect from it
a space occupied by solid objects. In both cases the act of
interpretation is become so habitual that we can hardly stop
short at the mere impression of sense.
4. But yet there are various ways in which we may satisfy
ourselves that these two parts of the process of seeing
objects are distinct. To separate these operations is
precisely the task which the artist has to execute, in
making a drawing of what he sees. He has to recover the
consciousness of his real and genuine sensations, and to
discern the lines of objects as they appear. This at first
he finds difficult; for he is tempted to draw what he knows
of the forms of visible objects, and not what he sees: but
as he improves in his art, he learns to put on paper what he
sees only, separated from what he infers, in order that thus
the inference, and with it a conception like that of the
reality, may be left to the spectator. And thus the natural
process of vision is the habit of seeing that which cannot
be seen; and the difficulty of the art of drawing consists
in learning not to see more than is visible.
5. But again; even in the simplest drawing we exhibit
something which we do not see. However slight is our
representation of objects, it contains something which we
create for ourselves. For we draw an outline. Now
an outline has no existence in nature. There are no visible
lines presented to the eye by a group of figures. We
separate each figure from the rest, and the boundary by
which we do this is the outline of the figure; and the like
may be said of each member of every figure. A painter of our
own times has made this remark in a work upon his art4:
‘The effect which natural objects produce upon our sense of
vision is that of a number of parts, or distinct masses of
form and colour, and not of lines. But when we endeavour to
represent by painting the objects which are before us, or
which invention supplies to our minds, 121 the first and
the simplest means we resort to is this picture, by which we
separate the form of each object from those that surround
it, marking its boundary, the extreme extent of its
dimensions in every direction, as impressed on our vision:
and this is termed drawing its outline.’</div></body></text></TEI>