<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="24">
CHAPTER V.

The Satellites.

1. A person of ordinary feelings, who, on a fine
moonlight night, sees our satellite pouring her mild
radiance on field and town, path and moor, will probably
not only be disposed to “bless the useful light,”
but also to believe that it was “ordained” for that
purpose;—that the lesser light was made to rule the
night as certainly as the greater light was made to
rule the day.
Laplace, however, does not assent to this belief.
He observes, that “some partisans of final causes
have imagined that the moon was given to the earth
to afford light during the night:” but he remarks that
this cannot be so, for that we are often deprived at
the same time of the light of the sun and the moon;
and he points out how the moon might have been
placed so as to be always “full.”
That the light of the moon affords, to a certain extent,
a supplement to the light of the sun, will hardly
be denied. If we take man in a condition in which
he uses artificial light scantily only, or not at all,
there can be no doubt that the moonlight nights are
for him a very important addition to the time of
daylight. And as a small proportion only of the
whole number of nights are without some portion of
moonlight, the fact that sometimes both luminaries
are invisible very little diminishes the value of this
advantage. Why we have not more moonlight,[138]
either in duration or in quantity, is an inquiry which
a philosopher could hardly be tempted to enter upon,
by any success which has attended previous speculations
of a similar nature. Why should not the moon
be ten times as large as she is? Why should not the
pupil of man’s eye be ten times as large as it is, so
as to receive more of the light which does arrive?
We do not conceive that our inability to answer the
latter question prevents our knowing that the eye was
made for seeing: nor does our inability to answer
the former, disturb our persuasion that the moon was
made to give light upon the earth.
Laplace suggests that if the moon had been placed
at a certain distance beyond the earth, it would have
revolved about the sun in the same time as the earth
does, and would have always presented to us a full
moon. For this purpose it must have been about four
times as far from us as it really is; and would therefore,
other things remaining unchanged, have only
been one sixteenth as large to the eye as our present
full moon. We shall not dwell on the discussion of
this suggestion, for the reason just intimated. But
we may observe that in such a system as Laplace
proposes, it is not yet proved, we believe, that the
arrangement would be stable under the influence of
the disturbing forces. And we may add that such
an arrangement, in which the motion of one body
has a co-ordinate reference to two others, as the motion
of the moon on this hypothesis would have to
the sun and the earth, neither motion being subordinate
to the other, is contrary to the whole known
analogy of cosmical phenomena, and therefore has
no claim to our notice as a subject of discussion.
2. In turning our consideration to the satellites of
the other planets of our system, there is one fact
which immediately arrests our attention;—the number
of such attendant bodies appears to increase as
we proceed to planets farther and farther from the
sun. Such at least is the general rule. Mercury and
Venus, the planets nearest the sun, have no such attendants:[139]
the Earth has one. Mars, indeed, who is
still farther removed, has none; nor have the minor
planets, Juno, Vesta, Ceres, Pallas; so that the rule
is only approximately verified. But Jupiter, who is
at five times the earth’s distance, has four satellites;
and Saturn, who is again at a distance nearly twice
as great, has seven, besides that most extraordinary
phenomenon his ring, which, for purposes of illumination,
is equivalent to many thousand satellites. Of
Uranus it is difficult to speak, for his great distance
renders it almost impossible to observe the smaller
circumstances of his condition. It does not appear
at all probable that he has a ring, like Saturn; but
he has at least five satellites which are visible to us,
at the enormous distance of nine hundred millions of
miles; and we believe that the astronomer will hardly
deny that he may possibly have thousands of smaller
ones circulating about him.
But leaving conjecture, and taking only the ascertained
cases of Venus, the Earth, Jupiter, and Saturn,
we conceive that a person of common understanding
will be strongly impressed with the persuasion that
the satellites are placed in the system with a view to
compensate for the diminished light of the sun at
greater distances. The smaller planets, Juno, Vesta,
Ceres, and Pallas, differ from the rest in so many
ways, and suggest so many conjectures of reasons
for such differences, that we should almost expect to
find them exceptions to such a rule. Mars is a more
obvious exception. Some persons might conjecture
from his case, that the arrangement itself, like other
useful arrangements, has been brought about by
some wider law which we have not yet detected.
But whether or not we entertain such a guess, (it can
be nothing more,) we see in other parts of creation,
so many examples of apparent exceptions to rules,
which are afterwards found to be explained, or provided
for by particular contrivances, that no one,
familiar with such contemplations, will, 
by one anomaly,[140]
be driven from the persuasion that the end
which the arrangements of the satellites seem suited
to answer is really one of the ends of their creation.
</div></body></text></TEI>