<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="113">CHAPTER IX.
Attempts at the Reform of Mineralogical
Systems.—Separation of the Chemical and Natural History
Methods.

Sect. 1.—Natural History System of
Mohs.
THE chemical principle of
classification, if pursued at random, as in the cases just spoken of
leads to results at which a philosophical spirit revolts; it separates
widely substances which are not distinguishable; joins together bodies
the most dissimilar; and in hardly any instance does it bring any
truth into view. The vices of classifications like that of Haüy could
not long be concealed; but even before time had exposed the weakness
of his system, Haüy himself had pointed out, clearly and without
reserve,46 that a chemical system is only one side
of the subject, and supposes, as its counterpart, a science of
external characters. In the mean time, the Wernerians were becoming
more and more in love with the form which they had given to such a
science. Indeed, the expertness which Werner and his scholars acquired
in the use of external characters, justified some partiality for them.
It is related of him,47 that, by looking at a piece of
iron-ore, and poising it in his hand, he was able to tell, almost
precisely, the proportion of pure metal which it contained. And in the
last year of his life,48 he had marked out, as the employment of
the ensuing winter, the study of the system of Berzelius, with a view
to find out the laws of combination as disclosed by external
characters. In the same spirit, his pupil 345 Breithaupt49 attempted to
discover the ingredients of minerals by their peculiarities of
crystallization. The persuasion that there must be some
connexion between composition and properties, transformed itself, in
their minds, into a belief that they could seize the nature of the
connexion by a sort of instinct.
46 See his Disc. Prél.
47 Frisch. Werner’s Leben, p.
78.
48 Frisch. 3.
49 Dresdn. Auswahl, vol. ii.
p. 97.
This opinion of the independency of the science of external
characters, and of its sufficiency for its own object, at last assumed
its complete form in the bold attempt to construct a system which
should borrow nothing from chemistry. This attempt was made by
Frederick Mohs, who had been the pupil of Werner, and was afterwards
his successor in the school of Freiberg; and who, by the acute and
methodical character of his intellect, and by his intimate knowledge
of minerals, was worthy of his predecessor. Rejecting altogether all
divisions of which the import was chemical, Mohs turned for guidance,
or at least for the light of analogy, to botany. His object was to
construct a Natural System of mineralogy. What the conditions
and advantages of a natural system of any province of nature are, we
must delay to explain till we have before us, in botany, a more
luminous example of such a scheme. But further; in mineralogy, as in
botany, besides the Natural System, by which we form our
classes, it is necessary to have an Artificial System by which
we recognize them;—a principle which, we have seen, had
already taken root in the school of Freiberg. Such an artificial
system Mohs produced in his Characteristic of the Mineral
Kingdom, which was published at Dresden in 1820; and which, though
extending only to a few pages, excited a strong interest in Germany,
where men’s minds were prepared to interpret the full import of such a
work. Some of the traits of such a “Characteristic” had, indeed, been
previously drawn by others; as for example, by Haüy, who notices that
each of his Classes has peculiar characters. For instance, his First
Class (acidiferous substances,) alone possesses these combinations of
properties; “division into a regular octohedron, without being able to
scratch glass; specific gravity above 3·5, without being able to
scratch glass.” The extension of such characters into a scheme which
should exhaust the whole mineral kingdom, was the undertaking of
Mohs.
Such a collection of marks of classes, implied a classification
previously established, and accordingly, Mohs had created his own
mineral system. His aim was to construct it, as we shall hereafter see
that other natural systems are constructed, by taking into account
all the 346 resemblances and differences of the
objects classified. It is obvious that to execute such a work, implied
a most intimate and universal acquaintance with minerals;—a
power of combining in one vivid survey the whole mineral kingdom. To
illustrate the spirit in which Professor Mohs performed his task, I
hope I may be allowed to refer to my own intercourse with him. At an
early period of my mineralogical studies, when the very conception of
a Natural System was new to me, he, with great kindliness of temper,
allowed me habitually to propose to him the scruples which arose in my
mind, before I could admit principles which appeared to me then so
vague and indefinite; and answered my objections with great patience
and most instructive clearness. Among other difficulties, I one day
propounded to him this;—“You have published a Treatise on
Mineralogy, in which you have described all the important
properties of all known minerals. On your principles, then, it ought
to be possible, merely by knowing the descriptions in your book, and
without seeing any minerals, to construct a natural system; and this
natural system ought to turn out identical with that which you have
produced, by so careful an examination of the minerals themselves.” He
pondered a moment, and then he answered, “It is true; but what an
enormous imagination (einbildungskraft, power of
inward imagining), a man must have for such a work!” Vividness of
conception of sensible properties, and the steady intuition
(anschauung) of objects, were deemed by him, and by the
Wernerian school in general, to be the most essential conditions of
complete knowledge.
It is not necessary to describe Mohs’s system in detail; it may
sufficiently indicate its form to state that the following substances,
such as I before gave as examples of other arrangements, calcspar,
gypsum, fluor spar, apatite, heavy spar, are by Mohs termed
respectively, Rhombohedral Lime Haloide, Gyps Haloide,
Octohedral Fluor Haloide, Rhombohedral Fluor Haloide,
Prismatic Hal Baryte. These substances are thus referred to the
Orders Haloide, and Baryte; to Genera Lime Haloide,
Fluor Haloide, Hal Baryte; and the Species is an additional
particularization.
Mohs not only aimed at framing such a system, but was also
ambitious of giving to all minerals Names which should accord
with the system. This design was too bold to succeed. It is true, that
a new nomenclature was much needed in mineralogy: it is true, too,
that it was reasonable to expect, from an improved classification, an
improved nomenclature, such as had been so happily obtained in botany
by the 347 reform
of Linnæus. But besides the defects of Mohs’s system, he had not
prepared his verbal novelties with the temperance and skill of the
great botanical reformer. He called upon mineralogists to change the
name of almost every mineral with which they were acquainted; and the
proposed appellations were mostly of a cumbrous form, as the above
example may serve to show. Such names could have obtained general
currency, only after a general and complete acceptance of the system;
and the system did not possess, in a sufficient degree, that evidence
which alone could gain it a home in the belief of
philosophers,—the coincidence of its results with those of
Chemistry. But before I speak finally of the fortunes of the
Natural-history System, I will say something of the other attempt
which was made about the same time to introduce a Reform into
Mineralogy from the opposite extremity of the science.
Sect. 2.—Chemical System of Berzelius and
others.
If the students of external
characters were satisfied of the independence of their method, the
chemical analysts were naturally no less confident of the legitimate
supremacy of their principles: and when the beginning of the present
century had been distinguished by the establishment of the theory of
definite proportions, and by discoveries which pointed to the
electro-chemical theory, it could not appear presumption to suppose,
that the classification of bodies, so far as it depended on chemistry,
might be presented in a form more complete and scientific than at any
previous time.
The attempt to do this was made by the great Swedish chemist Jacob
Berzelius. In 1816, he published his Essay to establish a purely
Scientific System of Mineralogy, by means of the Application of the
Electro-chemical Theory and the Chemical Doctrine of Definite
Proportions. It is manifest that, for minerals which are
constituted by the law of Definite Proportions, this constitution must
be a most essential part of their character. The electro-chemical
theory was called in aid, in addition to the composition, because,
distinguishing the elements of all compounds as electro-positive and
electro-negative, and giving to every element a place in a series, and
a place defined by the degree of these relations, it seemed to afford
a rigorous and complete principle of arrangement. Accordingly,
Berzelius, in his First System, arranged minerals according to their
electro-positive element, and the elements according to their
electro-positive rank; 348 and supposed that he had thus removed
all that was arbitrary and vague in the previous chemical systems of
mineralogy.
Though the attempt appeared so well justified by the state of
chemical science, and was so plausible in its principle, it was not
long before events showed that there was some fallacy in these
specious appearances. In 1820, Mitscherlich discovered Isomorphism: by
that discovery it appeared that bodies containing very different
electro-positive elements could not be distinguished from each other;
it was impossible, therefore, to put them in distant portions of the
classification;—and thus the first system of Berzelius crumbled
to pieces.
But Berzelius did not so easily resign his project. With the most
unhesitating confession of his first failure, but with undaunted
courage, he again girded himself to the task of rebuilding his
edifice. Defeated at the electro-positive position, he now resolved to
make a stand at the electro-negative element. In 1824, he published in
the Transactions of the Swedish Academy, a Memoir On the
Alterations in the Chemical Mineral System, which necessarily follow
from the Property exhibited by Isomorphous Bodies, of replacing each
other in given Proportions. The alteration was, in fact, an
inversion of the system, with an attempt still to preserve the
electro-chemical principle of arrangement. Thus, instead of arranging
metallic minerals according to the metal, under iron, copper,
&c., all the sulphurets were classed together, all the
oxides together, all the sulphates together, and so
in other respects. That such an order was a great improvement on the
preceding one, cannot be doubted; but we shall see, I think, that as a
strict scientific system it was not successful. The discovery of
isomorphism, however, naturally led to such attempts. Thus Gmelin
also, in 1825, published a mineral system,50 which, like
that of Berzelius, founded its leading distinctions on the
electro-negative, or, as it was sometimes termed, the formative
element of bodies; and, besides this, took account of the
numbers of atoms or proportions which appear in the
composition of the body; distinguishing, for instance, Silicates, as
simple silicates, double silicates, and so on, to quintuple
silicate (Pechstein) and sextuple silicate
(Perlstein). In like manner, Nordenskiöld devised a system
resting on the same bases, taking into account also the crystalline
form. In 1824, Beudant published his Traité Elémentaire de
Minéralogie, in which he professes to found his arrangement on the
electro-negative element, and on Ampère’s circular 349 arrangement of
elementary substances. Such schemes exhibit rather a play of the mere
logical faculty, exercising itself on assumed principles, than any
attempt at the real interpretation of nature. Other such pure chemical
systems may have been published, but it is not necessary to accumulate
instances. I proceed to consider their result.
50 Zeitsch. der Min. 1825, p.
435.
Sect. 3.—Failure of the Attempts at Systematic
Reform.
It may appear presumptuous to
speak of the failure of those whom, like Berzelius and Mohs, we
acknowledge as our masters, at a period when, probably, they and some
of their admirers still hold them to have succeeded in their attempt
to construct a consistent system. But I conceive that my office as an
historian requires me to exhibit the fortunes of this science in the
most distinct form of which they admit, and that I cannot evade the
duty of attempting to seize the true aspect of recent occurrences in
the world of science. Hence I venture to speak of the failure of both
the attempts at framing a pure scientific system of
mineralogy,—that founded on the chemical, and that founded on
the natural-history principle; because it is clear that they have not
obtained that which alone we could, according to the views here
presented, consider as success,—a coincidence of each with the
other. A Chemical System of arrangement, which should bring together,
in all cases, the substances which come nearest each other in external
properties;—a Natural-history System, which should be found to
arrange bodies in complete accordance with their chemical
constitution:—if such systems existed, they might, with justice,
claim to have succeeded. Their agreement would be their verification.
The interior and exterior system are the type and the antitype, and
their entire correspondence would establish the mode of interpretation
beyond doubt. But nothing less than this will satisfy the requisitions
of science. And when, therefore, the chemical and the natural-history
system, though evidently, as I conceive, tending towards each other,
are still far from coming together, it is impossible to allow that
either method has been successful in regard to its proper object.
But we may, I think, point out the fallacy of the principles, as
well as the imperfection of the results, of both of those methods.
With regard to that of Berzelius, indeed, the history of the subject
obviously betrays its unsoundness. The electro-positive principle was,
in a very short time after its adoption, proved and acknowledged to be
utterly untenable: what security have we that the electro-negative
element is 350 more
trustworthy? Was not the necessity of an entire change of system, a
proof that the ground, whatever that was, on which the
electro-chemical principle was adopted, was an unfounded assumption?
And, in fact, do we not find that the same argument which was allowed
to be fatal to the First System of Berzelius, applies in exactly the
same manner against the Second? If the electro-positive elements be
often isomorphous, are not the electro-negative elements sometimes
isomorphous also? for instance, the arsenic and phosphoric acids. But
to go further, what is the ground on which the
electro-chemical arrangement is adopted? Granted that the electrical
relations of bodies are important; but how do we come to know that
these relations have anything to do with mineralogy? How does it
appear that on them, principally, depend those external properties
which mineralogy must study? How does it appear that because sulphur
is the electro-negative part of one body, and an acid the
electro-negative part of another, these two elements similarly affect
the compounds? How does it appear that there is any analogy whatever
in their functions? We allow that the composition must, in some
way, determine the classified place of the mineral,—but why
in this way?
I do not dwell on the remark which Berzelius himself51 makes on Nordenskiöld’s
system;—that it assumes a perfect knowledge of the composition
in every case; although, considering the usual discrepancies of
analyses of minerals, this objection must make all pure chemical
systems useless. But I may observe, that mineralogists have not yet
determined what characters are sufficiently affixed to determine a
species of minerals. We have seen that the ancient notion of the
composition of a species, has been unsettled by the discovery of
isomorphism. The tenet of the constancy of the angle is rendered
doubtful by cases of plesiomorphism. The optical properties, which are
so closely connected with the crystalline, are still so imperfectly
known, that they are subject to changes which appear capricious and
arbitrary. Both the chemical and the optical mineralogists have
constantly, of late, found occasion to separate species which had been
united, and to bring together those which had been divided. Everything
shows that, in this science, we have our classification still to
begin. The detection of that fixity of characters, on which a right
establishment of species must rest, is not yet complete, great as the
progress is which we have made, by acquiring a knowledge of the laws
of crystallization and of 351 definite chemical constitution. Our
ignorance may surprise us; but it may diminish our surprise to
recollect, that the knowledge which we seek is that of the laws of the
physical constitution of all bodies whatever; for to us, as
mineralogists, all chemical compounds are minerals.
51 Jahres Bericht. viii.
188.
The defect of the principle of the natural-history classifiers may
be thus stated:—in studying the external characters of bodies,
they take for granted that they can, without any other light, discover
the relative value and importance of those characters. The grouping of
Species into a Genus, of Genera into an Order, according to the method
of this school, proceeds by no definite rules, but by a latent talent
of appreciation,—a sort of classifying instinct. But this course
cannot reasonably be expected to lead to scientific truth; for it can
hardly be hoped, by any one who looks at the general course of
science, that we shall discover the relation between external
characters and chemical composition, otherwise than by tracing their
association in cases where both are known. It is urged that in other
classificatory sciences, in botany, for example, we obtain a natural
classification from external characters without having recourse to any
other source of knowledge. But this is not true in the sense here
meant. In framing a natural system of botany, we have constantly
before our eyes the principles of physiology; and we estimate the
value of the characters of a plant by their bearing on its
functions,—by their place in its organization. In an unorganic
body, the chemical constitution is the law of its being; and we shall
never succeed in framing a science of such bodies but by studiously
directing our efforts to the interpretation of that law.
On these grounds, then, I conceive, that the bold attempts of Mohs
and of Berzelius to give new forms to mineralogy, cannot be deemed
successful in the manner in which their authors aspired to succeed.
Neither of them can be marked as a permanent reformation of the
science. I shall not inquire how far they have been accepted by men of
science, for I conceive that their greatest effect has been to point
out improvements which might be made in mineralogy without going the
whole length either of the pure chemical, or of the
pure natural-history system.
Sect. 4.—Return to Mixed Systems with
Improvements.
In spite of the efforts of
the purists, mineralogists returned to mixed systems of
classification; but these systems are much better than they were
before such efforts were made. 352
The Second System of Berzelius, though not tenable in its rigorous
form, approaches far nearer than any previous system to a complete
character, bringing together like substances in a large portion of its
extent. The System of Mohs also, whether or not unconsciously swayed
by chemical doctrines, forms orders which have a community of chemical
character; thus, the minerals of the order Haloide are salts of
oxides, and those of the order Pyrites are sulphurets of
metals. Thus the two methods appear to be converging to a common
centre; and though we are unable to follow either of them to this
point of union, we may learn from both in what direction we are to
look for it. If we regard the best of the pure systems hitherto
devised as indications of the nature of that system, perfect both as a
chemical and as a natural-history system, to which a more complete
condition of mineralogical knowledge may lead us, we may obtain, even
at present, a tolerably good approximation to a complete
classification; and such a one, if we recollect that it must be
imperfect, and is to be held as provisional only, may be of no small
value and use to us.
The best of the mixed systems produced by this compromise again
comes from Freiberg, and was published by Professor Naumann in 1828.
Most of his orders have both a chemical character and great external
resemblances. Thus his Haloides, divided into Unmetallic
and Metallic, and these again into Hydrous and
Anhydrous, give good natural groups. The most difficult
minerals to arrange in all systems are the siliceous ones. These M.
Naumann calls Silicides, and subdivides them into
Metallic, Unmetallic, and Amphoteric or mixed;
and again, into Hydrous and Anhydrous. Such a system is
at least a good basis for future researches; and this is, as we have
said, all that we can at present hope for. And when we recollect that
the natural-history principle of classification has begun, as we have
already seen, to make its appearance in our treatises of chemistry, we
cannot doubt that some progress is making towards the object which I
have pointed out. But we know not yet how far we are from the end. The
combination of chemical, crystallographical, physical and optical
properties into some lofty generalization, is probably a triumph
reserved for future and distant years.
Conclusion.—The history of Mineralogy, both in its
successes and by its failures, teaches us this lesson;—that in
the sciences of classification, the establishment of the fixity of
characters, and the discovery of such characters as are fixed, are
steps of the first importance in the progress of these sciences. The
recollection of this maxim may aid us in 353 shaping our course through the history
of other sciences of this kind; in which, from the extent of the
subject, and the mass of literature belonging to it, we might at first
almost despair of casting the history into distinct epochs and
periods. To the most prominent of such sciences, Botany, I now
proceed.
~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~


BOOK XVI.

CLASSIFICATORY SCIENCES.

HISTORY
OF
SYSTEMATIC BOTANY AND ZOOLOGY.

.  .  .  .  .  Vatem
aspicies quæ rupe sub altâ
Fata canit, foliisque notas et nomina
mandat.
Quæcunque in foliis descripsit carmina
virgo
Digerit in numerum atque antro seclusa
relinquit
Illa manent immorta locis neque ab ordine
cedunt.
Virgil. Æn.
iii. 443.

Behold the Sibyl!—Her who weaves a
long,
A tangled, full, yet sweetly flowing song.
Wondrous her skill; for leaf on leaf she
frames
Unerring symbols and enduring names;
And as her nicely measured line she binds,
For leaf on leaf a fitting place she finds;
Their place once found, no more the leaves
depart,
But fixed rest:—such is her magic
art.

</div></body></text></TEI>