<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="29">

SYSTEMATIC MINERALOGY.

CHAPTER VIII.
Attempts at the Classification of
Minerals.

Sect. 1.—Proper object of
Classification.
THE fixity of the crystalline
and other physical properties of minerals is turned to account by
being made the means of classifying such objects. To use the language
of Aristotle,39 Classification is the
architectonic science, to which Crystallography and the
Doctrine of External Characters are subordinate and ministerial, as
the art of the bricklayer and carpenter are to that of the architect.
But classification itself is useful only as subservient to an ulterior
science, which shall furnish us with knowledge concerning things so
classified. To classify is to divide and to name; and the value of the
Divisions which we thus make, and of the names which we give them, is
this;—that they render exact knowledge and general propositions
possible. Now the knowledge which we principally seek concerning
minerals is a knowledge of their chemical composition; the general
propositions to which we hope to be led are such as assert relations
between their intimate constitution and their external attributes.
Thus our Mineralogical Classification must always have an eye turned
towards Chemistry. We cannot get rid of the fundamental conviction,
that the elementary composition of bodies, since it fixes their
essence, must determine their properties. Hence all mineralogical
arrangements, whether they profess it or not, must be, in effect,
chemical; they must have it for their object to bring into view a set
of relations, which, whatever else they may be, are at least chemical
relations. We may begin with the outside, but it is only in order to
reach the inner 340
structure. We may classify without reference to chemistry; but if we
do so, it is only that we may assert chemical propositions with
reference to our classification.</div></body></text></TEI>