<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="21">ON HUME'S ARGUMENT AGAINST MIRACLES.
Few arguments have excited greater attention, and produced more attempts at
 refutation, than the celebrated one of David Hume, respecting miracles; and
 it might be added, that more sophistry has been advanced against it, than its
 author employed in the whole of his writings. It must be admitted that in the
 argument, as originally developed by its author, there exists some confusion
 between personal experience and that which is derived from testimony; and that
 there are several other points open to criticism and objection; but the main
 argu-
[page] 121
ment, divested of its less important adjuncts, never has, and never will be
 refuted. Dr. Johnson seems to have been of this opinion, as the following extract
 from his life by Boswell proves:—
 " Talking of Dr. Johnson's unwillingness to believe extraordinary things,
 I ventured to say— " ' Sir, you come near to Hume's argument against miracles—That
 it is more probable witnesses should lie, or be ' mistaken, than that they should
 happen.' " Johnson.—' Why, Sir, Hume, taking the proposition ' simply, is right.
 But the Christian revelation is not proved ' by miracles alone, but as connected
 with prophecies, and ' with the doctrines in confirmation of which miracles
 were ' wrought.' "*
Hume contends that a miracle is a violation of the laws of nature; and as a
 firm and unalterable experience has established these laws', the proof against
 a miracle from the very nature of the fact, is as entire as any argument from
 experience can possibly be imagined.
 * Boswell's Life of Johnson. Oxford, 1826. vol. iii. p. 169.
[page] 122
 " The plain consequence is (and it is a general maxim " worthy of our attention),
 that no testimony is sufficient " to establish a miracle, unless the testimony
 be of such a " kind, that its falsehood would be more miraculous than the "
 fact which it endeavours to establish: and even in that case " there is a mutual
 destruction of arguments, and the superior " only gives us an assurance suitable
 to that degree of force " which remains after deducting the inferior."-*
The word miraculous employed in this passage is evidently equivalent
 to improbable, although the improbability is of a very high degree. The
 condition, therefore, which, it is asserted by the argument of Hume, must be
 fulfilled with regard to the testimony, is that the improbability of
 its falsehood must be greater than the improbability of the occurrence
 of the fact. This is a condition which, when the terms in which it is expressed
 are understood, immediately commands our assent. It is in the .
* Hume's Essays, Edinburgh, 1817, vol. ii. p. 117. .
[page] 123
subsequent stage of the reasoning that the fallacy is introduced. Hume asserts,
 that this condition cannot be fulfilled by the evidence of any number of
 witnesses, because our experience of the truth of human testimony is not uniform
 and without any exceptions; whereas, our experience of the course of nature,
 or our experience against miracles, is uniform and uninterrupted. The only sound
 way of trying the validity of this assertion is to measure the numerical
 value of the two improbabilities, one of which it is admitted must be greater
 than the other; and to ascertain whether, by making any hypothesis respecting
 the veracity of each witness, it is possible to fulfil that condition by any
 finite number of such witnesses. Hume appears to have been but very slightly
 acquainted with the doctrine of probabilities, and, indeed, at the period when
 he wrote, the details by which the conclusions .
[page] 124
he had arrived at could be proved or refuted were yet to be examined and arranged.
 It is, however, remarkable that the opinion he maintained respecting our knowledge
 of causation is one which eminently brings the whole question within the province
 of the calculus of probabilities. In fact, its solution can only be completely understood by those who are acquainted with that most difficult branch of
 science. By those who are not so prepared, certain calculations, which will
 be found more fully developed in the Note (E), must be taken for granted; and
 all that can be attempted will be, to convey to them a general outline of the
 nature of the principles on which these enquiries depend. A miracle is, according
 to Hume, an event which has never happened within the experience of the whole
 human race. Now, the improbability of the future happening of such an occurrence
 may be calculated according to two different views. .
[page] 125
 We may conceive an urn, containing only black and white balls, from
 which m black balls have been successively drawn and replaced, one by
 one; and we may calculate the probability of the appearance of a white ball
 at the next drawing. This would be analogous to the case of one human being
 raised from the dead after m instances to the contrary. Looking, in another
 point of view, at a miracle, we may imagine an urn to contain a very large number
 of tickets, on each of which is written one of the series of natural numbers.
 These being thoroughly mixed together, a single ticket is drawn: the prediction
 of the particular number inscribed on the ticket about to be drawn may be assimilated
 to the occurrence of a miracle. According to either of these views, the probability
 of the occurrence of such an event by mere accident may be calculated. Now,
 the reply to Hume's argument is this: Admit-
[page] 126
ting at once the essential point, viz. that the improbability of the concurrence
 of the witnesses in falsehood must be greater than the improbability
 of the miracle, it may be denied that this does not take place. Hume has asserted
 that, in order to prove a miracle, a certain improbability must be greater than another; and he has also asserted that this never can take
 place. Now, as each improbability can be truly measured by number, the only way to refute Hume's argument is by examining the magnitude of these
 numbers. This examination depends on known and admitted principles, for which
 the reader, who is prepared by previous study, may refer to the work of Laplace, Théorie Analytique des Probabilités; Poisson, Recherches
 sur la Probabilité des Jugements, 1837; or he may consult the article Probabilities, by Mr. De Morgan, in the Encyclopaedia Metropolitana,
 in which he will find this subject examined. .
[page] 127
One of the most important principles on which the question rests, is the concurrence
 of the testimony of independent witnesses. This principle has been stated by
 Campbell, and has been employed by the Archbishop of Dublin,* and also by Dr.
 Chalmers.† It requires however to be combined with another principle,
 in order to obtain the numerical values of the quantities spoken of in the argument.
 The following example may be sufficient for a popular illustration. Let us suppose
 that there are witnesses who will speak the truth, and who are not themselves
 deceived in ninety-nine cases out of a hundred. Now, let us examine what is
 the probability of the falsehood of a statement about to be made by two such
 persons absolutely unknown to and unconnected with each other. Since the order
 in which independent wit- .
* Elements of Rhetoric, by R. Whately, D.D. p. 57,1832.
† Evidence of Christian Revelation, vol. i. p. 129.
[page] 128
nesses give their testimony does not affect their credit, we may suppose that,
 in a given number of statements, both witnesses tell the truth in the ninety-nine
 first cases, and the falsehood in the hundredth. Then the first time the second
 witness B testifies, he will agree with the testimony of the first witness A,
 in the ninety-nine first cases, and differ from him in the hundredth. Similarly,
 in the second testimony of B, he will again agree with A in ninety-nine cases,
 and differ in the hundredth, and so on for ninety-nine times; so that, after
 A has testified a hundred, and B ninety-nine times, we shall have .
 99 X 99 cases in which both agree, 99 cases in which they differ, A being
 wrong. .
 Now, in the hundredth case in which B testifies, he is wrong; and, if we
 combine this with the testimony of A, we have ninety-nine cases in which A will
 be right and B wrong; and one case only in which both A and B will .
[page] 129
 agree in error. The whole number of cases, which amounts to ten thousand,
 may be thus divided:—
.
As there is only one case in ten thousand in which two such independent witnesses
 can agree in error, the probability of their future testimony being false is
 .
..
 The reader will already perceive how great a reliance is due to the future concurring testimony of two independent witnesses of tolerably good character
 and understanding. It appears that, previously to the testimony, the chance
 of one such witness being in error is that of two concurring in the same error  isand
 if the same reasoning be applied to three independent witnesses, it will be
[page] 130
found that the probability of their agreeing in error is; or that the odds are 999,999 to 1 against  the agreement. Pursuing the same reasoning, the probability of the falsehood
 of a fact which six such independent witnesses attest is, previously to the
 testimony, or it is, in round numbers,
 .
1,000,000,000,000 to 1 against the falsehood of their testimony. .
 The improbability of the miracle of a dead man being restored, is, on the
 principles stated by Hume,  or it is—
 200,000,000.000 to 1 against its occurrence.
It follows, then, that the chances of accidental or other independent concurrence
 of only six such independent witnesses, is already five times as
 great as the improbability against
[page] 131
 the miracle of a dead man's being restored to life, deduced from Hume's method
 of estimating its probability solely from experience. This illustration shows
 the great accumulation of probability arising from the concurrence of independent
 witnesses: we must however combine this principle with another, before we can
 arrive at the real numerical value of the improbabilities referred to in the
 argument. The calculation of the numerical values of these improbabilities I
 have given in Note (E.) From this it results that, provided we assume that independent
 witnesses can be found of whose testimony it can be stated that it is more probable
 that it is true than that it is false, we can always assign a number of witnesses
 which will, according to Hume's argument, prove the truth of a miracle.
[page] 132</div></body></text></TEI>