<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 166, folios 119-121</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 166, folios 119-121.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1844">undated [August 1844?]</date>
          <note type="place">Brighton</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 166, folios 119-121</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_166_folios_119-121.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Brighton Weddy Afternoon</p>
      <p>Thanks, my Dear, for your kind few lines of last evening. I am anxious to hear how your visits to Lord John &amp; the Wilders went off tho'.</p>
      <p>How kind is the enclosed from Henry Currie! I have answered it, expressing of course my sense of this. I have said too that I really would not scruple (as he lives so near) asking for the mare if at any time I do feel she would be a comfort to me for a short while. I have proposed that during the week after my return from hence, he &amp; I should take a ride together, &amp; that I might try the mare on that occasion. I should</p>
      <p>just like to know what she is.--</p>
      <p>I feel so very glad, my Dear, that you go visiting about, &amp; being an affable social Crow. No crow ever was solitary!--</p>
      <p>I shall like to pay some riding visits with you when I return, if I am as well as I expect.</p>
      <p>You are a kind mate to feel so for me. I have indeed been in a most sad state. I think my organization is one of excessive acuteness in every item; &amp; that sensations (when I have them at all) are of an extreme kind, either for pain or pleasure. This fact would account for my youthful tendency to over-eagerness as to even the most laudable objects.</p>
      <p>The sensations over-ruled everything, until judgment experience &amp; knowledge had taught me what the sensations were worth. At 30 one may have a considerable amount of knowledge experience and judgment, but at 20 one could have but little.</p>
      <p>I am exceedingly struck with Miss Cosway. She has a defect in the palate, which mars her speech &amp; hearing sadly; a modified degree of your Aunt Cath's. She is thus shut out from many outward enjoyments &amp; advantages, &amp; has become a very contemplative &amp; thinking character. She is a little of a mathematician. Mrs King (who is vastly fastidious about young ladies, I don't mean religiously so however), says</p>
      <p>she has scarcely ever met with so superior a young person. She has lived much with the Kings.--</p>
      <p>Lady Caroline Sanford is here I belive, &amp; I think I should call. I rather think that Lady Acland too is here. Mrs. Lamb had left before I arrived.</p>
      <p>Thursdy Morning. A fine day, tho' windy. I am going out for the day, to make up for lost time in that line. I shall walk over to Shoreham Harbour, then row up the river there, &amp; get two swims probably before evening. All this I manage quite quietly &amp; incog.--</p>
      <p>I think you will well like my swimming dress. The black colour, (combined with the slimness &amp; boyish-ness of my</p>
      <p>straight figure), make it really a graceful feminine-looking costume, &amp; not the least startling.--</p>
      <p>I have learned many things here as to conveniences for dress, for wet &amp; windy weather, or climbing about &amp;c.</p>
      <p>I forgot to write you my applause of your reprobation of Miss Cooper's most sad dawdling. Pray brisken them up all you can, &amp; encourage Dr C-- to do so too.</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
