<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="105">CHAPTER I.
Prelude to the Epoch of De Lisle and
Haüy.
OF all the physical properties
of bodies, there is none so fixed, and in every way so remarkable, as
this;—that the same chemical compound always assumes, with the
utmost precision, the same geometrical form. This identity, however,
is not immediately obvious; it is often obscured by various mixtures
and imperfections in the substance; and even when it is complete, it
is not immediately recognized by a common eye, since it consists, not
in the equality of the sides or faces of the figures, but in the
equality of their angles. Hence it is not surprising that the
constancy of form was not detected by the early observers. Pliny
says,1 “Why crystal is generated in a hexagonal
form, it is difficult to assign a reason; and the more so, since,
while its faces are smoother than any art can make them, the pyramidal
points are not all of the same kind.” The quartz crystals of
the Alps, to which he refers, are, in some specimens, very regular,
while in others, one side of the pyramid becomes much the largest; yet
the angles remain constantly the same. But when the whole shape varied
so much, the angles also seemed to vary. Thus Conrad Gessner, a very
learned naturalist, who, in 1564, published at Zurich his work, De
rerum Fossilium, Lapidum et Gemmarum maxime, Figuris, says,2
“One crystal differs from another in its angles, and consequently in
its figure.” And Cæsalpinus, who, as we shall find, did so much in establishing fixed characters
in botany, was led by some of his general views to disbelieve the
fixity of the form of crystals. In his work De Metallicis,
published at Nuremberg in 1602, he says,3 “To ascribe to
inanimate bodies a definite form, does not appear consentaneous to
reason; for it is the office of organization to produce a definite
form;” 317 an
opinion very natural in one who had been immersed in the study of the
general analogies of the forms of plants. But though this is excusable
in Cæsalpinus, the rejection of this definiteness of form a hundred
years later, when its existence had been proved, and its laws
developed by numerous observers, cannot be ascribed to anything but
strong prejudice; yet this was the course taken by no less a person
than Buffon. “The form of crystallization,” says he,4
“is not a constant character, but is more equivocal and more
variable than any other of the characters by which minerals are to be
distinguished.” And accordingly, he makes no use of this most
important feature in his history of minerals. This strange
perverseness may perhaps be ascribed to the dislike which Buffon is
said to have entertained for Linnæus, who had made crystalline form a
leading character of minerals.
1 Nat. Hist. xxvii. 2.
2 p. 25.
3 p. 97.
4 Hist. des Min. p. 343.
It is not necessary to mark all the minute steps by which
mineralogists were gradually led to see clearly the nature and laws of
the fixity of crystalline forms. These forms were at first noticed in
that substance which is peculiarly called rock-crystal or quartz; and
afterwards in various stones and gems, in salts obtained from various
solutions, and in snow. But those who observed the remarkable regular
figures which these substances assume, were at first impelled onwards
in their speculations by the natural tendency of the human mind to
generalize and guess, rather than to examine and measure. They
attempted to snatch at once the general laws of geometrical regularity
of these occurrences, or to connect them with some doctrine concerning
formative causes. Thus Kepler,5 in his
Harmonics of the World, asserts a “formatrix facultas,
which has its seat in the entrails of the earth, and, after the manner
of a pregnant woman, expresses the five regular geometrical solids in
the forms of gems.” But Philosophers, in the course of time, came to
build more upon observation, and less upon abstract reasonings.
Nicolas Steno, a Dane, published, in 1669, a dissertation De Solido
intra Solidum Naturaliter contento, in which he says,6
that though the sides of the hexagonal crystal may vary, the
angles are not changed. And Dominic Gulielmini, in a
Dissertation on Salts, published in 1707, says,7
in a true inductive spirit, “Nature does not employ all figures, but
only certain ones of those which are possible; and of these, the
determination is not to be fetched from the brain, or proved à
priori, but obtained by experiments and observations.” And 318 he speaks8
with entire decision on this subject: “Nevertheless since there is
here a principle of crystallization, the inclination of the planes and
of the angles is always constant.” He even anticipates, very nearly,
the views of later crystallographers as to the mode in which crystals
are formed from elementary molecules. From this time, many persons
labored and speculated on this subject; as Cappeller, whose
Prodromus Crystallographiæ appeared at Lucern in 1723;
Bourguet, who published Lettres Philosophiques sur la Formation de
Sels et de Cristaux, at Amsterdam, in 1792; and Henckel, the
“Physicus” of the Elector of Saxony, whose Pyritologia came
forth in 1725. In this last work we have an example of the description
of the various forms of special classes of minerals, (iron pyrites,
copper pyrites, and arsenic pyrites;) and an example of the enthusiasm
which this apparently dry and laborious study can excite: “Neither
tongue nor stone,” he exclaims,9 “can express the
satisfaction which I received on setting eyes upon this sinter covered
with galena; and thus it constantly happens, that one must have more
pleasure in what seems worthless rubbish, than in the purest and most
precious ores, if we know aught of minerals.”
5 Linz. 1619, p. 161.
6 p. 69.
7 p. 19.
8 p. 83.
9 p. 343.
Still, however, Henckel10 disclaims the
intention of arranging minerals according to their mathematical forms;
and this, which may be considered as the first decided step in the
formation of crystallographic mineralogy, appears to have been first
attempted by Linnæus. In this attempt, however, he was by no means
happy; nor does he himself appear to have been satisfied. He begins
his preface by saying, “Lithology is not what I plume myself upon.”
(Lithologia mihi cristas non eriget.) Though his sagacity, as a
natural historian, led him to see that crystalline form was one of the
most definite, and therefore most important, characters of minerals,
he failed in profiting by this thought, because, in applying it, he
did not employ the light of geometry, but was regulated by what
appeared to him resemblances, arbitrarily selected, and often
delusive.11 Thus he derived the form of pyrites
from that of vitriol;12 and brought together alum and diamond
on account of their common octohedral form. But he had the great merit
of animating to this study one to whom, more perhaps than to any other
person, it owes its subsequent progress; I mean Romé de Lisle.
“Instructed,” this writer says, in his preface to his Essais de
Crystallographie, “by the works of the celebrated Von Linnée, how
319 greatly the
study of the angular form of crystals might become interesting, and
fitted to extend the sphere of our mineralogical knowledge, I have
followed them in all their metamorphoses with the most scrupulous
attention.” The views of Linnæus, as to the importance of this
character, had indeed been adopted by several others; as John Hill,
the King’s gardener at Kew, who, in 1777, published his
Spathogenesia; and Grignon, who, in 1775, says, “These
crystallizations may give the means of finding a new theory of the
generation of crystalline gems.”
10 p. 167.
11 Marx. Gesch. p. 97.
12 Syst. Nat. vi. p.
220.
The circumstance which threw so much difficulty in the way of those
who tried to follow out his thought was, that in consequence of the
apparent irregularity of crystals, arising from the extension or
contraction of particular sides of the figure, each kind of substance
may really appear under many different forms, connected with each
other by certain geometrical relations. These may be conceived by
considering a certain fundamental form to be cut into new forms in
particular ways. Thus if we take a cube, and cut off all the eight
corners, till the original faces disappear, we make it an octohedron;
and if we stop short of this, we have a figure of fourteen faces,
which has been called a cubo-octohedron. The first person who
appears distinctly to have conceived this truncation of angles
and edges, and to have introduced the word, is Démeste;13 although Wallerius14 had already
said, in speaking of the various crystalline forms of calcspar, “I
conceive it would be better not to attend to all differences, lest we
be overwhelmed by the number.” And Werner, in his celebrated work
On the External Characters of Minerals,15 had formally
spoken of truncation, acuation, and acumination,
or replacement by a plane, an edge, a point respectively,
(abstumpfung, zuschärfung, zuspitzung,) as ways
in which the forms of crystals are modified and often disguised. He
applied this process in particular to show the connexion of the
various forms which are related to the cube. But still the extension
of the process to the whole range of minerals and other crystalline
bodies, was due to Romé de Lisle.
13 Lettres, 1779, i. 48.
14 Systema Mineralogicum,
1772–5, i. 143.
15  Leipzig, 1774. 320</div></body></text></TEI>