<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="24">

CHAPTER XIV.
Of the Application of Mathematics to the Inductive Sciences.



1. ALL objects in the world which can be made the subjects
of our contemplation are subordinate to the conditions of
Space, Time, and Number; and on this account, the doctrines
of pure mathematics have most numerous and extensive
applications in every department of our investigations of
nature. And there is a peculiarity in these Ideas, which has
caused the mathematical sciences to be, in all cases, the
first successful efforts of the awakening speculative powers
of nations at the commencement of their intellectual
progress. Conceptions derived from these Ideas are, from the
very first, perfectly precise and clear, so as to be fit
elements of scientific truths. This is not the case with the
other conceptions which form the subjects of scientific
inquiries. The conception of statical force, for
instance, was never presented in a distinct form till the
works of Archimedes appeared: the conception of
accelerating force was confused, in the mind of
Kepler and his contemporaries, and only became clear enough
for purposes of sound scientific reasoning in the succeeding
century: the just conception of chemical composition
of elements gradually, in modern times, emerged from the
erroneous and vague notions of the ancients. If we take
works published on such subjects before the epoch when the
foundations of the true science were laid, we find the
knowledge not only small, but worthless. The writers did not
see any evidence in what we now consider as the axioms of
the science; nor any inconsistency where we now see
self-contradiction. But this was never the case with
speculations concerning 160 space and number. From their
first rise, these were true as far as they went. The
Geometry and Arithmetic of the Greeks and Indians, even in
their first and most scanty form, contained none but true
propositions. Men’s intuitions upon these subjects never
allowed them to slide into error and confusion; and the
truths to which they were led by the first efforts of their
faculties, so employed, form part of the present stock of
our mathematical knowledge.
2. But we are here not so much concerned with mathematics in
their pure form, as with their application to the phenomena
and laws of nature. And here also the very earliest history
of civilization presents to us some of the most remarkable
examples of man’s success in his attempts to attain to
science. Space and time, position and motion, govern all
visible objects; but by far the most conspicuous examples of
the relations which arise out of such elements, are
displayed by the ever-moving luminaries of the sky, which
measure days, and months, and years, by their motions, and
man’s place on the earth by their position. Hence the
sciences of space and number were from the first cultivated
with peculiar reference to Astronomy. I have elsewhere18
quoted Plato’s remark,—that it is absurd to call the
science of the relations of space geometry, the
measure of the earth, since its most important office is to
be found in its application to the heavens. And on other
occasions also it appears how strongly he, who may be
considered as the representative of the scientific and
speculative tendencies of his time and country, had been
impressed with the conviction, that the formation of a
science of the celestial motions must depend entirely upon
the progress of mathematics. In the Epilogue to the Dialogue
on the Laws19, he declares mathematical knowledge to be
the first and main requisite for the astronomer, and
describes the portions of it which he holds necessary for
astronomical speculators to cultivate. These seem to be,
Plane Geometry, Theoretical Arithmetic, the Application of
Arithmetic 161 to planes and to solids, and finally the
doctrine of Harmonics. Indeed the bias of Plato appears to
be rather to consider mathematics as the essence of the
science of astronomy, than as its instrument; and he seems
disposed, in this as in other things, to disparage
observation, and to aspire after a science founded upon
demonstration alone. ‘An astronomer,’ he says in the same
place, ‘must not be like Hesiod and persons of that kind,
whose astronomy consists in noting the settings and risings
of the stars; but he must be one who understands the
revolutions of the celestial spheres, each performing its
proper cycle.’</div></body></text></TEI>