<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="18">CHAPTER XVI.
Anxious to divert my thoughts from what I hoped was only
a temporary evil, I determined, accompanied by Charles, to
make a tour of some of the cities of Germany. Dresden
was the capital to which I was most desirous of conducting
him. Maurice, duke of Saxony, who held his court there,
and who was now only twenty-three years of age, was incomparably
the most accomplished prince of the empire.
Desirous as I was that my only son should fill a distinguished
career, I thought I could not better prepare him for the
theatre of his native country, than by thus initiating him
beforehand in scenes of distinction and greatness.
He was delighted with his tour. We had not proceeded
many leagues from Constance, before, indulging in the bent
of my mind, I laid aside the humbleness of our appearance,
and the obscure style in which we travelled; and having
procured a numerous cavalcade of horses and servants, I set
forward with considerable magnificence. We passed through
Munich, Ratisbon, and Prague. At Munich we found the
court of the elector palatine; the diet of the empire was
sitting at Ratisbon, when we arrived at that city. Charles
had been almost entirely a stranger to every thing princely
and magnificent from the time he was nine years of age;
and he was now exactly at that period of human life when
external appearances are apt to make the strongest impression.
To him every thing that occurred seemed like transportation
into a new world. The figure we made procured us, as
strangers, unquestioned admission into every circle. We
mixed with princes, ourselves in garb and figure confounded
with those we saw. I had lived too much and too
long in the most splendid society, to find difficulty in resuming
the unembarrassed and courtly manners which I had
for years laid aside; and Charles might be said to see his
father in a new character. Novelty prompted his admiration;
he was intoxicated with wonder. His disposition[181]
had always led him to bold and adventurous conceptions;
nothing less than an imperious sense of duty could have restrained
him from quitting our cottage, and casting himself
upon the world in search of honour and distinction. His
generous heart had beat to burst away from the obscurity
of his station; and it was with impatience and discontent
that he looked forward to the life of a swain. Yet he knew
not how to break through the obstacles that confined him.
It was therefore with transports of pleasure that he saw
them vanishing as of themselves, and the career of glory
opening, as if by enchantment, to his eager steps.
The court of Dresden was infinitely more delightful to
him than the court of Munich, or the imperial display at
Ratisbon. Here Charles saw a young prince in the flower
of his age, whose talents and spirit rendered him the universal
object of attention and adoration. He remarked, in
the fire of his eyes, the vivacity of his gestures, and the
grandeur of his port, something inexpressibly different from
those princes, of whom it is necessary that their rank should
be announced to you by some extrinsic circumstance, that
you may not mistake them for a merchant’s clerk or a city
magistrate. The sentiment that he breathed, as it were instinctively,
as we returned from the first time of our seeing
duke Maurice, was, “At twenty-three years of age may I,
in appearance, accomplishments, and spirit, resemble this
man!”
Here I was desirous of making a longer stay than at the
cities through which we had previously passed, and of procuring
for my son some personal intercourse with this great
ornament of the age. I judged this to be the more easy,
as, in our first visit to the palace, I had perceived some
French noblemen of the Protestant persuasion, who had resorted
to the duke’s court in search of employment. They
appeared not to know me; but that was little to be wondered
at, considering that I had been seven years absent from my
country, and that the calamities by which I had been overtaken
more than once during that period, might be supposed
to have produced a greater effect upon me than the
mere lapse of years would have done. Among the rest I
remarked Gaspar de Coligny, who was only twenty-one[182]
years of age at the time I quitted France, and had then
been remarked as one of the most promising young men his
country had to boast. His stay here was expected to be
short; his hopes in his own country, from the greatness of
his connections, were of the highest class; and he had only
come to Dresden at the earnest invitation of duke Maurice,
who entertained an ardent affection for him. My heart led
me towards him; policy concurred in dictating the application,
as, if I were fortunate enough to gain his favour, my
son could not have a friend better qualified either to form
his character or forward his advancement.
I wrote to Coligny to announce my request to him, and
in a few hours after the delivery of my letter that young
nobleman came in person to wait on me. He informed
me that he had done so, because he had something of delicacy
to mention, which he did not choose to trust to the
intermission of a third person, and upon which, as he
hoped I could remove his scruple, he did not like even to
bestow the formality of putting it on paper.
“I am a gentleman of France,” said Coligny; “you
will excuse my frankness. I am a gentleman of France;
you will not wonder at the niceness of my honour. Mixing
in society, I do not pretend minutely to investigate the
character of every person with whom I converse; but what
you ask of me obliges me to consult my understanding, and
enquire into facts. I cannot consent to vouch for any
man’s character to another, till I have paid some attention
to the ground upon which that character rests.
“I remember the count de St. Leon with pleasure and
advantage at the court of my own sovereign. Every one
admired his accomplishments, his gallantry, and his learning;
every one spoke of him with respect. Unfortunate
circumstances, as we all understood, deprived you of your
patrimony; that is nothing to me; I respect a nobleman in
misfortune, as much as when he is surrounded with wealth
and splendour. You retired into voluntary exile; I heard,
with great grief, of some subsequent calamities that have
overtaken you. But, here in Saxony, I see you resuming
all your former splendour, and coming forward with the
magnificence of a prince. Other of your countrymen have[183]
remarked it, as well as myself, and feel themselves at a loss
to account for what they see.
“Excuse me, count! by your application to me, you
oblige me to speak freely. I dare say you can clear up the
difficulty, and account for this second revolution in your
fortune, upon which I shall then be the first to congratulate
you. I cannot suspect a man, with your high descent
and the illustrious character you formerly maintained,
of any thing dishonourable. But you have not sufficiently
considered the account we all owe to one another,
and the clearness of proceeding we are obliged to maintain,
not only to our own hearts, but in the face of the world.
The present occasion is, I trust, fortunate for you; and,
when you have assisted me in complying with the rules by
which every honourable man governs himself, I shall be
eager to publish your justification, and render you all the
service in my power.”
I was ready to burst with astonishment and vexation
during this representation of Coligny. I could feel my
colour change from pale to red, and from red to pale. I
could only answer with suffocation and inward rage, that I
was much obliged to him; I would consider what he said;
I would acquaint him with my justification; and, whenever
it was made, he might be assured it should be an
ample one.—I was cautious as to what I uttered; I could
not immediately foresee what it was eligible, or what it was
possible, to do; and I was resolved that I would not, by
an idle or hasty expression, preclude myself, in a matter of
so much moment, from the benefits of future deliberation.
If what I had just heard had come from any other person,
I should probably have despised it; but I felt at once that
Gaspar de Coligny might be considered, in a case of this
sort, as the representative of all that was most honourable
and illustrious in my native country.—Finding that I was
indisposed to any further communication on the subject, he
took a polite leave, and departed.
I was no sooner alone than I felt myself overwhelmed
with mortification and shame. I had rejoiced in the bequests
of the stranger, because I regarded them as the
means of restoring me to splendour, and replacing my children[184]
in the situation to which they were entitled by their
birth. Was that which I had regarded as the instrument
of their glory, to become the medium of their ignominy
and disgrace? I had suffered all other misfortunes, but
the whisper of dishonour had never been breathed against
me. I was a son of honour, descended of a race of heroes,
and cradled in the lap of glory and fame. When we
quitted Paris in the year 1537, my incomparable wife had
set to sale our entire property, resolved that, though driven
into exile, we would not leave it in the power of the meanest
individual to controvert the sacred attention we yielded
to every just obligation. Since that time I had declined
from the splendour of rank to the humble situation of a
rustic, cultivating my little property with my own hands;
nay, I had even, for a short time, hired myself as a labourer
in the garden of the bishop of Constance. But the same
disdain of every thing disgraceful had followed me to my
cottage and my truckle bed, which I had originally learned
in the halls of chivalry and the castle of my ancestors.
Accordingly I had uniformly retained the same honourable
character and spotless fame. St. Leon, the virtuous cottager,
had in nothing blemished the name of St. Leon, surrounded
with glory in the siege of Pavia. Often, and with
pride, had I pointed out this circumstance to my son, adding,
Wherever fortune calls you, for whatever scenes you
may be reserved, remember that your father was unfortunate,
but that through life he never acted a deed nor conceived
a thought, that should stain your manly cheeks with
the blush of shame! I stand before you a culprit, as having
robbed you of your patrimony, but I have preserved
for you entire the inheritance of our honour!
This had been the first lesson imprinted upon my infant
mind. All other possessions I had ever held cheap and
worthless in comparison with that of an illustrious name.
My indignation at the attack it now sustained was boundless.
The more I thought, the more intolerable it appeared.
I was impatient and furious, like a lion struggling
in the toils. I could with joy have trampled under my
feet whoever aspersed me. I could have wantoned in blood,
and defied my adversaries to mortal combat. Alas, all my[185]
fury was useless here! It was no tale whispered in the
dark that I had to contend with; it was the commentary
of the world upon incontestable facts. Though a hecatomb
of souls should be sacrificed at the shrine of my blasted
name, the facts would still remain, the mystery still require
to be solved. Coligny, the virtuous Coligny, had made no
observations on the circumstances he mentioned; he merely
proposed a difficulty, and waited my answer.
I was called upon to exercise the whole of my deliberative
powers as to the reply which was to be returned, or
the conduct to be held, upon the question of Coligny.
Every thing I most valued was now at issue; and a false
step taken under the present circumstances could never be
retrieved. I had another sort of party to deal with here,
than when I had told Marguerite the tale of the stranger
and his legacy. Nothing would pass now, but what bore
an open, fair, and unequivocal appearance. I must vent
no assertion that could not bear to be sifted to the bottom,
and that did not fully accord with all the vouchers with
which it could be collated. I had written to Marguerite,
immediately after launching into the expense with which
our tour had been attended, that I had received an unexpected
acquisition from the death of a relation of my
own family in France. I knew that the story of the three
thousand crowns would no longer account for the style in
which I was proceeding, and this fabrication suggested
itself upon the spur of the moment. I hated to think of
the difficulties in the way of explanation in which I was
involved; I abhorred the system of falsehood I was driven
to practise. It did not occur to me at the time, infatuated
as I was! that I should have occasion to account for this
accession of wealth to any one out of my own family.
Marguerite, I well knew, had no correspondence in France,
nor therefore any obvious means of verifying or refuting
this second deception. But such a story could not be told
to noblemen of France, without being instantly liable to be
compared with known facts, and eventually investigated
upon the spot where the scene was laid. Marguerite herself,
I well knew, had listened with incredulity to the explanation
I had made, and the alleged legacy of the stranger;[186]
what could I expect from indifferent hearers? They might
not all possess her good sense and sagacity in judging; but
they were destitute of that personal kindness and partiality
which were calculated to induce her to credit whatever I
affirmed. Most men have a malignant pleasure in the detection
of specious pretences, in humbling the importunate
superiority that obscures their claims, and removing the
rival who might otherwise acquire the prize of which they
are in pursuit.
My mind was still torn and distracted with these contemplations,
when in the afternoon of the same day on
which I had received the visit of Coligny, my attention
was suddenly roused by the abrupt entrance of my son into
the chamber where I was sitting. He opened the door
with a hurried action as he entered, and, having closed it
impetuously after him, advanced directly towards me. He
then stopped himself; and, turning from me, I could perceive
a rush of crimson in his face like that of a man suffocated.
A passion of tears succeeded that shook his frame,
and sufficiently proved that his feelings had sustained some
extraordinary shock. My whole soul was alarmed at what
I saw; and, following him as he retired to the other side
of the room, in the gentlest accents I endeavoured to soothe
him, while I enquired with earnestness and trepidation into
the cause of his grief.
</div></body></text></TEI>