<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="21">

THERMOTICS PROPER.

CHAPTER I.
The Doctrines of Conduction and
Radiation.

Section 1.—Introduction of the
Doctrine of Conduction.
BY conduction is meant
the propagation of heat from one part to another of a continuous body;
or from one body to another in contact with it; as when one end of a
poker stuck in the fire heats the other end, or when this end heats
the hand which takes hold of it. By radiation is meant the
diffusion of heat from the surface of a body to points not in contact.
It is clear in both these cases, that, in proportion as the hot
portion is hotter, it produces a greater effect in warming the cooler
portion; that is, it communicates more Heat to it, if
Heat be the abstract conception of which this effect is the
measure. The simplest rule which can be proposed is, that the heat
thus communicated in a given instant is proportional to the excess of
the heat of the hot body over that of the contiguous bodies; there are
no obvious phenomena which contradict the supposition that this is the
true law; and it was thence assumed by Newton as the true law for
radiation and by other writers for conduction. This assumption was
confirmed approximately, and afterwards corrected, for the case of
Radiation; in its application to Conduction, it has been made the
basis of calculation up to the present time. We may observe that this
statement takes for granted that we have attained to a measure of heat
(or of temperature, as heat thus measured is termed),
corresponding to the law thus assumed; and, in fact, as we shall have
occasion to explain in speaking of the measures of sensible
qualities, 140 the
thermometrical scale of heat according to the expansion of liquids
(which is the measure of temperature here adopted), was constructed
with a reference to Newton’s law of radiation of heat; and thus the
law is necessarily consistent with the scale.
In any case in which the parts of a body are unequally hot, the
temperature will vary continuously in passing from one part of
the body to another; thus, a long bar of iron, of which one end is
kept red hot, will exhibit a gradual diminution of temperature at
successive points, proceeding to the other end. The law of temperature
of the parts of such a bar might be expressed by the ordinates of a
curve which should run alongside the bar. And, in order to
trace mathematically the consequences of the assumed law, some of
those processes would be necessary, by which mathematicians are
enabled to deal with the properties of curves; as the method of
infinitesimals, or the differential calculus; and the truth or
falsehood of the law would be determined, according to the usual rules
of inductive science, by a comparison of results so deduced from the
principle, with the observed phenomena.
It was easily perceived that this comparison was the task which
physical inquirers had to perform; but the execution of it was delayed
for some time; partly, perhaps, because the mathematical process
presented some difficulties. Even in a case so simple as that above
mentioned, of a linear bar with a stationary temperature at one end,
partial differentials entered; for there were three variable
quantities, the time, as well as the place of each point and its
temperature. And at first, another scruple occurred to M. Biot when,
about 1804, he undertook this problem.1 “A difficulty,”
says Laplace,2 in 1809, “presents itself, which has not
yet been solved. The quantities of heat received and communicated in
an instant (by any point of the bar) must be infinitely small
quantities of the same order as the excess of the heat of a slice of
the body over that of the contiguous slice; therefore the
excess of the heat received by any slice over the heat
communicated, is an infinitely small quantity of the second order; and
the accumulation in a finite time (which depends on this excess)
cannot be finite.” I conceive that this difficulty arises entirely
from an arbitrary and unnecessary assumption concerning the relation
of the infinitesimal parts of the body. Laplace resolved the
difficulty by further reasoning founded upon the same assumption which
occasioned 141 it;
but Fourier, who was the most distinguished of the cultivators of this
mathematical doctrine of conduction, follows a course of reasoning in
which the difficulty does not present itself. Indeed it is stated by
Laplace, in the Memoir above quoted,3 that Fourier had
already obtained the true fundamental equations by views of his
own.</div></body></text></TEI>