<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="35">
CHAPTER III.

On Man’s Place in the Universe.

The mere aspect of the starry heavens, without
taking into account the view of them to which science
introduces us, tends strongly to force upon man the[213]
impression of his own insignificance. The vault of
the sky arched at a vast and unknown distance over
our heads; the stars, apparently infinite in number,
each keeping its appointed place and course, and
seeming to belong to a wide system of things which
has no relation to the earth; while man is but one
among many millions of the earth’s inhabitants;—all
this makes the contemplative spectator feel how
exceedingly small a portion of the universe he is;
how little he must be, in the eyes of an intelligence
which can embrace the whole. Every person, in
every age and country, will recognize as irresistibly
natural the train of thought expressed by the Hebrew
psalmist: “when I consider the heavens the work of
thy hands—the moon and the stars which thou
hast ordained—Lord what is man that thou art
mindful of him, or the son of man that thou regardest
him?”
If this be the feeling of the untaught person, when
he contemplates the aspect of the skies, such as they
offer themselves to a casual and unassisted glance,
the impression must needs be incalculably augmented,
when we look at the universe with the aid of astronomical
discovery and theory. We then find,
that a few of the shining points which we see scattered
on the face of the sky in such profusion, appear
to be of the same nature as the earth, and may
perhaps, as analogy would suggest, be like the earth,
the habitations of organized beings;—that the rest
of “the host of heaven” may, by a like analogy, be
conjectured to be the centres of similar systems of
revolving worlds;—that the vision of man has gone
travelling onwards, to an extent never anticipated,
through this multitude of systems, and that while
myriads of new centres start up at every advance,
he appears as yet not to have received any intimation
of a limit. Every person probably feels, at first,
lost, confounded, overwhelmed, with the vastness of
this spectacle; and seems to himself, as it were, annihilated
by the magnitude and multitude of the objects[214]
which thus compose the universe. The distance
between him and the Creator of the world appears
to be increased beyond measure by this disclosure.
It seems as if a single individual could have no
chance and no claim for the regard of the Ruler of
the whole.
The mode in which the belief of God’s government
of the physical world is important and interesting
to man, is, as has already been said, through the
connexion which this belief has with the conviction
of God’s government of the moral world; this latter
government being, from its nature, one which has
a personal relation to each individual, his actions and
thoughts. It will, therefore, illustrate our subject to
show that this impression of the difficulty of a personal
superintendence and government, exercised by
the Maker of the world over each of his rational
and free creatures, is founded upon illusory views;
and that on an attentive and philosophical examination
of the subject, such a government is in accordance
with all that we can discover of the scheme
and the scale of the universe.
1. We may, in the first place, repeat the observation
made in the last chapter, on the confusion
which sometimes arises in our minds, and makes us
consider the number of the objects of the Divine care
as a difficulty in the way of its exercise. If we can
conceive this care employed on a million of persons,
on the population of a kingdom, of a city, of a street,
there is no real difficulty in supposing it extended to
every planet in the solar system, admitting each to
be peopled as ours is; nor to every part of the universe,
supposing each star the centre of such a system.
Numbers are nothing in themselves; and when
we reject the known, but unessential limits of our own
faculties, it is quite as allowable to suppose a million
millions of earths, as one, to be under the moral government
of God.
2. In the next place we may remark, not only that
no reason can be assigned why the Divine care should[215]
not extend to a much greater number of individuals
than we at first imagine, but that in fact we know
that it does so extend. It has been well observed,
that about the same time when the invention of the
telescope showed us that there might be myriads of
other worlds claiming the Creator’s care; the invention
of the microscope proved to us that there were
in our own world myriads of creatures, before unknown,
which this care was preserving. While one
discovery seemed to remove the Divine Providence
further from us, the other gave us most striking examples
that it was far more active in our neighbourhood
than we had supposed: while the first extended
the boundaries of God’s known kingdom, the second
made its known administration more minute and
careful. It appeared that in the leaf and in the bud,
in solids and in fluids, animals existed hitherto unsuspected;
the apparently dead masses and blank spaces
of the world were found to swarm with life. And
yet, of the animals thus revealed, all, though unknown
to us before, had never been forgotten by Providence.
Their structure, their vessels and limbs, their adaptation
to their situation, their food and habitations, were
regulated in as beautiful and complete a manner as
those of the largest and apparently most favoured
animals. The smallest insects are as exactly finished,
often as gaily ornamented, as the most graceful
beasts or the birds of brightest plumage. And when
we seem to go out of the domain of the complex animal
structure with which we are familiar, and come
to animals of apparently more scanty faculties, and
less developed powers of enjoyment and action, we
still find that their faculties and their senses are in
exact harmony with their situation and circumstances;
that the wants which they have are provided
for, and the powers which they possess called
into activity. So that Müller, the patient and accurate
observer of the smallest and most obscure microscopical
animalcula, declares that all classes alike,
those which have manifest organs, and those which[216]
have not, offer a vast quantity of new and striking
views of the animal economy; every step of our discoveries
leading us to admire the design and care of
the Creator.[27] We find, therefore, that the Divine
Providence is, in fact, capable of extending itself
adequately to an immense succession of tribes of beings,
surpassing what we can imagine or could previously
have anticipated; and thus we may feel secure,
so far as analogy can secure us, that the mere
multitude of created objects cannot remove us from
the government and superintendence of the Creator.
3. We may observe further, that, vast as are the
parts and proportions of the universe, we still appear
to be able to perceive that it is finite; the subordination
of magnitudes and numbers and classes appears
to have its limits. Thus, for any thing which we can
discover, the sun is the largest body in the universe;
and at any rate, bodies of the order of the sun are
the largest of which we have any evidence: we
know of no substance denser than gold, and it is improbable
that one denser, or at least much denser,
should ever be detected: the largest animals which
exist in the sea and on the earth are almost certainly
known to us. We may venture also to say, that the
smallest animals which possess in their structure a
clear analogy with larger ones, have been already
seen. Many of the animals which the microscope
detects, are as complete and complex in their organization
as those of larger size: but beyond a certain
point, they appear, as they become more minute, to
be reduced to a homogeneity and simplicity of composition
which almost excludes them from the domain
of animal life. The smallest microscopical objects
which can be supposed to be organic, are
points,[28] or gelatinous globules,[29] or threads,[30] in which
no distinct organs, interior or exterior, can be discovered.
These, it is clear, cannot be considered as[217]
indicating an indefinite progression of animal life in
a descending scale of minuteness. We can, mathematically
speaking, conceive one of these animals as
perfect and complicated in its structure as an elephant
or an eagle, but we do not find it so in nature.
It appears, on the contrary, in these objects, as if
we were, at a certain point of magnitude, reaching
the boundaries of the animal world. We need not
here consider the hypotheses and opinions to which
these ambiguous objects have given rise; but, without
any theory, they tend to show that the subordination
of organic life is finite on the side of the little as well
as of the great.
Some persons might, perhaps, imagine that a
ground for believing the smallness of organized beings
to be limited, might be found in what we know
of the constitution of matter. If solids and fluids
consist of particles of a definite, though exceeding
smallness, which cannot further be divided or diminished,
it is manifest that we have, in the smallness
of these particles, a limit to the possible size of the
vessels and organs of animals. The fluids which
are secreted, and which circulate in the body of a
mite, must needs consist of a vast number of particles,
or they would not be fluids: and an animal
might be so much smaller than a mite, that its tubes
could not contain a sufficient collection of the atoms
of matter, to carry on its functions. We should,
therefore, of necessity reach a limit of minuteness
in organic life, if we could demonstrate that matter
is composed of such indivisible atoms. We shall
not, however, build any thing on this argument;
because, though the atomic theory is sometimes said
to be proved, what is proved is, that chemical and
other effects take place as if they were the aggregate
of the effects of certain particles of elements,
the proportions of which particles are fixed and definite;
but that any limit can be assigned to the
smallness of these particles, has never yet been made
out. We prefer, therefore, to rest the proof of the[218]
finite extent of animal life, as to size, on the microscopical
observations previously referred to.
Probably we cannot yet be said to have reached
the limit of the universe with the power of our telescopes;
that is, it does not appear that telescopes
have yet been used, so powerful in exhibiting small
stars, that we can assume that more powerful instruments
would not discover new stars. Whether
or no, however, this degree of perfection has been
reached, we have no proof that it does not exist;
if it were once obtained we should have, with some
approximation, the limit of the universe as to the
number of worlds, as we have already endeavoured
to show we have obtained the limits with regard to
the largeness and smallness of the inhabitants of our
own world.
In like manner, although the discovery of new
species in some of the kingdoms of nature has gone
on recently with enormous rapidity, and to an immense
extent;—for instance in botany, where the
species known in the time of Linnæus were about
ten thousand, and are now probably fifty thousand;—there
can be no doubt that the number of species
and genera is really limited; and though a great extension
of our knowledge is required to reach these
limits, it is our ignorance merely, and not their nonexistence,
which removes them from us.
In the same way it would appear that the universe,
so far as it is an object of our knowledge, is finite
in other respects also. Now when we have once
attained this conviction, all the oppressive apprehension
of being overlooked in the government of the
universe has no longer any rational source. For in
the superintendence of a finite system of things, what
is there which can appear difficult or overwhelming
to a Being such as we must, from what we know,
conceive the Creator to be? Difficulties arising from
space, number, gradation, are such as we can conceive
ourselves capable of overcoming, merely by an
extension of our present faculties. Is it not then[219]
easy to imagine that such difficulties must vanish
before Him who made us and our faculties? Let it
be considered how enormous a proportion the largest
work of man bears to the smallest;—the great pyramid
to the point of a needle. This comparison
does not overwhelm us, because we know that man
has made both. Yet the difference between this
proportion and that of the sun to the claw of a mite,
does not at all correspond to the difference which we
must suppose to obtain between the Creator and the
creature. It appears then that, if the first flash of
that view of the universe which science reveals to
us, does sometimes dazzle and bewilder men, a more
attentive examination of the prospect, by the light
we thus obtain, shows us how unfounded is the despair
of our being the objects of Divine Providence,
how absurd the persuasion that we have discovered
the universe to be too large for its ruler.
4. Another ground of satisfactory reflection, having
the same tendency, is to be found in the admirable
order and consistency, the subordination and
proportion of parts, which we find to prevail in the
universe, as far as our discoveries reach. We have,
it may be, a multitude almost innumerable of worlds,
but no symptom of crowding, of confusion, of interference.
All such defects are avoided by the manner
in which these worlds are distributed into systems;—these
systems, each occupying a vast space, but yet
disposed at distances before which their own dimensions
shrink into insignificance;—all governed by one
law, yet this law so concentrating its operation on
each system, that each proceeds as if there were no
other, and so regulating its own effects that perpetual
change produces permanent uniformity. This
is the kind of harmonious relation which we perceive
in that part of the universe, the mechanical part
namely, the laws of which are best known to us.
In other provinces, where our knowledge is more
imperfect, we can see glimpses of a similar vastness
of combination, producing, by its very nature, completeness[220]
of detail. Any analogy by which we can
extend such views to the moral world, must be of a
very wide and indefinite kind; yet the contemplation
of this admirable relation of the arrangements of the
physical creation, and the perfect working of their
laws, is well calculated to give us confidence in a
similar beauty and perfection in the arrangements
by which our moral relations are directed, our
higher powers and hopes unfolded. We may readily
believe that there is, in this part of the creation also,
an order, a subordination of some relations to others,
which may remove all difficulty arising from the
vast multitude of moral agents and actions, and make
it possible that the superintendence of the moral
world shall be directed with as exact a tendency to
moral good, as that by which the government of the
physical world is directed to physical good.
We may perhaps see glimpses of such an order,
in the arrangements by which our highest and most
important duties depend upon our relation to a small
circle of persons immediately around us: and again,
in the manner in which our acting well or ill results
from the operation of a few principles within us; as
our conscience, our desire of moral excellence, and
of the favour of God. We can hardly consider such
principles otherwise than as intended to occupy their
proper place in the system by which man’s destination
is to be determined; and thus, as among the
means of the government and superintendence of
God in the moral world.
That there must be an order and a system to which
such regulative principles belong, the whole analogy
of creation compels us to believe. It would be strange
indeed, if, while the mechanical world, the system of
inert matter, is so arranged that we cannot contemplate
its order without an elevated intellectual pleasure;—while
organized life has no faculties without
their proper scope, no tendencies without their appointed
object;—the rational faculties and moral tendencies
of man should belong to no systematic order,[221]
should operate with no corresponding purpose: that,
while the perception of sweet and bitter has its acknowledged
and unmistakeable uses, the universal
perception of right and wrong, the unconquerable
belief of the merit of certain feelings and actions, the
craving alike after moral advancement and after the
means of attaining it, should exist only to delude,
perplex, and disappoint man. No one, with his contemplations
calmed and filled and harmonized by the
view of the known constitution of the universe, its
machinery “wheeling unshaken” in the farthest skies
and in the darkest cavern, its vital spirit breathing
alike effectively in the veins of the philosopher and
the worm;—no one, under the influence of such a
train of contemplations, can possibly admit into his
mind a persuasion which makes the moral part of
our nature a collection of inconsistent and futile impressions,
of idle dreams and warring opinions, each
having the same claims to our acceptance. Wide as
is the distance between the material and the moral
world; shadowy as all reasonings necessarily are
which attempt to carry the inferences of one into the
other; elevated above the region of matter as all the
principles and grounds of truth must be, which belong
to our responsibilities and hopes; still the astronomical
and natural philosopher can hardly fail to
draw from their studies an imperturbable conviction
that our moral nature cannot correspond to those representations
according to which it has no law, coherency,
or object. The mere natural reasoner may,
or must stop far short of all that it is his highest interest
to know, his first duty to pursue; but even he,
if he take any elevated and comprehensive views of
his own subject, must escape from the opinions, as
unphilosophical as they are comfortless, which would
expel from our view of the world all reference to
duty and moral good, all reliance on the most universal
grounds of trust and hope.
Men’s belief of their duty, and of the reasons for
practising it, connected as it is with the conviction[222]
of a personal relation to their Maker, and of His power
of superintendence and reward, is as manifest a fact
in the moral, as any that can be pointed out is in
the natural world. By mere analogy which has been
intimated, therefore, we cannot but conceive that
this fact belongs in some manner or other to the
order of the moral world, and of its government.
When any one acknowledges a moral governor of
the world; perceives that domestic and social relations
are perpetually operating and seem intended to
operate, to retain and direct men in the path of duty;
and feels that the voice of conscience, the peace of
heart which results from a course of virtue, and the
consolations of devotion, are ever ready to assume
their office as our guides and aids in the conduct of
all our actions;—he will probably be willing to acknowledge
also that the means of moral government
are not wanting, and will no longer be oppressed or
disturbed by the apprehension that the superintendence
of the world may be too difficult for its Ruler,
and that any of His subjects and servants may be
overlooked. He will no more fear that the moral
than that the physical laws of God’s creation
should be forgotten in any particular case: and as he
knows that every sparrow which falls to the ground
contains in its structure innumerable marks of the
Divine care and kindness, he will be persuaded that
every individual, however apparently humble and insignificant,
will have his moral being dealt with according
to the laws of God’s wisdom and love; will
be enlightened, supported, and raised, if he use the
appointed means which God’s administration of the
world of moral light and good offers to his use.
</div></body></text></TEI>