<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="22">

CHAPTER XII.
Of the Foundations of the Higher Mathematics.


1. The Idea of a Limit.—The general truths
concerning relations of space which depend upon the axioms
and definitions contained in Euclid’s Elements, and
which involve only properties of straight lines and circles,
are termed Elementary Geometry: all beyond this belongs to
the Higher Geometry. To this latter province appertain, for
example, all propositions respecting the lengths of any
portions of curve lines; for these cannot be obtained by
means of the principles of the Elements alone. Here then we
must ask to what other principles the geometer has recourse,
and from what source these are drawn. Is there any origin of
geometrical truth which we have not yet explored?
The Idea of a Limit supplies a new mode of
establishing mathematical truths. Thus with regard to the
length of any portion of a curve, a problem which we have
just mentioned; a curve is not made up of straight lines,
and therefore we cannot by means of any of the doctrines of
elementary geometry measure the length of any curve. But we
may make up a figure nearly resembling any curve by putting
together many short straight lines, just as a polygonal
building of very many sides may nearly resemble a circular
room. And in order to approach nearer and nearer to the
curve, we may make the sides more and more small, more and
more numerous. We may then possibly find some mode of
measurement, some relation of these small lines to other
lines, which is not disturbed by the multiplication of the
sides, however far it be carried. And thus, we may do what
is equivalent to measuring the curve itself; for by
multiplying the 152 sides we may approach more and more
closely to the curve till no appreciable difference remains.
The curve line is the Limit of the polygon; and in
this process we proceed on the Axiom, that ‘What is
true up to the Limit is true at the Limit.’
This mode of conceiving mathematical magnitudes is of wide
extent and use; for every curve may be considered as the
limit of some polygon; every varied magnitude, as the limit
of some aggregate of simpler forms; and thus the relations
of the elementary figures enable us to advance to the
properties of the most complex cases.
A Limit is a peculiar and fundamental conception, the use of
which in proving the propositions of the Higher Geometry
cannot be superseded by any combination of other hypotheses
and definitions14. The axiom just noticed, that what is
true up to the limit is true at the limit, is involved in
the very conception of a Limit: and this principle, with its
consequences, leads to all the results which form the
subject of the higher mathematics, whether proved by the
consideration of evanescent triangles, by the processes of
the Differential Calculus, or in any other way.</div></body></text></TEI>