<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 165, folios 132-135</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 165, folios 132-135.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1839">undated [after 2 July 1839]</date>
          <note type="place">[no place]</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 165, folios 132-135</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_165_folios_132-135.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Monday Evg. 6 o'clock</p>
      <p>Dearest William. Dr Locock is quite decided with respect to the baby, &amp; says that he must positively have one grain of calomel, &amp; that without delay;-- unless there is a decided amendment by the time this is received; and by a decided amendment he</p>
      <p>means cessation of sickness (&amp; especially of the yellowness that accompanied it), and and improved state of bowels.</p>
      <p>He says that the symptoms mentioned most clearly make the calomel imperative. His diet to be continued milk, but he advises it to be made thinner with water perhaps than it has hitherto been.--</p>
      <p>If the calomel should unsettle the stomach &amp;</p>
      <p>act perhaps rather overmuch I have with me to bring down tomorrow, what will be proper to give.-- I have directed that this letter be given to you the moment the man arrives, &amp; that if asleep you may be woke, as Dr Locock says that if the baby is not most decidedly better by that time, it will be of importance not to delay. You had better take this</p>
      <p>up stairs directly &amp; read Green what I have said. I, knowing she has neither medicines, scales, nor anything, have sent down two little papers of calomel containing one grain apiece. I send two of these only in case of an accident happening to one. The baby might spit it out, or some other accident occur.-- The calomel is to be mixed up with a little sugar &amp; water into a kind of paste &amp; put into its mouth to</p>
      <p>suck down. It is not to be given in any liquid.--</p>
      <p>Dr Locock also wishes enquiry to be made if there is any healthy young woman in the neighbourhood who could &amp; would act as wet-nurse, in case of need.-- She must be young (I suppose he means from 20 to 30 years) &amp; above all perfectly strong &amp; healthy. I trust we may not be driven to this extremity, but Dr L says that should</p>
      <p>the child continue disordered after the calamel has had fair trial, he must be suckled to save his life. In this case, taking him to Ashley would be out of the question, &amp; Green must then stay at Ockham with him. Annabella I should give to your sisters, &amp; take Byron with us.--</p>
      <p>I am very well indeed this evening, except a very slight cold;-- so slight that</p>
      <p>I think it very unlikely to interfere with my going tomorrow. I mean to go early, that is directly after luncheon, so send the horses in good time.--</p>
      <p>Dr Locock will not hear of even the quietest poney for riding, before Monday next, &amp; says that I might be unable to stand or quit a horizontal position for months, &amp; even receive irreparable injury, from an accidental start such as</p>
      <p>any dull beast might give, up to that time. Pray take care of my dear little Ralph, until I come.-- Oh! Dear William, I hope he will do well, for I am so fond of him, poor little fellow!--</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
