<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="49">

NOTE TO CHAPTER III.


[3rd Ed.]—[The doctrine here propounded, that All
Matter is Heavy, has been opposed by Sir William
Hamilton of Edinburgh. (Works of Reid, note, p. 853.)
This writer is a man of unquestionable acuteness and
of very extensive reading; but his acuteness shows
itself in barren ontological distinctions, which appear
to me to be of the same character as the speculations
of the eminent Schoolmen of the most sterile periods of
the dark ages. That he should have no conception of
progressive or inductive science is not wonderful, when
we recollect that he holds, as an important part of his
philosophy, that the study of mathematics perverts and
obscures the mind. But it may be of some interest to
consider his objections to the doctrine here maintained.
He says, 1st, that our reasoning assumes that we
must necessarily have it in our power to ascertain the
Quantity of Matter; whereas this may be a problem
out of the reach of human determination.
To this I reply, that my reasoning does assume that
there is a science, or sciences, which make assertions
concerning the Quantity of Matter: Mechanics and
Chemistry are such sciences. My assertion is, that to
make such sciences possible, Quantity of Matter must
be proportional to Weight. If my opponent deny that
Mechanics and Chemistry can exist as sciences, he may
invalidate my proof; but not otherwise.
2. He says that there are two conceivable ways of
estimating the Quantity of Matter: by the Space occupied, and by the Weight or Inertia; and that I assume
the second measure gratuitously.
To which I reply, that the most elementary steps in
Mechanics and in Chemistry contradict the notion that 38 the Quantity of Matter is proportionate to the Space.
They proceed necessarily on a distinction between
Space and Matter:—between mere Extension and material Substance.
3. He allows that we cannot make the Extension of
a body the measure of the Quantity of Matter, because,
he says, we do not know if ‘the compressing force’ is
such as to produce ‘the closest compression.’ That is,
he assumes a compressing force, assumes a closest compression, assumes a peculiar (and very improbable)
atomic hypothesis; and all this to supply a reason why
we are not to believe the first simple principle of
Mechanics and Chemistry.
4. He speaks of ‘a series of apparent fluids (as Light
or its vehicle, the Calorific, the Electro-galvanic, and
Magnetic agents) which we can neither denude of their
character of substance, nor clothe with the attribute of
weight.’
To which my reply is, that precisely because I cannot
‘clothe’ these agents with the attribute of Weight, I
do ‘denude them of the character of Substance.’ They
are not substances, but agencies. These Imponderable
Agents are not properly called ‘Imponderable Fluids.’
This I conceive that I have proved; and the proof is
not shaken by denying the conclusion without showing
any defect in the reasoning.
5. Finally, my critic speaks about ‘a logical canon,’
and about ‘a criterion of truth, subjectively necessary
and objectively certain;’ which matters I shall not
waste the reader’s time by discussing.]</div></body></text></TEI>