<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="3">CHAPTER I.
There is nothing that human imagination can figure
brilliant and enviable, that human genius and skill do not
aspire to realize. In the early ages of antiquity, one of
the favourite topics of speculation was a perfect system of
civil policy; and no sooner had Plato delineated his imaginary
republic, than he sought for a spot of earth upon
which to execute his plan. In my own times, and for
upwards of a century before them, the subject which has
chiefly occupied men of intrepid and persevering study,
has been the great secret of nature, the opus magnum, in
its two grand and inseparable branches, the art of multiplying
gold, and of defying the inroads of infirmity and
death.
It is notorious that uncommon talents and unparalleled
industry have been engaged in this mighty task. It has,
I know, been disputed by the audacious adversaries of
all sober and reasonable evidence, whether these talents
and industry have in any case attained the object they
sought. It is not to my purpose to ascertain the number
of those whose victory over the powers and inertness of
matter has been complete. It is enough that I am a living
instance of the existence of such men. To these two secrets,
if they are to be considered as two, I have been for
years in the habit of resorting for my gratification. I have
in my possession the choice of being as wealthy as I please,
and the gift of immortal life. Every thing that I see
almost, I can without difficulty make my own; for what
palaces, pictures, parks or gardens, rarities of art or nature,
have not a price at which their owner will consent to yield[2]
them? The luxuries of every quarter of the world are
emptied at my feet. I can command, to an extent almost
inconceivable, the passions of men. What heart can withstand
the assault of princely magnificence? What man is
inaccessible to a bribe? Add to these advantages, that I am
invulnerable to disease. Every sun that rises, finds the
circulations of my frame in the most perfect order. Decrepitude
can never approach me. A thousand winters want
the power to furrow my countenance with wrinkles, or
turn my hairs to silver. Exhaustless wealth and eternal
youth are the attributes by which I am distinguished from
the rest of mankind.
I do not sit down now to write a treatise of natural philosophy.
The condition by which I hold my privileges is,
that they must never be imparted. I sit down purely to
relate a few of those extraordinary events that have been
produced, in the period of my life which is already elapsed,
by the circumstances and the peculiarity to which I have
just alluded.
It is so obvious, as to make it almost improper to specify
it, that the pursuit in which so many of my contemporaries
are engaged, and the end of which I have so singularly
achieved, is in its appearance infinitely more grand and
interesting than that which occupied the thoughts of Plato
and the most eminent writers of antiquity. What is political
liberty compared with unbounded riches and immortal
vigour? The immediate application of political liberty is,
to render a man’s patrimony or the fruits of his industry
completely his own, and to preserve them from the invasion
of others. But the petty detail of preservation or gradual
acquisition can never enter into competition with the great
secret, which endows a man in a moment with every
thing that the human heart can wish. Considered in this
light, how mean and contemptible does the ambition of the
boasted ancients appear, compared with ours? What adept
or probationer of the present day would be content to
resign the study of God and the profounder secrets of
nature, and to bound his ardour to the investigation of his
own miserable existence?
It may seem perhaps to many, that the history of a person[3]
possessed of advantages so unparalleled as mine, must
be, like the history of paradise, or of the future happiness
of the blessed, too calm and motionless, too much of one
invariable texture and exempt from vicissitude, to excite
the attention or interest the passions of the reader. If he
will have patience, and apply to the perusal of my narrative,
he will in no long time perceive how far his conjecture
is founded in sagacity and reason.
Some persons may be curious to know what motives can
have induced a man of such enormous wealth, and so every
way qualified to revel in delights, to take the trouble of
penning his memoirs. The immortality with which I am
endowed seems to put out of the question the common motives
that relate to posthumous fame.
The curiosity here mentioned, if it really exists, I cannot
consent to gratify. I will anticipate nothing. In the
progress of my story, my motive for recording it will probably
become evident.
I am descended from one of the most ancient and honourable
families of the kingdom of France. I was the only
child of my father, who died while I was an infant. My
mother was a woman of rather a masculine understanding,
and full of the prejudices of nobility and magnificence.
Her whole soul was in a manner concentrated in the ambition
to render me the worthy successor of the counts de
St. Leon, who had figured with distinguished reputation in
the wars of the Holy Land. My father had died fighting
gallantly in the plains of Italy under the standard of Louis
the Twelfth; a prince whose name was never repeated to
me unaccompanied with the praises due to his military
prowess, and to the singular humanity of disposition by
which he acquired the title of The father of his people. My
mother’s mind was inflamed with the greatness of my ancestors,
and she indefatigably sought to kindle in my bosom
a similar flame. It has been a long-established custom for
the barons and feudal vassals of the kings of France to
enter with great personal expense into the brilliant and
dazzling expeditions of their sovereigns; and my father
greatly impaired his fortune in preparations for that very
campaign in which he terminated his life. My mother[4]
industriously applied herself to the restoration of my patrimony;
and the long period of my minority afforded her
scope for that purpose.
It was impossible for any boy to be treated with more
kindness and considerate indulgence than I was during the
period of my adolescence. My mother loved me to the
very utmost limits perhaps of human affection. I was
her darling and her pride, her waking study, and her nightly
dream. Yet I was not pampered into corporeal imbecility,
or suffered to rust in inactivity of mind. I was provided
with the best masters. I was excited, and successfully excited,
zealously to apply myself to the lessons they taught.
I became intimately acquainted with the Italian writers of
the twelfth and thirteenth centuries. I was initiated in the
study of the classics, to the cultivation of which the revival
of letters at this time gave particular ardour. I was instructed
in the principles of the fine arts. There was no
species of accomplishment at that time in vogue, that my
mother was not anxious I should make my own. The only
science I neglected was the very science which has since
given rise to the most extraordinary events of my life. But
the object to which my attention was principally called,
was the pursuit of military exercises, and the cultivation of
every thing that could add to the strength, agility, or grace
of my body, and to the adventurousness and enterprise of
my mind. My mother loved my honour and my fame
more than she loved my person.
A circumstance that tended perhaps more than any other
to fix the yet fluctuating character of my youthful mind,
was my being present as a spectator at the celebrated meeting
between Francis the First and Henry the Eighth, king
of England, in a field between Ardres and Guines. My
mother refused to accompany me, being already arrived at
an age in which curiosity and the love of festive scenes are
usually diminished, and the expenses incurred by all the
nobility who attended upon this scene being incompatible
with the economy to which she rigidly adhered. I was
therefore placed under the protection of the Marquis de
Villeroy, her brother, and, with two servants who attended
me, formed a part of his suite.
[5]
I was at this time fifteen years of age. My contemplations
had been familiar with ideas of magnificence and
grandeur, but my life had been spent in the most sequestered
retirement. This contrast had a particular effect
upon my disposition; it irritated to a very high degree my
passion for splendour and distinction; I lived in the fairy
fields of visionary greatness, and was more than indifferent
to the major part of the objects around me. I pined for
every thing the reverse of my present condition; I cultivated
the exercises in which I was engaged, only as they
were calculated to prepare me for future achievements.
By the incident I have mentioned, I was transported at
once from a scene of modest obscurity, to a scene of the
most lavish splendour that the world perhaps ever contemplated.
I never remembered to have seen even Paris itself.
The prevailing taste of Europe has for some time led very
much to costliness in dress. This taste, in its present profusion,
I believe took its rise in the field of the Vale of
Ardres. The two kings were both in the vigour of their
youth, and were said to be the handsomest men of the age
in which they lived. The beauty of Henry was sturdy and
muscular; that of Francis more refined and elegant, without
subtracting in any considerable degree from the firmness
of his make. Henry was four years older than his
brother monarch. The first of them might have been taken
as a model to represent a youthful Hercules, and the last an
Apollo.
The splendour of dress that was worn upon this occasion
exceeds almost all credibility. Every person of distinction
might be said in a manner to carry an estate upon his
shoulders; nor was the variety of garments inferior to the
richness. Wolsey, a man whose magnificence of disposition
was only surpassed by the pride of his soul, was for the
most part the director of the whole. He possessed the most
absolute ascendancy over the mind of his master, at the
same time that Francis artfully indulged his caprice, that
he might claim from him in return a similar indulgence in
weightier matters.
The pomp of processions, and the ceremony of opening
this memorable festival, went first; a sort of solemn and[6]
half-moving pageant, which the eye took in at leisure, and
took in till it was filled. This was succeeded by every
thing that was rapid, animated, and interesting: masques
and exhibitions of all kinds; and, which was still more to
me, and which my soul devoured with indescribable ardour,
joustings, tilts, and tournaments without end. The beauty
of the armour, the caparisons of the steeds, the mettle of
the animals themselves, and the ardour and grace of the
combatants, surpassed every thing that my fancy had ever
painted. These scenes were acted in the midst of a vast
amphitheatre of spectators, where all that was noble and
eminent of either country was assembled—the manliness of
aspiring youth, and the boundless varieties of female attraction.
All were in their gayest attire; every eye was
lighted up with complacency and joy. If Heraclitus, or
any other morose philosopher who has expatiated on the
universal misery of mankind, had entered the field of Ardres,
he must have retracted his assertions, or fled from the
scene with confusion. The kings were placed at either end
of the lists, surrounded with their courtiers. Every eye
through this vast assembly was fixed upon the combatants;
the body of every one present was inclined this way or that,
in unconscious sympathy with the redoubted knights. From
time to time, as the favourites of either party prevailed, the
air was rent with shouts and acclamations.
What added to the fascination of all that I have yet
mentioned, was that now, for the first time in an equal
degree perhaps for centuries, the stiffness of unwieldy form
was laid aside, and the heart of man expanded itself with
generosity and confidence. It burst the fetters of ages;
and, having burst them, it seemed to revel in its new-found
liberty. It is well known that, after a few days of idle
precaution and specious imprisonment on both sides, Francis
one morning mounted his horse, and appeared, without
guards or any previous notice, before the tent of Henry.
The example was contagious, and from this time all ceremony
was laid aside. The kings themselves entered personally
into the combats of their subjects. It was a
delightful and a ravishing spectacle, to witness the freedom
of the old Roman manners, almost of the old Roman Saturnalia,[7]
polished and refined with all that was graceful and
humane in the age of chivalry.
It may easily be imagined what an effect a scene like
this was calculated to produce upon a youth of my age and
my education. I recollected with anguish that the immaturity
of my years precluded me from taking any active
part in the spectacle. My appearance however was sufficiently
advantageous. I was presented to Francis the
First. He did me the honour to question me respecting
my studies; and, finding in me some knowledge of those
arts and that literature, of which he was himself so zealous
a favourer, he expressed to my uncle a great satisfaction
with my figure and acquisitions. I might from this time
have been taken to court, and made one of the pages to
this illustrious monarch. But the plan of my mother was
different. She did not wish for the present that my eye
should be satiated with public scenes, or that the public
should grow too familiarly acquainted with my person. She
rightly judged that my passion for the theatre of glory
would grow more impetuous, by being withheld for some
time from the gratifications for which it panted. She wished
that I should present myself for the first time among
the nobility of France an accomplished cavalier, and not
suffer the disadvantage of having exposed in the eye of the
world those false steps and frailties, from which the inexperience
of youth is never entirely free. These motives being
explained to the king, he was graciously pleased to
sanction them with his approbation. I accordingly returned
to finish the course of my education at my paternal château
upon the banks of the Garonne.
The state of my mind during the three succeeding years
amply justified the sagacity of my mother. I was more
eager for improvement than I had ever yet been. I
had before formed some conceptions of the career of honour
from the books I had read, and from the conversation of
this excellent matron. But my reveries were impotent and
little, compared with what I had now seen. Like the author
of our holy religion, I had spent my forty days without
food in the wilderness, when suddenly my eyes were
opened, and I was presented with all the kingdoms of the[8]
world, and all the glory of them. The fairy scene continued
for a moment, and then vanished; leaving nothing
behind it on all sides, but the same barrenness and gloom
by which it had been preceded. I never shut my eyes
without viewing in imagination the combats of knights and
the train of ladies. I had been regarded with distinction
by my sovereign; and Francis the First stood before my
mind the abstract and model of perfection and greatness.
I congratulated myself upon being born in an age and
country so favourable to the acquisition of all that my soul
desired.
I was already eighteen years of age, when I experienced
the first misfortune that ever befel me. It was the death
of my mother. She felt the approach of her dissolution
several weeks before it arrived, and held repeated conversations
with me, respecting the feelings I ought to entertain,
and the conduct it would become me to pursue, when she
should be no more.
“My son,” said she, “your character, and the promise
of your early years, have constituted my only consolation
since the death of your excellent father. Our marriage
was the result of a most sincere and exclusive attachment;
and never did man more deserve to be loved than Reginald
de St. Leon. When he died, the whole world would have
been nothing to me but one vast blank, if he had not left
behind him the representative of his person, and the heir
to his virtues. While I was busied in your education, I
seemed to be discharging the last duty to the memory of
my husband. The occupation was sacred to the honour of
the dead, even before it became so peculiarly pleasing to
me upon its own account, as I afterwards found it. I hope
I have in some measure discharged the task, in the manner
in which my lord your father would have wished it to have
been discharged, if he had lived. I am thankful to Heaven,
that I have been spared so long for so dear and honourable
a purpose.
“You must now, my son, stand by yourself, and be the
arbitrator of your own actions. I could have wished that
this necessity might have been a little further deferred;
but I trust your education has not been of that sort which[9]
is calculated to render a young man helpless and contemptible.
You have been taught to know your rank in society,
and to respect yourself. You have been instructed in every
thing that might most effectually forward you in the career
of glory. There is not a young cavalier among all the nobility
of France more accomplished, or that promises to do
greater honour to his name and his country. I shall not
live to witness the performance of this promise, but the
anticipation even now, pours a long stream of sunshine on
my departing hour.
“Farewell, my son! You no longer stand in need of
my maternal care. When I am gone, you will be compelled
more vividly to feel that singleness and self-dependence
which are the source of all virtue. Be careful of yourself.
Be careful that your career may be both spotless and
illustrious. Hold your life as a thing of no account, when
it enters into competition with your fame. A true knight
thinks no sacrifice and suffering hard, that honour demands.
Be humane, gentle, generous, and intrepid. Be prompt
to follow wherever your duty calls you. Remember your
ancestors, knights of the Holy Cross. Remember your
father. Follow your king, who is the mirror of valour:
and be ever ready for the service of the distressed. May
Providence be your guardian. May Heaven shower down
a thousand blessings, upon your innocence, and the gallantry
of your soul!”
The death of my mother was a severe blow to my heart.
For some time all the visions of greatness and renown which
had hitherto been my chosen delight appeared distasteful
to me. I hung over her insensible corpse. When it had
been committed to the earth, I repaired every day to the
spot where it was deposited, at the hour of dusk, when all
visible objects faded from the eye, when nature assumed
her saddest tints, and the whole world seemed about to be
wrapped in the darkness of the tomb. The dew of night
drizzled unheeded on my head; and I did not turn again
towards the turrets of the château, till the hour of midnight
had already sounded through the stillness of the scene.
Time is the healer of almost every grief, particularly in
the sprightly season of early youth. In no long period[10]
I changed the oppression of inactive sorrow, for the affectionate
and pious recollection of my mother’s last instructions.
I had been too deeply imbued with sentiments of
glory, for it to be possible, when the first excess of grief
was over, that I should remain in indolence. The tender
remembrance of my mother itself, in no long time, furnished
a new stimulus to my ambition. I forgot the melancholy
spectacle of the last struggles of her expiring life;
I even became accustomed no longer to hear her voice, no
longer to expect her presence, when I returned to the château
from a short excursion. Her last advice was now all that
survived of the author of my existence.
</div></body></text></TEI>