<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="15">
[102]
CHAPTER XV.

The Atmosphere.

We have considered in succession a number of
the properties and operations of the atmosphere, and
have found them separately very curious. But an
additional interest belongs to the subject when we
consider them as combined. The atmosphere under
this point of view must appear a contrivance of the
most extraordinary kind. To answer any of its purposes,
to carry on any of its processes, separately, requires
peculiar arrangements and adjustments; to
answer, all at once, purposes so varied, to combine
without confusion so many different trains, implies
powers and attributes which can hardly fail to excite
in a high degree our admiration and reverence.
If the atmosphere be considered as a vast machine,
it is difficult to form any just conception of the
profound skill and comprehensiveness of design which
it displays. It diffuses and tempers the heat of different
climates; for this purpose it performs a circulation
occupying the whole range from the pole to
the equator; and while it is doing this, it executes
many smaller circuits between the sea and the land.
At the same time, it is the means of forming clouds
and rain, and for this purpose, a perpetual circulation
of the watery part of the atmosphere goes on
between its lower and upper regions. Besides this
complication of circuits, it exercises a more irregular
agency, in the occasional winds which blow from
all quarters, tending perpetually to restore the equilibrium
of heat and moisture. But this incessant and
multiplied activity discharges only a part of the functions
of the air. It is, moreover, the most important
and universal material of the growth and sustenance[103]
of plants and animals; and is for this purpose every
where present and almost uniform in its quantity.
With all its local motion, it has also the office of a
medium of communication between intelligent creatures,
which office it performs by another set of motions,
entirely different both from the circulation and
the occasional movements already mentioned; these
different kinds of motions not interfering materially
with each other: and this last purpose, so remote
from the others in its nature, it answers in a manner
so perfect and so easy, that we cannot imagine that
the object could have been more completely attained,
if this had been the sole purpose for which the
atmosphere had been created. With all these qualities,
this extraordinary part of our terrestrial system
is scarcely ever in the way: and when we have occasion
to do so, we put forth our hand and push it
aside, without being aware of its being near us.
We may add, that it is, in addition to all that we
have hitherto noticed, a constant source of utility
and beauty in its effects on light. Without air we
should see nothing, except objects on which the sun’s
rays fell, directly or by reflection. It is the atmosphere
which converts sunbeams into daylight, and
fills the space in which we are with illumination.
The contemplation of the atmosphere, as a machine
which answers all these purposes, is well suited
to impress upon us the strongest conviction of the
most refined, far-seeing, and far-ruling contrivance.
It seems impossible to suppose that these various
properties were so bestowed and so combined, any
otherwise than by a beneficent and intelligent Being,
able and willing to diffuse organization, life, health,
and enjoyment through all parts of the visible world;
possessing a fertility of means which no multiplicity
of objects could exhaust, and a discrimination of consequences
which no complication of conditions could
embarrass.
</div></body></text></TEI>