<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="16">CHAPTER XIV.
From the moment of my last interview with the stranger
I was another creature. My thoughts incessantly rolled upon
his communications. They filled me with astonishment and
joy, almost to bursting. I was unable to contain myself;
I was unable to remain in any posture or any place. I
could scarcely command myself sufficiently to perform the
last duties to his body in the manner he had directed. I
paced with eager step the sands of the lake; I climbed the
neighbouring hills, and then descended with inconceivable
rapidity to the vales below; I traced with fierce impatience
the endless mazes of the wood in which I so hardly
recovered my bewildered guest. The uninterruptedness
and celerity of bodily motion seemed to communicate some
ease to my swelling heart.
Yet there was one thing I wanted. I wanted some
friendly bosom into which to pour out my feelings, and
thus by participation to render my transports balsamic and
tolerable. But this was for ever denied me. No human
ear must ever be astonished with the story of my endowments
and my privileges. I may whisper it to the woods
and the waters, but not in the face of man. Not only am
I bound to suppress the knowledge of the important secret
I possess, but even the feelings, the ruminations, the visions,
that are for ever floating in my soul. It is but a vain and
frivolous distinction upon which I act, when I commit to
this paper my history, and not the science which is its corner-stone.
The reason why the science may not be divulged
is obvious. Exhaustless wealth, if communicated to all
men, would be but an exhaustless heap of pebbles and dust;
and nature will not admit her everlasting laws to be so
abrogated, as they would be by rendering the whole race of
sublunary man immortal. But I am bound, as far as possible,
not only to hide my secrets, but to conceal that I have
any to hide. Senseless paper! be thou at least my confidant!
To thee I may impart what my soul spurns the
task to suppress. The human mind insatiably thirsts for a[162]
confidant and a friend. It is no matter that these pages
shall never he surveyed by other eyes than mine. They
afford at least the semblance of communication and the unburthening
of the mind; and I will press the illusion fondly
and for ever to my heart.
To return to the explanation of my feelings immediately
after receiving possession of my grand acquisition; for, without
that explanation, the spirit and meaning of my subsequent
narrative will scarcely be sufficiently apprehended.
“Happy, happy, happy man!” exclaimed I, in the
midst of my wanderings and reveries. “Wealth! thy power
Is unbounded and inconceivable. All men bow down to
thee; the most stubborn will is by thee rendered pliant as
wax; all obstacles are melted down and dissolved by the
ardour of thy beams! The man that possesses thee, finds
every path level before him, and every creature burning
to anticipate his wishes: but if these are the advantages
that wealth imparts to such as possess only those scanty
portions which states and nations allow to the richest, how
enviable must his condition be, whose wealth is literally
exhaustless and infinite! He possesses really the blessing,
which priestcraft and superstition have lyingly pronounced
upon the charitable: he may give away the revenues of
princes, and not be the poorer. He possesses the attribute
which we are accustomed to ascribe to the Creator of the
universe: he may say to a man, ‘Be rich,’ and he is rich.
He can bestow with equal facility the smallest gifts and the
greatest. Palaces, as if they were the native exhalations of
the soil, rise out of the earth at his bidding. He holds the
fate of nations and of the world in his hand. He can remove
forests, and level mountains, drain marshes, extend
canals, turn the course of rivers, and shut up the sea with
doors. He can assign to every individual in a nation the
task he pleases, can improve agriculture, and establish manufactures,
can found schools, and hospitals, and infirmaries,
and universities. He can study the genius of every man,
and enable every man to pursue the bent of his mind.
Poets and philosophers will be fostered, the sublimest flights
of genius be produced, and the most admirable discoveries
effected, under his auspicious patronage. The whole world[163]
are his servants, and he, if his temper be noble and upright,
will be the servant of the whole world. Nay, it cannot
happen otherwise. He has as few temptations to obliquity
as omnipotence itself. Weakness and want are the parents
of vice. But he possesses every thing; he cannot better
his situation; no man can come into rivalship or competition
with him. I thank God, I have known the extremes
of poverty, and therefore am properly qualified to enjoy my
present happiness. I have felt a reverse of fortune, driving
me in one instance to insanity, in another instance threatening
to destroy me, my wife, and children together, with
the plague of hunger. My heart has been racked with
never-dying remorse; because, by my guilt and folly, my
children have been deprived of the distinction and rank to
which they were born, and plunged in remediless obscurity.
Heaven has seen my sufferings, and at length has graciously
said, ‘It is enough.’ Because I have endured more than
man ever endured from the privation of fortune, God in his
justice has reserved for me this secret of the transmutation
of metals. I can never again fall into that wretchedness,
by which my understanding was subverted, and my heart
was broken.”
From this part of the legacy of the stranger, my mind
reverted to the other. I surveyed my limbs, all the joints
and articulations of my frame, with curiosity and astonishment.
“What!” exclaimed I, “these limbs, this complicated
but brittle frame, shall last for ever! No disease
shall attack it; no pain shall seize it; death shall withhold
from it for ever his abhorred grasp! Perpetual vigour,
perpetual activity, perpetual youth, shall take up their abode
with me! Time shall generate in me no decay, shall not
add a wrinkle to my brow, or convert a hair of my head to
grey! This body was formed to die; this edifice to crumble
into dust; the principles of corruption and mortality are
mixed up in every atom of my frame. But for me the
laws of nature are suspended; the eternal wheels of the
universe roll backward; I am destined to be triumphant
over fate and time!
“Months, years, cycles, centuries! To me all these are
but as indivisible moments. I shall never become old; I[164]
shall always be, as it were, in the porch and infancy of
existence; no lapse of years shall subtract any thing from
my future duration. I was born under Louis the Twelfth;
the life of Francis the First now threatens a speedy termination;
he will be gathered to his fathers, and Henry his
son will succeed him. But what are princes and kings and
generations of men to me? I shall become familiar with
the rise and fall of empires; in a little while the very name
of France, my country, will perish from the face of the
earth, and men will dispute about the situation of Paris, as
they dispute about the site of ancient Nineveh and Babylon
and Troy. Yet I shall still be young. I shall take my most
distant posterity by the hand; I shall accompany them in
their career; and, when they are worn out and exhausted,
shall shut up the tomb over them, and set forward.”
There was something however in this part of my speculation
that did not entirely please me. Methought the
race of mankind looked too insignificant in my eyes. I
felt a degree of uneasiness at the immeasurable distance
that was put between me and the rest of my species. I
found myself alone in the world. Must I for ever live
without a companion, a friend, any one with whom I can
associate upon equal terms, with whom I can have a
community of sensations, and feelings, and hopes, and
desires, and fears? I experienced something, less than a
wish, yet a something very capable of damping my joy,
that I also were subject to mortality. I could have been
well content to be partaker with a race of immortals, but I
was not satisfied to be single in this respect. I was not
pleased to recollect how trivial would appear to me those
concerns of a few years, about which the passions of men
are so eagerly occupied. I did not like the deadness of
heart that seemed to threaten me. I began to be afraid of
vacancy and torpor, and that my life would become too uniformly
quiet. Nor did it sufficiently console me to recollect
that, as one set of friends died off the stage, another
race would arise to be substituted in their stead. I felt that
human affections and passions are not made of this transferable
stuff, and that we can love nothing truly, unless, we
devote ourselves to it heart and soul, and our life is, as it,
were, bound up in the object of our attachment.
[165]
It was worse when I recollected my wife and my children.
When I considered for the first time that they were now in
a manner nothing to me, I felt a sensation that might be
said to mount to anguish. How can a man attach himself
to any thing, when he comes to consider it as the mere
plaything and amusement of the moment! In this statement
however I am not accurate. Habit is more potent than any
theoretical speculation. Past times had attached me deeply,
irrevocably, to all the members of my family. But I felt
that I should survive them all. They would die one by one,
and leave me alone. I should drop into their graves the
still renewing tear of anguish. In that tomb would my
heart be buried. Never, never, through the countless ages
of eternity, should I form another attachment. In the
happy age of delusion, happy and auspicious at least to the
cultivation of the passions, when I felt that I also was a
mortal, I was capable of a community of sentiments and a
going forth of the heart. But how could I, an immortal,
hope ever hereafter to feel a serious, an elevating and expansive
passion for the ephemeron of an hour!
As the first tumult of my thoughts subsided, I began, as
is usual with persons whose minds are turned loose in the
search of visionary happiness, to picture to myself, more
steadily and with greater minuteness, the objects I would
resolve early to accomplish. I would in the first place
return to France, my adored country, the residence of my
ancestors, whose annals they had adorned, whose plains had
witnessed their heroic feats, and whose earth enclosed their
ashes. To France I was endeared by every tie that binds
the human heart; her language had been the prattle of my
infancy; her national manners and temper were twined
with the fibres of my constitution, and could not be rooted
out; I felt that every Frenchman that lived was my brother.
Banishment had only caused these prejudices to strike their
tendrils deeper in my heart. I knew not that I should
finally limit my abode to France. A man who, like Melchisedec,
is “without end of life,” may well consider himself
as being also, like him, “without father, without mother,
and without descent.” But at all events I would first fix
my children, who did not participate in my privileges, in[166]
their native soil. I would reside there myself, at least till
they were fully disposed of, and till the admirable partner of
the last seventeen years of my life had resigned her breath. I
would immediately repurchase the property of my ancestors,
which had been so distressfully resigned. The exile should
return from his seven years’ banishment in triumph and
splendour. I would return to the court of my old patron
and friend, the gallant Francis, and present to him my boy,
the future representative of my family, now one year older
than I had been at the field of the Cloth of Gold. Though
an exile from my country, I had not been an inattentive
witness of her fortunes. The year fifteen hundred and
forty-four was a remarkable and interesting year in the
history of France. The endless animosities of Francis and
the emperor had broken out with new fury about two years
before. In the spring of the present year, the count d’Anguien
had won a battle in Piedmont[8], in which ten thousand
imperialists were left dead upon the field, and which
might be considered as having at length effaced the defeat
of Pavia, in the same part of the world nineteen years before.
The moment it had been announced that a battle was resolved
on, the young nobility of France, with their characteristic
ardour, had hurried to the scene, and the court of
Paris was, in an instant as it were, turned into a desert.
On the other hand, the emperor and the king of England
had concerted for the same season a formidable plan of
attack against our northern frontier. With an army of
twenty-five thousand men respectively, the one on the side
of Champagne, and the other of Picardy, they agreed to
advance directly into the heart of the kingdom, and to unite
their forces in the neighbourhood of Paris. The last intelligence
that had reached me was, that Château Thierry,
about twenty leagues from the metropolis, was in the hands
of the emperor, and that the inhabitants of the capital,
filled with consternation, were seeking their safety by flight
in every direction. These circumstances had passed idly
by me, and left little impression, so long as I considered
myself as an obscure peasant cut off for ever from the bosom
of my country. But, vested with the extraordinary powers[167]
now intrusted to me, the case was altered. I felt even a
greater interest in my sovereign, now pressed down with
disease and calamity, yet retaining the original alacrity and
confidence of his soul, than I had done, when I saw him in
all the pride of youth, and all the splendour of prosperity.
I was anxious that Charles should now enter into his service;
and I determined once again to assume the cuirass
and the falchion, that I might be the instructor of his
youth, and his pattern in feats of war. I resolved that my
shepherd-boy, bred in obscurity among woods and mountains,
should burst with sudden splendour upon his countrymen,
and prove in the field his noble blood and generous
strain. I also proposed to myself, both out of sympathy
for my king, and to give greater éclat to my son’s entrance
into life, to replenish with my treasures the empty coffers of
France, and thus to furnish what at this period seemed to
be the main spring upon which the fortune of war depended.
With the advantages I could afford him, the career of
Charles could not fail to be rapid and illustrious, and he
would undoubtedly obtain the staff of constable of France,
the possessor of which, Montmorency, was now in disgrace.
I would marry my daughters to such of the young nobility
as I should find most distinguished in talents and spotless
in character. When, by the death of her I most loved, my
affections should be weaned from my country, and the scenes
to which I had been accustomed were rendered painful and
distressing, I would then set out upon my travels. I would
travel with such splendour and profusion of expense (for
this, though mortified in me by a reverse of many years’
duration, continued to be the foible of my heart) as should
supersede the necessity of letters of recommendation, and
secure me a favourable reception wherever I appeared. I
might spend a life, in a manner, in every country that was
fortunate enough to allure my stay, spreading improvements,
dispensing blessings, and causing all distress and calamity
to vanish from before me.

[168]</div></body></text></TEI>