<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="23">CHAPTER XXIII.
VOLCANIC DISTRICT OF NAPLES.
History of the volcanic eruptions in the district round
Naples—Early convulsions
in the island of Ischia—Numerous cones thrown up there—Lake Avernus—The
Solfatara—Renewal of the eruptions of Vesuvius, A.D. 79—Pliny's description
of the phenomena—His silence respecting the destruction of Herculaneum
and Pompeii—Subsequent history of Vesuvius—Lava discharged in Ischia in
1302—Pause in the eruptions of Vesuvius—Monte Nuovo thrown
up—Uniformity
of the volcanic operations of Vesuvius and Phlegræan Fields in ancient
and modern times.
I shall next give a sketch of the history of some of the volcanic vents
dispersed throughout the great regions before described, and consider
the composition and arrangement of their lavas and ejected matter.
The only volcanic region known to the ancients was that of the Mediterranean;
and even of this they have transmitted to us very imperfect
records relating to the eruptions of the three principal districts, namely,
that round Naples, that of Sicily and its isles, and that of the Grecian
Archipelago. By far the most connected series of records throughout a
long period relates to the first of these provinces; and these cannot be
too attentively considered, as much historical information is indispensable
in order to enable us to obtain a clear view of the connection and
alternate mode of action of the different vents in a single volcanic group.
Early convulsions in the Island of Ischia.—-The Neapolitan volcanoes
extend from Vesuvius, through the Phlegræan Fields, to Procida and
Ischia, in a somewhat linear arrangement, ranging from the northeast
to the southwest, as will be seen in the annexed map of the volcanic
district of Naples (fig. 40). Within the space above limited, the volcanic
force is sometimes developed in single eruptions from a considerable
number of irregularly scattered points; but a great part of its
action has been confined to one principal and habitual vent, Vesuvius or
Somma. Before the Christian era, from the remotest periods of which
we have any tradition, this principal vent was in a state of inactivity.
But terrific convulsions then took place from time to time in Ischia
(Pithecusa), and seem to have extended to the neighboring isle of Procida
(Prochyta); for Strabo490 mentions a story of Procida having been
torn asunder from Ischia; and Pliny491 derives its name from its having
been poured forth by an eruption from Ischia.
The present circumference of Ischia along the water's edge is eighteen
miles, its length from west to east about five, and its breadth from north
361
to south three miles. Several Greek colonies which settled there before
the Christian era were compelled to abandon it in consequence of the
violence of the eruptions. First the Erythræans, and afterwards the
Chalcidians, are mentioned as having been driven out by earthquakes
and igneous exhalations. A colony was afterwards established by Hiero,
king of Syracuse, about 380 years before the Christian era; but when
they had built a fortress, they were compelled by an eruption to fly,
and never again returned. Strabo tells us that Timæus recorded a tradition,
that, a little before his time, Epomeus, the principal mountain in
the centre of the island, vomited fire during great earthquakes; that
the land between it and the coast had ejected much fiery matter, which
flowed into the sea, and that the sea receded for the distance of three
stadia, and then returning, overflowed the island. This eruption is
supposed by some to have been that which formed the crater of Monte
Corvo on one of the higher flanks of Epomeo, above Foria, the lava-current
of which may still be traced, by aid of the scoriæ on its surface,
from the crater to the sea.
Fig. 40.
A. Astroni. B. Monte Barbaro.   M. Monte Nuovo.   S. The Solfatara.
To one of the subsequent eruptions in the lower parts of the isle,
which caused the expulsion of the first Greek colony, Monte Rotaro
has been attributed, and it bears every mark of recent origin. The
cone, which I examined in 1828, is remarkably perfect, and has a crater
on its summit precisely resembling that of Monte Nuovo near Naples;
but the hill is larger, and resembles some of the more considerable
cones of single eruption near Clermont in Auvergne, and, like some of
them, it has given vent to a lava-stream at its base, instead of its summit.
A small ravine swept out by a torrent exposes the structure of
362
the cone, which is composed of innumerable inclined and slightly undulating
layers of pumice, scoriæ, white lapilli, and enormous angular
blocks of trachyte. These last have evidently been thrown out by violent
explosions, like those which in 1822 launched from Vesuvius a
mass of augitic lava, of many tons' weight, to the distance of three
miles, which fell in the garden of Prince Ottajano. The cone of Rotaro
is covered with the arbutus, and other beautiful evergreens. Such
is the strength of the virgin soil, that the shrubs have become almost
arborescent; and the growth of some of the smaller wild plants has
been so vigorous, that botanists have scarcely been able to recognize
the species.
The eruption which dislodged the Syracusan colony is supposed to
have given rise to that mighty current which forms the promontory of
Zaro and Caruso. The surface of these lavas is still very arid and
bristling, and is covered with black scoriæ; so that it is not without
great labor that human industry has redeemed some small spots, and
converted them into vineyards. Upon the produce of these vineyards
the population of the island is almost entirely supported. It amounted
when I was there, in 1828, to about twenty-five thousand, and was on
the increase.
Fig. 41.
Part of Ischia seen from the West.
a. Monte Epomeo or San Niccola.
b. Monte Vico.
c. Another of the minor cones with a crater.492
From the date of the great eruption last alluded to, down to our own
time, Ischia has enjoyed tranquillity, with the exception of one emission
of lava hereafter to be described, which, although it occasioned much
local damage, does not appear to have devastated the whole country,
in the manner of more ancient explosions. There are, upon the whole,
on different parts of Epomeo, or scattered through the lower tracts of
Ischia, twelve considerable volcanic cones which have been thrown up
since the island was raised above the surface of the deep; and many
streams of lava may have flowed, like that of "Arso" in 1302, without
cones having been produced; so that this island may, for ages before
the period of the remotest traditions, have served as a safety-valve to
the whole Terra di Lavoro, while the fires of Vesuvius were dormant.
363
Lake Avernus.—It seems also clear that Avernus, a circular lake
near Puzzuoli, about half a mile in diameter, which is now a salubrious
and cheerful spot, once exhaled mephitic vapors, such as are often emitted
by craters after eruptions. There is no reason for discrediting the
account of Lucretius, that birds could not fly over it without being
stifled, although they may now frequent it uninjured.493 There must
have been a time when this crater was in action; and for many centuries
afterwards it may have deserved the appellation of "atri jauna
Ditis," emitting, perhaps, gases as destructive of animal life as those
suffocating vapors given out by Lake Quilotoa, in Quito, in 1797, by
which whole herds of cattle on its shores were killed,494 or as those deleterious
emanations which annihilated all the cattle in the island of Lancerote,
one of the Canaries, in 1730.495 Bory St. Vincent mentions, that
in the same isle birds fell lifeless to the ground; and Sir William Hamilton
informs us that he picked up dead birds on Vesuvius during an
eruption.
Solfatara.—The Solfatara, near Puzzuoli, which may be considered
as a nearly extinguished crater, appears, by the accounts of Strabo and
others, to have been before the Christian era in very much the same
state as at present, giving vent continually to aqueous vapor, together
with sulphureous and muriatic acid gases, like those evolved by Vesuvius.
Ancient history of Vesuvius.—Such, then, were the points where the
subterranean fires obtained vent, from the earliest period to which tradition
reaches back, down to the first century of the Christian era; but
we then arrive at a crisis in the volcanic action of this district—one of
the most interesting events witnessed by man during the brief period
throughout which he has observed the physical changes on the earth's
surface. From the first colonization of Southern Italy by the Greeks,
Vesuvius afforded no other indications of its volcanic character than
such as the naturalist might infer, from the analogy of its structure to
other volcanoes. These were recognized by Strabo, but Pliny did not
include the mountain in his list of active vents. The ancient cone was
of a very regular form, terminating not as at present in two peaks, but
with a summit which presented, when seen from a distance, the even
outline of an abruptly truncated cone. On the summit, as we learn
from Plutarch, there was a crater with steep cliffs, and having its
interior overgrown with wild vines, and with a sterile plain at the bottom.
On the exterior, the flanks of the mountain were clothed with
fertile fields richly cultivated, and at its base were the populous cities
of Herculaneum and Pompeii. But the scene of repose was at length
doomed to cease, and the volcanic fire was recalled to the main channel,
which at some former unknown period had given passage to repeated
streams of melted lava, sand, and scoriæ.
364
Renewal of its eruptions.—The first symptom of the revival of the
energies of this volcano was the occurrence of an earthquake in the year
63 after Christ, which did considerable injury to the cities in its vicinity.
From that time to the year 79 slight shocks were frequent; and in the
month of August of that year they became more numerous and violent,
till they ended at length in an eruption. The elder Pliny, who commanded
the Roman fleet, was then stationed at Misenum; and in his
anxiety to obtain a near view of the phenomena, he lost his life, being
suffocated by sulphureous vapors. His nephew, the younger Pliny,
remained at Misenum, and has given us, in his Letters, a lively description
of the awful scene. A dense column of vapor was first seen rising
vertically from Vesuvius, and then spreading itself out laterally, so that
its upper portion resembled the head, and its lower the trunk of the
pine, which characterizes the Italian landscape. This black cloud was
pierced occasionally by flashes of fire, as vivid as lightning, succeeded
by darkness more profound than night. Ashes fell even upon the ships
at Misenum, and caused a shoal in one part of the sea—the ground
rocked, and the sea receded from the shores, so that many marine animals
were seen on the dry sand. The appearances above described
agree perfectly with those witnessed in more recent eruptions, especially
those of Monte Nuovo, in 1538, and of Vesuvius in 1822.
The younger Pliny, although giving a circumstantial detail of so many
physical facts, and describing the eruption and earthquake, and the shower
of ashes which fell at Stabiæ, makes no allusion to the sudden overwhelming
of two large and populous cities, Herculaneum and Pompeii. In explanation
of this omission, it has been suggested that his chief object was
simply to give Tacitus a full account of the particulars of his uncle's death.
It is worthy, however, of remark, that had the buried cities never been
discovered, the accounts transmitted to us of their tragical end might
well have been discredited by the majority, so vague and general are
the narratives, or so long subsequent to the event. Tacitus, the friend
and contemporary of Pliny, when adverting in general terms to the convulsions,
says merely that "cities were consumed or buried."496
Suetonius, although he alludes to the eruption incidentally, is silent
as to the cities. They are mentioned by Martial, in an epigram, as immersed
in cinders; but the first historian who alludes to them by name
is Dion Cassius,497 who flourished about a century and a half after Pliny.
He appears to have derived his information from the traditions of the
inhabitants, and to have recorded, without discrimination, all the facts
and fables which he could collect. He tells us, "that during the eruption
a multitude of men of superhuman stature, resembling giants, appeared,
sometimes on the mountain, and sometimes in the environs—that
stones and smoke were thrown out, the sun was hidden, and then
the giants seemed to rise again, while the sounds of trumpets were
heard, &c., &c.; and finally," he relates, "two entire cities, Herculaneum
365
and Pompeii, were buried under showers of ashes, while all the people
were sitting in the theatre." That many of these circumstances were
invented, would have been obvious, even without the aid of Pliny's letters;
and the examination of Herculaneum and Pompeii enables us to
prove, that none of the people were destroyed in the theatres, and indeed
that there were very few of the inhabitants who did not escape
from both cities. Yet some lives were lost, and there was ample foundation
for the tale in its most essential particulars.
It does not appear that in the year 79 any lava flowed from Vesuvius;
the ejected substances, perhaps, consisted entirely of lapilli, sand,
and fragments of older lava, as when Monte Nuovo was thrown up in
1538. The first era at which we have authentic accounts of the flowing
of a stream of lava, is the year 1036, which is the seventh eruption from
the revival of the fires of the volcano. A few years afterwards, in 1049,
another eruption is mentioned, and another in 1138 (or 1139), after
which a great pause ensued of 168 years. During this long interval of
repose, two minor vents opened at distant points. First, it is on tradition
that an eruption took place from the Solfatara, in the year 1198,
during the reign of Frederick II., Emperor of Germany; and although
no circumstantial detail of the event has reached us from those dark
ages, we may receive the fact without hesitation.498 Nothing more, however,
can be attributed to this eruption, as Mr. Scrope observes, than
the discharge of a light and scoriform trachytic lava, of recent aspect,
resting upon the strata of loose tuff which covers the principal mass of
trachyte.499
Volcanic eruption in Ischia, 1302.—The other occurrence is well
authenticated—the eruption, in the year 1302, of a lava-stream from a
new vent on the southeast end of the Island of Ischia. During part of
1301, earthquakes had succeeded one another with fearful rapidity; and
they terminated at last with the discharge of a lava-stream from a point
named the Campo del Arso, not far from the town of Ischia. This lava
ran quite down to the sea—a distance of about two miles; in color it
varies from iron-gray to reddish black, and is remarkable for the glassy
felspar which it contains. Its surface is almost as sterile, after a period
of five centuries, as if it had cooled down yesterday. A few scantlings
of wild thyme, and two or three other dwarfish plants, alone appear in
the interstices of the scoriæ, while the Vesuvian lava of 1767 is already
covered with a luxuriant vegetation. Pontanus, whose country-house
was burnt and overwhelmed, describes the dreadful scene as having
lasted two months.500 Many houses were swallowed up, and a partial
emigration of the inhabitants followed. This eruption produced no
cone, but only a slight depression, hardly deserving the name of a crater,
366
where heaps of black and red scoriæ lie scattered around. Until
this eruption, Ischia is generally believed to have enjoyed an interval of
rest for about seventeen centuries; but Julius Obsequens,501 who flourished
A. D. 214, refers to some volcanic convulsions in the year 662
after the building of Rome (91 B. C.) As Pliny, who lived a century
before Obsequens, does not enumerate this among other volcanic eruptions,
the statement of the latter author is supposed to have been erroneous;
but it would be more consistent, for reasons before stated, to
disregard the silence of Pliny, and to conclude, that some kind of subterranean
commotion, probably of no great violence, happened at the
period alluded to.
History of Vesuvius after 1138.—To return to Vesuvius:—the next
eruption occurred in 1306; between which era and 1631 there was
only one other (in 1500), and that a slight one. It has been remarked,
that throughout this period Etna was in a state of such unusual activity,
as to lend countenance to the idea that the great Sicilian volcano may
sometimes serve as a channel of discharge to elastic fluids and lava that
would otherwise rise to the vents in Campania.
Formation of Monte Nuovo, 1538.—The great pause was also marked
by a memorable event in the Phlegræan Fields—the sudden formation
of a new mountain in 1538, of which we have received authentic accounts
from contemporary writers.
Fig. 42.
Monte Nuovo, formed in the Bay of Baiæ, Sept. 29th, 1538.
1. Cone of Monte Nuovo.
2. Brim of crater of ditto.
3. Thermal spring, called Baths of Nero, or Stufe di Tritoli.

The height of this mountain, called ever since Monte Nuovo, has been
determined by the Italian mineralogist Pini, to be 440 English feet
above the level of the bay; its base is about eight thousand feet, or
more than a mile and a half in circumference. According to Pini, the
367
depth of the crater is 421 English feet from the summit of the hill, so
that its bottom is only nineteen feet above the level of the sea. The
cone is declared, by the best authorities, to stand partly on the site of
the Lucrine Lake (4, fig. 43),502 which was nothing more than the crater
of a pre-existent volcano, and was almost entirely filled during the explosion
of 1538. Nothing now remains but a shallow pool, separated
from the sea by an elevated beach, raised artificially.
Fig. 43.
The Phlegræan Fields.


1. Monte Nuovo.
4. Lucrine Lake.

2. Monte Barbaro.
5. The Solfatara.

3. Lake Avernus.
6. Puzzuoli.


7. Bay of Baiæ.
Sir William Hamilton has given us two original letters describing this
eruption. The first, by Falconi, dated 1538, contains the following
passages.503 "It is now two years since there have been frequent earthquakes
at Puzzuoli, Naples, and the neighboring parts. On the day
and in the night before the eruption (of Monte Nuovo), above twenty
shocks, great and small, were felt. The eruption began on the 29th of
September, 1538. It was on a Sunday, about one o'clock in the night,
when flames of fire were seen between the hot baths and Tripergola.
In a short time the fire increased to such a degree, that it burst open
the earth in this place, and threw up so great a quantity of ashes and
pumice-stones, mixed with water, as covered the whole country. The
next morning (after the formation of Monte Nuovo) the poor inhabitants
of Puzzuoli quitted their habitations in terror, covered with the muddy
and black shower which continued the whole day in that country—flying
from death, but with death painted in their countenances. Some
with their children in their arms, some with sacks full of their goods;
others leading an ass, loaded with their frightened family, towards Naples;
368
others carrying quantities of birds, of various sorts, that had fallen
dead at the beginning of the eruption; others, again, with fish which
they had found, and which were to be met with in plenty on the shore,
the sea having left them dry for a considerable time. I accompanied
Signor Moramaldo to behold the wonderful effects of the eruption. The
sea had retired on the side of Baiæ, abandoning a considerable tract,
and the shore appeared almost entirely dry, from the quantity of ashes
and broken pumice-stones thrown up by the eruption. I saw two
springs in the newly discovered ruins; one before the house that was
the queen's, of hot and salt water," &c.
So far Falconi: the other account is by Pietro Giacomo di Toledo,
which begins thus:—"It is now two years since this province of Campagna
has been afflicted with earthquakes, the country about Puzzuoli
much more so than any other parts; but the 27th and the 28th of the
month of September last, the earthquakes did not cease day or night
in the town of Puzzuoli: that plain which lies between Lake Avernus,
the Monte Barbaro, and the sea, was raised a little, and many cracks
were made in it, from some of which issued water; at the same time the
sea, immediately joining the plain, dried up about two hundred paces, so
that the fish were left on the sand a prey to the inhabitants of Puzzuoli.
At last, on the 29th of the same month, about two o'clock in the night,
the earth opened near the lake, and discovered a horrid mouth, from
which were vomited furiously smoke, fire, stones, and mud, composed of
ashes, making at the time of its opening a noise like the loudest thunder.
The stones which followed were by the flames converted to pumice,
and some of these were larger than an ox. The stones went about
as high as a cross-bow can carry, and then fell down, sometimes on the
edge, and sometimes into the mouth itself. The mud was of the color
of ashes, and at first very liquid, then by degrees less so, and in such
quantities, that in less than twelve hours, with the help of the above-mentioned
stones, a mountain was raised of 1000 paces in height. Not
only Puzzuoli and the neighboring country was full of this mud, but the
city of Naples also; so that many of its palaces were defaced by it.
Now this eruption lasted two nights and two days without intermission,
though, it is true, not always with the same force; the third day the
eruption ceased, and I went up with many people to the top of the new
hill, and saw down into its mouth, which was a round cavity about a
quarter of a mile in circumference, in the middle of which, the stones
which had fallen were boiling up, just as a caldron of water boils on
the fire. The fourth day it began to throw up again, and the seventh
much more, but still with less violence than the first night. At this
time many persons who were on the hill were knocked down by the
stones and killed, or smothered with the smoke. In the day the smoke
still continues, and you often see fire in the midst of it in the nighttime."504
It will be seen that both these accounts, written immediately after the
369
birth of Monte Nuovo, agree in stating that the sea retired; and one
mentions that its bottom was upraised; but they attribute the origin of
the new hill exclusively to the jets of mud, showers of scoriæ, and large
fragments of rock, cast out from a central orifice, for several days and
nights. Baron Von Buch, however, in his excellent work on the Canary
Islands, and volcanic phenomena in general, has declared his opinion
that the cone and crater of Monte Nuovo were formed, not in the manner
above described, but by the upheaval of solid beds of white tuff,
which were previously horizontal, but which were pushed up in 1538,
so as to dip away in all directions from the centre, with the same inclination
as the sloping surface of the cone itself. "It is an error," he
says, "to imagine that this hill was formed by eruption, or by the ejection
of pumice, scoriæ, and other incoherent matter; for the solid beds
of upraised tuff are visible all round the crater, and it is merely the superficial
covering of the cone which is made up of ejected scoriæ."505
In confirmation of this view, M. Dufrénoy has cited a passage from
the works of Porzio, a celebrated physician of that period, to prove
that in 1538 the ground where Monte Nuovo stands was pushed up in
the form of a great bubble or blister, which on bursting, gave origin to
the present deep crater. Porzio, says, "that after two days and nights
of violent earthquakes, the sea retired for nearly 200 yards; so that the
inhabitants could collect great numbers of fish on this part of the
shore, and see some springs of fresh water which rose up there. At
length, on the third day of the calends of October (September 29), they
saw a large tract of ground intervening between the foot of Monte Barbaro,
and part of the sea, near the Lake Avernus, rise, and suddenly
assume the form of an incipient hill; and at two o'clock at night, this
heap of earth, opening as it were its mouth, vomited, with a loud noise,
flames, pumice-stones, and ashes."506
So late as the year 1846 a fourth manuscript (written immediately
after the eruption) was discovered and published in Germany. It was
written in 1538 by Francesco del Nero,507 who mentions the drying up
of the bed of the sea near Puzzuoli, which enabled the inhabitants of
the town to carry off loads of fish. About eight o'clock in the morning
of the 29th September, the earth sunk down about 14 feet in that
place where the volcanic orifice now appears, and there issued forth a
small stream of water, at first cold, and afterwards tepid. At noon, on
the same day, the earth began to swell up in the same spot where it
had sunk down 14 feet, so as to form a hill. About this time fire
370
issued forth, and gave rise to the great gulf, "with such a force, noise,
and shining light, that I, who was standing in my garden, was seized
with terror. Forty minutes afterwards, although unwell, I got upon a
neighboring height, from which I saw all that took place, and by my
troth it was a splendid fire, that threw up for a long time much earth
and many stones, which fell back again all round the gulf, in a semicircle
of from one to three bow-shots in diameter, and, filling up part of
the sea, formed a hill nearly of the height of Monte Morello. Masses
of earth and stones, as large as an ox, were shot up from the fiery gulf
into the air, to a height which I estimate at a mile and a half. When
they descended, some were dry, others in a soft muddy state." He
concludes by alluding again to the sinking of the ground, and the elevation
of it which followed, and says that to him it was inconceivable how
such a mass of stones and ashes could have been poured forth from the
gulf. He also refers to the account which Porzio was to draw up for
the Viceroy.
On comparing these four accounts, recorded by eye-witnesses, there
appears to be no real discrepancy between them. It seems clear that
the ground first sunk down 14 feet on the site of the future volcano,
and after having subsided it was again propelled upwards by the lava
mingled with steam and gases, which were about to burst forth. Jets
of red-hot lava, fragments of fractured rock, and occasionally mud composed
of a mixture of pumice, tuff, and sea-water, were hurled into the
air. Some of the blocks of stone were very large, leading us to infer
that the ground which sank and rose again was much shattered and
torn to pieces by the elastic vapors. The whole hill was not formed at
once, but by an intermittent action extending over a week or more. It
seems that the chasm opened between Tripergola and the baths in its
suburbs, and that the ejected materials fell and buried that small town.
A considerable part, however, of the hill was formed in less than
twenty-four hours, and in the same manner as on a smaller scale the
mud cones of the air volcanoes are produced, with a cavity in the middle.
There is no difficulty in conceiving that the pumiceous mud, if
so thrown out, may have set into a kind of stone on drying, just as
some cements, composed of volcanic ashes, are known to consolidate
with facility.
I am informed that Baron Von Buch discovered some marine shells
of existing species, such as occur fossil in the tuff of the neighborhood,
in beds exposed low down in the walls of the crater of Monte Nuovo.
These may have been ejected in the mud mixed with sea-water which
was cast out of the boiling gulf; or, as Signor Arcangelo Scacchi has
suggested,508 they may have been derived from the older tuff, which
contains marine shells of recent species. The same observer remarks
that Porzio's account upon the whole corroborates the doctrine of the
cone having been formed by eruption, in proof of which he cites the
371
following passage:—"But what was truly astonishing, a hill of pumice-stones
and ashes was heaped up round the gulf to the height of a mile
in a single night."509 Signor Scacchi also adds that the ancient temple
of Apollo, now at the foot of Monte Nuovo, and the walls of which
still retain their perfect perpendicularity, could not possibly have maintained
that position had the cone of Monte Nuovo really been the result
of upheaval.
Tripergola was much frequented as a watering-place, and contained
a hospital for those who resorted there for the benefit of the thermal
springs; and it appears that there were no fewer than three inns in the
principal street. Had Porzio stated that any of these buildings, or the
ruins of them, were seen by himself or others raised up above the plain,
a short time before the first eruption, so as to stand on the summit or
slope of a newly-raised hillock, we might have been compelled, by so
circumstantial a narrative, to adopt M. Dufrénoy's interpretation.
But in the absence of such evidence, we must appeal to the crater
itself, where we behold a section of the whole mountain, without being
able to detect any original nucleus of upheaved rock distinct from the
rest; on the contrary, the whole mass is similar throughout in composition,
and the cone very symmetrical in form; nor are there any clefts,
such as might be looked for, as the effect of the sudden upthrow of
stony masses. M. C. Prevost has well remarked, that if beds of solid
and non-elastic materials had yielded to a violent pressure directed from
below upward, we should find not simply a deep empty cavity, but an

Fig. 44.

irregular opening, where many rents converged;
and these rents would be now
seen breaking through the walls of the
crater, widening as they approach the
centre. (See Fig. 44, a, b.)510 Not a
single fissure of this kind is observable in
the interior of Monte Nuovo, where the
walls of the crater are continuous and entire;
nor are there any dikes implying that
rents had existed, which were afterwards filled with lava or other matter.
It has moreover been often urged by Von Buch, De Beaumont, and
others, who ascribe the conical form of volcanoes chiefly to upheaval
from below, that in such mountains there are a great number of deep
rents and ravines, which diverge on all sides like the spokes of a wheel,
from near the central axis to the circumference or base of the cone, as
in the case of Palma, Cantal, and Teneriffe. Yet the entire absence of
such divergent fissures or ravines, in such cases as Monte Nuovo, Somma,
or Etna, is passed by unnoticed, and appears to have raised in their
minds no objection to their favorite theory.
It is, indeed, admitted by M. Dufrénoy that there are some facts
372
which it is very difficult to reconcile with his own view of Porzio's record.
Thus, for example, there are certain Roman monuments at the
base of Monte Nuovo, and on the borders of Lake Avernus, such as the
temples of Apollo (before mentioned) and Pluto, which do not seem to
have suffered in the least degree by the supposed upheaval. "The
walls which still exist have preserved their vertical position, and the
vaults are in the same state as other monuments on the shores of the
Bay of Baiæ. The long gallery which led to the Sibyl's Cave, on the
other side of Lake Avernus, has in like manner escaped injury, the roof
of the gallery remaining perfectly horizontal, the only change being that
the soil of the chamber in which the Sibyl gave out her oracles is now
covered by a few inches of water, which merely indicates a slight alteration
in the level of Lake Avernus."511 On the supposition, then, that
pre-existing beds of pumiceous tuff were upraised in 1538, so as to form
Monte Nuovo, it is acknowledged that the perfectly undisturbed state
of the contiguous soil on which these ancient monuments stand, is very
different from what might have been expected.
Mr. Darwin, in his "Volcanic Islands," has described several crateriform
hills in the Galapagos Archipelago as composed of tuff which has
evidently flowed like mud, and yet on consolidating has preserved an
inclination of twenty and even thirty degrees. The tuff does not fold in
continuous sheets round the hills as would have happened if they had
been formed by the upheaval of horizontal layers. The author describes
the composition of the tuff as very similar to that of Monte Nuovo, and
the high angles at which the beds slope, both those which have flowed
and those which have fallen in the form of ashes, entirely removes the
difficulty supposed by M. Dufrénoy to exist in regard to the slope of
Monte Nuovo, where it exceeds an angle of 18° to 20°.512 Mr. Dana,
also, in his account of the Sandwich Islands,513 shows that in the "cinder
cones" of that region, the strata have an original inclination of between
35° and 40°, while in the "tufa cones" formed near the sea, the beds
slope at about an angle of 30°. The same naturalist also observed in
the Samoan or Navigator Islands in Polynesia, that fragments of fresh
coral had been thrown up together with volcanic matter to the height of
200 feet above the level of the sea in cones of tufa.514
I shall again revert to the doctrine of the origin of volcanic cones by
upheaval, when speaking of Vesuvius, Etna, and Santorin, and shall now
merely add, that, in 1538, the whole coast, from Monte Nuovo to beyond
Puzzuoli, was upraised to the height of many feet above the bed
of the Mediterranean, and has since retained the greater part of the
elevation then acquired. The proofs of these remarkable changes of
level will be considered at length when the phenomena of the temple of
Serapis are described.515
373
Volcanoes of the Phlegræan Fields.—Immediately adjoining Monte
Nuovo is the larger volcanic cone of Monte Barbaro (2, fig. 43, p. 367),
the "Gaurus inanis" of Juvenal—an appellation given to it probably
from its deep circular crater, which is about a mile in diameter. Large
as is this cone, it was probably produced by a single eruption; and it
does not, perhaps, exceed in magnitude some of the largest of those
formed in Ischia, within the historical era. It is composed chiefly of
indurated tufa like Monte Nuovo, stratified conformably to its conical
surface. This hill was once very celebrated for its wines, and is still
covered with vineyards; but when the vine is not in leaf it has a sterile
appearance, and, late in the year, when seen from the beautiful Bay of
Baiæ, it often contrasts so strongly in verdure with Monte Nuovo, which
is always clothed with arbutus, myrtle, and other wild evergreens, that
a stranger might well imagine the cone of older date to be that thrown
up in the sixteenth century.516
There is nothing, indeed, so calculated to instruct the geologist as
the striking manner in which the recent volcanic hills of Ischia, and
that now under consideration, blend with the surrounding landscape.
Nothing seems wanting or redundant; every part of the picture is in
such perfect harmony with the rest, that the whole has the appearance
of having been called into existence by a single effort of creative power.
Yet what other result could we have anticipated if nature has ever been
governed by the same laws? Each new mountain thrown up—each
new tract of land raised or depressed by earthquakes—should be in
perfect accordance with those previously formed, if the entire configuration
of the surface has been due to a long series of similar disturbances.
Were it true that the greater part of the dry land originated simultaneously
in its present state, at some era of paroxysmal convulsion, and
that additions were afterwards made slowly and successively during a
period of comparative repose; then, indeed, there might be reason to
expect a strong line of demarcation between the signs of the ancient
and modern changes. But the very continuity of the plan, and the
perfect identity of the causes, are to many a source of deception; since
by producing a unity of effect, they lead them to exaggerate the energy
of the agents which operated in the earlier ages. In the absence of all
historical information, they are as unable to separate the dates of the
origin of different portions of our continents, as the stranger is to determine,
by their physical features alone, the distinct ages of Monte Nuovo,
Monte Barbara, Astroni, and the Solfatara.
The vast scale and violence of the volcanic operations in Campania,
in the olden time, has been a theme of declamation, and has been contrasted
with the comparative state of quiescence of this delightful region
in the modern era. Instead of inferring, from analogy, that the ancient
Vesuvius was always at rest when the craters of the Phlegræan Fields
374
were burning—that each cone rose in succession,—and that many years,
and often centuries, of repose intervened between different eruptions,—geologists
seem to have generally conjectured that the whole group
sprung up from the ground at once, like the soldiers of Cadmus when
he sowed the dragon's teeth. As well might they endeavor to persuade
us that on these Phlegræan Fields, as the poets feigned, the giants
warred with Jove, ere yet the puny race of mortals were in being.
Modern eruptions of Vesuvius.—For nearly a century after the birth
of Monte Nuovo, Vesuvius continued in a state of tranquillity. There
had been no violent eruption for 492 years; and it appears that the
crater was then exactly in the condition of the present extinct volcano
of Astroni, near Naples. Bracini, who visited Vesuvius not long before
the eruption of 1631, gives the following interesting description of the
interior:—"The crater was five miles in circumference, and about a
thousand paces deep: its sides were covered with brushwood, and at
the bottom there was a plain on which cattle grazed. In the woody
parts wild boars frequently harbored. In one part of the plain, covered
with ashes, were three small pools, one filled with hot and bitter water,
another salter than the sea, and a third hot, but tasteless."517 But at
length these forests and grassy plains were consumed, being suddenly
blown into the air, and their ashes scattered to the winds. In December,
1631, seven streams of lava poured at once from the crater, and
overflowed several villages, on the flanks and at the foot of the mountain.
Resina, partly built over the ancient site of Herculaneum, was
consumed by the fiery torrent. Great floods of mud were as destructive
as the lava itself,—no uncommon occurrence during these catastrophes;
for such is the violence of rains produced by the evolutions of
aqueous vapor, that torrents of water descend the cone, and becoming
charged with impalpable volcanic dust, and rolling along loose ashes,
acquire sufficient consistency to deserve their ordinary appellation of
"aqueous lavas."
A brief period of repose ensued, which lasted only until the year
1666, from which time to the present there has been a constant series
of eruptions, with rarely an interval of rest exceeding ten years. During
these three centuries, no irregular volcanic agency has convulsed
other points in this district. Brieslak remarked, that such irregular
convulsions had occurred in the Bay of Naples in every second century;
as, for example, the eruption of the Solfatara, in the twelfth; of the
lava of Arso, in Ischia, in the fourteenth; and of Monte Nuovo in the
sixteenth; but the eighteenth has formed an exception to this rule, and
this seems accounted for by the unprecedented number of eruptions of
Vesuvius during that period; whereas, when the new vents opened,
there had always been, as we have seen, a long intermittence of activity
in the principal volcano.

375</div></body></text></TEI>