<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="2">PREFACE.
The following passage from a work, said to be written by
the late Dr. John Campbel, and entitled Hermippus Redivivus,
suggested the first hint of the present performance:—
“There happened in the year 1687, an odd accident at
Venice, that made a very great stir then, and which I
think deserves to be rescued from oblivion. The great
freedom and ease with which all persons, who make a good
appearance, live in that city, is known sufficiently to all
who are acquainted with it; such will not therefore be surprised,
that a stranger, who went by the name of signor
Gualdi, and who made a considerable figure there, was
admitted into the best company, though nobody knew who
or what he was. He remained at Venice for some months;
and three things were remarked in his conduct. The first
was, that he had a small collection of fine pictures, which
he readily showed to any body that desired it; the next,
that he was perfectly versed in all arts and sciences, and
spoke on every subject with such readiness and sagacity, as
astonished all who heard him; and it was, in the third place,
observed, that he never wrote or received any letter, never
desired any credit, or made use of bills of exchange, but
paid for every thing in ready money and lived decently,
though not in splendour.
“This gentleman met one day at the coffee-house with
a Venetian nobleman, who was an extraordinary good judge
of pictures: he had heard of signor Gualdi’s collection, and
in a very polite manner desired to see them, to which the
other very readily consented. After the Venetian had[viii]
viewed signor Gualdi’s collection, and expressed his satisfaction,
by telling him that he had never seen a finer, considering
the number of pieces of which it consisted; he cast
his eye by chance over the chamber-door, where hung a
picture of this stranger. The Venetian looked upon it, and
then upon him. ‘This picture was drawn for you, sir,’
says he to signor Gualdi, to which the other made no answer,
but by a low bow. ‘You look,’ continued the Venetian,
‘like a man of fifty, and yet I know this picture to
be of the hand of Titian, who has been dead one hundred
and thirty years, how is this possible?’—‘It is not easy,’
said signor Gualdi, gravely, ‘to know all things that are
possible; but there is certainly no crime in my being like
a picture drawn by Titian.’ The Venetian easily perceived,
by his manner of speaking, that he had given the stranger
offence, and therefore took his leave.
“He could not forbear speaking of this in the evening
to some of his friends, who resolved to satisfy themselves
by looking upon the picture the next day. In order to
have an opportunity of doing so, they went to the coffee-house
about the time that signor Gualdi was wont to come
thither; and not meeting with him, one of them, who had
often conversed with him, went to his lodgings to enquire
after him, where he heard, that he had set out an hour before
for Vienna. This affair made a great noise, and found
a place in all the newspapers of that time.”[1]
It is well known that the philosopher’s stone, the art of
transmuting metals into gold, and the elixir vitæ, which
was to restore youth, and make him that possessed it immortal;
formed a principal object of the studies of the[ix]
curious for centuries. Many stories, beside this of signor
Gualdi, have been told, of persons who were supposed to be
in possession of those wonderful secrets, in search of which
hundreds of unfortunate adventurers wasted their fortunes
and their lives.
It has been said of Shakespear, that he


Exhausted worlds, and then imagined new[2]:


but the burthen sustained by Shakespear was too heavy for
the shoulders of any other individual. I leave the first part
of the task above mentioned to be divided among those celebrated
novelists, living and dead, who have attempted to
delineate the scenes of real life. In this little work I have
endeavoured to gain footing in one neglected track of the
latter province. The hearts and the curiosity of readers
have been assailed in so many ways, that we, writers who
bring up the rear of our illustrious predecessors, must be
contented to arrive at novelty in whatever mode we are able.
The foundation of the following tale is such as, it is not to
be supposed, ever existed. But, if I have mixed human
feelings and passions with incredible situations, and thus
rendered them impressive and interesting, I shall entertain
some hope to be pardoned the boldness and irregularity of
my design.
Some readers of my graver productions will perhaps, in
perusing these little volumes, accuse me of inconsistency;
the affections and charities of private life being every where
in this publication a topic of the warmest eulogium, while
in the Enquiry concerning Political Justice they seemed
to be treated with no great degree of indulgence and favour.
In answer to this objection, all I think it necessary to say
on the present occasion is, that, for more than four years,
I have been anxious for opportunity and leisure to modify[x]
some of the earlier chapters of that work in conformity to
the sentiments inculcated in this. Not that I see cause to
make any change respecting the principle of justice, or any
thing else fundamental to the system there delivered; but
that I apprehend domestic and private affections inseparable
from the nature of man, and from what may be styled the
culture of the heart, and am fully persuaded that they are
not incompatible with a profound and active sense of justice
in the mind of him that cherishes them. True wisdom
will recommend to us individual attachments; for with
them our minds are more thoroughly maintained in activity
and life than they can be under the privation of them; and
it is better that man should be a living being, than a stock
or a stone. True virtue will sanction this recommendation;
since it is the object of virtue to produce happiness, and
since the man who lives in the midst of domestic relations
will have many opportunities of conferring pleasure, minute
in the detail, yet not trivial in the amount, without interfering
with the purposes of general benevolence. Nay, by
kindling his sensibility, and harmonising his soul, they may
be expected, if he is endowed with a liberal and manly
spirit, to render him more prompt in the service of strangers
and the public.
Nov. 26, 1799.

[1]
TRAVELS OF ST. LEON.</div></body></text></TEI>