<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="44">CHAPTER XLIV.
EFFECTS PRODUCED BY THE POWERS OF VITALITY ON THE STATE
OF THE EARTH'S SURFACE.
Modifications in physical geography caused by organic beings—Why the vegetable
soil does not augment in thickness—The theory, that vegetation is an
antagonist power counterbalancing the degradation caused by running water
untenable—Conservative influence of vegetation—Rain diminished by felling
of forests—Distribution of American forests dependent on direction of predominant
winds—Influence of man in modifying the physical geography of
the globe.
The second branch of our inquiry, respecting changes of the organic
world, relates to the processes by which the remains of animals and
plants become fossil, or, to speak still more generally, to all the effects
produced by the powers of vitality on the surface and shell of the
earth.
Before entering on the principal division of this subject, the imbedding
and preservation of animal and vegetable remains, I shall offer a few remarks
on the superficial modifications caused directly by the agency of
organic beings, as when the growth of certain plants covers the slope of
a mountain with peat, or converts a swamp into dry land; or when vegetation
prevents the soil, in certain localities, from being washed away by
running water.
In considering alterations of this kind, brought about in the physical
geography of particular tracts, we are too apt to think exclusively of that
part of the earth's surface which has emerged from beneath the waters,
and with which alone, as terrestrial beings, we are familiar. Here the
direct power of animals and plants to cause any important variation is,
of necessity, very limited, except in checking the progress of that decay
of which the land is the chief theatre. But if we extend our views, and
instead of contemplating the dry land, consider that larger portion which
is assigned to the aquatic tribes, we discover the great influence of the
living creation, in imparting varieties of conformation to the solid exterior
which the agency of inanimate causes alone could not produce.
Thus, when timber is floated into the sea, it is often drifted to vast
distances, and subsides in spots where there might have been no deposit,
at that time and place, if the earth had not been tenanted by living
beings. If, therefore, in the course of ages, a hill of wood, or lignite,
be thus formed in the subaqueous regions, a change in the submarine
geography may be said to have resulted from the action of organic powers.
So in regard to the growth of coral reefs; it is probable that a large
709
portion of the matter of which they are composed is supplied by mineral
springs, which often rise up at the bottom of the sea, and which, on land,
abound throughout volcanic regions hundreds of leagues in extent. The
matter thus constantly given out could not go on accumulating for ever
in the waters, but would be precipitated in the abysses of the sea, even
if there were no polyps and testacea; but these animals arrest and secrete
the carbonate of lime on the summits of submarine mountains, and form
reefs many hundred feet in thickness, and hundreds of miles in length,
where, but for them, none might ever have existed.
Why the vegetable soil does not augment in thickness.—If no such
voluminous masses are formed on the land, it is not from the want of
solid matter in the structure of terrestrial animals and plants; but merely
because, as I have so often stated, the continents are those parts of the
globe where accessions of matter can scarcely ever take place—where,
on the contrary, the most solid parts already formed are, each in their
turn, exposed to gradual degradation. The quantity of timber and
vegetable matter which grows in a tropical forest in the course of a
century is enormous, and multitudes of animal skeletons are scattered
there during the same period, besides innumerable land shells and other
organic substances. The aggregate of these materials, therefore, might
constitute a mass greater in volume than that which is produced in any
coral-reef during the same lapse of years; but, although this process
should continue on the land for ever, no mountains of wood or bone
would be seen stretching far and wide over the country, or pushing out
bold promontories into the sea. The whole solid mass is either devoured
by animals, or decomposes, as does a portion of the rock and soil on
which the animals and plants are supported.
The waste of the strata themselves, accompanied by the decomposition
of their organic remains, and the setting free of their alkaline ingredients,
is one source from whence running water and the atmosphere may derive
the materials which are absorbed by the roots and leaves of plants.
Another source is the passage into a gaseous form of even the hardest
parts of animals and plants which die and putrefy in the air, where they
are soon resolved into the elements of which they are composed: and
while a portion of these constituents is volatilized, the rest is taken up
by rain-water, and sinks into the earth, or flows towards the sea; so that
they enter again and again into the composition of different organic
beings.
The principal elements found in plants are hydrogen, carbon, and
oxygen; so that water and the atmosphere contain all of them, either
in their own composition or in solution.994 The constant supply of
these elements is maintained not only by the putrefaction of animal
and vegetable substances, and the decay of rocks, but also by the
copious evolution of carbonic acid and other gases from volcanoes and
710
mineral springs, and by the effects of ordinary evaporation, whereby
aqueous vapors are made to rise from the ocean, and to circulate round
the globe.
It is well known, that when two gases of different specific gravity are
brought into contact, even though the heavier be the lowermost, they soon
become uniformly diffused by mutual absorption through the whole space
which they occupy. By virtue of this law, the heavy carbonic acid finds
its way upwards through the lighter air of the atmosphere, and conveys
nourishment to the lichen which covers the mountain top.
If the quantity of food consumed by terrestrial animals, and the
elements imbibed by the roots and leaves of plants, were derived entirely
from that supply of hydrogen, carbon, oxygen, nitrogen, and other
elements, given out into the atmosphere and the waters by the putrescence
of organic substances, then we might imagine that the vegetable
mould would, after a series of years, neither gain nor lose a single particle
by the action of organic beings; and this conclusion is not far from the
truth; but the operation which renovates the vegetable and animal mould
is by no means so simple as that here supposed. Thousands of carcases
of terrestrial animals are floated down, every century, into the sea; and,
together with forests of drift-timber, are imbedded in subaqueous deposits,
where their elements are imprisoned in solid strata, and may there remain
locked up throughout whole geological epochs before they again become
subservient to the purposes of life.
On the other hand, fresh supplies are derived by the atmosphere and
by running water, as before stated, from the disintegration of rocks and
their organic contents, and through the agency of mineral springs from the
interior of the earth, from whence all the elements before mentioned, which
enter principally into the composition of animals and vegetables, are continually
evolved. Even nitrogen is found, by chemists, to be contained
very generally in the waters of mineral springs.
Vegetation not an antagonist power counterbalancing the action of
running water.—If we suppose that the copious supply from the nether
regions, by springs and volcanic vents, of carbonic acid and other gases,
together with the decomposition of rocks, may be just sufficient to counterbalance
that loss of matter which, having already served for the nourishment
of animals and plants, is annually carried down in organized
forms, and buried in subaqueous strata, we concede the utmost that is
consistent with probability. An opinion, however, has been expressed,
that the processes of vegetable life, by absorbing various gases from the
atmosphere, cause so large a mass of solid matter to accumulate on
the surface of the land, that this mass alone may constitute a great counterpoise
to all the matter transported to lower levels by the aqueous
agents of decay. "Torrents and rivers," it is said—"the waves of the
sea and marine currents—act upon lines only; but the power of vegetation
to absorb the elastic and non-elastic fluids circulating round the
earth, extends over the whole surface of the continents. By the silent
but universal action of this great antagonist power, the spoliation and
711
waste caused by running water on the land, and by the movements of the
ocean, are neutralized, and even counterbalanced."995
In opposition to these views, I conceive that we shall form a juster
estimate of the influence of vegetation, if we consider it as being in a
slight degree conservative, and capable of retarding the waste of land,
but not of acting as an antagonist power. The vegetable mould is
seldom more than a few feet in thickness, and frequently does not exceed
a few inches; and we by no means find that its volume is more considerable
on those parts of our continents which we can prove, by geological
data, to have been elevated at more ancient periods, and where,
consequently, there has been the greatest time for the accumulation of
vegetable matter, produced throughout successive zoological epochs. On
the contrary, these higher and older regions are more frequently denuded,
so as to expose the bare rock to the action of the sun and air.
We find in the torrid zone, where the growth of plants is most rank
and luxurious, that accessions of matter due to their agency are by no
means the most conspicuous. Indeed it is in these latitudes, where the
vegetation is most active, that, for reasons to be explained in the next
chapter, even those superficial peat mosses are unknown which cover a
large area in some parts of our temperate zone. If the operation of
animal and vegetable life could restore to the general surface of the
continents a portion of the elements of those disintegrated rocks of
which such enormous masses are swept down annually into the sea, the
effects would long ere this have constituted one of the most striking
features in the structure and composition of our continents. All the
great steppes and table-lands of the world, where the action of running
water is feeble, would have become the grand repositories of organic
matter, accumulated without that intermixture of earthy sediment
which so generally characterizes the subaqueous strata.
I have already stated that, in the known operation of the igneous causes,
a real antagonist power is found, which may counterbalance the levelling
action of running water (p. 563); and there seems no good reason
for presuming that the upheaving and depressing force of earthquakes,
together with the ejection of matter by volcanoes, may not be fully adequate
to restore that inequality of the surface which rivers and the waves
and currents of the ocean annually tend to lessen. If a counterpoise be
derived from this source, the quantity and elevation of land above the
sea may for ever remain the same, in spite of the action of the aqueous
causes, which, if thus counteracted, may never be able to reduce the
surface of the earth more nearly to a state of equilibrium than that which
it has now attained; and, on the other hand, the force of the aqueous
agents themselves might thus continue for ever unimpaired.
Conservative influence of vegetation.—If, then, vegetation cannot act
as an antagonist power amid the mighty agents of change which are
always modifying the surface of the globe, let us next inquire how far
712
its influence is conservative,—how far it may retard the levelling effects
of running water, which it cannot oppose, much less counterbalance.
It is well known that a covering of herbage and shrubs may protect a
loose soil from being carried away by rain, or even by the ordinary
action of a river, and may prevent hills of loose sand from being blown
away by the wind; for the roots bind together the separate particles
into a firm mass, and the leaves intercept the rain-water, so that it dries
up gradually, instead of flowing off in a mass and with great velocity.
The old Italian hydrographers make frequent mention of the increased
degradation which has followed the clearing away of natural woods in
several parts of Italy. A remarkable example was afforded in the
Upper Val d' Arno, in Tuscany, on the removal of the woods clothing
the steep declivities of the hills by which that valley is bounded.
When the ancient forest laws were abolished by the Grand Duke Joseph,
during the last century, a considerable tract of surface in the Cassentina
(the Clausentinium of the Romans) was denuded, and immediately the
quantity of sand and soil washed down into the Arno increased enormously.
Frisi, alluding to such occurrences, observes, that as soon as
the bushes and plants were removed, the waters flowed off more rapidly,
and, in the manner of floods, swept away the vegetable soil.996
This effect of vegetation is of high interest to the geologist, when he
is considering the formation of those valleys which have been principally
due to the action of rivers. The spaces intervening between valleys,
whether they be flat or ridgy, when covered with vegetation, may
scarcely undergo the slightest waste, as the surface may be protected by
the green sward of grass; and this may be renewed, in the manner
before described, from elements derived from rain-water and the atmosphere.
Hence, while the river is continually bearing down matter in
the alluvial plain, and undermining the cliffs on each side of every valley,
the height of the intervening rising grounds may remain stationary.
In this manner, a cone of loose scoriæ, sand, and ashes, such as Monte
Nuovo, may, when it has once become densely clothed with herbage
and shrubs, suffer scarcely any further dilapidation; and the perfect
state of the cones of hundreds of extinct volcanoes in France, the Neapolitan
territory, Sicily, and elsewhere, may prove nothing whatever,
either as to their relative or absolute antiquity. We may be enabled
to infer, from the integrity of such conical hills of incoherent materials,
that no flood can have passed over the countries where they are situated,
since their formation; but the atmospheric action alone, in spots where
there happen to be no torrents, and where the surface was clothed with
vegetation, could scarcely in any lapse of ages have destroyed them.
During a tour in Spain, in 1830, I was surprised to see a district of
gently undulating ground in Catalonia, consisting of red and gray sandstone,
and in some parts of red marl, almost entirely denuded of herbage;
while the roots of the pines, holm oaks, and some other trees, were half
713
exposed, as if the soil had been washed away by a flood. Such is the
state of the forests, for example, between Oristo and Vich, and near San
Lorenzo. But, being overtaken by a violent thunder-storm, in the month
of August, I saw the whole surface, even the highest levels of some flat-topped
hills, streaming with mud, while on every declivity the devastation
of torrents was terrific. The peculiarities in the physiognomy of
the district were at once explained; and I was taught that, in speculating
on the greater effects which the direct action of rain may once have produced
on the surface of certain parts of England, we need not revert to
periods when the heat of the climate was tropical.
In the torrid zone the degradation of land is generally more rapid;
but the waste is by no means proportioned to the superior quantity of
rain or the suddenness of its fall, the transporting power of water being
counteracted by a greater luxuriance of vegetation. A geologist who is
no stranger to tropical countries observes, that the softer rocks would
speedily be washed away in such regions, if the numerous roots of plants
were not matted together in such a manner as to produce considerable
resistance to the destructive power of the rains. The parasitical and
creeping plants also entwine in every possible direction, so as to render
the forests nearly impervious, and the trees possess forms and leaves best
calculated to shoot off the heavy rains; which, when they have thus
been broken in their fall, are quickly absorbed by the ground beneath,
or, when thrown into the drainage depressions, give rise to furious
torrents.997
Influence of Man in modifying the Physical Geography of the
Globe.
Before concluding this chapter, I shall offer a few observations on the
influence of man in modifying the physical geography of the globe; for
we must class his agency among the powers of organic nature.
Felling of forests.—The felling of forests has been attended, in many
countries, by a diminution of rain, as in Barbadoes and Jamaica.998 For
in tropical countries, where the quantity of aqueous vapor in the atmosphere
is great, but where, on the other hand, the direct rays of the sun
are most powerful, any impediment to the free circulation of air, or any
screen which shades the earth from the solar rays, becomes a source of
humidity; and wherever dampness and cold have begun to be generated
by such causes, the condensation of vapor continues. The leaves, moreover,
of all plants are alembics, and some of those in the torrid zone have
the remarkable property of distilling water, thus contributing to prevent
the earth from becoming parched up.
Distribution of the American forests.—There can be no doubt then,
that the state of the climate, especially the humidity of the atmosphere,
influences vegetation, and that, in its turn, vegetation re-acts upon the
714
climate: but some writers seem to have attributed too much importance
to the influence of forests, particularly those of America, as if they were
the primary cause of the moisture of the climate.
The theory of a modern author on this subject "that forests exist in
those parts of America only where the predominant winds carry with them a
considerable quantity of moisture from the ocean," seems far more rational.
In all countries, he says, "having a summer heat exceeding 70°, the
presence or absence of natural woods, and their greater or less luxuriance,
may be taken as a measure of the amount of humidity, and of the fertility
of the soil. Short and heavy rains in a warm country will produce
grass, which, having its roots near to the surface, springs up in a few days,
and withers when the moisture is exhausted; but transitory rains, however
heavy, will not nourish trees; because, after the surface is saturated,
the remainder of the water runs off, and the moisture lodged in the soil
neither sinks deep enough, nor is in sufficient quantity, to furnish the
giants of the forests with the necessary sustenance. It may be assumed
that twenty inches of rain falling moderately or at intervals, will leave a
greater permanent supply in the soil than forty inches falling, as it sometimes
does in the torrid zone, in as many hours."999
"In all regions," he continues, "where ranges of mountains intercept
the course of the constant or predominant winds, the country on the
windward side of the mountains will be moist, and that on the leeward
dry; and hence parched deserts will generally be found on the west side
of countries within the tropics, and on the east side of those beyond
them, the prevailing winds in these cases being generally in opposite directions.
On this principle, the position of forests in North and South
America may be explained. Thus, for example, in the region within the
thirtieth parallel, the moisture swept up by the trade-wind from the Atlantic
is precipitated in part upon the mountains of Brazil, which are but
low, and so distributed as to extend far into the interior. The portion
which remains is borne westward, and, losing a little as it proceeds, is
at length arrested by the Andes, where it falls down in showers on their
summits. The aërial current, now deprived of all the humidity with
which it can part, arrives in a state of complete exsiccation at Peru, where
consequently no rain falls. But in the region of America, beyond the
thirtieth parallel, the Andes serve as a screen to intercept the moisture
brought by the prevailing winds from the Pacific Ocean: rains are copious
on their summits, and in Chili on their western declivities; but none
falls on the plains to the eastward, except occasionally when the wind
blows from the Atlantic."1000
I have been more particular in explaining these views, because they
appear to place in a true light the dependence of vegetation on climate,
the humidity being increased, and more uniformly diffused throughout
the year, by the gradual spreading of wood.
715
It has been affirmed, that formerly, when France and England were
covered with wood, Europe was much colder than at present; that the
winters in Italy were longer, and that the Seine, and many other rivers,
froze more regularly every winter than now. M. Arago, in an essay on
this subject, has endeavored to show, by tables of observations on the
congelation of the Rhine, Danube, Rhone, Po, Seine, and other rivers, at
different periods, that there is no reason to believe the cold to have been
in general more intense in ancient times.1001 He admits, however, that the
climate of Tuscany has been so far modified, by the removal of wood, as
that the winters are less cold; but the summers also, he contends, are
less hot than of old; and the summers, according to him, were formerly
hotter in France than in our own times. His evidence is derived chiefly
from documents showing that wine was made three centuries ago in
the Vivarais and several other provinces, at an earlier season, at greater
elevations, and in higher latitudes, than are now found suitable to the vine.
There seems little doubt that in the United States of North America
the rapid clearing of the country has rendered the winters less severe and
the summers less hot; in other words, the extreme temperatures of
January and July have been observed from year to year to approach
somewhat nearer to each other. Whether in this case, or in France, the
mean temperature has been raised, seems by no means as yet decided;
but there is no doubt that the climate has become, as Buffon would have
said, "less excessive."
I have before shown, when treating of the excavation of new estuaries
in Holland by inroads of the ocean, as also of the changes on our own
coasts, that although the conversion of sea into land by artificial labors
may be great, yet it must always be in subordination to the power of the
tides and currents, or to the great movements which alter the relative
level of the land and sea, (Chap. XX.) If, in addition to the assistance
obtained by parliamentary grants for defending Dunwich from the waves,
all the resources of Europe had been directed to the same end, the existence
of that port might perhaps have been prolonged for several centuries
(p. 310.) But in the mean time, the current would have continued to
sweep away portions from the adjoining cliffs on each side, giving to the
whole line of coast its present form, until at length the town, projecting as
a narrow promontory, must have become exposed to the irresistible fury
of the waves.
It is scarcely necessary to observe, that the control which man can
obtain over the igneous agents is less even than that which he may exert
over the aqueous. He cannot modify the upheaving or depressing force
of earthquakes, or the periods or degree of violence of volcanic eruptions;
and on these causes the inequalities of the earth's surface, and, consequently,
the shape of the sea and land, appear mainly to depend. The
utmost that man can hope to effect in this respect is occasionally to
divert the course of a lava-stream, and to prevent the burning matter, for
716
a season, from overwhelming a city, or some other of the proudest works
of human industry.
If all the nations of the earth should attempt to quarry away the lava
which flowed during one eruption from the Icelandic volcanoes in 1783,
and the two following years, and should attempt to consign it to the
deepest abysses of the ocean, they might toil for thousands of years and
not accomplish their task. Yet the matter borne down to the sea by two
great rivers, the Ganges and Burrampooter, in each quarter of a century,
probably equals in weight and volume the mass of Icelandic lava produced
by that great eruption (p. 282). So insignificant is the aggregate
force exerted by man, when contrasted with the ordinary operations of
aqueous or igneous agents in the natural world.
No application, perhaps, of human skill and labor tends so greatly to
vary the state of the habitable surface, as that employed in the drainage
of lakes and marshes, since not only the stations of many animals and
plants, but the general climate of a district, may thus be modified. It is
also a kind of alteration to which it is difficult to find anything analogous
in the agency of inferior beings; for we ought always, before we decide
that any part of the influence of man is novel and anomalous, carefully to
consider the powers of all other animated agents which may be limited
or superseded by him.1002 Many who have reasoned on these subjects seem
to have forgotten that the human race often succeeds to the discharge of
functions previously fulfilled by other species. Suppose the growth of some
of the larger terrestrial plants, or, in other words, the extent of forest, to
be diminished by man, and the climate to be thereby modified, it does
not follow that this kind of innovation is unprecedented. It is a change
in the state of vegetation, and such may often have been the result of
the appearance of new species upon the earth. The multiplication, for
example, of certain insects in parts of Germany, during the last century,
destroyed more trees than man, perhaps, could have felled during an
equal period.
It would be rash, however, to affirm that the power of man to modify
the surface may not differ in kind or degree from that of other living
beings; although the problem is certainly more complex than many
who have speculated on such topics have imagined. If land be raised
from the sea, the greatest alteration in its physical condition, which
could ever arise from the influence of organic beings, would probably
be produced by the first immigration of terrestrial plants, whereby
the new tract would become covered with vegetation. The change
next in importance would seem to be when animals first enter, and
modify the proportionate numbers of certain species of plants. If there
be any anomaly in the intervention of man, in farther varying the relative
717
numbers in the vegetable kingdom, it may not so much consist in
the kind or absolute quantity of alteration, as in the circumstance that
a single species, in this case, would exert, by its superior power and universal
distribution, an influence equal to that of hundreds of other terrestrial
animals.
If we inquire whether man, by his direct power, or by the changes
which he may give rise to indirectly, tends, upon the whole, to lessen or
increase the inequalities of the earth's surface, we shall incline, perhaps,
to the opinion that he is a levelling agent. In mining operations he
conveys upwards a certain quantity of materials from the bowels of the
earth; but, on the other hand, much rock is taken annually from the
land, in the shape of ballast, and afterwards thrown into the sea, and
by this means, in spite of prohibitory laws, many harbors, in various
parts of the world, have been blocked up. We rarely transport heavy
materials to higher levels, and our pyramids and cities are chiefly constructed
of stone brought down from more elevated situations. By
ploughing up thousands of square miles, and exposing a surface for
part of the year to the action of the elements, we assist the abrading
force of rain, and diminish the conservative effects of vegetation.

718</div></body></text></TEI>