<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="21">CHAPTER XXI.
REPRODUCTIVE EFFECTS OF TIDES AND CURRENTS.
Estuaries, how formed—Silting up of estuaries does not compensate the loss of
land on the borders of the ocean—Bed of the German
Ocean—Composition and
extent of its sand-banks—Strata deposited by currents in the English channel—On
the shores of the Mediterranean—At the mouths of the Amazon, Orinoco,
and Mississippi—Wide area over which strata may be formed by this cause.
From the facts enumerated in the last chapter, it appears that on the
borders of the ocean, currents and tides co-operating with the waves of
the sea are most powerful instruments in the destruction and transportation
of rocks; and as numerous tributaries discharge their alluvial burden
into the channel of one great river, so we find that many rivers
deliver their earthy contents to one marine current, to be borne by it to
a distance, and deposited in some deep receptacle of the ocean. The
current, besides receiving this tribute of sedimentary matter from streams
draining the land, acts also itself on the coast, as does a river on the
cliffs which bound a valley. Yet the waste of cliffs by marine currents
constitutes on the whole a very insignificant portion of the denudation
annually effected by aqueous causes, as I shall point out in the sequel
of this chapter (p. 339).
In inland seas, where the tides are insensible, or on those parts of the
borders of the ocean where they are feeble, it is scarcely possible to
prevent a harbor at a river's mouth from silting up; for a bar of sand
or mud is formed at points where the velocity of the turbid river is
checked by the sea, or where the river and a marine current neutralize
each other's force. For the current, as we have seen, may, like the
river, hold in suspension a large quantity of sediment, or, co-operating
with the waves, may cause the progressive motion of a shingle beach in
one direction. I have already alluded to the erection of piers and groins
at certain places on our southern coast, to arrest the course of the shingle
and sand (see p. 318318). The immediate effect of these temporary obstacles
is to cause a great accumulation of pebbles on one side of the barrier,
after which the beach still moves on round the end of the pier at a
greater distance from the land. This system, however, is often attended
with a serious evil, for during storms the waves throw suddenly into
the harbor the vast heap of pebbles which have collected for years
behind the groin or pier, as happened during a great gale (Jan. 1839)
at Dover.
The formation and keeping open of large estuaries are due to the
combined influence of tidal currents and rivers; for when the tide rises,
a large body of water suddenly enters the mouth of the river, where,
becoming confined within narrower bounds, while its momentum is not
destroyed, it is urged on, and, having to pass through a contracted
338
channel, rises and runs with increased velocity, just as a stream when it
reaches the arch of a bridge scarcely large enough to give passage to
its waters, rushes with a steep fall through the arch. During the ascent
of the tide, a body of fresh water, flowing down in an opposite direction
from the higher country, is arrested in its course for several hours;
and thus a large lake of fresh and brackish water is accumulated, which,
when the sea ebbs, is let loose, as on the removal of an artificial sluice
or dam. By the force of this retiring water, the alluvial sediment both
of the river and of the sea is swept away, and transported to such a
distance from the mouth of the estuary, that a small part only can
return with the next tide.
It sometimes happens, that during a violent storm a large bar of sand
is suddenly made to shift its position, so as to prevent the free influx of
the tides, or efflux of river water. Thus about the year 1500 the sands
at Bayonne were suddenly thrown across the mouth of the Adour.
That river, flowing back upon itself, soon forced a passage to the northward
along the sandy plain of Capbreton, till at last it reached the sea
at Boucau, at the distance of seven leagues from the point where it had
formerly entered. It was not till the year 1579 that the celebrated
architect Louis de Foix undertook, at the desire of Henry III., to reopen
the ancient channel, which he at last effected with great
difficulty.461
In the estuary of the Thames at London, and in the Gironde, the
tide rises only for five hours and ebbs seven, and in all estuaries the
water requires a longer time to run down than up; so that the preponderating
force is always in the direction which tends to keep open a
deep and broad passage. But for reasons already explained, there is
naturally a tendency in all estuaries to silt up partially, since eddies,
and backwaters, and points where opposing streams meet, are very
numerous, and constantly change their position.
Many writers have declared that the gain on our eastern coast, since
the earliest periods of history, has more than counterbalanced the loss;
but they have been at no pains to calculate the amount of loss, and have
often forgotten that, while the new acquisitions are manifest, there are
rarely any natural monuments to attest the former existence of the land
that has been carried away. They have also taken into their account
those tracts artificially recovered, which are often of great agricultural
importance, and may remain secure, perhaps, for thousands of years,
but which are only a few feet above the mean level of the sea, and are
therefore exposed to be overflowed again by a small proportion of the
force required to move cliffs of considerable height on our shores. If it
were true that the area of land annually abandoned by the sea in estuaries
were equal to that invaded by it, there would still be no compensation
in kind.
The tidal current which flows out from the northwest, and bears
against the eastern coast of England, transports, as we have seen, materials
339
of various kinds. Aided by the waves, it undermines and sweeps
away the granite, gneiss, trap-rocks, and sandstone of Shetland, and
removes the gravel and loam of the cliffs of Holderness, Norfolk, and
Suffolk, which are between twenty and three hundred feet in height,
and which waste at various rates of from one foot to six yards annually.
It also bears away, in co-operation with the Thames and the tides, the
strata of London clay on the coast of Essex and Sheppey. The sea at
the same time consumes the chalk with its flints for many miles continuously
on the shores of Kent and Sussex—commits annual ravages
on the freshwater beds, capped by a thick covering of chalk-flint gravel,
in Hampshire, and continually saps the foundations of the Portland limestone.
It receives, besides, during the rainy months, large supplies of
pebbles, sand, and mud, which numerous streams from the Grampians,
Cheviots, and other chains, send down to the sea. To what regions,
then, is all this matter consigned? It is not retained in mechanical
suspension by the waters of the ocean, nor does it mix with them in a
state of chemical solution—it is deposited somewhere, yet certainly not
in the immediate neighborhood of our shores; for, in that case, there
would soon be a cessation of the encroachment of the sea, and large
tracts of low land, like Romney Marsh, would almost everywhere encircle
our island.
As there is now a depth of water exceeding thirty feet, in some spots
where towns like Dunwich flourished but a few centuries ago, it is clear
that the current not only carries far away the materials of the wasted
cliffs, but is capable also of excavating the bed of the sea to a certain
moderate depth.
So great is the quantity of matter held in suspension by the tidal
current on our shores, that the waters are in some places artificially
introduced into certain lands below the level of the sea; and by repeating
this operation, which is called "warping," for two or three years,
considerable tracts have been raised, in the estuary of the Humber, to
the height of about six feet. If a current, charged with such materials,
meets with deep depressions in the bed of the ocean, it must often fill
them up; just as a river, when it meets with a lake in its course, fills it
gradually with sediment.
I have said (p. 337) that the action of the waves and currents on sea-cliffs,
or their power to remove matter from above to below the sea-level,
is insignificant in comparison with the power of rivers to perform
the same task. As an illustration we may take the coast of Holderness
described in the last chapter (p. 304). It is composed, as we have
seen, of very destructible materials, is thirty-six miles long, and its average
height may be taken at forty feet. As it has wasted away at the
rate of two and a quarter yards annually, for a long period, it will be
found on calculation that the quantity of matter thrown down into the
sea every year, and removed by the current, amounts to 51,321,600
cubic feet. It has been shown that the united Ganges and Brahmapootra
carry down to the Bay of Bengal 40,000,000,000 of cubic feet
340
of solid matter every year, so that their transporting power is no less
than 780 times greater than that of the sea on the coast above-mentioned;
and in order to produce a result equal to that of the two Indian
rivers, we must have a line of wasting coast, like that of Holderness,
nearly 28,000 miles in length, or longer than the entire circumference
of the globe by above 3000 miles. The reason of so great a difference
in the results may be understood when we reflect that the operations
of the ocean are limited to a single line of cliff surrounding a large area,
whereas great rivers with their tributaries, and the mountain torrents which
flow into them, act simultaneously on a length of bank almost indefinite.
Nevertheless we are by no means entitled to infer, that the denuding
force of the great ocean is a geological cause of small efficacy, or inferior
to that of rivers. Its chief influence is exerted at moderate depths
below the surface, on all those areas which are slowly rising, or are
attempting, as it were, to rise above the sea. From data hitherto obtained
respecting subterranean movements, we can scarcely speculate
on an average rate of upheaval of more than two or three feet in a
century. An elevation to this amount is taking place in Scandinavia,
and probably in many submarine areas as vast as those which we know
to be sinking from the proofs derived from circular lagoon islands or
coral atolls. (See chap. 50.) Suppose strata as destructible as those
of the Wealden, or the lower and upper cretaceous formation, or the
tertiary deposits of the British Isles to be thus slowly upheaved, how
readily might they all be swept away by waves and currents in an
open sea! How entirely might each stratum disappear as it was
brought up successively and exposed to the breakers! Shoals of wide
extent might be produced, but it is difficult to conceive how any continent
could ever be formed under such circumstances. Were it not
indeed for the hardness and toughness of the crystalline and volcanic
rocks, which are often capable of resisting the action of the waves, few
lands might ever emerge from the midst of an open sea.
Supposed filling up of the German Ocean.—The German Ocean is
deepest on the Norwegian side, where the soundings give 190 fathoms;
but the mean depth of the whole basin may be stated at no more than
thirty-one fathoms.462 The bed of this sea is traversed by several enormous
banks, the greatest of which is the Dogger Bank, extending for
upwards of 354 miles from north to south. The whole superficies of
these shoals is equal to about one-third of the whole extent of England
and Scotland. The average height of the banks measures, according to
Mr. Stevenson, about seventy-eight feet; the upper portion of them
consisting of fine and coarse siliceous sand, mixed with comminuted
corals and shells.463 It had been supposed that these vast submarine
hills were made up bodily of loose materials supplied from the waste of
the English, Dutch, and other coasts; but the survey of the North Sea,
341
conducted by Captain Hewett, affords ground for suspecting this opinion
to be erroneous. If such immense mounds of sand and mud had
been accumulated under the influence of currents, the same causes ought
nearly to have reduced to one level the entire bottom of the German
Ocean; instead of which some long narrow ravines are found to intersect
the banks. One of these varies from seventeen to forty-four
fathoms in depth, and has very precipitous sides; in one part, called
the "Inner Silver Pits," it is fifty-five fathoms deep. The shallowest
parts of the Dogger Bank were found to be forty-two feet under water,
except in one place, where the wreck of a ship had caused a shoal.
Such uniformity in the minimum depth of water seems to imply that
the currents, which vary in their velocity from a mile to two miles and
a half per hour, have power to prevent the accumulation of drift matter
in places of less depth.
Strata deposited by currents.—It appears extraordinary, that in some
tracts of the sea, adjoining the coast of England, where we know that
currents are not only sweeping along rocky masses, thrown down, from
time to time, from the high cliffs, but also occasionally scooping out
channels in the regular strata, there should exist fragile shells and tender
zoophytes in abundance, which live uninjured by these violent movements.
The ocean, however, is in this respect a counterpart of the
land; and as, on the continents, rivers may undermine their banks, uproot
trees, and roll along sand and gravel, while their waters are inhabited
by testacea and fish, and their alluvial plains are adorned with rich
vegetation and forests, so the sea may be traversed by rapid currents,
and its bed may here and there suffer great local derangement, without
any interruption of the general order and tranquillity. It has been ascertained
by soundings in all parts of the world, that where new deposits
are taking place in the sea, coarse sand and small pebbles commonly
occur near the shore, while farther from land, and in deeper water, finer
sand and broken shells are spread out over the bottom. Still farther
out, the finest mud and ooze are alone met with. Mr. Austen observes
that this rule holds good in every part of the English Channel examined
by him. He also informs us, that where the tidal current runs rapidly
in what are called "races," where surface undulations are perceived
in the calmest weather, over deep banks, the discoloration of the water
does not arise from the power of such a current to disturb the bottom
at a depth of 40 or 80 fathoms, as some have supposed. In these cases,
a column of water sometimes 500 feet in height, is moving onwards with
the tide clear and transparent above, while the lower portion holds fine
sediment in suspension (a fact ascertained by soundings), when suddenly
it impinges upon a bank, and its height is reduced to 300 feet.
It is thus made to boil up and flow off at the surface, a process which
forces up the lower strata of water charged with fine particles of mud,
which in their passage from the coast had gradually sunk to a depth of
300 feet or more.464
342
One important character in the formations produced by currents is,
the immense extent over which they may be the means of diffusing
homogeneous mixtures, for these are often coextensive with a great
line of coast; and, by comparison with their deposits, the deltas of
rivers must shrink into significance. In the Mediterranean, the same
current which is rapidly destroying many parts of the African coast,
between the Straits of Gibraltar and the Nile, checks also the growth
of the delta of the Nile, and drifts the sediment of that great river to
the eastward. To this source may be attributed the rapid accretions
of land on parts of the Syrian shores where rivers do not enter.
Among the greatest deposits now in progress, and of which the distribution
is chiefly determined by currents, we may class those between
the mouths of the Amazon and the southern coast of North America.
Captain Sabine found that the equatorial current before mentioned
(p. 292) was running with the rapidity of four miles an hour where it crosses
the stream of the Amazon, which river preserves part of its original
impulse, and has its waters not wholly mingled with those of the ocean
at the distance of 300 miles from its mouth.465 The sediment of the
Amazon is thus constantly carried to the northwest as far as to the
mouths of the Orinoco, and an immense tract of swamp is formed along
the coast of Guiana, with a long range of muddy shoals bordering the
marshes, and becoming converted into land.466 The sediment of the
Orinoco is partly detained, and settles near its mouth, causing the
shores of Trinidad to extend rapidly, and is partly swept away into the
Carribean Sea by the Guinea current. According to Humboldt, much
sediment is carried again out of the Carribean Sea into the Gulf of
Mexico.
It should not be overlooked that marine currents, even on coasts
where there are no large rivers, may still be the agents of spreading not
only sand and pebbles, but the finest mud, far and wide over the bottom
of the ocean. For several thousand miles along the western coast of
South America, comprising the larger parts of Peru and Chili, there is
a perpetual rolling of shingle along the shore, part of which, as Mr.
Darwin has shown, are incessantly reduced to the finest mud by the
waves, and swept into the depths of the Pacific by the tides and currents.
The same author however has remarked that, notwithstanding
the great force of the waves on that shore, all rocks 60 feet under water
are covered by sea-weed, showing that the bed of the sea is not denuded
at that depth, the effects of the winds being comparatively superficial.
In regard to the distribution of sediment by currents it may be observed,
that the rate of subsidence of the finer mud carried down by
every great river into the ocean, or of that caused by the rolling of the
waves upon a shore, must be extremely slow; for the more minute the
separate particles of mud, the slower will they sink to the bottom, and
343
the sooner will they acquire what is called their terminal velocity. It
is well known that a solid body, descending through a resisting medium,
falls by the force of gravity, which is constant, but its motion is
resisted by the medium more and more as its velocity increases, until
the resistance becomes sufficient to counteract the farther increase of
velocity. For example, a leaden ball, one inch diameter, falling through
air of density as at the earth's surface, will never acquire greater velocity
than 260 feet per second, and, in water, its greatest velocity will be
8 feet 6 inches per second. If the diameter of the ball were 1/100 of an
inch, the terminal velocities in air would be 26 feet, and in water ·86 of
a foot per second.
Now, every chemist is familiar with the fact, that minute particles
descend with extreme slowness through water, the extent of their
surface being very great in proportion to their weight, and the resistance
of the fluid depending on the amount of surface. A precipitate of
sulphate of baryta, for example, will sometimes require more than five
or six hours to subside one inch;467 while oxalate and phosphate of lime
require nearly an hour to subside about an inch and a half and two
inches respectively,468 so exceedingly small are the particles of which
these substances consist.
When we recollect that the depth of the ocean is supposed frequently
to exceed three miles, and that currents run through different parts of
that ocean at the rate of four miles an hour, and when at the same time
we consider that some fine mud carried away from the mouths of rivers
and from sea-beaches, where there is a heavy surf, as well as the impalpable
powder showered down by volcanoes, may subside at the rate
of only an inch per hour, we shall be prepared to find examples of the
transportation of sediment over areas of indefinite extent.
It is not uncommon for the emery powder used in polishing glass to
take more than an hour to sink one foot. Suppose mud composed of
coarser particles to fall at the rate of two feet per hour, and these to be
discharged into that part of the Gulf Stream which preserves a mean
velocity of three miles an hour for a distance of two thousand miles; in
twenty-eight days these particles will be carried 2016 miles, and will
have fallen only to a depth of 224 fathoms.
In this example, however, it is assumed that the current retains its
superficial velocity at the depth of 224 fathoms, for which we have as
yet no data, although we have seen that the motion of a current may
continue at the depth of 100 fathoms. (See above, p. 28.) Experiments
should be made to ascertain the rate of currents at considerable
distances from the surface, and the time taken by the finest sediment to
settle in sea-water of a given depth, and then the geologist may determine
the area over which homogeneous mixtures may be simultaneously
distributed in certain seas.

344</div></body></text></TEI>