<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="17">
[111]
CHAPTER XVII.

The Ether.

In what has just been said, we have spoken of
light, only with respect to its power of illuminating
objects, and conveying the impression of them to the
eye. It possesses, however, beyond all doubt, many
other qualities. Light is intimately connected with
heat, as we see in the case of the sun and of flame;
yet it is clear that light and heat are not identical.
Light is evidently connected too with electricity and
galvanism; and perhaps, through these, with magnetism:
it is, as has already been mentioned, indispensably
necessary to the healthy discharge of the functions
of vegetable life; without it plants cannot duly
exercise their vital powers: it manifests also chemical
action in various ways.
The luminiferous ether then, if we so call the medium
in which light is propagated, must possess
many other properties besides those mechanical ones
on which the illuminating power depends. It must
not be merely like a fluid poured into the vacant
spaces and interstices of the material world, and exercising
no action on objects; it must affect the physical,
chemical and vital powers of what it touches.
It must be a great and active agent in the work of
the universe, as well as an active reporter of what is
done by other agents. It must possess a number of
complex and refined contrivances and adjustments
which we cannot analyze, bearing upon plants and
chemical compounds, and the imponderable agents;
as well as those laws which we conceive that we
have analyzed, by which it is the vehicle of illumination
and vision.
[112]
We have had occasion to point out how complex
is the machinery of the atmosphere, and how varied
its objects; since, besides being the means of communication
as the medium of sound, it has known
laws which connect it with heat and moisture; and
other laws, in virtue of which it is decomposed by
vegetables. It appears, in like manner, that the
ether is not only the vehicle of light, but has also
laws, at present unknown, which connect it with
heat, electricity, and other agencies; and other laws
through which it is necessary to vegetables, enabling
them to decompose air. All analogy leads us to suppose
that if we knew as much of the constitution of
the luminiferous ether as we know of the constitution
of the atmosphere, we should find it a machine
as complex and artificial, as skilfully and admirably
constructed.
We know at present very little indeed of the construction
of this machine. Its existence is, perhaps,
satisfactorily made out; in order that we may not
interrupt the progress of our argument, we shall
refer to other works for the reasonings which appear
to lead to this conclusion. But whether heat, electricity,
galvanism, magnetism, be fluids; or effects or
modifications of fluids; and whether such fluids or
ethers be the same with the luminiferous ether, or
with each other; are questions of which all or most
appear to be at present undecided, and it would be
presumptuous and premature here to take one side
or the other.
The mere fact, however, that there is such an
ether, and that it has properties related to other
agents, in the way we have suggested, is well calculated
to extend our views of the structure of the universe,
and of the resources, if we may so speak, of
the Power by which it is arranged. The solid and
fluid matter of the earth is the most obvious to our
senses; over this, and in its cavities, is poured an
invisible fluid, the air, by which warmth and life are
diffused and fostered, and by which men communicate[113]
with men: over and through this again, and
reaching, so far as we know, to the utmost bounds of
the universe, is spread another most subtle and attenuated
fluid, which, by the play of another set of
agents, aids the energies of nature, and which, filling
all parts of space, is a means of communication
with other planets and other systems.
There is nothing in all this like any material necessity,
compelling the world to be as it is and no
otherwise. How should the properties of these three
great classes of agents, visible objects, air, and light,
so harmonize and assist each other, that order and
life should be the result. Without all the three, and
all the three constituted in their present manner, and
subject to their present laws, living things could not
exist. If the earth had no atmosphere, or if the
world had no ether, all must be inert and dead.
Who constructed these three extraordinary complex
pieces of machinery, the earth with its productions,
the atmosphere, and the ether? Who fitted them
into each other in many parts, and thus made it
possible for them to work together? We conceive
there can be but one answer; a most wise and good
God.
</div></body></text></TEI>