<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Reflections on the Decline of Science in England</title><author>Babbage, Charles (1791-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>B. Fellowes</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="6">
      CHAPTER III. GENERAL STATE OF LEARNED SOCIETIES IN ENGLAND.
    

      The progress of knowledge convinced the world that the system of the
      division of labour and of cooperation was as applicable to science, as it
      had been found available for the improvement of manufactures. The want of
      competition in science produced effects similar to those which the same
      cause gives birth to in the arts. The cultivators of botany were the first
      to feel that the range of knowledge embraced by the Royal Society was too
      comprehensive to admit of sufficient attention to their favourite subject,
      and they established the Linnean Society. After many years, a new science
      arose, and the Geological Society was produced. At an another and more
      recent epoch, the friends of astronomy, urged by the wants of their
      science, united to establish the Astronomical Society. Each of these
      bodies found, that the attention devoted to their science by the parent
      establishment was insufficient for their wants, and each in succession
      experienced from the Royal Society the most determined opposition.
    

      Instituted by the most enlightened philosophers, solely for the promotion
      of the natural sciences, that learned body justly conceived that nothing
      could be more likely to render these young institutions permanently
      successful, than discouragement and opposition at their commencement.
      Finding their first attempts so eminently successful, they redoubled the
      severity of their persecution, and the result was commensurate with their
      exertions, and surpassed even their wildest anticipations. The
      Astronomical Society became in six years known and respected throughout
      Europe, not from the halo of reputation which the glory of its vigourous
      youth had thrown around the weakness of its declining years; but from the
      sterling merit of "its unpretending deeds, from the sympathy it claimed
      and received from every practical astronomer, whose labours it relieved,
      and whose calculations it lightened."
    

      But the system which worked so well is now changed, and the Zoological and
      Medico-Botanical Societies were established without opposition: perhaps,
      indeed, the total failure of the latter society is the best proof of the
      wisdom which guided the councils of the Royal. At present, the various
      societies exist with no feelings of rivalry or hostility, each pursuing
      its separate objects, and all uniting in deploring with filial regret, the
      second childhood of their common parent, and the evil councils by which
      that sad event has been anticipated.
    

      It is the custom to attach certain letters to the names of those who
      belong to different societies, and these marks of ownership are by many
      considered the only valuable part of their purchase on entry. The
      following is a list of some of these societies. The second column gives
      the ready-money prices of the tail-pieces indicated in the third.
    

     SOCIETIES.               Fees on Admission         Appended
                              including Composition     Letters
                              for Annual Payments.

                                   L. s. d.
     Royal Society.............  50  0  0               F.R.S.
     Royal Society of Edinburgh. 25  4  0*              F.R.S.E.
     Royal Academy of Dublin...  26  5  0               M.R.I.A.
     Royal Society of Literature 36 15  0               F.R.S.Lit.
     Antiquarian...............  50  8  0               F.A.S.
     Linnean...................  36  0  0               F.L.S.
     Geological................  34 15  0               F.G.S.
     Astronomical..............  25  4  0               M.A.S.
     Zoological................  26  5  0               F.Z.S.
     Royal Institution.........  50  0  0               M.R.I.
     Royal Asiatic..............  31 10  0               F.R.A.S.
     Horticultural.............  43  6  0               F.H.S.
     Medico-Botanical..........  21  0  0               F.M.B.S.


      [* The Royal Society of Edinburgh now requires, for composition in lieu of
      annual contributions, a sum dependent on the value of the life of the
      member.]
    

      Thus, those who are ambitious of scientific distinction, may, according to
      their fancy, render their name a kind of comet, carrying with it a tail of
      upwards of forty letters, at the average cost of 10L. 9s. 9d. per letter.
    

      Perhaps the reader will remark, that science cannot be declining in a
      country which supports so many institutions for its cultivation. It is
      indeed creditable to us, that the greater part of these societies are
      maintained by the voluntary contributions of their members. But, unless
      the inquiries which have recently taken place in some of them should
      rectify the SYSTEM OF MANAGEMENT by which several have been oppressed, it
      is not difficult to predict that their duration will be short. Full
      PUBLICITY, PRINTED STATEMENTS OF ACCOUNTS, and occasional DISCUSSIONS and
      inquiries at GENERAL MEETINGS, are the only safeguards; and a due degree
      of VIGILANCE should be exercised on those who DISCOURAGE these principles.
      Of the Royal Society, I shall speak in a succeeding page; and I regret to
      add, that I might have said more. My object is to amend it; but, like all
      deeply-rooted complaints, the operation which alone can contribute to its
      cure, is necessarily painful. Had the words of remonstrance or reproof
      found utterance through other channels, I had gladly been silent, content
      to support by my vote the reasonings of the friend of science and of the
      Society. But this has not been the case, and after frustrated efforts to
      introduce improvements, I shall now endeavour, by the force of plain, but
      perhaps painful truths, to direct public opinion in calling for such a
      reform, as shall rescue the Royal Society from contempt in our own
      country, from ridicule in others.
    

      On the next five societies in the list, I shall offer no remarks. Of the
      Geological, I shall say a few words. It possesses all the freshness, the
      vigour, and the ardour of youth in the pursuit of a youthful science, and
      has succeeded in a most difficult experiment, that of having an oral
      discussion on the subject of each paper read at its meetings. To say of
      these discussions, that they are very entertaining, is the least part of
      the praise which is due to them. They are generally very instructive, and
      sometimes bring together isolated facts in the science which, though
      insignificant when separate, mutually illustrate each other, and
      ultimately lead to important conclusions. The continuance of these
      discussions evidently depends on the taste, the temper, and the good sense
      of the speakers. The things to be avoided are chiefly verbal criticisms—praise
      of each other beyond its reasonable limits, and contest for victory. This
      latter is, perhaps, the most important of the three, both for the
      interests of the Society and of truth. With regard to the published
      volumes of their Transactions, it may be remarked, that if members were in
      the habit of communicating their papers to the Society in a more finished
      state, it would be attended with several advantages; amongst others, with
      that of lightening the heavy duties of the officers, which are perhaps
      more laborious in this Society than in most others. To court publicity in
      their accounts and proceedings, and to endeavour to represent all the
      feelings of the Society in the Council, and to avoid permanent Presidents,
      is a recommendation not peculiarly addressed to this Society, but would
      contribute to the well-being of all.
    

      Of the Astronomical Society, which, from the nature of its pursuits, could
      scarcely admit of the discussions similar to those of the Geological, I
      shall merely observe, that I know of no secret which has caused its great
      success, unless it be attention to the maxims which have just been stated.
    

      On the Zoological Society, which affords much rational amusement to the
      public, a few hints may at present suffice. The largeness of its income is
      a frightful consideration. It is too tempting as the subject for jobs, and
      it is too fluctuating and uncertain in its amount, not to render
      embarrassment in the affairs of the Society a circumstance likely to
      occur, without the greatest circumspection. It is most probable, from the
      very recent formation of this Institution, that its Officers and Council
      are at present all that its best friends could wish; but it is still right
      to mention, that in such a Society, it is essentially necessary to have
      men of business on the Council, as well as persons possessing extensive
      knowledge of its pursuits. It is more dangerous in such a Society than in
      any other, to pay compliments, by placing gentlemen on the Council who
      have not the qualifications which are requisite; a frequent change in the
      members of the Council is desirable, in order to find out who are the most
      regular attendants, and most qualified to conduct its business. Publicity
      in its accounts and proceedings is, from the magnitude of its funds, more
      essential to the Zoological than to any other society; and it is rather a
      fearful omen, that a check was attempted to be given to such inquiries at
      the last anniversary meeting. If it is to be a scientific body, the
      friends of science should not for an instant tolerate such attempts.
    

      It frequently happens, that gentlemen take an active part in more than one
      scientific society: in that case, it may be useful to derive instruction
      as to their merits, by observing the success of their measures in other
      societies.
    

      The Asiatic Society has, amongst other benefits, caused many valuable
      works to be translated, which could not have otherwise been published.
    

      The Horticultural Society has been ridden almost to death, and is now
      rousing itself; but its constitution seems to have been somewhat impaired.
      There are hopes of its purgation, and ultimate restoration,
      notwithstanding a debt of 19,000L., which the Committee of Inquiry have
      ascertained to exist. This, after all, will not be without its advantage
      to science, if it puts a stop to HOUSE-LISTS, NAMED BY ONE OR TWO PERSONS,—to
      making COMPLIMENTARY councillors,—and to auditing the accounts
      WITHOUT EXAMINING EVERY ITEM, or to omitting even that form altogether.
    

      The Medico-Botanical Society suddenly claimed the attention of the public;
      its pretensions were great—its assurance unbounded. It speedily
      became distinguished, not by its publications or discoveries, but by the
      number of princes it enrolled in its list. It is needless now to expose
      the extent of its short-lived quackery; but the evil deeds of that
      institution will long remain in the impression they have contributed to
      confirm throughout Europe, of the character of our scientific
      establishments. It would be at once a judicious and a dignified course, if
      those lovers of science, who have been so grievously deceived in this
      Society, were to enrol upon the latest page of its history its highest
      claim to public approbation, and by signing its dissolution, offer the
      only atonement in their power to the insulted science of their country. As
      with a singular inversion of principle, the society contrived to render
      EXPULSION* the highest HONOUR it could confer; so it remains for it to
      exemplify, in suicide, the sublimest virtue of which it is capable. [*
      They expelled from amongst them a gentleman, of whom it is but slight
      praise to say, that he is the first and most philosophical botanist of our
      own country, and who is admired abroad as he is respected at home. The
      circumstance which surprised the world was not his exit from, but his
      previous entrance into that Society.]
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>