<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="35">CHAPTER XXXIII.
In the lane every thing was silent, and the darkness was
extreme. Man, woman, and child were gone out to view
the procession. For some time I could scarcely distinguish
a single object; the doors and windows were all closed. I
now chanced to come to an open door; within I saw no[341]
one but an old man, who was busy over some metallic work
at a chafing-dish of fire. I had no room for choice; I
expected every moment to hear the myrmidons of the inquisition
at my heels. I rushed in; I impetuously closed
the door, and bolted it; I then seized the old man by the
collar of his shirt with a determined grasp, and swore vehemently
that I would annihilate him that instant, if he
did not consent to afford me assistance. Though for some
time I had perhaps been feebler than he, the terror that
now drove me on, rendered me comparatively a giant. He
intreated me to permit him to breathe, and promised to do
whatever I should desire. I looked round the apartment,
and saw a rapier hanging against the wall, of which I instantly
proceeded to make myself master. While I was
doing this, my involuntary host, who was extremely terrified
at my procedure, nimbly attempted to slip by me and
rush into the street. With difficulty I caught hold of his
arm, and, pulling him back, put the point of my rapier to
his breast, solemnly assuring him that no consideration on
earth should save him from my fury, if he attempted to
escape a second time. He immediately dropped on his
knees, and with the most piteous accents intreated me to
spare his life. I told him that I was no robber, that I did
not intend him the slightest harm, and that, if he would
implicitly yield to my direction, he might assure himself
he never should have reason to repent his compliance. By
this declaration the terrors of the old man were somewhat
appeased. I took the opportunity of this calm to go to the
street door, which I instantly locked, and put the key in
my bosom.
Nothing but the most fortunate concurrence of circumstances
could have thus forwarded my escape. The rearing
of the horse of the life-guardsman was purely accidental.
The concourse and press of the crowd from all sides could
alone have rendered this circumstance of any magnitude.
The gap which was made by the pushing forwards and resiling
of the horses continued barely long enough for me to
spring through, and closed again in an instant. It is astonishing
that the thought of escape should have thus suddenly
darted into my mind, which, but a moment before,[342]
was in a state of dejection, equally incompatible with activity
and with hope. That in the lane down which I rushed
I should have met no human creature, and that the first
open door I saw should lead to the residence of a decrepid
old man, who appeared to be its single inhabitant, were
occurrences equally extraordinary, yet seem to have been
both indispensable to my safety. One point more concurred
with this fortunate train, and assisted to still the
palpitations of my beating heart: I perceived, by certain
indications in the countenance of my host, that he was by
parentage a Jew. I presently concluded, that he was what
in Spain they denominate a new christian; for that otherwise
he would not have been allowed to reside at large in a
Spanish city. But, upon that supposition, I did not believe
that christianity was very deeply mingled up in him with
the vital principle: the converts of the inquisition are not
conspicuous for their sincerity. Now, then, for the first
time I thought, in the course of twelve years, I had opportunity
to communicate with a man, whose soul was not
enslaved to the blood-thirsty superstition of this devoted
country. All I had seen during the period of my confinement
were hyenas, tigers, and crocodiles—they were not men.
I had no sooner soothed my host into a temper to listen
to my story, than I told him with all imaginable frankness
whence I came, and to what I had been destined. The
mention of sorcery however, and preternatural practices, I
suppressed; for I suspected that persons of all religions
entertained an equal horror against these. I suffered him
to imagine that the allegation against me had been the crime
of heresy: all sects of the christian superstition might be supposed
equally obnoxious or acceptable to a Jew. I emphatically
appealed to the persecutions which had been so long
directed against the religion of his ancestors, and observed
how disgraceful it would be in him to assist the operation
of a principle, the effects of which his fathers had so deeply
deplored, and so perfectly abhorred. I assured him that I
would bring him into no danger, and that all I asked was
the protection of a few hours: I would leave him in the
course of the following day, and he should hear of me no
more. I reminded him, that the danger he had to fear
was in betraying, not in protecting me. The inquisition[343]
looked upon every new christian with an eye of the severest
jealousy; and the mere fact, if known, that I had taken
refuge in his house, would infallibly subject him to the
purgation of a temporary imprisonment in their dungeons.
It would be in vain for him to affirm that he had no choice
in what had occurred; he was without a witness to confirm
his relation, and the assertions of a man born of Jewish
parents never obtained credit in the court of the inquisition.
I added, with solemn asseverations, that the moment I set
foot beyond the territory of Spain, I would remit to him
the sum of six hundred pistoles as an acknowledgment for
his kindness.
During the whole of my discourse, I watched his countenance
with the utmost minuteness. It gradually relaxed
from the terror which had at first appeared in it, to expressions
of compassion and complacence. I saw nothing
that ought to alarm me. When it was his turn to speak,
he earnestly assured me that he took a warm interest in
my story, and would cheerfully perform every thing I required.
He was happy that my favourable stars had led
me to his habitation, and would rejoice, to the latest hour
of his existence, if they rendered him instrumental in preserving
the life of a human being from so deplorable a
catastrophe. While I talked to him, I easily perceived that
the arguments I used, which produced the most sensible
effect upon his features, were those of the dangers arising
to him from betraying me, and the reward of six hundred
pistoles which I promised him in the event of my success.
His motives however were blended together in his mind; and
he had no sooner formed a determination, grounded perhaps
upon the meanest considerations, than he became eloquent
in a panegyric of his own benevolence, by which he was
not, I believe, more anxious to impose upon me, than to
put the change upon himself. I considered all that he said,
his gestures, and the very tones of his voice, with eager
anxiety; the terror of the inquisition penetrated to the
marrow in my bones; and the fate awarded against me by
that court became inexpressibly more horrible to my thoughts,
now that I saw the probability of escaping it. Every thing
that I observed in the Jew was apparently fair, plausible,[344]
and encouraging; but nothing had power to quell the agitations
of my apprehensive soul.
We were still engaged in discussing the topics I have
mentioned, when I was suddenly alarmed by the noise of
some one stirring in the inner apartment. I had looked
into this room, and had perceived nothing but the bed upon
which the old man nightly reposed himself. I sprung up
however at the sound, and, perceiving that the door had a
bolt on the outside, I eagerly fastened it. I then turned
to Mordecai, such previously to his conversion had been
the name of my host: “Wretch,” said I, “did not you
assure me that there was no one but yourself in the house?”
“Oh,” cried Mordecai, “it is my child! it is my child!
she went into the inner apartment, and has fallen asleep on
the bed.” “Beware!” I answered; “the slightest falsehood
more shall instantly be expiated in your blood.” “I
call Abraham to witness,” rejoined the once more terrified
Jew, “it is my child! only my child!” “Tell me,”
cried I, with severity of accent, “how old is this child?”
“Only five years,” said Mordecai: “my dear Leah died
when her babe was no more than a year old; and, though
we had several children, this single one has survived her.”
“Speak to your child; let me hear her voice!” He spoke
to her, and she answered, “Father, I want to come out.”
I was satisfied it was the voice of a little girl. I turned to
the Jew: “Take care,” said I, “how you deceive me
now; is there no other person in that room?” He imprecated
a curse on himself if there were: I opened the
door with caution, and the little girl came forward. As
soon as I saw her, I seized her with a rapid motion, and
retired back to a chair. “Man,” said I, “you have trifled
with me too rashly; you have not considered what I am
escaped from, and what I have to fear; from this moment
this child shall be the pledge of my safety; I will not part
with her an instant as long as I remain in your house; and
with this rapier in my hand I will pierce her to the heart,
the moment I am led to imagine that I am no longer in
safety.” The Jew trembled at my resolution; the emotions
of a father worked in his features, and glistened in his eye.
“At least let me kiss her!” said he. “Be it so!” replied[345]
I: “one embrace, and then, till the dawn of the
coming day, she remains with me.” I released my hold;
the child rushed to her father, and he caught her in his
arms. “My dear Leah,” cried Mordecai, “now a sainted
spirit in the bosom of our father Abraham! I call God to
witness between us, that, if all my caution and vigilance
can prevent it, not a hair of this child shall be injured!
Stranger, you little know by how strong a motive you have
now engaged me to your cause. We poor Jews, hunted
on the face of the earth, the abhorrence and execration of
mankind, have nothing but family affections to support us
under our multiplied disgraces; and family affections are
entwined with our existence, the fondest and best-loved
part of ourselves. The God of Abraham bless you, my
child! Now, sir, speak! what is it you require of me?”
I told the Jew that I must have a suit of clothes conformable
to the appearance of a Spanish cavalier, and certain
medical ingredients that I named to him, together with
his chafing-dish of coals to prepare them; and, that done,
I would then impose on him no further trouble. Having
received his instructions, he immediately set out to procure
what I demanded. He took with him the key of the
house; and, as soon as he was gone, I retired with the
child into the inner apartment, and fastened the door. At
first I applied myself to tranquillise the child, who had
been somewhat alarmed at what she had heard and seen:
this was no very difficult task. She presently left me, to
amuse herself with some playthings that lay scattered in a
corner of the apartment. My heart was now comparatively
at ease; I saw the powerful hold I had on the fidelity of
the Jew, and firmly persuaded myself that I had no treachery
to fear on his part. Thus circumstanced, the exertion
and activity with which I had lately been imbued left
me; and I insensibly sunk into a sort of slumber.
The night was now far advanced, and I was still reclined
insensible upon Mordecai’s bed, when suddenly a jargon of
various sounds seemed from all sides to assail me. My
mind was confused; I heard something, but seemed wholly
unconscious what I was, and where. I wanted to escape
from the disturbance; but it continued, and even increased.[346]
At length I was forced to command my attention; and the
first thing I perceived was a beating at the door of the
chamber. The little girl was come to the bedside, and endeavouring
to shake me. “Sir, sir,” she cried in an eager
accent, “my father wants to come in, and I cannot slip the
bolt of the door.” By slow degrees I began to comprehend
my situation, and to recollect what had happened immediately
before. I felt greatly alarmed; I feared by the disturbance
that Mordecai had not returned alone. I essayed
to speak; my organs refused their office. I endeavoured
to move; my limbs felt palsied, and absolutely lifeless. I
experienced a sinking and sickness of heart that seemed to
be the immediate precursor of death. By listening occasionally
to the discourse which the father and the daughter
began to hold with each other, I became satisfied that Mordecai
was without a companion. I endeavoured to make
the little girl understand that I was incapable of rising from
the bed; and, having at length succeeded, she communicated
the information to her father. With considerable
trouble he loosened the door at its hinges, and entered the
room. I found myself in the extremest degree feeble and
languid; the Jew however assiduously administered to me
of cordials he had in his possession, and by degrees I felt
myself considerably restored.
Now, for the first time, I was at leisure to attend to the
state of my strength and my health. My confinement in the
inquisition, and the treatment I had experienced, had
before rendered me feeble, and almost helpless; but these
appeared to be circumstances scarcely worthy of attention,
in the situation in which I was then placed. The impulse
I felt, in the midst of the confusion in the grand street of
Valladolid, produced in me an energy and power of exertion
which nothing but the actual experience of the fact could
have persuaded me was possible. This energy, once begun,
appeared to have the faculty of prolonging itself; and I did
not relapse into imbecility, till the occasion seemed to be
exhausted which called for my exertion. I examined myself
by a mirror with which Mordecai furnished me: I
found my hair as white as snow, and my face ploughed with
a thousand furrows. I was now fifty-four, an age which,[347]
with moderate exercise and a vigorous constitution, often
appears like the prime of human existence; but whoever
had looked upon me in my present condition, would not
have hesitated to affirm that I had reached the eightieth
year of my age. I examined with dispassionate remark the
state of my intellect: I was persuaded that it had subsided
into childishness. My mind had been as much cribbed and
immured as my body. I was the mere shadow of a man,
of no more power and worth than that which a magic lantern
produces upon a wall. These are thy works, Superstition!—this
the genuine and proper operation of what is
called Christianity! Let the reader judge of what I had
passed through and known within those cursed walls by the
effects; I have already refused, I continue to refuse, to tell
what I suffered, and how those effects were produced.
Enough of compassion, enough of complaint: I will confine
myself, as far as I am able, to simple history.
Being recovered, as far as the cordials and attention of
Mordecai were capable of recovering me, I desired for the
remainder of the night to be alone, except that I was still
resolved to retain the little Jewess as the pledge of my
safety. I was greatly obliged to my host for the punctuality
he had already displayed: he had found considerable difficulty
in procuring the articles of which I stood in need,
owing partly to the lateness of the hour, and partly to the
presence of the king, and the general hurry and confusion
which had been produced by the solemn entry of the inquisition.
His efforts too to recover me from the languor and
lethargy into which I had sunk, had a character of generosity;
and perhaps I ought now to have trusted him without
a hostage. But my heart was too earnestly bent upon
accomplishing its present object, to afford harbour to the
punctilios of delicacy. The same earnestness caused me to
insist upon Mordecai’s repairing the injury which the
hinges of the door had sustained; and I was careful to
satisfy myself that every thing was restored to a state of
perfect security.
I was now once again alone. The little girl, who had
been unusually disturbed, and roused at an unseasonable
hour, sunk into a profound sleep. I heard the noise which[348]
Mordecai made in undressing himself, and composing his
limbs upon a mattrass, which he had dragged for the present
occasion into the front room, and spread before the
hearth. I soon found by the hardness of his breathing that
he also was asleep. I unfolded the papers he had brought
me; they consisted of various medical ingredients I had
directed him to procure; there were also two or three vials,
containing syrups and essences. I had near me a pair of
scales with which to weigh my ingredients; a vessel of
water; the chafing-dish of my host, in which the fire was
nearly extinguished; and a small taper, with some charcoal
to relight the fire, in case of necessity. While I was occupied
in surveying these articles and arranging my materials,
a sort of torpor came suddenly over me, so as to allow me
no time for resistance. I sunk upon the bed. I remained
thus for about half an hour, seemingly without the power of
collecting my thoughts. At length I started, felt alarmed,
and applied my utmost force of mind to rouse my exertions.
While I drove, or attempted to drive, my animal spirits
from limb to limb, and from part to part, as if to enquire
into the general condition of my frame, I became convinced
that I was dying. Let not the reader be surprised at this:
twelve years’ imprisonment, in a narrow and unwholesome
cell, may well account for so sudden a catastrophe. Strange
and paradoxical as it may seem, I believe it will be found in
the experiment that the calm and security which succeed to
great internal injuries are more dangerous than the pangs
and hardships that went before. I was now thoroughly
alarmed: I applied myself, with all vigilance and expedition
to the compounding my materials. The fire was gone
out; the taper was glimmering in the socket: to swallow
the julep when I had prepared it, seemed to be the last
effort of which my organs and muscles were capable. It
was the elixir of immortality, exactly made up according to
the prescription of the stranger.
Whether from the potency of the medicine, or the
effect of imagination, I felt revived the moment I had
swallowed it. I placed myself deliberately in Mordecai’s
bed, and drew over me the bed-clothes. I fell
asleep almost instantly. I believe my first sleep was[349]
perfectly sound and insensible; but in no long time I was
visited with the pleasantest dreams imaginable. Nothing
was distinct; nothing was attended with the consciousness
of my former identity; but every thing was gay, cheerful,
invigorating, and delicious. I wandered amidst verdant
lawns, and flower-enamelled gardens. I was saluted with
the singing of a thousand birds, and the murmuring of a
thousand fountains. Kids, fawns, and lambs frisked and
gamboled before me. At a distance, through an opening
in the trees, I discerned nymphs and their swains dancing
a variety of antic measures. I advanced towards them;
they approached towards me. Fifes, oboes, recorders, and
instruments of a hundred names, commenced a cheerful
and melodious concert. Myself and the dancers now were
met; they placed me in the midst of them. They began a
choral song; the motion of their limbs conformed to their
numbers. I was the theme of the general chaunt; they
ascribed to me the beauty of Apollo, the strength of
Hercules, the invention of Mercury, and the youth of
Bacchus.
My sleep was not long; in a few hours I awakened.
With difficulty I recognised the objects about me, and
recollected where I had been. It seemed to me that my
heart had never beat so vigorously, nor my spirits flowed
so gay. I was all elasticity and life; I could scarcely hold
myself quiet; I felt impelled to bound and leap like a kid
upon the mountains. I perceived that my little Jewess
was still asleep; she had been unusually fatigued the night
before. I know not whether Mordecai’s hour of rising
were come; if it were, he was careful not to disturb
his guest. I put on the garments he had prepared;
I gazed upon the mirror he had left in my apartment.
I can recollect no sensation in the course of my life, so
unexpected and surprising as what I felt at that moment.
The evening before, I had seen my hair white, and
my face ploughed with furrows; I looked fourscore. What
I beheld now was totally different, yet altogether familiar;
it was myself, myself as I had appeared on the day of my
marriage with Marguerite de Damville; the eyes, the
mouth, the hair, the complexion, every circumstance, point
by point, the same. I leaped a gulf of thirty-two years. I[350]
waked from a dream, troublesome and distressful beyond
all description; but it vanished, like the shades of night
upon the burst of a glorious morning in July, and left not
a trace behind. I knew not how to take away my eyes
from the mirror before me.
I soon began to consider that, if it were astonishing to
me that, through all the regions of my countenance, I
could discover no trace of what I had been the night before,
it would be still more astonishing to my host. This sort
of sensation I had not the smallest ambition to produce: one
of the advantages of the metamorphosis I had sustained,
consisted in its tendency, in the eyes of all that saw me, to
cut off every species of connection between my present and
my former self. It fortunately happened that the room in
which I slept, being constructed upon the model of many
others in Spain, had a stair at the further end, with a trap-door
in the ceiling, for the purpose of enabling the inhabitant
to ascend on the roof in the cool of the day. The
roofs were flat, and so constructed, that there was little difficulty
in passing along them from house to house, from one
end of the street to the other. I availed myself of the
opportunity, and took leave of the residence of my land
host in a way perfectly unceremonious, determined however
speedily to transmit to him the reward I had promised. It
may easily be believed that Mordecai was not less rejoiced
at the absence of a guest whom the vigilance of the inquisition
rendered an uncommonly dangerous one, than I was
to quit his habitation. I closed the trap after me, and
clambered from roof to roof to a considerable distance. At
length I encountered the occasion of an open window, and
fortunately descended, unseen by any human being, into
the street. Having with difficulty succeeded, on this occasion
of public solemnity, in engaging an apartment in one
of the hotels of Valladolid, I sent into it, as soon as I was
able, a chest, containing every necessary of apparel, and
particularly a suit of clothes. I then changed my dress,
and threw the clothes which Mordecai had provided into
the chest I had purchased. As long as they continued
safely locked up, and the key in my possession, no faculty
possessed by any human creature could detect my identity,
and expose me afresh to my former jailors. The only[351]
peril under which I had before laboured, was from Mordecai,
who, if he had seen me in the garments he had procured,
might have recognised them; and, though a peril
from this source came barely within the limits of possibility,
it was easily avoided, and I therefore chose to avoid it.
I passed the whole of this day in a species of enjoyment,
which, as it has no parallel in the ordinary transactions of
mankind, so are there no terms in the received languages of
the world that are adequate to the description of it. It has
often been a subject of melancholy and complaint among
mortals, that, while the whole vegetable system contains in
it a principle of perpetual renewal, man alone,—the ornament
and lord of the universe, man,—knows no return to
youth. When the sun declines in the west, the flowers
droop, and fold up their frail and delicate leaves; but soon
the eyelids of the morn are again opened, and again they
rejoice in his invigorating beams. Upon the approach of
winter, the beech, the ash, and the monarch-oak, scatter
their withered foliage over the plains; but spring reappears,
and nakedness is no longer their reproach, and they clothe
themselves anew in their leafy honours. With what a
melancholy sensation does the old man survey his decaying
limbs! To me, he cries, there is no second morning, and
no returning spring. My head, pressed down with years,
shall never again erect itself in conscious manhood. These
hoary locks shall no more be adorned with the auburn of
glossy youth. My weather-beaten trunk shall at no time
clothe itself with a smoother rind. A recruited marrow
shall never fill these bones, nor a more vigorous sap circulate
through my unstrung limbs. I recollect what I was
in the prime of manhood, with vain regrets; the memory
answers no other end than to torment and upbraid me.
The useless wish of the old man, the object of his hopeless
sigh, was mine. Common and every-day blessings have
little value in the eye of their possessor. The young man
squanders the endowments of youth, and knows not to prize
them. If the young man had once been old, if the old man
could again be young, then, and then only, they would
justly estimate their wealth. The springy limb, the bounding
frame, the vigour that sets fatigue at defiance, and[352]
revels in pleasures unexhausted, would then by the near
and conscious comparison, of feebleness and lassitude, the
drooping limb, the aching head, and the frame decayed in
all its senses, be well understood. Such was my situation.
Yesterday I was fourscore; to-day I was twenty. Yesterday
I was a prisoner, crippled in every articulation; to-day
I was a citizen of the world, capable of all its delights.
To-morrow I was destined to have been dragged to the
stake with ignominy, and to suffer intolerable anguish amidst
the shouts and huzzas of an unfeeling populace; to-morrow
I was at liberty to employ as I pleased, to choose the theatre
upon which it should be spent, and the gratifications that
should be crowded into it. What was most material, my
mind was grown young with my body. Weary of eternal
struggle, I had lately resigned the contest, and sunk under
the ill-fortune that relentlessly pursued me. Now I felt
within me a superfluity of vigour; I panted for something
to contend with, and something to conquer. My senses unfolded
themselves to all the curiosity of remark; my thoughts
seemed capable of industry unwearied, and investigation the
most constant and invincible. Ambition revived in my
bosom; I longed for new engagements and new relations;
I desired to perform something, that I might myself regard
with complacence, and that I might see the world start at
and applaud.
I determined, for reasons that I shall presently have occasion
to unfold, that my first visit should be to my daughters
at my paternal estate of St. Leon. I proposed to spend
two or three days in preparations for this journey. By
mere accident, by a most censurable heedlessness, I became
in some degree a spectator of the auto da fé in which I
was destined to have been a victim. Unawares I had become
entangled in the crowd, and could with difficulty
escape, or even prevent my being carried nearer the centre
of the scene. I saw the galleries and accommodations that
had been erected for the spectators: I saw the windows and
roofs of the houses crowded with beholders. The shrieks
of the sufferers I could not hear; they were drowned in the
infernal exultations of the multitude. But what was worst
of all, I discerned some of the condemned, fixed as they[353]
were upon small boards, near the top of stakes about four
yards high, and therefore greatly above the heads of the
assembly, while the flames, abundantly fed with faggots and
dry fuel, climbed aloft, and seemed eager to embrace their
victims. As I have already said, there were thirty of these
death-devoted frames; and, if my eye did not count them
all, my fancy well supplied what sense was unable to discover.
The impression I felt at that moment was horrible
beyond all conception. I exerted my new-found strength,
and pushed out of the press with irresistible vigour. If at
that instant I could have felt exultation, even in the consciousness
of my own safety, I should regard myself as the
most execrable of monsters.
</div></body></text></TEI>