<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="17">CHAPTER XVII.
REPRODUCTIVE EFFECTS OF RIVERS.
Lake deltas—Growth of the delta of the Upper Rhine in the Lake of Geneva—Computation
of the age of deltas—Recent deposits in Lake Superior—Deltas
of inland seas—Course of the Po—Artificial embankments of the Po and Adige—Delta
of the Po, and other rivers entering the Adriatic—Rapid conversion of
that gulf into land—Mineral characters of the new deposits—Marine delta of
the Rhone—Various proofs of its increase—Stony nature of its deposits—Coast
of Asia Minor—Delta of the Nile.
DELTAS IN LAKES.
I have already spoken in the 14th chapter of the action of running
water, and of the denuding power of rivers, but we can only form a
just conception of the excavating and removing force exerted by such
bodies of water, when we have the advantage of examining the reproductive
effects of the same agents: in other words, of beholding in a
palpable form the aggregate amount of matter, which they have thrown
down at certain points in their alluvial plains, or in the basins of lakes
and seas. Yet it will appear, when we consider the action of currents,
that the growth of deltas affords a very inadequate standard by which
to measure the entire carrying power of running water, since a considerable
portion of fluviatile sediment is swept far out to sea.
Deltas may be divided into, first, those which are formed in lakes;
secondly, those in island seas, where the tides are almost imperceptible;
and, thirdly, those on the borders of the ocean. The most characteristic
distinction between the lacustrine and marine deltas consists in
the nature of the organic remains which become imbedded in their
deposits; for, in the case of a lake, it is obvious that these must
consist exclusively of such genera of animals as inhabit the land or
the waters of a river or a lake; whereas, in the other case, there will
be an admixture, and most frequently a predominance, of animals which
inhabit salt water. In regard, however, to the distribution of inorganic
252
matter, the deposits of lakes and seas are formed under very analogous
circumstances.
Lake of Geneva.—Lakes exemplify the first reproductive operations
in which rivers are engaged when they convey the detritus of rocks
and the ingredients of mineral springs from mountainous regions. The
accession of new land at the mouth of the Rhone, at the upper end of
the Lake of Geneva, or the Leman Lake, presents us with an example
of a considerable thickness of strata which have accumulated since the
historical era. This sheet of water is about thirty-seven miles long, and
its breadth is from two to eight miles. The shape of the bottom is
very irregular, the depth having been found by late measurements to
vary from 20 to 160 fathoms.335 The Rhone, where it enters at the upper
end, is turbid and discolored; but its waters, where it issues at the
town of Geneva, are beautifully clear and transparent. An ancient
town, called Port Vallais (Portus Valesiæ of the Romans), once situated
at the water's edge, at the upper end, is now more than a mile and a
half inland—this intervening alluvial tract having been acquired in
about eight centuries. The remainder of the delta consists of a flat
alluvial plain, about five or six miles in length, composed of sand and
mud, a little raised above the level of the river, and full of marshes.
Sir Henry De la Beche found, after numerous soundings in all parts
of the lake, that there was a pretty uniform depth of from 120 to 160
fathoms throughout the central region, and on approaching the delta,
the shallowing of the bottom began to be very sensible at a distance
of about a mile and three quarters from the mouth of the Rhone;
for a line drawn from St. Gingoulph to Vevey gives a mean depth
of somewhat less than 600 feet, and from that part of the Rhone,
the fluviatile mud is always found along the bottom.336 We may state,
therefore, that the new strata annually produced are thrown down
upon a slope about two miles in length; so that, notwithstanding the
great depth of the lake, the new deposits are inclined at so slight an
angle, that the dip of the beds would be termed, in ordinary geological
language, horizontal.
The strata probably consist of alternations of finer and coarser particles;
for, during the hotter months from April to August, when the
snows melt, the volume and velocity of the river are greatest, and large
quantities of sand, mud, vegetable matter, and drift-wood are introduced;
but during the rest of the year, the influx is comparatively
feeble, so much so, that the whole lake, according to Saussure, stands
six feet lower. If, then, we could obtain a section of the accumulation
formed in the last eight centuries, we should see a great series of
strata, probably from 600 to 900 feet thick (the supposed original
depth of the head of the lake), and nearly two miles in length, inclined
at a very slight angle. In the mean time, a great number of
253
smaller deltas are growing around the borders of the lake, at the
mouths of rapid torrents, which pour in large masses of sand and pebbles.
The body of water in these torrents is too small to enable them
to spread out the transported matter over so extensive an area as the
Rhone does. Thus, for example, there is a depth of eighty fathoms
within half a mile of the shore, immediately opposite the great torrent
which enters east of Ripaille, so that the dip of the strata in that minor
delta must be about four times as great as those deposited by the main
river at the upper extremity of the lake.337
Chronological computations of the age of deltas.—The capacity of this
basin being now ascertained, it would be an interesting subject of inquiry,
to determine in what number of years the Leman Lake will be
converted into dry land. It would not be very difficult to obtain the
elements for such a calculation, so as to approximate at least to the
quantity of time required for the accomplishment of the result. The
number of cubic feet of water annually discharged by the river into the
lake being estimated, experiments might be made in the winter and
summer months, to determine the proportion of matter held in suspension
or in chemical solution by the Rhone. It would be also necessary
to allow for the heavier matter drifted along at the bottom, which
might be estimated on hydrostatical principles, when the average size of
the gravel and the volume and velocity of the stream at different seasons
were known. Supposing all these observations to have been made, it
would be more easy to calculate the future than the former progress of
the delta, because it would be a laborious task to ascertain, with any
degree of precision, the original depth and extent of that part of the
lake which is already filled up. Even if this information were actually
obtained by borings, it would only enable us to approximate within a
certain number of centuries to the time when the Rhone began to form
its present delta; but this would not give us the date of the origin of
the Leman Lake in its present form, because the river may have flowed
into it for thousands of years, without importing any sediment whatever.
Such would have been the case, if the waters had first passed through a
chain of upper lakes; and that this was actually the fact, seems indicated
by the course of the Rhone between Martigny and the Lake of Geneva,
and, still more decidedly, by the channels of many of its principal feeders.
If we ascend, for example, the valley through which the Dranse flows,
we find that it consists of a succession of basins, one above the other, in
each of which there is a wide expanse of flat alluvial lands, separated
from the next basin by a rocky gorge, once perhaps the barrier of a lake.
The river seems to have filled these lakes, one after the other, and to
have partially cut through the barriers, some of which it is still gradually
eroding to a greater depth. Before, therefore, we can pretend even
to hazard a conjecture as to the era at which the principal delta of Lake
Leman or any other delta commenced, we must be thoroughly acquainted
254
with the geographical features and geological history of the whole
system of higher valleys which communicate with the main stream, and
all the changes which they have undergone since the last series of convulsions
which agitated and altered the face of the country.
Lake Superior.—Lake Superior is the largest body of freshwater in
the world, being above 1700 geographical miles in circumference when
we follow the sinuosities of its coasts, and its length, on a curved line
drawn through its centre, being more than 400, and its extreme breadth
above 150 geographical miles. Its surface is nearly as large as the
whole of England. Its average depth varies from 80 to 150 fathoms;
but, according to Captain Bayfield, there is reason to think that its
greatest depth would not be overrated at 200 fathoms, so that its bottom
is, in some parts, nearly 600 feet below the level of the Atlantic, its surface
being about as much above it. There are appearances in different
parts of this, as of the other Canadian lakes, leading us to infer that its
waters formerly occupied a higher level than they reach at present; for
at a considerable distance from the present shores, parallel lines of rolled
stones and shells are seen rising one above the other, like the seats of
an amphitheatre. These ancient lines of shingle are exactly similar to
the present beaches in most bays, and they often attain an elevation of
40 or 50 feet above the present level. As the heaviest gales of wind
do not raise the waters more than three or four feet, the elevated beaches
have by some been referred to the subsidence of the lake at former periods,
in consequence of the wearing down of its barrier; by others to
the upraising of the shores by earthquakes, like those which have produced
similar phenomena on the coast of Chili.
The streams which discharge their waters into Lake Superior are several
hundred in number, without reckoning those of smaller size; and
the quantity of water supplied by them is many times greater than that
discharged at the Falls of St. Mary, the only outlet. The evaporation,
therefore, is very great, and such as might be expected from so vast an
extent of surface. On the northern side, which is encircled by primary
mountains, the rivers sweep in many large boulders with smaller gravel
and sand, chiefly composed of granitic and trap rocks. There are also
currents in the lake in various directions, caused by the continued prevalence
of strong winds, and to their influence we may attribute the diffusion
of finer mud far and wide over great areas; for by numerous
soundings made during Captain Bayfield's survey, it was ascertained
that the bottom consists generally of a very adhesive clay, containing
shells of the species at present existing in the lake. When exposed to
the air, this clay immediately becomes indurated in so great a degree, as
to require a smart blow to break it. It effervesces slightly with diluted
nitric acid, and is of different colors in different parts of the lake; in one
district blue, in another red, and in a third white, hardening into a substance
resembling pipeclay.338 From these statements, the geologist will
255
not fail to remark how closely these recent lacustrine formations in
America resemble the tertiary argillaceous and calcareous marls of lacustrine
origin in Central France. In both cases many of the genera of
shells most abundant, as Limnea and Planorbis, are the same; and in
regard to other classes of organic remains there must be the closest
analogy, as I shall endeavor more fully to explain when speaking of the
imbedding of plants and animals in recent deposits.
DELTAS OF INLAND SEAS.
Having thus briefly considered some of the lacustrine deltas now in
progress, we may next turn our attention to those of inland seas.
Course of the Po.—The Po affords an instructive example of the
manner in which a great river bears down to the sea the matter poured
into it by a multitude of tributaries descending from lofty chains of
mountains. The changes gradually effected in the great plain of Northern
Italy, since the time of the Roman republic, are considerable. Extensive
lakes and marshes have been gradually filled up, as those near
Placentia, Parma, and Cremona, and many have been drained naturally
by the deepening of the beds of rivers. Deserted river-courses are not
unfrequent, as that of the Serio Morto, which formerly fell into the
Adda, in Lombardy. The Po also itself has often deviated from its
course, having after the year 1390 deserted part of the territory of
Cremona, and invaded that of Parma; its old channel being still recognizable,
and bearing the name of Po Morto. There is also an old channel
of the Po in the territory of Parma, called Po Vecchio, which was
abandoned in the twelfth century, when a great number of towns were
destroyed.
Artificial embankments of Italian rivers.—To check these and similar
aberrations, a general system of embankment has been adopted; and
the Po, Adige, and almost all their tributaries, are now confined between
high artificial banks. The increased velocity acquired by streams thus
closed in, enables them to convey a much larger portion of foreign matter
to the sea; and, consequently, the deltas of the Po and Adige have
gained far more rapidly on the Adriatic since the practice of embankment
became almost universal. But, although more sediment is borne
to the sea, part of the sand and mud, which in the natural state of
things would be spread out by annual inundations over the plain, now
subsides in the bottom of the river-channels; and their capacity being
thereby diminished, it is necessary, in order to prevent inundations in
the following spring, to extract matter from the bed, and to add it to
the banks of the river. Hence it happens that these streams now traverse
the plain on the top of high mounds, like the waters of aqueducts,
and at Ferrara the surface of the Po has become more elevated than
the roofs of the houses.339 The magnitude of these barriers is a subject
256
of increasing expense and anxiety, it having been sometimes found necessary
to give an additional height of nearly one foot to the banks of the
Adige and Po in a single season.
The practice of embankment was adopted on some of the Italian
rivers as early as the thirteenth century; and Dante, writing in the
beginning of the fourteenth, describes, in the seventh circle of hell, a
rivulet of tears separated from a burning sandy desert by embankments
"like those which, between Ghent and Bruges, were raised against the
ocean, or those which the Paduans had erected along the Brenta to
defend their villas on the melting of the Alpine snows."


Quale i Fiamminghi tra Guzzante e Bruggia,
Temendo il fiotto che in ver lor s'avventa,
Fanno lo schermo, perchè il mar si fuggia,
E quale i Padovan lungo la Brenta,
Per difender lor ville e lor castelli,
Anzi che Chiarentana il caldo senta.—
Inferno, Canto xv.


In the Adriatic, from the northern part of the Gulf of Trieste, where
the Isonzo enters, down to the south of Ravenna, there is an uninterrupted
series of recent accessions of land, more than 100 miles in length,
which, within the last 2000 years, have increased from two to twenty
miles in breadth. A line of sand-bars of great length has been formed
nearly all along the western coast of this gulf, inside of which are
lagunes, such as those of Venice, and the large lagune of Comacchio,
20 miles in diameter. Newly deposited mud brought down by the
streams is continually lessening the depth of the lagunes, and converting
part of them into meadows.340 The Isonzo, Tagliamento, Piave, Brenta,
Adige, and Po, besides many other inferior rivers, contribute to this
advance of the coast-line and to the shallowing of the lagunes and the
gulf.
Delta of the Po.—The Po and the Adige may now be considered as
entering by one common delta, for two branches of the Adige are connected
with arms of the Po, and thus the principal delta has been
pushed out beyond those bars which separate the lagunes from the sea.
The rate of the advance of this new land has been accelerated, as before
stated, since the system of embanking the rivers became general, especially
at that point where the Po and Adige enter. The waters are no
longer permitted to spread themselves far and wide over the plains, and
to leave behind them the larger portion of their sediment. Mountain
torrents also have become more turbid since the clearing away of forests,
which once clothed the southern flanks of the Alps. It is calculated
that the mean rate of advance of the delta of the Po on the
Adriatic between the years 1200 and 1600 was 25 yards or metres a
year, whereas the mean annual gain from 1600 to 1804 was 70 metres.341
257Adria was a seaport in the time of Augustus, and had, in ancient
times, given its name to the gulf; it is now about twenty Italian miles
inland. Ravenna was also a seaport, and is now about four miles from
the main sea. Yet even before the practice of embankment was introduced,
the alluvium of the Po advanced with rapidity on the Adriatic;
for Spina, a very ancient city, originally built in the district of Ravenna,
at the mouth of a great arm of the Po, was, so early as the commencement
of our era, eleven miles distant from the sea.342
But although so many rivers are rapidly converting the Adriatic into
land, it appears, by the observations of M. Morlot, that since the time
of the Romans, there has been a general subsidence of the coast and
bed of this sea in the same region to the amount of five feet, so that
the advance of the new-made land has not been so fast as it would have
been had the level of the coast remained unaltered. The signs of a
much greater depression anterior to the historical period have also been
brought to light by an Artesian well, bored in 1847, to the depth of
more than 400 feet, which still failed to penetrate through the modern
fluviatile deposit. The auger passed chiefly through beds of sand and
clay, but at four several depths, one of them very near the bottom of
the excavation, it pierced beds of turf, or accumulations of vegetable
matter, precisely similar to those now formed superficially on the extreme
borders of the Adriatic. Hence we learn that a considerable
area of what was once land has sunk down 400 feet in the course of
ages.343
The greatest depth of the Adriatic, between Dalmatia and the mouths
of the Po, is twenty-two fathoms; but a large part of the Gulf of Trieste
and the Adriatic, opposite Venice, is less than twelve fathoms deep.
Farther to the south, where it is less affected by the influx of great
rivers, the gulf deepens considerably. Donati, after dredging the bottom,
discovered the new deposits to consist partly of mud and partly of rock,
the rock being formed of calcareous matter, incrusting shells. He also
ascertained, that particular species of testacea were grouped together in
certain places, and were becoming slowly incorporated with the mud or
calcareous precipitates.344 Olivi, also, found some deposits of sand, and
others of mud, extending half way across the gulf; and he states that
their distribution along the bottom was evidently determined by the
prevailing current.345 It is probable, therefore, that the finer sediment
of all the rivers at the head of the Adriatic may be intermingled by the
influence of the current; and all the central parts of the gulf may be
considered as slowly filling up with horizontal deposits, similar to those
of the Subapennine hills, and containing many of the same species of
shells. The Po merely introduces at present fine sand and mud, for it
carries no pebbles farther than the spot where it joins the Trebia, west
of Piacenza. Near the northern borders of the basin, the Isonzo,
258
Tagliamento, and many other streams, are forming immense beds of
sand and some conglomerate; for here some high mountains of Alpine
limestone approach within a few miles of the sea.
In the time of the Romans, the hot-baths of Monfalcone were on one
of several islands of Alpine limestone, between which and the mainland,
on the north, was a channel of the sea, about a mile broad. This channel
is now converted into a grassy plain, which surrounds the islands on
all sides. Among the numerous changes on this coast, we find that the
present channel of the Isonzo is several miles to the west of its ancient
bed, in part of which, at Ronchi, the old Roman bridge which crossed
the Via Appia was lately found buried in fluviatile silt.
Marine delta of the Rhone.—The lacustrine delta of the Rhone in
Switzerland has already been considered (p. 251), its contemporaneous
marine delta may now be described. Scarcely has the river passed out
of the Lake of Geneva before its pure waters are again filled with sand
and sediment by the impetuous Arve, descending from the highest Alps,
and bearing along in its current the granitic detritus annually brought
down by the glaciers of Mont Blanc. The Rhone afterwards receives
vast contributions of transported matter from the Alps of Dauphiny,
and the primary and volcanic mountains of Central France; and when
at length it enters the Mediterranean, it discolors the blue waters of
that sea with a whitish sediment, for the distance of between six and
seven miles, throughout which space the current of fresh water is perceptible.
Strabo's description of the delta is so inapplicable to its present configuration,
as to attest a complete alteration in the physical features of
the country since the Augustan age. It appears, however, that the
head of the delta, or the point at which it begins to ramify, has remained
unaltered since the time of Pliny, for he states that the Rhone
divided itself at Arles into two arms. This is the case at present; one
of the branches, the western, being now called Le Petit Rhône, which
is again subdivided before entering the Mediterranean. The advance of
the base of the delta, in the last eighteen centuries, is demonstrated by
many curious antiquarian monuments. The most striking of these is the
great and unnatural détour of the old Roman road from Ugernum to
Beziers (Bœterræ) which went round by Nismes (Nemausus). It is
clear that, when this was first constructed, it was impossible to pass in
a direct line, as now, across the delta, and that either the sea or marshes
intervened in a tract now consisting of terra firma.346 Astruc also
remarks, that all the places on low lands, lying to the north of the old
Roman road between Nismes and Beziers, have names of Celtic origin,
evidently given to them by the first inhabitants of the country; whereas,
the places lying south of that road, towards the sea, have names of
Latin derivation, and were clearly founded after the Roman language
had been introduced.
259
Another proof, also, of the great extent of land which has come into
existence since the Romans conquered and colonized Gaul, is derived
from the fact, that the Roman writers never mention the thermal
waters of Balaruc in the delta, although they were well acquainted with
those of Aix, and others still more distant, and attached great importance
to them, as they invariably did to all hot springs. The waters of
Balaruc, therefore, must have formerly issued under the sea—a common
phenomenon on the borders of the Mediterranean; and on the
advance of the delta they continued to flow out through the new
deposits.
Among the more direct proofs of the increase of land, we find that
Mese, described under the appellation of Mesua Collis by Pomponius
Mela,347 and stated by him to be nearly an island, is now far inland.
Notre Dame des Ports, also, was a harbor in 898, but is now a league
from the shore. Psalmodi was an island in 815, and is now two
leagues from the sea. Several old lines of towers and sea-marks occur
at different distances from the present coast, all indicating the successive
retreat of the sea, for each line has in its turn become useless to
mariners; which may well be conceived, when we state that the Tower
of Tignaux, erected on the shore so late as the year 1737, is already a
mile remote from it.348
By the confluence of the Rhone and the currents of the Mediterranean,
driven by winds from the south, sand-bars are often formed across
the mouths of the river; by these means considerable spaces become
divided off from the sea, and subsequently from the river also, when it
shifts its channels of efflux. As some of these lagoons are subject to
the occasional ingress of the river when flooded, and of the sea during
storms, they are alternately salt and fresh. Others, after being filled
with salt water, are often lowered by evaporation till they become
more salt than the sea; and it has happened, occasionally, that a considerable
precipitate of muriate of soda has taken place in these natural
salterns. During the latter part of Napoleon's career, when the excise
laws were enforced with extreme rigor, the police was employed to
prevent such salt from being used. The fluviatile and marine shells
inclosed in these small lakes often live together in brackish water; but
the uncongenial nature of the fluid usually produces a dwarfish size,
and sometimes gives rise to strange varieties in form and color.
Captain Smyth in his survey of the coast of the Mediterranean,
found the sea opposite the mouth of the Rhone, to deepen gradually
from four to forty fathoms, within a distance of six or seven miles,
over which the discolored fresh water extends; so that the inclination
of the new deposits must be too slight to be appreciable in such an
extent of section as a geologist usually obtains in examining ancient
formations. When the wind blew from the southwest, the ships employed
260
in the survey were obliged to quit their moorings; and when
they returned, the new sand-banks in the delta were found covered
over with a great abundance of marine shells. By this means, we learn
how occasional beds of drifted marine shells may become interstratified
with freshwater strata at a river's mouth.
Stony nature of its deposits.—That a great proportion, at least,
of the new deposit in the delta of the Rhone consists of rock, and not
of loose incoherent matter, is perfectly ascertained. In the Museum at
Montpelier is a cannon taken up from the sea near the mouth of the
river, imbedded in a crystalline calcareous rock. Large masses, also,
are continually taken up of an arenaceous rock, cemented by calcareous
matter, including multitudes of broken shells of recent species. The
observations lately made on this subject corroborate the former statement
of Marsilli, that the earthy deposits of the coast of Languedoc form
a stony substance, for which reason he ascribes a certain bituminous,
saline, and glutinous nature to the substances brought down with sand
by the Rhone.349 If the number of mineral springs charged with carbonate
of lime which fall into the Rhone and its feeders in different
parts of France be considered, we shall feel no surprise at the lapidification
of the newly deposited sediment in this delta. It should be
remembered, that the fresh water introduced by rivers being lighter
than the water of the sea, floats over the latter, and remains upon the
surface for a considerable distance. Consequently it is exposed to
as much evaporation as the waters of a lake; and the area over which
the river-water is spread, at the junction of great rivers and the sea,
may well be compared, in point of extent, to that of considerable lakes.
Now, it is well known, that so great is the quantity of water carried
off by evaporation in some lakes, that it is nearly equal to the water
flowing in; and in some inland seas, as the Caspian, it is quite equal.
We may, therefore, well suppose that, in cases where a strong current
does not interfere, the greater portion not only of the matter held mechanically
in suspension, but of that also which is in chemical solution, may
be precipitated at no great distance from the shore. When these finer
ingredients are extremely small in quantity, they may only suffice to
supply crustaceous animals, corals, and marine plants, with the earthy
particles necessary for their secretions; but whenever it is in excess
(as generally happens if the basin of a river lie partly in a district of
active or extinct volcanoes), then will solid deposits be formed, and the
shells will at once be included in a rocky mass.
Coast of Asia Minor.—Examples of the advance of the land upon
the sea are afforded by the southern coast of Asia Minor. Admiral
Sir F. Beaufort has pointed out in his survey the great alterations
effected since the time of Strabo, where havens are filled up, islands
joined to the mainland, and where the whole continent has increased
many miles in extent. Strabo himself, on comparing the outline of the
coast in his time with its ancient state, was convinced, like our countryman,
261
that it had gained very considerably upon the sea. The new-formed
strata of Asia Minor consist of stone, not of loose incoherent
materials. Almost all the streamlets and rivers, like many of those in
Tuscany and the south of Italy, hold abundance of carbonate of lime
in solution, and precipitate travertin, or sometimes bind together the
sand and gravel into solid sandstones and conglomerates; every delta
and sand-bar thus acquires solidity, which often prevents streams from
forcing their way through them, so that their mouths are constantly
changing their position.350
Delta of the Nile.—That Egypt was "the gift of the Nile," was the
opinion of her priests before the time of Herodotus; and Rennell observes,
that the "configuration and composition of the low lands leave
no room for doubt that the sea once washed the base of the rocks on
which the pyramids of Memphis stand, the present base of which is
washed by the inundation of the Nile, at an elevation of 70 or 80 feet
above the Mediterranean. But when we attempt to carry back our ideas
to the remote period when the foundation of the delta was first laid, we
are lost in the contemplation of so vast an interval of time."351 Herodotus
observes, "that the country round Memphis seemed formerly to
have been an arm of the sea gradually filled by the Nile, in the same
manner as the Meander, Achelous, and other streams, had formed deltas.
Egypt, therefore, he says, like the Red Sea, was once a long narrow bay,
and both gulfs were separated by a small neck of land. If the Nile,
he adds, should by any means have an issue into the Arabian Gulf, it
might choke it up with earth in 20,000 or even, perhaps, in 10,000
years; and why may not the Nile have filled a still greater gulf with
mud in the space of time which has passed before our age?"352
The distance between Memphis and the most prominent part of the
delta in a straight line north and south, is about 100 geographical miles;
the length of the base of the delta is more than 200 miles if we follow
the coast between the ancient extreme eastern and western arms; but as
these are now blocked up, that part only of Lower Egypt which intervenes
between the Rosetta and Damietta branches, is usually called the
delta, the coast line of which is about 90 miles in length. The bed of
the river itself, says Sir J. G. Wilkinson, undergoes a gradual increase
of elevation varying in different places, and always lessening in proportion
as the river approaches the sea. "This increase of elevation in
perpendicular height is much smaller in Lower than in Upper Egypt,
and in the delta it diminishes still more; so that, according to an approximate
calculation, the land about Elephantine, or the first cataract,
lat. 24° 5', has been raised nine feet in 1700 years; at Thebes, lat. 25°
43', about seven feet; and at Heliopolis and Cairo, lat. 30°, about five
feet ten inches. At Rosetta and the mouths of the Nile, lat. 31° 30',
the diminution in the perpendicular thickness of the deposit is lessened
262
in a much greater decreasing ratio than in the straitened valley of Central
and Upper Egypt, owing to the great extent, east and west, over
which the inundation spreads."353
For this reason the alluvial deposit does not cause the delta to protrude
rapidly into the sea, although some ancient cities are now a mile or more
inland, and the mouths of the Nile, mentioned by the earlier geographers,
have been many of them silted up, and the outline of the coast entirely
changed.
The bed of the Nile always keeps pace with the general elevation of
the soil, and the banks of this river, like those of the Mississippi and its
tributaries (see p. 265, are much higher than the flat land at a distance,
so that they are seldom covered during the highest inundations. In
consequence of the gradual rise of the river's bed, the annual flood is
constantly spreading over a wider area, and the alluvial soil encroaches
on the desert, covering, to the depth of six or seven feet, the base of
statues and temples which the waters never reached 3000 years ago.
Although the sands of the Libyan deserts have in some places been
drifted into the valley of the Nile, yet these aggressions, says Wilkinson,
are far more than counterbalanced by the fertilizing effect of the water
which now reaches farther inland towards the desert, so that the number
of square miles of arable soil is greater at present than at any previous
period.
Mud of the Nile.—On comparing the different analyses which have
been published of this mud, it will be found that it contains a large
quantity of argillaceous matter, with much peroxide of iron, some carbonate
of lime, and a small proportion of carbonate of magnesia. The
latest and most careful analysis by M. Lassaigne shows a singularly close
resemblance in the proportions of the ingredients of silica, alumina, iron,
carbon, lime, and magnesia, and those observed in ordinary mica;354 but
a much larger quantity of calcareous matter is sometimes present.
In many places, as at Cairo, where artificial excavations have been
made, or where the river has undermined its banks, the mud is seen to
be thinly stratified, the upper part of each annual layer consisting of
earth of a lighter color than the lower, and the whole separating easily
from the deposit of the succeeding year. These annual layers are variable
in thickness; but, according to the calculations of Girard and Wilkinson,
the mean annual thickness of a layer at Cairo cannot exceed that
of a sheet of thin pasteboard, and a stratum of two or three feet must
represent the accumulation of a thousand years.
The depth of the Mediterranean is about twelve fathoms at a small
distance from the shore of the delta; it afterwards increases gradually to
50, and then suddenly descends to 380 fathoms, which is, perhaps, the
original depth of the sea where it has not been rendered shallower by
fluviatile matter. We learn from Lieut. Newbold that nothing but the
263
finest and lightest ingredients reach the Mediterranean, where he has
observed the sea discolored by them to the distance of 40 miles from
the shore.355 The small progress of the delta in the last 2000 years affords,
perhaps, no measure for estimating its rate of growth when it was an
inland bay, and had not yet protruded itself beyond the coast-line of
the Mediterranean. A powerful current now sweeps along the shores
of Africa, from the Straits of Gibraltar to the prominent convexity of
Egypt, the western side of which is continually the prey of the waves;
so that not only are fresh accessions of land checked, but ancient parts
of the delta are carried away. By this cause, Canopus and some other
towns have been overwhelmed; but to this subject I shall again refer
when speaking of tides and currents.
</div></body></text></TEI>