<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="12"> 

CHAPTER II.
Of Methods of Observation.


Aphorism XXVIII.
The Methods of Observation of Quantity in general are,
Numeration, which is precise by the nature of Number; the
Measurement of Space and of Time, which are easily made
precise; the Conversion of Space and Time, by which each
aids the measurement of the other; the Method of Repetition;
the Method of Coincidences or Interferences. The
measurement of Weight is made precise by the Method of
Double-weighing. Secondary Qualities are measured by
means of Scales of Degrees; but in order to apply these
Scales, the student requires the Education of the Senses.
The Education of the Senses is forwarded by the practical
study of Descriptive Natural History, Chemical Manipulation,
and Astronomical Observation.

1. I
SHALL speak, in this chapter, of Methods
of exact and systematic observation, by which
such facts are collected as form the materials of precise
scientific propositions. These Methods are very various,
according to the nature of the subject inquired
into, and other circumstances: but a great portion of
them agree in being processes of measurement. These
I shall peculiarly consider: and in the first place those
referring to Number, Space, and Time, which are at
the same time objects and instruments of measurement.
2. But though we have to explain how observations
may be made as perfect as possible, we must not
forget that in most cases complete perfection is
unattainable. Observations are never perfect.
For we 146
observe phenomena by our senses, and measure their
relations in time and space; but our senses and our
measures are all, from various causes, inaccurate. If
we have to observe the exact place of the moon among
the stars, how much of instrumental apparatus is
necessary! This apparatus has been improved by
many successive generations of astronomers, yet it is
still far from being perfect. And the senses of man,
as well as his implements, are limited in their exactness.
Two different observers do not obtain precisely
the same measures of the time and place of a phenomenon;
as, for instance, of the moment at which the
moon occults a star, and the point of her limb at which
the occultation takes place. Here, then, is a source of
inaccuracy and errour, even in astronomy, where the
means of exact observation are incomparably more
complete than they are in any other department of
human research. In other cases, the task of obtaining
accurate measures is far more difficult. If we have
to observe the tides of the ocean when rippled with
waves, we can see the average level of the water first
rise and then fall; but how hard is it to select the exact
moment when it is at its greatest height, or the exact
highest point which it reaches! It is very easy, in such
a case, to err by many minutes in time, and by several
inches in space.
Still, in many cases, good Methods can remove very
much of this inaccuracy, and to these we now proceed.
3. (I.) Number.—Number is the first step of
measurement, since it measures itself, and does not, like
space and time, require an arbitrary standard. Hence
the first exact observations, and the first advances of
rigorous knowledge, appear to have been made by means
of number; as for example,—the number of days in a
month and in a year;—the cycles according to which
eclipses occur;—the number of days in the revolutions
of the planets; and the like. All these discoveries, as
we have seen in the History of Astronomy, go back to
the earliest period of the science, anterior to any
distinct tradition; and these discoveries presuppose a series,
probably a very long series, of observations, made 147
principally by means of number. Nations so rude as to
have no other means of exact measurement, have still
systems of numeration by which they can reckon to a
considerable extent. Very often, such nations have very
complex systems, which are capable of expressing numbers
of great magnitude. Number supplies the means
of measuring other quantities, by the assumption of a
unit of measure of the appropriate kind: but where
nature supplies the unit, number is applicable directly
and immediately. Number is an important element in
the Classificatory as well as in the Mathematical Sciences.
The History of those Sciences shows how the
formation of botanical systems was effected by the
adoption of number as a leading element, by Cæsalpinus;
and how afterwards the Reform of Linnæus in classification
depended in a great degree on his finding, in the
pistils and stamens, a better numerical basis than those
before employed. In like manner, the number of rays
in the membrane of the gills1,
and the number of rays
in the fins of fish, were found to be important elements
in ichthyological classification by Artedi and Linnæus.
There are innumerable instances, in all parts of Natural
History, of the importance of the observation of number.
And in this observation, no instrument, scale or
standard is needed, or can be applied; except the
scale of natural numbers, expressed either in words or
in figures, can be considered as an instrument.</div></body></text></TEI>