<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="132">CHAPTER I.
Prelude to Systematic Descriptive Geology

Sect. 1.—Ancient Notices of
Geological Facts.
THE recent history of Geology,
as to its most important points, is bound up with what is doing at
present from day to day; and that portion of the history of the
science which belongs to the past, has been amply treated by other
writers.5 I shall, therefore, pass rapidly over
the series of events of which this history consists; and shall only
attempt to mention what may seem to illustrate and confirm my own view
of its state and principles.
5 As MM. Lyell, Fitton, Conybeare, in
our own country.
Agreeably to the order already pointed out, I shall notice, in the
first place, Phenomenal Geology, or the description of the facts, as
distinct from the inquiry into their causes. It is manifest that such
a merely descriptive kind of knowledge may exist; and it probably will
not be contested, that such knowledge ought to be collected, before we
attempt to frame theories concerning the causes of the phenomena. But
it must be observed, that we are here speaking of the formation of a
science; and that it is not a collection of miscellaneous,
unconnected, unarranged knowledge that can be considered as
constituting science; but a methodical, coherent, and, as far as
possible, complete body of facts, exhibiting fully the condition of
the earth as regards those circumstances which are the subject matter
of geological speculation. Such a Descriptive Geology is a
pre-requisite to Physical Geology, just as Phenomenal Astronomy
necessarily preceded Physical Astronomy, or as Classificatory Botany
is a necessary accompaniment to Botanical Physiology. We may observe
also that Descriptive Geology, such as we now speak of, is one of the
classificatory sciences, like 506 Mineralogy or Botany: and will be found
to exhibit some of the features of that class of sciences.
Since, then, our History of Descriptive Geology is to include only
systematic and scientific descriptions of the earth or portions of it,
we pass over, at once, all the casual and insulated statements of
facts, though they may be geological facts, which occur in early
writers; such, for instance, as the remark of Herodotus,6
that there are shells in the mountains of Egypt; or the general
statements which Ovid puts in the mouth of Pythagoras:7

  Vidi ego quod fuerat solidissima tellus,
Esse fretum; vidi factas ex æquore terras,
Et procul a pelago conchæ jacuere marinæ.

6 ii. 12.
7 Met. xv. 262.
We may remark here already how generally there are mingled with
descriptive notices of such geological facts, speculations concerning
their causes. Herodotus refers to the circumstance just quoted, for
the purpose of showing that Egypt was formerly a gulf of the sea; and
the passage of the Roman poet is part of a series of exemplifications
which he gives of the philosophical tenet, that nothing perishes but
everything changes. It will be only by constant attention that we
shall be able to keep our provinces of geology distinct.
Sect. 2.—Early Descriptions and Collections of
Fossils.
If we look, as we have
proposed to do, for systematic and exact knowledge of geological
facts, we find nothing which we can properly adduce till we come to
modern times. But when facts such as those already mentioned, (that
sea-shells and other marine objects are found imbedded in rocks,) and
other circumstances in the structure of the Earth, had attracted
considerable attention, the exact examination, collection, and record
of these circumstances began to be attempted. Among such steps in
Descriptive Geology, we may notice descriptions and pictures of
fossils, descriptions of veins and mines, collections of organic and
inorganic fossils, maps of the mineral structure of countries, and
finally, the discoveries concerning the superposition of strata, the
constancy of their organic contents, their correspondence in different
countries, and such great general relations of the materials and
features of the earth as have been discovered up to the present time.
507 Without
attempting to assign to every important advance its author, I shall
briefly exemplify each of the modes of contributing to descriptive
geology which I have just enumerated.
The study of organic fossils was first pursued with connexion and
system in Italy. The hills which on each side skirt the mountain-range
of the Apennines are singularly rich in remains of marine animals.
When these remarkable objects drew the attention of thoughtful men,
controversies soon arose whether they really were the remains of
living creatures, or the productions of some capricious or mysterious
power by which the forms of such creatures were mimicked; and again,
if the shells were really the spoils of the sea, whether they had been
carried to the hills by the deluge of which the Scripture speaks, or
whether they indicated revolutions of the earth of a different kind.
The earlier works which contain the descriptions of the phenomena
have, in almost all instances, by far the greater part of their pages
occupied with these speculations; indeed, the facts could not be
studied without leading to such inferences, and would not have been
collected but for the interest which such reasonings possessed. As one
of the first persons who applied a sound and vigorous intellect to
these subjects, we may notice the celebrated painter Leonardo da
Vinci, whom we have already had to refer to
as one of the founders of the modern mechanical sciences. He
strenuously asserts the contents of the rocks to be real shells, and
maintains the reality of the changes of the domain of land and sea
which these spoils of the ocean imply. “You will tell me,” he says,
“that nature and the influence of the stars have formed these shelly
forms in the mountains; then show me a place in the mountains where
the stars at the present day make shelly forms of different ages, and
of different species in the same place. And how, with that, will you
explain the gravel which is hardened in stages at different heights in
the mountains?” He then mentions several other particulars respecting
these evidences that the existing mountains were formerly in the bed
of the sea. Leonardo died in 1519. At present we refer to geological
essays like his, only so far as they are descriptive. Going onwards
with this view, we may notice Fracastoro, who wrote concerning the
petrifactions which were brought to light in the mountains of Verona,
when, in 1517, they were excavated for the purpose of repairing the
city. Little was done in the way of collection of facts for some time
after this. In 1669, Steno, a Dane resident in Italy, put forth his
treatise, De Solido intra Solidum naturaliter contento; and the
508 following year,
Augustino Scilla, a Sicilian painter, published a Latin epistle, De
Corporibus Marinis Lapidescentibus, illustrated by good engravings
of fossil-shells, teeth, and corals.8 After another
interval of speculative controversy, we come to Antonio Vallisneri,
whose letters, De’ Corpi Marini che su’ Monti si trovano,
appeared at Venice in 1721. In these letters he describes the fossils
of Monte Bolca, and attempts to trace the extent of the marine
deposits of Italy,9 and to distinguish the most important of
the fossils. Similar descriptions and figures were published with
reference to our own country at a later period. In 1766, Brander’s
Fossilia Hantoniensia, or Hampshire Fossils, appeared;
containing excellent figures of fossil shells from a part of the south
coast of England; and similar works came forth in other parts of
Europe.
8 Augustine Scilla’s original drawings
of fossil shells, teeth, and corals, from which the engravings
mentioned in the text were executed, as well as the natural objects
from which the drawings were made, were bought by Woodward, and are
now in the Woodwardian Museum at Cambridge.
9 p. 20.
However exact might be the descriptions and figures thus produced,
they could not give such complete information as the objects
themselves, collected and permanently preserved in museums. Vallisneri
says,10 that having begun to collect fossils
for the purpose of forming a grotto, he selected the best, and
preserved them “as a noble diversion for the more curious.” The museum
of Calceolarius at Verona contained a celebrated collection of such
remains. A copious description of it appeared in 1622. Such
collections had been made from an earlier period, and catalogues of
them published. Thus Gessner’s work, De Rerum Fossilium, Lapidum et
Gemmarum Figuris (1565), contains a catalogue of the cabinet of
petrifactions collected by John Kentman; many catalogues of the same
kind appeared in the seventeenth century.11 Lhwyd’s
Lythophylacii Britannici Iconographia, published at Oxford in
1669, and exhibiting a very ample catalogue of English Fossils
contained in the Ashmolean Museum, may be noticed as one of these.
10 p. 1.
11 Parkinson, Organic Remains,
vol. i. p. 20.
One of the most remarkable occurrences in the progress of
descriptive geology in England, was the formation of a geological
museum by William Woodward as early as 1695. This collection, formed
with great labor, systematically arranged, and carefully catalogued,
he bequeathed to the University of Cambridge; founding and endowing
509 at the same
time a professorship of the study of geology. The Woodwardian Museum
still subsists, a monument of the sagacity with which its author so
early saw the importance of such a collection.
Collections and descriptions of fossils, including in the term
specimens of minerals of all kinds, as well as organic remains, were
frequently made, and especially in places where mining was cultivated;
but under such circumstances, they scarcely tended at all to that
general and complete knowledge of the earth of which we are now
tracing the progress.
In more modern times, collections may be said to be the most
important books of the geologist, at least next to the strata
themselves. The identifications and arrangements of our best
geologists, the immense studies of fossil anatomy by Cuvier and
others, have been conducted mainly by means of collections of
specimens. They are more important in this study than in botany,
because specimens which contain important geological information are
both more rare and more permanent. Plants, though each individual is
perishable, perpetuate and diffuse their kind; while the organic
impression on a stone, if lost, may never occur in a second instance;
but, on the other hand, if it be preserved in the museum, the
individual is almost as permanent in this case, as the species in the
other.
I shall proceed to notice another mode in which such information
was conveyed.
Sect. 3.—First Construction of Geological
Maps.
Dr. Lister, a learned
physician, sent to the Royal Society, in 1683, a proposal for maps of
soils or minerals; in which he suggested that in the map of England,
for example, each soil and its boundaries might be distinguished by
color, or in some other way. Such a mode of expressing and connecting
our knowledge of the materials of the earth was, perhaps, obvious,
when the mass of knowledge became considerable. In 1720, Fontenelle,
in his observations on a paper of De Reaumur’s, which contained an
account of a deposit of fossil-shells in Touraine, says, that in order
to reason on such cases, “we must have a kind of geographical charts,
constructed according to the collection of shells found in the earth.”
But he justly adds, “What a quantity of observations, and what time
would it not require to form such maps!”
The execution of such projects required, not merely great labor,
but 510 several
steps in generalization and classification, before it could take
place. Still such attempts were made. In 1743, was published, A new
Philosophico-chorographical Chart of East Kent, invented and
delineated by Christopher Packe, M.D.; in which, however, the main
object is rather to express the course of the valleys than the
materials of the country. Guettard formed the project of a
mineralogical map of France, and Monnet carried this scheme into
effect in 1780,12 “by order of the king.” In these maps,
however, the country is not considered as divided into soils, still
less strata; but each part is marked with its predominant mineral
only. The spirit of generalization which constitutes the main value of
such a work is wanting.
12 Atlas et Description
Minéralogique de la France, entrepris par ordre du Roi, par MM.
Guettard et Monnet, Paris, 1780, pp. 212, with 31 maps.
Geological maps belong strictly to Descriptive Geology; they are
free from those wide and doubtful speculations which form so large a
portion of the earlier geological books. Yet even geological maps
cannot be usefully or consistently constructed without considerable
steps of classification and generalization. When, in our own time,
geologists were become weary of controversies respecting theory, they
applied themselves with extraordinary zeal to the construction of
stratigraphical maps of various countries; flattering themselves that
in this way they were merely recording incontestable facts and
differences. Nor do I mean to intimate that their facts were doubtful,
or their distinctions arbitrary. But still they were facts
interpreted, associated, and represented, by means of the
classifications and general laws which earlier geologists had
established; and thus even Descriptive Geology has been brought into
existence as a science by the formation of systems and the discovery
of principles. At this we cannot be surprized, when we recollect the
many steps which the formation of Classificatory Botany required. We
must now notice some of the discoveries which tended to the formation
of Systematic Descriptive Geology. 511</div></body></text></TEI>