<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="48">CHAPTER XLVIII.
IMBEDDING OF THE REMAINS OF MAN AND HIS WORKS IN
SUBAQUEOUS STRATA.
Drifting of human bodies to the sea by river inundations—Destruction of bridges
and houses—Loss of lives by shipwreck—How human corpses may be preserved
in recent deposits—Number of wrecked vessels—Fossil skeletons of
men—Fossil canoes, ships, and works of art—Chemical changes which metallic
articles have undergone after long submergence—Imbedding of cities and
forests in subaqueous strata by subsidence—Earthquake of Cutch in 1819—Buried
Temples of Cashmere—Berkeley's arguments for the recent date of the
creation of man—Concluding remarks.
I shall now proceed to inquire in what manner the mortal remains of
man and the works of his hands may be permanently preserved in subaqueous
strata. Of the many hundred million human beings which perish
in the course of every century on the land, every vestige is usually destroyed
in the course of a few thousand years; but of the smaller number
that perish in the waters, a certain proportion must be entombed under
circumstances that may enable parts of them to endure throughout entire
geological epochs.
The bodies of men, together with those of the inferior animals, are
occasionally washed down during river inundations into seas and lakes.
(See pp. 726-728.) Belzoni witnessed a flood on the Nile in September,
1818, where, although the river rose only three feet and a half above its
ordinary level, several villages, with some hundreds of men, women, and
children, were swept away.1079 It was before mentioned that a rise of six
feet of water in the Ganges, in 1763, was attended with a much greater
loss of lives. (See above, p. 278.)
In the year 1771, when the inundations in the north of England
appear to have equalled the floods of Morayshire in 1829, a great number
of houses and their inhabitants were swept away by the rivers Tyne,
Can, Wear, Tees, and Greta; and no less than twenty-one bridges were
destroyed in the courses of these rivers. At the village of Bywell the
flood tore the dead bodies and coffins out of the churchyard, and bore
them away, together with many of the living inhabitants. During the
same tempest an immense number of cattle, horses, and sheep, were also
transported to the sea, while the whole coast was covered with the wreck
of ships. Four centuries before (in 1338), the same district had been
visited by a similar continuance of heavy rains, followed by disastrous
floods, and it is not improbable that these catastrophes may recur periodically,
though at uncertain intervals. As the population increases, and
754
buildings and bridges are multiplied, we must expect the loss of lives and
property to augment.1080
Fossilization of human bodies in the bed of the sea.—If to the hundreds
of human bodies committed to the deep in the way of ordinary
burial we add those of individuals lost by shipwrecks, we shall find that
in the course of a single year, a great number of human remains are consigned
to the subaqueous regions. I shall hereafter advert to a calculation
by which it appears that more than five hundred British vessels
alone, averaging each a burthen of about 120 tons, are wrecked, and
sink to the bottom, annually. Of these the crews for the most part
escape, although it sometimes happens that all perish. In one great
naval action several thousand individuals sometimes share a watery grave.
Many of these corpses are instantly devoured by predaceous fish, sometimes
before they reach the bottom; still more frequently when they
rise again to the surface, and float in a state of putrefaction. Many
decompose on the floor of the ocean, where no sediment is thrown down
upon them; but if they fall upon a reef where corals and shells are
becoming agglutinated into a solid rock, or subside where the delta
of a river is advancing, they may be preserved for an incalculable series
of ages.
Often at the distance of a few hundred feet from a coral reef, where
wrecks are not unfrequent, there are no soundings at the depth of many
hundred fathoms. Canoes, merchant vessels, and ships of war, may have
sunk and have been enveloped, in such situations, in calcareous sand and
breccia, detached by the breakers from the summit of a submarine mountain.
Should a volcanic eruption happen to cover such remains with
ashes and sand, and a current of lava be afterwards poured over them,
the ships and human skeletons might remain uninjured beneath the
superincumbent mass, like the houses and works of art in the subterranean
cities of Campania. Already many human remains may have
been thus preserved beneath formations more than a thousand feet in
thickness; for, in some volcanic archipelagoes, a period of thirty or forty
centuries might well be supposed sufficient for such an accumulation. It
was stated, that at the distance of about forty miles from the base of the
delta of the Ganges there is an elliptical space about fifteen miles in
diameter, where soundings of from 100 to 300 fathoms sometimes fail to
reach the bottom. (See above, p. 279.) As during the flood season the quantity
of mud and sand poured by the great rivers into the Bay of Bengal
is so great that the sea only recovers its transparency at the distance of
sixty miles from the coast, this depression must be gradually shoaling,
especially as during the monsoons, the sea loaded with mud and sand, is
beaten back in that direction towards the delta. Now, if a ship or human
body sink to the bottom in such a spot, it is by no means improbable
that it may become buried under a depth of a thousand feet of sediment
in the same number of years.
755
Even on that part of the floor of the ocean to which no accession of drift
matter is carried (a part which probably constitutes, at any given period,
by far the larger proportion of the whole submarine area), there are circumstances
accompanying a wreck which favor the conservation of skeletons.
For when the vessel fills suddenly with water, especially in the
night, many persons are drowned between decks and in their cabins, so
that their bodies are prevented from rising again to the surface. The
vessel often strikes upon an uneven bottom, and is overturned; in which
case the ballast, consisting of sand, shingle, and rock, or the cargo, frequently
composed of heavy and durable materials, may be thrown down
upon the carcasses. In the case of ships of war, cannon, shot, and
other warlike stores, may press down with their weight the timbers of the
vessel as they decay, and beneath these and the metallic substances the
bones of man may be preserved.
Number of wrecked vessels.—When we reflect on the number of curious
monuments consigned to the bed of the ocean in the course of every
naval war from the earliest times, our conceptions are greatly raised
respecting the multiplicity of lasting memorials which man is leaving of
his labors. During our last great struggle with France, thirty-two of
our ships of the line went to the bottom in the space of twenty-two
years, besides seven 50-gun ships, eighty-six frigates, and a multitude of
smaller vessels. The navies of the other European powers, France, Holland,
Spain, and Denmark, were almost annihilated during the same
period, so that the aggregate of their losses must have many times
exceeded that of Great Britain. In every one of these ships were batteries
of cannon constructed of iron or brass, whereof a great number
had the dates and places of their manufacture inscribed upon them in
letters cast in metal. In each there were coins of copper, silver, and
often many of gold, capable of serving as valuable historical monuments;
in each were an infinite variety of instruments of the arts of war and
peace; many formed of materials, such as glass and earthenware, capable
of lasting for indefinite ages when once removed from the mechanical
action of the waves, and buried under a mass of matter which may
exclude the corroding action of sea-water. The quantity, moreover, of
timber which is conveyed from the land to the bed of the sea by the
sinking of ships of a large size is enormous, for it is computed that 2000
tons of wood are required for the building of one 74-gun ship; and
reckoning fifty oaks of 100 years growth to the acre, it would require
forty acres of oak forest to build one of these vessels.1081
It would be an error to imagine that the fury of war is more conducive
than the peaceful spirit of commercial enterprise to the accumulation of
wrecked vessels in the bed of the sea. From an examination of Lloyd's
lists, from the year 1793 to the commencement of 1829, Captain W. H.
Smyth ascertained that the number of British vessels alone lost during
that period amounted on an average to no less than one and a half daily;
756
an extent of loss which would hardly have been anticipated, although
we learn from Moreau's tables that the number of merchant vessels
employed at one time, in the navigation of England and Scotland, amounts
to about twenty thousand, having one with another a mean burthen of
120 tons.1082 My friend, Mr. J. L. Prevost, also informs me that on inspecting
Lloyd's list for the years 1829, 1830, and 1831, he finds that no less
than 1953 vessels were lost in those three years, their average tonnage
being about 150 tons, or in all nearly 300,000 tons, being at the enormous
rate of 100,000 tons annually of the merchant vessels of one nation
only. This increased loss arises, I presume, from increasing activity in
commerce.
Out of 551 ships of the royal navy lost to the country during the
period above mentioned, only 160 were taken or destroyed by the enemy,
the rest having either stranded or foundered, or having been burnt by
accident; a striking proof that the dangers of our naval warfare, however
great, may be far exceeded by the storm, the shoal, the lee-shore,
and all the other perils of the deep.1083
Durable nature of many of their contents.—Millions of silver dollars
and other coins have been sometimes submerged in a single ship, and on
these, when they happen to be enveloped in a matrix capable of protecting
them from chemical changes, much information of historical interest
will remain inscribed, and endure for periods as indefinite as have the
delicate markings of zoophytes or lapidified plants in some of the ancient
secondary rocks. In almost every large ship, moreover, there are some
precious stones set in seals, and other articles of use and ornament composed
of the hardest substances in nature, on which letters and various
images are carved—engravings which they may retain when included in
subaqueous strata, as long as a crystal preserves its natural form.
It was, therefore, a splendid boast, that the deeds of the English chivalry
at Agincourt made Henry's chronicle


———as rich with praise
As is the ooze and bottom of the deep
With sunken wreck and sumless treasuries


for it is probable that a greater number of monuments of the skill and
industry of man will, in the course of ages, be collected together in the
bed of the ocean, than will exist at any one time on the surface of the
continents.
If our species be of as recent a date as is generally supposed, it will
be vain to seek for the remains of man and the works of his hands imbedded
in submarine strata, except in those regions where violent earthquakes
are frequent, and the alterations of relative level so great, that
the bed of the sea may have been converted into land within the historical
era. We need not despair, however, of the discovery of such monuments,
757
when those regions which have been peopled by man from the
earliest ages, and which are at the same time the principal theatres of
volcanic action, shall be examined by the joint skill of the antiquary and
geologist.
Power of human remains to resist decay.—There can be no doubt
that human remains are as capable of resisting decay as are the harder
parts of the inferior animals; and I have already cited the remark of
Cuvier, that "in ancient fields of battle the bones of men have suffered
as little decomposition as those of horses which were buried in the same
grave." (See above, p. 147.) In the delta of the Ganges bones of men
have been found in digging a well at the depth of ninety feet;1084 but as
that river frequently shifts its course and fills up its ancient channels, we
are not called upon to suppose that these bodies are of extremely high
antiquity, or that they were buried when that part of the surrounding
delta where they occur was first gained from the sea.
Fossil skeletons of men.—Several skeletons of men, more or less mutilated,
have been found in the West Indies, on the north-west coast of
the main land of Guadaloupe, in a kind of rock which is known to be
forming daily, and which consists of minute fragments of shells and
corals, incrusted with a calcareous cement resembling travertin, by which
also the different grains are bound together. The lens shows that some
of the fragments of coral composing this stone still retain the same red
color which is seen in the reefs of living coral which surround the island.
The shells belong to species of the neighboring sea intermixed with
some terrestrial kinds which now live on the island, and among them is
the Bulimus Gaudaloupensis of Férussac. The human skeletons still
retain some of their animal matter, and all their phosphate of lime.
One of them, of which the head is wanting, may now be seen in the
British Museum, and another in the Royal Cabinet at Paris. According
to M. König, the rock in which the former is inclosed is harder under
the mason's saw and chisel than statuary marble. It is described as
forming a kind of glacis, probably an indurated beach, which slants from
the steep cliffs of the island to the sea, and is nearly all submerged at
high tide.
Similar formations are in progress in the whole of the West Indian
archipelago, and they have greatly extended the plain of Cayes in St.
Domingo, where fragments of vases and other human works have been
found at a depth of twenty feet. In digging wells also near Catania, in
Sicily, tools have been discovered in a rock somewhat similar.
Buried ships, canoes, and works of art.—When a vessel is stranded
in shallow water, it usually becomes the nucleus of a sand-bank, as has
been exemplified in several of our harbors, and this circumstance tends
greatly to its preservation. Between the years 1780 and 1790 a vessel
from Purbeck, laden with three hundred tons of stone, struck on a shoal
off the entrance of Poole harbor and foundered; the crew were saved,
758
but the vessel and cargo remain to this day at the bottom. Since that
period the shoal at the entrance of the harbor has so extended itself in a
westerly direction towards Peveril Point in Purbeck, that the navigable
channel is thrown a mile nearer that point.1085 The cause is obvious; the
tidal current deposits the sediment with which it is charged around any
object which checks its velocity. Matter also drifted along the bottom is
arrested by any obstacle, and accumulates round it, just as the African
sand-winds, before described, raise a small hillock over the carcass of
every dead camel exposed on the surface of the desert.
I before alluded to an ancient Dutch vessel, discovered in the deserted
channel of the river Rother in Sussex, of which the oak wood was much
blackened, but its texture unchanged. (See above, p. 316.) The interior
was filled with fluviatile silt, as was also the case in regard to a vessel
discovered in a former bed of the Mersey, and another disinterred
where the St. Katherine Docks are excavated in the alluvial plain of the
Thames. In like manner many ships have been found preserved entire
in modern strata, formed by the silting up of estuaries along the southern
shores of the Baltic, especially in Pomerania. Between Bromberg and
Nakel, for example, a vessel and two anchors in a very perfect state were
dug up far from the sea.1086
Several vessels have been lately detected half buried in the delta of
the Indus, in the numerous deserted branches of that river, far from
where the stream now flows. One of these found near Vikkar in Sinde,
was 400 tons in burthen, old fashioned, and pierced for fourteen guns,
and in a region where it had been matter of dispute whether the Indus
had ever been navigable by large vessels.1087
At the mouth of a river in Nova Scotia, a schooner of thirty-two tons,
laden with live stock, was lying with her side to the tide, when the bore,
or tidal wave, which rises there about ten feet in perpendicular height,
rushed into the estuary, and overturned the vessel, so that it instantly
disappeared. After the tide had ebbed, the schooner was so totally
buried in the sand, that the taffrel or upper rail over the stern was alone
visible.1088 We are informed by Leigh that, on draining Martin Meer, a
lake eighteen miles in circumference, in Lancashire, a bed of marl was
laid dry, wherein no fewer than eight canoes were found imbedded.
In figure and dimensions they were not unlike those now used in America.
In a morass about nine miles distant from this Meer a whetstone
and an axe of mixed metal were dug up.1089 In Ayrshire, also, three canoes
were found in Loch Doon some few years ago; and during the year 1831
four others, each hewn out of separate oak trees. They were twenty-three
feet in length, two and a half in depth, and nearly four feet in
breadth at the stern. In the mud which filled one of them was found a
759
war-club of oak and a stone battle-axe. A canoe of oak was also found
in 1820, in peat overlying the shell-marl of the Loch of Kinnordy, in
Forfarshire.1090
Manner in which ships may be preserved in a deep sea.—It is extremely
possible that the submerged woodwork of ships which have sunk where
the sea is two or three miles deep has undergone greater chemical
changes in an equal space of time, than in the cases above mentioned;
for the experiments of Scoresby show that wood may at certain depths
be impregnated in a single hour with salt water, so that its specific gravity
is entirely altered. It may often happen that hot springs, charged
with carbonate of lime, silex, and other mineral ingredients, may issue at
great depths, in which case every pore of the vegetable tissue may be
injected with the lapidifying liquid, whether calcareous or siliceous,
before the smallest decay commences. The conversion, also, of wood
into lignite is probably more rapid under enormous pressure. But the
change of the timber into lignite or coal would not prevent the original
form of a ship from being distinguished; for as we find, in strata of the
carboniferous era, the bark of the hollow reed-like trees converted into
coal, and the central cavity filled with sandstone, so might we trace the
outline of a ship in coal; while in the indurated mud, sandstone, or limestone,
filling the interior, we might discover instruments of human art,
ballast consisting of rocks foreign to the rest of the stratum, and other
contents of the ship.
Submerged metallic substances.—Many of the metallic substances
which fall into the waters probably lose, in the course of ages, the forms
artificially imparted to them; but under certain circumstances these may
be preserved for indefinite periods. The cannon enclosed in a calcareous
rock, drawn up from the delta of the Rhone, which is now in the museum
at Montpellier, might probably have endured as long as the calcareous
matrix; but even if the metallic matter had been removed, and had entered
into new combinations, still a mould of its original shape would
have been left, corresponding to those impressions of shells which we see
in rocks, from which all the carbonate of lime has been subtracted.
About the year 1776, says Mr. King, some fishermen, sweeping for
anchors in the Gulf stream (a part of the sea near the Downs), drew up
a very curious old swivel gun, nearly eight feet in length. The barrel,
which was about five feet long, was of brass; but the handle by which it
was traversed was about three feet in length, and the swivel and pivot on
which it turned were of iron. Around these latter were formed incrustations
of sand converted into a kind of stone, of exceedingly strong texture
and firmness; whereas round the barrel of the gun, except where it was
near adjoining to the iron, there were no such incrustations, the greater
part of it being clean, and in good condition, just as if it had still continued
in use. In the incrusting stone, adhering to it on the outside, were a
number of shells and corallines, "just as they are often found in a fossil
760
state." These were all so strongly attached, that it required as much
force to separate them from the matrix "as to break a fragment off any
hard rock."1091
In the year 1745, continues the same writer, the Fox man-of-war was
stranded on the coast of East Lothian, and went to pieces. About thirty-three
years afterwards a violent storm laid bare a part of the wreck, and
threw up near the place several masses, "consisting of iron, ropes, and
balls," covered over with ochreous sand, concreted and hardened into a
kind of stone. The substance of the rope was very little altered. The
consolidated sand retained perfect impressions of parts of an iron ring,
"just as impressions of extraneous fossil bodies are found in various kinds
of strata."1092
After a storm in the year 1824, which occasioned a considerable shifting
of the sands near St. Andrew's, in Scotland, a gun-barrel of ancient
construction was found, which is conjectured to have belonged to one of
the wrecked vessels of the Spanish Armada. It is now in the museum
of the Antiquarian Society of Scotland, and is incrusted over by a thin
coating of sand, the grains of which are cemented by brown ferruginous
matter. Attached to this coating are fragments of various shells, as of
the common cardium, mya, &c.
Many other examples are recorded of iron instruments taken up from
the bed of the sea near the British coast, incased by a thick coating
of conglomerate, consisting of pebbles and sand, cemented by oxide of
iron.
Dr. Davy describes a bronze helmet, of the antique Grecian form, taken
up in 1825, from a shallow part of the sea, between the citadel of Corfu
and the village of Castrades. Both the interior and exterior of the helmet
were partially incrusted with shells, and a deposit of carbonate of
lime. The surface generally, both under the incrustation, and where
freed from it, was of a variegated color, mottled with spots of green,
dirty white, and red. On minute inspection with a lens, the green and
red patches proved to consist of crystals of the red oxide and carbonate
of copper, and the dirty white chiefly of oxide of tin.
The mineralizing process, says Dr. Davy, which has produced these
new combinations, has, in general, penetrated very little into the substance
of the helmet. The incrustation and rust removed, the metal is
found bright beneath; in some places considerably corroded, in others
very slightly. It proves, on analysis, to be copper, alloyed with 18.5 per
cent. of tin. Its color is that of our common brass, and it possesses
a considerable degree of flexibility.
"It is a curious question," he adds, "how the crystals were formed in
the helmet, and on the adhering calcareous deposit. There being no
reason to suppose deposition from solution, are we not under the necessity
of inferring, that the mineralizing process depends on a small motion
and separation of the particles of the original compound? This motion
761
may have been due to the operation of electro-chemical powers which
may have separated the different metals of the alloy.1093
Effects of the Subsidence of Land, in imbedding Cities and Forests
in subaqueous Strata.
We have hitherto considered the transportation of plants and animals
from the land by aqueous agents, and their inhumation in lacustrine or
submarine deposits, and we may now inquire what tendency the subsidence
of tracts of land may have to produce analogous effects. Several
examples of the sinking down of buildings, and portions of towns near
the shore, to various depths beneath the level of the sea during subterranean
movements, were before enumerated in treating of the changes
brought about by inorganic causes. The events alluded to were comprised
within a brief portion of the historical period, and confined to a
small number of the regions of active volcanoes. Yet these authentic
facts, relating merely to the last century and a half, gave indications of
considerable changes in the physical geography of the globe, and we are
not to suppose that these were the only spots throughout the surrounding
land and sea which suffered similar depressions.
If, during the short period since South America has been colonized by
Europeans, we have proof of alterations of level at the three principal
ports on the western shores, Callao, Valparaiso, and Conception,1094 we
cannot for a moment suspect that these cities, so distant from each other,
have been selected as the peculiar points where the desolating power of
the earthquake has expended its chief fury. On considering how small
is the area occupied by the seaports of this disturbed region—points
where alone each slight change of the relative level of the sea and land
can be recognized,—and reflecting on the proofs in our possession of the
local revolutions that have happened on the site of each port, within the
last century and a half,—our conceptions must be greatly exalted respecting
the magnitude of the alterations which the country between the
Andes and the sea may have undergone, even in the course of the last
six thousand years.
Cutch earthquake.—The manner in which a large extent of surface
may be submerged, so that the terrestrial plants and animals may be
imbedded in subaqueous strata, cannot be better illustrated than by the
earthquake of Cutch, in 1819, before alluded to (p. 460). It is stated,
that, for some years after that earthquake, the withered tamarisks and
other shrubs protruded their tops above the waves, in parts of the lagoon
formed by subsidence, on the site of the village of Sindree and its environs;
but, after the flood of 1826, they were seen no longer. Every
geologist will at once perceive, that forests sunk by such subterranean
movements may become imbedded in subaqueous deposits, both fluviatile
762
and marine, and the trees may still remain erect, or sometimes the roots
and part of the trunks may continue in their original position, while the
current may have broken off, or levelled with the ground, their upper
stems and branches.
Buildings how preserved under water.—Some of the buildings which
have at different times subsided beneath the level of the sea have been
immediately covered up to a certain extent with strata of volcanic matter
showered down upon them. Such was the case at Tomboro in
Sumbawa, in the present century, and at the site of the Temple of Serapis,
in the environs of Puzzuoli, probably about the 12th century. The
entrance of a river charged with sediment in the vicinity may still more
frequently occasion the rapid envelopment of buildings in regularly stratified
formations. But if no foreign matter be introduced, the buildings,
when once removed to a depth where the action of the waves is insensible,
and where no great current happens to flow, may last for indefinite
periods, and be as durable as the floor of the ocean itself, which may
often be composed of the very same materials. There is no reason to
doubt the tradition mentioned by the classic writers, that the submerged
Grecian towns of Bura and Helice were seen under water; and it has
been already mentioned that different eye-witnesses have observed the
houses of Port Royal, at the bottom of the sea, at intervals of 88, 101,
and 143 years after the convulsion of 1692. (p. 505.)
Buried temples of Cashmere.—The celebrated valley of Cashmere
(or Kashmir) in India, situated at the southern foot of the Himalaya
range, is about 60 miles in length, and 20 in breadth, surrounded by
mountains which rise abruptly from the plain to the height of about
5000 feet. In the cliffs of the river Jelam and its tributaries, which traverse
this beautiful valley, strata consisting of fine clay, sand, soft sandstone,
pebbles, and conglomerate are exposed to view. They contain
freshwater shells, of the genera Lymneus, Paludina, and Cyrena, with
land shells, all of recent species, and are precisely such deposits as
would be formed if the whole valley were now converted into a great
lake, and if the numerous rivers and torrents descending from the surrounding
mountains were allowed sufficient time to fill up the lake-basin
with fine sediment and gravel. Fragments of pottery met with at the
depth of 40 and 50 feet in this lacustrine formation show that the upper
part of it at least has accumulated within the human epoch.
Dr. Thomas Thomson, who visited Cashmere in 1848, observes that
several of the lakes which still exist in the great valley, such as that
near the town of Cashmere, five miles in diameter, and some others, are
deeper than the adjoining river-channels, and may have been formed by
subsidence during the numerous earthquakes which have convulsed that
region in the course of the last 2000 years. It is also probable that the
freshwater strata seen to extend far and wide over the whole of Cashmere
originated not in one continuous sheet of water once occupying
the entire valley, but in many lakes of limited area, formed and filled
in succession. Among other proofs of such lake-basins of moderate
763
dimensions having once existed and having been converted into land at
different periods, Dr. Thomson mentions that the ruins of Avantipura,
not far from the modern village of that name, stand on an older freshwater
deposit at the base of the mountains, and terminate abruptly
towards the plain in a straight line, such as admits of no other explanation
than by supposing that the advance of the town in that direction
was arrested by a lake, now drained or represented only by a marsh.
In that neighborhood, as very generally throughout Cashmere, the
rivers run in channels or alluvial flats, bounded by cliffs of lacustrine
strata, horizontally stratified, and these strata form low table-lands from
20 to 50 feet high between the different watercourses. On a table-land
of this kind near Avantipura, portions of two buried temples are seen,
which have been partially explored by Major Cunningham, who, in
1847, discovered that in one of the buildings a magnificent colonnade
of seventy-four pillars is preserved underground. He exposed to view
three of the pillars in a cavity still open. All the architectural decorations
below the level of the soil are as perfect and fresh-looking as when
first executed. The spacious quadrangle must have been silted up
gradually at first, for some unsightly alterations, not in accordance with
the general plan and style of architecture, were detected, evidently of
subsequent date, and such as could only have been required when the
water and sediment had already gained a certain height in the interior
of the temple.
This edifice is supposed to have been erected about the year 850 of
our era, and was certainly submerged before the year 1416, when the
Mahomedan king, Sikandar, called Butshikan or the idol-breaker,
destroyed all the images of Hindoo temples in Cashmere. Ferishta the
historian particularly alludes to Sikandar having demolished every
Cashmerian temple save one, dedicated to Mahadéva, which escaped
"in consequence of its foundations being below the neighboring
water." The unharmed condition of the human-headed birds and other
images in the buried edifice near Avantipura leaves no doubt that they
escaped the fury of the iconoclast by being under water, and perhaps
silted up before the date of his conquest.1095
Berkeley's arguments for the recent date of the creation of man.—I
cannot conclude this chapter without recalling to the reader's mind a
memorable passage written by Bishop Berkeley a century ago, in which
he inferred, on grounds which may be termed strictly geological, the
recent date of the creation of man. "To any one," says he, "who
considers that on digging into the earth, such quantities of shells, and
in some places, bones and horns of animals, are found sound and entire,
after having lain there in all probability some thousands of years; it
should seem probable that guns, medals, and implements in metal or
stone, might have lasted entire, buried under ground forty or fifty
764
thousand years, if the world had been so old. How comes it then to
pass that no remains are found, no antiquities of those numerous ages
preceding the Scripture accounts of time; that no fragments of buildings,
no public monuments, no intaglios, cameos, statues, basso-relievos,
medals, inscriptions, utensils, or artificial works of any kind, are ever
discovered, which may bear testimony to the existence of those mighty
empires, those successions of monarchs, heroes, and demi-gods, for so
many thousand years? Let us look forward and suppose ten or twenty
thousand years to come, during which time we will suppose that plagues,
famine, wars, and earthquakes shall have made great havoc in the world,
is it not highly probable that at the end of such a period, pillars, vases,
and statues now in being, of granite, or porphyry, or jasper (stones of
such hardness as we know them to have lasted two thousand years
above ground, without any considerable alteration), would bear record
of these and past ages? Or that some of our current coins might then
be dug up, or old walls and the foundations of buildings show themselves,
as well as the shells and stones of the primeval world, which are
preserved down to our times."1096
That many signs of the agency of man would have lasted at least as
long as "the shells of the primeval world," had our race been so ancient,
we may feel as fully persuaded as Berkeley; and we may anticipate with
confidence that many edifices and implements of human workmanship
and the skeletons of men, and casts of the human form, will continue to
exist when a great part of the present mountains, continents, and seas
have disappeared. Assuming the future duration of the planet to be
indefinitely protracted, we can foresee no limit to the perpetuation of
some of the memorials of man, which are continually entombed in the
bowels of the earth or in the bed of the ocean, unless we carry forward
our views to a period sufficient to allow the various causes of change,
both igneous and aqueous, to remodel more than once the entire crust
of the earth. One complete revolution will be inadequate to efface
every monument of our existence; for many works of art might enter
again and again into the formations of successive eras, and escape
obliteration even though the very rocks in which they had been for
ages imbedded were destroyed, just as pebbles included in the conglomerates
of one epoch often contain the organized remains of beings
which flourished during a prior era.
Yet it is no less true, as a late distinguished philosopher has declared,
"that none of the works of a mortal being can be eternal."1097 They are
in the first place wrested from the hands of man, and lost as far as regards
their subserviency to his use, by the instrumentality of those very
causes which place them in situations where they are enabled to endure
for indefinite periods. And even when they have been included in rocky
strata, when they have been made to enter as it were into the solid frame
765work
of the globe itself, they must nevertheless eventually perish; for
every year some portion of the earth's crust is shattered by earthquakes,
or melted by volcanic fire, or ground to dust by the moving waters on the
surface. "The river of Lethe," as Bacon eloquently remarks, "runneth
as well above ground as below."1098
</div></body></text></TEI>