<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Chambers Robert</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="6">p.
76SECONDARY ROCKS.
ERA OF THE CARBONIFEROUS
FORMATION.
LAND FORMED.
COMMENCEMENT OF LAND PLANTS.
We now enter upon a new great epoch
in the history of our globe.  There was now dry land. 
As a consequence of this fact, there was fresh water, for rain,
instead of immediately returning to the sea, as formerly, was now
gathered in channels of the earth, and became springs, rivers,
and lakes.  There was now a theatre for the existence of
land plants and animals, and it remains to be inquired if these
accordingly were produced.
The Secondary Rocks, in which our further researches are to be
prosecuted, consist of a great and varied series, resting,
generally unconformably, against flanks of the upturned primary
rocks, sometimes themselves considerably inclined, at others,
forming extensive basin-like beds, nearly horizontal; in many
places, much broken up and shifted by disturbances from
below.  They have all been formed out of the materials of
the older rocks, by virtue of the wearing power of air and water,
which is still every day carrying down vast quantities of the
elevated matter of the globe into the sea.  But the separate
strata are each much more distinct in the matter of its
composition than might be expected.  Some are siliceous or
arenaceous (sandstones), composed mainly of fine grains from the
quartz rocks—the most abundant of the primary strata. 
Others are argillaceous—clays, shales, &c., chiefly
derived, probably, from the slate beds of the primary
series.  Others are calcareous, derived from the early
limestone.  As a general feature, they are softer and less
crystalline than the primary rocks, as if they had endured less
of both heat and pressure than the senior formation.  There
are beds (coal) formed solely of vegetable matter, and
some others in which the main ingredient is particles of iron,
(the iron black band.)  The secondary rocks are quite
as communicative with regard to their portion of the
earth’s history as the primitive were.
The first, or lowest, group of the secondary rocks is called
the Carboniferous Formation, from the remarkable feature
of its numerous interspersed beds of coal.  It commences
with the beds of the mountain limestone, which, in some
situations, as in Derbyshire and Ireland, are of great thickness,
being alternated with chert (a siliceous sandstone), sandstones,
shales, and beds of coal, generally of the harder and less
bituminous kind (anthracite), the whole being covered in
some places by the millstone grit, a siliceous conglomerate
composed of the detritus of the primary rocks.  The mountain
limestone, attaining in England to a depth of eight hundred
yards, greatly exceeds in volume any of the primary limestone
beds, and shews an enormous addition of power to the causes
formerly suggested as having produced this substance.  In
fact, remains of corals, crinoidea, and shells, are so abundant
in it, as to compose three-fourths of the mass in some
parts.  Above the mountain limestone commence the more
conspicuous coal beds, alternating with sandstones,
shales, beds of limestone, and ironstone.  Coal is
altogether composed of the matter of a terrestrial vegetation,
transmuted by pressure.  Some fresh-water shells have been
found in it, but few of marine origin, and no remains of those
zoophytes and crinoidea so abundant in the mountain limestone and
other rocks.  Coal beds exist in Europe, Asia, and America,
and have hitherto been esteemed as the most valuable of mineral
productions, from the important services which the substance
renders in manufactures and in domestic economy.  It is to
be remarked, that there are some local variations in the
arrangement of coal beds.  In France, they rest immediately
on the granite and other primary rocks, the intermediate strata
not having been found at those places.  In America, the kind
called anthracite occurs among the slate beds, and this species
also abounds more in the mountain limestone than with us. 
These last circumstances only shew that different parts of the
earth’s surface did not all witness the same events of a
certain fixed series exactly at the same time.  There had
been an exhibition of dry land about the site of America, a
little earlier than in Europe.
Some features of the condition of the earth during the
deposition of the carboniferous group, are made out with a
clearness which must satisfy most minds.  First we are told
of a time when carbonate of lime was formed in vast abundance at
the bottoms of profound seas, accompanied by an unusually large
population of corals and encrinites; while in some parts of the
earth there were patches of dry land, covered with a luxuriant
vegetation.  Next we have a comparatively brief period of
volcanic disturbance, (when the conglomerate was formed.) 
Then the causes favourable to the so abundant production of
limestone, and the large population of marine acrita, decline,
and we find the masses of dry land increase in number and extent,
and begin to bear an amount of forest vegetation, far exceeding
that of the most sheltered tropical spots of the present
surface.  The climate, even in the latitude of
Baffin’s Bay, was torrid, and perhaps the atmosphere
contained a larger charge of carbonic acid gas (the material of
vegetation) than it now does.  The forests or thickets of
the period, included no species of plants now known upon
earth.  They mainly consisted of gigantic shrubs, which are
either not represented by any existing types, or are akin to
kinds which are now only found in small and lowly forms. 
That these forests grew upon a Polynesia, or multitude of small
islands, is considered probable, from similar vegetation being
now found in such situations within the tropics.  With
regard to the circumstances under which the masses of vegetable
matter were transformed into successive coal strata, geologists
are divided.  From examples seen at the present day, at the
mouths of such rivers as the Mississippi, which traverse
extensive sylvan regions, and from other circumstances to be
adverted to, it is held likely by some that the vegetable matter,
the rubbish of decayed forests, was carried by rivers into
estuaries, and there accumulated in vast natural rafts, until it
sunk to the bottom, where an overlayer of sand or mud would
prepare it for becoming a stratum of coal.  Others conceive
that the vegetation first went into the condition of a peat moss,
that a sink in the level then exposed it to be overrun by the
sea, and covered with a layer of sand or mud; that a subsequent
uprise made the mud dry land, and fitted it to bear a new forest,
which afterwards, like its predecessor, became a bed of peat;
that, in short, by repetitions of this process, the alternate
layers of coal, sandstone, and shale, constituting the
carboniferous group, were formed.  It is favourable to this
last view that marine fossils are scarcely found in the body of
the coal itself, though abundant in the shale layers above and
below it; also that in several places erect stems of trees are
found with their roots still fixed in the shale beds, and
crossing the sandstone beds at almost right angles, shewing that
these, at least, had not been drifted from their original
situations.  On the other hand, it is not easy to admit such
repeated risings and sinkings of surface as would be required, on
this hypothesis, to form a series of coal strata.  Perhaps
we may most safely rest at present with the supposition that coal
has been formed under both classes of circumstances, though in
the latter only as an exception to the former.
Upwards of three hundred species of plants have been
ascertained to exist in the coal formation; but it is not
necessary to suppose that the whole contained in that system are
now, or ever will be distinguished.  Experiments shew that
some great classes of plants become decomposed in water in a much
less space of time than others, and it is remarkable that those
which decompose soonest, are of the classes found most rare, or
not at all, in the coal strata.  It is consequently to be
inferred that there may have been grasses and mosses at this era,
and many species of trees, the remains of which had lost all
trace of organic form before their substance sunk into the mass
of which coal was formed.  In speaking, therefore, of the
vegetation of this period, we must bear in mind that it may have
comprehended forms of which we have no memorial.
Supposing, nevertheless, that, in the main, the ascertained
vegetation of the coal system is that which grew at the time of
its formation, it is interesting to find that the terrestrial
botany of our globe begins with classes of comparatively simple
forms and structure.  In the ranks of the vegetable kingdom,
the lowest place is taken by plants of cellular tissue, and which
have no flowers, (cryptogamia,) as lichens, mosses, fungi,
ferns, sea-weeds.  Above these stand plants of vascular
tissue, and bearing flowers, in which again there are two great
subdivisions; first, plants having one seed-lobe,
(monocotyledons,) and in which the new matter is added
within, (endogenous,) of which the cane and palm are
examples; second, plants having two seed-lobes,
(dicotyledons,) and in which the new matter is added on
the outside under the bark, (exogenous,) of which the
pine, elm, oak, and most of the British forest-trees are
examples; these subdivisions also ranking in the order in which
they are here stated.  Now it is clear that a predominance
of these forms in succession marked the successive epochs
developed by fossil geology; the simple abounding first, and the
complex afterwards.
Two-thirds of the plants of the carboniferous era are of the
cellular or cryptogamic kind, a proportion which would probably
be much increased if we knew the whole Flora of that era. 
The ascertained dicotyledons, or higher-class plants, are
comparatively few in this formation; but it will be found that
they constantly increased as the globe grew older.
The master-form or type of the era was the fern, or
breckan, of which about one hundred and thirty species have
already been ascertained as entering into the composition of
coal. [84a]  The fern is a plant which
thrives best in warm, shaded, and moist situations.  In
tropical countries, where these conditions abound, there are many
more species than in temperate climes, and some of these are
arborescent, or of a tree-like size and luxuriance. [84b]  The ferns of the coal strata
have been of this magnitude, and that without regard to the parts
of the earth where they are found.  In the coal of
Baffin’s Bay, of Newcastle, and of the torrid zone alike,
are the fossil ferns arborescent, shewing clearly that, in that
era, the present tropical temperature, or one even higher,
existed in very high latitudes.
In the swamps and ditches of England there grows a plant
called the horse-tail (equisetum), having a succulent,
erect, jointed stem, with slender leaves, and a scaly catkin at
the top.  A second large section of the plants of the
carboniferous era were of this kind (equisetaceæ),
but, like the fern, reaching the magnitudes of trees.  While
existing equiseta rarely exceed three feet in height, and the
stems are generally under half an inch in diameter, their
kindred, entombed in the coal beds, seem to have been generally
fourteen or fifteen feet high, with stems from six inches to a
foot in thickness.  Arborescent plants of this family, like
the arborescent ferns, now grow only in tropical countries, and
their being found in the coal beds in all latitudes is
consequently held as an additional proof, that at this era a warm
climate was extended much farther to the north than at
present.  It is to be remarked that plants of this kind
(forming two genera, the most abundant of which is the
calamites) are only represented on the present surface by
plants of the same family: the species which
flourished at this era gradually lessen in number as we advance
upwards in the series of rocks, and disappear before we arrive at
the tertiary formation.
The club-moss family (lycopodiaceæ) are other
plants of the present surface, usually seen in a lowly and
creeping form in temperate latitudes, but presenting species
which rise to a greater magnitude within the tropics.  Many
specimens of this family are found in the coal beds; it is
thought they have contributed more to the substance of the coal
than any other family.  But, like the ferns and
equisetaceæ, they rise to a prodigious magnitude.  The
lepidodendra (so the fossil genus is called) have probably been
from sixty-five to eighty feet in height, having at their base a
diameter of about three feet, while their leaves measured twenty
inches in length.  In the forests of the coal era, the
lepidodendra would enjoy the rank of firs in our forests,
affording shade to the only less stately ferns and
calamites.  The internal structure of the stem, and the
character of the seed-vessels, shew them to have been a link
between single-lobed and double-lobed plants, a fact worthy of
note, as it favours the idea that, in vegetable, as well as
animal creation, a progress has been observed, in conformity with
advancing conditions.  It is also curious to find a missing
link of so much importance in a genus of plants which has long
ceased to have a living place upon earth.
The other leading plants of the coal era are without
representatives on the present surface, and their characters are
in general less clearly ascertained.  Amongst the most
remarkable are—the sigillaria, of which large stems
are very abundant, shewing that the interior has been soft, and
the exterior fluted with separate leaves inserted in vertical
rows along the flutings—and the stigmaria, plants
apparently calculated to flourish in marshes or pools, having a
short, thick, fleshy stem, with a dome-shaped top, from which
sprung branches of from twenty to thirty feet long.  Amongst
monocotyledons were some palms, (flabellaria and
næggerathia,) besides a few not distinctly
assignable to any class.
The dicotyledons of the coal are comparatively few, though on
the present surface they are the most numerous sub-class. 
Besides some of doubtful affinity, (annularia,
asterophyllites, &c.,) there were a few of the pine
family, which seem to have been the highest class of trees of
this era, and are only as yet found in isolated cases, and in
sandstone beds.  The first discovered lay in the Craigleith
quarry, near Edinburgh, and consisted of a stem about two feet
thick, and forty-seven feet in length.  Others have since
been found, both in the same situation, and at Newcastle. 
Leaves and fruit being wanting, an ingenious mode of detecting
the nature of these trees was hit upon by Mr. Witham of
Lartington.  Taking thin polished cross slices of the stem,
and subjecting them to the microscope, he detected the structure
of the wood to be that of a cone-bearing tree, by the presence of
certain “reticulations” which distinguish that
family, in addition to the usual radiating and concentric
lines.  That particular tree was concluded to be an
araucaria, a species now found in Norfolk Island, in the South
Sea, and in a few other remote situations.  The
coniferæ of this era form the dawn of dicotyledenous trees,
of which they may be said to be the simplest type, and to which,
it has already been noticed, the lepidodendra are a link from the
monocotyledons.  The concentric rings of the Craigleith and
other coniferæ of this era have been mentioned.  It is
interesting to find in these a record of the changing seasons of
those early ages, when as yet there were no human beings to
observe time or tide.  They are clearly traced; but it is
observed that they are more slightly marked than is the case with
their family at the present day, as if the changes of temperature
had been within a narrower range.
Such was the vegetation of the carbonigenous era, composed of
forms at the bottom of the botanical scale, flowerless,
fruitless, but luxuriant and abundant beyond what the most
favoured spots on earth can now shew.  The rigidity of the
leaves of its plants, and the absence of fleshy fruits and
farinaceous seeds, unfitted it to afford nutriment to animals;
and, monotonous in its forms, and destitute of brilliant
colouring, its sward probably unenlivened by any of the smaller
flowering herbs, its shades uncheered by the hum of insects, or
the music of birds, it must have been but a sombre scene to a
human visitant.  But neither man nor any other animals were
then in existence to look for such uses or such beauties in this
vegetation.  It was serving other and equally important
ends, clearing (probably) the atmosphere of matter noxious to
animal life, and storing up mineral masses which were in long
subsequent ages to prove of the greatest service to the human
race, even to the extent of favouring the progress of its
civilization.
The animal remains of this era are not numerous, in comparison
with those which go before, or those which come after.  The
mountain limestone, indeed, deposited at the commencement of it,
abounds unusually in polypiaria and crinoidea; but when we ascend
to the coal-beds themselves, the case is altered, and these
marine remains altogether disappear.  We have then only a
limited variety of conchifers and shell mollusks, with fragments
of a few species of fishes, and these are rarely or never found
in the coal seams, but in the shales alternating with them. 
Some of the fishes are of a sauroid character, that is, partake
of the nature of the lizard, a genus of the reptilia, a land
class of animals, so that we may be said here to have the first
approach to a kind of animals calculated to breathe the
atmosphere.  Such is the Megalichthys Hibbertii, found by
Dr. Hibbert Ware, in a limestone bed of fresh-water origin,
underneath the coal at Burdiehouse, near Edinburgh.  Others
of the same kind have been found in the coal measures in
Yorkshire, and in the low coal shales at Manchester.  This
is no more than might be expected, as collections of fresh water
now existed, and it is presumable that they would be
peopled.  The chief other fishes of the coal era are named
palæothrissum, palæoniscus, diperdus.
Coal strata are nearly confined to the group termed the
carboniferous formation.  Thin beds are not unknown
afterwards, but they occur only as a rare exception.  It is
therefore thought that the most important of the conditions which
allowed of so abundant a terrestrial vegetation, had ceased about
the time when this formation was closed.  The high
temperature was not one of the conditions which terminated, for
there are evidences of it afterwards; but probably the
superabundance of carbonic acid gas supposed to have existed
during this era was expended before its close.  There can be
little doubt that the infusion of a large dose of this gas into
the atmosphere at the present day would be attended by precisely
the same circumstances as in the time of the carboniferous
formation.  Land animal life would not have a place on
earth; vegetation would be enormous; and coal strata would be
formed from the vast accumulations of woody matter, which would
gather in every sea, near the mouths of great rivers.  On
the exhaustion of the superabundance of carbonic acid gas, the
coal formation would cease, and the earth might again become a
suitable theatre of being for land animals.
The termination of the carboniferous formation is marked by
symptoms of volcanic violence, which some geologists have
considered to denote the close of one system of things and the
beginning of another.  Coal beds generally lie in basins, as
if following the curve of the bottom of seas.  But there is
no such basin which is not broken up into pieces, some of which
have been tossed up on edge, others allowed to sink, causing the
ends of strata to be in some instances many yards, and in a few
several hundred feet, removed from the corresponding ends of
neighbouring fragments.  These are held to be results of
volcanic movements below, the operation of which is further seen
in numerous upbursts and intrusions of volcanic rock
(trap).  That these disturbances took place about the close
of the formation, and not later, is shewn in the fact of the next
higher group of strata being comparatively undisturbed. 
Other symptoms of this time of violence are seen in the beds of
conglomerate which occur amongst the first strata above the
coal.  These, as usual, consist of fragments of the elder
rocks, more or less worn from being tumbled about in agitated
water, and laid down in a mud paste, afterwards hardened. 
Volcanic disturbances break up the rocks; the pieces are worn in
seas; and a deposit of conglomerate is the consequence.  Of
porphyry, there are some such pieces in the conglomerate of
Devonshire, three or four tons in weight.  It is to be
admitted for strict truth that, in some parts of Europe, the
carboniferous formation is followed by superior deposits, without
the appearance of such disturbances between their respective
periods; but apparently this case belongs to the class of
exceptions already noticed. [93]  That
disturbance was general, is supported by the further and
important fact of the destruction of many forms of organic being
previously flourishing, particularly of the vegetable
kingdom.</div></body></text></TEI>