<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="134">CHAPTER III.
Sequel to the Formation of Systematic Descriptive
Geology.

Sect. 1.—Reception and Diffusion of
Systematic Geology.
IF our nearness to the time of
the discoveries to which we have just referred, embarrasses us in
speaking of their authors, it makes it still more difficult to narrate
the reception with which these discoveries met. Yet here we may notice
a few facts which may not be without their interest.
The impression which Werner made upon his hearers was very strong;
and, as we have already said, disciples were gathered to his school
from every country, and then went forward into all parts of the world,
animated by the views which they had caught from him. We may say of
him, as has been so wisely said of a philosopher of a very different
kind,46 “He owed his influence to various
causes; at the head of which may be placed that genius for system,
which, though it cramps the growth of knowledge, perhaps finally
atones for that mischief by the zeal and activity which it rouses
among followers and opponents, who discover truth by accident, when in
pursuit of weapons for their warfare.” The list of Werner’s pupils for
a considerable period included most of the principal geologists of
Europe; Freisleben, Mohs, Esmark, d’Andrada, Raumer, Engelhart,
Charpentier, Brocchi. Alexander von Humboldt and Leopold von Buch went
forth from his school to observe America and Siberia, the Isles of the
Atlantic, and the coast of Norway. Professor Jameson established at
Edinburgh a Wernerian Society; and his lecture-room became a second
centre of Wernerian doctrines, whence proceeded many zealous
geological observers; among these we may mention as one of the most
distinguished, M. Ami Boué, though, like several others, he soon cast
away the peculiar opinions of the Wernerian school. The
classifications of this school were, however, diffused over the
civilized world with 524 extraordinary success; and were looked
upon with great respect, till the study of organic fossils threw them
into the shade.
46 Mackintosh on Hobbes,
Dissert. p. 177.
Smith, on the other hand, long pursued his own thoughts without aid
and without sympathy. About 1799 he became acquainted with a few
gentlemen (Dr. Anderson, Mr. Richardson, Mr. Townsend, and Mr.
Davies), who had already given some attention to organic fossils, and
who were astonished to find his knowledge so much more exact and
extensive than their own. From this time he conceived the intention of
publishing his discoveries; but the want of literary leisure and
habits long prevented him. His knowledge was orally communicated
without reserve to many persons; and thus gradually and insensibly
became part of the public stock. When this diffusion of his views had
gone on for some time, his friends began to complain that the author
of them was deprived of his well-merited share of fame. His delay in
publication made it difficult to remedy this wrong; for soon after he
published his Geological Map of England, another appeared, founded
upon separate observations; and though, perhaps, not quite independent
of his, yet in many respects much more detailed and correct. Thus,
though his general ideas obtained universal currency, he did not
assume his due prominence as a geologist. In 1818, a generous attempt
was made to direct a proper degree of public gratitude to him, in an
article in the Edinburgh Review, the production of Dr. Fitton,
a distinguished English geologist. And when the eminent philosopher,
Wollaston, had bequeathed to the Geological Society of London a fund
from which a gold medal was to be awarded to geological services, the
first of such medals was, in 1831, “given to Mr. William Smith, in
consideration of his being a great original discoverer in English
geology; and especially for his having been the first in this country
to discover and to teach the identification of strata, and to
determine their succession by means of their imbedded fossils.”
Cuvier’s discoveries, on the other hand, both from the high
philosophic fame of their author, and from their intrinsic importance,
arrested at once the attention of scientific Europe; and,
notwithstanding the undoubted priority of Smith’s labors, for a long
time were looked upon as the starting-point of our knowledge of
organic fossils. And, in reality, although Cuvier’s memoirs derived
the greatest part of their value from his zoological conclusions, they
reflected back no small portion of interest on the classifications of
strata which were involved in his inferences. And the views which he
presented gave to geology an attractive and striking character, and a
connexion with 525
large physiological as well as physical principles, which added
incomparably to its dignity and charm.
In tracing the reception and diffusion of doctrines such as those
of Smith and Cuvier, we ought not to omit to notice more especially
the formation and history of the Geological Society of London, just
mentioned. It was established in 1807, with a view to multiply and
record observations, and patiently to await the result of some future
period; that is, its founders resolved to apply themselves to
Descriptive Geology, thinking the time not come for that theoretical
geology which had then long fired the controversial ardor of
Neptunists and Plutonists. The first volume of the Transactions of
this society was published in 1811. The greater part of the contents
of this volume47 savor of the notions of the Wernerian
school; and there are papers on some of the districts in England most
rich in fossils, which Mr. Conybeare says, well exhibit the low state
of secondary geology at that period. But a paper by Mr. Parkinson
refers to the discoveries both of Smith and of Cuvier; and in the next
volume, Mr. Webster gives an account of the Isle of Wight, following
the admirable model of Cuvier and Brongniart’s account of the Paris
basin. “If we compare this memoir of Mr. Webster with the preceding
one of Dr. Berger (also of the Isle of Wight), they at once show
themselves to belong to two very distinct eras of science; and it is
difficult to believe that the interval which elapsed between their
respective publication was only three or four years.”48
47 Conybeare, Report. Brit.
Assoc. p. 372.
48 Conybeare, Report, p.
372.
Among the events belonging to the diffusion of sound geological
views in this country, we may notice the publication of a little
volume entitled, The Geology of England and Wales, by Mr.
Conybeare and Mr. Phillips, in 1821; an event far more important than,
from the modest form and character of the work, it might at first
sight appear. By describing in detail the geological structure and
circumstances of England (at least as far downwards as the coal), it
enabled a very wide class of readers to understand and verify the
classifications which geology had then very recently established;
while the extensive knowledge and philosophical spirit of Mr.
Conybeare rendered it, under the guise of a topographical enumeration,
in reality a profound and instructive scientific treatise. The vast
impulse which it gave to the study of sound descriptive geology was
felt and acknowledged in other countries, as well as in Britain. 526
Since that period, Descriptive Geology in England has constantly
advanced. The advance has been due mainly to the labors of the members
of the Geological Society; on whose merits as cultivators of their
science, none but those who are themselves masters of the subject,
have a right to dwell. Yet some parts of the scientific character of
these men may be appreciated by the general speculator; for they have
shown that there are no talents and no endowments which may not find
their fitting employment in this science. Besides that they have
united laborious research and comprehensive views, acuteness and
learning, zeal and knowledge; the philosophical eloquence with which
they have conducted their discussions has had a most beneficial
influence on the tone of their speculations; and their researches in
the field, which have carried them into every country and every class
of society, have given them that prompt and liberal spirit, and that
open and cordial bearing, which results from intercourse with the
world on a large and unfettered scale. It is not too much to say, that
in our time, Practical Geology has been one of the best schools of
philosophical and general culture of mind.
Sect. 2.—Application of Systematic Geology.
Geological Surveys and Maps.
Such surveys as that which
Conybeare and Phillips’s book presented with respect to England, were
not only a means of disseminating the knowledge implied in the
classifications of such a work, but they were also an essential part
of the Application and Extension of the principles established by the
founders of Systematic Geology. As soon as the truth of such a system
was generally acknowledged, the persuasion of the propriety of
geological surveys and maps of each country could not but impress
itself on men’s minds.
When the earlier writers, as Lister and Fontenelle, spoke of
mineralogical and fossilological maps, they could hardly be said to
know the meaning of the terms which they thus used. But when
subsequent classifications had shown how such a suggestion might be
carried into effect, and to what important consequences it might lead,
the task was undertaken in various countries in a vigorous and
consistent manner. In England, besides Smith’s map, another, drawn up
by Mr. Greenough, was published by the Geological Society in 1819;
and, being founded on very numerous observations of the author and his
friends, made with great labor and cost, was not only an important
527 correction and
confirmation of Smith’s labors, but a valuable storehouse and standard
of what had then been done in English geology. Leopold von Buch had
constructed a geological map of a large portion of Germany, about the
same period; but, aware of the difficulty of the task he had thus
attempted, he still forbore to publish it. At a later period, and as
materials accumulated, more detailed maps of parts of Germany were
produced by Hoffmann and others. The French government entrusted to a
distinguished Professor of the School of Mines (M. Brochant de
Villiers), the task of constructing a map of France on the model of
Mr. Greenough’s; associating with him two younger persons, selected
for their energy and talents, MM. Beaumont and Dufrénoy. We shall have
occasion hereafter to speak of the execution
of this survey. By various persons, geological maps of almost every
country and province of Europe, and of many parts of Asia and America,
have been published. I need not enumerate these, but I may refer to
the account given of them by Mr. Conybeare, in the Reports of the
British Association for 1832, p. 384. These various essays may be
considered as contributions, though hitherto undoubtedly very
imperfect ones, to that at which Descriptive Geology ought to aim, and
which is requisite as a foundation for sound theory;—a complete
geological survey of the whole earth. But we must say a few words
respecting the language in which such a survey must be written.
As we have already said, that condition which made such maps and
the accompanying descriptions possible, was that the strata and their
contents had previously undergone classification and arrangement at
the hands of the fathers of geology. Classification, in this as in
other cases, implied names which should give to the classes
distinctness and permanence; and when the series of strata belonging
to one country were referred to in the description of another, in
which they appeared, as was usually the case, under an aspect at least
somewhat different, the supposed identification required a peculiar
study of each case; and thus Geology had arrived at the point, which
we have before had to notice as one of the stages of the progress of
Classificatory Botany, at which a technical nomenclature and a
well-understood synonymy were essential parts of the
science.
Sect. 3.—Geological Nomenclature.
By Nomenclature we mean a
system of names; and hence we can 528 not speak of a Geological Nomenclature
till we come to Werner and Smith. The earlier mineralogists had
employed names, often artificial and arbitrary, for special minerals,
but no technical and constant names for strata. The elements of
Werner’s names for the members of his geological series were words in
use among miners, as Gneiss, Grauwacke,
Thonschiefer, Rothe todte liegende, Zechstein; or
arbitrary names of the mineralogists, as Syenite, Serpentine,
Porphyry, Granite. But the more technical part of his phraseology was
taken from that which is the worst kind of name, arbitrary numeration.
Thus he had his first sandstone formation, second
sandstone, third sandstone; first flötz limestone,
second flötz limestone, third flötz limestone. Such
names are, beyond all others, liable to mistake in their application,
and likely to be expelled by the progress of knowledge; and
accordingly, though the Wernerian names for rocks mineralogically
distinguished, have still some currency, his sandstones and
limestones, after creating endless confusion while his authority had
any sway, have utterly disappeared from good geological works.
The nomenclature of Smith was founded upon English provincial terms
of very barbarous aspect, as Cornbrash, Lias,
Gault, Clunch Clay, Coral Rag. Yet these terms
were widely diffused when his classification was generally accepted;
they kept their place, precisely because they had no systematic
signification; and many of them are at present part of the geological
language of the whole civilized world.
Another kind of names which has been very prevalent among
geologists are those borrowed from places. Thus the Wernerians spoke
of Alpine Limestone and Jura Limestone; the English, of Kimmeridge
Clay and Oxford Clay, Purbeck Marble, and Portland Rock. These names,
referring to the stratum of a known locality as a type, were good, as
far as an identity with that type had been traced; but when this had
been incompletely done, they were liable to great ambiguity. If the
Alps or the Jura contain several formations of limestone, such terms
as we have noticed, borrowed from those mountains, cease to be
necessarily definite, and may give rise to much confusion.
Descriptive names, although they might be supposed to be the best,
have, in fact, rarely been fortunate. The reason of this is
obvious;—the mark which has been selected for description may
easily fail to be essential; and the obvious connexions of natural
facts may overleap the arbitrary definition. As we have already stated
in the history of botany, the establishment of descriptive marks of
real classes presupposes the important but difficult step, of the
discovery of such marks. 529 Hence those descriptive names only have
been really useful in geology which had been used without any
scrupulous regard to the appropriateness of the description. The
Green Sand may be white, brown, or red; the Mountain
Limestone may occur only in valleys; the Oolite may have no
roe-like structure; and yet these may be excellent geological names,
if they be applied to formations geologically identical with those
which the phrases originally designated. The signification may assist
the memory, but must not be allowed to subjugate the faculty of
natural classification.
The terms which have been formed by geologists in recent times have
been drawn from sources similar to those of the older ones, and will
have their fortune determined by the same conditions. Thus Mr. Lyell
has given to the divisions of the tertiary strata the appellations
Pleiocene, Meiocene, Eocene, accordingly as they
contain a majority of recent species of shells, a
minority of such species, or a small proportion of living
species, which may be looked upon as indicating the dawn of the
existing state of the animate creation. But in this case, he wisely
treats his distinctions, not as definitions, but as the marks of
natural groups. “The plurality of species indicated by the name
pleiocene must not,” he says,49 “be understood
to imply an absolute majority of recent fossil shells in all cases,
but a comparative preponderance wherever the pleiocene are contrasted
with strata of the period immediately preceding.”
49 Geol. iii. 392.
Mr. Lyell might have added, that no precise percentage of recent
species, nor any numerical criterion whatever, can be allowed to
overbear the closer natural relations of strata, proved by evidence of
a superior kind, if such can be found. And this would be the proper
answer to the objection made by De la Beche to these names; namely,
that it may happen that the meiocene rocks of one country may
be of the same date as the pleiocene of another; the same
formation having in one place a majority, in another a minority, of
existing species. We are not to run into this incongruity, for we are
not so to apply the names. The formation which has been called
pleiocene, must continue to be so called, even where the majority of
recent species fails; and all rocks that agree with that in date,
without further reference to the numerical relations of their fossils,
must also share in the name.
To invent good names for these large divisions of the series of
strata is indeed extremely difficult. The term Oolite is an
instance in which 530 a descriptive word has become permanent
in a case of this kind; and, in imitation of it, Pœcilite (from
ποικίλος, various,) has been proposed by Mr. Conybeare50 as a name for
the group of strata inferior to the oolites, of which the
Variegated Sandstone (Bunter Sandstein, Grès Bigarré,) is a
conspicuous member. For the series of formations which lies
immediately over the rocks in which no organic remains are found, the
term Transition was long used, but with extreme ambiguity and
vagueness. When this series, or rather the upper part of it, was well
examined in South Wales, where it consists of many well-marked
members, and may be probably taken as a type for a large portion of
the rest of the world, it became necessary to give to the group thus
explored a name not necessarily leading to assumption or controversy.
Mr. Murchison selected the term Silurian, borrowed from the
former inhabitants of the country in which his types were found; and
this is a term excellent in many respects; but one which will probably
not quite supersede “Transition,” because, in other places, transition
rocks occur which correspond to none of the members of the Silurian
region.
50 Report, p. 379.
Though new names are inevitable accompaniments of new views of
classification, and though, therefore, the geological discoverer must
be allowed a right to coin them, this is a privilege which, for the
sake of his own credit, and the circulation of his tokens, he must
exercise with great temperance and judgment. M. Brongniart may be
taken as an example of the neglect of this caution. Acting upon the
principle, in itself a sound one, that inconveniences arise from
geological terms which have a mineralogical signification, he has
given an entirely new list of names of the members of the geological
series. Thus the primitive unstratified rocks are terrains
agalysiens; the transition semi-compact are hemilysiens;
the sedimentary strata are yzemiens; the diluvial deposits are
clysmiens; and these divisions are subdivided by designations
equally novel; thus of the “terrains yzemiens,” members are—the
terrains clastiques, tritoniens, protéïques,
palæotheriens, epilymniques, thalassiques.51 Such a nomenclature appears to labor
under great inconveniences, since the terms are descriptive in their
derivation, yet are not generally intelligible, and refer to
theoretical views yet have not the recommendation of systematic
connexion.
51 Brongniart, Tableau des
Terrains, 1829. 531
Sect. 4.—Geological Synonymy, or Determination of
Geological Equivalents.
It will easily be supposed
that with so many different sources of names as we have mentioned, the
same stratum may be called by different designations; and thus a
synonymy may be necessary for geology; as it was for botany in the
time of Bauhin, when the same plants had been spoken of by so many
different appellations in different authors. But in reality, the
synonymy of geology is a still more important part of the subject than
the analogy of botany would lead us to suppose. For in plants, the
species are really fixed, and easily known when seen; and the
ambiguity is only in the imperfect communication or confused ideas of
the observers. But in geology, the identity of a stratum or formation
in different places, though not an arbitrary, may be a very doubtful
matter, even to him who has seen and examined. To assign its right
character and place to a stratum in a new country, is, in a great
degree, to establish the whole geological history of the country. To
assume that the same names may rightly be applied to the strata of
different countries, is to take for granted, not indeed the Wernerian
dogma of universal formations, but a considerable degree of generality
and uniformity in the known formations. And how far this generality
and uniformity prevail, observation alone can teach. The search for
geological synonyms in different countries brings before us two
questions;—first, are there such synonyms? and only in
the second place, and as far as they occur, what are
they?
In fact, it is found that although formations which must be
considered as geologically identical (because otherwise no
classification is possible,) do extend over large regions, and pass
from country to country, their identity includes certain
modifications; and the determination of the identity and of the
modifications are inseparably involved with each other, and almost
necessarily entangled with theoretical considerations. And in two
countries, in which we find this modified coincidence, instead of
saying that the strata are identical, and that their designations are
synonyms, we may, with more propriety, consider them as two
corresponding series; of which the members of the one may be treated
as the Representatives or Equivalents of the members of
the other.
This doctrine of Representatives or Equivalents supposes that the
geological phenomena in the two countries have been the results of
532 similar series
of events, which have, in some measure, coincided in time and order;
and thus, as we have said, refers us to a theory. But yet, considered
merely as a step in classification, the comparison of the geological
series of strata in different countries is, in the highest degree,
important and interesting. Indeed in the same manner in which the
separation of Classificatory from Chemical Mineralogy is necessary for
the completion of mineralogical science, the comparative
Classification of the strata of different countries according to their
resemblances and differences alone, is requisite as a basis for a
Theory of their causes. But, as will easily be imagined from its
nature, this part of descriptive geology deals with the most difficult
and the most elevated problems; and requires a rare union of laborious
observation with a comprehensive spirit of philosophical
classification.
In order to give instances of this process (for of the vast labor
and great talents which have been thus employed in England, France,
and Germany, it is only instances that we can give,) I may refer to
the geological survey of France, which was executed, as we have
already stated, by order of the government. In this undertaking it was
intended to obtain a knowledge of the whole mineral structure of
France; but no small portion of this knowledge was brought into view,
when a synonymy had been established between the Secondary Rocks of
France and the corresponding members of the English and German series,
which had been so well studied as to have become classical points of
standard reference. For the purpose of doing this, the principal
directors of the survey, MM. Brochant de Villiers, De Beaumont, and
Dufrénoy, came to England in 1822, and following the steps of the best
English geologists, in a few months made themselves acquainted with
the English series. They then returned to France, and, starting from
the chalk of Paris in various directions, travelled on the lines which
carried them over the edges of the strata which emerge from beneath
the chalk, identifying, as they could, the strata with their foreign
analogues. They thus recognized almost all of the principal beds of
the oolitic series of England.52 At the same
time they found differences as well as resemblances. Thus the Portland
and Kimmeridge beds of France were found to contain in abundance a
certain shell, the gryphæa virgula, which had not before been
much remarked in those beds in England. With regard to the synonyms in
Germany, on the other hand, a difference of opinion 533 arose between M. Elie
de Beaumont and M. Voltz,53 the former considering the Grès de
Vosges as the equivalent of the Rothe todte liegende, which
occurs beneath the Zechstein, while M. Voltz held that it was the
lower portion of the Red or Variegated Sandstone which rests on
the Zechstein.
52 De la Beche, Manual,
305.
53 De la Beche, Manual,
381.
In the same manner, from the first promulgation of the Wernerian
system, attempts were made to identify the English with the German
members of the geological alphabet; but it was long before this
alphabet was rightly read. Thus the English geologists who first tried
to apply the Wernerian series to this country, conceived the Old and
New Red Sandstone of England to be the same with the Old and New Red
Sandstone of Werner; whereas Werner’s Old Red, the Rothe todte
liegende, is above the coal, while the English Old Red is below it.
This mistake led to a further erroneous identification of our Mountain
Limestone with Werner’s First Flötz Limestone; and caused an almost
inextricable confusion, which, even at a recent period, has perplexed
the views of German geologists respecting this country. Again, the
Lias of England was, at first, supposed to be the equivalent of the
Muschelkalk of Germany. But the error of this identification was
brought into view by examinations and discussions in which MM.
Œyenhausen and Dechen took the lead; and at a later period, Professor
Sedgwick, by a laborious examination of the strata of England, was
enabled to show the true relation of this part of the geology of the
two countries. According to him, the New Red Sandstone of England,
considered as one great complex formation, may be divided into seven
members, composed of sandstones, limestones, and marls; five of which
represent respectively the Rothe todte liegende; the Kupfer
schiefer; the Zechstein, (with the Rauchwacké,
Asche, and Stinkstein of the Thuringenwald;) the
Bunter sandstein; and the Keuper: while the
Muschelkalk, which lies between the two last members of the
German list, has not yet been discovered in our geological series.
“Such a coincidence,” he observes,54 “in the
subdivisions of two distant mechanical deposits, even upon the
supposition of their being strictly contemporaneous, is truly
astonishing. It has not been assumed hypothetically, but is the fair
result of the facts which are recorded in this paper.”
54 Geol. Trans. Second Series,
iii. 121.
As an example in which the study of geological equivalents becomes
still more difficult, we may notice the attempts to refer the strata
of 534 the Alps to
those of the north-west of Europe. The dark-colored marbles and
schists resembling mica slate55 were, during
the prevalence of the Wernerian theory, referred, as was natural, to
the transition class. The striking physical characters of this
mountain region, and its long-standing celebrity as a subject of
mineralogical examination, made a complete subversion of the received
opinion respecting its place in the geological series, an event of
great importance in the history of the science. Yet this was what
occurred when Dr. Buckland, in 1820, threw his piercing glance upon
this district. He immediately pointed out that these masses, by their
fossils, approach to the Oolitic Series of this country. From this
view it followed, that the geological equivalents of that series were
to be found among rocks in which the mineralogical characters were
altogether different, and that the loose limestones of England
represent some of the highly-compact and crystalline marbles of Italy
and Greece. This view was confirmed by subsequent investigations; and
the correspondence was traced, not only in the general body of the
formations, but in the occurrence of the Red Marl at its bottom, and
the Green Sand and Chalk at its top.
55 De la Beche, Manual,
313.
The talents and the knowledge which such tasks require are of no
ordinary kind; nor, even with a consummate acquaintance with the
well-ascertained formations, can the place of problematical strata be
decided without immense labor. Thus the examination and delineation of
hundreds of shells by the most skilful conchologists, has been thought
necessary in order to determine whether the calcareous beds of
Maestricht and of Gosau are or are not intermediate, as to their
organic contents, between the chalk and the tertiary formations. And
scarcely any point of geological classification can be settled without
a similar union of the accomplished naturalist with the laborious
geological collector.
It follows from the views already presented, of this part of
geology, that no attempt to apply to distant countries the names by
which the well-known European strata have been described, can be of
any value, if not accompanied by a corresponding attempt to show how
far the European series is really applicable. This must be borne in
mind in estimating the import of the geological accounts which have
been given of various parts of Asia, Africa, and America. For
instance, when the carboniferous group and the new red sandstone are
stated to 535 be
found in India, we require to be assured that these formations are, in
some way, the equivalents of their synonyms in countries better
explored. Till this is done, the results of observation in such places
would be better conveyed by a nomenclature implying only those facts
of resemblance, difference, and order, which have been ascertained in
the country so described. We know that serious errors were incurred by
the attempts made to identify the Tertiary strata of other countries
with those first studied in the Paris basin. Fancied points of
resemblance, Mr. Lyell observes, were magnified into undue importance,
and essential differences in mineral character and organic contents
were slurred over.
[2nd Ed.] [The extension of geological surveys, the construction of
geological maps, and the determination of the geological equivalents
which replace each other in various countries, have been carried on in
continuation of the labors mentioned above, with enlarged activity,
range, and means. It is estimated that one-third of the land of each
hemisphere has been geologically explored; and that thus Descriptive
Geology has now been prosecuted so far, that it is not likely that
even the extension of it to the whole globe would give any material
novelty of aspect to Theoretical Geology. The recent literature of the
subject is so voluminous that it is impossible for me to give any
account of it here; very imperfectly acquainted, as I am, even with
the English portion, and still more, with what has been produced in
other countries.
While I admire the energetic and enlightened labors by which the
philosophers of France, Belgium, Germany, Italy, Russia, and America,
have promoted scientific geology, I may be allowed to rejoice to see
in the very phraseology of the subject, the evidence that English
geologists have not failed to contribute their share to the latest
advances in the science. The following order of strata proceeding
upwards is now, I think, recognized throughout Europe. The
Silurian; the Devonian (Old Red Sandstone;) the
Carboniferous; the Permian, (Lower part of the new Red
Sandstone series;) the Trias, (Upper three members of the New
Red Sandstone series;) the Lias; the Oolite, (in which
are reckoned by M. D’Orbigny the Etages Bathonien,
Oxonien, Kimmeridgien, and Portlandien;) the
Neocomien, (Lower Green Sand,) the Chalk; and above these,
Tertiary and Supra-Tertiary beds. Of these, the Silurian, described by
Sir R. Murchison from its types in South Wales, has been traced by
European Geologists through the Ardennes, Servia, Turkey, the shores
of the Gulf of Finland, the valley 536 of the Mississippi, the west coast of
North America, and the mountains of South America. Again, the labors
of Prof. Sedgwick and Sir R. Murchison, in 1836, ’7, and ’8, aided by
the sagacity of Mr. Lonsdale, led to their placing certain rocks of
Devon and Cornwall as a formation intermediate between the Silurian
and Carboniferous Series; and the Devonian System thus established has
been accepted by geologists in general, and has been traced, not only
in various parts of Europe, but in Australia and Tasmania, and in the
neighborhood of the Alleganies.
Above the Carboniferous Series, Sir R. Murchison and his fellow
laborers, M. de Verneuil and Count Keyserling, have found in Russia a
well-developed series of rocks occupying the ancient kingdom of
Permia, which they have hence called the Permian formation; and
this term also has found general acceptance. The next group, the
Keuper, Muschelkalk, and Bunter Sandstein of Germany, has been termed
Trias by the continental geologists. The Neocomien is
called from Neuchatel, where it is largely developed. Below all these
rocks come, in England, the Cambrian on which Prof. Sedgwick
has expended so many years of valuable labor. The comparison of the
Protozoic and Hypozoic rocks of different countries is probably still
incomplete.
The geologists of North America have made great progress in
decyphering and describing the structure of their own country; and
they have wisely gone, in a great measure, upon the plan which I have
commended at the end of the third Chapter;—they have compared the rocks of
their own country with each other, and given to the different beds and
formations names borrowed from their own localities. This course will facilitate rather than impede the redaction of
their classification to its synonyms and equivalents in the old
world.
Of course it is not to be expected nor desired that books belonging
to Descriptive Geology shall exclude the other two branches of the
subject, Geological Dynamics and Physical Geology. On the contrary,
among the most valuable contributions to both these departments have
been speculations appended to descriptive works. And this is naturally
and rightly more and more the case as the description embraces a wider
field. The noble work On the Geology of Russia and the Urals,
by Sir Roderick Murchison and his companions, is a great example of
this, as of other merits in a geological book. The author introduces
into his pages the various portions of geological dynamics of which I
shall have to speak afterwards; and thus endeavors to make out the
537 physical
history of the region, the boundaries of its raised sea bottoms, the
shores of the great continent on which the mammoths lived, the period
when the gold ore was formed, and when the watershed of the Ural chain
was elevated.]
</div></body></text></TEI>