<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="8">CHAPTER III.
Earliest Stages of Harmonics.
AMONG the ancients, the
science of Music was an application of Arithmetic, as Optics and
Mechanics were of Geometry. The story which is told concerning the
origin of their arithmetical music, is the following, as it stands in
the Arithmetical Treatise of Nicomachus.
Pythagoras, walking one day, meditating on the means of measuring
musical notes, happened to pass near a blacksmith’s shop, and had his
attention arrested by hearing the hammers, as they struck the anvil,
produce the sounds which had a musical relation to each other. On
listening further, he found that the intervals were a Fourth, a Fifth,
and an Octave; and on weighing the hammers, it appeared that the one
which gave the Octave was one-half the heaviest, the one which
gave the Fifth was two-thirds, and the one which gave the
Fourth was three-quarters. He returned home, reflected upon
this phenomenon, made trials, and finally discovered, that if he
stretched musical strings of equal lengths, by weights which have the
proportion of one-half, two-thirds, and three-fourths, they produced
intervals which were an Octave, a Fifth, and a Fourth. This
observation gave an arithmetical measure of the principal Musical
Intervals, and made Music an arithmetical subject of speculation.
This story, if not entirely a philosophical fable, is undoubtedly
inaccurate; for the musical intervals thus spoken of would not be
produced by striking with hammers of the weights there stated. But it
is true that the notes of strings have a definite relation to the
forces which stretch them; and this truth is still the groundwork of
the theory of musical concords and discords.
Nicomachus says that Pythagoras found the weights to be, as I have
mentioned, in the proportion of 12, 6, 8, 9; and the intervals, an
Octave, corresponding to the proportion 12 to 6, or 2 to 1; a Fifth,
corresponding to the proportion 12 to 8, or 3 to 2; and a Fourth,
corresponding to the proportion 12 to 9, or 4 to 3. There is no doubt
that this statement of the ancient writer is inexact as to the
physical fact, for the rate of vibration of a string, on which its
note depends, is, 106 other things being equal, not as the
weight, but as the square root of the weight. But he is right as to
the essential point, that those ratios of 2 to 1, 3 to 2, and 4 to 3,
are the characteristic ratios of the Octave, Fifth, and Fourth. In
order to produce these intervals, the appended weights must be, not as
12, 9, 8, and 6, but as 12, 6¾, 5⅓, and 3.
The numerical relations of the other intervals of the musical
scale, as well as of the Octave, Fifth, and Fourth, were discovered by
the Greeks. Thus they found that the proportion in a Major Third was 5
to 4; in a Minor Third, 6 to 5; in a Major Tone, 9 to 8; in a Semitone
or Diesis, 16 to 15. They even went so far as to determine the
Comma, in which the interval of two notes is so small that they
are in the proportion of 81 to 80. This is the interval between two
notes, each of which may be called the Seventeenth above the
key-note;—the one note being obtained by ascending a Fifth four
times over; the other being obtained by ascending through two Octaves
and a Major Third. The want of exact coincidence between these two
notes is an inherent arithmetical imperfection in the musical scale,
of which the consequences are very extensive.
The numerical properties of the musical scale were worked out to a
very great extent by the Greeks, and many of their Treatises on this
subject remain to us. The principal ones are the seven authors
published by Meibomius.2 These arithmetical elements of Music are
to the present day important and fundamental portions of the Science
of Harmonics.
2 Antiquæ Musicæ Scriptores
septem, 1652.
It may at first appear that the truth, or even the possibility of
this history, by referring the discovery to accident, disproves our
doctrine, that this, like all other fundamental discoveries, required
a distinct and well-pondered Idea as its condition. In this, however,
as in all cases of supposed accidental discoveries in science, it will
be found, that it was exactly the possession of such an Idea which
made the accident possible.
Pythagoras, assuming the truth of the tradition, must have had an
exact and ready apprehension of those relations of musical sounds,
which are called respectively an Octave, a Fifth, and a Fourth. If he
had not been able to conceive distinctly this relation, and to
apprehend it when heard, the sounds of the anvil would have struck his
ears to no more purpose than they did those of the smiths themselves.
He 107 must have
had, too, a ready familiarity with numerical ratios; and, moreover
(that in which, probably, his superiority most consisted), a
disposition to connect one notion with the other—the musical
relation with the arithmetical, if it were found possible. When the
connection was once suggested, it was easy to devise experiments by
which it might be confirmed.
“The philosophers of the Pythagorean School,3 and in particular,
Lasus of Hermione, and Hippasus of Metapontum, made many such
experiments upon strings; varying both their lengths and the weights
which stretched them; and also upon vessels filled with water, in a
greater or less degree.” And thus was established that connection of
the Idea with the Fact, which this Science, like all others,
requires.
3 Montucla, iii. 10.

I shall quit the Physical Sciences of Ancient Greece, with the
above brief statement of the discovery of the fundamental principles
which they involved; not only because such initial steps must always
be the most important in the progress of science, but because, in
reality, the Greeks made no advances beyond these. There took place
among them no additional inductive processes, by which new facts were
brought under the dominion of principles, or by which principles were
presented in a more comprehensive shape than before. Their advance
terminated in a single stride. Archimedes had stirred the intellectual
world, but had not put it in progressive motion: the science of
Mechanics stopped where he left it. And though, in some objects, as in
Harmonics, much was written, the works thus produced consisted of
deductions from the fundamental principles, by means of arithmetical
calculations; occasionally modified, indeed, by reference to the
pleasures which music, as an art, affords, but not enriched by any new
scientific truths.
[3d Ed.] We should, however, quit the philosophy of the ancient
Greeks without a due sense of the obligations which Physical Science
in all succeeding ages owes to the acute and penetrating spirit in
which their inquiries in that region of human knowledge were
conducted, and to the large and lofty aspirations which were
displayed, even in their failure, if we did not bear in mind both the
multifarious and comprehensive character of their attempts, and some
of the causes which limited their progress in positive science. They
speculated and 108
theorized under a lively persuasion that a Science of every part of
nature was possible, and was a fit object for the exercise of man’s
best faculties; and they were speedily led to the conviction that such
a science must clothe its conclusions in the language of mathematics.
This conviction is eminently conspicuous in the writings of Plato. In
the Republic, in the Epinomis, and above all in the
Timæus, this conviction makes him return, again and again, to a
discussion of the laws which had been established or conjectured in
his time, respecting Harmonics and Optics, such as we have seen, and
still more, respecting Astronomy, such as we shall see in the next
Book. Probably no succeeding step in the discovery of the Laws of
Nature was of so much importance as the full adoption of this
pervading conviction, that there must be Mathematical Laws of Nature,
and that it is the business of Philosophy to discover these Laws. This
conviction continues, through all the succeeding ages of the history
of science, to be the animating and supporting principle of scientific
investigation and discovery. And, especially in Astronomy, many of the
erroneous guesses which the Greeks made, contain, if not the germ, at
least the vivifying life-blood, of great truths, reserved for future
ages.
Moreover, the Greeks not only sought such theories of special parts
of nature, but a general Theory of the Universe. An essay at such a
theory is the Timæus of Plato; too wide and too ambitious an
attempt to succeed at that time; or, indeed, on the scale on which he
unfolds it, even in our time; but a vigorous and instructive example
of the claim which man’s Intellect feels that it may make to
understand the universal frame of things, and to render a reason for
all that is presented to it by the outward senses.
Further; we see in Plato, that one of the grounds of
the failure in this attempt, was the assumption that the reason
why every thing is what it is and as it is, must be that so it is
best, according to some view of better or worse attainable by
man. Socrates, in his dying conversation, as given in the
Phædo, declares this to have been what he sought in the
philosophy of his time; and tells his friends that he turned away from
the speculations of Anaxagoras because they did not give him such
reasons for the constitution of the world; and Plato’s Timæus
is, in reality, an attempt to supply this deficiency, and to present a
Theory of the Universe, in which every thing is accounted for by such
reasons. Though this is a failure, it is a noble as well as an
instructive failure.   ~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~ 


BOOK III.

HISTORY
OF
GREEK ASTRONOMY.

Τόδε δὲ μηδείς ποτε φοβηθῇ τῶν Ἑλλήνων, ὡς οὐ χρὴ περὶ τὰ θεῖα ποτὲ
πραγματεύεσθαι θνητοὺς ὄντας· πᾶν δε τούτου διανοηθῆναι τοὐναντίον, ὡς
οὔτε ἄφρον ἔστι ποτὲ τὸ θεῖον, οὔτε ἀγνοεῖ που τὴν ἀνθρωπίνην φυσιν·
ἀλλ’ οἶδεν ὅτι, διδάσκοντος αὐτοῦ, ξυνακολουθήσει καὶ μαθήσεται τὰ
διδάσκομενα.—Plato, Epinomis, p.
988.
Nor should any Greek have any misgiving of this kind; that it is
not fitting for us to inquire narrowly into the operations of Superior
Powers, such as those by which the motions of the heavenly bodies are
produced: but, on the contrary, men should consider that the Divine
Powers never act without purpose, and that they know the nature of
man: they know that by their guidance and aid, man may follow and
comprehend the lessons which are vouchsafed him on such
subjects.
</div></body></text></TEI>