<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="39">

CHAPTER XXX.
OF REAL AND FANTASTICAL IDEAS.

1. Ideas considered in reference to their Archetypes.


Besides what we have already mentioned concerning ideas, other considerations
belong to them, in reference to THINGS FROM WHENCE THEY ARE TAKEN, or WHICH
THEY MAY BE SUPPOSED TO REPRESENT; and thus, I think, they may come under a
threefold distinction, and are:—First, either real or fantastical;
Secondly, adequate or inadequate; Thirdly, true or false.


First, by REAL IDEAS, I mean such as have a foundation in nature; such as have
a conformity with the real being and existence of things, or with their
archetypes. FANTASTICAL or CHIMERICAL, I call such as have no foundation in
nature, nor have any conformity with that reality of being to which they are
tacitly referred, as to their archetypes. If we examine the several sorts of
ideas before mentioned, we shall find that,


2. Simple Ideas are all real appearances of things.


First, Our SIMPLE IDEAS are all real, all agree to the reality of things: not
that they are all of them the images or representations of what does exist; the
contrary whereof, in all but the primary qualities of bodies, hath been already
shown. But, though whiteness and coldness are no more in snow than pain is; yet
those ideas of whiteness and coldness, pain, &c., being in us the effects
of powers in things without us, ordained by our Maker to produce in us such
sensations; they are real ideas in us, whereby we distinguish the qualities
that are really in things themselves. For, these several appearances being
designed to be the mark whereby we are to know and distinguish things which we
have to do with, our ideas do as well serve us to that purpose, and are as real
distinguishing characters, whether they be only CONSTANT EFFECTS, or else EXACT
RESEMBLANCES of something in the things themselves: the reality lying in that
steady correspondence they have with the distinct constitutions of real beings.
But whether they answer to those constitutions, as to causes or patterns, it
matters not; it suffices that they are constantly produced by them. And thus
our simple ideas are all real and true, because they answer and agree to those
powers of things which produce them on our minds; that being all that is
requisite to make them real, and not fictions at pleasure. For in simple ideas
(as has been shown) the mind is wholly confined to the operation of things upon
it, and can make to itself no simple idea, more than what it was received.


3. Complex Ideas are voluntary Combinations.


Though the mind be wholly passive in respect of its simple ideas; yet, I think,
we may say it is not so in respect of its complex ideas. For those being
combinations of simple ideas put together, and united under one general name,
it is plain that the mind of man uses some kind of liberty in forming those
complex ideas: how else comes it to pass that one man’s idea of gold, or
justice, is different from another’s, but because he has put in, or left out of
his, some simple idea which the other has not? The question then is, Which of
these are real, and which barely imaginary combinations? What collections agree
to the reality of things, and what not? And to this I say that,


4. Mixed Modes and Relations, made of consistent Ideas, are real.


Secondly, MIXED MODES and RELATIONS, having no other reality but what they have
in the minds of men, there is nothing more required to this kind of ideas to
make them real, but that they be so framed, that there be a possibility of
existing conformable to them. These ideas themselves, being archetypes, cannot
differ from their archetypes, and so cannot be chimerical, unless any one will
jumble together in them inconsistent ideas. Indeed, as any of them have the
names of a known language assigned to them, by which he that has them in his
mind would signify them to others, so bare possibility of existing is not
enough; they must have a conformity to the ordinary signification of the name
that is given them, that they may not be thought fantastical: as if a man would
give the name of justice to that idea which common use calls liberality. But
this fantasticalness relates more to propriety of speech, than reality of
ideas. For a man to be undisturbed in danger, sedately to consider what is
fittest to be done, and to execute it steadily, is a mixed mode, or a complex
idea of an action which may exist. But to be undisturbed in danger, without
using one’s reason or industry, is what is also possible to be; and so is as
real an idea as the other. Though the first of these, having the name COURAGE
given to it, may, in respect of that name, be a right or wrong idea; but the
other, whilst it has not a common received name of any known language assigned
to it, is not capable of any deformity, being made with no reference to
anything but itself.


5. Complex Ideas of Substances are real, when they agree with the existence of
Things.


Thirdly, Our complex ideas of SUBSTANCES, being made all of them in reference
to things existing without us, and intended to be representations of substances
as they really are, are no further real than as they are such combinations of
simple ideas as are really united, and co-exist in things without us. On the
contrary, those are fantastical which are made up of such collections of simple
ideas as were really never united, never were found together in any substance:
v. g. a rational creature, consisting of a horse’s head, joined to a body of
human shape, or such as the CENTAURS are described: or, a body yellow, very
malleable, fusible, and fixed, but lighter than common water: or an uniform,
unorganized body, consisting, as to sense, all of similar parts, with
perception and voluntary motion joined to it. Whether such substances as these
can possibly exist or no, it is probable we do not know: but be that as it
will, these ideas of substances, being made conformable to no pattern existing
that we know; and consisting of such collections of ideas as no substance ever
showed us united together, they ought to pass with us for barely imaginary: but
much more are those complex ideas so, which contain in them any inconsistency
or contradiction of their parts.


</div></body></text></TEI>