<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="116">CHAPTER II.
Unsystematic Knowledge of Plants.
A STEP was made towards the
formation of the Science of Plants, although undoubtedly a slight one,
as soon as men began to collect information concerning them and their
properties, from a love and reverence for knowledge, independent of
the passion for the marvellous and the impulse of practical utility.
This step was very early made. The “wisdom” of Solomon, and the
admiration which was bestowed upon it, prove, even at that period,
such a working of the speculative faculty: and we are told, that among
other evidences of his being “wiser than all men,” “he spake of trees,
from the cedar-tree that is in Lebanon even unto the hyssop that
springeth out of the wall.”9 The father of history, Herodotus, shows
us that a taste for natural history had, in his time, found a place in
the minds of the Greeks. In speaking of the luxuriant vegetation of
the Babylonian plain,10 he is so far from desiring to astonish
merely, that he says, “the blades of wheat and barley are full four
fingers wide; but as to the size of the trees which grow from millet
and sesame, though I could mention it, I will not; knowing well that
those who have not been in that country will hardly believe what I
have said already.” He then proceeds to describe some remarkable
circumstances respecting the fertilization of the date-palms in
Assyria.
9 1 Kings iv. 33.
10 Herod. i. 193.
This curious and active spirit of the Greeks led rapidly, as we
have seen in other instances, to attempts at collecting and
systematizing knowledge on almost every subject: and in this, as in
almost every other department, Aristotle may be fixed upon, as the
representative of the highest stage of knowledge and system which they
ever attained. The vegetable kingdom, like every other province of
nature, was one of the fields of the labors of this universal
philosopher. But though his other works on natural history have come
down to us, and are a most valuable monument of the state of such
knowledge in his time, his Treatise on Plants is lost. The book De
Plantis 362
which appears with his name, is an imposture of the middle ages, full
of errors and absurdities.11
11 Mirbel, Botanique, ii.
505.
His disciple, friend, and successor, Theophrastus of Eresos, is, as
we have said already, the first great writer on botany whose works we
possess; and, as may be said in most cases of the first great writer,
he offers to us a richer store of genuine knowledge and good sense
than all his successors. But we find in him that the Greeks of his
time, who aspired, as we have said, to collect and
systematize a body of information on every subject, failed in
one half of their object, as far as related to the vegetable world.
Their attempts at a systematic distribution of plants were altogether
futile. Although Aristotle’s divisions of the animal kingdom are, even
at this day, looked upon with admiration by the best naturalists, the
arrangements and comparisons of plants which were contrived by
Theophrastus and his successors, have not left the slightest trace in
the modern form of the science; and, therefore, according to our plan,
are of no importance in our history. And thus we can treat all the
miscellaneous information concerning vegetables which was accumulated
by the whole of this school of writers, in no other way than as
something antecedent to the first progress towards systematic
knowledge.
The information thus collected by the unsystematic writers is of
various kinds; and relates to the economical and medicinal uses of
plants, their habits, mode of cultivation, and many other
circumstances: it frequently includes some description; but this is
always extremely imperfect, because the essential conditions of
description had not been discovered. Of works composed of materials so
heterogeneous, it can be of little use to produce specimens; but I may
quote a few words from Theophrastus, which may serve to connect him
with the future history of the science, as bearing upon one of the
many problems respecting the identification of ancient and modern
plants. It has been made a question whether the following description
does not refer to the potato.12 He is speaking
of the differences of roots: “Some roots,” he says, “are still
different from those which have been described; as that of the
arachidna13 plant: for this bears fruit underground
as well as above: the fleshy part sends one thick root deep into the
ground, but the others, which bear the fruit, are more slender 363 and higher up, and
ramified. It loves a sandy soil, and has no leaf whatever.”
12 Theoph. i. 11.
13 Most probably the Arachnis
hypogæa, or ground-nut. ~Correction to text in the 3rd edition.~
The books of Aristotle and Theophrastus soon took the place of the
Book of Nature in the attention of the degenerate philosophers who
succeeded them. A story is told by Strabo14 concerning the
fate of the works of these great naturalists. In the case of the wars
and changes which occurred among the successors of Alexander, the
heirs of Theophrastus tried to secure to themselves his books, and
those of his master, by burying them in the ground. There the
manuscripts suffered much from damp and worms; till Apollonicon, a
book-collector of those days, purchased them, and attempted, in his
own way, to supply what time had obliterated. When Sylla marched the
Roman troops into Athens, he took possession of the library of
Apollonicon; and the works which it contained were soon circulated
among the learned of Rome and Alexandria, who were thus enabled to
Aristotelize15 on botany as on other subjects.
14 Strabo, lib. xiii. c. i. §
54.
15 Ἀριστοτλίζειν.
The library collected by the Attalic kings of Pergamus, and the
Alexandrian Museum, founded and supported by the Ptolemies of Egypt,
rather fostered the commentatorial spirit than promoted the increase
of any real knowledge of nature. The Romans, in this as in other
subjects, were practical, not speculative. They had, in the times of
their national vigor, several writers on agriculture, who were highly
esteemed; but no author, till we come to Pliny, who dwells on the mere
knowledge of plants. And even in Pliny, it is easy to perceive that we
have before us a writer who extracted his information principally from
books. This remarkable man,16 in the middle
of a public and active life, of campaigns and voyages, contrived to
accumulate, by reading and study, an extraordinary store of knowledge
of all kinds. So unwilling was he to have his reading and note-making
interrupted, that, even before day-break in winter, and from his
litter as he travelled, he was wont to dictate to his amanuensis, who
was obliged to preserve his hand from the numbness which the cold
occasioned, by the use of gloves.17
16 Sprengel, i. 163.
17 Plin. Jun. Epist. 3, 5.
It has been ingeniously observed, that we may find traces in the
botanical part of his Natural History, of the errors which this
hurried and broken habit of study produced; and that he appears
frequently to have had books read to him and to have heard them
amiss.18 Thus, 364 among several other instances,
Theophrastus having said that the plane-tree is in Italy rare,19 Pliny, misled by the similarity of the
Greek word (spanian, rare), says that the tree occurs in Italy
and Spain.20 His work has, with great propriety,
been called the Encyclopædia of Antiquity; and, in truth, there are
few portions of the learning of the times to which it does not refer.
Of the thirty-seven Books of which it consists, no less than sixteen
(from the twelfth to the twenty-seventh) relate to plants. The
information which is collected in these books, is of the most
miscellaneous kind; and the author admits, with little distinction,
truth and error, useful knowledge and absurd fables. The declamatory
style, and the comprehensive and lofty tone of thought which we have
already spoken of as characteristic of the Roman writers, are
peculiarly observable in him. The manner of his death is well known:
it was occasioned by the eruption of Vesuvius, a.d. 79, to which, in his curiosity, he ventured so
near as to be suffocated.
18 Sprengel, i. 163.
19 Theoph. iv. 7. Ἔν μὲν γὰρ τῷ Ἀδρίᾳ
πλάτανον οὐ φασὶν εἶναι πλῆν περὶ το Διομήδους ἱερόν, σπανίαν  δὲ καὶ ἐν Ἰταλίᾳ πάσῃ
20 Plin. Nat. Hist. xii. 3. Et alias
(platanos) fuisse in Italia, ac nominatim Hispania, apud
auctores invenitur.
Pliny’s work acquired an almost unlimited authority, as one of the
standards of botanical knowledge, in the middle ages; but even more
than his, that of his contemporary, Pedanius Dioscorides, of Anazarbus
in Cilicia. This work, written in Greek, is held by the best judges21 to offer no evidence that the author
observed for himself. Yet he says expressly in his Preface, that his
love of natural history, and his military life, have led him into many
countries, in which he has had opportunity to become acquainted with
the nature of herbs and trees.22 He speaks of
six hundred plants, but often indicates only their names and
properties, giving no description by which they can be identified. The
main cause of his great reputation in subsequent times was, that he
says much of the medicinal virtues of vegetables.
21 Mirbel, 510.
22 Sprengel, i. 136.
We come now to the ages of darkness and lethargy, when the habit of
original thought seems to die away, as the talent of original
observation had done before. Commentators and mystics succeed to the
philosophical naturalists of better times. And though a new race,
altogether distinct in blood and character from the Greek,
appropriates to itself the stores of Grecian learning, this movement
does not, as might be expected, break the chains of literary slavery.
The Arabs 365
bring, to the cultivation of the science of the Greeks, their own
oriental habit of submission, their oriental love of wonder; and thus,
while they swell the herd of commentators and mystics, they produce no
philosopher.
Yet the Arabs discharged an important function in the history of
human knowledge,23 by preserving, and transmitting to more
enlightened times, the intellectual treasures of antiquity. The
unhappy dissensions which took place in the Christian church had
scattered these treasures over the East, at a period much antecedent
to the rise of the Saracen power. In the fifth century, the adherents
of Nestorius, bishop of Constantinople, were declared heretical by the
Council of Ephesus (a.d. 431), and driven into
exile. In this manner, many of the most learned and ingenious men of
the Christian world were removed to the Euphrates, where they formed
the Chaldean church, erected the celebrated Nestorian school of
Edessa, and gave rise to many offsets from this in various regions.
Already, in the fifth century, Hibas, Cumas, and Probus, translated
the writings of Aristotle into Syriac. But the learned Nestorians paid
an especial attention to the art of medicine, and were the most
zealous students of the works of the Greek physicians. At Djondisabor,
in Khusistan, they became an ostensible medical school, who
distributed academical honors as the result of public disputations.
The califs of Bagdad heard of the fame and the wisdom of the doctors
of Djondisabor, summoned some of them to Bagdad, and took measures for
the foundation of a school of learning in that city. The value of the
skill, the learning, and the virtues of the Nestorians, was so
strongly felt, that they were allowed by the Mohammedans the free
exercise of the Christian religion, and intrusted with the conduct of
the studies of those of the Moslemin, whose education was most cared
for. The affinity of the Syriac and Arabic languages made the task of
instruction more easy. The Nestorians translated the works of the
ancients out of the former into the latter language: hence there are
still found Arabic manuscripts of Dioscorides, with Syriac words in
the margin. Pliny and Aristotle likewise assumed an Arabic dress; and
were, as well as Dioscorides, the foundation of instruction in all the
Arabian academies; of which a great number were established throughout
the Saracen empire, from Bokhara in the remotest east, to Marocco and
Cordova in the west. After some time, the Mohammedans themselves began
to translate and 366 extract from their Syriac sources; and
at length to write works of their own. And thus arose vast libraries,
such as that of Cordova, which contained 250,000 volumes.
23 Sprengel, i. 203.
The Nestorians are stated24 to have first
established among the Arabs those collections of medicinal substances
(Apothecæ), from which our term Apothecary is taken; and
to have written books (Dispensatoria) containing systematic
instructions for the employment of these medicaments; a word which
long continued to be implied in the same sense, and which we also
retain, though in a modified application (Dispensary).
24 Sprengel, i. 205.
The directors of these collections were supposed to be intimately
acquainted with plants; and yet, in truth, the knowledge of plants
owed but little to them; for the Arabic Dioscorides was the source and
standard of their knowledge. The flourishing commerce of the Arabians,
their numerous and distant journeys, made them, no doubt, practically
acquainted with the productions of lands unknown to the Greeks and
Romans. Their Nestorian teachers had established Christianity even as
far as China and Malabar; and their travellers mention25 the camphor of Sumatra, the aloe-wood
of Socotra near Java, the tea of China. But they never learned the art
of converting their practical into speculative knowledge. They treat
of plants only in so far as their use in medicine is concerned,26 and followed Dioscorides in the
description, and even in the order of the plants, except when they
arrange them according to the Arabic alphabet. With little clearness
of view, they often mistake what they read:27 thus when
Dioscorides says that ligusticon grows on the Apennine,
a mountain not far from the Alps; Avicenna, misled by a
resemblance of the Arabic letters, quotes him as saying that the plant
grows on Akabis, a mountain near Egypt.
25 Sprengel, i. 206.
26 Ib. i. 207.
27 Ib. i. 211.
It is of little use to enumerate such writers. One of the most
noted of them was Mesuë, physician of the Calif of Kahirah. His work,
which was translated into Latin at a later period, was entitled, On
Simple Medicines; a title which was common to many medical
treatises, from the time of Galen in the second century. Indeed, of
this opposition of simple and compound medicines, we
still have traces in our language: 367

  He would ope his leathern scrip,
And show me simples of a thousand
names,
Telling their strange and vigorous
faculties.
Milton,
Comus.
Where the subject of our history is so entirely at a stand, it is
unprofitable to dwell on a list of names. The Arabians, small as their
science was, were able to instruct the Christians. Their writings were
translated by learned Europeans, for instance Michael Scot, and
Constantine of Africa, a Carthaginian who had lived forty years among
the Saracens28 and who died a.d. 1087. Among his works, is a Treatise, De
Gradibus, which contains the Arabian medicinal lore. In the
thirteenth century occur Encyclopædias, as that of Albertus Magnus,
and of Vincent of Beauvais; but these contain no natural history
except traditions and fables. Even the ancient writers were altogether
perverted and disfigured. The Dioscorides of the middle ages varied
materially from ours.29 Monks, merchants, and adventurers
travelled far, but knowledge was little increased. Simon of Genoa,30 a writer on plants in the fourteenth
century, boasts that he perambulated the East in order to collect
plants. “Yet in his Clavis Sanationis,” says a modern botanical
writer,31 “we discover no trace of an
acquaintance with nature. He merely compares the Greek, Arabic, and
Latin names of plants, and gives their medicinal effect after his
predecessors:”—so little true is it, that the use of the senses
alone necessarily leads to real knowledge.
28 Sprengel, i. 230.
29 Ib. i. 239.
30 Ib. i. 241.
31 Ib. ib.
Though the growing activity of thought in Europe, and the revived
acquaintance with the authors of Greece in their genuine form, were
gradually dispelling the intellectual clouds of the middle ages, yet
during the fifteenth century, botany makes no approach to a scientific
form. The greater part of the literature of this subject consisted of
Herbals, all of which were formed on the same plan, and appeared under
titles such as Hortus, or Ortus Sanitatis. There are,
for example, three32 such German Herbals, with woodcuts,
which date about 1490. But an important peculiarity in these works is
that they contain some indigenous species placed side by side with the
old ones. In 1516, The Grete Herbal was published in England,
also with woodcuts. It contains an account of more than four hundred
vegetables, and their 368 products; of which one hundred and fifty
are English, and are no way distinguished from the exotics by the mode
in which they are inserted in the work.
32 Augsburg, 1488. Mainz, 1491.
Lubec, 1492.
We shall see, in the next chapter, that
when the intellect of Europe began really to apply itself to the
observation of nature, the progress towards genuine science soon began
to be visible, in this as in other subjects; but before this tendency
could operate freely, the history of botany was destined to show, in
another instance, how much more grateful to man, even when roused to
intelligence and activity, is the study of tradition than the study of
nature. When the scholars of Europe had become acquainted with the
genuine works of the ancients in the original languages, the pleasure
and admiration which they felt, led them to the most zealous endeavors
to illustrate and apply what they read. They fell into the error of
supposing that the plants described by Theophrastus, Dioscorides,
Pliny, must be those which grew in their own fields. And thus
Ruellius,33 a French physician, who only travelled
in the environs of Paris and Picardy, imagined that he found there the
plants of Italy and Greece. The originators of genuine botany in
Germany, Brunfels and Tragus (Bock), committed the same mistake; and
hence arose the misapplication of classical names to many genera. The
labors of many other learned men took the same direction, of treating
the ancient writers as if they alone were the sources of knowledge and
truth.
33 De Natura Stirpium,
1536.
But the philosophical spirit of Europe was already too vigorous to
allow this superstitious erudition to exercise a lasting sway.
Leonicenus, who taught at Ferrara till he was almost a hundred years
old, and died in 1524,34 disputed, with great freedom, the
authority of the Arabian writers, and even of Pliny. He saw, and
showed by many examples, how little Pliny himself knew of nature, and
how many errors he had made or transmitted. The same independence of
thought with regard to other ancient writers, was manifested by other
scholars. Yet the power of ancient authority melted away but
gradually. Thus Antonius Brassavola, who established on the banks of
the Po the first botanical garden of modern times, published in 1536,
his Examen omnium Simplicium Medicamentorum; and, as Cuvier
says,35 though he studied plants in nature, his
book (written in the 369 Platonic form of dialogue), has still
the character of a commentary on the ancients.
34 Sprengel, i. 252.
35 Hist. des Sc. Nat. partie
ii. 169.
The Germans appear to have been the first to liberate themselves
from this thraldom, and to publish works founded mainly on actual
observation. The first of the botanists who had this great merit is
Otho Brunfels of Mentz, whose work, Herbarum Vivæ Icones,
appeared in 1530. It consists of two volumes in folio, with wood-cuts;
and in 1532, a German edition was published. The plants which it
contains are given without any arrangement, and thus he belongs to the
period of unsystematic knowledge. Yet the progress towards the
formation of a system manifested itself so immediately in the series
of German botanists to which he belongs, that we might with almost
equal propriety transfer him to the history of that progress; to which
we now proceed.
</div></body></text></TEI>