<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="66">

CHAPTER V.
Attempts to form Ideas of separate Vital
Forces, continued.—Voluntary Motion.



1. WE
formerly noticed the distinctions of organic
and animal functions, organic and animal
forces, as one of the most marked distinctions to
which physiologists have been led in their analysis of
the vital powers. I have now taken one of the former,
the organic class of functions, namely, Nutrition; and
have endeavoured to point out in some measure the
peculiar nature of the vital forces by which this function is carried on. It may serve to show the extent
and the difficulty of this subject, if, before quitting
it, I offer a few remarks suggested by a function
belonging to the other class, the animal functions.
This I shall briefly do with respect to Voluntary Motion.
2. In the History of Physiology, I have already
related the progress of the researches by which the
organs employed in voluntary motion became known
to anatomists. It was ascertained to the satisfaction
of all physiologists, that the immediate agents in such
motion are the muscles; that the muscles are in some
way contracted, when the nerves convey to them the
agency of the will; and that thus the limbs are moved.
It was ascertained, also, that the nerves convey sensations from the organs of sense inwards, so as to make
these sensations the object of the animal’s consciousness. In man and the higher animals, these impressions upon the nerves are all conveyed to one internal
organ, the brain; and from this organ all impressions
of the will appear to proceed; and thus the brain is 223 the center of animal life, towards which sensations
converge, and from which volitions diverge.
But this being the process, we are led to inquire
how far we can obtain any knowledge, or form any
conception, of the vital forces by means of which the
process is carried on. And here I have further stated
in the History87, that the transfer of sensations and
volitions along the nerves was often represented as
consisting in the motion of a Nervous Fluid. I have
related that the hypothesis of such a fluid, conveying
its impressions either by motions of translation or of
vibration, was countenanced by many great names,
as Newton, Haller, and even Cuvier. But I have
ventured to express my doubt whether this hypothesis
can have much value: ‘for,’ I have said, ‘this principle cannot be mechanical, chemical, or physical, and
therefore cannot be better understood by embodying it
in a fluid. The difficulty we have in conceiving what
the force is, is not got rid of by explaining the machinery by which it is transferred.’</div></body></text></TEI>