<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="96">CHAPTER III.
Doctrine of Elective Attractions. Geoffroy.
Bergman.
THOUGH the chemical
combinations of bodies had already been referred to attraction, in a
vague and general manner, it was impossible to explain the changes
that take place, without supposing the attraction to be greater or
less, according to the nature of the body. Yet it was some time before
the necessity of such a supposition was clearly seen. In the history
of the French Academy for 1718 (published 1719), the writer of the
introductory notice (probably Fontenelle) says, “That a body which is
united to another, for example, a solvent which has penetrated a
metal, should quit it to go and unite itself with another which we
present to it, is a thing of which the possibility had never been
guessed by the most subtle philosophers, and of which the explanation
even now is not easy.” The doctrine had, in fact, been stated by
Stahl, but the assertion just quoted shows, at least, that it was not
familiar. The principle, however, is very clearly stated7
in a memoir in the same volume, by Geoffroy, a French physician of
great talents and varied knowledge, “We observe in chemistry,” he
says, “certain relations amongst different bodies, which cause them to
unite. These relations have their degrees and their
laws. We observe their different degrees in this;—that
among different matters jumbled together, which have a certain
disposition to unite, we find that one of these substances always
unites constantly with a certain other, preferably to all the rest.”
He then states that those which unite by preference, have “plus de
rapport,” or, according to a phrase afterwards used, more
affinity. “And I have satisfied myself,” he adds, “that we may
deduce, from these observations, the following proposition, which is
very extensively true, though I cannot enunciate it as universal, not
having been able to examine all the possible combinations, to assure
myself that I should find no exception.” The proposition which he
states in this admirable spirit of philosophical caution, is this: “In
all cases where two substances, 266 which have any disposition to combine,
are united; if there approaches them a third, which has more affinity
with one of the two, this one unites with the third and lets go the
other.” He then states these affinities in the form of a Table;
placing a substance at the head of each column, and other substances
in succession below it, according to the order of their affinities for
the substance which stands at the head. He allows that the separation
is not always complete (an imperfection which he ascribes to the
glutinosity of fluids and other causes), but, with such exceptions, he
defends very resolutely and successfully his Table, and the notions
which it implies.
7 Mém. Acad. Par. 1718, p.
202.
The value of such a tabulation was immense at the time, and is even
still very great; it enabled the chemist to trace beforehand the
results of any operation; since, when the ingredients were given, he
could see which were the strongest of the affinities brought into
play, and, consequently, what compounds would be formed. Geoffroy
himself gave several good examples of this use of his table. It was
speedily adopted into works on chemistry. For instance, Macquer8
places it at the end of his book; “taking it,” as he says, “to be of
great use at the end of an elementary tract, as it collects into one
point of view, the most essential and fundamental doctrines which are
dispersed through the work.”
8 Pref., p. 13.
The doctrine of Elective Attraction, as thus promulgated,
contained so large a mass of truth, that it was never seriously
shaken, though it required further development and correction. In
particular the celebrated work of Torbern Bergman, professor at
Upsala, On Elective Attractions, published in 1775, introduced
into it material improvements. Bergman observed, that not only the
order of attractions, but the sum of those attractions which had to
form the new compounds, must be taken account of, in order to judge of
the result. Thus,9 if we have a combination of two
elements, P, s, (potassa and vitriolic acid), and
another combination, L, m, (lime and muriatic acid,)
though s has a greater affinity for P than for L,
yet the sum of the attractions of P to m, and of
L to s, is greater than that of the original compounds,
and therefore if the two combinations are brought together, the new
compounds, P, m, and L, s, are formed.
9 Elect. Attract., p. 19.
The Table of Elective Attractions, modified by Bergman in pursuance
of these views, and corrected according to the advanced knowledge of
the time, became still more important than before. The next step 267 was to take into
account the quantities of the elements which combined; but this leads
us into a new train of investigation, which was, indeed, a natural
sequel to the researches of Geoffroy and Bergman.
In 1803, however, a chemist of great eminence, Berthollet,
published a work (Essai de Statique Chimique), the tendency of
which appeared to be to throw the subject back into the condition in
which it had been before Geoffroy. For Berthollet maintained that the
rules of chemical combination were not definite, and dependent on the
nature of the substances alone, but indefinite, depending on the
quantity present, and other circumstances. Proust answered him, and as
Berzelius says,10 “Berthollet defended himself with an
acuteness which makes the reader hesitate in his judgment; but the
great mass of facts finally decided the point in favor of Proust.”
Before, however, we trace the result of these researches, we must
consider Chemistry as extending her inquiries to combustion as well as
mixture, to airs as well as fluids and solids, and to weight as well
as quality. These three steps we shall now briefly treat of.
10 Chem. t. iii. p. 23.
</div></body></text></TEI>