<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="23">
CHAPTER IV.

The Sun in the Centre.

The next circumstance which we shall notice as
indicative of design in the arrangement of the material
portions of the solar system, is the position of the
sun, the source of light and heat, in the centre of the[135]
system. This could hardly have occurred by any
thing which we can call chance. Let it be granted,
that the law of gravitation is established, and that
we have a large mass, with others much smaller in
its comparative vicinity. The small bodies may then
move round the larger, but this will do nothing towards
making it a sun to them. Their motions might
take place, the whole system remaining still utterly
dark and cold, without day or summer. In order that
we may have something more than this blank and
dead assemblage of moving clods, the machine must
be lighted up and warmed. Some of the advantages of
placing the lighting and warming apparatus in the
centre are obvious to us. It is in this way only that
we could have those regular periodical returns of
solar influence, which, as we have seen, are adapted
to the constitution of the living creation. And we
can easily conceive, that there may be other incongruities
in a system with a travelling sun, of which
we can only conjecture the nature. No one probably
will doubt that the existing system, with the sun in
the centre, is better than any one of a different kind
would be.
Now this lighting and warming by a central sun
are something superadded to the mere mechanical
arrangements of the universe. There is no apparent
reason why the largest mass of gravitating matter
should diffuse inexhaustible supplies of light and heat
in all directions, while the other masses are merely
passive, with respect to such influences. There is no
obvious connexion between mass and luminousness,
or temperature. No one, probably, will contend that
the materials of our system are necessarily luminous
or hot. According to the conjectures of astronomers,
the heat and light of the sun do not reside in its mass,
but in a coating which lies on its surface. If such a
coating were fixed there by the force of universal
gravitation, how could we avoid having a similar
coating on the surface of the earth, and of all the
other globes of the system. If light consist in the[136]
vibrations of an ether, which we have mentioned as
a probable opinion, why has the sun alone the power
of exciting such vibrations? If light be the emission
of material particles, why does the sun alone emit
such particles? Similar questions may be asked, with
regard to heat, whatever be the theory we adopt on
that subject. Here then we appear to find marks of
contrivance. The sun might become, we will suppose,
the centre of the motions of the planets by
mere mechanical causes: but what caused the centre
of their motions to be also the source of those vivifying
influences? Allowing that no interposition was
requisite to regulate the revolutions of the system,
yet observe what a peculiar arrangement in other
respects was necessary, in order that these revolutions
might produce days and seasons! The machine
will move of itself, we may grant: but who constructed
the machine, so that its movements might
answer the purposes of life? How was the candle
placed upon the candlestick? How was the fire deposited
on the hearth, so that the comfort and well-being
of the family might be secured? Did these too
fall into their places by the casual operation of
gravity? And, if not, is there not here a clear evidence
of intelligent design, of arrangement with a
benevolent end?
This argument is urged with great force by Newton
himself. In his first letter to Bentley, he allows
that matter might form itself into masses by the force
of attraction. “And thus,” says he, “might the sun
and fixed stars be formed, supposing the matter were
of a lucid nature. But how the matter should divide
itself into two sorts; and that part of it which is fit
to compose a shining body should fall down into one
mass, and make a sun; and the rest, which is fit to
compose an opaque body, should coalesce, not into
one great body, like the shining matter, but into
many little ones; or if the sun at first were an opake
body like the planets, or the planets lucid bodies like
the sun, how he alone should be changed into a[137]
shining body, whilst all they continue opake; or all
they be changed into opake ones, while he continued
unchanged: I do not think explicable by mere natural
causes, but am forced to ascribe it to the counsel
and contrivance of a voluntary Agent.”
</div></body></text></TEI>