<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="25">CHAPTER XXIII.
Having rejoined the remainder of my family, we set out
together for the plains of Italy. My first interview with
Marguerite after my return from Dresden had been melancholy.
But our situation was now such as to give additional
anguish to her serious thoughts. She had then regarded
me as ambiguous, mysterious, and impenetrable,
qualities from which the frankness of her nature spontaneously
revolted; she saw in me the destroyer of her son, the
idol of her heart; she believed me an alchymist, a character
which she viewed as base, degrading, and insensible;
she had heard that rumour had been busy with my fame.
But now she saw in me a man of blasted reputation, arraigned
and imprisoned for robbery and murder. She did
not credit these imputations. But did the ingenuous and
noble-minded Marguerite de Damville ever think to find
herself allied to a being thus loaded with the world’s abhorrence;
that she should be compelled to honour with the
sacred name of husband a fugitive, a prison-breaker, and
an outlaw? If I had suffered these things in the defence
of my children, my religion, or my country, the case would
have been widely different. If, while encountering the
contempt of men, I had carried within me the glorious
feeling, that what they regarded as my disgrace was indeed
my immortal honour, Marguerite de Damville, beyond all
women, was prepared to despise their senseless blame, and
proudly to demand her share in such a dishonour.
I know there are men who will listen with fretful impatience
to a detail of such sorrows as hers, and who will cry[248]
out, “If we must be distressed, give us more substantial
and genuine sources of distress!” They will regard the
dejection of Marguerite as an idle wilfulness of grief, better
entitled to aversion than to sympathy; and will tell me
that nothing but the most deplorable blindness could have
prevented her from discerning the happiness of her condition;
that she had the world before her, a rich, a brave,
and an enterprising husband, with a lovely family of children;
that they could move from country to country, and
from climate to climate, carrying with them the means of
luxury, indulgence, homage, and usefulness. To such
moralisers I write not. For those who are incapable of
sympathising with the delicate sensations of Marguerite, I
am as little qualified to enter into their feelings as they into
mine. In the sequel of the story however it is not impossible
they may meet with their gratification. I am hastening
to events corporeal and palpable. I and my family did
wander from country to country, and from climate to climate.
With what resulting success will speedily be seen.
Our destination at the present moment led us through
the territory of the Grisons, and over a limb of the Rhetian
Alps, to Como, Milan, Piacenza, Parma, and Pisa, in the
neighbourhood of which latter city we resolved to take up
our immediate residence. In this passage we met with few
adventures that merit to be recorded in my history. One
however seems entitled to a place, both as it tends to display
the singular worth of a dumb and unpretending brute,
and as it is in some sort connected with the fortunes I encountered
in the Pisan territory. It occurred in our journey
over the Alps.
One evening, in the wildest and most desolate part of
the mountain, after having lodged my family in an inn, I
wandered forth to take a survey of the neighbouring
scenery. It was moonlight; our travel of the day had
been short, and had left on me no impression of fatigue;
while the romantic appearance of every thing around,
tempted me to extend my excursion further than I had
originally purposed. Stories of robberies and murders in
the vicinity had been repeated to us, and Marguerite had
employed the precaution of desiring Hector, such was the[249]
name which the caprice of his former masters had bestowed
on my faithful negro, to follow my steps and hold me in
sight. No anticipations of danger however disturbed my
contemplations. I resigned myself, as all my life I had
been accustomed to do, to the impressions of the moment,
and sought to shut out memory and the world from all my
thoughts. The scene was inexpressibly beautiful; the silence
was uninterrupted and awful. The splendour of the
moon gave a sober and silvery tint to every thing by which
its light was caught; soft white clouds were scattered in
the deep azure of the sky; the shades were of a blackness
and profundity that could not be surpassed. Every thing
was calculated to soothe and subdue the mind, to inspire a
grand and expansive tranquillity. The enthusiasm it spoke
occupied every channel of my heart. I stood still. It seemed
as if motion would have jarred and broken the spell that
seized me; I yielded with eager transport to the sentiment
that shrowded and enveloped me in its ample embrace.
I had remained motionless for above half an hour, when
a sudden and eager sound burst upon my ear. It seemed
to be the shriek of some human creature in distress. It
was repeated several times. My first impulse was to fly to
the spot from which the sound appeared to proceed. Meanwhile
Hector came up to me, and endeavoured to detain me
by violence. His first principle was obedience to every just
and lawful command; and the errand upon which he was
commissioned, was to preserve me from the approach of
danger. He represented to me the stories of banditti we
had recently heard. He told me that we should too probably
fall in with a numerous party of these desperadoes,
against whom all our efforts, either for ourselves or for
those I was desirous to succour, would be nugatory. What
would become of my children? what would become of his
mistress, if my rashness were succeeded by a fatal event?
While he was thus speaking, and exerting himself to detain
me, the cries ceased. I believed they were those of a
person assassinated. I conceived that I should be the vilest
of poltroons if I suffered any consideration to prevent me
from endeavouring to afford to this unfortunate the relief in
my power.
[250]
I had not advanced far, before I perceived coming towards
us, in the same direction from which the sound had
reached my ear, a dog, entirely black, and of uncommon
stature and strength. He was alone. Having caught sight
of us, he increased his pace, and had no sooner reached the
spot on which we stood, than he seized the flap of my coat,
and pulled it with considerable violence. I was somewhat
alarmed at his size and action, the latter of which I apprehended
to have a hostile design; and, having shaken him
off, I put myself in a posture of defence with a cane that
I carried in my hand. Undeterred however by my gesture,
he returned to the attack, only pulling with something less
exertion of strength than he had done before. More accurate
attention convinced me that he had no intention to
injure me, and I withheld the action of Hector, who had
raised his hand to strike in defence of his master. I suffered
him to guide me; and, after a considerable circuit
which the nature of the road obliged us to take, he led me
to a spot where I found a man lying on the ground, and
weltering in his blood, but with no person near, to whom to
impute the violence he had sustained.
His blood flowed copiously from two or three different
wounds, one of them in particular near his left breast; and
my first care was to stop the effusion. For this purpose we
stripped him of his clothes, and tore his linen into bandages.
When we found him, he was insensible; but the anguish
of binding his wounds revived him a little, though only
enough to extort from him sighs and groans. This accomplished,
I dismissed Hector to the inn to procure something
in the nature of a litter, by which he might more easily be
conveyed within reach of effectual assistance.
I was now left for six hours with no other companions
than the wounded gentleman and his dog, upon the very
spot upon which he had just before sustained so ferocious a
treatment, probably from the hands of banditti. They
might every moment be expected to return. This was no
agreeable notion to a person circumstanced as I was. I was
compelled to feel that a man possessed of boundless and
illimitable wealth, and of the power of repelling old age
and disease, did not in these advantages possess every thing.[251]
Notwithstanding the disappointments and mortifications I
had sustained, I was yet attached to life: and though the
bequests of the stranger had hitherto produced to me
nothing but evil, I still looked, with almost puerile eagerness
and beating of heart, for the time when I might spread
out the whole extent of my treasures without parsimony or
the dread of reverse. During the interval which I employed
in these reflections, the wounded man was for the
most part in a state of insensibility, and constantly speechless.
I expected his death every moment, and I perceived,
as I thought with certainty, that there was no hope of his
recovery. While we had dressed his wounds, the dog had
watched our motions with the most restless attention, and,
now that it was over, he came and licked my hands, and
laid himself down at my feet. The least motion however,
so much as a rustling among the leaves, startled him: he
rose, looked round, and seemed to enquire into the cause of
the disturbance; but he abstained from barking and every
kind of noise; whether it were that he was conscious of
the advantage of quiet to a person in his master’s condition,
or that he had the sense to know, in the situation in which
we were placed, that whatever produced alarm, might eventually
expose us to undiscovered danger.
It was broad daylight before Hector re-appeared, and several
other persons in his company. Hector was not of a temper
to have receded from any thing he undertook, and the authority
of Marguerite had in this instance seconded his
remonstrances with the surly and inactive peasants of the
place. I had at this time only one other male servant;
but, when Hector returned, he brought with him a crazy
kind of litter, and a recruit of four mountaineers. The
wounded man still lived, and was conveyed alive to the
place at which I had taken up my lodging. He survived
three days; and, during the whole of that period, the dog
could neither be moved by force, nor prevailed on by entreaties,
to quit the apartment of his master. Before his
death my unfortunate guest recovered the power of speech.
He told me that his name was Andrea Filosanto, and,
which struck me as somewhat extraordinary, that he was of
Pisa, the very place at which I purposed to take up my[252]
abode. He had a brother resident in that city, and had
himself been about to marry a very beautiful and accomplished
young lady, an heiress, of the house of Carracciuoli
in Pisa. Previously to his marriage, he resolved to
make a visit to his mother, who had espoused to her second
husband a French nobleman of Languedoc. He had travelled
accompanied only by one servant, contrary to the
persuasions both of his brother and the family of his intended
bride; but that servant, though he had been a very
short time in his employment, was active, ingenious, and
obliging, and had established himself strongly in the favour
of his master. Signor Filosanto had taken with him a sum
of money, the produce of one year’s income of the dower
of his mother; and it was but too probable that the richness
of the charge he bore, had been fatal to the life of the
bearer. His servant had disappeared from his side not a
quarter of an hour before his being attacked by the banditti;
and various concurring circumstances seemed to fix
on this servant the accusation of being an accomplice with
the murderers. Having heard from the unfortunate sufferer
the tale of treachery of his human attendant, I related
to him the extraordinary example of fidelity and attachment
shown by his dog. The master was struck with the story
I told, and called the dog to him upon his bed. The poor
animal first leaped up upon the foot of the bed, and then
warily and with great caution crawled to his master’s face.
Filosanto embraced the dog, who by his manner showed
himself fully sensible of the purport of the action. That
very evening, having requested me to convey his remains to
the tomb of his ancestors at Pisa, the master expired. The
dog in dumb and constant grief watched by the corpse, and
followed the vehicle in which it was conveyed to Pisa.
After the funeral, he made the choice, from which he could
not be diverted, of living with me, and not with the brother
and relations of his master, to whom he was almost wholly
a stranger, but who would gladly have received him. One
of the advantages I derived from this adventure, was the
friendship and protection of the Filosanti and Carracciuoli,
two of the most powerful families in Pisa.
I have not yet finished the history of my dog. A few[253]
months after our establishment in the Pisan territory, the
valet of the deceased had the audacity to appear in that city.
He believed himself to be entirely unknown there, his
master having taken him into his service during his residence
as a student in the university of Bologna; and having
ordered him, previously to his projected tour into France,
to stay behind and settle his debts and other affairs at that
place. He found however an adversary in Pisa that in all
his anticipations had never occurred to his thoughts. The
dog saw him at a distance in the street, ran towards him
with incredible swiftness, and fell upon him with savage
violence and ferocity. The man was not extricated from
his grip, till he had been severely and dangerously wounded.
Thus assailed, all the terrors of superstition and an accusing
conscience seized on this devoted villain; he owned who he
was, and confessed that he had made one among the assassins
and plunderers of his master, visible probably to the
dog, though unseen by the unfortunate Filosanto. He declared,
that he knew not what motive had brought him to
Pisa, that he seemed to himself under the guidance of an
impulse which he had not power to resist, and that he rejoiced
that Providence had thus conducted him to the expiation
of his guilt. He was brought to his trial, and suffered
death for his crime.
Charon, such was the name by which my dog was
distinguished, showed himself in all his actions worthy of
the character for attachment and sagacity which he had in
these instances acquired. He was therefore the favourite of
my whole family, and particularly of Hector. But his own
partiality was with the nicest discrimination reserved for
me. The ruling passion of his preceding master had been
the sports of the field, and his leading singularity an uncommon
familiarity and friendship towards his brute attendants.
By this conduct he had won the affections, and perhaps
awakened the understanding and virtues, of the faithful
Charon. I own my weakness. I could not resist the assiduities
and regard of this generous brute; and, though I
had never before conceived any extraordinary partiality for
creatures of his species, his sagacity and nobleness of nature
took a strong hold of my affection. I admired his form[254]
and agility as he bounded and gamboled before me upon
the plain. In the midst of his gayest frolics he was all
attention, and the least sign I made him would instantly
divert his exertions to a different pursuit. He was accustomed
to salute me with honest, undesigning homage every
morning as I came from my chamber, and I should have
missed his presence with heaviness of heart upon this plain
and homely occasion. He was the associate of my solitary
walks, and my companion when pensive meditations induced
me to withdraw from all human society. I became
accustomed at such periods to observe him by my side, and
should have felt that all was not right if he were not there.
I was interested in his health, his well-being and his enjoyments;
and, if any calamity befell him, was prepared to
feel it more severely than a wise man is sometimes willing
to confess.—It would scarcely be necessary to add to this
simple history of my faithful Charon, the circumstance of
his having saved the life of a beautiful little boy of ten
years old, who had unluckily slipped into the Arno, and
whom he seized by his garments and drew to the shore, had
it not some connection with what I shall speedily have
occasion to relate.
</div></body></text></TEI>