<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="49">CHAPTER XLIX.
IMBEDDING OF AQUATIC SPECIES IN SUBAQUEOUS STRATA.
Inhumation of fresh water plants and animals—Shell marl—Fossilized seed-vessels
and stems of chara—Recent deposits in American lakes—Freshwater
species drifted into seas and estuaries—Lewes levels—Alternations of marine
and freshwater strata, how caused—Imbedding of marine plants and animals—Cetacea
stranded on our shores—Littoral and estuary Testacea swept into the
deep sea—Burrowing shells—Living Testacea found at considerable depths—Blending
of organic remains of different ages.
Having treated of the imbedding of terrestrial plants and animals,
and of human remains, in deposits now forming beneath the waters, I
come next to consider in what manner aquatic species may be entombed
in strata formed in their own element.
Freshwater plants and animals.—The remains of species belonging
to those genera of the animal and vegetable kingdoms which are more
or less exclusively confined to fresh water are for the most part preserved
in the beds of lakes or estuaries, but they are oftentimes swept down by
rivers into the sea, and there intermingled with the exuviæ of marine
races. The phenomena attending their inhumation in lacustrine deposits
are sometimes revealed to our observation by the drainage of small lakes,
such as are those in Scotland, which have been laid dry for the sake of
obtaining shell marl for agricultural uses.
In these recent formations, as seen in Forfarshire, two or three beds
of calcareous marl are sometimes observed separated from each other by
layers of drift peat, sand, or fissile clay. The marl often consists almost
entirely of an aggregate of shells of the genera Limnea, Planorbis, Valvata,
and Cyclas, of species now existing in Scotland. A considerable
proportion of the Testacea appear to have died very young, and few
of the shells are of a size which indicates their having attained a state
of maturity. The shells are sometimes entirely decomposed, forming a
pulverulent marl; sometimes in a state of good preservation. They are
frequently intermixed with stems of Charæ and other aquatic vegetables,
the whole being matted together and compressed, forming laminæ often
as thin as paper.
766
Fossilized seed-vessels and stems of Chara.—As the Chara is an
aquatic plant which occurs frequently fossil in formations of different
eras, and is often of much importance to the geologist in characterizing
entire groups of strata, I shall describe the manner in which I have
found the recent species in a petrified state. They occur in a marl-lake
in Forfarshire, inclosed in nodules, and sometimes in a continuous stratum
of a kind of travertin.
Fig. 102.
Seed-vessel of Chara hispida.
a, Part of the stem with the seed-vessel attached. Magnified.
b, Natural size of the seed vessel.
c, Integument of the Gyrogonite, or petrified seed-vessel of Chara hispida, found in the
Scotch marl-lakes. Magnified.
d, Section showing the nut within the integument.
e, Lower end of the integument to which the stem was attached.
f, Upper end of the integument to which the stigmata were attached.
g, One of the spiral valves of c.
The seed-vessel of these plants is remarkably tough and hard, and
consists of a membranous nut covered by an integument (d, fig. 102.)
both of which are spirally striated or ribbed. The integument is composed
of five spiral valves, of a quadrangular form (g). In Chara hispida,
which abounds in the lakes of Forfarshire, and which has become
fossil in the Bakie Loch, each of the spiral valves of the seed-vessel turns
rather more than twice round the circumference, the whole together
making between ten and eleven rings. The number of these rings differs
greatly in different species, but in the same appears to be very constant.
The stems of Charæ occur fossil in the Scotch marl in great abundance.
In some species, as in Chara hispida, the plant when living
contains so much carbonate of lime in its vegetable organization, independently
of calcareous incrustation, that it effervesces strongly with
acids when dry. The stems of Chara hispida are longitudinally striated,
with a tendency to be spiral. These striæ, as appears to be the case
with all Charæ, turn always like the worm of a screw from right to left,
while those of the seed-vessel wind round in a contrary direction. A
cross section of the stem exhibits a curious structure, for it is composed
767
of a large tube surrounded by smaller tubes (fig. 103., b, c) as is seen in
some extinct as well as recent species. In the stems of several species,
however, there is only a single tube.1099
Fig. 103.
Stem and branches of Chara hispida.
a, Stem and branches of the natural size.
b, Section of the stem magnified.
c, Showing the central tube surrounded by two rings of smaller tubes.

The valves of a small animal called cypris (C. ornata? Lam.) occur
completely fossilized, like the stems of Charæ, in the Scotch travertin
above mentioned. The same cypris inhabits the lakes and ponds of
England, where, together with many other species, it is not uncommon.
Although extremely minute, they are visible to the naked eye, and may
be observed in great numbers, swimming swiftly through the waters of
our stagnant pools and ditches. The antennæ, at the end of which are
fine pencils of hair, are the principal organs for swimming, and are
moved with great rapidity. The animal resides within two small valves,
not unlike those of a bivalve shell, and moults its integuments annually,
which the conchiferous mollusks do not. The cast-off shells, resembling
thin scales, and occurring in countless myriads in many ancient freshwater
marls, impart to them a divisional structure, like that so frequently
derived from plates of mica.


Fig. 104.
Fig. 105.

Cypris unifasciata, a living species, greatly
magnified.
a, Upper part. . . . b, Side view of the same.
Cypris vidua, a living species,
greatly magnified.1100


The recent strata of lacustrine origin above alluded to are of very
small extent, but analogous deposits on the grandest scale are forming
in the great Canadian lakes, as in Lakes Superior and Huron, where beds
768
of sand and clay are seen inclosing shells of existing species.1101 The
Chara also plays the same part in the subaqueous vegetation of North
America as in Europe. I observed along the borders of several freshwater
lakes in the state of New York a luxuriant crop of this plant in
clear water of moderate depth, rendering the bottom as verdant as a
grassy meadow. Here, therefore, we may expect some of the tough
seed vessels to be preserved in mud, just as we detect them fossil in the
Eocene strata of Hampshire, or in the neighborhood of Paris, and many
other countries.
Imbedding of freshwater Species in Estuary and Marine Deposits.
In Lewes levels.—We have sometimes an opportunity of examining
the deposits which within the historical period have silted up some of
our estuaries; and excavations made for wells and other purposes,
where the sea has been finally excluded, enable us to observe the state
of the organic remains in these tracts. The valley of the Ouze between
Newhaven and Lewes is one of several estuaries from which the sea has
retired within the last seven or eight centuries; and here, as appears
from the researches of Dr. Mantell, strata thirty feet and upwards in
thickness have accumulated. At the top, beneath the vegetable soil, is
a bed of peat about five feet thick, inclosing many trunks of trees.
Next below is a stratum of blue clay containing freshwater shells of
about nine species, such as now inhabit the district. Intermixed with
these was observed the skeleton of a deer. Lower down, the layers of
blue clay contain, with the above-mentioned freshwater shells, several
marine species well known on our coast. In the lowest beds, often at
the depth of thirty-six feet; these marine Testacea occur without the
slightest intermixture of fluviatile species, and amongst them the skull
of the narwal, or sea unicorn (Monodon monoceros), has been detected.
Underneath all these deposits is a bed of pipe-clay, derived from the
subjacent chalk.1102
769
If we had no historical information respecting the former existence of
an inlet of the sea in this valley and of its gradual obliteration, the
inspection of the section above described would show, as clearly as a
written chronicle, the following sequence of events. First, there was a
salt-water estuary peopled for many years by species of marine Testacea
identical with those now living, and into which some of the larger Cetacea
occasionally entered. Secondly, the inlet grew shallower, and the
water became brackish, or alternately salt and fresh, so that the remains
of freshwater and marine shells were mingled in the blue argillaceous
sediment of its bottom. Thirdly, the shoaling continued until the river-water
prevailed, so that it was no longer habitable by marine Testacea,
but fitted only for the abode of fluviatile species and aquatic insects.
Fourthly, a peaty swamp or morass was formed, where some trees grew,
or perhaps were drifted during floods, and where terrestrial quadrupeds
were mired. Finally, the soil being flooded by the river only at distant
intervals, became a verdant meadow.
In delta of Ganges and Indus.—It was before stated, that on the
sea-coast, in the delta of the Ganges, there are eight great openings,
each of which has evidently, at some ancient period, served in its turn
as the principal channel of discharge.1103 As the base of the delta is 200
miles in length, it must happen that, as often as the great volume of
river-water is thrown into the sea by a new mouth, the sea will at one
point be converted from salt to fresh, and at another from fresh to salt;
for, with the exception of those parts where the principal discharge takes
place, the salt water not only washes the base of the delta, but enters far
into every creek and lagoon. It is evident, then, that repeated alternations
of beds containing freshwater shells, with others filled with marine
exuviæ, may here be formed. It has also been shown by artesian borings
at Calcutta (see above, p. 267), that the delta once extended much farther
than now into the gulf, and that the river is only recovering
from the sea the ground which had been lost by subsidence at some
former period. Analogous phenomena must sometimes be occasioned
by such alternate elevation and depression as has occurred in modern
times in the delta of the Indus.1104 But the subterranean movements
affect but a small number of the deltas formed at one period on the
globe; whereas the silting up of some of the arms of great rivers
and the opening of others, and the consequent variation of the points
where the chief volume of their waters is discharged into the sea, are
phenomena common to almost every delta.
The variety of species of Testacea contained in the recent calcareous
marl of Scotland, before mentioned, is very small, but the abundance of
individuals extremely great, a circumstance very characteristic of freshwater
formations in general, as compared to marine; for in the latter, as
is seen on sea-beaches, coral-reefs, or in the bottom of the seas examined
by dredging, wherever the individual shells are exceedingly numerous,
there rarely fails to be a vast variety of species.
770
Imbedding of the Remains of Marine Plants and Animals.
Marine plants.—The large banks of drift sea-weed which occur on
each side of the equator in the Atlantic, Pacific, and Indian oceans, were
before alluded to.1105 These, when they subside, may often produce considerable
beds of vegetable matter. In Holland, sub-marine peat is
derived from Fuci, and on parts of our own coast from Zostera marina.
In places where Algæ do not generate peat, they may nevertheless leave
traces of their form imprinted on argillaceous and calcareous mud, as
they are usually very tough in their texture.
Sea-weeds are often cast up in such abundance on our shores during
heavy gales, that we cannot doubt that occasionally vast numbers of them
are imbedded in littoral deposits now in progress. We learn from the
researches of Dr. Forchhammer, that besides supplying in common with
land plants the materials of coal, the Algæ must give rise to important
chemical changes in the composition of strata in which they are imbedded.
These plants always contain sulphuric acid, and sometimes in as
large a quantity as 8½ per cent., combined with potash: magnesia also
and phosphoric acid are constant ingredients. Whenever large masses
of sea-weeds putrefy in contact with ferruginous clay, sulphuret of iron,
or iron pyrites, is formed by the union of the sulphur of the plants with
the iron of the clay; while the potash, released from its union with the
clay (i. e. silicate of alumina), forms with it a peculiar compound.
Many of the mineral characteristics of ancient rocks, especially the alum
slates, and the pyrites which occur in clay slate, and the fragments of
anthracite in marine Silurian strata, may be explained by the decomposition
of fucoids or sea-weeds.1106
Imbedding of cetacea.—It is not uncommon for the larger Cetacea,
which can float only in a considerable depth of water, to be carried during
storms or high tides into estuaries, or upon low shores, where, upon
the retiring of high water, they are stranded. Thus a narwal (Monodon
monoceros) was found on the beach, near Boston in Lincolnshire, in the
year 1800, the whole of its body buried in the mud. A fisherman going
to his boat saw the horn, and tried to pull it out, when the animal began
to stir itself.1107 An individual of the common whale (Balæna) mysticetus),
which measured seventy feet, came ashore near Peterhead, in 1682.
Many individuals of the genus Balænoptera have met the same fate. It
will be sufficient to refer to those cast on shore near Burnt Island, and
at Alloa, recorded by Sibbald and Neill. The other individual mentioned
by Sibbald, as having come ashore at Boyne, in Banffshire, was probably
a razor-back. Of the genus Catodon (Cachalot), Ray mentions a large
one stranded on the west coast of Holland in 1598, and the fact is also
commemorated in a Dutch engraving of the time of much merit. Sibbald,
too, records that a herd of Cachalots, upwards of 100 in number,
771
were found stranded at Cairston, in Orkney. The dead bodies of the
larger Cetacea are sometimes found floating on the surface of the waters,
as was the case with the immense whale exhibited in London in 1831.
And the carcase of a sea-cow or Lamantine (Halicora) was, in 1785,
cast ashore near Leith.
To some accident of this kind we may refer the position of the skeleton
of a whale, seventy-three feet long, which was found at Airthrey, on the
Forth, near Stirling, imbedded in clay twenty feet higher than the surface
of the highest tide of the river Forth at the present day. From the
situation of the Roman station and causeways at a small distance from
the spot, it is concluded that the whale must have been stranded there at
a period prior to the Christian era.1108
Other fossil remains of this class have also been found in estuaries known
to have been silted up in recent times, one example of which has been
already mentioned near Lewes, in Sussex.
Marine reptiles.—Some singular fossils have lately been discovered in
the Island of Ascension, in a stone said to be

Fig. 106.
Fossil eggs of turtles from the
Island of Ascension.1109

continually forming on the beach, where the
waves threw up small rounded fragments of
shells and corals, which, in the course of time,
become firmly agglutinated together, and constitute
a stone used largely for building and
making lime. In a quarry on the N. W. side
of the island, about 100 yards from the sea,
some fossil eggs of turtles have been discovered
in the hard rock thus formed. The eggs
must have been nearly hatched at the time when they perished; for the
bones of the young turtle are seen in the interior, with their shape fully developed,
the interstices between the bones being entirely filled with grains
of sand, which are cemented together, so that when the egg-shells are removed
perfect casts of their form remain in stone. In the single specimen
here figured (fig. 106), which is only five inches in its longest diameter,
no less than seven eggs are preserved.1110
To explain the state in which they occur fossil, it seems necessary to
suppose that after the eggs were almost hatched in the warm sand, a
great wave threw upon them so much more sand as to prevent the rays
of the sun from penetrating, so that the yolk was chilled and deprived of
772
vitality. The shells were, perhaps, slightly broken at the same time, so
that small grains of sand might gradually be introduced into the interior
by water as it percolated through the beach.
Fig. 107.

One of the eggs in fig. 106, of the natural size, showing the bones of the fœtus which had
been nearly hatched.
Marine testacea.—The aquatic animals and plants which inhabit an
estuary are liable, like the trees and land animals which people the alluvial
plains of a great river, to be swept from time to time far into the
deep; for as a river is perpetually shifting its course, and undermining a
portion of its banks with the forests which cover them, so the marine
current alters its direction from time to time, and bears away the banks
of sand and mud against which it turns its force. These banks may consist
in great measure of shells peculiar to shallow and sometimes brackish
water, which may have been accumulating for centuries, until at length
they are carried away and spread out along the bottom of the sea, at a
depth at which they could not have lived and multiplied. Thus littoral
and estuary shells are more frequently liable even than freshwater species,
to be intermixed with the exuviæ of pelagic tribes.
After the storm of February 4, 1831, when several vessels were
wrecked in the estuary of the Forth, the current was directed against a
bed of oysters with such force, that great heaps of them were thrown
alive upon the beach, and remained above high-water mark. I collected
many of these oysters, as also the common eatable whelks (Buccina),
thrown up with them, and observed that, although still living, their
shells were worn by the long attrition of sand which had passed over
them as they lay in their native bed, and which had evidently not resulted
from the mere action of the tempest by which they were cast
ashore.
From these facts we learn that the union of the two parts of a bivalve
shell does not prove that it has not been transported to a distance; and
773
when we find shells worn, and with all their prominent parts rubbed off,
they may still have been imbedded where they grew.
Burrowing shells.—It sometimes appears extraordinary, when we observe
the violence of the breakers on our coast, and see the strength of
the current in removing cliffs, and sweeping out new channels, that many
tender and fragile shells should inhabit the sea in the immediate vicinity
of this turmoil. But a great number of the bivalve Testacea, and many
also of the turbinated univalves, burrow in sand or mud. The Solen
and the Cardium, for example, which are usually found in shallow
water near the shore, pierce through a soft bottom without injury
to their shells; and the Pholas can drill a cavity through mud of considerable
hardness. The species of these and many other tribes can sink,
when alarmed, with considerable rapidity, often to the depth of several
feet, and can also penetrate upwards again to the surface, if a mass of
matter be heaped upon them. The hurricane, therefore, may expend its
fury in vain, and may sweep away even the upper part of banks of sand
or mud, or may roll pebbles over them, and yet these Testacea may remain
below secure and uninjured.
Shells become fossil at considerable depths.—I have already stated
that, at the depth of 950 fathoms, between Gibraltar and Ceuta, Captain
Smith found a gravelly bottom, with fragments of broken shells,
carried thither probably from the comparatively shallow parts of the
neighboring straits, through which a powerful current flows. Beds of
shelly sand might here, in the course of ages, be accumulated several
thousand feet thick. But, without the aid of the drifting power of a
current, shells may accumulate in the spot where they live and die, at
great depths from the surface, if sediment be thrown down upon them;
for even in our own colder latitudes, the depths at which living marine
animals abound is very considerable. Captain Vidal ascertained, by
soundings made off Tory Island, on the northwest coast of Ireland, that
Crustacea, Star-fish, and Testacea occurred at various depths between
fifty and one hundred fathoms; and he drew up Dentalia from the mud
of Galway Bay, in 230 and 240 fathoms water.
The same hydrographer discovered on the Rockhall Bank large quantities
of shells at depths varying from 45 to 190 fathoms. The shells
were for the most part pulverized, and evidently recent, as they retained
their colors. In the same region a bed of fish bones was observed extending
for two miles along the bottom of the sea in eighty and ninety
fathoms water. At the eastern extremity also of Rockhall Bank, fishbones
were met with, mingled with pieces of fresh shell, at the depth of
235 fathoms.
Analogous formations are in progress in the submarine tracts extending
from the Shetland Isles to the north of Ireland, wherever soundings
can be procured. A continuous deposit of sand and mud, replete with
broken and entire shells, Echini, &c., has been traced for upwards of
twenty miles to the eastward of the Faroe Islands, usually at the depth
of from forty to one hundred fathoms. In one part of this tract (lat.
774
61° 50', long. 6° 30') fish-bones occur in extraordinary profusion, so that
the lead cannot be drawn up without some vertebræ being attached.
This "bone bed," as it was called by our surveyors, is three miles and a
half in length, and forty-five fathoms under water, and contains a few
shells intermingled with the bones.
In the British seas, the shells and other organic remains lie in soft
mud or loose sand and gravel; whereas, in the bed of the Adriatic,
Donati found them frequently inclosed in stone of recent origin. This
is precisely the difference in character which we might have expected to
exist between the British marine formations now in progress and those
of the Adriatic; for calcareous and other mineral springs abound in the
Mediterranean and lands adjoining, while they are almost entirely wanting
in our own country. I have already adverted to the eight regions of
different depths in the Ægean Sea, each characterized by a peculiar assemblage
of shells, which have been described by Professor E. Forbes,
who explored them by dredging. (See above, p. 649.)
During his survey of the west coast of Africa, Captain Sir E. Belcher
found, by frequent soundings between the twenty-third and twentieth degrees
of north latitude, that the bottom of the sea, at the depth of from
twenty to about fifty fathoms, consists of sand with a great intermixture
of shells, often entire, but sometimes finely comminuted. Between the
eleventh and ninth degrees of north latitude, on the same coast, at soundings
varying from twenty to about eighty fathoms, he brought up abundance
of corals and shells mixed with sand. These also were in some
parts entire, and in others worn and broken.
In all these cases, it is only necessary that there should be some deposition
of sedimentary matter, however minute, such as may be supplied
by rivers draining a continent, or currents preying on a line of cliffs, in
order that stratified formations, hundreds of feet in thickness, and replete
with organic remains, should result in the course of ages.
But although some deposits may thus extend continuously for a thousand
miles or more near certain coasts, the greater part of the bed of the
ocean, remote from continents and islands, may very probably receive, at
the same time, no new accessions of drift matter, all sediment being intercepted
by intervening hollows, in which a marine current must clear its
waters as thoroughly as a turbid river in a lake. Erroneous theories in
geology may be formed not only from overlooking the great extent of
simultaneous deposits now in progress, but also from the assumption
that such formations may be universal or coextensive with the bed of
the ocean.
We frequently observe, on the sea beach, very perfect specimens of
fossil shells, quite detached from their matrix, which have been washed
out of older formations, constituting the sea-cliffs. They may be all of
extinct species, like the Eocene freshwater and marine shells strewed over
the shores of Hampshire, yet when they become mingled with the shells
of the present period, and buried in the same deposits of mud and sand,
they would appear, if upraised and examined by future geologists, to
775
have been all of the same age. That such intermixture and blending
of organic remains of different ages have actually taken place in former
times, is unquestionable, though the occurrence appears to be very local
and exceptional. It is, however, a class of accidents more likely than
almost any other to lead to serious anachronisms in geological chronology.
</div></body></text></TEI>