<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Chambers Robert</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="15">p.
236MACLEAY SYSTEM OF ANIMATED NATURE.
THIS SYSTEM CONSIDERED IN CONNEXION WITH
THE
PROGRESS OF ORGANIC CREATION, AND AS
INDICATING
THE NATURAL STATUS OF MAN.
It is now high time to advert to
the system formed by the animated tribes, both with a view to the
possible illustration of the preceding argument, and for the
light which it throws upon that general system of nature which it
is the more comprehensive object of this book to ascertain.
The vegetable and animal kingdoms are arranged upon a scale,
starting from simply organized forms, and going on to the more
complex, each of these forms being but slightly different from
those next to it on both sides.  The lowest and most
slightly developed forms in the two kingdoms are so closely
connected, that it is impossible to say where vegetable ends and
animal begins.  United at what may be called their bases,
they start away in different directions, but not altogether to
lose sight of each other.  On the contrary, they maintain a
strict analogy throughout the whole of their subsequent courses,
sub-kingdom for sub-kingdom, class for class; shewing a
beautiful, though as yet obscure relation between the two grand
forms of being, and consequently a unity in the laws which
brought them both into existence.  So complete does this
analogy appear, even in the present imperfect state of science,
that I fully expect in a few years to see the animal and
vegetable kingdoms duly ranked up against each other in a system
of parallels, which will admit of our assigning to each species
in the former the particular shrub or tree corresponding to it in
the latter, all marked by unmistakable analogies of the most
interesting kind.
It is as yet but a few years since a system of subordinate
analogies not less remarkable began to be speculated upon as
within the range of the animal kingdom.  Probably it also
exists in the vegetable kingdom; but to this point no direct
attention has been given; so we are left to infer that such is
the case from theoretical considerations only.  We are
indebted for what we know of these beautiful analogies to three
naturalists—Macleay, Vigors, and Swainson, whose labours
tempt us to dismiss in a great measure the artificial
classifications hitherto used, and make an entirely new
conspectus of the animal kingdom, not to speak of the
corresponding reform which will be required in our systems of
botany also.
The Macleay system, as it may be called in honour of its
principal author, announces that, whether we take the whole
animal kingdom, or any definite division of it, we shall find
that we are examining a group of beings which is capable of being
arranged along a series of close affinities, in a circular
form,—that is to say, starting from any one portion of
the group, when it is properly arranged, we can proceed from one
to another by minute gradations, till at length, having run
through the whole, we return to the point whence we set
out.  All natural groups of animals are, therefore, in the
language of Mr. Macleay, circular; and the possibility of
throwing any supposed group into a circular arrangement is held
as a decisive test of its being a real or natural one.  It
is of course to be understood that each circle is composed of a
set of inferior circles: for example, a set of tribe
circles composes an order; a set of order circles,
again, forms a class; and so on.  Of each group, the
component circles are invariably five in number: thus, in
the animal kingdom, there are five sub-kingdoms,—the
vertebrata, annulosa, [239a] radiata, acrita,
[239b] mollusca.  Take, again, one of
these sub-kingdoms, the vertebrata, and we find it composed of
five classes,—the mammalia, reptilia, pisces, amphibia, and
aves, each of the other sub-kingdoms being similarly
divisible.  Take the mammalia, and it is in like manner
found to be composed of five orders,—the cheirotheria, [239c] feræ, cetacea, glires,
ungulata.  Even in this numerical uniformity, which goes
down to the lowest ramifications of the system, there would be
something very remarkable, as arguing a definite and preconceived
arrangement; but this is only the least curious part of the
Macleay theory.
We shall best understand the wonderfully complex system of
analogies developed by that theory, if we start from the part of
the kingdom in which they were first traced,—namely, the
class aves, or birds.  This gives for its five
orders,—incessores, (perching birds,)
raptores, (birds of prey,) natatores, (swimming
birds,) grallatores, (waders,) rasores,
(scrapers.)  In these orders our naturalists discerned
distinct organic characters, of different degrees of perfectness,
the first being the most perfect with regard to the general
character of the class, and therefore the best representative of
that class; whence it was called the typical order. 
The second was found to be inferior, or rather to have a less
perfect balance of qualities; hence it was designated the
sub-typical.  In this are comprehended the chief
noxious and destructive animals of the circle to which it
belongs.  The other three groups were called aberrant, as
exhibiting a much wider departure from the typical standard,
although the last of the three is observed to make a certain
recovery, and join on to the typical group, so as to complete the
circle.  The first of the aberrant groups (natatores) is
remarkable for making the water the theatre of its existence, and
the birds composing it are in general of comparatively large
bulk.  The second (grallatores) are long-limbed and
long-billed, that they may wade and pick up their subsistence in
the shallows and marshes in which they chiefly live.  The
third (rasores) are distinguished by strong feet, for walking or
running on the ground, and for scraping in it for their food;
also by wings designed to scarcely raise them off the earth and,
farther, by a general domesticity of character and usefulness to
man.
Now the most remarkable circumstance is, that these organic
characters, habits, and moral properties, were found to be
traceable more or less distinctly in the corresponding portions
of every other group, even of those belonging to distant
subdivisions of the animal kingdom, as, for instance, the
insects.  The incessores (typical order of aves) being
reduced to its constituent circles or tribes, it was found that
these strictly represented the five orders.  In the
conirostres are the perfections which belong to the
incessores as an order, with the conspicuous external feature of
a comparatively small notch in their bills; in the
dentirostres, the notch is strong and toothlike, (hence
the name of the tribe) assimilating them to the raptores; the
fissirostres come into analogy with the natatores in the
slight development of their feet and their great powers of
flight; the tenuirostres have the small mouths and long
soft bills of the grallatores.  Finally, the
scansores resemble the rasores in their superior
intelligence and docility, and in their having strong limbs and a
bill entire at the tip.  This parity of qualities becomes
clearer when placed in a tabular form:—


Orders of Birds.

Characters.

Tribes of
Incessores.



Incessores

Most perfect of their circle; notch of bill small

Conirostres.



Raptores

Notch of bill like a tooth

Dentirostres.



Natatores

Slightly developed feet; strong flight

Fissirostres.



Grallatores

Small mouths; long soft bills

Tenuirostres.



Rasores

Strong feet, short wings; docile and domestic

Scansores.



Some comprehensive terms are much wanted to describe these
five characters, so curiously repeated throughout the whole of
the animal, and probably also the vegetable kingdom. 
Meanwhile, Mr. Swainson calls them typical, sub-typical,
natatorial, suctorial, [242] and
rasorial.  Some of his illustrations of the principle are
exceedingly interesting.  He shews that the leading animal
of a typical circle usually has a combination of properties
concentrated in itself, without any of these preponderating
remarkably over others.  The sub-typical circles, he says,
“do not comprise the largest individuals in bulk, but
always those which are the most powerfully armed, either for
inflicting injury on their own class, for exciting terror,
producing injury, or creating annoyance to man.  Their
dispositions are often sanguinary, since the forms most
conspicuous among them live by rapine, and subsist on the blood
of other animals.  They are, in short, symbolically types of
evil.”  This symbolical character is most
conspicuous about the centre of the series of
gradations:—


Kingdom

Annulosa.



Sub-kingdom

Reptilia.



Class (Mammalia)

Feræ.



(Aves)

Raptores.



In the annulosa it is not distinct, although we must also
remember that insects do produce enormous ravages and annoyance
in many parts of the earth.  In the reptilia it is more
distinct, since to this class belong the ophidia, (serpents,) an
order peculiarly noxious.  It comes to a kind of climax in
the feræ and raptores, which fulfil the function of
butchers among land animals.  As we descend through tribes,
families, genera, species, it becomes fainter and fainter, but
never altogether vanishes.  In the dentirostres, for
instance, we have in a subdued form the hooked bill and
predaceous character of the raptores; to this tribe belongs the
family of the shrikes, so deadly to all the lesser field
birds.  In the genus bos, we have, in the sub-typical group,
the bison, “wild, revengeful, and shewing an innate
detestation of man.”  In equus, we have, in the same
situation, the zebra, which actually shews the stripes of the
tiger, and is as remarkable for its wildness as its congeners,
the horse and ass, are for their docility and usefulness. 
To quote again from Mr. Swainson, “the singular threatening
aspect which the caterpillars of the sphinx moth assume on being
disturbed, is a remarkable modification of the terrific or evil
nature which is impressed in one form or another, palpable or
remote, upon all sub-typical groups; for this division of the
lepidopterous order is precisely of this denomination.  In
the pre-eminent type of this order of insects, the butterflies,
(papilionides,) our associations little prepare us for expecting
any trace of the evil principle; but here, too, there is a
sub-typical division.  These,” says our naturalist,
“are distinguished by their caterpillars being armed with
formidable spines or prickles, which in general are possessed of
some highly acrimonious or poisonous quality, capable of injuring
those who touch them.  It is only,” continues Mr.
Swainson, “when extensive researches bring to light a
uniformity of results, that we can venture to believe they are so
universal as to deserve being ranked as primary laws.  Thus,
when a celebrated entomologist denounced as impure the black and
lurid beetles forming the saprophagous petalocera of Mr. Macleay,
a tribe living only upon putrid vegetable matter, and hiding
themselves in their disgusting food, or in dark hollows of the
earth, neither of these celebrated men suspected the absolute
fact, elicited from our analogies of this group, that this very
tribe constituted the sub-typical group of one of the primary
divisions of coleopterous insects: nor had they any suspicion
that, by the filthy habits and repulsive forms of these beetles,
nature had intended that they should be types or emblems of
hundreds of other groups, distinguished by peculiarities equally
indicative of evil.  On the other hand, the thalerophagous
petalocera, forming the typical group of the same division,
present us with all the perfections and habits belonging to their
kind.  These families of beetles live only upon fresh
vegetables; they are diurnal, and sport in the glare of day, pure
in their food, elegant in their shapes, and beautiful in their
colours.” [246]
The third type, (first of the three aberrant,) called by Mr.
Swainson, the natatorial, or aquatic, are chiefly
remarkable for their bulk, the disproportionate size of the head,
and the absence, or slight development of the feet.  They
partake of the predaceous and destructive character of the
adjoining sub-typical group, and the means of their predacity are
generally found in the mouth alone.  In the primary division
of the animal kingdom, we find the type in the radiata, not one
of which lives out of water.  In the vertebrata, it is in
the fishes.  In both of these, feet are totally
wanting.  Descending to the class mammalia, we have this
type in the cetacea, which present a comparatively slight
development of limbs.  In the aves, as we have seen, the
type is presented in the natatores, whose name has been adopted
as an appropriate term for all the corresponding groups.  An
enumeration of some other examples of the natatorial type, as the
cephalopoda (instanced in the cuttle-fish) in the mollusca; the
crustacea (crabs, &c.) in the annulosa; the owls (which often
duck for fish) in the raptores; the ichthyosaurus, plesiosaurus,
&c., among reptilia, will serve to bring the general
character, and its pervasion of the whole animal world, forcibly
before the mind of the reader.
The next type is that of meanest and most imperfect
organization, the lower termination of all groups, as the typical
is the upper.  It is called by Mr. Swainson the suctorial,
from a very generally prevalent peculiarity, that of drawing
sustenance by suction.  The acrita, or polypes, among the
sub-kingdoms; the intestina, among the annulosa; the tortoises,
among the reptilia; the armadillo and scaly ant-eater, pig,
mouse, jerboa, and kangaroo, among quadrupeds; the waders and
tenuirostres, among birds; the coleoptera, (bug, louse, flea,
&c.) among insects; the gastrobranchus, among fishes; are
examples which will illustrate the special characters of this
type.  These are smallness, particularly in the head and
mouth, feebleness, and want of offensive protection, defect of
organs of mastication, considerable powers of swift movement, and
(often) a parasitic mode of living; while of negative qualities,
there are, besides, indisposition to domestication, and an
unsuitableness to serve as human food.
The rasorial type comprehends most of the animals which become
domesticated and useful to man, as, first, the fowls which give a
name to the type, the ungulata, and more particularly the
ruminantia, among quadrupeds, and the dog among the
feræ.  Gentleness, familiarity with man, and a
peculiar approach to human intelligence, are the leading mental
characteristics of animals of this type.  Amongst external
characters, we generally find power of limbs and feet for
locomotion on land, (to which the rasorial type is confined,)
abundant tail and ornaments for the head, whether in the form of
tufts, crests, horns, or bony excrescences.  In the animal
kingdom, the mollusca are the rasorial type, which, however, only
shews itself there in their soft and sluggish character, and
their being very generally edible.  In the ptilota, or
winged insects, the hymenopterous are the rasorial type, and it
is not therefore surprising to find amongst them the ants and
bees, “the most social, intelligent, and in the latter
case, most useful to man, of all the annulose animals.”
As yet the speculations on representation are imperfect, in
consequence of the novelty of the doctrine, and the defective
state of our knowledge of animated nature.  It has, however,
been so fully proved in the aves, and traced so clearly in other
parts of the animal kingdom, and as a general feature of that
part of nature, that hardly a doubt can exist of its being
universally applicable.  Even in the lowly forms of the
acrita, (polypes,) the suctorial type of the animal kingdom,
representation has been discerned, and with some remarkable
results as to the history of our world.  The acrita were the
first forms of animal life upon earth, the starting point of that
great branch of organization.  Now, this sub-kingdom
consists, like the rest, of five groups, (classes,) and these are
respectively representations of the acrita itself, and the other
four sub-kingdoms, which had not come into existence when the
acrita were formed.  The polypi vaginati, in the crustaceous
covering of the living mass, and their more or less articulated
structure, represent the annulosa.  In the radiated
forms of the rotifera, and the simple structure of the polypi
rudes, we are reminded of the radiata.  The
mollusca are typified in the soft, mucous, sluggish
intestina.  And, finally, in the fleshy living mass which
surrounds the bony and hollow axis of the polypi natantes, we
have a sketch of the vertebrata.  The acrita thus
appear as a prophecy of the higher events of animal
development.  They shew that the nobler orders of being,
including man himself, were contemplated from the first, and came
into existence by virtue of a law, the operation of which had
commenced ages before their forms were realized.
The system of representation is therefore to be regarded as
a powerful additional proof of the hypothesis of organic
progress by virtue of law.  It establishes the unity of
animated nature and the definite character of its entire
constitution.  It enables us to see how, under the flowing
robes of nature, where all looks arbitrary and accidental, there
is an artificiality of the most rigid kind.  The natural, we
now perceive, sinks into and merges in a Higher Artificial. 
To adopt a comparison more apt than dignified, we may be said to
be placed here as insects are in a garden of the old style. 
Our first unassisted view is limited, and we perceive only the
irregularities of the minute surface, and single shrubs which
appear arbitrarily scattered.  But our view at length
extending and becoming more comprehensive, we begin to see
parterres balancing each other, trees, statues, and arbours
placed symmetrically, and that the whole is an assemblage of
parts mutually reflective.  It can scarcely be necessary to
point to the inference hence arising with regard to the
origination of nature in some Power, of which man’s mind is
a faint and humble representation.  The insects of the
garden, supposing them to be invested with reasoning power, and
aware how artificial are their own works, might of course very
reasonably conclude that, being in its totality an artificial
object, the garden was the work of some maker or artificer. 
And so also must we conclude, when we attain a knowledge of the
artificiality which is at the basis of nature, that nature is
wholly the production of a Being resembling, but infinitely
greater than ourselves.
Organic beings are, then, bound together in development, and
in a system of both affinities and analogies.  Now, it will
be asked, does this agree with what we know of the geographical
distribution of organic beings, and of the history of organic
progress as delineated by geology?  Let us first advert to
the geographical question.
Plants, as is well known, require various kinds of soil, forms
of geographical surface, climate, and other conditions, for their
existence.  And it is everywhere found that, however
isolated a particular spot may be with regard to these
conditions,—as a mountain top in a torrid country, the
marsh round a salt spring far inland, or an island placed far
apart in the ocean,—appropriate plants have there taken up
their abode.  But the torrid zone divides the two temperate
regions from each other by the space of more than forty-six
degrees, and the torrid and temperate zones together form a much
broader line of division between the two arctic regions. 
The Atlantic and Pacific Oceans, and the Persian Gulf, also
divide the various portions of continent in the torrid and
temperate zones from each other.  Australia is also divided
by a broad sea from the continent of Asia.  Thus there are
various portions of the earth separated from each other in such a
way as to preclude anything like a general communication of the
seeds of their respective plants towards each other.  Hence
arises an interesting question—Are the plants of the
various isolated regions which enjoy a parity of climate and
other conditions, identical or the reverse?  The answer
is—that in such regions the vegetation bears a general
resemblance, but the species are nearly all different, and
there is even, in a considerable measure, a diversity of
families.
The general facts have been thus stated: in the arctic and
antarctic regions, and in those parts of lower latitudes, which,
from their elevation, possess the same cold climate, there is
always a similar or analogous vegetation, but few species are
common to the various situations.  In like manner, the
intertropical vegetation of Asia, Africa, and America, are
specifically different, though generally similar.  The
southern region of America is equally diverse from that of
Africa, a country similar in clime, but separated by a vast
extent of ocean.  The vegetation of Australia, another
region similarly placed in respect of clime, is even more
peculiar.  These facts are the more remarkable when we
discover that, in most instances, the plants of one region have
thriven when transplanted to another of parallel clime. 
This would shew that parity of conditions does not lead to a
parity of productions so exact as to include identity of species,
or even genera.  Besides the various isolated regions here
enumerated, there are some others indicated by naturalists as
exhibiting a vegetation equally peculiar.  Some of these are
isolated by mountains, or the interposition of sandy
wastes.  For example, the temperate region of the elder
continent is divided about the centre of Asia, and the east of
that line is different from the west.  So also is the same
region divided in North America by the Rocky Mountains. 
Abyssinia and Nubia constitute another distinct botanical
region.  De Candolle enumerates in all twenty well-marked
portions of the earth’s surface which are peculiar with
respect to vegetation; a number which would be greatly increased
if remote islands and isolated mountain ranges were to be
included.
When we come to the zoology, we find precisely similar
results, excepting that man (with, perhaps, some of the less
conspicuous forms of being) is universal, and that several
tribes, as the bear and dog, appear to have passed by the land
connexion from the arctic regions of the eastern to those of the
western hemisphere.  “With these exceptions,”
says Dr. Prichard, “and without any others, as far as
zoological researches have yet gone, it may be asserted that no
individual species are common to distant regions.  In
parallel climates, analogous species replace each other;
sometimes, but not frequently, the same genus is found in two
separate continents; but the species which are natives of one
region are not identical with corresponding races indigenous in
the opposite hemisphere.
“A similar result arises when we compare the three great
intertropical regions, as well as the extreme spaces of the three
great continents, which advance into the temperate climates of
the southern hemisphere.
“Thus, the tribes of simiæ, (monkeys,) of the dog
and cat kinds, of pachyderms, including elephants, tapirs,
rhinoceroses, hogs, of bats, of saurian and ophidian reptiles, as
well of birds and other terrene animals, are all different in the
three great continents.  In the lower departments of the
mammiferous family, we find that the bruta, or edendata, (sloths,
armadillos, &c.,) of Africa, are differently organized from
those of America, and these again from the tribes found in the
Malayan archipelago and Terra Australis.” [255]
It does not appear that the diversity between the similar
regions of Africa, Asia, and America, is occasioned in all
instances by any disqualification of these countries to support
precisely the same genera or species.  The ox, horse, goat,
&c., of the elder continent have thriven and extended
themselves in the new, and many of the indigenous tribes of
America would no doubt flourish in corresponding climates in
Europe, Asia, and Africa.  It has, however, been remarked by
naturalists unacquainted with the Macleay system, that the larger
and more powerful animals of their respective orders belong to
the elder continent, and that thus the animals of America, unlike
the features of inanimate nature, appear to be upon a small
scale.  The swiftest and most agile animals, and a large
proportion of those most useful to man, are also natives of the
elder continent.  On the other hand, the bulk of the
edentata, a group remarkable for defects and meanness of
organization, are American.  The zoology of America may be
said, upon the whole, to recede from that of Asia, “and
perhaps in a greater degree,” adds Dr. Prichard,
“from that of Africa.”  A much greater recession
is, however, observed in both the botany and zoology of
Australia.
There “we do not find, in the great masses of
vegetation, either the majesty of the virgin forests of America,
or the variety and elegance of those of Asia, or the delicacy and
freshness of the woods of our temperate countries of
Europe.  The vegetation is generally gloomy and sad; it has
the aspect of our evergreens or heaths; the plants are for the
most part woody; the leaves of nearly all the plants are linear,
lanceolated, small, coriaceous, and spinescent.  The
grasses, which elsewhere are generally soft and flexible,
participate in the stiffness of the other vegetables.  The
greater part of the plants of New Holland belong to new genera;
and those included in the genera already known are of new
species.  The natural families which prevail are those of
the heaths, the proteæ, compositæ, leguminosæ,
and myrthoideæ; the larger trees all belong to the last
family.” [257]
The prevalent animals of Australia are not less
peculiar.  It is well known that none above the marsupialia,
or pouched animals, are native to it.  The most conspicuous
are these marsupials, which exist in great varieties here, though
unknown in the elder continent, and only found in a few mean
forms in America.  Next to them are the monotremata, which
are entirely peculiar to this portion of the earth.  Now
these are animals at the bottom of the mammiferous class,
adjoining to that of birds, of whose character and organization
the monotremata largely partake, the ornithorynchus presenting
the bill and feet of a duck, producing its young in eggs, and
having, like birds, a clavicle between the two shoulders. 
The birds of Australia vary in structure and plumage, but all
have some singularity about them—the swan, for instance, is
black.  The country abounds in reptiles, and the prevalent
fishes are of the early kinds, having a cartilaginous
structure.
Altogether, the plants and animals of this minor continent
convey the impression of an early system of things, such as might
be displayed in other parts of the earth about the time of the
oolite.  In connexion with this circumstance, it is a fact
of some importance, that the geognostic character of Australia,
its vast arid plains, its little diversified surface and
consequent paucity of streams, and the very slight development of
volcanic rock on its surface, seem to indicate a system of
physical conditions, such as we may suppose to have existed
elsewhere in the oolitic era: perhaps we see the chalk formation
preparing there in the vast coral beds frontiering the
coast.  Australia thus appears as a portion of the earth
which has, from some unknown causes, been belated in its physical
and organic development.  And certainly the greater part of
its surface is not fitted to be an advantageous place of
residence for beings above the marsupialia, and judging from
analogy, it may yet be subjected to a series of changes in the
highest degree inconvenient to any human beings who may have
settled upon it.
The general conclusions regarding the geography of organic
nature, may be thus stated.  (1.) There are numerous
distinct foci of organic production throughout the earth. 
(2.) These have everywhere advanced in accordance with the local
conditions of climate &c., as far as at least the class and
order are concerned, a diversity taking place in the lower
gradations.  No physical or geographical reason appearing
for this diversity, we are led to infer that, (3,) it is the
result of minute and inappreciable causes giving the law of
organic development a particular direction in the lower
subdivisions of the two kingdoms.  (4.) Development has not
gone on to equal results in the various continents, being most
advanced in the eastern continent, next in the western, and least
in Australia, this inequality being perhaps the result of the
comparative antiquity of the various regions, geologically and
geographically.
It must at the same time be admitted that the line of organic
development has nowhere required for its advance the whole of the
families comprehended in the two kingdoms, seeing that some of
these are confined to one continent, and some to another, without
a conceivable possibility of one having been connected with the
other in the way of ancestry.  The two great families of
quadrumana, cebidæ and simiadæ, are a noted instance,
the one being exclusively American, while the other belongs
entirely to the old world.  There are many other cases in
which the full circular group can only be completed by taking
subdivisions from various continents.  This would seem to
imply that, while the entire system is so remarkable for its
unity, it has nevertheless been produced in lines geographically
detached, these lines perhaps consisting of particular typical
groups placed in an independent succession, or of two or more of
these groups.  And for this idea there is, even in the
present imperfect state of our knowledge of animated nature, some
countenance in ascertained facts, the birds of Australia, for
example, being chiefly of the suctorial type, while it may be
presumed that the observation as to the predominance of the
useful animals in the Old World, is not much different from
saying that the rasorial type is there peculiarly abundant. 
It does not appear that the idea of independent lines, consisting
of particular types, or sets of types, is necessarily
inconsistent with the general hypothesis, as nothing yet
ascertained of the Macleay system forbids their having an
independent set of affinities.  On this subject, however,
there is as yet much obscurity, and it must be left to future
inquirers to clear it up.
We must now call to mind that the geographical distribution of
plants and animals was very different in the geological ages from
what it is now.  Down to a time not long antecedent to man,
the same vegetation overspread every clime, and a similar
uniformity marked the zoology.  This is conceived by M.
Brogniart, with great plausibility, to have been the result of a
uniformity of climate, produced by the as yet unexhausted effect
of the internal heat of the earth upon its surface; whereas
climate has since depended chiefly on external sources of heat,
as modified by the various meteorological influences. 
However the early uniform climate was produced, certain it is
that, from about the close of the geological epoch, plants and
animals have been dispersed over the globe with a regard to their
particular characters, and specimens of both are found so
isolated in particular situations, as utterly to exclude the idea
that they came thither from any common centre.  It may be
asked,—Considering that, in the geological epoch, species
are not limited to particular regions, and that since the close
of that epoch, they are very peculiarly limited, are we to
presume the present organisms of the world to have been created
ab initio after that time?  To this it may be
answered,—Not necessarily, as it so happens that animals
begin to be much varied, or to appear in a considerable variety
of species, towards the close of the geological history.  It
may have been that the multitudes of locally peculiar species
only came into being after the uniform climate had passed
away.  It may have only been when a varied climate arose,
that the originally few species branched off into the present
extensive variety.
A question of a very interesting kind will now probably arise
in the reader’s mind—What place or status is
assigned to man in the new natural system.  Before going
into this inquiry, it is necessary to advert to several
particulars of the natural system not yet noticed.
It is necessary, in particular, to ascertain the grades which
exist in the classification of animals.  In the line of the
aves, Mr. Swainson finds these to be nine, the species pica, for
example, being thus indicated:—


Kingdom

Animalia.



Sub-kingdom

Vertebrata.



Class

Aves.



Order

Incessores.



Tribe

Conirostres.



Family

Corvidæ.



Sub-family

Corvinæ.



Genus

Corvus.



Sub-genus, or species

Pica.



This brings us down to species, the subdivision where
intermarriage or breeding is usually considered as natural to
animals, and where a resemblance of offspring to parents is
generally persevered in.  The dog, for instance, is a
species, because all dogs can breed together, and the progeny
partakes of the appearances of the parents.  The human race
is held as a species, primarily for the same reasons. 
Species, however, is liable to another subdivision, which
naturalists call variety; and variety appears to be subject to
exactly the same system of representation which have been
traced in species and higher denominations.  In canis, for
instance, the bull-dog and mastiff represent the ferocious
sub-typical group; the waterdog is natatorial; we see the speed
and length of muzzle of the suctorial group in the greyhound; and
the bushy tail and gentle and serviceable character of the
rasorial in the shepherd’s dog and spaniel.  Even the
striped and spotted skin of the tiger and panther is reproduced
in the more ferocious kind of dogs—an indication of a
fundamental connexion between physical and mental qualities which
we have also seen in the zebra, and which is likewise displayed
in the predominance of a yellow colour in the vultures and owls
in common with the lion and his congeners.
It is by no means clearly made out that this system of nine
gradations over and above that of variety applies in all
departments of nature.  On the contrary, even Mr. Swainson
gives series in which several of them are omitted.  It may
be that, in some departments of nature, variation from the class
or order has gone down into fewer shades than in others; or it
may be, that many of the variations have not survived till our
era, or have not been as yet detected by naturalists; in either
of which cases there may be a necessity for shortening the series
by the omission of one or two grades, as for instance
tribe or sub-family.  This, however, is much
to be regretted, as it introduces an irregularity into the
natural system, and consequently throws a difficulty and doubt in
the way of our investigating it.  With these preliminary
remarks, I shall proceed to inquire what is the natural status of
man.
That man’s place is to be looked for in the class
mammalia and sub-kingdom vertebrata admits of no doubt, from his
possessing both the characters on which these divisions are
founded.  When we descend, however, below the class,
we find no settled views on the subject amongst
naturalists.  Mr. Swainson, who alone has given a review of
the animal kingdom on the Macleay system, unfortunately writes on
this subject in a manner which excites a suspicion as to his
judgment.  His arrangement of the first or typical order of
the mammalia is therefore to be received with great
hesitation.  It is as follows:—


Typical

Quadrumana

Pre-eminently organized for grasping.



Sub-typical

Feræ

Claws retractile; carnivorous.



Natatorial

Cetacea

Pre-eminently aquatic; feet very short.



Suctorial

Glires

Muzzle lengthened and pointed.



Rasorial

Ungulata

Crests and other processes on the head.



He then takes the quadrumana, and places it in the following
arrangement:—


Typical

Simiadæ

(Monkeys of Old World.)



Sub-typical

Cebidæ

(Monkeys of New World.)



Natatorial

Unknown

 



Suctorial

Vespertilionidæ

(Bats.)



Rasorial

Lemuridæ

(Lemurs.)



He considers the simiadæ as a complete circle, and
argues thence that there is no room in the range of the animal
kingdom for man.  Man, he says, is not a constituent part of
any circle, for, if he were, there ought to be other animals on
each hand having affinity to him, whereas there are none, the
resemblance of the orangs being one of mere analogy.  Mr.
Swainson therefore considers our race as standing apart, and
forming a link between the unintelligent order of beings and the
angels!  And this in spite of the glaring fact that, in our
teeth, hands, and other features grounded on by naturalists as
characteristic, we do not differ more from the simiadæ than
the bats do from the lemurs—in spite also of that
resemblance of analogy to the orangs which he himself admits, and
which, at the least, must be held to imply a certain
relation.  He also overlooks that, though there may be no
room for man in the circle of the simiadæ, (this, indeed,
is quite true,) there may be in the order, where he actually
leaves a place entirely blank, or only to be filled up, as he
suggests, by mermen! [266]  Another
argument in his arrangement is, that it leaves the grades of
classification very much abridged, there being at the most seven
instead of nine.  But serious argument on a theory so
preposterous may be considered as nearly thrown away.  I
shall therefore at once proceed to suggest a new arrangement of
this portion of the animal kingdom, in which man is allowed the
place to which he is zoologically entitled.
I propose that the typical order of the mammalia should be
designated cheirotheria, from the sole character which is
universal amongst them, their possessing hands, and with a regard
to that pre-eminent qualification for grasping which has been
ascribed to them—an analogy to the perching habit of the
typical order of birds, which is worthy of particular
notice.  The tribes of the cheirotheria I arrange as
follows:—


Typical

Bimana.



Sub-typical

Simiadæ.



Natatorial

Vespertilionidæ.



Suctorial

Lemuridæ.



Rasorial

Cebidæ.



Here man is put into the typical place, as the genuine head,
not only of this order, but of the whole animal world.  The
double affinity which is requisite is obtained, for here he has
the simiadæ on one hand, and the cebidæ on the
other.  The five tribes of the order are completed, the
vespertilionidæ being shifted (provisionally) into the
natatorial place, for which their appropriateness is so far
evidenced by the aquatic habits of several of the tribe, and the
lemuridæ into the suctorial, to which their length of
muzzle and remarkable saltatory power are highly suitable. 
At the same time, the simiadæ are degraded from the typical
place, to which they have no sort of pretension, and placed where
their mean and mischievous character seem to require; the
cebidæ again being assigned that situation which their
comparatively inoffensive dispositions, their arboreal habits,
and their extraordinary development of the tail, (which with them
is like a fifth hand,) render so proper.
The zoological status thus assigned to the human race is
precisely what might be expected.  In order to understand
its full value, it is necessary to observe how the various type
peculiarities operate in fixing the character of the animals
ranked in them.  It is easy to conceive that they must be,
in some instances, much mixed up with each other, and
consequently obscured.  If an animal, for example, is the
suctorial member of a circle of species, forming the natatorial
type of genera, forming a family or sub-family which in its turn
is rasorial, its qualities must evidently be greatly mingled and
ill to define.  But, on the other hand, if we take the
rapacious or sub-typical group of birds, and look in it for the
tribe which is again the rapacious or sub-typical group of its
order, we may expect to find the qualities of that group exalted
or intensified, and accordingly made the more conspicuous. 
Such is really the case with the vultures, in the rapacious
birds, a family remarkable above all of their order for their
carnivorous and foul habits.  So, also, if we take the
typical group of the birds, the incessores or perchers, and look
in it for its typical group, the conirostres, and seek there
again for the typical family of that group, the corvidæ, we
may expect to find a very marked superiority in organization and
character.  Such is really the case.  “The
crow,” says Mr. Swainson, “unites in itself a greater
number of properties than are to be found individually in any
other genus of birds; as if in fact it had taken from all the
other orders a portion of their peculiar qualities, for the
purpose of exhibiting in what manner they could be
combined.  From the rapacious birds this “type of
types,” as the crow has been justly called, takes the power
of soaring in the air, and of seizing upon living birds, like the
hawks, while its habit of devouring putrid substances, and
picking out the eyes of young animals, is borrowed from the
vultures.  From the scansorial or climbing order it takes
the faculty of picking the ground, and discovering its food when
hidden from the eye, while the parrot family gives it the taste
for vegetable food, and furnishes it with great cunning,
sagacity, and powers of imitation, even to counterfeiting the
human voice.  Next come the order of waders, who impart
their quota to the perfection of the crow by giving it great
powers of flight, and perfect facility in walking, such being
among the chief attributes of the suctorial order.  Lastly,
the aquatic birds contribute their portion, by giving this
terrestrial bird the power of feeding not only on fish, which are
their peculiar food, but actually of occasionally catching it. [270]  In this wonderful manner do we
find the crow partially invested with the united properties of
all other birds, while in its own order, that of the incessores
or perchers, it stands the pre-eminent type.  We cannot also
fail to regard it as a remarkable proof of the superior
organization and character of the corvidæ, that they are
adapted for all climates, and accordingly found all over the
world.
Mr. Swainson’s description of the zoological status of
the crow, written without the least design of throwing any light
upon that of man, evidently does so in a remarkable degree. 
It prepares us to expect in the place among the mammalia,
corresponding to that of the corvidæ in the aves, a being
or set of beings possessing a remarkable concentration of
qualities from all the other groups of their order, but in
general character as far above the corvidæ as a typical
group is above an aberrant one, the mammalia above the
aves.  Can any of the simiadæ pretend to such a place,
narrowly and imperfectly endowed as these creatures are—a
mean reflection apparently of something higher?  Assuredly
not, and in this consideration alone Mr. Swainson’s
arrangement must fall to the ground.  To fill worthily so
lofty a station in the animated families man alone is
competent.  In him only is to be found that concentration of
qualities from all the other groups of his order which has been
described as marking the corvidæ.  That grasping
power, which has been selected as the leading physical quality of
his order, is nowhere so beautifully or so powerfully developed
as in his hand.  The intelligence and teachableness of the
simiadæ rise to a climax in his pre-eminent mental
nature.  His sub-analogy to the feræ is marked by his
canine teeth, and the universality of his rapacity, for where is
the department of animated nature which he does not without
scruple sacrifice to his convenience?  With sanguinary, he
has also gentle and domesticable dispositions, thus reflecting
the characters of the ungulata, (the rasorial type of the class,)
to which we perhaps see a further analogy in the use which he
makes of the surface of the earth as a source of food.  To
the aquatic type his love of maritime adventure very readily
assimilates him; and how far the suctorial is represented in his
nature it is hardly necessary to say.  As the corvidæ,
too, are found in every part of the earth—almost the only
one of the inferior animals which has been acknowledged as
universal—so do we find man.  He thrives in all
climates, and with regard to style of living, can adapt himself
to an infinitely greater diversity of circumstances than any
other animated creature.
Man, then, considered zoologically, and without regard to the
distinct character assigned to him by theology, simply takes his
place as the type of all types of the animal kingdom, the true
and unmistakable head of animated nature upon this earth. 
It will readily occur that some more particular investigations
into the ranks of types might throw additional light on
man’s status, and perhaps his nature; and such light we may
hope to obtain when the philosophy of zoology shall have been
studied as it deserves.  Perhaps some such diagram as the
one given on the next page will be found to be an approximation
to the expression of the merely natural or secular grade of man
in comparison with other animals.



 [274]
Here the upright lines, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, may represent the
comparative height and grade of organization of both the five
sub-kingdoms, and the five classes of each of these; 5 being the
vertebrata in the one case, and the mammalia in the other. 
The difference between the height of the line 1 and the line 5
gives an idea of the difference of being the head type of the
aves, (corvidæ,) and the head type of the mammalia,
(bimana;) a. b. c. d.  5, again, represent the five
groups of the first order of the mammalia; a, being the
organic structure of the highest simia, and 5, that of man. 
A set of tangent lines of this kind may yet prove one of the most
satisfactory means of ascertaining the height and breadth of the
psychology of our species.
It may be asked,—Is the existing human race the only
species designed to occupy the grade to which it is here
referred?  Such a question evidently ought not to be
answered rashly; and I shall therefore confine myself to the
admission that, judging by analogy, we might expect to see
several varieties of the being, homo.  There is no other
family approaching to this in importance, which presents but one
species.  The corvidæ, our parallel in aves, consist
of several distinct genera and sub-genera.  It is startling
to find such an appearance of imperfection in the circle to which
man belongs, and the ideas which rise in consequence are not less
startling.  Is our race but the initial of the grand
crowning type?  Are there yet to be species superior to us
in organization, purer in feeling, more powerful in device and
act, and who shall take a rule over us!  There is in this
nothing improbable on other grounds.  The present race, rude
and impulsive as it is, is perhaps the best adapted to the
present state of things in the world; but the external world goes
through slow and gradual changes, which may leave it in time a
much serener field of existence.  There may then be occasion
for a nobler type of humanity, which shall complete the
zoological circle on this planet, and realize some of the dreams
of the purest spirits of the present race.</div></body></text></TEI>