<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="28">
      SECTION 4. OF THE INFLUENCE OF THE ROYAL INSTITUTION ON THE ROYAL SOCIETY.
    

      The Royal Institution was founded for the cultivation of the more popular
      and elementary branches of scientific knowledge, and has risen, partly
      from the splendid discoveries of Davy, and partly from the decline of the
      Royal Society, to a more prominent station than it would otherwise have
      occupied in the science of England. Its general effects in diffusing
      knowledge among the more educated classes of the metropolis, have been,
      and continue to be, valuable. Its influence, however, in the government of
      the Royal Society, is by no means attended with similar advantages, and
      has justly been viewed with considerable jealousy by many of the Fellows
      of that body. It may be stated, without disparagement to the Royal
      Institution, that the scientific qualifications necessary for its
      officers, however respectable, are not quite of that high order which
      ought to be required for those of the Royal Society, if the latter body
      were in a state of vigour.
    

      The Royal Institution interest has always been sufficient to appoint one
      of the Secretaries of the Royal Society; and at the present moment they
      have appointed two. In a short time, unless some effectual check is put to
      this, we shall find them nominating the President and the rest of the
      officers. It is certainly not consistent with the dignity of the Royal
      Society thus to allow its offices to be given away as the rewards of
      services rendered to other institutions. The only effectual way to put a
      stop to this increasing interest would be, to declare that no manager or
      officer of the Royal Institution should ever, at the same time, hold
      office in the Royal Society.
    

      The use the Members of the Royal Institution endeavour to make of their
      power in the Council of the Royal Society, is exemplified in the minutes
      of the Council of March 11, 1830, which may be consulted with advantage by
      those who doubt.
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>