<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="56">CHAPTER II.
Problem of the Vibrations of Strings.
THAT the continuation of sound
depends on a continued minute and rapid motion, a shaking or
trembling, of the parts of the sounding body, was soon seen. Thus
Bacon says,5 “The duration of the sound of a bell or
a string when struck, which appears to be prolonged and gradually
extinguished, does not proceed from the first percussion; but the
trepidation of the body struck perpetually generates a new sound. For
if that trepidation be prevented, and the bell or string be stopped,
the sound soon dies: as in spinets, as soon as the spine
is let fall so as to touch the string, the sound ceases.” In the case
of a stretched string, it is not difficult to perceive that the motion
is a motion back and forwards across the straight line which the
string occupies when at rest. The further examination of the
quantitative circumstances of this oscillatory motion was an obvious
problem; and especially after oscillations, though of another kind
(those of a pendulous body), had attracted attention, as they had done
in the school of Galileo. Mersenne, one of the promulgators of
Galileo’s philosophy in France, is the first author in whom I find an
examination of the details of this case (Harmonicorum Liber,
Paris, 1636). He asserts,6 that the differences and concords of
acute and grave sounds depend on the rapidity of vibrations, and their
ratio; and he proves this doctrine by a series of experimental
comparisons. Thus he finds7 that the note of a string is as its
length, by taking a string first twice, and then four times as long as
the original string, other things remaining the same. This, indeed,
was known to the ancients, and was the basis of that numerical
indication of the notes which the proposition expresses. Mersenne
further proceeds to show the effect of thickness and tension. He finds
(Prop. 7) that a string must be four times as thick as another, to
give the octave below; he finds, also (Prop. 8), that the tension must
be about four times as great in order to produce the octave above.
From these proportions various others are deduced, and the law of
the 29
phenomena of this kind may be considered as determined.
Mersenne also undertook to measure the phenomena numerically,
that is to determine the number of vibrations of the string in each of
such cases; which at first might appear difficult, since it is
obviously impossible to count with the eye the passages of a sounding
string backwards and forwards. But Mersenne rightly assumed, that the
number of vibrations is the same so long as the tone is the same, and
that the ratios of the numbers of vibrations of different strings may
be determined from the numerical relations of their notes. He had,
therefore, only to determine the number of vibrations of one certain
string, or one known note, to know those of all others. He took a
musical string of three-quarters of a foot long, stretched with a
weight of six pounds and five eighths, which he found gave him by its
vibrations a certain standard note in his organ: he found that a
string of the same material and tension, fifteen feet, that is, twenty
times as long, made ten recurrences in a second; and he inferred that
the number of vibrations of the shorter string must also be twenty
times as great; and thus such a string must make in one second of time
two hundred vibrations.
5 Hist. Son. et Aud. vol. ix.
p. 71.
6 L. i. Prop. 15.
7 L. ii. Prop. 6.
This determination of Mersenne does not appear to have attracted
due notice; but some time afterwards attempts were made to ascertain
the connexion between the sound and its elementary pulsations in a
more direct manner. Hooke, in 1681, produced sounds by the striking of
the teeth of brass wheels,8 and Stancari, in 1706, by whirling round
a large wheel in air, showed, before the Academy of Bologna, how the
number of vibrations in a given note might be known. Sauveur, who,
though deaf for the first seven years of his life, was one of the
greatest promoters of the science of sound, and gave it its name of
Acoustics, endeavored also, about the same time, to determine
the number of vibrations of a standard note, or, as he called it,
Fixed Sound. He employed two methods, both ingenious and both
indirect. The first was the method of beats. Two organ-pipes,
which form a discord, are often heard to produce a kind of
howl, or wavy noise, the sound swelling and declining at
small intervals of time. This was readily and rightly ascribed to the
coincidences of the pulsations of sound of the two notes after certain
cycles. Thus, if the number of vibrations of the notes were as fifteen
to sixteen in the same time, every fifteenth vibration of the one
would coincide with every 30 sixteenth vibration of the other, while
all the intermediate vibrations of the two tones would, in various
degrees, disagree with each other; and thus every such cycle, of
fifteen and sixteen vibrations, might be heard as a separate beat of
sound. Now, Sauveur wished to take a case in which these beats were so
slow as to be counted,9 and in which the ratio of the vibrations
of the notes was known from a knowledge of their musical relations.
Thus if the two notes form an interval of a semitone, their ratio will
be that above supposed, fifteen to sixteen; and if the beats be found
to be six in a second, we know that, in that time, the graver note
makes ninety and the acuter ninety-six vibrations. In this manner
Sauveur found that an open organ-pipe, five feet long, gave one
hundred vibrations in a second.
8 Life, p. xxiii.
9 Ac. Sc. Hist. 1700, p.
131.
Sauveur’s other method is more recondite, and approaches to a
mechanical view of the question.10 He proceeded on
this basis; a string, horizontally stretched, cannot be drawn into a
mathematical straight line, but always hangs in a very flat curve, or
festoon. Hence Sauveur assumed that its transverse vibrations
may be conceived to be identical with the lateral swingings of such a
festoon. Observing that the string C, in the middle of a harpsichord,
hangs in such a festoon to the amount of 1⁄323rd of an inch, he
calculates, by the laws of pendulums, the time of oscillation, and
finds it 1⁄122nd of a second. Thus this
C, his fixed note, makes one hundred and twenty-two vibrations
in a second. It is curious that this process, seemingly so arbitrary,
is capable of being justified on mechanical principles; though we can
hardly give the author credit for the views which this justification
implies. It is, therefore, easy to understand that it agreed with
other experiments, in the laws which it gave for the dependence of the
tone on the length and tension.
10 Ac. Sc. Hist. 1713.
The problem of satisfactorily explaining this dependence, on
mechanical principles, naturally pressed upon the attention of
mathematicians when the law of the phenomena was thus completely
determined by Mersenne and Sauveur. It was desirable to show that both
the circumstances and the measure of the phenomena were such as known
mechanical causes and laws would explain. But this problem, as might
be expected, was not attacked till mechanical principles, and the
modes of applying them, had become tolerably familiar.
As the vibrations of a string are produced by its tension, it
appeared to be necessary, in the first place, to determine the law of
the tension 31 which
is called into action by the motion of the string; for it is manifest
that, when the string is drawn aside from the straight line into which
it is stretched, there arises an additional tension, which aids in
drawing it back to the straight line as soon as it is let go. Hooke
(On Spring, 1678) determined the law of this additional
tension, which he expressed in his noted formula, “Ut tensio sic vis,”
the Force is as the Tension; or rather, to express his meaning more
clearly, the Force of tension is as the Extension, or, in a string, as
the increase of length. But, in reality, this principle, which is
important in many acoustical problems, is, in the one now before us,
unimportant; the force which urges the string towards the straight
line, depends, with such small extensions as we have now to consider,
not on the extension, but on the curvature; and the power of treating
the mathematical difficulty of curvature, and its mechanical
consequences, was what was requisite for the solution of this
problem.
The problem, in its proper aspect, was first attacked and mastered
by Brook Taylor, an English mathematician of the school of Newton, by
whom the solution was published in 1715, in his Methodus
Incrementorum. Taylor’s solution was indeed imperfect, for it only
pointed out a form and a mode of vibration, with which the string
might move consistently with the laws of mechanics; not the
mode in which it must move, supposing its form to be any
whatever. It showed that the curve might be of the nature of that
which is called the companion to the cycloid; and, on the
supposition of the curve of the string being of this form, the
calculation confirmed the previously established laws by which the
tone, or the time of vibration, had been discovered to depend on the
length, tension, and bulk of the string. The mathematical
incompleteness of Taylor’s reasoning must not prevent us from looking
upon his solution of the problem as the most important step in the
progress of this part of the subject: for the difficulty of applying
mechanical principles to the question being once overcome, the
extension and correction of the application was sure to be undertaken
by succeeding mathematicians; and, accordingly, this soon happened. We
may add, moreover, that the subsequent and more general solutions
require to be considered with reference to Taylor’s, in order to
apprehend distinctly their import; and further, that it was almost
evident to a mathematician, even before the general solution had
appeared, that the dependence of the time of vibration on the length
and tension, would be the same in the general case as in the 32 Taylorian curve; so
that, for the ends of physical philosophy, the solution was not very
incomplete.
John Bernoulli, a few years afterwards,11 solved the
problem of vibrating chords on nearly the same principles and
suppositions as Taylor; but a little later (in 1747), the next
generation of great mathematicians, D’Alembert, Euler, and Daniel
Bernoulli, applied the increased powers of analysis to give generality
to the mode of treating this question; and especially the calculus of
partial differentials, invented for this purpose. But at this epoch,
the discussion, so far as it bore on physics, belonged rather to the
history of another problem, which comes under our notice hereafter, that of the composition of vibrations; we
shall, therefore, defer the further history of the problem of
vibrating strings, till we have to consider it in connexion with new
experimental facts.
11 Op. iii. p. 207.
</div></body></text></TEI>