<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 165, folios 149-152</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 165, folios 149-152.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1841">undated [June 1841]</date>
          <note type="place">[no place]</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 165, folios 149-152</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_165_folios_149-152.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Wednesday 4 o'clock</p>
      <p>Dearest W. Greig came in a great fuss this morning, when I was only half-dressed, urgent to see me. So I had to see him as I was, &amp; was ordered to write to you by today's post.-- It is about your accepting the Chair-man-ship of the Surrey Quarter Sessions.</p>
      <p>Greig thinks it of the utmost importance to the interests of the County altogether, &amp; says you would have a unanimous election.-- He is most anxious on the subject, &amp; has had a long conversation with Nicholson [two words crossed out] about it . I only repeat to you what I am told to say, as exactly as I can. And I think I have now communicated the pith of it.--</p>
      <p>I have had all sorts of people today, &amp; have been tending towards the arrangement of all my plans, &amp; correspondence, &amp;c for the country.</p>
      <p>Wheatstone promises to come &amp; see me-- soon at Ockham.-- Everything is going on well I believe &amp; as I could wish it.--</p>
      <p>But how much I owe my Dearest Mate for his generous &amp; wise encouragement of all that is best for me &amp; which</p>
      <p>tends most effectually to tranquillize &amp; fill up that capacious mind &amp; spirit of the Phoneix's!</p>
      <p>Pray call me the Phoneix!--</p>
      <p>Tomorrow the Norwood expedition is to take place, I believe, at 1/2 past one o'clock; &amp; if it is a fine day, it will be agreeable.--</p>
      <p>We were disappointed of our Mesmerism today. Williamson is very unwell.</p>
      <p>I do not know that I have much more of note to say; or much more time to say anything.--</p>
      <p>I am sorry to find that I have 2 more teeth in a very bad way. A visit to Lauzelle this morning resulted in this discovery. He says it is the extreme susceptibility &amp; irritability of the constitution, which causes this continually progressing mischief.-- I</p>
      <p>remember your kissing &amp; caressing the Avis before ou went this morning; for which, (altho' very sleepy), I was much obliged.--</p>
      <p>Avis Phoenix</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
