<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="25">CHAPTER XXV.
ETNA.
External physiognomy of Etna—Lateral cones—Their successive obliteration—Early
eruptions—Monti Rossi in 1669—Towns overflowed by lava—Part of
Catania overflowed—Mode of advance of a current of
lava—Subterranean
caverns—Marine strata at base of Etna—Val del Bove not an ancient crater—Its
scenery—Form, composition, and origin of the dikes—Linear direction of
cones formed in 1811 and 1819—Lavas and breccias—Flood produced by the
melting of snow by lava—Glacier covered by a lava stream—Val del Bove
how formed—Structure and origin of the cone of Etna—Whether the inclined
sheets of lava were originally horizontal—Antiquity of
Etna—Whether signs
of diluvial waves are observable on Etna.
External physiognomy of Etna.—After Vesuvius, our most authentic
records relate to Etna, which rises near the sea in solitary grandeur to
the height of nearly eleven thousand feet.560 The base of the cone is
almost circular, and eighty-seven English miles in circumference; but
if we include the whole district over which its lavas extend, the circuit
is probably twice that extent.
Divided into three regions.—The cone is divided by nature into three
distinct zones, called the fertile, the woody, and the desert regions. The
first of these, comprising the delightful country around the skirts of the
mountain, is well cultivated, thickly inhabited, and covered with olives,
397
vines, corn, fruit-trees, and aromatic herbs. Higher up, the woody
region encircles the mountain—an extensive forest six or seven miles in
width, affording pasturage for numerous flocks. The trees are of various
species, the chestnut, oak, and pine being most luxuriant; while in some
tracts are groves of cork and beech. Above the forest is the desert
region, a waste of black lava and scoriæ; where, on a kind of plain,
rises a cone of eruption to the height of about eleven hundred feet, from
which sulphureous vapors are continually evolved.
Cones produced by lateral eruption.—The most grand and original
feature in the physiognomy of Etna is the multitude of minor cones
which are distributed over its flanks, and which are most abundant in
the woody region. These, although they appear but trifling irregularities
when viewed from a distance as subordinate parts of so imposing
and colossal a mountain, would, nevertheless, be deemed hills of considerable
altitude in almost any other region. Without enumerating numerous
monticules of ashes thrown out at different points, there are
about eighty of these secondary volcanoes, of considerable dimensions;
fifty-two on the west and north, and twenty-seven on the east side of
Etna. One of the largest, called Monte Minardo, near Bronte, is upwards
of 700 feet in height, and a double hill near Nicolosi, called
Monti Rossi, formed in 1669, is 450 feet high, and the base two miles in
circumference; so that it somewhat exceeds in size Monte Nuovo, before
described. Yet it ranks only as a cone of the second magnitude
amongst those produced by the lateral eruptions of Etna. On looking
down from the lower borders of the desert region, these volcanoes present
us with one of the most delightful and characteristic scenes in
Europe. They afford every variety of height and size, and are arranged
in beautiful and picturesque groups. However uniform they may appear
when seen from the sea, or the plains below, nothing can be more
diversified than their shape when we look from above into their craters,
one side of which is generally broken down. There are, indeed, few
objects in nature more picturesque than a wooded volcanic crater. The
cones situated in the higher parts of the forest zone are chiefly clothed
with lofty pines; while those at a lower elevation are adorned with
chestnuts, oaks, beech, and holm.
Successive obliteration of these cones.—The history of the eruptions of
Etna, imperfect and interrupted as it is, affords us, nevertheless, much
insight into the manner in which the whole mountain has successively attained
its present magnitude and internal structure. The principal cone
has more than once fallen in and been reproduced. In 1444 it was 320
feet high, and fell in after the earthquakes of 1537. In the year 1693,
when a violent earthquake shook the whole of Sicily, and killed sixty
thousand persons, the cone lost so much of its height, says Boccone,
that it could not be seen from several places in Valdemone, from which
it was before visible. The greater number of eruptions happen either
from the great crater, or from lateral openings in the desert region.
When hills are thrown up in the middle zone, and project beyond the
398
general level, they gradually lose their height during subsequent eruptions;
for when lava runs down from the upper parts of the mountain,
and encounters any of these hills, the stream is divided, and flows round
them so as to elevate the gently sloping grounds from which they rise.
In this manner a deduction is often made at once of twenty or thirty
feet, or even more, from their height. Thus, one of the minor cones,
called Monte Peluso, was diminished in altitude by a great lava stream
which encircled it in 1444; and another current has recently taken the
same course—yet this hill still remains four or five hundred feet high.
There is a cone called Monte Nucilla near Nicolosi, round the base of
which several successive currents have flowed, and showers of ashes
have fallen, since the time of history, till at last, during an eruption in
1536, the surrounding plain was so raised, that the top of the cone
alone was left projecting above the general level. Monte Nero, situated
above the Grotta dell' Capre, was in 1766 almost submerged by a current:
and Monte Capreolo afforded, in the year 1669, a curious example
of one of the last stages of obliteration; for a lava stream, descending on
a high ridge which had been built up by the continued superposition
of successive lavas, flowed directly into the crater, and nearly filled it.
The lava, therefore, of each new lateral cone tends to detract from the
relative height of lower cones above their base: so that the flanks of
Etna, sloping with a gentle inclination, envelop in succession a great
multitude of minor volcanoes, while new ones spring up from time to
time.
Early eruptions of Etna.—Etna appears to have been in activity
from the earliest times of tradition; for Diodorus Siculus mentions an
eruption which caused a district to be deserted by the Sicani before the
Trojan war. Thucydides informs us, that in the sixth year of the Peloponnesian
war, or in the spring of the year 425 B. C., a lava stream
ravaged the environs of Catania, and this he says was the third eruption
which had happened in Sicily since the colonization of that island by
the Greeks.561 The second of the three eruptions alluded to by the historian
took place in the year 475 B. C., and was that so poetically
described by Pindar, two years afterwards, in his first Pythian ode:—


κιον
Δ' ουρανια συνεχει
Νιφοεσς' Αιτνα, πανετες
Χιονος οξειας τιθηνα.


In these and the seven verses which follow, a graphic description is
given of Etna, such as it appeared five centuries before the Christian
era, and such as it has been seen when in eruption in modern times. The
poet is only making a passing allusion to the Sicilian volcano, as the
mountain under which Typhœus lay buried, yet by a few touches of his
master-hand every striking feature of the scene has been faithfully portrayed.
399
We are told of "the snowy Etna, the pillar of heaven—the
nurse of everlasting frost, in whose deep caverns lie concealed the fountains
of unapproachable fire—a stream of eddying smoke by day—a
bright and ruddy flame by night; and burning rocks rolled down with
loud uproar into the sea."
Fig. 46.
Minor cones on the flanks of Etna.
1. Monti Rossi, near Nicolosi, formed in 1669.           2. Vampeluso?562
Eruption of 1669—Monti Rossi formed.—The great eruption which
happened in the year 1669 is the first which claims particular attention.
An earthquake had levelled to the ground all the houses in Nicolosi, a
town situated near the lower margin of the woody region, about twenty
miles from the summit of Etna, and ten from the sea at Catania. Two
gulfs then opened near that town, from whence sand and scoriæ were
thrown up in such quantity, that in the course of three or four months
a double cone was formed, called Monti Rossi, about 450 feet high. But
the most extraordinary phenomenon occurred at the commencement of
the convulsion in the plain of S. Lio. A fissure six feet broad, and of
unknown depth, opened with a loud crash, and ran in a somewhat tortuous
course to within a mile of the summit of Etna. Its direction was
from north to south, and its length twelve miles. It emitted a most
vivid light. Five other parallel fissures of considerable length afterwards
opened, one after the other, and emitted smoke, and gave out bellowing
sounds which were heard at the distance of forty miles. This
case seems to present the geologist with an illustration of the manner in
which those continuous dikes of vertical porphyry were formed, which
are seen to traverse some of the older lavas of Etna; for the light emitted
from the great rent of S. Lio appears to indicate that the fissure was
filled to a certain height with incandescent lava, probably to the height
of an orifice not far distant from Monti Rossi, which at that time opened
and poured out a lava current. When the melted matter in such a rent
400
has cooled, it must become a solid wall or dike, intersecting the older
rocks of which the mountain is composed; similar rents have been
observed during subsequent eruptions, as in 1832, when they ran in all
directions from the centre of the volcano. It has been justly remarked
by M. Elie de Beaumont, that such star-shaped fractures may indicate
a slight upheaval of the whole of Etna. They may be the signs of the
stretching of the mass, which may thus be raised gradually by a force
from below.563
The lava current of 1669, before alluded to, soon reached in its course
a minor cone called Mompiliere, at the base of which it entered a subterranean
grotto, communicating with a suite of those caverns which are
so common in the lavas of Etna. Here it appears to have melted down
some of the vaulted foundations of the hill, so that the whole of that
cone became slightly depressed and traversed by numerous open fissures.
Part of Catania destroyed.—The lava, after overflowing fourteen
towns and villages, some having a population of between three and four
thousand inhabitants, arrived at length at the walls of Catania. These
had been purposely raised to protect the city; but the burning flood
accumulated till it rose to the top of the rampart, which was sixty feet
in height, and then it fell in a fiery cascade and overwhelmed part of the
city. The wall, however, was not thrown down, but was discovered
long afterwards by excavations made in the rock by the Prince of Biscari;
so that the traveller may now see the solid lava curling over the
top of the rampart as if still in the very act of falling.
This great current performed the first thirteen miles of its course in
twenty days, or at the rate of 162 feet per hour, but required twenty-three
days for the last two miles, giving a velocity of only twenty-two
feet per hour; and we learn from Dolomieu that the stream moved
during part of its course at the rate of 1500 feet an hour, and in others
it took several days to cover a few yards.564 When it entered the sea it
was still six hundred yards broad, and forty feet deep. It covered some
territories in the environs of Catania which had never before been visited
by the lavas of Etna. While moving on, its surface was in general a
mass of solid rock; and its mode of advancing, as is usual with lava
streams, was by the occasional fissuring of the solid walls. A gentleman
of Catania, named Pappalardo, desiring to secure the city from the
approach of the threatening torrent, went out with a party of fifty men
whom he had dressed in skins to protect them from the heat, and armed
with iron crows and hooks. They broke open one of the solid walls
which flanked the current near Belpasso, and immediately forth issued
a rivulet of melted matter which took the direction of Paternó; but the
inhabitants of that town, being alarmed for their safety, took up arms
and put a stop to farther operations.565
401
As another illustration of the solidity of the walls of an advancing
lava stream, I may mention an adventure related by Recupero, who, in
1766, had ascended a small hill formed of ancient volcanic matter, to
behold the slow and gradual approach of a fiery current, two miles and
a half broad; when suddenly two small threads of liquid matter issuing
from a crevice detached themselves from the main stream, and ran rapidly
towards the hill. He and his guide had just time to escape, when
they saw the hill, which was fifty feet in height, surrounded, and in a
quarter of an hour melted down into the burning mass, so as to flow on
with it.
But it must not be supposed that this complete fusion of rocky matter
coming in contact with lava is of universal, or even common, occurrence.
It probably happens when fresh portions of incandescent matter come
successively in contact with fusible materials. In many of the dikes
which intersect the tuffs and lavas of Etna, there is scarcely any perceptible
alteration effected by heat on the edges of the horizontal beds, in
contact with the vertical and more crystalline mass. On the side of
Mompiliere, one of the towns overflowed in the great eruption above
described, an excavation was made in 1704; and by immense labor the
workmen reached, at the depth of thirty-five feet, the gate of the principal
church, where there were three statues, held in high veneration.
One of these, together with a bell, some money, and other articles, were
extracted in a good state of preservation from beneath a great arch
formed by the lava. It seems very extraordinary that any works of art,
not encased with tuff, like those in Herculaneum, should have escaped
fusion in hollow spaces left open in this lava-current, which was so hot
at Catania eight years after it entered the town, that it was impossible
to hold the hand in some of the crevices.
Subterranean caverns on Etna.—Mention was made of the entrance
of a lava-stream into a subterranean grotto, whereby the foundations of
a hill were partially undermined. Such underground passages are among
the most curious features on Etna, and appear to have been produced by
the hardening of the lava, during the escape of great volumes of elastic
fluids, which are often discharged for many days in succession, after the
crisis of the eruption is over. Near Nicolosi, not far from Monti Rossi,
one of these great openings may be seen, called the Fossa della Palomba,
625 feet in circumference at its mouth, and seventy-eight deep.
After reaching the bottom of this, we enter another dark cavity, and
then others in succession, sometimes descending precipices by means of
ladders. At length the vaults terminate in a great gallery ninety feet
long, and from fifteen to fifty broad, beyond which there is still a passage,
never yet explored; so that the extent of these caverns remains
unknown.566 The walls and roofs of these great vaults are composed of
rough and bristling scoriæ, of the most fantastic forms.
Marine strata at base of Etna.—If we skirt the fertile region at the
402
base of Etna on its southern and eastern sides, we behold marine strata
of clay sand, and volcanic tuff, cropping out from beneath the modern
lavas. The marine fossil shells occurring in these strata are all of them,
or nearly all, identical with species now inhabiting the Mediterranean;
and as they appear at the height of from 600 to 800 feet above the sea
near Catania, they clearly prove that there has been in this region, as in
other parts of Sicily farther to the south, an upward movement of the
ancient bed of the sea. It is fair, therefore, to infer that the whole
mountain, with the exception of those parts which are of very modern
origin, has participated in this upheaval.
If we view Etna from the south, we see the marine deposits above
alluded to, forming a low line of hills (e, e, Fig. 47), or a steep inland
slope or cliff (f), as in the annexed drawing taken from the limestone
platform of Primosole. It should be observed however, in reference to
this view, that the height of the volcanic cone is ten times greater than
the hills at its base (e, e), although it appears less elevated, because the
summit of the cone is ten or twelve times more distant from the plain of
Catania than is Licodia.
Fig. 47.
View of Etna from the summit of the limestone platform of Primosole.
a, Highest cone.      b, Montagnuola.
c, Monte Minardo, with smaller lateral cones above.
d, Town of Licodia dei Monaci.
e, Marine formation called creta, argillaceous and sandy beds with a few shells, and associated
volcanic rocks.
f, Escarpment of stratified subaqueous volcanic tuff, &c., northwest of Catania.
g, Town of Catania.
h i, Dotted line expressing the highest boundary along which the marine strata are occasionally
seen.
k, Plain of Catania.
l, Limestone platform of Primosole of the Newer Pliocene period.
m, La Motta di Catania.
The mountain is in general of a very symmetrical form, a flattened
cone broken on its eastern side, by a deep valley, called the Val del
Bove, or in the provincial dialect of the peasants, "Val di Bué," for here
the herdsman


—— "in reducta valle mugientium
Prospectat errantes greges."


Dr. Buckland was, I believe, the first English geologist who examined
this valley with attention, and I am indebted to him for having described
it to me, before I visited Sicily, as more worthy of attention than any
single spot in that island, or perhaps in Europe.
PLATE III.

VIEW LOOKING UP THE VAL DEL BOVE, ETNA.
The Val del Bove commences near the summit of Etna, and descending
403
into the woody region, is farther continued on one side by a second
and narrower valley, called the Val di Calanna. Below this another,
named the Val di St. Giacomo, begins,—a long narrow ravine, which
is prolonged to the neighborhood of Zaffarana (e, fig. 48), on the confines
of the fertile region. These natural incisions into the side of the volcano
are of such depth that they expose to view a great part of the structure
of the entire mass, which, in the Val del Bove, is laid open to the
depth of from 3000 to above 4000 feet from the summit of Etna. The
geologist thus enjoys an opportunity of ascertaining how far the internal
conformation of the cone corresponds with what he might have anticipated
as the result of that mode of increase which has been witnessed
during the historical era.
Fig. 48.
Great valley on the east side of Etna.


a, Highest cone.
b, Montagnuola.

c, Head of Val del Bove.
d, d, Serre del Solfizio.

e, Village of Zaffarana on the lower border of the woody region.

f, One of the lateral cones.
g, Monti Rossi.


Description of Plate III.—The accompanying view (Pl. III.) is part
of a panoramic sketch which I made in November, 1828, and may assist
the reader in comprehending some topographical details to be alluded
to in the sequel, although it can convey no idea of the picturesque
grandeur of the scene.
The great lava-currents of 1819 and 1811 are seen pouring down
from the higher parts of the valley, overrunning the forests of the great
plain, and rising up in the foreground on the left with a rugged surface,
on which many hillocks and depressions appear, such as often characterize
a lava-current immediately after its consolidation.
The small cone, No. 7, was formed in 1811, and was still smoking
when I saw it in 1828. The other small volcano to the left, from which
vapor is issuing, was, I believe, one of those formed in 1819.
The following are the names of some of the other points indicated in
the sketch:—


1, Montagnuola.
5, Finocchio.
9, Musara.

2, Torre del Filosofo.
6, Capra.
10, Zocolaro.

3, Highest cone.
7, Cone of 1811.
11, Rocca di Calanna.

4, Lepra.
8, Cima del Asino.
 


Description of Plate IV.—The second view (Pl. IV.) represents the
same valley as seen from above, or looking directly down the Val del
Bove, from the summit of the principal crater formed in 1819.567 I am
404
unable to point out the precise spot which this crater would occupy in
the view represented in Plate III.; but I conceive that it would appear
in the face of the great precipice, near which the smoke issuing from
the cone No. 7 is made to terminate. There are many ledges of rock
on the face of that precipice where eruptions have occurred.
The circular form of the Val del Bove is well shown in this view.
(Pl. IV.) To the right and left are the lofty precipices which form the
southern and northern sides of the great valley, and which are intersected
by dikes projecting in the manner afterwards to be described.
In the distance appears the "fertile region" of Etna, extending like a
great plain along the sea-coast.
The spots particularly referred to in the plate are the following:—

a, Cape Spartivento, in Italy, of which the outline is seen in the distance.

b, The promontory of Taormino, on the Sicilian coast.

c, The river Alcantra.

d, The small village of Riposto.

f, The town of Aci Reale.

g, Cyclopian islands, or "Faraglioni," in the Bay of Trezza.

h, The great harbor of Syracuse.

k, The Lake of Lentini.

i, The city of Catania, near which is marked the course of the lava which flowed
from the Monti Rossi in 1669, and destroyed part of the city.

l, To the left of the view is the crater of 1811, which is also shown at No. 7 in
Plate III.

m, Rock of Musara, also seen at No. 9 in Plate III.

e, Valley of Calanna.

The Val del Bove is of truly magnificent dimensions, a vast amphitheatre
four or five miles in diameter, surrounded by nearly vertical
precipices, varying from 1000 to above 3000 feet in height, the loftiest
being at the upper end, and the height gradually diminishing on both
sides. The feature which first strikes the geologist as distinguishing
the boundary cliffs of this valley, is the prodigious multitude of verticle
dikes which are seen in all directions traversing the volcanic beds. The
circular form of this great chasm, and the occurrence of these countless
dikes, amounting perhaps to several thousands in number, so forcibly
recalled to my mind the phenomena of the Atrio del Cavallo, on Vesuvius,
that I at first imagined that I had entered a vast crater, on a scale as
far exceeding that of Somma, as Etna surpasses Vesuvius in magnitude.
But I was soon undeceived when I had attentively explored the different
sides of the great amphitheatre, in order to satisfy myself whether
the semicircular wall of the Val del Bove had ever formed the boundary
of a crater, and whether the beds had the same quâquâ-versal dip
which is so beautifully exhibited in the escarpment of Somma. Had
the supposed analogy between Somma and the Val del Bove held true,
the tufts and lavas at the head of the valley would have dipped to the
west, those on the north side towards the north, and those on the
southern side to the south. But such I did not find to be the inclination
of the beds; they all dip towards the sea, or nearly east, as in the
valleys of St. Giacomo and Calanna below.
PLATE IV.

VIEW OF THE VAL DEL BOVE, ETNA, AS SEEN FROM ABOVE, OR FROM THE CRATER OF 1819.
405
Scenery of the Val del Bove.—Let the reader picture to himself a
large amphitheatre, five miles in diameter, and surrounded on three sides
by precipices from 2000 to 3000 feet in height. If he has beheld that
most picturesque scene in the chain of the Pyrenees, the celebrated
"cirque of Gavarnie," he may form some conception of the magnificent
circle of precipitous rocks which inclose, on three sides, the great plain
of the Val del Bove. This plain has been deluged by repeated streams
of lava; and although it appears almost level, when viewed from a distance,
it is, in fact, more uneven than the surface of the most tempestuous
sea. Besides the minor irregularities of the lava, the valley is in one
part interrupted by a ridge of rocks, two of which, Musara and Capra,
are very prominent. It can hardly be said that they


——"like giants stand
To sentinel enchanted land;"


for although, like the Trosachs, in the Highlands of Scotland, they are of
gigantic dimensions, and appear almost isolated, as seen from many points,
yet the stern and severe grandeur of the scenery which they adorn is
not such as would be selected by a poet for a vale of enchantment. The
character of the scene would accord far better with Milton's picture of
the infernal world; and if we imagine ourselves to behold in motion, in
the darkness of the night, one of those fiery currents which have so often
traversed the great valley, we may well recall


——"yon dreary plain, forlorn and wild,
The seat of desolation, void of light,
Save what the glimmering of these livid flames
Casts pale and dreadful."


The face of the precipices already mentioned is broken in the most
picturesque manner by the vertical walls of lava which traverse them.
These masses visually stand out in relief, are exceedingly diversified in
form, and of immense altitude. In the autumn, their black outline may
often be seen relieved by clouds of fleecy vapor which settle behind
them, and do not disperse until mid-day, continuing to fill the valley
while the sun is shining on every other part of Sicily, and on the higher
regions of Etna.
As soon as the vapors begin to rise, the changes of scene are varied
in the highest degree, different rocks being unveiled and hidden by turns,
and the summit of Etna often breaking through the clouds for a moment
with its dazzling snows, and being then as suddenly withdrawn from
the view.
An unusual silence prevails; for there are no torrents dashing from
the rocks, nor any movement of running water in this valley such as may
almost invariably be heard in mountainous regions. Every drop of water
that falls from the heavens, or flows from the melting ice and snow, is
instantly absorbed by the porous lava; and such is the dearth of springs,
406
that the herdsman is compelled to supply his flocks, during the hot season,
from stores of snow laid up in hollows of the mountain during winter.
The strips of green herbage and forest land, which have here and there
escaped the burning lavas, serve, by contrast, to heighten the desolation
of the scene. When I visited the valley, nine years after the eruption of
1819, I saw hundreds of trees, or rather the white skeletons of trees, on
the borders of the black lava, the trunks and branches being all leafless,
and deprived of their bark by the scorching heat emitted from the melted
rock; an image recalling those beautiful lines:—


——"As when heaven's fire
Hath scath'd the forest oaks, or mountain pines,
With singed top their stately growth, though bare,
Stands on the blasted heath."


Fig. 49.
Dikes at the base of the Serre del Solfizio, Etna.
Form, composition, and origin of the dikes.—But without indulging
the imagination any longer in descriptions of scenery, I may observe that
the dikes before mentioned form unquestionably the most interesting
geological phenomenon in the Val del Bove. Some of these are composed
of trachyte, others of compact blue basalt with olivine. They vary in
breadth from two to twenty feet and upwards, and usually project from
the face of the cliffs, as represented in the annexed drawing (fig. 49).
They consist of harder materials than the strata which they traverse, and
therefore waste away less rapidly under the influence of that repeated
407
congelation and thawing to which the rocks in this zone of Etna are exposed.
The dikes are for the most part vertical, but sometimes they
run in a tortuous course through the tuffs and breccias, as represented
in fig. 50. In the escarpment of Somma, where similar walls of lava cut
through alternating beds of sand and scoriæ, a coating of coal-black rock,
approaching in its nature and appearance to pitchstone, is seen at the
contact of the dike with the intersected beds. I did not observe such
parting layers at the junction of the Etnean dikes which I examined, but
they may perhaps be discoverable.
Fig. 50.
Tortuous veins of lava at Punto di Giumento, Etna.
The geographical position of these dikes is most interesting, as they
are very numerous near the head of the Val del Bove, where the cones
of 1811 and 1819 were thrown up, as also in that zone of the mountain
where lateral eruptions are frequent; whereas in the valley of Calanna,
which is below that parallel, and in a region where lateral eruptions are
extremely rare, scarcely any dikes are seen, and none whatever still lower
in the valley of St. Giacomo. This is precisely what we might have
expected, if we consider the vertical fissures now filled with rock to have
been the feeders of lateral cones, or, in other words, the channels which
gave passage to the lava-currents and scoriæ that have issued from vents
in the forest zone. In other parts of Etna there may be numerous dikes
at as low a level as the Valley of Calanna, because the line of lateral
eruptions is not everywhere at the same height above the sea; but in
the section above alluded to, there appeared to me an obvious connection
between the frequency of dikes and of lateral eruptions.
Some fissures may have been filled from above, but I did not see any
which, by terminating downwards, gave proof of such an origin. Almost
all the isolated masses in the Val del Bove, such as Capra, Musara, and
others, are traversed by dikes, and may, perhaps, have partly owed their
preservation to that circumstance, if at least the action of occasional
floods has been one of the destroying causes in the Val del Bove; for
there is nothing which affords so much protection to a mass of strata
against the undermining action of running water as a perpendicular dike
of hard rock.
408
In the accompanying drawing (fig. 51), the flowing of the lavas of
1811 and 1819, between the rocks Finochio, Capra, and Musara, is represented.
The height of the two last-mentioned isolated masses has
been much diminished by the elevation of their base, caused by these
currents. They may, perhaps, be the remnants of lateral cones which
existed before the Val del Bove was formed, and may hereafter be once
more buried by the lavas that are now accumulating in the valley.
Fig. 51.
View of the rocks Finochio, Capra, and Musara, Val del Bove.
From no point of view are the dikes more conspicuous than from the
summit of the highest cone of Etna; a view of some of them is given in
the annexed drawing. (Fig. 52.)
Eruption of 1811.—I have alluded to the streams of lava which were
poured forth in 1811 and 1819. Gemmellaro, who witnessed these
eruptions, informs us that the great crater in 1811 first testified by its
loud detonations that a column of lava had ascended to near the summit
of the mountain. A violent shock was then felt, and a stream broke out
from the side of the cone, at no great distance from its apex. Shortly
after this had ceased to flow, a second stream burst forth at another
opening, considerably below the first; then a third still lower, and so on
till seven different issues had been thus successively formed, all lying
upon the same straight line. It has been supposed that this line was a
perpendicular rent in the internal framework of the mountain, which rent
was probably not produced at one shock, but prolonged successively
downwards, by the lateral pressure and intense heat of the internal column
of lava, as it subsided by gradual discharge through each vent.568
Eruption of 1819.—In 1819 three large mouths or caverns opened
very near those which were formed in the eruptions of 1811, from which
flames, red-hot cinders, and sand were thrown up with loud explosions.
A few minutes afterwards another mouth opened below, from which
409
flames and smoke issued; and finally a fifth, lower still, whence a torrent
of lava flowed, which spread itself with great velocity over the
deep and broad valley called "Val del Bove." This stream flowed two
miles in the first twenty-four hours, and nearly as far in the succeeding
day and night. The three original mouths at length united into one
large crater, and sent forth lava, as did the inferior apertures, so that an
enormous torrent poured down the "Val del Bove." When it arrived
at a vast and almost perpendicular precipice, at the head of the Valley
of Calanna, it poured over in a cascade, and, being hardened in its descent,
made an inconceivable crash as it was dashed against the bottom.
So immense was the column of dust raised by the abrasion of the tufaceous
hill over which the hardened mass descended, that the Catanians
were in great alarm, supposing a new eruption to have burst out in the
woody region, exceeding in violence that near the summit of Etna.
Fig. 52.
View from the summit of Etna into the Val del Bove.569
Mode of advance of the lava.—Of the cones thrown up during this
eruption, not more than two are of sufficient magnitude to be numbered
among those eighty which were before described as adorning the
flanks of Etna. The surface of the lava which deluged the "Val del
Bove," consists of rocky and angular blocks, tossed together in the
410
utmost disorder. Nothing can be more rugged, or more unlike the
smooth and even superficies, which those who are unacquainted with
volcanic countries may have pictured to themselves, in a mass of matter
which had consolidated from a liquid state. Mr. Scrope observed
this current in the year 1819, slowly advancing down a considerable
slope, at the rate of about a yard an hour, nine months after its emission.
The lower stratum being arrested by the resistance of the ground,
the upper or central part gradually protruded itself, and, being unsupported,
fell down. This in its turn was covered by a mass of more
liquid lava, which swelled over it from above. The current had all the
appearance of a huge heap of rough and large cinders rolling over and
over upon itself by the effect of an extremely slow propulsion from
behind. The contraction of the crust as it solidified, and the friction
of the scoriform cakes against one another, produced a crackling sound.
Within the crevices a dull red heat might be seen by night, and vapor
issuing in considerable quantity was visible by day.570
It was stated that when the lava of 1819 arrived at the head of the
Valley of Calanna, after flowing down the Val del Bove, it descended
in a cascade. This stream, in fact, like many previous currents of
lava which have flowed down successively from the higher regions of
Etna, was turned by a great promontory projecting from the southern
side of the Val del Bove. This promontory consists of the hills called
Zocolaro and Calanna, and of a ridge of inferior height which connects
them. (See fig. 53.)
Fig. 53.

A, Zocolaro.
B, Monte di Calanna.
C, Plain at the head of the Valley of Calanna.
a, Lava of 1819 descending the precipice and flowing through the valley.
b, Lavas of 1811 and 1819 flowing round the hill of Calanna.
It happened in 1811 and 1819 that the flows of lava overtopped the
ridge intervening between the hills of Zocolaro and Calanna, so that
they fell in a cascade over a lofty precipice, and began to fill up the
valley of Calanna (a, fig. 53). Other portions of the same lava-current
(b) flowed round the promontory, and they exhibit one of the peculiar
411
characteristics of such streams, namely that of becoming solid externally,
even while yet in motion. Instead of thinning out gradually at their
edges, their sides may often be compared to two rocky walls which are
sometimes inclined at an angle of between thirty and forty degrees.
When such streams are turned from their course by a projecting rock,
they move right onwards in a new direction; and in the Valley of
Calanna a considerable space has thus been left between the steep sides
of the lavas b b, so deflected, and the precipitous escarpment of Zocolaro,
A, which bounds the plain C.
Lavas and breccias.—In regard to the volcanic masses which are intersected
by dikes in the Val del Bove, they consist in great part of
graystone lavas, of an intermediate character between basalt and
trachyte, and partly of porphyritic lava resembling trachyte, but to
which that name cannot, according to Von Buch and G. Rose, be in
strictness applied, because the felspar belongs to the variety called
Labradorite. There is great similarity in the composition of the ancient
and modern lavas of Etna, both consisting of felspar, augite, olivine,
and titaniferous iron. The alternating breccias are made up of scoriæ,
sand, and angular blocks of lava. Many of these fragments may have
been thrown out by volcanic explosions, which, falling on the hardened
surface of moving lava-currents, may have been carried to a considerable
distance. It may also happen that when lava advances very
slowly, in the manner of the flow of 1819, the angular masses resulting
from the frequent breaking of the mass as it rolls over upon
itself, may produce these breccias. It is at least certain that the upper
portion of the lava-currents of 1811 and 1819 now consist of angular
masses to the depth of many yards. D'Aubuisson has compared the
surface of one of the ancient lavas of Auvergne to that of a river suddenly
frozen over by the stoppage of immense fragments of drift-ice, a
description perfectly applicable to these modern Etnean flows. The
thickness of the separate beds of conglomerate or breccia which are seen
in the same vertical section, is often extremely different, varying from
3 to nearly 50 feet, as I observed in the hill of Calanna.
Flood produced by the melting of snow by lava.—It is possible that
some of the breccias or conglomerates may be referred to aqueous
causes, as great floods occasionally sweep down the flanks of Etna,
when eruptions take place in winter, and when the snows are melted
by lava. It is true that running water in general exerts no power on
Etna, the rain which falls being immediately imbibed by the porous
lavas; so that, vast as is the extent of the mountain, it feeds only a few
small rivulets, and these, even, are dry throughout the greater portion
of the year. The enormous rounded boulders, therefore, of felspar-porphyry
and basalt, a line of which can be traced from the sea, from
near Giardini, by Mascali, and Zafarana, to the "Val del Bove," would
offer a perplexing problem to the geologist, if history had not preserved
the memorials of a tremendous flood which happened in this district in
the year 1755. It appears that two streams of lava flowed in that
412
year, on the 2d of March, from the highest crater; they were immediately
precipitated upon an enormous mass of snow which then covered
the whole mountain, and was extremely deep near the summit. The
sudden melting of this frozen mass, by a fiery torrent three miles in
length, produced a frightful inundation, which devastated the sides of
the mountain for eight miles in length, and afterwards covered the lower
flanks of Etna, where they were less steep, together with the plains near
the sea, with great deposits of sand, scoriæ, and blocks of lava.
Many absurd stories circulated in Sicily respecting this event; such as
that the water was boiling, and that it was vomited from the highest
crater; that it was as salt as the sea, and full of marine shells; but
these were mere inventions, to which Recupero, although he relates
them as tales of the mountaineers, seems to have attached rather too
much importance.
Floods of considerable violence have also been produced on Etna by
the fall of heavy rains, aided, probably, by the melting of snow. By
this cause alone, in 1761, sixty of the inhabitants of Acicatena were
killed, and many of their houses swept away.571
Glacier covered by a lava-stream.—A remarkable discovery was made
on Etna in 1828 of a great mass of ice, preserved for many years, perhaps
for centuries, from melting, by the singular accident of a current
of red-hot lava having flowed over it. The following are the facts in
attestation of a phenomenon which must at first sight appear of so paradoxical
a character. The extraordinary heat experienced in the South
of Europe, during the summer and autumn of 1828, caused the supplies
of snow and ice which had been preserved in the spring of that
year, for the use of Catania and the adjoining parts of Sicily and the
island of Malta, to fail entirely. Great distress was consequently felt
for want of a commodity regarded in those countries as one of the necessaries
of life rather than an article of luxury, and the abundance of
which contributes in some of the larger cities to the salubrity of the
water and the general health of the community. The magistrates of
Catania applied to Signor M. Gemmellaro, in the hope that his local
knowledge of Etna might enable him to point out some crevice or natural
grotto on the mountain, where drift-snow was still preserved.
Nor were they disappointed; for he had long suspected that a small
mass of perennial ice at the foot of the highest cone was part of a large
and continuous glacier covered by a lava-current. Having procured a
large body of workmen, he quarried into this ice, and proved the superposition
of the lava for several hundred yards, so as completely to
satisfy himself that nothing but the subsequent flowing of the lava over
the ice could account for the position of the glacier. Unfortunately for
the geologist, the ice was so extremely hard, and the excavation so expensive,
that there is no probability of the operations being renewed.
On the first of December, 1828, I visited this spot, which is on the
413
southeast side of the cone, and not far above the Casa Inglese; but the
fresh snow had already nearly filled up the new opening, so that it had
only the appearance of the mouth of a grotto. I do not, however,
question the accuracy of the conclusion of Signer Gemmellaro, who,
being well acquainted with all the appearances of drift-snow in the fissures
and cavities of Etna, had recognized, even before the late excavations,
the peculiarity of the position of the ice in this locality. We may suppose
that, at the commencement of the eruption, a deep mass of drift-snow
had been covered by volcanic sand showered down upon it before
the descent of the lava. A dense stratum of this fine dust mixed with
scoriæ is well known to be an extremely bad conductor of heat; and
the shepherds in the higher regions of Etna are accustomed to provide
water for their flocks during summer, by strewing a layer of volcanic
sand a few inches thick over the snow, which effectually prevents the
heat of the sun from penetrating.
Suppose the mass of snow to have been preserved from liquefaction
until the lower part of the lava had consolidated, we may then readily
conceive that a glacier thus protected, at the height of ten thousand
feet above the level of the sea, would endure as long as the snows of
Mont Blanc, unless melted by volcanic heat from below. When I
visited the great crater in the beginning of winter (December 1st, 1828),
I found the crevices in the interior incrusted with thick ice, and in
some cases hot vapors were actually streaming out between masses of
ice and the rugged and steep walls of the crater.572
After the discovery of Signor Gemmellaro, it would not be surprising
to find in the cones of the Icelandic volcanoes, which are covered for
the most part with perpetual snow, repeated alternations of lava-streams
and glaciers. We have, indeed, Lieutenant Kendall's authority for the
fact that Deception Island, in New South Shetland, lat. 62° 55' S., is
principally composed of alternate layers of volcanic ashes and
ice.573
Origin of the Val del Bove.—It is recorded, as will be stated in the
history of earthquakes (ch. 29), that in the year 1772 a great subsidence
took place on Papandayang, the largest volcano in the island of
Java; an extent of ground fifteen miles in length, and six in breadth,
covered by no less than forty villages, was engulphed, and the cone
lost 4000 feet of its height. In like manner the summit of Carguairazo,
one of the loftiest of the Andes of Quito, fell in on the 19th July, 1698;
and another mountain of still greater altitude in the same chain, called
Capac Urcu, a short time before the conquest of America by the Spaniards.
414
It will also be seen in the next chapter that, so late as the year 1822,
during a violent earthquake and volcanic eruption in Java, one side of
the mountain called Galongoon, which was covered by a dense forest,
became an enormous gulf in the form of a semicircle. The new cavity
was about midway between the summit and the plain, and surrounded
by steep rocks.
Now we might imagine a similar event, or a series of subsidences to
have formerly occurred on the eastern side of Etna, although such
catastrophes have not been witnessed in modern times, or only on a
very trifling scale. A narrow ravine, about a mile long, twenty feet
wide, and from twenty to thirty-six in depth, has been formed, within
the historical era, on the flanks of the volcano, near the town of Mascalucia;
and a small circular tract, called the Cisterna, near the summit,
sank down in the year 1792, to the depth of about forty feet, and left
on all sides of the chasm a vertical section of the beds, exactly resembling
those which are seen in the precipices of the Val del Bove. At
some remote periods, therefore, we might suppose more extensive portions
of the mountain to have fallen in during great earthquakes.
But we ought not to exclude entirely from our speculations another
possible agency, by which the great cavity may in part at least have
been excavated, namely, the denuding action of the sea. Whether its
waves may once have had access to the great valley before the ancient
portion of Etna was upheaved to its present elevation, is a question
which will naturally present itself to every geologist. Marine shells
have been traced to a height of 800 feet above the base of Etna, and
would doubtless be seen to ascend much higher, were not the structure
of the lower region of the mountain concealed by floods of lava. We
cannot ascertain to what extent a change in the relative level of land
and sea may have been carried in this spot, but we know that some of
the tertiary strata in Sicily of no ancient date reach a height of 3000
feet, and the marine deposits on the flanks of Etna, full of recent species
of shells, may ascend to equal or greater heights. The narrow Valley
of Calanna leading out of the Val del Bove, and that of San Giacomo
lower down, have much the appearance of ravines swept out by aqueous
action.
Structure and origin of the cone of Etna.—Our data for framing a
correct theory of the manner in which the cone of Etna has acquired its
present dimensions and internal structure are very imperfect, because it
is on its eastern side only, in the Val del Bove above described, that we
see a deep section exposed. Even here we obtain no insight into the
interior composition of the mountain beyond a depth of between three
and four thousand feet below the base of that highest cone, which has
been several times destroyed and renewed. The precipices seen at the
head of the Val del Bove, in the escarpment called the Serre del Solfizio,
exhibit merely the same series of alternating lavas and breccias,
which, descending with a general dip towards the sea, form the boundary
cliffs of all other parts of the Val del Bove. If then we estimate
415
the height of Etna at about 11,000 feet, we may say that we know
from actual observation less than one-half of its component materials,
assuming it to extend downwards to the level of the sea; namely, first,
the highest cone, which is about 1000 feet above its base; and, secondly,
the alternations of lava, tuff, and volcanic breccia, which constitute
the rocks between the Cisterna, near the base of the upper cone, and
the foot of the precipices at the head of the Val del Bove. At the
lowest point to which the vertical section extends, there are no signs of
any approach to a termination of the purely volcanic mass, which may
perhaps penetrate many thousand feet farther downwards. There is,
indeed, a rock called Rocca Gianicola, near the foot of the great escarpment,
which consists of a large mass between 150 and 200 feet wide,
not divided into beds, and almost resembling granite in its structure,
although agreeing very closely in mineral composition with the lavas of
Etna in general.574 This mass may doubtless be taken as a representative
of those crystalline or plutonic formations which would be met with
in abundance if we could descend to greater depths in the direction of
the central axis of the mountain. For a great body of geological evidence
leads us to conclude, that rocks of this class result from the consolidation,
under great pressure, of melted matter, which has risen up
and filled rents and chasms, such, for example, as may communicate
with the principal and minor vents of eruption in a volcano like Etna.
But, if we speculate on the nature of the formation which the lava
may have pierced in its way upwards, we may fairly presume that a
portion of these consist of marine tertiary rocks, like those of the neighboring
Val di Noto, or those which skirt the borders of the Etnean cone,
on its southern and eastern sides. Etna may, in fact, have been at first
an insular volcano, raising its summit but slightly above the level of the
sea; but we have no grounds for concluding that any of the beds exposed
in the deep section of the Val del Bove have formed a part of such
a marine accumulation. On the contrary, all the usual signs of subaqueous
origin are wanting; and even if we believe the foundations of
the mountain to have been laid in the sea, we could not expect this portion
to be made visible in sections which only proceed downwards from
the summit through one-half the thickness of the mountain, especially as
the highest points attained by the tertiary strata in other parts of Sicily
very rarely exceed 3000 feet above the sea.
On the eastern and southern base of Etna, a marine deposit, already
alluded to, is traced up to the height of 800 or 1000 feet, before it becomes
concealed beneath that covering of modern lavas which is continually
extending its limits during successive eruptions, and prevents us
from ascertaining how much higher the marine strata may ascend. As
the imbedded shells belong almost entirely to species now inhabiting
the Mediterranean, it is evident that there has been here an upheaval of
the region at the base of Etna at a very modern period. It is fair, therefore,
416
to infer that the volcanic nucleus of the mountain, partly perhaps of
submarine, and partly of subaerial origin, participated in this movement,
and was carried up bodily. Now, in proportion as a cone gains height
by such a movement, combined with the cumulative effects of eruptions,
throwing out matter successively from one or more central vents, the
hydrostatic pressure of the columns of lava augments with their increasing
height, until the time arrives when the flanks of the cone can no
longer resist the increased pressure; and from that period they give
way more readily, lateral outbursts becoming more frequent. Hence,
independently of any local expansion of the fractured volcanic mass,
those general causes by which the modern tertiary strata of a great part
of Sicily have been raised to the height of several thousand feet above
their original level, would tend naturally to render the discharge of lava
and scoriæ from the summit of Etna less copious, and the lateral discharge
greater.
If, then, a conical or dome-shaped mass of volcanic materials was
accumulated to the height of 4000, or perhaps 7000 feet, before the upward
movement began, or, what is much more probable, during the
continuance of the upward movement, that ancient mass would not be
buried under the products of newer eruptions, because these last would
then be poured out chiefly at a lower level.
Since I visited Etna in 1828, M. de Beaumont has published a most
valuable memoir on the structure and origin of that mountain, which he
examined in 1834;575 and an excellent description of it has also appeared
in the posthumous work of Hoffmann.576
In M. de Beaumont's essay, in which he has explained his views with
uncommon perspicuity and talent, he maintains that all the alternating
stony and fragmentary beds, more than 3000 feet thick, which are exposed
in the Val del Bove, were formed originally on a surface so nearly
flat that the slope never exceeded three degrees. From this horizontal
position they were at length heaved up suddenly (d'un seul coup) into a
great mountain, to which no important additions have since been made.
Prior to this upthrow, a platform is supposed to have existed above the
level of the sea, in which various fissures opened; and from these melted
matter was poured forth again and again, which spread itself around
in thin sheets of uniform thickness. From the same rents issued showers
of scoriæ and fragmentary matter, which were spread out so as to form
equally uniform and horizontal beds, intervening between the sheets of
lava. But although, by the continued repetition of these operations, a
vast pile of volcanic matter, 4000 feet or more in thickness, was built up
precisely in that region where Etna now rises, and to which nothing
similar was produced elsewhere in Sicily, still we are told that Etna was
not yet a mountain. No hypothetical diagram has been given to help
us to conceive how this great mass of materials of supramarine origin
417
could have been disposed of in horizontal beds, so as not to constitute
an eminence towering far above the rest of Sicily; but it is assumed that
a powerful force from below at length burst suddenly through the horizontal
formation, uplifted it to a considerable height, and caused the beds
to be, in many places, highly inclined. This elevatory force was not all
expended on a single central point as Von Buch has imagined in the case
of Palma, Teneriffe, or Somma, but rather followed for a short distance
a linear direction.577
Among other objections that may be advanced against the theory
above proposed, I may mention, first, that the increasing number of
dikes as we approach the head of the Val del Bove, or the middle of
Etna, and the great thickness of lava, scoriæ, and conglomerates in that
region, imply that the great centre of eruption was always where it now
is, or nearly at the same point, and there must, therefore, have been a
tendency, from the beginning, to a conical or dome-shaped arrangement
in the ejected materials. Secondly, were we to admit a great number
of separate points of eruption, scattered over a plain or platform, there
must have been a great number of cones thrown up over these different
vents; and these hills, some of which would probably be as lofty as
those now seen on the flanks of Etna, or from 300 to 750 feet in height,
would break the continuity of the sheets of lava, while they would become
gradually enveloped by them. The ejected materials, moreover,
would slope at a high angle on the sides of these cones, and where they
fell on the surrounding plain, would form strata thicker near the base
of each cone than at a distance.
What then are the facts, it will be asked, to account for which this
hypothesis of original horizontality, followed by a single and sudden
effort of upheaval, which gave to the beds their present slope, has been
invented? M. de Beaumont observes, that in the boundary precipices
of the Val del Bove, sheets of lava and intercalated beds of cinders,
mixed with pulverulent and fragmentary matter evidently cast out
during eruptions, are sometimes inclined at steep angles, varying from
15° to 27°. It is impossible, he says, that the lavas could have flowed
originally on planes so steeply inclined, for streams which descend a
slope even of 10° form narrow stripes, and never acquire such a compact
texture. Their thickness, moreover, always inconsiderable, varies
with every variation of steepness, in the declivity down which they flow;
whereas, in several parts of the Val del Bove, the sheets of lava are
continuous for great distances, in spite of their steep inclination, and are
often compact, and perfectly parallel one to the other, even where there
are more than 100 beds of interpolated fragmentary matter.
The intersecting dikes also terminate upwards in many instances, at
different elevations, and blend (or, as M. de Beaumont terms it, articulate)
with sheets of lava, which they meet at right angles. It is therefore
assumed that such dikes were the feeders of the streams of lava
418
with which they unite, and they are supposed to prove that the platform,
on the surface of which the melted matter was poured out, was
at first so flat, that the fluid mass spread freely and equally in every
direction, and not towards one point only of the compass, as would
happen if it had descended the sloping sides of a cone. This argument
is ingeniously and plainly put in the following terms:—"Had the
melted matter poured down an inclined plane, after issuing from a rent,
the sheet of lava would, after consolidation, have formed an elbow with
the dike, like the upper bar of the letter F, instead of extending itself
on both sides like that of a T."578 It is also contended that a series of
sheets of lava, formed on a conical or dome-shaped mountain, would
have been more numerous at points farthest from the central axis, since
every dike which had been the source of a lava-stream, must have poured
its contents downwards, and never upwards.
Fig. 54.

Dikes as they would now appear had they been originally perpendicular.
In reference to the facts here stated, I may mention that the dikes
which I saw in the Val del Bove were either vertical, or made almost
all of them a near approach to the perpendicular, which could not have
been the case had they been the feeders of horizontal beds of lava, and
had they consequently joined them originally at right angles, for then
the dikes, as at a, b, c, fig. 54, ought subsequently to have acquired a
considerable slope, like the beds which they intersect. I may also urge
another objection to the views above set forth, namely, that had the
dikes been linear vents, or orifices of eruption, we must suppose the
inter-stratified scoriæ and lapilli, as well as the lavas, to have come
out of them, and in that case the irregular heaping up of fragmentary
matter around the vents would, as before hinted, have disturbed that
uniform thickness and parallelism of the beds which M. de Beaumont
describes.
If, however, some of the sheets of lava join the dikes in such a manner,
as to imply that they were in a melted state simultaneously with
the contents of the fissures,—a point not easily ascertained, where the
419
precipices are for the most part inaccessible,—the fact may admit of a
different interpretation from that proposed by the French geologists.
Rents like those before alluded to (p. 399), which opened in the plain
of S. Lio in 1669, filled below with incandescent lava, may have lain in
the way of currents of melted matter descending from higher openings.
In that case, the matter of the current would have flowed into the
fissure and mixed with the lava at its bottom. Numerous open rents of
this kind are described by Mr. Dana as having been caused, during a late
eruption, in one of the volcanic domes of the Sandwich Islands. They
remained open at various heights on the slopes of the great cone, running
in different directions, and demonstrate the possibility of future junctions
of slightly inclined lava-streams with perpendicular walls of lava.
To me, therefore, it appears far more easy to explain the uniform
thickness and parallelism of so many lavas and beds of fragmentary
matter seen in the Val del Bove, by supposing them to have issued
successively out of one or more higher vents near the summit of a great
dome, than to imagine them to have proceeded from lateral dikes or
rents opening in a level plain. In the Sandwich Islands, we have examples
of volcanic domes 15,000 feet high, produced by successive outpourings
from vents at or near the summit. One of these, Mount Loa,
has a slope in all directions of 6° 30'; another, Mount Kea, a mean
inclination of 7° 46'. That their lavas may occasionally consolidate on
slopes of 25°, and even more, and still preserve considerable solidity of
texture, has been already stated; see above, p. 383.
We know not how large a quantity of modern lava may have been
poured into the bottom of the Val del Bove, yet we perceive that eruptions
breaking forth near the centre of Etna have already made some
progress in filling up this great hollow. Even within the memory of
persons now living, the rocks of Musara and Capra have, as before
stated, lost much of their height and picturesque grandeur by the piling
up of recent lavas round their base (see fig. 51, p. 408), and the great
chasm has intercepted many streams which would otherwise have deluged
the fertile region below, as has happened on the side of Catania.
The volcanic forces are now laboring, therefore, to repair the breach
which subsidence has caused on one side of the great cone; and unless
their energy should decline, or a new sinking take place, they may in
time efface this inequality. In that event, the restored portion will always
be unconformable to the more ancient part, yet it will consist, like
it, of alternating beds of lava, scoriæ;, and conglomerates, which, with
all their irregularities, will have a general slope from the centre and
summit of Etna towards the sea.
I shall conclude, then, by remarking that I conceive the general inclination
of the alternating stony and fragmentary beds of the Val del
Bove, from the axis of Etna towards its circumference or base, and the
greater thickness of the volcanic pile as we approach the central parts of
the mountain, to be due to the preponderance of eruptions from that
centre. These gave rise, from the first, to a dome-shaped mass, which
420
has ever since been increasing in height and area, being fractured again
and again by the expansive force of vapors, and the several parts made
to cohere together more firmly after the solidification of the lava with
which every open fissure and chasm has been filled. At the same time
the cone may have gained a portion of its height by the elevatory effect
of such dislocating movements, and the sheets of lava may have acquired
in some places a greater, in others a less, inclination than that which at
first belonged to them.
Fig. 55.
Non-volcanic protuberance and valley of elevation.
But had the mountain been due solely, or even principally, to upheaval,
its structure would have resembled that which geologists have so
often recognized in dome-shaped hills, or certain elevated regions, which
all consider as having been thrust up by a force from below. In this case
there is often an elliptical cavity at the summit, due partly to the fracture
of the upraised rocks, but still more to aqueous denudation, as they
rose out of the sea. The central cavity, or valley, exposes to view the
subjacent formation c, fig. 55, and the incumbent mass dips away on all
sides from the axis, but has no tendency to thin out near the base of the
dome, or at x, x; whereas at this point the volcanic mass terminates
(see fig. 56) and allows the fundamental rock c to appear at the surface.
In the last diagram, the more ordinary case is represented of a great
hollow or crater at the summit of the volcanic cone; but instead of
this, we have seen that in the case of Etna there is a deep lateral depression,
called the Val del Bove, the upper part of which approaches
near to the central axis, and the origin of which we have attributed to
subsidence.
Fig. 56.
Volcanic mountain and crater.
Antiquity of the cone of Etna.—It was before remarked that confined
notions in regard to the quantity of past time have tended, more than
any other prepossessions, to retard the progress of sound theoretical
views in geology;579 the inadequacy of our conceptions of the earth's
antiquity having cramped the freedom of our speculations in this science,
very much in the same way as a belief in the existence of a vaulted firmament
once retarded the progress of astronomy. It was not until
Descartes assumed the indefinite extent of the celestial spaces, and removed
the supposed boundaries of the universe, that just opinions began
421
to be entertained of the relative distances of the heavenly bodies; and
until we habituate ourselves to contemplate the possibility of an indefinite
lapse of ages having been comprised within each of the modern
periods of the earth's history, we shall be in danger of forming most
erroneous and partial views in geology.
If history had bequeathed to us a faithful record of the eruptions of
Etna, and a hundred other of the principal active volcanoes of the globe,
during the last three thousand years,—if we had an exact account of the
volume of lava and matter ejected during that period, and the times
of their production,—we might, perhaps, be able to form a correct estimate
of the average rate of the growth of a volcanic cone. For we
might obtain a mean result from the comparison of the eruptions of so
great a number of vents, however irregular might be the development
of the igneous action in any one of them, if contemplated singly during
a brief period.
It would be necessary to balance protracted periods of inaction against
the occasional outburst of paroxysmal explosions. Sometimes we should
have evidence of a repose of seventeen centuries, like that which was
interposed in Ischia, between the end of the fourth century B. C., and the
beginning of the fourteenth century of our era.580 Occasionally a tremendous
eruption, like that of Jorullo, would be recorded, giving rise,
at once, to a considerable mountain.
If we desire to approximate to the age of a cone such as Etna, we
ought first to obtain some data in regard to the thickness of matter
which has been added during the historical era, and then endeavor to
estimate the time required for the accumulation of such alternating lavas
and beds of sand and scoriæ as are superimposed upon each other in the
Val del Bove; afterwards we should try to deduce, from observations
on other volcanoes, the more or less rapid increase of burning mountains
in all the different stages of their growth.
There is a considerable analogy between the mode of increase of a
volcanic cone and that of trees of exogenous growth. These trees augment,
both in height and diameter, by the successive application externally
of cone upon cone of new ligneous matter; so that if we make a
transverse section near the base of the trunk, we intersect a much greater
number of layers than nearer to the summit. When branches occasionally
shoot out from the trunk, they first pierce the bark, and then, after
growing to a certain size, if they chance to be broken off, they may become
inclosed in the body of the tree, as it augments in size, forming
knots in the wood, which are themselves composed of layers of ligneous
matter, cone within cone.
In like manner, a volcanic mountain, as we have seen, consists of a
succession of conical masses enveloping others, while lateral cones, having
a similar internal structure, often project, in the first instance, like
branches from the surface of the main cone, and then becoming buried
again, are hidden like the knots of a tree.
422
We can ascertain the age of an oak or pine by counting the number
of concentric rings of annual growth seen in a transverse section near
the base, so that we may know the date at which the seedling began to
vegetate. The Baobab-tree of Senegal (Adansonia digitata) is supposed
to exceed almost any other in longevity. Adanson inferred that one
which he measured, and found to be thirty feet in diameter, had attained
the age of 5150 years. Having made an incision to a certain depth, he
first counted three hundred rings of annual growth, and observed what
thickness the tree had gained in that period. The average rate of growth
of younger trees, of the same species, was then ascertained, and the
calculation made according to a supposed mean rate of increase. De
Candolle considers it not improbable that the celebrated Taxodium of
Chapultepec, in Mexico (Cupressus disticha, Linn.), which is 117 feet in
circumference, may be still more aged.581
It is, however, impossible, until more data are collected respecting
the average intensity of the volcanic action, to make any thing like an
approximation to the age of a cone like Etna; because, in this case, the
successive envelopes of lava and scoriæ are not continuous, like the layers
of wood in a tree, and afford us no definite measure of time. Each conical
envelope is made up of a great number of distinct lava-currents and
showers of sand and scoriæ, differing in quantity, and which may have
been accumulated in unequal periods of time. Yet we cannot fail to
form the most exalted conception of the antiquity of this mountain, when
we consider that its base is about ninety miles in circumference; so that
it would require ninety flows of lava, each a mile in breadth at their
termination, to raise the present foot of the volcano as much as the
average height of one lava-current.
There are no records within the historical era which lead to the opinion
that the altitude of Etna has materially varied within the last two
thousand years. Of the eighty most conspicuous minor cones which
adorn its flanks, only one of the largest, Monti Rossi, has been produced
within the times of authentic history. Even this hill, thrown up in the
year 1669, although 450 feet in height, only ranks as a cone of second
magnitude. Monte Minardo, near Bronte, rises, even now, to the height
of 750 feet, although its base has been elevated by more modern lavas
and ejections. The dimensions of these larger cones appear to bear
testimony to paroxysms of volcanic activity, after which we may conclude,
from analogy, that the fires of Etna remained dormant for many
years—since nearly a century of rest has sometimes followed a violent
eruption in the historical era. It must also be remembered, that of the
small number of eruptions which occur in a century, one only is estimated
to issue from the summit of Etna for every two that proceed from
the sides. Nor do all the lateral eruptions give rise to such cones as
would be reckoned amongst the smallest of the eighty hills above enumerated;
some of them produce merely insignificant monticules, which
are soon afterwards buried by showers of ashes.
423
How many years then must we not suppose to have been expended
in the formation of the eighty cones? It is difficult to imagine that a
fourth part of them have originated during the last thirty centuries.
But if we conjecture the whole of them to have been formed in twelve
thousand years, how inconsiderable an era would this portion of time
constitute in the history of the volcano! If we could strip off from
Etna all the lateral monticules now visible, together with the lavas and
scoriæ that have been poured out from them, and from the highest
crater, during the period of their growth, the diminution of the entire
mass would be extremely slight: Etna might lose, perhaps, several
miles in diameter at its base, and some hundreds of feet in elevation;
but it would still be the loftiest of Sicilian mountains, studded with
other cones, which would be recalled, as it were, into existence by the
removal of the rocks under which they are now buried.
There seems nothing in the deep sections of the Val del Bove to indicate
that the lava-currents of remote periods were greater in volume
than those of modern times; and there are abundant proofs that the
countless beds of solid rock and scoriæ were accumulated, as now, in
succession. On the grounds, therefore, already explained, we must
infer that a mass so many thousand feet in thickness must have required
an immense series of ages anterior to our historical periods for its growth;
yet the whole must be regarded as the product of a modern portion of
the tertiary epoch. Such, at least, is the conclusion that seems to follow
from geological data, which show that the oldest parts of the mountain,
if not of posterior date to the marine strata around its base, were
at least of coeval origin.
Some geologists contend, that the sudden elevation of large continents
from beneath the waters of the sea have again and again produced
waves which have swept over vast regions of the earth.582 But it is
clear that no devastating wave has passed over the forest zone of Etna
since any of the lateral cones before mentioned were thrown up; for
none of these heaps of loose sand and scoriæ could have resisted for a
moment the denuding action of a violent flood. To some, perhaps, it
may appear that hills of such incoherent materials cannot be of very
great antiquity, because the mere action of the atmosphere must, in the
course of several thousand years, have obliterated their original forms.
But there is no weight in this objection; for the older hills are covered
with trees and herbage, which protect them from waste; and, in regard
to the newer ones, such is the porosity of their component materials,
that the rain which falls upon them is instantly absorbed; and for the
same reason that the rivers on Etna have a subterranean course, there
are none descending the sides of the minor cones.
No sensible alteration has been observed in the form of these cones
since the earliest periods of which there are memorials; and there
seems no reason for anticipating that in the course of the next ten
424
thousand or twenty thousand years they will undergo any great alteration
in their appearance, unless they should be shattered by earthquakes
or covered by volcanic ejections.
In other parts of Europe, as in Auvergne and Velay, in France,
similar loose cones of scoriæ, probably of as high antiquity as the whole
mass of Etna, stand uninjured at inferior elevations above the level of
the sea.
</div></body></text></TEI>