<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="10">
CHAPTER V.
Of Certain Characteristics of Scientific Induction.
Aphorism X.
The process of scientific discovery is cautious and rigorous,
not by abstaining from hypotheses, but by rigorously comparing
hypotheses with facts, and by resolutely rejecting all
which the comparison does not confirm.
Aphorism XI.
Hypotheses may be useful, though involving much that is
superfluous, and even erroneous: for they may supply the
true bond of connexion of the facts; and the superfluity and
errour may afterwards be pared away.
Aphorism XII.
It is a test of true theories not only to account for, but to
predict phenomena.
Aphorism XIII.
Induction is a term applied to describe the process of a
true Colligation of Facts by means of an exact and appropriate
Conception. An Induction is also employed to denote
the proposition which results from this process.
Aphorism XIV.
The Consilience of Inductions takes place when an
Induction, obtained from one class of facts, coincides with
an Induction, obtained from another different class. This 71
Consilience is a test of the truth of the Theory in which it
occurs.
Aphorism XV.
An Induction is not the mere sum of the Facts which are
colligated. The Facts are not only brought together, but seen
in a new point of view. A new mental Element is superinduced;
and a peculiar constitution and discipline of mind
are requisite in order to make this Induction.
Aphorism XVI.
Although in Every Induction a new conception is superinduced
upon the Facts; yet this once effectually done, the
novelty of the conception is overlooked, and the conception is
considered as a part of the fact.
Sect. I.—Invention a part of Induction.
1. THE
two operations spoken of in the preceding
chapters,—the Explication of the Conceptions
of our own minds, and the Colligation of observed Facts
by the aid of such Conceptions,—are, as we have just
said, inseparably connected with each other. When
united, and employed in collecting knowledge from the
phenomena which the world presents to us, they constitute
the mental process of Induction; which is usually and
justly spoken of as the genuine source of all
our real general knowledge respecting the external
world. And we see, from the preceding analysis of
this process into its two constituents, from what origin
it derives each of its characters. It is real, because it
arises from the combination of Real Facts, but it is
general, because it implies the possession of General
Ideas. Without the former, it would not be knowledge of the
External World; without the latter, it
would not be Knowledge at all. When Ideas and
Facts are separated from each other, the neglect of
Facts gives rise to empty speculations, idle subtleties,
visionary inventions, false opinions concerning the laws
of phenomena, disregard of the true aspect of nature: 72
while the want of Ideas leaves the mind overwhelmed,
bewildered, and stupified by particular sensations, with
no means of connecting the past with the future, the
absent with the present, the example with the rule;
open to the impression of all appearances, but capable
of appropriating none. Ideas are the Form, facts the
Material, of our structure. Knowledge does not
consist in the empty mould, or in the brute mass of matter,
but in the rightly-moulded substance. Induction
gathers general truths from particular facts;—and in
her harvest, the corn and the reaper, the solid ears and
the binding band, are alike requisite. All our knowledge
of nature is obtained by Induction; the term
being understood according to the explanation we have
now given. And our knowledge is then most complete, then
most truly deserves the name of Science,
when both its elements are most perfect;—when the
Ideas which have been concerned in its formation have,
at every step, been clear and consistent; and when
they have, at every step also, been employed in binding
together real and certain Facts. Of such Induction,
I have already given so many examples and illustrations
in the two preceding chapters, that I need not
now dwell further upon the subject.
2. Induction is familiarly spoken of as the process
by which we collect a General Proposition from a number
of Particular Cases: and it appears to be frequently
imagined that the general proposition results
from a mere juxta-position of the cases, or at most, from
merely conjoining and extending them. But if we
consider the process more closely, as exhibited in the
cases lately spoken of, we shall perceive that this is an
inadequate account of the matter. The particular
facts are not merely brought together, but there is a
New Element added to the combination by the very
act of thought by which they are combined. There is
a Conception of the mind introduced in the general
proposition, which did not exist in any of the observed
facts. When the Greeks, after long observing the
motions of the planets, saw that these motions might
be rightly considered as produced by the motion of one 73
wheel revolving in the inside of another wheel, these
Wheels were Creations of their minds, added to the
Facts which they perceived by sense. And even if the
wheels were no longer supposed to be material, but
were reduced to mere geometrical spheres or circles,
they were not the less products of the mind alone,—something
additional to the facts observed. The same
is the case in all other discoveries. The facts are
known, but they are insulated and unconnected, till
the discoverer supplies from his own stores a Principle
of Connexion. The pearls are there, but they will not
hang together till some one provides the String. The
distances and periods of the planets were all so many
separate facts; by Kepler’s Third Law they are connected
into a single truth: but the Conceptions which
this law involves were supplied by Kepler’s mind, and
without these, the facts were of no avail. The planets
described ellipses round the sun, in the contemplation
of others as well as of Newton; but Newton conceived
the deflection from the tangent in these elliptical
motions in a new light,—as the effect of a Central Force
following a certain law; and then it was, that such a
force was discovered truly to exist.
Thus5
in each inference made by Induction, there is
introduced some General Conception, which is given,
not by the phenomena, but by the mind. The conclusion
is not contained in the premises, but includes
them by the introduction of a New Generality. In
order to obtain our inference, we travel beyond the
cases which we have before us; we consider them as
mere exemplifications of some Ideal Case in which the
relations are complete and intelligible. We take a
Standard, and measure the facts by it; and this
Standard is constructed by us, not offered by Nature.
We assert, for example, that a body left to itself will
move on with unaltered velocity; not because our
senses ever disclosed to us a body doing this, but
because (taking this as our Ideal Case) we find that all 74
actual cases are intelligible and explicable by means of
the Conception of Forces, causing change and motion,
and exerted by surrounding bodies. In like manner,
we see bodies striking each other, and thus moving and
stopping, accelerating and retarding each other: but
in all this, we do not perceive by our senses that
abstract quantity, Momentum, which is always lost by
one body as it is gained by another. This Momentum
is a creation of the mind, brought in among the facts,
in order to convert their apparent confusion into order,
their seeming chance into certainty, their perplexing
variety into simplicity. This the Conception of Momentum
gained and lost does: and in like manner, in
any other case in which a truth is established by Induction,
some Conception is introduced, some Idea is
applied, as the means of binding together the facts,
and thus producing the truth.
5
I repeat here remarks made at the end of the Mechanical Euclid, p. 178.
3. Hence in every inference by Induction, there is
some Conception superinduced upon the Facts: and
we may henceforth conceive this to be the peculiar
import of the term Induction. I am not to be understood
as asserting that the term was originally or
anciently employed with this notion of its meaning;
for the peculiar feature just pointed out in Induction
has generally been overlooked. This appears by the
accounts generally given of Induction. ‘Induction,’
says Aristotle6,
‘is when by means of one extreme
term7 we
infer the other extreme term to be true of
the middle term.’ Thus, (to take such exemplifications
as belong to our subject,) from knowing that Mercury,
Venus, Mars, describe ellipses about the Sun, we infer
that all Planets describe ellipses about the Sun. In
making this inference syllogistically, we assume that
the evident proposition, ‘Mercury, Venus, Mars, do
what all Planets do,’ may be taken conversely, ‘All 75
Planets do what Mercury, Venus, Mars, do.’ But we
may remark that, in this passage, Aristotle (as was
natural in his line of discussion) turns his attention
entirely to the evidence of the inference; and overlooks
a step which is of far more importance to our knowledge,
namely, the invention of the second extreme
term. In the above instance, the particular luminaries,
Mercury, Venus, Mars, are one logical Extreme; the
general designation Planets is the Middle Term; but
having these before us, how do we come to think of
description of ellipses, which is the other Extreme
of the syllogism? When we have once invented this
‘second Extreme Term,’ we may, or may not, be satisfied
with the evidence of the syllogism; we may, or
may not, be convinced that, so far as this property
goes, the extremes are co-extensive with the middle
term8;
but the statement of the syllogism is the
important step in science. We know how long Kepler
laboured, how hard he fought, how many devices he
tried, before he hit upon this Term, the Elliptical
Motion. He rejected, as we know, many other ‘second
extreme Terms,’ for example, various combinations of
epicyclical constructions, because they did not represent
with sufficient accuracy the special facts of observation.
When he had established his premiss, that ‘Mars
does describe an Ellipse about the Sun,’ he does not
hesitate to guess at least that, in this respect, he might
convert the other premiss, and assert that ‘All the
Planets do what Mars does.’ But the main business
was, the inventing and verifying the proposition
respecting the Ellipse. The Invention of the Conception
was the great step in the discovery; the Verification of
the Proposition was the great step in the proof of the
discovery. If Logic consists in pointing out the conditions
of proof, the Logic of Induction must consist in
showing what are the conditions of proof, in such
inferences as this: but this subject must be pursued in the
next chapter; I now speak principally of the act of 76
Invention, which is requisite in every inductive inference.
6
Analyt. Prior. lib. ii. c. xxiii. Περὶ τῆς ἐπαγωγῆς.
7 The syllogism here alluded to would
be this:—
  Mercury, Venus, Mars, describe ellipses about the Sun;
  All Planets do what Mercury, Venus, Mars, do;
  Therefore all Planets describe ellipses about the Sun.
8
Εἰ οὖν ἀντιστρέφει τὸ Γ τῷ Β καὶ μὴ ὑπερτείνει τὸ μέσον.—Aristot. Ibid.
4. Although in every inductive inference, an act of
invention is requisite, the act soon slips out of notice.
Although we bind together facts by superinducing
upon them a new Conception, this Conception, once
introduced and applied, is looked upon as inseparably
connected with the facts, and necessarily implied in
them. Having once had the phenomena bound together in
their minds in virtue of the Conception, men
can no longer easily restore them back to the detached
and incoherent condition in which they were before
they were thus combined. The pearls once strung,
they seem to form a chain by their nature. Induction
has given them a unity which it is so far from costing
us an effort to preserve, that it requires an effort to
imagine it dissolved. For instance, we usually represent
to ourselves the Earth as round, the Earth and
the Planets as revolving about the Sun, and as drawn
to the Sun by a Central Force; we can hardly understand
how it could cost the Greeks, and Copernicus,
and Newton, so much pains and trouble to arrive at a
view which to us is so familiar. These are no longer
to us Conceptions caught hold of and kept hold of by
a severe struggle; they are the simplest modes of
conceiving the facts: they are really Facts. We are
willing to own our obligation to those discoverers, but we
hardly feel it: for in what other manner (we ask in
our thoughts) could we represent the facts to ourselves?
Thus we see why it is that this step of which we
now speak, the Invention of a new Conception in
every inductive inference, is so generally overlooked
that it has hardly been noticed by preceding philosophers.
When once performed by the discoverer, it
takes a fixed and permanent place in the understanding
of every one. It is a thought which, once breathed
forth, permeates all men’s minds. All fancy they
nearly or quite knew it before. It oft was thought, or
almost thought, though never till now expressed. Men
accept it and retain it, and know it cannot be taken 77
from them, and look upon it as their own. They will not
and cannot part with it, even though they may deem
it trivial and obvious. It is a secret, which once
uttered, cannot be recalled, even though it be despised
by those to whom it is imparted. As soon as the leading
term of a new theory has been pronounced and
understood, all the phenomena change their aspect.
There is a standard to which we cannot help referring
them. We cannot fall back into the helpless and
bewildered state in which we gazed at them when we
possessed no principle which gave them unity. Eclipses
arrive in mysterious confusion: the notion of a Cycle
dispels the mystery. The Planets perform a tangled
and mazy dance; but Epicycles reduce the maze to
order. The Epicycles themselves run into confusion;
the conception of an Ellipse makes all clear and simple.
And thus from stage to stage, new elements of intelligible
order are introduced. But this intelligible order
is so completely adopted by the human understanding,
as to seem part of its texture. Men ask Whether
Eclipses follow a Cycle; Whether the Planets describe
Ellipses; and they imagine that so long as they do not
answer such questions rashly, they take nothing for
granted. They do not recollect how much they assume
in asking the question:—how far the conceptions of
Cycles and of Ellipses are beyond the visible surface of
the celestial phenomena:—how many ages elapsed,
how much thought, how much observation, were
needed, before men’s thoughts were fashioned into the
words which they now so familiarly use. And thus
they treat the subject, as we have seen Aristotle treating
it; as if it were a question, not of invention, but
of proof; not of substance, but of form: as if the main
thing were not what we assert, but how we assert it.
But for our purpose, it is requisite to bear in mind the
feature which we have thus attempted to mark; and
to recollect that, in every inference by induction, there
is a Conception supplied by the mind and superinduced
upon the Facts.
5. In collecting scientific truths by Induction, we
often find (as has already been observed) a Definition 78
and a Proposition established at the same time,—introduced
together, and mutually dependent on each
other. The combination of the two constitutes the
Inductive act; and we may consider the Definition as
representing the superinduced Conception, and the
Proposition as exhibiting the Colligation of Facts.
Sect. II.—Use of Hypotheses.
6. To discover a Conception of the mind which will
justly represent a train of observed facts is, in some
measure, a process of conjecture, as I have stated already;
and as I then observed, the business of conjecture is
commonly conducted by calling up before our
minds several suppositions, and selecting that one which
most agrees with what we know of the observed facts.
Hence he who has to discover the laws of nature may
have to invent many suppositions before he hits upon
the right one; and among the endowments which lead
to his success, we must reckon that fertility of invention
which ministers to him such imaginary schemes,
till at last he finds the one which conforms to the true
order of nature. A facility in devising hypotheses,
therefore, is so far from being a fault in the intellectual
character of a discoverer, that it is, in truth, a
faculty indispensable to his task. It is, for his purposes,
much better that he should be too ready in contriving,
too eager in pursuing systems which promise
to introduce law and order among a mass of unarranged
facts, than that he should be barren of such inventions
and hopeless of such success. Accordingly, as we have
already noticed, great discoverers have often invented
hypotheses which would not answer to all the facts, as
well as those which would; and have fancied themselves
to have discovered laws, which a more careful
examination of the facts overturned.
The tendencies of our speculative
nature9,
carrying 79
us onwards in pursuit of symmetry and rule, and thus
producing all true theories, perpetually show their
vigour by overshooting the mark. They obtain something,
by aiming at much more. They detect the order
and connexion which exist, by conceiving imaginary
relations of order and connexion which have no existence.
Real discoveries are thus mixed with baseless
assumptions; profound sagacity is combined with fanciful
conjecture; not rarely, or in peculiar instances,
but commonly, and in most cases; probably in all, if we
could read the thoughts of discoverers as we read the
books of Kepler. To try wrong guesses is, with most
persons, the only way to hit upon right ones. The
character of the true philosopher is, not that he never
conjectures hazardously, but that his conjectures are
clearly conceived, and brought into rigid contact with
facts. He sees and compares distinctly the Ideas and
the Things;—the relations of his notions to each other
and to phenomena. Under these conditions, it is not
only excusable, but necessary for him, to snatch at
every semblance of general rule,—to try all promising
forms of simplicity and symmetry.
9
I here take the liberty of characterizing inventive
minds in general in the same phraseology which, in the History
of Science, I have employed in reference to particular examples.
These expressions are what I have used in speaking of the
discoveries of Copernicus.—Hist. Ind. Sc. b. v. c. ii.
Hence advances in
knowledge10
are not commonly
made without the previous exercise of some boldness
and license in guessing. The discovery of new truths
requires, undoubtedly, minds careful and scrupulous in
examining what is suggested; but it requires, no less,
such as are quick and fertile in suggesting. What is
Invention, except the talent of rapidly calling before us
the many possibilities, and selecting the appropriate
one? It is true, that when we have rejected all the
inadmissible suppositions, they are often quickly forgotten;
and few think it necessary to dwell on these
discarded hypotheses, and on the process by which they
were condemned. But all who discover truths, must
have reasoned upon many errours to obtain each truth; 80
every accepted doctrine must have been one chosen
out of many candidates. If many of the guesses of
philosophers of bygone times now appear fanciful and
absurd, because time and observation have refuted them,
others, which were at the time equally gratuitous, have
been conformed in a manner which makes them appear
marvellously sagacious. To form hypotheses, and then
to employ much labour and skill in refuting them, if
they do not succeed in establishing them, is a part of
the usual process of inventive minds. Such a proceeding
belongs to the rule of the genius of discovery,
rather than (as has often been taught in modern times)
to the exception.
10
These observations are made on occasion of
Kepler’s speculations, and are illustrated by reference to his
discoveries.—Hist. Ind. Sc. b. v. c. iv. sect. 1.
7. But if it be an advantage for the discoverer of
truth that he be ingenious and fertile in inventing
hypotheses which may connect the phenomena of nature,
it is indispensably requisite that he be diligent
and careful in comparing his hypotheses with the facts,
and ready to abandon his invention as soon as it appears
that it does not agree with the course of actual
occurrences. This constant comparison of his own
conceptions and supposition with observed facts under
all aspects, forms the leading employment of the
discoverer: this candid and simple love of truth, which
makes him willing to suppress the most favourite
production of his own ingenuity as soon as it appears to
be at variance with realities, constitutes the first
characteristic of his temper. He must have neither the
blindness which cannot, nor the obstinacy which will
not, perceive the discrepancy of his fancies and his
facts. He must allow no indolence, or partial views,
or self-complacency, or delight in seeming demonstration,
to make him tenacious of the schemes which he
devises, any further than they are confirmed by their
accordance with nature. The framing of hypotheses
is, for the inquirer after truth, not the end, but the
beginning of his work. Each of his systems is invented,
not that he may admire it and follow it into
all its consistent consequences, but that he may make
it the occasion of a course of active experiment and
observation. And if the results of this process
81 contradict
his fundamental assumptions, however ingenious,
however symmetrical, however elegant his system may
be, he rejects it without hesitation. He allows no
natural yearning for the offspring of his own mind to
draw him aside from the higher duty of loyalty to his
sovereign, Truth: to her he not only gives his
affections and his wishes, but strenuous labour and
scrupulous minuteness of attention.
We may refer to what we have said of Kepler, Newton,
and other eminent philosophers, for illustrations
of this character. In Kepler we have
remarked11 the
courage and perseverance with which he undertook and
executed the task of computing his own hypotheses:
and, as a still more admirable characteristic, that he
never allowed the labour he had spent upon any conjecture
to produce any reluctance in abandoning the
hypothesis, as soon as he had evidence of its inaccuracy.
And in the history of Newton’s discovery
that the moon is retained in her orbit by the force of
gravity, we have noticed the same moderation in maintaining
the hypothesis, after it had once occurred to
the author’s mind. The hypothesis required that the
moon should fall from the tangent of her orbit every
second through a space of sixteen feet; but according
to his first calculations it appeared that in fact she only
fell through a space of thirteen feet in that time. The
difference seems small, the approximation encouraging,
the theory plausible; a man in love with his own fancies
would readily have discovered or invented some
probable cause of the difference. But Newton acquiesced
in it as a disproof of his conjecture, and ‘laid
aside at that time any further thoughts of this
matter12.’
11
Hist. Ind. Sc. b. v. c. iv. sect. 1.
12
Hist. Ind. Sc. b. vii. c. ii. sect. 3.
8. It has often happened that those who have undertaken
to instruct mankind have not possessed this pure
love of truth and comparative indifference to the
maintenance of their own inventions. Men have frequently
adhered with great tenacity and vehemence to the hypotheses
which they have once framed; and in their 82
affection for these, have been prone to overlook, to
distort, and to misinterpret facts. In this manner, Hypotheses
have so often been prejudicial to the genuine
pursuit of truth, that they have fallen into a kind of
obloquy; and have been considered as dangerous temptations
and fallacious guides. Many warnings have
been uttered against the fabrication of hypotheses, by
those who profess to teach philosophy; many disclaimers
of such a course by those who cultivate science.
Thus we shall find Bacon frequently discommending
this habit, under the name of ‘anticipation of the mind,’
and Newton thinks it necessary to say emphatically
‘hypotheses non fingo.’ It has been constantly urged
that the inductions by which sciences are formed must
be cautious and rigorous; and the various imaginations
which passed through Kepler’s brain, and to which he
has given utterance, have been blamed or pitied, as
lamentable instances of an unphilosophical frame of
mind. Yet it has appeared in the preceding remarks
that hypotheses rightly used are among the helps, far
more than the dangers, of science;—that scientific
induction is not a ‘cautious’ or a ‘rigorous’ process in
the sense of abstaining from such suppositions, but in
not adhering to them till they are confirmed by fact, and
in carefully seeking from facts confirmation or refutation.
Kepler’s distinctive character was, not that he was
peculiarly given to the construction of hypotheses, but
that he narrated with extraordinary copiousness and
candour the course of his thoughts, his labours, and
his feelings. In the minds of most persons, as we have
said, the inadmissible suppositions, when rejected, are
soon forgotten: and thus the trace of them vanishes
from the thoughts, and the successful hypothesis alone
holds its place in our memory. But in reality, many
other transient suppositions must have been made by
all discoverers;—hypotheses which are not afterwards
asserted as true systems, but entertained for an
instant;—‘tentative hypotheses,’ as they have been
called. Each of these hypotheses is followed by its
corresponding train of observations, from which it
derives its power of leading to truth. The hypothesis is 83
like the captain, and the observations like the soldiers
of an army: while he appears to command them, and
in this way to work his own will, he does in fact derive
all his power of conquest from their obedience, and
becomes helpless and useless if they mutiny.
Since the discoverer has thus constantly to work his
way onwards by means of hypotheses, false and true,
it is highly important for him to possess talents and
means for rapidly testing each supposition as it offers
itself. In this as in other parts of the work of discovery,
success has in general been mainly owing to the
native ingenuity and sagacity of the discoverer’s mind.
Yet some Rules tending to further this object have
been delivered by eminent philosophers, and some
others may perhaps be suggested. Of these we shall
here notice only some of the most general, leaving for
a future chapter the consideration of some more
limited and detailed processes by which, in certain
cases, the discovery of the laws of nature may be
materially assisted.
Sect. III.—Tests of Hypotheses.
9. A maxim which it may be useful to recollect is
this;—that hypotheses may often be of service to science,
when they involve a certain portion of incompleteness,
and even of errour. The object of such inventions is to
bind together facts which without them are loose and
detached; and if they do this, they may lead the way
to a perception of the true rule by which the phenomena
are associated together, even if they themselves
somewhat misstate the matter. The imagined arrangement
enables us to contemplate, as a whole, a collection
of special cases which perplex and overload our minds
when they are considered in succession; and if our
scheme has so much of truth in it as to conjoin what is
really connected, we may afterwards duly correct or
limit the mechanism of this connexion. If our hypothesis
renders a reason for the agreement of cases
really similar, we may afterwards find this reason to be 84
false, but we shall be able to translate it into the
language of truth.
A conspicuous example of such an hypothesis,—one
which was of the highest value to science, though very
incomplete, and as a representation of nature altogether
false,—is seen in the Doctrine of epicycles by
which the ancient astronomers explained the motions
of the sun, moon, and planets. This doctrine connected the
places and velocities of these bodies at particular times
in a manner which was, in its general
features, agreeable to nature. Yet this doctrine was
erroneous in its assertion of the circular nature of all
the celestial motions, and in making the heavenly
bodies revolve round the earth. It was, however, of
immense value to the progress of astronomical science;
for it enabled men to express and reason upon many
important truths which they discovered respecting the
motion of the stars, up to the time of Kepler. Indeed
we can hardly imagine that astronomy could, in its
outset, have made so great a progress under any other
form, as it did in consequence of being cultivated in
this shape of the incomplete and false epicyclical hypothesis.
We may notice another instance of an exploded
hypothesis, which is generally mentioned only to be
ridiculed, and which undoubtedly is both false in the
extent of its assertion, and unphilosophical in its
expression; but which still, in its day, was not without
merit. I mean the doctrine of Nature’s horrour
of a vacuum (fuga vacui), by which the action of
siphons and pumps and many other phenomena were
explained, till Mersenne and Pascal taught a truer
doctrine. This hypothesis was of real service; for it
brought together many facts which really belong to
the same class, although they are very different in their
first aspect. A scientific writer of modern
times13
appears to wonder that men did not at once divine the
weight of the air, from which the phenomena formerly
ascribed to the fuga vacui really result. ‘Loaded, 85
compressed by the atmosphere,’ he says, ‘they did not
recognize its action. In vain all nature testified that
air was elastic and heavy; they shut their eyes to her
testimony. The water rose in pumps and flowed in
siphons at that time, as it does at this day. They
could not separate the boards of a pair of bellows of
which the holes were stopped; and they could not
bring together the same boards without difficulty, if
they were at first separated. Infants sucked the milk
of their mothers; air entered rapidly into the lungs
of animals at every inspiration; cupping-glasses produced
tumours on the skin; and in spite of all these
striking proofs of the weight and elasticity of the air,
the ancient philosophers maintained resolutely that air
was light, and explained all these phenomena by the
horrour which they said nature had for a vacuum.’
It is curious that it should not have occurred to the
author while writing this, that if these facts, so
numerous and various, can all be accounted for by one
principle, there is a strong presumption that the
principle is not altogether baseless. And in reality is it
not true that nature does abhor a vacuum, and does all
she can to avoid it? No doubt this power is not unlimited;
and moreover we can trace it to a mechanical
cause, the pressure of the circumambient air. But the
tendency, arising from this pressure, which the bodies
surrounding a space void of air have to rush into it,
may be expressed, in no extravagant or unintelligible
manner, by saying that nature has a repugnance to a
vacuum.
13
 Deluc, Modifications de l’Atmosphère, Partie 1.
That imperfect and false hypotheses, though they
may thus explain some phenomena, and may be useful
in the progress of science, cannot explain all phenomena;—and
that we are never to rest in our labours
or acquiesce in our results, till we have found some
view of the subject which is consistent with all the
observed facts;—will of course be understood. We shall
afterwards have to speak of the other steps of such a
progress.
10. Thus the hypotheses which we accept ought to
explain phenomena which we have observed. But they 86
ought to do more than this: our hypotheses ought to
foretel phenomena which have not yet been observed;
at least all phenomena of the same kind as those which
the hypothesis was invented to explain. For our assent
to the hypothesis implies that it is held to be true of all
particular instances. That these cases belong to past or
to future times, that they have or have not already
occurred, makes no difference in the applicability of the
rule to them. Because the rule prevails, it includes all
cases; and will determine them all, if we can only calculate
its real consequences. Hence it will predict the
results of new combinations, as well as explain the
appearances which have occurred in old ones. And that
it does this with certainty and correctness, is one mode
in which the hypothesis is to be verified as right and
useful.
The scientific doctrines which have at various periods
been established have been verified in this manner.
For example, the Epicyclical Theory of the heavens
was confirmed by its predicting truly eclipses of the
sun and moon, configurations of the planets, and other
celestial phenomena; and by its leading to the construction
of Tables by which the places of the heavenly
bodies were given at every moment of time. The truth
and accuracy of these predictions were a proof that the
hypothesis was valuable, and, at least to a great extent,
true; although, as was afterwards found, it involved a
false representation of the structure of the heavens.
In like manner, the discovery of the Laws of Refraction
enabled mathematicians to predict, by calculation,
what would be the effect of any new form or combination of
transparent lenses. Newton’s hypothesis of
Fits of Easy Transmission and Easy Reflection in the
particles of light, although not confirmed by other
kinds of facts, involved a true statement of the law of
the phenomena which it was framed to include, and
served to predict the forms and colours of thin plates
for a wide range of given cases. The hypothesis that
Light operates by Undulations and Interferences,
afforded the means of predicting results under a still
larger extent of conditions. In like manner in the 87
progress of chemical knowledge, the doctrine of Phlogiston
supplied the means of foreseeing the consequence
of many combinations of elements, even before they
were tried; but the Oxygen Theory, besides affording
predictions, at least equally exact, with regard to the
general results of chemical operations, included all the
facts concerning the relations of weight of the elements
and their compounds, and enabled chemists to foresee
such facts in untried cases. And the Theory of Electromagnetic
Forces, as soon as it was rightly understood,
enabled those who had mastered it to predict motions
such as had not been before observed, which were
accordingly found to take place.
Men cannot help believing that the laws laid down
by discoverers must be in a great measure identical
with the real laws of nature, when the discoverers thus
determine effects beforehand in the same manner in
which nature herself determines them when the occasion
occurs. Those who can do this, must, to a considerable
extent, have detected nature’s secret;—must
have fixed upon the conditions to which she attends,
and must have seized the rules by which she applies
them. Such a coincidence of untried facts with speculative
assertions cannot be the work of chance, but implies some
large portion of truth in the principles on
which the reasoning is founded. To trace order and
law in that which has been observed, may be considered
as interpreting what nature has written down for us,
and will commonly prove that we understand her
alphabet. But to predict what has not been observed,
is to attempt ourselves to use the legislative phrases of
nature; and when she responds plainly and precisely
to that which we thus utter, we cannot but suppose
that we have in a great measure made ourselves masters
of the meaning and structure of her language. The
prediction of results, even of the same kind as those
which have been observed, in new cases, is a proof of
real success in our inductive processes.
11. We have here spoken of the prediction of
facts of the same kind as those from which our rule
was collected. But the evidence in favour of our 88
induction is of a much higher and more forcible character
when it enables us to explain and determine
cases of a kind different from those which were contemplated
in the formation of our hypothesis. The
instances in which this has occurred, indeed, impress
us with a conviction that the truth of our hypothesis
is certain. No accident could give rise to such an
extraordinary coincidence. No false supposition could,
after being adjusted to one class of phenomena, exactly
represent a different class, where the agreement was
unforeseen and uncontemplated. That rules springing
from remote and unconnected quarters should thus
leap to the same point, can only arise from that being
the point where truth resides.
Accordingly the cases in which inductions from
classes of facts altogether different have thus jumped
together, belong only to the best established theories
which the history of science contains. And as I shall
have occasion to refer to this peculiar feature in their
evidence, I will take the liberty of describing it by a
particular phrase; and will term it the Consilience of
Inductions.
It is exemplified principally in some of the greatest
discoveries. Thus it was found by Newton that the
doctrine of the Attraction of the Sun varying according
to the Inverse Square of this distance, which explained
Kepler’s Third Law, of the proportionality of
the cubes of the distances to the squares of the periodic
times of the planets, explained also his First and
Second Laws, of the elliptical motion of each planet;
although no connexion of these laws had been visible
before. Again, it appeared that the force of universal
Gravitation, which had been inferred from the Perturbations
of the moon and planets by the sun and by
each other, also accounted for the fact, apparently
altogether dissimilar and remote, of the Precession of
the equinoxes. Here was a most striking and surprising
coincidence, which gave to the theory a stamp
of truth beyond the power of ingenuity to counterfeit.
In like manner in Optics; the hypothesis of alternate
Fits of easy Transmission and Reflection would explain 89
the colours of thin plates, and indeed was devised and
adjusted for that very purpose; but it could give no
account of the phenomena of the fringes of shadows.
But the doctrine of Interferences, constructed at first
with reference to phenomena of the nature of the
Fringes, explained also the Colours of thin plates better
than the supposition of the Fits invented for that very
purpose. And we have in Physical Optics another
example of the same kind, which is quite as striking
as the explanation of Precession by inferences from the
facts of Perturbation. The doctrine of Undulations
propagated in a Spheroidal Form was contrived at first
by Huyghens, with a view to explain the laws of
Double Refraction in calc-spar; and was pursued with
the same view by Fresnel. But in the course of the
investigation it appeared, in a most unexpected and
wonderful manner, that this same doctrine of spheroidal
undulations, when it was so modified as to
account for the directions of the two refracted rays,
accounted also for the positions of their Planes of
Polarization14,
a phenomenon which, taken by itself,
it had perplexed previous mathematicians, even to
represent.
14
 Hist. Ind. Sc. b. ix. c. xi. sect. 4.
The Theory of Universal Gravitation, and of the
Undulatory Theory of Light, are, indeed, full of examples
of this Consilience of Inductions. With regard to
the latter, it has been justly asserted by Herschel, that
the history of the undulatory theory was a succession
of felicities15.
And it is precisely the unexpected
coincidences of results drawn from distant parts of the
subject which are properly thus described. Thus the
Laws of the Modification of polarization to which
Fresnel was led by his general views, accounted for
the Rule respecting the Angle at which light is polarized,
discovered by Sir D.
Brewster16.
The conceptions of the
theory pointed out peculiar Modifications
of the phenomena when Newton’s rings were produced
by polarised light, which modifications were 90 ascertained
to take place in fact, by Arago and
Airy17.
When the beautiful phenomena of Dipolarized light
were discovered by Arago and Biot, Young was able
to declare that they were reducible to the general laws
of Interference which he had already
established18.
And what was no less striking a confirmation of the
truth of the theory, Measures of the same element
deduced from various classes of facts were found to
coincide. Thus the Length of a luminiferous undulation,
calculated by Young from the measurement of
Fringes of shadows, was found to agree very nearly
with the previous calculation from the colours of Thin
plates19.
15
See Hist. Ind. Sc. b. ix. c. xii.
16
Ib. c. xi. sect. 4.
17
See Hist. Ind. Sc. b. ix. c. xiii. sect. 6.
18
Ib. c. xi. sect. 5.
19
Ib. c. xi. sect. 2.
No example can be pointed out, in the whole history of science,
so far as I am aware, in which this
Consilience of Inductions has given testimony in
favour of an hypothesis afterwards discovered to be
false. If we take one class of facts only, knowing the
law which they follow, we may construct an hypothesis,
or perhaps several, which may represent them:
and as new circumstances are discovered, we may often
adjust the hypothesis so as to correspond to these also.
But when the hypothesis, of itself and without adjustment
for the purpose, gives us the rule and reason of a
class of facts not contemplated in its construction, we
have a criterion of its reality, which has never yet
been produced in favour of falsehood.
12. In the preceding Article I have spoken of the
hypothesis with which we compare our facts as being
framed all at once, each of its parts being included in
the original scheme. In reality, however, it often happens
that the various suppositions which our system
contains are added upon occasion of different researches.
Thus in the Ptolemaic doctrine of the heavens, new epicycles
and eccentrics were added as new
inequalities of the motions of the heavenly bodies were
discovered; and in the Newtonian doctrine of material
rays of light, the supposition that these rays had 91
‘fits,’ was added to explain the colours of thin plates;
and the supposition that they had ‘sides’ was introduced
on occasion of the phenomena of polarization.
In like manner other theories have been built up of
parts devised at different times.
This being the mode in which theories are often
framed, we have to notice a distinction which is found
to prevail in the progress of true and false theories.
In the former class all the additional suppositions tend
to simplicity and harmony; the new suppositions resolve
themselves into the old ones, or at least require
only some easy modification of the hypothesis first
assumed: the system becomes more coherent as it is
further extended. The elements which we require for
explaining a new class of facts are already contained
in our system. Different members of the theory run
together, and we have thus a constant convergence to
unity. In false theories, the contrary is the case. The
new suppositions are something altogether additional;—not
suggested by the original scheme; perhaps difficult to
reconcile with it. Every such addition adds to
the complexity of the hypothetical system, which at
last becomes unmanageable, and is compelled to surrender
its place to some simpler explanation.
Such a false theory, for example, was the ancient
doctrine of eccentrics and epicycles. It explained the
general succession of the Places of the Sun, Moon,
and Planets; it would not have explained the proportion
of their Magnitudes at different times, if these
could have been accurately observed; but this the ancient
astronomers were unable to do. When, however,
Tycho and other astronomers came to be able to observe
the planets accurately in all positions, it was
found that no combination of equable circular motions
would exactly represent all the observations. We may
see, in Kepler’s works, the many new modifications of
the epicyclical hypothesis which offered themselves to
him; some of which would have agreed with the phenomena
with a certain degree of accuracy, but not with
so great a degree as Kepler, fortunately for the progress
of science, insisted upon obtaining. After these 92
epicycles had been thus accumulated, they all disappeared
and gave way to the simpler conception of an
elliptical motion. In like manner, the discovery of new
inequalities in the Moon’s motions encumbered her
system more and more with new machinery, which was
at last rejected all at once in favour of the elliptical
theory. Astronomers could not but suppose themselves in
a wrong path, when the prospect grew darker
and more entangled at every step.
Again; the Cartesian system of Vortices might be
said to explain the primary phenomena of the revolutions
of planets about the sun, and satellites about
planets. But the elliptical form of the orbits required
new suppositions. Bernoulli ascribed this curve to the
shape of the planet, operating on the stream of the
vortex in a manner similar to the rudder of a boat.
But then the motions of the aphelia, and of the nodes,—the
perturbations,—even the action of gravity towards the
earth,—could not be accounted for without
new and independent suppositions. Here was none of
the simplicity of truth. The theory of Gravitation,
on the other hand, became more simple as the facts to
be explained became more numerous. The attraction
of the sun accounted for the motions of the planets;
the attraction of the planets was the cause of the motion
of the satellites. But this being assumed, the
perturbations, and the motions of the nodes and aphelia,
only made it requisite to extend the attraction of the
sun to the satellites, and that of the planets to each
other:—the tides, the spheroidal form of the earth,
the precession, still required nothing more than that
the moon and sun should attract the parts of the earth,
and that these should attract each other;—so that
all the suppositions resolved themselves into the single
one, of the universal gravitation of all matter. It is
difficult to imagine a more convincing manifestation of
simplicity and unity.
Again, to take an example from another science;—the
doctrine of Phlogiston brought together many facts
in a very plausible manner,—combustion, acidification,
and others,—and very naturally prevailed for a while. 93
But the balance came to be used in chemical operations,
and the facts of weight as well as of combination
were to be accounted for. On the phlogistic theory, it
appeared that this could not be done without a new
supposition, and that, a very strange one;—that
phlogiston was an element not only not heavy, but
absolutely light, so that it diminished the weight of the
compounds into which it entered. Some chemists for a
time adopted this extravagant view, but the wiser of
them saw, in the necessity of such a supposition to the
defence of the theory, an evidence that the hypothesis
of an element phlogiston was erroneous. And the
opposite hypothesis, which taught that oxygen was
subtracted, and not phlogiston added, was accepted
because it required no such novel and inadmissible
assumption.
Again, we find the same evidence of truth in the
progress of the Undulatory Theory of light, in the
course of its application from one class of facts to another.
Thus we explain Reflection and Refraction by
undulations; when we come to Thin Plates, the requisite
‘fits’ are already involved in our fundamental
hypothesis, for they are the length of an undulation:
the phenomena of Diffraction also require such intervals;
and the intervals thus required agree exactly
with the others in magnitude, so that no new property
is needed. Polarization for a moment appears to require
some new hypothesis; yet this is hardly the case;
for the direction of our vibrations is hitherto arbitrary:—we
allow polarization to decide it, and we suppose
the undulations to be transverse. Having done this
for the sake of Polarization, we turn to the phenomena
of Double Refraction, and inquire what new hypothesis
they require. But the answer is, that they require
none: the supposition of transverse vibrations, which
we have made in order to explain Polarization, gives
us also the law of Double Refraction. Truth may give
rise to such a coincidence; falsehood cannot. Again,
the facts of Dipolarization come into view. But they
hardly require any new assumption; for the difference
of optical elasticity of crystals in different directions, 94
which is already assumed in uniaxal
crystals20,
is extended to biaxal exactly according to the law of symmetry;
and this being done, the laws of the phenomena, curious and
complex as they are, are fully
explained. The phenomena of Circular Polarization
by internal reflection, instead of requiring a new hypothesis,
are found to be given by an interpretation of
an apparently inexplicable result of an old hypothesis.
The Circular Polarization of Quartz and the Double
Refraction does indeed appear to require a new assumption,
but still not one which at all disturbs the form
of the theory; and in short, the whole history of this
theory is a progress, constant and steady, often striking
and startling, from one degree of evidence and consistence
to another of a higher order.
20
Hist. Ind. Sc. b. ix. c. xi. sect. 5.
In the Emission Theory, on the other hand, as in
the theory of solid epicycles, we see what we may
consider as the natural course of things in the career
of a false theory. Such a theory may, to a certain
extent, explain the phenomena which it was at first
contrived to meet; but every new class of facts requires
a new supposition—an addition to the machinery: and
as observation goes on, these incoherent appendages
accumulate, till they overwhelm and upset the original
frame-work. Such has been the hypothesis of the
Material Emission of light. In its original form, it
explained Reflection and Refraction: but the colours
of Thin Plates added to it the Fits of easy Transmission and
Reflection; the phenomena of Diffraction
further invested the emitted particles with complex
laws of Attraction and Repulsion; Polarization gave
them Sides: Double Refraction subjected them to
peculiar Forces emanating from the axes of the crystal:
Finally, Dipolarization loaded them with the complex
and unconnected contrivance of Moveable Polarization:
and even when all this had been done, additional
mechanism was wanting. There is here no unexpected
success, no happy coincidence, no convergence of
principles from remote quarters. The philosopher builds 95
the machine, but its parts do not fit. They hold
together only while he presses them. This is not the
character of truth.
As another example of the application of the Maxim
now under consideration, I may perhaps be allowed to
refer to the judgment which, in the History of Thermotics,
I have ventured to give respecting Laplace’s
Theory of Gases. I have stated21,
that we cannot help
forming an unfavourable judgment of this theory, by
looking for that great characteristic of true theory;
namely, that the hypotheses which were assumed to
account for one class of facts are found to explain
another class of a different nature. Thus Laplace’s first
suppositions explain the connexion of Compression
with Density, (the law of Boyle and Mariotte,) and
the connexion of Elasticity with Heat, (the law of
Dalton and Gay Lussac). But the theory requires
other assumptions when we come to Latent Heat; and
yet these new assumptions produce no effect upon the
calculations in any application of the theory. When
the hypothesis, constructed with reference to the Elasticity
and Temperature, is applied to another class of
facts, those of Latent Heat, we have no Simplification
of the Hypothesis, and therefore no evidence of the
truth of the theory.
21
Hist. Ind. Sc. b. x. c. iv.
13. The last two sections of this chapter direct our
attention to two circumstances, which tend to prove, in
a manner which we may term irresistible, the truth of
the theories which they characterize:—the Consilience
of Inductions from different and separate classes of
facts;—and the progressive Simplification of the Theory
as it is extended to new cases. These two Characters
are, in fact, hardly different; they are exemplified by
the same cases. For if these Inductions, collected from
one class of facts, supply an unexpected explanation of
a new class, which is the case first spoken of, there
will be no need for new machinery in the hypothesis
to apply it to the newly-contemplated facts; and thus,
we have a case in which the system does not become 96
more complex when its application is extended to a
wider field, which was the character of true theory
in its second aspect. The Consiliences of our Inductions
give rise to a constant Convergence of our Theory
towards Simplicity and Unity.
But, moreover, both these cases of the extension of
the theory, without difficulty or new suppositions, to a
wider range and to new classes of phenomena, may be
conveniently considered in yet another point of view;
namely, as successive steps by which we gradually
ascend in our speculative views to a higher and higher
point of generality. For when the theory, either by
the concurrence of two indications, or by an extension
without complication, has included a new range of
phenomena, we have, in fact, a new induction of a
more general kind, to which the inductions formerly
obtained are subordinate, as particular cases to a general
proposition. We have in such examples, in short,
an instance of successive generalization. This is a
subject of great importance, and deserving of being well
illustrated; it will come under our notice in the next
chapter.
</div></body></text></TEI>