<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="107">CHAPTER III.
Reception and Corrections of the Hauïan
Crystallography.
I HAVE not hitherto noticed
the imperfections of the crystallographic views and methods of Haüy,
because my business in the last section 325 was to mark the permanent additions he
made to the science. His system did, however, require completion and
rectification in various points; and in speaking of the
crystallographers of the subsequent time, who may all be considered as
the cultivators of the Hauïan doctrines, we must also consider what
they did in correcting them.
The three main points in which this improvement was needed
were;—a better determination of the crystalline forms of the
special substances;—a more general and less arbitrary method of
considering crystalline forms according to their symmetry; and a
detection of more general conditions by which the crystalline angle is
regulated. The first of these processes may be considered as the
natural sequel of the Hauïan epoch: the other two must be treated as
separate steps of discovery.
When it appeared that the angle of natural or of cleavage faces
could be used to determine the differences of minerals, it became
important to measure this angle with accuracy. Haüy’s measurements
were found very inaccurate by many succeeding crystallographers: Mohs
says26 that they are so generally inaccurate,
that no confidence can be placed in them. This was said, of course,
according to the more rigorous notions of accuracy to which the
establishment of Haüy’s system led. Among the persons who principally
labored in ascertaining, with precision, the crystalline angles of
minerals, were several Englishmen, especially Wollaston, Phillips, and
Brooke. Wollaston, by the invention of his Reflecting Goniometer,
placed an entirely new degree of accuracy within the reach of the
crystallographer; the angle of two faces being, in this instrument,
measured by means of the reflected images of bright objects seen in
them, so that the measure is the more accurate the more minute the
faces are. In the use of this instrument, no one was more laborious
and successful than William Phillips, whose power of apprehending the
most complex forms with steadiness and clearness, led Wollaston to say
that he had “a geometrical sense.” Phillips published a Treatise on
Mineralogy, containing a great collection of such determinations; and
Mr. Brooke, a crystallographer of the same exact and careful school,
has also published several works of the same kind. The precise
measurement of crystalline angles must be the familiar employment of
all who study crystallography; and, therefore, any further enumeration
of those 326 who
have added in this way to the stock of knowledge, would be
superfluous.
26 Marx. p. 153.
Nor need I dwell long on those who added to the knowledge which
Haüy left, of derived forms. The most remarkable work of this kind was
that of Count Bournon, who published a work on a single mineral
(calcspar) in three quarto volumes.27 He has here
given representations of seven hundred forms of crystals, of which,
however, only fifty-six are essentially different. From this example
the reader may judge what a length of time, and what a number of
observers and calculators, were requisite to exhaust the subject.
27 Traité complet de la Chaux
Carbonatée et d’Aragonite, par M. le Comte de Bournon. London,
1808.
If the calculations, thus occasioned, had been conducted upon the
basis of Haüy’s system, without any further generalization, they would
have belonged to that process, the natural sequel of inductive
discoveries, which we call deduction; and would have needed
only a very brief notice here. But some additional steps were made in
the upward road to scientific truth, and of these we must now give an
account.
</div></body></text></TEI>