<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="64">

CHAPTER III.
Attempts to Analyse the Idea of Life.


1. Definitions of Life.—We have seen in the preceding chapter that all attempts to obtain a distinct
conception of the nature of Life in general have ended
in failure, and produced nothing beyond a negative
result. And the conjecture may now naturally occur,
that the cause of this failure resides in an erroneous
mode of propounding to ourselves the problem. Instead
of contemplating Life as a single Idea, it may perhaps
be proper to separate it into several component notions: instead of seeking for one cause of all vital
operations, it may be well to look at the separate vital
functions, and to seek their causes. When the view of
this possibility opens upon us, how shall we endeavour
to verify it, and to take advantage of it?
Let us, as one obvious course, take some of the
attempts which have been made to define Life, and let
us see whether they appear to offer to us any analysis
of the idea into component parts. Such definitions,
when they proceed from men of philosophical minds,
are the ultimate result of a long course of thought and
observation; and by no means deserve to be slighted
as arbitrary selections of conditions, or empty forms
of words.
2. Life has been defined by Stahl60, ‘The condition by which a body resists a natural tendency to
chemical changes, such as putrefaction.’ In like manner, M. von Humboldt61 defines living bodies to be
‘those which, notwithstanding the constant operation 196 of causes tending to change their form, are hindered
by a certain inward power from undergoing such
change.’ The first of these definitions amounts only to
the assertion, that vital processes are not chemical; a
negative result, which we may accept as true, but
which is, as we have seen, a barren truth. The second
appears to be, in its import, identical with the first.
An inward principle can only be understood as distinguished from known external powers, such as mechanical and chemical agencies. Or if, by an internal
principle, we mean such a principle as that of which
we are conscious within ourselves, we ascribe a soul
to all living things: an hypothesis which we have seen
is not more effective than the former in promoting the
progress of biological science. Nearly the same criticism applies to such definitions as that of Kant: that
‘Life is an internal faculty producing change, motion,
and action.’</div></body></text></TEI>