<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="50">CHAPTER I.
Prelude to Newton.

The Ancients.
EXPRESSIONS in ancient writers
which may be interpreted as indicating a notion of gravitation in the
Newtonian sense, no doubt occur. But such a notion, we may be sure,
must have been in the highest degree obscure, wavering, and partial. I
have mentioned (Book i. Chap. 3) an author who
has fancied that he traces in the works of the ancients the origin of
most of the vaunted discoveries of the moderns. But to ascribe much
importance to such expressions would be to give a false representation
of the real progress of science. Yet some of Newton’s followers put
forward these passages as well deserving notice; and Newton himself
appears to have had some pleasure in citing such expressions; probably
with the feeling that they relieved him of some of the odium which, he
seems to have apprehended, hung over new discoveries. The Preface to
the Principia, begins by quoting40 the authority of
the ancients, as well as the moderns, in favor of applying the science
of Mechanics to Natural Philosophy. In the Preface to David Gregory’s
Astronomiæ Physicæ et Geometricæ Elementa, published in 1702,
is a large array of names of ancient authors, and of quotations, to
prove the early and wide diffusion of the doctrine of the gravity of
the Heavenly Bodies. And it appears to be now made out, that this
collection of ancient authorities 545 was supplied to Gregory by Newton
himself. The late Professor Rigaud, in his Historical Essay on the
First Publication of Sir Isaac Newton’s Principia, says (pp. 80
and 101) that having been allowed to examine Gregory’s papers, he
found that the quotations given by him in his Preface are copied or
abridged from notes which Newton had supplied to him in his own
handwriting. Some of the most noticeable of the quotations are those
taken from Plutarch’s Dialogue on the Face which appears in the
Moon’s Disk: it is there said, for example, by one of the
speakers, that the Moon is perhaps prevented from falling to the earth
by the rapidity of her revolution round it; as a stone whirled in a
sling keeps it stretched. Lucretius also is quoted, as teaching that
all bodies would descend with an equal celerity in a vacuum:

Omnia quapropter debent per inane quietum
Æque ponderibus non æquis concita ferri.
Lib. ii. v.
238.      
40 Cum veteres Mechanicam (uti
author est Pappus), in rerum Naturalium investigatione maximi
fecerint, et recentiores, missis formis substantialibus et
qualitatibus occultis, Phenonmena Naturæ ad leges mathematicas
revocare aggressa sunt; visum est in hoc Tractatu Mathesin
excolere quatenus ea ad Philosophiam spectat.
It is asserted in Gregory’s Preface that Pythagoras was not
unacquainted with the important law of gravity, the inverse squares of
the distances from the centre. For, it is argued, the seven strings of
Apollo’s lyre mean the seven planets; and the proportions of the notes
of strings are reciprocally as the inverse squares of the weights
which stretch them.
I have attempted, throughout this work, to trace the progress of
the discovery of the great truths which constitute real science, in a
more precise manner than that which these interpretations of ancient
authors exemplify.
Jeremiah Horrox.
In describing the Prelude to the Epoch of Newton, I have spoken (p. 395) of a group of philosophers in England
who began, in the first half of the seventeenth century, to knock at
the door where Truth was to be found, although it was left for Newton
to force it open; and I have there noticed the influence of the civil
wars on the progress of philosophical studies. To the persons thus
tending towards the true physical theory of the solar system, I ought
to have added Jeremy Horrox, whom I have mentioned in a former part
(Book v. chap. 5) as one of the earliest
admirers of Kepler’s discoveries. He died at the early age of
twenty-two, having been the first person who ever saw Venus pass
across the disk of the Sun according to astronomical prediction, which
took place in 1639. His Venus in sole visa, 546 in which this is
described, did not appear till 1661, when it was published by Hevelius
of Dantzic. Some of his papers were destroyed by the soldiers in the
English civil wars; and his remaining works were finally published by
Wallis, in 1673. The passage to which I here specially wish to refer
is contained in a letter to his astronomical ally, William Crabtree,
dated 1638. He appears to have been asked by his friend to suggest
some cause for the motion of the aphelion of a planet; and in reply,
he uses an experimental illustration which was afterwards employed by
Hooke in 1666. A ball at the end of a string is made to swing so that
it describes an oval. This contrivance Hooke employed to show the way
in which an orbit results from the combination of a projectile motion
with a central force. But the oval does not keep its axis constantly
in the same position. The apsides, as Horrox remarked, move in the
same direction as the pendulum, though much slower. And it is true,
that this experiment does illustrate, in a general way, the cause of
the motion of the aphelia of the Planetary Orbits; although the form
of the orbit is different in the experiment and in the solar system;
being an ellipse with the centre of force in the centre of the
ellipse, in the former case, and an ellipse with the centre of force
in the focus, in the latter case. These two forms of orbits correspond
to a central force varying directly as the distance, and a central
force varying inversely as the square of the distance; as Newton
proved in the Principia. But the illustration appears to show
that Horrox pretty clearly saw how an orbit arose from a central
force. So far, and no further, Newton’s contemporaries could get; and
then he had to help them onwards by showing what was the law of the
force, and what larger truths were now attainable.
Newton’s Discovery of Gravitation.
[Page 402.] As I have already remarked,
men have a willingness to believe that great discoveries are governed
by casual coincidences, and accompanied by sudden revolutions of
feeling. Newton had entertained the thought of the moon being retained
in her orbit by gravitation as early as 1665 or 1666. He resumed the
subject and worked the thought out into a system in 1684 and 5. What
induced him to return to the question? What led to his success on this
last occasion? With what feelings was the success attended? It is easy
to make an imaginary connection of facts. “His optical discoveries had
recommended him to the Royal Society, and he was now a member. He
547 there
learned the accurate measurement of the Earth by Picard, differing
very much from the estimation by which he had made his calculation in
1666; and he thought his conjecture now more likely to be just.”41 M. Biot gives his assent to this
guess.42 The English translation of M. Biot’s
biography43 converts the guess into an assertion.
But, says Professor Rigaud,44 Picard’s measurement of the Earth was
well known to the Fellows of the Royal Society as early as 1675, there
being an account of the results of it given in the Philosophical
Transactions for that year. Moreover, Norwood, in his Seaman’s
Practice, dated 1636, had given a much more exact measure than
Newton employed in 1666. But Norwood, says Voltaire, had been buried
in oblivion by the civil wars. No, again says the exact and
truth-loving Professor Rigaud, Norwood was in communication with the
Royal Society in 1667 and 1668. So these guesses at the accident which
made the apple of 1665 germinate in 1684, are to be carefully
distinguished from history.
41 Robison’s Mechanical
Philosophy, vol. iii. p. 94. (Art. 195.)
42 Biographie
Universelle.
43 Library of Useful
Knowledge.
44 Historical Essay on the First
Publication of the Principia (1838).
But with what feelings did Newton attain to his success? Here again
we have, I fear, nothing better than conjecture. “He went home, took
out his old papers, and resumed his calculations. As they drew near to
a close, he was so much agitated that he was obliged to desire a
friend to finish them. His former conjecture was now found to agree
with the phænomena with the utmost precision.”45 This conjectural
story has been called “a tradition;” but he who relates it does not
call it so. Every one must decide, says Professor Rigaud, from his
view of Newton’s character, how far he thinks it consistent with this
statement. Is it likely that Newton, so calm and so indifferent to
fame as he generally showed himself, should be thus agitated on such
an occasion? “No,” says Sir David Brewster; “it is not supported by
what we know of Newton’s character.”46 To this we may
assent; and this conjectural incident we must therefore, I conceive,
separate from history. I had incautiously admitted it into the text of
the first Edition.
45 Robison, ibid.
46 Life of Newton, vol. i. p.
292.
Newton appears to have discovered the method of demonstrating that
a body might describe an ellipse when acted upon by a force residing
in the focus, and varying inversely as the square of the distance, in
1669, upon occasion of his correspondence with Hooke. In 1684, 548 at Halley’s request,
he returned to the subject; and in February, 1685 there was inserted
in the Register of the Royal Society a paper of Newton’s (Isaaci
Newtoni Propositiones de Motu), which contained some of the
principal propositions of the first two Books of the Principia.
This paper, however, does not contain the proposition “Lunam gravitare
in Terram,” nor any of the propositions of the Third Book.
</div></body></text></TEI>