<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="53">BY SIR CHARLES LYELL, M. A., F. R. S.,
Author of "Principles of Geology" &c., &c.
Reprinted from the last London, Entirely Revised Edition. Illustrated
with Five Hundred Wood-Cuts. One handsome volume, large 8vo. Price $1
75.
 "The author of this work stands in the very front rank of scientific
men, and his works upon the sciences, to which he has devoted his great
powers, and his Indefatigable study, are the standard books upon those
subjects. This Manual has had a very great sale in England, and its
successive editions have kept pace with the steady progress of
geological science. To the last edition, new and important pages have
been added, containing the latest discoveries In geology. This study has
never before received so great attention as at present, and in no other
country can it be studied so profitably and with such practical results
as in this."—Providence Journal.
"This is a standard work, on one of the most wonderful of modern
sciences. In connection with the "Principles of Geology," by the same
author, it gives a complete survey of the science at its present stage
of advancement. We commend these works to the serious attention of those
fossil theologians who esteem it their duty to bring the Bible, if they
can, into conflict with the inductive sciences, and who think that their
interpretation of Genesis is a sufficient reply to all the inductions of
Geology."—Recorder.
"The author of this volume is among the most eminent of geologists, and
is well qualified to make an exposition of the science. This "Manual" is
not intended as an epitome of another work, "The Principles of Geology,"
but occupies a distinct place, the "Principles" containing a view of the
Modern changes of the Earth and its inhabitants, while the "Manual"
relates to the Monuments of Ancient changes. The author recommends to
the student of geology who wishes to examine his works, to commence with
the "Principles," a new and thoroughly revised edition of which is just
about tube issued by the Publishers of the present volume. "We are not
among those who apprehend injury to the cause of Scripture truth, by the
study of this science, and we only wish it were more generally and
thoroughly investigated by sound minds. It is imperative on all
theologians, and those designing to become such, to make this a branch,
of study, and thus to be prepared to defend the truth when it is
assayed, as it has been by men of science. The truth has nothing to
fear, but every thing to gain even from scientific
investigation."—Observer. 
 D. APPLETON & CO. HAVE JUST PUBLISHED,
A NEW AND ENLARGED EDITION OF
DR. URE'S DICTIONARY OF ARTS,</div></body></text></TEI>