<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="13">CHAPTER XIII
UNIFORMITY IN THE SERIES OF PAST CHANGES IN THE ANIMATE AND
INANIMATE WORLD.
Supposed alternate periods of repose and disorder—Observed facts in which this
doctrine has originated—These may be explained by supposing a uniform and
uninterrupted series of changes—Threefold consideration of this subject; first, in
reference to the living creation, extinction of species, and origin of new animals
and plants; secondly, in reference to the changes produced in the earth's crust by
the continuance of subterranean movements in certain areas, and their transference
after long periods to new areas; thirdly, in reference to the laws which govern
the formation of fossiliferous strata, and the shifting of the areas of sedimentary
deposition—On the combined influence of all these modes and causes of change
in producing breaks and chasms in the chain of records—Concluding remarks
on the identity of the ancient and present system of terrestrial changes.
Origin of the doctrine of alternate periods of repose and disorder.—It
has been truly observed, that when we arrange the fossiliferous formations
in chronological order, they constitute a broken and defective series
of monuments: we pass without any intermediate gradations, from systems
of strata which are horizontal to other systems which are highly
inclined, from rocks of peculiar mineral composition to others which have
a character wholly distinct,—from one assemblage of organic remains to
another, in which frequently all the species, and most of the genera, are
different. These violations of continuity are so common, as to constitute
the rule rather than the exception, and they have been considered by
many geologists as conclusive in favor of sudden revolutions in the inanimate
and animate world. According to the speculations of some writers,
there have been in the past history of the planet alternate periods of
tranquillity and convulsion, the former enduring for ages, and resembling
that state of things now experienced by man: the other brief, transient,
and paroxysmal, giving rise to new mountains, seas, and valleys, annihilating
one set of organic beings, and ushering in the creation of another.
It will be the object of the present chapter to demonstrate, that these
theoretical views are not borne out by a fair interpretation of geological
monuments. It is true that in the solid framework of the globe, we
have a chronological chain of natural records, and that many links in this
chain are wanting; but a careful consideration of all the phenomena
will lead to the opinion that the series was originally defective,—that it
has been rendered still more so by time—that a great part of what remains
is inaccessible to man, and even of that fraction which is accessible,
nine-tenths are to this day unexplored.
How the facts may be explained by assuming a uniform series of
changes.—The readiest way, perhaps, of persuading the reader that we
181
may dispense with great and sudden revolutions in the geological order
of events, is by showing him how a regular and uninterrupted series of
changes in the animate and inanimate world may give rise to such breaks
in the sequence, and such unconformability of stratified rocks, as are
usually thought to imply convulsions and catastrophes. It is scarcely
necessary to state, that the order of events thus assumed to occur, for
the sake of illustration, must be in harmony with all the conclusions
legitimately drawn by geologists from the structure of the earth, and
must be equally in accordance with the changes observed by man to be
now going on in the living as well as in the inorganic creation. It may
be necessary in the present state of science to supply some part of the
assumed course of nature hypothetically; but if so, this must be done
without any violation of probability, and always consistently with the
analogy of what is known both of the past and present economy of our
system. Although the discussion of so comprehensive a subject must
carry the beginner far beyond his depth, it will also, it is hoped, stimulate
his curiosity, and prepare him to read some elementary treatises on
geology with advantage, and teach him the bearing on that science of
the changes now in progress on the earth. At the same time it may
enable him the better to understand the intimate connection between
the second and third books of this work, the former of which is occupied
with the changes in the inorganic, the latter with those of the organic
creation.
In pursuance, then, of the plan above proposed, I shall consider in
this chapter, first, what may be the course of fluctuation in the animate
world; secondly, the mode in which contemporaneous subterranean
movements affect the earth's crust; and, thirdly, the laws which regulate
the deposition of sediment.
UNIFORMITY OF CHANGE CONSIDERED FIRST IN REFERENCE TO THE
LIVING CREATION.
First, in regard to the vicissitudes of the living creation, all are agreed
that the sedimentary strata found in the earth's crust are divisible into
a variety of groups, more or less dissimilar in their organic remains and
mineral composition. The conclusion universally drawn from the study
and comparison of these fossiliferous groups is this, that at successive
periods distinct tribes of animals and plants have inhabited the land and
waters, and that the organic types of the newer formations are more
analogous to species now existing, than those of more ancient rocks. If
we then turn to the present state of the animate creation, and inquire
whether it has now become fixed and stationary, we discover that, on
the contrary, it is in a state of continual flux—that there are many
causes in action which tend to the extinction of species, and which are
conclusive against the doctrine of their unlimited durability. But natural
history has been successfully cultivated for so short a period, that a
few examples only of local, and perhaps but one or two of absolute, extirpation
182
can as yet be proved, and these only where the interference of man
has been conspicuous. It will nevertheless appear evident, from the
facts and arguments detailed in the third book (from the thirty-seventh
to the forty-second chapters, inclusive) that man is not the only exterminating
agent; and that, independently of his intervention, the annihilation
of species is promoted by the multiplication and gradual diffusion
of every animal or plant. It will also appear, that every alteration
in the physical geography and climate of the globe cannot fail to have
the same tendency. If we proceed still farther, and inquire whether
new species are substituted from time to time for those which die out,
and whether there are certain laws appointed by the Author of Nature
to regulate such new creations, we find that the period of human observation
is as yet too short to afford data for determining so weighty a
question. All that can be done is to show that the successive introduction
of new species may be a constant part of the economy of the terrestrial
system, without our having any right to expect that we should
be in possession of direct proof of the fact. The appearance again and
again of new species may easily have escaped detection, since the numbers
of known animals and plants have augmented so rapidly within the
memory of persons now living, as to have doubled in some classes, and
quadrupled in others. It will also be remarked in the sequel (book iii.
chap. 43), that it must always be more easy if species proceeded originally
from single stocks, to prove that one which formerly abounded in
a given district has ceased to be, than that another has been called into
being for the first time. If, therefore, there be as yet only one or two
unequivocal instances of extinction, namely, those of the dodo and solitaire
(see ch. 41), it is scarcely reasonable as yet to hope that we should
be cognizant of a single instance of the first appearance of a new species.
Recent origin of man, and gradual approach in the tertiary fossils of
successive periods from an extinct to the recent fauna.—The geologist,
however, if required to advance some fact which may lend countenance
to the opinion that in the most modern times, that is to say, after the
greater part of the existing fauna and flora were established on the
earth, there has still been a new species superadded, may point to man
himself as furnishing the required illustration—for man must be regarded
by the geologist as a creature of yesterday, not merely in reference to
the past history of the organic world, but also in relation to that particular
state of the animate creation of which he forms a part. The
comparatively modern introduction of the human race is proved by the
absence of the remains of man and his works, not only from all strata
containing a certain proportion of fossil shells of extinct species, but even
from a large part of the newest strata, in which all the fossil individuals
are referable to species still living.
To enable the reader to appreciate the full force of this evidence, I
shall give a slight sketch of the information obtained from the newer
strata, respecting fluctuations in the animate world, in times immediately
antecedent to the appearance of man.
183
In tracing the series of fossiliferous formations from the more ancient
to the more modern, the first deposits in which we meet with assemblages
of organic remains, having a near analogy to the fauna of certain
parts of the globe in our own time, are those commonly called tertiary.
Even in the Eocene, or oldest subdivision of these tertiary
formations, some few of the testacea belong to existing species, although
almost all of them, and apparently all the associated vertebrata, are now
extinct. These Eocene strata are succeeded by a great number of
more modern deposits, which depart gradually in the character of their
fossils from the Eocene type, and approach more and more to that of
the living creation. In the present state of science, it is chiefly by the
aid of shells that we are enabled to arrive at these results, for of all
classes the testacea are the most generally diffused in a fossil state, and
may be called the medals principally employed by nature, in recording
the chronology of past events. In the Miocene deposits, which are
next in succession to the Eocene, we begin to find a considerable number,
although still a minority, of recent species, intermixed with some
fossils common to the preceding epoch. We then arrive at the Pliocene
strata, in which species now contemporary with man begin to preponderate,
and in the newest of which nine-tenths of the fossils agree
with species still inhabiting the neighboring sea.
In this passing from the older to the newer members of the tertiary
system we meet with many chasms, but none which separate entirely,
by a broad line of demarcation, one state of the organic world from another.
There are no signs of an abrupt termination of one fauna and
flora, and the starting into life of new and wholly distinct forms. Although
we are far from being able to demonstrate geologically an insensible
transition from the Eocene to the Miocene, or even from the latter
to the recent fauna, yet the more we enlarge and perfect our general
survey, the more nearly do we approximate to such a continuous series,
and the more gradually are we conducted from times when many of the
genera and nearly all the species were extinct, to those in which scarcely
a single species flourished which we do not know to exist at present.
Dr. A. Philippi, indeed, after an elaborate comparison of the fossil tertiary
shells of Sicily with those now living in the Mediterranean, announces
as the result of his examination that there are strata in that
island, which attest a very gradual passage from a period, when only
thirteen in a hundred of the shells were like the species now living in
the sea, to an era when the recent species had attained a proportion of
ninety-five in a hundred. There is therefore evidence, he says, in Sicily
of this revolution in the animate world having been effected "without
the intervention of any convulsion or abrupt changes, certain species
having from time to time died out, and others having been introduced,
until at length the existing fauna was elaborated."
It had often been objected that the evidence of fossil species occurring
in two consecutive formations, was confined to the testacea or zoophytes,
the characters of which are less marked and decisive than those
184
afforded by the vertebrate animals. But Mr. Owen has lately insisted
on the important fact, that not a few of the quadrupeds which now inhabit
our island, and among others the horse, the ass, the hog, the
smaller wild ox, the goat, the red deer, the roe, the beaver, and many
of the diminutive rodents, are the same as those which once coexisted
with the mammoth, the great northern hippopotamus, two kinds of rhinoceros,
and other mammalia long since extinct. "A part," he observes,
"and not the whole of the modern tertiary fauna has perished,
and hence we may conclude that the cause of their destruction has not
been a violent and universal catastrophe from which none could
escape."257
Had we discovered evidence that man had come into the earth at a
period as early as that when a large number of the fossil quadrupeds
now living, and almost all the recent species of land, freshwater, and
marine shells were in existence, we should have been compelled to
ascribe a much higher antiquity to our species, than even the boldest
speculations of the ethnologist require, for no small part of the great
physical revolution depicted on the map of Europe (Pl. 3), before described,
took place very gradually after the recent testacea abounded
almost to the exclusion of the extinct. Thus, for example, in the deposits
called the "northern drift," or the glacial formation of Europe
and North America, the fossil marine shells can easily be identified with
species either now inhabiting the neighboring sea, or living in the seas
of higher latitudes. Yet they exhibit no memorials of the human race,
or of articles fabricated by the hand of man. Some of the newest of
these strata passing by the name of "raised beaches," occur at moderate
elevations on the coast of England, Scotland, and Ireland. Other
examples are met with on a more extended scale in Scandinavia, as at
the height of 200 feet at Uddevalla in Sweden, and at twice that elevation,
near Christiana, in Norway, also at an altitude of 600 or 700 feet
in places farther north. They consist of beds of sand and clay, filling
hollows in a district of granite and gneiss, and they must closely resemble
the accumulations of shelly matter now in progress at the bottom of
the Norwegian fiords. The rate at which the land is now rising in
Scandinavia, is far too irregular in different places to afford a safe
standard for estimating the minimum of time required for the upheaval
185
of the fundamental granite, and its marine shelly covering, to the height
of so many hundred feet; but according to the greatest average, of five
or six feet in a century, the period required would be very considerable,
and nearly the whole of it, as well as the antecedent epoch of submergence,
seems to have preceded the introduction of man into these parts
of the earth.
There are other post-tertiary formations of fluviatile origin, in the
centre of Europe, in which the absence of human remains is perhaps
still more striking, because, when formed, they must have been surrounded
by dry land. I allude to the silt or loess of the basin of the
Rhine, which must have gradually filled up the great valley of that
river since the time when its waters, and the contiguous lands, were inhabited
by the existing species of freshwater and terrestrial mollusks.
Showers of ashes, thrown out by some of the last eruptions of the Eifel
volcanoes, fell during the deposition of this fluviatile silt, and were interstratified
with it. But these volcanoes became exhausted, the valley
was re-excavated through the silt, and again reduced to its present form
before the period of human history. The study, therefore, of this shelly
silt reveals to us the history of a long series of events, which occurred
after the testacea now living inhabited the land and rivers of Europe,
and the whole terminated without any signs of the coming of man into
that part of the globe.
To cite a still more remarkable example, we observe in Sicily a lofty
table-land and hills, sometimes rising to the height of 3000 feet, capped
with a limestone, in which from 70 to 85 per cent. of the fossil testacea
are specifically identical with those now inhabiting the Mediterranean.
These calcareous and other argillaceous strata of the same age are intersected
by deep valleys which have been gradually formed by denudation,
but have not varied materially in width or depth since Sicily was
first colonized by the Greeks. The limestone, moreover, which is of so
late a date in geological chronology, was quarried for building those
ancient temples of Girgenti and Syracuse, of which the ruins carry us
back to a remote era in human history. If we are lost in conjectures
when speculating on the ages required to lift up these formations to the
height of several thousand feet above the sea, how much more remote
must be the era when the same rocks were gradually formed beneath
the waters!
To conclude, it appears that, in going back from the recent to the
Eocene period, we are carried by many successive steps from the fauna
now contemporary with man to an assemblage of fossil species wholly
different from those now living. In this retrospect we have not yet succeeded
in tracing back a perfect transition from the recent to an extinct
fauna; but there are usually so many species in common to the groups
which stand next in succession as to show that there is no great chasm,
no signs of a crisis when one class of organic beings was annihilated to
give place suddenly to another. This analogy, therefore, derived from
a period of the earth's history which can best be compared with the
186
present state of things, and more thoroughly investigated than any
other, leads to the conclusion that the extinction and creation of species,
has been and is the result of a slow and gradual change in the organic
world.
UNIFORMITY OF CHANGE CONSIDERED, SECONDLY, IN REFERENCE TO SUBTERRANEAN
MOVEMENTS.
To pass on to another of the three topics before proposed for discussion,
the reader will find, in the account given in the second book of the
earthquakes recorded in history, that certain countries have, from time
immemorial, been rudely shaken again and again, while others, comprising
by far the largest part of the globe, have remained to all appearance
motionless. In the regions of convulsion rocks have been rent
asunder, the surface has been forced up into ridges, chasms have opened,
or the ground throughout large spaces has been permanently lifted up
above or let down below its former level. In the regions of tranquillity
some areas have remained at rest, but others have been ascertained by
a comparison of measurements, made at different periods, to have risen
by an insensible motion, as in Sweden, or to have subsided very slowly,
as in Greenland. That these same movements, whether ascending or
descending, have continued for ages in the same direction has been
established by geological evidence. Thus, we find both on the east and
west coast of Sweden, that ground which formerly constituted the bottom
of the Baltic and of the ocean has been lifted up to an elevation of
several hundred feet above high-water mark. The rise within the historical
period has not amounted to many yards, but the greater extent
of antecedent upheaval is proved by the occurrence in inland spots,
several hundred feet high, of deposits filled with fossil shells of species
now living either in the ocean or the Baltic.
To detect proofs of slow and gradual subsidence must in general be
more difficult; but the theory which accounts for the form of circular
coral reefs and lagoon islands, and which will be explained in the last
chapter of the third book, will satisfy the reader that there are spaces
on the globe, several thousand miles in circumference, throughout which
the downward movement has predominated for ages, and yet the land
has never, in a single instance, gone down suddenly for several hundred
feet at once. Yet geology demonstrates that the persistency of subterranean
movements in one direction has not been perpetual throughout
all past time. There have been great oscillations of level by which
a surface of dry land has been submerged to a depth of several thousand
feet, and then at a period long subsequent raised again and made
to emerge. Nor have the regions now motionless been always at rest;
and some of those which are at present the theatres of reiterated earthquakes
have formerly enjoyed a long continuance of tranquillity. But
although disturbances have ceased after having long prevailed, or have
recommenced after a suspension for ages, there has been no universal
disruption of the earth's crust or desolation of the surface since times
187
the most remote. The non-occurrence of such a general convulsion is
proved by the perfect horizontally now retained by some of the most
ancient fossiliferous strata throughout wide areas.
Inferences derived from unconformable strata.—That the subterranean
forces have visited different parts of the globe at successive periods, is
inferred chiefly from the unconformability of strata belonging to groups
of different ages. Thus, for example, on the borders of Wales and
Shropshire we find the slaty beds of the ancient Silurian system curved
and vertical, while the beds of the overlying carboniferous shale and
sandstone are horizontal. All are agreed, that in such a case the older
set of strata had suffered great dislocation before the deposition of the
newer or carboniferous beds, and that these last have never since been
convulsed by any movements of excessive violence. But the strata of
the inferior group suffered only a local derangement, and rocks of the
same age are by no means found everywhere in a curved or vertical
position. In various parts of Europe, and particularly near Lake Wener
in the south of Sweden, and in many parts of Russia, beds of the same
Silurian system maintain the most perfect horizontality; and a similar
observation may be made respecting limestones and shales of the like
antiquity in the great lake district of Canada and the United States.
They are still as flat and horizontal as when first formed; yet since
their origin not only have most of the actual mountain-chains been uplifted,
but the very rocks of which those mountains are composed have
been formed.
It would be easy to multiply instances of similar unconformability in
formations of other ages; but a few more will suffice. The coal measures
before alluded to as horizontal on the borders of Wales are vertical
in the Mendip Hills in Somersetshire, where the overlying beds of
the New Red Sandstone are horizontal. Again, in the Wolds of Yorkshire
the last mentioned sandstone supports on its curved and inclined
beds the horizontal Chalk. The Chalk again is vertical on the flanks
of the Pyrenees, and the tertiary strata repose unconformably upon it.
Consistency of local disturbances with general uniformity.—As almost
every country supplies illustrations of the same phenomena, they
who advocate the doctrine of alternate periods of disorder and repose
may appeal to the facts above described, as proving that every district
has been by turns convulsed by earthquakes and then respited
for ages from convulsions. But so it might with equal truth be
affirmed that every part of Europe has been visited alternately by winter
and summer, although it has always been winter and always summer
in some part of the planet, and neither of these seasons has ever
reigned simultaneously over the entire globe. They have been always
shifting about from place to place; but the vicissitudes which recur
thus annually in a single spot are never allowed to interfere with the
invariable uniformity of seasons throughout the whole planet.
So, in regard to subterranean movements, the theory of the perpetual
uniformity of the force which they exert on the earth's crust is
188
quite consistent with the admission of their alternate development and
suspension for indefinite periods within limited geographical areas.
UNIFORMITY OF CHANGE CONSIDERED, THIRDLY, IN REFERENCE TO
SEDIMENTARY DEPOSITION.
It now remains to speak of the laws governing the deposition of
new strata. If we survey the surface of the globe we immediately
perceive that it is divisible into areas of deposition and non-deposition,
or, in other words, at any given time there are spaces which are the
recipients, others which are not the recipients of sedimentary matter.
No new strata, for example, are thrown down on dry land, which
remains the same from year to year; whereas, in many parts of the
bottom of seas and lakes, mud, sand, and pebbles are annually spread
out by rivers and currents. There are also great masses of limestone
growing in some seas, or in mid-ocean, chiefly composed of corals and
shells.
No sediment deposited on dry land.—As to the dry land, so far
from being the receptacle of fresh accessions of matter, it is exposed
almost everywhere to waste away. Forests may be as dense and
lofty as those of Brazil, and may swarm with quadrupeds, birds, and
insects, yet at the end of ten thousand years one layer of black
mould, a few inches thick, may be the sole representative of those
myriads of trees, leaves, flowers, and fruits, those innumerable bones
and skeletons of birds, quadrupeds, and reptiles, which tenanted the
fertile region. Should this land be at length submerged, the waves
of the sea may wash away in a few hours the scanty covering of
mould, and it may merely impart a darker shade of color to the next
stratum of marl, sand, or other matter newly thrown down. So also
at the bottom of the ocean where no sediment is accumulating, sea-weed,
zoophytes, fish, and even shells, may multiply for ages and decompose,
leaving no vestige of their form or substance behind. Their
decay, in water, although more slow, is as certain and eventually as
complete as in the open air. Nor can they be perpetuated for indefinite
periods in a fossil state, unless imbedded in some matrix which is
impervious to water, or which at least does not allow a free percolation
of that fluid, impregnated as it usually is, with a slight quantity of carbonic
or other acid. Such a free percolation may be prevented either
by the mineral nature of the matrix itself, or by the superposition of an
impermeable stratum: but if unimpeded, the fossil shell or bone will be
dissolved and removed, particle after particle, and thus entirely effaced,
unless petrifaction or the substitution of mineral for organic matter happen
to take place.
That there has been land as well as sea at all former geological periods,
we know from the fact, that fossil trees and terrestrial plants are
imbedded in rocks of every age. Occasionally lacustrine and fluviatile
shells, insects, or the bones of amphibious or land reptiles, point to the
189
same conclusion. The existence of dry land at all periods of the past
implies, as before mentioned, the partial deposition of sediment, or its
limitation to certain areas; and the next point to which I shall call
the reader's attention, is the shifting of these areas from one region to
another.
First, then, variations in the site of sedimentary deposition are
brought about independently of subterranean movements. There is
always a slight change from year to year, or from century to century.
The sediment of the Rhone, for example, thrown into the Lake of
Geneva, is now conveyed to a spot a mile and a half distant from that
where it accumulated in the tenth century, and six miles from the point
where the delta began originally to form. We may look forward to
the period when this lake will be filled up, and then the distribution of
the transported matter will be suddenly altered, for the mud and sand
brought down from the Alps will thenceforth, instead of being deposited
near Geneva, be carried nearly 200 miles southwards, where the Rhone
enters the Mediterranean.
In the deltas of large rivers, such as those of the Ganges and Indus,
the mud is first carried down for many centuries through one arm, and
on this being stopped up it is discharged by another, and may then
enter the sea at a point 50 or 100 miles distant from its first receptacle.
The direction of marine currents is also liable to be changed by various
accidents, as by the heaping up of new sand-banks, or the wearing
away of cliffs and promontories.
But, secondly, all these causes of fluctuation in the sedimentary areas
are entirely subordinate to those great upward or downward movements
of land which have been already described as prevailing over large
tracts of the globe. By such elevation or subsidence certain spaces are
gradually submerged, or made gradually to emerge:—in the one case
sedimentary deposition may be suddenly renewed after having been suspended
for ages, in the other as suddenly made to cease after having
continued for an indefinite period.
Causes of variation in mineral character of successive sedimentary
groups.—If deposition be renewed after a long interval, the new strata
will usually differ greatly from the sedimentary rocks previously formed
in the same place, and especially if the older rocks have suffered derangement,
which implies a change in the physical geography of the
district since the previous conveyance of sediment to the same spot. It
may happen, however, that, even when the inferior group is horizontal
and conformable to the upper strata, these last may still differ entirely
in mineral character, because since the origin of the older formation the
geography of some distant country has been altered. In that country
rocks before concealed may have become exposed by denudation; volcanoes
may have burst out and covered the surface with scoriæ and
lava, or new lakes may have been formed by subsidence; and other fluctuations
may have occurred, by which the materials brought down from
thence by rivers to the sea have acquired a distinct mineral character.
190
It is well known that the stream of the Mississippi is charged with
sediment of a different color from that of the Arkansas and Red Rivers,
which are tinged with red mud, derived from rocks of porphyry in
"the far west." The waters of the Uruguay, says Darwin, draining a
granitic country, are clear and black, those of the Parana, red.258 The
mud with which the Indus is loaded, says Burnes, is of a clayey hue,
that of the Chenab, on the other hand, is reddish, that of the Sutlej is
more pale.259 The same causes which make these several rivers, sometimes
situated at no great distance the one from the other, to differ
greatly in the character of their sediment, will make the waters draining
the same country at different epochs, especially before and after great
revolutions in physical geography, to be entirely dissimilar. It is
scarcely necessary to add, that marine currents will be affected in an
analogous manner in consequence of the formation of new shoals, the
emergence of new islands, the subsidence of others, the gradual waste
of neighboring coasts, the growth of new deltas, the increase of coral
reefs, and other changes.
Why successive sedimentary groups contain distinct fossils.—If, in
the next place, we assume, for reasons before stated, a continual extinction
of species and introduction of others into the globe, it will then
follow that the fossils of strata formed at two distant periods on the
same spot, will differ even more certainly than the mineral composition
of the same. For rocks of the same kind have sometimes been reproduced
in the same district after a long interval of time, whereas there
are no facts leading to the opinion that species which have once died
out have ever been reproduced. The submergence then of land must
be often attended by the commencement of a new class of sedimentary
deposits, characterized by a new set of fossil animals and plants, while
the reconversion of the bed of the sea into land may arrest at once
and for an indefinite time the formation of geological monuments.
Should the land again sink, strata will again be formed; but one or
many entire revolutions in animal or vegetable life may have been completed
in the interval.
Conditions requisite for the original completeness of a fossiliferous
series.—If we infer, for reasons before explained, that fluctuations in
the animate world are brought about by the slow and successive
removal and creation of species, we shall be convinced that a rare combination
of circumstances alone can give rise to such a series of strata
as will bear testimony to a gradual passage from one state of organic
life to another. To produce such strata nothing less will be requisite
than the fortunate coincidence of the following conditions: first, a
never-failing supply of sediment in the same region throughout a period
of vast duration; secondly, the fitness of the deposit in every part for
the permanent preservation of imbedded fossils; and, thirdly, a gradual
191
subsidence to prevent the sea or lake from being filled up and converted
into land.
It will appear in the chapter on coral reefs,260 that, in certain parts of
the Pacific and Indian Oceans, most of these conditions, if not all, are
complied with, and the constant growth of coral, keeping pace with the
sinking of the bottom of the sea, seems to have gone on so slowly, for
such indefinite periods, that the signs of a gradual change in organic
life might probably be detected in that quarter of the globe, if we
could explore its submarine geology. Instead of the growth of coralline
limestone, let us suppose, in some other place, the continuous deposition
of fluviatile mud and sand, such as the Ganges and Brahmapootra
have poured for thousands of years into the Bay of Bengal.
Part of this bay, although of considerable depth, might at length be
filled up before an appreciable amount of change was effected in the
fish, mollusca, and other inhabitants of the sea and neighboring land.
But, if the bottom be lowered by sinking at the same rate that it is
raised by fluviatile mud, the bay can never be turned into dry land.
In that case one new layer of matter may be superimposed upon
another for a thickness of many thousand feet, and the fossils of the
inferior beds may differ greatly from those entombed in the uppermost,
yet every intermediate gradation may be indicated in the passage from
an older to a newer assemblage of species. Granting, however, that
such an unbroken sequence of monuments may thus be elaborated in
certain parts of the sea, and that the strata happen to be all of them
well adapted to preserve the included fossils from decomposition, how
many accidents must still concur before these submarine formations will
be laid open to our investigation! The whole deposit must first be
raised several thousand feet, in order to bring into view the very foundation;
and during the process of exposure the superior beds must not
be entirely swept away by denudation.
In the first place, the chances are as three to one against the mere
emergence of the mass above the waters, because three-fourths of the
globe are covered by the ocean. But if it be upheaved and made to
constitute part of the dry land, it must also, before it can be available
for our instruction, become part of that area already surveyed by geologists;
and this area comprehends perhaps less than a tenth of the
whole earth. In this small fraction of land already explored, and still
very imperfectly known, we are required to find a set of strata, originally
of limited extent, and probably much lessened by subsequent
denudation.
Yet it is precisely because we do not encounter at every step the
evidence of such gradations from one state of the organic world to
another, that so many geologists embrace the doctrine of great and
sudden revolutions in the history of the animate world. Not content
with simply availing themselves, for the convenience of classification, of
192
those gaps and chasms which here and there interrupt the continuity of
the chronological series, as at present known, they deduce, from the
frequency of these breaks in the chain of records, an irregular mode of
succession in the events themselves both in the organic and inorganic
world. But, besides that some links of the chain which once existed
are now clearly lost and others concealed from view, we have good reason
to suspect that it was never complete originally. It may undoubtedly
be said, that strata have been always forming somewhere, and
therefore at every moment of past time nature has added a page to her
archives; but, in reference to this subject, it should be remembered
that we can never hope to compile a consecutive history by gathering
together monuments which were originally detached and scattered over
the globe. For as the species of organic beings contemporaneously
inhabiting remote regions are distinct, the fossils of the first of several
periods which may be preserved in any one country, as in America,
for example, will have no connection with those of a second period
found in India, and will therefore no more enable us to trace the signs
of a gradual change in the living creation, than a fragment of Chinese
history will fill up a blank in the political annals of Europe.
The absence of any deposits of importance containing recent shells in
Chili, or anywhere on the western coast of South America, naturally
led Mr. Darwin to the conclusion that "where the bed of the sea is
either stationary or rising, circumstances are far less favorable than
where the level is sinking to the accumulation of conchiferous strata of
sufficient thickness and extension to resist the average vast amount of
denudation."261 An examination of the superficial clay, sand, and gravel
of the most modern date in Norway and Sweden, where the land is also
rising, would incline us to admit a similar proposition. Yet in these
cases there has been a supply of sediment from the waste of the coast
and the interior, especially in Patagonia and Chili. Nevertheless wherever
the bottom of the sea has been continually elevated, the total
thickness of sedimentary matter accumulating at depths suited to the
habitation of most of the species of shells can never be great, nor can
the deposits be thickly covered by superincumbent matter, so as to be
consolidated by pressure. When they are upheaved, therefore, the
waves on the beach will bear down and disperse the loose materials;
whereas if the bed of the sea subsides slowly, a mass of strata containing
abundance of such species as live at moderate depths may increase
in thickness to any amount, and may extend over a broad area, as the
water gradually encroaches on the land. If, then, at particular periods,
as in the Miocene epoch, for example, both in Europe and North America,
contemporaneous shelly deposits have originated, and have been
preserved at very distant points, it may arise from the prevalence at
that period of simultaneous subsidence throughout very wide areas.
The absence in the same quarters of the globe of strata marking the
193
ages which immediately succeeded, may be accounted for by supposing
that the level of the bed of the sea and the adjoining land was stationary
or was undergoing slow upheaval.
How far some of the great violations of continuity which now exist in
the chronological table of fossiliferous rocks, will hereafter be removed
or lessened, must at present be mere matter of conjecture. The hiatus
which exists in Great Britain between the fossils of the Lias and those
of the Magnesian Limestone, is supplied in Germany by the rich fauna
and flora of the Muschelkalk, Keuper, and Bunter Sandstein, which we
know to be of a date precisely intermediate; those three formations
being interposed in Germany between others which agree perfectly in
their organic remains with our Lias and Magnesian Limestone. Until
lately the fossils of the Coal-measures were separated from those of the
antecedent Silurian group by a very abrupt and decided line of demarcation;
but recent discoveries have brought to light in Devonshire, Belgium,
the Eifel, and Westphalia, the remains of a fauna of an intervening
period. This connecting link is furnished by the fossil shells, fish, and
corals of the Devonian or Old Red Sandstone group, and some species
of this newly intercalated fauna are found to be common to it and the
subjacent Silurian rocks, while other species belong to it in common
with the Coal-measures. We have also in like manner had some success
of late years in diminishing the hiatus which still separates the Cretaceous
and Eocene periods in Europe. Still we must expect, for reasons
before stated, that some such chasms will forever continue to occur
in some parts of our sedimentary series.
Consistency of the theory of gradual change with the existence of great
breaks in the series.—To return to the general argument pursued in this
chapter, it is assumed, for reasons above explained, that a slow change
of species is in simultaneous operation everywhere throughout the habitable
surface of sea and land; whereas the fossilization of plants and
animals is confined to those areas where new strata are produced.
These areas, as we have seen, are always shifting their position; so that
the fossilizing process, by means of which the commemoration of the
particular state of the organic world, at any given time, is affected, may
be said to move about, visiting and revisiting different tracts in succession.
To make still more clear the supposed working of this machinery, I
shall compare it to a somewhat analogous case that might be imagined
to occur in the history of human affairs. Let the mortality of the population
of a large country represent the successive extinction of species,
and the births of new individuals the introduction of new species.
While these fluctuations are gradually taking place everywhere, suppose
commissioners to be appointed to visit each province of the country
in succession, taking an exact account of the number, names, and individual
peculiarities of all the inhabitants, and leaving in each district a
register containing a record of this information. If, after the completion
of one census, another is immediately made on the same plan, and then
another, there will, at last, be a series of statistical documents in each
194
province. When those belonging to any one province are arranged in
chronological order, the contents of such as stand next to each other
will differ according to the length of the intervals of time between the
taking of each census. If, for example, there are sixty provinces, and
all the registers are made in a single year, and renewed annually, the
number of births and deaths will be so small, in proportion to the whole
of the inhabitants, during the interval between the compiling of the two
consecutive documents, that the individuals described in such documents
will be nearly identical; whereas, if the survey of each of the sixty
provinces occupies all the commissioners for a whole year, so that they
are unable to revisit the same place until the expiration of sixty years,
there will then be an almost entire discordance between the persons
enumerated in two consecutive registers in the same province. There
are, undoubtedly, other causes besides the mere quantity of time, which
may augment or diminish the amount of discrepancy. Thus, at some
periods a pestilential disease may have lessened the average duration of
human life, or a variety of circumstances may have caused the births to
be unusually numerous, and the population to multiply; or, a province
may be suddenly colonized by persons migrating from surrounding districts.
These exceptions may be compared to the accelerated rate of fluctuation
in the fauna and flora of a particular region, in which the climate
and physical geography may be undergoing an extraordinary degree of
alteration.
But I must remind the reader, that the case above proposed has no
pretensions to be regarded as an exact parallel to the geological phenomena
which I desire to illustrate; for the commissioners are supposed
to visit the different provinces in rotation; whereas the commemorating
processes by which organic remains become fossilized, although they
are always shifting from one area to the other, are yet very irregular in
their movements. They may abandon and revisit many spaces again
and again before they once approach another district; and, besides this
source of irregularity, it may often happen that, while the depositing
process is suspended, denudation may take place, which may be compared
to the occasional destruction by fire or other causes of some of
the statistical documents before mentioned. It is evident that, where
such accidents occur, the want of continuity in the series may become
indefinitely great, and that the monuments which follow next in succession
will by no means be equidistant from each other in point of time.
If this train of reasoning be admitted, the occasional distinctness of
the fossil remains, in formations immediately in contact, would be a
necessary consequence of the existing laws of sedimentary deposition
and subterranean movement, accompanied by a constant mortality and
renovation of species.
As all the conclusions above insisted on are directly opposed to opinions
still popular, I shall add another comparison, in the hope of preventing
any possible misapprehension of the argument. Suppose we
195
had discovered two buried cities at the foot of Vesuvius, immediately
superimposed upon each other, with a great mass of tuff and lava intervening,
just as Portici and Resina, if now covered with ashes, would
overlie Herculaneum. An antiquary might possibly be entitled to infer,
from the inscriptions on public edifices, that the inhabitants of the inferior
and older city were Greeks, and those of the modern towns Italians.
But he would reason very hastily if he also concluded from these data
that there had been a sudden change from the Greek to the Italian language
in Campania. But if he afterwards found three buried cities, one
above the other, the intermediate one being Roman, while, as in the
former example, the lowest was Greek and the uppermost Italian, he
would then perceive the fallacy of his former opinion, and would begin
to suspect that the catastrophes by which the cities were inhumed
might have no relation whatever to the fluctuations in the language of
the inhabitants; and that, as the Roman tongue had evidently intervened
between the Greek and Italian, so many other dialects may have been
spoken in succession, and the passage from the Greek to the Italian may
have been very gradual; some terms growing obsolete, while others
were introduced from time to time.
If this antiquary could have shown that the volcanic paroxysms of
Vesuvius were so governed as that cities should be buried one above the
other, just as often as any variation occurred in the language of the
inhabitants, then, indeed, the abrupt passage from a Greek to a Roman,
and from a Roman to an Italian city, would afford proof of fluctuations
no less sudden in the language of the people.
So, in Geology, if we could assume that it is part of the plan of
Nature to preserve, in every region of the globe, an unbroken series of
monuments to commemorate the vicissitudes of the organic creation, we
might infer the sudden extirpation of species, and the simultaneous
introduction of others, as often as two formations in contact are found to
include dissimilar organic fossils. But we must shut our eyes to the
whole economy of the existing causes, aqueous, igneous, and organic, if
we fail to perceive that such in not the plan of Nature.
Concluding remarks on the identity of the ancient and present system
of terrestrial changes.—I shall now conclude the discussion of a question
with which we have been occupied since the beginning of the fifth
chapter; namely, whether there has been any interruption, from the
remotest periods, of one uniform system of change in the animate and
inanimate world. We were induced to enter into that inquiry by reflecting
how much the progress of opinion in Geology had been influenced
by the assumption that the analogy was slight in kind, and still more
slight in degree, between the causes which produced the former revolutions
of the globe, and those now in every-day operation. It appeared
clear that the earlier geologists had not only a scanty acquaintance with
existing changes, but were singularly unconscious of the amount of their
ignorance. With the presumption naturally inspired by this unconsciousness,
they had no hesitation in deciding at once that time could never
196
enable the existing powers of nature to work out changes of great magnitude,
still less such important revolutions as those which are brought to
light by Geology. They, therefore, felt themselves at liberty to indulge
their imaginations in guessing at what might be, rather than inquiring
what is; in other words, they employed themselves in conjecturing
what might have been the course of nature at a remote period, rather
than in the investigation of what was the course of nature in their own
times.
It appeared to them more philosophical to speculate on the possibilities
of the past, than patiently to explore the realities of the present;
and having invented theories under the influence of such maxims, they
were consistently unwilling to test their validity by the criterion of their
accordance with the ordinary operations of nature. On the contrary,
the claims of each new hypothesis to credibility appeared enhanced by
the great contrast, in kind or intensity, of the causes referred to, and
those now in operation.
Never was there a dogma more calculated to foster indolence, and
to blunt the keen edge of curiosity, than this assumption of the discordance
between the ancient and existing causes of change. It produced a
state of mind unfavorable in the highest degree to the candid reception
of the evidence of those minute but incessant alterations which every
part of the earth's surface is undergoing, and by which the condition of
its living inhabitants is continually made to vary. The student, instead
of being encouraged with the hope of interpreting the enigmas presented
to him in the earth's structure,—instead of being prompted to undertake
laborious inquiries into the natural history of the organic world, and
the complicated effects of the igneous and aqueous causes now in operation,
was taught to despond from the first. Geology, it was affirmed,
could never rise to the rank of an exact science,—the greater number of
phenomena must forever remain inexplicable, or only be partially elucidated
by ingenious conjectures. Even the mystery which invested the
subject was said to constitute one of its principal charms, affording, as it
did, full scope to the fancy to indulge in a boundless field of speculation.
The course directly opposed to this method of philosophizing consists
in an earnest and patient inquiry, how far geological appearances are
reconcilable with the effect of changes now in progress, or which may
be in progress in regions inaccessible to us, and of which the reality is
attested by volcanoes and subterranean movements. It also endeavors
to estimate the aggregate result of ordinary operations multiplied by
time, and cherishes a sanguine hope that the resources to be derived
from observation and experiment, or from the study of nature such as
she now is, are very far from-being exhausted. For this reason all
theories are rejected which involve the assumption of sudden and violent
catastrophes and revolutions of the whole earth, and its inhabitants,—theories
which are restrained by no reference to existing analogies, and
in which a desire is manifested to cut, rather than patiently to untie, the
Gordian knot.
197
We have now, at least, the advantage of knowing, from experience,
that an opposite method has always put geologists on the road that
leads to truth,—suggesting views which, although imperfect at first,
have been found capable of improvement, until at last adopted by universal
consent; while the method of speculating on a former distinct
state of things and causes, has led invariably to a multitude of contradictory
systems, which have been overthrown one after the other,—have
been found incapable of modification,—and which have often required
to be precisely reversed.
The remainder of this work will be devoted to an investigation of the
changes now going on in the crust of the earth and its inhabitants.
The importance which the student will attach to such researches will
mainly depend in the degree of confidence which he feels in the principles
above expounded. If he firmly believes in the resemblance
or identity of the ancient and present system of terrestrial changes, he
will regard every fact collected respecting the causes in diurnal action
as affording him a key to the interpretation of some mystery in the
past. Events which have occurred at the most distant periods in
the animate and inanimate world, will be acknowledged to throw light
on each other, and the deficiency of our information respecting some
of the most obscure parts of the present creation will be removed. For
as, by studying the external configuration of the existing land and its
inhabitants, we may restore in imagination the appearance of the ancient
continents which have passed away, so may we obtain from the
deposits of ancient seas and lakes an insight into the nature of the subaqueous
processes now in operation, and of many forms of organic life,
which, though now existing, are veiled from sight. Rocks, also, produced
by subterranean fire in former ages, at great depths in the bowels
of the earth, present us, when upraised by gradual movements, and
exposed to the light of heaven, with an image of those changes which
the deep-seated volcano may now occasion in the nether regions.
Thus, although we are mere sojourners on the surface of the planet,
chained to a mere point in space, enduring but for a moment of time,
the human mind is not only enabled to number worlds beyond the
unassisted ken of mortal eye, but to trace the events of indefinite
ages before the creation of our race, and is not even withheld from
penetrating into the dark secrets of the ocean, or the interior of the
solid globe; free, like the spirit which the poet described as animating
the universe,


——ire per omnes
Terrasque, tractusque maris, cœlumque profundum.



198
BOOK II.
CHANGES IN THE INORGANIC WORLD.
AQUEOUS CAUSES.
</div></body></text></TEI>