<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="29">CHAPTER XXIX.
EARTHQUAKES—continued.
Earthquake of Java, 1772—Truncation of a lofty cone—St. Domingo, 1770—Lisbon,
1755—Great area over which the shocks extended—Retreat of the sea—Proposed
explanations—Conception Bay, 1750—Permanent elevation—Peru,
1746—Java, 1699—Rivers obstructed by landslips—Subsidence in Sicily, 1693—Moluccas,
1693—Jamaica, 1692—Large tracts engulfed—Portion of Port
Royal sunk—Amount of change in the last 150 years—Elevation and subsidence
of land in Bay of Baiæ—Evidence of the same afforded by the Temple of
Serapis.
In the preceding chapters we have considered a small part only of
those earthquakes which have occurred during the last seventy years,
of which accurate and authentic descriptions happen to have been recorded.
In examining those of earlier date, we find their number so great
that allusion can be made to a few only respecting which information
of peculiar geological interest has been obtained.
Java, 1772.—Truncation of a lofty cone.—In the year 1772, Papandayang,
formerly one of the loftiest volcanoes in the island of Java, was
in eruption. Before all the inhabitants on the declivities of the mountain
could save themselves by flight, the ground began to give way,
and a great part of the volcano fell in and disappeared. It is estimated
that an extent of ground of the mountain itself and its immediate environs,
494
fifteen miles long and full six broad, was by this commotion swallowed
up in the bowels of the earth. Forty villages were destroyed,
some being engulfed and some covered by the substances thrown out
on this occasion, and 2957 of the inhabitants perished. A proportionate
number of cattle were also killed, and most of the plantations of cotton,
indigo, and coffee in the adjacent districts were buried under the volcanic
matter. This catastrophe appears to have resembled, although on
a grander scale, that of the ancient Vesuvius in the year 79. The cone
was reduced in height from 9000 to about 5000 feet; and, as vapors
still escape from the crater on its summit, a new cone may one day rise
out of the ruins of the ancient mountain, as the modern Vesuvius has
risen from the remains of Somma.675
St. Domingo, 1770.—During a tremendous earthquake which destroyed
a great part of St. Domingo, innumerable fissures were caused
throughout the island, from which mephitic vapors emanated and produced
an epidemic. Hot springs burst forth in many places where there
had been no water before; but after a time they ceased to flow.676
In a previous earthquake, in November, 1751, a violent shock destroyed
the capital, Port au Prince, and part of the coast, twenty
leagues in length, sank down, and has ever since formed a bay of the
sea.677
Hindostan, 1762.—The town of Chittagong, in Bengal, was violently
shaken by an earthquake, on the 2d of April, 1762, the earth opening
in many places, and throwing up water and mud of a sulphureous smell.
At a place called Bardavan, a large river was dried up; and at Bar
Charra, near the sea, a tract of ground sunk down, and 200 people,
with all their cattle, were lost. It is said, that sixty square miles of the
Chittagong coast suddenly and permanently subsided during this earthquake,
and that Ces-lung-Toom, one of the Mug mountains, entirely disappeared,
and another sank so low, that its summit only remained visible.
Four hills are also described as having been variously rent asunder,
leaving open chasms from thirty to sixty feet in width. Towns which
subsided several cubits, were overflowed with water; among others,
Deep Gong, which was submerged to the depth of seven cubits. Two
volcanoes are said to have opened in the Secta Cunda hills. The shock
was also felt at Calcutta.678 While the Chittagong coast was sinking, a
corresponding rise of the ground took place at the island of Ramree,
and at Cheduba (see Map, fig. 39, p. 351).679
Lisbon, 1755.—In no part of the volcanic region of southern Europe
495
has so tremendous an earthquake occurred in modern times, as that
which began on the 1st of November, 1755, at Lisbon. A sound of
thunder was heard underground, and immediately afterwards a violent
shock threw down the greater part of that city. In the course of about
six minutes, sixty thousand persons perished. The sea first retired and
laid the bar dry; it then rolled in, rising fifty feet or more above its
ordinary level. The mountains of Arrabida, Estrella, Julio, Marvan,
and Cintra, being some of the largest in Portugal, were impetuously
shaken, as it were, from their very foundations; and some of them
opened at their summits, which were split and rent in a wonderful manner,
huge masses of them being thrown down into the subjacent valleys.680
Flames are related to have issued from these mountains, which
are supposed to have been electric; they are also said to have smoked;
but vast clouds of dust may have given rise to this appearance.
The area over which this convulsion extended is very remarkable.
It has been computed, says Humboldt,681 that on the 1st November,
1755, a portion of the earth's surface four times greater than the extent
of Europe was simultaneously shaken. The shock was felt in the
Alps, and on the coast of Sweden, in small inland lakes on the shores
of the Baltic, in Thuringia, and in the flat country of northern Germany.
The thermal springs of Toplitz dried up, and again returned, inundating
every thing with water discolored by ochre. In the islands of Antigua,
Barbadoes, and Martinique in the West Indies, where the tide usually
rises little more than two feet, it suddenly rose above twenty feet, the
water being discolored and of an inky blackness. The movement was
also sensible in the great lakes of Canada. At Algiers and Fez, in the
north of Africa, the agitation of the earth was as violent as in Spain
and Portugal; and at the distance of eight leagues from Morocco, a
village with the inhabitants, to the number of about 8000 or 10,000
persons, are said to have been swallowed up; the earth soon afterwards
closing over them.
Subsidence of the quay.—Among other extraordinary events related
to have occurred at Lisbon during the catastrophe was the subsidence
of a new quay, built entirely of marble at an immense expense. A
great concourse of people had collected there for safety, as a spot where
they might be beyond the reach of falling ruins; but suddenly the
quay sank down with all the people on it, and not one of the dead
bodies ever floated to the surface. A great number of boats and small
vessels anchored near it, all full of people, were swallowed up, as in
a whirlpool.682 No fragments of these wrecks ever rose again to the surface,
and the water in the place where the quay had stood is stated, in
many accounts, to be unfathomable; but Whitehurst says he ascertained
it to be one hundred fathoms.683
496
Circumstantial as are the contemporary narratives, I learn from a
correspondent, Mr. F. Freeman, in 1841, that no part of the Tagus was
then more than thirty feet deep at high tide, and an examination of the
position of the new quay, and the memorials preserved of the time and
manner in which it was built, rendered the statement of so great a subsidence
in 1755 quite unintelligible. Perhaps a deep narrow chasm, such
as was before described in Calabria (p. 481), opened and closed again
in the bed of the Tagus, after swallowing up some incumbent buildings
and vessels. We have already seen that such openings may collapse
after the shock suddenly, or, in places where the strata are of soft and
yielding materials, very gradually. According to the observations made
at Lisbon, in 1837, by Mr. Sharpe, the destroying effects of this earthquake
were confined to the tertiary strata, and were most violent on the
blue clay, on which the lower part of the city is constructed. Not a
building, he says, on the secondary limestone or the basalt was injured.684
Shocks felt at sea.—The shock was felt at sea, on the deck of a ship
to the west of Lisbon, and produced very much the same sensation as
on dry land. Off St. Lucar, the captain of the ship Nancy felt his
vessel so violently shaken, that he thought she had struck the ground;
but, on heaving the lead, found a great depth of water. Captain Clark,
from Denia, in latitude 36° 24' N., between nine and ten in the morning,
had his ship shaken and strained as if she had struck upon a rock,
so that the seams of the deck opened, and the compass was overturned
in the binnacle. Another ship, forty leagues west of St. Vincent, experienced
so violent a concussion, that the men were thrown a foot and
a half perpendicularly up from the deck.
Rate at which the movement travelled.—The agitation of lakes, rivers,
and springs, in Great Britain, was remarkable. At Loch Lomond, in
Scotland, for example, the water, without, the least apparent cause,
rose against its banks, and then subsided below its usual level. The
greatest perpendicular height of this swell was two feet four inches. It
is said that the movement of this earthquake was undulatory, and that
it travelled at the rate of twenty miles a minute, its velocity being calculated
by the intervals between the time when the first shock was felt
at Lisbon, and its time of occurrence at other distant places.685
Great wave and retreat of the sea.—A great wave swept over the
coast of Spain, and is said to have been sixty feet high at Cadiz. At
Tangier, in Africa, it rose and fell eighteen times on the coast. At
Funchal, in Madeira, it rose full fifteen feet perpendicular above high-water
mark, although the tide, which ebbs and flows there seven feet,
was then at half-ebb. Besides entering the city, and committing great
havoc, it overflowed other seaports in the island. At Kinsale, in Ireland,
a body of water rushed into the harbor, whirled round several vessels,
and poured into the market-place.
497
It was before stated that the sea first retired at Lisbon; and this retreat
of the ocean from the shore, at the commencement of an earthquake,
and its subsequent return in a violent wave, is a common occurrence.
In order to account for the phenomenon, Michell imagined a subsidence
at the bottom of the sea, from the giving way of the roof of some cavity
in consequence of a vacuum produced by the condensation of steam.
Such condensation, he observes, might be the first effect of the introduction
of a large body of water into fissures and cavities already filled
with steam, before there has been sufficient time for the heat of the incandescent
lava to turn so large a supply of water into steam, which
being soon accomplished causes a greater explosion.
Another proposed explanation is, the sudden rise of the land, which
would cause the sea to abandon immediately the ancient line of coast;
and if the shore, after being thus heaved up, should fall again to its
original level, the ocean would return. This theory, however, will not
account for the facts observed during the Lisbon earthquake; for the
retreat preceded the wave, not only on the coast of Portugal, but also
at the island of Madeira, and several other places. If the upheaving of
the coast of Portugal had caused the retreat, the motion of the waters,
when propagated to Madeira, would have produced a wave previous to
the retreat. Nor could the motion of the waters at Madeira have been
caused by a different local earthquake; for the shock travelled from
Lisbon to Madeira in two hours, which agrees with the time which it
required to reach other places equally distant.686
The following is another solution of the problem, which has been
offered:—Suppose a portion of the bed of the sea to be suddenly upheaved;
the first effect will be to raise over the elevated part a body
of water, the momentum of which will carry it much above the level it
will afterwards assume, causing a draught or receding of the water from
the neighboring coasts, followed immediately by the return of the displaced
water, which will also be impelled by its momentum much farther
and higher on the coast than its former level.687
Mr. Darwin, when alluding to similar waves on the coast of Chili,
states his opinion, that "the whole phenomenon is due to a common undulation
in the water, proceeding from a line or point of disturbance
some little way distant. If the waves," he says, "sent off from the
paddles of a steam-vessel be watched breaking on the sloping shore of
a still river, the water will be seen first to retire two or three feet, and
then to return in little breakers, precisely analogous to those consequent
on an earthquake." He also adds, that "the earthquake-wave occurs
some time after the shock, the water at first retiring both from the
shores of the mainland and of outlying islands, and then returning in
mountainous breakers. Their size is modified by the form of the neighboring
coast; for it is ascertained in South America, that places situated
498
at the head of shoaling bays have suffered most, whereas towns like
Valparaiso, seated close on the border of a profound ocean, have never
been inundated, though severely shaken by earthquakes."688
More recently (February, 1846), Mr. Mallet, in his memoir above
cited (p. 475), has endeavored to bring to bear on this difficult subject
the more advanced knowledge obtained of late years respecting the true
theory of waves. He conceives that when the origin of the shock is beneath
the deep ocean, one wave is propagated through the land, and
another moving with inferior velocity is formed on the surface of the
ocean. This last rolls in upon the land long after the earth-wave has
arrived and spent itself. However irreconcilable it may be to our common
notions of solid bodies, to imagine them capable of transmitting,
with such extreme velocity, motions analogous to tidal waves, it seems
nevertheless certain that such undulations are produced, and it is supposed
that when the shock passes a given point, each particle of the solid
earth describes an ellipse in space. The facility with which all the particles
of a solid mass can be made to vibrate may be illustrated, says
Gay Lussac, by many familiar examples. If we apply the ear to one
end of a long wooden beam, and listen attentively when the other end
is struck by a pin's head, we hear the shock distinctly; which shows
that every fibre throughout the whole length has been made to vibrate.
The rattling of carriages on the pavement shakes the largest edifices;
and in the quarries underneath some quarters in Paris, it is found that
the movement is communicated through a considerable thickness of
rock.689
The great sea-wave originating directly over the centre of disturbance
is propagated, as Michell correctly stated, in every direction, like the
circle upon a pond when a pebble is dropped into it, the different rates
at which it moves depending (as he also suggested) on variations in the
depth of the water. This wave of the sea, says Mr. Mallet, is raised by
the impulse of the shock immediately below it, which in great earthquakes
lifts up the ground two or three feet perpendicularly. The
velocity of the shock, or earth-wave, is greater because it "depends upon
a function of the elasticity of the crust of the earth, whereas the velocity
of the sea-wave depends upon a function of the depth of the sea."
"Although the shock in its passage under the deep ocean gives no
trace of its progress, it no sooner gets into soundings or shallow water,
than it gives rise to another and smaller wave of the sea. It carries, as
it were, upon its back, this lesser aqueous undulation; a long narrow ridge
of water which corresponds in form and velocity to itself, being pushed
up by the partial elevation of the bottom. It is this small wave, called
technically the 'forced sea-wave,' which communicates the earthquake-shock
to ships at sea, as if they had struck upon a rock. It breaks
upon a coast at the same moment that the shock reaches it, and sometimes
499
it may cause an apparent slight recession from the shore, followed
by its flowing up somewhat higher than the usual tide mark: this will
happen where the beach is very sloping, as is usual where the sea is
shallow, for then the velocity of the low flat earth-wave is such, that it
slips as it were, from under the undulation in the fluid above. It does
this at the moment of reaching the beach, which it elevates by a vertical
height equal to its own, and as instantly lets drop again to its former
level."
"While the shock propagated through the solid earth has thus travelled
with extra rapidity to the land, the great sea-wave has been following
at a slower pace, though advancing at the rate of several miles
in a minute. It consists, in the deep ocean, of a long low swell of enormous
volume, having an equal slope before and behind, and that so
gentle that it might pass under a ship without being noticed. But when
it reaches the edge of soundings, its front slope, like that of a tidal wave
under similar circumstances, becomes short and steep, while its rear
slope is long and gentle. If there be water of some depth close into
shore, this great wave may roll in long after the shock, and do little
damage; but if the shore be shelving, there will be first a retreat of the
water, and then the wave will break upon the beach and roll in far
upon the land."690
The various opinions which have been offered by Michell and later
writers, respecting the remote causes of earthquake shocks in the interior
of the earth, will more properly be discussed in the thirty-second
chapter.
Chili, 1751.—On the 24th of May, 1751, the ancient town of Conception,
otherwise called Penco, was totally destroyed by an earthquake,
and the sea rolled over it. (See plan of the bay, fig. 70, p. 455.) The
ancient port was rendered entirely useless, and the inhabitants built
another town about ten miles from the sea-coast, in order to be beyond
the reach of similar inundations. At the same time, a colony recently
settled on the sea-shore of Juan Fernandez was almost entirely overwhelmed
by a wave which broke upon the shore.
It has been already stated, that in 1835, or eighty-four years after
the destruction of Penco, the same coast was overwhelmed by a similar
flood from the sea during an earthquake; and it is also known that
twenty-one years before (or in 1730), a like wave rolled over these
fated shores, in which many of the inhabitants perished. A series of
similar catastrophes has also been tracked back as far as the year 1590,691
beyond which we have no memorials save those of oral tradition. Molina,
who has recorded the customs and legends of the aborigines, tells us,
that the Araucanian Indians, a tribe inhabiting the country between the
Andes and the Pacific, including the part now called Chili, "had among
them a tradition of a great deluge, in which only a few persons were
500
saved, who took refuge upon a high mountain called Thegtheg, "the
thundering," which had three points. Whenever a violent earthquake
occurs, these people fly for safety to the mountains, assigning as a reason,
that they are fearful, after the shock, that the sea will again return
and deluge the world.692
Notwithstanding the tendency of writers in his day to refer all traditionary
inundations to one remote period, Molina remarks that this
flood of the Araucanians "was probably very different from that of
Noah." We have, indeed, no means of conjecturing how long this same
tribe had flourished in Chili, but we can scarcely doubt, that if its experience
reached back even for three or four centuries, several inroads
of the ocean must have occurred within that period. But the memory
of a succession of physical events, similar in kind, though distinct in
time, can never be preserved by a people destitute of written annals.
Before two or three generations have passed away all dates are forgotten,
and even the events themselves, unless they have given origin to
some customs, or religious rites and ceremonies. Oftentimes the incidents
of many different earthquakes and floods become blended
together in the same narrative; and in such cases the single catastrophe
is described in terms so exaggerated, or is so disguised by
mythological fictions, as to be utterly valueless to the antiquary or philosopher.
Proofs of elevation of twenty-four feet.—During a late survey of Conception
Bay, Captain Beechey and Sir E. Belcher discovered that the
ancient harbor, which formerly admitted all large merchant vessels
which went round the Cape, is now occupied by a reef of sandstone,
certain points of which project above the sea at low water, the greater
part being very shallow. A tract of a mile and a half in length, where,
according to the report of the inhabitants, the water was formerly four
or five fathoms deep, is now a shoal; consisting, as our hydrographers
found, of hard sandstone, so that it cannot be supposed to have been
formed by recent deposits of the river Biobio, an arm of which carries
down loose micaceous sand into the same bay.
It is impossible at this distance of time to affirm that the bed of the
sea was uplifted at once to the height of twenty-four feet, during the
single earthquake of 1751, because other movements may have occurred
subsequently; but it is said, that ever since the shock of 1751, no vessels
have been able to approach within a mile and a half of the ancient
port of Penco. (See Map, p. 455.) In proof of the former elevation
of the coast near Penco our surveyors found above high-water mark an
enormous bed of shells of the same species as those now living in the
bay, filled with micaceous sand like that which the Biobio now conveys
to the bay. These shells, as well as others, which cover the adjoining
hills of mica-schist to the height of several hundred feet, have lately
been examined by experienced conchologists in London, and identified
501
with those taken at the same time in a living state from the bay and its
neighborhood.693
Ulloa, therefore, was perfectly correct in his statement that, at various
heights above the sea between Talcahuano and Conception, "mines
were found of various sorts of shells used for lime of the very same kinds
as those found in the adjoining sea." Among them he mentions the
great mussel called Choros, and two others which he describes. Some
of these, he says, are entire, and others broken; they occur at the bottom
of the sea, in four, six, ten, or twelve fathom water, where they adhere
to a sea-plant called Cochayuyo. They are taken in dredges, and
have no resemblance to those found on the shore or in shallow water;
yet beds of them occur at various heights on the hills. "I was the
more pleased with the sight," he adds, "as it appeared to me a convincing
proof of the universality of the deluge, although I am not ignorant
that some have attributed their position to other causes."694 It has,
however, been ascertained that the foundation of the Castle of Penco
was so low in 1835, or at so inconsiderable an elevation above the highest
spring tides, as to discountenance the idea of any permanent upheaval
in modern times, on the site of that ancient port; but no exact measurements
or levellings appear as yet to have been made to determine this
point, which is the more worthy of investigation, because it may throw
some light on an opinion often promulgated of late years, that there
is a tendency in the Chilian coast, after each upheaval, to sink gradually
and return towards its former position.
Peru, 1746.—Peru was visited, on the 28th of October, 1746, by a
tremendous earthquake. In the first twenty-four hours, two hundred
shocks were experienced. The ocean twice retired and returned impetuously
upon the land: Lima was destroyed, and part of the coast near
Callao was converted into a bay: four other harbors, among which were
Cavalla and Guanape, shared the same fate. There were twenty-three
ships and vessels, great and small, in the harbor of Callao, of which
nineteen were sunk; and the other four, among which was a frigate
called St. Fermin, were carried by the force of the waves to a great distance
up the country, and left on dry ground at a considerable height
above the sea. The number of inhabitants in this city amounted to four
thousand. Two hundred only escaped, twenty-two of whom were saved
on a small fragment of the fort of Vera Cruz, which remained as the only
memorial of the town after this dreadful inundation. Other portions of
its site were completely covered with heaps of sand and gravel.
A volcano in Lucanas burst forth the same night, and such quantities
of water descended from the cone that the whole country was overflowed;
and in the mountain near Pataz, called Conversiones de Caxamarquilla,
three other volcanoes burst out, and frightful torrents of water
swept down their sides.695
502
There are several records of prior convulsions in Peru, accompanied by
similar inroads in the sea, one of which happened fifty-nine years before
(in 1687), when the ocean, according to Ulloa, first retired and then returned
in a mountainous wave, overwhelming Callao and its environs,
with the miserable inhabitants.696 This same wave, according to Lionel
Wafer, carried ships a league into the country, and drowned man and
beast for fifty leagues along the shore.697 Inundations of still earlier dates
are carefully recorded by Ulloa, Wafer, Acosta, and various writers, who
describe them as having expended their chief fury, some on one part of
the coast and some on another.
But all authentic accounts cease when we ascend to the era of the
conquest of Peru by the Spaniards. The ancient Peruvians, although
far removed from barbarism, were without written annals, and therefore
unable to preserve a distinct recollection of a long series of natural
events. They had, however, according to Antonio de Herrera, who, in
the beginning of the seventeenth century, investigated their antiquities,
a tradition, "that many years before the reign of the Incas, at a
time when the country was very populous, there happened a great flood;
the sea breaking out beyond its bounds, so that the land was covered
with water and all the people perished. To this the Guacas, inhabiting
the vale of Xausca, and the natives of Chiquito, in the province of Callao,
add that some persons remained in the hollows and caves of the
highest mountains, who again peopled the land. Others of the mountain
people affirm that all perished in the deluge, only six persons being
saved on a float, from whom descended all the inhabitants of that country."698
On the mainland near Lima, and on the neighboring island of San
Lorenzo, Mr. Darwin found proofs that the ancient bed of the sea had
been raised to the height of more than eighty feet above water within
the human epoch, strata having been discovered at that altitude, containing
pieces of cotton thread and plaited rush, together with sea-weed
and marine shells.699 The same author learnt from Mr. Gill, a civil
engineer, that he discovered in the interior near Lima, between Casma
and Huaraz, the dried-up channel of a large river, sometimes worn
through solid rock, which, instead of continually ascending towards its
source, has, in one place, a steep downward slope in that direction, for a
ridge or line of hills has been uplifted directly across the bed of the
stream, which is now arched. By these changes the water has been
turned into some other course; and a district, once fertile, and still covered
with ruins, and bearing the marks of ancient cultivation, has been
converted into a desert.700
Java, 1699.—On the 5th of January, 1699, a terrible earthquake
visited Java, and no less than 208 considerable shocks were reckoned.
503
Many houses in Batavia were overturned, and the flame and noise of a
volcanic eruption were seen and heard in that city, which were afterwards
found to proceed from Mount Salek,701 a volcano six days' journey
distant. Next morning the Batavian river, which has its rise from that
mountain, became very high and muddy, and brought down abundance
of bushes and trees, half burnt. The channel of the river being stopped
up, the water overflowed the country round the gardens about the town,
and some of the streets, so that fishes lay dead in them. All the fish
in the river, except the carps, were killed by the mud and turbid water.
A great number of drowned buffaloes, tigers, rhinoceroses, deer, apes,
and other wild beasts, were brought down by the current; and, "notwithstanding,"
observes one of the writers, "that a crocodile is amphibious,
several of them were found dead among the rest."702
It is stated that seven hills bounding the river sank down; by which
is merely meant, as by similar expressions in the description of the Calabrian
earthquakes, seven great landslips. These hills, descending some
from one side of the valley and some from the other, filled the channel,
and the waters then finding their way under the mass, flowed out thick
and muddy. The Tangaran river was also dammed up by nine hills,
and in its channel were large quantities of drift trees. Seven of its
tributaries also are said to have been "covered up with earth." A high
tract of forest land, between the two great rivers before mentioned, is
described as having been changed into an open country, destitute of
trees, the surface being spread over with fine red clay. This part of
the account may, perhaps, merely refer to the sliding down of woody
tracts into the valleys, as happened to so many extensive vineyards and
olive-grounds in Calabria, in 1783. The close packing of large trees in
the Batavian river is represented as very remarkable, and it attests in a
striking manner the destruction of soil bordering the valleys which had
been caused by floods and landslips.703
Quito, 1698.—In Quito, on the 19th of July, 1698, during an earthquake,
a great part of the crater and summit of the volcano Carguairazo
fell in, and a stream of water and mud issued from the broken sides of
the hill.704
Sicily, 1693.—Shocks of earthquakes spread over all Sicily in 1693,
and on the 11th of January the city of Catania and forty-nine other
places were levelled to the ground, and about one hundred thousand
people killed. The bottom of the sea, says Vicentino Bonajutus, sank
down considerably, both in ports, inclosed bays, and open parts of the
coast, and water bubbled up along the shores. Numerous long fissures
of various breadths were caused, which threw out sulphurous water;
and one of them, in the plain of Catania (the delta of the Simeto), at
the distance of four miles from the sea, sent forth water as salt as the
sea. The stone buildings of a street in the city of Noto, for the length
504
of half a mile, sank into the ground, and remained hanging on one side.
In another street, an opening large enough to swallow a man and horse
appeared.705
Moluccas, 1693.—The small Isle of Sorea, which consists of one
great volcano, was in eruption in the year 1693. Different parts of the
cone fell, one after the other, into a deep crater, until almost half the
space of the island was converted into a fiery lake. Most of the inhabitants
fled to Banda; but great pieces of the mountain continued to
fall down, so that the lake of lava became wider; and finally the whole
population was compelled to emigrate. It is stated that, in proportion
as the burning lake increased in size, the earthquakes were less vehement.706
Jamaica, 1692.—In the year 1692, the island of Jamaica was visited
by a violent earthquake; the ground swelled and heaved like a rolling
sea, and was traversed by numerous cracks, two or three hundred of
which were often seen at a time, opening and then closing rapidly
again. Many people were swallowed up in these rents; some the earth
caught by the middle, and squeezed to death; the heads of others only
appeared above ground; and some were first engulfed, and then cast
up again with great quantities of water. Such was the devastation,
that even in Port Royal, then the capital, where more houses are said
to have been left standing than in the whole island besides, three-quarters
of the buildings, together with the ground they stood on, sank down
with their inhabitants entirely under water.
Subsidence in the harbor.—The large storehouses on the harbor side
subsided, so as to be twenty-four, thirty-six, and forty-eight feet under
water; yet many of them appear to have remained standing, for it is
stated that, after the earthquake, the mast-heads of several ships
wrecked in the harbor, together with the chimney-tops of houses, were
just seen projecting above the waves. A tract of land round the town,
about a thousand acres in extent, sank down in less than one minute,
during the first shock, and the sea immediately rolled in. The Swan
frigate, which was repairing in the wharf, was driven over the tops of
many buildings, and then thrown upon one of the roofs, through which
it broke. The breadth of one of the streets is said to have been doubled
by the earthquake.
According to Sir H. De la Beche, the part of Port Royal described
as having sunk was built upon newly formed land, consisting of sand,
in which piles had been driven; and the settlement of this loose sand,
charged with the weight of heavy houses, may, he suggests, have given
rise to the subsidence alluded to.707
There have undoubtedly been instances in Calabria and elsewhere
of slides of land on which the houses have still remained standing; and
it is possible that such may have been the case at Port Royal. The
505
fact at least of submergence is unquestionable, for I was informed by
the late Admiral Sir Charles Hamilton that he frequently saw the submerged
houses of Port Royal in the year 1780, in that part of the harbor
which lies between the town and the usual anchorage of men-of-war.
Bryan Edwards also says, in his history of the West Indies, that
in 1793 the ruins were visible in clear weather from the boats which
sailed over them.708 Lastly, Lieutenant B. Jeffery, R. N., tells me that,
being engaged in a survey between the years 1824 and 1835, he repeatedly
visited the site in question, where the depth of the water is
from four to six fathoms, and whenever there was but little wind perceived
distinct traces of houses. He saw these more clearly when he
used the instrument called the "diver's eye," which is let down below
the ripple of the wave.709
At several thousand places in Jamaica the earth is related to have
opened. On the north of the island several plantations, with their inhabitants,
were swallowed up, and a lake appeared in their place, covering
above a thousand acres, which afterwards dried up, leaving nothing
but sand and gravel, without the least sign that there had ever been a
house or a tree there. Several tenements at Yallows were buried under
land-slips; and one plantation was removed half a mile from its place,
the crops continuing to grow upon it uninjured. Between Spanish Town
and Sixteen-mile Walk, the high and perpendicular cliffs bounding the
river fell in, stopped the passage of the river and flooded the latter place
for nine days, so that the people "concluded it had been sunk as Port
Royal was." But the flood at length subsided, for the river had found
some new passage at a great distance.
Mountains shattered.—The Blue and other of the highest mountains
are declared to have been strangely torn and rent. They appeared
shattered and half-naked, no longer affording a fine green prospect, as
before, but stripped of their woods and natural verdure. The rivers on
these mountains first ceased to flow for about twenty-four hours, and
then brought down into the sea, at Port Royal and other places, several
hundred thousand tons of timber, which looked like floating islands on
the ocean. The trees were in general barked, most of their branches
having been torn off in the descent. It is particularly remarked in this,
as in the narratives of so many earthquakes, that fish were taken in great
numbers on the coast during the shocks. The correspondents of Sir
Hans Sloane, who collected with care the accounts of eye-witnesses of
the catastrophe, refer constantly to subsidences, and some supposed the
whole of Jamaica to have sunk down.710
Reflections on the amount of change in the last one hundred and sixty
years.—I have now only enumerated some few of the earthquakes of the
last 160 years, respecting which facts illustrative of geological inquiries
are on record. Even if my limits permitted, it would be an unprofitable
506
task to examine all the obscure and ambiguous narratives of similar
events of earlier epochs; although, if the places were now examined by
geologists well practised in the art of interpreting the monuments of
physical changes, many events which have happened within the historical
era might doubtless be still determined with precision. It must
not be imagined that, in the above sketch of the occurrences of a short
period, I have given an account of all, or even the greater part, of the
mutations which the earth has undergone by the agency of subterranean
movements. Thus, for example, the earthquake of Aleppo, in the
present century, and of Syria, in the middle of the eighteenth, would
doubtless have afforded numerous phenomena, of great geological importance,
had those catastrophes been described by scientific observers.
The shocks in Syria in 1759, were protracted for three months, throughout
a space of ten thousand square leagues: an area compared to which
that of the Calabrian earthquake in 1783 was insignificant. Accon,
Saphat, Balbeck, Damascus, Sidon, Tripoli, and many other places, were
almost entirely levelled to the ground. Many thousands of the inhabitants
perished in each; and, in the valley of Balbeck alone, 20,000 men
are said to have been victims to the convulsion. In the absence of
scientific accounts, it would be as irrelevant to our present purpose to
enter into a detailed account of such calamities, as to follow the track of
an invading army, to enumerate the cities burnt or rased to the ground,
and reckon the number of individuals who perished by famine or the
sword.
Deficiency of historical records.—If such, then, be the amount of
ascertained changes in the last 160 years, notwithstanding the extreme
deficiency of our records during that brief period, how important must
we presume the physical revolutions to have been in the course of thirty
or forty centuries, during which some countries habitually convulsed by
earthquakes have been peopled by civilized nations! Towns engulfed
during one earthquake may, by repeated shocks, have sunk to great
depths beneath the surface, while the ruins remain as imperishable as
the hardest rocks in which they are inclosed. Buildings and cities, submerged,
for a time, beneath seas or lakes, and covered with sedimentary
deposits, must, in some places, have been re-elevated to considerable
heights above the level of the ocean. The signs of these events have,
probably, been rendered visible by subsequent mutations, as by the encroachments
of the sea upon the coast, by deep excavations made by
torrents and rivers, by the opening of new ravines, and chasms, and other
effects of natural agents, so active in districts agitated by subterranean
movements.
If it be asked why, if such wonderful monuments exist, so few have
hitherto been brought to light, we reply—because they have not been
searched for. In order to rescue from oblivion the memorials of former
occurrences, the inquirer must know what he may reasonably expect to
discover, and under what peculiar local circumstances. He must be
acquainted with the action and effect of physical causes, in order to recognize,
507
explain, and describe correctly the phenomena when they present
themselves.
The best known of the great volcanic regions, of which the boundaries
were sketched in the twenty-second chapter, is that which includes
Southern Europe, Northern Africa, and Central Asia; yet nearly the
whole, even of this region, must be laid down, in a geological map, as
"Terra Incognita." Even Calabria may be regarded as unexplored, as
also Spain, Portugal, the Barbary States, the Ionian Isles, Asia Minor,
Cyprus, Syria, and the countries between the Caspian and Black seas.
We are, in truth, beginning to obtain some insight into one small spot
of that great zone of volcanic disturbance, the district around Naples; a
tract by no means remarkable for the violence of the earthquakes which
have convulsed it.
If, in this part of Campania, we are enabled to establish that considerable
changes in the relative level of land and sea have taken place since
the Christian era, it is all that we could have expected; and it is to recent
antiquarian and geological research, not to history, that we are
principally indebted for the information. I shall now proceed to lay
before the reader some of the results of modern investigations in the
Bay of Baiæ and the adjoining coast.
PROOFS OF ELEVATION AND SUBSIDENCE IN THE BAY OF BAIÆ.
Fig. 86.
Ground plan of the coast of the Bay of Baiæ, in the environs of Puzzuoli
Temple of Jupiter Serapis.—This celebrated monument of antiquity,
a representation of which is given in the frontispiece,711 affords in itself
alone, unequivocal evidence that the relative level of land and sea has
changed twice at Puzzuoli since the Christian era; and each movement,
508
both of elevation and subsidence, has exceeded twenty feet. Before
examining these proofs, I may observe, that a geological examination of
the coast of Baiæ, both on the north and south of Puzzuoli, establishes,
in the most satisfactory manner, an elevation, at no remote period, of
more than twenty feet, and, at one point, of more than thirty feet; and
the evidence of this change would have been complete, if even the temple
had, to this day, remained undiscovered.
Coast south of Puzzuoli.—If we coast along the shore from Naples
to Puzzuoli, we find, on approaching the latter place, that the lofty and
precipitous cliffs of indurated tuff, resembling that of which Naples is
built, retire slightly from the sea; and that a low level tract of fertile
land, of a very different aspect, intervenes between the present sea-beach
and what was evidently the ancient line of coast.
The inland cliff may be seen opposite the small island of Nisida, about
two miles and a half southeast of Puzzuoli (see Map, fig. 40, p. 361),
where, at the height of thirty-two feet above the level of the sea, Mr.
Babbage observed an ancient mark, such as might have been worn by
the waves; and, upon farther examination, discovered that, along that
line, the face of the perpendicular rock, consisting of very hard tuff, was
covered with barnacles (Balanus sulcatus, Lamk.), and drilled by boring
testacea. Some of the hollows of the lithodomi contained the shells;

Fig. 87.


a, Antiquities on hill S. E. of Puzzuoli
     (see ground plan, fig. 86).
b, Ancient cliff now inland.
c, Terrace composed of recent    submarine deposit.


while others were filled with the valves of
a species of Area.712 Nearer to Puzzuoli,
the inland cliff is eighty feet high, and as
perpendicular as if it was still undermined
by the waves. At its base, a new deposit,
constituting the fertile tract above alluded
to, attains a height of about twenty feet
above the sea; and, since it is composed
of regular sedimentary deposits, containing
marine shells, its position proves that, subsequently
to its formation, there has been a
change of more than twenty feet in the
relative level of land and sea.
The sea encroaches on these new incoherent strata; and as the soil is
valuable, a wall has been built for its protection; but when I visited the
spot in 1828, the waves had swept away part of this rampart, and exposed
to view a regular series of strata of tuff, more or less argillaceous,
alternating with beds of pumice and lapilli, and containing great abundance
of marine shells, of species now common on this coast, and amongst
them Cardium rusticum, Ostrea edulis, Donax trunculus, Lamk., and
others. The strata vary from about a foot to a foot and a half in thickness,
and one of them contains abundantly remains of works of art, tiles,
squares of mosaic pavement of different colors, and small sculptured ornaments,
510
perfectly uninjured. Intermixed with these I collected some
teeth of the pig and ox. These fragments of building occur below as
well as above strata containing marine shells. Puzzuoli itself stands
chiefly on a promontory of the older tufaceous formation, which cuts off
the new deposit, although I detected a small patch of the latter in a garden
under the town.
Fig. 88.VIEW OF BAY OF BAIÆ.


1. Puzzuoli.
2. Temple of Serapis.
3. Caligula's Bridge.
4. Monte Barbaro.
5. Monte Nuovo.

6. Baths of Nero.
7. Baiæ.
8. Castle of Baiæ.
9. Bauli.
10. Cape Misenum.

11. Mount Epomeo in Ischia.
12. South Part of Ischia.
 



From the town the ruins of a mole, called Caligula's Bridge, run out
into the sea (see fig. 88, p. 509).713 This mole, which is believed to be
eighteen centuries old, consists of a number of piers and arches, thirteen
of which are now standing, and two others appear to have been overthrown.
Mr. Babbage found, on the sixth pier, perforations of lithodomi
four feet above the level of the sea; and, near the termination of
the mole on the last pier but one, marks of the same, ten feet above the
level of the sea, together with great numbers of balani and flustra. The
depth of the sea, at a very small distance from most of the piers, is
from thirty to fifty feet.
Fig. 89.

a, Remains of Cicero's villa, N. side of Puzzuoli.714
b, Ancient cliff now inland.
c, Terrace (called La Starza) composed of recent submarine deposits.
d, Temple of Serapis.
Coast north of Puzzuoli.—If we then pass to the north of Puzzuoli,
and examine the coast between that town and Monte Nuovo, we find a
repetition of analogous phenomena. The sloping sides of Monte Barbaro
slant down within a short distance of the coast, and terminate in an
inland cliff of moderate elevation, to which the geologist perceives at
once that the sea must, at some former period, have extended. Between
this cliff and the sea is a low plain or terrace, called La Starza (c, fig. 89),
corresponding to that before described on the southeast of the town;
and as the sea encroaches rapidly, fresh sections of the strata may readily
be obtained, of which the annexed is an example.
Section on the shore north of the town of Puzzuoli:—


 
Ft.
In.

1. Vegetable soil
1  
0  

2. Horizontal beds of pumice and scoriæ, with broken fragments of
unrolled bricks, bones of animals, and marine shells
1  
6  

3. Beds of lapilli, containing abundance of marine shells, principally
Cardium rusticum, Donax trunculus, Lam.,
Ostrea edulis, Triton cutaceum, Lam., and
Buccinum serratum, Brocchi, the beds varying in thickness
from one to eighteen inches
10  
0  

4. Argillaceous tuff, containing bricks and fragments of buildings
not rounded by attrition.
1  
6  


511
The thickness of many of these beds varies greatly as we trace them
along the shore, and sometimes the whole group rises to a greater height
than at the point above described. The surface of the tract which
they compose appears to slope gently upwards towards the base of the
old cliffs.
Now, if such appearances presented themselves on the coast of England,
a geologist might endeavor to seek an explanation in some local
change in the set of the tides and currents: but there are scarce any
tides in the Mediterranean; and, to suppose the sea to have sunk generally
from twenty to twenty-five feet since the shores of Campania were
covered with sumptuous buildings is an hypothesis obviously untenable.
The observations, indeed, made during modern surveys on the moles
and cothons (docks) constructed by the ancients in various ports of the
Mediterranean, have proved that there has been no sensible variation of
level in that sea during the last two thousand years.715
Thus we arrive, without the aid of the celebrated temple, at the conclusion,
that the recent marine deposit at Puzzuoli was upraised in
modern times above the level of the sea, and that not only this change
of position, but the accumulation of the modern strata, was posterior to
the destruction of many edifices, of which they contain the imbedded
remains. If we next examine the evidence afforded by the temple
itself, it appears, from the most authentic accounts, that the three pillars
now standing erect continued, down to the middle of the last century,
almost buried in the new marine strata (c, fig. 89). The upper part of
each protruding several feet above the surface was concealed by bushes,
and had not attracted, until the year 1749, the notice of antiquaries;
but, when the soil was removed in 1750, they were seen to form part
of the remains of a splendid edifice, the pavement of which was still
preserved, and upon it lay a number of columns of African breccia and
of granite. The original plan of the building could be traced distinctly:
it was of a quadrangular form, seventy feet in diameter, and the roof
had been supported by forty-six noble columns, twenty-four of granite
and the rest of marble. The large court was surrounded by apartments,
supposed to have been used as bathing-rooms; for a thermal
spring, still used for medicinal purposes, issues just behind the building,
and the water of this spring appears to have been originally conveyed
by a marble duct, still extant, into the chambers, and then across the
pavement by a groove an inch or two deep, to a conduit made of Roman
brickwork, by which it gained the sea.
Many antiquaries have entered into elaborate discussions as to the
deity to which this edifice was consecrated. It is admitted that, among
other images found in excavating the ruins, there was one of the god
Serapis; and at Puzzuoli a marble column was dug up, on which was
carved an ancient inscription, of the date of the building of Rome 648
(or B. C. 105), entitled "Lex parieti faciundo." This inscription, written
512
in very obscure Latin, sets forth a contract, between the municipality of
the town, and a company of builders who undertook to keep in repair
certain public edifices, the Temple of Serapis being mentioned amongst
the rest, and described as being near or towards the sea, "mare vorsum."
Sir Edmund Head, after studying, in 1828, the topography and antiquities
of this district, and the Greek, Roman, and Italian writers on the
subject, informed me, that at Alexandria, on the Nile, the chief seat of
the worship of Serapis, there was a Serapeum of the same form as this
temple at Puzzuoli, and surrounded in like manner by chambers, in
which the devotees were accustomed to pass the night, in the hope of
receiving during sleep a revelation from the god, as to the nature and
cure of their diseases. Hence it was very natural that the priests of
Serapis, a pantheistic divinity, who, among other usurpations, had appropriated
to himself the attributes of Esculapius, should regard the
hot spring as a suitable appendage to the temple, although the original
Serapeum of Alexandria could boast no such medicinal waters. Signor
Carelli716 and others, in objecting to these views, have insisted on the
fact, that the worship of Serapis, which we know prevailed at Rome in
the days of Catullus (in the first century before Christ), was prohibited
by the Roman Senate, during the reign of the Emperor Tiberius. But
there is little doubt that, during the reigns of that emperor's successors,
the shrines of the Egyptian god were again thronged by zealous votaries;
and in no place more so than at Puteoli (now Puzzuoli), one of
the principal marts for the produce of Alexandria.
Without entering farther into an inquiry which is not strictly geological,
I shall designate this valuable relic of antiquity by its generally
received name, and proceed to consider the memorials of physical
changes inscribed on the three standing columns in most legible characters
by the hand of Nature. (See Frontispiece.) These pillars, which
have been carved each out of a single block of marble, are forty feet
three inches and a half in height. A horizontal fissure nearly intersects
one of the columns; the other two are entire. They are all
slightly out of the perpendicular, inclining somewhat to the southwest,
that is, towards the sea.717 Their surface is smooth and uninjured to the
height of about twelve feet above their pedestals. Above this is a zone,
about nine feet in height, where the marble has been pierced by a species
of marine perforating bivalve—Lithodomus, Cuv.718 The holes of
these animals are pear-shaped, the external opening being minute, and
gradually increasing downwards. At the bottom of the cavities, many
shells are still found, notwithstanding the great numbers that have been
513
taken out by visitors; in many the valves of a species of arca, an animal
which conceals itself in small hollows, occur. The perforations are
so considerable in depth and size, that they manifest a long-continued
abode of the lithodomi in the columns, for, as the inhabitant grows
older and increases in size, it bores a larger cavity, to correspond with
the increased magnitude of its shell. We must, consequently, infer a
long-continued immersion of the pillars in sea-water, at a time when the
lower part was covered up and protected by marine, fresh-water, and
volcanic strata, afterwards to be described, and by the rubbish of buildings;
the highest part, at the same time, projecting above the waters,
and being consequently weathered, but not materially injured. (See fig.
90, p. 514.)
On the pavement of the temple lie some columns of marble, which are
also perforated in certain parts; one, for example, to the length of eight
feet, while, for the length of four feet, it is uninjured. Several of these
broken columns are eaten into, not only on the exterior, but on the cross
fracture, and, on some of them, other marine animals (serpulæ, &c.) have
fixed themselves.719 All the granite pillars are untouched by lithodomi.
The platform of the temple, which is not perfectly even, was, when I
visited it in 1828, about one foot below high-water mark (for there are
small tides in the bay of Naples); and the sea, which was only one hundred
feet distant, soaked through the intervening soil. The upper part
of the perforations, therefore, were at least twenty-three feet above highwater
mark; and it is clear that the columns must have continued for a
long time in an erect position, immersed in salt water, and then the submerged
portion must have been upraised to the height of about twenty-three
feet above the level of the sea.
By excavations carried on in 1828, below the marble pavement on
which the columns stand, another costly pavement of mosaic was found,
at the depth of about five feet below the upper one (a, b, fig. 90). The
existence of these two pavements, at different levels, clearly implies some
subsidence previously to the building of the more modern temple which
had rendered it necessary to construct the new floor at a higher level.
Fig. 90.
Temple of Serapis at its period of greatest depression.


a b, Ancient mosaic pavement.
e e, Freshwater calcareous deposit.

c c, Dark marine incrustation.
f f, Second filling up.

d d, First filling up, shower of ashes.
A, Stadium.



We have already seen (p. 512) that a temple of Serapis existed long
before the Christian era. The change of level just mentioned must have
taken place some time before the end of the second century, for inscriptions
have been found in the temple, from which we learn that Septimius
Severus adorned its walls with precious marbles, between the years 194
and 211 of our era, and the emperor Alexander Severus displayed the
like munificence between the years 222 and 235.720 From that era there
is an entire dearth of historical information for a period of more than
twelve centuries, except the significant fact that Alaric and his Goths
sacked Puzzuoli in 456, and that Genseric did the like in 545, A. D. Yet
we have fortunately a series of natural archives self-registered during the
514
dark ages, by which many events which occurred in and about the temple
are revealed to us. These natural records consist partly of deposits,
which envelop the pillars below the zone of lithodomous perforations, and
partly of those which surround the outer walls of the temple. Mr.
Babbage, after a minute examination of these, has shown (see p. 507, note)
that incrustations on the walls of the exterior chambers and on the floor
of the building demonstrate that the pavement did not sink down suddenly,
but was depressed by a gradual movement. The sea first entered
the court or atrium and mingled its waters partially with those of the
hot spring. From this brackish medium a dark calcareous precipitate
(c c, fig. 90) was thrown down, which became, in the course of time,
more than two feet thick, including some serpulæ in it. The presence of
these annelids teaches us that the water was salt or brackish. After this
period the temple was filled up with an irregular mass of volcanic tuff
(d d, fig. 90), probably derived from an eruption of the neighboring
crater of the Solfatara, to the height of from five to nine feet above the
pavement. Over this again a purely freshwater deposit of carbonate of
lime (e e, fig. 90) accumulated with an uneven bottom since it necessarily
accommodated itself to the irregular outline of the upper surface of the
volcanic shower before thrown down. The top of the same deposit (a
freshwater limestone) was perfectly even and flat, bespeaking an ancient
water level. It is suggested by Mr. Babbage that this freshwater lake
may have been caused by the fall of ashes which choked up the channel
previously communicating with the sea, so that the hot spring threw
down calcareous matter in the atrium, without any marine intermixture.
To the freshwater limestone succeeded another irregular mass of volcanic
ashes and rubbish (f f, fig. 90), some of it perhaps washed in by the
waves of the sea during a storm, its surface rising to ten or eleven feet
above the pavement. And thus we arrive at the period of greatest
depression expressed in the accompanying diagram, when the lower half
of the pillars were enveloped in the deposits above enumerated, and the
uppermost twenty feet were exposed in the atmosphere, the remaining
or middle portion, about nine feet long, being for years immersed in salt
515
water and drilled by perforating bivalves. After this period other strata,
consisting of showers of volcanic ashes and materials washed in during
storms, covered up the pillars to the height in some places of thirty-five
feet above the pavement. The exact time when these enveloping masses
were heaped up, and how much of them were formed during submergence,
and how much after the re-elevation of the temple, cannot be
made out with certainty.
The period of deep submergence was certainly antecedent to the close
of the fifteenth century. Professor James Forbes721 has reminded us of
a passage in an old Italian writer Loffredo, who says that in 1530, or
fifty years before he wrote, which was in 1580, the sea washed the base
of the hills which rise from the flat land called La Starza, as represented
in fig. 90, so that, to quote his words, "a person might then have fished
from the site of those ruins which are now called the stadium" (A,
fig. 90).
But we know from other evidence that the upward movement had
begun before 1530, for the Canonico Andrea di Jorio cites two authentic
documents in illustration of this point. The first, dated Oct. 1503,
is a deed written in Italian, by which Ferdinand and Isabella grant to
the University of Puzzuoli a portion of land, "where the sea is drying
up" (che va seccando el mare); the second, a document in Latin, dated
May 23, 1511, or nearly eight years after, by which Ferdinand grants
to the city a certain territory around Puzzuoli, where the ground is dried
up from the sea (desiccatum).722
The principal elevation, however, of the low tract unquestionably took
place at the time of the great eruption of Monte Nuovo in 1538. That
event and the earthquakes which preceded it have been already described
(p. 368); and we have seen that two of the eye-witnesses of the
convulsion, Falconi and Giacomo di Toledo, agree in declaring that the
sea abandoned a considerable tract of the shore, so that fish were taken
by the inhabitants; and, among other things, Falconi mentions that he
saw two springs in the newly discovered ruins.
The flat land, when first upraised, must have been more extensive than
now, for the sea encroaches somewhat rapidly, both to the north and
southeast of Puzzuoli. The coast had, when I examined it in 1828, given
way more than a foot in a twelvemonth; and I was assured, by fishermen
in the bay, that it has lost ground near Puzzuoli, to the extent of
thirty feet, within their memory.
It is, moreover, very probable that the land rose to a greater height
at first before it ceased to move upwards, than the level at which it was
observed to stand when the temple was rediscovered in 1749, for we
learn from a memoir, of Niccolini, published in 1838, that since the beginning
of the nineteenth century, the temple of Serapis has subsided
more than two feet. That learned architect visited the ruins frequently,
for the sake of making drawings, in the beginning of the year 1807, and
516
was in the habit of remaining there throughout the day, yet never saw
the pavement overflowed by the sea, except occasionally when the south
wind blew violently. On his return, sixteen years after, to superintend
some excavations ordered by the king of Naples, he found the pavement
covered by sea-water twice every day at high tide, so that he was
obliged to place there a line of stones to stand upon. This induced him
to make a series of observations from Oct. 1822 to July 1838, by which
means he ascertained that the ground had been and was sinking, at the
average rate of about seven millimetres a year, or about one inch in four
years; so that, in 1838, fish were caught every day on that part of the
pavement where, in 1807, there was never a drop of water in calm
weather.723
On inquiring still more recently as to the condition of the temple and
the continuance of the sinking of the ground, I learn from Signor
Scacchi in a letter, dated June 1852, that the downward movement has
ceased for several years, or has at least become almost inappreciable.
During an examination undertaken by him at my request in the summer
of that year (1852), he observed that the rising tide spread first over the
seaward side of the flat surface of the pedestals of each column (confirming
the fact previously noticed by others, that they are out of the
perpendicular); and he also remarked that the water gained unequally
on the base of each pillar, in such a manner as to prove that they have
neither the same amount of inclination, nor lean precisely in the same
direction.
From what was said before (p. 510), we saw that the marine shells
in the strata forming the plain called La Starza, considered separately,
establish the fact of an upheaval of the ground to the height of twenty-three
feet and upwards. The temple proves much more, because it
could not have been built originally under water, and must therefore
first have sunk down twenty feet at least below the waves, to be afterwards
restored to its original position. Yet if such was the order of
events we ought to meet with other independent signs of a like subsidence
round the margin of a bay once so studded with buildings as the
Bay of Baiæ. Accordingly memorials of such submergence are not
wanting. About a mile northwest of the temple of Serapis, and about
500 feet from the shore, are the ruins of a temple of Neptune and others
of a temple of the Nymphs, now underwater. The columns of the
former edifice stand erect in five feet of water, their upper portions just
rising to the surface of the sea. The pedestals are doubtless buried in
the sand or mud; so that, if this part of the bottom of the bay should
hereafter be elevated, the exhumation of these temples might take place
after the manner of that of Serapis. Both these buildings probably participated
in the movement which raised the Starza; but either they were
deeper under water than the temple of Serapis, or they were not raised
517
up again to so great a height. There are also two Roman roads under
water in the bay, one reaching from Puzzuoli to the Lucrine Lake, which
may still be seen, and the other near the castle of Baiæ (No. 8, fig. 88,
p. 509). The ancient mole, too, of Puzzuoli (No. 4, ibid.) before alluded
to, has the water up to a considerable height of the arches; whereas
Brieslak justly observes, it is next to certain that the piers must formerly
have reached the surface before the springing of the arches;724 so that,
although the phenomena before described prove that this mole has been
uplifted ten feet above the level at which it once stood, it is still evident
that it has not yet been restored to its original position.
A modern writer also reminds us, that these effects are not so local
as some would have us to believe; for on the opposite side of the Bay
of Naples, on the Sorrentine coast, which, as well as Puzzuoli, is subject
to earthquakes, a road, with some fragments of Roman buildings,
is covered to some depth by the sea. In the island of Capri, also,
which is situated some way out at sea, in the opening of the Bay of
Naples, one of the palaces of Tiberius is now covered with water.725
That buildings should have been submerged, and afterwards upheaved,
without being entirely reduced to a heap of ruins, will appear
no anomaly, when we recollect that, in the year 1819, when the delta
of the Indus sank down, the houses within the fort of Sindree subsided
beneath the waves without being overthrown. In like manner, in the
year 1692, the buildings round the harbor of Port Royal, in Jamaica,
descended suddenly to the depth of between thirty and fifty feet under
the sea without falling. Even on small portions of land transported to
a distance of a mile down a declivity, tenements, like those near Mileto,
in Calabria, were carried entire. At Valparaiso buildings were left
standing in 1822, when their foundations, together with a long tract of
the Chilian coast, were permanently upraised to the height of several
feet. It is still more easy to conceive that an edifice may escape falling
during the upheaval or subsidence of land, if the walls are supported
on the exterior and interior with a deposit like that which surrounded
and filled to the height of ten or eleven feet the temple of Serapis all
the time it was sinking, and which enveloped it to more than twice
that height when it was rising again to its original level.
We can scarcely avoid the conclusion, as Mr. Babbage has hinted,
"that the action of heat is in some way or other the cause of the phenomena
of the change of level of the temple. Its own hot spring, its
immediate contiguity to the Solfatara, its nearness to the Monte Nuovo,
the hot spring at the baths of Nero (No. 6, fig. 88), on the opposite
side of the Bay of Baiæ; the boiling springs and ancient volcanoes of
Ischia on one side and Vesuvius on the other, are the most prominent
518
of a multitude of facts which point to that conclusion."726 And when
we reflect on the dates of the principal oscillations of level, and the
volcanic history of the country before described (chap. 23), we seem to
discover a connection between each era of upheaval and a local development
of volcanic heat, and again between each era of depression and
the local quiescence or dormant condition of the subterranean igneous
causes. Thus for example, before the Christian era, when so many
vents were in frequent eruption in Ischia, and when Avernus and other
points in the Phlegræan Fields were celebrated for their volcanic aspect
and character, the ground on which the temple stood was several feet
above water. Vesuvius was then regarded as a spent volcano; but
when, after the Christian era, the fires of that mountain were rekindled,
scarcely a single outburst was ever witnessed in Ischia, or around the
Bay of Baiæ. Then the temple was sinking. Vesuvius, at a subsequent
period, became nearly dormant for five centuries preceding the great
outbreak of 1631 (see p. 374), and in that interval the Solfatara was
in eruption A. D. 1198, Ischia in 1302, and Monte Nuovo was formed in
1538. Then the foundations on which the temple stood were rising
again. Lastly, Vesuvius once more became a most active vent, and has
been so ever since, and during the same lapse of time the area of the
temple, so far as we know any thing of its history, has been subsiding.
These phenomena would agree well with the hypothesis, that when
the subterranean heat is on the increase, and when lava is forming
without obtaining an easy vent, like that afforded by a great habitual
chimney, such as Vesuvius, the incumbent surface is uplifted; but when
the heated rocks below are cooling and contracting, and sheets of lava
are slowly consolidating and diminishing in volume, then the incumbent
land subsides.
Signor Niccolini, when he ascertained in 1838 that the relative levels
of the floor of the temple and of the sea were slowly changing from
year to year, embraced the opinion that it was the sea which was rising.
But Signor Capocci successfully controverted this view, appealing to
many appearances which attest the local character of the movements of
the adjoining country, besides the historical fact that in 1538, when
the sea retired permanently 200 yards from the ancient shore at Puzzuoli,
there was no simultaneous retreat of the waters from Naples,
Castelamare, and Ischia.727
Permanence of the ocean's level.—In concluding this subject I may
observe, that the interminable controversies to which the phenomena of
the Bay of Baiæ gave rise, have sprung from an extreme reluctance to
admit that the land, rather than the sea, is subject alternately to rise
and fall. Had it been assumed that the level of the ocean was invariable,
on the ground that no fluctuations have as yet been clearly established,
and that, on the other hand, the continents are inconstant in
519
their level, as has been demonstrated by the most unequivocal proofs
again and again, from the time of Strabo to our own times, the appearances
of the temple at Puzzuoli could never have been regarded as
enigmatical. Even if contemporary accounts had not distinctly attested
the upraising of the coast, this explanation should have been proposed in
the first instance as the most natural, instead of being now adopted
unwillingly when all others have failed.
To the strong prejudices still existing in regard to the mobility of the
land, we may attribute the rarity of such discoveries as have been recently
brought to light in the Bay of Baiæ and the Bay of Conception.
A false theory, it is well known, may render us blind to facts which are
opposed to our prepossessions, or may conceal from us their true import
when we behold them. But it is time that the geologist should, in
some degree, overcome those first and natural impressions, which induced
the poets of old to select the rock as the emblem of firmness—the sea
as the image of inconstancy. Our modern poet, in a more philosophical
spirit, saw in the sea "The image of eternity," and has finely contrasted
the fleeting existence of the successive empires which have flourished and
fallen on the borders of the ocean with its own unchanged stability.


———Their decay
Has dried up realms to deserts:—not so thou,
Unchangeable, save to thy wild wave's play:
Time writes no wrinkle on thine azure brow;
Such as creation's dawn beheld, thou rollest now.
Childe Harold, Canto iv.


</div></body></text></TEI>