<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="103">CHAPTER X.
Transition from the Chemical to the Classificatory
Sciences.
IT is the object and the boast
of chemistry to acquire a knowledge of bodies which is more exact and
constant than any knowledge borrowed from their sensible qualities can
be; since it penetrates into their intimate constitution, and
discloses to us the invariable laws of their composition. But yet it
will be seen, on a little reflection, that such knowledge could not
have any existence, if we were not also attentive to their sensible
qualities.
The whole fabric of chemistry rests, even at the present day, upon
the opposition of acids and bases: an acid was certainly at first
known by its sensible qualities, and how otherwise, even now, do we
perceive its quality? It was a great discovery of modern times that
earths and alkalies have for their bases metals: but what are
metals? or how, except from lustre, hardness, weight, and the
like, do we recognize a body as a metal? And how, except by such
characters, even before its analysis, was it known to be an earth or
an alkali? We must suppose some classification established, before we
can make any advance by experiment or observation.
It is easy to see that all attempts to avoid this difficulty by
referring to processes and analogies, as well as to substances, bring
us back to the same point in a circle of fallacies. If we say that an
acid and alkali are known by combining with each other, we still must
ask, What is the criterion that they have combined? If we say
that the distinctive qualities of metals and earths are, that metals
become earths by oxidation, we must still inquire how we recognize the
process of oxidation? We have seen how important a part
combustion plays in the history of chemical speculation; and we may
usefully form such classes of 306 bodies as combustibles and
supporters of combustion. But even combustion is not
capable of being infallibly known, for it passes by insensible shades
into oxidation. We can find no basis for our reasonings, which does
not assume a classification of obvious facts and qualities.
But any classification of substances on such grounds, appears, at
first sight, to involve us in vagueness, ambiguity, and contradiction.
Do we really take the sensible qualities of an acid as the criterion
of its being an acid?—for instance, its sourness? Prussic acid,
arsenious acid, are not sour. “I remember,” says Dr. Paris,100 “a chemist having been exposed to much
ridicule from speaking of a sweet acid,—why not?” When
Davy had discovered potassium, it was disputed whether it was a metal;
for though its lustre and texture are metallic, it is so light as to
swim on water. And if potassium be allowed to be a metal, is silicium
one, a body which wants the metallic lustre, and is a non-conductor of
electricity? It is clear that, at least, the obvious
application of a classification by physical characters, is attended
with endless perplexity.
100 Life of Davy, i.
263.
But since we cannot even begin our researches without assuming a
classification, and since the forms of such a classification which
first occur, end in apparent confusion, it is clear that we must look
to our philosophy for a solution of this difficulty; and must avoid
the embarrassments and contradictions of casual and unreflective
classification, by obtaining a consistent and philosophical
arrangement. We must employ external characters and analogies in a
connected and systematic manner; we must have Classificatory
Sciences, and these must have a bearing even on Chemistry.
Accordingly, the most philosophical chemists now proceed upon this
principle. “The method which I have followed,” says M. Thenard, in his
Traité de Chimie, published in 1824, “is, to unite in one group
all analogous bodies; and the advantage of this method, which is that
employed by naturalists, is very great, especially in the study of the
metals and their compounds.”101 In this, as
in all good systems of chemistry, which have appeared since the
establishment of the phlogistic theory, combustion, and the analogous
processes, are one great element in the arrangement, while the
difference of metallic and non-metallic, is another element. Thus
Thenard, in the first place, speaks of Oxygen; in the next place, of
the Non-metallic Combustibles, as Hydrogen, Carbon, Sulphur, Chlorine;
and in the next place, of Metals. But the Metals are again divided
into six Sections, with reference, 307 principally, to their facility of
combination with oxygen. Thus, the First Section is the Metals of the
Earths; the Second, the Metals of the Alkalies; the Third, the Easily
Oxidable Metals, as Iron; the Fourth, Metals Less Oxidable, as Copper
and Lead; the Fifth Section contains only Mercury and Osmium; and the
Sixth, what were at an earlier period termed the Noble Metals,
Gold, Silver, Platinum, and others.
101 Pref., p. viii.
How such principles are to be applied, so as to produce a definite
and consistent arrangement, will be explained in speaking of the
philosophy of the Classificatory Sciences; but there are one or two
peculiarities in the classes of bodies thus recognized by modern
chemistry, which it may be useful to notice.
1. The distinction of Metallic and Non-metallic is still employed,
as of fundamental importance. The discovery of new metals is so much
connected with the inquiries concerning chemical elements, that we may
notice the general progress of such discoveries. Gold,
Silver, Iron, Copper, Quicksilver,
Lead, Tin, were known from the earliest antiquity. In
the beginning of the sixteenth century, mine-directors, like George
Agricola, had advanced so far in practical metallurgy, that they had
discovered the means of extracting three additional metals,
Zinc, Bismuth, Antimony. After this, there was no
new metal discovered for a century, and then such discoveries were
made by the theoretical chemists, a race of men who had not existed
before Beccher and Stahl. Thus Arsenic and Cobalt were
made known by Brandt, in the middle of the eighteenth century, and we
have a long list of similar discoveries belonging to the same period;
Nickel, Manganese, and Tungsten, which were
detected by Cronstedt, Gahn, and Scheele, and Delhuyart, respectively;
metals of a very different kind, Tellurium and
Molybdenum, which were brought to light by Müller, Scheele,
Bergman, and Hielm; Platinum, which was known as early as 1741,
but with the ore of which, in 1802 and 1803, the English chemists,
Wollaston and Tennant, found that no less than four other new metals
(Palladium, Rhodium, Iridium and Osmium)
were associated. Finally, (omitting some other new metals,) we have
another period of discovery, opened in 1807, by Davy’s discovery of
Potassium, and including the resolution of all, or almost all,
the alkalies and earths into metallic bases.
[2nd Ed.] [The next few years made some, at least some conjectural,
additions to the list of simple substances, detected by a more minute
scrutiny of known substances. Thorium was discovered by
Berzelius in 1828; and Vanadium by Professor Sefström in 1830.
A 308 metal named
Cerium, was discovered in 1803, by Hisinger and Berzelius, in a
rare Swedish mineral known by the name of Cerit. Mosander more
recently has found combined with Cerium, other new metals which he has
called Lanthanium, Didymium, Erbium, and
Terbium: M. Klaus has found a new metal, Ruthenium, in
the ore of Platinum; and Rose has discovered in Tantalite two other
new metals, which he has announced under the names of Pelopium
and Niobium. Svanberg is said to have discovered a new earth in
Eudialyt, which is supposed to have, like the rest, a new radical. If
these last discoveries be confirmed, the number of simple substances
will be raised to sixty-two.]
2. Attempts have been made to indicate the classification of
chemical substances by some peculiarity in the Name; and the Metals,
for example, have been designated generally by names in um,
like the Latin names of the ancient metals, aurum,
ferrum. This artifice is a convenient nomenclature for the
purpose of marking a recognized difference; and it would be worth the
while of chemists to agree to make it universal, by writing
molybdenum and platinum; which is sometimes done, but
not always.
3. I am not now to attempt to determine how far this
class,—Metals,—extends; but where the analogies of the
class cease to hold there the nomenclature must also change. Thus,
some chemists, as Dr. Thomson, have conceived that the base of Silica
is more analogous to Carbon and Boron, which form acids with oxygen,
than it is to the metals: and he has accordingly associated this base
with these substances, and has given it the same termination,
Silicon. But on the validity of this analogy chemists appear
not to be generally agreed.
4. There is another class of bodies which have attracted much
notice among modern chemists, and which have also been assimilated to
each other in the form of their names; the English writers calling
them Chlorine, Fluorine, Iodine, Bromine,
while the French use the terms Chlore, Phtore,
Iode, Brome. We have already noticed the establishment
of the doctrine—that muriatic acid is formed of a base,
chlorine, and of hydrogen,—as a great reform in the oxygen
theory; with regard to which rival claims were advanced by Davy, and
by MM. Gay-Lussac and Thenard in 1800. Iodine, a remarkable body
which, from a dark powder, is converted into a violet-colored gas by
the application of heat, was also, in 1813, the subject of a similar
rivalry between the same English and French chemists. Bromine 309 was only discovered
as late as 1826; and Fluorine, or Phtore, as, from its
destructive nature, it has been proposed to term it, has not been
obtained as a separate substance, and is inferred to exist by analogy
only. The analogies of these bodies (Chlore, Phtore, &c.) are very
peculiar; for instance, by combination with metals they form salts; by
combination with hydrogen they form very strong acids; and all, at the
common temperature of the atmosphere, operate on other bodies in the
most energetic manner. Berzelius102 proposes to
call them halogenous bodies, or halogenes.
102 Chem. i. 262.
5. The number of Elementary Substances which are at present
presented in our treatises of chemistry103 is
fifty-three, [or rather, as we have said above,
sixty-two.] It is naturally often asked what evidence we
have, that all these are elementary, and what evidence that
they are all the elementary bodies;—how we know that
new elements may not hereafter be discovered, or these supposed simple
bodies resolved into simpler still? To these questions we can only
answer, by referring to the history of chemistry;—by pointing
out what chemists have understood by analysis, according to the
preceding narrative. They have considered, as the analysis of a
substance, that elementary constitution of it which gives the only
intelligible explanation of the results of chemical manipulation, and
which is proved to be complete as to quantity, by the balance, since
the whole can only be equal to all its parts. It is impossible to
maintain that new substances may not hereafter be discovered; for they
may lurk, even in familiar substances, in doses so minute that they
have not yet been missed amid the inevitable slight inaccuracies of
all analysis; in the way in which iodine and bromine remained so long
undetected in sea-water; and new minerals, or old ones not yet
sufficiently examined, can hardly fail to add something to our list.
As to the possibility of a further analysis of our supposed simple
bodies, we may venture to say that, in regard to such supposed simple
bodies as compose a numerous and well-characterized class, no such
step can be made, except through some great change in chemical theory,
which gives us a new view of all the general relations which chemistry
has yet discovered. The proper evidence of the reality of any supposed
new analysis is, that it is more consistent with the known analogies
of chemistry, to suppose the process analytical than synthetical.
Thus, as has already been said, chemists admit the existence of
fluorine, from the analogy of chlorine; and Davy, when it was found
310 that ammonia
formed an amalgam with mercury, was tempted to assign to it a metallic
basis. But then he again hesitates,104 and doubts
whether the analogies of our knowledge are not better preserved by
supposing that ammonia, as a compound of hydrogen and another
principle, is “a type of the composition of the metals.”
103 Turner, p. 971.
104 Elem. Chem. Phil. 1812,
p. 481.
Our history, which is the history of what we know, has little to do
with such conjectures. There are, however, some not unimportant
principles which bear upon them, and which, as they are usually
employed, belong to the science which next comes under our review,
Mineralogy.
~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~


BOOK XV.


THE ANALYTICO-CLASSIFICATORY SCIENCE.

HISTORY OF MINERALOGY.

Κρύσταλλον φαέθοντα διαυγέα λάζεο χερσὶ,
Λᾶαν ἀπόῤῥοιαν περιφεγγέος ἀμβρότου αἴγλης,
Αἰθέρι δ’ ἀθανάτων μέγα τέρπεται ἄφθιτον
ἦτορ.
Τόν κ’ εἴπερ μετὰ χειρὰς ἔχων, περὶ νηὸν
ἵκηαι,
Οὔτις τοι μακάρων ἀρνήσεται εὐχωλῆσι.
Orpheus.
Lithica.

Now, if the bold but pious thought be
thine,
To reach our spacious temple’s inner
shrine,
Take in thy reverent hands the crystal
stone,
Where heavenly light in earthy shroud is
shown:—
Where, moulded into measured form, with
rays
Complex yet clear, the eternal Ether plays;
This if thou firmly hold and rightly use,
Not long the gods thy ardent wish refuse.

</div></body></text></TEI>