<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="10">

CHAPTER I.
OF IDEAS IN GENERAL, AND THEIR ORIGINAL.

1. Idea is the Object of Thinking.


Every man being conscious to himself that he thinks; and that which his mind is
applied about whilst thinking being the IDEAS that are there, it is past doubt
that men have in their minds several ideas,—such as are those expressed
by the words whiteness, hardness, sweetness, thinking, motion, man, elephant,
army, drunkenness, and others: it is in the first place then to be inquired,
HOW HE COMES BY THEM?


I know it is a received doctrine, that men have native ideas, and original
characters, stamped upon their minds in their very first being. This opinion I
have at large examined already; and, I suppose what I have said in the
foregoing Book will be much more easily admitted, when I have shown whence the
understanding may get all the ideas it has; and by what ways and degrees they
may come into the mind;—for which I shall appeal to every one’s own
observation and experience.


2. All Ideas come from Sensation or Reflection.


Let us then suppose the mind to be, as we say, white paper, void of all
characters, without any ideas:—How comes it to be furnished? Whence comes
it by that vast store which the busy and boundless fancy of man has painted on
it with an almost endless variety? Whence has it all the MATERIALS of reason
and knowledge? To this I answer, in one word, from EXPERIENCE. In that all our
knowledge is founded; and from that it ultimately derives itself. Our
observation employed either, about external sensible objects, or about the
internal operations of our minds perceived and reflected on by ourselves, is
that which supplies our understandings with all the MATERIALS of thinking.
These two are the fountains of knowledge, from whence all the ideas we have, or
can naturally have, do spring.


3. The Objects of Sensation one Source of Ideas


First, our Senses, conversant about particular sensible objects, do convey into
the mind several distinct perceptions of things, according to those various
ways wherein those objects do affect them. And thus we come by those IDEAS we
have of yellow, white, heat, cold, soft, hard, bitter, sweet, and all those
which we call sensible qualities; which when I say the senses convey into the
mind, I mean, they from external objects convey into the mind what produces
there those perceptions. This great source of most of the ideas we have,
depending wholly upon our senses, and derived by them to the understanding, I
call SENSATION.


4. The Operations of our Minds, the other Source of them.


Secondly, the other fountain from which experience furnisheth the understanding
with ideas is,—the perception of the operations of our own mind within
us, as it is employed about the ideas it has got;—which operations, when
the soul comes to reflect on and consider, do furnish the understanding with
another set of ideas, which could not be had from things without. And such are
perception, thinking, doubting, believing, reasoning, knowing, willing, and all
the different actings of our own minds;—which we being conscious of, and
observing in ourselves, do from these receive into our understandings as
distinct ideas as we do from bodies affecting our senses. This source of ideas
every man has wholly in himself; and though it be not sense, as having nothing
to do with external objects, yet it is very like it, and might properly enough
be called INTERNAL SENSE. But as I call the other Sensation, so I call this
REFLECTION, the ideas it affords being such only as the mind gets by reflecting
on its own operations within itself. By reflection then, in the following part
of this discourse, I would be understood to mean, that notice which the mind
takes of its own operations, and the manner of them, by reason whereof there
come to be ideas of these operations in the understanding. These two, I say,
viz. external material things, as the objects of SENSATION, and the operations
of our own minds within, as the objects of REFLECTION, are to me the only
originals from whence all our ideas take their beginnings. The term OPERATIONS
here I use in a large sense, as comprehending not barely the actions of the
mind about its ideas, but some sort of passions arising sometimes from them,
such as is the satisfaction or uneasiness arising from any thought.


5. All our Ideas are of the one or of the other of these.


The understanding seems to me not to have the least glimmering of any ideas
which it doth not receive from one of these two. EXTERNAL OBJECTS furnish the
mind with the ideas of sensible qualities, which are all those different
perceptions they produce in us; and THE MIND furnishes the understanding with
ideas of its own operations.


These, when we have taken a full survey of them, and their several modes, and
the compositions made out of them we shall find to contain all our whole stock
of ideas; and that we have nothing in our minds which did not come in one of
these two ways. Let any one examine his own thoughts, and thoroughly search
into his understanding; and then let him tell me, whether all the original
ideas he has there, are any other than of the objects of his senses, or of the
operations of his mind, considered as objects of his reflection. And how great
a mass of knowledge soever he imagines to be lodged there, he will, upon taking
a strict view, see that he has not any idea in his mind but what one of these
two have imprinted;—though perhaps, with infinite variety compounded and
enlarged by the understanding, as we shall see hereafter.


6. Observable in Children.


He that attentively considers the state of a child, at his first coming into
the world, will have little reason to think him stored with plenty of ideas,
that are to be the matter of his future knowledge. It is BY DEGREES he comes to
be furnished with them. And though the ideas of obvious and familiar qualities
imprint themselves before the memory begins to keep a register of time or
order, yet it is often so late before some unusual qualities come in the way,
that there are few men that cannot recollect the beginning of their
acquaintance with them. And if it were worth while, no doubt a child might be
so ordered as to have but a very few, even of the ordinary ideas, till he were
grown up to a man. But all that are born into the world, being surrounded with
bodies that perpetually and diversely affect them, variety of ideas, whether
care be taken of it or not, are imprinted on the minds of children. Light and
colours are busy at hand everywhere, when the eye is but open; sounds and some
tangible qualities fail not to solicit their proper senses, and force an
entrance to the mind;—but yet, I think, it will be granted easily, that
if a child were kept in a place where he never saw any other but black and
white till he were a man, he would have no more ideas of scarlet or green, than
he that from his childhood never tasted an oyster, or a pine-apple, has of
those particular relishes.


7. Men are differently furnished with these, according to the different Objects
they converse with.


Men then come to be furnished with fewer or more simple ideas from without,
according as the objects they converse with afford greater or less variety; and
from the operations of their minds within, according as they more or less
reflect on them. For, though he that contemplates the operations of his mind,
cannot but have plain and clear ideas of them; yet, unless he turn his thoughts
that way, and considers them ATTENTIVELY, he will no more have clear and
distinct ideas of all the operations of his mind, and all that may be observed
therein, than he will have all the particular ideas of any landscape, or of the
parts and motions of a clock, who will not turn his eyes to it, and with
attention heed all the parts of it. The picture, or clock may be so placed,
that they may come in his way every day; but yet he will have but a confused
idea of all the parts they are made up of, till he applies himself with
attention, to consider them each in particular.


8. Ideas of Reflection later, because they need Attention.


And hence we see the reason why it is pretty late before most children get
ideas of the operations of their own minds; and some have not any very clear or
perfect ideas of the greatest part of them all their lives. Because, though
they pass there continually, yet, like floating visions, they make not deep
impressions enough to leave in their mind clear, distinct, lasting ideas, till
the understanding turns inward upon itself, reflects on its own operations, and
makes them the objects of its own contemplation. Children when they come first
into it, are surrounded with a world of new things which, by a constant
solicitation of their senses, draw the mind constantly to them; forward to take
notice of new, and apt to be delighted with the variety of changing objects.
Thus the first years are usually employed and diverted in looking abroad. Men’s
business in them is to acquaint themselves with what is to be found without;
and so growing up in a constant attention to outward sensations, seldom make
any considerable reflection on what passes within them, till they come to be of
riper years; and some scarce ever at all.


9. The Soul begins to have Ideas when it begins to perceive.


To ask, at what TIME a man has first any ideas, is to ask, when he begins to
perceive;—HAVING IDEAS, and PERCEPTION, being the same thing. I know it
is an opinion, that the soul always thinks, and that it has the actual
perception of ideas in itself constantly, as long as it exists; and that actual
thinking is as inseparable from the soul as actual extension is from the body;
which if true, to inquire after the beginning of a man’s ideas is the same as
to inquire after the beginning of his soul. For, by this account, soul and its
ideas, as body and its extension, will begin to exist both at the same time.


10. The Soul thinks not always; for this wants Proofs.


But whether the soul be supposed to exist antecedent to, or coeval with, or
some time after the first rudiments of organization, or the beginnings of life
in the body, I leave to be disputed by those who have better thought of that
matter. I confess myself to have one of those dull souls, that doth not
perceive itself always to contemplate ideas; nor can conceive it any more
necessary for the soul always to think, than for the body always to move: the
perception of ideas being (as I conceive) to the soul, what motion is to the
body; not its essence, but one of its operations. And therefore, though
thinking be supposed never so much the proper action of the soul, yet it is not
necessary to suppose that it should be always thinking, always in action. That,
perhaps, is the privilege of the infinite Author and Preserver of all things,
who “never slumbers nor sleeps”; but is not competent to any finite being, at
least not to the soul of man. We know certainly, by experience, that we
SOMETIMES think; and thence draw this infallible consequence,—that there
is something in us that has a power to think. But whether that substance
PERPETUALLY thinks or no, we can be no further assured than experience informs
us. For, to say that actual thinking is essential to the soul, and inseparable
from it, is to beg what is in question, and not to prove it by
reason;—which is necessary to be done, if it be not a self-evident
proposition. But whether this, “That the soul always thinks,” be a self-evident
proposition, that everybody assents to at first hearing, I appeal to mankind.
It is doubted whether I thought at all last night or no. The question being
about a matter of fact, it is begging it to bring, as a proof for it, an
hypothesis, which is the very thing in dispute: by which way one may prove
anything, and it is but supposing that all watches, whilst the balance beats,
think, and it is sufficiently proved, and past doubt, that my watch thought all
last night. But he that would not deceive himself, ought to build his
hypothesis on matter of fact, and make it out by sensible experience, and not
presume on matter of fact, because of his hypothesis, that is, because he
supposes it to be so; which way of proving amounts to this, that I must
necessarily think all last night, because another supposes I always think,
though I myself cannot perceive that I always do so.


But men in love with their opinions may not only suppose what is in question,
but allege wrong matter of fact. How else could any one make it an inference of
mine, that a thing is not, because we are not sensible of it in our sleep? I do
not say there is no SOUL in a man, because he is not sensible of it in his
sleep; but I do say, he cannot THINK at any time, waking or sleeping, without
being sensible of it. Our being sensible of it is not necessary to anything but
to our thoughts; and to them it is; and to them it always will be necessary,
till we can think without being conscious of it.


11. It is not always conscious of it.


I grant that the soul, in a waking man, is never without thought, because it is
the condition of being awake. But whether sleeping without dreaming be not an
affection of the whole man, mind as well as body, may be worth a waking man’s
consideration; it being hard to conceive that anything should think and not be
conscious of it. If the soul doth think in a sleeping man without being
conscious of it, I ask whether, during such thinking, it has any pleasure or
pain, or be capable of happiness or misery? I am sure the man is not; no more
than the bed or earth he lies on. For to be happy or miserable without being
conscious of it, seems to me utterly inconsistent and impossible. Or if it be
possible that the SOUL can, whilst the body is sleeping, have its thinking,
enjoyments, and concerns, its pleasures or pain, apart, which the MAN is not
conscious of nor partakes in,—it is certain that Socrates asleep and
Socrates awake is not the same person; but his soul when he sleeps, and
Socrates the man, consisting of body and soul, when he is waking, are two
persons: since waking Socrates has no knowledge of, or concernment for that
happiness or misery of his soul, which it enjoys alone by itself whilst he
sleeps, without perceiving anything of it; no more than he has for the
happiness or misery of a man in the Indies, whom he knows not. For, if we take
wholly away all consciousness of our actions and sensations, especially of
pleasure and pain, and the concernment that accompanies it, it will be hard to
know wherein to place personal identity.


12. If a sleeping Man thinks without knowing it, the sleeping and waking Man
are two Persons.


The soul, during sound sleep, thinks, say these men. Whilst it thinks and
perceives, it is capable certainly of those of delight or trouble, as well as
any other perceptions; and IT must necessarily be CONSCIOUS of its own
perceptions. But it has all this apart: the sleeping MAN, it is plain, is
conscious of nothing of all this. Let us suppose, then, the soul of Castor,
while he is sleeping, retired from his body; which is no impossible supposition
for the men I have here to do with, who so liberally allow life, without a
thinking soul, to all other animals. These men cannot then judge it impossible,
or a contradiction, that the body should live without the soul; nor that the
soul should subsist and think, or have perception, even perception of happiness
or misery, without the body. Let us then, I say, suppose the soul of Castor
separated during his sleep from his body, to think apart. Let us suppose, too,
that it chooses for its scene of thinking the body of another man, v. g.
Pollux, who is sleeping without a soul. For, if Castor’s soul can think, whilst
Castor is asleep, what Castor is never conscious of, it is no matter what PLACE
it chooses to think in. We have here, then, the bodies of two men with only one
soul between them, which we will suppose to sleep and wake by turns; and the
soul still thinking in the waking man, whereof the sleeping man is never
conscious, has never the least perception. I ask, then, whether Castor and
Pollux, thus with only one soul between them, which thinks and perceives in one
what the other is never conscious of, nor is concerned for, are not two as
distinct PERSONS as Castor and Hercules, or as Socrates and Plato were? And
whether one of them might not be very happy, and the other very miserable? Just
by the same reason, they make the soul and the man two persons, who make the
soul think apart what the man is not conscious of. For, I suppose nobody will
make identity of persons to consist in the soul’s being united to the very same
numerical particles of matter. For if that be necessary to identity, it will be
impossible, in that constant flux of the particles of our bodies, that any man
should be the same person two days, or two moments, together.


13. Impossible to convince those that sleep without dreaming, that they think.


Thus, methinks, every drowsy nod shakes their doctrine, who teach that the soul
is always thinking. Those, at least, who do at any time SLEEP WITHOUT DREAMING,
can never be convinced that their thoughts are sometimes for four hours busy
without their knowing of it; and if they are taken in the very act, waked in
the middle of that sleeping contemplation, can give no manner of account of it.


14. That men dream without remembering it, in vain urged.


It will perhaps be said,—That the soul thinks even in the soundest sleep,
but the MEMORY retains it not. That the soul in a sleeping man should be this
moment busy a thinking, and the next moment in a waking man not remember nor be
able to recollect one jot of all those thoughts, is very hard to be conceived,
and would need some better proof than bare assertion to make it be believed.
For who can without any more ado, but being barely told so, imagine that the
greatest part of men do, during all their lives, for several hours every day,
think of something, which if they were asked, even in the middle of these
thoughts, they could remember nothing at all of? Most men, I think, pass a
great part of their sleep without dreaming. I once knew a man that was bred a
scholar, and had no bad memory, who told me he had never dreamed in his life,
till he had that fever he was then newly recovered of, which was about the five
or six and twentieth year of his age. I suppose the world affords more such
instances: at least every one’s acquaintance will furnish him with examples
enough of such as pass most of their nights without dreaming.


15. Upon this Hypothesis, the Thoughts of a sleeping Man ought to be most
rational.


To think often, and never to retain it so much as one moment, is a very useless
sort of thinking; and the soul, in such a state of thinking, does very little,
if at all, excel that of a looking-glass, which constantly receives variety of
images, or ideas, but retains none; they disappear and vanish, and there remain
no footsteps of them; the looking-glass is never the better for such ideas, nor
the soul for such thoughts. Perhaps it will be said, that in a waking MAN the
materials of the body are employed, and made use of, in thinking; and that the
memory of thoughts is retained by the impressions that are made on the brain,
and the traces there left after such thinking; but that in the thinking of the
SOUL, which is not perceived in a sleeping man, there the soul thinks apart,
and making no use of the organs of the body, leaves no impressions on it, and
consequently no memory of such thoughts. Not to mention again the absurdity of
two distinct persons, which follows from this supposition, I answer,
further,—That whatever ideas the mind can receive and contemplate without
the help of the body, it is reasonable to conclude it can retain without the
help of the body too; or else the soul, or any separate spirit, will have but
little advantage by thinking. If it has no memory of its own thoughts; if it
cannot lay them up for its own use, and be able to recall them upon occasion;
if it cannot reflect upon what is past, and make use of its former experiences,
reasonings, and contemplations, to what purpose does it think? They who make
the soul a thinking thing, at this rate, will not make it a much more noble
being than those do whom they condemn, for allowing it to be nothing but the
subtilist parts of matter. Characters drawn on dust, that the first breath of
wind effaces; or impressions made on a heap of atoms, or animal spirits, are
altogether as useful, and render the subject as noble, as the thoughts of a
soul that perish in thinking; that, once out of sight, are gone for ever, and
leave no memory of themselves behind them. Nature never makes excellent things
for mean or no uses: and it is hardly to be conceived that our infinitely wise
Creator should make so admirable a faculty as the power of thinking, that
faculty which comes nearest the excellency of his own incomprehensible being,
to be so idly and uselessly employed, at least a fourth part of its time here,
as to think constantly, without remembering any of those thoughts, without
doing any good to itself or others, or being any way useful to any other part
of the creation. If we will examine it, we shall not find, I suppose, the
motion of dull and senseless matter, any where in the universe, made so little
use of and so wholly thrown away.


16. On this Hypothesis, the Soul must have Ideas not derived from Sensation or
Reflection, of which there is no Appearance.


It is true, we have sometimes instances of perception whilst we are asleep, and
retain the memory of those thoughts: but how extravagant and incoherent for the
most part they are; how little conformable to the perfection and order of a
rational being, those who are acquainted with dreams need not be told. This I
would willingly be satisfied in,—whether the soul, when it thinks thus
apart, and as it were separate from the body, acts less rationally than when
conjointly with it, or no. If its separate thoughts be less rational, then
these men must say, that the soul owes the perfection of rational thinking to
the body: if it does not, it is a wonder that our dreams should be, for the
most part, so frivolous and irrational; and that the soul should retain none of
its more rational soliloquies and meditations.


17. If I think when I know it not, nobody else can know it.


Those who so confidently tell us that the soul always actually thinks, I would
they would also tell us, what those ideas are that are in the soul of a child,
before or just at the union with the body, before it hath received any by
sensation. The dreams of sleeping men are, as I take it, all made up of the
waking man’s ideas; though for the most part oddly put together. It is strange,
if the soul has ideas of its own that it derived not from sensation or
reflection, (as it must have, if it thought before it received any impressions
from the body,) that it should never, in its private thinking, (so private,
that the man himself perceives it not,) retain any of them the very moment it
wakes out of them, and then make the man glad with new discoveries. Who can
find it reason that the soul should, in its retirement during sleep, have so
many hours’ thoughts, and yet never light on any of those ideas it borrowed not
from sensation or reflection; or at least preserve the memory of none but such,
which, being occasioned from the body, must needs be less natural to a spirit?
It is strange the soul should never once in a man’s whole life recall over any
of its pure native thoughts, and those ideas it had before it borrowed anything
from the body; never bring into the waking man’s view any other ideas but what
have a tang of the cask, and manifestly derive their original from that union.
If it always thinks, and so had ideas before it was united, or before it
received any from the body, it is not to be supposed but that during sleep it
recollects its native ideas; and during that retirement from communicating with
the body, whilst it thinks by itself, the ideas it is busied about should be,
sometimes at least, those more natural and congenial ones which it had in
itself, underived from the body, or its own operations about them: which, since
the waking man never remembers, we must from this hypothesis conclude either
that the soul remembers something that the man does not; or else that memory
belongs only to such ideas as are derived from the body, or the mind’s
operations about them.


18. How knows any one that the Soul always thinks? For if it be not a
self-evident Proposition, it needs Proof.


I would be glad also to learn from these men who so confidently pronounce that
the human soul, or, which is all one, that a man always thinks, how they come
to know it; nay, how they come to know that they themselves think, when they
themselves do not perceive it. This, I am afraid, is to be sure without proofs,
and to know without perceiving. It is, I suspect, a confused notion, taken up
to serve an hypothesis; and none of those clear truths, that either their own
evidence forces us to admit, or common experience makes it impudence to deny.
For the most that can be said of it is, that it is possible the soul may always
think, but not always retain it in memory. And I say, it is as possible that
the soul may not always think; and much more probable that it should sometimes
not think, than that it should often think, and that a long while together, and
not be conscious to itself, the next moment after, that it had thought.


19. That a Man should be busy in Thinking, and yet not retain it the next
moment, very improbable.


To suppose the soul to think, and the man not to perceive it, is, as has been
said, to make two persons in one man. And if one considers well these men’s way
of speaking, one should be led into a suspicion that they do so. For those who
tell us that the SOUL always thinks, do never, that I remember, say that a MAN
always thinks. Can the soul think, and not the man? Or a man think, and not be
conscious of it? This, perhaps, would be suspected of jargon in others. If they
say the man thinks always, but is not always conscious of it, they may as well
say his body is extended without having parts. For it is altogether as
intelligible to say that a body is extended without parts, as that anything
thinks without being conscious of it, or perceiving that it does so. They who
talk thus may, with as much reason, if it be necessary to their hypothesis, say
that a man is always hungry, but that he does not always feel it; whereas
hunger consists in that very sensation, as thinking consists in being conscious
that one thinks. If they say that a man is always conscious to himself of
thinking, I ask, How they know it? Consciousness is the perception of what
passes in a man’s own mind. Can another man perceive that I am conscious of
anything, when I perceive it not myself? No man’s knowledge here can go beyond
his experience. Wake a man out of a sound sleep, and ask him what he was that
moment thinking of. If he himself be conscious of nothing he then thought on,
he must be a notable diviner of thoughts that can assure him that he was
thinking. May he not, with more reason, assure him he was not asleep? This is
something beyond philosophy; and it cannot be less than revelation, that
discovers to another thoughts in my mind, when I can find none there myself.
And they must needs have a penetrating sight who can certainly see that I
think, when I cannot perceive it myself, and when I declare that I do not; and
yet can see that dogs or elephants do not think, when they give all the
demonstration of it imaginable, except only telling us that they do so. This
some may suspect to be a step beyond the Rosicrucians; it seeming easier to
make one’s self invisible to others, than to make another’s thoughts visible to
me, which are not visible to himself. But it is but defining the soul to be “a
substance that always thinks,” and the business is done. If such definition be
of any authority, I know not what it can serve for but to make many men suspect
that they have no souls at all; since they find a good part of their lives pass
away without thinking. For no definitions that I know, no suppositions of any
sect, are of force enough to destroy constant experience; and perhaps it is the
affectation of knowing beyond what we perceive, that makes so much useless
dispute and noise in the world.


20. No ideas but from Sensation and Reflection, evident, if we observe
Children.


I see no reason, therefore, to believe that the soul thinks before the senses
have furnished it with ideas to think on; and as those are increased and
retained, so it comes, by exercise, to improve its faculty of thinking in the
several parts of it; as well as, afterwards, by compounding those ideas, and
reflecting on its own operations, it increases its stock, as well as facility
in remembering, imagining, reasoning, and other modes of thinking.


21. State of a child in the mother’s womb.


He that will suffer himself to be informed by observation and experience, and
not make his own hypothesis the rule of nature, will find few signs of a soul
accustomed to much thinking in a new-born child, and much fewer of any
reasoning at all. And yet it is hard to imagine that the rational soul should
think so much, and not reason at all. And he that will consider that infants
newly come into the world spend the greatest part of their time in sleep, and
are seldom awake but when either hunger calls for the teat, or some pain (the
most importunate of all sensations), or some other violent impression on the
body, forces the mind to perceive and attend to it;—he, I say, who
considers this, will perhaps find reason to imagine that a Fœtus in the
mother’s womb differs not much from the state of a vegetable, but passes the
greatest part of its time without perception or thought; doing very little but
sleep in a place where it needs not seek for food, and is surrounded with
liquor, always equally soft, and near of the same temper; where the eyes have
no light, and the ears so shut up are not very susceptible of sounds; and where
there is little or no variety, or change of objects, to move the senses.


22. The mind thinks in proportion to the matter it gets from experience to
think about.


Follow a child from its birth, and observe the alterations that time makes, and
you shall find, as the mind by the senses comes more and more to be furnished
with ideas, it comes to be more and more awake; thinks more, the more it has
matter to think on. After some time it begins to know the objects which, being
most familiar with it, have made lasting impressions. Thus it comes by degrees
to know the persons it daily converses with, and distinguishes them from
strangers; which are instances and effects of its coming to retain and
distinguish the ideas the senses convey to it. And so we may observe how the
mind, BY DEGREES, improves in these; and ADVANCES to the exercise of those
other faculties of enlarging, compounding, and abstracting its ideas, and of
reasoning about them, and reflecting upon all these; of which I shall have
occasion to speak more hereafter.


23. A man begins to have ideas when he first has sensation. What sensation is.


If it shall be demanded then, WHEN a man BEGINS to have any ideas, I think the
true answer is,—WHEN HE FIRST HAS ANY SENSATION. For, since there appear
not to be any ideas in the mind before the senses have conveyed any in, I
conceive that ideas in the understanding are coeval with SENSATION; WHICH IS
SUCH AN IMPRESSION OR MOTION MADE IN SOME PART OF THE BODY, AS MAKES IT BE
TAKEN NOTICE OF IN THE UNDERSTANDING.


24. The Original of all our Knowledge.


The impressions then that are made on our sense by outward objects that are
extrinsical to the mind; and its own operations about these impressions,
reflected on by itself, as proper objects to be contemplated by it, are, I
conceive, the original of all knowledge. Thus the first capacity of human
intellect is,—that the mind is fitted to receive the impressions made on
it; either through the senses by outward objects, or by its own operations when
it reflects on them. This is the first step a man makes towards the discovery
of anything, and the groundwork whereon to build all those notions which ever
he shall have naturally in this world. All those sublime thoughts which tower
above the clouds, and reach as high as heaven itself, take their rise and
footing here: in all that great extent wherein the mind wanders, in those
remote speculations it may seem to be elevated with, it stirs not one jot
beyond those ideas which SENSE or REFLECTION have offered for its
contemplation.


25. In the Reception of simple Ideas, the Understanding is for the most part
passive.


In this part the understanding is merely passive; and whether or no it will
have these beginnings, and as it were materials of knowledge, is not in its own
power. For the objects of our senses do, many of them, obtrude their particular
ideas upon our minds whether we will or not; and the operations of our minds
will not let us be without, at least, some obscure notions of them. No man can
be wholly ignorant of what he does when he thinks. These simple ideas, when
offered to the mind, the understanding can no more refuse to have, nor alter
when they are imprinted, nor blot them out and make new ones itself, than a
mirror can refuse, alter, or obliterate the images or ideas which the objects
set before it do therein produce. As the bodies that surround us do diversely
affect our organs, the mind is forced to receive the impressions; and cannot
avoid the perception of those ideas that are annexed to them.


</div></body></text></TEI>