<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="28">

CHAPTER XIX.
OF THE MODES OF THINKING.

1. Sensation, Remembrance, Contemplation, &c., modes of thinking.


When the mind turns its view inwards upon itself, and contemplates its own
actions, THINKING is the first that occurs. In it the mind observes a great
variety of modifications, and from thence receives distinct ideas. Thus the
perception or thought which actually accompanies, and is annexed to, any
impression on the body, made by an external object, being distinct from all
other modifications of thinking, furnishes the mind with a distinct idea, which
we call SENSATION;—which is, as it were, the actual entrance of any idea
into the understanding by the senses. The same idea, when it again recurs
without the operation of the like object on the external sensory, is
REMEMBRANCE: if it be sought after by the mind, and with pain and endeavour
found, and brought again in view, it is RECOLLECTION: if it be held there long
under attentive consideration, it is CONTEMPLATION: when ideas float in our
mind without any reflection or regard of the understanding, it is that which
the French call REVERIE; our language has scarce a name for it: when the ideas
that offer themselves (for, as I have observed in another place, whilst we are
awake, there will always be a train of ideas succeeding one another in our
minds) are taken notice of, and, as it were, registered in the memory, it is
ATTENTION: when the mind with great earnestness, and of choice, fixes its view
on any idea, considers it on all sides, and will not be called off by the
ordinary solicitation of other ideas, it is that we call INTENTION or STUDY:
sleep, without dreaming, is rest from all these: and DREAMING itself is the
having of ideas (whilst the outward senses are stopped, so that they receive
not outward objects with their usual quickness) in the mind, not suggested by
any external objects, or known occasion; nor under any choice or conduct of the
understanding at all: and whether that which we call ECSTASY be not dreaming
with the eyes open, I leave to be examined.


2. Other modes of thinking.


These are some few instances of those various modes of thinking, which the mind
may observe in itself, and so have as distinct ideas of as it hath of white and
red, a square or a circle. I do not pretend to enumerate them all, nor to treat
at large of this set of ideas, which are got from reflection: that would be to
make a volume. It suffices to my present purpose to have shown here, by some
few examples, of what sort these ideas are, and how the mind comes by them;
especially since I shall have occasion hereafter to treat more at large of
REASONING, JUDGING, VOLITION, and KNOWLEDGE, which are some of the most
considerable operations of the mind, and modes of thinking.


3. The various degrees of Attention in thinking.


But perhaps it may not be an unpardonable digression, nor wholly impertinent to
our present design, if we reflect here upon the different state of the mind in
thinking, which those instances of attention, reverie, and dreaming, &c.,
before mentioned, naturally enough suggest. That there are ideas, some or
other, always present in the mind of a waking man, every one’s experience
convinces him; though the mind employs itself about them with several degrees
of attention. Sometimes the mind fixes itself with so much earnestness on the
contemplation of some objects, that it turns their ideas on all sides; marks
their relations and circumstances; and views every part so nicely and with such
intention, that it shuts out all other thoughts, and takes no notice of the
ordinary impressions made then on the senses, which at another season would
produce very sensible perceptions: at other times it barely observes the train
of ideas that succeed in the understanding, without directing and pursuing any
of them: and at other times it lets them pass almost quite unregarded, as faint
shadows that make no impression.


4. Hence it is probable that Thinking is the Action, not the Essence of the
Soul.


This difference of intention, and remission of the mind in thinking, with a
great variety of degrees between earnest study and very near minding nothing at
all, every one, I think, has experimented in himself. Trace it a little
further, and you find the mind in sleep retired as it were from the senses, and
out of the reach of those motions made on the organs of sense, which at other
times produce very vivid and sensible ideas. I need not, for this, instance in
those who sleep out whole stormy nights, without hearing the thunder, or seeing
the lightning, or feeling the shaking of the house, which are sensible enough
to those who are waking. But in this retirement of the mind from the senses, it
often retains a yet more loose and incoherent manner of thinking, which we call
dreaming. And, last of all, sound sleep closes the scene quite, and puts an end
to all appearances. This, I think almost every one has experience of in
himself, and his own observation without difficulty leads him thus far. That
which I would further conclude from hence is, that since the mind can sensibly
put on, at several times, several degrees of thinking, and be sometimes, even
in a waking man, so remiss, as to have thoughts dim and obscure to that degree
that they are very little removed from none at all; and at last, in the dark
retirements of sound sleep, loses the sight perfectly of all ideas whatsoever:
since, I say, this is evidently so in matter of fact and constant experience, I
ask whether it be not probable, that thinking is the action and not the essence
of the soul? Since the operations of agents will easily admit of intention and
remission: but the essences of things are not conceived capable of any such
variation. But this by the by.


</div></body></text></TEI>