<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="71">CHAPTER X.
Prelude to the Epoch of Young and
Fresnel.
BY Physical Optics we
mean, as has already been stated, the theories which explain optical
phenomena on mechanical principles. No such explanation could be given
till true mechanical principles had been obtained; and, accordingly,
we must date the commencement of the essays towards physical optics
from Descartes, the founder of the modern mechanical philosophy. His
hypothesis concerning light is, that it consists of small particles
emitted by the luminous body. He compares these particles to balls,
and endeavors to explain, by means of this comparison, the laws of
reflection and refraction.62 In order to account for the production
of colors by refraction, he ascribes to these balls an alternating
rotatory motion.63 This form of the emission
theory, was, like most of the physical speculations of its author,
hasty and gratuitous; but was extensively accepted, like the rest of
the Cartesian doctrines, in consequence of the love which men have for
sweeping and simple dogmas, and deductive reasonings from them. In a
short time, however, the rival optical theory of undulations
made its appearance. Hooke in his Micrographia (1664) propounds
it, upon occasion of his observations, already noticed, (chap. vii.,) on the colors of thin plates. He there
asserts64 light to consist in a “quick, short,
vibrating motion,” and that it is propagated in a homogeneous medium,
in such a way that “every pulse or vibration of the luminous body will
generate a sphere, which will continually increase and grow bigger,
just after the same manner (though indefinitely swifter) as the waves
or rings on the surface of water do swell into bigger and bigger
circles about a point in it.”65 He applies this
to the explanation of refraction, 86 by supposing that the rays in a denser
medium move more easily, and hence that the pulses become oblique; a
far less satisfactory and consistent hypothesis than that of Huyghens,
of which we shall next have to speak. But Hooke has the merit of
having also combined with his theory, though somewhat obscurely, the
Principle of Interferences, in the application which he makes
of it to the colors of thin plates. Thus66 he supposes the
light to be reflected at the first surface of such plates; and he
adds, “after two refractions and one reflection (from the second
surface) there is propagated a kind of fainter ray,” which comes
behind the other reflected pulse; “so that hereby (the surfaces ab and ef being so near
together that the eye cannot discriminate them from one), this
compound or duplicated pulse does produce on the retina the sensation
of a yellow.” The reason for the production of this particular color,
in the case of which he here speaks, depends on his views concerning
the kind of pulses appropriate to each color; and, for the same
reason, when the thickness is different, he finds that the result will
be a red or a green. This is a very remarkable anticipation of the
explanation ultimately given of these colors; and we may observe that
if Hooke could have measured the thickness of his thin plates, he
could hardly have avoided making considerable progress in the doctrine
of interferences.
62 Diopt. c. ii. 4.
63 Meteor. c. viii. 6.
64 Micrographia, p. 56.
65 Micrographia, p. 57.
66 Micrographia, p. 66.
But the person who is generally, and with justice, looked upon as
the great author of the undulatory theory, at the period now under
notice, is Huyghens, whose Traité de la Lumière, containing a
developement of his theory, was written in 1678, though not published
till 1690. In this work he maintained, as Hooke had done, that light
consists in undulations, and expands itself spherically, nearly in the
same manner as sound does; and he referred to the observations of
Römer on Jupiter’s satellites, both to prove that this difference
takes place successively, and to show its exceeding swiftness. In
order to trace the effect of an undulation, Huyghens considers that
every point of a wave diffuses its motion in all directions; and hence
he draws the conclusion, so long looked upon as the turning-point of
the combat between the rival theories, that the light will not be
diffused beyond the rectilinear space, when it passes through
an aperture; “for,” says he,67 “although the
partial waves, produced by the particles comprised in the
aperture, do diffuse themselves beyond the rectilinear space, these
waves do not concur anywhere except in front of the 87 aperture.” He rightly
considers this observation as of the most essential value. “This,” he
says, “was not known by those who began to consider the waves of
light, among whom are Mr. Hooke in his Micrography, and Father
Pardies; who, in a treatise of which he showed me a part, and which he
did not live to finish, had undertaken to prove, by these waves, the
effects of reflection and refraction. But the principal foundation,
which consists in the remark I have just made, was wanting in his
demonstrations.”
67 Tracts on Optics, p.
209.
By the help of this view, Huyghens gave a perfectly satisfactory
and correct explanation of the laws of reflection and refraction; and
he also applied the same theory, as we have seen, to the double
refraction of Iceland spar with great sagacity and success. He
conceived that in this crystal, besides the spherical waves, there
might be others of a spheroidal form, the axis of the spheroid being
symmetrically disposed with regard to the faces of the rhombohedron,
for to these faces the optical phenomena are symmetrically related. He
found68 that the position of the refracted ray,
determined by such spheroidal undulations, would give an oblique
refraction, which would coincide in its laws with the refraction
observed in Iceland spar; and, as we have stated, this coincidence was long after fully
confirmed by other observers.
68 Tracts on Optics, 237.
Since Huyghens, at this early period, expounded the undulatory
theory with so much distinctness, and applied it with so much skill,
it may be asked why we do not hold him up as the great Author of the
induction of undulations of light;—the person who marks the
epoch of the theory? To this we reply, that though Huyghens discovered
strong presumptions in favor of the undulatory theory, it was not
established till a later era, when the fringes of shadows,
rightly understood, made the waves visible, and when the hypothesis
which had been assumed to account for double refraction, was found to
contain also an explanation of polarization. It is then that
this theory of light assumes its commanding form; and the persons who
gave it this form, we must make the great names of our narrative;
without, however, denying the genius and merit of Huyghens, who is,
undoubtedly, the leading character in the prelude to the
discovery.
The undulatory theory, from this time to our own,
was unfortunate in its career. It was by no means destitute of
defenders, but these were not experimenters; and none of them thought
of applying it to 88
Grimaldi’s experiments on fringes, of which we have spoken a little while ago. And the great
authority of the period, Newton, adopted the opposite hypothesis, that
of emission, and gave it a currency among his followers which kept
down the sounder theory for above a century.
Newton’s first disposition appears to have been by no means averse
to the assumption of an ether as the vehicle of luminiferous
undulations. When Hooke brought against his prismatic analysis of
light some objections, founded on his own hypothetical notions,
Newton, in his reply, said,69 “The hypothesis has a much greater
affinity with his own hypothesis than he seems to be aware of; the
vibrations of the ether being as useful and necessary in this as in
his.” This was in 1672; and we might produce, from Newton’s writing,
passages of the same kind, of a much later date. Indeed it would seem
that, to the last, Newton considered the assumption of an ether as
highly probable, and its vibrations important parts of the phenomena
of light; but he also introduced into his system the hypothesis of
emission, and having followed this hypothesis into mathematical
detail, while he has left all that concerns the ether in the form of
queries and conjectures, the emission theory has naturally been
treated as the leading part of his optical doctrines.
69 Phil. Trans. vii.
5087.
The principal propositions of the Principia which bear upon
the question of optical theory are those of the fourteenth Section of
the first Book,70 in which the law of the sines in
refraction is proved on the hypothesis that the particles of bodies
act on light only at very small distances; and the proposition of the
eighth Section of the second Book;71 in which it is
pretended to be demonstrated that the motion propagated in a fluid
must diverge when it has passed through an aperture. The former
proposition shows that the law of refraction, an optical truth which
mainly affected the choice of a theory, (for about reflection there is
no difficulty on any mechanical hypothesis,) follows from the theory
of emission: the latter proposition was intended to prove the
inadmissibility of the rival hypothesis, that of undulations. As to
the former point,—the hypothetical explanation of refraction, on
the assumptions there made,—the conclusion is quite
satisfactory; but the reasoning in the latter case, (respecting the
propagation of undulations,) is certainly inconclusive and vague; and
something better might the more reasonably have been expected, since
Huyghens had at least 89 endeavored to prove the opposite
proposition. But supposing we leave these properties, the rectilinear
course, the reflection, and the refraction of light, as problems in
which neither theory has a decided advantage, what is the next
material point? The colors of thin plates. Now, how does Newton’s
theory explain these? By a new and special supposition;—that of
fits of easy transmission and reflection: a supposition which,
though it truly expresses these facts, is not borne out by any other
phenomena. But, passing over this, when we come to the peculiar laws
of polarization in Iceland spar, how does Newton’s meet this? Again by
a special and new supposition;—that the rays of light have
sides. Thus we find no fresh evidence in favor of the emission
hypothesis springing out of the fresh demands made upon it. It may be
urged, in reply, that the same is true of the undulatory theory; and
it must be allowed that, at the time of which we now speak, its
superiority in this respect was not manifested; though Hooke, as we
have seen, had caught a glimpse of the
explanation, which this theory supplies, of the colors of thin
plates.
70 Principia, Prop. 94, et
seq.
71 Ib. Prop. 42.
At a later period, Newton certainly seems to have been strongly
disinclined to believe light to consist in undulations merely. “Are
not,” he says, in Question twenty-eight of the Opticks, “all
hypotheses erroneous, in which light is supposed to consist in
pression or motion propagated through a fluid medium?” The arguments
which most weighed with him to produce this conviction, appear to have
been the one already mentioned,—that, on the undulatory
hypothesis, undulations passing through an aperture would be diffused;
and again,—his conviction, that the properties of light,
developed in various optical phenomena, “depend not upon new
modifications, but upon the original and unchangeable properties of
the rays.” (Question twenty-seven.)
But yet, even in this state of his views, he was very far from
abandoning the machinery of vibrations altogether. He is disposed to
use such machinery to produce his “fits of easy transmission.” In his
seventeenth Query, he says,72 “when a ray of light falls upon the
surface of any pellucid body, and is there refracted or reflected; may
not waves of vibrations or tremors be thereby excited in the
refracting or reflecting medium at the point of incidence? . . . . and
do not these vibrations overtake the rays of light, and by overtaking
them successively, do they not put them into the fits of easy
reflection and easy 90 transmission described above?” Several of
the other queries imply the same persuasion, of the necessity for the
assumption of an ether and its vibrations. And it might have been
asked, whether any good reason could be given for the hypothesis of an
ether as a part of the mechanism of light, which would not be
equally valid in favor of this being the whole of the
mechanism, especially if it could be shown that nothing more was
wanted to produce the results.
72 Opticks, p. 322.
The emission theory was, however, embraced in the most strenuous
manner by the disciples of Newton. That propositions existed in the
Principia which proceeded on this hypothesis, was, with many of
these persons, ground enough for adopting the doctrine; and it had
also the advantage of being more ready of conception, for though the
propagation of a wave is not very difficult to conceive, at least by a
mathematician, the motion of a particle is still easier.
On the other hand, the undulation theory was maintained by no less
a person than Euler; and the war between the two opinions was carried
on with great earnestness. The arguments on one side and on the other
soon became trite and familiar, for no person explained any new class
of facts by either theory. Thus it was urged by Euler against the
system of emission,73—that the perpetual emanation of
light from the sun must have diminished the mass;—that the
stream of matter thus constantly flowing must affect the motions of
the planets and comets; that the rays must disturb each
other;—that the passage of light through transparent bodies is,
on this system, inconceivable: all such arguments were answered by
representations of the exceeding minuteness and velocity of the matter
of light. On the other hand, there was urged against the theory of
waves, the favorite Newtonian argument, that on this theory the light
passing through an aperture ought to be diffused, as sound is. It is
curious that Euler does not make to this argument the reply which
Huyghens had made before. The fact really was, that he was not aware
of the true ground of the difference of the result in the cases of
sound and light; namely, that any ordinary aperture bears an immense
ratio to the length of an undulation of light, but does not bear a
very great ratio to the length of an undulation of sound. The
demonstrable consequence of this difference is, that light darts
through such an orifice in straight rays, while sound is diffused in
all directions. Euler, not perceiving this difference, rested his
answer mainly upon a circumstance by no means 91 unimportant, that the partitions usually
employed are not impermeable to sound, as opake bodies are to light.
He observes that the sound does not all come through the aperture; for
we hear, though the aperture be stopped. These were the main original
points of attack and defence, and they continued nearly the same for
the whole of the last century; the same difficulties were over and
over again proposed, and the same solutions given, much in the manner
of the disputations of the schoolmen of the middle ages.
73 Fischer, iv. 449.
The struggle being thus apparently balanced, the scale was
naturally turned by the general ascendancy of the Newtonian doctrines:
and the emission theory was the one most generally adopted. It was
still more firmly established, in consequence of the turn generally
taken by the scientific activity of the latter half of the eighteenth
century: for while nothing was added to our knowledge of optical laws,
the chemical effects of light were studied to a considerable extent by
various inquirers;74 and the opinions at which these persons
arrived, they found that they could express most readily, in
consistency with the reigning chemical views, by assuming the
materiality of light. It is, however, clear, that no reasonings of the
inevitably vague and doubtful character which belong to these portions
of chemistry, ought to be allowed to interfere with the steady and
regular progress of induction and generalization, founded on relations
of space and number, by which procedure the mechanical sciences are
formed. We reject, therefore, all these chemical speculations, as
belonging to other subjects; and consider the history of optical
theory as a blank, till we arrive at some very different events, of
which we have now to speak.
74 As Scheele, Selle, Lavoisier, De
Luc, Richter, Leonhardi, Gren, Girtanner, Link, Hagen, Voigt, De la
Metherie, Scherer, Dizé, Brugnatelli. See Fischer, vii. p. 20.
92</div></body></text></TEI>