<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="34">
      APPENDIX, No. 2.
    

      An examination into some charges brought against one of the twenty-four
      candidates, mentioned in a note as having their names suspended in the
      meeting-room of the Royal Society, at one time, has caused a printed
      pamphlet to be circulated amongst the members of the Society. Of the
      charges themselves I shall offer no opinion, but entreat every member to
      judge for himself. I shall, however, make one extract, which tends to show
      how the ranks of the Society are recruited.
    

      EXTRACT FROM A PRINTED LETTER FROM A. F. M. TO J. G. CHILDREN, ESQ. DATED,
      22, UPPER BEDFORD-PLACE, MARCH 13, 1830.
    

      "When I wished you to Propose me at the Geological Society, you asked me
      why you should not propose me also at the Royal Society; and my answer
      was, that it was an honour to which I did not think I could aspire; that
      my talents were too insignificant to warrant such pretensions. Many days
      passed, and still you pressed me on the subject, because your partiality
      made you think me deserving of the honour; but I resisted, really through
      modesty, not that I did not covet the distinction, until something was
      said of my paper on the meteoric mass of iron of Brazil, which was
      published some years ago in the Transactions of the Royal Society; when
      you insisted on proposing me, and I assented gratefully, because I was and
      am desirous of being a Fellow of the Royal Society, if I can be supposed
      worthy of having my name so honourably enrolled."
    

      EXTRACT FROM A LETTER OF J. G. CHILDREN, ESQ. TO A. F. M. ESQ. DATED,
      BRITISH MUSEUM, MARCH 24, 1830.
    

      "All that you have said respecting your being a candidate for admission
      into the Royal Society, is correct to the letter. I pressed the subject
      upon you, and I would do it again to-morrow, were it necessary."
    

      Here, then, we find Mr. Children, who has been on the Council of the Royal
      Society, and who was, a few years since, one of its Secretaries, pressing
      one of his friends to become, and actually insisting on proposing him as,
      a Fellow of the Royal Society, He must have been well aware of the
      feelings which prevail amongst the Council as to the propriety of such a
      step, and by publishing the fact, seems quite satisfied that such a course
      is advantageous to the interests of the Society. That similar applications
      were not unfrequently made in private, is well known; but it remains for
      the Society to consider whether, now they are publicly and officially
      announced to them, it will sanction this mode of augmenting the already
      numerous list of its fellows.
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>