<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="19">

CHAPTER X.
Of the Perception of Time and Number.



1. OUR
perception of the passage of time involves a series
of acts of memory. This is easily seen and assented to, when
large intervals of time and a complex train of occurrences
are concerned. But since memory is requisite in order to
apprehend time in such cases, we cannot doubt that the same
faculty must be concerned in the shortest and simplest cases
of succession; for it will hardly be maintained that the
process by which we contemplate the progress of time is
different, when small, and when large intervals are
concerned. If memory be absolutely requisite to connect two
events which begin and end a day, and to perceive a tract of
time between them, it must be equally indispensable to
connect the beginning and end of a minute, or a second;
though in this case the effort may be smaller, and
consequently more easily overlooked. In common cases, we are
unconscious of the act of thought by which we recollect the
preceding instant, though we perceive the effort when we
recollect some distant event. And this is analogous to what
happens in other instances. Thus, we walk without being
conscious of the volitions by which we move our muscles;
but, in order to leap, a distinct and manifest exertion of
the same muscles is necessary. Yet no one will doubt that we
walk as well as leap by an act of the will exerted through
the muscles; and in like manner, our consciousness of small
as well as large intervals of time involves something of the
nature of an act of memory.
2. But this constant and almost imperceptible kind of
memory, by which we connect the beginning and 142 end of
each instant as it passes, may very fitly be distinguished
in common cases from manifest acts of recollection, although
it may be difficult or impossible to separate the two
operations in general. This perpetual and latent kind of
memory may be termed a sense of successiveness; and
must be considered as an internal sense by which we perceive
ourselves existing in time, much in the same way as by our
external and muscular sense we perceive ourselves existing
in space. And both our internal thoughts and feelings, and
the events which take place around us, are apprehended as
objects of this internal sense, and thus as taking place in
time.
3. In the same manner in which our interpretation of the
notices of the muscular sense implies the power of moving
our limbs, and of touching at will this object or that; our
apprehension of the relations of time, by means of the
internal sense of successiveness, implies a power of
recalling what has past, and of retaining what is passing.
We are able to seize the occurrences which have just taken
place, and to hold them fast in our minds so as mentally to
measure their distance in time from occurrences now present.
And thus, this sense of successiveness, like the muscular
sense with which we have compared it, implies activity of
the mind itself, and is not a sense passively receiving
impressions.
4. The conception of Number appears to require the
exercise of the same sense of succession. At first sight,
indeed, we seem to apprehend Number without any act of
memory, or any reference to time: for example, we look at a
horse, and see that his legs are four; and this we seem to
do at once, without reckoning them. But it is not difficult
to see that this seeming instantaneousness of the perception
of small numbers is an illusion. This resembles the many
other cases in which we perform short and easy acts so
rapidly and familiarly that we are unconscious of them; as
in the acts of seeing, and of articulating our words. And
this is the more manifest, since we begin our acquaintance
with number by counting even the 143 smallest numbers.
Children and very rude savages must use an effort to reckon
even their five fingers, and find a difficulty in going
further. And persons have been known who were able by habit,
or by a peculiar natural aptitude, to count by dozens as
rapidly as common persons can by units. We may conclude,
therefore, that when we appear to catch a small number by a
single glance of the eye, we do in fact count the units of
it in a regular, though very brief succession. To count
requires an act of memory. Of this we are sensible when we
count very slowly, as when we reckon the strokes of a
church-clock; for in such a case we may forget in the
intervals of the strokes, and miscount. Now it will
not be doubted that the nature of the process in counting is
the same whether we count fast or slow. There is no definite
speed of reckoning at which the faculties which it requires
are changed; and therefore memory, which is requisite in
some cases, must be so in all13.</div></body></text></TEI>