<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="14">INTRODUCTION.
WE have now to consider more
especially a long and barren period, which intervened between the
scientific activity of ancient Greece and that of modern Europe; and
which we may, therefore, call the Stationary Period of Science. It
would be to no purpose to enumerate the various forms in which, during
these times, men reproduced the discoveries of the inventive ages; or
to trace in them the small successes of Art, void of any principle of
genuine Philosophy. Our object requires rather that we should point
out the general and distinguishing features of the intellect and
habits of those times. We must endeavor to delineate the character of
the Stationary Period, and, as far as possible, to analyze its defects
and errors; and thus obtain some knowledge of the causes of its
barrenness and darkness.
We have already stated, that real scientific progress requires
distinct general Ideas, applied to many special and certain Facts. In
the period of which we now have to speak, men’s Ideas were obscured;
their disposition to bring their general views into accordance with
Facts was enfeebled. They were thus led to employ themselves
unprofitably, among indistinct and unreal notions. And the evil of
these tendencies was further inflamed by moral peculiarities in the
character of those times;—by an abjectness of thought on the one
hand, which could not help looking towards some intellectual superior,
and by an impatience of dissent on the other. To this must be added an
enthusiastic temper, which, when introduced into speculation, tends to
subject the mind’s operations to ideas altogether distorted and
delusive.
These characteristics of the stationary period, its obscurity of
thought, its servility, its intolerant disposition, and its
enthusiastic temper, will be treated of in the four following
chapters, on the Indistinctness of Ideas, the Commentatorial Spirit,
the Dogmatism, and the Mysticism of the Middle Ages.  ~Additional
material in the 3rd edition.~ 186</div></body></text></TEI>