<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Chambers Robert</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="8">p. 105ERA
OF THE OOLITE.
COMMENCEMENT OF MAMMALIA.
The chronicles of this period
consist of a series of beds, mostly calcareous, taking their
general name (Oolite System) from a conspicuous member of
them—the oolite—a limestone composed of an
aggregation of small round grains or spherules, and so called
from its fancied resemblance to a cluster of eggs, or the roe of
a fish.  This texture of stone is novel and striking. 
It is supposed to be of chemical origin, each spherule being an
aggregation of particles round a central nucleus.  The
oolite system is largely developed in England, France,
Westphalia, and Northern Italy; it appears in Northern India and
Africa, and patches of it exist in Scotland, and in the vale of
the Mississippi.  It may of course be yet discovered in many
other parts of the world.
The series, as shewn in the neighbourhood of Bath, is
(beginning with the lowest) as follows:—1.  Lias, a
set of strata variously composed of limestone, clay, marl, and
shale, clay being predominant; 2.  Lower oolitic formation,
including, besides the great oolite bed of central England,
fullers’ earth beds, forest marble, and cornbrash; 3. 
Middle oolitic formation, composed of two sub-groups, the Oxford
clay and coral rag, the latter being a mere layer of the works of
the coral polype; 4.  Upper oolitic formation, including
what are called Kimmeridge clay and Portland oolite.  In
Yorkshire there is an additional group above the lias, and in
Sutherlandshire there is another group above that again.  In
the wealds (moorlands) of Kent and Sussex, there is, in like
manner, above the fourth of the Bath series, another additional
group, to which the name of the Wealden has been given,
from its situation, and which, composed of sandstones and clays,
is subdivided into Purbeck beds, Hastings sand, and Weald
clay.
There are no particular appearances of disturbance between the
close of the new red sandstone and the beginning of the oolite
system, as far as has been observed in England.  Yet there
is a great change in the materials of the rocks of the two
formations, shewing that while the bottoms of the seas of the one
period had been chiefly arenaceous, those of the other were
chiefly clayey and limy.  And there is an equal difference
between the two periods in respect of both botany and
zoology.  While the new red sandstone shews comparatively
scanty traces of organic creation, those in the oolite are
extremely abundant, particularly in the department of animals,
and more particularly still of sea mollusca, which, it has been
observed, are always the more conspicuous in proportion to the
predominance of calcareous rocks.  It is also remarkable
that the animals of the oolitic system are entirely different in
species from those of the preceding age, and that these species
cease before the next.  In this system we likewise find that
uniformity over great space which has been remarked of the Faunas
of earlier formations.  “In the equivalent deposits in
the Himalaya Mountains, at Fernando Po, in the region north of
the Cape of Good Hope, and in the Run of Cutch, and other parts
of Hindostan, fossils have been discovered, which, as far as
English naturalists who have seen them can determine, are
undistinguishable from certain oolite and lias fossils of
Europe.” [108a]
The dry land of this age presented cycadeæ, “a
beautiful class of plants between the palms and conifers, having
a tall, straight trunk, terminating in a magnificent crown of
foliage.” [108b]  There were
tree ferns, but in smaller proportion than in former ages; also
equisetaceæ, lilia, and conifers.  The vegetation was
generally analogous to that of the Cape of Good Hope and
Australia, which seems to argue a climate (we must remember, a
universal climate) between the tropical and temperate.  It
was, however, sufficiently luxuriant in some instances to produce
thin seams of coal, for such are found in the oolite formation of
both Yorkshire and Sutherland.  The sea, as for ages before,
contained algæ, of which, however, only a few species have
been preserved to our day.  The lower classes of the
inhabitants of the ocean were unprecedentedly abundant.  The
polypiaria were in such abundance as to form whole strata of
themselves.  The crinoidea and echinites were also extremely
numerous.  Shell mollusks, in hundreds of new species,
occupied the bottoms of the seas of those ages, while of the
swimming shell-fish, ammonites and belemnites, there were also
many scores of varieties.  The belemnite here calls for some
particular notice.  It commences in the oolite, and
terminates in the next formation.  It is an elongated,
conical shell, terminating in a point, and having, at the larger
end, a cavity for the residence of the animal, with a series of
air-chambers below.  The animal, placed in the upper cavity,
could raise or depress itself in the water at pleasure by a
pneumatic operation upon the entral air tube pervading its
shell.  Its tentacula, sent abroad over the summit of the
shell, searched the sea for prey.  The creature had an
ink-bag, with which it could muddle the water around it, to
protect itself from more powerful animals, and, strange to say,
this has been found so well preserved that an artist has used it
in one instance as a paint, wherewith to delineate the belemnite
itself.
The crustacea discovered in this formation are less
numerous.  There are many fishes, some of which
(acrodus, psammodus, &c.,) are presumed from
remains of their palatal bones, to have been of the gigantic
cartilaginous class, now represented by such as the
cestraceon.  It has been considered by Professor Owen as
worthy of notice, that, the cestraceon being an inhabitant of the
Australian seas, we have, in both the botany and ichthyology of
this period, an analogy to that continent.  The pycnodontes,
(thick-toothed,) and lepidoides, (having thick scales,) are other
families described by M. Agassiz as extensively prevalent. 
In the shallow waters of the oolitic formation, the
ichthyosaurus, plesiosaurus, and other huge saurian carnivora of
the preceding age, plied, in increased numbers, their destructive
vocation. [110]  To them were added new genera,
the cetiosaurus, mososaurus, and some others, all of similar
character and habits.
Land reptiles abounded, including species of the pterodactyle
of the preceding age—tortoises, trionyces,
crocodilians—and the pliosaurus, a creature which appears
to have formed a link between the plesiosaurus and the
crocodile.  We know of at least six species of the flying
saurian, the pterodactyle, in this formation.
Now, for the first time, we find remains of insects, an order
of animals not well calculated for fossil preservation, and which
are therefore amongst the rarest of the animal tribes found in
rocks, though they are the most numerous of all living
families.  A single libellula (dragon-fly) was found in the
Stonesfield slate, a member of the lower oolitic group quarried
near Oxford; and this was for several years the only specimen
known to exist so early; but now many species have been found in
a corresponding rock at Solenhofen, in Germany.  It is
remarkable that the remains of insects are found most plentifully
near the remains of pterodactyles, to which undoubtedly they
served as prey.
The first glimpse of the highest class of the vertebrate
sub-kingdom—mammalia—is obtained from the
Stonesfield slate, where there has been found the jaw-bone of a
quadruped evidently insectivorous, and inferred, from
peculiarities in the structure of that small fragment, to have
belonged to the marsupial family, (pouched animals).  It may
be observed, although no specimens of so high a class of animals
as mammalia are found earlier, such may nevertheless have
existed: the defect may be in our not having found them; but,
other things considered, the probability is that heretofore there
were no mammifers.  It is an interesting circumstance that
the first mammifers found should have belonged to the
marsupialia, when the place of that order in the scale of
creation is considered.  In the imperfect structure of their
brain, deficient in the organs connecting the two
hemispheres—and in the mode of gestation, which is only in
small part uterine—this family is clearly a link between
the oviparous vertebrata (birds, reptiles, and fishes) and the
higher mammifers.  This is further established by their
possessing a faint development of two canals passing from near
the anus to the external surface of the viscera, which are fully
possessed in reptiles and fishes, for the purpose of supplying
aerated water to the blood circulating in particular vessels, but
which are unneeded by mammifers.  Such rudiments of organs
in certain species which do not require them in any degree, are
common in both the animal and vegetable kingdoms, but are always
most conspicuous in families approaching in character to those
classes to which the full organs are proper.  This subject
will be more particularly adverted to in the sequel.
The highest part of the oolitic formation presents some
phenomena of an unusual and interesting character, which demand
special notice.  Immediately above the upper oolitic group
in Buckinghamshire, in the vicinity of Weymouth, and other
situations, there is a thin stratum, usually called by workmen
the dirt-bed, which appears, from incontestable evidence,
to have been a soil, formed, like soils of the present day, in
the course of time, upon a surface which had previously been the
bottom of the sea.  The dirt-bed contains exuviæ of
tropical trees, accumulated through time, as the forest shed its
honours on the spot where it grew, and became itself
decayed.  Near Weymouth there is a piece of this stratum, in
which stumps of trees remain rooted, mostly erect or slightly
inclined, and from one to three feet high; while trunks of the
same forest, also silicified, lie imbedded on the surface of the
soil in which they grew.
Above this bed lie those which have been called the Wealden,
from their full development in the Weald of Sussex; and these as
incontestably argue that the dry land forming the dirt-bed had
next afterwards become the area of brackish estuaries, or lakes
partially connected with the sea; for the Wealden strata contain
exuviæ of fresh-water tribes, besides those of the great
saurians and chelonia.  The area of this estuary comprehends
the whole south-east province of England.  A geologist thus
confidently narrates the subsequent events: “Much
calcareous matter was first deposited [in this estuary], and in
it were entombed myriads of shells, apparently analogous to those
of the vivipara.  Then came a thick envelope of sand,
sometimes interstratified with mud; and, finally, muddy matter
prevailed.  The solid surface beneath the waters would
appear to have suffered a long continued and gradual depression,
which was as gradually filled, or nearly so, with transported
matter; in the end, however, after a depression of several
hundred feet, the sea again entered upon the area, not suddenly
or violently—for the Wealden rocks pass gradually into the
superincumbent cretaceous series—but so quietly, that the
mud containing the remains of terrestrial and fresh-water
creatures was tranquilly covered up by sands replete with marine
exuviæ.” [114]  A subsequent
depression of the same area, to the depth of at least three
hundred fathoms, is believed to have taken place, to admit of the
deposition of the cretaceous beds lying above.
From the scattered way in which remains of the larger
terrestrial animals occur in the Wealden, and the intermixture of
pebbles of the special appearance of those worn in rivers, it is
also inferred that the estuary which once covered the south-east
part of England was the mouth of a river of that far-descending
class of which the Mississippi and Amazon are examples. 
What part of the earth’s surface presented the dry land
through which that and other similar rivers flowed, no one can
tell for certain.  It has been surmised, that the particular
one here spoken of may have flowed from a point not nearer than
the site of the present Newfoundland.  Professor Philips has
suggested, from the analogy of the mineral composition, that
anciently elevated coal strata may have composed the dry land
from which the sandy matters of these strata were washed. 
Such a deposit as the Wealden almost necessarily implies a local,
not a general condition; yet it has been thought that similar
strata and remains exist in the Pays de Bray, near
Beauvais.  This leads to the supposition that there may have
been, in that age, a series of river-receiving estuaries along
the border of some such great ocean as the Atlantic, of which
that of modern Sussex is only an example.</div></body></text></TEI>