<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="26">INTRODUCTION.
WE enter now upon a new region
of the human mind. In passing from Astronomy to Mechanics we make a
transition from the formal to the physical
sciences;—from time and space to force and matter;—from
phenomena to causes. Hitherto we have been concerned
only with the paths and orbits, the periods and cycles, the angles and
distances, of the objects to which our sciences applied, namely, the
heavenly bodies. How these motions are produced;—by what
agencies, impulses, powers, they are determined to be what they
are;—of what nature are the objects themselves;—are
speculations which we have hitherto not dwelt upon. The history of
such speculations now comes before us; but, in the first place, we
must consider the history of speculations concerning motion in
general, terrestrial as well as celestial. We must first attend to
Mechanics, and afterwards return to Physical Astronomy.
In the same way in which the development of Pure Mathematics, which
began with the Greeks, was a necessary condition of the progress of
Formal Astronomy, the creation of the science of Mechanics now became
necessary to the formation and progress of Physical Astronomy.
Geometry and Mechanics were studied for their own sakes; but they also
supplied ideas, language, and reasoning to other sciences. If the
Greeks had not cultivated Conic Sections, Kepler could not have
superseded Ptolemy; if the Greeks had cultivated Dynamics,1
Kepler might have anticipated Newton.
1 Dynamics is the science which
treats of the Motions of Bodies; Statics is the science which
treats of the Pressure of Bodies which are in equilibrium, and
therefore at rest. 312</div></body></text></TEI>