<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="24">CHAPTER IV.
Inductive Epoch of Kepler.

Sect. 1.—Intellectual Character of
Kepler.
SEVERAL persons,30 especially in recent times, who have
taken a view of the discoveries of Kepler, appear to have been
surprised and somewhat discontented that conjectures, apparently so
fanciful and arbitrary as his, should have led to important
discoveries. They seem to have been alarmed at the Moral that
their readers might draw, from the tale of a Quest of Knowledge, in
which the Hero, though fantastical and self-willed, and violating in
his conduct, as they conceived, all right rule and sound philosophy,
is rewarded with the most signal triumphs. Perhaps one or two
reflections may in some measure reconcile us to this result.
30 Laplace, Précis de l’Hist.
d’Ast. p. 94. “Il est affligeant pour l’esprit humain de voir ce
grand homme, même dans ses derniers ouvrages, se complaire avec
délices dans ses chimériques spéculations, et les regarder comme l’âme
et la vie de l’astronomie.”
 Hist. of Ast., L. U. K., p. 53. “This success [of Kepler]
may well inspire with dismay those who are accustomed to consider
experiment and rigorous induction as the only means to interrogate
nature with success.”
 Life of Kepler, L. U. K., p. 14, “Bad philosophy.” P. 15,
“Kepler’s miraculous good fortune in seizing truths across the wildest
and most absurd theories.” P. 54, “The danger of attempting to follow
his method in the pursuit of truth.”
291 In the first
place, we may observe that the leading thought which suggested and
animated all Kepler’s attempts was true, and we may add, sagacious and
philosophical; namely, that there must be some numerical or
geometrical relations among the times, distances, and velocities of
the revolving bodies of the solar system. This settled and constant
conviction of an important truth regulated all the conjectures,
apparently so capricious and fanciful, which he made and examined,
respecting particular relations in the system.
In the next place, we may venture to say, that advances in
knowledge are not commonly made without the previous exercise of some
boldness and license in guessing. The discovery of new truths
requires, undoubtedly, minds careful and scrupulous in examining what
is suggested; but it requires, no less, such as are quick and fertile
in suggesting. What is Invention, except the talent of rapidly calling
before us many possibilities, and selecting the appropriate one? It is
true, that when we have rejected all the inadmissible suppositions,
they are quickly forgotten by most persons; and few think it necessary
to dwell on these discarded hypotheses, and on the process by which
they were condemned, as Kepler has done. But all who discover truths
must have reasoned upon many errors, to obtain each truth; every
accepted doctrine must have been one selected out of many candidates.
In making many conjectures, which on trial proved erroneous, Kepler
was no more fanciful or unphilosophical than other discoverers have
been. Discovery is not a “cautious” or “rigorous” process, in the
sense of abstaining from such suppositions. But there are great
differences in different cases, in the facility with which guesses are
proved to be errors, and in the degree of attention with which the
error and the proof are afterwards dwelt on. Kepler certainly was
remarkable for the labor which he gave to such self-refutations, and
for the candor and copiousness with which he narrated them; his works
are in this way extremely curious and amusing; and are a very
instructive exhibition of the mental process of discovery. But in this
respect, I venture to believe, they exhibit to us the usual process
(somewhat caricatured) of inventive minds: they rather exemplify the
rule of genius than (as has generally been hitherto taught)
the exception. We may add, that if many of Kepler’s guesses
now appear fanciful and absurd, because time and observation have
refuted them, others, which were at the time equally gratuitous, have
been confirmed by succeeding discoveries in a manner which makes them
appear marvellously sagacious; as, for instance, his assertion of the
rotation of 292 the
sun on his axis, before the invention of the telescope, and his
opinion that the obliquity of the ecliptic was decreasing, but would,
after a long-continued diminution, stop, and then increase again.31 Nothing can be more just, as well as
more poetically happy, than Kepler’s picture of the philosopher’s
pursuit of scientific truth, conveyed by means of an allusion to
Virgil’s shepherd and shepherdess:


Malo me Galatea petit, lasciva puella
Et fugit ad salices et se cupit ante
videri.
Coy yet inviting, Galatea loves
To sport in sight, then plunge into the
groves;
The challenge given, she darts along the
green,
Will not be caught, yet would not run
unseen.

31 Bailly, A. M. iii.
175.
We may notice as another peculiarity of Kepler’s reasonings, the
length and laboriousness of the processes by which he discovered the
errors of his first guesses. One of the most important talents
requisite for a discoverer, is the ingenuity and skill which devises
means for rapidly testing false suppositions as they offer themselves.
This talent Kepler did not possess: he was not even a good
arithmetical calculator, often making mistakes, some of which he
detected and laments, while others escaped him to the last. But his
defects in this respect were compensated by his courage and
perseverance in undertaking and executing such tasks; and, what was
still more admirable, he never allowed the labor he had spent upon any
conjecture to produce any reluctance in abandoning the hypothesis, as
soon as he had evidence of its inaccuracy. The only way in which he
rewarded himself for his trouble, was by describing to the world, in
his lively manner, his schemes, exertions, and feelings.
The mystical parts of Kepler’s opinions, as his belief in
astrology, his persuasion that the earth was an animal, and many of
the loose moral and spiritual as well as sensible analyses by which he
represented to himself the powers which he supposed to prevail in the
universe, do not appear to have interfered with his discovery, but
rather to have stimulated his invention, and animated his exertions.
Indeed, where there are clear scientific ideas on one subject in the
mind, it does not appear that mysticism on others is at all
unfavorable to the successful prosecution of research.
I conceive, then, that we may consider Kepler’s character as
containing the general features of the character of a scientific
discoverer, 293
though some of the features are exaggerated, and some too feebly
marked. His spirit of invention was undoubtedly very fertile and
ready, and this and his perseverance served to remedy his deficiency
in mathematical artifice and method. But the peculiar physiognomy is
given to his intellectual aspect by his dwelling in a most prominent
manner on those erroneous trains of thought which other persons
conceal from the world, and often themselves forget, because they find
means of stopping them at the outset. In the beginning of his book
(Argumenta Capitum) he says, “if Christopher Columbus, if
Magellan, if the Portuguese, when they narrate their wanderings, are
not only excused, but if we do not wish these passages omitted, and
should lose much pleasure if they were, let no one blame me for doing
the same.” Kepler’s talents were a kindly and fertile soil, which he
cultivated with abundant toil and vigor; but with great scantiness of
agricultural skill and implements. Weeds and the grain throve and
flourished side by side almost undistinguished; and he gave a peculiar
appearance to his harvest, by gathering and preserving the one class
of plants with as much care and diligence as the other.
Sect. 2.—Kepler’s Discovery of his
Third Law.
I shall now give some account of Kepler’s
speculations and discoveries. The first discovery which he attempted,
the relation among the successive distances of the planets from the
sun, was a failure; his doctrine being without any solid foundation,
although propounded by him with great triumph, in a work which he
called Mysterium Cosmographicum, and which was published in
1596. The account which he gives of the train of his thoughts on this
subject, namely, the various suppositions assumed, examined, and
rejected, is curious and instructive, for the reasons just stated; but
we shall not dwell upon these essays, since they led only to an
opinion now entirely abandoned. The doctrine which professed to give
the true relation of the orbits of the different planets, was thus
delivered:32 “The orbit of the earth is a circle:
round the sphere to which this circle belongs, describe a
dodecahedron; the sphere including this will give the orbit of Mars.
Round Mars describe a tetrahedron; the circle including this will be
the orbit of Jupiter. Describe a cube round Jupiter’s orbit; the
circle including this will be the orbit of Saturn. Now inscribe in the
Earth’s orbit an icosahedron; the circle inscribed in it will be the
orbit of Venus. 294
Inscribe an octahedron in the orbit of Venus; the circle inscribed in
it will be Mercury’s orbit. This is the reason of the number of the
planets.” The five kinds of polyhedral bodies here mentioned are the
only “Regular Solids.”
32 L. U. K. Kepler, 6.
But though this part of the Mysterium Cosmographicum was a
failure, the same researches continued to occupy Kepler’s mind; and
twenty-two years later led him to one of the important rules known to
us as “Kepler’s Laws;” namely, to the rule connecting the mean
distances of the planets from the sun with the times of their
revolutions. This rule is expressed in mathematical terms, by saying
that the squares of the periodic times are in the same proportion as
the cubes of the distances; and was of great importance to Newton in
leading him to the law of the sun’s attractive force. We may properly
consider this discovery as the sequel of the train of thought already
noticed. In the beginning of the Mysterium, Kepler had said,
“In the year 1595, I brooded with the whole energy of my mind on the
subject of the Copernican system. There were three things in
particular of which I pertinaciously sought the causes why they are
not other than they are; the number, the size, and the motion of the
orbits.” We have seen the nature of his attempt to account for the two
first of these points. He had also made some essays to connect the
motions of the planets with their distances, but with his success in
this respect he was not himself completely satisfied. But in the fifth
book of the Harmonice Mundi, published in 1619, he says, “What
I prophesied two-and-twenty years ago as soon as I had discovered the
Five Solids among the Heavenly Bodies; what I firmly believed before I
had seen the Harmonics of Ptolemy; what I promised my friends
in the title of this book (On the most perfect Harmony of the
Celestial Motions) which I named before I was sure of my
discovery; what sixteen years ago I regarded as a thing to be sought;
that for which I joined Tycho Brahe, for which I settled in Prague,
for which I have devoted the best part of my life to astronomical
contemplations; at length I have brought to light, and have recognized
its truth beyond my most sanguine expectations.”
The rule thus referred to is stated in the third Chapter of this
fifth Book. “It is,” he says, “a most certain and exact thing that the
proportion which exists between the periodic times of any two planets
is precisely the sesquiplicate of the proportion of their mean
distances; that is, of the radii of the orbits. Thus, the period of
the earth is one year, that of Saturn thirty years; if any one trisect
the proportion, that 295 is, take the cube root of it, and double
the proportion so found, that is, square it, he will find the exact
proportion of the distances of the Earth and of Saturn from the sun.
For the cube root of 1 is 1, and the square of this is 1; and the cube
root of 30 is greater than 3, and therefore the square of it is
greater than 9. And Saturn at his mean distance from the sun is at a
little more than 9 times the mean distance of the Earth.”
When we now look back at the time and exertions which the
establishment of this law cost Kepler, we are tempted to imagine that
he was strangely blind in not seeing it sooner. His object, we might
reason, was to discover a law connecting the distances and the
periodic times. What law of connection could be more simple and
obvious, we might say, than that one of these quantities should vary
as some power of the other, or as some root; or as
some combination of the two, which in a more general view, may still
be called a power? And if the problem had been viewed in this
way, the question must have occurred, to what power of the
periodic times are the distances proportional? And the answer must
have been, the trial being made, that they are proportional to the
square of the cube root. This ex-post-facto obviousness of
discoveries is a delusion to which we are liable with regard to many
of the most important principles. In the case of Kepler, we may
observe, that the process of connecting two classes of quantities by
comparing their powers, is obvious only to those who are
familiar with general algebraical views; and that in Kepler’s time,
algebra had not taken the place of geometry, as the most usual vehicle
of mathematical reasoning. It may be added, also, that Kepler always
sought his formal laws by means of physical
reasonings; and these, though vague or erroneous, determined the
nature of the mathematical connection which he assumed. Thus in the
Mysterium he had been led by his notions of moving virtue of
the sun to this conjecture, among others—that, in the planets,
the increase of the periods will be double of the difference of the
distances; which supposition he found to give him an approach to the
actual proportion of the distances, but one not sufficiently close to
satisfy him.
The greater part of the fifth Book of the Harmonics of the
Universe consists in attempts to explain various relations among
the distances, times, and eccentricities of the planets, by means of
the ratios which belong to certain concords and discords. This portion
of the work is so complex and laborious, that probably few modern
readers have had courage to go through it. Delambre acknowledged that
his patience 296
often failed him during the task;33 and subscribes
to the judgment of Bailly: “After this sublime effort, Kepler
replunges himself in the relations of music to the motions, the
distance, and the eccentricities of the planets. In all these harmonic
ratios there is not one true relation; in a crowd of ideas there is
not one truth: he becomes a man after being a spirit of light.”
Certainly these speculations are of no value, but we may look on them
with toleration, when we recollect that Newton has sought for
analogies between the spaces occupied by the prismatic colors and the
notes of the gamut.34 The numerical relations of Concords are
so peculiar that we can easily suppose them to have other bearings
than those which first offer themselves.
33 A. M. a. 358.
34 Optics, b. ii. p. iv. Obs.
5.
It does not belong to my present purpose to speak at length of the
speculations concerning the forces producing the celestial motions by
which Kepler was led to this celebrated law, or of those which he
deduced from it, and which are found in the Epitome Astronomiæ
Copernicanæ, published in 1622. In that work also (p. 554), he
extended this law, though in a loose manner, to the satellites of
Jupiter. These physical speculations were only a vague and
distant prelude to Newton’s discoveries; and the law, as a
formal rule, was complete in itself. We must now attend to
the history of the other two laws with which Kepler’s name is
associated.
Sect. 3.—Kepler’s Discovery of his First and
Second Laws.—Elliptical Theory of the Planets.
The propositions designated as Kepler’s
First and Second Laws are these: That the orbits of the planets are
elliptical; and, That the areas described, or swept, by lines
drawn from the sun to the planet, are proportional to the times
employed in the motion.
The occasion of the discovery of these laws was the attempt to
reconcile the theory of Mars to the theory of eccentrics and
epicycles; the event of it was the complete overthrow of that theory,
and the establishment, in its stead, of the Elliptical Theory of the
planets. Astronomy was now ripe for such a change. As soon as
Copernicus had taught men that the orbits of the planets were to be
referred to the sun, it obviously became a question, what was the true
form of these orbits, and the rule of motion of each planet in its own
orbit. Copernicus represented the motions in longitude by means of
297 eccentrics and
epicycles, as we have already said; and the motions in latitude by
certain librations, or alternate elevations and depressions of
epicycles. If a mathematician had obtained a collection of true
positions of a planet, the form of the orbit and the motion of the
star would have been determined with reference to the sun as well as
to the earth; but this was not possible, for though the
geocentric position, or the direction in which the planet was
seen, could be observed, its distance from the earth was not known.
Hence, when Kepler attempted to determine the orbit of a planet, he
combined the observed geocentric places with successive modifications
of the theory of epicycles, till at last he was led, by one step after
another, to change the epicyclical into the elliptical theory. We may
observe, moreover, that at every step he endeavored to support his new
suppositions by what he called, in his fanciful phraseology, “sending
into the field a reserve of new physical reasonings on the rout and
dispersion of the veterans;”35 that is, by
connecting his astronomical hypotheses with new imaginations, when the
old ones became untenable. We find, indeed, that this is the spirit in
which the pursuit of knowledge is generally carried on with success;
those men arrive at truth who eagerly endeavor to connect remote
points of their knowledge, not those who stop cautiously at each point
till something compels them to go beyond it.
35 I will insert this passage, as a
specimen of Kepler’s fanciful mode of narrating the defeats which he
received in the war which he carried on with Mars. “Dum in hunc modum
de Martis motibus triumpho, eique ut planè devicto tabularum carceres
et equationum compedes necto, diversis nuntiatur locis, futilem
victoriam ut bellam totâ mole recrudescere. Nam domi quidam hostis ut
captivus contemptus, rupit omnia equationum vincula, carceresque
tabularum effregit. Foris speculatores profligerunt meas causarum
physicarum arcessitas copias earumque jugum excusserunt resumtà
libertate. Jamque parum abfuit quia hostis fugitivus sese cum
rebellibus suis conjungeret meque in desperationem adigeret: nisi
raptim, nova rationum physicarum subsidia, fusis et palantibus
veteribus, submisissem, et qua se captivus proripuisset, omni
diligentia, edoctus vestigiis ipsius nullâ morâ interpositâ
inhæsisserem.”
Kepler joined Tycho Brahe at Prague in 1600, and found him and
Longomontanus busily employed in correcting the theory of Mars; and he
also then entered upon that train of researches which he published in
1609 in his extraordinary work On the Motions of Mars. In this
work, as in others, he gives an account, not only of his success, but
of his failures, explaining, at length, the various suppositions which
he had made, the notions by which he had been led to invent or to
entertain them, the processes by which he had proved their 298 falsehood, and the
alternations of hope and sorrow, of vexation and triumph, through
which he had gone. It will not be necessary for us to cite many
passages of these kinds, curious and amusing as they are.
One of the most important truths contained in the motions of Man is
the discovery that the plane of the orbit of the planet should be
considered with reference to the sun itself, instead of referring it
to any of the other centres of motion which the eccentric hypothesis
introduced: and that, when so considered, it had none of the
librations which Ptolemy and Copernicus had attributed to it. The
fourteenth chapter of the second part asserts, “Plana eccentricorum
esse ἀτάλαντα;” that the planes are unlibrating; retaining
always the same inclination to the ecliptic, and the same line of
nodes. With this step Kepler appears to have been justly
delighted. “Copernicus,” he says, “not knowing the value of what he
possessed (his system), undertook to represent Ptolemy, rather than
nature, to which, however, he had approached more nearly than any
other person. For being rejoiced that the quantity of the latitude of
each planet was increased by the approach of the earth to the planet,
according to his theory, he did not venture to reject the rest of
Ptolemy’s increase of latitude, but in order to express it, devised
librations of the planes of the eccentric, depending not upon its own
eccentric, but (most improbably) upon the orbit of the earth, which
has nothing to do with it. I always fought against this impertinent
tying together of two orbits, even before I saw the observations of
Tycho; and I therefore rejoice much that in this, as in others of my
preconceived opinions, the observations were found to be on my side.”
Kepler established his point by a fair and laborious calculation of
the results of observations of Mars made by himself and Tycho Brahe;
and had a right to exult when the result of these calculations
confirmed his views of the symmetry and simplicity of nature.
We may judge of the difficulty of casting off the theory of
eccentrics and epicycles, by recollecting that Copernicus did not do
it at all, and that Kepler only did it after repeated struggles; the
history of which occupies thirty-nine Chapters of his book. At the end
of them he says, “This prolix disputation was necessary, in order to
prepare the way to the natural form of the equations, of which I am
now to treat.36 My first error was, that the path of a
planet is a perfect circle;—an opinion which was a more
mischievous thief of my time, 299 in proportion as it was supported by the
authority of all philosophers, and apparently agreeable to
metaphysics.” But before he attempts to correct this erroneous part of
his hypothesis, he sets about discovering the law according to which
the different parts of the orbit are described in the case of the
earth, in which case the eccentricity is so small that the effect of
the oval form is insensible. The result of this inquiry was37 the Rule, that the time of describing
any arc of the orbit is proportional to the area intercepted between
the curve and two lines drawn from the sun to the extremities of the
arc. It is to be observed that this rule, at first, though it had the
recommendation of being selected after the unavoidable abandonment of
many, which were suggested by the notions of those times, was far from
being adopted upon any very rigid or cautious grounds. A rule had been
proved at the apsides of the orbit, by calculation from observations,
and had then been extended by conjecture to other parts of the orbit;
and the rule of the areas was only an approximate and inaccurate mode
of representing this rule, employed for the purpose of brevity and
convenience, in consequence of the difficulty of applying,
geometrically, that which Kepler now conceived to be the true rule,
and which required him to find the sum of the lines drawn from the sun
to every point of the orbit. When he proceeded to apply this
rule to Mars, in whose orbit the oval form is much more marked,
additional difficulties came in his way; and here again the true
supposition, that the oval is of that special kind called
ellipse, was adopted at first only in order to simplify
calculation,38 and the deviation from exactness in the
result was attributed to the inaccuracy of those approximate
processes. The supposition of the oval had already been forced upon
Purbach in the case of Mercury, and upon Reinhold in the case of the
Moon. The centre of the epicycle was made to describe an egg-shaped
figure in the former case, and a lenticular figure in the latter.39
36 De Stellâ Martis, iii.
40.
37 De Stellâ Martis, p.
194.
38 Ib. iv. c. 47.
39 L. U. K. Kepler, p. 30.
It may serve to show the kind of labor by which Kepler was led to
his result, if we here enumerate, as he does in his forty-seventh
Chapter,40 six hypotheses, on which he calculated
the longitude of Mars, in order to see which best agreed with
observation.
40 De Stellâ Martis, p.
228.
1. The simple eccentricity.
2. The bisection of the eccentricity, and the duplication of the
superior part of the equation. 300
3. The bisection of the eccentricity, and a stationary point of
equations, after the manner of Ptolemy.
4. The vicarious hypothesis by a free section of the eccentricity
made to agree as nearly as possible with the truth.
5. The physical hypothesis on the supposition of a perfect
circle.
6. The physical hypothesis on the supposition of a perfect
ellipse.
By the physical hypothesis, he meant the doctrine that the time of
a planet’s describing any part of its orbit is proportional to the
distance of the planet from the sun, for which supposition, as we have
said, he conceived that he had assigned physical reasons.
The two last hypotheses came the nearest to the truth, and differed
from it only by about eight minutes, the one in excess and the other
in defect. And, after being much perplexed by this remaining error, it
at last occurred to him41 that he might take another ellipsis,
exactly intermediate between the former one and the circle, and that
this must give the path and the motion of the planet. Making this
assumption, and taking the areas to represent the times, he now saw42 that both the longitude and the
distances of Mars would agree with observation to the requisite degree
of accuracy. The rectification of the former hypothesis, when thus
stated, may, perhaps, appear obvious. And Kepler informs us that he
had nearly been anticipated in this step (c. 55). “David Fabricius, to
whom I had communicated my hypothesis of cap. 45, was able, by his
observations, to show that it erred in making the distances too short
at mean longitudes; of which he informed me by letter while I was
laboring, by repeated efforts, to discover the true hypothesis. So
nearly did he get the start of me in detecting the truth.” But this
was less easy than it might seem. When Kepler’s first hypothesis was
enveloped in the complex construction requisite in order to apply it
to each point of the orbit, it was far more difficult to see where the
error lay, and Kepler hit upon it only by noticing the coincidences of
certain numbers, which, as he says, raised him as if from sleep, and
gave him a new light. We may observe, also, that he was perplexed to
reconcile this new view, according to which the planet described an
exact ellipse, with his former opinion, which represented the motion
by means of libration in an epicycle. “This,” he says, “was my
greatest trouble, that, though I considered and reflected till I was
almost mad, I could not find why the planet to which, with so much
probability, and with such an exact 301 accordance of the distances, libration
in the diameter of the epicycle was attributed, should, according to
the indication of the equations, go in an elliptical path. What an
absurdity on my part! as if libration in the diameter might not be a
way to the ellipse!”
41 De Stellâ Martis, c.
58.
42 Ibid. p. 235.
Another scruple respecting this theory arose from the impossibility
of solving, by any geometrical construction, the problem to which
Kepler was thus led, namely, “To divide the area of a semicircle in a
given ratio, by a line drawn from any point of the diameter.” This is
still termed “Kepler’s Problem,” and is, in fact, incapable of exact
geometrical solution. As, however, the calculation can be performed,
and, indeed, was performed by Kepler himself, with a sufficient degree
of accuracy to show that the elliptical hypothesis is true, the
insolubility of this problem is a mere mathematical difficulty in the
deductive process, to which Kepler’s induction gave rise.
Of Kepler’s physical reasonings we shall speak more at length on
another occasion. His numerous and fanciful
hypotheses had discharged their office, when they had suggested to him
his many lines of laborious calculation, and encouraged him under the
exertions and disappointments to which these led. The result of this
work was the formal laws of the motion of Mars, established by a clear
induction, since they represented, with sufficient accuracy, the best
observations. And we may allow that Kepler was entitled to the praise
which he claims in the motto on his first leaf. Ramus had said that if
any one would construct an astronomy without hypothesis, he would be
ready to resign to him his professorship in the University of Paris.
Kepler quotes this passage, and adds, “it is well, Ramus, that you
have run from this pledge, by quitting life and your professorship;43 if you held it still, I should, with
justice, claim it.” This was not saying too much, since he had
entirely overturned the hypothesis of eccentrics and epicycles, and
had obtained a theory which was a mere representation of the motions
and distances as they were observed.
43 Ramus perished in the Massacre of
St. Bartholomew.  302</div></body></text></TEI>