<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ninth Bridgewater Treatise</title><author>Babbage, Charles (1791-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="27">A PRIORI ARGUMENT IN FAVOUR OF THE OCCURRENCE OF MIRACLES.


 IN the present chapter it is proposed to prove, that—
 It is more probable that any
 law, at the knowledge of which we have arrived by observation, shall be subject
 to one of those violations which, according to Humes definition, constitutes
 a miracle, than that it should not be so subjected. 
 To show this, we may be allowed
 again to revert to the Calculating Engine: and to assume that it is possible
 to set the
[page] 150
 machine, so that it shall calculate any algebraic law whatsoever: and also possible so to arrange it, that
 at any periods, however remote, the first law shall be interrupted for
 one or more times, and be superseded by any other law; after which the
 original law shall again be produced, and no other deviation shall ever take
 place. Now, as all laws, which appear to us regular and uniform in their course,
 and to be subject to no exception, can be calculated by the engine: and as
 each of these laws may also be calculated by the same machine, subject to any
 assigned interruption, at distinct and definite periods; each simple law may
 be interrupted at any point by the temporary action of a portion of any one
 of all the other simple laws: it follows, that the class of laws subject
 to Interruption is far more extensive than that of laws which are uninterrupted. It is, in fact, infinitely more numerous. Therefore, the probability of
 any law with which we have become acquainted
[page] 151
 by observation being part of a
 much more extensive law, and of its having, to use mathematical language, singular
 points or discontinuous functions contained within it, is very large. Perhaps
 it may be objected, that the laws calculated by such an engine as I have referred
 to are not laws of nature; and that any deviation from laws produced by human
 mechanism does not come within Hume's definition of miracles. To this it may
 be answered, that a law of nature has been defined by Hume to rest upon experience,
 or repeated observation, just as the truth of testimony does. Now, the law produced
 by the engine may be arrived at by precisely the same means—namely, repeated
 observation. It may, however, be desirable to explain further the nature of
 the evidence, on which the fact, that the engine possesses those powers, rests.
[page] 152
 When the Calculating Engine has
 been set to compute the successive terms of any given law, which the observer
 is told will have an apparent exception (at, for example, the ten million and
 twenty-third term,) the observer is directed to note down the commencement of
 its computations; and, by comparing these results with his own independent
 calculations of the same law, he may verify the accuracy of the engine as far
 as he chooses. It may then be demonstrated to him, by the very structure of
 the machine, that if its motion were continued, it would, necessarily, at
 the end of a very long time, arrive at the ten-millionth term of the law assigned
 to it; and that, by an equal necessity, it would have passed through
 all the intermediate terms.* The inquirer is now desired to turn on the wheels
 with his own hand, until they are precisely in the same situation as they would
 have been had the engine itself gone on continuously, to the ten-millionth term.
 The machine is again put in motion,
 * This can be done in a few minutes.
[page] 153
 and the observer again finds that each successive term it calculates fulfils
 the original law. But, after passing twenty-two terms, he now observes one term which does not fulfil the original law, but which does coincide with
 the predicted exception. The continued movement now again produces terms according
 with the first law, and the observer may continue to verify them as long as
 he wishes. It may then be demonstrated to him, by the very structure of the
 machine, that, if its motion were continued, it would be impossible that
 any other deviation from the apparent law could ever occur at any future time.
 Such is the evidence to the observer; and, if the superintendent of the engine
 were, at his request, to make it calculate a great variety of different laws,
 each interrupted by special and remote exceptions, he would have ample ground
 to believe in the assertion of its director, that he could so arrange the engine
 that any
[page] 154
 law, however complicated, might
 be calculated to any assigned extent, and then there should arise one apparent
 exception; after which the original law should continue uninterrupted for ever.
 Let us now consider the miracle alluded to by Hume—the restoration of a dead
 man to life. According to the definition of that author, our belief that such
 a fact is contrary to the laws of nature, arises from our uniform experience
 against it. Our personal experience is small: we must therefore have recourse
 to testimony; and from that we learn, that the dead are never restored
 to life; and, consequently, we have the uniform experience of all mankind since
 the creation, against one assigned instance of a dead man being so restored.
 Let us now find the numerical amount of this evidence. Assuming the origin of
 the human race to have been about six thousand years ago, and taking thirty
 years as the duration of a generation, we have—
[page] 155

 And allowing that the average population
 of the earth has been a thousand millions, we find that there have been born
 and have died since the creation,

 Such, then, according to Hume,
 are the odds against the truth of the miracle: that is to say, it is found
 from experience, that it is about two hundred thousand millions to one against
 a dead man having been restored to life. Let us now compare this with a parallel
 case in the calculations of the engine; let us suppose the number above stated
 to be a hundred million times as great, or that the truth of the miracles is
 opposed by a number of instances, expressed by twenty places of figures.
[page] 156
 The engine may be set to count the natural numbers—1,2, 3, 4, &c.; and
 it shall continue to fulfil that law, not merely for the number of times just
 mentioned, for that number is quite insignificant among the vast periods it
 involves; but the natural numbers shall follow in continual succession, until
 they have reached an amount which requires for its expression above a hundred
 million places of figures. If every letter in the volume now before the reader's
 eyes were changed into a figure, and if all the figures contained in a thousand
 such volumes were arranged in order, the whole together would yet fall far short
 of the vast induction the observer would then have had in favour of the truth
 of the law of natural numbers. The widest range of all the cycles of astronomy
 and geology combined, sink into insignificance before such a period. Yet, shall
 the engine, true to the prediction of its director, after the lapse of myriads
 of ages, fulfil its task, and give that one, the first and only exception
 to that time-sanctioned law. What would have
[page] 157
 been the chances against the appearance
 of the excepted case, immediately prior to its occurrence? It would have had,
 according to Hume, the evidence of all experience against it, with a force myriads
 of times more strong than that against any miracle. Now, let the reader, who
 has fully entered into the nature of the argument, ask himself this question:—Does he believe that such an engine has really been contrived, and hat reasonable
 grounds has he for that belief? The testimony of any single witness is small
 against such odds; besides, the witness may deceive himself. Whether he speaks
 truly, will be estimated by his moral character—whether he deceives himself,
 will be estimated by his intellectual character. The probability that such an
 engine has been contrived, will, however, receive great addition, when it is
 remarked, that mathematical—and, especially, geometrical evidence is, of all
 others, that in
[page] 158
 which the fewest mistakes arise,
 and in which they are most readily discovered; and when it is added, that the
 fact of the invention of such an engine rests on precisely the same species
 of evidence as the propositions of Euclid, and may be deduced from the drawings
 with all the force of demonstration. Whether such an engine could be actually
 made in the present state of mechanical art, is a question of quite a different
 order: it must rest upon the opinions of those who have had extensive experience
 in that art. The author has not the slightest hesitation in stating his opinion
 to be, that it is fully within those limits. This, however, is a question foreign
 to the nature of the argument, which might have been stated in a more abstract
 manner, without any reference to such an engine. As, however, the argument really
 arose from that machine, and as visible forms make a much deeper impression
 on the mind than any abstract reasonings, it has been stated in conjunction
 with that subject.
[page] 159</div></body></text></TEI>