<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ninth Bridgewater Treatise</title><author>Babbage, Charles (1791-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="17">ARGUMENT FROM LAWS INTERMITTING ON THE NATURE OF MIRACLES.*
 The object of the present chapter
 is to show that it is more consistent with the attributes of the Deity to look
 upon miracles not as deviations from the laws assigned by the Almighty for the
 government of matter and of mind; but as the exact fulfilment of much more
 extensive laws than those we suppose to exist. In fact, if we were endued with
 acuter senses and higher reasoning faculties, they are the very points we should
 seek to observe, as the tests of any hypothesis we had been led to frame concerning
 the nature of
 * See Note D in Appendix.
[page] 93
 those laws. Even with our present
 imperfect faculties we frequently arrive at the highest confirmation of our
 views of the laws of nature, by tracing their action under singular circumstances.
 The mode by which I propose to arrive at these conclusions is, by again appealing
 to the judgment which each individual will himself form, when examining that
 piece of mere human mechanism, to which the argument so frequently compels me
 to advert. If he agrees with me, that the second of the two views presented
 to him exhibits a higher degree of knowledge, and a higher exertion of power,
 than the first, he must inevitably conclude, that the view here suggested of
 the nature of miracles, assigns a far higher degree of knowledge and power to
 the Deity. Let the reader suppose himself placed before the calculating engine,
 and let him again observe and ascertain, by lengthened
[page] 94
 induction, the nature of the law it is computing. Let him imagine that he
 has seen the changes wrought on its face during the lapse of thousands of years,
 and that, without one solitary exception, he has found the engine register the
 series of square numbers. Suppose, now, the maker of that machine to say to
 the observer, "I will, by moving a certain mechanism, which is invisible to
 you, cause the "engine to make one cube number instead "of a square,
 and then to revert to its former "course of square numbers;" the observer would
 be inclined to attribute to him a degree of power but little superior to that
 which was necessary to form the original engine. But, let the same observer,
 after the same lapse of time—the same amount of uninterrupted experience of
 the uniformity of the law of square numbers, hear the maker of the engine say
 to him— "The next number which "shall appear on those wheels, and which "you expect to find a square number, shall
[page] 95
 "not be so. When the machine was originally ordered to make these calculations,
 " I impressed on it a law, which should coincide with that of square numbers
 in every " case, except the one which is now about to " appear; after
 which no future exception can " ever occur, but the unvarying law of the " squares
 shall be pursued until the machine " itself perishes from decay." Undoubtedly
 the observer would ascribe a greater degree of power to the artist who had thus
 willed that event which he foretells at the distance of ages before its arrival.
 If the contriver of the engine then explain to him, that, by the very structure
 of it, he has power to order any number of such apparent deviations from
 its laws to occur at any future periods, however remote, and that each of these
 may be of a different kind; and, if he also inform him, that he gave it that
 structure in order to meet events, which he foresaw must
[page] 96
 happen at those respective periods,
 there can be no doubt that the observer would ascribe to the inventor far higher
 knowledge than if, when those events severally occurred, he were to intervene,
 and temporarily to alter the calculations of the machine. If, besides this,
 the contriver were so far to explain the structure of the engine that the observer
 could himself, by some simple process, such as the mere moving of a bolt, call
 into action those apparent deviations whenever certain combinations were presented
 to his eye; if he were thus to impart a power of predicting such excepted cases,
 dependent on the will, though in other respects beyond the limits of the observer's
 power and knowledge,—such a structure would be admitted as evidence of a still
 more skilful contrivance. The engine which, in a former chapter, I introduced
 to the reader, possesses these powers. It may be set, so as to obey any
[page] 97
 given law; and, at any periods, however remote, to make one or more seeming exceptions to that law. It is, however, to be observed, that the apparent law which the spectator arrived at, by an almost unlimited induction, is
 not the full expression of the law by which the machine acts; and that the
 excepted case is as absolutely and irresistibly the necessary consequence of
 its primitive adjustment, as is any individual calculation amongst the countless
 multitude which it may previously have produced. When the construction of that
 engine was first attempted, I did not seek to give to it the power of making
 calculations so far beyond the reach of mathematical analysis as these appear
 to be: nor can I now foresee a probable period at which they may become practically
 available to human purposes. I had determined to invest the invention with a
 degree of generality which should include a wide range of mathematical power; and I was
[page] 98
 well aware that the mechanical
 generalisations I had organised contained within them much more than I had leisure
 to study, and some things which will probably remain unproductive to a far distant
 day. Amongst those combinations which I was afterwards induced to examine, I
 observed the powers I have now recorded; and the reflections they produced
 in my own mind, impelled me to pursue them for a time. If the reader agrees
 with me in opinion, that these speculations lead to a more exalted view of the
 great Author of the universe than any we have hitherto possessed, he must also
 have arrived at the conclusion, that the study of the most abstract branch of
 practical mechanics, combined with that of the most abstruse portions of mathematical
 science, has no tendency to incapacitate the human mind from the perception
 of the evidences of natural religion; and that even those very sources themselves
 may furnish arguments which open views of the grandeur of creation
[page] 99
 perhaps more extensive than any
 which the sciences of observation or of physics have yet supplied. It may not,
 perhaps, be without its use to suggest another illustration derived from the
 same quarter respecting the nature of miracles. It is known that mathematical
 laws are sometimes expressed by curves. The figure 1 (p. 101) represents a re-entering
 curve of four dimensions, whose law of formation is given in the n te.* A slight
 change in the nature of the constants makes it assume the form of fig. 2, which
 is still a continuous curve; but a further change of the constants causes it
 to have two ovals, quite disconnected from the larger portion; and, as the
 constants again alter, these ovals are reduced to points.

[page] 100
 In all four cases, every point
 in each branch of the curve obeys the same general law. The points, P and Q,
 though strictly invisible to the eye, are yet detected by mathematical analysis,
 and fulfil as precisely the original equation as any of the infinite number
 of other points, which constitute the rest of the curve. These points might
 be situated on the curve itself, and they are well known to mathematicians.
 It is to these singular points, which really fulfil the law of the curve,
 but which present to those who judge of them only by the organ of sight an apparent
 discontinuity, that I wish to call the attention, as offering an illustration
 of the doctrine here explained respecting miracles. It has been remarked, in
 the beginning of the present chapter, that it is to the singular points—to those
 points of such infinitely rare occurrence in a curve—that we frequently have
 recourse, as the test of our theories, for explaining the phenomena of nature.
[page] 101

[page 102]
[page] 103
 The existence of conical refraction
 in certain crystals, under peculiar circumstances, was predicted by Sir W. Hamilton; and, from an analytical investigation into the nature of the curve surface,
 which represents the form of the luminiferous wave within the crystal, he ascertained
 that it had four conoidal cusps, at each of which there were, consequently,
 an infinite number of tangent planes. The course of the refracted ray being
 determined by the tangent plane to the wave surface, it followed that a single
 ray within the crystal, transmitted in the direction of the line joining two
 opposite cusps, corresponded to an infinite number of refracted rays without,
 constituting a refracted cone. A second case of conical refraction, predicted
 by Sir William Hamilton, depended on another mathematical fact—namely, that
 the wave surface is touched in an infinite number of points, constituting a
 small circle of contact, by a single plane parallel to one of the circular sections
 of the surface of elasticity.
[page] 104
 Professor Lloyd undertook to make the very delicate experiments required for
 this most interesting investigation. Of its great importance he was fully aware,
 for he remarks— "Here, then, are two singular and unexpected consequences of
 the undulatory theory, " not only unsupported by any facts hitherto " observed,
 but even opposed to all the analogies derived from experience. If confirmed
 " by experiment, they would furnish new and "almost convincing proofs of
 that theory; " and, if disproved, on the other hand, it is " evident that the
 theory must be abandoned " or modified.* On examining the first of these cases,
 experimentally, the fact of conical refraction was fully established. But a
 new result now presented itself: the rays of light thus conically
 * Trans, of Royal Irish Academy,
 Vol. XVII.
[page] 105
 refracted were found to be polarized; and it was observed, that "the angle between the " planes of polarization
 of any two rays of " the cone was half the angle between the " planes, containing
 the rays themselves, and " the axis." This new law, thus approximately obtained
 by experiment, led the observer back to the theory; and, on a further examination,
 he detected in that theory the very law he had just discovered by observation.
 The second case of conical refraction required experiments of a still more delicate
 nature. They were, however, made, and succeeded equally. The conically refracted
 ray was found to be polarised, according to the law which, in this instance,
 analysis had predicted; and, to complete the triumph of this union of theory
 and experiment, the measures in both cases, when made under proper circumstances,
 accorded with the theoretical conclusions,
[page] 106
 within such limits as might be fairly attributed to the unavoidable errors
 of observation. It is worthy of remark, that, at first, two facts presented
 themselves, which seemed to be at variance with the theory. In the first place,
 the emergent rays formed a solid cone, instead of a conical surface; and, in
 the second place, the calculated angle, subtended by the sides of the cone,
 was only one half the observed angle. Both the facts were shown to depend upon
 the size of the aperture through which the light was admitted, and to
 arise from the rays which were inclined at small angles to the single theoretical
 direction. When the aperture was diminished, so as to be very small,
 (the case calculated by Sir William Hamilton,) then the cone of light became
 truly a conical surface, and the observed angle was the same as the calculated
 one.*
 * Those who are acquainted with
 the history of astronomy, cannot fail to recall a parallel discrepancy between
 observation and calculation in the theory of gravity. It appeared
[page] 107
 to result from that law, that the
 motion of the moon's apogee was only one half of what observation proved it
 to be; and it is singular that Euler, D'Alembert, and Clairaut arrived, by
 different methods, at the same erroneous result; and the truth of the great
 law of gravity appeared for a time to be doubtful. Clairaut, however, having
 assumed that the law of gravity contained a term sensible only at small distances
 (such as that of the moon), re-calculated the question, and finding it necessary,
 in consequence of the existence of this term, to push his approximation further
 than he had done, arrived at the conclusion, that the co-efficient of the new
 term vanished; and also, that when the approximations were sufficiently pursued,
 the simple law of the inverse square of the distance accounted for the whole
 of the motions which observations had discovered.
[page] 108</div></body></text></TEI>