<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="4">CHAPTER II.
I was in this state of mind, when early one morning in the
beginning of summer, soon after I rose, I was startled by
the sound of trumpets in the plain near the château. The
bugle at the gate was presently sounded; the drawbridge
was let down; and the Marquis de Villeroy entered the
court-yard, accompanied by about thirty knights in complete
armour. I saluted him with respect, and the tenderness
excited by recent grief. He took me by the hand,
after a short repast in the hall, and led me to my closet.
“My son,” said he, “it is time to throw off the effeminacy
of sorrow, and to prove yourself a true soldier of
the standard of France.”
“I trust, my lord,” replied I, with modest earnestness,
“that you well know, there is nothing after which my heart
so ardently aspires. There is nothing that I know worth
living for but honour. Show me the path that leads to it,
or rather show me the occasion that affords scope for the
love of honour to display itself, and you shall then see
whether I am backward to embrace it. I have a passion
pent up within me, that feeds upon my vitals: it disdains
speech; it burns for something more unambiguous and substantial.”
[11]
“It is well,” rejoined my uncle. “I expected to find
you thus. Your reply to my admonition is worthy of the
blood of your ancestors, and of the maternal instructions
of my sister. And, were you as dull as the very stones
you tread on, what I have to tell you might even then rouse
you into animation and ardour.”
After this short preface my uncle proceeded to relate a
tale, every word of which inflamed my spirits, and raised
all my passions in arms. I had heard something imperfectly
of the state of my country; but my mother carefully
kept me in ignorance, that my ambition might not be excited
too soon, and that, when excited, it might be with the
fullest effect. While I impatiently longed for an occasion
of glory, I was far from apprehending, what I now found
to be true, that the occasion which at this period presented
itself, was such, that all the licence of fiction could scarcely
have improved it.
The Marquis de Villeroy described to me the league now
subsisting against France. He revived in my memory, by
terms of the most fervent loyalty, the accomplishments and
talents of my royal master. He spoke with aversion of the
phlegmatic and crafty disposition of his imperial rival[3];
and, with the language of glowing indignation, inveighed
against the fickleness of the capricious Henry.[4] He described
the train of disasters, which had at length induced
the king to take the field in person. He contrasted, with
great effect, the story of the gallant Chevalier Bayard, the
knight without fear and without reproach, whose blood was
still fresh in the plains of the Milanese, with that of the
Constable of Bourbon, the stain of chivalry, whom inglorious
resentment and ungoverned ambition had urged to join the
enemies of his country, in neglect of his loyalty and his
oath. He stimulated me by the example of the one, and
the infamy of the other; and assured me that there never
was an opportunity more favourable for acquiring immortal
renown.
I wanted no prompter in a passion of this sort; and immediately
set about collecting the whole force of my clients
and retainers. I shook off the inglorious softness of my[12]
melancholy, and was all activity and animation. The lessons
of my youth were now called into play. I judged it
necessary to invite the assistance of some person of experience
to assist me in marshalling my men; but I did much
of what was to be done myself, and I did it well. It was
my first employment in the morning: and the last that was
witnessed by the setting sun. My excellent mother had
left my revenues in the best order, and I spared no expense
in the gratification of my favourite passion.
However eager I felt myself to take the field, the desire
to appear in a manner worthy of a Count de St. Leon restrained
me; and I did not join the royal army till the
Imperialists, having broken up the siege of Marseilles, and
retreated with precipitation into Italy, the king had already
crossed the Alps, entered the Milanese, and gained uncontested
possession of the capital.
From Milan Francis proceeded to Pavia. Glory was the
idol of his heart; and he was the more powerfully excited
to the attack of that place, because it was the strongest and
best fortified post in the whole duchy. The more he displayed
of military prowess, the more firmly he believed he
should fix himself in his newly acquired dominions; the
inhabitants would submit to him the more willingly, and
the enemy be less encouraged to enter into a fresh contention
for what he had acquired. Such at least were the
motives that he assigned for his proceedings: in reality
perhaps he was principally induced by the brilliancy which
he conceived would attend on the undertaking.
It was a few weeks after the opening of the siege, that
I presented myself to my royal master. He received me
with those winning and impressive manners by which he
was so eminently distinguished. He recollected immediately
all that had passed at our interview in the Vale of
Ardres, and warmly expressed the obligations which France
had at various times owed to my ancestors. He spoke with
earnest respect of the virtues and wisdom of my mother,
and commended the resolution by which she had in former
instances held me back from the public theatre. “Young
gentleman,” said the king, “I doubt not the gallantry of
your spirit; I see the impatience of a martial temper written[13]
in your face: I expect you to act in a manner worthy
of your illustrious race, and of the instructions of a woman
who deserved to be herself a pattern to all the matrons of
France. Fear not that I shall suffer your accomplishments
to rust in obscurity. I shall employ you. I shall assign
you the post of danger and of renown. Fill it nobly; and
from that hour I shall rank you in the catalogue of my
chosen friends.”
The siege of Pavia proved indeed to be a transaction, in
the course of which military honour might well be acquired.
It was defended by a small, but veteran garrison, and by
one of the ablest captains that Europe at that time possessed.[5]
He interrupted the approaches of the besiegers
by frequent and furious sallies. In vain, by the aid of our
excellent artillery, did we make wide and repeated breaches
in the fortifications. No sooner did we attempt to enter by
the passage we had opened, than we found ourselves encountered
by a body composed of the choicest and bravest
soldiers of the garrison. The governor of the city, who,
though grey-headed and advanced in years, was profuse of
every youthful exertion, was ordinarily at the head of this
body. If we deferred our attack, or, not having succeeded
in it, proposed to commence it anew with the dawn of the
following day, we were sure to find a new wall sprung up
in the room of the other, as if by enchantment. Frequently
the governor anticipated the success of our batteries;
and the old fortification was no sooner demolished, than we
beheld, to our astonishment and mortification, a new wall,
which his prudence and skill had erected at a small interval
within the line of the former.
One of these attacks took place on the second day after
my arrival at the camp of our sovereign. Every thing that
I saw was new to me, and inflamed me with ardour. The
noise of the cannon, which had preceded the attack, and
which was now hushed; the inspiring sounds of martial
music which succeeded that noise; the standards floating
in the air; the firm and equal tread of the battalion that
advanced; the armour of the knights; the rugged, resolute,
and intrepid countenances of the infantry;—all swelled my[14]
soul with transport hitherto unexperienced. I had beheld
the smoke of the artillery, in the midst of which every
thing was lost and confounded; I had waited in awful
suspense till the obscurity should be dissipated; I saw with
pleasure and surprise the ruin of the wall, and the wideness
of the breach. All that had been recorded of the military
feats of Christian valour seemed then to stand crowded in
my busy brain; the generosity, the condescension, the kindness,
with which the king had addressed me the day before,
urged me to treble exertion. I was in the foremost rank.
We surmounted the ditch. We were resisted by a chosen
body of Spaniards. The contention was obstinate; brave
men, generous and enterprising spirits, fell on the one side
and the other. I seized the cloth of a standard, as, in the
playing of the wind, it was brought near to my hand. Between
me and the Spaniard that held it there ensued an obstinate
struggle. I watched my opportunity, and with my
sword severed the flag from its staff. At this moment the
trumpets of the king sounded a retreat. I had received
two severe wounds, one in the shoulder and the other in
the thigh, in the contest. I felt myself faint with the loss
of blood. A French officer, of a rude appearance and gigantic
stature, accosting me with the appellation of boy;
commanded me to surrender the standard to him. I refused;
and, to convince him I was in earnest, proceeded
to wrap it round my body, and fastened it under my arm.
Soon after I became insensible, and in this situation was
accidentally found by my uncle and his companions, who
immediately took me and my prize under their care. As
soon as I was a little recovered of my wounds, the king
seized an opportunity, after having bestowed loud commendations
upon my gallantry, of conferring the honours
of knighthood upon me in the face of the whole army.
While our tents were pitched under the walls of Pavia,
I was continually extending the circle of my acquaintance
among the young gentry of France, who, like myself, had
attended their sovereign in this memorable expedition. I
had some enemies, made such by the distinctions I obtained
during the siege. But they were few; the greater
part courted me the more, the more I showed myself worthy[15]
of their attachment. Envy is not a passion that finds easy
root in a Frenchman’s bosom. I was one of the youngest
of those who attended on the siege; but my brothers in
arms were generous rivals, who in the field obstinately
strove with me for superior glory, but over the convivial
board forgot their mutual competitions, and opened their
hearts to benevolence and friendship. “Let us not,” was
a sentiment I heard often repeated, “forget the object that
led us from our pleasant homes to pour from the heights
of the Alps upon the fields of Italy. It is to humble the
imperious Spaniard—to punish the disloyal Bourbon—to
vindicate the honour of our beloved and illustrious monarch.
Those walls cover the enemy; yonder mountains serve to
hide them from our assault; let no Frenchman mistake
him who marches under the same standard for an adversary.”
The trenches had not been opened before Pavia till about
the beginning of November. The winter overtook us, and
the siege was yet in progress; with some apparent advantage
indeed to our side of the question, but by no means
promising an instant conclusion. The season set in with
unusual severity; and both officer and soldier were glad,
as much as possible, to fence out its rigour by the indulgences
of the genial board. My finances, as I have said,
were at the commencement of the expedition in excellent
order: I had brought with me a considerable sum; and it
was not spared upon the present occasion.
There were however other things to be attended to, beside
the demands of conviviality. The king became impatient
of the delays of the siege. The garrison and the
inhabitants were reduced to great extremities; but the governor
discovered no symptoms of a purpose to surrender.
In the mean time intelligence was brought, that Bourbon
was making the most extraordinary exertions in Germany,
and promised to lead to the enemy a reinforcement of
twelve thousand men from that country; while the imperial
generals, by mortgaging their revenues, and pawning their
jewels, and still more by their eloquence and influence with
those under their command, were able to keep together the
remains of a disheartened and defeated army in expectation[16]
of his arrival. There was some danger therefore, if the
siege were not speedily terminated, that the king might
ultimately be obliged to raise it with ignominy, or to fight
the enemy under every disadvantage. Francis however
was not to be deterred from his undertaking. He swore a
solemn oath, that Pavia should be his, or he would perish
in the attempt.
Thus circumstanced, he conceived a very extraordinary
project. Pavia is defended on one side by the Tesino, the
scene of the first of the four famous battles by which Hannibal
signalised his invasion of Italy. The king believed
that if this river could by the labour of his army be diverted
from its course, the town must instantly fall into his hands.
He was encouraged to the undertaking, by recollecting a
stratagem of a similar nature by which Cyrus formerly
made himself master of the city of Babylon. It was a
thought highly flattering to the grandeur of his soul, to
imagine that posterity would in this instance institute a
parallel between him and Cyrus the Great.
The plan for diverting the course of the Tesino produced
a new and extraordinary scene. It was, as may well
be believed, a work of uncommon labour. A new channel
was to be scooped out and deepened; and, while the stream
was turned into this channel, piles were to be sunk, and an
immense mound of earth created, as an effectual impediment
to the waters resuming their former course. This
was a heavy burthen to the soldier, in addition to the disadvantage
of being encamped during the course of a winter
remarkably severe for the climate in which we fought. By
any other army the task would have been performed with
cloudiness and discontent, if not complained of with repining
and murmurs. But here the gaiety of the French
character displayed itself. The nobility of France, who
attended their sovereign in great numbers, accompanied the
infantry in their labour. We laid aside the indulgence of
the marquée, of tapestry and carpets; we threw off our
upper garments; and each seized a spade, a barrow of earth,
or a mattock. We put our hands to the engines, and refused
no effort under pretence that it was sordid or severe.
While the trees were leafless, and nature appeared bound[17]
up in frost, sweat ran down our faces and bedewed our
limbs. The army were encouraged by our example. An
employment which, under other circumstances, would have
been regarded as rigid, was thus made a source of new
hilarity and amusement. It was a memorable sight to behold
the venerable and grey-headed leaders of the French
army endeavouring to exert the strength and activity of
their early years. To me, who had but lately arrived at
the stature of manhood, and who was accustomed to all the
exercises which give strength and vigour to the frame, this
new employment was in no degree burdensome. I felt in
it the satisfaction that a swift man experiences when he
enters the lists of the race; I congratulated myself upon
the nature of my education; if it be a sin to covet honour,
that guilt was mine; and, so great was my appetite for it,
that I was inexpressibly rejoiced to observe the various
ways in which it might be gratified.
Strange as it may seem, this scene of a winter-camp, in the
midst of blood and sweat, surrounded with dangers, and called
on for unparalleled exertions, appears to me, through the vista
of years that is now interposed between, to have been one of
the happiest of my life. The gay labours and surprises of
the day were succeeded by a convivial evening, in which
we did not the less open our hearts, though frequently
liable to be interrupted in our midnight revels by the inexhaustible
activity and stratagems of the enemy. In this
various and ever-shifting scene, I forgot the disasters that
occurred, and the blood that flowed around me. All sense
of a large and impartial morality was, for the time at least,
deadened in my breast. I was ever upon the alert. The
diversity of events neither suffered my spirits to flag, nor
reflection to awake. It is only upon such occasions, or
occasions like these, that a man is able fully to feel what life
is, and to revel in its exuberance. Above all, I was delighted
with the society and friendship of my brother-officers.
They honoured me; they loved me. I seemed to feel what
sympathy was; and to have conscious pleasure in making
one in a race of beings like myself. Such were my sensations.
[18]
It must not, however, be imagined, that all about me
felt in these respects as I did. I was deeply indebted in
this particular to my youth and my fortune. The old endeavoured
to brace themselves in vain; they sunk under
the continual pressure. The poor soldier from the ranks
laboured incessantly, and I laboured as much as he; but
he had little opportunity to recruit his vigour and renovate
his strength. There was yet another class of persons in the
camp, whose gaiety was much less interrupted than mine.
These were, the king, and the generals who commanded
under him. They could not be entirely devoid of thought
and consideration. They suffered much anxiety from the
length of the siege; and felt that every period of delay
increased the doubtfulness of the event.
Antonio de Leyva, governor of the city, necessarily felt
himself alarmed at the extraordinary project in which we
were engaged, and made every exertion to prevent it. One
evening the king sent for me to his tent, and told me in
confidence that the enemy intended that very night to make
three several attacks upon our mound, one on each side of
the stream, and one by means of boats in the centre. Two
of these, he said, were merely intended as feints; the west
bank of the Tesino was the point against which their principal
exertions would be directed. On that side he was
resolved to command in person; the boats with which he
proposed to resist their flota he confided to one of the most
famous and valuable officers of his army; the detachment
on the east bank he purposed to intrust to my uncle and
myself. He observed, that the detachment he could spare
for that purpose, after having formed the other two bodies,
and reserved a sufficient number for the defence of the
camp and the works, would be small; and he warned me
to the exertion of a particular vigilance. It would be
doubly unfortunate, if a body, the attack upon which was
to be merely a feigned one, should nevertheless be routed.
“Go,” added he, “fulfil my expectations; deport yourself
answerably to the merit of your first achievement; and
depend upon it that you will prove hereafter one of the most
eminent supporters of the martial glory of France.”
[19]
The Marquis de Villeroy divided our little force into
two bodies: with the larger he lay in wait for the enemy
near the scene of the expected attack: the smaller he confided
to my direction, and placed so that we might be able
to fall upon the rear of the garrison-troops as soon as they
should be fully engaged with our comrades. In the situation
assigned me I took advantage of the skirts of a
wood, which enabled me to approach very near to the expected
route of our assailants, without being perceived by
them. The night was extremely dark, yet the vicinity of
my position was such, that I could count the numbers of
the adversary as they passed along before my hiding-place.
I was alarmed to find that they amounted to at least the
triple of what we had been taught to expect. They were
no sooner past, than I despatched to the king a young
knight, my particular friend, who happened to be with me,
to urge the necessity of a reinforcement. At the same time
I sent a messenger to my uncle, by a circuitous route, to
inform him of what I had observed, and the step I had
taken, and to entreat him to defer the attack as long as consistently
with propriety it should be possible. The enemy,
however, had no sooner arrived at the place of his destination,
than the troops of the marquis, no longer capable of
restraint, rushed to engage. The Spaniards were at first surprised,
but a short time led them to suspect the weakness
of their assailants; nor was the assistance I brought to my
uncle sufficient to turn the fortune of the fight. We lost
many of our men; the rest apparently gave ground; and
it was a vain attempt, amidst the darkness of the night, to
endeavour to restore order and rally them to the assault.
We were already almost completely overpowered, when
the succours we expected reached us. They were, however,
unable to distinguish friend from enemy. A storm of
mingled rain and snow had come on, which benumbed our
limbs, drove fiercely in our faces, and rendered every object
alike viewless. The carnage which in this situation took
place was terrible. Our blows were struck at random. A
Frenchman was not less dreadful than a Spaniard. When
the battle ceased, scarcely one of the enemy was left alive;
but we observed with astonishment and horror the number[20]
of the besiegers who had probably, in the midst of the confusion,
been cut to pieces by their own countrymen.
I am now arrived at the period which put an end to the
festivity and jocundness of the campaign. All after this
was one continued series of disaster. About the close of
January, our work, though not wholly interrupted, was considerably
retarded by a succession of heavy rains. This
was injurious to us in many ways; our project, which was
executed in the midst of waters, rendered additional damp
a matter of serious consideration. We were also seized
with an apprehension of still greater magnitude, which was
speedily realised. The snows being at length completely
dissolved, and the quantity of water continually increasing,
we perceived one afternoon strong symptoms that our
mound, the principal subject of our labour and source of
our hope, was giving way in various places. The next
morning at daybreak, it rushed down every where at once
with wonderful violence and noise. It is difficult to describe
the sensation of anguish which was instantly and
universally diffused. The labour of many weeks was overthrown
in a moment. As we had proceeded in our work,
we every day saw ourselves nearer the object to which we
aspired. At this time our project was almost completed, and
Pavia was in imagination already in our hands, to gain
possession of which had cost us such unremitted exertions,
the display of so much gallantry, and the loss of so many
soldiers. We were confounded at the catastrophe we saw.
We gazed at each other, each in want of encouragement,
and every one unable to afford it.
Still, however, we were not destitute of advantages. The
garrison began to be in want both of ammunition and provisions.
They were in a general state of discontent, almost
of mutiny, which scarcely all the address and authority of
the governor were able to suppress. If the town continued
longer unrelieved, it was sure to fall into our hands. But
even this our last hope was considerably diminished by the
intelligence we received the very day after the destruction
of our mound, that the imperial army, after having received
large reinforcements, was approaching in considerable force.
The king had some time before, in the height of his confidence,[21]
and elation of his heart, sent off a detachment of
six thousand men to invade the kingdom of Naples; for
upon that, as well as the Milanese, he had inherited pretensions
from his immediate predecessors.
But, though the enemy was superior in numbers, and a
part perhaps of their forces better disciplined than ours,
they laboured under several disadvantages to which we were
not exposed. The Emperor, though his dominions were
more extensive, did not derive from them a revenue equal
to that of Francis. As he did not take the field in person,
the war appeared to his subjects only a common war, proceeding
upon the ordinary motives of war. But my countrymen
were led by their sovereign, were fresh from the
recent insolence of an invasion of their own territory, and
fought at once for personal glory and their country’s honour.
The king, who commanded them, seemed expressly formed
to obtain their attachment and affection. His nobles became
enthusiastic by the example of his enthusiasm, and willingly
disbursed their revenues to give prosperity and éclat to the
campaign.
The first question that arose upon the approach of the
enemy was, whether we should break up the siege, and
attend in some strong post the slow, but sure, effect of their
want of money, and the consequent dispersion of their
troops, or wait their attack in our present posture. The
former advice was safe; but to the gallant spirit of Francis
it appeared ignominious. He was upon all occasions the
partisan of rapid measures and decisive proceedings; and
his temper, with the exception of a few wary and deliberate
counsellors, accorded with that of our whole army. For
some days we congratulated ourselves upon the wisdom of
our choice; we presented to the enemy so formidable an
appearance, that, notwithstanding the cogent motives he
had to proceed, he hesitated long before he ventured to
attack us. At length, however, the day came that was
pregnant with so momentous expectation.
If through the whole limits of our camp there was not
a man that did not feel himself roused upon this glorious
occasion, to me it was especially interesting. The scene
accorded with the whole purpose of my education, and[22]
novelty made it impressive. I lived only in the present
moment. I had not a thought, a wish, a straggling imagination,
that wandered beyond the circuit of the day. My
soul was filled; at one minute wild with expectation, and
at another awed into solemnity. There is something indescribably
delicious in this concentration of the mind. It
raises a man above himself; and makes him feel a certain
nobleness and elevation of character, of the possession of
which he was to that hour unconscious. Fear and pain
were ideas that could find no harbour in my bosom: I regarded
this as the most memorable of days, and myself as
the most fortunate of mortals. Far indeed was I from anticipating
the disgraceful event, in which this elation of
heart speedily terminated.
The sun rose bright in a cloudless sky. The cold of the
season was such, as only to give new lightness and elasticity
to the muscles and animal spirits. I saw few of those
objects of nature, which in this delightful climate gave so
sacred a pleasure to the human soul. But in my present
temper there was no object of sight so ravishing, as the firm
and equal steps of the martial bands, the impatience of the
war-horse, and the display of military standards; nor any
music so enchanting, as the shrillness of the pipe, the
clangor of the trumpet, the neighing of steeds, and the
roaring of cannon. It is thus that man disguises to himself
the real nature of his occupation; and clothes that which
is of all things the most nefarious or most to be lamented,
with the semblance of jubilee and festival.
The Imperialists were at first unable to withstand the
efforts of French valour. They gave way on every side;
we pursued our advantage with impetuosity. To the
slaughter of whole ranks mowed down with tremendous
celerity, to the agonies of the dying, I was blind; their
groans had no effect on my organ, for my soul was occupied
in another direction. My horse’s heels spurned their
mangled limbs, and were red with their blood. I fought
not merely with valour, but with fury; I animated those
around me by my example and my acclamations. It may
seem contrary to delicacy to speak with this freedom of my
own praises; but I am at my present writing totally changed[23]
and removed from what I was, and I write with the freedom
of a general historian. It is this simplicity and ingenuousness
that shall pervade the whole of my narrative.
The fortune of the day speedily changed. The cowardice
and desertion of our Swiss allies gave the first signal
of adversity. The gallant commander of the garrison of
Pavia sallied out in the midst of the fight, and suddenly
attacked us in the rear. A stratagem of the Imperial general
effected the rout of our cavalry. The whole face of the
field was utterly reversed.
It would be in vain for me to attempt to describe even
the small part that I beheld of the calamity and slaughter
of the French army. At this distance of time, the recollection
of it opens afresh the almost obliterated wounds of
my heart. I saw my friends cut down, and perish on
every side. Those who, together with myself, had marched
out in the morning, swelled with exultation and hope, now
lay weltering in their blood. Their desires, their thoughts,
their existence, were brought to a fatal termination. The
common soldiers were hewed and cut to pieces by hundreds,
without note and observation. Many of the first nobility
of France, made desperate by the change of the battle,
rushed into the thickest of the foe, and became so many
voluntary sacrifices; choosing rather to perish, than to turn
their backs with dishonour.
In the battle I had two horses killed under me. The
first of them suffered a sort of gradual destruction. He had
already received one wound in the nostrils, and another in
the neck, when a third shot carried away two of his feet,
and laid him prostrate on the earth. Bernardin, my
faithful attendant, observed what was passing, and immediately
brought me a fresh charger; but I had not long
mounted him, when he received a wound which killed him
on the spot. I was myself hurt in several places, and at
length the stroke of a sabre brought me to the ground.
Here I remained for a long time insensible. When I recovered,
and looked around me, I found myself in entire
solitude, and could at present perceive no trace either of the
enemy or of my own people. Soon, however, I recollected
what had passed, and was but too well assured of the[24]
defeat my countrymen had sustained. Weak and battered
as I was, I attempted to retire to a place of greater security.
I had scarcely changed my ground, before I saw a
trooper of the enemy rushing towards me, with the intention
to take away my life. Fortunately I observed a tree
at hand, to the shelter of which I hastened; and, partly by
moving the branches to and fro, and partly by shifting my
position, I baffled my adversary, till he became weary of
the attempt. A moment after, I saw one of my most intimate
and familiar companions killed before my eyes. It
was not long, however, before a party of fugitive French
came up to the spot where I stood, and I, like the rest, was
hurried from the field. My uncle perished in the battle.
It is wonderful how men can harden their hearts against
such scenes as I then witnessed. It is wonderful how
they can be brought to co-operate in such demoniac fury,
and more than demoniac mischief, barbarity, and murder.
But they are brought to it; and enter, not from a deplorable
necessity, but as to a festival, in which each man is eager
to occupy his place, and share the amusements. It seemed
to me at that time, as it seems to me now, that it should
be enough for a man to contemplate such a field as I saw
at Pavia, to induce him to abjure the trade of violence for
ever, and to commit his sword once more to the bowels
of the earth, from which it was torn for so nefarious a
purpose.
These sensations, though now finally established in my
mind, were, at the time of which I am writing, but of fleeting
duration. The force of education, and the first bent
of my mind, were too strong. The horror which overwhelmed
me in the first moments of this great national
defeat subsided; and the military passion returned upon me
in its original ardour. My convictions, and the moral integrity
of my soul, were temporary; and I became myself
a monument of that inconstancy and that wonder, to which
I have just alluded.
Various circumstances, however, prevented this passion
from its direct operation. The character of France was
altered by the battle of Pavia, though mine remained the
same. It was in the fullest degree decisive of the fortune[25]
of the war. Milan, and every other place in the duchy,
opened their gates to the conqueror; and, in a fortnight,
not a Frenchman was left in the fields of Italy. Of the
whole army only a small body effected an orderly retreat,
under the command of the Duke of Alençon. Many persons
of the highest distinction perished in the battle: many
were made prisoners by the enemy. France by this event
found the list of her noblesse considerably reduced in numbers;
add to which, those whose loss she sustained, were
almost all of them taken from among the most distinguished
and meritorious in the catalogue.
But what constituted the principal feature in this memorable
event was, that the king himself was found in the
number of the prisoners; nor was he released by his ungenerous
competitor till after more than a twelvemonth’s
confinement. During this period Francis tasted of the
dregs of adversity. Inclined in the first instance to judge
of his rival by himself, he expected a liberal treatment. In
this he was deeply disappointed. After a detention of
many months in the Milanese, the scene of his former successes,
he was transferred to Madrid. He was personally
neglected by the emperor, while his disloyal subject[6] was
treated with singular distinction. The most rigorous terms
were proposed to him. All this had the effect, in one instance,
of sinking him into a disease of languor and dejection
which he was not expected to survive; and, in another,
of inducing him to execute an instrument by which he abdicated
the crown, and declared his resolution of remaining
a prisoner for life. His confinement was at length terminated
by his solemnly engaging to compulsory articles, which
he was determined to break as soon as he found himself at
liberty; an alternative peculiarly grating to the liberality
of his spirit. This reverse of fortune materially changed his
character. The fine spirit of his ambition was from this
time evaporated; and, while he still retained the indefeasible
qualities of his soul, and was gallant, kind-hearted, and
generous, he bartered, as far as was compatible with his
disposition, the enterprising and audacious temper he had
previously manifested, for the wary and phlegmatic system[26]
of his more fortunate competitor. His genius cowered before
that of Charles; and the defeat of Pavia may, perhaps,
be considered as having given a deadly wound to the reign
of chivalry, and a secure foundation to that of craft, dissimulation,
corruption, and commerce.
</div></body></text></TEI>