<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="59">CHAPTER V.
Problem of the Sounds of Pipes.
IT was taken for granted by
those who reasoned on sounds, that the sounds of flutes, organ-pipes,
and wind-instruments in general, 39 consisted in vibrations of some kind; but
to determine the nature and laws of these vibrations, and to reconcile
them with mechanical principles, was far from easy. The leading facts
which had been noticed were, that the note of a pipe was proportional
to its length, and that a flute and similar instruments might be made
to produce some of the acute harmonics, as well as the genuine note.
It had further been noticed,28 that pipes
closed at the end, instead of giving the series of harmonics 1, ½, ⅓,
¼, &c., would give only those notes which answer to the odd
numbers 1, ⅓, ⅕, &c. In this problem also, Newton29 made the first step to the solution. At
the end of the propositions respecting the velocity of sound, of which
we have spoken, he noticed that it appeared by
taking Mersenne’s or Sauveur’s determination of the number of
vibrations corresponding to a given note, that the pulse of air runs
over twice the length of the pipe in the time of each vibration. He
does not follow out this observation, but it obviously points to the
theory, that the sound of a pipe consists of pulses which travel back
and forwards along its length, and are kept in motion by the breath of
the player. This supposition would account for the observed dependence
of the note on the length of the pipe. The subject does not appear to
have been again taken up in a theoretical way till about 1760; when
Lagrange in the second volume of the Turin Memoirs, and D.
Bernoulli in the Memoirs of the French Academy for 1762,
published important essays, in which some of the leading facts were
satisfactorily explained, and which may therefore be considered as the
principal solutions of the problem.
28 D. Bernoulli, Berlin. Mem.
1753, p. 150.
29 Princip. Schol. Prop.
50.
In these solutions there was necessarily something hypothetical. In
the case of vibrating strings, as we have seen, the Form of the
vibrating curve was guessed at only, but the existence and position of
the Nodes could be rendered visible to the eye. In the vibrations of
air, we cannot see either the places of nodes, or the mode of
vibration; but several of the results are independent of these
circumstances. Thus both of the solutions explain the fact, that a
tube closed at one end is in unison with an open tube of double the
length; and, by supposing nodes to occur, they account for the
existence of the odd series of harmonics alone, 1, 3, 5, in closed
tubes, while the whole series, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, &c., occurs in open
ones. Both views of the nature of the vibration appear to be nearly
the same; though Lagrange’s is expressed with an analytical generality
which renders it obscure, and Bernoulli has perhaps 40 laid down an hypothesis
more special than was necessary. Lagrange30 considers the
vibration of open flutes as “the oscillations of a fibre of air,”
under the condition that its elasticity at the two ends is, during the
whole oscillation, the same as that of the surrounding atmosphere.
Bernoulli supposes31 the whole inertia of the air in the
flute to be collected into one particle, and this to be moved by the
whole elasticity arising from this displacement. It may be observed
that both these modes of treating the matter come very near to what we
have stated as Newton’s theory; for though Bernoulli supposes all the
air in the flute to be moved at once, and not successively, as by
Newton’s pulse, in either case the whole elasticity moves the whole
air in the tube, and requires more time to do this according to its
quantity. Since that time, the subject has received further
mathematical developement from Euler,32 Lambert,33 and Poisson;34 but no new
explanation of facts has arisen. Attempts have however been made to
ascertain experimentally the places of the nodes. Bernoulli himself
had shown that this place was affected by the amount of the opening,
and Lambert35 had examined other cases with the same
view. Savart traced the node in various musical pipes under different
conditions; and very recently Mr. Hopkins, of Cambridge, has pursued
the same experimental inquiry.36 It appears from
these researches, that the early assumptions of mathematicians with
regard to the position of the nodes, are not exactly verified by the
facts. When the air in a pipe is made to vibrate so as to have several
nodes which divide it into equal parts, it had been supposed by
acoustical writers that the part adjacent to the open end was half of
the other parts; the outermost node, however, is found experimentally
to be displaced from the position thus assigned to it, by a
quantity depending on several collateral circumstances.
30 Mém. Turin, vol. ii. p. 154.
31 Mém. Berlin, 1753, p.
446.
32 Nov. Act. Petrop. tom.
xvi.
33 Acad. Berlin, 1775.
34 Journ. Ec. Polyt. cap.
14.
35 Acad. Berlin, 1775.
36 Camb. Trans. vol. v. p.
234.
Since our purpose was to consider this problem only so far as it
has tended towards its mathematical solution, we have avoided saying
anything of the dependence of the mode of vibration on the cause by
which the sound is produced; and consequently, the researches on the
effects of reeds, embouchures, and the like, by Chladni, Savart,
Willis, and others, do not belong to our subject. It is easily seen
that the complex effect of the elasticity and other properties of the
reed and of the air together, is a problem of which we can hardly
41 hope to give a
complete solution till our knowledge has advanced much beyond its
present condition.
Indeed, in the science of Acoustics there is a vast body of facts
to which we might apply what has just been said; but for the sake of
pointing out some of them, we shall consider them as the subjects of
one extensive and yet unsolved problem.
</div></body></text></TEI>