<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Chambers Robert</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="3">p. 44THE
EARTH FORMED—ERA OF THE
PRIMARY ROCKS.
Although the earth has not been
actually penetrated to a greater depth than three thousand feet,
the nature of its substance can, in many instances, be inferred
for the depth of many miles by other means of observation. 
We see a mountain composed of a particular substance, with
strata, or beds of other rock, lying against its sloped sides;
we, of course, infer that the substance of the mountain dips away
under the strata which we see lying against it.  Suppose
that we walk away from the mountain across the turned up edges of
the stratified rocks, and that for many miles we continue to pass
over other stratified rocks, all disposed in the same way, till
by and bye we come to a place where we begin to cross the
opposite edges of the same beds; after which we pass over these
rocks all in reverse order till we come to another extensive
mountain composed of similar material to the first, and shelving
away under the strata in the same way.  We should then infer
that the stratified rocks occupied a basin formed by the rock of
these two mountains, and by calculating the thickness right
through these strata, could be able to say to what depth the rock
of the mountain extended below.  By such means, the kind of
rock existing many miles below the surface can often be inferred
with considerable confidence.
The interior of the globe has now been inspected in this way
in many places, and a tolerably distinct notion of its general
arrangements has consequently been arrived at.  It appears
that the basis rock of the earth, as it may be called, is of hard
texture, and crystalline in its constitution.  Of this rock,
granite may be said to be the type, though it runs into many
varieties.  Over this, except in the comparatively few
places where it projects above the general level in mountains,
other rocks are disposed in sheets or strata, with the appearance
of having been deposited originally from water; but these last
rocks have nowhere been allowed to rest in their original
arrangement.  Uneasy movements from below have broken them
up in great inclined masses, while in many cases there has been
projected through the rents rocky matter more or less resembling
the great inferior crystalline mass.  This rocky matter must
have been in a state of fusion from heat at the time of its
projection, for it is often found to have run into and filled up
lateral chinks in these rents.  There are even instances
where it has been rent again, and a newer melted matter of the
same character sent through the opening.  Finally, in the
crust as thus arranged there are, in many places, chinks
containing veins of metal.  Thus, there is first a great
inferior mass, composed of crystalline rock, and probably resting
immediately on the fused and expanded matter of the interior:
next, layers or strata of aqueous origin; next, irregular masses
of melted inferior rock that have been sent up volcanically and
confusedly at various times amongst the aqueous rocks, breaking
up these into masses, and tossing them out of their original
levels.  This is an outline of the arrangements of the crust
of the earth, as far as we can observe it.  It is, at first
sight, a most confused scene; but after some careful observation,
we readily detect in it a regularity and order from which much
instruction in the history of our globe is to be derived.
The deposition of the aqueous rocks, and the projection of the
volcanic, have unquestionably taken place since the settlement of
the earth in its present form.  They are indeed of an order
of events which we see going on, under the agency of more or less
intelligible causes, even down to the present day.  We may
therefore consider them generally as comparatively recent
transactions.  Abstracting them from the investigations
before us, we arrive at the idea of the earth in its first
condition as a globe of its present size—namely, as a mass,
externally at least, consisting of the crystalline kind of rock,
with the waters of the present seas and the present atmosphere
around it, though these were probably in considerably different
conditions, both as to temperature and their constituent
materials, from what they now are.  We are thus to presume
that that crystalline texture of rock which we see exemplified in
granite is the condition into which the great bulk of the solids
of our earth were agglomerated directly from the nebulous or
vaporiform state.  It is a condition eminently of
combination, for such rock is invariably composed of two or more
of four substances—silica, mica, quartz, and
hornblende—which associate in it in the form of grains or
crystals, and which are themselves each composed of a group of
the simple or elementary substances.
Judging from the results and from still remaining conditions,
we must suppose that the heat retained in the interior of the
globe was more intense, or had greater freedom to act, in some
places than in others.  These became the scenes of volcanic
operations, and in time marked their situations by the extrusion
of traps and basalts from below—namely, rocks composed of
the crystalline matter fused by intense heat, and developed on
the surface in various conditions, according to the particular
circumstances under which it was sent up; some, for example,
being thrown up under water, and some in the open air, which
conditions are found to have made considerable difference in its
texture and appearance.  The great stores of subterranean
heat also served an important purpose in the formation of the
aqueous rocks.  These rocks might, according to Sir John
Herschel, become subject to heat in the following
manner:—While the surface of a particular mass of rock
forms the bed of the sea, the heat is kept at a certain distance
from that surface by the contact of the water; philosophically
speaking, it radiates away the heat into the sea, and (to resort
to common language) is cooled a good way down.  But when new
sediment settles at the bottom of that sea, the heat rises up to
what was formerly the surface; and when a second quantity of
sediment is laid down, it continues to rise through the first of
the deposits, which then becomes subjected to those changes which
heat is calculated to produce.  This process is precisely
the same as that of putting additional coats upon our own bodies;
when, of course, the internal heat rises through each coat in
succession, and the third (supposing there is a fourth above it)
becomes as warm as perhaps the first originally was.
In speaking of sedimentary rocks, we may be said to be
anticipating.  It is necessary, first, to shew how such
rocks were formed, or how stratification commenced.
Geology tells us as plainly as possible, that the original
crystalline mass was not a perfectly smooth ball, with air and
water playing round it.  There were vast irregularities in
the surface,—irregularities trifling, perhaps, compared
with the whole bulk of the globe, but assuredly vast in
comparison with any which now exist upon it.  These
irregularities might be occasioned by inequalities in the cooling
of the substance, or by accidental and local sluggishness of the
materials, or by local effects of the concentrated internal
heat.  From whatever cause they arose, there they
were—enormous granitic mountains, interspersed with seas
which sunk to a depth equally profound, and by which, perhaps,
the mountains were wholly or partially covered.  Now, it is
a fact of which the very first principles of geology assure us,
that the solids of the globe cannot for a moment be exposed to
water, or to the atmosphere, without becoming liable to
change.  They instantly begin to wear down.  This
operation, we may be assured, proceeded with as much certainty in
the earliest ages of our earth’s history, as it does now,
but upon a much more magnificent scale.  There is the
clearest evidence that the seas of those days were not in some
instances less than a hundred miles in depth, however much
more.  The sub-aqueous mountains must necessarily have been
of at least equal magnitude.  The system of disintegration
consequent upon such conditions would be enormous.  The
matters worn off, being carried into the neighbouring depths, and
there deposited, became the components of the earliest stratified
rocks, the first series of which is the Gneiss and Mica Slate
System, or series, examples of which are exposed to view in
the Highlands of Scotland and in the West of England.  The
vast thickness of these beds, in some instances, is what attests
the profoundness of the primeval oceans in which they were
formed; the Pensylvanian grawacke, a member of the next highest
series, is not less than a hundred miles in direct
thickness.  We have also evidence that the earliest strata
were formed in the presence of a stronger degree of heat than
what operated in subsequent stages of the world, for the
laminæ of the gneiss and of the mica and chlorite schists
are contorted in a way which could only be the result of a very
high temperature.  It appears as if the seas in which these
deposits were formed, had been in the troubled state of a caldron
of water nearly at boiling heat.  Such a condition would
probably add not a little to the disintegrating power of the
ocean.
The earliest stratified rocks contain no matters which are not
to be found in the primitive granite.  They are the same in
material, but only changed into new forms and combinations; hence
they have been called by Mr. Lyell, metamorphic rocks.  But
how comes it that some of them are composed almost exclusively of
one of the materials of granite; the mica schists, for example,
of mica—the quartz rocks, of quartz, &c.?  For
this there are both chemical and mechanical causes.  Suppose
that a river has a certain quantity of material to carry down, it
is evident that it will soonest drop the larger particles, and
carry the lightest farthest on.  To such a cause is it owing
that some of the materials of the worn-down granite have settled
in one place and some in another. [52]  Again, some of
these materials must be presumed to have been in a state of
chemical solution in the primeval seas.  It would be, of
course, in conformity with chemical laws, that certain of these
materials would be precipitated singly, or in modified
combinations, to the bottom, so as to form rocks by
themselves.
The rocks hitherto spoken of contain none of those petrified
remains of vegetables and animals which abound so much in
subsequently formed rocks, and tell so wondrous a tale of the
past history of our globe.  They simply contain, as has been
said, mineral materials derived from the primitive mass, and
which appear to have been formed into strata in seas of vast
depth.  The absence from these rocks of all traces of
vegetable and animal life, joined to a consideration of the
excessive temperature which seems to have prevailed in their
epoch, has led to the inference that no plants or animals of any
kind then existed.  A few geologists have indeed endeavoured
to shew that the absence of organic remains is no proof of the
globe having been then unfruitful or uninhabited, as the heat to
which these rocks have been subjected at the time of their
solidification, might have obliterated any remains of either
plants or animals which were included in them.  But this is
only an hypothesis of negation; and it certainly seems very
unlikely that a degree of heat sufficient to obliterate the
remains of plants or animals when dead, would ever allow of their
coming into or continuing in existence.</div></body></text></TEI>