<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="45">

BOOK XVII.

PHYSIOLOGY AND COMPARATIVE
ANATOMY.

Vegetable Morphology.

Morphology in Linnæus.
I HAVE stated that Linnæus had
some views on this subject. Dr. Hooker conceives these views to be
more complete and correct than is generally allowed, though unhappily
clothed in metaphorical language and mixed with speculative matter. By
his permission I insert some remarks which I have received from
him.
The fundamental passage on this subject is in the Systema
Naturæ; in the Introduction to which work the following passage
occurs:—
“Prolepsis (Anticipation) exhibits the mystery of the metamorphosis
of plants, by which the herb, which is the larva or imperfect
condition, is changed into the declared fructification: for the plant
is capable of producing either a leafy herb or a fructification. . . .
. .
“When a tree produces a flower, nature anticipates the produce of
five years where these come out all at once; forming of the bud-leaves
of the next year bracts; of those of the following year, the
calyx; of the following, the corolla; of the next, the
stamina; of the subsequent, the pistils, filled with the
granulated marrow of the seed, the terminus of the life of a
vegetable.”
Dr. Hooker says, “I derive my idea of his having a better knowledge
of the subject than most Botanists admit, not only from the Prolepsis,
but from his paper called Reformatio Botanices (Amœn.
Acad. vol. vi.); a remarkable work, in respect of his candor in
speaking of his predecessors’ labors, and the sagacity he shows in
indicating researches to be undertaken or completed. Amongst the
latter is V. ‘Prolepsis plantarum, ulterius extendenda per earum
metamorphoses.’ The last word occurs rarely in his Prolepsis;
but when it does it seems to me that he uses it as indicating a normal
change and not an accidental one. 637
“In the Prolepsis the speculative matter, which Linnæus
himself carefully distinguishes as such, must be separated from the
rest, and this may I think be done in most of the sections. He starts
with explaining clearly and well the origin and position of buds, and
their constant presence, whether developed or not, in the axil of the
leaf: adding abundance of acute observations and experiments to prove
his statements. The leaf he declares to be the first effort of the
plant in spring: he proceeds to show, successively, that bracts,
calyx, corolla, stamens, and pistil are each of them metamorphosed
leaves, in every case giving many examples,
both from monsters and from characters presented by those organs in
their normal condition.
“The (to me) obscure and critical part of the Prolepsis was
that relating to the change of the style of Carduus into two
leaves. Mr. Brown has explained this. He says it was a puzzle to him,
till he went to Upsala and consulted Fries and Wahlenberg, who
informed him that such monstrous Cardui grew in the
neighborhood, and procured him some. Considering how minute and masked
the organs of Compositæ are, it shows no little skill in
Linnæus, and a very clear view of the whole matter, to have traced the
metamorphosis of all their floral organs into leaves, except their
stamens, of which he says, ‘Sexti anni folia e staminibus me non in
compositis vidisse fateor, sed illorum loco folia pistillacea, quæ in
compositis aut plenis sunt frequentissima.’ I must say that nothing
could well be clearer to my mind than the full and accurate
appreciation which Linnæus shows of the whole series of phenomena, and
their rationale. He over and over again asserts that these
organs are leaves, every one of them,—I do not understand him to
say that the prolepsis is an accidental change of leaves into bracts,
of bracts into calyx, and so forth. Even were the language more
obscure, much might be inferred from the wide range and accuracy of
the observations he details so scientifically. It is inconceivable
that a man should have traced the sequence of the phenomena under so
many varied aspects, and shown such skill, knowledge, ingenuity, and
accuracy in his methods of observing and describing, and yet missed
the rationale of the whole. Eliminate the speculative parts
and there is not a single error of observation or judgment; whilst his
history of the developement of buds, leaves, and floral organs, and of
various other obscure matters of equal interest and importance, are of
a very high order of merit, are, in fact, for the time profound.
“There is nothing in all this that detracts from the merit of
Goethe’s 638
re-discovery. With Goethe it was, I think, a deductive
process,—with Linnæus an inductive. Analyse Linnæus’s
observations and method, and I think it will prove a good example of
inductive reasoning.
“P. 473. Perhaps Professor Auguste St Hilaire of Montpellier should
share with De Candolle the honor of contributing largely to establish
the metamorphic doctrine;—their labors were cotemporaneous.
“P. 474. Linnæus pointed out that the pappus was calyx: ‘Et
pappum gigni ex quarti anni foliis, in jam nominatis
Carduis.’—Prol. Plant. 338.” (J. D. H.)

CHAPTER VII.
Animal Morphology.
THE subject of Animal
Morphology has recently been expanded into a form strikingly
comprehensive and systematic by Mr. Owen; and supplied by him with a
copious and carefully-chosen language; which in his hands facilitates
vastly the comparison and appreciation of the previous labors of
physiologists, and opens the way to new truths and philosophical
generalizations. Though the steps which have been made had been
prepared by previous anatomists, I will borrow my view of them mainly
from him; with the less scruple, inasmuch as he has brought into full
view the labors of his predecessors.
I have stated in the History that the
skeletons of all vertebrate animals are conceived to be reducible to a
single Type, and the skull reducible to a series of vertebræ. But
inasmuch as this reduction includes not only a detailed correspondence
of the bones of man with those of beasts, but also with those of
birds, fishes, and reptiles, it may easily be conceived that the
similarities and connexions are of a various and often remote kind.
The views of such relations, held by previous Comparative Anatomists,
have led to the designations of the bones of animals which have been
employed in anatomical descriptions; and these designations having
been framed and adopted by anatomists looking at the subject from
different sides, and having different views of analogies and
relations, have been very various and unstable; besides being often of
cumbrous length and inconvenient form.
The corresponding parts in different animals are called
homologues, 639 a term first applied to anatomy by the
philosophers of Germany; and this term Mr. Owen adopts, to the
exclusion of terms more loosely denoting identity or similarity. And
the Homology of the various bones of vertebrates having been in a
great degree determined by the labors of previous anatomists, Mr. Owen
has proposed names for each of the bones: the condition of such names
being, that the homologues in all vertebrates shall be called by the
same name, and that these names shall be founded upon the terms and
phrases in which the great anatomists of the 16th, 17th, and 18th
centuries expressed the results of their researches respecting the
human skeleton. These names, thus selected, so far as concerned the
bones of the Head of Fishes, one of the most difficult cases of this
Special Homology, he published in a Table,44 in which they
were compared, in parallel columns, with the names or phrases used for
the like purpose by Cuvier, Agassiz, Geoffroy, Hallman, Sœmmering,
Meckel, and Wagner. As an example of the considerations by which this
selection of names was determined, I may quote what he says with
regard to one of these bones of the skull.</div></body></text></TEI>