<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="108">CHAPTER IV.
Establishment of the Distinction of Systems of
Crystallization.—Weiss and Mohs.
IN Haüy’s views, as generally
happens in new systems, however true, there was involved something
that was arbitrary, something that was false or doubtful, something
that was unnecessarily limited. The principal points of this kind
were;—his having made the laws of crystalline derivation depend
so much upon cleavage;—his having assumed an atomic constitution
of bodies as an essential part of his system; and his having taken a
set of primary forms, which, being selected by no general view, were
partly superfluous, and partly defective.
How far evidence, such as has been referred to by various
philosophers, has proved, or can prove, that bodies are constituted of
indivisible atoms, will be more fully examined in the work which
treats of the Philosophy of this subject. There can be little doubt
that the 327
portion of Haüy’s doctrine which most riveted popular attention and
applause, was his dissection of crystals, in a manner which was
supposed to lead actually to their ultimate material elements. Yet it
is clear, that since the solids given by cleavage are, in many cases,
such as cannot make up a solid space, the primary conception of a
necessary geometrical identity between the results of division and the
elements of composition, which is the sole foundation of the
supposition that crystallography points out the actual elements,
disappears on being scrutinized: and when Haüy, pressed by this
difficulty, as in the case of fluor-spar, put his integrant octohedral
molecules together, touching by the edges only, his method became an
empty geometrical diagram, with no physical meaning.
The real fact, divested of the hypothesis which was contained in
the fiction of decrements, was, that when the relation of the
derivative to the primary faces is expressed by means of numerical
indices, these numbers are integers, and generally very small ones;
and this was the form which the law gradually assumed, as the method
of derivation was made more general and simple by Weiss and
others.
“When, in 1809, I published my Dissertation,” says Weiss,28 “I shared the common opinion as to the
necessity of the assumption and the reality of the existence of a
primitive form, at least in a sense not very different from the usual
sense of the expression. While I sought,” he adds, referring to
certain doctrines of general philosophy which he and others
entertained, “a dynamical ground for this, instead of the
untenable atomistic view, I found that, out of my primitive forms,
there was gradually unfolded to my hands, that which really governs
them, and is not affected by their casual fluctuations, the
fundamental relations of those Dimensions according to which a
multiplicity of internal oppositions, necessarily and mutually
interdependent, are developed in the mass, each having its own
polarity; so that the crystalline character is co-extensive with these
polarities.”
28 Mem. Acad. Berl. 1816, p.
307.
The “Dimensions” of which Weiss here speaks, are the Axes of
Symmetry of the crystal; that is, those lines in reference to
which, every face is accompanied by other faces, having like positions
and properties. Thus a rhomb, or more properly a
rhombohedron,29 of 328 calcspar may be placed with one of its
obtuse corners uppermost, so that all the three faces which meet there
are equally inclined to the vertical line. In this position, every
derivative face, which is obtained by any modification of the faces or
edges of the rhombohedron, implies either three or six such derivative
faces; for no one of the three upper faces of the rhombohedron has any
character or property different from the other two; and, therefore,
there is no reason for the existence of a derivative from one of these
primitive faces, which does not equally hold for the other primitive
faces. Hence the derivative forms will, in all cases, contain none but
faces connected by this kind of correspondence. The axis thus made
vertical will be an Axis of Symmetry, and the crystal will consist of
three divisions, ranged round this axis, and exactly resembling each
other. According to Weiss’s nomenclature, such a crystal is
“three-and-three-membered.”
29 I use this name for the solid
figure, since rhomb has always been used for a plane
figure.
But this is only one of the kinds of symmetry which crystalline
forms may exhibit. They may have three axes of complete and
equal symmetry at right angles to each other, as the cube and
the regular octohedron;—or, two axes of equal symmetry,
perpendicular to each other and to a third axis, which is not
affected with the same symmetry with which they are; such a figure is
a square pyramid;—or they may have three rectangular
axes, all of unequal symmetry, the modifications
referring to each axis separately from the other two.
These are essential and necessary distinctions of crystalline form;
and the introduction of a classification of forms founded on such
relations, or, as they were called, Systems of Crystallization,
was a great improvement upon the divisions of the earlier
crystallographers, for those divisions were separated according to
certain arbitrarily-assumed primary forms. Thus Romé de Lisle’s
fundamental forms were, the tetrahedron, the cube, the octohedron, the
rhombic prism, the rhombic octohedron, the dodecahedron with
triangular faces: Haüy’s primary forms are the cube, the rhombohedron,
the oblique rhombic prism, the right rhombic prism, the rhombic
dodecahedron, the regular octohedron, tetrahedron, and six-sided
prism, and the bipyramidal dodecahedron. This division, as I have
already said, errs both by excess and defect, for some of these
primary forms might be made derivatives from others; and no solid
reason could be assigned why they were not. Thus the cube may be
derived from the tetrahedron, by truncating the edges; and the rhombic
dodecahedron again from the cube, by truncating its edges; while the
square pyramid could not be legitimately identified with the
derivative of any of these forms; for if we were to 329 derive it from the
rhombic prism, why should the acute angles always suffer decrements
corresponding in a certain way to those of the obtuse angles, as they
must do in order to give rise to a square pyramid?
The introduction of the method of reference to Systems of
Crystallization has been a subject of controversy, some ascribing this
valuable step to Weiss, and some to Mohs.30 It appears, I
think, on the whole, that Weiss first published works in which the
method is employed; but that Mohs, by applying it to all the known
species of minerals, has had the merit of making it the basis of real
crystallography. Weiss, in 1809, published a Dissertation On the
mode of investigating the principal geometrical character of
crystalline forms, in which he says,31 “No part, line,
or quantity, is so important as the axis; no consideration is more
essential or of a higher order than the relation of a crystalline
plane to the axis;” and again, “An axis is any line governing the
figure, about which all parts are similarly disposed, and with
reference to which they correspond mutually.” This he soon followed
out by examination of some difficult cases, as Felspar and Epidote. In
the Memoirs of the Berlin Academy,32 for
1814–15, he published An Exhibition of the natural Divisions
of Systems of Crystallization. In this Memoir, his divisions are
as follows:—The regular system, the four-membered,
the two-and-two-membered, the three-and-three-membered,
and some others of inferior degrees of symmetry. These divisions are
by Mohs (Outlines of Mineralogy, 1822), termed the
tessular, pyramidal, prismatic, and
rhombohedral systems respectively. Hausmann, in his
Investigations concerning the Forms of Inanimate Nature,33 makes a nearly corresponding
arrangement;—the isometric, monodimetric,
trimetric, and monotrimetic; and one or other of these
sets of terms have been adopted by most succeeding writers.
30 Edin. Phil. Trans. 1823,
vols. xv. and xvi.
31 pp. 16, 42.
32 Ibid.
33 Göttingen, 1821.
In order to make the distinctions more apparent, I have purposely
omitted to speak of the systems which arise when the prismatic
system loses some part of its symmetry;—when it has only half or
a quarter its complete number of faces;—or, according to Mohs’s
phraseology, when it is hemihedral or tetartohedral.
Such systems are represented by the singly-oblique or doubly-oblique
prism; they are termed by Weiss two-and-one-membered, and
one-and-one-membered; by other writers, Monoklinometric,
and Triklinometric Systems. There are also other 330 peculiarities of
Symmetry, such, for instance, as that of the plagihedral faces
of quartz, and other minerals.
The introduction of an arrangement of crystalline forms into
systems, according to their degree of symmetry, was a step which was
rather founded on a distinct and comprehensive perception of
mathematical relations, than on an acquaintance with experimental
facts, beyond what earlier mineralogists had possessed. This
arrangement was, however, remarkably confirmed by some of the
properties of minerals which attracted notice about the time now
spoken of, as we shall see in the next chapter.
~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~
</div></body></text></TEI>