<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="29">

CHAPTER IV.
Of the Axioms which relate to the Idea of Cause.


1. Causes are abstract Conceptions.—We have now to
express, as well as we can, the fundamental character of
that Idea of Cause of which we have just proved the
existence. This may be done, at least for purposes of
reasoning, in this as in former instances, by means of
axioms. I shall state the principal axioms which belong to
this subject, referring the reader to his own thoughts for
the axiomatic evidence which belongs to them.
But I must first observe, that in order to express general
and abstract truths concerning cause and effect, these
terms, cause and effect, must be understood in
a general and abstract manner. When one event gives rise to
another, the first event is, in common language,
often called the cause, and the second the effect. Thus the
meeting of two billiard-balls may be said to be the cause of
one of them turning aside out of the path in which it was
moving. For our present purposes, however, we must not apply
the term cause to such occurrences as this meeting and
turning, but to a certain conception, force,
abstracted from all such special events, and considered as a
quality or property by which one body affects the motion of
the other. And in like manner in other cases, cause is to be
conceived as some abstract quality, power, or efficacy, by
which change is produced; a quality not identical with the
events, but disclosed by means of them. Not only is this
abstract mode of conceiving force and cause useful in
expressing the fundamental principles of science; but it
supplies us with the only mode by which such principles can
be 185 stated in a general manner, and made to lead to
substantial truth and real knowledge.
Understanding cause, therefore, in this sense, we
proceed to our Axioms.
2. First Axiom. Nothing can take place without a
Cause.
Every event, of whatever kind, must have a cause in the
sense of the term which we have just indicated; and that it
must, is a universal and necessary proposition to which we
irresistibly assent as soon as it is understood. We believe
each appearance to come into existence,—we conceive every
change to take place,—not only with something preceding it,
but something by which it is made to be what it is. An
effect without a cause;—an event without a preceding
condition involving the efficacy by which the event is
produced;—are suppositions which we cannot for a moment
admit. That the connexion of effect with cause is universal
and necessary, is a universal and constant conviction of
mankind. It persists in the minds of all men, undisturbed by
all the assaults of sophistry and skepticism; and, as we
have seen in the last chapter, remains unshaken, even when
its foundations seem to be ruined. This axiom expresses, to
a certain extent, our Idea of Cause; and when that idea is
clearly apprehended, the axiom requires no proof, and indeed
admits of none which makes it more evident. That
notwithstanding its simplicity, it is of use in our
speculations, we shall hereafter see; but in the first
place, we must consider the other axioms belonging to this
subject.
3. Second Axiom. Effects are proportional to their
Causes, and Causes are measured by their Effects.
We have already said that cause is that quality or
power, in the circumstances of each case, by which the
effect is produced; and this power, an abstract property of
the condition of things to which it belongs, can in no way
fall directly under the cognizance of the senses. Cause, of
whatever kind, is not apprehended as including objects and
events which share its nature by being co-extensive with
certain portions of it, as space and time are. It cannot
therefore, like them, be 186 measured by repetition of its
own parts, as space is measured by repetition of inches, and
time by repetition of minutes. Causes may be greater or
less; as, for instance, the force of a man is greater than
the force of a child. But how much is the one greater than
the other? How are we to compare the abstract conception,
force, in such cases as these?
To this, the obvious and only answer is, that we must
compare causes by means of their effects;—that we must
compare force by something which force can do. The child can
lift one fagot; the man can lift ten such fagots: we have
here a means of comparison. And whether or not the rule is
to be applied in this manner, that is, by the number of
things operated on, (a question which we shall have to
consider hereafter,) it is clear that this form of rule,
namely, a reference to some effect or other as our measure,
is the right, because the only possible form. The cause
determines the effect. The cause being the same, the effect
must be the same. The connexion of the two is governed by a
fixed and inviolable rule. It admits of no ambiguity. Every
degree of intensity in the cause has some peculiar
modification of the effect corresponding to it. Hence the
effect is an unfailing index of the amount of the cause; and
if it be a measurable effect, gives a measure of the cause.
We can have no other measure; but we need no other, for this
is exact, sufficient and complete.
It may be said, that various effects are produced by the
same cause. The sun’s heat melts wax and expands
quicksilver. The force of gravity causes bodies to move
downwards if they are free, and to press down upon their
supports if they are supported. Which of the effects is to
be taken as the measure of heat, or of gravity, in these
cases? To this we reply, that if we had merely different
states of the same cause to compare, any of the effects
might be taken. The sun’s heat on different days might be
measured by the expansion of quicksilver, or by the quantity
of wax melted. The force of gravity, if it were different at
different places, might be measured by the spaces through
which a given weight would bend an elastic 187 support, or
by the spaces through which a body would fall in a given
time. All these measures are consistent with the general
character of our idea of cause.
4. Limitation of the Second Axiom.—But there may be
circumstances in the nature of the case which may further
determine the kind of effect which we must take for the
measure of the cause. For example, if causes are conceived
to be of such a nature as to be capable of addition, the
effects taken as their measure must conform to this
condition. This is the case with mechanical causes. The
weights of two bodies are the causes of the pressure which
they exert downwards; and these weights are capable of
addition. The weight of the two is the sum of the weight of
each. We are therefore not at liberty to say that weights
shall be measured by the spaces through which they bend a
certain elastic support, except we have first ascertained
that the whole weight bends it through a space equal to the
sum of the inflections produced by the separate weights.
Without this precaution, we might obtain inconsistent
results. Two weights, each of the magnitude 3 as measured by
their effects, might, if we took the inflections of a spring
for the effects, be together equal to 5 or to 7 by the same
kind of measurement. For the inflection produced by two
weights of 3 might, for aught we can see beforehand, be more
or less than twice as great as the inflection produced by
one weight of 3. That forces are capable of addition, is a
condition which limits, and, as we shall see, in some cases
rigorously fixes, the kind of effects which are to be taken
as their measures.
Causes which are thus capable of addition are to be measured
by the repeated addition of equal quantities. Two such
causes are equal to each other when they produce
exactly the same effect. So far our axiom is applied
directly. But these two causes can be added
together; and being thus added, they are double of
one of them; and the cause composed by addition of
three such, is three times as great as the
first; and so on for any measure whatever. By this means,
and by this 188 means only, we have a complete and
consistent measure of those causes which are so conceived as
to be subject to this condition of being added and
multiplied.
Causes are, in the present chapter, to be understood in the
widest sense of the term; and the axiom now under our
consideration applies to them, whenever they are of such a
nature as to admit of any measure at all. But the cases
which we have more particularly in view are
mechanical causes, the causes of the motion and of
the equilibrium of bodies. In these cases, forces are
conceived as capable of addition; and what has been said of
the measure of causes in such cases, applies peculiarly to
mechanical forces. Two weights, placed together, may be
considered as a single weight, equal to the sum of
the two. Two pressures, pushing a body in the same direction
at the same point, are identical in all respects with some
single pressure, their sum, pushing in like manner;
and this is true whether or not they put the body in motion.
In the cases of mechanical forces, therefore, we take some
certain effect, velocity generated or weight supported,
which may fix the unit of force; and we then measure
all other forces by the successive repetition of this unit,
as we measure all spaces by the successive repetition of our
unit of lineal measure.
But these steps in the formation of the science of Mechanics
will be further explained, when we come to follow our axioms
concerning cause into their application in that science. At
present we have, perhaps, sufficiently explained the axiom
that causes are measured by their effects, and we now
proceed to a third axiom, also of great importance.
5. Third Axiom. Reaction is equal and opposite to
Action.
In the case of mechanical forces, the action of a cause
often takes place by an operation of one body upon another;
and in this case, the action is always and inevitably
accompanied by an opposite action. If I press a
stone with my hand, the stone presses my hand in return. If
one ball strike another and put it in motion, the second
ball diminishes the motion of 189 the first. In these
cases the operation is mutual; the Action is accompanied by
a Reaction. And in all such cases the Reaction is a force of
exactly the same nature as the Action, exerted in an
opposite direction. A pressure exerted upon a body at rest
is resisted and balanced by another pressure; when the
pressure of one body puts another in motion, the body,
though it yields to the force, nevertheless exerts upon the
pressing body a force like that which it suffers.
Now the axiom asserts further, that this Reaction is
equal, as well as opposite, to the Action. For the
Reaction is an effect of the Action, and is determined by
it. And since the two, Action and Reaction, are forces of
the same nature, each may be considered as cause and as
effect; and they must, therefore, determine each other by a
common rule. But this consideration leads necessarily to
their equality: for since the rule is mutual, if we could
for an instant suppose the Reaction to be less than the
Action, we must, by the same rule, suppose the Action to be
less than the Reaction. And thus Action and Reaction, in
every such case, are rigorously equal to each other.
It is easily seen that this axiom is not a proposition which
is, or can be, proved by experience; but that its truth is
anterior to special observation, and depends on our
conception of Action and Reaction. Like our other axioms,
this has its source in an Idea; namely, the Idea of Cause,
under that particular condition in which cause and effect
are mutual. The necessary and universal truth which we
cannot help ascribing to the axiom, shows that it is not
derived from the stores of experience, which can never
contain truths of this character. Accordingly, it was
asserted with equal confidence and generality by those who
did not refer to experience for their principles, and by
those who did. Leonicus Tomæus, a commentator of Aristotle,
whose work was published in 1552, and therefore at a period
when no right opinions concerning mechanical reaction were
current, at least in his school, says, in his remarks on the
Author’s Questions concerning the communication of motion,
that ‘Reaction is equal and 190 contrary to Action.’ The
same principle was taken for granted by all parties, in all
the controversies concerning the proper measure of force, of
which we shall have to speak: and would be rigorously true,
as a law of motion, whichever of the rival interpretations
of the measure of the term ‘Action’ we were to take.
6. Extent of the Third Axiom.—It may naturally be
asked whether this third Axiom respecting causation extends
to any other cases than those of mechanical action, since
the notion of Cause in general has certainly a much wider
extent. For instance, when a hot body heats a cold one, is
there necessarily an equal reaction of the second body upon
the first? Does the snowball cool the boy’s hand exactly as
much as the hand heats the snow? To this we reply, that, in
every case in which one body acts upon another by its
physical qualities, there must be some reaction. No body can
affect another without being itself also affected. But in
any physical change the action exerted is an
abstract term which may be variously understood. The hot
hand may melt a cool body, or may warm it:
which kind of effect is to be taken as action? This remains
to be determined by other considerations.
In all cases of physical change produced by one body in
another, it is generally possible to assume such a meaning
of action, that the reaction shall be of the same nature as
the action; and when this is done, the third axiom of
causation, that reaction is equal to action, is universally
true. Thus if a hot body heat a cold one, the change may be
conceived as the transfer of a certain substance,
heat or caloric, from the first body to the
second. On this supposition, the first body loses
just as much heat as the other gains; action and
reaction are equal. But if the reaction be of a different
kind to the action we can no longer apply the axiom. If a
hot body melt a cold one, the latter cools
the former: here, then, is reaction; but so long as the
action and reaction are stated in this form, we cannot
assert any equality between them.
In treating of the secondary mechanical sciences, we 191
shall see further in what way we may conceive the physical
action of one body upon another, so that the same axioms
which are the basis of the science of Mechanics shall apply
to changes not at first sight manifestly mechanical.
The three axioms of causation which we have now stated are
the fundamental maxims of all reasoning concerning causes as
to their quantities; and it will be shown in the sequel that
these axioms form the basis of the science of Mechanics,
determining its form, extent, and certainty. We must,
however, in the first place, consider how we acquire those
conceptions upon which the axioms now established are to be
employed.
[2d Ed.] [The Axiom that Reaction is equal and opposite
to Action, may appear to be at variance with a maxim
concerning Cause which is commonly current; namely, that the
‘Cause precedes Effect, and Effect follows Cause.’ For it
may be said, if A, the Action, and R, the
Reaction, can be considered as mutually the cause of each
other, A must precede R, and yet must follow
it, which is impossible. But to this I reply, that in those
cases of direct Causation to which the maxim applies, the
Cause and Effect are not successive, but simultaneous. If I
press against some obstacle, the obstacle resists and
returns the pressure at the instant it is exerted, not after
any interval of time, however small. The common maxim, that
the effect follows the cause, has arisen from the practice
of considering, as examples of cause and effect, not
instantaneous forces or causes, and the instantaneous
changes which they produce; but taking, instead of this
latter, the cumulative effects produced in the
course of time, and compared with like results occurring
without the action of the cause. Thus, if we alter the
length of a clock-pendulum, this change produces, as its
effect, a subsequent change of rate in the clock: because
the rate is measured by the accumulated effects of the
pendulum’s gravity, before and after the change. But the
pendulum produces its mechanical effect upon the escapement,
at the moment of its contact, and each wheel upon the next,
at the moment of its contact. As has 192 been
said in a Review of this work, ‘The time lost in cases of
indirect physical causation is consumed in the movements
which take place among the parts of the mechanism in action,
by which the active forces so transformed into momentum are
transported over intervals of space to new points of action,
the motion of matter in such cases being regarded as a mere
carrier of force.’ (Quarterly Rev. No. cxxxv. p.
212.)
This subject I have further treated in the Memoirs of the
Cambridge Philosophical Society, vol. vii. part iii.]
[In this Third Edition I add this discussion.]</div></body></text></TEI>