<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Chambers Robert</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="17">p.
324MENTAL CONSTITUTION OF ANIMALS.
It has been one of the most
agreeable tasks of modern science to trace the wonderfully exact
adaptations of the organization of animals to the physical
circumstances amidst which they are destined to live.  From
the mandibles of insects to the hand of man, all is seen to be in
the most harmonious relation to the things of the outward world,
thus clearly proving that design presided in the creation
of the whole—design again implying a designer, another word
for a Creator.
It would be tiresome to present in this place even a selection
of the proofs which have been adduced on this point.  The
Natural Theology of Paley, and the Bridgewater Treatises, place
the subject in so clear a light, that the general postulate may
be taken for granted.  The physical constitution of animals
is, then, to be regarded as in the nicest congruity and
adaptation to the external world.
Less clear ideas have hitherto been entertained on the mental
constitution of animals.  The very nature of this
constitution is not as yet generally known or held as
ascertained.  There is, indeed, a notion of old standing,
that the mind is in some way connected with the brain; but the
metaphysicians insist that it is, in reality, known only by its
acts or effects, and they accordingly present the subject in a
form which is unlike any other kind of science, for it does not
so much as pretend to have nature for its basis.  There is a
general disinclination to regard mind in connexion with
organization, from a fear that this must needs interfere with the
cherished religious doctrine of the spirit of man, and lower him
to the level of the brutes.  A distinction is therefore
drawn between our mental manifestations and those of the lower
animals, the latter being comprehended under the term instinct,
while ours are collectively described as mind, mind being again a
received synonyme with soul, the immortal part of man. 
There is here a strange system of confusion and error, which it
is most imprudent to regard as essential to religion, since
candid investigations of nature tend to shew its
untenableness.  There is, in reality, nothing to prevent our
regarding man as specially endowed with an immortal spirit, at
the same time that his ordinary mental manifestations are looked
upon as simple phenomena resulting from organization, those of
the lower animals being phenomena absolutely the same in
character, though developed within much narrower limits. [326]
What has chiefly tended to take mind, in the eyes of learned
and unlearned, out of the range of nature, is its apparently
irregular and wayward character.  How different the
manifestations in different beings! how unstable in all!—at
one time so calm, at another so wild and impulsive!  It
seemed impossible that anything so subtle and aberrant could be
part of a system, the main features of which are regularity and
precision.  But the irregularity of mental phenomena is only
in appearance.  When we give up the individual, and take the
mass, we find as much uniformity of result as in any other class
of natural phenomena.  The irregularity is exactly of the
same kind as that of the weather.  No man can say what may
be the weather of to-morrow; but the quantity of rain which falls
in any particular place in any five years, is precisely the same
as the quantity which falls in any other five years at the same
place.  Thus, while it is absolutely impossible to predict
of any one Frenchman that during next year he will commit a
crime, it is quite certain that about one in every six hundred
and fifty of the French people will do so, because in past years
the proportion has generally been about that amount, the
tendencies to crime in relation to the temptations being
everywhere invariable over a sufficiently wide range of
time.  So also, the number of persons taken in charge by the
police in London for being drunk and disorderly on the streets,
is, week by week, a nearly uniform quantity, shewing that the
inclination to drink to excess is always in the mass about the
same, regard being had to the existing temptations or
stimulations to this vice.  Even mistakes and oversights are
of regular recurrence, for it is found in the post-offices of
large cities, that the number of letters put in without addresses
is year by year the same.  Statistics has made out an
equally distinct regularity in a wide range, with regard to many
other things concerning the mind, and the doctrine founded upon
it has lately produced a scheme which may well strike the
ignorant with surprise.  It was proposed to establish in
London a society for ensuring the integrity of clerks,
secretaries, collectors, and all such functionaries as are
usually obliged to find security for money passing through their
hands in the course of business.  A gentleman of the highest
character as an actuary spoke of the plan in the following
terms:—“If a thousand bankers’ clerks were to
club together to indemnify their securities, by the payment of
one pound a year each, and if each had given security for
500l., it is obvious that two in each year might become
defaulters to that amount, four to half the amount, and so on,
without rendering the guarantee fund insolvent.  If it be
tolerably well ascertained that the instances of dishonesty
(yearly) among such persons amount to one in five hundred, this
club would continue to exist, subject to being in debt in a bad
year, to an amount which it would be able to discharge in good
ones.  The only question necessary to be asked previous to
the formation of such a club would be,—may it not be feared
that the motive to resist dishonesty would be lessened by the
existence of the club, or that ready-made rogues, by belonging to
it, might find the means of obtaining situations which they would
otherwise have been kept out of by the impossibility of obtaining
security among those who know them?  Suppose this be
sufficiently answered by saying, that none but those who could
bring satisfactory testimony to their previous good character
should be allowed to join the club; that persons who may now hope
that a deficiency on their parts will be made up and hushed up by
the relative or friend who is security, will know very well that
the club will have no motive to decline a prosecution, or to keep
the secret, and so on.  It then only remains to ask, whether
the sum demanded for the guarantee is sufficient?” [331]  The philosophical principle on
which the scheme proceeds, seems to be simply this, that, amongst
a given (large) number of persons of good character, there will
be, within a year or other considerable space of time, a
determinate number of instances in which moral principle and the
terror of the consequences of guilt will be overcome by
temptations of a determinate kind and amount, and thus occasion a
certain periodical amount of loss which the association must make
up.
This statistical regularity in moral affairs fully establishes
their being under the presidency of law.  Man is now seen to
be an enigma only as an individual; in the mass he is a
mathematical problem.  It is hardly necessary to say, much
less to argue, that mental action, being proved to be under law,
passes at once into the category of natural things.  Its old
metaphysical character vanishes in a moment, and the distinction
usually taken between physical and moral is annulled, as only an
error in terms.  This view agrees with what all observation
teaches, that mental phenomena flow directly from the
brain.  They are seen to be dependent on naturally
constituted and naturally conditioned organs, and thus obedient,
like all other organic phenomena, to law.  And how wondrous
must the constitution of this apparatus be, which gives us
consciousness of thought and of affection, which makes us
familiar with the numberless things of earth, and enables us to
rise in conception and communion to the councils of God
himself!  It is matter which forms the medium or
instrument—a little mass which, decomposed, is but so much
common dust; yet in its living constitution, designed, formed,
and sustained by Almighty Wisdom, how admirable its character!
how reflective of the unutterable depths of that Power by which
it was so formed, and is so sustained!
In the mundane economy, mental action takes its place as a
means of providing for the independent existence and the various
relations of animals, each species being furnished according to
its special necessities and the demands of its various
relations.  The nervous system—the more comprehensive
term for its organic apparatus—is variously developed in
different classes and species, and also in different individuals,
the volume or mass bearing a general relation to the amount of
power.  In the mollusca and crustacea we see simply a
ganglionic cord pervading the extent of the body, and sending out
lateral filaments.  In the vertebrata, we find a brain with
a spinal cord, and branching lines of nervous tissue. [333]  But here, as in the general
structure of animals, the great principle of unity is
observed.  The brain of the vertebrata is merely an
expansion of one of the ganglions of the nervous cord of the
mollusca and crustacea.  Or the corresponding ganglion of
the mollusca and crustacea may be regarded as the rudiment of a
brain; the superior organ thus appearing as only a farther
development of the inferior.  There are many facts which
tend to prove that the action of this apparatus is of an electric
nature, a modification of that surprising agent, which takes
magnetism, heat, and light, as other subordinate forms, and of
whose general scope in this great system of things we are only
beginning to have a right conception.  It has been found
that simple electricity, artificially produced, and sent along
the nerves of a dead body, excites muscular action.  The
brain of a newly-killed animal being taken out, and replaced by a
substance which produces electric action, the operation of
digestion, which had been interrupted by the death of the animal,
was resumed, shewing the absolute identity of the brain with a
galvanic battery.  Nor is this a very startling idea, when
we reflect that electricity is almost as metaphysical as ever
mind was supposed to be.  It is a thing perfectly
intangible, weightless.  Metal may be magnetized, or heated
to seven hundred of Fahrenheit, without becoming the hundredth
part of a grain heavier.  And yet electricity is a real
thing, an actual existence in nature, as witness the effects of
heat and light in vegetation—the power of the galvanic
current to re-assemble the particles of copper from a solution,
and make them again into a solid plate—the rending force of
the thunderbolt as it strikes the oak; see also how both heat and
light observe the angle of incidence in reflection, as exactly as
does the grossest stone thrown obliquely against a wall.  So
mental action may be imponderable, intangible, and yet a real
existence, and ruled by the Eternal through his laws. [335]
Common observation shews a great general superiority of the
human mind over that of the inferior animals.  Man’s
mind is almost infinite in device; it ranges over all the world;
it forms the most wonderful combinations; it seeks back into the
past, and stretches forward into the future; while the animals
generally appear to have a narrow range of thought and
action.  But so also has an infant but a limited range, and
yet it is mind which works there, as well as in the most
accomplished adults.  The difference between mind in the
lower animals and in man is a difference in degree only; it is
not a specific difference.  All who have studied animals by
actual observation, and even those who have given a candid
attention to the subject in books, must attain more or less clear
convictions of this truth, notwithstanding all the obscurity
which prejudice may have engendered.  We see animals capable
of affection, jealousy, envy; we see them quarrel, and conduct
quarrels, in the very manner pursued by the more impulsive of our
own race.  We see them liable to flattery, inflated with
pride, and dejected by shame.  We see them as tender to
their young as human parents are, and as faithful to a trust as
the most conscientious of human servants.  The horse is
startled by marvellous objects, as a man is.  The dog and
many others shew tenacious memory.  The dog also proves
himself possessed of imagination, by the act of dreaming. 
Horses, finding themselves in want of a shoe, have of their own
accord gone to a farrier’s shop where they were shod
before.  Cats, closed up in rooms, will endeavour to obtain
their liberation by pulling a latch or ringing a bell.  It
has several times been observed that in a field of cattle, when
one or two were mischievous, and persisted long in annoying or
tyrannizing over the rest, the herd, to all appearance,
consulted, and then, making a united effort, drove the troublers
off the ground.  The members of a rookery have also been
observed to take turns in supplying the needs of a family reduced
to orphanhood.  All of these are acts of reason, in no
respect different from similar acts of men.  Moreover,
although there is no heritage of accumulated knowledge amongst
the lower animals, as there is amongst us, they are in some
degree susceptible of those modifications of natural character,
and capable of those accomplishments, which we call
education.  The taming and domestication of animals, and the
changes thus produced upon their nature in the course of
generations, are results identical with civilization amongst
ourselves; and the quiet, servile steer is probably as unlike the
original wild cattle of this country, as the English gentleman of
the present day is unlike the rude baron of the age of King
John.  Between a young, unbroken horse, and a trained one,
there is, again, all the difference which exists between a wild
youth reared at his own discretion in the country, and the same
person when he has been toned down by long exposure to the
influences of refined society.  On the accomplishments
acquired by animals it were superfluous to enter at any length;
but I may advert to the dogs of M. Leonard, as remarkable
examples of what the animal intellect may be trained to. 
When four pieces of card are laid down before them, each having a
number pronounced once in connexion with it, they will,
after a re-arrangement of the pieces, select any one named by its
number.  They also play at dominoes, and with so much skill
as to triumph over biped opponents, whining if the adversary
place a wrong piece, or if they themselves be deficient in a
right one.  Of extensive combinations of thought we have no
reason to believe that any animal is capable—and yet most
of us must feel the force of Walter Scott’s remark, that
there was scarcely anything which he would not believe of a
dog.  There is a curious result of education in certain
animals, namely, that habits to which they have been trained in
some instances become hereditary.  For example, the
accomplishment of pointing at game, although a pure result of
education, appears in the young pups brought up apart from their
parents and kind.  The peculiar leap of the Irish horse,
acquired in the course of traversing a boggy country, is
continued in the progeny brought up in England.  This
hereditariness of specific habits suggests a relation to that
form of psychological demonstration usually called instinct; but
instinct is only another term for mind, or is mind in a peculiar
stage of development; and though the fact were otherwise, it
could not affect the postulate, that demonstrations such as have
been enumerated are mainly intellectual demonstrations, not to be
distinguished as such from those of human beings.
More than this, the lower animals manifested mental phenomena
long before man existed.  While as yet there was no brain
capable of working out a mathematical problem, the economy of the
six-sided figure was exemplified by the instinct of the
bee.  Ere human musician had whistled or piped, the owl
hooted in B flat, the cuckoo had her song of a falling third, and
the chirp of the cricket was in B.  The dog and the elephant
prefigured the sagacity of the human mind.  The love of a
human mother for her babe was anticipated by nearly every humbler
mammal, the carnaria not excepted.  The peacock strutted,
the turkey blustered, and the cock fought for victory, just as
human beings afterwards did, and still do.  Our faculty of
imitation, on which so much of our amusement depends, was
exercised by the mocking-bird; and the whole tribe of monkeys
must have walked about the pre-human world, playing off those
tricks in which we see the comicality and mischief-making of our
character so curiously exaggerated.
The unity and simplicity which characterize nature give great
antecedent probability to what observation seems about to
establish, that, as the brain of the vertebrata generally is just
an advanced condition of a particular ganglion in the mollusca
and crustacea, so are the brains of the higher and more
intelligent mammalia only farther developments of the brains of
the inferior orders of the same class.  Or, to the same
purpose, it may be said, that each species has certain superior
developments, according to its needs, while others are in a
rudimental or repressed state.  This will more clearly
appear after some inquiry has been made into the various powers
comprehended under the term mind.
One of the first and simplest functions of mind is to give
consciousness—consciousness of our identity and of our
existence.  This, apparently, is independent of the
senses, which are simply media, and, as Locke has shewn,
the only media, through which ideas respecting the external world
reach the brain.  The access of such ideas to the brain is
the act to which the metaphysicians have given the name of
perception.  Gall, however, has shewn, by induction from a
vast number of actual cases, that there is a part of the brain
devoted to perception, and that even this is subdivided into
portions which are respectively dedicated to the reception of
different sets of ideas, as those of form, size, colour, weight,
objects in their totality, events in their progress or
occurrence, time, musical sounds, &c.  The system of
mind invented by this philosopher—the only one founded upon
nature, or which even pretends to or admits of that necessary
basis—shews a portion of the brain acting as a faculty of
comic ideas, another of imitation, another of wonder, one for
discriminating or observing differences, and another in which
resides the power of tracing effects to causes.  There are
also parts of the brain for the sentimental part of our nature,
or the affections, at the head of which stand the moral feelings
of benevolence, conscientiousness, and veneration.  Through
these, man stands in relation to himself, his fellow-men, the
external world, and his God; and through these comes most of the
happiness of man’s life, as well as that which he derives
from the contemplation of the world to come, and the cultivation
of his relation to it, (pure religion.)  The other
sentiments may be briefly enumerated, their names being
sufficient in general to denote their functions—firmness,
hope, cautiousness, self-esteem, love of approbation,
secretiveness, marvellousness, constructiveness, imitation,
combativeness, destructiveness, concentrativeness, adhesiveness,
love of the opposite sex, love of offspring, alimentiveness, and
love of life.  Through these faculties, man is connected
with the external world, and supplied with active impulses to
maintain his place in it as an individual and as a species. 
There is also a faculty, (language) for expressing, by whatever
means, (signs, gestures, looks, conventional terms in speech,)
the ideas which arise in the mind.  There is a particular
state of each of these faculties, when the ideas of objects once
formed by it are revived or reproduced, a process which seems to
be intimately allied with some of the phenomena of the new
science of photography, when images impressed by reflection of
the sun’s rays upon sensitive paper are, after a temporary
obliteration, resuscitated on the sheet being exposed to the
fumes of mercury.  Such are the phenomena of memory, that
handmaid of intellect, without which there could be no
accumulation of mental capital, but an universal and continual
infancy.  Conception and imagination appear to be only
intensities, so to speak, of the state of brain in which memory
is produced.  On their promptness and power depend most of
the exertions which distinguish the man of arts and letters, and
even in no small measure the cultivator of science.
The faculties above described—the actual elements of the
mental constitution—are seen in mature man in an indefinite
potentiality and range of action.  It is different with the
lower animals.  They are there comparatively definite in
their power and restricted in their application.  The reader
is familiar with what are called instincts in some of the humbler
species, that is, an uniform and unprompted tendency towards
certain particular acts, as the building of cells by the bee, the
storing of provisions by that insect and several others, and the
construction of nests for a coming progeny by birds.  This
quality is nothing more than a mode of operation peculiar to the
faculties in a humble state of endowment, or early stage of
development.  The cell formation of the bee, the
house-building of ants and beavers, the web-spinning of spiders,
are but primitive exercises of constructiveness, the faculty
which, indefinite with us, leads to the arts of the weaver,
upholsterer, architect, and mechanist, and makes us often work
delightedly where our labours are in vain, or nearly so. 
The storing of provisions by the ants is an exercise of
acquisitiveness,—the faculty which with us makes rich men
and misers.  A vast number of curious devices, by which
insects provide for the protection and subsistence of their
young, whom they are perhaps never to see, are most probably a
peculiar restricted effort of philoprogenitiveness.  The
common source of this class of acts, and of common mental
operations, is shewn very convincingly by the melting of the one
set into the other.  Thus, for example, the bee and bird
will make modifications in the ordinary form of their cells and
nests when necessity compels them.  Thus, the alimentiveness
of such animals as the dog, usually definite with regard to
quantity and quality, can be pampered or educated up to a kind of
epicurism, that is, an indefiniteness of object and action. 
The same faculty acts limitedly in ourselves at first, dictating
the special act of sucking; afterwards it acquires
indefiniteness.  Such is the real nature of the distinction
between what are called instincts and reason, upon which so many
volumes have been written without profit to the world.  All
faculties are instinctive, that is, dependent on internal and
inherent impulses.  This term is therefore not specially
applicable to either of the recognised modes of the operation of
the faculties.  We only, in the one case, see the faculty in
an immature and slightly developed state; in the other, in its
most advanced condition.  In the one case it is
definite, in the other indefinite, in its range of
action.  These terms would perhaps be the most suitable for
expressing the distinction.
In the humblest forms of being we can trace scarcely anything
besides a definite action in a few of the faculties. 
Generally speaking, as we ascend in the scale, we see more and
more of the faculties in exercise, and these tending more to the
indefinite mode of manifestation.  And for this there is the
obvious reason in providence, that the lowest animals have all of
them a very limited sphere of existence, born only to perform a
few functions, and enjoy a brief term of life, and then give way
to another generation, so that they do not need much mental
guidance.  At higher points in the scale, the sphere of
existence is considerably extended, and the mental operations are
less definite accordingly.  The horse, dog, and a few other
rasorial types, noted for their serviceableness to our race, have
the indefinite powers in no small endowment.  Man, again,
shews very little of the definite mode of operation, and that
little chiefly in childhood, or in barbarism or idiocy. 
Destined for a wide field of action, and to be applicable to
infinitely varied contingencies, he has all the faculties
developed to a high pitch of indefiniteness, that he may be ready
to act well in all imaginable cases.  His commission, it may
be said, gives large discretionary powers, while that of the
inferior animals is limited to a few precise directions. 
But when the human brain is congenitally imperfect or diseased,
or when it is in the state of infancy, we see in it an approach
towards the character of the brains of some of the inferior
animals.  Dr. G. J. Davey states that he has frequently
witnessed, among his patients at the Hanwell Lunatic Asylum,
indications of a particular abnormal cerebration which forcibly
reminded him of the specific healthy characteristics of animals
lower in the scale of organization; [346] and every one must
have observed how often the actions of children, especially in
their moments of play, and where their selfish feelings are
concerned, bear a resemblance to those of certain familiar
animals. [347]  Behold, then, the wonderful
unity of the whole system.  The grades of mind, like the
forms of being, are mere stages of development.  In the
humbler forms, but a few of the mental faculties are traceable,
just as we see in them but a few of the lineaments of universal
structure.  In man the system has arrived at its highest
condition.  The few gleams of reason, then, which we see in
the lower animals, are precisely analogous to such a development
of the fore-arm as we find in the paddle of the whale. 
Causality, comparison, and other of the nobler faculties, are in
them rudimental.
Bound up as we thus are by an identity in the character of our
mental organization with the lower animals, we are yet, it will
be observed, strikingly distinguished from them by this great
advance in development.  We have faculties in full force and
activity which the animals either possess not at all, or in so
low and obscure a form as to be equivalent to
non-existence.  Now these parts of mind are those which
connect us with the things that are not of this world.  We
have veneration, prompting us to the worship of the Deity, which
the animals lack.  We have hope, to carry us on in thought
beyond the bounds of time.  We have reason, to enable us to
inquire into the character of the Great Father, and the relation
of us, his humble creatures, towards him.  We have
conscientiousness and benevolence, by which we can in a faint and
humble measure imitate, in our conduct, that which he exemplifies
in the whole of his wondrous doings.  Beyond this, mental
science does not carry us in support of religion: the rest
depends on evidence of a different kind.  But it is surely
much that we thus discover in nature a provision for things so
important.  The existence of faculties having a regard to
such things is a good evidence that such things exist.  The
face of God is reflected in the organization of man, as a little
pool reflects the glorious sun.
The affective or sentimental faculties are all of them liable
to operate whenever appropriate objects or stimuli are presented,
and this they do as irresistibly and unerringly as the tree sucks
up moisture which it requires, with only this exception, that one
faculty often interferes with the action of another, and operates
instead by force of superior inherent strength or temporary
activity.  For example, alimentiveness may be in powerful
operation with regard to its appropriate object, producing a keen
appetite, and yet it may not act, in consequence of the more
powerful operation of cautiousness, warning against evil
consequences likely to ensue from the desired indulgence. 
This liability to flit from under the control of one feeling to
the control of another, constitutes what is recognised as free
will in man, being nothing more than a vicissitude in the
supremacy of the faculties over each other.
It is a common mistake to suppose that the individuals of our
own species are all of them formed with similar
faculties—similar in power and tendency—and that
education and the influence of circumstances produce all the
differences which we observe.  There is not, in the old
systems of mental philosophy, any doctrine more opposite to the
truth than this.  It is refuted at once by the great
differences of intellectual tendency and moral disposition to be
observed amongst a group of young children who have been all
brought up in circumstances perfectly identical—even in
twins, who have never been but in one place, under the charge of
one nurse, attended to alike in all respects.  The mental
characters of individuals are inherently various, as the forms of
their persons and the features of their faces are; and education
and circumstances, though their influence is not to be despised,
are incapable of entirely altering these characters, where they
are strongly developed.  That the original characters of
mind are dependent on the volume of particular parts of the brain
and the general quality of that viscus, is proved by induction
from an extensive range of observations, the force of which must
have been long since universally acknowledged but for the
unpreparedness of mankind to admit a functional connexion between
mind and body.  The different mental characters of
individuals may be presumed from analogy to depend on the same
law of development which we have seen determining forms of being
and the mental characters of particular species.  This we
may conceive as carrying forward the intellectual powers and
moral dispositions of some to a high pitch, repressing those of
others at a moderate amount, and thus producing all the varieties
which we see in our fellow-creatures.  Thus a Cuvier and a
Newton are but expansions of a clown, and the person emphatically
called the wicked man, is one whose highest moral feelings are
rudimental.  Such differences are not confined to our
species; they are only less strongly marked in many of the
inferior animals.  There are clever dogs and wicked horses,
as well as clever men and wicked men, and education sharpens the
talents, and in some degree regulates the dispositions of
animals, as it does our own.  Here I may advert to a very
interesting analogy between the mental characters of the types in
the quinary system of zoology and the characters of individual
men.  We have seen that the pre-eminent type is usually
endowed with an harmonious assemblage of the mental qualities
belonging to the whole group, while the sub-typical inclines to
ferocity, the rasorial to gentleness, and so on.  Now,
amongst individuals, some appear to be almost exclusively of the
sub-typical, and others of the rasorial characters, while to a
limited number is given the finely assorted assemblage of
qualities which places them on a parallel with the typical. 
To this may be attributed the universality which marks all the
very highest brains, such as those of Shakespeare and Scott, men
of whom it has been remarked that they must have possessed within
themselves not only the poet, but the warrior, the statesman, and
the philosopher; and who, moreover, appear to have had the mild
and manly, the moral and the forcible parts of our nature, in the
most perfect balance.
There is, nevertheless, a general adaptation of the mental
constitution of man to the circumstances in which he lives, as
there is between all the parts of nature to each other.  The
goods of the physical world are only to be realized by ingenuity
and industrious exertion; behold, accordingly, an intellect full
of device, and a fabric of the faculties which would go to pieces
or destroy itself if it were not kept in constant
occupation.  Nature presents to us much that is sublime and
beautiful: behold faculties which delight in contemplating these
properties of hers, and in rising upon them, as upon wings, to
the presence of the Eternal.  It is also a world of
difficulties and perils, and see how a large portion of our
species are endowed with vigorous powers which take a pleasure in
meeting and overcoming difficulty and danger.  Even that
principle on which our faculties are constituted—a wide
range of freedom in which to act for all various
occasions—necessitates a resentful faculty, by which
individuals may protect themselves from the undue and capricious
exercise of each other’s faculties, and thus preserve their
individual rights.  So also there is cautiousness, to give
us a tendency to provide against the evils by which we may be
assailed; and secretiveness, to enable us to conceal whatever,
being divulged, would be offensive to others or injurious to
ourselves,—a function which obviously has a certain
legitimate range of action, however liable to be abused. 
The constitution of the mind generally points to a state of
intimate relation of individuals towards society, towards the
external world, and towards things above this world.  No
individual being is integral or independent; he is only part of
an extensive piece of social mechanism.  The inferior mind,
full of rude energy and unregulated impulse, does not more
require a superior nature to act as its master and its mentor,
than does the superior nature require to be surrounded by such
rough elements on which to exercise its high endowments as a
ruling and tutelary power.  This relation of each to each
produces a vast portion of the active business of life.  It
is easy to see that, if we were all alike in our moral
tendencies, and all placed on a medium of perfect moderation in
this respect, the world would be a scene of everlasting dulness
and apathy.  It requires the variety of individual
constitution to give moral life to the scene.
The indefiniteness of the potentiality of the human faculties,
and the complexity which thus attends their relations, lead
unavoidably to occasional error.  If we consider for a
moment that there are not less than thirty such faculties, that
they are each given in different proportions to different
persons, that each is at the same time endowed with a wide
discretion as to the force and frequency of its action, and that
our neighbours, the world, and our connexions with something
beyond it, are all exercising an ever-varying influence over us,
we cannot be surprised at the irregularities attending human
conduct.  It is simply the penalty paid for the superior
endowment.  It is here that the imperfection of our nature
resides.  Causality and conscientiousness are, it is true,
guides over all; but even these are only faculties of the same
indeterminate constitution as the rest, and partake accordingly
of the same inequality of action.  Man is therefore a piece
of mechanism, which never can act so as to satisfy his own ideas
of what he might be—for he can imagine a state of moral
perfection, (as he can imagine a globe formed of diamonds,
pearls, and rubies,) though his constitution forbids him to
realize it.  There ever will, in the best disposed and most
disciplined minds, be occasional discrepancies between the amount
of temptation and the power summoned for regulation or
resistance, or between the stimulus and the mobility of the
faculty; and hence those errors, and shortcomings, and excesses,
without end, with which the good are constantly finding cause to
charge themselves.  There is at the same time even here a
possibility of improvement.  In infancy, the impulses are
all of them irregular; a child is cruel, cunning, and false,
under the slightest temptation, but in time learns to control
these inclinations, and to be habitually humane, frank, and
truthful.  So is human society, in its earliest stages,
sanguinary, aggressive, and deceitful, but in time becomes just,
faithful, and benevolent.  To such improvements there is a
natural tendency which will operate in all fair circumstances,
though it is not to be expected that irregular and undue impulses
will ever be altogether banished from the system.
It may still be a puzzle to many, how beings should be born
into the world whose organization is such that they unavoidably,
even in a civilized country, become malefactors.  Does God,
it may be asked, make criminals?  Does he fashion certain
beings with a predestination to evil?  He does not do so;
and yet the criminal type of brain, as it is called, comes into
existence in accordance with laws which the Deity has
established.  It is not, however, as the result of the first
or general intention of those laws, but as an exception from
their ordinary and proper action.  The production of those
evilly disposed beings is in this manner.  The moral
character of the progeny depends in a general way, (as does the
physical character also,) upon conditions of the
parents,—both general conditions, and conditions at the
particular time of the commencement of the existence of the new
being, and likewise external conditions affecting the fœtus
through the mother.  Now the amount of these conditions is
indefinite.  The faculties of the parents, as far as these
are concerned, may have oscillated for the time towards the
extreme of tensibility in one direction.  The influences
upon the fœtus may have also been of an extreme and unusual
kind.  Let us suppose that the conditions upon the whole
have been favourable for the development, not of the higher, but
of the lower sentiments, and of the propensities of the new
being, the result will necessarily be a mean type of brain. 
Here, it will be observed, God no more decreed an immoral being,
than he decreed an immoral paroxysm of the sentiments.  Our
perplexity is in considering the ill-disposed being by
himself.  He is only a part of a series of phenomena,
traceable to a principle good in the main, but which admits of
evil as an exception.  We have seen that it is for wise ends
that God leaves our moral faculties to an indefinite range of
action; the general good results of this arrangement are obvious;
but exceptions of evil are inseparable from such a system, and
this is one of them.  To come to particular
illustration—when a people are oppressed, or kept in a
state of slavery, they invariably contract habits of lying, for
the purpose of deceiving and outwitting their superiors,
falsehood being a refuge of the weak under difficulties. 
What is a habit in parents becomes an inherent quality in
children.  We are not, therefore, to be surprised when a
traveller tells us that black children in the West Indies appear
to lie by instinct, and never answer a white person truly even in
the simplest matter.  Here we have secretiveness roused in a
people to a state of constant and exalted exercise; an over
tendency of the nervous energy in that direction is the
consequence, and a new organic condition is established. 
This tells upon the progeny, which comes into the world with
secretiveness excessive in volume and activity.  All other
evil characteristics may be readily conceived as being implanted
in a new generation in the same way.  And sometimes not one,
but several generations, may be concerned in bringing up the
result to a pitch which produces crime.  It is, however, to
be observed, that the general tendency of things is to a
limitation, not the extension of such abnormally constituted
beings.  The criminal brain finds itself in a social scene
where all is against it.  It may struggle on for a time, but
the medium and superior natures are never long at a loss in
getting the better of it.  The disposal of such beings will
always depend much on the moral state of a community, the degree
in which just views prevail with regard to human nature, and the
feelings which accident may have caused to predominate at a
particular time.  Where the mass was little enlightened or
refined, and terrors for life or property were highly excited,
malefactors have ever been treated severely.  But when order
is generally triumphant, and reason allowed sway, men begin to
see the true case of criminals—namely, that while one large
department are victims of erroneous social conditions, another
are brought to error by tendencies which they are only
unfortunate in having inherited from nature.  Criminal
jurisprudence then addresses itself less to the direct punishment
than to the reformation and care-taking of those liable to its
attention.  And such a treatment of criminals, it may be
farther remarked, so that it stop short of affording any
encouragement to crime, (a point which experience will
determine,) is evidently no more than justice, seeing how
accidentally all forms of the moral constitution are distributed,
and how thoroughly mutual obligation shines throughout the whole
frame of society—the strong to help the weak, the good to
redeem and restrain the bad.
The sum of all we have seen of the psychical constitution of
man is, that its Almighty Author has destined it, like everything
else, to be developed from inherent qualities, and to have a mode
of action depending solely on its own organization.  Thus
the whole is complete on one principle.  The masses of space
are formed by law; law makes them in due time theatres of
existence for plants and animals; sensation, disposition,
intellect, are all in like manner developed and sustained in
action by law.  It is most interesting to observe into how
small a field the whole of the mysteries of nature thus
ultimately resolve themselves.  The inorganic has one final
comprehensive law, GRAVITATION.  The organic, the other
great department of mundane things, rests in like manner on one
law, and that is,—DEVELOPMENT.  Nor may even these be
after all twain, but only branches of one still more
comprehensive law, the expression of that unity which man’s
wit can scarcely separate from Deity itself.</div></body></text></TEI>