<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="33">
      APPENDIX, No. 1.
    

      In presenting to my readers the account of the meeting of men of science
      at Berlin, in the autumn of 1828, I am happy to be able to state, that its
      influence has been most beneficial, and that the annual meeting to be held
      in 1831, will take place at Vienna, the Emperor of Austria having
      expressed a wish that every facility which his capital affords should be
      given to promote its objects.
    

      It is gratifying to find that a country, which has hitherto been
      considered adverse to the progress of knowledge, should become convinced
      of its value; and it is sincerely to be hoped, that every one of the
      numerous members of the Society will show, by his conduct, that the paths
      of science are less likely than any others to interfere with those of
      politics.
    

      ACCOUNT OF THE GREAT CONGRESS OF PHILOSOPHERS AT BERLIN, ON THE 18TH OF
      SEPTEMBER 1828. FROM THE EDINBURGH JOURNAL OF SCIENCE, APRIL, 1829.
    

      The existence of a large society of cultivators of the natural sciences
      meeting annually at some great capital, or some central town of Europe, is
      a circumstance almost unknown to us, and deserving of our attention, from
      the important advantages which may arise from it.
    

      About eight years ago, Dr. Okens, of Munich, suggested a plan for an
      annual meeting of all Germans who cultivated the sciences of medicine and
      botany. The first meeting, of about forty members, took place at Leipsic,
      in 1822, and it was successively held at Halle, Wurtzburg, Frankfort on
      the Maine, Dresden, Munich, and Berlin. All those who had printed a
      certain number of sheets of their inquiries on these subjects were
      considered members of this academy.
    

      The great advantages which resulted to these sciences from the
      communication of observations from all quarters of Germany, soon induced
      an extension of the plan, and other departments of natural knowledge were
      admitted, until, at the last meeting, the cultivators even of pure
      mathematics were found amongst the ranks of this academy.
    

      Several circumstances, independent of the form and constitution of the
      academy, contributed to give unwonted splendour to the last meeting, which
      took place at Berlin in the middle of September of the last year.
    

      The capital selected for its temporary residence is scarcely surpassed by
      any in Europe in the number and celebrity of its savans.
    

      The taste for knowledge possessed by the reigning family, has made
      knowledge itself fashionable; and the severe sufferings of the Prussians
      previous to the war, by which themselves and Europe were freed, have
      impressed on them so strongly the lesson that "knowledge is power," that
      its effects are visible in every department of the government; and there
      is no country in Europe in which talents and genius so surely open for
      their possessors the road to wealth and distinction.
    

      Another circumstance also contributed its portion to increase the numbers
      of the meeting of the past year. The office of president, which is
      annually changed, was assigned to M. Alexander de Humboldt. The
      universality of his acquirements, which have left no branch within the
      wide range of science indifferent or unexplored, has connected him by
      friendship with almost all the most celebrated philosophers of the age;
      whilst the polished amenity of his manners, and that intense desire of
      acquiring and of spreading knowledge, which so peculiarly characterizes
      his mind, renders him accessible to all strangers, and insures for them
      the assistance of his counsel in their scientific pursuits, and the
      advantage of being made known to all those who are interested or occupied
      in similar inquiries.
    

      Professor Lichtenstein, (Director of the Museum of Zoology,) as secretary
      of the academy, was indefatigable in his attentions, and most ably
      seconded the wishes of its distinguished president.
    

      These two gentlemen, assisted by several of the residents at Berlin,
      undertook the numerous preliminary arrangements necessary for the
      accommodation of the meeting.
    

      On the 18th of September, 1828, there were assembled at Berlin 377 members
      of the academy, whose names and residences (in Berlin) were printed in a
      small pamphlet, and to each name was attached a number, to indicate his
      seat in the great concert room, in which the morning meetings took place.
      Each member was also provided with an engraved card of the hall of
      meeting, on which the numbers of the seats were printed in black ink, and
      his own peculiar seat marked in red ink, so that every person immediately
      found his own place, and knew where to look for any friend whom he might
      wish to find.
    

      At the hour appointed for the opening of the meeting, the members being
      assembled, and the galleries and orchestra being filled by an assemblage
      of a large part of the rank and beauty of the capital, and the side-boxes
      being occupied by several branches of the royal family, and by the foreign
      ambassadors, the session of the academy was opened by the eloquent address
      of the president.
    

      SPEECH made at the Opening of the Society of German Naturalists and
      Natural Philosophers at Berlin, the 18th of September, 1828.—By
      ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT.
    

      Since through your choice, which does me so much honour, I am permitted to
      open this meeting, the first duty which I have to discharge is one of
      gratitude. The distinction which has been conferred on him who has never
      yet been able to attend your excellent society, is not the reward of
      scientific efforts, or of feeble and persevering attempts to discover new
      phenomena, or to draw the light of knowledge from the unexplored depths of
      nature. A finer feeling, however, directed your attention to me. You have
      assured me, that while, during an absence of many years, and in a distant
      quarter of the globe, I was labouring in the same cause with yourselves, I
      was not a stranger in your thoughts. You have likewise greeted my return
      home, that, by the sacred tie of gratitude, you might bind me still longer
      and closer to our common country.
    

      What, however, can the picture of this, our native land, present more
      agreeable to the mind, than the assembly which we receive to-day for the
      first time within our walls; from the banks of the Neckar, the birth-place
      of Kepler and of Schiller, to the remotest border of the Baltic plains;
      from hence to the mouths of the Rhine, where, under the beneficent
      influence of commerce, the treasuries of exotic nature have for centuries
      been collected and investigated, the friends of nature, inspired with the
      same zeal, and, urged by the same passion, flock together to this
      assembly. Everywhere, where the German language is used, and its peculiar
      structure affects the spirit and disposition of the people. From the Great
      European Alps, to the other side of the Weichsel, where, in the country of
      Copernicus, astronomy rose to renewed splendour; everywhere in the
      extensive dominions of the German nation we attempt to discover the secret
      operations of nature, whether in the heavens, or in the deepest problems
      of mechanics, or in the interior of the earth, or in the finely woven
      tissues of organic structure.
    

      Protected by noble princes, this assembly has annually increased in
      interest and extent. Every distinction which difference of religion or
      form of government can occasion is here annulled. Germany manifests itself
      as it were in its intellectual unity; and since knowledge of truth and
      performance of duty are the highest object of morality, that feeling of
      unity weakens none of the bonds which the religion, constitution, and laws
      of our country, have rendered dear to each of us. Even this emulation in
      mental struggles has called forth (as the glorious history of our country
      tells us,) the fairest blossoms of humanity, science, and art.
    

      The assembly of German naturalists and natural philosophers since its last
      meeting, when it was so hospitably received at Munich, has, through the
      flattering interest of neighbouring states and academies, shone with
      peculiar lustre. Allied nations have renewed the ancient alliance between
      Germany and the ancient Scandinavian North.
    

      Such an interest deserves acknowledgment the more, because it unexpectedly
      increases the mass of facts and opinions which are here brought into one
      common and useful union. It also recalls lofty recollections into the mind
      of the naturalist. Scarcely half a century has elapsed since Linne
      appears, in the boldness of the undertakings which he has attempted and
      accomplished, as one of the greatest men of the last century. His glory,
      however bright, has not rendered Europe blind to the merits of Scheele and
      Bergman. The catalogue of these great names is not completed; but lest I
      shall offend noble modesty, I dare not speak of the light which is still
      flowing in richest profusion from the North, nor mention the discoveries
      in the chemical nature of substances, in the numerical relation of their
      elements, or the eddying streams of electro-magnetic powers. [The
      philosophers here referred to are Berzelius and Oersted.] May those
      excellent persons, who, deterred neither by perils of sea or land, have
      hastened to our meeting from Sweden, Norway, Denmark, Holland, England,
      and Poland, point our the way to other strangers in succeeding years, so
      that by turns every part of Germany may enjoy the effects of scientific
      communication with the different nations of Europe.
    

      But although I must restrain the expression of my personal feelings in
      presence of this assembly, I must be permitted at least to name the
      patriarchs of our national glory, who are detained from us by a regard for
      those lives so dear to their country;—Goethe, whom the great
      creations of poetical fancy have not prevented from penetrating the ARCANA
      of nature, and who now in rural solitude mourns for his princely friend,
      as Germany for one of her greatest ornaments;—Olbers, who has
      discovered two bodies where he had already predicted they were to be
      found;—the greatest anatomists of our age—Soemmering, who,
      with equal zeal, has investigated the wonders of organic structure, and
      the spots and FACULAE of the sun, (condensations and openings of the
      photosphere;) Blumenbach, whose pupil I have the honour to be, who, by his
      works and his immortal eloquence, has inspired everywhere a love of
      comparative anatomy, physiology, and the general history of nature, and
      who has laboured diligently for half a century. How could I resist the
      temptation to adorn my discourse with names which posterity will repeat,
      as we are not favoured with their presence?
    

      These observations on the literary wealth of our native country, and the
      progressive developement of our institution, lead us naturally to the
      obstructions which will arise from the increasing number of our
      fellow-labourers, The chief object of this assembly does not consist, as
      in other societies whose sphere is more limited, in the mutual interchange
      of treatises, or in innumerable memoirs, destined to be printed in some
      general collection. The principal object of this Society is, to bring
      those personally together who are engaged in the same field of science. It
      is the immediate, and therefore more obvious interchange of ideas, whether
      they present themselves as facts, opinions, or doubts. It is the
      foundation of friendly connexion which throws light on science, adds
      cheerfulness to life, and gives patience and amenity to the manners.
    

      In the most flourishing period of ancient Greece, the distinction between
      words and writing first manifested itself most strongly amongst a race,
      which had raised itself to the most splendid intellectual superiority, and
      to whose latest descendants, as preserved from the shipwreck of nations,
      we still consecrate our most anxious wishes. It was not the difficulty of
      interchange of ideas alone, nor the want of German science, which has
      spread thought as on wings through the world, and insured it a long
      continuance, that then induced the friends of philosophy and natural
      history in Magna Graecia and Asia Minor to wander on long journeys. That
      ancient race knew the inspiring influence of conversation as it
      extemporaneously, freely, and prudently penetrates the tissue of
      scientific opinions and doubts. The discovery of the truth without
      difference of opinion is unattainable, because the truth, in its greatest
      extent, can never be recognized by all, and at the same time. Each step,
      which seems to bring the explorer of nature nearer to his object, only
      carries him to the threshold of new labyrinths. The mass of doubt does not
      diminish, but spreads like a moving cloud over other and new fields; and
      whoever has called that a golden period, when difference of opinions, or,
      as some are accustomed to express it, the disputes of the learned, will be
      finished, has as imperfect a conception of the wants of science, and of
      its continued advancement, as a person who expects that the same opinions
      in geognosy, chemistry, or physiology, will be maintained for several
      centuries.
    

      The founders of this society, with a deep sense of the unity of nature,
      have combined in the completest manner, all the branches of physical
      knowledge, and the historical, geometrical, and experimental philosophy.
      The names of natural historian and natural philosopher are here,
      therefore, nearly synonymous, chained by a terrestrial link to the type of
      the lower animals. Man completes the scale of higher organization. In his
      physiological and pathological qualities, he scarcely presents to us a
      distinct class of beings. As to what has brought him to this exalted
      object of physical study, and has raised him to general scientific
      investigation, belongs principally to this society. Important as it is not
      to break that link which embraces equally the investigation of organic and
      inorganic nature, still the increasing ties and daily developement of this
      institution renders it necessary, besides the general meeting which is
      destined for these halls, to have specific meetings for single branches of
      science. For it is only in such contracted circles,—it is only among
      men whom reciprocity of studies has brought together, that verbal
      discussions can take place. Without this sort of communication, would the
      voluntary association of men in search of truth be deprived of an
      inspiring principle.
    

      Among the preparations which are made in this city for the advancement of
      the society, attention has been principally paid to the possibility of
      such a subdivision into sections. The hope that these preparations will
      meet with your approbation, imposes upon me the duty of reminding you,
      that, although you had entrusted to two travellers, equally, the duty of
      making these arrangements, yet it is to one alone, my noble friend, M.
      Lichtenstein, that the merit of careful precaution and indefatigable
      activity is due. Out of respect to the scientific spirit which animates
      the Society of German Naturalists and Natural Philosophy, and in
      acknowledgment of the utility of their efforts, government have seconded
      all our wishes with the greatest cheerfulness.
    

      In the vicinity of the place of meeting, which has in this manner been
      prepared for our general and special labours, are situated the museums
      dedicated to anatomy, zoology, oryctognosy, and geology. They exhibit to
      the naturalist a rich mine for observation and critical discussion. The
      greater number of these well-arranged collections have existed, like the
      University of Berlin, scarcely twenty years. The oldest of them, to which
      the Botanical Garden, (one of the richest in Europe) belongs, have during
      this period not only been increased, but entirely remodelled. The
      amusement and instruction derived from such institutions, call to our
      minds, with deep feelings of gratitude, that they are the work of that
      great monarch, who modestly and in simple grandeur, adorns every year this
      royal city with new treasures of nature and art; and what is of still
      greater value than the treasures themselves,—what inspires every
      Prussian with youthful strength, and with an enthusiastic love for the
      ancient reigning family,—that he graciously attaches to himself
      every species of talent, and extends with confidence his royal protection
      to the free cultivation of the understanding.
    

      This was followed by a paper on magnetism, by Professor Oersted; and
      several other memoirs were then read.
    

      The arrival of so many persons of similar pursuit, (for 464 members were
      present,) rendered it convenient to have some ordinary, at which those who
      chose might dine, and introduce their friends or families. This had been
      foreseen, and his Majesty had condescended to allow the immense building
      used for the exercise of his troops, to be employed for this purpose.
      One-third of it was floored on the occasion, and tables were arranged, at
      which, on one occasion, 850 persons sat down to dinner. On the evening of
      the first day, M. de Humboldt gave a large SOIREE in the concert rooms
      attached to the theatre. About 1200 persons assembled on this occasion,
      and his Majesty the King of Prussia honoured with his presence the fete of
      his illustrious chamberlain. The nobility of the country, foreign princes,
      and foreign ambassadors, were present. It was gratifying to observe the
      princes of the blood mingling with the cultivators of science, and to see
      the heir-apparent to the throne, during the course of the evening, engaged
      in conversation with those most celebrated for their talents, of his own,
      or of other countries.
    

      Nor were the minor arrangements of the evening beneath the consideration
      of the President. The words of the music selected for the concert, were
      printed and distributed to the visitors. The names of the most illustrious
      philosophers which Germany had produced, were inscribed in letters of gold
      at the end of the great concert room.
    

      In the first rank amongst these stood a name which, England, too, enrolls
      amongst the brightest in her scientific annals; and proud, as well she may
      be, of having fostered and brought to maturity the genius of the first
      Herschel, she has reaped an ample reward in being able to claim as
      entirely her own, the inheritor of his talents and his name.
    

      The six succeeding days were occupied, in the morning, by a meeting of the
      academy, at which papers of general interest were read. In the afternoon,
      through the arrangement of M. de Humboldt and M. Lichtenstein, various
      rooms were appropriated for different sections of the academy. In one, the
      chemical philosophers attended to some chemical memoir, whilst the
      botanists assembled in another room, the physiologists in a third, and the
      natural philosophers in a fourth. Each attended to the reading of papers
      connected with their several sciences. Thus every member was at liberty to
      choose that section in which he felt most interest at the moment, and he
      had at all times power of access to the others. The evenings were
      generally spent at some of the SOIREES of the savans, resident at Berlin,
      whose hospitality and attentions to their learned brethren of other
      countries were unbounded. During the unoccupied hours of the morning, the
      collections of natural history, which are rapidly rising into importance,
      were open to examination; and the various professors and directors who
      assisted the stranger in his inquiries, left him equally gratified by the
      knowledge and urbanity of those who so kindly aided him.
    

      A map of Europe was printed, on which those towns only appeared which had
      sent representatives to this scientific congress; and the numbers sent by
      different kingdoms appeared by the following table, which was attached to
      it;—
    

     Russia.........  1
     Austria........  0
     England........  1
     Holland........  2
     Denmark........  7
     France ........  1
     Sardinia .......  0
     Prussia........ 95
     Bavaria........ 12
     Hanover........  5
     Saxony ........ 21
     Wirtemburg ......  2
     Sweden ........ 13
     Naples ........  1
     Poland ........  3
     German States..... 43
                            —-                       206
     Berlin .......  172
                            —-                       378


      The proportion in which the cultivators of different sciences appeared,
      was not easy to ascertain, because there were few amongst the more eminent
      who had not added to more than one branch of human knowledge. The
      following table, though not professing to be very accurate, will afford,
      perhaps, a tolerably fair view:—
    

     Geometers.............  11
     Astronomers...........   5
     Natural Philosophers .  23
                             — 39

     Mines............   5
     Mineralogy ......  16
     Geology..........   9
                         — 30

     Chemistry........... 18
     Geography...........  8
     Anatomy............. 12

     Zoology............  14
     Natural History....   8
     Botany.............. 35
                          — 57

     Physicians.......   175
     Amateurs  .......     9
     Various .........    35
                         —-381


      A medal was struck in commemoration of this meeting, and it was proposed
      that it should form the first of a series, which should comprise all those
      persons most celebrated for their scientific discoveries in the past and
      present age.
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>