<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 166, folios 159-166</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 166, folios 159-166.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1844">29 November [1844]</date>
          <note type="place">St. James' Square</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 166, folios 159-166</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_166_folios_159-166.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>St James' Sqre Friday. 29th Novr (2 o'clock).</p>
      <p>My Dear Crow. I feel rather disappointed at not hearing from you this morning. I wonder why you did not write me a line, &amp; yet I have no business to expect daily communications from you.</p>
      <p>I have had Wheatstone with me the last 5 hours. He is just gone. He is going to Paris on Monday &amp; will be back in a month.</p>
      <p>He will visit me at Ockham in Jany. He has given me much important information, &amp; still more important advice. He is anxious I</p>
      <p>should take such a position as may enable me to influence Prince Albert, who is (he knows) a very clever young man. John Crosse told me the same thing, which he knew from the first-rate men of science in Germany. The Prince's Whole &amp; sole desire was to be at the head of a scientific circle in England, &amp; he has expressed his utter mortification at the opposition &amp; cold water which have been thrown on all his desires in this respect.</p>
      <p>Wheatstone says none but some woman can put him in the right way, &amp; open the door to him towards all he desires; &amp; that a woman can say that which any man would get into</p>
      <p>a scrape by doing. Wheatstone does not wish me to think of doing anything immediate.</p>
      <p>By no means. But he says it would occur in the natural course of things that if I can take a certain standing in the course of the next few years, the Prince would on some occasion speak to me about science; and that in that case, if I happily seize the moment, I may do for science an inestimable benefit; for that all the Prince wants is a sensible adviser &amp; suggester, to indicate to him the channels for his exercising a scientific influence.</p>
      <p>He is very clever they say, but in a slow way; not a brilliant man.</p>
      <p>All this is very curious; &amp; it is odd enough that both John Crosse &amp; Wheatstone should have given me the same account within a week, tho' derived from very different sources.</p>
      <p>Oddly enough too, Wheatstone has spoken to me of the great importance of studying the German philosophy &amp; science. Altogether my visit to Broomfield seems to have been very opportune, &amp; to have laid the foundations for much that is wanted for me just at this epoch of my progress.</p>
      <p>I am glad however that I stuck to my original day for leaving it. I should not have derived much more by staying there a few days longer at the present time.</p>
      <p>2. As far as the German studies are concerned, they cannot be carried on while upon a visit; &amp; it is at home only that I should make any real progress in such. If young Crosse stays with us, some hours can be daily given for the time-being, to that purpose; but when one is visiting a family one must be diluted a little amongst all the members of it, of course; besides which the electrical experiments are a main engrosser of one's attention at Bromfield. Add to this that the irregularity of the family habits are a most serious drawback both to my health, &amp; to anything like study there. Wheatstone burst out laughing at the very idea of my having stayed there any time, &amp; yet Wheatstone</p>
      <p>is no man of luxuries certainly. He says it is the strangest &amp; most uncomfortable house he ever stayed in.</p>
      <p>There are certainly inconceivable oddities there. For instance: the Water-closet can only be got at thro' the Drawing Room; &amp; of course it is perfectly evident the errand one is going on, since the exit leads no where else.</p>
      <p>I don't mind that sort of thing the least, when it is inevitable, &amp; I take everything coolly &amp; as a matter of course. That is the only way. Sometimes they lock up the Water Closet, &amp; then one has to make a hue &amp; cry after the key.</p>
      <p>Latterly I got into the way of dictating a little,</p>
      <p>in a good-humoured way. I used to say I really must ask them to do this or the other at this or that time.</p>
      <p>A handsome young lady like me can do these things, but men must take their chance; &amp; I can conceive its being a queer chaos for a many like even Wheatstone.</p>
      <p>Now it was almost impossible to set seriously to anything. Thus, I soom determined that I must try &amp; get what I want with young Crosse, at my home.</p>
      <p>Wheatstone has given me some very striking counsels. I did not think the little man had such depth in him. I can't write it all to you, or even a small part, but I know you</p>
      <p>will agree fully with him, when you do hear it.</p>
      <p>The plan for my writing on Babbage's subject, clearly won't do. Don't be vexed at this; a subject is fixed on instead, so it will make no difference, &amp; I can as easily do the one as the other. I have not yet fixed when to leave Town, excepting that on Sunday I go to Esher for 2 nights. I fear my teeth will oblige me to be in Town for 3 days of next week, otherwise I rather think I should not have to return here again for another week or two at soonest.</p>
      <p>However I can't exactly say about anything yet. I shall see how I get on between this &amp; Sunday. I find</p>
      <p>3. it necessary not to hurry myself, but to take on the contrary plenty of time; or else I am knocked up directly.</p>
      <p>The electrical telegraph is laying down on our Southampton Rail, &amp; by &amp; bye Wheatstone says that we shall be able to send any message to Town for a shilling, &amp; get an answer. There will be a secretary at the terminus to write down &amp; dispatch notes to all parts of Town.</p>
      <p>For instance, I might from Bridgwater the other day (had the telegraph reached to that station) have sent word in two seconds to London:</p>
      <p>"I shall arrive by the two "o'clock Train, instead of the "12 o'clock. Send my carriage for</p>
      <p>"the latter hour. A. A. L." Deliver this at 10. St James' Sqre.--</p>
      <p>Think what a delight. Wheatstone says that sometimes friends hold conversations from one terminus to the other; that one can send for any one to speak to one. For instance, I might desire a tradesman to go directly to the Nine Elm's Station, &amp; might discuss an order with him about goods &amp;c. Wonderful agent and invention!--</p>
      <p>Wheatstone doubts clairvoyance greatly, tho' he believes in all the physical effects of Mesmerism.</p>
      <p>Certainly the wonders require to be sifted very rigidly.</p>
      <p>Babbage roars with laughter about the state of the Church. He says he never could have conceived such a state of mutual tearing into (not 2 or 3) but hundreds of shreds &amp; atoms. He is uneasy about it, fearing it will all go too fast, which he don't wish. He thinks that we must all turn Church people to stop the crash. That is a joke of his, you understand.--</p>
      <p>Today is wretched, everything dreary &amp; bad, a compound of rain, cold &amp;c. This is better however than snow. I never saw London looking more dismal than at present.--</p>
      <p>I have written you indeed a long letter, &amp; yet</p>
      <p>not a quarter of what I might say.</p>
      <p>Wheatstone has fully accounted to me about Herschel &amp; Mrs Woodford. I could not believe that so great a man could seriously admire (I don't mean anything but an intellectual admiration of course) so silly a woman. Wheatstone says that Sir J. H is so affable, so kind, that he never repulses any one; &amp; that he consquently is taken advantage of by silly ladies &amp; silly people of all kinds.</p>
      <p>Besides which he is a man of much chivalrous politeness towards women; a politeness of the best kind, &amp; much to Herschel's credit, Wheatstone says.</p>
      <p>Mrs. Woodford quite</p>
      <p>provoked me by talking so continually of "my poor friend Herschel". I don't like to be too sarcastic, so I forbore; but I was on the point of saying at last, with an apparently naive simplicity,</p>
      <p>"Has Sir John Herschel "met with any misfortune "lately?" And when she had stared &amp; answered No, or something of the sort, I should have of course said something playfully witty about the silly use of the word poor.</p>
      <p>But I prefer usually holding my peace, &amp; keeping out of the way; tho' I must say that pretension greatly excites me to a sarcastic tone.</p>
      <p>I am vexed to find how generally the Queen is disliked for her strange</p>
      <p>taste for seeing animals killed.</p>
      <p>I cannot make it out. She certainly seems a hard person, in some points.</p>
      <p>I don't like some traits I hear, I must say; not from Tories, but from liberal people. I fear she is selfish in certain ways, &amp; about her husband too.</p>
      <p>It is difficult to say however.</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
