<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="2">CHAPTER I.
Prelude to the Greek School Philosophy.
Sect. 1.—First Attempts of the
Speculative Faculty in Physical Inquiries.
AT an early period of history
there appeared in men a propensity to pursue speculative inquiries
concerning the various parts and properties of the material world.
What they saw excited them to meditate, to conjecture, and to reason:
they endeavored to account for natural events, to trace their causes,
to reduce them to their principles. This habit of mind, or, at least
that modification of it which we have here to consider, seems to have
been first unfolded among the Greeks. And during that obscure
introductory interval which elapsed while the speculative tendencies
of men were as yet hardly disentangled from the practical, those who
were most eminent in such inquiries were distinguished by the same
term of praise which is applied to sagacity in matters of action, and
were called wise men—σοφοὶ. But when it came to be
clearly felt by such persons that their endeavors were suggested by
the love of knowledge, a motive different from the motives which lead
to the wisdom of active life, a name was adopted of a more
appropriate, as well as of a more modest signification, and they were
termed philosophers, or lovers of wisdom. This appellation is
said7 to have been first assumed by
Pythagoras. Yet he, in Herodotus, instead of having this title, is
called a powerful sophist—Ἑλλήνων οὐ τῷ ἀσθενεστάτῳ
σοφιστῇ Πυθαγόρῃ;8 the historian using this word, as it
would seem, without intending to imply that misuse of reason which the
term afterwards came to denote. The historians of literature 56 placed Pythagoras at
the origin of the Italic School, one of the two main lines of
succession of the early Greek philosophers: but the other, the Ionic
School, which more peculiarly demands our attention, in consequence of
its character and subsequent progress, is deduced from Thales, who
preceded the age of Philosophy, and was one of the
sophi, or “wise men of Greece.”
7 Cic. Tusc. v. 3.
8 Herod. iv. 95.
The Ionic School was succeeded in Greece by several others; and the
subjects which occupied the attention of these schools became very
extensive. In fact, the first attempts were, to form systems which
should explain the laws and causes of the material universe; and to
these were soon added all the great questions which our moral
condition and faculties suggest. The physical philosophy of these
schools is especially deserving of our study, as exhibiting the
character and fortunes of the most memorable attempt at universal
knowledge which has ever been made. It is highly instructive to trace
the principles of this undertaking; for the course pursued was
certainly one of the most natural and tempting which can be imagined;
the essay was made by a nation unequalled in fine mental endowments,
at the period of its greatest activity and vigor; and yet it must be
allowed (for, at least so far as physical science is concerned, none
will contest this), to have been entirely unsuccessful. We cannot
consider otherwise than as an utter failure, an endeavor to discover
the causes of things, of which the most complete results are the
Aristotelian physical treatises; and which, after reaching the point
which these treatises mark, left the human mind to remain stationary,
at any rate on all such subjects, for nearly two thousand years.
The early philosophers of Greece entered upon the work of physical
speculation in a manner which showed the vigor and confidence of the
questioning spirit, as yet untamed by labors and reverses. It was for
later ages to learn that man must acquire, slowly and patiently,
letter by letter, the alphabet in which nature writes her answers to
such inquiries. The first students wished to divine, at a single
glance, the whole import of her book. They endeavored to discover the
origin and principle of the universe; according to Thales,
water was the origin of all things, according to Anaximenes,
air; and Heraclitus considered fire as the essential
principle of the universe. It has been conjectured, with great
plausibility, that this tendency to give to their Philosophy the form
of a Cosmogony, was owing to the influence of the poetical Cosmogonies
and Theogonies which had been produced and admired at a still earlier
age. Indeed,  such wide and ambitious 57 doctrines as those which have been
mentioned, were better suited to the dim magnificence of poetry, than
to the purpose of a philosophy which was to bear the sharp scrutiny of
reason. When we speak of the principles of things, the term,
even now, is very ambiguous and indefinite in its import, but how much
more was that the case in the first attempts to use such abstractions!
The term which is commonly used in this sense (ἀρχὴ), signified at
first the beginning; and in its early philosophical
applications implied some obscure mixed reference to the mechanical,
chemical, organic, and historical causes of the visible state of
things, besides the theological views which at this period were only
just beginning to be separated from the physical. Hence we are not to
be surprised if the sources from which the opinions of this period
appear to be derived are rather vague suggestions and casual
analogies, than any reasons which will bear examination. Aristotle
conjectures, with considerable probability, that the doctrine of
Thales, according to which water was the universal element, resulted
from the manifest importance of moisture in the support of animal and
vegetable life.9 But such precarious analyses of these
obscure and loose dogmas of early antiquity are of small consequence
to our object.
9 Metaph. i. 3.
In more limited and more definite examples of inquiry concerning
the causes of natural appearances, and in the attempts made to satisfy
men’s curiosity in such cases, we appear to discern a more genuine
prelude to the true spirit of physical inquiry. One of the most
remarkable instances of this kind is to be found in the speculations
which Herodotus records, relative to the cause of the floods of the
Nile. “Concerning the nature of this river,” says the father of
history,10 “I was not able to learn any thing,
either from the priests or from any one besides, though I questioned
them very pressingly. For the Nile is flooded for a hundred days,
beginning with the summer solstice; and after this time it diminishes,
and is, during the whole winter, very small. And on this head I was
not able to obtain any thing satisfactory from any one of the
Egyptians, when I asked what is the power by which the Nile is in its
nature the reverse of other rivers.”
10 Herod. ii. 19.
We may see, I think, in the historian’s account, that the Grecian
mind felt a craving to discover the reasons of things which other
nations did not feel. The Egyptians, it appears, had no theory, and
felt no want of a theory. Not so the Greeks; they had their reasons to
render, though they were not such as satisfied Herodotus. “Some 58 of the Greeks,” he
says, “who wish to be considered great philosophers (Ἑλλήνων τινες
ἐπισήμοι βουλόμενοι γενέσθαι σοφίην), have propounded three ways of
accounting for these floods. Two of them,” he adds, “I do not think
worthy of record, except just so far as to mention them.” But as these
are some of the earliest Greek essays in physical philosophy, it will
be worth while, even at this day, to preserve the brief notice he has
given of them, and his own reasonings upon the same subject.
“One of these opinions holds that the Etesian winds [which blew
from the north] are the cause of these floods, by preventing the Nile
from flowing into the sea.” Against this the historian reasons very
simply and sensibly. “Very often when the Etesian winds do not blow,
the Nile is flooded nevertheless. And moreover, if the Etesian winds
were the cause, all other rivers, which have their course opposite to
these winds, ought to undergo the same changes as the Nile; which the
rivers of Syria and Libya so circumstanced do not.”
“The next opinion is still more unscientific (ἀνεπιστημονεστέρη),
and is, in truth, marvellous for its folly. This holds that the ocean
flows all round the earth, and that the Nile comes out of the ocean,
and by that means produces its effects.” “Now,” says the historian,
“the man who talks about this ocean-river, goes into the region of
fable, where it is not easy to demonstrate that he is wrong. I know of
no such river. But I suppose that Homer and some of the earlier poets
invented this fiction and introduced it into their poetry.”
He then proceeds to a third account, which to a modern reasoner
would appear not at all unphilosophical in itself, but which he,
nevertheless, rejects in a manner no less decided than the others.
“The third opinion, though much the most plausible, is still more
wrong than the others; for it asserts an impossibility, namely, that
the Nile proceeds from the melting of the snow. Now the Nile flows out
of Libya, and through Ethiopia, which are very hot countries, and thus
comes into Egypt, which is a colder region. How then can it proceed
from snow?” He then offers several other reasons “to show,” as he
says, “to any one capable of reasoning on such subjects (ἀνδρί γε
λογίζεσθαι τοιούτων πέρι οἵῳ τε ἔοντι), that the assertion cannot be
true. The winds which blow from the southern regions are hot; the
inhabitants are black; the swallows and kites (ἰκτῖνοι) stay in the
country the whole year; the cranes fly the colds of Scythia, and seek
their warm winter-quarters there; which would not be if it snowed ever
so little.” He adds another reason, founded apparently upon 59 some limited empirical
maxim of weather-wisdom taken from the climate of Greece. “Libya,” he
said, “has neither rain nor ice, and therefore no snow; for, in
five days after a fall of snow there must be a fall of rain; so that
if it snowed in those regions it must rain too.” I need not observe
that Herodotus was not aware of the difference between the climate of
high mountains and plains in a torrid region; but it is impossible not
to be struck both with the activity and the coherency of thought
displayed by the Greek mind in this primitive physical inquiry.
But I must not omit the hypothesis which Herodotus himself
proposes, after rejecting those which have been already given. It does
not appear to me easy to catch his exact meaning, but the statement
will still be curious. “If,” he says, “one who has condemned opinions
previously promulgated may put forward his own opinion concerning so
obscure a matter, I will state why it seems to me that the Nile is
flooded in summer.” This opinion he propounds at first with an
oracular brevity, which it is difficult to suppose that he did not
intend to be impressive. “In winter the sun is carried by the seasons
away from his former course, and goes to the upper parts of Libya. And
there, in short, is the whole account; for that region to
which this divinity (the sun) is nearest, must naturally be most scant
of water, and the river-sources of that country must be dried up.”
But the lively and garrulous Ionian immediately relaxes from this
apparent reserve. “To explain the matter more at length,” he proceeds,
“it is thus. The sun when he traverses the upper parts of Libya, does
what he commonly does in summer;—he draws the water to
him (ἕλκει ἐπ’ ἑωϋτὸν τὸ ὕδωρ), and having thus drawn it, he pushes it
to the upper regions (of the air probably), and then the winds take it
and disperse it till they dissolve in moisture. And thus the winds
which blow from those countries, Libs and Notus, are the most moist of
all winds. Now when the winter relaxes and the sun returns to the
north, he still draws water from all the rivers, but they are
increased by showers and rain torrents so that they are in flood till
the summer comes; and then, the rain falling and the sun still drawing
them, they become small. But the Nile, not being fed by rains, yet
being drawn by the sun, is, alone of all rivers, much more scanty in
the winter than in the summer. For in summer it is drawn like all
other rivers, but in winter it alone has its supplies shut up. And in
this way, I have been led to think the sun is the cause of the
occurrence in question.” We may remark that the historian here appears
to 60 ascribe the
inequality of the Nile at different seasons to the influence of the
sun upon its springs alone, the other cause of change, the rains being
here excluded; and that, on this supposition, the same relative
effects would be produced whether the sun increase the sources in
winter by melting the snows, or diminish them in summer by what he
calls drawing them upwards.
This specimen of the early efforts of the Greeks in physical
speculations, appears to me to speak strongly for the opinion that
their philosophy on such subjects was the native growth of the Greek
mind, and owed nothing to the supposed lore of Egypt and the East; an
opinion which has been adopted with regard to the Greek Philosophy in
general by the most competent judges on a full survey of the
evidence.11 Indeed, we have no evidence whatever
that, at any period, the African or Asiatic nations (with the
exception perhaps of the Indians) ever felt this importunate curiosity
with regard to the definite application of the idea of cause and
effect to visible phenomena; or drew so strong a line between a
fabulous legend and a reason rendered; or attempted to ascend to a
natural cause by classing together phenomena of the same kind. We may
be well excused, therefore, for believing that they could not impart
to the Greeks what they themselves did not possess; and so far as our
survey goes, physical philosophy has its origin, apparently
spontaneous and independent, in the active and acute intellect of
Greece.
11 Thirlwall, Hist. Gr., ii.
130; and, as there quoted, Ritter, Geschichte der Philosophie,
i. 159–173.
Sect. 2.—Primitive Mistake in Greek Physical
Philosophy.
We now proceed to examine with what success
the Greeks followed the track into which they had thus struck. And
here we are obliged to confess that they very soon turned aside from
the right road to truth, and deviated into a vast field of error, in
which they and their successors have wandered almost to the present
time. It is not necessary here to inquire why those faculties which
appear to be bestowed upon us for the discovery of truth, were
permitted by Providence to fail so signally in answering that purpose;
whether, like the powers by which we seek our happiness, they involve
a responsibility on our part, and may be defeated by rejecting the
guidance of a higher faculty; or whether these endowments, though they
did not 61
immediately lead man to profound physical knowledge, answered some
nobler and better purpose in his constitution and government. The fact
undoubtedly was, that the physical philosophy of the Greeks soon
became trifling and worthless; and it is proper to point out, as
precisely as we can, in what the fundamental mistake consisted.
To explain this, we may in the first place return for a moment to
Herodotus’s account of the cause of the floods of the Nile.
The reader will probably have observed a remarkable phrase used by
Herodotus, in his own explanation of these inundations. He says that
the sun draws, or attracts, the water; a metaphorical term,
obviously intended to denote some more general and abstract conception
than that of the visible operation which the word primarily signifies.
This abstract notion of “drawing” is, in the historian, as we see,
very vague and loose; it might, with equal propriety, be explained to
mean what we now understand by mechanical or by chemical attraction,
or pressure, or evaporation. And in like manner, all the first
attempts to comprehend the operations of nature, led to the
introduction of abstract conceptions, often vague, indeed, but not,
therefore, unmeaning; such as motion and velocity,
force and pressure, impetus and momentum
(ῥοπὴ). And the next step in philosophizing, necessarily was to
endeavor to make these vague abstractions more clear and fixed, so
that the logical faculty should be able to employ them securely and
coherently. But there were two ways of making this attempt; the one,
by examining the words only, and the thoughts which they call up; the
other, by attending to the facts and things which bring these abstract
terms into use. The latter, the method of real inquiry, was
the way to success; but the Greeks followed the former, the
verbal or notional course, and failed.
If Herodotus, when the notion of the sun’s attracting the waters of
rivers had entered into his mind, had gone on to instruct himself, by
attention to facts, in what manner this notion could be made more
definite, while it still remained applicable to all the knowledge
which could be obtained, he would have made some progress towards a
true solution of his problem. If, for instance, he had tried to
ascertain whether this Attraction which the sun exerted upon the
waters of rivers, depended on his influence at their fountains only,
or was exerted over their whole course, and over waters which were not
parts of rivers, he would have been led to reject his hypothesis; for
he would have found, by observations sufficiently obvious, that the
sun’s Attraction, as shown in such cases, is a tendency to lessen all
expanded and 62 open
collections of moisture, whether flowing from a spring or not; and it
would then be seen that this influence, operating on the whole surface
of the Nile, must diminish it as well as other rivers, in summer, and
therefore could not be the cause of its overflow. He would thus have
corrected his first loose conjecture by a real study of nature, and
might, in the course of his meditations, have been led to available
notions of Evaporation, or other natural actions. And, in like manner,
in other cases, the rude attempts at explanation, which the first
exercise of the speculative faculty produced, might have been
gradually concentrated and refined, so as to fall in, both with the
requisitions of reason and the testimony of sense.
But this was not the direction which the Greek speculators took. On
the contrary; as soon as they had introduced into their philosophy any
abstract and general conceptions, they proceeded to scrutinize these
by the internal light of the mind alone, without any longer looking
abroad into the world of sense. They took for granted that philosophy
must result from the relations of those notions which are involved in
the common use of language, and they proceeded to seek their
philosophical doctrines by studying such notions. They ought to have
reformed and fixed their usual conceptions by Observation; they only
analyzed and expanded them by Reflection: they ought to have sought by
trial, among the Notions which passed through their minds, some one
which admitted of exact application to Facts; they selected
arbitrarily, and, consequently, erroneously, the Notions according to
which Facts should be assembled and arranged: they ought to have
collected clear Fundamental Ideas from the world of things by
inductive acts of thought; they only derived results by
Deduction from one or other of their familiar Conceptions.12
12 The course by which the Sciences
were formed, and which is here referred to as that which the Greeks
did not follow, is described in detail in the
Philosophy, book xi., Of the Construction of
Science.
When this false direction had been extensively adopted by the Greek
philosophers, we may treat of it as the method of their
Schools. Under that title we must give a further account of it.
63</div></body></text></TEI>