<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="23">CHAPTER III.
Sequel to Copernicus.—The Reception and
Development of the Copernican Theory.

Sect. 1.—First Reception of the
Copernican Theory.
THE theories of Copernicus
made their way among astronomers, in the manner in which true
astronomical theories always obtain the assent of competent judges.
They led to the construction of Tables of the motion of the sun, moon,
and planets, as the theories of Hipparchus and Ptolemy had done; and
the verification of the doctrines was to be looked for, from the
agreement of these Tables with observation, through a sufficient
course of time. The work De Revolutionibus contains such
Tables. In 1551 Reinhold improved and republished Tables founded on
the principles of Copernicus. “We owe,” he says in his preface, “great
obligations to Copernicus, both for his laborious 270 observations, and for
restoring the doctrine of the Motions. But though his geometry is
perfect, the good old man appears to have been, at times, careless in
his numerical calculations. I have, therefore, recalculated the whole,
from a comparison of his observations with those of Ptolemy and
others, following nothing but the general plan of Copernicus’s
demonstrations.” These “Prutenic Tables” were republished in 1571 and
1585, and continued in repute for some time; till superseded by the
Rudolphine Tables of Kepler in 1627. The name Prutenic, or
Prussian, was employed by the author as a mark of gratitude to his
benefactor Albert, Markgrave of Brandenbourg. The discoveries of
Copernicus had inspired neighboring nations with the ambition of
claiming a place in the literary community of Europe. In something of
the same spirit, Rheticus wrote an Encomium Borussiæ, which was
published along with his Narratio.
The Tables founded upon the Copernican system were, at first, much
more generally adopted than the heliocentric doctrine on which they
were founded. Thus Magini published at Venice, in 1587, New
Theories of the Celestial Orbits, agreeing with the Observations of
Nicholas Copernicus. But in the preface, after praising
Copernicus, he says, “Since, however, he, either for the sake of
showing his talents, or induced by his own reasons, has revived the
opinion of Nicetas, Aristarchus, and others, concerning the motion of
the earth, and has disturbed the established constitution of the
world, which was a reason why many rejected, or received with dislike,
his hypothesis, I have thought it worth while, that, rejecting the
suppositions of Copernicus, I should accommodate other causes to his
observations, and to the Prutenic Tables.”
This doctrine, however, was, as we have shown, received with favor
by many persons, even before its general publication. The doctrine of
the motion of the earth was first publicly maintained at Rome by
Widmanstadt,16 who professed to have received it from
Copernicus, and explained the System before the Pope and the
Cardinals, but did not teach it to the public.
16  See Venturi, Essai sur les
Ouvrages Physico-Mathématiques de Leonard da Vinci, avec des Fragmens
tirés de ses Manuscrits apportés d’Italie. Paris, 1797; and, as
there quoted, Marini Archiatri Pontificii, tom. ii. p.
251.
Leonardo da Vinci, who was an eminent mathematician, as well as
painter, about 1510, explained how a body, by describing a kind of
spiral, might descend towards a revolving globe, so that its apparent
motion relative to a point in the surface of the globe, might be in a
271 straight line
leading to the centre. He thus showed that he had entertained in his
thoughts the hypothesis of the earth’s rotation, and was employed in
removing the difficulties which accompanied this supposition, by means
of the consideration of the composition of motions.
In like manner we find the question stirred by other eminent men.
Thus John Muller of Konigsberg, a celebrated astronomer who died in
1476, better known by the name of Regiomontanus, wrote a dissertation
on the subject “Whether the earth be in motion or at rest,” in which
he decides ex professo17 against the
motion. Yet such discussions must have made generally known the
arguments for the heliocentric theory.
17 Schoneri Opera, part ii. p.
129.
We have already seen the enthusiasm with which Rheticus, who was
Copernicus’s pupil in the latter years of his life, speaks of him.
“Thus,” says he, “God has given to my excellent preceptor a reign
without end; which may He vouchsafe to guide, govern, and increase, to
the restoration of astronomical truth. Amen.”
Of the immediate converts of the Copernican system, who adopted it
before the controversy on the subject had attracted attention, I shall
only add Mæstlin, and his pupil, Kepler. Mæstlin
published in 1588 an Epitome Astronomiæ, in which the
immobility of the earth is asserted; but in 1596 he edited Kepler’s
Mysterium Cosmographicum, and the Narratio of Rheticus:
and in an epistle of his own, which he inserts, he defends the
Copernican system by those physical reasonings which we shall shortly
have to mention, as the usual arguments in this dispute. Kepler
himself, in the outset of the work just named, says, “When I was at
Tübingen, attending to Michael Mæstlin, being disturbed by the
manifold inconveniences of the usual opinion concerning the world, I
was so delighted with Copernicus, of whom he made great mention in his
lectures, that I not only defended his opinions in our disputations of
the candidates, but wrote a thesis concerning the First Motion which
is produced by the revolution of the earth.” This must have been in
1590.
The differences of opinion respecting the Copernican system, of
which we thus see traces, led to a controversy of some length and
extent. This controversy turned principally upon physical
considerations, which were much more distinctly dealt with by Kepler,
and others of the followers of Copernicus, than they had been by the
272 discoverer
himself. I shall, therefore, give a separate consideration to this
part of the subject. It may be proper, however, in the first place, to
make a few observations on the progress of the doctrine, independently
of these physical speculations.
Sect. 2.—Diffusion of the Copernican
Theory.
The diffusion of the Copernican opinions in
the world did not take place rapidly at first. Indeed, it was
necessarily some time before the progress of observation and of
theoretical mechanics gave the heliocentric doctrine that superiority
in argument, which now makes us wonder that men should have hesitated
when it was presented to them. Yet there were some speculators of this
kind, who were attracted at once by the enlarged views of the universe
which it opened to them. Among these was the unfortunate Giordano
Bruno of Nola, who was burnt as a heretic at Rome in 1600. The
heresies which led to his unhappy fate were, however, not his
astronomical opinions, but a work which he published in England, and
dedicated to Sir Philip Sydney, under the title of Spaccio della
Bestia Trionfante, and which is understood to contain a bitter
satire of religion and the papal government. Montucla conceives that,
by his rashness in visiting Italy after putting forth such a work, he
compelled the government to act against him. Bruno embraced the
Copernican opinions at an early period, and connected with them the
belief in innumerable worlds besides that which we inhabit; as also
certain metaphysical or theological doctrines which he called the
Nolan philosophy. In 1591 he published De innumerabilibus, immenso,
et infigurabili, seu de Universo et Mundis, in which he maintains
that each star is a sun, about which revolve planets like our earth;
but this opinion is mixed up with a large mass of baseless verbal
speculations.
Giordano Bruno is a disciple of Copernicus on whom we may look with
peculiar interest, since he probably had a considerable share in
introducing the new opinions into England;18 although other
persons, as Recorde, Field, Dee, had adopted it nearly thirty years
earlier; and Thomas Digges ten years before, much more expressly.
Bruno visited this country in the reign of Queen Elizabeth, and speaks
of her and of her councillors in terms of praise, which appear to show
that 273 his book
was intended for English readers; though he describes the mob which
was usually to be met with in the streets of London with expressions
of great disgust: “Una plebe la quale in essere irrespettevole,
incivile, rozza, rustica, selvatica, et male allevata, non cede ad
altra che pascer possa la terra nel suo seno.”19 The work to
which I refer is La Cena de le Cenere, and narrates what took
place at a supper held on the evening of Ash Wednesday (about 1583,
see p. 145 of the book), at the house of Sir Fulk Greville, in order
to give “Il Nolano” an opportunity of defending his peculiar opinions.
His principal antagonists are two “Dottori d’ Oxonia,” whom Bruno
calls Nundinio and Torquato. The subject is not treated in any very
masterly manner on either side; but the author makes himself have
greatly the advantage not only in argument, but in temper and
courtesy: and in support of his representations of “pedantesca,
ostinatissima ignoranza et presunzione, mista con una rustica
incivilità, che farebbe prevaricar la pazienza di Giobbe,” in his
opponents, he refers to a public disputation which he had held at
Oxford with these doctors of theology, in presence of Prince Alasco,
and many of the English nobility.20  ~Additional
material in the 3rd edition.~
18 See Burton’s Anat. Mel.
Pref. “Some prodigious tenet or paradox of the earth’s motion,”
&c. “Bruno,” &c.
19 Opere di Giordano Bruno,
vol. i. p. 146.
20 Ib. vol. i. p. 179.
Among the evidences of the difficulties which still lay in the way
of the reception of the Copernican system, we may notice Bacon, who,
as is well known, never gave a full assent to it. It is to be
observed, however, that he does not reject the opinion of the earth’s
motion in so peremptory and dogmatical a manner as he is sometimes
accused of doing: thus in the Thema Cœli he says, “The earth,
then, being supposed to be at rest (for that now appears to us the
more true opinion).” And in his tract On the Cause of the
Tides, he says, “If the tide of the sea be the extreme and
diminished limit of the diurnal motion of the heavens, it will follow
that the earth is immovable; or at least that it moves with a much
slower motion than the water.” In the Descriptio Globi
Intellectualis he gives his reasons for not accepting the
heliocentric theory. “In the system of Copernicus there are many and
grave difficulties: for the threefold motion with which he encumbers
the earth is a serious inconvenience; and the separation of the sun
from the planets, with which he has so many affections in common, is
likewise a harsh step; and the introduction of so many immovable
bodies into nature, as when he makes the sun and the stars immovable,
the bodies which are peculiarly lucid and radiant; and his making the
moon adhere to the earth in a sort of epicycle; and some 274 other things which he
assumes, are proceedings which mark a man who thinks nothing of
introducing fictions of any kind into nature, provided his
calculations turn out well.” We have already explained that, in
attributing three motions to the earth, Copernicus had
presented his system encumbered with a complexity not really belonging
to it. But it will be seen shortly, that Bacon’s fundamental objection
to this system was his wish for a system which could be supported by
sound physical considerations; and it must be allowed, that at the
period of which we are speaking, this had not yet been done in favor
of the Copernican hypothesis. We may add, however, that it is not
quite clear that Bacon was in full possession of the details of the
astronomical systems which that of Copernicus was intended to
supersede; and that thus he, perhaps, did not see how much less harsh
were these fictions, as he called them, than those which were the
inevitable alternatives. Perhaps he might even be liable to a little
of that indistinctness, with respect to strictly geometrical
conceptions, which we have remarked in Aristotle. We can hardly
otherwise account for his not seeing any use in resolving the
apparently irregular motion of a planet into separate regular motions.
Yet he speaks slightingly of this important step.21 “The motion of
planets, which is constantly talked of as the motion of regression, or
renitency, from west to east, and which is ascribed to the planets as
a proper motion, is not true; but only arises from appearance, from
the greater advance of the starry heavens towards the west, by which
the planets are left behind to the east.” Undoubtedly those who spoke
of such a motion of regression were aware of this; but they saw
how the motion was simplified by this way of conceiving it, which
Bacon seems not to have seen. Though, therefore, we may admire Bacon
for the steadfastness with which he looked forward to physical
astronomy as the great and proper object of philosophical interest, we
cannot give him credit for seeing the full value and meaning of what
had been done, up to his time, in Formal Astronomy.
21 Thema Cœli, p. 246.
Bacon’s contemporary, Gilbert, whom he frequently praises as a
philosopher, was much more disposed to adopt the Copernican opinions,
though even he does not appear to have made up his mind to assent to
the whole of the system. In his work. De Magnete (printed
1600), he gives the principal arguments in favor of the Copernican
system, and decides that the earth revolves on its axis.22 He connects 275 this opinion with his magnetic
doctrines; and especially endeavors by that means to account for the
precession of the equinoxes. But he does not seem to have been equally
confident of its annual motion. In a posthumous work, published in
1661 (De Mundo Nostra Sublunari Philosophia Nova) he appears to
hesitate between the systems of Tycho and Copernicus.23 Indeed, it is probable that at this
period many persons were in a state of doubt on such subjects. Milton,
at a period somewhat later, appears to have been still undecided. In
the opening of the eighth book of the Paradise Lost, he makes
Adam state the difficulties of the Ptolemaic hypothesis, to which the
archangel Raphael opposes the usual answers; but afterwards suggests
to his pupil the newer system:


.  .  . .  What if seventh to
these
The planet earth, so steadfast though she
seem,
Insensibly three different motions move?
Par. Lost, b.
viii.   
22 Lib. vi. cap. 3, 4.
23 Lib. ii. cap. 20.
Milton’s leaning, however, seems to have been for the new system;
we can hardly believe that he would otherwise have conceived so
distinctly, and described with such obvious pleasure, the motion of
the earth:


Or she from west her silent course advance
With inoffensive pace, that spinning
sleeps
On her soft axle, while she paces even,
And bears thee soft with the smooth air
along.
Par. Lost, b.
viii.   
Perhaps the works of the celebrated Bishop Wilkins tended more than
any others to the diffusion of the Copernican system in England, since
even their extravagances drew a stronger attention to them. In 1638,
when he was only twenty-four years old, he published a book entitled
The Discovery of a New World; or a Discourse tending to prove that
it is probable there may be another habitable World in the Moon; with
a Discourse concerning the possibility of a passage thither. The
latter part of his subject was, of course, an obvious mark for the
sneers and witticisms of critics. Two years afterwards, in 1640,
appeared his Discourse concerning a new Planet; tending to prove
that it is probable our Earth is one of the Planets: in which he
urged the reasons in favor of the heliocentric system; and explained
away the opposite arguments, especially those drawn from the 276 supposed declarations
of Scripture. Probably a good deal was done for the establishment of
those opinions by Thomas Salusbury, who was a warm admirer of Galileo,
and published, in 1661, a translation of several of his works bearing
upon this subject. The mathematicians of this country, in the
seventeenth century, as Napier and Briggs, Horrox and Crabtree,
Oughtred and Seth Ward, Wallis and Wren, were probably all decided
Copernicans. Kepler dedicates one of his works to Napier, and Ward
invented an approximate method of solving Kepler’s problem, still
known as “the simple elliptical hypothesis.” Horrox wrote, and wrote
well, in defence of the Copernican opinion, in his Keplerian
Astronomy defended and promoted, composed (in Latin) probably
about 1635, but not published till 1673, the author having died at the
age of twenty-two, and his papers having been lost. But Salusbury’s
work was calculated for another circle of readers. “The book,” he says
in the introductory address, “being, for subject and design, intended
chiefly for gentlemen, I have been as careless of using a studied
pedantry in my style, as careful in contriving a pleasant and
beautiful impression.” In order, however, to judge of the advantage
under which the Copernican system now came forward, we must consider
the additional evidence for it which was brought to light by Galileo’s
astronomical discoveries.
Sect. 3.—The Heliocentric Theory confirmed by
Facts.—Galileo’s Astronomical Discoveries.
The long interval which elapsed between the
last great discoveries made by the ancients and the first made by the
moderns, had afforded ample time for the development of all the
important consequences of the ancient doctrines. But when the human
mind had been thoroughly roused again into activity, this was no
longer the course of events. Discoveries crowded on each other; one
wide field of speculation was only just opened, when a richer promise
tempted the laborers away into another quarter. Hence the history of
this period contains the beginnings of many sciences, but exhibits
none fully worked out into a complete or final form. Thus the science
of Statics, soon after its revival, was eclipsed and overlaid by that
of Dynamics; and the Copernican system, considered merely with
reference to the views of its author, was absorbed in the commanding
interest of Physical Astronomy.
Still, advances were made which had an important bearing on the
277 heliocentric
theory, in other ways than by throwing light upon its physical
principles. I speak of the new views of the heavens which the
Telescope gave; the visible inequalities of the moon’s surface; the
moon-like phases of the planet Venus; the discovery of the Satellites
of Jupiter, and of the Ring of Saturn. These discoveries excited at
the time the strongest interest; both from the novelty and beauty of
the objects they presented to the sense; from the way in which they
seemed to gratify man’s curiosity with regard to the remote parts of
the universe; and also from that of which we have here to speak, their
bearing upon the conflict of the old and the new philosophy, the
heliocentric and geocentric theories. It may be true, as Lagrange and
Montucla say, that the laws which Galileo discovered in Mechanics
implied a profounder genius than the novelties he detected in the sky:
but the latter naturally attracted the greater share of the attention
of the world, and were matter of keener discussion.
It is not to our purpose to speak here of the details and of the
occasion of the invention of the Telescope; it is well known that
Galileo constructed his about 1609, and proceeded immediately to apply
it to the heavens. The discovery of the Satellites of Jupiter was
almost immediately the reward of his activity; and these were
announced in his Nuncius Sidereus, published at Venice in 1610.
The title of this work will best convey an idea of the claim it made
to public notice: “The Sidereal Messenger, announcing great and
very wonderful spectacles, and offering them to the consideration of
every one, but especially of philosophers and astronomers; which have
been observed by Galileo Galilei, &c. &c., by the
assistance of a perspective glass lately invented by him; namely, in
the face of the moon, in innumerable fixed stars in the milky-way, in
nebulous stars, but especially in four planets which revolve round
Jupiter at different intervals and periods with a wonderful celerity;
which, hitherto not known to any one, the author has recently been the
first to detect, and has decreed to call the Medicean
stars.”
The interest this discovery excited was intense: and men were at
this period so little habituated to accommodate their convictions on
matters of science to newly observed facts, that several of the
“paper-philosophers,” as Galileo termed them, appear to have thought
they could get rid of these new objects by writing books against them.
The effect which the discovery had upon the reception of the
Copernican system was immediately very considerable. It showed that
the real universe was very different from that which ancient
philosophers had imagined, 278 and suggested at once the thought that
it contained mechanism more various and more vast than had yet been
conjectured. And when the system of the planet Jupiter thus offered to
the bodily eye a model or image of the solar system according to the
views of Copernicus, it supported the belief of such an arrangement of
the planets, by an analogy all but irresistible. It thus, as a
writer24 of our own times has said, “gave the
holding turn to the opinions of mankind respecting the
Copernican system.” We may trace this effect in Bacon, even though he
does not assent to the motion of the earth. “We affirm,” he says,25 “the sun-following arrangement
(solisequium) of Venus and Mercury; since it has been found by Galileo
that Jupiter also has attendants.”
24 Sir J. Herschel.
25 Thema Cœli, ix. p.
253.
The Nuncius Sidereus contained other discoveries which had
the same tendency in other ways. The examination of the moon showed,
or at least seemed to show, that she was a solid body, with a surface
extremely rugged and irregular. This, though perhaps not bearing
directly upon the question of the heliocentric theory, was yet a blow
to the Aristotelians, who had, in their philosophy, made the moon a
body of a kind altogether different from this, and had given an
abundant quantity of reasons for the visible marks on her surface, all
proceeding on these preconceived views. Others of his discoveries
produced the same effect; for instance, the new stars invisible to the
naked eye, and those extraordinary appearances called Nebulæ.
But before the end of the year, Galileo had new information to
communicate, bearing more decidedly on the Copernican controversy.
This intelligence was indeed decisive with regard to the motion of
Venus about the sun; for he found that that planet, in the course of
her revolution, assumes the same succession of phases which the moon
exhibits in the course of a month. This he expressed by a Latin
verse:


Cynthiæ figuras æmulatur mater amorum:
The Queen of Love like Cynthia shapes her
forms:

transposing the letters of this line in the published
account, according to the practice of the age; which thus showed the
ancient love for combining verbal puzzles with scientific discoveries,
while it betrayed the newer feeling, of jealousy respecting the
priority of discovery of physical facts.
It had always been a formidable objection to the Copernican theory
that this appearance of the planets had not been observed. The author
279 of that theory
had endeavored to account for this, by supposing that the rays of the
sun passed freely through the body of the planet; and Galileo takes
occasion to praise him for not being deterred from adopting the system
which, on the whole, appeared to agree best with the phenomena, by
meeting with some appearances which it did not enable him to
explain.26 Yet while the fate of the theory was
yet undecided, this could not but be looked upon as a weak point in
its defences.
26 Drinkwater-Bethune, Life of
Galileo, p. 35.
The objection, in another form also, was embarrassing alike to the
Ptolemaic and Copernican systems. Why, it was asked, did not Venus
appear four times as large when nearest to the earth, as when furthest
from it? The author of the Epistle prefixed to Copernicus’s work had
taken refuge in this argument from the danger of being supposed to
believe in the reality of the system; and Bruno had attempted to
answer it by saying, that luminous bodies were not governed by the
same laws of perspective as opake ones. But a more satisfactory answer
now readily offered itself. Venus does not appear four times as large
when she is four times as near, because her bright part is
not four times as large, though her visible diameter is; and
as she is too small for us to see her shape with the naked eye, we
judge of her size only by the quantity of light.
The other great discoveries made in the heavens by means of
telescopes, as that of Saturn’s ring and his satellites, the spots in
the sun, and others, belong to the further progress of astronomy. But
we may here observe, that this doctrine of the motion of Mercury and
Venus about the sun was further confirmed by Kepler’s observation of
the transit of the former planet over the sun in 1631. Our countryman
Horrox was the first person who, in 1639, had the satisfaction of
seeing a transit of Venus.
These events are a remarkable instance of the way in which a
discovery in art (for at this period, the making of telescopes must be
mainly so considered) may influence the progress of science. We shall
soon have to notice a still more remarkable example of the way in
which two sciences (Astronomy and Mechanics) may influence and promote
the progress of each other. 280
Sect. 4.—The Copernican System opposed on
Theological Grounds.
The doctrine of the Earth’s motion round
the Sun, when it was asserted and promulgated by Copernicus, soon
after 1500, excited no visible alarm among the theologians of his own
time. Indeed, it was received with favor by the most intelligent
ecclesiastics; and lectures in support of the heliocentric doctrine
were delivered in the ecclesiastical colleges. But the assertion and
confirmation of this doctrine by Galileo, about a century later,
excited a storm of controversy, and was visited with severe
condemnation. Galileo’s own behavior appears to have provoked the
interference of the ecclesiastical authorities; but there must have
been a great change in the temper of the times to make it possible for
his adversaries to bring down the sentence of the Inquisition upon
opinions which had been so long current without giving any serious
offence.
[2d Ed.] [It appears to me that the different degree of toleration
accorded to the heliocentric theory in the time of Copernicus and of
Galileo, must be ascribed in a great measure to the controversies and
alarms which had in the mean time arisen out of the Reformation in
religion, and which had rendered the Romish Church more jealous of
innovations in received opinions than it had previously been. It
appears too that the discussion of such novel doctrines was, at that
time at least, less freely tolerated in Italy than in other countries.
In 1597, Kepler writes to Galileo thus: “Confide Galilæe et
progredere. Si bene conjecto, pauci de præcipuis Europæ Mathematicis a
nobis secedere volent; tanta vis est veritatis. Si tibi Italia minus
est idonea ad publicationem et si aliqua habitures es impedimenta,
forsan Germania nobis hanc libertatem concedet.”—Venturi,
Mem. di Galileo, vol. i. p. 19.
I would not however be understood to assert the condemnation of new
doctrines in science to be either a general or a characteristic
practice of the Romish Church. Certainly the intelligent and
cultivated minds of Italy, and many of the most eminent of her
ecclesiastics among them, have always been the foremost in promoting
and welcoming the progress of science: and, as I have stated, there
were found among the Italian ecclesiastics of Galileo’s time many of
the earliest and most enlightened adherents of the Copernican system.
The condemnation of the doctrine of the earth’s motion, is, so far as
I am aware, the only instance in which the Papal authority has
pronounced a decree upon a point of science. And the most candid of
the 281 adherents
of the Romish Church condemn the assumption of authority in such
matters, which in this one instance, at least, was made by the
ecclesiastical tribunals. The author of the Ages of Faith (book
viii. p. 248) says, “A congregation, it is to be lamented, declared
the new system to be opposed to Scripture, and therefore heretical.”
In more recent times, as I have elsewhere remarked,27 the Church of Authority and the Church
of Private Judgment have each its peculiar temptations and dangers,
when there appears to be a discrepance between Scripture and
Philosophy.
27 Phil. Ind. Sci. book x.
chap. 4.
But though we may acquit the popes and cardinals in Galileo’s time
of stupidity and perverseness in rejecting manifest scientific truths,
I do not see how we can acquit them of dissimulation and duplicity.
Those persons appear to me to defend in a very strange manner the
conduct of the ecclesiastical authorities of that period, who boast of
the liberality with which Copernican professors were placed by them in
important offices, at the very time when the motion of the earth had
been declared by the same authorities contrary to Scripture. Such
merits cannot make us approve of their conduct in demanding from
Galileo a public recantation of the system which they thus favored in
other ways, and which they had repeatedly told Galileo he might hold
as much as he pleased. Nor can any one, reading the plain language of
the Sentence passed upon Galileo, and of the Abjuration forced from
him, find any value in the plea which has been urged, that the opinion
was denominated a heresy only in a wide, improper, and
technical sense.
But if we are thus unable to excuse the conduct of Galileo’s
judges, I do not see how we can give our unconditional admiration to
the philosopher himself. Perhaps the conventional decorum which, as we
have seen, was required in treating of the Copernican system, may
excuse or explain the furtive mode of insinuating his doctrines which
he often employs, and which some of his historians admire as subtle
irony, while others blame it as insincerity. But I do not see with
what propriety Galileo can be looked upon as a “Martyr of Science.”
Undoubtedly he was very desirous of promoting what he conceived to be
the cause of philosophical truth; but it would seem that, while he was
restless and eager in urging his opinions, he was always ready to make
such submissions as the spiritual tribunals required. He would really
have acted as a martyr, if he had uttered 282 his “E pur si muove,” in the place of
his abjuration, not after it. But even in this case he would have been
a martyr to a cause of which the merit was of a mingled scientific
character; for his own special and favorite share in the reasonings by
which the Copernican system was supported, was the argument drawn from
the flux and reflux of the sea, which argument is altogether false. He
considered this as supplying a mechanical ground of belief, without
which the mere astronomical reasons were quite insufficient; but in
this case he was deserted by the mechanical sagacity which appeared in
his other speculations.]
The heliocentric doctrine had for a century been making its way
into the minds of thoughtful men, on the general ground of its
simplicity and symmetry. Galileo appears to have thought that now,
when these original recommendations of the system had been reinforced
by his own discoveries and reasonings, it ought to be universally
acknowledged as a truth and a reality. And when arguments against the
fixity of the sun and the motion of the earth were adduced from the
expressions of Scripture, he could not be satisfied without
maintaining his favorite opinion to be conformable to Scripture as
well as to Philosophy; and he was very eager in his attempts to obtain
from authority a declaration to this effect. The ecclesiastical
authorities were naturally averse to express themselves in favor of a
novel opinion, startling to the common mind, and contrary to the most
obvious meaning of the words of the Bible; and when they were
compelled to pronounce, they decided against Galileo and his
doctrines. He was accused before the Inquisition in 1615; but at that
period the result was that he was merely recommended to confine
himself to the mathematical reasonings upon the system, and to abstain
from meddling with the Scripture. Galileo’s zeal for his opinions soon
led him again to bring the question under the notice of the Pope, and
the result was a declaration of the Inquisition that the doctrine of
the earth’s motion appeared to be contrary to the Sacred Scripture.
Galileo was prohibited from defending and teaching this doctrine in
any manner, and promised obedience to this injunction. But in 1632 he
published his “Dialogo delli due Massimi Sistemi del Mondo,
Tolemaico e Copernicano:” and in this he defended the heliocentric
system by all the strongest arguments which its admirers used. Not
only so, but he introduced into this Dialogue a character under
the name of Simplicius, in whose mouth was put the defence of all the
ancient dogmas, and who was represented as defeated at all points in
the discussion; 283
and he prefixed to the Dialogue a Notice, To the Discreet
Reader, in which, in a vein of transparent irony, he assigned his
reasons for the publication. “Some years ago,” he says, “a wholesome
edict was promulgated at Rome, which, in order to check the perilous
scandals of the present age, imposed silence upon the Pythagorean
opinion of the motion of the earth. There were not wanting,” he adds,
“persons who rashly asserted that this decree was the result, not of a
judicious inquiry, but of a passion ill-informed; and complaints were
heard that counsellors, utterly unacquainted with astronomical
observations, ought not to be allowed, with their undue prohibitions,
to clip the wings of speculative intellects. At the hearing of rash
lamentations like these, my zeal could not keep silence.” And he then
goes on to say that he wishes, by the publication of his
Dialogue to show that the subject had been fully examined at
Rome. The result of this was that Galileo was condemned for his
infraction of the injunction laid upon him in 1616; his
Dialogue was prohibited; he himself was commanded to abjure on
his knees the doctrine which he had taught; and this abjuration he
performed.
This celebrated event must be looked upon rather as a question of
decorum than a struggle in which the interests of truth and free
inquiry were deeply concerned. The general acceptance of the
Copernican System was no longer a matter of doubt. Several persons in
the highest positions, including the Pope himself, looked upon the
doctrine with favorable eyes; and had shown their interest in Galileo
and his discoveries. They had tried to prevent his involving himself
in trouble by discussing the question on scriptural grounds. It is
probable that his knowledge of those favorable dispositions towards
himself and his opinions led him to suppose that the slightest color
of professed submission to the Church in his belief, would enable his
arguments in favor of the system to pass unvisited: the notice which I
have quoted, in which the irony is quite transparent and the sarcasm
glaringly obvious, was deemed too flimsy a veil for the purpose of
decency, and indeed must have aggravated the offence. But it is not to
be supposed that the inquisitors believed Galileo’s abjuration to be
sincere, or even that they wished it to be so. It is stated that when
Galileo had made his renunciation of the earth’s motion, he rose from
his knees, and stamping on the earth with his foot, said, E pur si
muove—“And yet it does move.” This is sometimes
represented as the heroic soliloquy of a mind cherishing its
conviction of the truth in spite of persecution; I think we may more
naturally conceive it uttered as a playful 284 epigram in the ear of a cardinal’s
secretary, with a full knowledge that it would be immediately repeated
to his master.
[2d Ed.] [Throughout the course of the proceedings against him,
Galileo was treated with great courtesy and indulgence. He was
condemned to a formal imprisonment and a very light discipline. “Te
damnamus ad formalem carcerem hujus S. Officii ad tempus arbitrio
nostro limitandum; et titulo pœnitentiæ salutaris præcipimus ut tribus
annis futuris recites semel in hebdomadâ septem psalmos
penitentiales.” But this confinement was reduced to his being placed
under some slight restrictions, first at the house of Nicolini, the
ambassador of his own sovereign, and afterwards at the country seat of
Archbishop Piccolomini, one of his own warmest friends.
It has sometimes been asserted or insinuated that Galileo was
subjected to bodily torture. An argument has been drawn from the
expressions used in his sentence: “Cum vero nobis videretur non esse a
te integram veritatem pronunciatam circa tuam intentionem; judicavimus
necesse esse venire ad rigorosum examen tui, in quo respondisti
catholicè.” It has been argued by M. Libri (Hist. des Sciences
Mathématiques en Italie, vol. iv. p. 259),
and M. Quinet (L’Ultramontanisme, iv.
Leçon, p. 104), that the rigorosum examen necessarily implies
bodily torture, notwithstanding that no such thing is mentioned by
Galileo and his contemporaries, and notwithstanding the consideration
with which he was treated in all other respects: but M. Biot more
justly remarks (Biogr. Univ. Art. Galileo), that such a
procedure is incredible.
To the opinion of M. Biot, we may add that of Delambre, who rejects
the notion of Galileo’s having been put to the torture, as
inconsistent with the general conduct of the authorities towards him,
and as irreconcilable with the accounts of the trial given by Galileo
himself, and by a servant of his, who never quitted him for an
instant. He adds also, that it is inconsistent with the words of his
sentence, “ne tuus iste gravis et perniciosus error ac transgressio
remaneat omnino impunitus;” for the error would have been
already very far from impunity, if Galileo had been previously
subjected to the rack. He adds, very reasonably, “il ne faut noircir
personne sans preuve, pas même l’Inquisition;”—we must not
calumniate even the Inquisition.]
The ecclesiastical authorities having once declared the doctrine of
the earth’s motion to be contrary to Scripture and heretical, long
adhered in form to this declaration, and did not allow the Copernican
system to be taught in any other way than as an “hypothesis.” The
285 Padua edition
of Galileo’s works, published in 1744, contains the Dialogue
which now, the editors say, “Esce finalmente a pubblico libero uso
colle debite licenze,” is now at last freely published with the
requisite license; but they add, “quanto alla Quistione principale del
moto della terra, anche noi ci conformiamo alla ritrazione et protesta
dell’ Autore, dichiarando nella piu solenne forma, che non può, nè dee
ammetersi se non come pura Ipotesi Mathematice, che serve a spiegare
piu agevolamento certi fenomeni;” “neither can nor ought to be
admitted except as a convenient hypothesis.” And in the edition of
Newton’s Principia, published in 1760, by Le Sueur and
Jacquier, of the Order of Minims, the editors prefix to the Third Book
their Declaratio, that though Newton assumes the hypothesis of
the motion of the earth, and therefore they had used similar language,
they were, in doing this, assuming a character which did not belong to
them. “Hinc alienam coacti sumus gerere personam.” They add, “Cæterum
latis a summis Pontificibus contra telluris motum Decretis, nos
obsequi profitemur.”
By thus making decrees against a doctrine which in the course of
time was established as an indisputable scientific truth, the See of
Rome was guilty of an unwise and unfortunate stretch of ecclesiastical
authority. But though we do not hesitate to pronounce such a judgment
on this case, we may add that there is a question of no small real
difficulty, which the progress of science often brings into notice, as
it did then. The Revelation on which our religion is founded, seems to
declare, or to take for granted, opinions on points on which Science
also gives her decision; and we then come to this dilemma,—that
doctrines, established by a scientific use of reason, may seem to
contradict the declarations of Revelation, according to our view of
its meaning;—and yet, that we cannot, in consistency with our
religious views, make reason a judge of the truth of revealed
doctrines. In the case of Astronomy, on which Galileo was called in
question, the general sense of cultivated and sober-minded men has
long ago drawn that distinction between religious and physical tenets,
which is necessary to resolve this dilemma. On this point, it is
reasonably held, that the phrases which are employed in Scripture
respecting astronomical facts, are not to be made use of to guide our
scientific opinions; they may be supposed to answer their end if they
fall in with common notions, and are thus effectually subservient to
the moral and religions import of Revelation. But the establishment of
this distinction was not accomplished without long and distressing
controversies. Nor, if we wish to 286 include all cases in which the same
dilemma may again come into play is it easy to lay down an adequate
canon for the purpose. For we can hardly foresee, beforehand, what
part of the past history of the universe may eventually be found to
come within the domain of science; or what bearing the tenets, which
science establishes, may have upon our view of the providential and
revealed government of the world. But without attempting here to
generalize on this subject, there are two reflections which may be
worth our notice: they are supported by what took place in reference
to Astronomy on the occasion of which we are speaking; and may, at
other periods, be applicable to other sciences.
In the first place, the meaning which any generation puts upon the
phrases of Scripture, depends, more than is at first sight supposed
upon the received philosophy of the time. Hence, while men imagine
that they are contending for Revelation, they are, in fact, contending
for their own interpretation of Revelation, unconsciously adapted to
what they believe to be rationally probable. And the new
interpretation, which the new philosophy requires, and which appears
to the older school to be a fatal violence done to the authority of
religion, is accepted by their successors without the dangerous
results which were apprehended. When the language of Scripture,
invested with its new meaning, has become familiar to men, it is found
that the ideas which it calls up, are quite as reconcilable as the
former ones were with the soundest religious views. And the world then
looks back with surprise at the error of those who thought that the
essence of Revelation was involved in their own arbitrary version of
some collateral circumstance. At the present day we can hardly
conceive how reasonable men should have imagined that religious
reflections on the stability of the earth, and the beauty and use of
the luminaries which revolve round it, would be interfered with by its
being acknowledged that this rest and motion are apparent only.
In the next place, we may observe that those who thus adhere
tenaciously to the traditionary or arbitrary mode of understanding
Scriptural expressions of physical events, are always strongly
condemned by succeeding generations. They are looked upon with
contempt by the world at large, who cannot enter into the obsolete
difficulties with which they encumbered themselves; and with pity by
the more considerate and serious, who know how much sagacity and
rightmindedness are requisite for the conduct of philosophers and
religious men on such occasions; but who know also how weak and vain
is the attempt 287
to get rid of the difficulty by merely denouncing the new tenets as
inconsistent with religious belief, and by visiting the promulgators
of them with severity such as the state of opinions and institutions
may allow. The prosecutors of Galileo are still up to the scorn and
aversion of mankind: although, as we have seen, they did not act till
it seemed that their position compelled them to do so, and then
proceeded with all the gentleness and moderation which were compatible
with judicial forms.
Sect. 5.—The Heliocentric Theory confirmed on
Physical considerations.—(Prelude to Kepler’s
Astronomical Discoveries.)
By physical views, I mean, as I have
already said, those which depend on the causes of the motions of
matter, as, for instance, the consideration of the nature and laws of
the force by which bodies fall downwards. Such considerations were
necessarily and immediately brought under notice by the examination of
the Copernican theory; but the loose and inaccurate notions which
prevailed respecting the nature and laws of force, prevented, for some
time, all distinct reasoning on this subject, and gave truth little
advantage over error. The formation of a new Science, the Science of
Motion and its Causes, was requisite, before the heliocentric system
could have justice done it with regard to this part of the
subject.
This discussion was at first carried on, as was to be expected, in
terms of the received, that is, the Aristotelian doctrines. Thus,
Copernicus says that terrestrial things appear to be at rest when they
have a motion according to nature, that is, a circular motion; and
ascend or descend when they have, in addition to this, a rectilinear
motion by which they endeavor to get into their own place. But his
disciples soon began to question the Aristotelian dogmas, and to seek
for sounder views by the use of their own reason. “The great argument
against this system,” says Mæstlin, “is that heavy bodies are said to
move to the centre of the universe, and light bodies from the centre.
But I would ask, where do we get this experience of heavy and light
bodies? and how is our knowledge on these subjects extended so far
that we can reason with certainty concerning the centre of the whole
universe? Is not the only residence and home of all the things which
are heavy and light to us, the earth and the air which surrounds it?
and what is the earth and the ambient air, with respect to the
immensity of the universe? It is a point, a punctule, or something, if
there be any thing, still less. As our light and heavy bodies tend to
288 the centre of
our earth, it is credible that the sun, the moon, and the other
lights, have a similar affection, by which they remain round as we see
them; but none of these centres is necessarily the centre of the
universe.”
The most obvious and important physical difficulty attendant upon
the supposition of the motion of the earth was thus stated: If the
earth move, how is it that a stone, dropped from the top of a high
tower, falls exactly at the foot of the tower? since the tower being
carried from west to east by the diurnal revolution of the earth, the
stone must be left behind to the west of the place from which it was
let fall. The proper answer to this was, that the motion which the
falling body received from its tendency downwards was
compounded with the motion which, before it fell, it had in
virtue of the earth’s rotation: but this answer could not be clearly
made or apprehended, till Galileo and his pupils had established the
laws of such Compositions of motion arising from different forces.
Rothman, Kepler, and other defenders of the Copernican system, gave
their reply somewhat at a venture, when they asserted that the motion
of the earth was communicated to bodies at its surface. Still, the
facts which indicate and establish this truth are obvious, when the
subject is steadily considered; and the Copernicans soon found that
they had the superiority of argument on this point as well as others.
The attacks upon the Copernican system by Durret, Morin, Riccioli, and
the defence of it by Galileo, Lansberg, Gassendi,28 left on all
candid reasoners a clear impression in favour of the system. Morin
attempted to stop the motion of the earth, which he called breaking
its wings; his Alæ Terræ Fractæ was published in 1643, and
answered by Gassendi. And Riccioli, as late as 1653, in his
Almagestum Novum, enumerated fifty-seven Copernican arguments,
and pretended to refute them all: but such reasonings now made no
converts; and by this time the mechanical objections to the motion of
the earth were generally seen to be baseless, as we shall relate when
we come to speak of the progress of Mechanics as a distinct science.
In the mean time, the beauty and simplicity of the heliocentric theory
were perpetually winning the admiration even of those who, from one
cause or other, refused their assent to it. Thus Riccioli, the last of
its considerable opponents, allows its superiority in these respects;
and acknowledges (in 1653) that the Copernican belief appears rather
to increase than diminish under the condemnation of the decrees of the
Cardinals. He applies to it the lines of Horace:29


Per damna per cædes, ab ipso
Sumit opes animumque ferro.
Untamed its pride, unchecked its course,
From foes and wounds it gathers force.

28 Del. A. M. vol. i. p.
594.
29 Almag. Nov. p. 102.
289 We have
spoken of the influence of the motion of the earth on the motions of
bodies at its surface; but the notion of a physical connection among
the parts of the universe was taken up by Kepler in another point of
view, which would probably have been considered as highly fantastical,
if the result had not been, that it led to by far the most magnificent
and most certain train of truths which the whole expanse of human
knowledge can show. I speak of the persuasion of the existence of
numerical and geometrical laws connecting the distances, times, and
forces of the bodies which revolve about the central sun. That steady
and intense conviction of this governing principle, which made its
development and verification the leading employment of Kepler’s most
active and busy life, cannot be considered otherwise than as an
example of profound sagacity. That it was connected, though dimly and
obscurely, with the notion of a central agency or influence of some
sort, emanating from the sun, cannot be doubted. Kepler, in his first
essay of this kind, the Mysterium Cosmographicum, says, “The
motion of the earth, which Copernicus had proved by
mathematical reasons, I wanted to prove by physical,
or, if you prefer it, metaphysical.” In the twentieth chapter of that
work, he endeavors to make out some relation between the distances of
the Planets from the Sun and their velocities. The inveterate yet
vague notions of forces which preside in this attempt, may be judged
of by such passages as the following:—“We must suppose one of
two things; either that the moving spirits, in proportion as they are
more removed from the sun, are more feeble; or that there is one
moving spirit in the centre of all the orbits, namely, in the sun,
which urges each body the more vehemently in proportion as it is
nearer; but in more distant spaces languishes in consequence of the
remoteness and attenuation of its virtue.”
We must not forget, in reading such passages, that they were
written under a belief that force was requisite to keep up, as well as
to change the motion of each planet; and that a body, moving in a
circle, would stop when the force of the central point
ceased, instead of moving off in a tangent to the circle, as we now
know it would do. The force which Kepler supposes is a tangential
force, in the direction of the body’s motion, and nearly perpendicular
to the radius; the 290 force which modern philosophy has
established, is in the direction of the radius, and nearly
perpendicular to the body’s path. Kepler was right no further than in
his suspicion of a connection between the cause of motion and the
distance from the centre; not only was his knowledge imperfect in all
particulars, but his most general conception of the mode of action of
a cause of motion was erroneous.
With these general convictions and these physical notions in his
mind, Kepler endeavored to detect numerical and geometrical relations
among the parts of the solar system. After extraordinary labor,
perseverance, and ingenuity, he was eminently successful in
discovering such relations; but the glory and merit of interpreting
them according to their physical meaning, was reserved for his greater
successor, Newton.  ~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~
</div></body></text></TEI>