<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="148">ZOOLOGY.
I have exemplified the considerations which govern zoological
classification by quoting the reflexions which Cuvier gives us, as
having led him to his own classification of Fishes. Since the
varieties of Quadrupeds, or Mammals (omitting whales, &c.),
are more familiar to the common reader than those of Fishes, I may
notice some of the steps in their classification; the more so as some
curious questions have recently arisen thereupon.
Linnæus first divides Mammals into two groups, as they have Claws,
or Hoofs (unguiculata, ungulata.) But he then again
divides them into six orders (omitting whales, &c.), according to
their number of incisor, laniary, and molar
teeth; namely:—
Primates. (Man, Monkey, &c.)
Bruta. (Rhinoceros, Elephant, &c.)
Feræ. (Dog, Cat, Bear, Mole, &c.)
Glires. (Mouse, Squirrel, Hare, &c.)
Pecora. (Camel, Giraffe, Stag, Goat, Sheep, Ox, &c.)
Belluæ. (Horse, Hippopotamus, Tapir, Sow, &c.)
In the place of these, Cuvier, as I have stated in the
Philosophy (On the Language of Sciences, Aphorism xvi.),
introduced the following orders: Bimanes, Quadrumanes,
Carnassiers, Rongeurs, Edentés,
Pachyderms, Ruminans. Of these, the Carnassiers
correspond to the Feræ of Linnæus; the Rongeurs to his
Glires; the Edentés are a new order, taking the Sloths,
Ant-eaters, &c., from the Bruta of Linnæus, the Megatherium
from extinct animals, and the Ornithorhynchus, &c., from the new
animals of Australia; the Ruminans agree with the 635 Pecora; the
Pachyderms include some of the Bruta and the
Belluæ, comprehending also extinct animals, as
Anoplotherium and Palæotherium.
But the two orders of Hoofed Animals, the Pachyderms and the
Ruminants, form a group which is held by Mr. Owen to admit of a better
separation, on the ground of a character already pointed out by
Cuvier; namely, as to whether they are two-toed or
three-toed. According to this view, the Horse is connected with
the Tapir, the Palæotherium, and the Rhinoceros, not only by his
teeth, but by his feet, for he has really three digits. And Cuvier
notices that in the two-toed or even-toed Pachyderms, the astragalus
bone has its face divided into two equal parts by a ridge; while in
the uneven-toed pachyderms it has a narrow cuboid face. Mr. Owen has
adopted this division of Pachyderms and Ruminants, giving the names
artiodactyla and perissodactyla to the two groups; the
former including the Ox, Hog, Peccary, Hippopotamus, &c.; the
latter comprehending the Horse, Tapir, Rhinoceros, Hyrax, &c. And
thus the Ruminants take their place as a subordinate group of the
great natural even-toed Division of the Hoofed Section of Mammals; and
the Horse is widely separated from them, inasmuch as he belongs to the
odd-toed division.42
42 Owen, Odontography.
As we have seen, these modern classifications are so constructed as
to include extinct as well as living species of animals; and indeed
the species which have been discovered in a fossil state have tended
to fill up the gaps in the series of zoological forms which had marred
the systems of modern zoologists. This has been the case with the
division of which we are speaking.
Mr. Owen had established two genera of extinct Herbivorous Animals,
on the strength of fossil remains brought from South
America:—Toxodon, and Nesodon. In a recent
communication to the Royal Society43 he has
considered the bearing of these genera upon the divisions of odd-toed
and even-toed animals. He had already been led to the opinion that the
three sections, Proboscidea, Perissodactyla, and
Artiodactyla, formed a natural division of Ungulata; and he is
now led to think that this division implies another group, “a distinct
division of the Ungulata, of equal value, if not with the
Perissodactyla and Artiodactyla at least with the
Proboscidea. This group he proposes to call
Toxodonta.
43 Phil. Trans., 1853.


BOOK XVII.

PHYSIOLOGY AND COMPARATIVE
ANATOMY.
</div></body></text></TEI>