<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="104">INTRODUCTION.
Sect. 1.—Of the Classificatory
Sciences.
THE horizon of the sciences
spreads wider and wider before us, as we advance in our task of taking
a survey of the vast domain. We have seen that the existence of
Chemistry as a science which declares the ingredients and essential
constitution of all kinds of bodies, implies the existence of another
corresponding science, which shall divide bodies into kinds, and point
out steadily and precisely what bodies they are which we have
analysed. But a science thus dividing and defining bodies, is but one
member of an order of sciences, different from those which we have
hitherto described; namely, of the classificatory sciences.
Such sciences there must be, not only having reference to the bodies
with which chemistry deals, but also to all things respecting which we
aspire to obtain any general knowledge, as, for instance, plants and
animals. Indeed it will be found, that it is with regard to these
latter objects, to organized beings, that the process of scientific
classification has been most successfully exercised; while with regard
to inorganic substances, the formation of a satisfactory system of
arrangement has been found extremely difficult; nor has the necessity
of such a system been recognised by chemists so distinctly and
constantly as it ought to be. The best exemplification of these
branches of knowledge, of which we now have to speak, will, therefore,
be found in the organic world, in Botany and Zoology; but we will, in
the first place, take a brief view of the science which classifies
inorganic bodies, and of which Mineralogy is hitherto the very
imperfect representative.
The principles and rules of the Classificatory Sciences, as well as
of those of the other orders of sciences, must be fully explained when
we come to treat of the Philosophy of the Sciences; and cannot be
introduced here, where we have to do with history only. But I may
observe very briefly, that with the process of classing, is
joined the process of naming;—that names imply
classification;—and that even the rudest and earliest
application of language presupposes a distribution of objects
according to their kinds;—but that such a spontaneous 314 and unsystematic
distribution cannot, in the cases we now have to consider, answer the
purposes of exact and general knowledge. Our classification of objects
must be made consistent and systematic, in order to be scientific; we
must discover marks and characters, properties and conditions, which
are constant in their occurrence and relations; we must form our
classes, we must impose our names, according to such marks. We can
thus, and thus alone, arrive at that precise, certain, and systematic
knowledge, which we seek; that is, at science. The object, then, of
the classificatory sciences is to obtain fixed
characters of the kinds of things; and the criterion of the
fitness of names is, that they make general
propositions possible.
I proceed to review the progress of certain sciences on these
principles, and first, though briefly, the science of Mineralogy.
Sect. 2.—Mineralogy as the
Analytico-classificatory Science.
Mineralogy, as it has
hitherto been cultivated, is, as I have already said, an imperfect
representative of the department of human knowledge to which it
belongs. The attempts at the science have generally been made by
collecting various kinds of information respecting mineral bodies; but
the science which we require is a complete and consistent classified
system of all inorganic bodies. For chemistry proceeds upon the
principle that the constitution of a body invariably determines its
properties; and, consequently, its kind: but we cannot apply this
principle, except we can speak with precision of the kind of
a body, as well as of its composition. We cannot attach any sense to
the assertion, that “soda or baryta has a metal for its base,” except
we know what a metal is, or at least what properties it
implies. It may not be, indeed it is not, possible, to define the
kinds of bodies by words only; but the classification must proceed by
some constant and generally applicable process; and the knowledge
which has reference to the classification will be precise as far as
this process is precise, and vague as far as this is vague.
There must be, then, as a necessary supplement to Chemistry, a
Science of those properties of bodies by which we divide them into
kinds. Mineralogy is the branch of knowledge which has
discharged the office of such a science, so far as it has been
discharged; and, indeed, Mineralogy has been gradually approaching to
a clear consciousness of her real place, and of her whole task; I
shall give the history of some of the advances which have thus been
made. They are, principally, 315 the establishment and use of External
Characters, especially of Crystalline Form, as a fixed
character of definite substances; and the attempts to bring into view
the connexion of Chemical Constitution and External Properties, made
in the shape of mineralogical Systems; both those in which
chemical methods of arrangement are adopted, and those which
profess to classify by the natural-history method.


CRYSTALLOGRAPHY.
</div></body></text></TEI>