<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="13">
CHAPTER VIII.
Of Art and Science.
Aphorism XXV.
Art and Science differ. The object of Science is Knowledge;
the objects of Art, are Works. In Art, truth is a
means to an end; in Science, it is the only end. Hence the
Practical Arts are not to be classed among the Sciences.
Aphorism XXVI.
Practical Knowledge, such as Art implies, is not Knowledge
such as Science includes. Brute animals have a practical
knowledge of relations of space and force; but they have
no knowledge of Geometry or Mechanics.
1. THE
distinction of Arts and Sciences very materially
affects all classifications of the departments
of Human Knowledge. It is often maintained, expressly or
tacitly, that the Arts are a part of our
knowledge, in the same sense in which the Sciences
are so; and that Art is the application of Science to the
purposes of practical life. It will be found that these
views require some correction, when we understand
Science in the exact sense in which we have throughout
endeavoured to contemplate it, and in which alone
our examination of its nature can instruct us in the
true foundations of our knowledge.
When we cast our eyes upon the early stages of
the histories of nations, we cannot fail to be struck
with the consideration, that in many countries the
Arts of life already appear, at least in some rude form
or other, when, as yet, nothing of science exists. A 130
practical knowledge of Astronomy, such as enables them
to reckon months and years, is found among all nations
except the mere savages. A practical knowledge of
Mechanics must have existed in those nations which
have left us the gigantic monuments of early architecture.
The pyramids and temples of Egypt and Nubia,
the Cyclopean walls of Italy and Greece, the temples
of Magna Græcia and Sicily, the obelisks and edifices
of India, the cromlechs and Druidical circles of countries
formerly Celtic,—must have demanded no small
practical mechanical skill and power. Yet those
modes of reckoning time must have preceded the rise
of speculative Astronomy; these structures must have
been erected before the theory of Mechanics was
known. To suppose, as some have done, a great body
of science, now lost, to have existed in the remote
ages to which these remains belong, is not only quite
gratuitous, and contrary to all analogy, but is a
supposition which cannot be extended so far as to explain
all such cases. For it is impossible to imagine that
every art has been preceded by the science which
renders a reason for its processes. Certainly men formed
wine from the grape, before they possessed a Science of
Fermentation; the first instructor of every artificer in
brass and iron can hardly be supposed to have taught
the Chemistry of metals as a Science; the inventor
of the square and the compasses had probably no more
knowledge of demonstrated Geometry than have the
artisans who now use those implements; and finally,
the use of speech, the employment of the inflections
and combinations of words, must needs be assumed as
having been prior to any general view of the nature
and analogy of Language. Even at this moment, the
greater part of the arts which exist in the world are
not accompanied by the sciences on which they theoretically
depend. Who shall state to us the general
chemical truths to which the manufactures of glass,
and porcelain, and iron, and brass, owe their existence?
Do not almost all artisans practise many successful
artifices long before science explains the ground of the
process? Do not arts at this day exist, in a high state 131
of perfection, in countries in which there is no science,
as China and India? These countries and many others
have no theories of mechanics, of optics, of chemistry,
of physiology; yet they construct and use mechanical
and optical instruments, make chemical combinations,
take advantage of physiological laws. It is too evident
to need further illustration that Art may exist without
Science;—that the former has usually been anterior to
the latter, and even now commonly advances independently,
leaving science to follow as it can.
2. We here mean by Science, that exact, general,
speculative knowledge, of which we have, throughout
this work, been endeavouring to exhibit the nature
and rules. Between such Science and the practical
Arts of life, the points of difference are sufficiently
manifest. The object of Science is Knowledge; the
object of Art are Works. The latter is satisfied with
producing its material results; to the former, the
operations of matter, whether natural or artificial, are
interesting only so far as they can be embraced by
intelligible principles. The End of Art is the Beginning
of Science; for when it is seen what is done, then
comes the question why it is done. Art may have
fixed general rules, stated in words; but she has
these merely as means to an end: to Science, the propositions
which she obtains are each, in itself, a sufficient end of
the effort by which it is acquired. When
Art has brought forth her product, her task is finished;
Science is constantly led by one step of her path to
another: each proposition which she obtains impels
her to go onwards to other propositions more general,
more profound, more simple. Art puts elements together,
without caring to know what they are, or why
they coalesce. Science analyses the compound, and at
every such step strives not only to perform, but to
understand the analysis. Art advances in proportion
as she becomes able to bring forth products more
multiplied, more complex, more various; but Science,
straining her eyes to penetrate more and more deeply
into the nature of things, reckons her success in
proportion as she sees, in all the phenomena, however 132
multiplied; complex, and varied, the results of one or
two simple and general laws.
3. There are many acts which man, as well as
animals, performs by the guidance of nature, without
seeing or seeking the reason why he does so; as, the
acts by which he balances himself in standing or
moving, and those by which he judges of the form and
position of the objects around him. These actions
have their reason in the principles of geometry and
mechanics; but of such reasons he who thus acts is
unaware: he works blindly, under the impulse of an
unknown principle which we call Instinct. When
man’s speculative nature seeks and finds the reasons
why he should act thus or thus;—why he should
stretch out his arm to prevent his falling, or assign a
certain position to an object in consequence of the
angles under which it is seen;—he may perform the
same actions as before, but they are then done by the
aid of a different faculty, which, for the sake of
distinction, we may call Insight. Instinct is a purely
active principle; it is seen in deeds alone; it has no
power of looking inwards; it asks no questions; it has
no tendency to discover reasons or rules; it is the
opposite of Insight.
4. Art is not identical with Instinct: on the contrary,
there are broad differences. Instinct is stationary;
Art is progressive. Instinct is mute; it acts,
but gives no rules for acting: Art can speak; she can
lay down rules. But though Art is thus separate
from Instinct, she is not essentially combined with
Insight. She can see what to do, but she needs not
to see why it is done. She may lay down Rules, but it
is not her business to give Reasons. When man makes
that his employment, he enters upon the domain of
Science. Art takes the phenomena and laws of nature
as she finds them: that they are multiplied, complex,
capricious, incoherent, disturbs her not. She is content
that the rules of nature’s operations should be
perfectly arbitrary and unintelligible, provided they
are constant, so that she can depend upon their effects.
But Science is impatient of all appearance of caprice, 133
inconsistency, irregularity, in nature. She will not
believe in the existence of such characters. She resolves
one apparent anomaly after another; her task is
not ended till every thing is so plain and simple, that
she is tempted to believe that she sees that it could by
no possibility have been otherwise than it is.
5. It may be said that, after all, Art does really
involve the knowledge which Science delivers;—that
the artisan who raises large weights, practically knows
the properties of the mechanical powers;—that he
who manufactures chemical compounds is virtually
acquainted with the laws of chemical combination.
To this we reply, that it might on the same grounds
be asserted, that he who acts upon the principle that
two sides of a triangle are greater than the third is
really acquainted with geometry; and that he who
balances himself on one foot knows the properties of
the center of gravity. But this is an acquaintance
with geometry and mechanics which even brute animals
possess. It is evident that it is not of such
knowledge as this that we have here to treat. It is
plain that this mode of possessing principles is
altogether different from that contemplation of them on
which science is founded. We neglect the most essential
and manifest differences, if we confound our unconscious
assumptions with our demonstrative reasonings.
6. The real state of the case is, that the principles
which Art involves, Science alone evolves. The truths
on which the success of Art depends, lurk in the
artist’s mind in an undeveloped state; guiding his
hand, stimulating his invention, balancing his judgment;
but not appearing in the form of enunciated
Propositions. Principles are not to him direct objects
of meditation: they are secret Powers of Nature, to
which the forms which tenant the world owe their
constancy, their movements, their changes, their luxuriant
and varied growth, but which he can nowhere
directly contemplate. That the creative and directive
Principles which have their lodgment in the artist’s
mind, when unfolded by our speculative powers into 134
systematic shape, become Science, is true; but it is
precisely this process of development which gives to
them their character of Science. In practical Art,
principles are unseen guides, leading us by invisible
strings through paths where the end alone is looked
at: it is for Science to direct and purge our vision so
that these airy ties, these principles and laws,
generalizations and theories, become distinct objects of vision.
Many may feel the intellectual monitor, but it is only
to her favourite heroes that the Goddess of Wisdom
visibly reveals herself.
7. Thus Art, in its earlier stages at least, is widely
different from Science, is independent of it, and is
anterior to it. At a later period, no doubt, Art may borrow
aid from Science; and the discoveries of the philosopher
may be of great value to the manufacturer and
the artist. But even then, this application forms no
essential part of the science: the interest which belongs
to it is not an intellectual interest. The augmentation
of human power and convenience may impel
or reward the physical philosopher; but the processes
by which man’s repasts are rendered more delicious,
his journeys more rapid, his weapons more terrible,
are not, therefore, Science. They may involve principles
which are of the highest interest to science; but
as the advantage is not practically more precious because
it results from a beautiful theory, so the theoretical
principle has no more conspicuous place in science
because it leads to convenient practical consequences.
The nature of Science is purely intellectual; Knowledge
alone,—exact general Truth,—is her object; and we
cannot mix with such material, as matters of the same
kind, the merely Empirical maxims of Art, without
introducing endless confusion into the subject, and
making it impossible to attain any solid footing in our
philosophy.
8. I shall therefore not place, in our Classification
of the Sciences, the Arts, as has generally been done;
nor shall I notice the applications of sciences to art,
as forming any separate portion of each science. The
sciences, considered as bodies of general speculative 135
truths, are what we are here concerned with; and
applications of such truths, whether useful or useless,
are important to us only as illustrations and examples.
Whatever place in human knowledge the Practical
Arts may hold, they are not Sciences. And it is only
by this rigorous separation of the Practical from the
Theoretical, that we can arrive at any solid conclusions
respecting the nature of Truth, and the mode of arriving
at it, such as it is our object to attain.
</div></body></text></TEI>