<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="99">CHAPTER VI.
Epoch of the Theory of
Oxygen.—Lavoisier.

Sect. 1.—Prelude to the
Theory.—Its Publication.
WE arrive now at a great epoch
in the history of Chemistry. Few revolutions in science have
immediately excited so much general notice as the introduction of the
theory of oxygen. The simplicity and symmetry of the modes of
combination which it assumed; and, above all, the construction and
universal adoption of a nomenclature which applied to all substances,
and which seemed to reveal their inmost constitution by their name,
naturally gave it an almost irresistible sway over men’s minds. We
must, however, dispassionately trace the course of its introduction.
276
Antoine Laurent Lavoisier, an accomplished French chemist, had
pursued, with zeal and skill, researches such as those of Black,
Cavendish, and Priestley, which we have described above. In 1774, he
showed that, in the calcination of metals in air, the metal acquires
as much weight as the air loses. It might appear that this discovery
at once overturned the view which supposed the metal to be phlogiston
added to the calx. Lavoisier’s contemporaries were, however,
far from allowing this; a greater mass of argument was needed to bring
them to this conclusion. Convincing proofs of the new opinion were,
however, rapidly supplied. Thus, when Priestley had discovered
dephlogisticated air, in 1774, Lavoisier showed, in 1776, that fixed
air consisted of charcoal and the dephlogisticated or pure air; for
the mercurial calx which, heated by itself, gives out pure air, gives
out, when heated with charcoal, fixed air,27 which has,
therefore, since been called carbonic acid gas.
27 Mém. Ac. Par. 1775.
Again, Lavoisier showed that the atmospheric air consists of pure
or vital air, and of an unvital air, which he thence called
azot. The vital air he found to be the agent in combustion,
acidification, calcination, respiration; all of these processes were
analogous: all consisted in a decomposition of the atmospheric air,
and a fixation of the pure or vital portion of it.
But he thus arrived at the conclusion, that this pure air was
added, in all the cases in which, according to the received theory,
phlogiston was subtracted, and vice versâ. He gave the
name28 of oxygen (principe
oxygène) to “the substance which thus unites itself with metals to
form their calces, and with combustible substances to form acids.”
28 Mém. Ac. Par. 1781, p.
448.
A new theory was thus produced, which would account for all the
facts which the old one would explain, and had besides the evidence of
the balance in its favor. But there still remained some apparent
objections to be removed. In the action of dilute acids on metals,
inflammable air was produced. Whence came this element? The discovery
of the decomposition of water sufficiently answered this question, and
converted the objection into an argument on the side of the theory:
and thus the decomposition of water was, in fact, one of the most
critical events for the fortune of the Lavoisierian doctrine, and one
which, more than any other, decided chemists in its favor. In
succeeding years, Lavoisier showed the consistency of his theory with
277 all that was
discovered concerning the composition of alcohol, oil, animal and
vegetable substances, and many other bodies.
It is not necessary for us to consider any further the evidence for
this theory, but we must record a few circumstances respecting its
earlier history. Rey, a French physician, had in 1630, published a
book, in which he inquires into the grounds of the increase of the
weight of metals by calcination.29 He says, “To
this question, then, supported on the grounds already mentioned, I
answer, and maintain with confidence, that the increase of weight
arises from the air, which is condensed, rendered heavy and adhesive,
by the heat of the furnace.” Hooke and Mayow had entertained the
opinion that the air contains a “nitrous spirit,” which is the
supporter of combustion. But Lavoisier disclaimed the charge of having
derived anything from these sources; nor is it difficult to understand
how the received generalizations of the phlogistic theory had thrown
all such narrower explanations into obscurity. The merit of Lavoisier
consisted in his combining the generality of Stahl with the verified
conjectures of Rey and Mayow.
29 Thomson, Hist. Chem. ii.
95.
No one could have a better claim, by his early enthusiasm for
science, his extensive knowledge, and his zealous labors, to hope that
a great discovery might fall to his share, than Lavoisier. His
father,30 a man of considerable fortune, had
allowed him to make science his only profession; and the zealous
philosopher collected about him a number of the most active physical
inquirers of his time, who met and experimented at his house one day
in the week. In this school, the new chemistry was gradually formed. A
few years after the publication of Priestley’s first experiments,
Lavoisier was struck with the presentiment of the theory which he was
afterwards to produce. In 1772, he deposited31 with the
secretary of the Academy, a note which contained the germ of his
future doctrines. “At that time,” he says, in explaining this step,
“there was a kind of rivalry between France and England in science,
which gave importance to new experiments, and which sometimes was the
cause that the writers of the one or other of the nations disputed the
discovery with the real author.” In 1777, the editor of the Memoirs of
the Academy speaks of his theory as overturning that of Stahl; but the
general acceptance of the new opinion did not take place till
later.
30 Biogr. Univ.
(Cuvier.)
31 Thomson, ii. 99. 278
Sect. 2.—Reception and Confirmation of the Theory
of Oxygen.
The Oxygen Theory made its
way with extraordinary rapidity among the best philosophers.32 In 1785, that is, soon after
Cavendish’s synthesis of water had removed some of the most formidable
objections to it, Berthollet, already an eminent chemist, declared
himself a convert. Indeed it was so soon generally adopted in France,
that Fourcroy promulgated its doctrines under the name of “La Chimie
Française,” a title which Lavoisier did not altogether relish. The
extraordinary eloquence and success of Fourcroy as a lecturer at the
Jardin des Plantes, had no small share in the diffusion of the oxygen
theory; and the name of “the apostle of the new chemistry” which was
at first given him in ridicule, was justly held by him to be a
glorious distinction.33
32 Thomson, ii. 130.
33 Cuvier, Eloges, i. p.
20.
Guyton de Morveau, who had at first been a strenuous advocate of
the phlogistic theory, was invited to Paris, and brought over to the
opinions of Lavoisier; and soon joined in the formation of the
nomenclature founded upon the theory. This step, of which we shall
shortly speak, fixed the new doctrine, and diffused it further.
Delametherie alone defended the phlogistic theory with vigor, and
indeed with violence. He was the editor of the Journal de
Physique, and to evade the influence which this gave him, the
antiphlogistians34 established, as the vehicle of their
opinions, another periodical, the Annales de Chimie.
34 Thomson, ii. 133.
In England, indeed, their success was not so immediate.
Cavendish,35 in his Memoir of 1784, speaks of the
question between the two opinions as doubtful. “There are,” he says,
“several Memoirs of M. Lavoisier, in which he entirely discards
phlogiston; and as not only the foregoing experiments, but most other
phenomena of nature, seem explicable as well, or nearly as well, upon
this as upon the commonly believed principle of phlogiston,” Cavendish
proceeds to explain his experiments according to the new views,
expressing no decided preference, however, for either system. But
Kirwan, another English chemist, contested the point much more
resolutely. His theory identified inflammable air, or hydrogen, with
phlogiston; and in this view, he wrote a work which was intended as a
confutation of 279
the essential part of the oxygen theory. It is a strong proof of the
steadiness and clearness with which the advocates of the new system
possessed their principles, that they immediately translated this
work, adding, at the end of each chapter, a refutation of the
phlogistic doctrines which it contained. Lavoisier, Berthollet, De
Morveau, Fourcroy, and Monge, were the authors of this curious
specimen of scientific polemics. It is also remarkable evidence of the
candor of Kirwan, that notwithstanding the prominent part he had taken
in the controversy, he allowed himself at last to be convinced. After
a struggle of ten years, he wrote36 to Berthollet
in 1796, “I lay down my arms, and abandon the cause of phlogiston.”
Black followed the same course. Priestley alone, of all the chemists
of great name, would never assent to the new doctrines, though his own
discoveries had contributed so much to their establishment. “He saw,”
says Cuvier,37 “without flinching, the most skilful
defenders of the ancient theory go over to the enemy in succession;
and when Kirwan had, almost the last of all, abjured phlogiston,
Priestley remained alone on the field of battle, and threw out a new
challenge, in a memoir addressed to the principal French chemists.” It
happened, curiously enough, that the challenge was accepted, and the
arguments answered by M. Adet, who was at that time (1798,) the French
ambassador to the United States, in which country Priestley’s work was
published. Even in Germany, the birth-place and home of the phlogistic
theory, the struggle was not long protracted. There was, indeed, a
controversy, the older philosophers being, as usual, the defenders of
the established doctrines; but in 1792, Klaproth repeated, before the
Academy of Berlin, all the fundamental experiments; and “the result
was a full conviction on the part of Klaproth and the Academy, that
the Lavoisierian theory was the true one.”38 Upon the whole,
the introduction of the Lavoisierian theory in the scientific world,
when compared with the great revolution of opinion to which it comes
nearest in importance, the introduction of the Newtonian theory,
shows, by the rapidity and temper with which it took place, a great
improvement, both in the means of arriving at truth, and in the spirit
with which they were used.
35 Phil. Trans. 1784, p.
150.
36 Pref. to Fourcroy’s
Chemistry, xiv.
37 Cuvier, Eloge de Priestley,
p. 208.
38 Thomson, vol. ii. p. 136.
Some English writers39 have expressed an opinion that there
was 280 little that
was original in the new doctrines. But if they were so obvious, what
are we to say of eminent chemists, as Black and Cavendish, who
hesitated when they were presented, or Kirwan and Priestley, who
rejected them? This at least shows that it required some peculiar
insight to see the evidence of these truths. To say that most of the
materials of Lavoisier’s theory existed before him, is only to say
that his great merit was, that which must always be the great merit of
a new theory, his generalization. The effect which the publication of
his doctrines produced, shows us that he was the first person who,
possessing clearly the idea of quantitative composition, applied it
steadily to a great range of well-ascertained facts. This is, as we
have often had to observe, precisely the universal description of an
inductive discoverer. It has been objected, in like manner, to the
originality of Newton’s discoveries, that they were contained in those
of Kepler. They were so, but they needed a Newton to find them there.
The originality of the theory of oxygen is proved by the conflict,
short as it was, which accompanied its promulgation; its importance is
shown by the changes which it soon occasioned in every part of the
science.
39 Brande, Hist. Diss. in
Enc, Brit. p. 182. Lunn, Chem. in Enc. Met. p.
596.
Thus Lavoisier, far more fortunate than most of those who had, in
earlier ages, produced revolutions in science, saw his theory accepted
by all the most eminent men of his time, and established over a great
part of Europe within a few years from its first promulgation. In the
common course of events, it might have been expected that the later
years of his life would have been spent amid the admiration and
reverence which naturally wait upon the patriarch of a new system of
acknowledged truths. But the times in which he lived allowed no such
euthanasia to eminence of any kind. The democracy which overthrew the
ancient political institutions of France, and swept away the nobles of
the land, was not, as might have been expected, enthusiastic in its
admiration of a great revolution in science, and forward to offer its
homage to the genuine nobility of a great discoverer. Lavoisier was
thrown into prison on some wretched charge of having, in the discharge
of a public office which he had held, adulterated certain tobacco; but
in reality, for the purpose of confiscating his property.40 In his imprisonment, his philosophy was
his resource; and he employed himself in the preparation of his papers
for printing. When he was brought before the revolutionary tribunal,
he begged for a respite of a few days, in order to complete some
researches, the results of which 281 were, he said, important to the good of
humanity. The brutish idiot, whom the state of the country at that
time had placed in the judgment-seat, told him that the republic
wanted no sçavans. He was dragged to the guillotine, May the 8th,
1794, and beheaded, in the fifty-second year of his age; a melancholy
proof that, in periods of political ferocity, innocence and merit,
private virtues and public services, amiable manners and the love of
friends, literary fame and exalted genius, are all as nothing to
protect their possessor from the last extremes of violence and wrong,
inflicted under judicial forms.
40 Biog. Univ. (Cuvier.)
Sect. 3.—Nomenclature of the Oxygen
Theory.
As we have already said, a
powerful instrument in establishing and diffusing the new chemical
theory, was a Systematic Nomenclature founded upon it, and applicable
to all chemical compounds, which was soon constructed and published by
the authors of the theory. Such a nomenclature made its way into
general use the more easily, in that the want of such a system had
already been severely felt; the names in common use being fantastical,
arbitrary, and multiplied beyond measure. The number of known
substances had become so great, that a list of names with no
regulative principle, founded on accident, caprice, and error, was too
cumbrous and inconvenient to be tolerated. Even before the currency
which Lavoisier’s theory obtained, these evils had led to attempts
towards a more convenient set of names. Bergman and Black had
constructed such lists; and Guyton de Morveau, a clever and
accomplished lawyer of Dijon, had formed a system of nomenclature in
1782, before he had become a convert to Lavoisier’s theory, in which
task he had been exhorted and encouraged by Bergman and Macquer. In
this system,41 we do not find most of the characters
of the method which was afterwards adopted. But a few years later,
Lavoisier, De Morveau, Berthollet and Fourcroy, associated themselves
for the purpose of producing a nomenclature which should correspond to
the new theoretical views. This appeared in 1787, and soon made its
way into general use. The main features of this system are, a
selection of the simplest radical words, by which substances are
designated, and a systematic distribution of terminations, to express
their relations. Thus, sulphur, combined with oxygen in two different
proportions, forms two acids, the 282 sulphurous and the
sulphuric; and these acids form, with earthy or alkaline
bases, sulphides and sulphates; while sulphur
directly combined with another element, forms a sulphuret.
The term oxyd (now usually written oxide) expressed a
lower degree of combination with oxygen than the acids. The Méthode
de Nomenclature Chimique was published in 1787; and in 1789,
Lavoisier published a treatise on chemistry in order further to
explain this method. In the preface to this volume, he apologizes for
the great amount of the changes, and pleads the authority of Bergman,
who had exhorted De Morveau “to spare no improper names; those who are
learned will always be learned, and those who are ignorant will thus
learn sooner.” To this maxim they so far conformed, that their system
offers few anomalies; and though the progress of discovery, and the
consequent changes of theoretical opinion, which have since gone on,
appear now to require a further change of nomenclature, it is no small
evidence of the skill with which this scheme was arranged, that for
half a century it was universally used, and felt to be far more useful
and effective than any nomenclature in any science had ever been
before.
41 Journal de Physique, 1782,
p. 370.
</div></body></text></TEI>