<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="28">

CRYSTALLOGRAPHY.

CHAPTER I.
Prelude to the Epoch of De Lisle and
Haüy.
OF all the physical properties
of bodies, there is none so fixed, and in every way so remarkable, as
this;—that the same chemical compound always assumes, with the
utmost precision, the same geometrical form. This identity, however,
is not immediately obvious; it is often obscured by various mixtures
and imperfections in the substance; and even when it is complete, it
is not immediately recognized by a common eye, since it consists, not
in the equality of the sides or faces of the figures, but in the
equality of their angles. Hence it is not surprising that the
constancy of form was not detected by the early observers. Pliny
says,1 “Why crystal is generated in a hexagonal
form, it is difficult to assign a reason; and the more so, since,
while its faces are smoother than any art can make them, the pyramidal
points are not all of the same kind.” The quartz crystals of
the Alps, to which he refers, are, in some specimens, very regular,
while in others, one side of the pyramid becomes much the largest; yet
the angles remain constantly the same. But when the whole shape varied
so much, the angles also seemed to vary. Thus Conrad Gessner, a very
learned naturalist, who, in 1564, published at Zurich his work, De
rerum Fossilium, Lapidum et Gemmarum maxime, Figuris, says,2
“One crystal differs from another in its angles, and consequently in
its figure.” And Cæsalpinus, who, as we shall find, did so much in establishing fixed characters
in botany, was led by some of his general views to disbelieve the
fixity of the form of crystals. In his work De Metallicis,
published at Nuremberg in 1602, he says,3 “To ascribe to
inanimate bodies a definite form, does not appear consentaneous to
reason; for it is the office of organization to produce a definite
form;” 317 an
opinion very natural in one who had been immersed in the study of the
general analogies of the forms of plants. But though this is excusable
in Cæsalpinus, the rejection of this definiteness of form a hundred
years later, when its existence had been proved, and its laws
developed by numerous observers, cannot be ascribed to anything but
strong prejudice; yet this was the course taken by no less a person
than Buffon. “The form of crystallization,” says he,4
“is not a constant character, but is more equivocal and more
variable than any other of the characters by which minerals are to be
distinguished.” And accordingly, he makes no use of this most
important feature in his history of minerals. This strange
perverseness may perhaps be ascribed to the dislike which Buffon is
said to have entertained for Linnæus, who had made crystalline form a
leading character of minerals.</div></body></text></TEI>