<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Vestiges of the Natural History of Creation</title><author>Chambers, Robert (1802-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="14">p.
191HYPOTHESIS OF THE DEVELOPMENT
OF THE
VEGETABLE AND ANIMAL KINGDOMS.
It has been already intimated, as a
general fact, that there is an obvious gradation amongst the
families of both the vegetable and animal kingdoms, from the
simple lichen and animalcule respectively up to the highest order
of dicotyledonous trees and the mammalia.  Confining our
attention, in the meantime, to the animal kingdom—it does
not appear that this gradation passes along one line, on which
every form of animal life can be, as it were, strung; there may
be branching or double lines at some places; or the whole may be
in a circle composed of minor circles, as has been recently
suggested.  But still it is incontestable that there are
general appearances of a scale beginning with the simple and
advancing to the complicated.  The animal kingdom was
divided by Cuvier into four sub-kingdoms, or divisions, and these
exhibit an unequivocal gradation in the order in which they are
here enumerated:—Radiata, (polypes, &c.;) mollusca,
(pulpy animals;) articulata, (jointed animals;) vertebrata,
(animals with internal skeleton.)  The gradation can, in
like manner, be clearly traced in the classes into which
the sub-kingdoms are subdivided, as, for instance, when we take
those of the vertebrata in this order—reptiles, fishes,
birds, mammals.
While the external forms of all these various animals are so
different, it is very remarkable that the whole are, after all,
variations of a fundamental plan, which can be traced as a basis
throughout the whole, the variations being merely modifications
of that plan to suit the particular conditions in which each
particular animal has been designed to live.  Starting from
the primeval germ, which, as we have seen, is the representative
of a particular order of full-grown animals, we find all others
to be merely advances from that type, with the extension of
endowments and modification of forms which are required in each
particular case; each form, also, retaining a strong affinity to
that which precedes it, and tending to impress its own features
on that which succeeds.  This unity of structure, as it is
called, becomes the more remarkable, when we observe that the
organs, while preserving a resemblance, are often put to
different uses.  For example: the ribs become, in the
serpent, organs of locomotion, and the snout is extended, in the
elephant, into a prehensile instrument.
It is equally remarkable that analogous purposes are served in
different animals by organs essentially different.  Thus,
the mammalia breathe by lungs; the fishes, by gills.  These
are not modifications of one organ, but distinct organs.  In
mammifers, the gills exist and act at an early stage of the
fœtal state, but afterwards go back and appear no more;
while the lungs are developed.  In fishes, again, the gills
only are fully developed; while the lung structure either makes
no advance at all, or only appears in the rudimentary form of an
air-bladder.  So, also, the baleen of the whale and the
teeth of the land mammalia are different organs.  The whale,
in embryo, shews the rudiments of teeth; but these, not being
wanted, are not developed, and the baleen is brought forward
instead.  The land animals, we may also be sure, have the
rudiments of baleen in their organization.  In many
instances, a particular structure is found advanced to a certain
point in a particular set of animals, (for instance, feet in the
serpent tribe,) although it is not there required in any degree;
but the peculiarity, being carried a little farther forward, is
perhaps useful in the next set of animals in the scale. 
Such are called rudimentary organs.  With this class of
phenomena are to be ranked the useless mammæ of the male
human being, and the unrequired process of bone in the male
opossum, which is needed in the female for supporting her
pouch.  Such curious features are most conspicuous in
animals which form links between various classes.
As formerly stated, the marsupials, standing at the bottom of
the mammalia, shew their affinity to the oviparous vertebrata, by
the rudiments of two canals passing from near the anus to the
external surfaces of the viscera, which are fully developed in
fishes, being required by them for the respiration of aerated
waters, but which are not needed by the atmosphere-breathing
marsupials.  We have also the peculiar form of the sternum
and rib-bones of the lizards represented in the mammalia
in certain white cartilaginous lines traceable among their
abdominal muscles.  The struphionidæ (birds of the
ostrich type) form a link between birds and mammalia, and in them
we find the wings imperfectly or not at all developed, a
diaphragm and urinary sac, (organs wanting in other birds,) and
feathers approaching the nature of hair.  Again, the
ornithorynchus belongs to a class at the bottom of the mammalia,
and approximating to birds, and in it behold the bill and
web-feet of that order!
For further illustration, it is obvious that, various as may
be the lengths of the upper part of the vertebral column in the
mammalia, it always consists of the same parts.  The giraffe
has in its tall neck the same number of bones with the pig, which
scarcely appears to have a neck at all. [195]  Man, again, has no tail; but the
notion of a much-ridiculed philosopher of the last century is not
altogether, as it happens, without foundation, for the bones of a
caudal extremity exist in an undeveloped state in the os
coccygis of the human subject.  The limbs of all the
vertebrate animals are, in like manner, on one plan, however
various they may appear.  In the hind-leg of a horse, for
example, the angle called the hock is the same part which in us
forms the heel; and the horse, and all other quadrupeds, with
almost the solitary exception of the bear, walk, in reality, upon
what answers to the toes of a human being.  In this and many
other quadrupeds the fore part of the extremities is shrunk up in
a hoof, as the tail of the human being is shrunk up in the bony
mass at the bottom of the back.  The bat, on the other hand,
has these parts largely developed.  The membrane, commonly
called its wing, is framed chiefly upon bones answering precisely
to those of the human hand; its extinct congener, the
pterodactyle, had the same membrane extended upon the fore-finger
only, which in that animal was prolonged to an extraordinary
extent.  In the paddles of the whale and other animals of
its order, we see the same bones as in the more highly developed
extremities of the land mammifers; and even the serpent tribes,
which present no external appearance of such extremities, possess
them in reality, but in an undeveloped or rudimental state.
The same law of development presides over the vegetable
kingdom.  Amongst phanerogamous plants, a certain number of
organs appear to be always present, either in a developed or
rudimentary state; and those which are rudimentary can be
developed by cultivation.  The flowers which bear stamens on
one stalk and pistils on another, can be caused to produce both,
or to become perfect flowers, by having a sufficiency of
nourishment supplied to them.  So also, where a special
function is required for particular circumstances, nature has
provided for it, not by a new organ, but by a modification of a
common one, which she has effected in development.  Thus,
for instance, some plants destined to live in arid situations,
require to have a store of water which they may slowly
absorb.  The need is arranged for by a cup-like expansion
round the stalk, in which water remains after a shower.  Now
the pitcher, as this is called, is not a new organ, but
simply a metamorphose of a leaf.
These facts clearly shew how all the various organic forms of
our world are bound up in one—how a fundamental unity
pervades and embraces them all, collecting them, from the
humblest lichen up to the highest mammifer, in one system, the
whole creation of which must have depended upon one law or decree
of the Almighty, though it did not all come forth at one
time.  After what we have seen, the idea of a separate
exertion for each must appear totally inadmissible.  The
single fact of abortive or rudimentary organs condemns it; for
these, on such a supposition, could be regarded in no other light
than as blemishes or blunders—the thing of all others most
irreconcilable with that idea of Almighty Perfection which a
general view of nature so irresistibly conveys.  On the
other hand, when the organic creation is admitted to have been
effected by a general law, we see nothing in these abortive parts
but harmless peculiarities of development, and interesting
evidences of the manner in which the Divine Author has been
pleased to work.
We have yet to advert to the most interesting class of facts
connected with the laws of organic development.  It is only
in recent times that physiologists have observed that each animal
passes, in the course of its germinal history, through a series
of changes resembling the permanent forms of the various
orders of animals inferior to it in the scale.  Thus, for
instance, an insect, standing at the head of the articulated
animals, is, in the larva state, a true annelid, or worm, the
annelida being the lowest in the same class.  The embryo of
a crab resembles the perfect animal of the inferior order
myriapoda, and passes through all the forms of transition which
characterize the intermediate tribes of crustacea.  The
frog, for some time after its birth, is a fish with external
gills, and other organs fitting it for an aquatic life, all of
which are changed as it advances to maturity, and becomes a land
animal.  The mammifer only passes through still more stages,
according to its higher place in the scale.  Nor is man
himself exempt from this law.  His first form is that which
is permanent in the animalcule.  His organization gradually
passes through conditions generally resembling a fish, a reptile,
a bird, and the lower mammalia, before it attains its specific
maturity.  At one of the last stages of his fœtal
career, he exhibits an intermaxillary bone, which is
characteristic of the perfect ape; this is suppressed, and he may
then be said to take leave of the simial type, and become a true
human creature.  Even, as we shall see, the varieties of his
race are represented in the progressive development of an
individual of the highest, before we see the adult Caucasian, the
highest point yet attained in the animal scale.
To come to particular points of the organization.  The
brain of man, which exceeds that of all other animals in
complexity of organization and fulness of development, is, at one
early period, only “a simple fold of nervous matter, with
difficulty distinguishable into three parts, while a little
tail-like prolongation towards the hinder parts, and which had
been the first to appear, is the only representation of a spinal
marrow.  Now, in this state it perfectly resembles the brain
of an adult fish, thus assuming in transitu the form that
in the fish is permanent.  In a short time, however, the
structure is become more complex, the parts more distinct, the
spinal marrow better marked; it is now the brain of a
reptile.  The change continues; by a singular motion,
certain parts (corpora quadragemina) which had hitherto
appeared on the upper surface, now pass towards the lower; the
former is their permanent situation in fishes and reptiles, the
latter in birds and mammalia.  This is another advance in
the scale, but more remains yet to be done.  The
complication of the organ increases; cavities termed
ventricles are formed, which do not exist in fishes,
reptiles, or birds; curiously organized parts, such as the
corpora striata, are added; it is now the brain of the
mammalia.  Its last and final change alone seems wanting,
that which shall render it the brain of MAN.” [201]  And this
change in time takes place.
So also with the heart.  This organ, in the mammalia,
consists of four cavities, but in the reptiles of only three, and
in fishes of two only, while in the articulated animals it is
merely a prolonged tube.  Now in the mammal fœtus, at
a certain early stage, the organ has the form of a prolonged
tube; and a human being may be said to have then the heart of an
insect.  Subsequently it is shortened and widened, and
becomes divided by a contraction into two parts, a ventricle and
an auricle; it is now the heart of a fish.  A subdivision of
the auricle afterwards makes a triple-chambered form, as in the
heart of the reptile tribes; lastly, the ventricle being also
subdivided, it becomes a full mammal heart.
Another illustration here presents itself with the force of
the most powerful and interesting analogy.  Some of the
earliest fishes of our globe, those of the Old Red Sandstone,
present, as we have seen, certain peculiarities, as the one-sided
tail and an inferior position of the mouth.  No fishes of
the present day, in a mature state, are so characterized; but
some, at a certain stage of their existence, have such
peculiarities.  It occurred to a geologist to inquire if the
fish which existed before the Old Red Sandstone had any
peculiarities assimilating them to the fœtal condition of
existing fish, and particularly if they were small.  The
first which occur before the time of the Old Red Sandstone, are
those described by Mr. Murchison, as belonging to the Upper
Ludlow Rocks; they are all rather small.  Still older
are those detected by Mr. Philips, in the Aymestry Limestone,
being the most ancient of the class which have as yet been
discovered; these are so extremely minute as only to be
distinguishable by the microscope.  Here we apparently
have very clear demonstrations of a parity, or rather identity,
of laws presiding over the development of the animated tribes on
the face of the earth, and that of the individual in embryo.
The tendency of all these illustrations is to make us look to
development as the principle which has been immediately
concerned in the peopling of this globe, a process extending over
a vast space of time, but which is nevertheless connected in
character with the briefer process by which an individual being
is evoked from a simple germ.  What mystery is there
here—and how shall I proceed to enunciate the conception
which I have ventured to form of what may prove to be its proper
solution!  It is an idea by no means calculated to impress
by its greatness, or to puzzle by its profoundness.  It is
an idea more marked by simplicity than perhaps any other of those
which have explained the great secrets of nature.  But in
this lies, perhaps, one of its strongest claims to the faith of
mankind.
The whole train of animated beings, from the simplest and
oldest up to the highest and most recent, are, then, to be
regarded as a series of advances of the principle of
development, which have depended upon external physical
circumstances, to which the resulting animals are
appropriate.  I contemplate the whole phenomena as having
been in the first place arranged in the counsels of Divine
Wisdom, to take place, not only upon this sphere, but upon all
the others in space, under necessary modifications, and as being
carried on, from first to last, here and elsewhere, under
immediate favour of the creative will or energy. [204]  The nucleated vesicle, the
fundamental form of all organization, we must regard as the
meeting-point between the inorganic and the organic—the end
of the mineral and beginning of the vegetable and animal
kingdoms, which thence start in different directions, but in
perfect parallelism and analogy.  We have already seen that
this nucleated vesicle is itself a type of mature and independent
being in the infusory animalcules, as well as the starting point
of the fœtal progress of every higher individual in
creation, both animal and vegetable.  We have seen that it
is a form of being which electric agency will
produce—though not perhaps usher into full life—in
albumen, one of those compound elements of animal bodies, of
which another (urea) has been made by artificial means. 
Remembering these things, we are drawn on to the supposition,
that the first step in the creation of life upon this planet was
a chemico-electric operation, by which simple germinal
vesicles were produced.  This is so much, but what were
the next steps?  Let a common vegetable infusion help us to
an answer.  There, as we have seen, simple forms are
produced at first, but afterwards they become more complicated,
until at length the life-producing powers of the infusion are
exhausted.  Are we to presume that, in this case, the simple
engender the complicated?  Undoubtedly, this would not be
more wonderful as a natural process than one which we never think
of wondering at, because familiar to us—namely, that in the
gestation of the mammals, the animalcule-like ovum of a few days
is the parent, in a sense, of the chick-like form of a few weeks,
and that in all the subsequent stages—fish, reptile,
&c.—the one may, with scarcely a metaphor, be said to
be the progenitor of the other.  I suggest, then, as an
hypothesis already countenanced by much that is ascertained, and
likely to be further sanctioned by much that remains to be known,
that the first step was an advance under favour of peculiar
conditions, from the simplest forms of being, to
the next more complicated, and this through the medium of
the ordinary process of generation.
Unquestionably, what we ordinarily see of nature is calculated
to impress a conviction that each species invariably produces its
like.  But I would here call attention to a remarkable
illustration of natural law which has been brought forward by Mr.
Babbage, in his Ninth Bridgewater Treatise.  The
reader is requested to suppose himself seated before the
calculating machine, and observing it.  It is moved by a
weight, and there is a wheel which revolves through a small angle
round its axis, at short intervals, presenting to his eye
successively, a series of numbers engraved on its divided
circumference.
Let the figures thus seen be the series, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
&c., of natural numbers, each of which exceeds its immediate
antecedent by unity.
“Now, reader,” says Mr. Babbage, “let me ask
you how long you will have counted before you are firmly
convinced that the engine has been so adjusted, that it will
continue, while its motion is maintained, to produce the same
series of natural numbers?  Some minds are so constituted,
that, after passing the first hundred terms, they will be
satisfied that they are acquainted with the law.  After
seeing five hundred terms few will doubt, and after the fifty
thousandth term the propensity to believe that the succeeding
term will be fifty thousand and one, will be almost
irresistible.  That term will be fifty thousand and
one; and the same regular succession will continue; the five
millionth and the fifty millionth term will still appear in their
expected order, and one unbroken chain of natural numbers will
pass before your eyes, from one up to one hundred
million.
“True to the vast induction which has been made, the
next succeeding term will be one hundred million and one; but the
next number presented by the rim of the wheel, instead of being
one hundred million and two, is one hundred million ten
thousand and two.  The whole series from the
commencement being thus,—


 

1

 



 

2

 



 

3

 



 

4

 



 

5

 



 

.

 



 

. .

 



 

. . .

 



 

99,999,999

 



 

100,000,000

 



regularly as far as

100,000,001

 



 

100,010,002

the law changes.



 

100,030,003

 



 

100,060,004

 



 

100,100,005

 



 

100,150,006

 



 

100,210,007

 



 

100,280,008

 



 

. . .

 



 

. . .

 



 

. . .

 



“The law which seemed at first to govern this series
failed at the hundred million and second term.  This term is
larger than we expected by 10,000.  The next term is larger
than was anticipated by 30,000, and the excess of each term above
what we had expected forms the following table:—


10,000



30,000



60,000



100,000



150,000



. . .



. . .



being, in fact, the series of triangular numbers, [208] each multiplied by 10,000.
“If we now continue to observe the numbers presented by
the wheel, we shall find, that for a hundred, or even for a
thousand terms, they continue to follow the new law relating to
the triangular numbers; but after watching them for 2761 terms,
we find that this law fails in the case of the 2762d term.
“If we continue to observe, we shall discover another
law then coming into action, which also is dependent, but in a
different manner, on triangular numbers.  This will continue
through about 1430 terms, when a new law is again introduced
which extends over about 950 terms, and this, too, like all its
predecessors, fails, and gives place to other laws, which appear
at different intervals.
“Now it must be observed that the law that each
number presented by the engine is greater by unity than the
preceding number, which law the observer had deduced from an
induction of a hundred million instances, was not the true law
that regulated its action, and that the occurrence of the
number 100,010,002 at the 100,000,002nd term was as necessary
a consequence of the original adjustment, and might have
been as fully foreknown at the commencement, as was the
regular succession of any one of the intermediate numbers to its
immediate antecedent.  The same remark applies to the
next apparent deviation from the new law, which was founded on an
induction of 2761 terms, and also to the succeeding law, with
this limitation only—that, whilst their consecutive
introduction at various definite intervals, is a necessary
consequence of the mechanical structure of the engine, our
knowledge of analysis does not enable us to predict the periods
themselves at which the more distant laws will be
introduced.”
It is not difficult to apply the philosophy of this passage to
the question under consideration.  It must be borne in mind
that the gestation of a single organism is the work of but a few
days, weeks, or months; but the gestation (so to speak) of a
whole creation is a matter probably involving enormous spaces of
time.  Suppose that an ephemeron, hovering over a pool for
its one April day of life, were capable of observing the fry of
the frog in the water below.  In its aged afternoon, having
seen no change upon them for such a long time, it would be little
qualified to conceive that the external branchiæ of these
creatures were to decay, and be replaced by internal lungs, that
feet were to be developed, the tail erased, and the animal then
to become a denizen of the land.  Precisely such may be our
difficulty in conceiving that any of the species which people our
earth is capable of advancing by generation to a higher type of
being.  During the whole time which we call the historical
era, the limits of species have been, to ordinary observation,
rigidly adhered to.  But the historical era is, we know,
only a small portion of the entire age of our globe.  We do
not know what may have happened during the ages which preceded
its commencement, as we do not know what may happen in ages yet
in the distant future.  All, therefore, that we can properly
infer from the apparently invariable production of like by like
is, that such is the ordinary procedure of nature in the time
immediately passing before our eyes.  Mr. Babbage’s
illustration powerfully suggests that this ordinary procedure may
be subordinate to a higher law which only permits it for a
time, and in proper season interrupts and changes it.  We
shall soon see some philosophical evidence for this very
conclusion.
It has been seen that, in the reproduction of the higher
animals, the new being passes through stages in which it is
successively fish-like and reptile-like.  But the
resemblance is not to the adult fish or the adult reptile, but to
the fish and reptile at a certain point in their fœtal
progress; this holds true with regard to the vascular, nervous,
and other systems alike.  It may be illustrated by a simple
diagram.  The fœtus of all the four classes may be
supposed to advance in an identical condition to the point
A.  


  The fish there diverges and passes along a line apart,
and peculiar to A itself, to its mature state at F.  The
reptile, bird, and mammal, go on together to C, where the reptile
diverges in like manner, and advances by itself to R.  The
bird diverges at D, and goes on to B.  The mammal then goes
forward in a straight line to the highest point of organization
at M.  This diagram shews only the main ramifications; but
the reader must suppose minor ones, representing the subordinate
differences of orders, tribes, families, genera, &c., if he
wishes to extend his views to the whole varieties of being in the
animal kingdom.  Limiting ourselves at present to the
outline afforded by this diagram, it is apparent that the only
thing required for an advance from one type to another in the
generative process is that, for example, the fish embryo should
not diverge at A, but go on to C before it diverges, in which
case the progeny will be, not a fish, but a reptile.  To
protract the straightforward part of the gestation over a
small space—and from species to species the space would
be small indeed—is all that is necessary.
This might be done by the force of certain external conditions
operating upon the parturient system.  The nature of these
conditions we can only conjecture, for their operation, which in
the geological eras was so powerful, has in its main strength
been long interrupted, and is now perhaps only allowed to work in
some of the lowest departments of the organic world, or under
extraordinary casualties in some of the higher, and to these
points the attention of science has as yet been little
directed.  But though this knowledge were never to be
clearly attained, it need not much affect the present argument,
provided it be satisfactorily shewn that there must be some such
influence within the range of natural things.
To this conclusion it must be greatly conducive that the law
of organic development is still daily seen at work to certain
effects, only somewhat short of a transition from species to
species.  Sex we have seen to be a matter of
development.  There is an instance, in a humble department
of the animal world, of arrangements being made by the animals
themselves for adjusting this law to the production of a
particular sex.  Amongst bees, as amongst several other
insect tribes, there is in each community but one true female,
the queen bee, the workers being false females or neuters; that
is to say, sex is carried on in them to a point where it is
attended by sterility.  The preparatory states of the queen
bee occupy sixteen days; those of the neuters, twenty; and those
of males, twenty-four.  Now it is a fact, settled by
innumerable observations and experiments, that the bees can so
modify a worker in the larva state, that, when it emerges from
the pupa, it is found to be a queen or true female.  For
this purpose they enlarge its cell, make a pyramidal hollow to
allow of its assuming a vertical instead of a horizontal
position, keep it warmer than other larvæ are kept, and
feed it with a peculiar kind of food.  From these simple
circumstances, leading to a shortening of the embryotic
condition, results a creature different in form, and also in
dispositions, from what would have otherwise been produced. 
Some of the organs possessed by the worker are here altogether
wanting.  We have a creature “destined to enjoy love,
to burn with jealousy and anger, to be incited to vengeance, and
to pass her time without labour,” instead of one
“zealous for the good of the community, a defender of the
public rights, enjoying an immunity from the stimulus of sexual
appetite and the pains of parturition; laborious, industrious,
patient, ingenious, skilful; incessantly engaged in the nurture
of the young, in collecting honey and pollen, in elaborating wax,
in constructing cells and the like!—paying the most
respectful and assiduous attention to objects which, had its
ovaries been developed, it would have hated and pursued with the
most vindictive fury till it had destroyed them!” [215]  All these changes may be
produced by a mere modification of the embryotic progress, which
it is within the power of the adult animals to effect.  But
it is important to observe that this modification is different
from working a direct change upon the embryo.  It is not the
different food which effects a metamorphosis.  All that is
done is merely to accelerate the period of the insect’s
perfection.  By the arrangements made and the food given,
the embryo becomes sooner fit for being ushered forth in its
imago or perfect state.  Development may be said to be thus
arrested at a particular stage—that early one at which the
female sex is complete.  In the other circumstances, it is
allowed to go on four days longer, and a stage is then reached
between the two sexes, which in this species is designed to be
the perfect condition of a large portion of the community. 
Four days more make it a perfect male.  It is at the same
time to be observed that there is, from the period of
oviposition, a destined distinction between the sexes of the
young bees.  The queen lays the whole of the eggs which are
designed to become workers, before she begins to lay those which
become males.  But probably the condition of her
reproductive system governs the matter of sex, for it is remarked
that when her impregnation is delayed beyond the twenty-eighth
day of her entire existence, she lays only eggs which become
males.
We have here, it will be admitted, a most remarkable
illustration of the principle of development, although in an
operation limited to the production of sex only.  Let it not
be said that the phenomena concerned in the generation of bees
may be very different from those concerned in the reproduction of
the higher animals.  There is a unity throughout nature
which makes the one case an instructive reflection of the
other.
We shall now see an instance of development operating within
the production of what approaches to the character of variety of
species.  It is fully established that a human family,
tribe, or nation, is liable, in the course of generations, to be
either advanced from a mean form to a higher one, or degraded
from a higher to a lower, by the influence of the physical
conditions in which it lives.  The coarse features, and
other structural peculiarities of the negro race only continue
while these people live amidst the circumstances usually
associated with barbarism.  In a more temperate clime, and
higher social state, the face and figure become greatly
refined.  The few African nations which possess any
civilization also exhibit forms approaching the European; and
when the same people in the United States of America have enjoyed
a within-door life for several generations, they assimilate to
the whites amongst whom they live.  On the other hand, there
are authentic instances of a people originally well-formed and
good-looking, being brought, by imperfect diet and a variety of
physical hardships, to a meaner form.  It is remarkable that
prominence of the jaws, a recession and diminution of the
cranium, and an elongation and attenuation of the limbs, are
peculiarities always produced by these miserable conditions, for
they indicate an unequivocal retrogression towards the type of
the lower animals.  Thus we see nature alike willing to go
back and to go forward.  Both effects are simply the result
of the operation of the law of development in the generative
system.  Give good conditions, it advances; bad ones, it
recedes.  Now, perhaps, it is only because there is no
longer a possibility, in the higher types of being, of giving
sufficiently favourable conditions to carry on species to
species, that we see the operation of the law so far limited.
Let us trace this law also in the production of certain
classes of monstrosities.  A human fœtus is often left
with one of the most important parts of its frame imperfectly
developed: the heart, for instance, goes no farther than the
three-chambered form, so that it is the heart of a reptile. 
There are even instances of this organ being left in the
two-chambered or fish form.  Such defects are the result of
nothing more than a failure of the power of development in the
system of the mother, occasioned by weak health or misery. 
Here we have apparently a realization of the converse of those
conditions which carry on species to species, so far, at least,
as one organ is concerned.  Seeing a complete specific
retrogression in this one point, how easy it is to imagine an
access of favourable conditions sufficient to reverse the
phenomenon, and make a fish mother develop a reptile heart, or a
reptile mother develop a mammal one.  It is no great
boldness to surmise that a super-adequacy in the measure of this
under-adequacy (and the one thing seems as natural an occurrence
as the other) would suffice in a goose to give its progeny the
body of a rat, and produce the ornithorynchus, or might give the
progeny of an ornithorynchus the mouth and feet of a true rodent,
and thus complete at two stages the passage from the aves to the
mammalia.
Perhaps even the transition from species to species does still
take place in some of the obscurer fields of creation, or under
extraordinary casualties, though science professes to have no
such facts on record.  It is here to be remarked, that such
facts might often happen, and yet no record be taken of them, for
so strong is the prepossession for the doctrine of invariable
like-production, that such circumstances, on occurring, would be
almost sure to be explained away on some other supposition, or,
if presented, would be disbelieved and neglected.  Science,
therefore, has no such facts, for the very same reason that some
small sects are said to have no discreditable
members—namely, that they do not receive such persons, and
extrude all who begin to verge upon the character.  There
are, nevertheless, some facts which have chanced to be reported
without any reference to this hypothesis, and which it seems
extremely difficult to explain satisfactorily upon any
other.  One of these has already been mentioned—a
progression in the forms of the animalcules in a vegetable
infusion from the simpler to the more complicated, a sort of
microcosm, representing the whole history of the progress of
animal creation as displayed by geology.  Another is given
in the history of the Acarus Crossii, which may be only the
ultimate stage of a series of similar transformations effected by
electric agency in the solution subjected to it.  There is,
however, one direct case of a translation of species, which has
been presented with a respectable amount of authority. [221]  It appears that, whenever oats
sown at the usual time are kept cropped down during summer and
autumn, and allowed to remain over the winter, a thin crop of rye
is the harvest presented at the close of the ensuing
summer.  This experiment has been tried repeatedly, with but
one result; invariably the secale cereale is the crop
reaped where the avena sativa, a recognised different
species, was sown.  Now it will not satisfy a strict
inquirer to be told that the seeds of the rye were latent in the
ground and only superseded the dead product of the oats; for if
any such fact were in the case, why should the usurping grain be
always rye?  Perhaps those curious facts which have been
stated with regard to forests of one kind of trees, when burnt
down, being succeeded (without planting) by other kinds, may yet
be found most explicable, as this is, upon the hypothesis of a
progression of species which takes place under certain favouring
conditions, now apparently of comparatively rare
occurrence.  The case of the oats is the more valuable, as
bearing upon the suggestion as to a protraction of the gestation
at a particular part of its course.  Here, the generative
process is, by the simple mode of cropping down, kept up for a
whole year beyond its usual term.  The type is thus allowed
to advance, and what was oats becomes rye.
The idea, then, which I form of the progress of organic life
upon the globe—and the hypothesis is applicable to all
similar theatres of vital being—is, that the simplest
and most primitive type, under a law to which that of
like-production is subordinate, gave birth to the type
next above it, that this again produced the next
higher, and so on to the very highest, the stages of
advance being in all cases very small—namely, from one
species only to another; so that the phenomenon has always been
of a simple and modest character.  Whether the whole of any
species was at once translated forward, or only a few parents
were employed to give birth to the new type, must remain
undetermined; but, supposing that the former was the case, we
must presume that the moves along the line or lines were
simultaneous, so that the place vacated by one species was
immediately taken by the next in succession, and so on back to
the first, for the supply of which the formation of a new
germinal vesicle out of inorganic matter was alone
necessary.  Thus, the production of new forms, as shewn in
the pages of the geological record, has never been anything more
than a new stage of progress in gestation, an event as simply
natural, and attended as little by any circumstances of a
wonderful or startling kind, as the silent advance of an ordinary
mother from one week to another of her pregnancy.  Yet, be
it remembered, the whole phenomena are, in another point of view,
wonders of the highest kind, for in each of them we have to trace
the effect of an Almighty Will which had arranged the whole in
such harmony with external physical circumstances, that both were
developed in parallel steps—and probably this development
upon our planet is but a sample of what has taken place, through
the same cause, in all the other countless theatres of being
which are suspended in space.
This may be the proper place at which to introduce the
preceding illustrations in a form calculated to bring them more
forcibly before the mind of the reader.  The following table
was suggested to me, in consequence of seeing the scale of
animated nature presented in Dr. Fletcher’s Rudiments of
Physiology.  Taking that scale as its basis, it shews the
wonderful parity observed in the progress of creation, as
presented to our observation in the succession of fossils, and
also in the fœtal progress of one of the principal human
organs. [224]  This scale, it may be remarked,
was not made up with a view to support such an hypothesis as the
present, nor with any apparent regard to the history of fossils,
but merely to express the appearance of advancement in the orders
of the Cuvierian system, assuming, as the criterion of that
advancement, “an increase in the number and extent of the
manifestations of life, or of the relations which an organized
being bears to the external world.”  Excepting in the
relative situation of the annelida and a few of the mammal
orders, the parity is perfect; nor may even these small
discrepancies appear when the order of fossils shall have been
further investigated, or a more correct scale shall have been
formed.  Meanwhile, it is a wonderful evidence in favour of
our hypothesis, that a scale formed so arbitrarily should
coincide to such a nearness with our present knowledge of the
succession of animal forms upon earth, and also that both of
these series should harmonize so well with the view given by
modern physiologists of the embryotic progress of one of the
organs of the highest order of animals.



 [226]
The reader has seen physical conditions several times referred
to, as to be presumed to have in some way governed the progress
of the development of the zoological circle.  This language
may seem vague, and, it may be asked,—can any particular
physical condition be adduced as likely to have affected
development?  To this it may be answered, that air and light
are probably amongst the principal agencies of this kind which
operated in educing the various forms of being.  Light is
found to be essential to the development of the individual
embryo.  When tadpoles were placed in a perforated box, and
that box sunk in the Seine, light being the only condition thus
abstracted, they grew to a great size in their original form, but
did not pass through the usual metamorphose which brings them to
their mature state as frogs.  The proteus, an animal of the
frog kind, inhabiting the subterraneous waters of Carniola, and
which never acquires perfect lungs so as to become a land animal,
is presumed to be an example of arrested development, from the
same cause.  When, in connexion with these facts, we learn
that human mothers living in dark and close cells under
ground,—that is to say, with an inadequate provision of air
and light,—are found to produce an unusual proportion of
defective children, [229] we can appreciate
the important effects of both these physical conditions in
ordinary reproduction.  Now there is nothing to forbid the
supposition that the earth has been at different stages of its
career under different conditions, as to both air and
light.  On the contrary, we have seen reason for supposing
that the proportion of carbonic acid gas (the element fatal to
animal life) was larger at the time of the carboniferous
formation than it afterwards became.  We have also seen that
astronomers regard the zodiacal light as a residuum of matter
enveloping the sun, and which was probably at one time denser
than it is now.  Here we have the indications of causes for
a progress in the purification of the atmosphere and in the
diffusion of light during the earlier ages of the earth’s
history, with which the progress of organic life may have been
conformable.  An accession to the proportion of oxygen, and
the effulgence of the central luminary, may have been the
immediate prompting cause of all those advances from species to
species which we have seen, upon other grounds, to be necessarily
supposed as having taken place.  And causes of the like
nature may well be supposed to operate on other spheres of being,
as well as on this.  I do not indeed present these ideas as
furnishing the true explanation of the progress of organic
creation; they are merely thrown out as hints towards the
formation of a just hypothesis, the completion of which is only
to be looked for when some considerable advances shall have been
made in the amount and character of our stock of knowledge.
Early in this century, M. Lamarck, a naturalist of the highest
character, suggested an hypothesis of organic progress which
deservedly incurred much ridicule, although it contained a
glimmer of the truth.  He surmised, and endeavoured, with a
great deal of ingenuity, to prove, that one being advanced in the
course of generations to another, in consequence merely of its
experience of wants calling for the exercise of its faculties in
a particular direction, by which exercise new developments of
organs took place, ending in variations sufficient to constitute
a new species.  Thus he thought that a bird would be driven
by necessity to seek its food in the water, and that, in its
efforts to swim, the outstretching of its claws would lead to the
expansion of the intermediate membranes, and it would thus become
web-footed.  Now it is possible that wants and the exercise
of faculties have entered in some manner into the production of
the phenomena which we have been considering; but certainly not
in the way suggested by Lamarck, whose whole notion is obviously
so inadequate to account for the rise of the organic kingdoms,
that we only can place it with pity among the follies of the
wise.  Had the laws of organic development been known in his
time, his theory might have been of a more imposing kind. 
It is upon these that the present hypothesis is mainly
founded.  I take existing natural means, and shew them to
have been capable of producing all the existing organisms, with
the simple and easily conceivable aid of a higher generative law,
which we perhaps still see operating upon a limited scale. 
I also go beyond the French philosopher to a very important
point, the original Divine conception of all the forms of being
which these natural laws were only instruments in working out and
realizing.  The actuality of such a conception I hold to be
strikingly demonstrated by the discoveries of Macleay, Vigors,
and Swainson, with respect to the affinities and analogies of
animal (and by implication vegetable) organisms. [232]  Such a regularity in the
structure, as we may call it, of the classification of
animals, as is shewn in their systems, is totally
irreconcilable with the idea of form going on to form merely as
needs and wishes in the animals themselves dictated.  Had
such been the case, all would have been irregular, as things
arbitrary necessarily are.  But, lo, the whole plan of being
is as symmetrical as the plan of a house, or the laying out of an
old-fashioned garden!  This must needs have been devised and
arranged for beforehand.  And what a preconception or
forethought have we here!  Let us only for a moment consider
how various are the external physical conditions in which animals
live—climate, soil, temperature, land, water, air—the
peculiarities of food, and the various ways in which it is to be
sought; the peculiar circumstances in which the business of
reproduction and the care-taking of the young are to be attended
to—all these required to be taken into account, and
thousands of animals were to be formed suitable in organization
and mental character for the concerns they were to have with
these various conditions and circumstances—here a tooth
fitted for crushing nuts; there a claw fitted to serve as a hook
for suspension; here to repress teeth and develop a bony net-work
instead; there to arrange for a bronchial apparatus, to last only
for a certain brief time; and all these animals were to be
schemed out, each as a part of a great range, which was on the
whole to be rigidly regular: let us, I say, only consider these
things, and we shall see that the decreeing of laws to bring the
whole about was an act involving such a degree of wisdom and
device as we only can attribute, adoringly, to the one Eternal
and Unchangeable.  It may be asked, how does this reflection
comport with that timid philosophy which would have us to draw
back from the investigation of God’s works, lest the
knowledge of them should make us undervalue his greatness and
forget his paternal character?  Does it not rather appear
that our ideas of the Deity can only be worthy of him in the
ratio in which we advance in a knowledge of his works and ways;
and that the acquisition of this knowledge is consequently an
available means of our growing in a genuine reverence for
him!
But the idea that any of the lower animals have been concerned
in any way with the origin of man—is not this
degrading?  Degrading is a term, expressive of a notion of
the human mind, and the human mind is liable to prejudices which
prevent its notions from being invariably correct.  Were we
acquainted for the first time with the circumstances attending
the production of an individual of our race, we might equally
think them degrading, and be eager to deny them, and exclude them
from the admitted truths of nature.  Knowing this fact
familiarly and beyond contradiction, a healthy and natural mind
finds no difficulty in regarding it complacently.  Creative
Providence has been pleased to order that it should be so, and it
must therefore be submitted to.  Now the idea as to the
progress of organic creation, if we become satisfied of its
truth, ought to be received precisely in this spirit.  It
has pleased Providence to arrange that one species should give
birth to another, until the second highest gave birth to man, who
is the very highest: be it so, it is our part to admire and to
submit.  The very faintest notion of there being anything
ridiculous or degrading in the theory—how absurd does it
appear, when we remember that every individual amongst us
actually passes through the characters of the insect, the fish,
and reptile, (to speak nothing of others,) before he is permitted
to breathe the breath of life!  But such notions are mere
emanations of false pride and ignorant prejudice.  He who
conceives them little reflects that they, in reality, involve the
principle of a contempt for the works and ways of God.  For
it may be asked, if He, as appears, has chosen to employ inferior
organisms as a generative medium for the production of higher
ones, even including ourselves, what right have we, his humble
creatures, to find fault?  There is, also, in this
prejudice, an element of unkindliness towards the lower animals,
which is utterly out of place.  These creatures are all of
them part products of the Almighty Conception, as well as
ourselves.  All of them display wondrous evidences of his
wisdom and benevolence.  All of them have had assigned to
them by their Great Father a part in the drama of the organic
world, as well as ourselves.  Why should they be held in
such contempt?  Let us regard them in a proper spirit, as
parts of the grand plan, instead of contemplating them in the
light of frivolous prejudices, and we shall be altogether at a
loss to see how there should be any degradation in the idea of
our race having been genealogically connected with them.</div></body></text></TEI>