<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="18">CHAPTER IV.
Of the Dogmatism of the Stationary
Period.
IN speaking of the character
of the age of commentators, we noticed principally the ingenious
servility which it displays;—the acuteness with which it finds
ground for speculation in the expression of other men’s
thoughts;—the want of all vigor and fertility in acquiring any
real and new truths. Such was the character of the reasoners of the
stationary period from the first; but, at a later day, this character,
from various causes, was modified by new features. The servility which
had yielded itself to the yoke, insisted upon forcing it on the necks
of others: the subtlety which found all the truth it needed in certain
accredited writings, resolved that no one should find there, or in any
other region, any other truths; speculative men became tyrants without
ceasing to be slaves; to their character of Commentators they added
that of Dogmatists.
1. Origin of the Scholastic Philosophy.—The causes of
this change have been very happily analyzed and described by several
modern writers.62 The general nature of the process may
be briefly stated to have been the following.
62  Dr. Hampden, in the Life of Thomas
Aquinas, in the Encyc. Metrop. Degerando, Hist.
Comparée, vol. iv. Also Tennemann, Hist. of Phil. vol.
viii. Introduction.
The tendencies of the later times of the Roman empire to a
commenting literature, and a second-hand philosophy, have already been
noticed. The loss of the dignity of political freedom, the want of the
cheerfulness of advancing prosperity, and the substitution of the less
philosophical structure of the Latin language for the delicate
intellectual mechanism of the Greek, fixed and augmented the prevalent
feebleness and barrenness of intellect. Men forgot, or feared, to
consult nature, to seek for new truths, to do what the great
discoverers of other times had done; they were content to consult
libraries, to study and defend old opinions, to talk of what great
geniuses had said. They sought their philosophy in accredited
treatises, and dared not question such doctrines as they there
found.
The character of the philosophy to which they were thus led, was
determined by this want of courage and originality. There are various
229 antagonist
principles of opinion, which seem alike to have their root in the
intellectual constitution of man, and which are maintained and
developed by opposing sects, when the intellect is in vigorous action.
Such principles are, for instance,—the claims of Authority and
of Reason to our assent;—the source of our knowledge in
Experience or in Ideas;—the superiority of a Mystical or of a
Skeptical turn of thought. Such oppositions of doctrine were found in
writers of the greatest fame; and two of those, who most occupied the
attention of students, Plato and Aristotle, were, on several points of
this nature, very diverse from each other in their tendency. The
attempt to reconcile these philosophers by Boëthius and others, we
have already noticed; and the attempt was so
far successful, that it left on men’s minds the belief in the
possibility of a great philosophical system which should be based on
both these writers, and have a claim to the assent of all sober
speculators.
But, in the mean time, the Christian Religion had become the
leading subject of men’s thoughts; and divines had put forward its
claims to be, not merely the guide of men’s lives, and the means of
reconciling them to their heavenly Master, but also to be a Philosophy
in the widest sense in which the term had been used;—a
consistent speculative view of man’s condition and nature, and of the
world in which he is placed.
These claims had been acknowledged; and, unfortunately, from the
intellectual condition of the times, with no due apprehension of the
necessary ministry of Observation, and Reason dealing with
observation, by which alone such a system can be embodied. It was held
without any regulating principle, that the philosophy which had been
bequeathed to the world by the great geniuses of heathen antiquity,
and the Philosophy which was deduced from, and implied by, the
Revelations made by God to man, must be identical; and, therefore,
that Theology is the only true philosophy. Indeed, the Neoplatonists
had already arrived, by other roads, at the same conviction. John Scot
Erigena, in the reign of Alfred, and consequently before the existence
of the Scholastic Philosophy, properly so called, had reasserted this
doctrine.63 Anselm, in the eleventh century, again
brought it forward;64 and Bernard de Chartres, in the
thirteenth.65
63 Deg. iv. 351.
64 Ib. iv. 388.
65 Ib. iv. 418.
This view was confirmed by the opinion which prevailed, concerning
the nature of philosophical truth; a view supported by the theory
230 of Plato, the
practice of Aristotle, and the general propensities of the human mind:
I mean the opinion that all science may be obtained by the use of
reasoning alone;—that by analysing and combining the notions
which common language brings before us, we may learn all that we can
know. Thus Logic came to include the whole of Science; and accordingly
this Abelard expressly maintained.66 I have already explained, in some measure, the fallacy
of this belief, which consists, as has been well said,67 “in mistaking the universality of the
theory of language for the generalization of facts.” But on all
accounts this opinion is readily accepted; and it led at once to the
conclusion, that the Theological Philosophy which we have described,
is complete as well as true.
66 Deg. iv. 407.
67 Enc. Met. 807.
Thus a Universal Science was established, with the authority of a
Religious Creed. Its universality rested on erroneous views of the
relation of words and truths; its pretensions as a science were
admitted by the servile temper of men’s intellects; and its religious
authority was assigned it, by making all truth part of religion. And
as Religion claimed assent within her own jurisdiction under the most
solemn and imperative sanctions, Philosophy shared in her imperial
power, and dissent from their doctrines was no longer blameless or
allowable. Error became wicked, dissent became heresy; to reject the
received human doctrines, was nearly the same as to doubt the Divine
declarations. The Scholastic Philosophy claimed the assent of
all believers.
The external form, the details, and the text of this philosophy,
were taken, in a great measure, from Aristotle; though, in the spirit,
the general notions, and the style of interpretation, Plato and the
Platonists had no inconsiderable share. Various causes contributed to
the elevation of Aristotle to this distinction. His Logic had early
been adopted as an instrument of theological disputation; and his
spirit of systematization, of subtle distinction, and of analysis of
words, as well as his disposition to argumentation, afforded the most
natural and grateful employment to the commentating propensities.
Those principles which we before noted as the leading points of his
physical philosophy, were selected and adopted; and these, presented
in a most technical form, and applied in a systematic manner,
constitute a large portion of the philosophy of which we now speak, so
far as it pretends to deal with physics.
2. Scholastic Dogmas.—But before the complete
ascendancy of Aristotle was thus established, when something of an
intellectual waking 231 took place after the darkness and sleep
of the ninth and tenth centuries, the Platonic doctrines seem to have
had, at first, a strong attraction for men’s minds, as better falling
in with the mystical speculations and contemplative piety which
belonged to the times. John Scot Erigena68 may be looked
upon as the reviver of the New Platonism in the tenth century. Towards
the end of the eleventh, Peter Damien,69 in Italy,
reproduced, involved in a theological discussion, some Neoplatonic
ideas. Godefroy70 also, censor of St. Victor, has left a
treatise, entitled Microcosmus; this is founded on a mystical
analogy, often afterwards again brought forward, between Man and the
Universe. “Philosophers and theologians,” says the writer, “agree in
considering man as a little world; and as the world is composed of
four elements, man is endowed with four faculties, the senses, the
imagination, reason, and understanding.” Bernard of Chartres,71 in his Megascosmus and
Microcosmus, took up the same notions. Hugo, abbot of St.
Victor, made a contemplative life the main point and crown of his
philosophy; and is said to have been the first of the scholastic
writers who made psychology his special study.72 He says the
faculties of the mind are “the senses, the imagination, the reason,
the memory, the understanding, and the intelligence.”
68 Deg. iv. 35.
69 Ib. iv. 367.
70 Ib. iv. 413.
71 Ib. iv. 419.
72 Ib. iv. 415.
Physics does not originally and properly form any prominent part of
the Scholastic Philosophy, which consists mainly of a series of
questions and determinations upon the various points of a certain
technical divinity. Of this kind is the Book of Sentences of
Peter the Lombard (bishop of Paris), who is, on that account, usually
called “Magister Sententiarum;” a work which was published in the
twelfth century, and was long the text and standard of such
discussions. The questions are decided by the authority of Scripture
and of the Fathers of the Church, and are divided into four Books, of
which the first contains questions concerning God and the doctrine of
the Trinity in particular; the second is concerning the Creation; the
third, concerning Christ and the Christian Religion; and the fourth
treats of Religious and Moral Duties. In the second book, as in many
of the writers of this time, the nature of Angels is considered in
detail, and the Orders of their Hierarchy, of which there were held to
be nine. The physical discussions enter only as bearing upon the
scriptural history of the creation, and cannot be taken as a specimen
of the work; but I may observe, that in speaking of the division of
the waters above the 232 firmament, he gives one opinion, that of
Bede, that the former waters are the solid crystalline heavens in
which the stars are fixed,73 “for crystal, which is so hard and
transparent, is made of water.” But he mentions also the opinion of
St. Augustine, that the waters above the heavens are in a state of
vapor, (vaporaliter) and in minute drops; “if, then, water
can, as we see in clouds, be so minutely divided that it may be thus
supported as vapor on air, which is naturally lighter than water; why
may we not believe that it floats above that lighter celestial element
in still minuter drops and still lighter vapors? But in whatever
manner the waters are there, we do not doubt that they are there.”
73 Lib. ii. Distinct. xiv. De opere
secundæ diei.
The celebrated Summa Theologicæ of Thomas Aquinas
is a work of the same kind; and anything which has a physical bearing
forms an equally small part of it. Thus, of the 512 Questions of the
Summa, there is only one (Part I., Quest. 115), “on Corporeal
Action,” or on any part of the material world; though there are
several concerning the celestial Hierarchies, as “on the Act of
Angels,” “on the Speaking of Angels,” “on the Subordination of
Angels,” “on Guardian Angels,” and the like. This, of course, would
not be remarkable in a treatise on Theology, except this Theology were
intended to constitute the whole of Philosophy.
We may observe, that in this work, though Plato, Avecibron, and
many other heathen as well as Christian philosophers, are adduced as
authority, Aristotle is referred to in a peculiar manner as “the
philosopher.” This is noticed by John of Salisbury, as attracting
attention in his time (he died a.d. 1182).
“The various Masters of Dialectic,” says he,74 “shine each with
his peculiar merit; but all are proud to worship the footsteps of
Aristotle; so much so, indeed, that the name of philosopher,
which belongs to them all, has been pre-eminently appropriated to him.
He is called the philosopher autonomatice, that is, by
excellence.”
74 Metalogicus, lib. ii. cap.
16.
The Question concerning Corporeal Action, in Aquinas, is divided
into six Articles; and the conclusion delivered upon the first is,75 that “Body being compounded of power
and act, is active as well as passive.” Against this it is urged, that
quantity is an attribute of body, and that quantity prevents action;
that this appears in fact, since a larger body is more difficult to
move. The author replies, that 233 “quantity does not prevent corporeal
form from action altogether, but prevents it from being a universal
agent, inasmuch as the form is individualized, which, in matter
subject to quantity, it is. Moreover, the illustration deduced from
the ponderousness of bodies is not to the purpose; first, because the
addition of quantity is not the cause of gravity, as is proved in the
fourth book, De Cœlo and De Mundo” (we see that he quotes familiarly
the physical treatises of Aristotle); “second, because it is false
that ponderousness makes motion slower; on the contrary, in proportion
as any thing is heavier, the more does it move with its proper motion;
thirdly, because action does not take place by local motion, as
Democritus asserted; but by this, that something is drawn from power
into act.”
75 Summa, P. i. Q. 115. Art.
1.
It does not belong to our purpose to consider either the
theological or the metaphysical doctrines which form so large a
portion of the treatises of the schoolmen. Perhaps it may hereafter
appear, that some light is thrown on some of the questions which have
occupied metaphysicians in all ages, by that examination of the
history of the Progressive Sciences in which we are now engaged; but
till we are able to analyze the leading controversies of this kind, it
would be of little service to speak of them in detail. It may be
noticed, however, that many of the most prominent of them refer to the
great question, “What is the relation between actual things and
general terms?” Perhaps in modern times, the actual things would be
more commonly taken as the point to start from; and men would begin by
considering how classes and universals are obtained from individuals.
But the schoolmen, founding their speculations on the received modes
of considering such subjects, to which both Aristotle and Plato had
contributed, travelled in the opposite direction, and endeavored to
discover how individuals were deduced from genera and
species;—what was “the Principle of Individuation.” This was
variously stated by different reasoners. Thus Bonaventura76 solves the difficulty by the aid of the
Aristotelian distinction of Matter and Form. The individual derives
from the Form the property of being something, and from the
Matter the property of being that particular thing. Duns
Scotus,77 the great adversary of Thomas Aquinas
in theology, placed the principle of Individuation in “a certain
determining positive entity,” which his school called Hæcceity
or thisness. “Thus an individual man is Peter, because his
humanity is combined with Petreity.” The force 234 of abstract terms is
a curious question, and some remarkable experiments in their use had
been made by the Latin Aristotelians before this time. In the same way
in which we talk of the quantity and quality of a thing,
they spoke of its quiddity.78
76 Deg. iv. 573.
77 Ib. iv. 523.
78 Deg. iv. 494.
We may consider the reign of mere disputation as fully established
at the time of which we are now speaking; and the only kind of
philosophy henceforth studied was one in which no sound physical
science had or could have a place. The wavering abstractions,
indistinct generalizations, and loose classifications of common
language, which we have already noted as the fountain of the physics
of the Greek Schools of philosophy, were also the only source from
which the Schoolmen of the middle ages drew their views, or rather
their arguments: and though these notional and verbal relations were
invested with a most complex and pedantic technicality, they did not,
on that account, become at all more precise as notions, or more likely
to lead to a single real truth. Instead of acquiring distinct ideas,
they multiplied abstract terms; instead of real generalizations, they
had recourse to verbal distinctions. The whole course of their
employments tended to make them, not only ignorant of physical truth,
but incapable of conceiving its nature.
Having thus taken upon themselves the task of raising and
discussing questions by means of abstract terms, verbal distinctions,
and logical rules alone, there was no tendency in their activity to
come to an end, as there was no progress. The same questions, the same
answers, the same difficulties, the same solutions, the same verbal
subtleties,—sought for, admired, cavilled at, abandoned,
reproduced, and again admired,—might recur without limit. John
of Salisbury79 observes of the Parisian teachers,
that, after several years’ absence, he found them not a step advanced,
and still employed in urging and parrying the same arguments; and
this, as Mr. Hallam remarks,80 “was equally
applicable to the period of centuries.” The same knots were tied and
235 untied; the
same clouds were formed and dissipated. The poet’s censure of “the
Sons of Aristotle,” is just as happily expressed:


  They stand
Locked up together hand in hand
Every one leads as he is led,
The same bare path they tread,
And dance like Fairies a fantastic round,
But neither change their motion nor their
ground.

79 He studied logic at Paris, at St.
Geneviève, and then left them. “Duodecennium mihi elapsum est diversis
studiis occupatum. Jucundum itaque visum est veteres quos reliqueram,
et quos adhuc Dialectica detinebat in monte, (Sanctæ Genovefæ)
revisere socios, conferre cum eis super ambiguitatibus pristinis; ut
nostrûm invicem collatione mutuâ commetiremur profectum. Inventi sunt,
qui fuerant, et ubi; neque enim ad palmam visi sunt processisse ad
quæstiones pristinis dirimendas, neque propositiunculam unam
adjecerant. Quibus urgebant stimulis eisdem et ipsi urgebantur,”
&c. Metalogicus, lib. ii. cap. 10.
80 Middle Ages, iii. 537.
It will therefore be unnecessary to go into any detail respecting
the history of the School Philosophy of the thirteenth, fourteenth,
and fifteenth centuries. We may suppose it to have been, during the
intermediate time, such as it was at first and at last. An occasion to
consider its later days will be brought before us by the course of our
subject. But, even during the most entire ascendency of the scholastic
doctrines, the elements of change were at work. While the doctors and
the philosophers received all the ostensible homage of men, a doctrine
and a philosophy of another kind were gradually forming: the practical
instincts of man, their impatience of tyranny, the progress of the
useful arts, the promises of alchemy, were all disposing men to reject
the authority and deny the pretensions of the received philosophical
creed. Two antagonist forms of opinion were in existence, which for
some time went on detached, and almost independent of each other; but,
finally, these came into conflict, at the time of Galileo; and the war
speedily extended to every part of civilized Europe.
3. Scholastic Physics.—It is difficult to give briefly
any appropriate examples of the nature of the Aristotelian physics
which are to be found in the works of this time. As the gravity of
bodies was one of the first subjects of dispute when the struggle of
the rival methods began, we may notice the mode in which it was
treated.81 “Zabarella maintains that the proximate
cause of the motion of elements is the form, in the
Aristotelian sense of the term: but to this sentence we,” says
Keckerman, “cannot agree; for in all other things the form is
the proximate cause, not of the act, but of the power or
faculty from which the act flows. Thus in man, the rational soul is
not the cause of the act of laughing, but of the risible faculty or
power.” Keckerman’s system was at one time a work of considerable
authority: it was published in 1614. By comparing and systematizing
what he finds in Aristotle, he is led to state his results in the form
of definitions 236
and theorems. Thus, “gravity is a motive quality, arising from cold,
density, and bulk, by which the elements are carried downwards.”
“Water is the lower, intermediate element, cold and moist.” The first
theorem concerning water is, “The moistness of the water is controlled
by its coldness, so that it is less than the moistness of the air;
though, according to the sense of the vulgar, water appears to moisten
more than air.” It is obvious that the two properties of fluids, to
have their parts easily moved, and to wet other bodies, are here
confounded. I may, as a concluding specimen of this kind, mention
those propositions or maxims concerning fluids, which were so firmly
established, that, when Boyle propounded the true mechanical
principles of fluid action, he was obliged to state his opinions as
“hydrostatical paradoxes.” These were,—that fluids do
not gravitate in proprio loco; that is, that water has no
gravity in or on water, since it is in its own place;—that air
has no gravity on water, since it is above water, which is its proper
place;—that earth in water tends to descend, since its place is
below water;—that the water rises in a pump or siphon, because
nature abhors a vacuum;—that some bodies have a positive levity
in others, as oil in water; and the like.
81 Keckerman, p. 1428.
4. Authority of Aristotle among the Schoolmen.—The
authority of Aristotle, and the practice of making him the text and
basis of the system, especially as it regarded physics, prevailed
during the period of which we speak. This authority was not, however,
without its fluctuations. Launoy has traced one part of its history in
a book On the various Fortune of Aristotle in the University of
Paris. The most material turns of this fortune depend on the
bearing which the works of Aristotle were supposed to have upon
theology. Several of Aristotle’s works, and more especially his
metaphysical writings, had been translated into Latin, and were
explained in the schools of the University of Paris, as early as the
beginning of the thirteenth century.82 At a council
held at Paris in 1209, they were prohibited, as having given occasion
to the heresy of Almeric (or Amauri), and because “they might give
occasion to other heresies not yet invented.” The Logic of Aristotle
recovered its credit some years after this, and was publicly taught in
the University of Paris in the year 1215; but the Natural Philosophy
and Metaphysics were prohibited by a decree of Gregory the Ninth, in
1231. The Emperor Frederic the Second employed a number of learned men
to translate into Latin, from the Greek and 237 Arabic, certain books of Aristotle, and
of other ancient sages; and we have a letter of Peter de Vineis, in
which they are recommended to the attention of the University of
Bologna: probably the same recommendation was addressed to other
Universities. Both Albertus Magnus and Thomas Aquinas wrote
commentaries on Aristotle’s works; and as this was done soon after the
decree of Gregory the Ninth, Launoy is much perplexed to reconcile the
fact with the orthodoxy of the two doctors. Campanella, who was one of
the first to cast off the authority of Aristotle, says, “We are by no
means to think that St. Thomas aristotelized; he only
expounded Aristotle, that he might correct his errors; and I should
conceive he did this with the license of the Pope.” This statement,
however, by no means gives a just view of the nature of Albertus’s and
Aquinas’s commentaries. Both have followed their author with profound
deference.83 For instance, Aquinas84 attempts to defend Aristotle’s
assertion, that if there were no resistance, a body would move through
a space in no time; and the same defence is given by Scotus.
82 Mosheim, iii. 157.
83 Deg. N. 475.
84 F. Piccolomini, ii. 835.
We may imagine the extent of authority and admiration which
Aristotle would attain, when thus countenanced, both by the powerful
and the learned. In universities, no degree could be taken without a
knowledge of the philosopher. In 1452, Cardinal Totaril established
this rule in the University of Paris.85 When Ramus, in
1543, published an attack upon Aristotle, it was repelled by the power
of the court, and the severity of the law. Francis the First published
an edict, in which he states that he had appointed certain judges, who
had been of opinion,86 “que le dit Ramus avoit été téméraire,
arrogant et impudent; et que parcequ’en son livre des animadversions
il reprenait Aristotle, estait évidemment connue et manifeste son
ignorance.” The books are then declared to be suppressed. It was often
a complaint of pious men, that theology was corrupted by the influence
of Aristotle and his commentators. Petrarch says,87 that one of the
Italian learned men conversing with him, after expressing much
contempt for the apostles and fathers, exclaimed, “Utinam tu Averroen
pati posses, ut videres quanto ille tuis his nugatoribus major
sit!”
85 Launoy, pp. 108, 128.
86 Launoy, p. 132.
87 Hallam, M. A. iii.
536.
When the revival of letters began to take place, and a number of
men of ardent and elegant minds, susceptible to the impressions of
beauty of style and dignity of thought, were brought into contact with
Greek literature, Plato had naturally greater charms for them. A 238 powerful school of
Platonists (not Neoplatonists) was formed in Italy, including some of
the principal scholars and men of genius of the time; as Picus of
Mirandula in the middle, Marsilius Ficinus at the end, of the
fifteenth century. At one time, it appeared as if the ascendency of
Aristotle was about to be overturned; but, in physics at least, his
authority passed unshaken through this trial. It was not by
disputation that Aristotle could be overthrown; and the Platonists
were not persons whose doctrines led them to use the only decisive
method in such cases, the observation and unfettered interpretation of
facts.
The history of their controversies, therefore, does not belong to
our design. For like reasons we do not here speak of other authors,
who opposed the scholastic philosophy on general theoretical grounds
of various kinds. Such examples of insurrection against the dogmatism
which we have been reviewing, are extremely interesting events in the
history of the philosophy of science. But, in the present work, we are
to confine ourselves to the history of science itself; in the hope
that we may thus be able, hereafter, to throw a steadier light upon
that philosophy by which the succession of stationary and progressive
periods, which we are here tracing, may be in some measure explained.
We are now to close our account of the stationary period, and to enter
upon the great subject of the progress of physical science in modern
times.
5. Subjects omitted. Civil Law, Medicine.—My object
has been to make my way, as rapidly as possible, to this period of
progress; and in doing this, I have had to pass over a long and barren
track, where almost all traces of the right road disappear. In
exploring this region, it is not without some difficulty that he who
is travelling with objects such as mine, continues a steady progress
in the proper direction; for many curious and attractive subjects of
research come in his way: he crosses the track of many a controversy,
which in its time divided the world of speculators, and of which the
results may be traced, even now, in the conduct of moral, or
political, or metaphysical discussions; or in the common associations
of thought, and forms of language. The wars of the Nominalists and
Realists; the disputes concerning the foundations of morals, and the
motives of human actions; the controversies concerning predestination,
free will, grace, and the many other points of metaphysical divinity;
the influence of theology and metaphysics upon each other, and upon
other subjects of human curiosity; the effects of opinion upon
politics, and of political condition upon opinion; the influence of
literature and philosophy 239 upon each other, and upon society; and
many other subjects;—might be well worth examination, if our
hope of success did not reside in pursuing, steadily and directly,
those inquiries in which we can look for a definite and certain reply.
We must even neglect two of the leading studies of those times, which
occupied much of men’s time and thoughts, and had a very great
influence on society; the one dealing with Notions, the other with
Things; the one employed about moral rules, the other about material
causes, but both for practical ends; I mean, the study of the Civil
Law, and of Medicine. The second of these studies will
hereafter come before us, as one of the principal occasions which led
to the cultivation of chemistry; but, in itself, its progress is of
too complex and indefinite a nature to be advantageously compared with
that of the more exact sciences. The Roman Law is held, by its
admirers, to be a system of deductive science, as exact as the
mathematical sciences themselves; and it may, therefore, be useful to
consider it, if we should, in the sequel, have to examine how far
there can exist an analogy between moral and physical science. But,
after a few more words on the middle ages, we must return to our task
of tracing the progress of the latter.
</div></body></text></TEI>