<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="67">CHAPTER VI.
Discovery of the Laws of Polarization.
IF the Extraordinary
Refraction of Iceland spar had appeared strange, another phenomenon
was soon noticed in the same 73 substance, which appeared stranger still,
and which in the sequel was found to be no less important. I speak of
the facts which were afterwards described under the term
Polarization. Huyghens was the discoverer of this class of
facts. At the end of the treatise which we have already quoted, he
says,42 “Before I quit the subject of this
crystal, I will add one other marvellous phenomenon, which I have
discovered since writing the above; for though hitherto I have not
been able to find out its cause, I will not, on that account, omit
pointing it out, that I may give occasion to others to examine it.” He
then states the phenomena; which are, that when two rhombohedrons of
Iceland spar are in parallel positions, a ray doubly refracted by the
first, is not further divided when it falls on the second: the
ordinarily refracted ray is ordinarily refracted only, and
the extraordinary ray is only extraordinarily refracted by the second
crystal, neither ray being doubly refracted. The same is still the
case, if the two crystals have their principal planes
parallel, though they themselves are not parallel. But if the
principal plane of the second crystal be perpendicular to that of the
first, the reverse of what has been described takes place; the
ordinarily refracted ray of the first crystal suffers, at the second,
extraordinary refraction only, and the extraordinary ray of
the first suffers ordinary refraction only at the second. Thus, in
each of these positions, the double refraction of each ray at the
second crystal is reduced to single refraction, though in a different
manner in the two cases. But in any other position of the crystals,
each ray, produced by the first, is doubly refracted by the second, so
as to produce four rays.
42 Tr. Opt. p. 252.
A step in the right conception of these phenomena was made by
Newton, in the second edition of his Opticks (1717). He
represented them as resulting from this;—that the rays of light
have “sides,” and that they undergo the ordinary or extraordinary
refraction, according as these sides are parallel to the principal
plane of the crystal, or at right angles to it (Query 26). In this
way, it is clear, that those rays which, in the first crystal, had
been selected for extraordinary refraction, because their sides were
perpendicular to the principal plane, would all suffer extraordinary
refraction at the second crystal for the same reason, if its principal
plane were parallel to that of the first; and would all suffer
ordinary refraction, if the principal plane of the second crystal were
perpendicular to that of the first, and 74 consequently parallel to the sides of the
refracted ray. This view of the subject includes some of the leading
features of the case, but still leaves several considerable
difficulties.
No material advance was made in the subject till it was taken up by
Malus,43 along with the other circumstances of
double refraction, about a hundred years afterwards. He verified what
had been observed by Huyghens and Newton, on the subject of the
variations which light thus exhibits; but he discovered that this
modification, in virtue of which light undergoes the ordinary, or the
extraordinary, refraction, according to the position of the plane of
the crystal, may be impressed upon it many other ways. One part of
this discovery was made accidentally.44 In 1808, Malus
happened to be observing the light of the setting sun, reflected from
the windows of the Luxembourg, through a rhombohedron of Iceland spar;
and he observed that in turning round the crystal, the two images
varied in their intensity. Neither of the images completely vanished,
because the light from the windows was not properly modified, or, to
use the term which Malus soon adopted, was not completely
polarized. The complete polarization of light by reflection
from glass, or any other transparent substance, was found to take
place at a certain definite angle, different for each substance. It
was found also that in all crystals in which double refraction
occurred, the separation of the refracted rays was accompanied by
polarization; the two rays, the ordinary and the extraordinary, being
always polarized oppositely, that is, in planes at right
angles to each other. The term poles, used by Malus, conveyed
nearly the same notion as the term sides which had been
employed by Newton, with the additional conception of a property which
appeared or disappeared according as the poles of the particles were
or were not in a certain direction; a property thus resembling the
polarity of magnetic bodies. When a spot of polarized light is
looked at through a transparent crystal of Iceland spar, each of the
two images produced by the double refraction varies in brightness as
the crystal is turned round. If, for the sake of example, we suppose
the crystal to be turned round in the direction of the points of the
compass, N, E, S, W, and if one image be brightest when the crystal
marks N and S, it will disappear when the crystal marks E and W: and
on the contrary, the second image will vanish when the crystal marks N
and S, 75 and will
be brightest when the crystal marks E and W. The first of these images
is polarized in the plane NS passing through the ray, and the
second in the plane EW, perpendicular to the other. And these
rays are oppositely polarized. It was further found that
whether the ray were polarized by reflection from glass, or from
water, or by double refraction, the modification of light so produced,
or the nature of the polarization, was identical in all these
cases;—that the alternatives of ordinary and extraordinary
refraction and non-refraction, were the same, by whatever crystal they
were tested, or in whatever manner the polarization had been impressed
upon the light; in short, that the property, when once acquired, was
independent of everything except the sides or poles of the ray;
and thus, in 1811, the term “polarization” was introduced.45
43 Malus, Th. de la Doub. Réf.
p. 296.
44 Arago, art. Polarization,
Supp. Enc. Brit.
45 Mém. Inst. 1810.
This being the state of the subject, it became an obvious question,
by what other means, and according to what laws, this property was
communicated. It was found that some crystals, instead of giving, by
double refraction, two images oppositely polarized, give a single
polarized image. This property was discovered in the agate by Sir D.
Brewster, and in tourmaline by M. Biot and Dr. Seebeck. The latter
mineral became, in consequence, a very convenient part of the
apparatus used in such observations. Various peculiarities bearing
upon this subject, were detected by different experimenters. It was in
a short time discovered, that light might be polarized by refraction,
as well as by reflection, at the surface of uncrystallized bodies, as
glass; the plane of polarization being perpendicular to the plane of
refraction; further, that when a portion of a ray of light was
polarized by reflection, a corresponding portion was polarized by
transmission, the planes of the two polarizations being at right
angles to each other. It was found also that the polarization which
was incomplete with a single plate, either by reflection or
refraction, might be made more and more complete by increasing the
number of plates.
Among an accumulation of phenomena like this, it is our business to
inquire what general laws were discovered. To make such discoveries
without possessing the general theory of the facts, required no
ordinary sagacity and good fortune. Yet several laws were detected at
this stage of the subject. Malus, in 1811, obtained the important
generalization that, whenever we obtain, by any means, a polarized ray
of light, we produce also another ray, polarized in a contrary 76 direction; thus when
reflection gives a polarized ray, the companion-ray is refracted
polarized oppositely, along with a quantity of unpolarized light. And
we must particularly notice Sir D. Brewster’s rule for the
polarizing angle of different bodies.
Malus46 had said that the angle of reflection
from transparent bodies which most completely polarizes the reflected
ray, does not follow any discoverable rule with regard to the order of
refractive or dispersive powers of the substances. Yet the rule was in
reality very simple. In 1815, Sir D. Brewster stated47 as the law, which in all cases
determines this angle, that “the index of refraction is the tangent of
the angle of polarization.” It follows from this, that the
polarization takes place when the reflected and refracted rays are at
right angles to each other. This simple and elegant rule has been
fully confirmed by all subsequent observations, as by those of MM.
Biot and Seebeck; and must be considered one of the happiest and most
important discoveries of the laws of phenomena in Optics.
46 Mém. Inst. 1810.
47 Phil. Trans. 1815.
The rule for polarization by one reflection being thus discovered,
tentative formulæ were proposed by Sir D. Brewster and M. Biot, for
the cases in which several reflections or refractions take place.
Fresnel also in 1817 and 1818, traced the effect of reflection in
modifying the direction of polarization, which Malus had done
inaccurately in 1810. But the complexity of the subject made all such
attempts extremely precarious, till the theory of the phenomena was
understood, a period which now comes under notice. The laws which we
have spoken of were important materials for the establishment of the
theory; but in the mean time, its progress at first had been more
forwarded by some other classes of facts, of a different kind, and of
a longer standing notoriety, to which we must now turn our
attention.
</div></body></text></TEI>