<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="1">

BOOK I.

OF IDEAS IN GENERAL.

CHAPTER I.
Of the Fundamental Antithesis of Philosophy.

Sect. 1.—Thoughts and Things.
IN order that we may do something towards determining the
nature and conditions of human knowledge, (which I have
already stated as the purpose of this work,) I shall have to
refer to an antithesis or opposition, which is familiar and
generally recognized, and in which the distinction of the
things opposed to each other is commonly considered very
clear and plain. I shall have to attempt to make this
opposition sharper and stronger than it is usually
conceived, and yet to shew that the distinction is far from
being so clear and definite as it is usually assumed to be:
I shall have to point the contrast, yet shew that the things
which are contrasted cannot be separated:—I must explain
that the antithesis is constant and essential, but yet that
there is no fixed and permanent line dividing its members. I
may thus appear, in different parts of my discussion, to be
proceeding in opposite directions, but I hope that the
reader who gives me a patient attention will see that both
steps lead to the point of view to which I wish to lead him.
The antithesis or opposition of which I speak is denoted,
with various modifications, by various pairs of terms: I
shall endeavour to shew the connexion of these different
modes of expression, and I will begin with that form which
is the simplest and most idiomatic. 24
The simplest and most idiomatic expression of the antithesis
to which I refer is that in which we oppose to each other
Things and Thoughts. The opposition is familiar and plain.
Our thoughts are something which belongs to ourselves;
something which takes place within us; they are what we
think; they are actions of our minds. Things, on the
contrary, are something different from ourselves and
independent of us; something which is without us; they
are; we see them, touch them, and thus know that
they exist; but we do not make them by seeing or touching
them, as we make our Thoughts by thinking them; we
are passive, and Things act upon our organs of
perception.
Now what I wish especially to remark is this: that in all
human Knowledge both Thoughts and Things are concerned. In
every part of my knowledge there must be some thing
about which I know, and an internal act of me who know.
Thus, to take simple yet definite parts of our knowledge, if
I know that a solar year consists of 365 days, or a lunar
month of 30 days, I know something about the sun or the
moon; namely, that those objects perform certain revolutions
and go through certain changes, in those numbers of days;
but I count such numbers and conceive such revolutions and
changes by acts of my own thoughts. And both these elements
of my knowledge are indispensable. If there were not such
external Things as the sun and the moon I could not have any
knowledge of the progress of time as marked by them. And
however regular were the motions of the sun and moon, if I
could not count their appearances and combine their changes
into a cycle, or if I could not understand this when done by
other men, I could not know anything about a year or a
month. In the former case I might be conceived as a human
being, possessing the human powers of thinking and
reckoning, but kept in a dark world with nothing to mark the
progress of existence. The latter is the case of brute
animals, which see the sun and moon, but do not know how
many days make a month or a year, because they have not
human powers of thinking and reckoning. 25
The two elements which are essential to our knowledge in the
above cases, are necessary to human knowledge in all cases.
In all cases, Knowledge implies a combination of Thoughts
and Things. Without this combination, it would not be
Knowledge. Without Thoughts, there could be no connexion;
without Things, there could be no reality. Thoughts and
Things are so intimately combined in our Knowledge, that we
do not look upon them as distinct. One single act of the
mind involves them both; and their contrast disappears in
their union.
But though Knowledge requires the union of these two
elements, Philosophy requires the separation of them, in
order that the nature and structure of Knowledge may be
seen. Therefore I begin by considering this separation. And
I now proceed to speak of another way of looking at the
antithesis of which I have spoken; and which I may, for the
reasons which I have just mentioned, call the Fundamental
Antithesis of Philosophy.
Sect. 2.—Necessary and Experiential Truths.
Most persons are familiar with the distinction of
necessary and contingent truths. The former
kind are Truths which cannot but be true; as that 19 and 11
make 30;—that parallelograms upon the same base and between
the same parallels are equal;—that all the angles in the
same segment of a circle are equal. The latter are Truths
which it happens (contingit) are true; but
which, for anything which we can see, might have been
otherwise; as that a lunar month contains 30 days, or that
the stars revolve in circles round the pole. The latter kind
of Truths are learnt by experience, and hence we may call
them Truths of Experience, or, for the sake of
convenience, Experiential Truths, in contrast with
Necessary Truths.
Geometrical propositions are the most manifest examples of
Necessary Truths. All persons who have read and understood
the elements of geometry, know that the propositions above
stated (that parallelograms 26 upon the same base and
between the same parallels are equal; that all the angles in
the same segment of a circle are equal,) are necessarily
true; not only they are true, but they must be
true. The meaning of the terms being understood, and the
proof being gone through, the truth of the propositions must
be assented to. We learn these propositions to be true by
demonstrations deduced from definitions and axioms; and when
we have thus learnt them, we see that they could not be
otherwise. In the same manner, the truths which concern
numbers are necessary truths: 19 and 11 not only do make 30,
but must make that number, and cannot make anything
else. In the same manner, it is a necessary truth that half
the sum of two numbers added to half their difference is
equal to the greater number.
It is easy to find examples of Experiential Truths;—propositions which we know to be true, but know by
experience only. We know, in this way, that salt will
dissolve in water; that plants cannot live without light;—in short, we know in this way all that we do know in
chemistry, physiology, and the material sciences in general.
I take the Sciences as my examples of human
knowledge, rather than the common truths of daily life, or
moral or political truths; because, though the latter are
more generally interesting, the former are much more
definite and certain, and therefore better starting-points
for our speculations, as I have already said. And we may
take elementary astronomical truths as the most familiar
examples of Experiential Truths in the domain of science.
With these examples, the distinction of Necessary and
Experiential Truths is, I hope, clear. The former kind, we
see to be true by thinking about them, and see that they
could not be otherwise. The latter kind, men could never
have discovered to be true without looking at them; and
having so discovered them, still no one will pretend to say
they might not have been otherwise. For aught we can see,
the astronomical truths which express the motions and
periods of the sun, moon and stars, might have been
otherwise. If we had been placed in another part of the
solar system, our 27 experiential truths respecting days,
years, and the motions of the heavenly bodies, would have
been other than they are, as we know from astronomy itself.
It is evident that this distinction of Necessary and
Experiential Truths involves the same antithesis which we
have already considered;—the antithesis of Thoughts and
Things. Necessary Truths are derived from our own Thoughts:
Experiential truths are derived from our observation of
Things about us. The opposition of Necessary and
Experiential Truths is another aspect of the Fundamental
Antithesis of Philosophy.
Sect. 3.—Deduction and Induction.
I have already stated that geometrical truths are
established by demonstrations deduced from
definitions and axioms. The term Deduction is
specially applied to such a course of demonstration of
truths from definitions and axioms. In the case of the
parallelograms upon the same base and between the same
parallels, we prove certain triangles to be equal, by
supposing them placed so that their two bases have the same
extremities; and hence, referring to an Axiom respecting
straight lines, we infer that the bases coincide. We combine
these equal triangles with other equal spaces, and in this
way make up both the one and the other of the
parallelograms, in such a manner as to shew that they are
equal. In this manner, going on step by step, deducing the
equality of the triangles from the axiom, and the equality
of the parallelograms from that of the triangles, we travel
to the conclusion. And this process of successive deduction
is the scheme of all geometrical proof. We begin with
Definitions of the notions which we reason about, and with
Axioms, or self-evident truths, respecting these notions;
and we get, by reasoning from these, other truths which are
demonstratively evident; and from these truths again, others
of the same kind, and so on. We begin with our own Thoughts,
which supply us with Axioms to start from; and we reason
from these, till we come to propositions 28 which are
applicable to the Things about us; as for instance, the
propositions respecting circles and spheres applicable to
the motions of the heavenly bodies. This is
Deduction, or Deductive Reasoning.
Experiential truths are acquired in a very different way. In
order to obtain such truths, we begin with Things. In order
to learn how many days there are in a year, or in a lunar
month, we must begin by observing the sun and the moon. We
must observe their changes day by day, and try to make the
cycle of change fit into some notion of number which we
supply from our own Thoughts. We shall find that a cycle of
30 days nearly will fit the changes of phase of the
moon;—that a cycle of 365 days nearly will fit the changes
of daily motion of the sun. Or, to go on to experiential
truths of which the discovery comes within the limits of the
history of science—we shall find (as Hipparchus found) that
the unequal motion of the sun among the stars, such as
observation shews it to be, may be fitly represented by the
notion of an eccentric;—a circle in which the sun
has an equable annual motion, the spectator not being in the
center of the circle. Again, in the same manner, at a later
period, Kepler started from more exact observations of the
sun, and compared them with a supposed motion in a certain
ellipse; and was able to shew that, not a circle about an
eccentric point, but an ellipse, supplied the mode of
conception which truly agreed with the motion of the sun
about the earth; or rather, as Copernicus had already shewn,
of the earth about the sun. In such cases, in which truths
are obtained by beginning from observation of external
things and by finding some notion with which the Things, as
observed, agree, the truths are said to be obtained by
Induction. The process is an Inductive Process.
The contrast of the Deductive and Inductive process is
obvious. In the former, we proceed at each step from general
truths to particular applications of them; in the latter,
from particular observations to a general truth which
includes them. In the former case we may be said to reason
downwards, in the latter case, 29 upwards;
for general notions are conceived as standing above
particulars. Necessary truths are proved, like arithmetical
sums, by adding together the portions of which they consist.
An inductive truth is proved, like the guess which answers a
riddle, by its agreeing with the facts described.
Demonstration is irresistible in its effect on the belief,
but does not produce surprize, because all the steps to the
conclusion are exhibited, before we arrive at the
conclusion. Inductive inference is not demonstrative, but it
is often more striking than demonstrative reasoning, because
the intermediate links between the particulars and the
inference are not shewn. Deductive truths are the results of
relations among our own Thoughts. Inductive truths are
relations which we discern among existing Things; and thus,
this opposition of Deduction and Induction is again an
aspect of the Fundamental Antithesis already spoken of.
Sect. 4.—Theories and Facts.
General experiential Truths, such as we have just spoken of,
are called Theories, and the particular observations
from which they are collected, and which they include and
explain, are called Facts. Thus Hipparchus’s
doctrine, that the sun moves in an eccentric about the
earth, is his Theory of the Sun, or the Eccentric
Theory. The doctrine of Kepler, that the Earth moves in
an Ellipse about the Sun, is Kepler’s Theory of the
Earth, the Elliptical Theory. Newton’s doctrine that this
elliptical motion of the Earth about the Sun is produced and
governed by the Sun’s attraction upon the Earth, is the
Newtonian theory, the Theory of Attraction.
Each of these Theories was accepted, because it included,
connected and explained the Facts; the Facts being,
in the two former cases, the motions of the Sun as observed;
and in the other case, the elliptical motion of the Earth as
known by Kepler’s Theory. This antithesis of Theory
and Fact is included in what has just been said of
Inductive Propositions. A Theory is an Inductive
Proposition, and the Facts 30 are the particular
observations from which, as I have said, such Propositions
are inferred by Induction. The Antithesis of Theory and Fact
implies the fundamental Antithesis of Thoughts and Things;
for a Theory (that is, a true Theory) may be described as a
Thought which is contemplated distinct from Things and seen
to agree with them; while a Fact is a combination of our
Thoughts with Things in so complete agreement that we do not
regard them as separate.
Thus the antithesis of Theory and Fact involves the
antithesis of Thoughts and Things, but is not identical with
it. Facts involve Thoughts, for we know Facts only by
thinking about them. The Fact that the year consists of 365
days; the Fact that the month consists of 30 days, cannot be
known to us, except we have the Thoughts of Time, Number and
Recurrence. But these Thoughts are so familiar, that we have
the fact in our mind as a simple Thing without attending to
the Thought which it involves. When we mould our Thoughts
into a Theory, we consider the thought as distinct from the
Facts; but yet, though distinct, not independent of them;
for it is a true Theory, only by including and agreeing with
the Facts.
Sect. 5.—Ideas and Sensations.
We have just seen that the antithesis of Theory and Fact,
although it involves the antithesis of Thoughts and Things,
is not identical with it. There are other modes of
expression also, which involve the same Fundamental
Antithesis, more or less modified. Of these, the pair of
words which in their relations appear to separate the
members of the antithesis most distinctly are Ideas and
Sensations. We see and hear and touch external things, and
thus perceive them by our senses; but in perceiving them, we
connect the impressions of sense according to relations of
space, time, number, likeness, cause, &c. Now some at least
of these kinds of connexion, as space, time, number, may be
contemplated distinct from the things to which they are
applied; and so contemplated, I term them Ideas. And
31 the other element, the impressions upon our senses
which they connect, are called Sensations.
I term space, time, cause, &c., Ideas, because they
are general relations among our sensations, apprehended by
an act of the mind, not by the senses simply. These
relations involve something beyond what the senses alone
could furnish. By the sense of sight we see various shades
and colours and shapes before us, but the outlines by which
they are separated into distinct objects of definite forms,
are the work of the mind itself. And again, when we conceive
visible things, not only as surfaces of a certain form, but
as solid bodies, placed at various distances in space, we
again exert an act of the mind upon them. When we see a body
move, we see it move in a path or orbit, but this orbit is
not itself seen; it is constructed by the mind. In like
manner when we see the motions of a needle towards a magnet,
we do not see the attraction or force which produces the
effects; but we infer the force, by having in our minds the
Idea of Cause. Such acts of thought, such Ideas,
enter into our perceptions of external things.
But though our perceptions of external things involve some
act of the mind, they must involve something else besides an
act of the mind. If we must exercise an act of thought in
order to see force exerted, or orbits described by bodies in
motion, or even in order to see bodies existing in space,
and to distinguish one kind of object from another, still
the act of thought alone does not make the Bodies. There
must be something besides, on which the thought is exerted.
A colour, a form, a sound, are not produced by the mind,
however they may be moulded, combined, and interpreted by
our mental acts. A philosophical poet has spoken of</div></body></text></TEI>