<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="21">CHAPTER XIX.
It was thus that I spurred myself to persist in the path
upon which I had entered. Having remained some time
at Dresden, flattering myself with the hope that Charles
might yet join me before I quitted that city, I began to
think of once more turning my steps towards the residence
of my family. This was no cheerful thought; but upon
what was I to determine? I had a wife whom I ardently
loved, and three daughters the darlings of my heart. Because
I had lost a beloved son was I to estrange myself
from these? I already felt most painfully the detachment
and widowhood to which I was reduced, and I clung with
imperious affection to what remained of my race. The
meeting I purposed must be a melancholy one; but, in the
sorrows of the heart there is a purer and nobler gratification
than in the most tumultuous pleasures where affection
is silent. I looked forward indeed to scenes of endless
variety and attraction, but in the mean time what seemed
first to demand my attention was the beloved circle I had
left behind in the city of Constance.
I retraced, upon the present occasion, the route I had
lately pursued with my son. How different were now my
sensations! My heart was then indeed painfully impressed
with the variance and dissolution of confidence that had
arisen between me and his mother. It was perhaps principally
for the sake of banishing this impression that I had
had recourse to the splendour of equipage and attendance
which was first assumed upon the journey from Constance
to Dresden. Nor, frivolous as this expedient may appear
in the unattractive dispassionateness of narrative, had it
been by any means weak of effect at the time it was employed.
When Charles was once mounted on his proud
and impatient steed, and decorated in rich and costly attire,
I felt, as it were, the sluggishness of my imagination roused;
I surveyed his shape and his countenance with inexpressible
complacence; and already anticipated the period when he
was to become the favourite of his sovereign and his country’s[202]
pride. Now I returned with the same retinue; but
the place that had been occupied by my son was empty. I
sought him with frantic and restless gaze; I figured him
to my disturbed and furious imagination, till the sensations
and phantoms of my brain became intolerable; I raved
and imprecated curses on myself. I endeavoured to divert
my thoughts by observing the scenes that passed before me.
They talked to me of Charles; they had been pointed out
by each to each, and had been the subject of our mutual
comment. Though Charles was endowed with a high relish
for the beauties of nature, and, in our little retreat on the
borders of the lake, had lived in the midst of them, he had
seen little of the variety of her features; and the journey
we made through the heart of Germany had furnished him
with continual food for admiration and delight. Nor did
the scenes I beheld merely remind me of the sensations
they produced in Charles; they led me through a wider
field. I recollected long conversations and digressive excursions
which had been started by the impression they
made. I recollected many passages and occurrences to
which they had not the slightest reference, but which,
having arisen while they constituted the visible scene, were
forcibly revived by its re-appearance. Thus, from various
causes, my lost and lamented son was not a moment out of
my thoughts during the journey. While I continued at
Dresden, I seemed daily to expect his return; but no
sooner did I quit that city than despair took possession of
my heart.
Thus, anxious and distressed, I arrived at Prague, and
soon after at Ratisbon. I travelled slowly, because, though
I was desirous of returning to Constance, I anticipated my
arrival there with little complacence. As I drew nearer to
my family, I felt more distinctly the impossibility of presenting
myself before them, without first endeavouring to
take off the shock they would sustain at seeing me return
without my son. I therefore resolved to send forward a
servant from Ratisbon, whom I directed to make all practicable
speed, as I designed to wait for an answer he should
bring me at the city of Munich. To attempt to write to
Marguerite on this subject was a severe trial to me. The[203]
whole however that I proposed to myself was, to remove
the surprise which would be occasioned by seeing me alone,
and to anticipate questions that it would be impossible for
me to hear without anguish of mind and perturbation of
countenance. I therefore took care to express myself in
such terms as should lead Marguerite to believe that I had
voluntarily left her son in Saxony, and that in no very long
time he would rejoin his family. I trusted to subsequent
events to unfold the painful catastrophe, and could not prevail
on myself to shock her maternal feelings so much as I
must necessarily do, if I informed her of the whole at once.
Charles had not been mentioned but in ordinary terms and
the accustomed language of affection, in the letters I had
recently received from Constance; and I was therefore convinced
that he had neither gone to that place, nor had
conveyed thither any account of his proceedings.
The answer I received from Marguerite by my messenger
was as follows:—
“Your absence has been long and critical, and the welfare
of your daughters seems to require that we should rejoin
each other as speedily as may be. Whether we should
meet here or at any other place you must determine. It
is, however, right I should inform you that, during your
absence, rumour has been busy with your reputation. What
the extent or importance of the ill reports circulated of you
may be, I am scarcely competent to judge. We have lived
in uniform privacy, and it is natural to suppose that the
portion of censure that has reached us is but a small part
of what really exists. The mode in which you have proceeded,
and the extraordinary figure you have made in a
progress through Germany, have given weight to these insinuations.
But it is not my intention to comment on
what you have done.
“You appear to design that I should understand you
have left my son behind you in Saxony. Poor Charles! I
had a letter from him three weeks ago, in which he informs
me of what has happened, and apologises in the most pathetic
terms for any seeming want of regard to me in his
conduct, at the very moment that his heart bleeds for my
fate. I did not think it necessary to communicate this circumstance[204]
to you. I have done with complaining. Now
that I have fallen into the worst and most unlooked-for
misfortunes, I have a gratification that I do not choose to
part with, in shutting up my sorrows in my own breast.
“Oh, Charles! my son, my idol! What is become of
you? For what calamities are you reserved? He tells me
it is necessary that I should never see or hear of him again.
Never—I—his mother!—Reginald, there are some wounds
that we may endeavour to forgive; but they leave a sentiment
in the heart, the demonstrations of which may perhaps
be restrained, but which it is not in nature wholly to
subdue. If I did but know where to find or to write to
my poor boy, I would take my girls with me, and partake
his honest and honourable poverty, and never again join
the shadow of him who was my husband. Forgive me,
Reginald! I did not intend to say this. If I should prove
unable to control the impatience of my grief, do not inflict
the punishment of my offence on your innocent daughters!
“As to your fiction of voluntarily leaving him behind
for further improvement, it corresponds with every thing
you have lately attempted to make me believe. I no longer
expect truth from you. For seventeen years I had a husband.
Well, well! I ought not perhaps to repine. I have
had my share of the happiness which the present life is
calculated to afford.
“Reginald! I have not long to live. When I tell you
this, I am not giving way to melancholy presentiment. I
will exert myself for the benefit of my girls. They will
have a grievous loss in me; and for their sake I will live
as long as I can. But I feel that you have struck me to
the heart. My nights are sleepless; my flesh is wasted;
my appetite is entirely gone. You will presently be able
to judge whether I am deceiving myself. The prospect
for these poor creatures, who are at present all my care, is
a dismal one. I know not for what they are reserved; but
I can hope for nothing good. When I am dead, remember,
and be a father to them. I ask nothing for myself; I have
no longer any concern with life; but, if my dying request
can have weight with you, make up to them the duty you[205]
have broken to me. By all out past loves, by the cordiality
and confidence in which we have so long lived, by the
singleness and sincerity of our affection, by the pure delights,
so seldom experienced in married life, that have
attended our union, I conjure you listen to me and obey
me in this.”
If I were deeply distressed for the loss of my son, if I
looked forward with a mingled sensation of eagerness and
alarm to the approaching interview with my family, it may
easily be imagined that this letter formed a heavy addition
to my mental anguish. I confess I thought it a cruel one.
Marguerite might well suppose, that the departure of Charles
was a circumstance I must strongly feel; and she should
not have thus aggravated the recent wounds of paternal
grief. Some allowance, however, was to be made for a
mother. When we are ourselves racked with intolerable
pain, that certainly is not the time at which we can rationally
be expected to exert the nicest and most vigilant consideration
for another. Add to which, she was innocent
of the calamities she suffered, and could not but know that
I was their sole author. But, whatever may be decided as
to the propriety of the letter, its effect upon my mind was
eminently salutary. I instantly determined on the conduct
it became me to pursue.
I lost not a moment. From Dresden to Munich I had
advanced with slow and unwilling steps; from Munich to
Constance I proceeded as rapidly as the modes of travelling
and the nature of the roads would permit. I left my retinue
at the gates of the town, and flew instantly to the
apartments of my family. I hastened up stairs, and, as I
entered the sitting-room, I saw the first and most exemplary
of matrons surrounded by her blooming daughters. I instantly
perceived a great alteration in her appearance. Her
look was dejected; her form emaciated; her countenance
sickly and pale. She lifted up her eyes as I entered, but
immediately dropped them again, without any discernible
expression, either of congratulation or resentment. I embraced
my children with undescribable emotion; I said
within myself, the love and affection I had reserved for
Charles shall be divided among you, and added to the share[206]
you each possess of my heart! Having saluted them in
turn, I addressed myself to Marguerite, telling her that I
must have some conversation with her instantly. My manner
was earnest: she led the way into another apartment.
I felt my heart overflowing at my tongue.
“I am come to you,” cried I, “a repenting prodigal.
Take me and mould me at your pleasure!”
She looked up. She was struck with the honest fervour
of my expression. She answered in almost forgotten terms,
and with a peculiar fulness of meaning, “My husband!”—It
seemed as if the best years and the best emotions of
our life were suddenly renewed.
“Most adorable of women!” I continued: “do you
think I can bear that you should die, and I your murderer?
No man in any age or climate of the world ever owed so
much to a human creature as I owe to you; no woman was
ever so ardently loved! no woman ever so much deserved
to be loved! If you were to die, I should never know
peace again. If you were to die the victim of any miscalculation
of mine, I should be the blackest of criminals!”
“Reginald!” replied she, “I am afraid I have been
wrong. I am afraid I have written harshly to you. You
have a feeling heart, and I have been too severe. Forgive
me! it was the effect of love. Affection cannot view with
a tranquil eye the faults of the object beloved.”
“Let them be forgotten! Let the last six months be
blotted from our memory, be as though they had never
existed!”
She looked at me. Her look seemed to say, though she
would not give the sentiment words, that can never be; the
loss of Charles, and certain other calamities of that period,
are irretrievable!
“I resign myself into your hands! I have been guilty;
I have had secrets; meditations engendered and shut up in
my own bosom; but it shall be so no more! The tide of
affection kept back from its natural channel, now flows with
double impetuousness. Never did I love you, not when
you first came a virgin to my arms, not on the banks of
the Garonne, not in the cottage of the lake, so fervently,
so entirely, as I love you now! Be my director; do with[207]
me as you please! I have never been either wise or virtuous
but when I have been implicitly guided by you!
“I have wealth; I am forbidden by the most solemn obligations
to discover the source of that wealth. This only
I may not communicate; in all things else govern me despotically!
Shall I resign it all? Shall I return to the
cottage of the lake? Shall I go, a houseless and helpless
wanderer, to the farthest quarter of the globe? Speak the
word only, and it shall be done! I prefer your affection,
your cordial regard, in the most obscure and meanest retreat,
to all that wealth can purchase or kings can give!”
“Reginald, I thank you! I acknowledge in your present
language and earnestness the object of my first and
only love. This return to your true character gives me all
the pleasure I am now capable of receiving. But it is too
late My son is lost; that cannot be retrieved. Your reputation
is blasted; I am sorry you are returned hither;
Constance is in arms against you, and I will not answer for
the consequence. For myself; I grieve to tell you so; I
am ashamed of my weakness; but—my heart is broken!
I loved you so entirely, that I was not able to bear any
suspension of our confidence. I had passed with you through
all other misfortunes, and the firmness of my temper was
not shaken. For this one misfortune, that seemed the entire
dissolution of our attachment, I was not prepared. I
feel, every morning as I rise, the warnings of my decease.
My nights are sleepless; my appetite is gone from me.”
“Oh, Marguerite, talk not thus; distract me not with
the most fatal of images! Our confidence shall return;
all the causes of your malady shall be removed! With the
causes, the symptoms, depend on it, will disappear. Your
youth, your tranquillity, your happiness, shall be renewed!
Oh, no, you shall not die! We will yet live to love and
peace!”
“Flatter not yourself with vain hopes, my love! I feel
something wrong within me, which is rapidly wearing my
body to decay. Reconcile your mind to what very soon
must happen! Prepare yourself for being the only parent
to your remaining offspring! I have composed my spirit,
and calmly wait my fate. You have now administered to[208]
me the only consolation I aspired to, by this return to your
true character, which affords me a sanguine hope that you
will faithfully discharge the duty to your offspring, which,
when I am gone, will be doubly urgent on you.”
I was grieved to see that the mind of Marguerite was so
deeply impressed with the notion that she had but a short
time to live. I could not bear to imagine for a moment
that her prognostic was just. The thought seemed capable
of driving me to distraction. I however conceived that
the best thing that could be done for the present, was to
turn the conversation to some other topic.
“Well, well, my love!” I answered. “There are some
things that are immediately pressing. Direct me, direct a
husband so amply convinced of your discretion, what I am
to do at present! Shall I instantly annihilate all that has
made this unfortunate breach between us; shall I resign
my wealth, from whatever source derived? Whither shall
we go? Shall we return to the cottage of the lake? Shall
we retreat into some distant part of the world?”
“How can you expect me,” said Marguerite, faintly
smiling, “to advise you respecting the disposal of a wealth,
of the amount of which I am uninformed, and the source
of which is invisible? But I guess your secret. The
stranger who died your guest was in possession of the philosopher’s
stone, and he has bequeathed to you his discovery.
I have heard of this art, though I confess I was not
much inclined to credit it. I do not ask you to confirm my
conjecture: I do not wish that you should violate my engagements
into which you have entered. But, upon putting
circumstances together, which I have been inevitably
compelled to do, I apprehend it can be nothing else. I am
astonished that a conjecture so obvious should have offered
itself to my mind so late.
“If your wealth is of any other nature, ample as it apparently
is, it is a natural question to ask, to whom is it to
be resigned? The ordinary wealth of the world is something
real and substantial, and can neither be created nor
dissipated with a breath. But if your wealth be of the
kind I have named, let me ask, is it possible to resign it?
A secret is a thing with which we may choose whether we[209]
will become acquainted; but, once known, we cannot become
unacquainted with it at pleasure. Your wealth, upon
my supposition, will always be at your beck; and it is
perhaps beyond the strength of human nature to refuse,
under some circumstances, at least in some emergencies, to
use the wealth which is within our reach.
“It has been our mutual misfortune that such an engine
has been put into your hands. It has been your fault to
make an indiscreet use of it. Gladly would I return to the
tranquil and unsuspected poverty of the cottage of the lake.
But that is impossible. You have lost your son; you have
lost your honest fame; the life of your Marguerite is undermined
and perishing. If it were possible for us to
return to our former situation and our former peace, still,
my Reginald! forgive me if I say, I doubt the inflexibleness
of your resolution. The gift of unbounded wealth, if
you possess it, and, with wealth, apparently at least, distinction
and greatness, is too powerful a temptation. Nor,
though I should trust your resistance, could I be pleased in
a husband with the possession of these extraordinary powers.
It sets too great a distance between the parties. It destroys
that communion of spirit which is the soul of the marriage-tie.
A consort should be a human being and an equal. But
to this equality and simple humanity it is no longer in your
power to return.
“Circumstanced then as we now are, the marriage union,
you must allow me to say, irreparably dissolved, your son
lost, your fair fame destroyed, your orphan daughters to be
provided for, I know not if I should advise you to forget
the prerogative that has been bought for you at so dreadful
a price. Beside, if I am not mistaken, there are great trials
in reserve for you. I am afraid your present situation is
extremely critical. I am afraid the suspicions you have
excited will cost you dear. At all events I believe it to
be but a necessary precaution that we should fly from
Constance. I have nothing therefore to recommend to
you on the subject of wealth, but discretion. I shall not
long live to be your adviser. I shall always regard the
donation you have received, you cannot wonder that I
should so regard it, as one of the most fearful calamities to[210]
which a human being can be exposed. If you had used
your prerogative with discretion, you might perhaps,
though I confess I do not see how, have escaped the obloquy
of the world. Into your domestic scene, where the interest
is more lively, and the watch upon you more unremitted, it
must have introduced alienation and distrust. As it is,
I see you surrounded with dangers of a thousand denominations.
Police has its eyes upon you; superstition will
regard you as the familiar of demons; avarice will turn
upon you a regard of jealousy and insatiable appetite. If I
could recover from the weakness that at present besets me,
and continue to live, I foresee more and severer trials, both
at home and abroad, than any I have yet sustained; and I
am almost thankful to that Providence which has decreed
to take me away from the evil to come.
“One thing further let me add. I will speak it, not in
the character of a censor, but a friend. It must ever be
right and useful, that a man should be undeceived in any
erroneous estimate he may make of himself. I have loved
you much; I found in you many good qualities; my imagination
decorated you in the virtues that you had not; but
you have removed the veil. An adept and an alchemist is
a low character. When I married you, I supposed myself
united to a nobleman, a knight, and a soldier, a man who
would have revolted with disdain from every thing that was
poor-spirited and base. I lived with you long and happily.
I saw faults; I saw imbecilities. I did not see them with
indifference; but I endeavoured, and with a degree of success,
to forget and to forgive them; they did not contaminate
and corrupt the vitals of honour. At length you have
completely reversed the scene. For a soldier you present
me with a projector and a chemist, a cold-blooded mortal,
raking in the ashes of a crucible for a selfish and solitary
advantage. Here is an end of all genuine dignity, and the
truest generosity of soul. You cannot be ingenuous; for
all your dealings are secrecy and darkness. You cannot
have a friend; for the mortal lives not that can sympathise
with your thoughts and emotions. A generous spirit,
Reginald, delights to live upon equal terms with his associates
and fellows. He would disdain, when offered to him,
excessive and clandestine advantages. Equality is the soul[211]
of real and cordial society. A man of rank indeed does
not live upon equal terms with the whole of his species;
but his heart also can exult, for he has his equals. How
unhappy the wretch, the monster rather let me say, who
is without an equal; who looks through the world, and
in the world cannot find a brother; who is endowed
with attributes which no living being participates with
him; and who is therefore cut off for ever from all cordiality
and confidence, can never unbend himself, but
lives the solitary, joyless tenant of a prison, the materials of
which are emeralds and rubies! How unhappy this wretch!
How weak and ignoble the man that voluntarily accepts
these laws of existence!”
In the advice of Marguerite I saw that sound wisdom
and discernment, by which in all the periods of our connection
she had been so eminently characterised. With her
views of the future I was not disposed to accord. I regarded
them as obscured and discoloured by the unfortunate state
of her health. I could not indeed refuse to believe that
the prerogative I had received had been the parent of much
domestic unhappiness. Willingly would I have resigned
all that I had derived from the stranger, to be replaced in
the situation in which his pernicious legacies had found me.
He had robbed me of my son; he had destroyed my domestic
peace; he had undermined the tranquillity and
health of the partner of my life. These calamities pressed
with a heavy and intolerable weight at my heart. But, if,
as Marguerite affirmed, they were irretrievable, or if they
could once be removed, and the domestic advantages I had
heretofore enjoyed be restored, I was not disposed to fear
those external mischiefs which Marguerite so feelingly predicted.
I could not believe that I should have such a
league of foreign enemies to encounter, nor could I easily
image to myself any external evils which it was not in the
power of gold to remedy. These considerations I urged to
my beloved partner, and by enforcing them endeavoured to
remove those gloomy apprehensions, from the prevalence of
which I feared much injury to her health. There was
another circumstance I was led particularly to insist on; I
mean the nature of the secret intrusted to me.
[212]
“I admire your discernment and ingenuity, Marguerite,”
said I, “in your conjecture respecting the source of my
wealth. I admire your delicacy in not pressing me to decide
upon the truth of your conjecture. This only I must
be permitted to say on that subject. It is a secret; and you
will perceive that the same reasons, whatever they are,
which make that secret obligatory on me, require that it
should be respected by you. The same evils that my own
indiscretion may draw on me, I shall be equally exposed to
by any error or miscalculation of yours. I have therefore
most earnestly and solemnly to conjure you, whatever misfortunes
may hereafter befall me, in whatever perilous situation
I may be involved, that you will never utter a syllable
on this subject; and that, as I am the selected depository of
this secret, and alone know with certainty what is its nature,
you will trust our prosperity in this point to me.”—Marguerite
engaged to conduct herself as I desired.
The night which succeeded this explanation, was particularly
soothing and grateful to me. I was relieved from
a great and oppressive burthen. I was conscious of that
particular species of pleasure which arises from the resolute
discharge of an heroic duty. The peace I felt within shed
its gay and reviving beams upon all around me. Reconciled
to myself, I was filled with sanguine and agreeable
visions of the future. My mind obstinately rejected all
dark and hateful presages. I had intrusted myself and the
direction of my conduct, as far as it was possible, to that
better pilot, under whose guidance, if I had not avoided the
rocks and quicksands of life, I had at least escaped with
little comparative injury. I felt therefore as if my domestic
enjoyments were restored, and the pleasures of my better
years were about to run over again their auspicious career.
Not so Marguerite. She was mild, gentle, and soothing.
Displeasure and resentment towards me were banished from
her mind. She endeavoured to conquer her melancholy,
and to forget the wounds that had been so fatal to her
hopes. But her endeavours were fruitless. A fixed dejection
clung to her heart: nor could the generous sweetness
that pervaded her manners hide from me entirely what was
passing in her bosom.
During this interval we had talked over the plan of our[213]
future operations. Marguerite was exceedingly urgent with
me to quit Constance; nor did I, though not impressed
with her presentiments, feel any reluctance to that change
of scene, which, I believed, would materially contribute to
the serenity of her mind and the restoration of her health.
We determined on some of the cities of Italy as the next
place of our residence, and, fixed, if possible, to set out
some time in the next day or the day after. The plan of
proceeding to France, which had lately been a favourite
with me, was a favourite no longer. That had been the
project of cheerful and wanton prosperity. It had had for its
object the re-establishment of my family honours, and the
elevation of my son. Now my son was lost, my wife was
oppressed with languor and disease, my house was overwhelmed
with sorrow. This was no time for wantonness
and triumph. If I could ever hope to resume the plans
my frolic fancy had sketched, an interval at least of soberer
hue must first be suffered to elapse.
My mind at this time sustained a revolution sufficiently
remarkable, but of which the urgency of events that immediately
succeeded prevented me from ever ascertaining
whether it would have proved temporary or permanent.
When I first received the donation of the stranger, my
thoughts, as I have already said, were in a state of enthusiastic
transport; and, amidst the golden visions in which
my fancy revelled, I became in a considerable degree alienated
from domestic sentiments and pleasures. If I still
loved my wife and children, it was the love of habit rather
than sympathy; more an anxiety for their prosperous success
in the world, than an earnest craving for their presence
and intercourse. This state of intoxication and rapture had
now subsided. The events of the few last weeks had sobered
my thoughts. Having lost my son, and being threatened
with the loss of his mother, I was roused to a sense
of their value. The influx of wealth and supernatural gifts
had grown familiar to my mind, and now only occupied
the back-ground of the picture. I was once more a man,
and I hoped to partake of the privileges and advantages of
a man. The fate reserved for these hopes will speedily be
seen.
[214]
Some readers will perhaps ask me why, anxious as I was
for the life of Marguerite, and visible as was the decline of
her health, I did not administer to her of the elixir of immortality
which was one of my peculiar endowments. Such
readers I have only to remind, that the pivot upon which
the history I am composing turns, is a mystery. If they
will not accept of my communication upon my own terms,
they must lay aside my book. I am engaged in relating
the incidents of my life; I have no intention to furnish the
remotest hint respecting the science of which I am the
depository. That science affords abundant reasons why the
elixir in question might not, or rather could not, be imbibed
by any other than an adept.
</div></body></text></TEI>