<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="40">

CHAPTER XXXI.
OF ADEQUATE AND INADEQUATE IDEAS.

1. Adequate Ideas are such as perfectly represent their Archetypes.


Of our real ideas, some are adequate, and some are inadequate. Those I call
ADEQUATE, which perfectly represent those archetypes which the mind supposes
them taken from: which it intends them to stand for, and to which it refers
them. INADEQUATE IDEAS are such, which are but a partial or incomplete
representation of those archetypes to which they are referred. Upon which
account it is plain,


2. Adequate Ideas are such as perfectly represent their Archetypes. Simple
Ideas all adequate.


First, that ALL OUR SIMPLE IDEAS ARE ADEQUATE. Because, being nothing but the
effects of certain powers in things, fitted and ordained by God to produce such
sensations in us, they cannot but be correspondent and adequate to those
powers: and we are sure they agree to the reality of things. For, if sugar
produce in us the ideas which we call whiteness and sweetness, we are sure
there is a power in sugar to produce those ideas in our minds, or else they
could not have been produced by it. And so each sensation answering the power
that operates on any of our senses, the idea so produced is a real idea, (and
not a fiction of the mind, which has no power to produce any simple idea); and
cannot but be adequate, since it ought only to answer that power: and so all
simple ideas are adequate. It is true, the things producing in us these simple
ideas are but few of them denominated by us, as if they were only the CAUSES of
them; but as if those ideas were real beings IN them. For, though fire be
called painful to the touch, whereby is signified the power of producing in us
the idea of pain, yet it is denominated also light and hot; as if light and
heat were really something in the fire, more than a power to excite these ideas
in us; and therefore are called qualities in or of the fire. But these being
nothing, in truth, but powers to excite such ideas in us, I must in that sense
be understood, when I speak of secondary qualities as being in things; or of
their ideas as being the objects that excite them in us. Such ways of speaking,
though accommodated to the vulgar notions, without which one cannot be well
understood, yet truly signify nothing but those powers which are in things to
excite certain sensations or ideas in us. Since were there no fit organs to
receive the impressions fire makes on the sight and touch, nor a mind joined to
those organs to receive the ideas of light and heat by those impressions from
the fire or sun, there would yet be no more light or heat in the world than
there would be pain if there were no sensible creature to feel it, though the
sun should continue just as it is now, and Mount AEtna flame higher than ever
it did. Solidity and extension, and the termination of it, figure, with motion
and rest, whereof we have the ideas, would be really in the world as they are,
whether there were any sensible being to perceive them or no: and therefore we
have reason to look on those as the real modifications of matter, and such as
are the exciting causes of all our various sensations from bodies. But this
being an inquiry not belonging to this place, I shall enter no further into it,
but proceed to show what complex ideas are adequate, and what not.


3. Modes are all adequate.


Secondly, OUR COMPLEX IDEAS OF MODES, being voluntary collections of simple
ideas, which the mind puts together, without reference to any real archetypes,
or standing patterns, existing anywhere, are and cannot but be ADEQUATE IDEAS.
Because they, not being intended for copies of things really existing, but for
archetypes made by the mind, to rank and denominate things by, cannot want
anything; they having each of them that combination of ideas, and thereby that
perfection, which the mind intended they should: so that the mind acquiesces in
them, and can find nothing wanting. Thus, by having the idea of a figure with
three sides meeting at three angles, I have a complete idea, wherein I require
nothing else to make it perfect. That the mind is satisfied with the perfection
of this its idea is plain, in that it does not conceive that any understanding
hath, or can have, a more complete or perfect idea of that thing it signifies
by the word triangle, supposing it to exist, than itself has, in that complex
idea of three sides and three angles, in which is contained all that is or can
be essential to it, or necessary to complete it, wherever or however it exists.
But in our IDEAS OF SUBSTANCES it is otherwise. For there, desiring to copy
things as they really do exist, and to represent to ourselves that constitution
on which all their properties depend, we perceive our ideas attain not that
perfection we intend: we find they still want something we should be glad were
in them; and so are all inadequate. But MIXED MODES and RELATIONS, being
archetypes without patterns, and so having nothing to represent but themselves,
cannot but be adequate, everything being so to itself. He that at first put
together the idea of danger perceived, absence of disorder from fear, sedate
consideration of what was justly to be done, and executing that without
disturbance, or being deterred by the danger of it, had certainly in his mind
that complex idea made up of that combination: and intending it to be nothing
else but what is, nor to have in it any other simple ideas but what it hath, it
could not also but be an adequate idea: and laying this up in his memory, with
the name COURAGE annexed to it, to signify to others, and denominate from
thence any action he should observe to agree with it, had thereby a standard to
measure and denominate actions by, as they agreed to it. This idea, thus made
and laid up for a pattern, must necessarily be adequate, being referred to
nothing else but itself, nor made by any other original but the good liking and
will of him that first made this combination.


4. Modes, in reference to settled Names, may be inadequate.


Indeed another coming after, and in conversation learning from him the word
COURAGE, may make an idea, to which he gives the name courage, different from
what the first author applied it to, and has in his mind when he uses it. And
in this case, if he designs that his idea in thinking should be conformable to
the other’s idea, as the name he uses in speaking is conformable in sound to
his from whom he learned it, his idea may be very wrong and inadequate: because
in this case, making the other man’s idea the pattern of his idea in thinking,
as the other man’s word or sound is the pattern of his in speaking, his idea is
so far defective and inadequate, as it is distant from the archetype and
pattern he refers it to, and intends to express and signify by the name he uses
for it; which name he would have to be a sign of the other man’s idea, (to
which, in its proper use, it is primarily annexed,) and of his own, as agreeing
to it: to which if his own does not exactly correspond, it is faulty and
inadequate.


5. Because then means, in propriety of speech, to correspond to the ideas in
some other mind.


Therefore these complex ideas of MODES, which they are referred by the mind,
and intended to correspond to the ideas in the mind of some other intelligent
being, expressed by the names we apply to them, they may be very deficient,
wrong, and inadequate; because they agree not to that which the mind designs to
be their archetype and pattern: in which respect only any idea of modes can be
wrong, imperfect, or inadequate. And on this account our ideas of mixed modes
are the most liable to be faulty of any other; but this refers more to proper
speaking than knowing right.


6. Ideas of Substances, as referred to real Essences, not adequate.


Thirdly, what IDEAS WE HAVE OF SUBSTANCES, I have above shown. Now, those ideas
have in the mind a double reference: 1. Sometimes they are referred to a
supposed real essence of each species of things. 2. Sometimes they are only
designed to be pictures and representations in the mind of things that do
exist, by ideas of those qualities that are discoverable in them. In both which
ways these copies of those originals and archetypes are imperfect and
inadequate.


First, it is usual for men to make the names of substances stand for things as
supposed to have certain real essences, whereby they are of this or that
species: and names standing for nothing but the ideas that are in men’s minds,
they must constantly refer their ideas to such real essences, as to their
archetypes. That men (especially such as have been bred up in the learning
taught in this part of the world) do suppose certain specific essences of
substances, which each individual in its several kinds is made conformable to
and partakes of, is so far from needing proof that it will be thought strange
if any one should do otherwise. And thus they ordinarily apply the specific
names they rank particular substances under, to things as distinguished by such
specific real essences. Who is there almost, who would not take it amiss if it
should be doubted whether he called himself a man, with any other meaning than
as having the real essence of a man? And yet if you demand what those real
essences are, it is plain men are ignorant, and know them not. From whence it
follows, that the ideas they have in their minds, being referred to real
essences, as to archetypes which are unknown, must be so far from being
adequate that they cannot be supposed to be any representation of them at all.
The complex ideas we have of substances are, as it has been shown, certain
collections of simple ideas that have been observed or supposed constantly to
exist together. But such a complex idea cannot be the real essence of any
substance; for then the properties we discover in that body would depend on
that complex idea, and be deducible from it, and their necessary connexion with
it be known; as all properties of a triangle depend on, and, as far as they are
discoverable, are deducible from the complex idea of three lines including a
space. But it is plain that in our complex ideas of substances are not
contained such ideas, on which all the other qualities that are to be found in
them do depend. The common idea men have of iron is, a body of a certain
colour, weight, and hardness; and a property that they look on as belonging to
it, is malleableness. But yet this property has no necessary connexion with
that complex idea, or any part of it: and there is no more reason to think that
malleableness depends on that colour, weight, and hardness, than that colour or
that weight depends on its malleableness. And yet, though we know nothing of
these real essences, there is nothing more ordinary than that men should
attribute the sorts of things to such essences. The particular parcel of matter
which makes the ring I have on my finger is forwardly by most men supposed to
have a real essence, whereby it is gold; and from whence those qualities flow
which I find in it, viz. its peculiar colour, weight, hardness, fusibility,
fixedness, and change of colour upon a slight touch of mercury, &c. This
essence, from which all these properties flow, when I inquire into it and
search after it, I plainly perceive I cannot discover: the furthest I can go
is, only to presume that, it being nothing but body, its real essence or
internal constitution, on which these qualities depend, can be nothing but the
figure, size, and connexion of its solid parts; of neither of which having any
distinct perception at all can I have any idea of its essence: which is the
cause that it has that particular shining yellowness; a greater weight than
anything I know of the same bulk; and a fitness to have its colour changed by
the touch of quicksilver. If any one will say, that the real essence and
internal constitution, on which these properties depend, is not the figure,
size, and arrangement or connexion of its solid parts, but something else,
called its particular FORM, I am further from having any idea of its real
essence than I was before. For I have an idea of figure, size, and situation of
solid parts in general, though I have none of the particular figure, size, or
putting together of parts, whereby the qualities above mentioned are produced;
which qualities I find in that particular parcel of matter that is on my
finger, and not in another parcel of matter, with which I cut the pen I write
with. But, when I am told that something besides the figure, size, and posture
of the solid parts of that body in its essence, something called SUBSTANTIAL
FORM, of that I confess I have no idea at all, but only of the sound form;
which is far enough from an idea of its real essence or constitution. The like
ignorance as I have of the real essence of this particular substance, I have
also of the real essence of all other natural ones: of which essences I confess
I have no distinct ideas at all; and, I am apt to suppose, others, when they
examine their own knowledge, will find in themselves, in this one point, the
same sort of ignorance.


7. Because men know not the real essence of substances.


Now, then, when men apply to this particular parcel of matter on my finger a
general name already in use, and denominate it GOLD, do they not ordinarily, or
are they not understood to give it that name, as belonging to a particular
species of bodies, having a real internal essence; by having of which essence
this particular substance comes to be of that species, and to be called by that
name? If it be so, as it is plain it is, the name by which things are marked as
having that essence must be referred primarily to that essence; and
consequently the idea to which that name is given must be referred also to that
essence, and be intended to represent it. Which essence, since they who so use
the names know not, their ideas of substances must be all inadequate in that
respect, as not containing in them that real essence which the mind intends
they should.


8. Ideas of Substances, when regarded as Collections of their Qualities, are
all inadequate.


Secondly, those who, neglecting that useless supposition of unknown real
essences, whereby they are distinguished, endeavour to copy the substances that
exist in the world, by putting together the ideas of those sensible qualities
which are found co-existing in them, though they come much nearer a likeness of
them than those who imagine they know not what real specific essences: yet they
arrive not at perfectly adequate ideas of those substances they would thus copy
into their minds: nor do those copies exactly and fully contain all that is to
be found in their archetypes. Because those qualities and powers of substances,
whereof we make their complex ideas, are so many and various, that no man’s
complex idea contains them all. That our complex ideas of substances do not
contain in them ALL the simple ideas that are united in the things themselves
is evident, in that men do rarely put into their complex idea of any substance
all the simple ideas they do know to exist in it. Because, endeavouring to make
the signification of their names as clear and as little cumbersome as they can,
they make their specific ideas of the sorts of substance, for the most part, of
a few of those simple ideas which are to be found in them: but these having no
original precedency, or right to be put in, and make the specific idea, more
than others that are left out, it is plain that both these ways our ideas of
substances are deficient and inadequate. The simple ideas whereof we make our
complex ones of substances are all of them (bating only the figure and bulk of
some sorts) powers; which being relations to other substances, we can never be
sure that we know ALL the powers that are in any one body, till we have tried
what changes it is fitted to give to or receive from other substances in their
several ways of application: which being impossible to be tried upon any one
body, much less upon all, it is impossible we should have adequate ideas of any
substance made up of a collection of all its properties.


9. Their powers usually make up our complex ideas of substances.


Whosoever first lighted on a parcel of that sort of substance we denote by the
word GOLD, could not rationally take the bulk and figure he observed in that
lump to depend on its real essence, or internal constitution. Therefore those
never went into his idea of that species of body; but its peculiar colour,
perhaps, and weight, were the first he abstracted from it, to make the complex
idea of that species. Which both are but powers; the one to affect our eyes
after such a manner, and to produce in us that idea we call yellow; and the
other to force upwards any other body of equal bulk, they being put into a pair
of equal scales, one against another. Another perhaps added to these the ideas
of fusibility and fixedness, two other passive powers, in relation to the
operation of fire upon it; another, its ductility and solubility in aqua regia,
two other powers, relating to the operation of other bodies, in changing its
outward figure, or separation of it into insensible parts. These, or parts of
these, put together, usually make the complex idea in men’s minds of that sort
of body we call GOLD.


10. Substances have innumerable powers not contained in our complex ideas of
them.


But no one who hath considered the properties of bodies in general, or this
sort in particular, can doubt that this, called GOLD, has infinite other
properties not contained in that complex idea. Some who have examined this
species more accurately could, I believe, enumerate ten times as many
properties in gold, all of them as inseparable from its internal constitution,
as its colour or weight: and it is probable, if any one knew all the properties
that are by divers men known of this metal, there would be an hundred times as
many ideas go to the complex idea of gold as any one man yet has in his; and
yet perhaps that not be the thousandth part of what is to be discovered in it.
The changes that that one body is apt to receive, and make in other bodies,
upon a due application, exceeding far not only what we know, but what we are
apt to imagine. Which will not appear so much a paradox to any one who will but
consider how far men are yet from knowing all the properties of that one, no
very compound figure, a triangle; though it be no small number that are already
by mathematicians discovered of it.


11. Ideas of Substances, being got only by collecting their qualities, are all
inadequate.


So that all our complex ideas of substances are imperfect and inadequate. Which
would be so also in mathematical figures, if we were to have our complex ideas
of them, only by collecting their properties in reference to other figures. How
uncertain and imperfect would our ideas be of an ellipsis, if we had no other
idea of it, but some few of its properties? Whereas, having in our plain idea
the WHOLE essence of that figure, we from thence discover those properties, and
demonstratively see how they flow, and are inseparable from it.


12. Simple Ideas, [word in Greek], and adequate.


Thus the mind has three sorts of abstract ideas or nominal essences:


First, SIMPLE ideas, which are [word in Greek] or copies; but yet certainly
adequate. Because, being intended to express nothing but the power in things to
produce in the mind such a sensation, that sensation, when it is produced,
cannot but be the effect of that power. So the paper I write on, having the
power in the light (I speak according to the common notion of light) to produce
in men the sensation which I call white, it cannot but be the effect of such a
power in something without the mind; since the mind has not the power to
produce any such idea in itself: and being meant for nothing else but the
effect of such a power that simple idea is [* words missing] the sensation of
white, in my mind, being the effect of that power which is in the paper to
produce it, is perfectly adequate to that power; or else that power would
produce a different idea.


13. Ideas of Substances are Echthypa, and inadequate.


Secondly, the COMPLEX ideas of SUBSTANCES are ectypes, copies too; but not
perfect ones, not adequate: which is very evident to the mind, in that it
plainly perceives, that whatever collection of simple ideas it makes of any
substance that exists, it cannot be sure that it exactly answers all that are
in that substance. Since, not having tried all the operations of all other
substances upon it, and found all the alterations it would receive from, or
cause in, other substances, it cannot have an exact adequate collection of all
its active and passive capacities; and so not have an adequate complex idea of
the powers of any substance existing, and its relations; which is that sort of
complex idea of substances we have. And, after all, if we would have, and
actually had, in our complex idea, an exact collection of all the secondary
qualities or powers of any substance, we should not yet thereby have an idea of
the ESSENCE of that thing. For, since the powers or qualities that are
observable by us are not the real essence of that substance, but depend on it,
and flow from it, any collection whatsoever of these qualities cannot be the
real essence of that thing. Whereby it is plain, that our ideas of substances
are not adequate; are not what the mind intends them to be. Besides, a man has
no idea of substance in general, nor knows what substance is in itself.


14. Ideas of Modes and Relations are Archetypes, and cannot but be adequate.


Thirdly, COMPLEX ideas of MODES AND RELATIONS are originals, and archetypes;
are not copies, nor made after the pattern of any real existence, to which the
mind intends them to be conformable, and exactly to answer. These being such
collections of simple ideas that the mind itself puts together, and such
collections that each of them contains in it precisely all that the mind
intends that it should, they are archetypes and essences of modes that may
exist; and so are designed only for, and belong only to such modes as, when
they do exist, have an exact conformity with those complex ideas The ideas,
therefore, of modes and relations cannot but be adequate.


</div></body></text></TEI>