<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol I</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1794</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="22">SECT. XXII.
OF PROPENSITY TO MOTION, REPETITION AND IMITATION.

I. Accumulation of sensorial power in
  hemiplagia, in sleep, in cold fit of fever, in the locomotive muscles, in
  the organs of sense. Produces propensity to action. II. Repetition by three sensorial powers. In
  rhimes and alliterations, in music, dancing, architecture,
  landscape-painting, beauty. III. 1. Perception consists in imitation. Four
  kinds of imitation. 2. Voluntary.
  Dogs taught to dance. 3. Sensitive.
  Hence sympathy, and all our virtues. Contagious matter of venereal
  ulcers, of hydrophobia, of jail-fever, of small-pox, produced by
  imitation, and the sex of the embryon. 4. Irritative imitation. 5. Imitations resolvable into
  associations.

I. 1. In the
  hemiplagia, when the limbs on one side have lost their power of voluntary
  motion, the patient is for many days perpetually employed in moving those
  of the other. 2. When the voluntary power is
  suspended during sleep, there commences a ceaseless flow of sensitive
  motions, or ideas of imagination, which compose our dreams. 3. When in the cold fit of an intermittent fever
  some parts of the system have for a time continued torpid, and have thus
  expended less than their usual expenditure of sensorial power; a hot fit
  succeeds, with violent action of those vessels, which had previously been
  quiescent. All these are explained from an accumulation of sensorial
  power during the inactivity of some part of the system.
Besides the very great quantity of sensorial power perpetually
  produced and expended in moving the arterial, venous, and glandular
  systems, with the various organs or digestion, as described in Section XXXII. 3. 2. there is also a constant
  expenditure of it by the action of our locomotive muscles and organs of
  sense. Thus the thickness of the optic nerves, where they enter the eye,
  and the great expansion of the nerves of touch beneath the whole of the
  cuticle, evince the great consumption of sensorial power by these senses.
  And our perpetual muscular actions in the common offices of life, and in
  constantly preserving the perpendicularity of our bodies during the day,
  evince a considerable expenditure of the spirit of animation by our
  locomotive muscles. It follows, that if the exertion of these organs of
  sense and muscles be for a while intermitted, that some quantity of
  sensorial power must be accumulated, and a propensity to activity of some
  kind ensue from the increased excitability of the system. Whence proceeds
  the irksomeness of a continued attitude, and of an indolent life.
However small this hourly accumulation of the spirit of animation may
  be, it produces a propensity to some kind of action; but it nevertheless
  requires either desire or aversion, either pleasure or pain, or some
  external stimulus, or a previous link of association, to excite the
  system into activity; thus it frequently happens, when the mind and body
  are so unemployed as not to possess any of the three first kinds of
  stimuli, that the last takes place, and consumes the small but perpetual
  accumulation of sensorial power. Whence some indolent people repeat the
  same verse for hours together, or hum the same tune. Thus the poet:


Onward he trudged, not knowing what he sought,
And whistled, as he went, for want of thought.


II. The repetitions of motions may be at
  first produced either by volition, or by sensation, or by irritation, but
  they soon become easier to perform than any other kinds of action,
  because they soon become associated together, according to Law the
  seventh, Section IV. on Animal Causation. And
  because their frequency of repetition, if as much sensorial power be
  produced during every reiteration as is expended, adds to the facility of
  their production.
If a stimulus be repeated at uniform intervals of time, as described
  in Sect. XII. 3. 3. the action, whether of
  our muscles or organs of sense, is produced with still greater facility
  or energy; because the sensorial power of association, mentioned above,
  is combined with the sensorial power of irritation; that is, in common
  language, the acquired habit assists the power of the stimulus.
This not only obtains in the annual, lunar, and diurnal catenations of
  animal motions, as explained in Sect. XXXVI.
  which are thus performed with great facility and energy; but in every
  less circle of actions or ideas, as in the burthen of a song, or the
  reiterations of a dance. To the facility and distinctness, with which we
  hear sounds at repeated intervals, we owe the pleasure, which we receive
  from musical time, and from poetic time; as described in Botanic Garden,
  P. 2. Interlude 3. And to this the pleasure we receive from the rhimes
  and alliterations of modern verification; the source of which without
  this key would be difficult to discover. And to this likewise should be
  ascribed the beauty of the duplicature in the perfect tense of the Greek
  verbs, and of some Latin ones, as tango tetegi, mordeo momordi.
There is no variety of notes referable to the gamut in the beating of
  the drum, yet if it be performed in musical time, it is agreeable to our
  ears; and therefore this pleasurable sensation must be owing to the
  repetition of the divisions of the sounds at certain intervals of time,
  or musical bars. Whether these times or bars are distinguished by a
  pause, or by an emphasis, or accent, certain it is, that this distinction
  is perpetually repeated; otherwise the ear could not determine instantly,
  whether the successions of sound were in common or in triple time. In
  common time there is a division between every two crotchets, or other
  notes of equivalent time; though the bar in written music is put after
  every fourth crotchet, or notes equivalent in time; in triple time the
  division or bar is after every three crotchets, or notes equivalent; so
  that in common time the repetition recurs more frequently than in triple
  time. The grave or heroic verses of the Greek and Latin poets are written
  in common time; the French heroic verses, and Mr. Anstie's humorous
  verses in his Bath Guide, are written in the same time as the Greek and
  Latin verses, but are one bar shorter. The English grave or heroic verses
  are measured by triple time, as Mr. Pope's translation of Homer.
But besides these little circles of musical time, there are the
  greater returning periods, and the still more distant choruses, which,
  like the rhimes at the ends of verses, owe their beauty to repetition;
  that is, to the facility and distinctness with which we perceive sounds,
  which we expect to perceive, or have perceived before; or in the language
  of this work, to the greater ease and energy with which our organ is
  excited by the combined sensorial powers of association and irritation,
  than by the latter singly.
A certain uniformity or repetition of parts enters the very
  composition of harmony. Thus two octaves nearest to each other in the
  scale commence their vibrations together after every second vibration of
  the higher one. And where the first, third, and fifth compose a chord the
  vibrations concur or coincide frequently, though less to than in the two
  octaves. It is probable that these chords bear some analogy to a mixture
  of three alternate colours in the sun's spectrum separated by a
  prism.
The pleasure we receive from a melodious succession of notes referable
  to the gamut is derived from another source, viz. to the pandiculation or
  counteraction of antagonist fibres. See Botanic Garden, P. 2. Interlude
  3. If to these be added our early associations of agreeable ideas with
  certain proportions of sound, I suppose, from these three sources springs
  all the delight of music, so celebrated by ancient authors, and so
  enthusiastically cultivated at present. See Sect. XVI. No. 10. on Instinct.
This kind of pleasure arising from repetition, that is from the
  facility and distinctness, with which we perceive and understand repeated
  sensations, enters into all the agreeable arts; and when it is carried to
  excess is termed formality. The art of dancing like that of music depends
  for a great part of the pleasure, it affords, on repetition;
  architecture, especially the Grecian, consists of one part being a
  repetition of another; and hence the beauty of the pyramidal outline in
  landscape-painting; where one side of the picture may be said in some
  measure to balance the other. So universally does repetition contribute
  to our pleasure in the fine arts, that beauty itself has been defined by
  some writers to consist in a due combination of uniformity and variety.
  See Sect. XVI. 6.
III. 1. Man is
  termed by Aristotle an imitative animal; this propensity to imitation not
  only appears in the actions of children, but in all the customs and
  fashions of the world: many thousands tread in the beaten paths of
  others, for one who traverses regions of his own discovery. The origin of
  this propensity of imitation has not, that I recollect, been deduced from
  any known principle; when any action presents itself to the view of a
  child, as of whetting a knife, or threading a needle, the parts of this
  action in respect of time, motion, figure, is imitated by a part of the
  retina of his eye; to perform this action therefore with his hands is
  easier to him than to invent any new action, because it consists in
  repeating with another set of fibres, viz. with the moving muscles, what
  he had just performed by some parts of the retina; just as in dancing we
  transfer the times of motion from the actions of the auditory nerves to
  the muscles of the limbs. Imitation therefore consists of repetition,
  which we have shewn above to be the easiest kind of animal action, and
  which we perpetually fall into, when we possess an accumulation of
  sensorial power, which is not otherwise called into exertion.
It has been shewn, that our ideas are configurations of the organs of
  sense, produced originally in consequence of the stimulus of external
  bodies. And that these ideas, or configurations of the organs of sense,
  referable in some property a correspondent property of external matter;
  as the parts of the senses of light and of touch, which are excited into
  action, resemble in figure the figure of the stimulating body; and
  probably also the colour, and the quantity of density, which they
  perceive. As explained in Sect. XIV. 2. 2.
  Hence it appears, that our perceptions themselves are copies, that is,
  imitations of some properties of external matter; and the propensity to
  imitation is thus interwoven with our existence, as it is produced by the
  stimuli of external bodies, and is afterwards repeated by our volitions
  and sensations, and thus constitutes all the operations of our minds.
2. Imitations resolve themselves into four
  kinds, voluntary, sensitive, irritative, and associate. The voluntary
  imitations are, when we imitate deliberately the actions of others,
  either by mimicry, as in acting a play, or in delineating a flower; or in
  the common actions of our lives, as in our dress, cookery, language,
  manners, and even in our habits of thinking.
Not only the greatest part of mankind learn all the common arts of
  life by imitating others, but brute animals seem capable of acquiring
  knowledge with greater facility by imitating each other, than by any
  methods by which we can teach them; as dogs and cats, when they are sick,
  learn of each other to eat grass; and I suppose, that by making an
  artificial dog perform certain tricks, as in dancing on his hinder legs,
  a living dog might be easily induced to imitate them; and that the
  readiest way of instructing dumb animals is by practising them with
  others of the same species, which have already learned the arts we wish
  to teach them. The important use of imitation in acquiring natural
  language is mentioned in Section XVI. 7. and 8. on Instinct.
3. The sensitive imitations are the
  immediate consequences of pleasure or pain, and these are often produced
  even contrary to the efforts of the will. Thus many young men on seeing
  cruel surgical operations become sick, and some even feel pain in the
  parts of their own bodies, which they see tortured or wounded in others;
  that is, they in some measure imitate by the exertions of their own
  fibres the violent actions, which they witnessed in those of others. In
  this case a double imitation takes place, first the observer imitates
  with the extremities of the optic nerve the mangled limbs, which are
  present before his eyes; then by a second imitation he excites to violent
  action of the fibres of his own limbs as to produce pain in those parts
  of his own body, which he saw wounded in another. In these pains produced
  by imitation the effect has some similarity to the cause, which
  distinguishes them from those produced by association; as the pains of
  the teeth, called tooth-edge, which are produced by association with
  disagreeable sounds, as explained in Sect. XVI.
  10.
The effect of this powerful agent, imitation, in the moral world, is
  mentioned in Sect. XVI. 7. as it is the
  foundation of all our intellectual sympathies with the pains and
  pleasures of others, and is in consequence the source of all our virtues.
  For in what consists our sympathy with the miseries, or with the joys, of
  our fellow creatures, but in an involuntary excitation of ideas in some
  measure similar or imitative of those, which we believe to exist in the
  minds of the persons, whom we commiserate or congratulate?
There are certain concurrent or successive actions of some of the
  glands, or other parts of the body, which are possessed of sensation,
  which become intelligible from this propensity to imitation. Of these are
  the production of matter by the membranes of the fauces, or by the skin,
  in consequence of the venereal disease previously affecting the parts of
  generation. Since as no fever is excited, and as neither the blood of
  such patients, nor even the matter from ulcers of the throat, or from
  cutaneous ulcers, will by inoculation produce the venereal disease in
  others, as observed by Mr. Hunter, there is reason to conclude, that no
  contagious matter is conveyed thither by the blood-vessels, but that a
  milder matter is formed by the actions of the fine vessels in those
  membranes imitating each other. See Section XXXIII. 2. 9. In this disease the actions of
  these vessels producing ulcers on the throat and skin are imperfect
  imitations of those producing chanker, or gonorrhœa; since the
  matter produced by them is not infectious, while the imitative actions in
  the hydrophobia appear to be perfect resemblances, as they produce a
  material equally infectious with the original one, which induced
  them.
The contagion from the bite of a mad dog differs from other contagious
  materials, from its being communicable from other animals to mankind, and
  from many animals to each other; the phenomena attending the hydrophobia
  are in some degree explicable on the foregoing theory. The infectious
  matter does not appear to enter the circulation, as it cannot be traced
  along the course of the lymphatics from the wound, nor is there any
  swelling of the lymphatic glands, nor does any fever attend, as occurs in
  the small-pox, and in many other contagious diseases; yet by some unknown
  process the disease is communicated from the wound to the throat, and
  that many months after the injury, so as to produce pain and hydrophobia,
  with a secretion of infectious saliva of the same kind, as that of the
  mad dog, which inflicted the wound.
This subject is very intricate.—It would appear, that by certain
  morbid actions of the salivary glands of the mad dog, a peculiar kind of
  saliva is produced; which being instilled into a wound of another animal
  stimulates the cutaneous or mucous glands into morbid actions, but which
  are ineffectual in respect to the production of a similar contagious
  material; but the salivary glands by irritative sympathy are thrown into
  similar action, and produce an infectious saliva similar to that
  instilled into the wound.
Though in many contagious fevers a material similar to that which
  produced the disease, is thus generated by imitation; yet there are other
  infectious materials, which do not thus propagate themselves, but which
  seem to act like slow poisons. Of this kind was the contagious matter,
  which produced the jail-fever at the assizes at Oxford about a century
  ago. Which, though fatal to so many, was not communicated to their nurses
  or attendants. In these cases, the imitations of the fine vessels, as
  above described, appear to be imperfect, and do not therefore produce a
  matter similar to that, which stimulates them; in this circumstance
  resembling the venereal matter in ulcers of the throat or skin, according
  to the curious discovery of Mr. Hunter above related, who found, by
  repeated inoculations, that it would not infect. Hunter on Venereal
  Disease, Part vi. ch. 1.
Another example of morbid imitation is in the production of a great
  quantity of contagious matter, as in the inoculated small-pox, from a
  small quantity of it inserted into the arm, and probably diffused in the
  blood. These particles of contagious matter stimulate the extremities of
  the fine arteries of the skin, and cause them to imitate some properties
  of those particles of contagious matter, so as to produce a thousandfold
  of a similar material. See Sect. XXXIII. 2.
  6. Other instances are mentioned in the Section on Generation, which
  shew the probability that the extremities of the seminal glands may
  imitate certain ideas of the mind, or actions of the organs of sense, and
  thus occasion the male or female sex of the embryon. See Sect. XXXIX. 6.
4. We come now to those imitations, which
  are not attended with sensation. Of these are all the irritative ideas
  already explained, as when the retina of the eye imitates by its action
  or configuration the tree or the bench, which I shun in walking past
  without attending to them. Other examples of these irritative imitations
  are daily observable in common life; thus one yawning person shall set a
  whole company a yawning; and some have acquired winking of the eyes or
  impediments of speech by imitating their companions without being
  conscious of it.
5. Besides the three species of imitations
  above described there may be some associate motions, which may imitate
  each other in the kind as well as in the quantity of their action; but it
  is difficult to distinguish them from the associations of motions treated
  of in Section XXXV. Where the actions of other
  persons are imitated there can be no doubt, or where we imitate a
  preconceived idea by exertion of our locomotive muscles, as in painting a
  dragon; all these imitations may aptly be referred to the sources above
  described of the propensity to activity, and the facility of repetition;
  at the same time I do not affirm, that all those other apparent sensitive
  and irritative imitations may not be resolvable into associations of a
  peculiar kind, in which certain distant parts of similar irritability or
  sensibility, and which have habitually acted together, may affect each
  other exactly with the same kinds of motion; as many parts are known to
  sympathise in the quantity of their motions. And that therefore they may
  be ultimately resolvable into associations of action, as described in
  Sect. XXXV.

</div></body></text></TEI>