<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="5">
CHAPTER V.

The Magnitude of the Atmosphere.

The total quantity of air of which our atmosphere
is composed is another of the arbitrary magnitudes
of our terrestrial system; and we may apply to this
subject considerations similar to those of the last section.
We can see no reason why the atmosphere
might not have been larger in comparison to the
globe which it surrounds; those of Mars and Jupiter
appear to be so. But if the quantity of air were
increased, the structure of organized beings would
in many ways cease to be adapted to their place.
The atmospheric pressure, for instance, would be increased,
which, as we have already noticed, would
require an alteration in the structure of vegetables.
Another way in which an increase of the mass of
the atmosphere would produce inconvenience would
be in the force of winds. If the current of air in a
strong gale were doubled or tripled, as might be the
case if the atmosphere were augmented, the destructive
effects would be more than doubled or tripled.
With such a change, nothing could stand against a
storm. In general, houses and trees resist the violence[52]
of the wind; and except in extreme cases, as
for instance in occasional hurricanes in the West Indies,
a few large trees in a forest are unusual trophies
of the power of the tempest. The breezes which we
commonly have are harmless messengers to bring
about the salutary changes of the atmosphere, even
the motion which they communicate to vegetables
tends to promote their growth, and is so advantageous,
that it has been proposed to imitate it by
artificial breezes in the hothouse. But with a stream
of wind blowing against them, like three, or five, or
ten, gales compressed into the space of one, none of
the existing trees could stand; and except they could
either bend like rushes in a stream, or extend their
roots far wider than their branches, they must be
torn up in whole groves. We have thus a manifest
adaptation of the present usual strength of the materials
and of the workmanship of the world to the
stress of wind and weather which they have to
sustain.
</div></body></text></TEI>