<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="39">

CHAPTER III.
Successive Attempts at the Scientific Application of the
Idea of a Medium.



1. IN
what precedes, we have shown by various considerations
that we necessarily and universally assume the perception of
secondary qualities to take place by means of a medium
interjacent between the object and the person perceiving.
Perception is affected by various peculiarities, according
to the nature of the quality perceived: but in all cases a
medium is equally essential to the process.
This principle, which, as we have seen, is accepted as
evident by the common understanding of mankind, is confirmed
by all additional reflection and discipline of the mind, and
is the foundation of all the theories which have been
proposed concerning the processes by which the perception
takes place, and concerning the modifications of the
qualities thus perceived. The medium, and the mode in which
the impression is conveyed through the medium, seem to be
different for different qualities; but the existence of the
medium leads to certain necessary conditions or
alternatives, which have successively made their appearance
in science, in the course of the attempts of men to theorize
concerning the principal secondary qualities, sound, light,
and heat. We must now point out some of the ways, at first
imperfect and erroneous, in which the consequences of the
fundamental assumption were traced.
2. Sound.—In all cases the medium of sensation,
whatever it is, is supposed to produce the effect of
conveying secondary qualities to our perception by means of
its primary qualities. It was conceived to operate 323 by
the size, form, and motion of its parts. This is a
fundamental principle of the class of sciences of which we
have at present to speak.
It was assumed from the first, as we have seen in the
passage lately quoted from Aristotle21, that in the
conveyance of sound, the medium of communication
was the air. But although the first theorists were right so
far, that circumstance did not prevent their going entirely
wrong when they had further to determine the nature of the
process. It was conceived by Aristotle that the air acted
after the manner of a rigid body;—like a staff, which,
receiving an impulse at one end, transmits it to the other.
Now this is altogether an erroneous view of the manner in
which the air conveys the impulse by which sound is
perceived. An approach was made to the true view of this
process, by assimilating it to the diffusion of the little
circular waves which are produced on the surface of still
water when a stone is dropt into it. These little waves
begin from the point thus disturbed, and run outwards,
expanding on every side, in concentric circles, till they
are lost. The propagation of sound through the air from the
point where it is produced, was compared by Vitruvius to
this diffusion of circular waves in water; and thus the
notion of a propagation of impulse by the waves of
a fluid was introduced, in the place of the former notion of
the impulse of an unyielding body.</div></body></text></TEI>