<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="32">CHAPTER VI.
Sequel to the Generalization of the Principles of
Mechanics.—Period of Mathematical Deduction.—Analytical
Mechanics.
WE have now finished the
history of the discovery of Mechanical Principles, strictly so called.
The three Laws of Motion, generalized in the manner we have described,
contain the materials of the whole structure of Mechanics; and in the
remaining progress of the science, we are led to no new truth which
was not implicitly involved in those previously known. It may be
thought, therefore, that the narrative of this progress is of
comparatively small interest. Nor do we maintain that the application
and development of principles is a matter of so much importance to the
philosophy of science, as the advance towards and to them. Still,
there are many circumstances in the latter stages of the progress of
the science of Mechanics, which well deserve notice, and make a rapid
survey of that part of its history indispensable to our purpose.
The Laws of Motion are expressed in terms of Space and Number; the
development of the consequences of these laws must, therefore, be
performed by means of the reasonings of mathematics; and the science
363 of Mechanics
may assume the various aspects which belong to the different modes of
dealing with mathematical quantities. Mechanics, like pure
mathematics, may be geometrical or may be analytical; that is, it may
treat space either by a direct consideration of its properties, or by
a symbolical representation of them: Mechanics, like pure mathematics,
may proceed from special cases, to problems and methods of extreme
generality;—may summon to its aid the curious and refined
relations of symmetry, by which general and complex conditions are
simplified;—may become more powerful by the discovery of more
powerful analytical artifices;—may even have the generality of
its principles further expanded, inasmuch as symbols are a more
general language than words. We shall very briefly notice a series of
modifications of this kind.
1. Geometrical Mechanics. Newton, &c.—The first
great systematical Treatise on Mechanics, in the most general sense,
is the two first Books of the Principia of Newton. In this
work, the method employed is predominantly geometrical: not only space
is not represented symbolically, or by reference to number; but
numbers, as, for instance, those which measure time and force, are
represented by spaces; and the laws of their changes are indicated by
the properties of curve lines. It is well known that Newton employed,
by preference, methods of this kind in the exposition of his theorems,
even where he had made the discovery of them by analytical
calculations. The intuitions of space appeared to him, as they have
appeared to many of his followers, to be a more clear and satisfactory
road to knowledge, than the operations of symbolical language.
Hermann, whose Phoronomia was the next great work on this
subject, pursued a like course; employing curves, which he calls “the
scale of velocities,” “of forces,” &c. Methods nearly similar were
employed by the two first Bernoullis, and other mathematicians of that
period; and were, indeed, so long familiar, that the influence of them
may still be traced in some of the terms which are used on such
subjects; as, for instance, when we talk of “reducing a problem to
quadratures,” that is, to the finding the area of the curves employed
in these methods.
2. Analytical Mechanics. Euler.—As analysis was more
cultivated, it gained a predominancy over geometry; being found to be
a far more powerful instrument for obtaining results; and possessing a
beauty and an evidence, which, though different from those of
geometry, had great attractions for minds to which they became
familiar. The person who did most to give to analysis the generality
and  364 symmetry
which are now its pride, was also the person who made Mechanics
analytical; I mean Euler. He began his execution of this task in
various memoirs which appeared in the Transactions of the Academy
of Sciences at St. Petersburg, commencing with its earliest
volumes; and in 1736, he published there his Mechanics, or the
Science of Motion analytically expounded; in the way of a Supplement
to the Transactions of the Imperial Academy of Sciences. In the
preface to this work, he says, that though the solutions of problems
by Newton and Hermann were quite satisfactory, yet he found that he
had a difficulty in applying them to new problems, differing little
from theirs; and that, therefore, he thought it would be useful to
extract an analysis out of their synthesis.
3. Mechanical Problems.—In reality, however, Euler has
done much more than merely give analytical methods, which may be
applied to mechanical problems: he has himself applied such methods to
an immense number of cases. His transcendent mathematical powers, his
long and studious life, and the interest with which he pursued the
subject, led him to solve an almost inconceivable number and variety
of mechanical problems. Such problems suggested themselves to him on
all occasions. One of his memoirs begins, by stating that, happening
to think of the line of Virgil,

Anchora de prorà jacitur stant litore
puppes;
The anchor drops, the rushing keel is
staid;
he could not help inquiring what would be the nature
of the ship’s motion under the circumstances here described. And in
the last few days of his life, after his mortal illness had begun,
having seen in the newspapers some statements respecting balloons, he
proceeded to calculate their motions; and performed a difficult
integration, in which this undertaking engaged him. His Memoirs occupy
a very large portion of the Petropolitan Transactions during
his life, from 1728 to 1783; and he declared that he should leave
papers which might enrich the publications of the Academy of
Petersburg for twenty years after his death;—a promise which has
been more than fulfilled; for, up to 1818, the volumes usually contain
several Memoirs of his. He and his contemporaries may be said to have
exhausted the subject; for there are few mechanical problems which
have been since treated, which they have not in some manner touched
upon.
I do not dwell upon the details of such problems; for the next
great step in Analytical Mechanics, the publication of D’Alembert’s
365 Principle in
1743, in a great degree superseded their interest. The Transactions of
the Academies of Paris and Berlin, as well as St. Petersburg, are
filled, up to this time, with various questions of this kind. They
require, for the most part, the determination of the motions of
several bodies, with or without weight, which pull or push each other
by means of threads, or levers, to which they are fastened, or along
which they can slide; and which, having a certain impulse given them
at first, are then left to themselves, or are compelled to move in
given lines and surfaces. The postulate of Huyghens, respecting the
motion of the centre of gravity, was generally one of the principles
of the solution; but other principles were always needed in addition
to this; and it required the exercise of ingenuity and skill to detect
the most suitable in each case. Such problems were, for some time, a
sort of trial of strength among mathematicians: the principle of
D’Alembert put an end to this kind of challenges, by supplying a
direct and general method of resolving, or at least of throwing into
equations, any imaginable problem. The mechanical difficulties were in
this way reduced to difficulties of pure mathematics.
4. D’Alembert’s Principle.—D’Alembert’s Principle is
only the expression, in the most general form, of the principle upon
which John Bernoulli, Hermann, and others, had solved the problem of
the centre of oscillation. It was thus stated, “The motion
impressed on each particle of any system by the forces which
act upon it, may be resolved into two, the effective motion,
and the motion gained or lost: the effective motions will be
the real motions of the parts, and the motions gained and lost will be
such as would keep the system at rest.” The distinction of
statics, the doctrine of equilibrium, and dynamics, the
doctrine of motion, was, as we have seen, fundamental; and the
difference of difficulty and complexity in the two subjects was well
understood, and generally recognized by mathematicians. D’Alembert’s
principle reduces every dynamical question to a statical one; and
hence, by means of the conditions which connect the possible motions
of the system, we can determine what the actual motions must be. The
difficulty of determining the laws of equilibrium, in the application
of this principle in complex cases is, however, often as great as if
we apply more simple and direct considerations.
5. Motion in Resisting Media. Ballistics.—We shall
notice more particularly the history of some of the problems of
mechanics. Though John Bernoulli always spoke with admiration of
Newton’s Principia, and of its author, he appears to have been
well disposed to point out 366 real or imagined blemishes in the work.
Against the validity of Newton’s determination of the path described
by a body projected in any part of the solar system, Bernoulli urges a
cavil which it is difficult to conceive that a mathematician, such as
he was, could seriously believe to be well founded. On Newton’s
determination of the path of a body in a resisting medium, his
criticism is more just. He pointed out a material error in this
solution: this correction came to Newton’s knowledge in London, in
October, 1712, when the impression of the second edition of the
Principia was just drawing to a close, under the care of Cotes at
Cambridge; and Newton immediately cancelled the leaf and corrected the
error.48
48 MS. Correspondence in Trin. Coll.
Library.
This problem of the motion of a body in a resisting medium, led to
another collision between the English and the German mathematicians.
The proposition to which we have referred, gave only an indirect view
of the nature of the curve described by a projectile in the air; and
it is probable that Newton, when he wrote the Principia, did
not see his way to any direct and complete solution of this problem.
At a later period, in 1718, when the quarrel had waxed hot between the
admirers of Newton and Leibnitz, Keill, who had come forward as a
champion on the English side, proposed this problem to the foreigners
as a challenge. Keill probably imagined that what Newton had not
discovered, no one of his time would be able to discover. But the
sedulous cultivation of analysis by the Germans had given them
mathematical powers beyond the expectations of the English; who,
whatever might be their talents, had made little advance in the
effective use of general methods; and for a long period seemed to be
fascinated to the spot, in their admiration of Newton’s excellence.
Bernoulli speedily solved the problem; and reasonably enough,
according to the law of honor of such challenges, called upon the
challenger to produce his solution. Keill was unable to do this; and
after some attempts at procrastination, was driven to very paltry
evasions. Bernoulli then published his solution, with very just
expressions of scorn towards his antagonist. And this may, perhaps, be
considered as the first material addition which was made to the
Principia by subsequent writers.
6. Constellation of Mathematicians.—We pass with
admiration along the great series of mathematicians, by whom the
science of theoretical mechanics has been cultivated, from the time of
Newton to our own. There is no group of men of science whose fame is
367 higher or
brighter. The great discoveries of Copernicus, Galileo, Newton, had
fixed all eyes on those portions of human knowledge on which their
successors employed their labors. The certainty belonging to this line
of speculation seemed to elevate mathematicians above the students of
other subjects; and the beauty of mathematical relations, and the
subtlety of intellect which may be shown in dealing with them, were
fitted to win unbounded applause. The successors of Newton and the
Bernoullis, as Euler, Clairaut, D’Alembert, Lagrange, Laplace, not to
introduce living names, have been some of the most remarkable men of
talent which the world has seen. That their talent is, for the most
part, of a different kind from that by which the laws of nature were
discovered, I shall have occasion to explain elsewhere; for the
present, I must endeavor to arrange the principal achievements of
those whom I have mentioned.
The series of persons is connected by social relations. Euler was
the pupil of the first generation of Bernoullis, and the intimate
friend of the second generation; and all these extraordinary men, as
well as Hermann, were of the city of Basil, in that age a spot fertile
of great mathematicians to an unparalleled degree. In 1740, Clairaut
and Maupertuis visited John Bernoulli, at that time the Nestor of
mathematicians, who died, full of age and honors, in 1748. Euler,
several of the Bernoullis, Maupertuis, Lagrange, among other
mathematicians of smaller note, were called into the north by
Catharine of Russia and Frederic of Prussia, to inspire and instruct
academies which the brilliant fame then attached to science, had
induced those monarchs to establish. The prizes proposed by these
societies, and by the French Academy of Sciences, gave occasion to
many of the most valuable mathematical works of the century.
7. The Problem of Three Bodies.—In 1747,
Clairaut and D’Alembert sent, on the same day, to this body, their
solutions of the celebrated “Problem of Three Bodies,” which, from
that time, became the great object of attention of
mathematicians;—the bow in which each tried his strength, and
endeavored to shoot further than his predecessors.
This problem was, in fact, the astronomical question of the effect
produced by the attraction of the sun, in disturbing the motions of
the moon about the earth; or by the attraction of one planet,
disturbing the motion of another planet about the sun; but being
expressed generally, as referring to one body which disturbs any two
others, it became a mechanical problem, and the history of it belongs
to the present subject. 368
One consequence of the synthetical form adopted by Newton in the
Principia, was, that his successors had the problem of the
solar system to begin entirely anew. Those who would not do this, made
no progress, as was long the case with the English. Clairaut says,
that he tried for a long time to make some use of Newton’s labors; but
that, at last, he resolved to take up the subject in an independent
manner. This, accordingly, he did, using analysis throughout, and
following methods not much different from those still employed. We do
not now speak of the comparison of this theory with observation,
except to remark, that both by the agreements and by the discrepancies
of this comparison, Clairaut and other writers were perpetually driven
on to carry forwards the calculation to a greater and greater degree
of accuracy.
One of the most important of the cases in which this happened, was
that of the movement of the Apogee of the Moon; and in this case, a
mode of approximating to the truth, which had been depended on as
nearly exact, was, after having caused great perplexity, found by
Clairaut and Euler to give only half the truth. This same Problem of
Three Bodies was the occasion of a memoir of Clairaut, which gained
the prize of the Academy of St. Petersburg in 1751; and, finally, of
his Théorie de la Lune, published in 1765. D’Alembert labored
at the same time on the same problem; and the value of their methods,
and the merit of the inventors, unhappily became a subject of
controversy between those two great mathematicians. Euler also, in
1753, published a Theory of the Moon, which was, perhaps, more
useful than either of the others, since it was afterwards the basis of
Mayer’s method, and of his Tables. It is difficult to give the general
reader any distinct notion of these solutions. We may observe, that
the quantities which determine the moon’s position, are to be
determined by means of certain algebraical equations, which express
the mechanical conditions of the motion. The operation, by which the
result is to be obtained, involves the process of integration; which,
in this instance, cannot be performed in an immediate and definite
manner; since the quantities thus to be operated on depend upon the
moon’s position, and thus require us to know the very thing which we
have to determine by the operation. The result must be got at,
therefore, by successive approximations: we must first find a quantity
near the truth; and then, by the help of this, one nearer still; and
so on; and, in this manner, the moon’s place will be given by a
converging series of terms. The form of these terms depends upon the
relations of position between the sun 369 and moon, their apogees, the moon’s
nodes, and other quantities; and by the variety of combinations of
which these admit, the terms become very numerous and complex. The
magnitude of the terms depends also upon various circumstances; as the
relative force of the sun and earth, the relative times of the solar
and lunar revolutions, the eccentricities and inclinations of the two
orbits. These are combined so as to give terms of different orders of
magnitudes; and it depends upon the skill and perseverance of the
mathematician how far he will continue this series of terms. For there
is no limit to their number: and though the methods of which we have
spoken do theoretically enable us to calculate as many terms as we
please, the labor and the complexity of the operations are so serious
that common calculators are stopped by them. None but very great
mathematicians have been able to walk safely any considerable distance
into this avenue,—so rapidly does it darken as we proceed. And
even the possibility of doing what has been done, depends upon what we
may call accidental circumstances; the smallness of the inclinations
and eccentricities of the system, and the like. “If nature had not
favored us in this way,” Lagrange used to say, “there would have been
an end of the geometers in this problem.” The expected return of the
comet of 1682 in 1759, gave a new interest to the problem, and
Clairaut proceeded to calculate the case which was thus suggested.
When this was treated by the methods which had succeeded for the moon,
it offered no prospect of success, in consequence of the absence of
the favorable circumstances just referred to, and, accordingly,
Clairaut, after obtaining the six equations to which he reduces the
solution,49 adds, “Integrate them who can” (Intègre
maintenant qui pourra). New methods of approximation were devised for
this case.
49 Journal des Sçavans, Aug.
1759.
The problem of three bodies was not prosecuted in consequence of
its analytical beauty, or its intrinsic attraction; but its great
difficulties were thus resolutely combated from necessity; because in
no other way could the theory of universal gravitation be known to be
true or made to be useful. The construction of Tables of the
Moon, an object which offered a large pecuniary reward, as well as
mathematical glory, to the successful adventurer, was the main purpose
of these labors.
The Theory of the Planets presented the Problem of Three
Bodies in a new form, and involved in peculiar difficulties; for the
370 approximations
which succeed in the Lunar theory fail here. Artifices somewhat
modified are required to overcome the difficulties of this case.
Euler had investigated, in particular, the motions of Jupiter and
Saturn, in which there was a secular acceleration and retardation,
known by observation, but not easily explicable by theory. Euler’s
memoirs, which gained the prize of the French Academy, in 1748 and
1752, contained much beautiful analysis; and Lagrange published also a
theory of Jupiter and Saturn, in which he obtained results different
from those of Euler. Laplace, in 1787, showed that this inequality
arose from the circumstance that two of Saturn’s years are very nearly
equal to five of Jupiter’s.
The problems relating to Jupiter’s Satellites, were found to
be even more complex than those which refer to the planets: for it was
necessary to consider each satellite as disturbed by the other three
at once; and thus there occurred the Problem of Five Bodies.
This problem was resolved by Lagrange.50
50 Bailly, Ast. Mod. iii.
178.
Again, the newly-discovered small Planets, Juno, Ceres,
Vesta, Pallas, whose orbits almost coincide with each other, and are
more inclined and more eccentric than those of the ancient planets,
give rise, by their perturbations, to new forms of the problem, and
require new artifices.
In the course of these researches respecting Jupiter, Lagrange and
Laplace were led to consider particularly the secular
Inequalities of the solar system; that is, those inequalities in
which the duration of the cycle of change embraces very many
revolutions of the bodies themselves. Euler in 1749 and 1755, and
Lagrange51 in 1766, had introduced the method of
the Variation of the Elements of the orbit; which consists in
tracing the effect of the perturbing forces, not as directly altering
the place of the planet, but as producing a change from one instant to
another, in the dimensions and position of the Elliptical orbit which
the planet describes.52 Taking this view, he 371 determines the
secular changes of each of the elements or determining
quantities of the orbit. In 1773, Laplace also attacked this subject
of secular changes, and obtained expressions for them. On this
occasion, he proved the celebrated proposition that, “the mean motions
of the planets are invariable:” that is, that there is, in the
revolutions of the system, no progressive change which is not finally
stopped and reversed; no increase, which is not, after some period,
changed into decrease; no retardation which is not at last succeeded
by acceleration; although, in some cases, millions of years may elapse
before the system reaches the turning-point. Thomas Simpson noticed
the same consequence of the laws of universal attraction. In 1774 and
1776, Lagrange53 still labored at the secular equations;
extending his researches to the nodes and inclinations; and showed
that the invariability of the mean motions of the planets, which
Laplace had proved, neglecting the fourth powers of the eccentricities
and inclinations of the orbits,54 was true,
however far the approximation was carried, so long as the squares of
the disturbing masses were neglected. He afterwards improved his
methods;55 and, in 1783, he endeavored to extend
the calculation of the changes of the elements to the periodical
equations, as well as the secular.
51 Gautier, Prob. de Trois
Corps, p. 155.
52 In the first edition of this
History, I had ascribed to Lagrange the invention of the Method of
Variation of Elements in the theory of Perturbations. But justice to
Euler requires that we should assign this distinction to him; at
least, next to Newton, whose mode of representing the paths of bodies
by means of a Revolving Orbit, in the Ninth Section of the
Principia, may be considered as an anticipation of the method
of variation of elements. In the fifth volume of the Mécanique
Céleste, livre xv. p. 305, is an abstract of Euler’s paper of
1749; where Laplace adds, “C’est le premier essai de la méthode de la
variation des constantes arbitraires.” And in page 310 is an abstract
of the paper of 1756: and speaking of the method, Laplace says, “It
consists in regarding the elements of the elliptical motion as
variable in virtue of the perturbing forces. Those elements are, 1,
the axis major; 2, the epoch of the body being at the apse; 3, the
eccentricity; 4, the movement of the apse; 5, the inclination; 6, the
longitude of the node;” and he then proceeds to show how Euler did
this. It is possible that Lagrange knew nothing of Euler’s paper. See
Méc. Cél. vol. v. p. 312. But Euler’s conception and treatment
of the method are complete, so that he must be looked upon as the
author of it.
53 Gautier, p. 104.
54 Ib. p. 184.
55 Ib. p. 196.
8. Mécanique Céleste, &c.—Laplace also
resumed the consideration of the secular changes; and, finally,
undertook his vast work, the Mécanique Céleste, which he
intended to contain a complete view of the existing state of this
splendid department of science. We may see, in the exultation which
the author obviously feels at the thought of erecting this monument of
his age, the enthusiasm which had been excited by the splendid course
of mathematical successes of which I have given a sketch. The two
first volumes of this great work appeared in 1799. The third and
fourth volumes were published in 1802 and 1805 respectively. Since its
publication, little has been added to the solution of the great
problems of which it treats. In 1808, Laplace presented to the French
Bureau des Longitudes, a Supplement to the Mécanique Céleste;
the object of which was to improve still further 372 the mode of obtaining
the secular variations of the elements. Poisson and Lagrange proved
the invariability of the major axes of the orbits, as far as the
second order of the perturbing forces. Various other authors have
since labored at this subject. Burckhardt, in 1808, extended the
perturbing function as far as the sixth order of the eccentricities.
Gauss, Hansen, and Bessel, Ivory, MM. Lubbock, Plana, Pontécoulant,
and Airy, have, at different periods up to the present time, either
extended or illustrated some particular part of the theory, or applied
it to special cases; as in the instance of Professor Airy’s
calculation of an inequality of Venus and the earth, of which the
period is 240 years. The approximation of the Moon’s motions has been
pushed to an almost incredible extent by M. Damoiseau, and, finally,
Plana has once more attempted to present, in a single work (three
thick quarto volumes), all that has hitherto been executed with regard
to the theory of the Moon.
I give only the leading points of the progress of analytical
dynamics. Hence I have not spoken in detail of the theory of the
Satellites of Jupiter, a subject on which Lagrange gained a prize for
a Memoir, in 1766, and in which Laplace discovered some most curious
properties in 1784. Still less have I referred to the purely
speculative question of Tautochronous Curves in a resisting
medium, though it was a subject of the labors of Bernoulli, Euler,
Fontaine, D’Alembert, Lagrange, and Laplace. The reader will rightly
suppose that many other curious investigations are passed over in
utter silence.
[2d Ed.] [Although the analytical calculations of the great
mathematicians of the last century had determined, in a demonstrative
manner, a vast series of inequalities to which the motions of the sun,
moon, and planets were subject in virtue of their mutual attraction,
there were still unsatisfactory points in the solutions thus given of
the great mechanical problems suggested by the System of the Universe.
One of these points was the want of any evident mechanical
significance in the successive members of these series. Lindenau
relates that Lagrange, near the end of his life, expressed his sorrow
that the methods of approximation employed in Physical Astronomy
rested on arbitrary processes, and not on any insight into the results
of mechanical action. But something was subsequently done to remove
the ground of this complaint. In 1818, Gauss pointed out that secular
equations may be conceived to result from the disturbing body being
distributed along its orbit so as to form a ring, and thus made the
result conceivable more distinctly than as a mere result of
calculation. And it appears 373 to me that Professor Airy’s treatise
entitled Gravitation, published at Cambridge in 1834, is of
great value in supplying similar modes of conception with regard to
the mechanical origin of many of the principal inequalities of the
solar system.
Bessel in 1824, and Hansen in 1828, published works which are
considered as belonging, along with those of Gauss, to a new era in
physical astronomy.56 Gauss’s Theoria Motuum Corporum
Celestium, which had Lalande’s medal assigned to it by the French
Institute, had already (1810) resolved all problems concerning the
determination of the place of a planet or comet in its orbit in
function of the elements. The value of Hansen’s labors respecting the
Perturbations of the Planets was recognized by the Astronomical
Society of London, which awarded to them its gold medal.
56 Abhand. der Akad. d. Wissensch.
zu Berlin. 1824; and Disquisitiones circa Theoriam
Perturbationum. See Jahn. Gesch. der Astron. p. 84.
The investigations of M. Damoiseau, and of MM. Plana and Carlini,
on the Problem of the Lunar Theory, followed nearly the same course as
those of their predecessors. In these, as in the Mécanique
Céleste and in preceding works on the same subject, the Moon’s
co-ordinates (time, radius vector, and latitude) were expressed in
function of her true longitude. The integrations were effected in
series, and then by reversion of the series, the longitude was
expressed in function of the time; and then in the same manner the
other two co-ordinates. But Sir John Lubbock and M. Pontécoulant have
made the mean longitude of the moon, that is, the time, the
independent variable, and have expressed the moon’s co-ordinates in
terms of sines and cosines of angles increasing proportionally to the
time. And this method has been adopted by M. Poisson (Mem.
Inst. xiii. 1835, p. 212). M. Damoiseau, like Laplace and
Clairaut, had deduced the successive coefficients of the lunar
inequalities by numerical equations. But M. Plana expresses explicitly
each coefficient in general terms of the letters expressing the
constants of the problem, arranging them according to the order of the
quantities, and substituting numbers at the end of the operation only.
By attending to this arrangement, MM. Lubbock and Pontécoulant have
verified or corrected a large portion of the terms contained in the
investigations of MM. Damoiseau and Plana. Sir John Lubbock has
calculated the polar co-ordinates of the Moon directly; M. Poisson, on
the other hand, has obtained the variable elliptical elements; M.
Pontécoulant conceives that the method of variation or arbitrary 374 constants may most
conveniently be reserved for secular inequalities and inequalities of
long periods.
MM. Lubbock and Pontécoulant have made the mode of treating the
Lunar Theory and the Planetary Theory agree with each other, instead
of following two different paths in the calculation of the two
problems, which had previously been done.
Prof. Hansen, also, in his Fundamenta Nova Investigationis
Orbitæ veræ quam Luna perlustrat (Gothæ, 1838), gives a
general method, including the Lunar Theory and the Planetary Theory as
two special cases. To this is annexed a solution of the Problem of
Four Bodies.
I am here speaking of the Lunar and Planetary Theories as
Mechanical Problems only. Connected with this subject, I will not omit
to notice a very general and beautiful method of solving problems
respecting the motion of systems of mutually attracting bodies, given by
Sir W. R. Hamilton, in the Philosophical Transactions for
1834–5 (“On a General Method in Dynamics”). His method consists
in investigating the Principal Function of the co-ordinates of
the bodies: this function being one, by the differentiation of which,
the co-ordinates of the bodies of the system may be found. Moreover,
an approximate value of this function being obtained, the same formulæ
supply a means of successive approximation without limit.]
9. Precession. Motion of Rigid Bodies.—The series of
investigations of which I have spoken, extensive and complex as it is,
treats the moving bodies as points only, and takes no account of any
peculiarity of their form or motion of their parts. The investigation
of the motion of a body of any magnitude and form, is another branch
of analytical mechanics, which well deserves notice. Like the former
branch, it mainly owed its cultivation to the problems suggested by
the solar system. Newton, as we have seen, endeavored to calculate the
effect of the attraction of the sun and moon in producing the
precession of the equinoxes; but in doing this he made some
mistakes. In 1747, D’Alembert solved this problem by the aid of his
“Principle;” and it was not difficult for him to show, as he did in
his Opuscules, in 1761, that the same method enabled him to
determine the motion of a body of any figure acted upon by any forces.
But, as the reader will have observed in the course of this narrative,
the great mathematicians of this period were always nearly abreast of
each other in their advances.—Euler,57 in the mean
time, had published, in 1751, a solution of the 375 problem of the
precession; and in 1752, a memoir which he entitled Discovery of a
New Principle of Mechanics, and which contains a solution of the
general problem of the alteration of rotary motion by forces.
D’Alembert noticed with disapprobation the assumption of priority
which this title implied, though allowing the merit of the memoir.
Various improvements were made in these solutions; but the final form
was given them by Euler; and they were applied to a great variety of
problems in his Theory of the Motion of Solid and Rigid Bodies,
which was written58 about 1760, and published in 1765. The
formulæ in this work were much simplified by the use of a discovery of
Segner, that every body has three axes which were called Principal
Axes, about which alone (in general) it would permanently revolve. The
equations which Euler and other writers had obtained, were attacked as
erroneous by Landen in the Philosophical Transactions for 1785; but I
think it is impossible to consider this criticism otherwise than as an
example of the inability of the English mathematicians of that period
to take a steady hold of the analytical generalizations to which the
great Continental authors had been led. Perhaps one of the most
remarkable calculations of the motion of a rigid body is that which
Lagrange performed with regard to the Moon’s Libration; and by
which he showed that the Nodes of the Moon’s Equator and those of her
Orbit must always coincide.
57 Ac. Berl. 1745, 1750.
58 See the preface to the book.
10. Vibrating Strings.—Other mechanical questions,
unconnected with astronomy, were also pursued with great zeal and
success. Among these was the problem of a vibrating string, stretched
between two fixed points. There is not much complexity in the
mechanical conceptions which belong to this case, but considerable
difficulty in reducing them to analysis. Taylor, in his Method of
Increments, published in 1716, had annexed to his work a solution
of this problem; obtained on suppositions, limited indeed, but
apparently conformable to the most common circumstances of practice.
John Bernoulli, in 1728, had also treated the same problem. But it
assumed an interest altogether new, when, in 1747, D’Alembert
published his views on the subject; in which he maintained that,
instead of one kind of curve only, there were an infinite number of
different curves, which answered the conditions of the question. The
problem, thus put forward by one great mathematician, was, as usual,
taken up by the others, whose names the reader is now so familiar with
in such an association. In 376 1748, Euler not only assented to the
generalization of D’Alembert, but held that it was not necessary that
the curves so introduced should be defined by any algebraical
condition whatever. From this extreme indeterminateness D’Alembert
dissented; while Daniel Bernoulli, trusting more to physical and less
to analytical reasonings, maintained that both these generalizations
were inapplicable in fact, and that the solution was really
restricted, as had at first been supposed, to the form of the
trochoid, and to other forms derivable from that. He introduced, in
such problems, the “Law of Coexistent Vibrations,” which is of eminent
use in enabling us to conceive the results of complex mechanical
conditions, and the real import of many analytical expressions. In the
mean time, the wonderful analytical genius of Lagrange had applied
itself to this problem. He had formed the Academy of Turin, in
conjunction with his friends Saluces and Cigna; and the first memoir
in their Transactions was one by him on this subject: in this and in
subsequent writings he has established, to the satisfaction of the
mathematical world, that the functions introduced in such cases are
not necessarily continuous, but are arbitrary to the same degree that
the motion is so practically; though capable of expression by a series
of circular functions. This controversy, concerning the degree of
lawlessness with which the conditions of the solution may be assumed,
is of consequence, not only with respect to vibrating strings, but
also with respect to many problems, belonging to a branch of Mechanics
which we now have to mention, the Doctrine of Fluids.
11. Equilibrium of Fluids. Figure of the Earth.
Tides.—The application of the general doctrines of Mechanics
to fluids was a natural and inevitable step, when the principles of
the science had been generalized. It was easily seen that a fluid is,
for this purpose, nothing more than a body of which the parts are
movable amongst each other with entire facility; and that the
mathematician must trace the consequences of this condition upon his
equations. This accordingly was done, by the founders of mechanics,
both for the cases of the equilibrium and of motion. Newton’s attempt
to solve the problem of the figure of the earth, supposing it
fluid, is the first example of such an investigation: and this
solution rested upon principles which we have already explained,
applied with the skill and sagacity which distinguished all that
Newton did.
We have already seen how the generality of
the principle, that fluids press equally in all directions, was
established. In applying it to calculation, Newton took for his
fundamental principle, the equal 377 weight of columns of the fluid reaching
to the centre; Huyghens took, as his basis, the perpendicularity of the resulting force at
each point to the surface of the fluid; Bouguer conceived that both
principles were necessary; and Clairaut showed that the equilibrium of
all canals is requisite. He also was the first mathematician
who deduced from this principle the Equations of Partial Differentials
by which these laws are expressed; a step which, as Lagrange says,59 changed the face of Hydrostatics, and
made it a new science. Euler simplified the mode of obtaining the
Equations of Equilibrium for any forces whatever; and put them in the
form which is now generally adopted in our treatises.
59 Méc. Analyt. ii. p.
180.
The explanation of the Tides, in the way in which Newton
attempted it in the third book of the Principia, is another
example of a hydrostatical investigation: for he considered only the
form that the ocean would have if it were at rest. The memoirs of
Maclaurin, Daniel Bernoulli, and Euler, on the question of the Tides,
which shared among them the prize of the Academy of Sciences in 1740,
went upon the same views.
The Treatise of the Figure of the Earth, by Clairaut, in
1743, extended Newton’s solution of the same problem, by supposing a
solid nucleus covered with a fluid of different density. No peculiar
novelty has been introduced into this subject, except a method
employed by Laplace for determining the attractions of spheroids of
small eccentricity, which is, as Professor Airy has said,60 “a calculus the most singular in its
nature, and the most powerful in its effects, of any which has yet
appeared.”
60 Enc. Met. Fig. of Earth, p.
192.
12. Capillary Action.—There is only one other problem
of the statics of fluids on which it is necessary to say a
word,—the doctrine of Capillary Attraction. Daniel Bernoulli,61 in 1738, states that he passes over the
subject, because he could not reduce the facts to general laws: but
Clairaut was more successful, and Laplace and Poisson have since given
great analytical completeness to his theory. At present our business
is, not so much with the sufficiency of the theory to explain
phenomena, as with the mechanical problem of which this is an example,
which is one of a very remarkable and important character; namely, to
determine the effect of attractions which are exercised by all the
particles of bodies, on the hypothesis that the 378 attraction of each
particle, though sensible when it acts upon another particle at an
extremely small distance from it, becomes insensible and vanishes the
moment this distance assumes a perceptible magnitude. It may easily be
imagined that the analysis by which results are obtained under
conditions so general and so peculiar, is curious and abstract; the
problem has been resolved in some very extensive cases.
61 Hydrodyn. Pref. p. 5.
13. Motion of Fluids.—The only branch of mathematical
mechanics which remains to be considered, is that which is, we may
venture to say, hitherto incomparably the most incomplete of
all,—Hydrodynamics. It may easily be imagined that the mere
hypothesis of absolute relative mobility in the parts, combined with
the laws of motion and nothing more, are conditions too vague and
general to lead to definite conclusions. Yet such are the conditions
of the problems which relate to the motion of fluids. Accordingly, the
mode of solving them has been, to introduce certain other hypotheses,
often acknowledged to be false, and almost always in some measure
arbitrary, which may assist in determining and obtaining the solution.
The Velocity of a fluid issuing from an orifice in a vessel, and the
Resistance which a solid body suffers in moving in a fluid, have been
the two main problems on which mathematicians have employed
themselves. We have already spoken of the manner in which Newton
attacked both these, and endeavored to connect them. The subject
became a branch of Analytical Mechanics by the labors of D. Bernoulli,
whose Hydrodynamica was published in 1738. This work rests upon
the Huyghenian principle of which we have already spoken in the history of the centre of
oscillation; namely, the equality of the actual descent of
the particles and the potential ascent; or, in other words,
the conservation of vis viva. This was the first analytical
treatise; and the analysis is declared by Lagrange to be as elegant in
its steps as it is simple in its results. Maclaurin also treated the
subject; but is accused of reasoning in such a way as to show that he
had determined upon his result beforehand; and the method of John
Bernoulli, who likewise wrote upon it, has been strongly objected to
by D’Alembert. D’Alembert himself applied the principle which bears
his name to this subject; publishing a Treatise on the Equilibrium
and Motion of Fluids in 1744, and on the Resistance of
Fluids in 1753. His Réflexions sur la Cause Générale des
Vents, printed in 1747, are also a celebrated work, belonging to
this part of mathematics. Euler, in this as in other cases, was one of
those who most contributed to give analytical elegance to the subject.
In addition to the questions which 379 have been mentioned, he and Lagrange
treated the problems of the small vibrations of fluids, both inelastic
and elastic;—a subject which leads, like the question of
vibrating strings, to some subtle and abstruse considerations
concerning the significations of the integrals of partial differential
equations. Laplace also took up the subject of waves propagated along
the surface of water; and deduced a very celebrated theory of the
tides, in which he considered the ocean to be, not in equilibrium, as
preceding writers had supposed, but agitated by a constant series of
undulations, produced by the solar and lunar forces. The difficulty of
such an investigation may be judged of from this, that Laplace, in
order to carry it on, is obliged to assume a mechanical proposition,
unproved, and only conjectured to be true; namely,62 that, “in a
system of bodies acted upon by forces which are periodical, the state
of the system is periodical like the forces.” Even with this
assumption, various other arbitrary processes are requisite; and it
appears still very doubtful whether Laplace’s theory is either a
better mechanical solution of the problem, or a nearer approximation
to the laws of the phenomena, than that obtained by D. Bernoulli,
following the views of Newton.
62 Méc. Cél. t. ii. p.
218.
In most cases, the solutions of problems of hydrodynamics are not
satisfactorily confirmed by the results of observation. Poisson and
Cauchy have prosecuted the subject of waves, and have deduced very
curious conclusions by a very recondite and profound analysis. The
assumptions of the mathematician here do not represent the conditions
of nature; the rules of theory, therefore, are not a good standard to
which we may refer the aberrations of particular cases; and the laws
which we obtain from experiment are very imperfectly illustrated by
à priori calculation. The case of this department of knowledge,
Hydrodynamics, is very peculiar; we have reached the highest point of
the science,—the laws of extreme simplicity and generality from
which the phenomena flow; we cannot doubt that the ultimate principles
which we have obtained are the true ones, and those which really apply
to the facts; and yet we are far from being able to apply the
principles to explain or find out the facts. In order to do this, we
want, in addition to what we have, true and useful principles,
intermediate between the highest and the lowest;—between the
extreme and almost barren generality of the laws of motion, and the
endless varieties and inextricable complexity of fluid motions in
special cases. 380
The reason of this peculiarity in the science of Hydrodynamics appears
to be, that its general principles were not discovered with reference
to the science itself, but by extension from the sister science of the
Mechanics of Solids; they were not obtained by ascending gradually
from particulars, to truths more and more general, respecting the
motions of fluids; but were caught at once, by a perception that the
parts of fluids are included in that range of generality which we are
entitled to give to the supreme laws of motions of solids. Thus, Solid
Dynamics and Fluid Dynamics resemble two edifices which have their
highest apartment in common, and though we can explore every part of
the former building, we have not yet succeeded in traversing the
staircase of the latter, either from the top or from the bottom. If we
had lived in a world in which there were no solid bodies, we should
probably not have yet discovered the laws of motion; if we had lived
in a world in which there were no fluids, we should have no idea how
insufficient a complete possession of the general laws of motion may
be, to give us a true knowledge of particular results.
14. Various General Mechanical Principles.—The
generalized laws of motion, the points to which I have endeavored to
conduct my history, include in them all other laws by which the
motions of bodies can be regulated; and among such, several laws which
had been discovered before the highest point of generalization was
reached, and which thus served as stepping-stones to the ultimate
principles. Such were, as we have seen, the Principles of the
Conservation of vis viva, the Principle of the Conservation of
the Motion of the Centre of Gravity, and the like. These principles
may, of course, be deduced from our elementary laws, and were finally
established by mathematicians on that footing. There are other
principles which may be similarly demonstrated; among the rest, I may
mention the Principle of the Conservation of areas, which
extends to any number of bodies a law analogous to that which Kepler
had observed, and Newton demonstrated, respecting the areas described
by each planet round the sun. I may mention also, the Principle of the
Immobility of the plane of maximum areas, a plane which is not
disturbed by any mutual action of the parts of any system. The former
of these principles was published about the same time by Euler, D.
Bernoulli, and Darcy, under different forms, in 1746 and 1747; the
latter by Laplace.
To these may be added a law, very celebrated in its time, and the
occasion of an angry controversy, the Principle of least
action. 381
Maupertuis conceived that he could establish à priori, by
theological arguments, that all mechanical changes must take place in
the world so as to occasion the least possible quantity of
action. In asserting this, it was proposed to measure the
Action by the product of Velocity and Space; and this measure being
adopted, the mathematicians, though they did not generally assent to
Maupertuis’ reasonings, found that his principle expressed a
remarkable and useful truth, which might be established on known
mechanical grounds.
15. Analytical Generality. Connection of Statics and
Dynamics.—Before I quit this subject, it is important to
remark the peculiar character which the science of Mechanics has now
assumed, in consequence of the extreme analytical generality which has
been given it. Symbols, and operations upon symbols, include the whole
of the reasoner’s task; and though the relations of space are the
leading subjects in the science, the great analytical treatises upon
it do not contain a single diagram. The Mécanique Analytique of
Lagrange, of which the first edition appeared in 1788, is by far the
most consummate example of this analytical generality. “The plan of
this work,” says the author, “is entirely new. I have proposed to
myself to reduce the whole theory of this science, and the art of
resolving the problems which it includes, to general formulæ, of which
the simple development gives all the equations necessary for the
solution of the problem.”—“The reader will find no figures in
the work. The methods which I deliver do not require either
constructions, or geometrical or mechanical reasonings; but only
algebraical operations, subject to a regular and uniform rule of
proceeding.” Thus this writer makes Mechanics a branch of Analysis;
instead of making, as had previously been done, Analysis an implement
of Mechanics.63 The transcendent generalizing genius of
Lagrange, and his matchless analytical skill and elegance, have made
this undertaking as successful as it is striking.
63 Lagrange himself terms Mechanics,
“An Analytical Geometry of four dimensions.” Besides the three
co-ordinates which determine the place of a body in space,
the time enters as a fourth co-ordinate. [Note by
Littrow.]
The mathematical reader is aware that the language of mathematical
symbols is, in its nature, more general than the language of words:
and that in this way truths, translated into symbols, often suggest
their own generalizations. Something of this kind has happened in
Mechanics. The same Formula expresses the general condition of Statics
and that of Dynamics. The tendency to generalization which is thus
introduced by analysis, makes mathematicians unwilling to 382 acknowledge a
plurality of Mechanical principles; and in the most recent analytical
treatises on the subject, all the doctrines are deduced from the
single Law of Inertia. Indeed, if we identify Forces with the
Velocities which produce them, and allow the Composition of Forces to
be applicable to force so understood, it is easy to see that
we can reduce the Laws of Motion to the Principles of Statics; and
this conjunction, though it may not be considered as philosophically
just, is verbally correct. If we thus multiply or extend the meanings
of the term Force, we make our elementary principles simpler and fewer
than before; and those persons, therefore, who are willing to assent
to such a use of words, can thus obtain an additional generalisation
of dynamical principles; and this, as I have stated, has been adopted
in several recent treatises. I shall not further discuss here how far
this is a real advance in science.
Having thus rapidly gone through the history of Force and
Attraction in the abstract, we return to the attempt to interpret the
phenomena of the universe by the aid of these abstractions thus
established.
But before we do so, we may make one remark on the history of this
part of science. In consequence of the vast career into which the
Doctrine of Motion has been drawn by the splendid problems proposed to
it by Astronomy, the origin and starting-point of Mechanics, namely
Machines, had almost been lost out of sight. Machines had
become the smallest part of Mechanics, as
Land-measuring had become the smallest part of
Geometry. Yet the application of Mathematics to the doctrine
of Machines has led, at all periods of the Science, and especially in
our own time, to curious and valuable results. Some of these will be
noticed in the Additions to this volume.


BOOK VII.

THE MECHANICAL SCIENCES.
(CONTINUED.)

HISTORY
OF
PHYSICAL ASTRONOMY.


DESCEND from heaven, Urania, by that name
If rightly thou art called, whose voice
divine
Following, above the Olympian hill I soar,
Above the flight of Pegasean wing.
The meaning, not the name, I call, for thou
Nor of the muses nine, nor on the top
Of old Olympus dwell’st: but heavenly-born,
Before the hills appeared, or fountain
flowed,
Thou with Eternal Wisdom didst converse,
Wisdom, thy sister.
Paradise Lost, B.
vii.   

</div></body></text></TEI>