<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="6">

CHAPTER VI.
The Fundamental Ideas are not Derived from Experience.



1. BY
the course of speculation contained in the last three
Chapters, we are again led to the conclusion which we have
already stated, that our knowledge contains an ideal
element, and that this element is not derived from
experience. For we have seen that there are propositions
which are known to be necessarily true; and that such
knowledge is not, and cannot be, obtained by mere
observation of actual facts. It has been shown, also, that
these necessary truths are the results of certain
fundamental ideas, such as those of space, number, and the
like. Hence it follows inevitably that these ideas and
others of the same kind are not derived from experience. For
these ideas possess a power of infusing into their
developments that very necessity which experience can in no
way bestow. This power they do not borrow from the external
world, but possess by their own nature. Thus we unfold out
of the Idea of Space the propositions of geometry, which are
plainly truths of the most rigorous necessity and
universality. But if the idea of space were merely collected
from observation of the external world, it could never
enable or entitle us to assert such propositions: it could
never authorize us to say that not merely some lines, but
all lines, not only have, but must have,
those properties which geometry teaches. Geometry in every
proposition speaks a language which experience never dares
to utter; and indeed of which she but half comprehends the
meaning. Experience sees that the assertions are true, but
she sees not how profound and absolute is their truth. 77
She unhesitatingly assents to the laws which geometry
delivers, but she does not pretend to see the origin of
their obligation. She is always ready to acknowledge the
sway of pure scientific principles as a matter of fact, but
she does not dream of offering her opinion on their
authority as a matter of right; still less can she justly
claim to be herself the source of that authority.
David Hume asserted7, that we are incapable of seeing in
any of the appearances which the world presents anything of
necessary connexion; and hence he inferred that our
knowledge cannot extend to any such connexion. It will be
seen from what we have said that we assent to his remark as
to the fact, but we differ from him altogether in the
consequence to be drawn from it. Our inference from Hume’s
observation is, not the truth of his conclusion, but the
falsehood of his premises;—not that, therefore, we can know
nothing of natural connexion, but that, therefore, we have
some other source of knowledge than experience:—not, that
we can have no idea of connexion or causation, because, in
his language, it cannot be the copy of an impression; but
that since we have such an idea, our ideas are not the
copies of our impressions.</div></body></text></TEI>