<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="22">
CHAPTER III.

The Stability of the Solar System.

There is a consequence resulting from the actual
structure of the solar system, which has been brought
to light by the investigations of mathematicians concerning
the cause and laws of its motions, and which
has an important bearing on our argument. It appears
that the arrangement which at present obtains
is precisely that which is necessary to secure the
stability of the system. This point we must endeavour
to explain.
If each planet were to revolve round the sun
without being affected by the other planets, there
would be a certain degree of regularity in its motion;
and this regularity would continue for ever.
But it appears, by the discovery of the law of universal[128]
gravitation, that the planets do not execute
their movements in this insulated and independent
manner. Each of them is acted on by the attraction
of all the rest. The Earth is constantly drawn by
Venus, by Mars, by Jupiter, bodies of various magnitudes,
perpetually changing their distances and positions
with regard to the earth; the Earth in return
is perpetually drawing these bodies. What, in the
course of time, will be the result of this mutual attraction?
All the planets are very small compared with the
sun, and therefore the derangement which they produce
in the motion of one of their number will be
very small in the course of one revolution. But this
gives us no security that the derangement may not
become very large in the course of many revolutions.
The cause acts perpetually, and it has the
whole extent of time to work in. Is it not easily
conceivable then that in the lapse of ages the derangements
of the motions of the planets may accumulate,
the orbits may change their form, their mutual
distances may be much increased or much
diminished? Is it not possible that these changes
may go on without limit, and end in the complete
subversion and ruin of the system?
If, for instance, the result of this mutual gravitation
should be to increase considerably the eccentricity
of the earth’s orbit, that is to make it a longer
and longer oval; or to make the moon approach
perpetually nearer and nearer the earth every revolution;
it is easy to see that in the one case our year
would change its character, as we have noticed in
the last section; in the other, our satellite might
finally fall to the earth, which must of course bring
about a dreadful catastrophe. If the positions of the
planetary orbits, with respect to that of the earth,
were to change much, the planets might sometimes
come very near us, and thus exaggerate the effects
of their attraction beyond calculable limits. Under
such circumstances, we might have “years of unequal[129]
length, and seasons of capricious temperature,
planets and moons of portentous size and aspect,
glaring and disappearing at uncertain intervals;”
tides like deluges, sweeping over whole continents;
and, perhaps, the collision of two of the planets, and
the consequent destruction of all organization on
both of them.
Nor is it, on a common examination of the history
of the solar system, at all clear that there is no tendency
to indefinite derangement. The fact really is,
that changes are taking place in the motions of the
heavenly bodies, which have gone on progressively
from the first dawn of science. The eccentricity of
the earth’s orbit has been diminishing from the earliest
observations to our times. The moon has been
moving quicker and quicker from the time of the
first recorded eclipses, and is now in advance, by
about four times her own breadth, of what her place
would have been if it had not been affected by this
acceleration. The obliquity of the ecliptic also is in
a state of diminution, and is now about two-fifths of
a degree less than it was in the time of Aristotle.
Will these changes go on without limit or reaction?
If so, we tend by natural causes to a termination of
the present system of things: If not, by what adjustment
or combination are we secured from such a
tendency? Is the system stable, and if so, what is the
condition on which its stability depends?
To answer these questions is far from easy. The
mechanical problem which they involve is no less
than this;—Having given the directions and velocities
with which about thirty bodies are moving at
one time, to find their places and motions after any
number of ages; each of the bodies, all the while,
attracting all the others, and being attracted by
them all.
It may readily be imagined that this is a problem
of extreme complexity, when it is considered that
every new configuration or arrangement of the bodies
will give rise to a new amount of action on[130]
each; and every new action to a new configuration.
Accordingly, the mathematical investigation of such
questions as the above was too difficult to be attempted
in the earlier periods of the progress of Physical
Astronomy. Newton did not undertake to demonstrate
either the stability or the instability of the system.
The decision of this point required a great
number of preparatory steps and simplifications, and
such progress in the invention and improvement of
mathematical methods, as occupied the best mathematicians
of Europe for the greater part of last
century. But, towards the end of that time, it was
shown by Lagrange and Laplace that the arrangements
of the solar system are stable: that in the long
run, the orbits and motions remain unchanged; and
that the changes in the orbits, which take place in
shorter periods, never transgress certain very moderate
limits. Each orbit undergoes deviations on this
side and on that of its average state; but these deviations
are never very great, and it finally recovers
from them, so that the average is preserved. The
planets produce perpetual perturbations in each
other’s motions, but these perturbations are not indefinitely
progressive, they are periodical: they
reach a maximum value and then diminish. The
periods which this restoration requires are, for the
most part, enormous; not less than thousands, and,
in some instances, millions of years; and hence it is,
that some of these apparent derangements have been
going on in the same direction since the beginning
of the history of the world. But the restoration is
in the sequel as complete as the derangement; and
in the meantime the disturbance never attains a sufficient
amount seriously to alter the adaptations of
the system.[17]
The same examination of the subject by which this
is proved, points out also the conditions on which
this stability depends. “I have succeeded in demonstrating,”[131]
says Laplace, “that whatever be the
masses of the planets, in consequence of the fact that
they all move in the same direction, in orbits of
small eccentricity, and slightly inclined to each other—their
secular inequalities are periodical and included
within narrow limits; so that the planetary system
will only oscillate about a mean state, and will never
deviate from it except by a very small quantity. The
ellipses of the planets have been, and always will be,
nearly circular. The ecliptic will never coincide with
the equator, and the entire extent of the variation in
its inclination cannot exceed three degrees.”
There exists, therefore, it appears, in the solar system,
a provision for the permanent regularity of its
motions; and this provision is found in the fact that
the orbits of the planets 
are nearly circular, and nearly
in the same plane, and the motions all in the same
direction, namely, from west to east.[18]
Now is it probable that the occurrence of these
conditions of stability in the disposition of the solar
system is the work of chance? Such a supposition
appears to be quite inadmissible. Any one of the orbits[132]
might have had any eccentricity.[19] In that of
Mercury, where it is much the greatest, it is only
one-fifth. How came it to pass that the orbits were
not more elongated? A little more or a little less
velocity in their original motions would have made
them so. They might have had any inclination to
the ecliptic from no degrees to 90 degrees. Mercury,
which again deviates most widely, is inclined 7¾ degrees,
Venus 3¾, Saturn 2¾, Jupiter 1½, Mars 2. How
came it that their motions are thus contained within
such a narrow strip of the sky? One, or any number
of them, might have moved from east to west:
none of them does so. And these circumstances,
which appear to be, each in particular, requisite for
the stability of the system and the smallness of its disturbances,
are all found in combination. Does not
this imply both clear purpose and profound skill?
It is difficult to convey an adequate notion of the
extreme complexity of the task thus executed. A
number of bodies, all attracting each other, are to be
projected in such a manner that their revolutions
shall be permanent and stable, their mutual perturbations
always small. If we return to the basin with
its rolling balls, by which we before represented the
solar system, we must complicate with new conditions
the trial of skill which we supposed. The problem
must now be to project at once seven such balls,
all connected by strings which influence their movements,
so that each may hit its respective mark.
And we must further suppose, that the marks are to
be hit after many thousand revolutions of the balls.
No one will imagine that this could be done by
accident.
In fact it is allowed by all those who have considered
this subject, that such a coincidence of the existing[133]
state with the mechanical requisites of permanency
cannot be accidental. Laplace has attempted
to calculate the probability that it is not the result of
accident. He takes into account, in addition to the
motions which we have mentioned, the revolutions
of the satellites about their primaries, and of the sun
and planets about their axes: and he finds that there
is a probability, far higher than that which we have
for the greater part of undoubted historical events,
that these appearances are not the effect of chance.
“We ought, therefore,” he says, “to believe, with at
least the same confidence, that a primitive cause has
directed the planetary motions.”
The solar system is thus, by the confession of all
sides, completely different from any thing which we
might anticipate from the casual operation of its
known laws. The laws of motion are no less obeyed
to the letter in the most irregular than in the most regular
motions; no less in the varied circuit of the
ball which flies round a tennis court, than in the going
of a clock; no less in the fantastical jets and leaps
which breakers make when they burst in a corner of
a rocky shore, than in the steady swell of the open
sea. The laws of motion alone will not produce the
regularity which we admire in the motions of the
heavenly bodies. There must be an original adjustment
of the system on which these laws are to act;
a selection of the arbitrary quantities which they are
to involve; a primitive cause which shall dispose the
elements in due relation to each other, in order that
regular recurrence may accompany constant change;
that perpetual motion may be combined with perpetual
stability; that derangements which go on increasing
for thousands or for millions of years may
finally cure themselves; and that the same laws which
lead the planets slightly aside from their paths, may
narrowly limit their deviations, and bring them back
from their almost imperceptible wanderings.
If a man does not deny that any possible peculiarity
in the disposition of the planets with regard to the[134]
sun could afford evidence of a controlling and ordering
purpose, it seems difficult to imagine how he
could look for evidence stronger than that which
there actually is. Of all the innumerable possible
cases of systems, governed by the existing laws of
force and motion, that one is selected which alone
produces such a steadfast periodicity, such a constant
average of circumstances, as are, so far as we can
conceive, necessary conditions for the existence of
organic and sentient life. And this selection is so far
from being an obvious or easily discovered means to
this end, that the most profound and attentive consideration
of the properties of space and number, with
all the appliances and aids we can obtain, are barely
sufficient to enable us to see that the end is thus secured,
and that it can be secured in no other way.
Surely the obvious impression which arises from this
view of the subject is, that the solar system, with its
adjustments, is the work of an intelligence, who perceives,
as self-evident, those truths, to which we attain
painfully and slowly, and after all imperfectly;
who has employed in every part of creation refined
contrivances, which we can only with effort understand;
and who, in innumerable instances, exhibits to
us what we should look upon as remarkable difficulties
remarkably overcome, if it were not that, through
the perfection of the provision, the trace of the difficulty
is almost obliterated.
</div></body></text></TEI>