<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="13"> 

CHAPTER III.
Of Methods of acquiring clear Scientific Ideas;
and first of Intellectual Education.


Aphorism XXIX.
The Methods by which the acquisition of clear Scientific
Ideas is promoted, are mainly two; Intellectual Education
and Discussion of Ideas.
Aphorism XXX.
The Idea of Space becomes more clear by studying Geometry;
the Idea of Force, by studying Mechanics; the Ideas
of Likeness, of Kind, of Subordination of Classes, by studying
Natural History.
Aphorism XXXI.
Elementary Mechanics should now form a part of intellectual
education, in order that the student may understand
the Theory of Universal Gravitation: for an intellectual
education should cultivate such ideas as enable the student to
understand the most complete and admirable portions of the
knowledge which the human race has attained to.
Aphorism XXXII.
Natural History ought to form a part of intellectual education,
in order to correct certain prejudices which arise from
cultivating the intellect by means of mathematics alone; and
in order to lead the student to see that the division of things
into Kinds, and the attribution and use of Names, are processes
susceptible of great precision. 165
THE
ways in which men become masters of those
clear and yet comprehensive conceptions which
the formation and reception of science require, are
mainly two; which, although we cannot reduce them
to any exact scheme, we may still, in a loose use of
the term, call Methods of acquiring clear Ideas. These
two ways are Education and Discussion.
1. (I.) Idea of Space.—It is easily seen that
Education may do at least something to render our ideas
distinct and precise. To learn Geometry in youth,
tends, manifestly, to render our idea of space clear and
exact. By such an education, all the relations, and all
the consequences of this idea, come to be readily and
steadily apprehended; and thus it becomes easy for us
to understand portions of science which otherwise we
should by no means be able to comprehend. The conception
of similar triangles was to be mastered, before
the disciples of Thales could see the validity of his
method of determining the height of lofty objects by
the length of their shadows. The conception of the
sphere with its circles had to become familiar, before
the annual motion of the sun and its influence upon
the lengths of days could be rightly traced. The
properties of circles, combined with the
pure13
doctrine of
motion, were required as an introduction to the theory
of Epicycles: the properties of conic sections were
needed, as a preparation for the discoveries of Kepler.
And not only was it necessary that men should possess
a knowledge of certain figures and their properties; but
it was equally necessary that they should have the
habit of reasoning with perfect steadiness, precision,
and conclusiveness concerning the relations of space.
No small discipline of the mind is requisite, in most
cases, to accustom it to go, with complete insight and
security, through the demonstrations respecting intersecting
planes and lines, dihedral and trihedral angles,
which occur in solid geometry. Yet how absolutely
necessary is a perfect mastery of such reasonings, to
him who is to explain the motions of the moon in 166
latitude and longitude! How necessary, again, is the
same faculty to the student of crystallography! Without
mathematical habits of conception and of thinking,
these portions of science are perfectly inaccessible. But
the early study of plane and solid geometry gives to
all tolerably gifted persons, the habits which are thus
needed. The discipline of following the reasonings of
didactic works on this subject, till we are quite familiar
with them, and of devising for ourselves reasonings of
the same kind, (as, for instance, the solutions of problems
proposed,) soon gives the mind the power of discoursing
with perfect facility concerning the most
complex and multiplied relations of space, and enables
us to refer to the properties of all plane and solid
figures as surely as to the visible forms of objects.
Thus we have here a signal instance of the efficacy of
education in giving to our Conceptions that clearness,
which the formation and existence of science indispensably require.</div></body></text></TEI>