<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="51">CHAPTER  III.
The Principia.

Sect. 2.—Reception of the Principia.
LORD BROUGHAM has very
recently (Analytical View of Sir Isaac Newton’s Principia,
1855) shown a strong disposition still to maintain, what he says has
frequently been alleged, that the reception of the work was not, even
in this country, “such as might have been expected.” He says, in
explanation of the facts which I have adduced, showing the high
estimation in which Newton was held immediately after the publication
of the Principia, that Newton’s previous fame was great by
former discoveries. This is true; but the effect of this was precisely
what was most honorable to Newton’s countrymen, that they received
with immediate acclamations this new and greater discovery. Lord
Brougham adds, “after its appearance the Principia was more
admired than studied;” which is probably true of the Principia
still, and of all great works of like novelty and difficulty at all
times. But, says Lord Brougham, “there is no getting over the
inference on this head which arises from the dates of the two first
editions. There elapsed an interval of no less than twenty-seven years
between them; and although Cotes [in his Preface] speaks of the copies
having become scarce and in very great demand when the second edition
appeared in 1713, yet had this urgent demand been of many years’
continuance, the reprinting could never have been so long delayed.”
But Lord Brougham might have learnt from Sir David Brewster’s Life
of Newton (vol. i. p. 312), which he extols so emphatically, that
already in 1691 (only four years after the publication), a copy of the
Principia could hardly be procured, and that even at that 549 time an improved
edition was in contemplation; that Newton had been pressed by his
friends to undertake it, and had refused.
When Bentley had induced Newton to consent that a new edition
should be printed, he announces his success with obvious exultation to
Cotes, who was to superintend the work. And in the mean time the
Astronomy of David Gregory, published in 1702, showed in every
page how familiar the Newtonian doctrines were to English
philosophers, and tended to make them more so, as the sermons of
Bentley himself had done in 1692.
Newton’s Cambridge contemporaries were among those who took a part
in bringing the Principia before the world. The manuscript
draft of it was conveyed to the Royal Society (April 28, 1686) by Dr.
Vincent, Fellow of Clare Hall, who was the tutor of Whiston, Newton’s
deputy in his professorship; and he, in presenting the work, spoke of
the novelty and dignity of the subject. There exists in the library of
the University of Cambridge a manuscript containing the early
Propositions of the Principia as far as Prop. xxxiii. (which is
a part of Section vii., about Falling Bodies). This appears to have
been a transcript of Newton’s Lectures, delivered as Lucasian
Professor: it is dated October, 1684.
Is Gravitation proportional to Quantity of Matter?
It was a portion of Newton’s assertion in his great discovery, that
all the bodies of the universe attract each other with forces which
are as the quantity of matter in each: that is, for instance,
the sun attracts the satellites of any planet just as much as he
attracts the planet itself, in proportion to the quantity of matter in
each; and the planets attract one another just as much as they attract
the sun, according to the quantity of matter.
To prove this part of the law exactly is a matter which
requires careful experiments; and though proved experimentally by
Newton, has been considered in our time worthy of re-examination by
the great astronomer Bessel. There was some ground for doubt; for the
mass of Jupiter, as deduced from the perturbations of Saturn, was only
1⁄1070 of the mass of the sun;
the mass of the same planet as deduced from the perturbations of Juno
and Pallas was  1⁄1045 of that of the Sun. If
this difference were to be confirmed by accurate observations and
calculations, it would follow that the attractive power exercised by
Jupiter upon the minor planets was greater than that exercised upon
550 Saturn. And in
the same way, if the attraction of the Earth had any specific
relation to different kinds of matter, the time of oscillation of a
pendulum of equal length composed wholly or in part of the two
substances would be different. If, for instance, it were more intense
for magnetized iron than for stone, the iron pendulum would oscillate
more quickly. Bessel showed47 that it was possible to assume
hypothetically a constitution of the sun, planets, and their
appendages, such that the attraction of the Sun on the Planets and
Satellites should be proportional to the quantity of matter in each;
but that the attraction of the Planets on one another would not be on
the same scale.
47 Berlin Mem. 1824.
Newton had made experiments (described in the Principia,
Book iii., Prop. vi.) by which it was shown that there could be no
considerable or palpable amount of such specific difference among
terrestrial bodies, but his experiments could not be regarded as exact
enough for the requirements of modern science. Bessel instituted a
laborious series of experiments (presented to the Berlin Academy in
1832) which completely disproved the conjecture of such a difference;
every substance examined having given exactly the same coefficient of
gravitating intensity as compared with inertia. Among the substances
examined were metallic and stony masses of meteoric origin, which
might be supposed, if any bodies could, to come from other parts of
the solar system.
</div></body></text></TEI>