<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="12">
CHAPTER XII.

The Laws of Magnetism.

Magnetism has no very obvious or apparently extensive
office in the mechanism of the atmosphere
and the earth: but the mention of it may be introduced,
because its ascertained relations to the other
powers which exist in the system are well suited to
show us the connexion subsisting throughout the universe,
and to check the suspicion, if any such should
arise, that any law of nature is without its use. The
parts of creation when these uses are most obscure,
are precisely those parts when the laws themselves
are least known.
When indeed we consider the vast service of
which magnetism is to man, by supplying him with
that invaluable instrument the mariners’ compass,
many persons will require no further evidence of this
property being introduced into the frame of things
with a worthy purpose. As however, we have hitherto
excluded use in the arts from our line of argument,
we shall not here make an exception in favour
of navigation, and what we shall observe belongs to
another view of the subject.
Magnetism has been discovered in modern times
to have so close a connexion with galvanism, that
they may be said to be almost different aspects of
the same agent. All the phenomena which we can
produce with magnets, we can imitate with coils of
galvanic wire. That galvanism exists in the earth,
we need no proof. Electricity, which appears to be
only galvanism in equilibrium, is there in abundance;[94]
and recently, Mr. Fox[13] has shown by experiment
that metalliferous veins, as they lie in the earth, exercise
a galvanic influence on each other. Something
of this kind might have been anticipated; for
masses of metal in contact, if they differ in temperature
or other circumstances, are known to produce
a galvanic current. Hence we have undoubtedly
streams of galvanic influence moving along in the
earth. Whether or not such causes as these produce
the directive power of the magnetic needle, we
cannot here pretend to decide; they can hardly fail
to affect it. The Aurora Borealis too, probably an
electrical phenomenon, is said, under particular circumstances,
to agitate the magnetic needle. It is
not surprising, therefore, that, if electricity have an
important office in the atmosphere, magnetism should
exist in the earth. It seems likely, that the magnetic
properties of the earth may be collateral results of
the existence of the same cause by which electrical
agency operates; an agency which, as we have already
seen, has important offices in the processes of
vegetable life. And thus magnetism belongs to the
same system of beneficial contrivance to which electricity
has been already traced.
We see, however, on this subject very dimly and
a very small way. It can hardly be doubted that
magnetism has other functions than those we have
noticed.
</div></body></text></TEI>