<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="26">CHAPTER XXVI.
Volcanic eruption in Iceland in 1783—New island thrown up—Lava currents of
Skaptár Jokul, in same year—their immense volume—Eruption of Jorullo in
Mexico—Humboldt's theory of the convexity of the plain of Malpais—Eruption
of Galongoon in Java—Submarine volcanoes—Graham island, formed in
1831—Volcanic archipelagoes—Submarine eruptions in mid-Atlantic—The
Canaries—Teneriffe—Cones thrown up in Lancerote, 1730-36—Santorin and
its contiguous isles—Barren island in the Bay of Bengal—Mud volcanoes—Mineral
composition of volcanic products.
Volcanic eruptions in Iceland.—With the exception of Etna and Vesuvius,
the most complete chronological records of a series of eruptions
are those of Iceland, for their history reaches as far back as the ninth
century of our era; and, from the beginning of the twelfth century,
there is clear evidence that, during the whole period, there has never
been an interval of more than forty, and very rarely one of twenty years,
without either an eruption or a great earthquake. So intense is the
energy of the volcanic action in this region, that some eruptions of
Hecla have lasted six years without ceasing. Earthquakes have often
shaken the whole island at once, causing great changes in the interior,
such as the sinking down of hills, the rending of mountains, the desertion
by rivers of their channels, and the appearance of new lakes.583
New islands have often been thrown up near the coast, some of which
still exist; while others have disappeared, either by subsidence or the
action of the waves.
In the interval between eruptions, innumerable hot springs afford
vent to subterranean heat, and solfataras discharge copious streams of
inflammable matter. The volcanoes in different parts of this island are
observed, like those of the Phlegræan Fields, to be in activity by turns,
one vent often serving for a time as a safety-valve to the rest. Many
cones are often thrown up in one eruption, and in this case they take a
linear direction, running generally from northeast to southwest, from
the northeastern part of the island, where the volcano Krabla lies, to
the promontory Reykianas.
425
New island thrown up in 1783.—The convulsions of the year 1783
appear to have been more tremendous than any recorded in the modern
annals of Iceland; and the original Danish narrative of the catastrophe,
drawn up in great detail, has since been substantiated by several English
travellers, particularly in regard to the prodigious extent of country laid
waste, and the volume of lava produced.584 About a month previous to
the eruption on the mainland, a submarine volcano burst forth in the sea
in lat. 63° 25' N., long. 23° 44' W., at a distance of thirty miles in a
southwest direction from Cape Reykianas, and ejected so much pumice,
that the ocean was covered with that substance to the distance of 150
miles, and ships were considerably impeded in their course. A new
island was thrown up, consisting of high cliffs, within which fire, smoke,
and pumice were emitted from two or three different points. This island
was claimed by his Danish Majesty, who denominated it Nyöe, or the
New Island; but before a year had elapsed, the sea resumed its ancient
domain, and nothing was left but a reef of rocks from five to thirty
fathoms under water.
Great eruption of Skaptár Jokul.—Earthquakes which had long been
felt in Iceland, became violent on the 11th of June, 1783, when Skaptár
Jokul, distant nearly 200 miles from Nyöe, threw out a torrent of lava
which flowed down into the river Skaptâ, and completely dried it up.
The channel of the river was between high rocks, in many places from
four hundred to six hundred feet in depth, and near two hundred in
breadth. Not only did the lava fill up this great defile to the brink, but
it overflowed the adjacent fields to a considerable extent. The burning
flood, on issuing from the confined rocky gorge, was then arrested for
some time by a deep lake, which formerly existed in the course of the
river, between Skaptardal and Aa, which it entirely filled. The current
then advanced again, and reaching some ancient lava full of subterraneous
caverns, penetrated and melted down part of it; and in some
places, where the steam could not gain vent, it blew up the rock,
throwing fragments to the height of more than 150 feet. On the 18th
of June another ejection of liquid lava rushed from the volcano, which
flowed down with amazing velocity over the surface of the first stream.
By the damming up of the mouths of some of the tributaries of the
Skaptâ, many villages were completely overflowed with water, and thus
great destruction of property was caused. The lava, after flowing for
several days, was precipitated down a tremendous cataract called Stapafoss,
where it filled a profound abyss, which that great waterfall had
426
been hollowing out for ages, and after this, the fiery current again continued
its course.
On the third of August, fresh floods of lava still pouring from the
volcano, a new branch was sent off in a different direction; for the
channel of the Skaptâ was now so entirely choked up, and every opening
to the west and north so obstructed, that the melted matter was
forced to take a new course, so that it ran in a southeast direction, and
discharged itself into the bed of the river Hverfisfliot, where a scene of
destruction scarcely inferior to the former was occasioned. These Icelandic
lavas (like the ancient streams which are met with in Auvergne,
and other provinces of Central France), are stated by Stephenson to
have accumulated to a prodigious depth in narrow rocky gorges; but
when they came to wide alluvial plains, they spread themselves out into
broad burning lakes, sometimes from twelve to fifteen miles wide, and
one hundred feet deep. When the "fiery lake" which filled up the
lower portion of the valley of the Skaptâ, had been augmented by new
supplies, the lava flowed up the course of the river to the foot of the
hills from whence the Skaptâ takes its rise. This affords a parallel case
to one which can be shown to have happened at a remote era in the
volcanic region of the Vivarais in France, where lava issued from the
cone of Thueyts, and while one branch ran down, another more powerful
stream flowed up the channel of the river Ardêche.
The sides of the valley of the Skaptâ present superb ranges of basaltic
columns of older lava, resembling those which are laid open in the valleys
descending from Mont Dor, in Auvergne, where more modern lava-currents,
on a scale very inferior in magnitude to those of Iceland, have
also usurped the beds of the existing rivers. The eruption of Skaptár
Jokul did not entirely cease till the end of two years; and when Mr.
Paulson visited the tract eleven years afterwards, in 1794, he found
columns of smoke still rising from parts of the lava, and several rents
filled with hot water.585
Although the population of Iceland was very much scattered, and did
not exceed fifty thousand, no less than twenty villages were destroyed,
besides those inundated by water; and more than nine thousand human
beings perished, together with an immense number of cattle, partly by
the depredations of the lava, partly by the noxious vapors which impregnated
the air, and, in part, by the famine caused by showers of ashes
throughout the island, and the desertion of the coasts by the fish.
Immense volume of the lava.—But the extraordinary volume of melted
matter produced in this eruption deserves the particular attention of the
geologist. Of the two branches, which flowed in nearly opposite directions,
the greatest was fifty, and the lesser forty miles in length. The
extreme breadth which the Skaptâ branch attained in the low countries
was from twelve to fifteen miles, that of the other about seven. The
ordinary height of both currents was one hundred feet, but in narrow
427
defiles it sometimes amounted to six hundred. Professor Bischoff has
calculated that the mass of lava brought up from the subterranean
regions by this single eruption "surpassed in magnitude the bulk of
Mont Blanc."586 But a more distinct idea will be formed of the dimensions
of the two streams, if we consider how striking a feature they
would now form in the geology of England, had they been poured out
on the bottom of the sea after the deposition and before the elevation of
our secondary and tertiary rocks. The same causes which have excavated
valleys through parts of our marine strata, once continuous, might
have acted with equal force on the igneous rocks, leaving, at the same
time, a sufficient portion undestroyed to enable us to discover their former
extent. Let us, then, imagine the termination of the Skaptá branch
of lava to rest on the escarpment of the inferior and middle oolite, where
it commands the vale of Gloucester. The great platform might be one
hundred feet thick, and from ten to fifteen miles broad, exceeding any
which can be found in Central France. We may also suppose great
tabular masses to occur at intervals, capping the summit of the Cotswold
Hills between Gloucester and Oxford, by Northleach, Burford, and
other towns. The wide valley of the Oxford clay would then occasion
an interruption for many miles; but the same rocks might recur on the
summit of Cumnor and Shotover Hills, and all the other oolitic eminences
of that district. On the chalk of Berkshire, extensive plateaus,
six or seven miles wide, would again be formed; and lastly, crowning
the highest sands of Highgate and Hampstead, we might behold some
remnants of the current five or six hundred feet in thickness, causing
those hills to rival, or even to surpass, in height, Salisbury Craigs and
Arthur's Seat.
The distance between the extreme points here indicated would not
exceed ninety miles in a direct line; and we might then add, at the distance
of nearly two hundred miles from London, along the coast of
Dorsetshire and Devonshire, for example, a great mass of igneous rocks,
to represent those of contemporary origin, which were produced beneath
the level of the sea, where the island of Nyöe rose up.
Volume of ancient and modern flows of lava compared.—Yet, gigantic
as must appear the scale of these modern volcanic operations, we must
be content to regard them as perfectly insignificant in comparison to
currents of the primeval ages, if we embrace the theoretical views of
many geologists, which were not inaccurately expressed by the late Professor
Alexander Brongniart, when he declared that "aux époques
géognostiques anciennes, tous les phénomènes géologiques se passoient
dans des dimensions centuples de celles qu'ils présentent aujourd'hui."587
Had Skaptár Jokul, therefore, been a volcano of the olden time, it would
have poured forth lavas at a single eruption a hundred times more voluminous
than those which were witnessed by the present generation in
428
1783. But it may, on the contrary, be affirmed that, among the older
formations, no igneous rock of such colossal magnitude has yet been met
with; nay, it would be most difficult to point out a mass of ancient date
(distinctly referable to a single eruption) which would even rival in
volume the matter poured out from Skaptár Jokul in 1783.
Eruption of Jorullo in 1759.—As another example of the stupendous
scale of modern volcanic eruptions, I may mention that of Jorullo in
Mexico, in 1759. The great region to which this mountain belongs has
already been described. The plain of Malpais forms part of an elevated
platform, between two and three thousand feet above the level of the
sea, and is bounded by hills composed of basalt, trachyte, and volcanic
tuff, clearly indicating that the country had previously, though probably
at a remote period, been the theatre of igneous action. From the era
of the discovery of the New World to the middle of the last century, the
district had remained undisturbed, and the space, now the site of the
volcano, which is thirty-six leagues distant from the nearest sea, was
occupied by fertile fields of sugar-cane and indigo, and watered by the
two brooks Cuitimba and San Pedro. In the month of June, 1759,
hollow sounds of an alarming nature were heard, and earthquakes succeeded
each other for two months, until, at the end of September, flames
issued from the ground, and fragments of burning rocks were thrown to
prodigious heights. Six volcanic cones, composed of scoriæ and fragmentary
lava, were formed on the line of a chasm which ran in the direction
from N. N. E. to S. S. W. The least of these cones was 300 feet in
height; and Jorullo, the central volcano, was elevated 1600 feet above
the level of the plain. It sent forth great streams of basaltic lava, containing
included fragments of granitic rocks, and its ejections did not
cease till the month of February, 1760.588
Fig. 57.
a, Summit of Jorullo. b, c, Inclined plane sloping at an angle of 6° from the base of the cones.
Humboldt visited the country more than forty years after this occurrence,
and was informed by the Indians, that when they returned, long
after the catastrophe, to the plain, they found the ground uninhabitable
from the excessive heat. When he himself visited the place, there
appeared, around the base of the cones, and spreading from them, as
from a centre, over an extent of four square miles, a mass of matter of
a convex form, about 550 feet high at its junction with the cones, and
gradually sloping from them in all directions towards the plain. This
mass was still in a heated state, the temperature in the fissures being on
the decrease from year to year, but in 1780 it was still sufficient to light
a cigar at the depth of a few inches. On this slightly convex protuberance,
429
the slope of which must form an angle of about 6° with the horizon,
were thousands of flattish conical mounds, from six to nine feet high,
which, as well as large fissures traversing the plain, acted as fumeroles,
giving out clouds of sulphurous acid and hot aqueous vapor. The two
small rivers before mentioned disappeared during the eruption, losing
themselves below the eastern extremity of the plain, and reappearing as
hot springs at its western limit.
Cause of the convexity of the plain of Malpais.—Humboldt attributed
the convexity of the plain to inflation from below; supposing the ground,
for four square miles in extent, to have risen up in the shape of a bladder
to the elevation of 550 feet above the plain in the highest part.
But Mr. Scrope has suggested that the phenomena may be accounted
for far more naturally, by supposing that lava flowing simultaneously
from the different orifices, and principally from Jorullo, united
into a sort of pool or lake. As they were poured forth on a surface
previously flat, they would, if their liquidity was not very great, remain
thickest and deepest near their source, and diminish in bulk from thence
towards the limits of the space which they covered. Fresh supplies
were probably emitted successively during the course of an eruption
which lasted more than half a year; and some of these, resting on those
first emitted, might only spread to a small distance from the foot of the
cone, where they would necessarily accumulate to a great height. The
average slope of the great dome-shaped volcanoes of the Sandwich
Islands, formed almost exclusively of lava, with scarce any scoriæ, is
between 6° 30' and 7° 46', so that the inclination of the convex mass
around Jorullo, if we adopt Mr. Scrope's explanation (see fig. 57), is
quite in accordance with the known laws which govern the flow of lava.
The showers, also, of loose and pulverulent matter from the six craters,
and principally from Jorullo, would be composed of heavier and
more bulky particles near the cones, and would raise the ground at
their base, where, mixing with rain, they might have given rise to the
stratum of black clay, which is described as covering the lava. The
small conical mounds (called "hornitos," or little ovens) may resemble
those five or six small hillocks which existed in 1823 on the Vesuvian
lava, and sent forth columns of vapor, having been produced by the
disengagement of elastic fluids heaping up small dome-shaped masses
of lava. The fissures mentioned by Humboldt as of frequent occurrence,
are such as might naturally accompany the consolidation of a thick bed
of lava, contracting as it congeals; and the disappearance of rivers is
the usual result of the occupation of the lower part of a valley or plain
by lava, of which there are many beautiful examples in the old lava-currents
of Auvergne. The heat of the "hornitos" is stated to have
diminished from the first; and Mr. Bullock, who visited the spot many
years after Humboldt, found the temperature of the hot spring very
low,—a fact which seems clearly to indicate the gradual congelation of
a subjacent bed of lava, which from its immense thickness may have
been enabled to retain its heat for half a century. The reader may be
430
reminded, that when we thus suppose the lava near the volcano to have
been, together with the ejected ashes, more than five hundred feet in
depth, we merely assign a thickness which the current of Skaptár Jokul
attained in some places in 1783.
Hollow sound of the plain when struck.—Another argument adduced
in support of the theory of inflation from below, was, the hollow sound
made by the steps of a horse upon the plain; which, however, proves
nothing more than that the materials of which the convex mass is composed
are light and porous. The sound called "rimbombo" by the
Italians is very commonly returned by made ground when struck sharply;
and has been observed not only on the sides of Vesuvius and other volcanic
cones where there is a cavity below, but in such regions as the
Campagna di Roma, composed in a great measure of tuff and porous
volcanic rocks. The reverberation, however, may perhaps be assisted
by grottoes and caverns, for these may be as numerous in the lavas of
Jorullo as in many of those of Etna; but their existence would lend no
countenance to the hypothesis of a great arched cavity, four square
miles in extent, and in the centre 550 feet high.589
No recent eruptions of Jorullo.—In a former edition I stated that I
had been informed by Captain Vetch, that in 1819 a tower at Guadalaxara
was thrown down by an earthquake, and that ashes, supposed to
have come from Jorullo, fell at the same time at Guanaxuato, a town
situated 140 English miles from the volcano. But Mr. Burkhardt, a
German director of mines, who examined Jorullo in 1827, ascertained
that there had been no eruption there since Humboldt's visit in 1803.
He went to the bottom of the crater, and observed a slight evolution of
sulphurous acid vapors, but the "hornitos" had entirely ceased to send
forth steam. During the twenty-four years intervening between his
visit and that of Humboldt, vegetation had made great progress on the
flanks of the new hills; the rich soil of the surrounding country was
once more covered with luxuriant crops of sugar-cane and indigo, and
there was an abundant growth of natural underwood on all the uncultivated
tracts.590
Galongoon, Java, 1822.—The mountain of Galongoon (or Galung
Gung) was in 1822 covered by a dense forest, and situated in a fruitful
and thickly-peopled part of Java. There was a circular hollow at its
summit, but no tradition existed of any former eruption. In July, 1822,
the waters of the river Kunir, one of those which flowed from its flanks,
became for a time hot and turbid. On the 8th of October following a
loud explosion was heard, the earth shook, and immense columns of hot
water and boiling mud, mixed with burning brimstone, ashes, and lapilli,
of the size of nuts, were projected from the mountain like a waterspout,
with such prodigious violence that large quantities fell beyond the river
Tandoi, which is forty miles distant. Every valley within the range of
431
this eruption became filled with a burning torrent, and the rivers, swollen
with hot water and mud, overflowed their banks, and carried away
great numbers of the people, who were endeavoring to escape, and the
bodies of cattle, wild beasts, and birds. A space of twenty-four miles
between the mountain and the river Tandoi was covered to such a
depth with bluish mud that people were buried in their houses, and
not a trace of the numerous villages and plantations throughout that
extent was visible. Within this space the bodies of those who perished
were buried in mud and concealed, but near the limits of the volcanic
action they were exposed, and strewed over the ground in great numbers,
partly boiled and partly burnt.
It was remarked, that the boiling mud and cinders were projected
with such violence from the mountain, that while many remote villages
were utterly destroyed and buried, others much nearer the volcano
were scarcely injured.
The first eruption lasted nearly five hours, and on the following days
the rain fell in torrents, and the rivers, densely charged with mud,
deluged the country far and wide. At the end of four days (October
12th) a second eruption occurred more violent than the first, in which
hot water and mud were again vomited, and great blocks of basalt were
thrown to the distance of seven miles from the volcano. There was at
the same time a violent earthquake, and in one account it is stated that the
face of the mountain was utterly changed, its summits broken down, and
one side, which had been covered with trees, became an enormous gulf
in the form of a semicircle. This cavity was about midway between the
summit and the plain, and surrounded by steep rocks, said to be newly
heaped up during the eruption. New hills and valleys are said to have
been formed, and the rivers Banjarang and Wulan changed their course,
and in one night (October 12th) 2000 persons were killed.
The first intimation which the inhabitants of Bandong received of this
calamity on the 8th of October, was the news that the river Wulna was
bearing down into the sea the dead bodies of men, and the carcasses of
stags, rhinoceroses, tigers, and other animals. The Dutch painter Payen
determined to travel from thence to the volcano, and he found that the
quantity of the ashes diminished as he approached the base of the mountain.
He alludes to the altered form of the mountain after the 12th,
but does not describe the new semicircular gulf on its side.
The official accounts state that 114 villages were destroyed, and above
4000 persons killed.591
Submarine volcanoes.—Although we have every reason to believe that
volcanic eruptions as well as earthquakes are common in the bed of the
sea, it was not to be expected that many opportunities would occur to
scientific observers of witnessing the phenomena. The crews of vessels
have sometimes reported that they have seen in different places sulphur
432ous
smoke, flame, jets of water, and steam, rising up from the sea, or
they have observed the waters greatly discolored, and in a state of violent
agitation as if boiling. New shoals have also been encountered, or
a reef of rocks just emerging above the surface, where previously there
was always supposed to have been deep water. On some few occasions
the gradual formation of an island by a submarine eruption has been observed,
as that of Sabrina, in the year 1811, off St. Michael's in the
Azores. The throwing up of ashes in that case, and the formation of
a cone about three hundred feet in height, with a crater in the centre,
closely resembled the phenomena usually accompanying a volcanic eruption
on land. Sabrina was soon washed away by the waves. Previous
eruptions in the same part of the sea were recorded to have happened
in 1691 and 1720. The rise of Nyöe, also, a small island off the coast
of Iceland, in 1783, has already been alluded to; and another volcanic
isle was produced by an eruption near Reikiavig, on the same coast, in
June, 1830.592
Graham Island593, 1831.—We have still more recent and minute information
respecting the appearance, in 1831, of a new volcanic island in
the Mediterranean, between the S. W. coast of Sicily and that projecting
part of the African coast where ancient Carthage stood. The site of the
island was not any part of the great shoal, or bank, called "Nerita," as
was first asserted, but a spot where Captain W. H. Smyth had found,
in his survey a few years before, a depth of more than one hundred
fathoms water.594
Fig. 58.
Form of the cliffs of Graham Island, as seen from S. S. E., distant one mile, 7th August, 1831.596
Fig. 59.
View of the interior of Graham Island, 29th Sept., 1831.
Fig. 60.
Graham Island, 29th Sept., 1831.597
The position of the island (lat. 37° 8' 30" N., long. 12° 42' 15" E.)
was about thirty miles S. W. of Sciacca, in Sicily, and thirty-three miles
N. E. of Pantellaria.595 On the 28th of June, about a fortnight before
the eruption was visible, Sir Pulteney Malcolm, in passing over the spot
in his ship, felt the shocks of an earthquake, as if he had struck on a
sand-bank; and the same shocks were felt on the west coast of Sicily,
in a direction from S. W. to N. E. About the 10th of July, John
Corrao, the captain of a Sicilian vessel, reported that, as he passed near
the place, he saw a column of water like a water-spout, sixty feet high,
and 800 yards in circumference, rising from the sea, and soon afterwards
a dense steam in its place, which ascended to the height of 1800 feet.
The same Corrao, on his return from Girgenti, on the 18th of July,
found a small island, twelve feet high with a crater in its centre, ejecting
volcanic matter, and immense columns of vapor; the sea around being
433
covered with floating cinders and dead fish. The scoriæ were of a
chocolate color, and the water which boiled in the circular basin was of
a dingy red. The eruption continued with great violence to the end of
the same month; at which time the island was visited by several persons,
434
and among others by Capt. Swinburne, R. N., and M. Hoffmann,
the Prussian geologist. It was then from fifty to ninety feet in height,
and three-quarters of a mile in circumference. By the 4th of August
it became, according to some accounts, above 200 feet high, and three
miles in circumference; after which it began to diminish in size by the
action of the waves, and it was only two miles round on the 25th of
August; and on the 3d of September, when it was carefully examined
by Captain Wodehouse, only three-fifths of a mile in circumference; its
greatest height being then 107 feet. At this time the crater was about 780
feet in circumference. On the 29th of September, when it was visited
by Mons. C. Prevost, its circumference was reduced to about 700 yards.
It was composed entirely of incoherent ejected matter, scoriæ, pumice,
and lapilli, forming regular strata, some of which are described as having
been parallel to the steep inward slope of the crater, while the rest
were inclined outwards, like those of Vesuvius.598 When the arrangement
of the ejected materials has been determined by their falling continually
on two steep slopes, that of the external cone and that of the crater,
which is always a hollow inverted cone, a transverse section would
probably resemble that given in the annexed figure (61). But when I
visited Vesuvius, in 1828, I saw no beds of scoriæ inclined towards the
axis of the cone. (See fig. 45, p. 381.) Such may have once existed;
but the explosions or subsidences, or whatever causes produced the
great crater of 1822, had possibly destroyed them.
Fig. 61.

Few of the pieces of stone thrown out from Graham Island exceeded
a foot in diameter. Some fragments of dolomitic limestone were intermixed;
but these were the only non-volcanic substances. During the
month of August, there occurred on the S. W. side of the new island
a violent ebullition and agitation of the sea, accompanied by the constant
ascension of a column of dense white steam, indicating the existence
of a second vent at no great depth from the surface. Towards
the close of October, no vestige of the crater remained, and the island
was nearly levelled with the surface of the ocean, with the exception,
at one point, of a small monticule of sand and scoriæ. It was reported
that, at the commencement of the year following (1832), there was a
depth of 150 feet where the island had been: but this account was
quite erroneous; for in the early part of that year Captain Swinburne
found a shoal and discolored water there, and towards the end of 1833
a dangerous reef existed of an oval figure, about three-fifths of a mile
in extent. In the centre was a black rock, of the diameter of about
435
twenty-six fathoms, from nine to eleven feet under water; and round
this rock are banks of black volcanic stones and loose sand. At the
distance of sixty fathoms from this central mass, the depth increased
rapidly. There was also a second shoal at the distance of 450 feet
S. W. of the great reef, with fifteen feet water over it, also composed
of rock, surrounded by deep sea. We can scarcely doubt that the rock
in the middle of the larger reef is solid lava, which rose up in the principal
crater, and that the second shoal marks the site of the submarine
eruption observed in August, 1831, to the S. W. of the island.
From the whole of the facts above detailed, it appears that a hill
eight hundred feet or more in height was formed by a submarine volcanic
vent, of which the upper part (only about two hundred feet high)
emerged above the waters, so as to form an island. This cone must
have been equal in size to one of the largest of the lateral volcanoes on
the flanks of Etna, and about half the height of the mountain Jorullo
in Mexico, which was formed in the course of nine months, in 1759. In
the centre of the new volcano a large cavity was kept open by gaseous
discharges, which threw out scoriæ; and fluid lava probably rose up
in this cavity. It is not uncommon for small subsidiary craters to open
near the summit of a cone, and one of these may have been formed in
the case of Graham Island; a vent, perhaps, connected with the main
channel of discharge which gave passage in that direction to elastic
fluids, scoriæ, and melted lava. It does not appear that, either from
this duct, or from the principal vent, there was any overflowing of lava;
but melted rock may have flowed from the flanks or base of the cone
(a common occurrence on land), and may have spread in a broad sheet
over the bottom of the sea.
Fig. 62.
Supposed section of Graham Island. (C. Maclaren.599)
The dotted lines in the annexed figure are an imaginary restoration
of the upper part of the cone, now removed by the waves: the strong
lines represent the part of the volcano which is still under water: in
the centre is a great column, or dike, of solid lava, two hundred feet in
diameter, supposed to fill the space by which the gaseous fluids rose;
and on each side of the dike is a stratified mass of scoriæ and fragmentary
lava. The solid nucleus of the reef, where the black rock is now
found, withstands the movements of the sea; while the surrounding
loose tuffs are cut away to a somewhat lower level. In this manner the
436
lava, which was the lowest part of the island, or, to speak more correctly,
which scarcely ever rose above the level of the sea when the
island existed, has now become the highest point in the reef.
No appearances observed, either during the eruption or since the
island disappeared, gave the least support to the opinion promulgated
by some writers, that part of the ancient bed of the sea had been lifted
up bodily.
The solid products, says Dr. John Davy, whether they consisted of
sand, light cinders, or vesicular lava, differed more in form than in
composition. The lava contained augite; and the specific gravity was
2·07 and 2·70. When the light spongy cinder, which floated on the
sea, was reduced to fine powder by trituration, and the greater part of
the entangled air got rid of, it was found to be of the specific gravity
2·64; and that of some of the sand which fell in the eruption was
2·75;600 so that the materials equalled ordinary granites in weight and
solidity. The only gas evolved in any considerable quantity was carbonic
acid.601
Submarine eruptions in mid-Atlantic.—In the Nautical Magazine for
1835, p. 642, and for 1838, p. 361, and in the Comptes Rendus, April,
1838, accounts are given of a series of volcanic phenomena, earthquakes,
troubled water, floating scoriæ and columns of smoke, which have been
observed at intervals since the middle of the last century, in a space of
open sea between longitudes 20° and 22° west, about half a degree
south of the equator. These facts, says Mr. Darwin, seem to show,
that an island or an archipelago is in process of formation in the middle
of the Atlantic; a line joining St. Helena and Ascension would, if prolonged,
intersect this slowly nascent focus of volcanic action.602 Should
land be eventually formed here, it will not be the first that has been
produced by igneous action in this ocean since it was inhabited by the
existing species of testacea. At Porto Praya in St. Jago, one of the
Azores, a horizontal, calcareous stratum occurs, containing shells of
recent marine species, covered by a great sheet of basalt eighty feet
thick.603 It would be difficult to estimate too highly the commercial
and political importance which a group of islands might acquire, if in
the next two or three thousand years they should rise in mid-ocean
between St. Helena and Ascension.
CANARY ISLANDS.
Eruption in Lancerote, 1730 to 1736.—The effects of an eruption
which happened in Lancerote, one of the Canary Islands, between the
years 1730 and 1736, were very remarkable; and a detailed description
has been published by Von Buch, who had an opportunity, when
he visited that island in 1815, of comparing the accounts transmitted to
us of the event, with the present state and geological appearances of the
437
country.604 On the 1st of September, 1730, the earth split open on a
sudden two leagues from Yaira. In one night a considerable hill of
ejected matter was thrown up; and, a few days later, another vent
opened, and gave out a lava-stream, which overran Chinanfaya and
other villages. It flowed first rapidly, like water, but became afterwards
heavy and slow, like honey. On the 7th of September an immense
rock was protruded from the bottom of the lava with a noise like
thunder, and the stream was forced to change its course from N. to
N. W., so that St. Catalina and other villages were overflowed.
Whether this mass was protruded by an earthquake, or was a mass
of ancient lava, blown up like that before mentioned in 1783 in Iceland,
is not explained.
On the 11th of September more lava flowed out, and covered the
village of Maso entirely, and for the space of eight days precipitated
itself with a horrible roar into the sea. Dead fish floated on the waters
in indescribable multitudes, or were thrown dying on the shore. After
a brief interval of repose, three new openings broke forth immediately
from the site of the consumed St. Catalina, and sent out an enormous
quantity of lapilli, sand, and ashes. On the 28th of October the cattle
throughout the whole country dropped lifeless to the ground, suffocated
by putrid vapors, which condensed and fell down in drops. On the
1st of December a lava-stream reached the sea, and formed an island,
round which dead fish were strewed.
Number of cones thrown up.—It is unnecessary here to give the
details of the overwhelming of other places by fiery torrents, or of a
storm which was equally new and terrifying to the inhabitants, as they
had never known one in their country before. On the 10th of January,
1731, a high hill was thrown up, which, on the same day, precipitated
itself back again into its own crater; fiery brooks of lava flowed from it
to the sea. On the 3d of February a new cone arose. Others were
thrown up in March, and poured forth lava-streams. Numerous other
volcanic cones were subsequently formed in succession, till at last their
number amounted to about thirty. In June, 1731, during a renewal of
the eruptions, all the banks and shores in the western part of the island
were covered with dying fish, of different species, some of which had
never before been seen. Smoke and flame arose from the sea, with
loud detonations. These dreadful commotions lasted without interruption
for five successive years, so that a great emigration of the inhabitants
became necessary.
Their linear direction.—As to the height of the new cones, Von Buch
was assured that the formerly great and flourishing St. Catalina lay
buried under hills 400 feet in height; and he observes that the most
elevated cone of the series rose 600 feet above its base, and 1378 feet
above the sea, and that several others were nearly as high. The new
438
vents were all arranged in one line, about two geographical miles long,
and in a direction nearly east and west. If we admit the probability of
Von Buch's conjecture, that these vents opened along the line of a cleft,
it seems necessary to suppose that this subterranean fissure was only
prolonged upwards to the surface by degrees, and that the rent was
narrow at first, as is usually the case with fissures caused by earthquakes.
Lava and elastic fluids might escape from some point on the
rent where there was least resistance, till, the first aperture becoming
obstructed by ejections and the consolidation of lava, other orifices burst
open in succession along the line of the original fissure. Von Buch
found that each crater was lowest on that side on which lava had
issued; but some craters were not breached, and were without any lava
streams. In one of these were open fissures, out of which hot vapors
rose, which in 1815 raised the thermometer to 145° Fahrenheit, and
was probably at the boiling point lower down. The exhalations
seemed to consist of aqueous vapor; yet they could not be pure steam,
for the crevices were incrusted on either side by siliceous sinter (an
opal-like hydrate of silica of a white color), which extended almost to
the middle. This important fact attests the length of time during
which chemical processes continue after eruptions, and how open fissures
may be filled up laterally by mineral matter, sublimed from volcanic
exhalations. The lavas of this eruption covered nearly a third of the
whole island, often forming on slightly inclined planes great horizontal
sheets several square leagues in area, resembling very much the basaltic
platforms of Auvergne.
Pretended distinction between ancient and modern lavas.—One of the
new lavas was observed to contain masses of olivine of an olive-green
color, resembling those which occur in one of the lavas of the Vivarais.
Von Buch supposes the great crystals of olivine to have been derived
from a previously existing basalt melted up by the new volcanoes; but
we have scarcely sufficient data to bear out such a conjecture. The
older rocks of the island consist, in a great measure, of that kind
of basaltic lava called dolerite, sometimes columnar, and partly of common
basalt and amygdaloid. Some recent lavas assumed, on entering
the sea, a prismatic form, and so much resembled the older lavas of
the Canaries, that the only geological distinction which Von Buch
appears to have been able to draw between them was, that they did
not alternate with conglomerates, like the ancient basalts. Some
modern writers have endeavored to discover, in the abundance of these
conglomerates, a proof of the dissimilarity of the volcanic action in
ancient and modern times; but this character is more probably attributable
to the difference between submarine operations and those on the
land. All the blocks and imperfectly rounded fragments of lava, transported
during the intervals of eruption, by rivers and torrents, into the
adjoining sea, or torn by the continued action of the waves from cliffs
which are undermined, must accumulate in stratified breccias and conglomerates,
and be covered again and again by other lavas. This is
439
now taking place on the shores of Sicily, between Catania and Trezza,
where the sea breaks down and covers the shore with blocks and pebbles
of the modern lavas of Etna; and on parts of the coast of Ischia,
where numerous currents of trachyte are in like manner undermined in
lofty precipices. So often, then, as an island is raised in a volcanic
archipelago by earthquakes from the deep, the fundamental and (relatively
to all above) the oldest lava will often be distinguishable from
those formed by subsequent eruptions on dry land, by their alternation
with beds of sandstone and fragmentary rocks.
The supposed want of identity, then, between the volcanic phenomena
of different epochs resolves itself partly at least into the marked difference
between the operations simultaneously in progress, above and below
the waters. Such, indeed, is the source, as was before stated in the First
Book (Chap. V.), of many of our strongest theoretical prejudices in geology.
No sooner do we study and endeavor to explain submarine appearances,
than we feel, to use a common expression, out of our element;
and unwilling to concede that our extreme ignorance of processes now
continually going on can be the cause of our perplexity, we take refuge
in a "pre-existent order of nature."
Recent formation of oolitic travertin in Lancerote.—Throughout a considerable
part of Lancerote, the old lavas are covered by a thin stratum
of limestone, from an inch to two feet in thickness. It is of a hard stalactitic
nature, sometimes oolitic, like the Jura limestone, and contains fragments
of lava and terrestrial shells, chiefly helices and spiral bulimi. It
sometimes rises to the height of 800 feet above the level of the sea. Von
Buch imagines that this remarkable superstratum has been produced by
the furious northwest storms, which in winter drive the spray of the sea
in clouds over the whole island; from whence calcareous particles may
be deposited stalactitically. Mr. Darwin informs me that he found a
limestone in St. Helena, the harder parts of which correspond precisely to
the stone of Lancerote. He attributes the origin of this rock in St. Helena
not to the spray of the sea, but to drifting by violent winds of the finer
particles of shells from the sea-beach. Some parts of this drift are subsequently
dissolved by atmospheric moisture, and redeposited, so as to
convert calcareous sand into oolite.
Recent eruption in Lancerote.—From the year 1736 to 1815, when Von
Buch visited Lancerote, there had been no eruption; but, in August, 1824,
a crater opened near the port of Rescif, and formed by its ejections, in
the space of twenty-four hours, a considerable hill. Violent earthquakes
preceded and accompanied this eruption.605
Teneriffe.—The Peak of Teneriffe is about 12,000 feet high, and stands,
says Von Buch, like a tower encircled by its fosse and bastion. The bastion
consists, like the semicircular escarpment of Somma turned towards
Vesuvius, of precipitous cliffs, composed of trachyte, basalt, coarse conglomerates,
and tuffs, traversed by volcanic dikes, mostly vertical, and of
440
basalt. These cliffs vary in height from 1000 to 1800 feet, and are supposed
by Von Buch to have been heaved up into their present position
by a force exerted from below, in accordance with the theory proposed
by the same author for the origin of the cones of Vesuvius and Etna.
According to the observations of M. Deville in 1839606, the trachytes are
often granitoid in their aspect, and contain instead of glassy felspar the
allied mineral called oligoclase, which had been previously considered as
characteristic of more ancient igneous rocks. The same traveller supposes,
although he found no limestone or trace of fossils in any of the
rocks of Teneriffe, that the alternating trachytes and trachytic conglomerates
originated beneath the sea. If this opinion be correct, and it is
at least very probable, geologists may still speculate on two modes in
which the mass of the island acquired its present form and elevation
above the sea. 1st, The advocates of Von Buch's crater-of-elevation
hypothesis may imagine that a succession of horizontally superimposed
beds were upheaved by a sudden movement, and tilted so as to dip in
all directions outwards from the centre of a new dome-shaped eminence,
in the middle of which a large opening or bowl-shaped cavity was produced.
2dly, Or according to the theory which to me appears preferable,
a submarine hill in the form of a flattened dome may have gradually
accumulated, partly below the waters and partly above by the continued
outpourings of sheets of lava and the ejection of ashes from a
central orifice. In this case the dikes would represent the fissures, which
were filled during successive eruptions, and the original inclination of the
beds may have been increased by the distension and upheaval of the mass
during reiterated convulsions, acting most forcibly at or near the channel
of discharge, which would become partially sealed up with lava from time
to time, and then be burst open again during eruptions. At length the
whole island may have been raised bodily out of the sea by a gradual
upward movement.
Whatever theory we adopt, we must always explain the abrupt termination
of the dikes and layers of trachyte and basalt in the steep walls of
the escarpments surrounding the great crater by supposing the removal
of part of the materials once prolonged farther inward towards the centre.
If, according to the elevation-crater hypothesis, a series of sheets of lava
and ashes originally spread over a level and even surface have been violently
broken and uplifted, why do not the opposite walls of the chasm
correspond in such a manner as to imply by their present outline that
they were formerly united? It is evident that the precipices on opposite
sides of the crateriform hollow would not fit if brought together, there
being no projecting masses in one wall to enter into indentations in the
other, as would happen with the sides of many mineral veins, trap-dikes,
and faults, could we extract the intrusive matter now separating them,
and reunite the rocks which have been fractured and disjoined.
The highest crater of the peak has merely disengaged sulphureous
441
vapors ever since it has been known to Europeans; but an eruption
happened in June, 1798, not far from the summit, and others are recorded,
which poured out streams of lava from great heights, besides
many which have broken out nearer the level of the sea. All these, however,
seem to be dependent on one great centre of eruption, or on that
open channel communicating between the interior of the earth and the
atmosphere, which terminates in the highest crater of the peak.
We may consider Teneriffe, then, as having been from a remote period
the principal and habitual vent of the volcanic archipelago of the
Canaries. The discharges which have taken place in the contiguous
isles of Palma, Lancerote, and the rest, may be of a subsidiary kind, and
have probably been most frequent and violent when the greater crater
has been partially sealed up, just as the violent eruptions of Ischia or
that of Monte Nuovo coincided with the dormant state of Vesuvius.
SANTORIN.
The Gulf of Santorin, in the Grecian Archipelago, has been for two
thousand years a scene of active volcanic operations. The largest of the
three outer islands of the group (to which the general name of Santorin
is given) is called Thera (or sometimes Santorin), and forms more than
two-thirds of the circuit of the gulf (see Map, fig. 63, p. 442). The
length of the exterior coast-line of this and the other two islands named
Therasia and Aspronisi, taken together, amounts to about thirty miles,
and that of the inner coast-line of the same islands to about eighteen
miles. In the middle of the gulf are three other islands, called the
Little, the New, and the Old "Kaimenis," or "Burnt Islands." The
accompanying map has been reduced from a recent survey executed in
1848 by Captain Graves, R. N., and shortly to be published by the
Admiralty.
442
Fig. 63.
Map of Santorin in the Grecian Archipelago, from a Survey in 1848, by Captain Graves, R. N.
The soundings are given in fathoms.

A, Shoal formed by submarine volcanic eruption in 1650.
B, Northern entrance.
C, Mansell's Rock.
D, Mount St. Elias, 1887 feet high.

Fig. 64.
Section of Santorin, in a N. E. and S. W. direction, from Thera through the Kaimenia to Aspronisi.
Fig. 65.
Part of the section, fig. 64, enlarged.
Pliny informs us that the year 186, B. C., gave birth to the Old Kaimeni,
also called Hiera, or the "Sacred Isle," and in the year 19 of our
era "Thia" (the Divine) made its appearance above water, and was soon
joined by subsequent eruptions to the older island, from which it was
only 250 paces distant. The Old Kaimeni also increased successively in
size in 726 and in 1427. A century and a half later, in 1573, another
eruption produced the cone and crater called Micra-Kaimeni, or "the
Small Burnt Island." The next great event which we find recorded
occurred in 1650, when a submarine outbreak violently agitated the sea,
at a point three and a half miles to the N. E. of Thera, and which gave
rise to a shoal (see A in the map) carefully examined during the late
survey in 1848 by Captain Graves, and found to have ten fathoms water
over it, the sea deepening around it in all directions. This eruption
lasted three months, covering the sea with floating pumice. At the same
time an earthquake destroyed many houses in Thera, while the sea broke
upon the coast and overthrew two churches, exposing to view two villages,
one on each side of the mountain of St. Stephen, both of which
443
must have been overwhelmed by showers of volcanic matter during some
previous eruptions of unknown date.607 The accompanying evolution of
sulphur and hydrogen issuing from the sea killed more than fifty persons,
and above 1000 domestic animals. A wave, also, 50 feet high, broke
upon the rocks of the Isle of Nia, about four leagues distant, and advanced
450 yards into the interior of the Island of Sikino. Lastly, in 1707 and
1709, Nea-Kaimeni, or the New Burnt Island, was formed between the
two others, Palaia and Micra, the Old and Little isles. This isle was
composed originally of two distinct parts; the first which rose was called
the White Island, composed of a mass of pumice, extremely porous.
Gorce, the Jesuit, who was then in Santorin, says that the rock "cut
like bread," and that, when the inhabitants landed on it, they found a
multitude of full-grown fresh oysters adhering to it, which they ate.608
This mass was afterwards covered, in great part, by the matter ejected
from the crater of a twin-island formed simultaneously, and called Black
Island, consisting of brown trachyte. The trachytic lava which rose on
this spot appears to have been a long time in an intumescent state, for
the New Kaimeni was sometimes lowered on one side while it gained
height on the other, and rocks rose up in the sea at different distances
from the shore and then disappeared again. The eruption was renewed
at intervals during the years 1711 and 1712, and at length a cone was
piled up to the height of 330 feet above the level of the sea, its exterior
slope forming an angle of 33° with the horizon, and the crater on its
summit being 80 yards in diameter. In addition to the two points of
subaerial eruption on the New and Little Kaimenis, two other cones,
indicating the sites of submarine outbursts of unknown date, were discovered
under water near the Kaimenis during the late survey.
In regard to the "White Island," which was described and visited by
Gorce in 1707, we are indebted to Mr. Edward Forbes for having, in
1842, carefully investigated the layer of pumiceous ash of which it is
constituted. He obtained from it many shells of marine genera, Pectunculus,
Arca, Cardita, Trochus, and others, both univalve and bivalve, all
of recent Mediterranean species. They were in a fine state of preservation,
the bivalves with the epidermis remaining, and valves closed,
showing that they had been suddenly destroyed. Mr. Forbes, from his
study of the habits of the mollusca living at different depths in the
Mediterranean, was able to decide that such an assemblage of species
could not have lived at a less depth than 220 feet, so that a bodily upheaval
of the mass to that amount must have taken place in order to
bring up this bed of ashes and shells to the level of the sea, and they
now rise five or six feet above that level.609
We may compare this partial elevation of solid matter to the rise of a
hardened crust of scoriæ, such as is usually formed on the surface of
lava-currents, even while they are in motion, and which, although stony
and capable of supporting heavy weights, may be upraised without
444
bursting by the intumescence of the melted matter below. That the
upheaval was merely local is proved by the fact that the neighboring
Kaimenis did not participate in the movement, still less the three more
distant or outer islands before mentioned. The history, therefore, of
the Kaimenis shows that they have been the result of intermittent action,
and it lends no support to the hypothesis of the sudden distension of
horizontal beds blown up like a bladder by a single paroxysmal effort of
expansive gases.
It will be seen by the accompanying map and sections, that the Kaimenis
are arranged in a linear direction, running N. E. and S. W., in a
manner different from that represented in the older charts. In their
longest diameter they form at their base a ridge nearly bisecting the gulf
or crater (see sections, figs. 64, 65).
On considering these facts we are naturally led to compare the smaller
and newer islands in the centre of the gulf to the modern cone of Vesuvius,
surrounded by the older semicircular escarpment of Somma, or to
liken them to the Peak of Teneriffe before described, as surrounded by
its "fosse and bastion." This idea will appear to be still more fully
confirmed when we study the soundings taken during the late hydrographical
survey. Thera, which constitutes alone more than two-thirds
of the outer circuit, presents everywhere towards the gulf, high and
steep precipices composed of rocks of volcanic origin. In all places
near the base of its cliffs, a depth of from 800 to 1000 feet of water was
found, and Lieut. Leycester informs us610 that if the gulf, which is six
miles in diameter, could be drained, a bowl-shaped cavity would appear
with walls 2449 feet high in some places, and even on the southwest
side, where it is lowest, nowhere less than 1200 feet high; while the
Kaimenis would be seen to form in the centre a huge mountain five and
a half miles in circumference at its base, with three principal summits
(the Old, the New, and the Little Burnt Islands) rising severally to the
heights of 1251, 1629, and 1158 feet above the bottom of the abyss.
The rim of the great caldron thus exposed would be observed to be
in all parts perfect and unbroken, except at one point where there is a
deep and long chasm or channel, known by mariners as "the northern
entrance" (B, fig. 63) between Thera and Therasia, and called by Lieut.
Leycester "the door into the crater." It is no less than 1170 feet
deep, and constitutes, as will appear by the soundings (see map), a remarkable
feature in the bed of the sea. There is no corresponding
channel passing out from the gulf into the Mediterranean at any other
point in the circuit between the outer islands, the greatest depth there
ranging from 7 to 66 feet.
We may conceive, therefore, if at some former time the whole mass
of Santorin stood at a higher level by 1200 feet, that this single ravine
or narrow valley now forming "the northern entrance," was the passage
by which the sea entered a circular bay and swept out in the form of
445
mud and pebbles, the materials derived by denudation from wasting
cliffs. In this manner the original crater may have been slowly widened
and deepened, after which the whole archipelago may have been partially
submerged to its present depth.
That such oscillations of level may in the course of ages have taken
place, will be the more readily admitted when we state that part of
Thera has actually sunk down in modern times, as, for example, during
the great earthquake before alluded to, which happened in 1650. The
subsidence alluded to is proved not only by tradition, but by the fact
that a road which formerly led between two places on the east coast of
Thera is now twelve fathoms under water.
MM. Boblaye and Virlet mention,611 that the waves are constantly undermining
and encroaching on the cliffs of Therasia and Aspronisi, and
shoals or submarine ledges were found, during the late survey, to occur
round a great part of these islands, attesting the recent progress of
denudation. M. Virlet also remarks, in regard to the separation of the
three islands forming the walls of the crater, that the channels between
them are all to the W. and N. W., the quarter most exposed to
the waves and currents.
Mr. Darwin, in his work on volcanic islands, has shown that in the
Mauritius and in Santiago, there is an external circle of basaltic rocks
of vast diameter, in the interior of which more modern eruptions have
taken place, the older rocks dipping away from the central space in
every direction, as in the outer islands of Santorin. He refers the numerous
breaches, some of them very wide in the external ramparts of
those islands, to the denuding action of the sea. Every geologist, therefore,
will be prepared to call in the aid of the same powerful cause, to
account for the removal of a large part of the rocks which must once
have occupied the interior space, in the same manner as they attribute
the abstraction of matter from elliptical "valleys of elevation," such as
those of Woolhope and the Wealden in England, to the waves and currents
of the sea.
Thera, Therasia, and Aspronisi are all composed of volcanic matter,
except the southern part of Thera, where Mount St. Elias rises to three
times the height of the loftiest of the igneous rocks, reaching an elevation
of 1887 feet above the sea.612 This mountain is formed of
granular limestone and argillaceous schist, and must have been originally
a submarine eminence in the bed of the Mediterranean, before
the volcanic cone, one side of the base of which now abuts against
it, was formed. The inclination, strike, and fractures of the calcareous
and argillaceous strata of St. Elias have no relation to the great cone,
but, according to M. Bory St. Vincent, have the same direction as those
of the other isles of the Grecian Archipelago, namely, from N. N. W.
to S. S. E. Each of the three islands, Thera, Therasia, and Aspronisi,
446
is capped by an enormous mass of white tufaceous conglomerate, from
forty to fifty feet thick, beneath which are beds of trachytic lava and
tuff, having a gentle inclination of only 3° or 4°. Each bed is usually
very narrow and discontinuous, the successive layers being moulded or
dove-tailed, as M. Virlet expresses it, into the inequalities of the previously
existing surface, on which showers of cinders or streams of
melted matter have been poured. Nothing, therefore, seems more
evident than that we have in Santorin the basal remains of a great
ruined cone, or flattened dome; and the absence of dikes in the cliffs
surrounding the gulf would indicate that the eruptions took place originally,
as they have done in the last two thousand years, not near the
margin but in the centre of the space now occupied by the gulf. The
central portions of the dome have since been removed by engulfment,
or denudation, or by both these causes.
An important fact is adduced by M. Virlet, to show that the gentle
dip of the lava-streams in the three outer islands towards all points of
the compass, away from the centre of the gulf, has not been due to
the upheaval of horizontal beds, as conjectured by Von Buch, who
had not visited Santorin.613 The French geologist found that the vesicles
or pores of the trachytic masses were lengthened out in the several
directions in which they would have flowed if they had descended
from the axis of a cone once occupying the centre of the crater. For
it is well known that the bubbles of confined gas in a fluid in motion
assume an oval form, and the direction of their longer axis coincides
always with that of the stream.
On a review, therefore, of all the facts now brought to light respecting
Santorin, I attribute the moderate slope of the beds in Thera and
the other external islands to their having originally descended the
inclined flanks of a large volcanic cone, the principal orifice or vents of
eruption having been always situated where they are now, in or near
the centre of the space occupied by the gulf or crater—in other words,
where the outburst of the Kaimenis has been witnessed in historical
times. The single long and deep opening into the crater is a feature
common to all those remnants of ancient volcanoes, the central portions
of which have been removed, and is probably connected with aqueous
denudation. This denuding process has been the work of ages when
the sea was admitted into an original crater, and has taken place during
the gradual emergence of the island from the sea, or during various
oscillations in its level.
The volcanic island of St. Paul in the midst of the Indian Ocean, lat.
38° 44' S., long. 77° 37' E., surveyed by Capt. Blackwood in 1842,
seems to exemplify the first stage in the formation of such an archipelago
as that of Santorin. We have there a crater one mile in diameter, surrounded
by steep and lofty cliffs on every side save one, where the sea
enters by a single passage nearly dry at low water. In the interior of
447
the small circular bay or crater there is a depth of 30 fathoms, or 180
feet. The surface of the island slopes away on all sides from the crest
of the rocks encircling the crater.614
Fig. 66.
Cone and crater of Barren Island, in the Bay of Bengal. Height of the central cone (according
to Capt Miller, in 1834), 500 feet.
Barren Island.—There is great analogy between the structure of
Barren Island in the Bay of Bengal, lat. 12° 15', and that of Santorin
last described. When seen from the ocean, this island presents, on almost
all sides, a surface of bare rocks, rising, with a moderate acclivity,
towards the interior; but at one point there is a cleft by which we can
penetrate into the centre, and there discover that it is occupied by a
great circular basin, filled by the waters of the sea, and bordered all
around by steep rocks, in the midst of which rises a volcanic cone, very
frequently in eruption. The summit of this cone is about 500 feet in
height, corresponding to that of the circular border which incloses the
basin; so that it can be seen from the sea only through the ravine.
It is most probable that the exterior inclosure of Barren Island (c, d,
fig. 67) is nothing more than the remains of a truncated cone c, a, b, d,
a great portion of which has been removed by engulfment, explosion,
or denudation, which may have preceded the formation of the new interior
cone, f, e, g.615
Fig. 67.
Supposed section of Barren Island, in the Bay of Bengal.
MUD VOLCANOES.
Iceland.—Mr. R. Bunsen, in his account of the pseudo-volcanic phenomena
of Iceland, describes many valleys where sulphurous and
aqueous vapors burst forth with a hissing sound, from the hot soil
448
formed of volcanic tuff. In such spots a pool of boiling water is seen,
in which a bluish-black argillaceous paste rises in huge bubbles. These
bubbles on bursting throw the boiling mud to a height of fifteen feet and
upwards, accumulating it in ledges round the crater or basin of the spring.
Baku on the Caspian.—The formation of a new mud volcano was witnessed
on the 27th of November, 1827, at Tokmali, on the peninsula
of Abscheron, east of Baku. Flames blazed up to an extraordinary
height for a space of three hours, and continued for twenty hours to
rise about three feet above a crater, from which mud was ejected. At
another point in the same district where flames issued, fragments of
rock of large size were hurled up into the air, and scattered around.616
Fig. 68.
Mud cones and craters of Hinglaj near Beila, district of Lus, 120 miles northwest of mouth
of Indus. From original drawing by Capt. Robertson. (See Map, p. 460.)
Sicily.—At a place called Macaluba, near Girgenti in Sicily, are
several conical mounds from ten to thirty feet in height, with small
craters at their summits, from which cold water, mixed with mud and
bitumen, is cast out. Bubbles of carbonic acid and carburetted hydrogen
gas are also disengaged from these springs, and at certain periods
with such violence, as to throw the mud to the height of 200 feet.
These "air volcanoes," as they are sometimes termed, are known to
have been in the same state of activity for the last fifteen centuries; and
Dr. Daubeny imagines that the gases which escape may be generated
449
by the slow combustion of beds of sulphur, which is actually in progress
in the blue clay, out of which the springs rise.617 But as the gases
are similar to those disengaged in volcanic eruptions, and as they have
continued to stream out for so long a period, they may perhaps be
derived from a more deep-seated source.
Beila in India.—In the district of Luss or Lus, south of Beila, about
120 miles N. W. of Cutch and the mouths of the Indus (see Map, fig.
71, p. 460), numerous mud volcanoes are scattered over an area of probably
not less than 1000 square miles. Some of these have been well
described by Captain Hart, and subsequently by Captain Robertson, who
has paid a visit to that region, and made sketches of them, which he has
kindly placed at my disposal. From one of these the annexed view has
been selected. These conical hills occur to the westward of the Hara
mountains and the river Hubb. (See Map, p. 460.) One of the cones
is 400 feet high, composed of light-colored earth, and having at its summit
a crater thirty yards in diameter. The liquid mud which fills the
crater is continually disturbed by air-bubbles, and here and there is cast
up in small jets.618
Mineral composition of volcanic products.—The mineral called felspar
forms in general more than half of the mass of modern lavas. When it
is in great excess, lavas are called trachytic: they consist generally of a
base of compact felspar, in which crystals of glassy felspar are disseminated.619
When augite (or pyroxene) predominates, lavas are termed basaltic.
They contain about 50 per cent. of silica, or much less than the
trachytes, in which there is usually about 75 per cent. of that mineral.
They also contain about 11 per cent. of protoxide of iron, and as much
of lime, both of which are wanting, or only in insignificant quantities in
the trachytic rocks.620 But lavas occur of an intermediate composition
between the trachytic and basaltic, which from their color have been
called graystones. The abundance of quartz, forming distinct crystals or
concretions, characterizes the granitic and other ancient rocks, now generally
considered by geologists as of igneous origin; whereas that mineral
is rarely exhibited in a separate form in recent lavas, although silica
enters so largely into their composition. Hornblende, so common in hypogene
rocks, or those commonly called "primary," is rare in modern
lava; nor does it enter largely into rocks of any age in which augite
abounds. It should, however, be stated, that the experiments of Mr.
Gustav Rose have made it very questionable, whether the minerals called
hornblende and augite can be separated as distinct species, as their different
varieties seem to pass into each other, whether we consider the
characters derived from their angles of crystallization, their chemical
composition, or their specific gravity. The difference in form of the two
substances may be explained by the different circumstances under which
450
they have been produced, the form of hornblende being the result of
slower cooling. Crystals of augite have been met with in the scoriæ of
furnaces, but never those of hornblende; and crystals of augite have
been obtained by melting hornblende in a platina crucible; but hornblende
itself has not been formed artificially.621 Mica occurs plentifully in
some recent trachytes, but is rarely present where augite is in excess.
Frequency of eruptions, and nature of subterranean igneous rocks.—When
we speak of the igneous rocks of our own times, we mean that
small portion which, in violent eruptions, is forced up by elastic fluids to
the surface of the earth,—the sand, scoriæ, and lava, which cool in the
open air. But we cannot obtain access to that which is congealed far
beneath the surface under great pressure, equal to that of many hundred,
or many thousand atmospheres.
During the last century, about fifty eruptions are recorded of the five
European volcanic districts, of Vesuvius, Etna, Volcano, Santorin, and
Iceland; but many beneath the sea in the Grecian archipelago and near
Iceland may doubtless have passed unnoticed. If some of them produced
no lava, others, on the contrary, like that of Skaptár Jokul, in 1783,
poured out melted matter for five or six years consecutively; which cases,
being reckoned as single eruptions, will compensate for those of inferior
strength. Now, if we consider the active volcanoes of Europe to constitute
about a fortieth part of those already known on the globe, and calculate
that, one with another, they are about equal in activity to the burning
mountains in other districts, we may then compute that there happen
on the earth about 2000 eruptions in the course of a century, or about
twenty every year.
However inconsiderable, therefore, may be the superficial rocks which
the operations of fire produce on the surface, we must suppose the subterranean
changes now constantly in progress to be on the grandest scale.
The loftiest volcanic cones must be as insignificant, when contrasted to the
products of fire in the nether regions, as are the deposits formed in shallow
estuaries when compared to submarine formations accumulating in
the abysses of the ocean. In regard to the characters of these volcanic
rocks, formed in our own times in the bowels of the earth, whether in rents
and caverns, or by the cooling of lakes of melted lava, we may safely infer
that the rocks are heavier and less porous than ordinary lavas, and
more crystalline, although composed of the same mineral ingredients. As
the hardest crystals produced artificially in the laboratory require the
longest time for their formation, so we must suppose that where the cooling
down of melted matter takes place by insensible degrees, in the course
of ages, a variety of minerals will be produced far harder than any formed
by natural processes within the short period of human observation.
These subterranean volcanic rocks, moreover, cannot be stratified in
the same manner as sedimentary deposits from water, although it is evident
that when great masses consolidate from a state of fusion, they may
451
separate into natural divisions; for this is seen to be the case in many
lava-currents. We may also expect that the rocks in question will often
be rent by earthquakes, since these are common in volcanic regions; and
the fissures will be often injected with similar matter, so that dikes of
crystalline rock will traverse masses of similar composition. It is also
clear, that no organic remains can be included in such masses, as also
that these deep-seated igneous formations considered in mass must underlie
all the strata containing organic remains, because the heat proceeds
from below upwards, and the intensity required to reduce the mineral
ingredients to a fluid state must destroy all organic bodies in rocks included
in the midst of them.
If by a continued series of elevatory movements, such masses shall
hereafter be brought up to the surface, in the same manner as sedimentary
marine strata have, in the course of ages, been upheaved to the
summit of the loftiest mountains, it is not difficult to foresee what
perplexing problems may be presented to the geologist. He may then,
perhaps, study in some mountain-chain the very rocks produced at the
depth of several miles beneath the Andes, Iceland, or Java, in the time
of Leibnitz, and draw from them the same conclusion which that philosopher
derived from certain igneous products of high antiquity; for he
conceived our globe to have been, for an indefinite period, in the state
of a comet, without an ocean, and uninhabitable alike by aquatic or
terrestrial animals.
</div></body></text></TEI>