<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="32">
[193]
BOOK III.
RELIGIOUS VIEWS.

The contemplation of the material universe exhibits
God to us as the author of the laws of material
nature; bringing before us a wonderful spectacle, in
the simplicity, the comprehensiveness, the mutual
adaptation of these laws, and in the vast variety of
harmonious and beneficial effects produced by their
mutual bearing and combined operation. But it is
the consideration of the moral world, of the results
of our powers of thought and action, which leads us
to regard the Deity in that light in which our relation
to him becomes a matter of the highest interest and
importance. We perceive that man is capable of referring
his actions to principles of right and wrong;
that both his faculties and his virtues may be unfolded
and advanced by the discipline which arises from
the circumstances of human society; that good men
can be discriminated from the bad, only by a course
of trial, by struggles with difficulty and temptation;
that the best men feel deeply the need of relying, in
such conflicts, on the thought of a superintending
Spiritual power; that our views of justice, our capacity
for intellectual and moral advancement, and a
crowd of hopes and anticipations which rise in our
bosoms unsought, and cling there with inexhaustible
tenacity, will not allow us to acquiesce in the belief
that this life is the end of our existence. We are
thus led to see that our relation the Superintender of
our moral being, to the Depositary of the supreme[194]
law of just and right, is a relation of incalculable
consequence. We find that we cannot be permitted
to be merely contemplators and speculators with regard
to the Governor of the moral world; we must
obey His will; we must turn our affections to Him;
we must advance in His favour; or we offend against
the nature of our position in the scheme of which
He is the author and sustainer.
It is far from our purpose to represent natural religion,
as of itself sufficient for our support and guidance;
or to underrate the manner in which our views
of the Lord of the universe have been, much more,
perhaps, than we are sometimes aware, illustrated
and confirmed by lights derived from revelation.
We do not here speak of the manner in which men
have come to believe in God, as the Governor of the
moral world; but of the fact, that by the aid of one
or both of these two guides, Reason or Revelation,
reflecting persons in every age have been led to such
a belief. And we conceive it may be useful to point
out some connexion between such a belief of a just
and holy Governor, and the conviction, which we
have already endeavoured to impress upon the
reader, of a wise and benevolent Creator of the physical
world. This we shall endeavour to do in the present
book.
At the same time that men have thus learnt to look
upon God as their Governor and Judge, the source
of their support and reward, they have also been led,
not only to ascribe to him power and skill, knowledge
and goodness, but also attribute to him these qualities
in a mode and degree excluding all limit:—to
consider him as almighty, all-wise, of infinite knowledge
and inexhaustible goodness; every where
present and active, but incomprehensible by our
minds, both in the manner of his agency, and the
degree of his perfections. And this impression concerning
the Deity appears to be that which the
mind receives from all objects of contemplation and
all modes of advance towards truth. To this conception[195]
it leaps with alacrity and joy, and in this
it acquiesces with tranquil satisfaction and growing
confidence; while any other view of the nature of
the Divine Power which formed and sustained the
world, is incoherent and untenable, exposed to insurmountable
objections and intolerable incongruities.
We shall endeavour to show that the modes of employment
of the thoughts to which the well conducted
study of nature gives rise, do tend, in all their forms,
to produce or strengthen this impression on the
mind; and that such an impression, and no other, is
consistent with the widest views and most comprehensive
aspects of nature and of philosophy, which
our Natural Philosophy opens to us. This will be
the purpose of the latter part of the present book. In
the first place we shall proceed with the object first
mentioned, the connexion which may be perceived
between the evidences of creative power, and of moral
government, in the world.
</div></body></text></TEI>