<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Temple of Nature</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1803</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="9">(p. 129) CANTO IV.
OF GOOD AND EVIL.

I. "How few," the Muse in plaintive accents cries,
  And mingles with her words pathetic sighs.—
  "How few, alas! in Nature's wide domains
  The sacred charm of Sympathy restrains!
  Uncheck'd desires from appetite commence,
  And pure reflection yields to selfish sense!
  —Blest is the Sage, who learn'd in Nature's laws
  With nice distinction marks effect and cause;
  Who views the insatiate Grave with eye sedate,
  Nor fears thy voice, inexorable Fate!      10
(p. 130)   "When War, the Demon, lifts his banner high,
  And loud artillery rends the affrighted sky;
  Swords clash with swords, on horses horses rush,
  Man tramples man, and nations nations crush;
  Death his vast sithe with sweep enormous wields,
  And shuddering Pity quits the sanguine fields.
"The wolf, escorted by his milk-drawn dam,
  Unknown to mercy, tears the guiltless lamb;
The towering eagle, darting from above,
  Unfeeling rends the inoffensive dove;      20
  The lamb and dove on living nature feed,
  Crop the young herb, or crush the embryon seed.
  Nor spares the loud owl in her dusky flight,
  Smit with sweet notes, the minstrel of the night;
  Nor spares, enamour'd of his radiant form,
  The hungry nightingale the glowing worm;
(p. 131) Who with bright lamp alarms the midnight hour,
  Climbs the green stem, and slays the sleeping flower.
"Fell Oestrus buries in her rapid course
  Her countless brood in stag, or bull, or horse;      30
  Whose hungry larva eats its living way,
  Hatch'd by the warmth, and issues into day.
The wing'd Ichneumon for her embryon young
  Gores with sharp horn the caterpillar throng.
(p. 132) The cruel larva mines its silky course,
  And tears the vitals of its fostering nurse.
While fierce Libellula with jaws of steel
  Ingulfs an insect-province at a meal;
Contending bee-swarms rise on rustling wings,
  And slay their thousands with envenom'd stings.      40
"Yes! smiling Flora drives her armed car
  Through the thick ranks of vegetable war;
(p. 133) Herb, shrub, and tree, with strong emotions rise
  For light and air, and battle in the skies;
  Whose roots diverging with opposing toil
  Contend below for moisture and for soil;
  Round the tall Elm the flattering Ivies bend,
  And strangle, as they clasp, their struggling friend;
  Envenom'd dews from Mancinella flow,
  And scald with caustic touch the tribes below;      50
  Dense shadowy leaves on stems aspiring borne
  With blight and mildew thin the realms of corn;
  And insect hordes with restless tooth devour
  The unfolded bud, and pierce the ravell'd flower.
"In ocean's pearly haunts, the waves beneath
  Sits the grim monarch of insatiate Death;
The shark rapacious with descending blow
  Darts on the scaly brood, that swims below;
(p. 134) The crawling crocodiles, beneath that move,
  Arrest with rising jaw the tribes above;      60
  With monstrous gape sepulchral whales devour
  Shoals at a gulp, a million in an hour.
  —Air, earth, and ocean, to astonish'd day
  One scene of blood, one mighty tomb display!
  From Hunger's arm the shafts of Death are hurl'd,
And one great Slaughter-house the warring world!
(p. 135)   "The brow of Man erect, with thought elate,
  Ducks to the mandate of resistless fate;
  Nor Love retains him, nor can Virtue save
  Her sages, saints, or heroes from the grave.      70
While cold and hunger by defect oppress,
  Repletion, heat, and labour by excess,
(p. 136) The whip, the sting, the spur, the fiery brand,
  And, cursed Slavery! thy iron hand;
  And led by Luxury Disease's trains,
  Load human life with unextinguish'd pains.
"Here laughs Ebriety more fell than arms,
  And thins the nations with her fatal charms,
  With Gout, and Hydrops groaning in her train,
  And cold Debility, and grinning Pain,      80
  With harlot's smiles deluded man salutes,
  Revenging all his cruelties to brutes!
  There the curst spells of Superstition blind,
  And fix her fetters on the tortured mind;
  She bids in dreams tormenting shapes appear,
  With shrieks that shock Imagination's ear,
(p. 137) E'en o'er the grave a deeper shadow flings,
  And maddening Conscience darts a thousand stings.
"There writhing Mania sits on Reason's throne,
  Or Melancholy marks it for her own,      90
  Sheds o'er the scene a voluntary gloom,
  Requests oblivion, and demands the tomb.
And last Association's trains suggest
Ideal ills, that harrow up the breast,
(p. 138) Call for the dead from Time's o'erwhelming main,
  And bid departed Sorrow live again.
"Here ragged Avarice guards with bolted door
  His useless treasures from the starving poor;
  Loads the lorn hours with misery and care,
  And lives a beggar to enrich his heir.      100
  Unthinking crowds thy forms, Imposture, gull,
  A Saint in sackcloth, or a Wolf in wool.
(p. 139) While mad with foolish fame, or drunk with power,
  Ambition slays his thousands in an hour;
  Demoniac Envy scowls with haggard mien,
  And blights the bloom of other's joys, unseen;
  Or wrathful Jealousy invades the grove,
  And turns to night meridian beams of Love!
"Here wide o'er earth impetuous waters sweep,
  And fields and forests rush into the deep;      110
  Or dread Volcano with explosion dire
  Involves the mountains in a flood of fire;
  Or yawning Earth with closing jaws inhumes
  Unwarned nations, living in their tombs;
  Or Famine seizes with her tiger-paw,
  And swallows millions with unsated maw.
"There livid Pestilence in league with Dearth
  Walks forth malignant o'er the shuddering earth,
(p. 140) Her rapid shafts with airs volcanic wings,
  Or steeps in putrid vaults her venom'd stings.      120
  Arrests the young in Beauty's vernal bloom,
  And bears the innocuous strangers to the tomb!—
"And now, e'en I, whose verse reluctant sings
  The changeful state of sublunary things,
  Bend o'er Mortality with silent sighs,
  And wipe the secret tear-drops from my eyes,
  Hear through the night one universal groan,
  And mourn unseen for evils not my own,
  With restless limbs and throbbing heart complain,
  Stretch'd on the rack of sentimental pain!      130
(p. 141) —Ah where can Sympathy reflecting find
  One bright idea to console the mind?
  One ray of light in this terrene abode
  To prove to Man the Goodness of his God?"
II. "Hear, O ye Sons of Time!" the Nymph replies,
  Quick indignation darting from her eyes;
  "When in soft tones the Muse lamenting sings,
  And weighs with tremulous hand the sum of things;
  She loads the scale in melancholy mood,
  Presents the evil, but forgets the good.      140
(p. 142) But if the beam some firmer hand suspends,
  And good and evil load the adverse ends;
  With strong libration, where the Good abides,
  Quick nods the beam, the ponderous gold subsides.
"Hear, O ye Sons of Time! the powers of Life
  Arrest the elements, and stay their strife;
From wandering atoms, ethers, airs, and gas,
  By combination form the organic mass;
  And,—as they seize, digest, secrete,—dispense
  The bliss of Being to the vital Ens.      150
  Hence in bright groups from Irritation rise
  Young Pleasure's trains, and roll their azure eyes.
(p. 143)   "With fond delight we feel the potent charm,
  When Zephyrs cool us, or when sun-beams warm;
  With fond delight inhale the fragrant flowers,
  Taste the sweet fruits, which bend the blushing bowers,
  Admire the music of the vernal grove,
  Or drink the raptures of delirious love.
"So with long gaze admiring eyes behold
The varied landscape all its lights unfold;      160
  Huge rocks opposing o'er the stream project
  Their naked bosoms, and the beams reflect;
(p. 144) Wave high in air their fringed crests of wood,
  And checker'd shadows dance upon the flood;
  Green sloping lawns construct the sidelong scene,
  And guide the sparkling rill that winds between;
  Conduct on murmuring wings the pausing gale,
  And rural echoes talk along the vale;
  Dim hills behind in pomp aerial rise,
  Lift their blue tops, and melt into the skies.      170
"So when by Handel tuned to measured sounds
  The trumpet vibrates, or the drum rebounds;
  Alarm'd we listen with ecstatic wonder
  To mimic battles, or imagined thunder.
  When the soft lute in sweet impassion'd strains
  Of cruel nymphs or broken vows complains;
  As on the breeze the fine vibration floats,
We drink delighted the melodious notes.
(p. 145) But when young Beauty on the realms above
  Bends her bright eye, and trills the tones of love;      180
  Seraphic sounds enchant this nether sphere;
  And listening angels lean from Heaven to hear.
"Next by Sensation led, new joys commence
  From the fine movements of the excited sense;
  In swarms ideal urge their airy flight,
  Adorn the day-scenes, and illume the night.
  Her spells o'er all the hand of Fancy flings,
  Gives form and substance to unreal things;
(p. 146) With fruits and foliage decks the barren waste,
  And brightens Life with sentiment and taste;      190
  Pleased o'er the level and the rule presides,
  The painter's brush, the sculptor's chisel guides,
  With ray ethereal lights the poet's fire,
  Tunes the rude pipe, or strings the heroic lyre:
  Charm'd round the nymph on frolic footsteps move
  The angelic forms of Beauty, Grace, and Love.
"So dreams the Patriot, who indignant draws
  The sword of vengeance in his Country's cause;
  Bright for his brows unfading honours bloom,
  Or kneeling Virgins weep around his tomb.      200
  So holy transports in the cloister's shade
  Play round thy toilet, visionary maid!
  Charm'd o'er thy bed celestial voices sing,
  And Seraphs hover on enamour'd wing.
"So Howard, Moira, Burdett, sought the cells,
  Where want, or woe, or guilt in darkness dwells;
(p. 147) With Pity's torch illumed the dread domains,
  Wiped the wet eye, and eased the galling chains;
  With Hope's bright blushes warm'd the midnight air,
  And drove from earth the Demon of Despair.      210
  Erewhile emerging from the caves of night
  The Friends of Man ascended into light;
  With soft assuasive eloquence address'd
  The ear of Power to stay his stern behest;
  At Mercy's call to stretch his arm and save
  His tottering victims from the gaping grave.
  These with sweet smiles Imagination greets,
  For these she opens all her treasured sweets,
  Strews round their couch, by Pity's hand combined,
  Bright flowers of joy, the sunshine of the mind;      220
  While Fame's loud trump with sounds applausive breathes
  And Virtue crowns them with immortal wreathes.
"Thy acts, Volition, to the world impart
  The plans of Science with the works of art;
(p. 148) Give to proud Reason her comparing power,
  Warm every clime, and brighten every hour.
  In Life's first cradle, ere the dawn began
  Of young Society to polish man;
  The staff that propp'd him, and the bow that arm'd,
  The boat that bore him, and the shed that warm'd,      230
  Fire, raiment, food, the ploughshare, and the sword,
  Arose, Volition, at thy plastic word.
"By thee instructed, Newton's eye sublime
  Mark'd the bright periods of revolving time;
  Explored in Nature's scenes the effect and cause,
  And, charm'd, unravell'd all her latent laws.
  Delighted Herschel with reflected light
  Pursues his radiant journey through the night;
  Detects new guards, that roll their orbs afar
  In lucid ringlets round the Georgian star.      240
(p. 149)   "Inspired by thee, with scientific wand
  Pleased Archimedes mark'd the figured sand;
  Seized with mechanic grasp the approaching decks,
  And shook the assailants from the inverted wrecks.
  —Then cried the Sage, with grand effects elate,
  And proud to save the Syracusian state;
  While crowds exulting shout their noisy mirth,
  'Give where to stand, and I will move the earth.'
So Savery guided his explosive steam
  In iron cells to raise the balanced beam;      250
  The Giant-form its ponderous mass uprears,
  Descending nods and seems to shake the spheres.
(p. 150)   "Led by Volition on the banks of Nile
  Where bloom'd the waving flax on Delta's isle,
  Pleased Isis taught the fibrous stems to bind,
  And part with hammers from the adhesive rind;
  With locks of flax to deck the distaff-pole,
  And whirl with graceful bend the dancing spole.
  In level lines the length of woof to spread,
  And dart the shuttle through the parting thread.      260
So Arkwright taught from Cotton-pods to cull,
  And stretch in lines the vegetable wool;
  With teeth of steel its fibre-knots unfurl'd,
  And with the silver tissue clothed the world.
"Ages remote by thee, Volition, taught
  Chain'd down in characters the winged thought;
  With silent language mark'd the letter'd ground,
  And gave to sight the evanescent sound.
(p. 151) Now, happier lot! enlighten'd realms possess
  The learned labours of the immortal Press;      270
  Nursed on whose lap the births of science thrive,
  And rising Arts the wrecks of Time survive.
"Ye patriot heroes! in the glorious cause
  Of Justice, Mercy, Liberty, and Laws,
  Who call to Virtue's shrine the British youth,
  And shake the senate with the voice of Truth;
  Rouse the dull ear, the hoodwink'd eye unbind,
  And give to energy the public mind;
(p. 152) While rival realms with blood unsated wage
  Wide-wasting war with fell demoniac rage;      280
  In every clime while army army meets,
  And oceans groan beneath contending fleets;
  Oh save, oh save, in this eventful hour
  The tree of knowledge from the axe of power;
  With fostering peace the suffering nations bless,
  And guard the freedom of the immortal Press!
  So shall your deathless fame from age to age
  Survive recorded in the historic page;
  And future bards with voice inspired prolong
  Your sacred names immortalized in song.      290
"Thy power Association next affords
  Ideal trains annex'd to volant words,
  Conveys to listening ears the thought superb,
  And gives to Language her expressive verb;
(p. 153) Which in one changeful sound suggests the fact
  At once to be, to suffer, or to act;
  And marks on rapid wing o'er every clime
  The viewless flight of evanescent Time.
"Call'd by thy voice contiguous thoughts embrace
  In endless streams arranged by Time or Place;      300
  The Muse historic hence in every age
  Gives to the world her interesting page;
  While in bright landscape from her moving pen
  Rise the fine tints of manners and of men.
(p. 154)   "Call'd by thy voice Resemblance next describes
  Her sister-thoughts in lucid trains or tribes;
  Whence pleased Imagination oft combines
  By loose analogies her fair designs;
  Each winning grace of polish'd wit bestows
  To deck the Nymphs of Poetry and Prose.      310
"Last, at thy potent nod, Effect and Cause
  Walk hand in hand accordant to thy laws;
  Rise at Volition's call, in groups combined,
  Amuse, delight, instruct, and serve Mankind;
(p. 155) Bid raised in air the ponderous structure stand,
  Or pour obedient rivers through the land;
  With cars unnumber'd crowd the living streets,
  Or people oceans with triumphant fleets.
"Thy magic touch imagined forms supplies
  From colour'd light, the language of the eyes;      320
  On Memory's page departed hours inscribes,
  Sweet scenes of youth, and Pleasure's vanish'd tribes.
  By thee Antinous leads the dance sublime
  On wavy step, and moves in measured time;
  Charm'd round the Youth successive Graces throng,
  And Ease conducts him, as he moves along;
  Unbreathing crowds the floating form admire,
  And Vestal bosoms feel forbidden fire.
"When rapp'd Cecilia breathes her matin vow,
  And lifts to Heaven her fair adoring brow;      330
  From her sweet lips, and rising bosom part
  Impassion'd notes, that thrill the melting heart;
(p. 156) Tuned by thy hand the dulcet harp she rings,
  And sounds responsive echo from the strings;
  Bright scenes of bliss in trains suggested move,
  And charm the world with melody and love.
III. "Soon the fair forms with vital being bless'd,
  Time's feeble children, lose the boon possess'd;
The goaded fibre ceases to obey,
  And sense deserts the uncontractile clay;      340
  While births unnumber'd, ere the parents die,
  The hourly waste of lovely life supply;
  And thus, alternating with death, fulfil
  The silent mandates of the Almighty Will;
  Whose hand unseen the works of nature dooms
  By laws unknown—WHO GIVES, AND WHO RESUMES.
"Each pregnant Oak ten thousand acorns forms
  Profusely scatter'd by autumnal storms;
(p. 157) Ten thousand seeds each pregnant poppy sheds
  Profusely scatter'd from its waving heads;      350
The countless Aphides, prolific tribe,
  With greedy trunks the honey'd sap imbibe;
(p. 158) Swarm on each leaf with eggs or embryons big,
  And pendent nations tenant every twig.
  Amorous with double sex, the snail and worm,
  Scoop'd in the soil, their cradling caverns form;
  Heap their white eggs, secure from frost and floods,
  And crowd their nurseries with uncounted broods.
  Ere yet with wavy tail the tadpole swims,
  Breathes with new lungs, or tries his nascent limbs;      360
  Her countless shoals the amphibious frog forsakes,
  And living islands float upon the lakes.
(p. 159) The migrant herring steers her myriad bands
  From seas of ice to visit warmer strands;
  Unfathom'd depths and climes unknown explores,
  And covers with her spawn unmeasured shores.
  —All these, increasing by successive birth,
  Would each o'erpeople ocean, air, and earth.
"So human progenies, if unrestrain'd,
  By climate friended, and by food sustain'd,      370
  O'er seas and soils, prolific hordes! would spread
  Erelong, and deluge their terraqueous bed;
  But war, and pestilence, disease, and dearth,
  Sweep the superfluous myriads from the earth.
Thus while new forms reviving tribes acquire
  Each passing moment, as the old expire;
  Like insects swarming in the noontide bower,
  Rise into being, and exist an hour;
  The births and deaths contend with equal strife,
  And every pore of Nature teems with Life;      380
(p. 160) Which buds or breathes from Indus to the Poles,
  And Earth's vast surface kindles, as it rolls!
"Hence when a Monarch or a mushroom dies,
  Awhile extinct the organic matter lies;
  But, as a few short hours or years revolve,
  Alchemic powers the changing mass dissolve;
Born to new life unnumber'd insects pant,
  New buds surround the microscopic plant;
  Whose embryon senses, and unwearied frames,
  Feel finer goads, and blush with purer flames;      390
(p. 161) Renascent joys from irritation spring,
  Stretch the long root, or wave the aurelian wing.
"When thus a squadron or an army yields,
  And festering carnage loads the waves or fields;
  When few from famines or from plagues survive,
  Or earthquakes swallow half a realm alive;—
  While Nature sinks in Time's destructive storms,
  The wrecks of Death are but a change of forms;
  Emerging matter from the grave returns,
  Feels new desires, with new sensations burns;      400
  With youth's first bloom a finer sense acquires,
  And Loves and Pleasures fan the rising fires.—
Thus sainted Paul, 'O Death!' exulting cries,
  'Where is thy sting? O Grave! thy victories?'
(p. 162)   "Immortal Happiness from realms deceased
  Wakes, as from sleep, unlessen'd or increased;
  Calls to the wise in accents loud and clear,
  Sooths with sweet tones the sympathetic ear;
  Informs and fires the revivescent clay,
And lights the dawn of Life's returning day.      410
"So when Arabia's Bird, by age oppress'd,
  Consumes delighted on his spicy nest;
  A filial Phœnix from his ashes springs,
  Crown'd with a star, on renovated wings;
  Ascends exulting from his funeral flame,
  And soars and shines, another and the same.
(p. 163)   "So erst the Sage with scientific truth
  In Grecian temples taught the attentive youth;
  With ceaseless change how restless atoms pass
  From life to life, a transmigrating mass;      420
  How the same organs, which to day compose
  The poisonous henbane, or the fragrant rose,
  May with to morrow's sun new forms compile,
  Frown in the Hero, in the Beauty smile.
  Whence drew the enlighten'd Sage the moral plan,
  That man should ever be the friend of man;
  Should eye with tenderness all living forms,
  His brother-emmets, and his sister-worms.
"Hear, O ye Sons of Time! your final doom,
  And read the characters, that mark your tomb:      430
(p. 164) The marble mountain, and the sparry steep,
  Were built by myriad nations of the deep,—
  Age after age, who form'd their spiral shells,
  Their sea-fan gardens and their coral cells;
  Till central fires with unextinguished sway
  Raised the primeval islands into day;—
  The sand-fill'd strata stretch'd from pole to pole;
  Unmeasured beds of clay, and marl, and coal,
(p. 165) Black ore of manganese, the zinky stone,
  And dusky steel on his magnetic throne,      440
  In deep morass, or eminence superb,
  Rose from the wrecks of animal or herb;
  These from their elements by Life combined,
  Form'd by digestion, and in glands refined,
  Gave by their just excitement of the sense
  The Bliss of Being to the vital Ens.
"Thus the tall mountains, that emboss the lands,
  Huge isles of rock, and continents of sands,
  Whose dim extent eludes the inquiring sight,
Are mighty Monuments of past Delight;      450
(p. 166) Shout round the globe, how Reproduction strives
  With vanquish'd Death,—and Happiness survives;
How Life increasing peoples every clime,
  And young renascent Nature conquers Time;
(p. 167) —And high in golden characters record
  The immense munificence of Nature's Lord!—
"He gives and guides the sun's attractive force,
  And steers the planets in their silver course;
  With heat and light revives the golden day,
  And breathes his spirit on organic clay;      460
  With hand unseen directs the general cause
  By firm immutable immortal laws."
Charm'd with her words the Muse astonish'd stands,
  The Nymphs enraptured clasp their velvet hands;
  Applausive thunder from the fane recoils,
  And holy echoes peal along the ailes;
  O'er Nature's shrine celestial lustres glow,
  And lambent glories circle round her brow.
(p. 168)   IV. Now sinks the golden sun,—the vesper song
  Demands the tribute of Urania's tongue;      470
  Onward she steps, her fair associates calls
  From leaf-wove avenues, and vaulted halls.
  Fair virgin trains in bright procession move,
  Trail their long robes, and whiten all the grove;
  Pair after pair to Nature's temple sweep,
  Thread the broad arch, ascend the winding steep;
  Through brazen gates along susurrant ailes
  Stream round their Goddess the successive files;
  Curve above curve to golden seats retire,
  And star with beauty the refulgent quire.      480
And first to Heaven the consecrated throng
  With chant alternate pour the adoring song,
  Swell the full hymn, now high, and now profound,
  With sweet responsive symphony of sound.
  Seen through their wiry harps, below, above,
  Nods the fair brow, the twinkling fingers move;
(p. 169) Soft-warbling flutes the ruby lip commands,
  And cymbals ring with high uplifted hands.
To Chaos next the notes melodious pass,
  How suns exploded from the kindling mass,      490
  Waved o'er the vast inane their tresses bright,
  And charm'd young Nature's opening eyes with light.
  Next from each sun how spheres reluctant burst,
  And second planets issued from the first.
  And then to Earth descends the moral strain,
  How isles, emerging from the shoreless main,
  With sparkling streams and fruitful groves began,
  And form'd a Paradise for mortal man.
Sublimer notes record Celestial Love,
  And high rewards in brighter climes above;      500
(p. 170) How Virtue's beams with mental charm engage
  Youth's raptured eye, and warm the frost of age,
  Gild with soft lustre Death's tremendous gloom,
  And light the dreary chambers of the tomb.
  How fell Remorse shall strike with venom'd dart,
  Though mail'd in adamant, the guilty heart;
  Fierce furies drag to pains and realms unknown
  The blood-stain'd tyrant from his tottering throne.
By hands unseen are struck aerial wires,
  And Angel-tongues are heard amid the quires;      510
  From aile to aile the trembling concord floats,
  And the wide roof returns the mingled notes,
  Through each fine nerve the keen vibrations dart,
  Pierce the charm'd ear, and thrill the echoing heart.—
Mute the sweet voice, and still the quivering strings,
  Now Silence hovers on unmoving wings.—
—Slow to the altar fair Urania bends
  Her graceful march, the sacred steps ascends,
(p. 171) High in the midst with blazing censer stands,
  And scatters incense with illumined hands:      520
  Thrice to the Goddess bows with solemn pause,
  With trembling awe the mystic veil withdraws,
  And, meekly kneeling on the gorgeous shrine,
  Lifts her ecstatic eyes to Truth Divine!      524

END OF CANTO IV.</div></body></text></TEI>