<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="41">
CHAPTER IX.

On the Impression produced by considering the Nature
and Prospects of Science;
or, on the Impossibility
of the Progress of our Knowledge ever enabling us
to comprehend the Nature of the Deity.

If we were to stop at the view presented in the
last chapter, it might be supposed that—by considering[274]
God as eternal and omnipresent, conscious of all
the relations, and of all the objects of the universe,
instituting laws founded on the contemplation of
these relations, and carrying these laws into effect
by his immediate energy,—we had attained to a conception,
in some degree definite, of the Deity, such
as natural philosophy leads us to conceive him. But
by resting in this mode of conception, we should
overlook, or at least should disconnect from our
philosophical doctrines, all that most interests and
affects us in the character of the Creator and Preserver
of the world;—namely, that he is the lawgiver
and judge of our actions; the proper object of
our prayer and adoration; the source from which
we may hope for moral strength here, and for the
reward of our obedience and the elevation of our
nature in another state of existence.
We are very far from believing that our philosophy
alone can give us such assurance of these important
truths as is requisite for our guidance and
support; but we think that even our physical philosophy
will point out to us the necessity of proceeding
far beyond that conception of God, which represents
him merely as the mind in which reside all
the contrivance, law, and energy of the material
world. We believe that the view of the universe
which modern science has already opened to us,
compared with the prospect of what she has still to
do in pursuing the path on which she has just entered,
will show us how immeasurably inadequate such
a mode of conception would be: and that if we take
into our account, as we must in reason do, all that
of which we have knowledge and consciousness, and
of which we have as yet no systematic science, we
shall be led to a conviction that the Creator and Preserver
of the material world must also contain in
him such properties and attributes as imply his moral
character, and as fall in most consistently with all
that we learn in any other way of his providence
and holiness, his justice and mercy.
[275]
1. The sciences which have at present acquired
any considerable degree of completeness, are those
in which an extensive and varied collection of phenomena,
and their proximate causes, have been reduced
to a few simple general laws. Such are
Astronomy and Mechanics, and perhaps, so far as
its physical conditions are concerned, Optics. Other
portions of human knowledge can be considered as
perfect sciences, in any strict sense of the term, only
when they have assumed this form; when the various
appearances which they involve are reduced
to a few principles, such as the laws of motion and
the mechanical properties of the luminiferous ether.
If we could trace the endless varieties of the forms
of crystals, and the complicated results of chemical
composition, to some one comprehensive law necessarily
pointing out the crystalline form of any given
chemical compound, Mineralogy would become an
exact science. As yet, however, we can scarcely
boast of the existence of any other such sciences
than those which we at first mentioned: and so far
therefore as we attempt to give definiteness to our
conception of the Deity, by considering him as the
intelligent depositary and executor of laws of nature,
we can subordinate to such a mode of conception
no portion of the creation, save the mechanical
movements of the universe, and the propagation and
properties of light.
2. And if we attempt to argue concerning the nature
of the laws and relations which govern those
provinces of creation whither our science has not
yet reached, by applying some analogy borrowed
from cases where it has been successful, we have no
chance of attaining any except the most erroneous
and worthless guesses. The history of human speculations,
as well as the nature of the objects of
them, shows how certainly this must happen. The
great generalizations which have been established in
one department of our knowledge, have been applied
in vain to the purpose of throwing light on the[276]
other portions which still continue in obscurity.
When the Newtonian philosophy had explained so
many mechanical facts, by the two great steps,—of
resolving the action of a whole mass into the actions
of its minutest particles, and considering these particles
as centres of force,—attempts were naturally
soon made to apply the same mode of explanation
to facts of other different kinds. It was conceived
that the whole of natural philosophy must consist in
investigating the laws of force by which particles of
different substances attracted and repelled, and thus
produced motions, or vibrations to and from the particles.
Yet what were the next great discoveries in
physics? The action of a galvanic wire upon a
magnet; which is not to attract or repel it, but to
turn it to the right and left; to produce motion, not
to or from, but transverse to the line drawn to the
acting particles; and again, the undulatory theory
of light, in which it appeared that the undulations
must not be longitudinal, as all philosophers, following
the analogy of all cases previously conceived,
had, at first, supposed them to be, but transverse to
the path of the ray. Here, though the step from
the known to the unknown was comparatively small,
when made conjecturally it was made in a direction
very wide of the truth. How impossible then must
it be to attain in this manner to any conception of a
law which shall help us to understand the whole
government of the universe!
3. Still, however, in the laws of the luminiferous
ether, and of the other fluid, (if it be another fluid)
by which galvanism and magnetism are connected,
we have something approaching nearly to mechanical
action, and, possibly, hereafter to be identified
with it. But we cannot turn to any other part of our
physical knowledge, without perceiving that the gulf
which separates it from the exact sciences is yet
wider and more obscure. Who shall enunciate for
us, and in terms of what notions, the general law of
chemical composition and decomposition? sometimes[277]
indeed we give the name of attraction to the affinity
by which we suppose the particles of the various ingredients
of bodies to be aggregated; but no one
can point out any common feature between this and
the attractions of which alone we know the exact
effects. He who shall discover the true general law
of the forces by which elements form compounds,
will probably advance as far beyond the discoveries
of Newton, as Newton went beyond Aristotle. But
who shall say in what direction this vast flight shall
be, and what new views it shall open to us of the
manner in which matter obeys the laws of the
Creator?
4. But suppose this flight performed;—we are yet
but at the outset of the progress which must carry
us towards Him. We have yet to begin to learn all
that we are to know concerning the ultimate laws
of organized bodies. What is the principle of life?
What is the rule of that action of which assimilation,
secretion, developement, are manifestations?
and which appears to be farther removed from mere
chemistry than chemistry is from mechanics. And
what again is the new principle, as it seems to be,
which is exhibited in the irritability of an animal nerve?
the existence of a sense? How different is this from
all the preceding notions! No efforts can avoid or
conceal the vast but inscrutable chasm. Those theorists,
who have maintained most strenuously the possibility
of tracing the phenomena of animal life to the
influence of physical agents, have constantly been
obliged to suppose a mode of agency altogether different
from any yet known in physics. Thus Lamarck,
one of the most noted of such speculators, in
describing the course of his researches, says, “I was
soon persuaded that the internal sentiment constituted
a power which it was necessary to take into
account.” And Bichat, another writer on the same
subject, while he declares his dissent from Stahl, and
the earlier speculators, who had referred every thing
in the economy of life to a single principle, which[278]
they called the anima, the vital principle, and so
forth, himself introduces several principles, or laws,
all utterly foreign to the region of physics; namely,
organic sensibility, organic contractility, animal sensibility,
animal contractility, and the like. Supposing
such principles really to exist, how far enlarged and
changed must our views be before we can conceive
these properties, including the faculty of perception,
which they imply, to be produced by the will and
power of one supreme Being, acting by fixed laws.
Yet without conceiving this, we cannot conceive the
agency of that Deity, who is incessantly thus acting,
in countless millions of forms and modes.
How strongly then does science represent God to
us as incomprehensible! his attributes as unfathomable!
His power, his wisdom, his goodness, appear
in each of the provinces of nature which are thus
brought before us; and in each, the more we study
them, the more impressive, the more admirable do
they appear. When then we find these qualities
manifested in each of so many successive ways, and
each manifestation rising above the preceding by
unknown degrees, and through a progression of unknown
extent, what other language can we use concerning
such attributes than that they are infinite?
What mode of expression can the most cautious philosophy
suggest, other than that He, to whom we
thus endeavour to approach, is infinitely wise, powerful,
and good?
5. But with sense and consciousness the history of
living things only begins. They have instincts, affections,
passions, will. How entirely lost and bewildered
do we find ourselves when we endeavour to
conceive these faculties communicated by means of
general laws! Yet they are so communicated from
God, and of such laws he is the lawgiver. At what
an immeasurable interval is he thus placed above
every thing which the creation of the inanimate
world alone would imply; and how far must he[279]
transcend all ideas founded on such laws as we find
there!
6. But we have still to go further and far higher.
The world of reason and of morality is a part of the
same creation, as the world of matter and of sense.
The will of man is swayed by rational motives; its
workings are inevitably compared with a rule of action;
he has a conscience which speaks of right and
wrong. These are laws of man’s nature no less than
the laws of his material existence, or his animal impulses.
Yet what entirely new conceptions do they
involve? How incapable of being resolved into, or
assimilated to, the results of mere matter, or mere
sense! Moral good and evil, merit and demerit,
virtue and depravity, if ever they are the subjects of
strict science, must belong to a science which views
these things, not with reference to time or space, or
mechanical causation, not with reference to fluid or
ether, nervous irritability or corporeal feeling, but to
their own proper modes of conception; with reference
to the relations with which it is possible that
these notions may be connected, and not to relations
suggested by other subjects of a completely extraneous
and heterogeneous nature. And according to
such relations must the laws of the moral world be
apprehended, by any intelligence which contemplates
them at all.
There can be no wider interval in philosophy than
the separation which must exist between the laws of
mechanical force and motion, and the laws of free
moral action. Yet the tendency of men to assume,
in the portions of human knowledge which are out
of their reach, a similarity of type to those with
which they are familiar, can leap over even this
interval. Laplace has asserted that “an intelligence
which, at a given instant, should know all the
forces by which nature is urged, and the respective
situation of the beings of which nature is composed,
if, moreover, it were sufficiently comprehensive to
subject these data to calculation, would include in[280]
the same formula, the movements of the largest bodies
of the universe and those of the slightest atom.
Nothing would be uncertain to such an intelligence,
and the future, no less than the past, would be present
to its eyes.” If we speak merely of mechanical
actions, this may, perhaps, be assumed to be an admissible
representation of the nature of their connexion
in the sight of the supreme intelligence. But to
the rest of what passes in the world, such language
is altogether inapplicable. A formula is a brief mode
of denoting a rule of calculating in which numbers
are to be used: and numerical measures are applicable
only to things of which the relation depend on
time and space. By such elements, in such a mode,
how are we to estimate happiness and virtue, thought
and will? To speak of a formula with regard to such
things, would be to assume that their laws must needs
take the shape of those laws of the material world
which our intellect most fully comprehends. A more
absurd and unphilosophical assumption we can hardly
imagine.
We conceive, therefore, that the laws by which
God governs his moral creatures, reside in his mind,
invested with that kind of generality, whatever it be,
of which such laws are capable; but of the character
of such general laws, we know nothing more certainly
than this, that it must be altogether different
from the character of those laws which regulate the
material world. The inevitable necessity of such a
total difference is suggested by the analogy of all the
knowledge which we possess and all the conceptions
which we can form. And, accordingly, no persons,
except those whose minds have been biassed
by some peculiar habit or course of thought, are
likely to run into the confusion and perplexity which
are produced by assimilating too closely the government
and direction of voluntary agents to the production
of trains of mechanical and physical phenomena.
In whatever manner voluntary and moral
agency depend upon the Supreme Being, it must be[281]
in some such way that they still continue to bear the
character of will, action, and morality. And, though
too exclusive an attention to material phenomena
may sometimes have made physical philosophers
blind to this manifest difference, it has been clearly
seen and plainly asserted by those who have taken
the most comprehensive views of the nature and
tendency of science. “I believe,” says Bacon, in his
Confession of Faith, “that, at the first the soul of
man was not produced by heaven or earth, but was
breathed immediately from God; so that the ways
and proceedings of God with spirits are not included
in nature; that is in the laws of heaven and earth;
but are reserved to the law of his secret will and
grace; wherein God worketh still, and resteth not
from the work of redemption, as he resteth from the
work of creation; but continueth working to the end
of the world.” We may be permitted to observe
here, that, when Bacon has thus to speak of God’s
dealings with his moral creatures, he does not take
his phraseology from those sciences which can offer
none but false and delusive analogies; but helps out
the inevitable scantiness of our human knowledge,
by words borrowed from a source more fitted to
supply our imperfections. Our natural speculations
cannot carry us to the ideas of “grace” and “redemption;”
but in the wide blank which they leave,
of all that concerns our hopes of the Divine support
and favour, the inestimable knowledge which revelation,
as we conceive, gives us, finds ample room
and appropriate place.
7. Yet even in the view of our moral constitution
which natural reason gives, we may trace laws that
imply a personal relation to our Creator. How can
we avoid considering that as a true view of man’s
being and place, without which, his best faculties are
never fully developed, his noblest energies never
called out, his highest point of perfection never
reached? Without the thought of a God over all,
superintending our actions, approving our virtues,[282]
transcending our highest conceptions of good, man
would never rise to those higher regions of moral
excellence which we know him to be capable of attaining.
“To deny a God,” again says the great
philosopher, “destroys magnanimity and the raising
of human nature; for take an example of a dog, and
mark what a generosity and courage he will put on,
when he finds himself maintained by a man; who,
to him, is instead of a God, or melior natura: which
courage is manifestly such, as that creature, without
that confidence of a better nature than his own,
could never attain. So man, when he resteth and
assureth himself upon divine protection and favour,
gathereth a force and faith, which human nature
could not obtain. Therefore, as atheism is in all respects
hateful, so in this, that it depriveth human
nature of the means to exalt itself above human
frailty.”[45]
Such a law, then, of reference to a Supremely
Good Being, is impressed upon our nature, as the
condition and means of its highest moral advancement.
And strange indeed it would be if we should
suppose, that in a system where all besides indicates
purpose and design, this law should proceed from no
such origin; and no less inconceivable, that such a
law, purposely impressed upon man to purify and
elevate his nature, should delude and deceive him.
8. Nothing remains, therefore, but that the Creator,
who, for purposes that even we can see to be
wise and good, has impressed upon man this tendency
to look to him for support, for advancement,
for such happiness as is reconcileable with holiness;—to
believe him to be the union of all perfection, the
highest point of all intellectual and moral excellence;—IS,
in reality, such a guardian and judge, such a
good, and wise, and perfect Being, as we thus irresistibly
conceive him. It would indeed be extravagant
to assert that the imagination of the creature,[283]
itself the work of God, can invent a higher point of
goodness, of justice, of holiness, than the Creator
himself possesses: that the Eternal Mind, from whom
our notions of good and right are derived, is not himself
directed by the rules which these notions imply.
It is difficult to dwell steadily on such thoughts.
But they will at least serve to confirm the view which
it was our object to illustrate; namely, how incomparably
the nature of God must be elevated above
any conceptions which our natural reason enables us
to form; and we have been led to these reflections, it
will be recollected, by following the clue of which
science gave us the beginning. The Divine Mind
must be conceived by us as the seat of those laws of
nature which we have discovered. It must be no
less the seat of those laws which we have not yet
discovered, though these may and must be of a character
far different from any thing we can guess.
The Supreme Intelligence must therefore contain the
laws, each according to their true dependence, of organic
life, of sense, of animal impulse, and must contain
also the purpose and intent for which these powers
were put in play. But the Governing Mind must
comprehend also the laws of the responsible creatures
which the world contains, and must entertain
the purposes for which their responsible agency was
given them. It must include these laws and purposes,
connected by means of the notions, which responsibility
implies, of desert and reward, of moral excellence
in various degrees, and of well-being as associated
with right doing. All the laws which govern
the moral world are expressions of the thought and
intentions of our Supreme Ruler. All the contrivances
for moral no less than for physical good, for
the peace of mind, and other rewards of virtue, for
the elevation and purification of individual character,
for the civilization and refinement of states, their advancement
in intellect and virtue, for the diffusion of
good, and the repression of evil; all the blessings that
wait on perseverance and energy in a good cause;[284]
on unquenchable love of mankind, and unconquerable
devotedness to truth; on purity and self-denial;
on faith, hope, and charity;—all these things are indications
of the character, will, and future intentions
of that God, of whom we have endeavoured to track
the footsteps upon earth, and to show his handiwork
in the heavens. “This God is our God, for ever and
ever.” And if, in endeavouring to trace the tendencies
of the vast labyrinth of laws by which the universe
is governed, we are sometimes lost and bewildered,
and can scarce, or not at all, discern the
line by which pain, and sorrow, and vice fall in with
a scheme directed to the strictest right and greatest
good, we yet find no room to faint or falter; knowing
that these are the darkest and most tangled recesses
of our knowledge; that into them science has as yet
cast no ray of light; that in them reason has as yet
caught sight of no general law by which we may securely
hold: while, in those regions where we can
see clearly, where science has thrown her strongest
illumination upon the scheme of creation; where we
have had displayed to us the general laws which give
rise to all multifarious variety of particular facts;—we
find all full wisdom, and harmony, and beauty:
and all this wise selection of means, this harmonious
combination of laws, this beautiful symmetry of relations,
directed, with no exception which human investigation
has yet discovered, to the preservation,
the diffusion, the well-being of those living things,
which, though of their nature we know so little, we
cannot doubt to be the worthiest objects of the Creator’s
care.
FINIS.
</div></body></text></TEI>