<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="22">

CHAPTER XIII.
COMPLEX IDEAS OF SIMPLE MODES:—AND FIRST, OF THE SIMPLE MODES OF IDEA OF
SPACE.

1. Simple modes of simple ideas.


Though in the foregoing part I have often mentioned simple ideas, which are
truly the materials of all our knowledge; yet having treated of them there,
rather in the way that they come into the mind, than as distinguished from
others more compounded, it will not be perhaps amiss to take a view of some of
them again under this consideration, and examine those different modifications
of the SAME idea; which the mind either finds in things existing, or is able to
make within itself without the help of any extrinsical object, or any foreign
suggestion.


Those modifications of any ONE simple idea (which, as has been said, I call
SIMPLE MODES) are as perfectly different and distinct ideas in the mind as
those of the greatest distance or contrariety. For the idea of two is as
distinct from that of one, as blueness from heat, or either of them from any
number: and yet it is made up only of that simple idea of an unit repeated; and
repetitions of this kind joined together make those distinct simple modes, of a
dozen, a gross, a million. Simple Modes of Idea of Space.


2. Idea of Space.


I shall begin with the simple idea of SPACE. I have showed above, chap. 4, that
we get the idea of space, both by our sight and touch; which, I think, is so
evident, that it would be as needless to go to prove that men perceive, by
their sight, a distance between bodies of different colours, or between the
parts of the same body, as that they see colours themselves: nor is it less
obvious, that they can do so in the dark by feeling and touch.


3. Space and Extension.


This space, considered barely in length between any two beings, without
considering anything else between them, is called DISTANCE: if considered in
length, breadth, and thickness, I think it may be called CAPACITY. When
considered between the extremities of matter, which fills the capacity of space
with something solid, tangible, and moveable, it is properly called EXTENSION.
And so extension is an idea belonging to body only; but space may, as is
evident, be considered without it. At least I think it most intelligible, and
the best way to avoid confusion, if we use the word extension for an affection
of matter or the distance of the extremities of particular solid bodies; and
space in the more general signification, for distance, with or without solid
matter possessing it.


4. Immensity.


Each different distance is a different modification of space; and each idea of
any different distance, or space, is a SIMPLE MODE of this idea. Men having, by
accustoming themselves to stated lengths of space, which they use for measuring
other distances—as a foot, a yard or a fathom, a league, or diameter of
the earth—made those ideas familiar to their thoughts, can, in their
minds, repeat them as often as they will, without mixing or joining to them the
idea of body, or anything else; and frame to themselves the ideas of long,
square, or cubic feet, yards or fathoms, here amongst the bodies of the
universe, or else beyond the utmost bounds of all bodies; and, by adding these
still one to another, enlarge their ideas of space as much as they please. The
power of repeating or doubling any idea we have of any distance, and adding it
to the former as often as we will, without being ever able to come to any stop
or stint, let us enlarge it as much as we will, is that which gives us the idea
of IMMENSITY.


5. Figure.


There is another modification of this idea, which is nothing but the relation
which the parts of the termination of extension, or circumscribed space, have
amongst themselves. This the touch discovers in sensible bodies, whose
extremities come within our reach; and the eye takes both from bodies and
colours, whose boundaries are within its view: where, observing how the
extremities terminate,—either in straight lines which meet at discernible
angles, or in crooked lines wherein no angles can be perceived; by considering
these as they relate to one another, in all parts of the extremities of any
body or space, it has that idea we call FIGURE, which affords to the mind
infinite variety. For, besides the vast number of different figures that do
really exist in the coherent masses of matter, the stock that the mind has in
its power, by varying the idea of space, and thereby making still new
compositions, by repeating its own ideas, and joining them as it pleases, is
perfectly inexhaustible. And so it can multiply figures IN INFINITUM.


6. Endless variety of figures.


For the mind having a power to repeat the idea of any length directly stretched
out, and join it to another in the same direction, which is to double the
length of that straight line; or else join another with what inclination it
thinks fit, and so make what sort of angle it pleases: and being able also to
shorten any line it imagines, by taking from it one half, one fourth, or what
part it pleases, without being able to come to an end of any such divisions, it
can make an angle of any bigness. So also the lines that are its sides, of what
length it pleases, which joining again to other lines, of different lengths,
and at different angles, till it has wholly enclosed any space, it is evident
that it can multiply figures, both in their shape and capacity, IN INFINITUM;
all which are but so many different simple modes of space.


The same that it can do with straight lines, it can also do with crooked, or
crooked and straight together; and the same it can do in lines, it can also in
superficies; by which we may be led into farther thoughts of the endless
variety of figures that the mind has a power to make, and thereby to multiply
the simple modes of space.


7. Place.


Another idea coming under this head, and belonging to this tribe, is that we
call PLACE. As in simple space, we consider the relation of distance between
any two bodies or points; so in our idea of place, we consider the relation of
distance betwixt anything, and any two or more points, which are considered as
keeping the same distance one with another, and so considered as at rest. For
when we find anything at the same distance now which it was yesterday, from any
two or more points, which have not since changed their distance one with
another, and with which we then compared it, we say it hath kept the same
place: but if it hath sensibly altered its distance with either of those
points, we say it hath changed its place: though, vulgarly speaking, in the
common notion of place, we do not always exactly observe the distance from
these precise points, but from larger portions of sensible objects, to which we
consider the thing placed to bear relation, and its distance from which we have
some reason to observe.


8. Place relative to particular bodies.


Thus, a company of chess-men, standing on the same squares of the chess-board
where we left them, we say they are all in the SAME place, or unmoved, though
perhaps the chessboard hath been in the mean time carried out of one room into
another; because we compared them only to the parts of the chess-board, which
keep the same distance one with another. The chess-board, we also say, is in
the same place it was, if it remain in the same part of the cabin, though
perhaps the ship which it is in sails all the while. And the ship is said to be
in the same place, supposing it kept the same distance with the parts of the
neighbouring land; though perhaps the earth hath turned round, and so both
chess-men, and board, and ship, have every one changed place, in respect of
remoter bodies, which have kept the same distance one with another. But yet the
distance from certain parts of the board being that which determines the place
of the chess-men; and the distance from the fixed parts of the cabin (with
which we made the comparison) being that which determined the place of the
chess-board; and the fixed parts of the earth that by which we determined the
place of the ship,—these things may be said to be in the same place in
those respects: though their distance from some other things, which in this
matter we did not consider, being varied, they have undoubtedly changed place
in that respect; and we ourselves shall think so, when we have occasion to
compare them with those other.


9. Place relative to a present purpose.


But this modification of distance we call place, being made by men for their
common use, that by it they might be able to design the particular position of
things, where they had occasion for such designation; men consider and
determine of this place by reference to those adjacent things which best served
to their present purpose, without considering other things which, to another
purpose, would better determine the place of the same thing. Thus in the
chess-board, the use of the designation of the place of each chess-man being
determined only within that chequered piece of wood, it would cross that
purpose to measure it by anything else; but when these very chess-men are put
up in a bag, if any one should ask where the black king is, it would be proper
to determine the place by the part of the room it was in, and not by the
chessboard; there being another use of designing the place it is now in, than
when in play it was on the chessboard, and so must be determined by other
bodies. So if any one should ask, in what place are the verses which report the
story of Nisus and Euryalus, it would be very improper to determine this place,
by saying, they were in such a part of the earth, or in Bodley’s library: but
the right designation of the place would be by the parts of Virgil’s works; and
the proper answer would be, that these verses were about the middle of the
ninth book of his AEneids, and that they have been always constantly in the
same place ever since Virgil was printed: which is true, though the book itself
hath moved a thousand times, the use of the idea of place here being, to know
in what part of the book that story is, that so, upon occasion, we may know
where to find it, and have recourse to it for use.


10. Place of the universe.


That our idea of place is nothing else but such a relative position of anything
as I have before mentioned, I think is plain, and will be easily admitted, when
we consider that we can have no idea of the place of the universe, though we
can of all the parts of it; because beyond that we have not the idea of any
fixed, distinct, particular beings, in reference to which we can imagine it to
have any relation of distance; but all beyond it is one uniform space or
expansion, wherein the mind finds no variety, no marks. For to say that the
world is somewhere, means no more than that it does exist; this, though a
phrase borrowed from place, signifying only its existence, not location: and
when one can find out, and frame in his mind, clearly and distinctly the place
of the universe, he will be able to tell us whether it moves or stands still in
the undistinguishable inane of infinite space: though it be true that the word
place has sometimes a more confused sense, and stands for that space which
anybody takes up; and so the universe is in a place. The idea, therefore, of
place we have by the same means that we get the idea of space, (whereof this is
but a particular limited consideration,) viz. by our sight and touch; by either
of which we receive into our minds the ideas of extension or distance.


11. Extension and Body not the same.


There are some that would persuade us, that body and extension are the same
thing, who either change the signification of words, which I would not suspect
them of,—they having so severely condemned the philosophy of others,
because it hath been too much placed in the uncertain meaning, or deceitful
obscurity of doubtful or insignificant terms. If, therefore, they mean by body
and extension the same that other people do, viz. by BODY something that is
solid and extended, whose parts are separable and movable different ways; and
by EXTENSION, only the space that lies between the extremities of those solid
coherent parts, and which is possessed by them,—they confound very
different ideas one with another; for I appeal to every man’s own thoughts,
whether the idea of space be not as distinct from that of solidity, as it is
from the idea of scarlet colour? It is true, solidity cannot exist without
extension, neither can scarlet colour exist without extension, but this hinders
not, but that they are distinct ideas. Many ideas require others, as necessary
to their existence or conception, which yet are very distinct ideas. Motion can
neither be, nor be conceived, without space; and yet motion is not space, nor
space motion; space can exist without it, and they are very distinct ideas; and
so, I think, are those of space and solidity. Solidity is so inseparable an
idea from body, that upon that depends its filling of space, its contact,
impulse, and communication of motion upon impulse. And if it be a reason to
prove that spirit is different from body, because thinking includes not the
idea of extension in it; the same reason will be as valid, I suppose, to prove
that space is not body, because it includes not the idea of solidity in it;
SPACE and SOLIDITY being as distinct ideas as THINKING and EXTENSION, and as
wholly separable in the mind one from another. Body then and extension, it is
evident, are two distinct ideas. For,


12. Extension not solidity.


First, Extension includes no solidity, nor resistance to the motion of body, as
body does.


13. The parts of space inseparable, both really and mentally.


Secondly, The parts of pure space are inseparable one from the other; so that
the continuity cannot be separated, both neither really nor mentally. For I
demand of any one to remove any part of it from another, with which it is
continued, even so much as in thought. To divide and separate actually is, as I
think, by removing the parts one from another, to make two superficies, where
before there was a continuity: and to divide mentally is, to make in the mind
two superficies, where before there was a continuity, and consider them as
removed one from the other; which can only be done in things considered by the
mind as capable of being separated; and by separation, of acquiring new
distinct superficies, which they then have not, but are capable of. But neither
of these ways of separation, whether real or mental, is, as I think, compatible
to pure space.


It is true, a man may consider so much of such a space as is answerable or
commensurate to a foot, without considering the rest, which is, indeed, a
partial consideration, but not so much as mental separation or division; since
a man can no more mentally divide, without considering two superficies separate
one from the other, than he can actually divide, without making two superficies
disjoined one from the other: but a partial consideration is not separating. A
man may consider light in the sun without its heat, or mobility in body without
its extension, without thinking of their separation. One is only a partial
consideration, terminating in one alone; and the other is a consideration of
both, as existing separately.


14. The parts of space immovable.


Thirdly, The parts of pure space are immovable, which follows from their
inseparability; motion being nothing but change of distance between any two
things; but this cannot be between parts that are inseparable, which,
therefore, must needs be at perpetual rest one amongst another.


Thus the determined idea of simple space distinguishes it plainly and
sufficiently from body; since its parts are inseparable, immovable, and without
resistance to the motion of body.


15. The Definition of Extension explains it not.


If any one ask me WHAT this space I speak of IS, I will tell him when he tells
me what his extension is. For to say, as is usually done, that extension is to
have partes extra partes, is to say only, that extension is extension. For what
am I the better informed in the nature of extension, when I am told that
extension is to have parts that are extended, exterior to parts that are
extended, i. e. extension consists of extended parts? As if one, asking what a
fibre was, I should answer him,—that it was a thing made up of several
fibres. Would he thereby be enabled to understand what a fibre was better than
he did before? Or rather, would he not have reason to think that my design was
to make sport with him, rather than seriously to instruct him?


16. Division of Beings into Bodies and Spirits proves not Space and Body the
same.


Those who contend that space and body are the same, bring this
dilemma:—either this space is something or nothing; if nothing be between
two bodies, they must necessarily touch; if it be allowed to be something, they
ask, Whether it be body or spirit? To which I answer by another question, Who
told them that there was, or could be, nothing; but SOLID BEINGS, WHICH COULD
NOT THINK, and THINKING BEINGS THAT WERE NOT EXTENDED?—which is all they
mean by the terms BODY and SPIRIT.


17. Substance, which we know not, no Proof against Space without Body.


If it be demanded (as usually it is) whether this space, void of body, be
SUBSTANCE or ACCIDENT, I shall readily answer I know not; nor shall be ashamed
to own my ignorance, till they that ask show me a clear distinct idea of
substance.


18. Different meanings of substance.


I endeavour as much as I can to deliver myself from those fallacies which we
are apt to put upon ourselves, by taking words for things. It helps not our
ignorance to feign a knowledge where we have none, by making a noise with
sounds, without clear and distinct significations. Names made at pleasure,
neither alter the nature of things, nor make us understand them, but as they
are signs of and stand for determined ideas. And I desire those who lay so much
stress on the sound of these two syllables, SUBSTANCE, to consider whether
applying it, as they do, to the infinite, incomprehensible God, to finite
spirits, and to body, it be in the same sense; and whether it stands for the
same idea, when each of those three so different beings are called substances.
If so, whether it will thence follow—that God, spirits, and body,
agreeing in the same common nature of substance, differ not any otherwise than
in a bare different MODIFICATION of that substance; as a tree and a pebble,
being in the same sense body, and agreeing in the common nature of body, differ
only in a bare modification of that common matter, which will be a very harsh
doctrine. If they say, that they apply it to God, finite spirit, and matter, in
three different significations and that it stands for one idea when God is said
to be a substance; for another when the soul is called substance; and for a
third when body is called so;—if the name substance stands for three
several distinct ideas, they would do well to make known those distinct ideas,
or at least to give three distinct names to them, to prevent in so important a
notion the confusion and errors that will naturally follow from the promiscuous
use of so doubtful a term; which is so far from being suspected to have three
distinct, that in ordinary use it has scarce one clear distinct signification.
And if they can thus make three distinct ideas of substance, what hinders why
another may not make a fourth?


19. Substance and accidents of little use in Philosophy.


They who first ran into the notion of ACCIDENTS, as a sort of real beings that
needed something to inhere in, were forced to find out the word SUBSTANCE to
support them. Had the poor Indian philosopher (who imagined that the earth also
wanted something to bear it up) but thought of this word substance, he needed
not to have been at the trouble to find an elephant to support it, and a
tortoise to support his elephant: the word substance would have done it
effectually. And he that inquired might have taken it for as good an answer
from an Indian philosopher,—that substance, without knowing what it is,
is that which supports the earth, as take it for a sufficient answer and good
doctrine from our European philosophers,—that substance, without knowing
what it is, is that which supports accidents. So that of substance, we have no
idea of what it is, but only a confused obscure one of what it does.


20. Sticking on and under-propping.


Whatever a learned man may do here, an intelligent American, who inquired into
the nature of things, would scarce take it for a satisfactory account, if,
desiring to learn our architecture, he should be told that a pillar is a thing
supported by a basis, and a basis something that supported a pillar. Would he
not think himself mocked, instead of taught, with such an account as this? And
a stranger to them would be very liberally instructed in the nature of books,
and the things they contained, if he should be told that all learned books
consisted of paper and letters, and that letters were things inhering in paper,
and paper a thing that held forth letters: a notable way of having clear ideas
of letters and paper. But were the Latin words, inhaerentia and substantio, put
into the plain English ones that answer them, and were called STICKING ON and
UNDER-PROPPING, they would better discover to us the very great clearness there
is in the doctrine of substance and accidents, and show of what use they are in
deciding of questions in philosophy.


21. A Vacuum beyond the utmost Bounds of Body.


But to return to our idea of space. If body be not supposed infinite, (which I
think no one will affirm,) I would ask, whether, if God placed a man at the
extremity of corporeal beings, he could not stretch his hand beyond his body?
If he could, then he would put his arm where there was before space without
body; and if there he spread his fingers, there would still be space between
them without body. If he could not stretch out his hand, it must be because of
some external hindrance; (for we suppose him alive, with such a power of moving
the parts of his body that he hath now, which is not in itself impossible, if
God so pleased to have it; or at least it is not impossible for God so to move
him:) and then I ask,—whether that which hinders his hand from moving
outwards be substance or accident, something or nothing? And when they have
resolved that, they will be able to resolve themselves,—what that is,
which is or may be between two bodies at a distance, that is not body, and has
no solidity. In the mean time, the argument is at least as good, that, where
nothing hinders, (as beyond the utmost bounds of all bodies,) a body put in
motion may move on, as where there is nothing between, there two bodies must
necessarily touch. For pure space between is sufficient to take away the
necessity of mutual contact; but bare space in the way is not sufficient to
stop motion. The truth is, these men must either own that they think body
infinite, though they are loth to speak it out, or else affirm that space is
not body. For I would fain meet with that thinking man that can in his thoughts
set any bounds to space, more than he can to duration; or by thinking hope to
arrive at the end of either. And therefore, if his idea of eternity be
infinite, so is his idea of immensity; they are both finite or infinite alike.


22. The Power of Annihilation proves a Vacuum.


Farther, those who assert the impossibility of space existing without matter,
must not only make body infinite, but must also deny a power in God to
annihilate any part of matter. No one, I suppose, will deny that God can put an
end to all motion that is in matter, and fix all the bodies of the universe in
a perfect quiet and rest, and continue them so long as he pleases. Whoever then
will allow that God can, during such a general rest, ANNIHILATE either this
book or the body of him that reads it, must necessarily admit the possibility
of a vacuum. For, it is evident that the space that was filled by the parts of
the annihilated body will still remain, and be a space without body. For the
circumambient bodies being in perfect rest, are a wall of adamant, and in that
state make it a perfect impossibility for any other body to get into that
space. And indeed the necessary motion of one particle of matter into the place
from whence another particle of matter is removed, is but a consequence from
the supposition of plenitude; which will therefore need some better proof than
a supposed matter of fact, which experiment can never make out;—our own
clear and distinct ideas plainly satisfying that there is no necessary
connexion between space and solidity, since we can conceive the one without the
other. And those who dispute for or against a vacuum, do thereby confess they
have distinct IDEAS of vacuum and plenum, i. e. that they have an idea of
extension void of solidity, though they deny its EXISTENCE; or else they
dispute about nothing at all. For they who so much alter the signification of
words, as to call extension body, and consequently make the whole essence of
body to be nothing but pure extension without solidity, must talk absurdly
whenever they speak of vacuum; since it is impossible for extension to be
without extension. For vacuum, whether we affirm or deny its existence,
signifies space without body; whose very existence no one can deny to be
possible, who will not make matter infinite, and take from God a power to
annihilate any particle of it.


23. Motion proves a Vacuum.


But not to go so far as beyond the utmost bounds of body in the universe, nor
appeal to God’s omnipotency to find a vacuum, the motion of bodies that are in
our view and neighbourhood seems to me plainly to evince it. For I desire any
one so to divide a solid body, of any dimension he pleases, as to make it
possible for the solid parts to move up and down freely every way within the
bounds of that superficies, if there be not left in it a void space as big as
the least part into which he has divided the said solid body. And if, where the
least particle of the body divided is as big as a mustard-seed, a void space
equal to the bulk of a mustard-seed be requisite to make room for the free
motion of the parts of the divided body within the bounds of its superficies,
where the particles of matter are 100,000,000 less than a mustard-seed, there
must also be a space void of solid matter as big as 100,000,000 part of a
mustard-seed; for if it hold in the one it will hold in the other, and so on IN
INFINITUM. And let this void space be as little as it will, it destroys the
hypothesis of plenitude. For if there can be a space void of body equal to the
smallest separate particle of matter now existing in nature, it is still space
without body; and makes as great a difference between space and body as if it
were mega chasma, a distance as wide as any in nature. And therefore, if we
suppose not the void space necessary to motion equal to the least parcel of the
divided solid matter, but to 1/10 or 1/1000 of it, the same consequence will
always follow of space without matter.


24. The Ideas of Space and Body distinct.


But the question being here,—Whether the idea of space or extension be
the same with the idea of body? it is not necessary to prove the real existence
of a VACUUM, but the idea of it; which it is plain men have when they inquire
and dispute whether there be a VACUUM or no. For if they had not the idea of
space without body, they could not make a question about its existence: and if
their idea of body did not include in it something more than the bare idea of
space, they could have no doubt about the plenitude of the world; and it would
be as absurd to demand, whether there were space without body, as whether there
were space without space, or body without body, since these were but different
names of the same idea.


25. Extension being inseparable from Body, proves it not the same.


It is true, the idea of extension joins itself so inseparably with all visible,
and most tangible qualities, that it suffers us to SEE no one, or FEEL very few
external objects, without taking in impressions of extension too. This
readiness of extension to make itself be taken notice of so constantly with
other ideas, has been the occasion, I guess, that some have made the whole
essence of body to consist in extension; which is not much to be wondered at,
since some have had their minds, by their eyes and touch, (the busiest of all
our senses,) so filled with the idea of extension, and, as it were, wholly
possessed with it, that they allowed no existence to anything that had not
extension. I shall not now argue with those men, who take the measure and
possibility of all being only from their narrow and gross imaginations: but
having here to do only with those who conclude the essence of body to be
extension, because they say they cannot imagine any sensible quality of any
body without extension,—I shall desire them to consider, that, had they
reflected on their ideas of tastes and smells as much as on those of sight and
touch; nay, had they examined their ideas of hunger and thirst, and several
other pains, they would have found that THEY included in them no idea of
extension at all, which is but an affection of body, as well as the rest,
discoverable by our senses, which are scarce acute enough to look into the pure
essences of things.


26. Essences of Things.


If those ideas which are constantly joined to all others, must therefore be
concluded to be the essence of those things which have constantly those ideas
joined to them, and are inseparable from them; then unity is without doubt the
essence of everything. For there is not any object of sensation or reflection
which does not carry with it the idea of one: but the weakness of this kind of
argument we have already shown sufficiently.


27. Ideas of Space and Solidity distinct.


To conclude: whatever men shall think concerning the existence of a VACUUM,
this is plain to me—that we have as clear an idea of space distinct from
solidity, as we have of solidity distinct from motion, or motion from space. We
have not any two more distinct ideas; and we can as easily conceive space
without solidity, as we can conceive body or space without motion, though it be
never so certain that neither body nor motion can exist without space. But
whether any one will take space to be only a RELATION resulting from the
existence of other beings at a distance; or whether they will think the words
of the most knowing King Solomon, ‘The heaven, and the heaven of heavens,
cannot contain thee;’ or those more emphatical ones of the inspired philosopher
St. Paul, ‘In him we live, move, and have our being,’ are to be understood in a
literal sense, I leave every one to consider: only our idea of space is, I
think, such as I have mentioned, and distinct from that of body. For, whether
we consider, in matter itself, the distance of its coherent solid parts, and
call it, in respect of those solid parts, extension; or whether, considering it
as lying between the extremities of any body in its several dimensions, we call
it length, breadth, and thickness; or else, considering it as lying between any
two bodies or positive beings, without any consideration whether there be any
matter or not between, we call it distance;—however named or considered,
it is always the same uniform simple idea of space, taken from objects about
which our senses have been conversant; whereof, having settled ideas in our
minds, we can revive, repeat, and add them one to another as often as we will,
and consider the space or distance so imagined, either as filled with solid
parts, so that another body cannot come there without displacing and thrusting
out the body that was there before; or else as void of solidity, so that a body
of equal dimensions to that empty or pure space may be placed in it, without
the removing or expulsion of anything that was there.


28. Men differ little in clear, simple ideas.


The knowing precisely what our words stand for, would, I imagine, in this as
well as a great many other cases, quickly end the dispute. For I am apt to
think that men, when they come to examine them, find their simple ideas all
generally to agree, though in discourse with one another they perhaps confound
one another with different names. I imagine that men who abstract their
thoughts, and do well examine the ideas of their own minds, cannot much differ
in thinking; however they may perplex themselves with words, according to the
way of speaking of the several schools or sects they have been bred up in:
though amongst unthinking men, who examine not scrupulously and carefully their
own ideas, and strip them not from the marks men use for them, but confound
them with words, there must be endless dispute, wrangling, and jargon;
especially if they be learned, bookish men, devoted to some sect, and
accustomed to the language of it, and have learned to talk after others. But if
it should happen that any two thinking men should really have different ideas,
I do not see how they could discourse or argue one with another. Here I must
not be mistaken, to think that every floating imagination in men’s brains is
presently of that sort of ideas I speak of. It is not easy for the mind to put
off those confused notions and prejudices it has imbibed from custom,
inadvertency, and common conversation. It requires pains and assiduity to
examine its ideas, till it resolves them into those clear and distinct simple
ones, out of which they are compounded; and to see which, amongst its simple
ones, have or have not a NECESSARY connexion and dependence one upon another.
Till a man doth this in the primary and original notions of things, he builds
upon floating and uncertain principles, and will often find himself at a loss.


</div></body></text></TEI>