<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ninth Bridgewater Treatise</title><author>Babbage, Charles (1791-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="9">ON THE ACCOUNT OF THE CREATION, IN THE FIRST CHAPTER OF GENESIS.
 A strange and singular argument has frequently been brought against the truth
 of the facts presented to us by Geology,—facts which every instructed person
 may confirm by the evidence of his senses. It has been asserted that they cannot
 be true; because, if admitted, they lead inevitably to the conclusion, that
 the earth has existed for an enormous period, extending, perhaps, over millions
 of years; whereas, it was supposed, from the history of the creation as delivered
 by Moses, that the
[page] 64
 earth was first created about six thousand years ago. A different interpretation
 has been lately put upon that passage of the sacred writings; and, according
 to the highest authorities of the present time, it was not the intention of
 the writer of the book of Genesis to assign this date to the creation of our
 globe, but only to that of its most favoured inhabitants. Now, it is obvious
 that additional observations, and another advance in science, may at no distant
 period render necessary another interpretation of the Mosaic narrative; and
 this again, at a more remote time, may be superseded by one more in accordance
 with the existing knowledge of that day. And thus, the authority of Scripture
 will be gradually undermined by the weak though well-intentioned efforts of
 its friends in its support. For it is clear that when a work, translated by
 persons most highly instructed in its language, and seeking,
[page] 65
 in plainness and sincerity, to understand its true meaning, admits of such
 discordant interpretations, it can have little authority as a history of the
 past, or a guide to the future. It is time, therefore, to examine this question
 by another light, and to point out to those who support what is called the literal
 interpretation of Scripture, the precipice to which their doctrines, if true,
 would inevitably lead; and to show, not by the glimmerings of elaborate criticism,
 but by the plainest principles of common sense, that there exists no such fatal
 collision between the words of Scripture and the facts of nature. And first,
 let us examine what must of necessity be the conclusion of any candid mind from
 the mass of evidence presented to it. Looking solely at the facts in which all
 capable of investigation agree—facts which it is needless to recite, they having
 been so fully and ably stated in the works of Mr. Lyell and
[page] 66
Dr. Buckland,—we there see, and with no theoretic eye, the remains of animated
 beings, more and more differing from existing races, as we descend in the series
 of strata. Not merely are the petrified bones preserved, displaying marks of
 the insertion of every muscle necessary for the movement of the living animal,
 but in some cases we discover even the secretions of their organs, prepared
 either for nourishment or for defence. Almost every stratum we pause to examine,
 affords indubitable evidence of having, at some former period, existed for ages
 at the bottom of some lake or estuary, some inland sea, or some extensive ocean
 teeming with animal existence, or of having been the surface of a country covered
 with vegetation, which perished and was renewed at distant and successive periods.
 Those, however, who, without the knowledge which enables them to form an opinion
 on the subject, feel any latent wish that this evidence should be overthrown,
 would do
[page] 67
 well to remember that geology also furnishes strong evidence in favour of
 the much more direct statement of Moses, as to the recent creation of man. And
 although we must ever feel a certain degree of caution in admitting negative
 evidence as conclusive; yet, in the present instance, the fact that the multitude
 of fossil bones which have been discovered, and which, when examined by persons duly qualified for the task, have been uniformly pronounced to be those
 of various tribes of animals, and not those of the human race, undoubtedly affords
 strong corroborative evidence in confirmation of the Mosaic account. In truth,
 the mass of evidence which combines to prove the great antiquity of the earth
 itself, is so irresistible, and so unshaken by any opposing facts, that none
 but those who are alike incapable of observing the facts, and of appreciating
 the reasoning, can for a moment conceive the present state of its
[page] 68
 surface to have been the result of only six thousand years of existence. What,
 then, have those accomplished who have restricted the Mosaic account of the
 creation to that diminutive period, which is, as it were, but a span in the
 duration of the earth's existence, and who have imprudently rejected the testimony
 of the senses, when opposed to their philological criticisms? Undoubtedly,
 if they have succeeded in convincing either themselves or others, that one side
 of the question must be given up as untenable; those who are so convinced are
 bound to reject that which rests on testimony, not that which is supported by
 still existing facts. The very argument which Protestants have opposed to the
 doctrine of transubstantiation,* would, if
* The historian of the "Decline of the Roman Empire," carried the argument
 yet further;—
" I still remember (he remarks) my solitary transport at "the discovery of
 a philosophical argument against transubstantiation; that the text of Scripture
 which seems to
[page] 69
their view of the case were correct, be equally irresistible against
 the book of Genesis.
 But let us consider what would be the conclusion of every reasonable being
 in a parallel case. Let us imagine a manuscript written three thousand years
 ago, and professing to be a revelation from the Deity, in which it was stated
 that the colour of the paper of the very book now in the reader's hands is black, and that the colour of the ink in the characters which he is now reading
 is white: —with that reasonable doubt of his own individual faculties
 which would become the inquirer into the truth of a statement said to be derived
 from so high an origin, he would ask of all those around him, whether to their
 senses the paper appeared to be black and the ink to be white. If
 he found the senses of other individuals agree with his own, then he would undoubt-
 "indicate the real presence is attested only by a single" sense—our sight; while the real presence itself is disproved "by three of our senses — the
 sight, the touch, the taste." Gibbon's Memoirs of his Life, vol. i. p.
 58.
[page] 70
 edly pronounce the alleged revelation a forgery, and those who propounded
 it to be either deceived or deceivers. He would rightly impute the attempted
 deceit to moral turpitude, to gross ignorance, or to interested motives in the
 supporters of it; but he certainly would not commit the impiety of supposing
 the Deity to have wrought a miraculous change upon the senses of our whole species,
 and then to demand their belief in a fact directly opposed to those senses;—thus
 throwing doubt upon every conclusion of reason in regard to external objects,
 and amongst others, upon the very evidence by which the authenticity of that
 questionable manuscript was itself supported, and even upon the fact of its
 existence when before their eyes. Thus, then, had those who attempt to show
 that the account of the creation, in the book of Genesis, is contradicted by
 the discoveries of modern science, succeeded, they would have destroyed the
 testimony of Moses—they would
[page] 71
 have uncanonised one portion of Scripture, and by implication have thrown
 doubt on the remainder. But minds which thus failed to trace out the necessary
 consequences of their own argument, were not likely to have laid very secure
 foundations for the basis on which it rested; and I shall presently prove that
 the contradiction they have imagined can have no real existence; and that whilst
 the testimony of Moses remains unimpeached, we may also be permitted to confide
 in the testimony of our senses.
[page] 72</div></body></text></TEI>