<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="42">

BOOK XIV.

CHEMISTRY.

CHAPTER IX.
The Electro-chemical Theory.
AMONG the consequences of the
Electro-chemical Theory, must be ranged the various improvements which
have been made in the voltaic battery. Daniel introduced between the
two metals a partition permeable by chemical action, but such as to
allow of two different acid solutions being in contact with the two
metals. Mr. Grove’s battery, in which the partition is of porous
porcelain, and the metals are platinum and amalgamated zinc, is one of
the most powerful hitherto known. Another has been constructed by Dr.
Callan, in which the negative or conducting plate is a cylinder of
cast iron, and the positive element a cylinder of amalgamated zinc
placed in a porous cell. This also has great energy.
The Number of Elementary Substances.
There have not been, I believe, any well-established additions to
the list of the simple substances recognized by chemists. Indeed the
tendency at present appears to be rather to deny the separate
elementary character of some already announced as such substances.
Pelopium and Niobium were, as I have said, two of the new metals. But
Naumann, in his Elemente der Mineralogie (4th ed. 1855), says,
in a foot note (page 25): “Pelopium is happily again got rid
of; for Pelopic Acid and Niobic Acid possess the same Radical.
Donarium had a still shorter existence.”
In the same way, when Hermann imagined that he had discovered a new
simple metallic substance in the mineral Samarskite from Miask, the
discovery was disproved by H. Rose (Pogg. Ann. B. 73, s. 449).
626
In general the insulation of the new simple substances, the
metallic bases of the earths, and the like,—their separation
from their combinations, and the exhibition of them in a metallic
form—has been a difficult chemical process, and has rarely been
executed on any considerable scale. But in the case of
Aluminium, the basis of the earth Alumina, the process of its
extraction has recently been so much facilitated, that the metal can
be produced in abundance. This being the case, it will probably soon
be applied to special economical uses, for which it is fitted by
possessing special properties.
</div></body></text></TEI>