<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="4">

CHAPTER IV.
Of Experience.



1. I
HERE employ the term Experience in a more definite and
limited sense than that which it possesses in common usage;
for I restrict it to matters belonging to the domain of
science. In such cases, the knowledge which we acquire, by
means of experience, is of a clear and precise nature; and
the passions and feelings and interests, which make the
lessons of experience in practical matters so difficult to
read aright, no longer disturb and confuse us. We may,
therefore, hope, by attending to such cases, to learn what
efficacy experience really has, in the discovery of truth.
That from experience (including intentional
experience, or observation,) we obtain much knowledge
which is highly important, and which could not be procured
from any other source, is abundantly clear. We have already
taken several examples of such knowledge. We know by
experience that animals which ruminate are cloven-hoofed;
and we know this in no other manner. We know, in like
manner, that all the planets and their satellites revolve
round the sun from west to east. It has been found by
experience that all meteoric stones contain chrome. Many
similar portions of our knowledge might be mentioned.
Now what we have here to remark is this;—that in no case
can experience prove a proposition to be
necessarily or universally true. However
many instances we may have observed of the truth of a
proposition, yet if it be known merely by observation, there
is nothing to assure us that the next case shall not be an
exception to the rule. If it be strictly true that every
ruminant animal yet known has cloven hoofs, we 66 still
cannot be sure that some creature will not hereafter be
discovered which has the first of these attributes without
having the other. When the planets and their satellites, as
far as Saturn, had been all found to move round the sun in
one direction, it was still possible that there might be
other such bodies not obeying this rule; and, accordingly,
when the satellites of Uranus were detected, they appeared
to offer an exception of this kind. Even in the mathematical
sciences, we have examples of such rules suggested by
experience, and also of their precariousness. However far
they may have been tested, we cannot depend upon their
correctness, except we see some reason for the rule. For
instance, various rules have been given, for the purpose of
pointing out prime numbers; that is, those which
cannot be divided by any other number. We may try, as an
example of such a rule, this one—any odd power of the
number two, diminished by one. Thus the third power of two,
diminished by one, is seven; the fifth power, diminished by
one, is thirty-one; the seventh power so diminished is one
hundred and twenty-seven. All these are prime numbers: and
we might be led to suppose that the rule is universal. But
the next example shows us the fallaciousness of such a
belief. The ninth power of two, diminished by one, is five
hundred and eleven, which is not a prime, being divisible by
seven.
Experience must always consist of a limited number of
observations. And, however numerous these may be, they can
show nothing with regard to the infinite number of cases in
which the experiment has not been made. Experience being
thus unable to prove a fact to be universal, is, as will
readily be seen, still more incapable of proving a truth to
be necessary. Experience cannot, indeed, offer the smallest
ground for the necessity of a proposition. She can observe
and record what has happened; but she cannot find, in any
case, or in any accumulation of cases, any reason for what
must happen. She may see objects side by side; but she
cannot see a reason why they must ever be side by side. She
finds certain events to occur in succession; but the
succession supplies, in its occurrence, no 67 reason for
its recurrence. She contemplates external objects; but she
cannot detect any internal bond, which indissolubly connects
the future with the past, the possible with the real. To
learn a proposition by experience, and to see it to be
necessarily true, are two altogether different processes of
thought.
2. But it may be said, that we do learn by means of
observation and experience many universal truths; indeed,
all the general truths of which science consists. Is not the
doctrine of universal gravitation learnt by experience? Are
not the laws of motion, the properties of light, the general
principles of chemistry, so learnt? How, with these examples
before us, can we say that experience teaches no universal
truths?
To this we reply, that these truths can only be known to be
general, not universal, if they depend upon experience
alone. Experience cannot bestow that universality which she
herself cannot have, and that necessity of which she has no
comprehension. If these doctrines are universally true, this
universality flows from the ideas which we apply to
our experience, and which are, as we have seen, the real
sources of necessary truth. How far these ideas can
communicate their universality and necessity to the results
of experience, it will hereafter be our business to
consider. It will then appear, that when the mind collects
from observation truths of a wide and comprehensive kind,
which approach to the simplicity and universality of the
truths of pure science; she gives them this character by
throwing upon them the light of her own Fundamental Ideas.
But the truths which we discover by observation of the
external world, even when most strikingly simple and
universal, are not necessary truths. Is the doctrine of
universal gravitation necessarily true? It was doubted by
Clairaut (so far as it refers to the moon), when the
progression of the apogee in fact appeared to be twice as
great as the theory admitted. It has been doubted, even more
recently, with respect to the planets, their mutual
perturbations appearing to indicate a deviation from the
law. It is doubted still, by some 68 persons, with respect
to the double stars. But suppose all these doubts to be
banished, and the law to be universal; is it then proved to
be necessary? Manifestly not: the very existence of these
doubts proves that it is not so. For the doubts were
dissipated by reference to observation and calculation, not
by reasoning on the nature of the law. Clairaut’s difficulty
was removed by a more exact calculation of the effect of the
sun’s force on the motion of the apogee. The suggestion of
Bessel, that the intensity of gravitation might be different
for different planets, was found to be unnecessary, when
Professor Airy gave a more accurate determination of the
mass of Jupiter. And the question whether the extension of
the law of the inverse square to the double stars be true,
(one of the most remarkable questions now before the
scientific world,) must be answered, not by any speculations
concerning what the laws of attraction must necessarily be,
but by carefully determining the actual laws of the motion
of these curious objects, by means of the observations such
as those which Sir John Herschel has collected for that
purpose, by his unexampled survey of both hemispheres of the
sky. And since the extent of this truth is thus to be
determined by reference to observed facts, it is clear that
no mere accumulation of them can make its universality
certain, or its necessity apparent.
Thus no knowledge of the necessity of any truths can result
from the observation of what really happens. This being
clearly understood, we are led to an important inquiry.
The characters of universality and necessity in the truths
which form part of our knowledge, can never be derived from
experience, by which so large a part of our knowledge is
obtained. But since, as we have seen, we really do possess a
large body of truths which are necessary, and because
necessary, therefore universal, the question still recurs,
from what source these characters of universality and
necessity are derived.
The answer to this question we will attempt to give in the
next chapter.</div></body></text></TEI>