<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="5">INTRODUCTION.
IN order to the acquisition of
any such exact and real knowledge of nature as that which we properly
call Physical Science, it is requisite, as has already been said, that
men should possess Ideas both distinct and appropriate, and should
apply them to ascertained Facts. They are thus led to propositions of
a general character, which are obtained by Induction, as will
elsewhere be more fully explained. We proceed now to trace the
formation of Sciences among the Greeks by such processes. The
provinces of knowledge which thus demand our attention are, Astronomy,
Mechanics and Hydrostatics, Optics and Harmonics; of which I must
relate, first, the earliest stages, and next, the subsequent
progress.
Of these portions of human knowledge, Astronomy is, beyond doubt or
comparison, much the most ancient and the most remarkable; and
probably existed, in somewhat of a scientific form, in Chaldea and
Egypt, and other countries, before the period of the intellectual
activity of the Greeks. But I will give a brief account of some of the
other Sciences before I proceed to Astronomy, for two reasons; first,
because the origin of Astronomy is lost in the obscurity of a remote
antiquity; and therefore we cannot exemplify the conditions of the
first rise of science so well in that subject as we can in others
which assumed their scientific form at known periods; and next, in
order that I may not have to interrupt, after I have once begun it,
the history of the only progressive Science which the ancient world
produced.
It has been objected to the arrangement here employed that it is
not symmetrical; and that Astronomy, as being one of the Physical
Sciences, ought to have occupied a chapter in this Second Book,
instead of having a whole Book to itself (Book
iii). I do not pretend that the
arrangement is symmetrical, and have employed it only on the ground of
convenience. The importance and extent of the history of Astronomy are
such that this science could not, with a view to our purposes, be made
co-ordinate with Mechanics or Optics. 96</div></body></text></TEI>