<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol I</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1794</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="6">SECT. VI.
OF THE FOUR CLASSES OF FIBROUS MOTIONS.

I. Origin of fibrous contractions. II. Distribution of them into four classes,
  irritative motions, sensitive motions, voluntary motions, and associate
  motions, defined.

I. All the fibrous contractions of animal
  bodies originate from the sensorium, and resolve themselves into four
  classes, correspondent with the four powers or motions of the sensorium
  above described, and from which they have their causation.
1. These fibrous contractions were
  originally caused by the irritations excited by objects, which are
  external to the moving organ. As the pulsations of the heart are owing to
  the irritations excited by the stimulus of the blood; and the ideas of
  perception are owing to the irritations excited by external bodies.
2. But as painful or pleasurable sensations
  frequently accompanied those irritations, by habit these fibrous
  contractions became causeable by the sensations, and the irritations
  ceased to be necessary to their production. As the secretion of tears in
  grief is caused by the sensation of pain; and the ideas of imagination,
  as in dreams or delirium, are excited by the pleasure or pain, with which
  they were formerly accompanied.
3. But as the efforts of the will frequently
  accompanied these painful or pleasureable sensations, by habit the
  fibrous contractions became causable by volition; and both the
  irritations and sensations ceased to be necessary to their production. As
  the deliberate locomotions of the body, and the ideas of recollection, as
  when we will to repeat the alphabet backwards.
4. But as many of these fibrous contractions
  frequently accompanied other fibrous contractions, by habit they became
  causable by their associations with them; and the irritations,
  sensations, and volition, ceased to be necessary to their production. As
  the actions of the muscles of the lower limbs in fencing are associated
  with those of the arms; and the ideas of suggestion are associated with
  other ideas, which precede or accompany them; as in repeating carelessly
  the alphabet in its usual order after having began it.
II. We shall give the following names to these
  four classes of fibrous motions, and subjoin their definitions.
1. Irritative motions. That exertion or
  change of the sensorium, which is caused by the appulses of external
  bodies, either simply subsides, or is succeeded by sensation, or it
  produces fibrous motions; it is termed irritation, and irritative motions
  are those contractions of the muscular fibres, or of the organs of sense,
  that are immediately consequent to this exertion or change of the
  sensorium.
2. Sensitive motions. That exertion or
  change of the sensorium, which constitutes pleasure or pain, either
  simply subsides, or is succeeded by volition, or it produces fibrous
  motions; it is termed sensation, and the sensitive motions are those
  contractions of the muscular fibres, or of the organs of sense, that are
  immediately consequent to this exertion or change of the sensorium.
3. Voluntary motions. That exertion or
  change of the sensorium, which constitutes desire or aversion, either
  simply subsides, or is succeeded by fibrous motions; it is then termed
  volition, and voluntary motions are those contractions of the muscular
  fibres, or of the organs of sense, that are immediately consequent to
  this exertion or change of the sensorium.
4. Associate motions. That exertion or
  change of the sensorium, which accompanies fibrous motions, either simply
  subsides, or is succeeded by sensation or volition, or it produces other
  fibrous motions; it is then termed association, and the associate motions
  are those contractions of the muscular fibres, or of the organs of sense,
  that are immediately consequent to this exertion or change of the
  sensorium.

</div></body></text></TEI>