<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="47">CHAPTER XLVII.
IMBEDDING OF ORGANIC REMAINS IN SUBAQUEOUS DEPOSITS.
Division of the subject—Imbedding of terrestrial animals and plants—Increased
specific gravity of wood sunk to great depths in the sea—Drift-timber of the
Mackenzie in Slave Lake and Polar Sea—Floating trees in the Mississippi—in
the Gulf Stream—on the coast of Iceland, Spitzbergen, and Labrador—Submarine
forests—Example on coast of Hampshire—Mineralization of plants—Imbedding
of marine plants—of insects—of reptiles—Bones of birds why rare—Imbedding
of terrestrial quadrupeds by river floods—Skeletons in recent
shell marl—Imbedding of mammiferous remains in marine strata.
Division of the subject.—Having treated of the imbedding of organic
remains in deposits formed upon the land, I shall next consider the
including of the same in deposits formed under water.
It will be convenient to divide this branch of our subject into three
parts; considering, first, the various modes whereby the relics of terrestrial
species may be buried in subaqueous formations; secondly, the
modes whereby animals and plants inhabiting fresh water may be so
entombed; thirdly, how marine species may become preserved in new
strata.
The phenomena above enumerated demand a fuller share of attention
than those previously examined, since the deposits which originate upon
dry land are insignificant in thickness, superficial extent, and durability,
when contrasted with those of subaqueous origin. At the same time,
the study of the latter is beset with greater difficulties; for we are here
concerned with the results of processes much farther removed from the
sphere of ordinary observation. There is, indeed, no circumstance
which so seriously impedes the acquisition of just views in our science
as an habitual disregard of the important fact, that the reproductive
effects of the principal agents of change are confined to another
element—to that larger portion of the globe, from which by our very
organization we are almost entirely excluded.1059
Imbedding of Terrestrial Plants.
When a tree falls into a river from the undermining of the banks or
from being washed in by a torrent or flood, it floats on the surface, not
because the woody portion is specifically lighter than water, but because
it is full of pores containing air. When soaked for a considerable time,
the water makes its way into these pores, and the wood becomes waterlogged
and sinks. The time required for this process varies in different
woods; but several kinds may be drifted to great distances, sometimes
across the ocean, before they lose their buoyancy.
743
Wood sunk to a great depth in the sea.—If wood be sunk to vast
depths in the sea, it may be impregnated with water suddenly. Captain
Scoresby informs us, in his Account of the Arctic Regions, that on one
occasion a whale, on being harpooned, ran out all the lines in the boat,
which it then dragged under water, to the depth of several thousand feet,
the men having just time to escape to a piece of ice. When the fish
returned to the surface "to blow," it was struck a second time, and soon
afterwards killed. The moment it expired it began to sink,—an unusual
circumstance, which was found to be caused by the weight of the sunken
boat, which still remained attached to it. By means of harpoons and ropes
the fish was prevented from sinking, until it was released from the weight
by connecting a rope to the lines of the attached boat, which was no
sooner done than the fish rose again to the surface. The sunken boat
was then hauled up with great labor; for so heavy was it, that although
before the accident it would have been buoyant when full of water, yet
it now required a boat at each end to keep it from sinking. "When it
was hoisted into the ship, the paint came off the wood in large sheets;
and the planks, which were of wainscot, were as completely soaked in
every pore as if they had lain at the bottom of the sea since the flood!
A wooden apparatus that accompanied the boat in its progress through
the deep, consisting chiefly of a piece of thick deal, about fifteen inches
square, happened to fall overboard, and, though it originally consisted of
the lightest fir, sank in the water like a stone. The boat was rendered
useless; even the wood of which it was built, on being offered to the
cook for fuel, was tried and rejected as incombustible."1060
Captain Scoresby found that, by sinking pieces of fir, elm, ash, &c., to
the depth of four thousand and sometimes six thousand feet, they became
impregnated with sea-water, and when drawn up again, after immersion
for an hour, would no longer float. The effect of this impregnation was
to increase the dimensions as well as the specific gravity of the wood,
every solid inch having increased one-twentieth in size and twenty-one
twenty-fifths in weight.1061
Drift-wood of the Mackenzie River.—When timber is drifted down
by a river, it is often arrested by lakes; and, becoming water-logged, it
may sink and be imbedded in lacustrine strata, if any be there forming;
sometimes a portion floats on till it reaches the sea. In the course of
the Mackenzie River we have an example of vast accumulations of vegetable
matter now in progress under both these circumstances.
In Slave Lake in particular, which vies in dimensions with some of the
great fresh-water seas of Canada, the quantity of drift-timber brought
down annually is enormous. "As the trees," says Dr. Richardson,
"retain their roots, which are often loaded with earth and stones, they
readily sink, especially when water-soaked; and, accumulating in the
eddies, form shoals, which ultimately augment into islands. A thicket
of small willows covers the new-formed island as soon as it appears
744
above water, and their fibrous roots serve to bind the whole firmly
together. Sections of these islands are annually made by the river,
assisted by the frost; and it is interesting to study the diversity of appearances
they present, according to their different ages. The trunks of the
trees gradually decay until they are converted into a blackish brown
substance resembling peat, but which still retains more or less of the
fibrous structure of the wood; and layers of this often alternate with layers
of clay and sand, the whole being penetrated, to the depth of four or
five yards or more, by the long fibrous roots of the willows. A deposition
of this kind, with the aid of a little infiltration of bituminous matter,
would produce an excellent imitation of coal, with vegetable impressions
of the willow-roots. What appeared most remarkable was the horizontal
slaty structure that the old alluvial banks presented, or the regular curve
that the strata assumed from unequal subsidence.
"It was in the rivers only that we could observe sections of these
deposits; but the same operation goes on, on a much more magnificent
scale, in the lakes. A shoal of many miles in extent is formed on the
south side of Athabasca Lake, by the drift-timber and vegetable debris
brought down by the Elk River; and the Slave Lake itself must in
process of time be filled up by matters daily conveyed into it from Slave
River. Vast quantities of drift-timber are buried under the sand at the
mouth of the river, and enormous piles of it are accumulated on the
shores of every part of the lake."1062
The banks of the Mackenzie display almost everywhere horizontal
beds of wood coal, alternating with bituminous clay, gravel, sand, and
friable sandstone; sections, in short, of such deposits as are now evidently
forming at the bottom of the lakes which it traverses.
Notwithstanding the vast forests intercepted by the lakes, a still
greater mass of drift-wood is found where the Mackenzie reaches the
sea, in a latitude where no wood grows at present except a few stunted
willows. At the mouths of the river the alluvial matter has formed a
barrier of islands and shoals, where we may expect a great formation
of coal at some distant period.
The abundance of floating timber on the Mackenzie is owing, as Dr.
Richardson informs me, to the direction and to the length of the course
of this river, which runs from south to north, so that the sources of the
stream lie in much warmer latitudes than its mouths. In the country,
therefore, where the sources are situated, the frost breaks up at an
earlier season, while yet the waters in the lower part of its course are
ice-bound. Hence the current of water, rushing down northward,
reaches a point where the thaw has not begun, and, finding the channel
of the river blocked up with ice, it overflows the banks, sweeping
through forests of pines, and carrying away thousands of uprooted trees.
Drift-timber on coasts of Iceland, Spitzbergen, &c.—The ancient
forests of Iceland, observes Malte-Brun, have been improvidently exhausted;
745
but, although the Icelander can obtain no timber from the land, he is supplied
with it abundantly by the ocean. An immense quantity of thick
trunks of pines, firs, and other trees, are thrown upon the northern coast
of the island, especially upon the North Cape and Cape Langaness, and
are then carried by the waves along these two promontories to other parts
of the coast, so as to afford sufficiency of wood for fuel and for constructing
boats. Timber is also carried to the shores of Labrador and Greenland;
and Crantz assures us that the masses of floating wood thrown by the
waves upon the island of John de Mayen often equal the whole of that
island in extent.1063
In a similar manner the bays of Spitzbergen are filled with drift-wood,
which accumulates also upon those parts of the coast of Siberia that are
exposed to the east, consisting of larch trees, pines, Siberian cedars, firs,
and Pernambuco and Campeachy woods. These trunks appear to have
been swept away by the great rivers of Asia and America. Some of them
are brought from the Gulf of Mexico by the Bahama stream; while
others are hurried forward by the current which, to the north of Siberia,
constantly sets in from east to west. Some of these trees have been deprived
of their bark by friction, but are in such a state of preservation as
to form excellent building timber.1064 Parts of the branches and almost all
the roots remain fixed to the pines which have been drifted into the North
Sea, into latitudes too cold for the growth of such timber, but the trunks
are usually barked.
The leaves and lighter parts of plants are seldom carried out to sea, in
any part of the globe, except during tropical hurricanes among islands,
and during the agitations of the atmosphere which sometimes accompany
earthquakes and volcanic eruptions.
Comparative number of living and fossilized species of plants.—It will
appear from these observations that, although the remains of terrestrial
vegetation, borne down by aqueous causes from the land, are chiefly deposited
at the bottom of lakes or at the mouths of rivers, yet a considerable
quantity is drifted about in all directions by currents, and may become
imbedded in any marine formation, or may sink down, when water-logged,
to the bottom of unfathomable abysses, and there accumulate without intermixture
with other substances.
It may be asked whether we have any data for inferring that the
remains of a considerable proportion of the existing species of plants will
be permanently preserved, so as to be hereafter recognizable, supposing
the strata now in progress to be at some future period upraised? To this
inquiry it may be answered, that there are no reasons for expecting that
more than a small number of the plants now flourishing in the globe will
become fossilized; since the entire habitations of a great number of them
are remote from lakes and seas, and even where they grow near to large
bodies of water, the circumstances are quite accidental and partial which
746
favor the imbedding and conservation of vegetable remains. Suppose, for
example, that the species of plants inhabiting the hydrographical basin
of the Rhine, or that region, extending from the Alps to the sea, which is
watered by the Rhine and its numerous tributaries, to be about 2500 in
number, exclusive of the cryptogamic class. This estimate is by no means
exaggerated; yet if a geologist could explore the deposits which have
resulted from the sediment of the Rhine in the Lake of Constance, and
off the coast of Holland, he could scarcely expect to obtain from the
recent strata the leaves, wood, and seeds of fifty species in such a state
of preservation as to enable a botanist to determine their specific characters
with certainty.
Those naturalists, therefore, who infer that the ancient flora of the globe
was, at certain periods, less varied than now, merely because they have
as yet discovered only a few hundred fossil species of a particular epoch,
while they can enumerate more than one hundred thousand living ones,
are reasoning on a false basis, and their standard of comparison is not the
same in the two cases.
Submarine forests on coast of Hants.—We have already seen that the
submarine position of several forests, or the remains of trees standing in a
vertical position on the British shores, has been due, in some instances,
to the subsidence of land.1065 There are some cases which require a different
explanation. My friend, Mr. Charles Harris, discovered, in 1831, evident
traces of a fir-wood beneath the mean level of the sea, at Bournmouth,
in Hampshire, the formation having been laid open during a low spring
tide. It is composed of peat and wood, and is situated between the beach
and a bar of sand about 200 yards off, and extends fifty yards along the
shore. It also lies in the direct line of the Bournmouth Valley, from the
termination of which it is separated by 200 yards of shingle and drift-sand.
Down the valley flows a large brook, traversing near its mouth a
considerable tract of rough, boggy, and heathy ground, which produces a
few birch-trees, and a great abundance of the Myrica gale. Seventy-six
rings of annual growth were counted in a transverse section of one of the
buried fir-trees, which was fourteen inches in diameter. Besides the
stumps and roots of fir, pieces of alder and birch are found in the peat;
and it is a curious fact, that a part of many of the trees have been converted
into iron pyrites. The peat rests on pebbly strata, precisely similar
to the sand and pebbles occurring on the adjoining heaths.
As the sea is encroaching on this shore, we may suppose that at some
former period the Bourne Valley extended farther, and that its extremity
consisted, as at present, of boggy ground, partly clothed with fir-trees.
The bog rested on that bed of pebbles which we now see below the
peat; and the sea, in its progressive encroachments, eventually laid bare,
at low water, the sandy foundations; upon which a stream of fresh
water, rushing through the sand at the fall of the tides, carried out loose
sand with it. The super-stratum of vegetable matter, being matted and
747
bound together by the roots of trees, remained; but being undermined,
sank down below the level of the sea, and then the waves washed sand
and shingle over it. In support of this hypothesis, it may be observed,
that small streams of fresh water often pass under the sands of the sea-beach,
so that they may be crossed dry-shod; and the water is seen, at
the point where it issues, to carry out sand and even pebbles.
Mineralization of plants—Although the botanist and chemist have
as yet been unable to explain fully the manner in which wood becomes
petrified, it is nevertheless ascertained that, under favorable circumstances,
the lapidifying process is now continually going on. A piece
of wood was lately procured by Mr. Stokes, from an ancient Roman
aqueduct in Westphalia, in which some portions were converted into
spindle-shaped bodies, consisting of carbonate of lime, while the rest of
the wood remained in a comparatively unchanged state.1066 It appears
that in some cases the most perishable, in others the most durable,
portions of plants are preserved, variations which doubtless depend on
the time when the mineral matter was supplied. If introduced immediately,
on the first commencement of decomposition, then the most
destructible parts are lapidified, while the more durable do not waste
away till afterwards, when the supply has failed, and so never become
petrified. The converse of these circumstances gives rise to exactly
opposite results.
Professor Göppert, of Breslau, has instituted a series of curious
experiments, in which he has succeeded in producing some very remarkable
imitations of fossil petrifactions. He placed recent ferns between
soft layers of clay, dried these in the shade, and then slowly and
gradually heated them, till they were red-hot. The result was the
production of so perfect a counterpart of fossil plants as might have
deceived an experienced geologist. According to the different degrees
of heat applied, the plants were obtained in a brown or perfectly carbonized
condition; and sometimes, but more rarely, they were in a black
shining state, adhering closely to the layer of clay. If the red heat
was sustained until all the organic matter was burnt up, only an
impression of the plant remained.
The same chemist steeped plants in a moderately strong solution of
sulphate of iron, and left them immersed in it for several days, until
they were thoroughly soaked in the liquid. They were then dried, and
kept heated until they would no longer shrink in volume, and until
every trace of organic matter had disappeared. On cooling them he
found that the oxide formed by this process had taken the form of the
plants. A variety of other experiments were made by steeping animal
and vegetable substances in siliceous, calcareous, and metallic solutions,
and all tended to prove that the mineralization of organic bodies can be
carried much farther in a short time than had been previously supposed.1067
748
Imbedding of the Remains of Insects.
I have observed the elytra and other parts of beetles in a band of
fissile clay, separating two beds of recent shell-marl, in the Loch of
Kinnordy in Forfarshire. Amongst these, Mr. Curtis recognized Elator
lineatus and Atopa cervina, species still living in Scotland. These, as
well as other remains which accompanied them, appear to belong to
terrestrial, not aquatic species, and must have been carried down in
muddy water during an inundation. In the lacustrine peat of the same
locality, the elytra of beetles are not uncommon; but in the deposits
of drained lakes generally, and in the silt of our estuaries, the relics of
this class of the animal kingdom are rare. In the blue clay of very
modern origin of Lewes levels, Dr. Mantell has found the Indusia, or
cases of the larvæ of Phryganea, in abundance, with minute shells
belonging to the genera Planorbis, Limnea, &c., adhering to them.1068
When speaking of the migrations of insects, I pointed out that an
immense number are floated into lakes and seas by rivers, or blown by
winds far from the land; but they are so buoyant that we can only suppose
them, under very peculiar circumstances, to sink to the bottom
before they are either devoured by insectivorous animals or decomposed.
Remains of Reptiles.
As the bodies of several crocodiles were found in the mud brought
down to the sea by the river inundation which attended an earthquake
in Java, in the year 1699, we may imagine that extraordinary floods
of mud may stifle many individuals of the shoals of alligators and other
reptiles which frequent lakes and the deltas of rivers in tropical climates.
Thousands of frogs were found leaping about among the wreck, carried
into the sea by the inundations in Morayshire, in 1829;1069 and it is
evident that whenever a sea-cliff is undermined, or land is swept by
other violent causes into the sea, land reptiles may be carried in.
Remains of Birds.
We might have anticipated that the imbedding of the remains of birds
in new strata would be of very rare occurrence; for their powers of flight
insure them against perishing, by numerous casualties to which quadrupeds
are exposed during floods; and if they chance to be drowned, or to die
when swimming on the water, it will scarcely ever happen that they will
be submerged so as to become preserved in sedimentary deposits. In
consequence of the hollow tubular structure of their bones and the
quantity of their feathers, they are extremely light in proportion to their
volume; so that when first killed they do not sink to the bottom like
749
quadrupeds, but float on the surface until the carcass either rots away or
is devoured by predaceous animals. To these causes we may ascribe the
absence of any vestige of the bones of birds in the recent marl formations
of Scotland; although these lakes, until the moment when they were
artificially drained, were frequented by a great abundance of waterfowl.
Imbedding of Terrestrial Quadrupeds.
River inundations recur in most climates at very irregular intervals,
and expend their fury on those rich alluvial plains where herds of herbivorous
quadrupeds congregate together. These animals are often surprised;
and, being unable to stem the current, are hurried along until
they are drowned, when they sink at first immediately to the bottom.
Here their bodies are drifted along, together with sediment, into lakes or
seas, and may then be covered by a mass of mud, sand, and pebbles,
thrown down upon them. If there be no sediment superimposed, the
gases generated by putrefaction usually cause the bodies to rise again to
the surface about the ninth, or at latest the fourteenth day. The pressure
of a thin covering of mud would not be sufficient to retain them at the
bottom; for we see the putrid carcasses of dogs and cats, even in rivers,
floating with considerable weights attached to them, and in sea-water they
would be still more buoyant.
Where the body is so buried in drift sand, or mud accumulated upon
it, as never to rise again, the skeleton may be preserved entire; but if it
comes again to the surface while in the process of putrefaction, the bones
commonly fall piecemeal from the floating carcass, and may in that case
be scattered at random over the bottom of the lake, estuary, or sea; so
that a jaw may afterwards be found in one place, a rib in another, a
humerus in a third—all included, perhaps, in a matrix of fine materials,
where there may be evidence of slight transporting power in the current,
or even of none, but simply of some chemical precipitate.
A large number of the bodies of drowned animals, if they float into
the sea or a lake, especially in hot climates, are instantly devoured by
sharks, alligators, and other carnivorous beasts, which may have power
to digest even the bones; but during extraordinary floods, when the
greatest number of land animals are destroyed, the waters are commonly
so turbid, especially at the bottom of the channel, that even aquatic species
are compelled to escape into some retreat where there is clearer water,
lest they should be stifled. For this reason, as well as the rapidity of
sedimentary deposition at such seasons, the probability of carcasses
becoming permanently imbedded is considerable.
Flood in the Solway Firth, 1794.—One of the most memorable
floods of modern date, in our island, is that which visited part of the
southern borders of Scotland, on the 24th of January, 1794, and which
spread particular devastation over the country adjoining the Solway
Firth.
750
We learn from the account of Captain Napier, that the heavy rains
had swollen every stream which entered the Firth of Solway; so that
the inundation not only carried away a great number of cattle and sheep,
but many of the herdsmen and shepherds, washing down their bodies
into the estuary. After the storm, when the flood subsided, an extraordinary
spectacle was seen on a large sand-bank called "the beds of Esk,"
where there is a meeting of the tidal waters, and where heavy bodies are
usually left stranded after great floods. On this single bank were found
collected together the bodies of 9 black cattle, 3 horses, 1840 sheep,
45 dogs, 180 hares, besides a great number of smaller animals, and,
mingled with the rest, the corpses of two men and one woman.1070
Floods in Scotland, 1829.—In those more recent floods in Scotland,
in August, 1829, whereby a fertile district on the east coast became a
scene of dreadful desolation, a vast number of animals and plants
were washed from the land, and found scattered about after the storm,
around the mouths of the principal rivers. An eye-witness thus
describes the scene which presented itself at the mouth of the Spey,
in Morayshire:—"For several miles along the beach crowds were
employed in endeavoring to save the wood and other wreck with which
the heavy-rolling tide was loaded; whilst the margin of the sea was
strewed with the carcasses of domestic animals, and with millions of
dead hares and rabbits."1071
Savannahs of South America.—We are informed by Humboldt,
that during the periodical swellings of the large rivers in South America
great numbers of quadrupeds are annually drowned. Of the wild
horses, for example, which graze in immense troops in the savannahs,
thousands are said to perish when the river Apure, a tributary of the
Orinoco, is swollen, before they have time to reach the rising ground
of the Llanos. The mares, during the season of high water, may be
seen, followed by their colts, swimming about and feeding on the grass,
of which the top alone waves above the waters. In this state they are
pursued by crocodiles; and their thighs frequently bear the prints of
the teeth of these carnivorous reptiles. "Such is the pliability,"
observes the celebrated traveller, "of the organization of the animals
which man has subjected to his sway, that horses, cows, and other species
of European origin, lead, for a time, an amphibious life, surrounded
by crocodiles, water-serpents, and manatees. When the rivers return
again into their beds, they roam in the savannah, which is then spread
over with a fine odoriferous grass, and enjoy, as in their native climate,
the renewed vegetation of spring."1072
Floods of the Parana.—The great number of animals which are
drowned in seasons of drought in the tributaries of the Plata, was before
mentioned. Sir W. Parish states, that the Parana, flowing from the
mountains of Brazil to the estuary of the Plata, is liable to great floods,
751
and during one of these, in the year 1812, vast quantities of cattle were
carried away, "and when the waters began to subside, and the islands
which they had covered became again visible, the whole atmosphere
for a time was poisoned by the effluvia from the innumerable carcasses
of skunks, capybaras, tigers, and other wild beasts which had been
drowned."1073
Floods of the Ganges.—We find it continually stated, by those who
describe the Ganges and Burrampooter, that these rivers carry before
them, during the flood season, not only floats of reeds and timber, but
dead bodies of men, deer, and oxen.1074
In Java, 1699.—I have already referred to the effects of a flood which
attended an earthquake in Java in 1699, when the turbid waters of the
Batavian river destroyed all the fish except the carp; and when drowned
buffaloes, tigers, rhinoceroses, deer, apes, and other wild beasts, were
brought down to the sea-coast by the current, with several crocodiles
which had been stifled in the mud. (See above, p. 503.)
On the western side of the same island, in the territory of Galongoon,
in the Regencies, a more recent volcanic eruption (that of 1822, before
described) (see above, p. 431) was attended by a flood, during which the
river Tandoi bore down hundreds of carcasses of rhinoceroses and buffaloes,
and swept away more than one hundred men and women from a
multitude assembled on its banks to celebrate a festival. Whether the
bodies reached the sea, or were deposited, with drift matter, in some large
intervening alluvial plains, we are not informed.1075
Sumatra.—"On the coast of Orissa," says Heynes, "I have seen tigers
and whole herds of black cattle carried along by what are called freshes,
and trees of immense size."1076
In Virginia, 1771.—I might enumerate a great number of local deluges
that have swept through the fertile lands bordering on large rivers,
especially in tropical countries, but I should surpass the limits assigned to
this work. I may observe, however, that the destruction of the islands,
in rivers, is often attended with great loss of lives. Thus when the principal
river in Virginia rose, in 1771, to the height of twenty-five feet above
its ordinary level, it swept entirely away Elk Island, on which were seven
hundred head of quadrupeds,—horses, oxen, sheep, and hogs,—and nearly
one hundred houses.1077
The reader will gather, from what was before said respecting the deposition
of sediment by aqueous causes, that the greater number of the
remains of quadrupeds drifted away by rivers must be intercepted by
lakes before they reach the sea, or buried in freshwater formations near
the mouths of rivers. If they are carried still farther, the probabilities
are increased of their rising to the surface in a state of putrefaction,
and, in that case, of being there devoured by aquatic beasts of prey, or of
752
subsiding into some spots whither no sediment is conveyed, and, consequently,
where every vestige of them will, in the course of time, disappear.
Skeletons of animals in recent shell-marl, Scotland.—In some instances,
the skeletons of quadrupeds are met with abundantly in recent
shell-marls in Scotland, where we cannot suppose them to have been
imbedded by the action of rivers or floods. They all belong to species
which now inhabit, or are known to have been indigenous in Scotland.
The remains of several hundred skeletons have been procured within the
last century from five or six small lakes in Forfarshire, where shell-marl
has been worked. Those of the stag (Cervus Elaphas) are most numerous;
and if the others be arranged in the order of their relative abundance,
they will nearly follow thus—the ox, the boar, the horse, the
sheep, the dog, the hare, the fox, the wolf, and the cat. The beaver seems
extremely rare; but it has been found in the shell-marl of Loch Marlie, in
Perthshire, and in the parish of Edrom, in Berwickshire.
In the greater part of these lake-deposits there are no signs of floods;
and the expanse of water was originally so confined, that the smallest of
the above-mentioned quadrupeds could have crossed, by swimming from
one shore to the other. Deer, and such species as take readily to the
water, may often have been mired in trying to land, where the bottom
was soft and quaggy, and in their efforts to escape may have plunged
deeper into the marly bottom. Some individuals, I suspect, of different
species, have fallen in when crossing the frozen surface in winter; for
nothing can be more treacherous than the ice when covered with snow,
in consequence of the springs, which are numerous, and which, retaining
always an equal temperature, cause the ice, in certain spots, to be extremely
thin, while in every other part of the lake it is strong enough to bear the
heaviest weights.
Mammiferous remains in marine strata.—As the bones of mammalia
are often so abundantly preserved in peat, and such lakes as have just
been described, the encroachments of a sea upon a coast may sometimes
throw down the imbedded skeletons, so that they may be carried away
by tides and currents, and entombed in submarine formations. Some of
the smaller quadrupeds, also, which burrow in the ground, as well as reptiles
and every species of plant, are liable to be cast down into the waves
by this cause, which must not be overlooked, although probably of comparatively
small importance amongst the numerous agents whereby terrestrial
organic remains are included in submarine strata.
During the great earthquake of Conception in 1835, some cattle,
which were standing on the steep sides of the island of Quiriquina, were
rolled by the shock into the sea, while on a low island at the head of the
Bay of Conception seventy animals were washed off by a great wave and
drowned.1078

753</div></body></text></TEI>