<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="92">CHAPTER VIII.
Discovery of the Laws of Magneto-Electric
Induction.—Faraday.
IT was clearly established by
Ampère, as we have seen, that magnetic action is a peculiar form of
electromotive actions, and that, in 254 this kind of agency, action and reaction
are equal and opposite. It appeared to follow almost irresistibly from
these considerations, that magnetism might be made to produce
electricity, as electricity could be made to imitate all the effects
of magnetism. Yet for a long time the attempts to obtain such a result
were fruitless. Faraday, in 1825, endeavored to make the
conducting-wire of the voltaic circuit excite electricity in a
neighboring wire by induction, as the conductor charged with common
electricity would have done, but he obtained no such effect. If this
attempt had succeeded, the magnet, which, for all such purposes, is an
assemblage of voltaic circuits, might also have been made to excite
electricity. About the same time, an experiment was made in France by
M. Arago, which really involved the effect thus sought; though this
effect was not extricated from the complex phenomenon, till Faraday
began his splendid career of discovery on this subject in 1832.
Arago’s observation was, that the rapid revolution of a
conducting-plate in the neighborhood of a magnet, gave rise to a force
acting on the magnet. In England, Messrs. Barlow and Christie,
Herschel and Babbage, repeated and tried to analyse this experiment;
but referring the forces only to conditions of space and time, and
overlooking the real cause, the electrical currents produced by the
motion, these philosophers were altogether unsuccessful in their
labors. In 1831, Faraday again sought for electro-dynamical induction,
and after some futile trials, at last found it in a form different
from that in which he had looked for it. It was then seen, that at the
precise time of making or breaking the contact which closed the
galvanic circuit, a momentary effect was induced in a neighboring
wire, but disappeared instantly.24 Once in
possession of this fact, Mr. Faraday ran rapidly up the ladder of
discovery, to the general point of view.—Instead of suddenly
making or breaking the contact of the inducing circuit, a similar
effect was produced by removing the inducible wire nearer to or
further from the circuit;25—the effects were increased by the
proximity of soft iron;26—when the soft iron was affected
by an ordinary magnet instead of the voltaic wire, the same effect
still recurred;27—and thus it appeared, that by
making and breaking magnetic contact, a momentary electric current was
produced. It was produced also by moving the magnet;28—or by moving the wire with
reference to the magnet.29 Finally, it was found that the earth
might supply the place of a magnet 255 in this as in other experiments;30 and the mere motion of a wire, under
proper circumstances, produced in it, it appeared, a momentary
electric current.31 These facts were curiously confirmed by
the results in special cases. They explained Arago’s experiments: for
the momentary effect became permanent by the revolution of the plate.
And without using the magnet, a revolving plate became an electrical
machine;32—a revolving globe exhibited
electro-magnetic action,33 the circuit being complete in the globe
itself without the addition of any wire;—and a mere motion of
the wire of a galvanometer produced an electro-dynamic effect upon its
needle.34
24 Phil. Trans. 1832, p. 127,
First Series, Art. 10.
25 Art. 18.
26 Art. 28.
27 Art. 37.
28 Art. 39.
29 Art. 53.
30 Second Series, Phil. Trans.
p. 163.
31 Art. 141.
32 Art. 150.
33 Art. 164.
34 Art. 171.
But the question occurs, What is the general law which determines
the direction of electric currents thus produced by the joint effects
of motion and magnetism? Nothing but a peculiar steadiness and
clearness in his conceptions of space, could have enabled Mr. Faraday
to detect the law of this phenomenon. For the question required that
he should determine the mutual relations in space which connect the
magnetic poles, the position of the wire, the direction of the wire’s
motion, and the electrical current produced in it. This was no easy
problem; indeed, the mere relation of the magnetic to the electric
forces, the one set being perpendicular to the other, is of itself
sufficient to perplex the mind; as we have seen in the history of the
electrodynamical discoveries. But Mr. Faraday appears to have seized
at once the law of the phenomena. “The relation,” he says,35 “which holds between the magnetic pole,
the moving wire or metal, and the direction of the current evolved, is
very simple (so it seemed to him) although rather difficult to
express.” He represents it by referring position and motion to the
“magnetic curves,” which go from a magnetic pole to the opposite pole.
The current in the wire sets one way or the other, according to the
direction in which the motion of the wire cuts these curves. And thus
he was enabled, at the end of his Second Series of Researches
(December, 1831), to give, in general terms, the law of nature to
which may be referred the extraordinary number of new and curious
experiments which he has stated;36—namely,
that if a wire move so as to cut a magnetic curve, a power is called
into action which tends to urge a magnetic current through the wire;
and that if a mass move so that its parts do not move in the same
direction across the magnetic curves, 256 and with the same angular velocity,
electrical currents are called into play in the mass.
35 First Series, Art. 114.
36 Art. 256–264.
This rule, thus simple from its generality, though inevitably
complex in every special case, may be looked upon as supplying the
first demand of philosophy, the law of the phenomena; and
accordingly Dr. Faraday has, in all his subsequent researches on
magneto-electric induction, applied this law to his experiments; and
has thereby unravelled an immense amount of apparent inconsistency and
confusion, for those who have followed him in his mode of conceiving
the subject.
But yet other philosophers have regarded these phenomena in other
points of view, and have stated the laws of the phenomena in a manner
different from Faraday’s, although for the most part equivalent to
his. And these attempts to express, in the most simple and general
form, the law of the phenomena of magneto-electrical induction, have
naturally been combined with the expression of other laws of
electrical and magnetical phenomena. Further, these endeavors to
connect and generalize the Facts have naturally been clothed in the
garb of various Theories:—the laws of phenomena have been
expressed in terms of the supposed causes of the phenomena; as
fluids, attractions and repulsions, particles with currents running
through them or round them, physical lines of force, and the like.
Such views, and the conflict of them, are the natural and hopeful
prognostics of a theory which shall harmonize their discords and
include all that each contains of Truth. The fermentation at present
is perhaps too great to allow us to see clearly the truth which lies
at the bottom. But a few of the leading points of recent discussions
on these subjects will be noticed in the Additions
to this volume.
</div></body></text></TEI>