<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="6">
CHAPTER VI.

The Constancy and Variety of Climates.

It is possible to conceive arrangements of our system,
according to which all parts of the earth might
have the same, or nearly the same, climate. If, for
example, we suppose the earth to be a flat disk, or
flat ring, like the ring of Saturn, revolving in its own
plane as that does, each part of both the flat surfaces
would have the same exposure to the sun, and
the same temperature, so far as the sun’s effect is
concerned. There is no obvious reason why a planet
of such a form might not be occupied by animals
and vegetables, as well as our present earth; and on
this supposition the climate would be every where[53]
the same, and the whole surface might be covered
with life, without the necessity of there being any
difference in the kind of inhabitants belonging to different
parts.
Again, it is possible to conceive arrangements according
to which no part of our planet should have
any steady climate. This may probably be the case
with a comet. If we suppose such a body, revolving
round the sun in a very oblong ellipse, to be of small
size and of a very high temperature, and therefore
to cool rapidly; and if we suppose it also to be surrounded
by a large atmosphere, composed of various
gases; there would, on the surface of such a body,
be no average climate or seasons for each place.
The years, if we give this name to the intervals of
time occupied by its successive revolutions, would be
entirely unlike one another. The greatest heat of
one year might be cool compared with the greatest
cold of a preceding one. The greatest heats and
colds might succeed each other at intervals perpetually
unequal. The atmosphere might be perpetually
changing its composition by the condensation
of some of its constituent gases. In the operations
of the elements, all would be incessant and
rapid change, without recurrence or compensation.
We cannot say that organized beings could not be
fitted for such a habitation; but if they were, the
adaptation must be made by means of a constitution
quite different from that of almost all organized beings
known to us.
The state of things upon the earth, in its present
condition, is very different from both these suppositions.
The climate of the same place, notwithstanding
perpetual and apparently irregular change, possesses
a remarkable steadiness. And, though in
different places the annual succession of appearances
in the earth and heavens, is, in some of its
main characters, the same, the result of these influences
in the average climate is very different.
Now, to this remarkable constitution of the earth[54]
as to climate, the constitution of the animal and vegetable
world is precisely adapted. The differences
of different climates are provided for by the existence
of entirely different classes of plants and animals
in different countries. The constancy of climate
at the same place is a necessary condition of the
prosperity of each species there fixed.
We shall illustrate, by a few details, these characteristics
in the constitution of inorganic and of organic
nature, with the view of fixing the reader’s
attention upon the correspondence of the two.
1. The succession and alternation, at any given
place, of heat and cold, rain and sunshine, wind and
calm, and other atmospheric changes, appears at first
sight to be extremely irregular, and not subject to
any law. It is, however, easy to see, with a little
attention, that there is a certain degree of constancy
in the average weather and seasons of each place,
though the particular facts of which these generalities
are made up seem to be out of the reach of fixed
laws. And when we apply any numerical measure
to these particular occurrences, and take the average
of the numbers thus observed, we generally find a
remarkably close correspondence in the numbers belonging
to the whole, or to analogous portions of
successive years. This will be found to apply to the
measures given by the thermometer, the barometer,
the hygrometer, 
the rain gauge, and similar instruments.
Thus it is found that very hot summers, or
very cold winters, raise or depress the mean annual
temperature very little above or below the general
standard.
The heat may be expressed by degrees of the
thermometer; the temperature of the day is estimated
by this measure taken at a certain period of
the day, which is found by experience to correspond
with the daily average; and the mean annual temperature
will then be the average of all the heights
of the thermometer for every day in the year.
The mean annual temperature of London, thus[55]
measured, is about 50 degrees 4-10ths. The frost of
the year 1788 was so severe that the Thames was
passable on the ice; the mean temperature of that
year was 50 degrees 6-10ths, being within a small
fraction a degree of the standard. In 1796, when the
greatest cold ever observed in London occurred, the
mean temperature of the year was 50 degrees 1-10th,
which is likewise within a fraction of a degree of the
standard. In the severe winter of 1813-14, when the
Thames, Tyne, and other large rivers in England
were completely frozen over, the mean temperature
of the two years was 49 degrees, being little more
than a degree below the standard. And in the year
1808, when the summer was so hot that the temperature
in London was as high as 93½ degrees, the mean
heat of the year was 50½, which is about that of the
standard.
The same numerical indications of the constancy
of climate at the same place might be collected from
the records of other instruments of the kind above-mentioned.
We shall, hereafter, consider some of the very
complex agencies by which this steadiness is produced;
and shall endeavour to point out intentional
adaptations to this object. But we may, in the meantime,
observe how this property of the atmospheric
changes is made subservient to a further object.
To this constancy of the climates of each place,
the structure of plants is adapted; almost all vegetables
require a particular mean temperature of the
year, or of some season of the year; a particular degree
of moisture, and similar conditions. This will
be seen by observing that the range of most plants
as to climate is very limited. A vegetable which
flourishes where the mean temperature is 55 degrees,
would pine and wither when removed to a region
where the average is 50 degrees. If, therefore, the
average at each place were to vary as much as this,
our plants with their present constitutions would suffer,
languish, and soon die.
[56]
2. It will be readily understood that the same
mode of measurement by which we learn the constancy
of climate at the same place, serves to show
us the variety which belongs to different places.
While the variations of the same region vanish when
we take the averages even of moderate periods,
those of distant countries are fixed and perpetual;
and stand out more clear and distinct, the longer is
the interval for which we measure their operation.
In the way of measuring already described, the
mean temperature of Petersburg is 39 degrees, of
Rome 60, of Cairo 72. Such observations as these,
and others of the same kind, have been made at various
places, collected and recorded; and in this way
the surface of the earth can be divided by boundary
lines into various strips, according to these physical
differences. Thus, the zones which take in all the
places having the same or nearly the same mean annual
temperature, have been called isothermal zones.
These zones run nearly parallel to the equator, but
not exactly, for, in Europe, they bend to the north
in going eastward. In the same manner, the lines
passing through all places which have an equal temperature
for the summer or the winter half of the
year, have been called respectively isotheral and isochimal
lines. These do not coincide with the isothermal
lines, for a place may have the same temperature
as another, though its summer be hotter and its
winter colder, as is the case of Pekin compared with
London. In the same way we might conceive lines
drawn according to the conditions of clouds, rain,
wind, and the like circumstances, if we had observations
enough to enable us to lay down such lines.
The course of vegetation depends upon the combined
influence of all such conditions; and the lines which
bound the spread of particular vegetable productions
do not, in most cases, coincide with any of the separate
meteorological boundaries above spoken of.
Thus, the northern limit of vineyards runs through
France, in a direction very nearly north-east and[57]
south-west, while the line of equal temperature is
nearly east and west. And the spontaneous growth
or advantageous cultivation of other plants, is in like
manner bounded by lines of which the course depends
upon very complex causes, but of which the
position is generally precise and fixed.
</div></body></text></TEI>