<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="58">

CHAPTER II.
The Methods of Natural History, as regulated by the Idea of Likeness.


Sect. I.—Natural History in general.
1. Idea of Likeness in Natural History.—The
various branches of Natural History, in so far as they
are classificatory sciences merely, and do not depend
upon physiological views, rest upon the same Idea of
Likeness which is the ground of the application of the
names, more or less general, of common language. But
the nature of science requires that, for her purposes,
this Idea should be applied in a more exact and rigourous manner than in its common and popular employment; just as occurs with regard to the other Ideas
on which science is founded;—for instance, as the idea
of space gives rise, in popular use, to the relations
implied in the prepositions and adjectives which refer
to position and form, and in its scientific development gives rise to the more precise relations of geometry.
The way in which the Idea of Likeness has been
applied, so as to lead to the construction of a science,
is best seen in Botany: for, in the Classification of
Animals, we are inevitably guided by a consideration
of the function of parts; that is, by an idea of purpose,
and not of likeness merely: and in Mineralogy, the
attempts at classification on the principles of Natural
History have been hitherto very imperfectly successful. But in Botany we have an example of a branch
of knowledge in which systematic classification has
been effected with great beauty and advantage; and
in which the peculiarities and principles on which such 109 classification must depend have been carefully studied.
Many of the principal botanists, as Linnæus, Adanson,
Decandolle, have not only practically applied, but have
theoretically enunciated, what they held to be the
sound maxims of classificatory science: and have thus
enabled us to place before the reader with confidence
the philosophy of this kind of science.
2. Condition of its Use.—We may begin by remarking that the Idea of Likeness, in its systematic employment, is governed by the same principle which we
have already spoken of as regulating the distribution
of things into kinds, and the assignment of names in
unsystematic thought and speech; namely, the condition that general propositions shall be possible. But as
in this case the propositions are to be of a scientific
form and exactness, the likeness must be treated with
a corresponding precision; and its consequences traced
by steady and distinct processes. Naturalists must,
for their purposes, employ the resemblances of objects
in a technical manner. This technical process may be
considered as consisting of three steps;—The fixation
of the resemblances; The use of them in making a
classification; The means of applying the classification.
These three steps may be spoken of as the Terminology,
the Plan of the System, and the Scheme of the Characters.
Sect. II.—Terminology.5</div></body></text></TEI>