<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="40">CHAPTER XL.
THEORIES RESPECTING THE ORIGINAL INTRODUCTION OF SPECIES.
Proposal of an hypothesis on this subject—Supposed centres or foci of creation—Why
distinct provinces of animals and plants have not become more blended
together—Brocchi's speculations on the loss of species—Stations of plants and
animals—Causes on which they depend—Stations of plants how affected
by animals—Equilibrium in the number of species how preserved—Peculiar
efficacy of insects in this task—Rapidity with which certain insects multiply
or decrease in numbers—Effect of omnivorous animals in preserving the
equilibrium of species—Reciprocal influence of aquatic and terrestrial species
on each other.
Theory of Linnæus.—It would be superfluous to examine the various
attempts which were made to explain the phenomena of the distribution
of species alluded to in the preceding chapters, in the infancy
of the sciences of botany, zoology, and physical geography. The
theories or rather conjectures then indulged now stand refuted by a
simple statement of facts; and if Linnæus were living he would be the
first to renounce the notions which he promulgated. For he imagined
the habitable world to have been for a certain time limited to one small
tract, the only portion of the earth's surface that was as yet laid bare
by the subsidence of the primæval ocean. In this fertile spot he supposed
the originals of all the species of plants which exist on this globe
to have been congregated together with the first ancestors of all animals
and of the human race. "In quâ commodè habitaverint animalia
omnia, et vegetabilia lætè germinaverint." In order to accommodate the
various habitudes of so many creatures, and to provide a diversity of
climate suited to their several natures, the tract in which the creation
took place was supposed to have been situated in some warm region of
the earth, but to have contained a lofty mountain range, on the heights
and in the declivities of which were to be found all temperatures and
every climate, from that of the torrid to that of the frozen zone.948
That there never was a universal ocean since the planet was inhabited,
or, rather, since the oldest groups of strata yet known to contain organic
remains were formed, is proved by the presence of terrestrial plants or
by indications of shores in all the older formations; and if this conclusion
was not established, yet no geologist could deny that, since the
first small portion of the earth was laid dry, there have been many
entire changes in the species of plants and animals inhabiting the land.
But, without dwelling on the above and other refuted theories, let
us inquire whether some hypothesis cannot be substituted as simple as
that of Linnæus, to which the phenomena now ascertained in regard to
the distribution both of aquatic and terrestrial species may be referred.
666
The following may, perhaps, be reconcileable with known facts:—Each
species may have had its origin in a single pair, or individual, where an
individual was sufficient, and species may have been created in succession
at such times and in such places as to enable them to multiply and endure
for an appointed period, and occupy an appointed space on the globe.
In order to explain this theory, let us suppose every living thing to
be destroyed in the western hemisphere, both on the land and in the
ocean, and permission to be given to man to people this great desert,
by transporting into it animals and plants from the eastern hemisphere,
a strict prohibition being enforced against introducing two original
stocks of the same species.
Now it is easy to show that the result of such a mode of colonizing
would correspond exactly, so far as regards the grouping of animals and
plants, with that now observed throughout the globe. In the first place,
it would be necessary for naturalists, before they imported species into
particular localities, to study attentively the climate and other physical
conditions of each spot. It would be no less requisite to introduce the
different species in succession, so that each plant and animal might
have time and opportunity to multiply before the species destined to
prey upon it was admitted. Many herbs and shrubs, for example, must
spread far and wide before the sheep, the deer, and the goat could be
allowed to enter, lest they should devour and annihilate the original
stocks of many plants, and then perish themselves for want of food.
The above-mentioned herbivorous animals in their turn must be permitted
to make considerable progress before the entrance of the first
pair of wolves or lions. Insects must be allowed to swarm before the
swallow could be permitted to skim through the air, and feast on
thousands at one repast.
It is evident that, however equally in this case our original stocks
were distributed over the whole surface of land and water, there would
nevertheless arise distinct botanical and zoological provinces, for there
are a great many natural barriers which oppose common obstacles to
the advance of a variety of species. Thus, for example, almost all the
animals and plants naturalized by us, towards the extremity of South
America, would be unable to spread beyond a certain limit, towards the
east, west, and south; because they would be stopped by the ocean,
and a few of them only would succeed in reaching the cooler latitudes
of the northern hemisphere, because they would be incapable of bearing
the heat of the tropics, through which they must pass. In the
course of ages, undoubtedly, exceptions would arise, and some species
might become common to the temperate and polar regions, or both
sides of the equator; for I have before shown that the powers of diffusion
conferred on some classes are very great. But we might confidently
predict that these exceptions would never become so numerous
as to invalidate the general rule.
Some of the plants and animals transplanted by us to the coast of
Chili and Peru would never be able to cross the Andes, so as to reach
667
the eastern plains; nor, for a similar reason, would those first established
in the Pampas, or the valleys of the Amazon and the Orinoco, ever
arrive at the shores of the Pacific.
In the ocean an analogous state of things would prevail; for there,
also, climate would exert a great influence in limiting the range of species,
and the land would stop the migrations of aquatic tribes as effectually
as the sea arrests the dispersion of the terrestrial. As certain birds, insects,
and the seeds of plants, can never cross the direction of prevailing
winds, so currents form natural barriers to the dissemination of many
oceanic races. A line of shoals may be as impassable to deep-water
species, as are the Alps and the Andes to plants and animals peculiar to
plains; while deep abysses may prove insuperable obstacles to the migrations
of the inhabitants of shallow waters.
Supposed centres, or foci, of creation.—It is worthy of observation,
that one effect of the introduction of single pairs of each species must be
the confined range of certain groups in spots, which, like small islands,
or solitary inland lakes, have few means of interchanging their inhabitants
with adjoining regions. Now this congregating in a small space
of many peculiar species, would give an appearance of centres or foci of
creation, as they have been termed, as if they were favourite points
where the creative energy has been in greater action than in others, and
where the numbers of peculiar organic beings have consequently become
more considerable.
I do not mean to call in question the soundness of the inferences of
some botanists, as to the former existence of certain limited spots whence
species of plants have been propagated, radiating, as it were, in all directions
from a common centre. On the contrary, I conceive these phenomena
to be the necessary consequences of the plan of nature before suggested,
operating during the successive mutations of the surface, some of
which the geologist can prove to have taken place subsequently to the
period when many species now existing were created. In order to exemplify
how this arrangement of plants may have been produced, let us
imagine that, about three centuries before the discovery of St. Helena
(itself of submarine volcanic origin), a multitude of new islands had
been thrown up in the surrounding sea, and that these had each become
clothed with plants emigrating from St. Helena, in the same manner as
the wild plants of Campania have diffused themselves over Monte Nuovo.
Whenever the first botanist investigated the new archipelago, he would,
in all probability, find a different assemblage of plants in each of the
islands of recent formation; but in St. Helena itself, he would meet with
individuals of every species, belonging to all parts of the archipelago,
and some, in addition, peculiar to itself, viz., those which had not been
able to obtain a passage into any one of the surrounding new-formed
lands. In this case it might be truly said that the original island was
the primitive focus, or centre, of a certain type of vegetation; whereas,
in the surrounding islands, there would be a smaller number of species,
yet all belonging to the same group.
668
But this peculiar distribution of plants would not warrant the conclusion
that, in the space occupied by St. Helena, there had been a greater
exertion of creative power than in the spaces of equal area occupied by
the new adjacent lands; because, within the period in which St. Helena
had acquired its peculiar vegetation, each of the spots supposed to be
subsequently converted into land may have been the birth-place of a great
number of marine animals and plants, which may have had time to
scatter themselves far and wide over the southern Atlantic.
Why distinct provinces not more blended.—Perhaps it may be objected
to some parts of the foregoing train of reasoning, that during the
lapse of past ages, especially during many partial revolutions of the
globe of comparatively modern date, different zoological and botanical
provinces ought to have become more confounded and blended together—that
the distribution of species approaches too nearly to what might
have been expected, if animals and plants had been introduced into the
globe when its physical geography had already assumed the features
which it now wears; whereas we know that, in certain districts, considerable
geographical changes have taken place since species identical with
those now in being were created.
Brocchi's speculations on loss of species.—These and many kindred
topics cannot be fully discussed until we have considered, not merely the
general laws which may regulate the first introduction of species, but
those which may limit their duration on the earth. Brocchi remarked,
when hazarding some interesting conjectures respecting "the loss of
species," that a modern naturalist had no small assurance, who declared
"that individuals alone were capable of destruction, and that species
were so perpetuated that nature could not annihilate them, so long as
the planet lasted, or at least that nothing less than the shock of a comet,
or some similar disaster, could put an end to their existence."949 The
Italian geologist, on the contrary, had satisfied himself that many species
of Testacea, which formerly inhabited the Mediterranean, had become
extinct, although a great number of others, which had been the contemporaries
of those lost races, still survived. He came to the opinion that
about half the species which peopled the waters when the Subapennine
strata were deposited had gone out of existence; and in this inference he
does not appear to have been far wrong.
But, instead of seeking a solution of this problem; like some other
geologists of his time, in a violent and general catastrophe, Brocchi endeavoured
to imagine some regular and constant law by which species
might be made to disappear from the earth gradually and in succession.
The death, he suggested, of a species might depend, like that of individuals,
on certain peculiarities of constitution conferred upon them at
their birth; and as the longevity of the one depends on a certain force
of vitality, which, after a period, grows weaker and weaker, so the duration
of the other may be governed by the quantity of prolific power
669
bestowed upon the species which, after a season, may decline in energy,
so that the fecundity and multiplication of individuals may be gradually
lessened from century to century, "until that fatal term arrives when the
embryo, incapable of extending and developing itself, abandons, almost
at the instant of its formation, the slender principle of life by which it
was scarcely animated,—and so all dies with it."
Now we may coincide in opinion with the Italian naturalist, as to the
gradual extinction of species one after another, by the operation of regular
and constant causes, without admitting an inherent principle of deterioration
in their physiological attributes. We might concede, "that many
species are on the decline, and that the day is not far distant when they
will cease to exist;" yet deem it consistent with what we know of the
nature of organic beings, to believe that the last individuals of each species
retain their prolific powers in their full intensity.
Brocchi has himself speculated on the share which a change of climate
may have had in rendering the Mediterranean unfit for the habitation of
certain Testacea, which still continued to thrive in the Indian Ocean, and
of others which were now only represented by analogous forms within
the tropics. He must also have been aware that other extrinsic causes,
such as the progress of human population, or the increase of some one
of the inferior animals, might gradually lead to the extirpation of a particular
species, although its fecundity might remain to the last unimpaired.
If, therefore, amid the vicissitudes of the animate and inanimate world,
there are known causes capable of bringing about the decline and extirpation
of species, it became him thoroughly to investigate the full extent
to which these might operate, before he speculated on any cause of so
purely hypothetical a kind as "the diminution of the prolific virtue."
If it could have been shown that some wild plant had insensibly dwindled
away and died out, as sometimes happens to cultivated varieties propagated
by cuttings, even though climate, soil, and every other circumstance,
should continue identically the same—if any animal had perished
while the physical condition of the earth, and the number and force of
its foes, with every other extrinsic cause, remain unaltered, then might we
have some ground for suspecting that the infirmities of age creep on as
naturally on species as upon individuals. But, in the absence of such observations,
let us turn to another class of facts, and examine attentively
the circumstances which determine the stations of particular animals and
plants, and perhaps we shall discover, in the vicissitudes to which these
stations are exposed, a cause fully adequate to explain the phenomena
under consideration.
Stations of plants and animals.—Stations comprehend all the circumstances,
whether relating to the animate or inanimate world, which
determine whether a given plant or animal can exist in a given place;
so that if it be shown that stations can become essentially modified by
the influence of known causes, it will follow that species, as well as individuals,
are mortal.
Every naturalist is familiar with the fact, that although in a particular
670
country, such as Great Britain, there may be more than three thousand
species of plants, ten thousand insects, and a great variety in each of the
other classes; yet there will not be more than a hundred, perhaps not
half that number, inhabiting any given locality. There may be no want
of space in the supposed tract: it may be a large mountain, or an extensive
moor, or a great river plain, containing room enough for individuals
of every species in our island; yet the spot will be occupied by a few to
the exclusion of many, and these few are enabled, throughout long periods,
to maintain their ground successfully against every intruder, notwithstanding
the facilities which species enjoy, by virtue of their power of diffusion,
of invading adjacent territories.
The principal causes which enable a certain assemblage of plants thus
to maintain their ground against all others depend, as is well known, on
the relations between the physiological nature of each species, and the
climate, exposure, soil, and other physical conditions of the locality. Some
plants live only on rocks, others in meadows, a third class in marshes.
Of the latter, some delight in a fresh-water morass,—others in salt marshes,
where their roots may copiously absorb saline particles. Some prefer an
alpine region in a warm latitude, where, during the heat of summer,
they are constantly irrigated by the cool waters of melting snows. To
others loose sand, so fatal to the generality of species, affords the most
proper station. The Carex arenaria and the Elymus arenarius acquire
their full vigor on a sandy dune, obtaining an ascendancy over the very
plants which in a stiff clay would immediately stifle them.
Where the soil of a district is of so peculiar a nature that it is extremely
favorable to certain species, and agrees ill with every other, the former
get exclusive possession of the ground, and, as in the case of heaths, live
in societies. In like manner the bog moss (Sphagnum) is fully developed
in peaty swamps, and becomes, like the heath, in the language of botanists,
a social plant. Such monopolies, however, are not common, for they
are checked by various causes. Not only are many species endowed with
equal powers to obtain and keep possession of similar stations, but each
plant, for reasons not fully explained by the physiologist, has the property
of rendering the soil where it has grown less fitted for the support of
other individuals of its own species, or even other species of the same
family. Yet the same spot, so far from being impoverished, is improved,
for plants of another family. Oaks, for example, render the soil more
fertile for the fir tribe, and firs prepare the soil for oaks. Every agriculturist
feels the force of this law of the organic world, and regulates accordingly
the rotation of his crops.
Equilibrium in the number of species, how preserved.—"All the plants
of a given country," says De Candolle, in his usual spirited style, "are at
war one with another. The first which establish themselves by chance
in a particular spot tend, by the mere occupancy of space, to exclude
other species—the greater choke the smaller; the longest livers replace
those which last for a shorter period; the more prolific gradually make
671
themselves masters of the ground, which species multiplying more slowly
would otherwise fill."
In this continual strife it is not always the resources of the plant itself
which enable it to maintain or extend its ground. Its success depends,
in a great measure, on the number of its foes or allies among the animals
and plants inhabiting the same region. Thus, for example, a herb
which loves the shade may multiply, if some tree with spreading boughs
and dense foliage flourish in the neighborhood. Another, which, if unassisted,
would be overpowered by the rank growth of some hardy competitor,
is secure because its leaves are unpalatable to cattle; which, on
the other hand, annually crop down its antagonist, and rarely suffer it to
ripen its seed.
Oftentimes we see some herb which has flowered in the midst of a
thorny shrub, when all the other individuals of the same species, in the
open fields around, are eaten down, and cannot bring their seed to
maturity. In this case, the shrub has lent his armor of spines and
prickles to protect the defenceless herb against the mouths of the cattle,
and thus a few individuals which occupied, perhaps, the most unfavorable
station in regard to exposure, soil, and other circumstances, may,
nevertheless, by the aid of an ally, become the principal source whereby
the winds are supplied with seeds which perpetuate the species throughout
the surrounding tract. Thus, in the New Forest in Hampshire, the
young oaks which are not consumed by the deer, or uprooted by the
swine, are indebted to the holly for their escape.
In the above examples we see one plant shielding another from the
attacks of animals; but instances are, perhaps, still more numerous,
where some animal defends a plant against the enmity of some other
subject of the vegetable kingdom.
Scarcely any beast, observes a Swedish naturalist, will touch the
nettle, but fifty different kinds of insects are fed by it.950 Some of these
seize upon the root, others upon the stem; some eat the leaves, others
devour the seeds and flowers; but for this multitude of enemies, the
nettle (Urtica dioica), which is now found in all the four quarters of the
globe, would annihilate a great number of plants. Linnæus tells us, in
his "Tour in Scania," that goats were turned into an island which
abounded with the Agrostis arundinacea, where they perished by famine;
but horses which followed them grew fat on the same plant. The goat,
also, he says, thrives on the meadow-sweet and water-hemlock, plants
which are injurious to cattle.951
Agency of insects.—Every plant, observes Wilcke, has its proper insect
allotted to it to curb its luxuriancy, and to prevent it from multiplying
to the exclusion of others. "Thus grass in meadows sometimes
flourishes so as to exclude all other plants; here the Phalæna graminis
(Bombyx gram.), with her numerous progeny, finds a well-spread table;
672
they multiply in immense numbers, and the farmer, for some years,
laments the failure of his crop; but the grass being consumed, the
moths die with hunger, or remove to another place. Now the quantity
of grass being greatly diminished, the other plants, which were before
choked by it, spring up, and the ground becomes variegated with a multitude
of different species of flowers. Had not nature given a commission
to this minister for that purpose, the grass would destroy a great
number of species of vegetables, of which the equilibrium is now kept
up."952
In the above passage allusion is made to the ravages committed in
1740, and the two following years, in many provinces of Sweden, by a
most destructive insect. The same moth is said never to touch the foxtail
grass, so that it may be classed as a most active ally and benefactor
of that species, and as peculiarly instrumental in preserving it in its
present abundance.953 A discovery of Rolander, cited in the treatise of
Wilcke above mentioned, affords a good illustration of the checks and
counter-checks which nature has appointed to preserve the balance of
power among species. "The Phalæna strobilella has the fir cone
assigned to it to deposit its eggs upon; the young caterpillars coming
out of the shell consume the cone and superfluous seed; but, lest the
destruction should be too general, the Ichneumon strobilellæ lays its eggs
in the caterpillar, inserting its long tail in the openings of the cone till it
touches the included insect, for its body is too large to enter. Thus it
fixes its minute egg upon the caterpillar, which being hatched, destroys
it."954
Entomologists enumerate many parallel cases where insects, appropriated
to certain plants, are kept down by other insects, and these again
by parasites expressly appointed to prey on them.955 Few perhaps are in
the habit of duly appreciating the extent to which insects are active in
preserving the balance of species among plants, and thus regulating indirectly
the relative numbers of many of the higher orders of terrestrial
animals.
The peculiarity of their agency consists in their power of suddenly
multiplying their numbers to a degree which could only be accomplished
in a considerable lapse of time in any of the larger animals, and then as
instantaneously relapsing, without the intervention of any violent disturbing
cause, into their former insignificance.
If, for the sake of employing, on different but rare occasions, a power
of many hundred horses, we were under the necessity of feeding all these
animals at great cost in the intervals when their services were not required,
we should greatly admire the invention of a machine, such as the
steam-engine, which was capable at any moment of exerting the same
degree of strength without any consumption of food during periods of
inaction. The same kind of admiration is strongly excited when we
contemplate the powers of insect life, in the creation of which the Author
673
of nature has been so prodigal. A scanty number of minute individuals,
to be detected only by careful research, are ready in a few days, weeks,
or months, to give birth to myriads, which may repress any degree of
monopoly in another species, or remove nuisances, such as dead carcases,
which might taint the air. But no sooner has the destroying commission
been executed than the gigantic power becomes dormant—each of
the mighty host soon reaches the term of its transient existence, and the
season arrives when the whole species passes naturally into the egg, and
thence into the larva and pupa state. In this defenceless condition it
may be destroyed either by the elements, or by the augmentation of
some of its numerous foes which may prey upon it in the early stages of
its transformation: or it often happens that in the following year the
season proves unfavorable to the hatching of the eggs or the development
of the pupæ.
Thus the swarming myriads depart which may have covered the vegetation
like the aphides, or darkened the air like locusts. In almost every
season there are some species which in this manner put forth their
strength, and then, like Milton's spirits, which thronged the spacious
hall, "reduce to smallest forms their shapes immense"—


  ———So thick the aëry crowd
Swarm'd and were straiten'd; till the signal given,
Behold a wonder! they but how who seem'd
In bigness to surpass earth's giant sons,
Now less than smallest dwarfs.


A few examples will illustrate the mode in which this force operates.
It is well known that, among the countless species of the insect creation,
some feed on animal, others on vegetable matter; and upon considering
a catalogue of eight thousand British Insects and Arachnidæ, Mr. Kirby
found that these two divisions were nearly a counterpoise to each other,
the carnivorous being somewhat preponderant. There are also distinct
species, some appointed to consume living, others dead or putrid animal
and vegetable substances. One female, of Musca carnaria, will give birth
to twenty thousand young; and the larvæ of many flesh-flies devour so
much food in twenty-four hours, and grow so quickly, as to increase their
weight two hundred-fold! In five days after being hatched they arrive
at their full growth and size, so that there was ground, says Kirby, for the
assertion of Linnæus, that three flies of M. vomitoria could devour a dead
horse as quickly as a lion956; and another Swedish naturalist remarks, that so
great are the powers of propagation of a single species even of the
smallest insects, that each can commit, when required, more ravages than
the elephant.957
Next to locusts, the aphides, perhaps, exert the greatest power over
the vegetable world, and, like them, are so sometimes so numerous as to
darken the air. The multiplication of these little creatures is without
674
parallel, and almost every plant has its peculiar species. Reaumur has
proved that in five generations one aphis may be the progenitor of
5,904,900,000 descendants; and it is supposed that in one year there
may be twenty generations.958 Mr. Curtis observes that, as among caterpillars
we find some that are constantly and unalterably attached to one
or more particular species of plants, and others that feed indiscriminately
on most sorts of herbage, so it is precisely with the aphides: some are
particular, others more general feeders; and as they resemble other insects
in this respect, so they do also in being more abundant in some years
than in others.959 In 1793 they were the chief, and in 1798 the sole,
cause of the failure of the hops. In 1794, a season, almost unparalleled
for drought, the hop was perfectly free from them; while peas and beans,
especially the former, suffered very much from their depredations.
The ravages of the caterpillars of some of our smaller moths afford a
good illustration of the temporary increase of a species. The oak-trees
of a considerable wood have been stripped of their leaves as bare as in
winter by the caterpillars of a small green moth (Tortrix viridana),
which has been observed the year following not to abound.960 The silver
Y moth (Plusia gamma), although one of our common species, is not
dreaded by us for its devastations; but legions of their caterpillars have
at times created alarm in France, as in 1735. Reaumur observes that
the female moth lays about four hundred eggs; so that if twenty caterpillars
were distributed in a garden, and all lived through the winter and
became moths in the succeeding May, the eggs laid by these, if half of
them were female and all fertile, would in the next generation produce
800,000 caterpillars.961 A modern writer, therefore, justly observes that,
did not Providence put causes in operation to keep them in due bounds,
the caterpillars of this moth alone, leaving out of consideration the two
thousand other British species, might soon destroy more than half of our
vegetation.962
In the latter part of the last century an ant most destructive to the
sugar-cane (Formica saccharivora), appeared in such infinite hosts in the
island of Granada, as to put a stop to the cultivation of that vegetable.
Their numbers were incredible. The plantations and roads were filled
with them; many domestic quadrupeds, together with rats, mice, and
reptiles, and even birds, perished in consequence of this plague. It was
not till 1780 that they were at length annihilated by torrents of rain,
which accompanied a dreadful hurricane.963
Devastations caused by locusts.—We may conclude by mentioning
some instances of the devastations of locusts in various countries. Among
other parts of Africa, Cyrenaica has been at different periods infested by
myriads of these creatures, which have consumed nearly every green
thing. The effect of the havoc committed by them may be estimated
675
by the famine they occasioned. St. Augustin mentions a plague of this
kind in Africa, which destroyed no less than 800,000 men in the kingdom
of Massinissa alone, and many more upon the territories bordering
upon the sea. It is also related, that in the year 591 an infinite army
of locusts migrated from Africa into Italy; and, after grievously ravaging
the country, were cast into the sea, when there arose a pestilence from
their stench, which carried off nearly a million of men and beasts.
In the Venetian territory, also, in 1748, more than thirty thousand
persons are said to have perished in a famine occasioned by this scourge;
and other instances are recorded of their devastations in France, Spain,
Italy, Germany, &c. In different parts of Russia also, Hungary, and
Poland, in Arabia and India, and other countries, their visitations have
been periodically experienced. Although they have a preference for
certain plants, yet, when these are consumed, they will attack almost all
the remainder. In the accounts of the invasion of locusts, the statements
which appear most marvellous relate to the prodigious mass of
matter which encumbers the sea wherever they are blown into it, and the
pestilence arising from its putrefaction. Their dead bodies are said to
have been, in some places, heaped one upon another, to the depth of four
feet, in Russia, Poland and Lithuania; and when, in Southern Africa,
they were driven into the sea, by a north-west wind, they formed, says
Barrow, along the shore, for fifty miles, a bank three or four feet high.964
But when we consider that forests are stripped of their foliage, and the
earth of its green garment for thousands of square miles, it may well be
supposed that the volume of animal matter produced may equal that of
great herds of quadrupeds and flights of large birds suddenly precipitated
into the sea.
The occurrence of such events, at certain intervals, in hot countries,
like the severe winters and damp summers returning after a series of
years in the temperate zone, may affect the proportional numbers of
almost all classes of animals and plants, and probably prove fatal to the
existence of many which would otherwise thrive there; while, on the
contrary, the same occurrences can scarcely fail to be favorable to
certain species which, if deprived of such aid, might not maintain their
ground.
Although it may usually be remarked that the extraordinary increase
of some one species is immediately followed and checked by the multiplication
of another, yet this does not always happen; partly because
many species feed in common on the same kinds of food, and partly because
many kinds of food are often consumed indifferently by one and
the same species. In the former case, where a variety of different animals
have precisely the same taste, as, for example, when many insectivorous
birds and reptiles devour alike some particular fly or beetle, the
unusual numbers of these insects may cause only a slight and almost
imperceptible augmentation of each of these species of bird and reptile.
676
In the other instances, where one animal preys on others of almost every
class, as for example, where our English buzzards devour not only small
quadrupeds, as rabbits and field-mice, but also birds, frogs, lizards, and
insects, the profusion of any one of these last may cause all such general
feeders to subsist more exclusively upon the species thus in excess, by
which means the balance may be restored.
Agency of omnivorous animals.—The number of species which are
nearly omnivorous is considerable; and although every animal has, perhaps,
a predilection for some one description of food rather than another,
yet some are not even confined to one of the great kingdoms of the organic
world. Thus, when the raccoon of the West Indies can procure
neither fowls, fish, snails, nor insects, it will attack the sugar-canes, and
devour various kinds of grain. The civets, when animal food is scarce,
maintain themselves on fruits and roots.
Numerous birds, which feed indiscriminately on insects and plants,
are perhaps more instrumental than any other of the terrestrial tribes in
preserving a constant equilibrium between the relative numbers of different
classes of animals and vegetables. If the insects become very numerous
and devour the plants, these birds will immediately derive a
larger portion of their subsistence from insects, just as the Arabians,
Syrians, and Hottentots feed on locusts, when the locusts devour their
crops.
Reciprocal influence of aquatic and terrestrial species.—The intimate
relation of the inhabitants of the water to those of the land, and the influence
exerted by each on the relative number of species, must not be
overlooked amongst the complicated causes which determine the existence
of animals and plants in certain regions. A large portion of the
amphibious quadrupeds and reptiles prey partly on aquatic plants and
animals, and in part on terrestrial; and a deficiency of one kind of prey
causes them to have immediate recourse to the other. The voracity of
certain insects, as the dragon-fly, for example, is confined to the water
during one stage of their transformations, and in their perfect state to the
air. Innumerable water-birds, both of rivers and seas, derive in like
manner their food indifferently from either element; so that the abundance
or scarcity of prey in one induces them either to forsake or more
constantly to haunt the other. Thus an intimate connection between
the state of the animate creation in a lake or river, and in the adjoining
dry land, is maintained; or between a continent, with its lakes and rivers,
and the ocean. It is well known that many birds migrate, during
stormy seasons, from the sea-shore into the interior, in search of food;
while others, on the contrary, urged by like wants, forsake their inland
haunts, and live on substances rejected by the tide.
The migration of fish into rivers during the spawning season supplies
another link of the same kind. Suppose the salmon to be reduced in
numbers by some marine foes, as by seals and grampuses, the consequence
must often be, that in the course of a few years the otters at the distance
of several hundred miles inland will be lessened in number from the
677
scarcity of fish. On the other hand, if there be a dearth of food for the
young fry of the salmon in rivers and estuaries, so that few return to the
sea, the sand eels and other marine species, which are usually kept down
by the salmon, will swarm in greater profusion.
It is unnecessary to accumulate a greater number of illustrations
in order to prove that the stations of different plants and animals
depend on a great complication of circumstances,—on an immense
variety of relations in the state of the inanimate worlds. Every plant
requires a certain climate, soil, and other conditions, and often the aid
of many animals, in order to maintain its ground. Many animals feed
on certain plants, being often restricted to a small number, and sometimes
to one only; other members of the animal kingdom feed on
plant-eating species, and thus become dependent on the conditions of
the stations not only of their prey, but of the plants consumed by them.
Having duly reflected on the nature and extent of these mutual
relations in the different parts of the organic and inorganic worlds, we
may next proceed to examine the results which may be anticipated
from the fluctuations now continually in progress in the state of the
earth's surface, and in the geographical distribution of its living productions.
</div></body></text></TEI>