<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Chambers Robert</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="1">p. 1THE
BODIES OF SPACE,
THEIR ARRANGEMENTS AND
FORMATION.
It is familiar knowledge that the
earth which we inhabit is a globe of somewhat less than 8000
miles in diameter, being one of a series of eleven which revolve
at different distances around the sun, and some of which have
satellites in like manner revolving around them.  The sun,
planets, and satellites, with the less intelligible orbs termed
comets, are comprehensively called the solar system, and if we
take as the uttermost bounds of this system the orbit of Uranus
(though the comets actually have a wider range), we shall find
that it occupies a portion of space not less than three thousand
six hundred millions of miles in extent.  The mind fails to
form an exact notion of a portion of space so immense; but some
faint idea of it may be obtained from the fact, that, if the
swiftest race-horse ever known had begun to traverse it, at full
speed, at the time of the birth of Moses, he would only as yet
have accomplished half his journey.
It has long been concluded amongst astronomers, that the
stars, though they only appear to our eyes as brilliant points,
are all to be considered as suns, representing so many solar
systems, each bearing a general resemblance to our own.  The
stars have a brilliancy and apparent magnitude which we may
safely presume to be in proportion to their actual size and the
distance at which they are placed from us.  Attempts have
been made to ascertain the distance of some of the stars by
calculations founded on parallax, it being previously understood
that, if a parallax of so much as one second, or the 3600th of a
degree, could be ascertained in any one instance, the distance
might be assumed in that instance as not less than 19,200
millions of miles!  In the case of the most brilliant star,
Sirius, even this minute parallax could not be found; from which
of course it was to be inferred that the distance of that star is
something beyond the vast distance which has been stated. 
In some others, on which the experiment has been tried, no
sensible parallax could be detected; from which the same
inference was to be made in their case.  But a sensible
parallax of about one second has been ascertained in the case of
the double star, α α, of the constellation of the
Centaur, [3] and one of the third of that amount for
the double star, 61 Cygni; which gave reason to presume that the
distance of the former might be about twenty thousand millions of
miles, and the latter of much greater amount.  If we suppose
that similar intervals exist between all the stars, we shall
readily see that the space occupied by even the comparatively
small number visible to the naked eye, must be vast beyond all
powers of conception.
The number visible to the eye is about three thousand; but
when a telescope of small power is directed to the heavens, a
great number more come into view, and the number is ever
increased in proportion to the increased power of the
instrument.  In one place, where they are more thickly sown
than elsewhere, Sir William Herschel reckoned that fifty thousand
passed over a field of view two degrees in breadth in a single
hour.  It was first surmised by the ancient philosopher,
Democritus, that the faintly white zone which spans the sky under
the name of the Milky Way, might be only a dense collection of
stars too remote to be distinguished.  This conjecture has
been verified by the instruments of modern astronomers, and some
speculations of a most remarkable kind have been formed in
connexion with it.  By the joint labours of the two
Herschels, the sky has been “gauged” in all
directions by the telescope, so as to ascertain the conditions of
different parts with respect to the frequency of the stars. 
The result has been a conviction that, as the planets are parts
of solar systems, so are solar systems parts of what may be
called astral systems—that is, systems composed of a
multitude of stars, bearing a certain relation to each
other.  The astral system to which we belong, is conceived
to be of an oblong, flattish form, with a space wholly or
comparatively vacant in the centre, while the extremity in one
direction parts into two.  The stars are most thickly sown
in the outer parts of this vast ring, and these constitute the
Milky Way.  Our sun is believed to be placed in the southern
portion of the ring, near its inner edge, so that we are
presented with many more stars, and see the Milky Way much more
clearly, in that direction, than towards the north, in which line
our eye has to traverse the vacant central space.  Nor is
this all.  Sir William Herschel, so early as 1783, detected
a motion in our solar system with respect to the stars, and
announced that it was tending towards the star λ, in the
constellation Hercules.  This has been generally verified by
recent and more exact calculations, [5] which fix on a point
in Hercules, near the star 143 of the 17th hour, according to
Piozzi’s catalogue, as that towards which our sun is
proceeding.  It is, therefore, receding from the inner edge
of the ring.  Motions of this kind, through such vast
regions of space, must be long in producing any change sensible
to the inhabitants of our planet, and it is not easy to grasp
their general character; but grounds have nevertheless been found
for supposing that not only our sun, but the other suns of the
system pursue a wavy course round the ring from west to
east, crossing and recrossing the middle of the annular
circle.  “Some stars will depart more, others less,
from either side of the circumference of equilibrium, according
to the places in which they are situated, and according to the
direction and the velocity with which they are put in
motion.  Our sun is probably one of those which depart
furthest from it, and descend furthest into the empty space
within the ring.” [6]  According to
this view, a time may come when we shall be much more in the
thick of the stars of our astral system than we are now, and have
of course much more brilliant nocturnal skies; but it may be
countless ages before the eyes which are to see this added
resplendence shall exist.
The evidence of the existence of other astral systems besides
our own is much more decided than might be expected, when we
consider that the nearest of them must needs be placed at a
mighty interval beyond our own.  The elder Herschel,
directing his wonderful tube towards the sides of our
system, where stars are planted most rarely, and raising the
powers of the instrument to the required pitch, was enabled with
awe-struck mind to see suspended in the vast empyrean astral
systems, or, as he called them, firmaments, resembling our
own.  Like light cloudlets to a certain power of the
telescope, they resolved themselves, under a greater power, into
stars, though these generally seemed no larger than the finest
particles of diamond dust.  The general forms of these
systems are various; but one at least has been detected as
bearing a striking resemblance to the supposed form of our
own.  The distances are also various, as proved by the
different degrees of telescopic power necessary to bring them
into view.  The farthest observed by the astronomer were
estimated by him as thirty-five thousand times more remote than
Sirius, supposing its distance to be about twenty thousand
millions of miles.  It would thus appear, that not only does
gravitation keep our earth in its place in the solar system, and
the solar system in its place in our astral system, but it also
may be presumed to have the mightier duty of preserving a local
arrangement between that astral system and an immensity of
others, through which the imagination is left to wander on and on
without limit or stay, save that which is given by its inability
to grasp the unbounded.
The two Herschels have in succession made some other most
remarkable observations on the regions of space.  They have
found within the limits of our astral system, and generally in
its outer fields, a great number of objects which, from their
foggy appearance, are called nebulæ; some of vast
extent and irregular figure, as that in the sword of Orion, which
is visible to the naked eye; others of shape more defined;
others, again, in which small bright nuclei appear here and there
over the surface.  Between this last form and another class
of objects, which appear as clusters of nuclei with nebulous
matter around each nucleus, there is but a step in what appears a
chain of related things.  Then, again, our astral space
shews what are called nebulous stars,—namely, luminous
spherical objects, bright in the centre and dull towards the
extremities.  These appear to be only an advanced condition
of the class of objects above described.  Finally, nebulous
stars exist in every stage of concentration, down to that state
in which we see only a common star with a slight bur
around it.  It may be presumed that all these are but stages
in a progress, just as if, seeing a child, a boy, a youth, a
middle-aged, and an old man together, we might presume that the
whole were only variations of one being.  Are we to suppose
that we have got a glimpse of the process through which a sun
goes between its original condition, as a mass of diffused
nebulous matter, and its full-formed state as a compact
body?  We shall see how far such an idea is supported by
other things known with regard to the occupants of space, and the
laws of matter.
A superficial view of the astronomy of the solar system gives
us only the idea of a vast luminous body (the sun) in the centre,
and a few smaller, though various sized bodies, revolving at
different distances around it; some of these, again, having
smaller planets (satellites) revolving around them.  There
are, however, some general features of the solar system, which,
when a profounder attention makes us acquainted with them, strike
the mind very forcibly.
It is, in the first place, remarkable, that the planets all
move nearly in one plane, corresponding with the centre of
the sun’s body.  Next, it is not less remarkable that
the motion of the sun on its axis, those of the planets around
the sun, and the satellites around their primaries, [9] and the motions of all on their axes,
are in one direction—namely, from west to
east.  Had all these matters been left to accident, the
chances against the uniformity which we find would have been,
though calculable, inconceivably great.  Laplace states them
at four millions of millions to one.  It is thus powerfully
impressed on us, that the uniformity of the motions, as well as
their general adjustment to one plane, must have been a
consequence of some cause acting throughout the whole system.
Some of the other relations of the bodies are not less
remarkable.  The primary planets shew a progressive increase
of bulk and diminution of density, from the one nearest to the
sun to that which is most distant.  With respect to density
alone, we find, taking water as a measure and counting it as one,
that Saturn is 13/32, or less than half; Jupiter, 1 1/24; Mars, 3
2/7; Earth, 4 1/2; Venus, 5 11/15; Mercury 9 9/10, or about the
weight of lead.  Then the distances are curiously
relative.  It has been found that if we place the following
line of numbers,—
0 3 6 12 24 48 96 192,
and add 4 to each, we shall have a series denoting the
respective distances of the planets from the sun.  It will
stand thus—


4

7

10

16

28

52

100

196



Merc.

Venus.

Earth.

Mars.

 

Jupiter.

Saturn.

Uranus.



It will be observed that the first row of figures goes on from
the second on the left hand in a succession of duplications, or
multiplications by 2.  Surely there is here a most
surprising proof of the unity which I am claiming for the solar
system.  It was remarked when this curious relation was
first detected, that there was a want of a planet corresponding
to 28; the difficulty was afterwards considered as in a great
measure overcome, by the discovery of four small planets
revolving at nearly one mean distance from the sun, between Mars
and Jupiter.  The distances bear an equally interesting
mathematical relation to the times of the revolutions round the
sun.  It has been found that, with respect to any two
planets, the squares of the times of revolution are to each other
in the same proportion as the cubes of their mean
distances,—a most surprising result, for the discovery of
which the world was indebted to the illustrious Kepler.  Sir
John Herschel truly observes—“When we contemplate the
constituents of the planetary system from the point of view which
this relation affords us, it is no longer mere analogy which
strikes us, no longer a general resemblance among them, as
individuals independent of each other, and circulating about the
sun, each according to its own peculiar nature, and connected
with it by its own peculiar tie.  The resemblance is now
perceived to be a true family likeness; they are bound up
in one chain—interwoven in one web of mutual relation and
harmonious agreement, subjected to one pervading influence which
extends from the centre to the farthest limits of that great
system, of which all of them, the Earth included, must henceforth
be regarded as members.” [12]
Connecting what has been observed of the series of nebulous
stars with this wonderful relationship seen to exist among the
constituents of our system, and further taking advantage of the
light afforded by the ascertained laws of matter, modern
astronomers have suggested the following hypothesis of the
formation of that system.
Of nebulous matter in its original state we know too little to
enable us to suggest how nuclei should be established in
it.  But, supposing that, from a peculiarity in its
constitution, nuclei are formed, we know very well how, by virtue
of the law of gravitation, the process of an aggregation of the
neighbouring matter to those nuclei should proceed, until masses
more or less solid should become detached from the rest.  It
is a well-known law in physics that, when fluid matter collects
towards or meets in a centre, it establishes a rotatory
motion.  See minor results of this law in the whirlwind and
the whirlpool—nay, on so humble a scale as the water
sinking through the aperture of a funnel.  It thus becomes
certain that when we arrive at the stage of a nebulous star, we
have a rotation on an axis commenced.
Now, mechanical philosophy informs us that, the instant a mass
begins to rotate, there is generated a tendency to fling off its
outer portions—in other words, the law of centrifugal force
begins to operate.  There are, then, two forces acting in
opposition to each other, the one attracting to, the other
throwing from, the centre.  While these remain
exactly counterpoised, the mass necessarily continues entire; but
the least excess of the centrifugal over the attractive force
would be attended with the effect of separating the mass and its
outer parts.  These outer parts would, then, be left as a
ring round the central body, which ring would continue to revolve
with the velocity possessed by the central mass at the moment of
separation, but not necessarily participating in any changes
afterwards undergone by that body.  This is a process which
might be repeated as soon as a new excess arose in the
centrifugal over the attractive forces working in the parent
mass.  It might, indeed, continue to be repeated, until the
mass attained the ultimate limits of the condensation which its
constitution imposed upon it.  From what cause might arise
the periodical occurrence of an excess of the centrifugal
force?  If we suppose the agglomeration of a nebulous mass
to be a process attended by refrigeration or cooling, which many
facts render likely, we can easily understand why the outer
parts, hardening under this process, might, by virtue of the
greater solidity thence acquired, begin to present some
resistance to the attractive force.  As the solidification
proceeded, this resistance would become greater, though there
would still be a tendency to adhere.  Meanwhile, the
condensation of the central mass would be going on, tending to
produce a separation from what may now be termed the
solidifying crust.  During the contention between the
attractions of these two bodies, or parts of one body, there
would probably be a ring of attenuation between the mass and its
crust.  At length, when the central mass had reached a
certain stage in its advance towards solidification, a separation
would take place, and the crust would become a detached
ring.  It is clear, of course, that some law presiding over
the refrigeration of heated gaseous bodies would determine the
stages at which rings were thus formed and detached.  We do
not know any such law, but what we have seen assures us it is one
observing and reducible to mathematical formulæ.
If these rings consisted of matter nearly uniform throughout,
they would probably continue each in its original form; but there
are many chances against their being uniform in
constitution.  The unavoidable effects of irregularity in
their constitution would be to cause them to gather towards
centres of superior solidity, by which the annular form would, of
course, be destroyed.  The ring would, in short, break into
several masses, the largest of which would be likely to attract
the lesser into itself.  The whole mass would then
necessarily settle into a spherical form by virtue of the law of
gravitation; in short, would then become a planet revolving round
the sun.  Its rotatory motion would, of course, continue,
and satellites might then be thrown off in turn from its body in
exactly the same way as the primary planets had been thrown off
from the sun.  The rule, if I can be allowed so to call it,
receives a striking support from what appear to be its
exceptions.  While there are many chances against the matter
of the rings being sufficiently equable to remain in the annular
form till they were consolidated, it might nevertheless be
otherwise in some instances; that is to say, the equableness
might, in those instances, be sufficiently great.  Such was
probably the case with the two rings around the body of Saturn,
which remain a living picture of the arrangement, if not the
condition, in which all the planetary masses at one time
stood.  It may also be admitted that, when a ring broke up,
it was possible that the fragments might spherify
separately.  Such seems to be the actual history of the ring
between Jupiter and Mars, in whose place we now find four planets
much beneath the smallest of the rest in size, and moving nearly
at the same distance from the sun, though in orbits so
elliptical, and of such different planes, that they keep
apart.
It has been seen that there are mathematical proportions in
the relative distances and revolutions of the planets of our
system.  It has also been suggested that the periods in the
condensation of the nebulous mass, at which rings were
disengaged, must have depended on some particular crises in the
condition of that mass, in connexion with the laws of centrifugal
force and attraction.  M. Compte, of Paris, has made some
approach to the verification of the hypothesis, by calculating
what ought to have been the rotation of the solar mass at the
successive times when its surface extended to the various
planetary orbits.  He ascertained that that rotation
corresponded in every case with the actual sidereal revolution of
the planets, and that the rotation of the primary planets
in like manner corresponded with the orbitual periods of the
secondaries.  The process by which he arrived at this
conclusion is not to be readily comprehended by the unlearned;
but those who are otherwise, allow that it is a powerful support
to the present hypothesis of the formation of the globes of
space. [17]
The nebular hypothesis, as it has been called, obtains a
remarkable support in what would at first seem to militate
against it—the existence in our firmament of several
thousands of solar systems, in which there are more than one
sun.  These are called double and triple stars.  Some
double stars, upon which careful observations have been made, are
found to have a regular revolutionary motion round each other in
ellipses.  This kind of solar system has also been observed
in what appears to be its rudimental state, for there are
examples of nebulous stars containing two and three nuclei in
near association.  At a certain point in the confluence of
the matter of these nebulous stars, they would all become
involved in a common revolutionary motion, linked inextricably
with each other, though it might be at sufficient distances to
allow of each distinct centre having afterwards its attendant
planets.  We have seen that the law which causes rotation in
the single solar masses, is exactly the same which produces the
familiar phenomenon of a small whirlpool or dimple in the surface
of a stream.  Such dimples are not always single.  Upon
the face of a river where there are various contending currents,
it may often be observed that two or more dimples are formed near
each other with more or less regularity.  These fantastic
eddies, which the musing poet will sometimes watch abstractedly
for an hour, little thinking of the law which produces and
connects them, are an illustration of the wonders of binary and
ternary solar systems.
The nebular hypothesis is, indeed, supported by so many
ascertained features of the celestial scenery, and by so many
calculations of exact science, that it is impossible for a candid
mind to refrain from giving it a cordial reception, if not to
repose full reliance upon it, even without seeking for it support
of any other kind.  Some other support I trust yet to bring
to it; but in the meantime, assuming its truth, let us see what
idea it gives of the constitution of what we term the universe,
of the development of its various parts, and of its original
condition.
Reverting to a former illustration—if we could suppose a
number of persons of various ages presented to the inspection of
an intelligent being newly introduced into the world, we cannot
doubt that he would soon become convinced that men had once been
boys, that boys had once been infants, and, finally, that all had
been brought into the world in exactly the same
circumstances.  Precisely thus, seeing in our astral system
many thousands of worlds in all stages of formation, from the
most rudimental to that immediately preceding the present
condition of those we deem perfect, it is unavoidable to conclude
that all the perfect have gone through the various stages which
we see in the rudimental.  This leads us at once to the
conclusion that the whole of our firmament was at one time a
diffused mass of nebulous matter, extending through the space
which it still occupies.  So also, of course, must have been
the other astral systems.  Indeed, we must presume the whole
to have been originally in one connected mass, the astral systems
being only the first division into parts, and solar systems the
second.
The first idea which all this impresses upon us is, that the
formation of bodies in space is still and at present in
progress.  We live at a time when many have been formed,
and many are still forming.  Our own solar system is to be
regarded as completed, supposing its perfection to consist in the
formation of a series of planets, for there are mathematical
reasons for concluding that Mercury is the nearest planet to the
sun, which can, according to the laws of the system, exist. 
But there are other solar systems within our astral system, which
are as yet in a less advanced state, and even some quantities of
nebulous matter which have scarcely begun to advance towards the
stellar form.  On the other hand, there are vast numbers of
stars which have all the appearance of being fully formed
systems, if we are to judge from the complete and definite
appearance which they present to our vision through the
telescope.  We have no means of judging of the seniority of
systems; but it is reasonable to suppose that, among the many,
some are older than ours.  There is, indeed, one piece of
evidence for the probability of the comparative youth of our
system, altogether apart from human traditions and the geognostic
appearances of the surface of our planet.  This consists in
a thin nebulous matter, which is diffused around the sun to
nearly the orbit of Mercury, of a very oblately spheroidal
shape.  This matter, which sometimes appears to our naked
eyes, at sunset, in the form of a cone projecting upwards in the
line of the sun’s path, and which bears the name of the
Zodiacal Light, has been thought a residuum or last remnant of
the concentrating matter of our system, and thus may be supposed
to indicate the comparative recentness of the principal events of
our cosmogony.  Supposing the surmise and inference to be
correct, and they may be held as so far supported by more
familiar evidence, we might with the more confidence speak of our
system as not amongst the elder born of Heaven, but one whose
various phenomena, physical and moral, as yet lay undeveloped,
while myriads of others were fully fashioned and in complete
arrangement.  Thus, in the sublime chronology to which we
are directing our inquiries, we first find ourselves called upon
to consider the globe which we inhabit as a child of the sun,
elder than Venus and her younger brother Mercury, but posterior
in date of birth to Mars, Jupiter, Saturn, and Uranus; next to
regard our whole system as probably of recent formation in
comparison with many of the stars of our firmament.  We
must, however, be on our guard against supposing the earth as a
recent globe in our ordinary conceptions of time.  From
evidence afterwards to be adduced, it will be seen that it cannot
be presumed to be less than many hundreds of centuries old. 
How much older Uranus may be no one can tell, much less how more
aged may be many of the stars of our firmament, or the stars of
other firmaments than ours.
Another and more important consideration arises from the
hypothesis; namely, as to the means by which the grand process is
conducted.  The nebulous matter collects around nuclei by
virtue of the law of attraction.  The agglomeration brings
into operation another physical law, by force of which the
separate masses of matter are either made to rotate singly, or,
in addition to that single motion, are set into a coupled
revolution in ellipses.  Next centrifugal force comes into
play, flinging off portions of the rotating masses, which become
spheres by virtue of the same law of attraction, and are held in
orbits of revolution round the central body by means of a
composition between the centrifugal and gravitating forces. 
All, we see, is done by certain laws of matter, so that it
becomes a question of extreme interest, what are such laws? 
All that can yet be said, in answer, is, that we see certain
natural events proceeding in an invariable order under certain
conditions, and thence infer the existence of some fundamental
arrangement which, for the bringing about of these events, has a
force and certainty of action similar to, but more precise and
unerring than those arrangements which human society makes for
its own benefit, and calls laws.  It is remarkable of
physical laws, that we see them operating on every kind of scale
as to magnitude, with the same regularity and perseverance. 
The tear that falls from childhood’s cheek is globular,
through the efficacy of that same law of mutual attraction of
particles which made the sun and planets round.  The
rapidity of Mercury is quicker than that of Saturn, for the same
reason that, when we wheel a ball round by a string and make the
string wind up round our fingers, the ball always flies quicker
and quicker as the string is shortened.  Two eddies in a
stream, as has been stated, fall into a mutual revolution at the
distance of a couple of inches, through the same cause which
makes a pair of suns link in mutual revolution at the distance of
millions of miles.  There is, we might say, a sublime
simplicity in this indifference of the grand regulations to the
vastness or minuteness of the field of their operation. 
Their being uniform, too, throughout space, as far as we can scan
it, and their being so unfailing in their tendency to operate, so
that only the proper conditions are presented, afford to our
minds matter for the gravest consideration.  Nor should it
escape our careful notice that the regulations on which all the
laws of matter operate, are established on a rigidly accurate
mathematical basis.  Proportions of numbers and geometrical
figures rest at the bottom of the whole.  All these
considerations, when the mind is thoroughly prepared for them,
tend to raise our ideas with respect to the character of physical
laws, even though we do not go a single step further in the
investigation.  But it is impossible for an intelligent mind
to stop there.  We advance from law to the cause of law, and
ask, What is that?  Whence have come all these beautiful
regulations?  Here science leaves us, but only to conclude,
from other grounds, that there is a First Cause to which all
others are secondary and ministrative, a primitive almighty will,
of which these laws are merely the mandates.  That great
Being, who shall say where is his dwelling-place, or what his
history!  Man pauses breathless at the contemplation of a
subject so much above his finite faculties, and only can wonder
and adore!</div></body></text></TEI>