<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="21"> 

NOVUM ORGANON RENOVATUM.

BOOK IV.
of the language of science.


Introduction.
IT has been shown in the History of the Sciences,
and has further appeared in the course of the
History of Ideas, that almost every step in the progress
of science is marked by the formation or appropriation
of a technical term. Common language has,
in most cases, a certain degree of looseness and ambiguity;
as common knowledge has usually something of
vagueness and indistinctness. In common cases too,
knowledge usually does not occupy the intellect alone,
but more or less interests some affection, or puts in
action the fancy; and common language, accommodating itself
to the office of expressing such knowledge, contains,
in every sentence, a tinge of emotion
or of imagination. But when our knowledge becomes
perfectly exact and purely intellectual, we require a
language which shall also be exact and intellectual;—which
shall exclude alike vagueness and fancy, imperfection
and superfluity;—in which each term shall
convey a meaning steadily fixed and rigorously limited.
Such a language that of science becomes, through the
use of Technical Terms. And we must now endeavour
to lay down some maxims and suggestions, by attention
to which Technical Terms may be better fitted to
answer their purpose. In order to do this, we shall in 258
the first place take a rapid survey of the manner in
which Technical Terms have been employed from the
earliest periods of scientific history.
The progress of the use of technical scientific language
offers to our notice two different and successive
periods; in the first of which, technical terms were
formed casually, as convenience in each case prompted;
while in the second period, technical language was
constructed intentionally, with set purpose, with a regard
to its connexion, and with a view of constructing a
system. Though the casual and the systematic formation
of technical terms cannot be separated by any
precise date of time, (for at all periods some terms in
some sciences have been framed unsystematically,) we
may, as a general description, call the former the Ancient
and the latter the Modern Period. In illustrating
the two following Aphorisms, I will give examples of
the course followed in each of these periods.
Aphorism I.
In the Ancient Period of Sciences, Technical Terms were
formed in three different ways:—by appropriating common
words and fixing their meaning;—by constructing terms
containing a description;—by constructing terms containing
reference to a theory.
The earliest sciences offer the earliest examples of
technical terms. These are Geometry, Arithmetic, and
Astronomy; to which we have soon after to add Harmonics,
Mechanics, and Optics. In these sciences, we
may notice the above-mentioned three different modes
in which technical terms were formed.
I. The simplest and first mode of acquiring technical
terms, is to take words current in common usage,
and by rigorously defining or otherwise fixing their
meaning, to fit them for the expression of scientific
truths. In this manner almost all the fundamental
technical terms of Geometry were formed. A sphere,
a cone, a cylinder, had among the Greeks, at first, 259
meanings less precise than those which geometers gave
to these words, and besides the mere designation of
form, implied some use or application. A sphere
(σφαῖρα) was a hand-ball used in games; a cone (κῶνος)
was a boy’s spinning-top, or the crest of a helmet; a
cylinder (κύλινδρος) was a roller; a cube (κύβος) was a
die: till these words were adopted by the geometers,
and made to signify among them pure modifications of
space. So an angle (γωνία) was only a corner; a point
(σημεῖον) was a signal; a line (γραμμὴ) was a mark; a
straight line (εὐθεῖα) was marked by an adjective which
at first meant only direct. A plane (ἐπίπεδον) is the
neuter form of an adjective, which by its derivation
means on the ground, and hence flat. In all these
cases, the word adopted as a term of science has its
sense rigorously fixed; and where the common use of
the term is in any degree vague, its meaning may be
modified at the same time that it is thus limited.
Thus a rhombus (ῥόμβος) by its derivation, might mean
any figure which is twisted out of a regular form; but
it is confined by geometers to that figure which has
four equal sides, its angles being oblique. In like
manner, a trapezium (τραπέζιον) originally signifies a
table, and thus might denote any form; but as the tables
of the Greeks had one side shorter than the opposite one, such a
figure was at first called a trapezium.
Afterwards the term was made to signify any figure
with four unequal sides; a name being more needful in
geometry for this kind of figure than for the original
form.
This class of technical terms, namely, words adopted
from common language, but rendered precise and
determinate for purposes of science, may also be
exemplified in other sciences. Thus, as was observed in the
early portion of the history of
astronomy1,
a day, a
month, a year, described at first portions of time marked
by familiar changes, but afterwards portions determined
by rigorous mathematical definitions. The conception
of the heavens as a revolving sphere, is so obvious, 260
that we may consider the terms which involve this
conception as parts of common language; as the pole
(πόλος); the arctic circle, which includes the stars that
never set2;
the horizon (ὁρίζων) a boundary, applied
technically to the circle bounding the visible earth
and sky. The turnings of the sun (τροπαὶ ἠελίοιο),
which are mentioned by Hesiod, gave occasion to the
term tropics, the circles at which the sun in his annual
motion turns back from his northward or southward
advance. The zones of the earth, (the torrid,
temperate, and frigid;) the gnomon of a dial; the limb (or
border) of the moon, or of a circular instrument, are
terms of the same class. An eclipse (ἔκλειψις) is
originally a deficiency or disappearance, and joined with
the name of the luminary, an eclipse of the sun or of
the moon, described the phenomenon; but when the
term became technical, it sufficed, without addition, to
designate the phenomenon.</div></body></text></TEI>