<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="119">CHAPTER V.
Progress towards a Natural System of
Botany.
WE have already said, that the
formation of a Natural System of classification must result from a
comparison of all the resemblances and differences of the
things classed; but that, in acting upon this maxim, the naturalist is
necessarily either guided by an obscure and instinctive feeling, which
is, in fact, an undeveloped recognition of physiological relations, or
else acknowledges physiology for his guide, though he is obliged to
assume arbitrary rules in order to interpret its indications. Thus all
Natural Classification of organized beings, either begins or soon ends
in Physiology; and can never advance far without the aid of that
science. Still, the progress of the Natural Method in botany went to
such a length before it was grounded entirely on the anatomy of
plants, that it will be proper, and I hope instructive, to attempt a
sketch of it here.
As I have already had occasion to remark, the earlier systems of
plants were natural; and they only ceased to be so, when it appeared
that the problem of constructing a system admitted of a very
useful solution, while the problem of devising a natural system
remained insoluble. But many botanists did not so easily renounce the
highest object of their science. In France, especially, a succession
of extraordinary men labored at it with no inconsiderable success: and
they were seconded by worthy fellow-laborers in Germany and
elsewhere.
The precept of taking into account all the parts of plants
according to their importance, may be applied according to arbitrary
rules. We may, for instance, assume that the fruit is the most
important part; or we may make a long list of parts, and look for
agreement in the greatest possible number of these, in order to
construct our natural orders. The former course was followed by
Gærtner;109 the latter by Adanson. Gærtner’s
principles, deduced from the dissection of more than a thousand kinds
of fruits,110 exercised, in the sequel, a great and
405 permanent
influence on the formation of natural classes. Adanson’s attempt, bold
and ingenious, belonged, both in time and character, to a somewhat
earlier stage of the subject.111 Enthusiastic
and laborious beyond belief but self-confident, and contemptuous of
the labors of others, Michael Adanson had collected, during five years
spent in Senegal, an enormous mass of knowledge and materials; and had
formed plans for the systems which he conceived himself thus empowered
to reach, far beyond the strength and the lot of man.112 In his Families of Plants,
however, all agree that his labors were of real value to the science.
The method which he followed is thus described by his eloquent and
philosophical eulogist.113
109 De Fructibus et Seminibus
Plantarum. Stuttg. 1788–1791.
110 Sprengel, ii. 290.
111 Familles des Plantes,
1763.
112 Cuvier’s Eloge.
113 Cuv. Eloges, tom. i. p.
282.
Considering each organ by itself, he formed, by pursuing its
various modifications, a system of division, in which he arranged all
known species according to that organ alone. Doing the same for
another organ, and another, and so for many, he constructed a
collection of systems of arrangement, each artificial,—each
founded upon one assumed organ. The species which come together in all
these systems are, of all, naturally the nearest to each other; those
which are separated in a few of the systems, but contiguous in the
greatest number, are naturally near to each other, though less near
than the former; those which are separated in a greater number, are
further removed from each other in nature; and they are the more
removed, the fewer are the systems in which they are associated.
Thus, by this method, we obtain the means of estimating precisely
the degree of natural affinity of all the species which our systems
include, independent of a physiological knowledge of the influence of
the organs. But the method has, Cuvier adds, the inconvenience of
presupposing another kind of knowledge, which, though it belongs only
to descriptive natural history, is no less difficult to
obtain;—the knowledge, namely, of all species, and of all the
organs of each. A single one neglected, may lead to relations the most
false; and Adanson himself, in spite of the immense number of his
observations, exemplifies this in some instances.
We may add, that in the division of the structure into organs, and
in the estimation of the gradations of these in each artificial
system, there is still room for arbitrary assumption.
In the mean time, the two Jussieus had presented to the world a
“Natural Method,” which produced a stronger impression than the 406 “Universal Method” of
Adanson. The first author of the system was Bernard de Jussieu, who
applied it in the arrangement of the garden of the Trianon, in 1759,
though he never published upon it. His nephew, Antoine Laurent de
Jussieu, in his Treatise of the Arrangement of the Trianon,114 gave an account of the principles and
orders of his uncle, which he adopted when he succeeded him; and, at a
later period, published his Genera Plantarum secundum Ordines
Naturales disposita; a work, says Cuvier, which perhaps forms as
important an epoch in the sciences of observation, as the
Chimie of Lavoisier does in the sciences of experiment. The
object of the Jussieus was to obtain a system which should be governed
by the natural affinities of the plants, while, at the same time, the
characters by which the orders were ostensibly determined, should be
as clear, simple, and precise, as those of the best artificial system.
The main points in these characters were the number of the cotyledons,
and the structure of the seed: and subordinate to this, the insertion
of the stamina, which they distinguished as epigynous,
perigynous, and hypogynous, according as they were
inserted over, about, or under, the germen. And the classes which were
formed by the Jussieus, though they have since been modified by
succeeding writers, have been so far retained by the most profound
botanists, notwithstanding all the new care and new light which have
been bestowed upon the subject, as to show that what was done at
first, was a real and important step in the solution of the
problem.
114 Mém. Ac. P. 1774.
The merit of the formation of this natural method of plants must be
divided between the two Jussieus. It has been common to speak of the
nephew, Antoine Laurent, as only the publisher of his uncle’s work.115 But this appears, from a recent
statement,116 to be highly unjust. Bernard left
nothing in writing but the catalogues of the garden of the Trianon,
which he had arranged according to his own views; but these catalogues
consist merely of a series of names without explanation or reason
added. The nephew, in 1773, undertook and executed for himself the
examination of a natural family, the Ranunculaceæ; and he was
wont to relate (as his son informs us) that it 407 was this employment
which first opened his eyes and rendered him a botanist. In the memoir
which he wrote, he explained fully the relative importance of the
characters of plants, and the subordination of some to
others;—an essential consideration, which Adanson’s scheme had
failed to take account of. The uncle died in 1777; and his nephew, in
speaking of him, compares his arrangement to the Ordines
Naturales of Linnæus: “Both these authors,” he says, “have
satisfied themselves with giving a catalogue of genera which approach
each other in different points, without explaining the motives which
induced them to place one order before another, or to arrange a genus
under a certain order. These two arrangements may be conceived as
problems which their authors have left for botanists to solve. Linnæus
published his; that of M. de Jussieu is only known by the manuscript
catalogues of the garden of the Trianon.”
115 Prodromus Floræ Penins. Ind.
Orient. Wight and Walker-Arnott, Introd. p. xxxv.
116 By Adrien de Jussieu, son of
Antoine Laurent, in the Annales des Sc. Nat., Nov. 1834.
It was not till the younger Jussieu had employed himself for
nineteen years upon botany, that he published, in 1789, his Genera
Plantarum; and by this time he had so entirely formed his scheme
in his head, that he began the impression without having written the
book, and the manuscript was never more than two pages in advance of
the printer’s type.
When this work appeared, it was not received with any enthusiasm;
indeed, at that time, the revolution of states absorbed the thoughts
of all Europe, and left men little leisure to attend to the
revolutions of science. The author himself was drawn into the vortex
of public affairs, and for some years forgot his book. The method made
its way slowly and with difficulty: it was a long time before it was
comprehended and adopted in France, although the botanists of that
country had, a little while before, been so eager in pursuit of a
natural system. In England and Germany, which had readily received the
Linnæan method, its progress was still more tardy.
There is only one point, on which it appears necessary further to
dwell. A main and fundamental distinction in all natural systems, is
that of the Monocotyledonous and Dicotyledonous plants; that is,
plants which unfold themselves from an embryo with two little leaves,
or with one leaf only. This distinction produces its effects in the
systems which are regulated by numbers; for the flowers and fruit of
the monocotyledons are generally referrible to some law in which the
number three prevails; a type which rarely occurs in
dicotyledons, these affecting most commonly an arrangement founded on
the number five. But it appears, when we attempt to rise
towards a natural 408 method, that this division according to
the cotyledons is of a higher order than the other divisions according
to number; and corresponds to a distinction in the general structure
and organization of the plant. The apprehension of the due rank of
this distinction has gradually grown clearer. Cuvier117 conceives that he finds such a
division clearly marked in Lobel, in 1581, and employed by Ray as the
basis of his classification a century later. This difference has had
its due place assigned it in more recent systems of arrangement; but
it is only later still that its full import has been distinctly
brought into view. Desfontaines discovered118 that the
ligneous fibre is developed in an opposite manner in vegetables with
one and with two cotyledons;—towards the inside in the former
case, and towards the outside in the latter; and hence these two great
classes have been since termed endogenous and exogenous.
~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~
117 Hist. Sc. Nat. ii.
197.
118 Hist. Sc. Nat. i. pp.
196, 290.
Thus this division, according to the cotyledons, appears to have
the stamp of reality put upon it, by acquiring a physiological
meaning. Yet we are not allowed to forget, even at this elevated point
of generalization, that no one character can be imperative in
a natural method. Lamarck, who employed his great talents on botany,
before he devoted himself exclusively to other branches of natural
history, published his views concerning methods, systems,119 and characters. His main principle is,
that no single part of a plant, however essential, can be an absolute
rule for classification; and hence he blames the Jussieuian method, as
giving this inadmissible authority to the cotyledons. Roscoe120 further urges that some plants, as
Orchis morio, and Limodorum verecundum, have no visible
cotyledons. Yet De Candolle, who labored along with Lamarck, in the
new edition of the Flore Française, has, as we have already
intimated, been led, by the most careful application of the wisest
principles, to a system of Natural Orders, of which Jussieu’s may be
looked upon as the basis; and we shall find the greatest botanists, up
to the most recent period, recognizing, and employing themselves in
improving, Jussieu’s Natural Families; so that in the progress of this
part of our knowledge, vague and perplexing as it is, we have no
exception to our general aphorism, that no real acquisition in science
is ever discarded.
119 Sprengel, ii. 296; and, there
quoted, Flore Française, t. i. 3, 1778. Mém. Ac. P.
1785. Journ. Hist. Nat. t. i. For Lamarck’s Méthode
Analytique, see Dumeril, Sc. Nat. i. Art. 390.
120 Roscoe, Linn. Tr. vol.
xi. Cuscuta also has no cotyledons.
409 The
reception of the system of Jussieu in this country was not so ready
and cordial as that of Linnæus. As we have already noticed, the two
systems were looked upon as rivals. Thus Roscoe, in 1810,121 endeavored to show that Jussieu’s
system was not more natural than the Linnæan, and was inferior as an
artificial system: but he argues his points as if Jussieu’s characters
were the grounds of his distribution; which, as we have said, is to
mistake the construction of a natural system. In 1803, Salisbury122 had already assailed the machinery of
the system, maintaining that there are no cases of perigynous stamens,
as Jussieu assumes; but this he urges with great expressions of
respect for the author of the method. And the more profound botanists
of England soon showed that they could appreciate and extend the
natural method. Robert Brown, who had accompanied Captain Flinders to
New Holland in 1801, and who, after examining that country, brought
home, in 1805, nearly four thousand species of plants, was the most
distinguished example of this. In his preface to the Prodromus
Floræ Novæ Hollandiæ, he says, that he found himself under the
necessity of employing the natural method, as the only way of avoiding
serious error, when he had to deal with so many new genera as occur in
New Holland; and that he has, therefore, followed the method of
Jussieu; the greater part of whose orders are truly natural, “although
their arrangement in classes, as is,” he says, “conceded by their
author, no less candid than learned, is often artificial, and, as
appears to me, rests on doubtful grounds.”
121 Linn. Tr. vol. xi. p.
50.
122 Ibid. vol. viii.
From what has already been said, the reader will, I trust, see what
an extensive and exact knowledge of the vegetable world, and what
comprehensive views of affinity, must be requisite in a person who has
to modify the natural system so as to make it suited to receive and
arrange a great number of new plants, extremely different from the
genera on which the arrangement was first formed, as the New Holland
genera for the most part were. He will also see how impossible it must
be to convey by extract or description any notion of the nature of
these modifications: it is enough to say, that they have excited the
applause of botanists wherever the science is studied, and that they
have induced M. de Humboldt and his fellow-laborers, themselves
botanists of the first rank, to dedicate one of their works to him in
terms of the strongest admiration.123 Mr. Brown has
also published 410
special disquisitions on parts of the Natural System; as on Jussieu’s
Proteaceæ;124 on the Asclepiadeæ, a natural
family of plants which must be separated from Jussieu’s
Apocyneæ;125 and other similar labors.
123 Roberto Brown, Britanniarum
gloriæ atque ornamento, totam Botanices scientiam ingenio mirifico
complectenti. &c.
124 Linn. Tr. vol. x.
1809.
125 Mem. of Wernerian N. H.
Soc. vol. i. 1809.
We have, I think, been led, by our survey of the history of Botany,
to this point;—that a Natural Method directs us to the study of
Physiology, as the only means by which we can reach the object. This
conviction, which in botany comes at the end of a long series of
attempts at classification, offers itself at once in the natural
history of animals, where the physiological signification of the
resemblances and differences is so much more obvious. I shall not,
therefore, consider any of these branches of natural history in detail
as examples of mere classification. They will come before us, if at
all, more properly when we consider the classifications which depend
on the functions of organs, and on the corresponding modifications
which they necessarily undergo; that is, when we trace the results of
Physiology. But before we proceed to sketch the history of that part
of our knowledge, there are a few points in the progress of Zoology,
understood as a mere classificatory science, which appear to me
sufficiently instructive to make it worth our while to dwell upon
them.
[2nd Ed.] [Mr. Lindley’s recent work, The Vegetable Kingdom
(1846), may be looked upon as containing the best view of the recent
history of Systematic Botany. In the Introduction to this work, Mr.
Lindley has given an account of various recent works on the subject;
as Agardh’s Classes Plantarum (1826); Perleb’s Lehrbuch der
Naturgeschichte der Pflanzenreich (1826); Dumortier’s Florula
Belgica (1827); Bartling’s Ordines Naturales Plantarum
(1830); Hess’s Uebersicht der Phanerogenischen Natürlichen
Pflanzenfamilien (1832); Schulz’s Natürliches System des
Pflanzenreich’s (1832); Horaninow’s Primæ Lineæ Systematis
Naturæ (1834); Fries’s Corpus Florarum provincialium Sueciæ
(1835); Martins’s Conspectus Regni Vegetablis secundum Characteres
Morphologicos (1835); Sir Edward F. Bromhead’s System, as
published in the Edinburgh Journal and other Journals
(1836–1840); Endlicher’s Genera Plantarum secundum Ordines
Naturales disposita (1836–1840); Perleb’s Clavis Classicum
Ordinum et Familiarum (1838); Adolphe Brongniart’s Enumération
des Genres de Plantes (1843); Meisner’s Plantarum vascularium
Genera secundum Ordines Naturales digesta (1843); Horaninow’s
Tetractys Naturæ, seu Systema quinquemembre omnium Naturalium
411 (1843); Adrien
de Jussieu’s Cours Elémentaire d’Histoire Naturelle.
Botanique (1844).
Mr. Lindley, in this as in all his works, urges strongly the
superior value of natural as compared with artificial systems; his
principles being, I think, nearly such as I have attempted to
establish in the Philosophy of the Sciences, Book viii.,
Chapter ii. He states that the leading idea which has been kept in
view in the compilation of his work is this maxim of Fries: “Singula
sphæra (sectio) ideam quandam exponit, indeque ejus character
notione simplici optime exprimitur;” and he is hence led to think that
the true characters of all natural assemblages are extremely
simple.
One of the leading features in Mr. Lindley’s system is that he has
thrown the Natural Orders into groups subordinate to the higher
divisions of Classes and Sub-classes. He had already attempted this,
in imitation of Agardh and Bartling, in his Nixus Plantarum
(1838). The groups of Natural Orders were there called Nixus
(tendencies); and they were denoted by names ending in ales;
but these groups were further subordinated to Cohorts. Thus the
first member of the arrangement was Class 1. Exogenæ. Sub-class 1. Polypetalæ. Cohort 1. Albuminosæ. Nixus 1. Ranales. Natural
Orders included in this Nixus, Ranunculaceæ, Saraceniceæ,
Papaveraceæ, &c. In the Vegetable Kingdom, the groups of
Natural Orders are termed Alliances. In this work, the
Sub-classes of the Exogens are four: i. Diclinous; ii.
Hypogynous; iii. Perigynous;  iv. Epigynous; and the Alliances are subordinated to
these without the intervention of Cohorts.
Mr. Lindley has also, in this as in other works, given English
names for the Natural Orders. Thus for Nymphaceæ,
Ranunculaceæ, Tamaricaceæ, Zygophyllaceæ,
Eleatrinaceæ, he substitutes Water-Lilies, Crowfoots,
Tamarisks, Bean-Capers, and Water-Peppers; for Malvaceæ,
Aurantiaceæ, Gentianaceæ, Primulaceæ,
Urtiaceæ, Euphorbiaceæ, he employs Mallow-worts,
Citron-worts, Gentian-worts, Prim-worts, Nettle-worts, Spurge-worts;
and the terms Orchids, Hippurids, Amaryllids, Irids, Typhads, Arads,
Cucurbits, are taken as English equivalents for Orchidaceæ,
Haloragaceæ, Amaryllidaceæ, Iridaceæ,
Typhaceæ, Araceæ, Cucurbitaceæ. All persons who
wish success to the study of botany in England must rejoice to see it
tend to assume this idiomatic shape.] 
~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~
412</div></body></text></TEI>