<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="12">CHAPTER XII
DIFFERENCE IN TEXTURE OF THE OLDER AND NEWER ROCKS.
Consolidation of fossiliferous strata—Some deposits originally solid—Transition
and slaty texture—Crystalline character of Plutonic and Metamorphic rocks—Theory
of their origin—Essentially subterranean—No proofs that they were
produced more abundantly at remote periods.
Another argument in favor of the dissimilarity of the causes operating
at remote and recent eras has been derived by many geologists from
the more compact, stony, and crystalline texture of the older as compared
with the newer rocks.
Consolidation of strata.—This subject may be considered, first in
reference to the fossiliferous strata; and, secondly, in reference to
those crystalline and stratified rocks which contain no organic remains,
such as gneiss and mica-schist. There can be no doubt that the former
of these classes, or the fossiliferous, are generally more compact and
stony in proportion as they are more ancient. It is also certain that a
great part of them were originally in a soft and incoherent state, and
that they have been since consolidated. Thus we find occasionally
that shingle and sand have been agglutinated firmly together by a ferruginous
or siliceous cement, or that lime in solution has been introduced,
so as to bind together materials previously incoherent. Organic
remains have sometimes suffered a singular transformation, as for
176
example, where shells, corals, and wood are silicified, their calcareous or
ligneous matter having been replaced by nearly pure silica. The constituents
of some beds have probably set and become hard for the first
time when they emerged from beneath the water.
But, on the other hand, we observe in certain formations now in progress,
particularly in coral reefs, and in deposits from the waters of
mineral springs, both calcareous and siliceous, that the texture of rocks
may sometimes be stony from the first. This circumstance may account
for exceptions to the general rule, not unfrequently met with,
where solid strata are superimposed on others of a plastic and incoherent
nature, as in the neighborhood of Paris, where the tertiary formations,
consisting often of compact limestone and siliceous grit, are more
stony than the subjacent chalk.
It will readily be understood, that the various solidifying causes, including
those above enumerated, together with the pressure of incumbent
rocks and the influence of subterranean heat, must all of them
require time in order to exert their full power. If in the course of ages
they modify the aspect and internal structure of stratified deposits, they
will give rise to a general distinctness of character in the older as contrasted
with the newer formations. But this distinctness will not be
the consequence of any original diversity; they will be unlike, just as
the wood in the older trees of a forest usually differs in texture and
hardness from that of younger individuals of the same species.
Transition texture.—In the original classification, of Werner, the
highly crystalline rocks, such as granite and gneiss, which contain no
organic remains, were called primary, and the fossiliferous strata secondary,
while to another class of an age intermediate between the
primary and secondary he gave the name of transition. They were
termed transition because they partook in some degree in their mineral
composition of the nature of the most crystalline rocks, such as gneiss
and mica-schist, while they resembled the fossiliferous series in containing
occasionally organic remains, and exhibiting evident signs of a mechanical
origin. It was at first imagined, that the rocks having this intermediate
texture had been all deposited subsequently to the series
called primary, and before all the more earthy and fossiliferous formations.
But when the relative position and organic remains of these
transition rocks were better understood, it was perceived that they did
not all belong to one period. On the contrary, the same mineral characters
were found in strata of very different ages, and some formations
occurring in the Alps, which several of the ablest scholars of Werner
had determined to be transition, were ultimately ascertained, by means
of their fossil contents and position, to be members of the Cretaceous,
and even of the nummulitic or Eocene period. These strata had, in
fact, acquired the transition texture from the influence of causes which,
since their deposition had modified their internal arrangement.
Texture and origin of Plutonic and metamorphic rocks.—Among the
most singular of the changes superinduced on rocks, we have occasionally
177
to include the slaty texture, the divisional planes of which sometimes
intersect the true planes of stratification, and even pass directly
through imbedded fossils. If, then, the crystalline, the slaty, and other
modes of arrangement, once deemed characteristic of certain periods in
the history of the earth, have in reality been assumed by fossiliferous
rocks of different ages and at different times, we are prepared to inquire
whether the same may not be true of the most highly crystalline state,
such as that of gneiss, mica-schist, and statuary marble. That the
peculiar characteristics of such rocks are really due to a variety of modifying
causes has long been suspected by many geologists, and the
doctrine has gained ground of late, although a considerable difference
of opinion still prevails. According to the original Neptunian theory,
all the crystalline formations were precipitated from a universal menstruum
or chaotic fluid antecedently to the creation of animals and
plants, the unstratified granite having been first thrown down so as to
serve as a floor or foundation on which gneiss and other stratified
rocks might repose. Afterwards, when the igneous origin of granite
was no longer disputed, many conceived that a thermal ocean enveloped
the globe, at a time when the first-formed crust of granite was
cooling, but when it still retained much of its heat. The hot waters
of this ocean held in solution the ingredients of gneiss, mica-schist,
hornblende-schist, clay-slate, and marble, rocks which were precipitated,
one after the other, in a crystalline form. No fossils could be
inclosed in them, the high temperature of the fluid and the quantity of
mineral matter which it held in solution, rendering it unfit for the support
of organic beings.
It would be inconsistent with the plan of this work to enter here into
a detailed account of what I have elsewhere termed the metamorphic
theory;256 but I may state that it is now demonstrable in some countries
that fossiliferous formations, some of them of the age of the Silurian
strata, as near Christiana in Norway, others belonging to the Oolitic
period, as around Carrara in Italy, have been converted partially into
gneiss, mica-schist, and statuary marble. The transmutation has been
effected apparently by the influence of subterranean heat, acting under
great pressure, or by chemical and electrical causes operating in a manner
not yet understood, and which have been termed Plutonic action,
as expressing, in one word, all the modifying causes which may be
brought into play at great depths, and under conditions never exemplified
at the surface. To this Plutonic action the fusion of granite itself
in the bowels of the earth, as well as the superinducement of the metamorphic
texture into sedimentary strata, must be attributed; and in
accordance with these views the age of each metamorphic formation
may be said to be twofold, for we have first to consider the period
when it originated, as an aqueous deposit, in the form of mud, sand,
marl, or limestone; secondly, the date at which it acquired a crystalline
178
texture. The same strata, therefore, may, according to this view,
be very ancient in reference to the time of their deposition, and very
modern in regard to the period of their assuming the metamorphic
character.
No proofs that these crystalline rocks were produced more abundantly
at remote periods.—Several modern writers, without denying the truth
of the Plutonic or metamorphic theory, still contend that the crystalline
and non-fossiliferous formations, whether stratified or unstratified, such
as gneiss and granite, are essentially ancient as a class of rocks. They
were generated, say they, most abundantly in the primeval state of
the globe, since which time the quantity produced has been always on
the decrease, until it became very inconsiderable in the Oolitic and Cretaceous
periods, and quite evanescent before the commencement of the
tertiary epoch.
Now the justness of these views depends almost entirely on the question
whether granite, gneiss, and other rocks of the same order ever
originated at the surface, or whether, according to the opinions above
adopted, they are essentially subterranean in their origin, and therefore
entitled to the appellation of hypogene. If they were formed superficially
in their present state, and as copiously in the modern as in the
more ancient periods, we ought to see a greater abundance of tertiary
and secondary than of primary granite and gneiss; but if we adopt the
hypogene theory before explained, their rapid diminution in volume
among the visible rocks in the earth's crust in proportion as we investigate
the formations of newer date, is quite intelligible. If a melted
mass of matter be now cooling very slowly at the depth of several
miles beneath the crater of an active volcano, it must remain invisible
until great revolutions in the earth's crust have been brought about.
So also if stratified rocks have been subjected to Plutonic action, and
after having been baked or reduced to semi-fusion, are now cooling and
crystallizing far under ground, it will probably require the lapse of
many periods before they will be forced up to the surface and exposed
to view, even at a single point. To effect this purpose there may be
need of as great a development of subterranean movement as that which
in the Alps, Andes, and Himalaya has raised marine strata containing
ammonites to the height of 8000, 14,000, and 16,000 feet. By parity
of reasoning we can hardly expect that any hypogene rocks of the
tertiary periods will have been brought within the reach of human
observation, seeing that the emergence of such rocks must always be so
long posterior to the date of their origin, and still less can formations
of this class become generally visible until so much time has elapsed as
to confer on them a high relative antiquity. Extensive denudation must
also combine with upheaval before they can be displayed at the surface
throughout wide areas.
All geologists who reflect on subterranean movements now going on,
and the eruptions of active volcanoes, are convinced that great changes
are now continually in progress in the interior of the earth's crust far out
179
of sight. They must be conscious, therefore, that the inaccessibility of
the regions in which these alterations are taking place, compels them to
remain in ignorance of a great part of the working of existing causes, so
that they can only form vague conjectures in regard to the nature of the
products which volcanic heat may elaborate under great pressure.
But when they find in mountain-chains of high antiquity, that what
was once the interior of the earth's crust has since been forced outwards
and exposed to view, they will naturally expect in the examination of
those mountainous regions, to have an opportunity of gratifying their
curiosity by obtaining a sight not only of the superficial strata of remote
eras, but also of the contemporaneous nether-formed rocks. Having
recognized, therefore, in such mountain-chains some ancient rocks of
aqueous and volcanic origin, corresponding in character to superficial
formations of modern date, they will regard any other class of ancient
rocks, such as granite and gneiss, as the residual phenomena of which
they are in search. These latter rocks will not answer the expectations
previously formed of their probable nature and texture, unless they wear
a foreign and mysterious aspect, and have in some places been fused or
altered by subterranean heat; in a word, unless they differ wholly from
the fossiliferous strata deposited at the surface, or from the lava and
scoriæ thrown out by volcanoes in the open air. It is the total distinctness,
therefore, of crystalline formations, such as granite, hornblende-schist,
and the rest, from every substance of which the origin is familiar
to us, that constitutes their claim to be regarded as the effects of causes
now in action in the subterranean regions. They belong not to an order
of things which has passed away; they are not the monuments of a
primeval period, bearing inscribed upon them in obsolete characters the
words and phrases of a dead language; but they teach us that part of
the living language of nature, which we cannot learn by our daily intercourse
with what passes on the habitable surface.

180</div></body></text></TEI>