<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="11"> 

NOVUM ORGANON RENOVATUM.

BOOK III.
OF METHODS EMPLOYED IN THE FORMATION OF SCIENCE.

CHAPTER I.
Introduction.


Aphorism XXVII.
The Methods by which the construction of Science is promoted are,
Methods of Observation, Methods of obtaining
clear Ideas, and Methods of Induction.

1. IN the
preceding Book, we pointed out certain
general Characters of scientific knowledge which
may often serve to distinguish it from opinions of a
looser or vaguer kind. In the course of the progress
of knowledge from the earliest to the present time, men
have been led to a perception, more or less clear, of
these characteristics. Various philosophers, from Plato
and Aristotle in the ancient world, to Richard de Saint
Victor and Roger Bacon in the middle ages, Galileo
and Gilbert, Francis Bacon and Isaac Newton, in modern
times, were led to offer precepts and maxims, as fitted
to guide us to a real and fundamental knowledge of
nature. It may on another occasion be our business
to estimate the value of these precepts and maxims.
And other contributions of the same kind to the philosophy
of science might be noticed, and some which 142
contain still more valuable suggestions, and indicate a
more practical acquaintance with the subject. Among
these, I must especially distinguish Sir John Herschel’s
Discourse on the Study of Natural Philosophy. But my
object at present is not to relate the history, but to
present the really valuable results of preceding labours: and
I shall endeavour to collect, both from them and from
my own researches and reflections, such views and
such rules as seem best adapted to assist us in the
discovery and recognition of scientific truth; or, at
least, such as may enable us to understand the process
by which this truth is obtained. I would present
to the reader the Philosophy and, if possible, the Art
of Discovery.
2. But, in truth, we must acknowledge, before we
proceed with this subject, that, speaking with strictness,
an Art of Discovery is not possible;—that we can
give no Rules for the pursuit of truth which shall be
universally and peremptorily applicable;—and that the
helps which we can offer to the inquirer in such cases
are limited and precarious. Still, we trust it will be
found that aids may be pointed out which are neither
worthless nor uninstructive. The mere classification
of examples of successful inquiry, to which our rules
give occasion, is full of interest for the philosophical
speculator. And if our maxims direct the discoverer
to no operations which might not have occurred to
his mind of themselves, they may still concentrate our
attention on that which is most important and characteristic
in these operations, and may direct us to
the best mode of insuring their success. I shall,
therefore, attempt to resolve the Process of Discovery
into its parts, and to give an account as distinct as
may be of Rules and Methods which belong to each
portion of the process.
3. In Book II. we considered the three main
parts of the process by which science is constructed:
namely, the Decomposition and Observation of Complex Facts;
the Explication of our Ideal Conceptions; and the
Colligation of Elementary Facts by
means of those Conceptions. The first and last of 143
these three steps are capable of receiving additional
accuracy by peculiar processes. They may further the
advance of science in a more effectual manner, when
directed by special technical Methods, of which in the
present Book we must give a brief view. In this more
technical form, the observation of facts involves the
Measurement of Phenomena; and the Colligation of
Facts includes all arts and rules by which the process
of Induction can be assisted. Hence we shall have
here to consider Methods of Observation, and Methods
of Induction, using these phrases in the widest sense.
The second of the three steps above mentioned, the
Explication of our Conceptions, does not admit of being
much assisted by methods, although something may
be done by Education and Discussion.
4. The Methods of Induction, of which we have to
speak, apply only to the first step in our ascent from
phenomena to laws of nature;—the discovery of Laws
of Phenomena. A higher and ulterior step remains
behind, and follows in natural order the discovery of
Laws of Phenomena; namely, the Discovery of Causes;
and this must be stated as a distinct and essential process
in a complete view of the course of science. Again,
when we have thus ascended to the causes of phenomena and
of their laws, we can often reason downwards from the cause
so discovered; and we are thus
led to suggestions of new phenomena, or to new explanations
of phenomena already known. Such proceedings may be termed
Applications of our Discoveries;
including in the phrase, Verifications of our Doctrines
by such an application of them to observed facts.
Hence we have the following series of processes concerned
in the formation of science.
  (1.) Decomposition of Facts;
  (2.) Measurement of Phenomena;
  (3.) Explication of Conceptions;
  (4.) Induction of Laws of Phenomena;
  (5.) Induction of Causes;
  (6.) Application of Inductive Discoveries.
5. Of these six processes, the methods by which
the second and fourth may be assisted are here our 144
peculiar object of attention. The treatment of these
subjects in the present work must necessarily be scanty
and imperfect, although we may perhaps be able to add
something to what has hitherto been systematically
taught on these heads. Methods of Observation and
of Induction might of themselves form an abundant
subject for a treatise, and hereafter probably will do
so, in the hands of future writers. A few remarks,
offered as contributions to this subject, may serve to
show how extensive it is, and how much more ready
it now is than it ever before was, for a systematic discussion.
Of the above steps of the formation of science, the
first, the Decomposition of Facts, has already been
sufficiently explained in the last Book: for if we
pursue it into further detail and exactitude, we find
that we gradually trench upon some of the succeeding
parts. I, therefore, proceed to treat of the second
step, the Measurement of Phenomena;—of Methods
by which this work, in its widest sense, is executed,
and these I shall term Methods of Observation.</div></body></text></TEI>