<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="36">CHAPTER IV.
Sequel to the Epoch of Newton,
continued.—Verification and Completion of the Newtonian
Theory.

Sect. 1.—Division of the
Subject.
THE verification of the Law of
Universal Gravitation as the governing principle of all cosmical
phenomena, led, as we have already stated, to a number of different
lines of research, all long and difficult. Of these we may treat
successively, the motions of the Moon, of the Sun, of the Planets, of
the Satellites, of Comets; we may also consider separately the Secular
Inequalities, which at first sight appear to follow a different law
from the other changes; we may then speak of the results of the
principle as they affect this Earth, in its Figure, in the amount of
Gravity at different places, and in the phenomena of the Tides. Each
of these subjects has lent its aid to confirm the general law: but in
each the confirmation has had its peculiar difficulties, and has its
separate history. Our sketch of this history must be very rapid, for
our aim is only to show what is the kind and course of the
confirmation which such a theory demands and receives.
For the same reason we pass over many events of this period which
are highly important in the history of astronomy. They have lost much
of their interest for us, and even for common readers, because they
are of a class with which we are already familiar, truths included in
more general truths to which our eyes now most readily turn. Thus, the
discovery of new satellites and planets is but a repetition of what
was done by Galileo: the determination of their nodes and apses, the
reduction of their motions to the law of the ellipse, is but a fresh
exemplification of the discoveries of Kepler. Otherwise, the formation
of Tables of the satellites of Jupiter and Saturn, the discovery of
the eccentricities of the orbits, and of the motions of the nodes and
apses, by Cassini, Halley, and others, would rank with the great
achievements in astronomy. Newton’s peculiar advance in the
Tables of the celestial motions is the introduction of
Perturbations. To these motions, so affected, we now proceed. 434
Sect. 2.—Application of the Newtonian Theory to
the Moon.
The Motions of the Moon may be first spoken
of, as the most obvious and the most important of the applications of
the Newtonian Theory. The verification of such a theory consists, as
we have seen in previous cases, in the construction of Tables derived
from the theory, and the comparison of these with observation. The
advancement of astronomy would alone have been a sufficient motive for
this labor; but there were other reasons which urged it on with a
stronger impulse. A perfect Lunar Theory, if the theory could be
perfected, promised to supply a method of finding the Longitude of any
place on the earth’s surface; and thus the verification of a theory
which professed to be complete in its foundations, was identified with
an object of immediate practical use to navigators and geographers,
and of vast acknowledged value. A good method for the near discovery
of the longitude had been estimated by nations and princes at large
sums of money. The Dutch were willing to tempt Galileo to this task by
the offer of a chain of gold: Philip the Third of Spain had promised a
reward for this object still earlier;63 the parliament
of England, in 1714, proposed a recompense of 20,000l.
sterling; the Regent Duke of Orléans, two years afterwards, offered
100,000 francs for the same purpose. These prizes, added to the love
of truth and of fame, kept this object constantly before the eyes of
mathematicians, during the first half of the last century.
63 Del. A. M. i. 39, 66.
If the Tables could be so constructed as to represent the moon’s
real place in the heavens with extreme precision, as it would be seen
from a standard observatory, the observation of her apparent
place, as seen from any other point of the earth’s surface, would
enable the observer to find his longitude from the standard point. The
motions of the moon had hitherto so ill agreed with the best Tables,
that this method failed altogether. Newton had discovered the ground
of this want of agreement. He had shown that the same force which
produces the Evection, Variation, and Annual Equation, must produce
also a long series of other Inequalities, of various magnitudes and
cycles, which perpetually drag the moon before or behind the place
where she would be sought by an astronomer who knew only of those
principal and notorious inequalities. But to calculate and apply the
new inequalities, was no slight undertaking. 435
In the first edition of the Principia in 1687, Newton had
not given any calculations of new inequalities affecting the longitude
of the moon. But in David Gregory’s Elements of Physical and
Geometrical Astronomy, published in 1702, is inserted64 “Newton’s Lunar Theory as applied by
him to Practice;” in which the great discoverer has given the results
of his calculations of eight of the lunar Equations, their quantities,
epochs, and periods. These calculations were for a long period the
basis of new Tables of the Moon, which were published by various
persons;65 as by Delisle in 1715 or 1716,
Grammatici at Ingoldstadt in 1726, Wright in 1732, Angelo Capelli at
Venice in 1733, Dunthorne at Cambridge in 1739.
64 P. 332.
65 Lalande, 1457.
Flamsteed had given Tables of the Moon upon Horrox’s theory in
1681, and wished to improve them; and though, as we have seen, he
would not, or could not, accept Newton’s doctrines in their whole
extent, Newton communicated his theory to the observer in the shape in
which he could understand it and use it:66 and Flamsteed
employed these directions in constructing new Lunar Tables, which he
called his Theory.67 These Tables were not published till
long after his death, by Le Monnier at Paris in 1746. They are said,
by Lalande,68 not to differ much from Halley’s.
Halley’s Tables of the Moon were printed in 1719 or 1720, but not
published till after his death in 1749. They had been founded on
Flamsteed’s observations and his own; and when, in 1720, Halley
succeeded Flamsteed in the post of Astronomer Royal at Greenwich, and
conceived that he had the means of much improving what he had done
before, he began by printing what he had already executed.69
66 Baily. Account of Flamsteed,
p. 72.
67 P. 211.
68 Lal. 1459.
69 Mr. Baily* says that Mayer’s
Nouvelles Tables de la Lune in 1753, published upwards of fifty
years after Gregory’s Astronomy, may be considered as the first
lunar tables formed solely on Newton’s principles. Though
Wright in 1732 published New and Correct Tables of the Lunar
Motions according to the Newtonian Theory, Newton’s rules were in
them only partially adopted. In 1735 Leadbetter published his
Uranoscopia, in which those rules were more fully followed. But
these Newtonian Tables did not supersede Flamsteed’s Horroxian
Tables, till both were supplanted by those of Mayer.
*Supp. p. 702.
But Halley had long proposed a method, different from that of
Newton, but marked by great ingenuity, for amending the Lunar Tables.
He proposed to do this by the use of a cycle, which we have mentioned
as one of the earliest discoveries in astronomy;—the Period of
223 lunations, or eighteen years and eleven days, the Chaldean 436 Saros. This period
was anciently used for predicting the eclipses of the sun and moon;
for those eclipses which happen during this period, are repeated again
in the same order, and with nearly the same circumstances, after the
expiration of one such period and the commencement of a second. The
reason of this is, that at the end of such a cycle, the moon is in
nearly the same position with respect to the sun, her nodes, and her
apogee, as she was at first; and is only a few degrees distant from
the same part of the heavens. But on the strength of this
consideration, Halley conjectured that all the irregularities of the
moon’s motion, however complex they may be, would recur after such an
interval; and that, therefore, if the requisite corrections were
determined by observation for one such period, we might by means of
them give accuracy to the Tables for all succeeding periods. This idea
occurred to him before he was acquainted with Newton’s views.70 After the lunar theory of the
Principia had appeared, he could not help seeing that the idea
was confirmed; for the inequalities of the moon’s motion, which arise
from the attraction of the sun, will depend on her positions with
regard to the sun, the apogee, and the node; and therefore, however
numerous, will recur when these positions recur.
70 Phil. Trans. 1731, p.
188.
Halley announced, in 1691,71 his intention of
following this idea into practice; in a paper in which he corrected
the text of three passages in Pliny, in which this period is
mentioned, and from which it is sometimes called the Plinian period.
In 1710, in the preface to a new edition to Street’s Caroline
Tables, he stated that he had already confirmed it to a
considerable extent.72 And even after Newton’s theory had been
applied, he still resolved to use his cycle as a means of obtaining
further accuracy. On succeeding to the Observatory at Greenwich in
1720, he was further delayed by finding that the instruments had
belonged to Flamsteed, and were removed by his executors. “And this,”
he says,73 “was the more grievous to me, on
account of my advanced age, being then in my sixty-fourth year: which
put me past all hopes of ever living to see a complete period of
eighteen years’ observation. But, thanks to God, he has been pleased
hitherto (in 1731) to afford me sufficient health and strength to
execute my office, in all its parts, with my own hands and eyes,
without any assistance or interruption, during one whole period of the
moon’s 437 apogee,
which period is performed in somewhat less than nine years.” He found
the agreement very remarkable, and conceived hopes of attaining the
great object, of finding the Longitude with the requisite degree of
exactness; nor did he give up his labors on this subject till he had
completed his Plinian period in 1739.
71 Ib. p. 536.
72 Ib. 1731, p. 187.
73 Ib. p. 193.
The accuracy with which Halley conceived himself able to predict
the moon’s place74 was within two minutes of space, or one
fifteenth of the breadth of the moon herself. The accuracy required
for obtaining the national reward was considerably greater. Le Monnier
pursued the idea of Halley.75 But before Halley’s method had been
completed, it was superseded by the more direct prosecution of
Newton’s views.
74 Phil. Trans. 1731, p.
195.
75 Bailly, A. M. c. 131.
We have already remarked, in the history of analytical mechanics,
that in the Lunar Theory, considered as one of the cases of the
Problem of Three Bodies, no advance was made beyond what Newton had
done, till mathematicians threw aside the Newtonian artifices, and
applied the newly developed generalizations of the analytical method.
The first great apparent deficiency in the agreement of the law of
universal gravitation with astronomical observation, was removed by
Clairaut’s improved approximation to the theoretical Motion of the
Moon’s Apogee, in 1750; yet not till it had caused so much
disquietude, that Clairaut himself had suggested a modification of the
law of attraction; and it was only in tracing the consequences of this
suggestion, that he found the Newtonian law of the inverse square to
be that which, when rightly developed, agreed with the facts. Euler
solved the problem by the aid of his analysis in 1745,76 and published Tables of the Moon in
1746. His tables were not very accurate at first;77 but he,
D’Alembert, and Clairaut, continued to labor at this object, and the
two latter published Tables of the Moon in 1754.78 Finally, Tobias
Mayer, an astronomer of Göttingen, having compared Euler’s tables with
observations, corrected them so successfully, that in 1753 he
published Tables of the Moon, which really did possess the accuracy
which Halley only flattered himself that he had attained. Mayer’s
success in his first Tables encouraged him to make them still more
perfect. He applied himself to the mechanical theory of the moon’s
orbit; corrected all the coefficients of the series by a great number
of observations; and in 1755, sent his new Tables to London as worthy
to claim the prize offered for the discovery of longitude. He died
soon after 438 (in
1762), at the early age of thirty-nine, worn out by his incessant
labors; and his widow sent to London a copy of his Tables with
additional corrections. These Tables were committed to Bradley, then
Astronomer Royal, in order to be compared with observation. Bradley
labored at this task with unremitting zeal and industry, having
himself long entertained hopes that the Lunar Method of finding the
Longitude might be brought into general use. He and his assistant,
Gael Morris, introduced corrections into Mayer’s Tables of 1755. In
his report of 1756, he says,79 that he did not
find any difference so great as a minute and a quarter; and in 1760,
he adds, that this deviation had been further diminished by his
corrections. It is not foreign to our purpose to observe the great
labor which this verification required. Not less than 1220
observations, and long calculations founded upon each, were employed.
The accuracy which Mayer’s Tables possessed was considered to entitle
them to a part of the parliamentary reward; they were printed in 1770,
and his widow received 3000l. from the English nation. At the
same time, Euler, whose Tables had been the origin and foundation of
Mayer’s, also had a recompense of the same amount.
76 Lal. 1460.
77 Bradley’s Correspondence.
78 Lal. 1460.
79 Bradley’s Mem. p.
xcviii.
This public national acknowledgment of the practical accuracy of
these Tables is, it will be observed, also a solemn recognition of the
truth of the Newtonian theory, as far as truth can be judged of by men
acting under the highest official responsibility, and aided by the
most complete command of the resources of the skill and talents of
others. The finding the Longitude is thus the seal of the moon’s
gravitation to the sun and earth; and with this occurrence, therefore,
our main concern with the history of the Lunar Theory ends. Various
improvements have been since introduced into this research; but on
these we, with so many other subjects before us, must forbear to
enter.
Sect. 3.—Application of the Newtonian Theory to
the Planets, Satellites, and Earth.
The theories of the Planets and Satellites,
as affected by the law of universal gravitation, and therefore by
perturbations, were naturally subjects of interest, after the
promulgation of that law. Some of the effects of the mutual attraction
of the planets had, indeed, already attracted notice. The inequality
produced by the mutual attraction of Jupiter and Saturn cannot be
overlooked by a good observer. In the 439 preface to the second edition of the
Principia, Cotes remarks,80 that the
perturbation of Jupiter and Saturn is not unknown to astronomers. In
Halley’s Tables it was noticed81 that there are
very great deviations from regularity in these two planets, and these
deviations are ascribed to the perturbing force of the planets on each
other; but the correction of these by a suitable equation is left to
succeeding astronomers.
80 Preface to Principia, p.
xxi.
81 End of Planetary Tables.
The motion of the planes and apsides of the planetary orbits was
one of the first results of their mutual perturbation which was
observed. In 1706, La Hire and Maraldi compared Jupiter with the
Rudolphine Tables, and those of Bullialdus: it appeared that his
aphelion had advanced, and that his nodes had regressed. In 1728, J.
Cassini found that Saturn’s aphelion had in like manner travelled
forwards. In 1720, when Louville refused to allow in his solar tables
the motion of the aphelion of the earth, Fontenelle observed that this
was a misplaced scrupulousness, since the aphelion of Mercury
certainly advances. Yet this reluctance to admit change and
irregularity was not yet overcome. When astronomers had found an
approximate and apparent constancy and regularity, they were willing
to believe it absolute and exact. In the satellites of Jupiter, for
instance, they were unwilling to admit even the eccentricity of the
orbits; and still more, the variation of the nodes, inclinations, and
apsides. But all the fixedness of these was successively disproved.
Fontenelle in 1732, on the occasion of Maraldi’s discovery of the
change of inclination of the fourth satellite, expresses a suspicion
that all the elements might prove liable to change. “We see,” says he,
“the constancy of the inclination already shaken in the three first
satellites, and the eccentricity in the fourth. The immobility of the
nodes holds out so far, but there are strong indications that it will
share the same fate.”
The motions of the nodes and apsides of the satellites are a
necessary part of the Newtonian theory; and even the Cartesian
astronomers now required only data, in order to introduce these
changes into their Tables.
The complete reformation of the Tables of the Sun, Planets, and
Satellites, which followed as a natural consequence from the
revolution which Newton had introduced, was rendered possible by the
labors of the great constellation of mathematicians of whom we have
spoken in the last book, Clairaut, Euler, D’Alembert, and their
successors; and 440
it was carried into effect in the course of the last century. Thus
Lalande applied Clairaut’s theory to Mars, as did Mayer; and the
inequalities in this case, says Bailly82 in 1785, may
amount to two minutes, and therefore must not be neglected. Lalande
determined the inequalities of Venus, as did Father Walmesley, an
English mathematician; these were found to reach only to thirty
seconds.
82 Ast. Mod. iii. 170.
The Planetary Tables83 which were in highest repute, up to the
end of the last century, were those of Lalande. In these, the
perturbations of Jupiter and Saturn were introduced, their magnitude
being such that they cannot be dispensed with; but the Tables of
Mercury, Venus, and Mars, had no perturbations. Hence these latter
Tables might be considered as accurate enough to enable the observer
to find the object, but not to test the theory of perturbations. But
when the calculation of the mutual disturbances of the planets was
applied, it was always found that it enabled mathematicians to bring
the theoretical places to coincide more exactly with those observed.
In improving, as much as possible, this coincidence, it is necessary
to determine the mass of each planet; for upon that, according to the
law of universal gravitation, its disturbing power depends. Thus, in
1813, Lindenau published Tables of Mercury, and concluded, from them,
that a considerable increase of the supposed mass of Venus was
necessary to reconcile theory with observation.84 He had published
Tables of Venus in 1810, and of Mars in 1811. And, in proving
Bouvard’s Tables of Jupiter and Saturn, values were obtained of the
masses of those planets. The form in which the question of the truth
of the doctrine of universal gravitation now offers itself to the
minds of astronomers, is this:—that it is taken for granted that
it will account for the motions of the heavenly bodies, and the
question is, with what supposed masses it will give the best
account.85 The continually increasing accuracy of
the table shows the truth of the fundamental assumption.
83 Airy, Report on Ast. to Brit.
Ass. 1832.
84 Airy, Report on Ast. to Brit.
Ass.
1832.
85 Among the most important
corrections of the supposed masses of the planets, we may notice that
of Jupiter, by Professor Airy.  This determination of Jupiter’s mass
was founded, not on the effect as seen in perturbations, but on a much
more direct datum, the time of revolution of his fourth satellite. It
appeared, from this calculation, that Jupiter’s mass required to be
increased by about 1⁄80th. This result agrees
with that which has been derived by German astronomers from the
perturbations which the attractions of Jupiter produce in the four new
planets, and has been generally adopted as an improvement of the
elements of our system.
The question of perturbation is exemplified in the satellites also.
441 Thus the
satellites of Jupiter are not only disturbed by the sun, as the moon
is, but also by each other, as the planets are. This mutual action
gives rise to some very curious relations among their motions; which,
like most of the other leading inequalities, were forced upon the
notice of astronomers by observation before they were obtained by
mathematical calculation. In Bradley’s remarks upon his own Tables of
Jupiter’s Satellites, published among Halley’s Tables, he observes
that the places of the three interior satellites are affected by
errors which recur in a cycle of 437 days, answering to the time in
which they return to the same relative position with regard to each
other, and to the axis of Jupiter’s shadow. Wargentin, who had noticed
the same circumstance without knowledge of what Bradley had done,
applied it, with all diligence, to the purpose of improving the tables
of the satellites in 1746. But, at a later period, Laplace
established, by mathematical reasoning, the very curious theorem on
which this cycle depends, which he calls the libration of Jupiter’s
satellites; and Delambre was then able to publish Tables of
Jupiter’s Satellites more accurate than those of Wargentin, which he
did in 1789.86
86 Voiron, Hist. Ast. p.
322.
The progress of physical astronomy from the time of Euler and
Clairaut, has consisted of a series of calculations and comparisons of
the most abstruse and recondite kind. The formation of Tables of the
Planets and Satellites from the theory, required the solution of
problems much more complex than the original case of the Problem of
Three Bodies. The real motions of the planets and their orbits are
rendered still further intricate by this, that all the lines and
points to which we can refer them, are themselves in motion. The task
of carrying order and law into this mass of apparent confusion, has
required a long series of men of transcendent intellectual powers; and
a perseverance and delicacy of observation, such as we have not the
smallest example of in any other subject. It is impossible here to
give any detailed account of these labors; but we may mention one
instance of the complex considerations which enter into them. The
nodes of Jupiter’s fourth satellite do not go backwards,87 as the Newtonian theory seems to
require; they advance upon Jupiter’s orbit. But then, it is to be
recollected that the theory requires the nodes to retrograde upon the
orbit of the perturbing body, which is here the third satellite; and
Lalande showed that, by the necessary relations of space, the latter
motion may be retrograde though the former is direct.
87 Bailly, iii. 175.
442 Attempts
have been made, from the time of the solution of the Problem of three
bodies to the present, to give the greatest possible accuracy to the
Tables of the Sun, by considering the effect of the various
perturbations to which the earth is subject. Thus, in 1756, Euler
calculated the effect of the attractions of the planets on the earth
(the prize-question of the French Academy of Sciences), and Clairaut
soon after. Lacaille, making use of these results, and of his own
numerous observations, published Tables of the Sun. In 1786,
Delambre88 undertook to verify and improve these
tables, by comparing them with 314 observations made by Maskelyne, at
Greenwich, in 1775 and 1784, and in some of the intermediate years. He
corrected most of the elements; but he could not remove the
uncertainty which occurred respecting the amount of the inequality
produced by the reaction of the moon. He admitted also, in pursuance
of Clairaut’s theory, a second term of this inequality depending on
the moon’s latitude; but irresolutely, and half disposed to reject it
on the authority of the observations. Succeeding researches of
mathematicians have shown, that this term is not admissible as a
result of mechanical principles. Delambre’s Tables, thus improved,
were exact to seven or eight seconds;89 which was
thought, and truly, a very close coincidence for the time. But
astronomers were far from resting content with this. In 1806, the
French Board of Longitude published Delambre’s improved Solar Tables;
and in the Connaissance des Tems for 1816, Burckhardt gave the
results of a comparison of Delambre’s Tables with a great number of
Maskelyne’s observations;—far greater than the number on which
they were founded.90 It appeared that the epoch, the
perigee, and the eccentricity, required sensible alterations, and that
the mass of Venus ought to be reduced about one-ninth, and that of the
Moon to be sensibly diminished. In 1827, Professor Airy91 compared Delambre’s tables with 2000
Greenwich observations, made with the new transit-instrument at
Cambridge, and deduced from this comparison the correction of the
elements. These in general agreed closely with Burckhardt’s, excepting
that a diminution of Mars appeared necessary. Some discordances,
however, led Professor Airy to suspect the existence of an inequality
which had escaped the sagacity of Laplace and Burckhardt. And, a few
weeks after this suspicion had been expressed, the same mathematician
announced to the Royal Society that he had 443 detected, in the planetary theory such
an inequality, hitherto unnoticed, arising from the mutual attraction
of Venus and the Earth. Its whole effect on the earth’s longitude,
would be to increase or diminish it by nearly three seconds of space,
and its period is about 240 years. “This term,” he adds, “accounts
completely for the difference of the secular motions given by the
comparison of the epochs of 1783 and 1821, and by that of the epochs
of 1801 and 1821.”
88 Voiron, Hist. p. 315.
89 Montucla, iv. 42.
90 Airy, Report, p. 150.
91 Phil. Trans. 1828.
Many excellent Tables of the motions of the sun, moon, and planets,
were published in the latter part of the last century; but the Bureau
des Longitudes which was established in France in 1795, endeavored to
give new or improved tables of most of these motions. Thus were
produced Delambre’s Tables of the Sun, Burg’s Tables of the Moon,
Bouvard’s Tables of Jupiter, Saturn, and Uranus. The agreement between
these and observation is, in general, truly marvellous.
We may notice here a difference in the mode of referring to
observation when a theory is first established, and when it is
afterwards to be confirmed and corrected. It was remarked as a merit
in the method of Hipparchus, and an evidence of the mathematical
coherence of his theory, that in order to determine the place of the
sun’s apogee, and the eccentricity of his orbit, he required to know
nothing besides the lengths of winter and spring. But if the fewness
of the requisite data is a beauty in the first fixation of a theory,
the multitude of observations to which it applies is its excellence
when it is established; and in correcting Tables, mathematicians take
far more data than would be requisite to determine the elements. For
the theory ought to account for all the facts: and since it
will not do this with mathematical rigor (for observation is not
perfect), the elements are determined, not so as to satisfy any
selected observations, but so as to make the whole mass of error as
small as possible. And thus, in the adaptation of theory to
observation, even in its most advanced state, there is room for
sagacity and skill, prudence and judgment.
In this manner, by selecting the best mean elements of the motions
of the heavenly bodies, the observed motions deviate from this mean in
the way the theory points out, and constantly return to it. To this
general rule, of the constant return to a mean, there are, however,
some apparent exceptions, of which we shall now speak. ~Additional
material in the 3rd edition.~ 444
Sect. 4.—Application of the Newtonian Theory to
Secular Inequalities.
Secular Inequalities in the motions of the
heavenly bodies occur in consequence of changes in the elements of the
solar system, which go on progressively from age to age. The example
of such changes which was first studied by astronomers, was the
Acceleration of the Moon’s Mean Motion, discovered by Halley. The
observed fact was, that the moon now moves in a very small degree
quicker than she did in the earlier ages of the world. When this was
ascertained, the various hypotheses which appeared likely to account
for the fact were reduced to calculation. The resistance of the medium
in which the heavenly bodies move was the most obvious of these
hypotheses. Another, which was for some time dwelt upon by Laplace,
was the successive transmission of gravity, that is, the hypothesis
that the gravity of the earth takes a certain finite time to reach the
moon. But none of these suppositions gave satisfactory conclusions;
and the strength of Euler, D’Alembert, Lagrange, and Laplace, was for
a time foiled by this difficulty. At length, in 1787, Laplace
announced to the Academy that he had discovered the true cause of this
acceleration, and that it arose from the action of the sun upon the
moon, combined with the secular variation of the eccentricity of the
earth’s orbit. It was found that the effects of this combination would
exactly account for the changes which had hitherto so perplexed
mathematicians. A very remarkable result of this investigation was,
that “this Secular Inequality of the motion of the moon is periodical,
but it requires millions of years to re-establish itself;” so that
after an almost inconceivable time, the acceleration will become a
retardation. Laplace some time after (in 1797), announced other
discoveries, relative to the secular motions of the apogee and the
nodes of the moon’s orbit. Laplace collected these researches in his
“Theory of the Moon,” which he published in the third volume of the
Mécanique Céleste in 1802.
A similar case occurred with regard to an acceleration of Jupiter’s
mean motion, and a retardation of Saturn’s, which had been observed by
Cassini, Maraldi, and Horrox. After several imperfect attempts by
other mathematicians, Laplace, in 1787, found that there resulted from
the mutual attraction of these two planets a great Inequality, of
which the period is 929 years and a half, and which has accelerated
Jupiter and retarded Saturn ever since the restoration of astronomy.
445
Thus the secular inequalities of the celestial motions, like all
the others, confirm the law of universal gravitation. They are called
“secular,” because ages are requisite to unfold their existence, and
because they are not obviously periodical. They might, in some
measure, be considered as extensions of the Newtonian theory, for
though Newton’s law accounts for such facts, he did not, so far as we
know, foresee such a result of it. But on the other hand, they are
exactly of the same nature as those which he did foresee and
calculate. And when we call them secular in opposition to
periodical, it is not that there is any real difference, for
they, too, have their cycle; but it is that we have assumed our
mean motion without allowing for these long inequalities. And
thus, as Laplace observes on this very occasion,92 the lot of this
great discovery of gravitation is no less than this, that every
apparent exception becomes a proof, every difficulty a new occasion of
a triumph. And such, as he truly adds, is the character of a true
theory,—of a real representation of nature.
92 Syst. du Monde, 8vo, ii.
37.
It is impossible for us here to enumerate even the principal
objects which have thus filled the triumphal march of the Newtonian
theory from its outset up to the present time. But among these secular
changes, we may mention the Diminution of the Obliquity of the
Ecliptic, which has been going on from the earliest times to the
present. This change has been explained by theory, and shown to have,
like all the other changes of the system, a limit, after which the
diminution will be converted into an increase.
We may mention here some subjects of a kind somewhat different from
those just spoken of. The true theoretical quantity of the Precession
of the Equinoxes, which had been erroneously calculated by Newton, was
shown by D’Alembert to agree with observation. The constant
coincidence of the Nodes of the Moon’s Equator with those of her
Orbit, was proved to result from mechanical principles by Lagrange.
The curious circumstance that the Time of the Moon’s rotation on her
axis is equal to the Time of her revolution about the earth, was shown
to be consistent with the results of the laws of motion by Laplace.
Laplace also, as we have seen, explained certain remarkable relations
which constantly connect the longitudes of the three first satellites
of Jupiter; Bailly and Lagrange analyzed and explained the curious
librations of the nodes and inclinations of their orbits; and Laplace
traced the effect of Jupiter’s oblate figure on their motions, 446 which masks the other
causes of inequality, by determining the direction of the motions of
the perijove and node of each satellite.
Sect. 5.—Application of the Newtonian
Theory to the New Planets.
We are now so accustomed to consider the
Newtonian theory as true, that we can hardly imagine to ourselves the
possibility that those planets which were not discovered when the
theory was founded, should contradict its doctrines. We can scarcely
conceive it possible that Uranus or Ceres should have been found to
violate Kepler’s laws, or to move without suffering perturbations from
Jupiter and Saturn. Yet if we can suppose men to have had any doubt of
the exact and universal truth of the doctrine of universal
gravitation, at the period of these discoveries, they must have
scrutinized the motions of these new bodies with an interest far more
lively than that with which we now look for the predicted return of a
comet. The solid establishment of the Newtonian theory is thus shown
by the manner in which we take it for granted not only in our
reasonings, but in our feelings. But though this is so, a short notice
of the process by which the new planets were brought within the domain
of the theory may properly find a place here.
William Herschel, a man of great energy and ingenuity, who had made
material improvements in reflecting telescopes, observing at Bath on
the 13th of March, 1781, discovered, in the constellation Gemini, a
star larger and less luminous than the fixed stars. On the application
of a more powerful telescope, it was seen magnified, and two days
afterwards he perceived that it had changed its place. The attention
of the astronomical world was directed to this new object, and the
best astronomers in every part of Europe employed themselves in
following it along the sky.93
93 Voiron, Hist. Ast. p.
12.
The admission of an eighth planet into the long-established list,
was a notion so foreign to men’s thoughts at that time, that other
suppositions were first tried. The orbit of the new body was at first
calculated as if it had been a comet running in a parabolic path. But
in a few days the star deviated from the course thus assigned it: and
it was in vain that in order to represent the observations, the
perihelion distance of the parabola was increased from fourteen to
eighteen times the earth’s distance from the sun. Saron, of the
Academy of Sciences of Paris, is said94 to have been the
first person who perceived that the 447 places were better represented by a
circle than by a parabola: and Lexell, a celebrated mathematician of
Petersburg, found that a motion in a circular orbit, with a radius
double of that of Saturn, would satisfy all the observations. This
made its period about eighty-two years.
94 Ibid.
Lalande soon discovered that the circular motion was subject to a
sensible inequality: the orbit was, in fact, an ellipse, like those of
the other planets. To determine the equation of the centre of a body
which revolves so slowly, would, according to the ancient methods,
have required many years; but Laplace contrived methods by which the
elliptical elements were determined from four observations, within
little more than a year from its first discovery by Herschel. These
calculations were soon followed by tables of the new planet, published
by Nouet.
In order to obtain additional accuracy, it now became necessary to
take account of the perturbations. The French Academy of Sciences
proposed, in 1789, the construction of new Tables of this Planet as
its prize-question. It is a curious illustration of the constantly
accumulating evidence of the theory, that the calculation of the
perturbations of the planet enabled astronomers to discover that it
had been observed as a star in three different positions in former
times; namely, by Flamsteed in 1690, by Mayer in 1756, and by Le
Monnier in 1769. Delambre, aided by this discovery and by the theory
of Laplace, calculated Tables of the planet, which, being compared
with observation for three years, never deviated from it more than
seven seconds. The Academy awarded its prize to these Tables, they
were adopted by the astronomers of Europe, and the planet of Herschel
now conforms to the laws of attraction, along with those ancient
members of the known system from which the theory was inferred.
The history of the discovery of the other new planets, Ceres,
Pallas, Juno, and Vesta, is nearly similar to that just related,
except that their planetary character was more readily believed. The
first of these was discovered on the first day of this century by
Piazzi, the astronomer at Palermo; but he had only begun to suspect
its nature, and had not completed his third observation, when his
labors were suspended by a dangerous illness; and on his recovery the
star was invisible, being lost in the rays of the sun.
He declared it to be a planet with an elliptical orbit; but the
path which it followed, on emerging from the neighborhood of the sun,
was not that which Piazzi had traced out for it. Its extreme smallness
made it difficult to rediscover; and the whole of the year 1801 was
448 employed in
searching the sky for it in vain. At last, after many trials, Von Zach
and Olbers again found it, the one on the last day of 1801, the other
on the first day of 1802. Gauss and Burckhardt immediately used the
new observations in determining the elements of the orbit; and the
former invented a new method for the purpose. Ceres now moves in a
path of which the course and inequalities are known, and can no more
escape the scrutiny of astronomers.
The second year of the nineteenth century also produced its planet.
This was discovered by Dr. Olbers, a physician of Bremen, while he was
searching for Ceres among the stars of the constellation Virgo. He
found a star which had a perceptible motion even in the space of two
hours. It was soon announced as a new planet, and received from its
discoverer the name of Pallas. As in the case of Ceres, Burckhardt and
Gauss employed themselves in calculating its orbit. But some peculiar
difficulties here occurred. Its eccentricity is greater than that of
any of the old planets, and the inclination of its orbit to the
ecliptic is not less than thirty-five degrees. These circumstances
both made its perturbations large, and rendered them difficult to
calculate. Burckhardt employed the known processes of analysis, but
they were found insufficient: and the Imperial Institute (as the
French Academy was termed during the reign of Napoleon) proposed the
Perturbations of Pallas as a prize-question.
To these discoveries succeeded others of the same kind. The German
astronomers agreed to examine the whole of the zone in which Ceres and
Pallas move; in the hope of finding other planets, fragments, as
Olbers conceived they might possibly be, of one original mass. In the
course of this research, Mr. Harding of Lilienthal, on the first of
September, 1804, found a new star, which he soon was led to consider
as a planet. Gauss and Burckhardt also calculated the elements of this
orbit, and the planet was named Juno.
After this discovery, Olbers sought the sky for additional
fragments of his planet with extraordinary perseverance. He conceived
that one of two opposite constellations, the Virgin or the Whale, was
the place where its separation must have taken place; and where,
therefore, all the orbits of all the portions must pass. He resolved
to survey, three times a year, all the small stars in these two
regions. This undertaking, so curious in its nature, was successful.
The 29th of March, 1807, he discovered Vesta, which was soon found to
be a planet. And to show the manner in which Olbers pursued his
labors, we may state that he afterwards published a notification that
he had examined the 449 same parts of the heavens with such
regularity, that he was certain no new planet had passed that way
between 1808 and 1816. Gauss and Burckhardt computed the orbit of
Vesta; and when Gauss compared one of his orbits with twenty-two
observations of M. Bouvard, he found the errors below seventeen
seconds of space in right ascension, and still less in
declination.
The elements of all these orbits have been successively improved,
and this has been done entirely by the German mathematicians.95 These perturbations are calculated, and
the places for some time before and after opposition are now given in
the Berlin Ephemeris. “I have lately observed,” says Professor Airy,
“and compared with the Berlin Ephemeris, the right ascensions of Juno
and Vesta, and I find that they are rather more accurate than those of
Venus:” so complete is the confirmation of the theory by these new
bodies; so exact are the methods of tracing the theory to its
consequences.
95 Airy, Rep. 157.
We may observe that all these new-discovered bodies have received
names taken from the ancient mythology. In the case of the first of
these, astronomers were originally divided; the discoverer himself
named it the Georgium Sidus, in honor of his patron, George the
Third; Lalande and others called it Herschel. Nothing can be
more just than this mode of perpetuating the fame of the author of a
discovery; but it was felt to be ungraceful to violate the homogeneity
of the ancient system of names. Astronomers tried to find for the
hitherto neglected denizen of the skies, an appropriate place among
the deities to whose assembly he was at last admitted; and
Uranus, the father of Saturn, was fixed upon as best suiting
the order of the course.
The mythological nomenclature of planets appeared, from this time,
to be generally agreed to. Piazzi termed his Ceres Ferdinandea.
The first term, which contains a happy allusion to Sicily, the country
of the discovery in modern, and of the goddess in ancient, times, has
been accepted; the attempt to pay a compliment to royalty out of the
products of science, in this as in most other cases, has been set
aside. Pallas, Juno, and Vesta, were named, without any peculiar
propriety of selection, according to the choice of their discoverers.
~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~
Sect. 6.—Application of the Newtonian Theory to
Comets.
A few words must be said upon another class
of bodies, which at first seemed as lawless as the clouds and winds;
and which astronomy 450 has reduced to a regularity as complete
as that of the sun;—upon Comets. No part of the Newtonian
discoveries excited a more intense interest than this. These anomalous
visitants were anciently gazed at with wonder and alarm; and might
still, as in former times, be accused of “perplexing nations,” though
with very different fears and questionings. The conjecture that they,
too, obeyed the law of universal gravitation, was to be verified by
showing that they described a curve such as that force would produce.
Hevelius, who was a most diligent observer of these objects, had,
without reference to gravitation, satisfied himself that they moved in
parabolas.96 To determine the elements of the
parabola from observations, even Newton called97 “problema longe
difficillimum.” Newton determined the orbit of the comet of 1680 by
certain graphical methods. His methods supposed the orbit to be a
parabola, and satisfactorily represented the motion in the visible
part of the comet’s path. But this method did not apply to the
possible return of the wandering star. Halley has the glory of having
first detected a periodical comet, in the case of that which has since
borne his name. But this great discovery was not made without labor.
In 1705, Halley98 explained how the parabolic orbit of a
planet may be determined from three observations; and, joining example
to precept, himself calculated the positions and orbits of twenty-four
comets. He found, as the reward of this industry, that the comets of
1607 and of 1531 had the same orbit as that of 1682. And here the
intervals are also nearly the same, namely, about seventy-five years.
Are the three comets then identical? In looking back into the history
of such appearances, he found comets recorded in 1456, in 1380, and in
1305; the intervals are still the same, seventy-five or seventy-six
years. It was impossible now to doubt that they were the periods of a
revolving body; that the comet was a planet; its orbit a long ellipse,
not a parabola.99
96 Bailly, ii. 246.
97 Principia, ed. 1. p.
494.
98 Bailly, ii. 646.
99 The importance of Halley’s labors
on Comets has always been acknowledged. In speaking of Halley’s
Synopsis Astronomicæ Cometicæ, Delambre says (Ast.
xviii. Siècle, p. 130), “Voilà bien, depuis Kepler, ce qu’on a
fait de plus grand, de plus beau, de plus neuf en astronomie.” Halley,
in predicting the comet of 1758, says, if it returns, “Hoc primum ab
homine Anglo iuventum fuisse non inficiabitur æqua posteritas.”
But if this were so, the Comet must reappear in 1758 or 1759.
Halley predicted that it would do so; and the fulfilment of this
prediction was naturally looked forwards to, as an additional stamp of
the truths of the theory of gravitation. 451
But in all this, the Comet had been supposed to be affected only by
the attraction of the sun. The planets must disturb its motion as they
disturb each other. How would this disturbance affect the time and
circumstances of its reappearance? Halley had proposed, but not
attempted to solve, this question.
The effect of perturbations upon a comet defeats all known methods
of approximation, and requires immense labor. “Clairaut,” says
Bailly,100 “undertook this: with courage enough
to dare the adventure, he had talent enough to obtain a memorable
victory;” the difficulties, the labors, grew upon him as he advanced,
but he fought his way through them, assisted by Lalande, and by a
female calculator, Madame Lepaute. He predicted that the comet would
reach its perihelion April 13, 1759, but claimed the license of a
month for the inevitable inaccuracy of a calculation which, in
addition to all other sources of error, was made in haste, that it
might appear as a prediction. The comet justified his calculations and
his caution together; for it arrived at its perihelion on the 13th of
March.
100 Bailly, A. M. iii.
190.
Two other Comets, of much shorter period, have been detected of
late years; Encke’s, which revolves round the sun in three years and
one-third, and Biela’s which describes an ellipse, not extremely
eccentric, in six years and three-quarters. These bodies, apparently
thin and vaporous masses, like other comets, have, since their orbits
were calculated, punctually conformed to the law of gravitation. If it
were still doubtful whether the more conspicuous comets do so, these
bodies would tend to prove the fact, by showing it to be true in an
intermediate case.
[2d Ed.] [A third Comet of short period was discovered by Faye, at
the Observatory of Paris, Nov. 22, 1843. It is included between the
orbits of Mars and Saturn, and its period is seven years and
three-tenths.
This is commonly called Faye’s Comet, as the two mentioned
in the text are called Encke’s and Biela’s. In the
former edition I had expressed my assent to the rule proposed by M.
Arago, that the latter ought to be called Gambart’s Comet, in
honor of the astronomer who first proved it to revolve round the Sun.
But astronomers in general have used the former name, considering that
the discovery and observation of the object are more distinct and
conspicuous merits than a calculation founded upon the observations of
others. And in reality 452 Biela had great merit in the discovery
of his Comet’s periodicity, having set about his search of it from an
anticipation of its return founded upon former observations.
Also a Comet was discovered by De Vico at Rome on Aug. 22, 1844,
which was found to describe an elliptical orbit having its aphelion
near the orbit of Jupiter, which is consequently one of those of short
period. And on Feb. 26, 1846, M. Brorsen of Kiel discovered a
telescopic Comet whose orbit is found to be elliptical.]
We may add to the history of Comets, that of Lexell’s, which, in
1770, appeared to be revolving in a period of about five years, and
whose motion was predicted accordingly. The prediction was
disappointed; but the failure was sufficiently explained by the
comet’s having passed close to Jupiter, by which occurrence its orbit
was utterly deranged.
It results from the theory of universal gravitation, that Comets
are collections of extremely attenuated matter. Lexell’s is supposed
to have passed twice (in 1767 and 1779) through the system of
Jupiter’s Satellites, without disturbing their motions, though
suffering itself so great a disturbance as to have its orbit entirely
altered. The same result is still more decidedly proved by the last
appearance of Biela’s Comet. It appeared double, but the two bodies
did not perceptibly affect each other’s motions, as I am informed by
Professor Challis of Cambridge, who observed both of them from Jan. 23
to Mar. 25, 1846. This proves the quantity of matter in each body to
have been exceedingly small.
Thus, no verification of the Newtonian theory, which was possible
in the motions of the stars, has yet been wanting. The return of
Halley’s Comet again in 1835, and the extreme exactitude with which it
conformed to its predicted course, is a testimony of truth, which must
appear striking even to the most incurious respecting such matters.101
101 M. de Humboldt (Kosmos, p.
116) speaks of nine returns of Halley’s Comet, the comet
observed in China in 1378 being identified with this. But whether we
take 1378 or 1380 for the appearance in that century, if we begin with
that, we have only seven appearances, namely, in 1378 or
1380, in 1456, in 1531, in 1607, in 1682, in 1759, and in 1835.
Sect. 7.—Application of the Newtonian
Theory to the Figure of the Earth.
The Heavens had thus been consulted
respecting the Newtonian doctrine, and the answer given, over and over
again, in a thousand 453 different forms, had been, that it was
true; nor had the most persevering cross-examination been able to
establish any thing of contradiction or prevarication. The same
question was also to be put to the Earth and the Ocean, and we must
briefly notice the result.
According to the Newtonian principles, the form of the earth must
be a globe somewhat flattened at the poles. This conclusion, or at
least the amount of the flattening, depends not only upon the
existence and law of attraction, but upon its belonging to each
particle of the mass separately; and thus the experimental
confirmation of the form asserted from calculation, would be a
verification of the theory in its widest sense. The application of
such a test was the more necessary to the interests of science,
inasmuch as the French astronomers had collected from their measures,
and had connected with their Cartesian system, the opinion that the
earth was not oblate but oblong. Dominic Cassini had
measured seven degrees of latitude from Amiens to Perpignan, in 1701,
and found them to decrease in going from south to north. The
prolongation of this measure to Dunkirk confirmed the same result. But
if the Newtonian doctrine was true, the contrary ought to be the case,
and the degrees ought to increase in proceeding towards the pole.
The only answer which the Newtonians could at this time make to the
difficulty thus presented, was, that an arc so short as that thus
measured, was not to be depended upon for the determination of such a
question; inasmuch as the inevitable errors of observation might
exceed the differences which were the object of research. It would,
undoubtedly, have become the English to have given a more complete
answer, by executing measurements under circumstances not liable to
this uncertainty. The glory of doing this, however, they for a long
time abandoned to other nations. The French undertook the task with
great spirit.102 In 1733, in one of the meetings of the
French Academy, when this question was discussed, De la Condamine, an
ardent and eager man, proposed to settle this question by sending
members of the Academy to measure a degree of the meridian near the
equator, in order to compare it with the French degrees, and offered
himself for the expedition. Maupertuis, in like manner, urged the
necessity of another expedition to measure a degree in the
neighborhood of the pole. The government received the applications
favorably, and these remarkable scientific missions were sent out at
the national expense.
102 Bailly, iii. 11.
454 As soon as
the result of these measurements was known, there was no longer any
doubt as to the fact of the earth’s oblateness, and the question only
turned upon its quantity. Even before the return of the academicians,
the Cassinis and Lacaille had measured the French arc, and found
errors which subverted the former result, making the earth oblate to
the amount of 1⁄168th of its diameter. The
expeditions to Peru and to Lapland had to struggle with difficulties
in the execution of their design, which make their narratives resemble
some romantic history of irregular warfare, rather than the monotonous
records of mere measurements. The equatorial degree employed the
observers not less than eight years. When they did return, and the
results were compared, their discrepancy, as to quantity, was
considerable. The comparison of the Peruvian and French arcs gave an
ellipticity of nearly 1⁄314th, that of the Peruvian
and Swedish arcs gave 1⁄213th for its value.
Newton had deduced from his theory, by reasonings of singular
ingenuity, an ellipticity of 1⁄230th; but this result had
been obtained by supposing the earth homogeneous. If the earth be, as
we should most readily conjecture it to be, more dense in its interior
than at its exterior, its ellipticity will be less than that of a
homogeneous spheroid revolving in the same time. It does not appear
that Newton was aware of this; but Clairaut, in 1743, in his Figure
of the Earth, proved this and many other important results of the
attraction of the particles. Especially he established that, in
proportion as the fraction expressing the Ellipticity becomes smaller,
that expressing the Excess of the polar over the equatorial gravity
becomes larger; and he thus connected the measures of the ellipticity
obtained by means of Degrees, with those obtained by means of
Pendulums in different latitudes.
The altered rate of a Pendulum when carried towards the equator,
had been long ago observed by Richer and Halley, and had been quoted
by Newton as confirmatory of his theory. Pendulums were swung by the
academicians who measured the degrees, and confirmed the general
character of the results.
But having reached this point of the verification of the Newtonian
theory, any additional step becomes more difficult. Many excellent
measures, both of Degrees and of Pendulums, have been made since those
just mentioned. The results of the Arcs103 is an
Ellipticity of 1⁄298th;—of the
Pendulums, an Ellipticity of about 1⁄285th. This difference 455 is considerable, if
compared with the quantities themselves; but does not throw a shadow
of doubt on the truth of the theory. Indeed, the observations of each
kind exhibit irregularities which we may easily account for, by
ascribing them to the unknown distribution of the denser portions of
the earth; but which preclude the extreme of accuracy and certainty in
our result.
103 Airy, Fig. Earth, p.
230.
But the near agreement of the determination, from Degrees and from
Pendulums, is not the only coincidence by which the doctrine is
confirmed. We can trace the effect of the earth’s Oblateness in
certain minute apparent motions of the stars; for the attraction of
the sun and moon on the protuberant matter of the spheroid produces
the Precession of the equinoxes, and a Nutation of the earth’s axis.
The Precession had been known from the time of Hipparchus, and the
existence of Nutation was foreseen by Newton; but the quantity is so
small, that it required consummate skill and great labor in Bradley to
detect it by astronomical observation. Being, however, so detected,
its amount, as well as that of the Precession, gives us the means of
determining the amount of Terrestrial Ellipticity, by which the effect
is produced. But it is found, upon calculation, that we cannot obtain
this determination without assuming some law of density in the
homogeneous strata of which we suppose the earth to consist104 The density will certainly increase in
proceeding towards the centre, and there is a simple and probable law
of this increase, which will give 1⁄300th for the Ellipticity,
from the amount of two lunar Inequalities (one in latitude and one in
longitude), which are produced by the earth’s oblateness. Nearly the
same result follows from the quantity of Nutation. Thus every thing
tends to convince us that the ellipticity cannot deviate much from
this fraction.
104 Airy, Fig. Earth, p.
235.
[2d Ed.] [I ought not to omit another class of phenomena in which
the effects of the Earth’s Oblateness, acting according to the law of
universal gravitation, have manifested themselves;—I speak of
the Moon’s Motion, as affected by the Earth’s Ellipticity. In this
case, as in most others, observation anticipated theory. Mason had
inferred from lunar observations a certain Inequality in Longitude,
depending upon the distance of the Moon’s Node from the Equinox.
Doubts were entertained by astronomers whether this inequality really
existed; but Laplace showed that such an inequality would arise from
the oblate form of the earth; and that its magnitude might serve to
456 determine the
amount of the oblateness. Laplace showed, at the same time, that along
with this Inequality in Longitude there must be an Inequality in
Latitude; and this assertion Burg confirmed by the discussion of
observations. The two Inequalities, as shown in the observations,
agree in assigning to the earth’s form an Ellipticity of 1⁄305th.]
Sect. 8.—Confirmation of the Newtonian Theory by
Experiments on Attraction.
The attraction of all the parts of the
earth to one another was thus proved by experiments, in which the
whole mass of the earth is concerned. But attempts have also been made
to measure the attraction of smaller portions; as mountains, or
artificial masses. This is an experiment of great difficulty; for the
attraction of such masses must be compared with that of the earth, of
which it is a scarcely perceptible fraction; and, moreover, in the
case of mountains, the effect of the mountain will be modified or
disguised by unknown or unappreciable circumstances. In many of the
measurements of degrees, indications of the attraction of mountains
had been perceived; but at the suggestion of Maskelyne, the experiment
was carefully made, in 1774, upon the mountain Schehallien, in
Scotland, the mountain being mineralogically surveyed by Playfair. The
result obtained was, that the attraction of the mountain drew the
plumb-line about six seconds from the vertical; and it was deduced
from this, by Hutton’s calculations, that the density of the earth was
about once and four-fifths that of Schehallien, or four and a half
times that of water.
Cavendish, who had suggested many of the artifices in this
calculation, himself made the experiment in the other form, by using
leaden balls, about nine inches diameter. This observation was
conducted with an extreme degree of ingenuity and delicacy, which
could alone make it valuable; and the result agreed very nearly with
that of the Schehallien experiment, giving for the density of the
earth about five and one-third times that of water. Nearly the same
result was obtained by Carlini, in 1824, from observations of the
pendulum, made at a point of the Alps (the Hospice, on Mount Cenis) at
a considerable elevation above the average surface of the earth.
~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~ 457
Sect. 9.—Application of the Newtonian Theory to
the Tides.
We come, finally, to that result, in which
most remains to be done for the verification of the general law of
attraction—the subject of the Tides. Yet, even here, the
verification is striking, as far as observations have been carried.
Newton’s theory explained, with singular felicity, all the prominent
circumstances of the tides then known;—the difference of spring
and neap tides; the effect of the moon’s and sun’s declination and
parallax; even the difference of morning and evening tides, and the
anomalous tides of particular places. About, and after, this time,
attempts were made both by the Royal Society of England, and by the
French Academy, to collect numerous observations  but these were not
followed up with sufficient perseverance. Perhaps, indeed, the theory
had not been at that time sufficiently developed  but the admirable
prize-essays of Euler, Bernoulli, and D’Alembert, in 1740, removed, in
a great measure, this deficiency. These dissertations supplied the
means of bringing this subject to the same test to which all the other
consequences of gravitation had been subjected;—namely, the
calculation of tables, and the continued and orderly comparison of
these with observation. Laplace has attempted this verification in
another way, by calculating the results of the theory (which he has
done with an extraordinary command of analysis), and then by comparing
these, in supposed critical cases, with the Brest observations. This
method has confirmed the theory as far as it could do so; but such a
process cannot supersede the necessity of applying the proper
criterion of truth in such cases, the construction and verification of
Tables. Bernoulli’s theory, on the other hand, has been used for the
construction of Tide-tables; but these have not been properly compared
with experiment; and when the comparison has been made, having been
executed for purposes of gain rather than of science, it has not been
published, and cannot be quoted as a verification of the theory.
Thus we have, as yet, no sufficient comparison of fact with theory,
for Laplace’s is far from a complete comparison. In this, as in other
parts of physical astronomy, our theory ought not only to agree with
observations selected and grouped in a particular manner, but with the
whole course of observation, and with every part of the phenomena. In
this, as in other cases, the true theory should be verified by its
giving us the best Tables; but Tide-tables were never, I believe,
458 calculated upon
Laplace’s theory, and thus it was never fairly brought to the
test.
It is, perhaps, remarkable, considering all the experience which
astronomy had furnished, that men should have expected to reach the
completion of this branch of science by improving the mathematical
theory, without, at the same time, ascertaining the laws of the facts.
In all other departments of astronomy, as, for instance, in the cases
of the moon and the planets, the leading features of the phenomena had
been made out empirically, before the theory explained them. The
course which analogy would have recommended for the cultivation of our
knowledge of the tides, would have been, to ascertain, by an analysis
of long series of observations, the effect of changes in the time of
transit, parallax, and declination of the moon, and thus to obtain the
laws of phenomena  and then proceed to investigate the laws of
causation.
Though this was not the course followed by mathematical theorists,
it was really pursued by those who practically calculated Tide-tables;
and the application of knowledge to the useful purposes of life being
thus separated from the promotion of the theory, was naturally treated
as a gainful property, and preserved by secrecy. Art, in this
instance, having cast off her legitimate subordination to Science, or
rather, being deprived of the guidance which it was the duty of
Science to afford, resumed her ancient practices of exclusiveness and
mystery. Liverpool, London, and other places, had their Tide-tables,
constructed by undivulged methods, which methods, in some instances at
least, were handed down from father to son for several generations as
a family possession; and the publication of new Tables, accompanied by
a statement of the mode of calculation, was resented as an
infringement of the rights of property.
The mode in which these secret methods were invented, was that
which we have pointed out;—the analysis of a considerable series
of observations. Probably the best example of this was afforded by the
Liverpool Tide-tables. These were deduced by a clergyman named Holden,
from observations made at that port by a harbor-master of the name of
Hutchinson; who was led, by a love of such pursuits, to observe the
tides carefully for above twenty years, day and night. Holden’s
Tables, founded on four years of these observations, were remarkably
accurate.
At length men of science began to perceive that such calculations
were part of their business; and that they were called upon, as the
459 guardians of
the established theory of the universe, to compare it in the greatest
possible detail with the facts. Mr. Lubbock was the first
mathematician who undertook the extensive labors which such a
conviction suggested. Finding that regular tide-observations had been
made at the London Docks from 1795, he took nineteen years of these
(purposely selecting the length of a cycle of the motions of the lunar
orbit), and caused them (in 1831) to be analyzed by Mr. Dessiou, an
expert calculator. He thus obtained105 Tables for the
effect of the Moon’s Declination, Parallax, and hour of Transit, on
the tides; and was enabled to produce Tide-tables founded upon the
data thus obtained. Some mistakes in these as first published
(mistakes unimportant as to the theoretical value of the work), served
to show the jealousy of the practical tide-table calculators, by the
acrimony with which the oversights were dwelt upon; but in a very few
years, the tables thus produced by an open and scientific process were
more exact than those which resulted from any of the secrets; and thus
practice was brought into its proper subordination to theory.
105 Phil. Trans. 1831.
British Almanac, 1832.
The theory with which Mr. Lubbock was led to compare his results,
was the Equilibrium-theory of Daniel Bernoulli; and it was found that
this theory, with certain modifications of its elements, represented
the facts to a remarkable degree of precision. Mr. Lubbock pointed out
this agreement especially in the semi-mensual inequality of the times
of high water. The like agreement was afterwards (in 1833) shown by
Mr. Whewell106 to obtain still more accurately at
Liverpool, both for the Times and Heights; for by this time, nineteen
years of Hutchinson’s Liverpool Observations had also been discussed
by Mr. Lubbock. The other inequalities of the Times and Heights
(depending upon the Declination and Parallax of the Moon and Sun,)
were variously compared with the Equilibrium-theory by Mr. Lubbock and
Mr. Whewell; and the general result was, that the facts agreed with
the condition of equilibrium at a certain anterior time, but that this
anterior time was different for different phenomena. In like manner it
appeared to follow from these researches, that in order to explain the
facts, the mass of the moon must be supposed different in the
calculation at different places. A result in effect the same was
obtained by M. Daussy,107 an active French Hydrographer; for he
found that observations at various stations could not be reconciled
with the formulæ of Laplace’s Mécanique 460 Céleste (in
which the ratio of the heights of spring-tides and neap-tides was
computed on an assumed mass of the moon) without an alteration of
level which was, in fact, equivalent to an alteration of the moon’s
mass. Thus all things appeared to tend to show that the
Equilibrium-theory would give the formulæ for the
inequalities of the tides, but that the magnitudes which
enter into these formulæ must be sought from observation.
106 Phil. Trans. 1834.
107 Connaissance des Tems,
1838.
Whether this result is consistent with theory, is a question not so
much of Physical Astronomy as of Hydrodynamics, and has not yet been
solved. A Theory of the Tides which should include in its conditions
the phenomena of Derivative Tides, and of their combinations, will
probably require all the resources of the mathematical
mechanician.
As a contribution of empirical materials to the treatment of this
hydrodynamical problem, it may be allowable to mention here Mr.
Whewell’s attempts to trace the progress of the tide into all the seas
of the globe, by drawing on maps of the ocean what he calls Cotidal
Lines;—lines marking the contemporaneous position of the
various points of the great wave which carries high water from shore
to shore.108 This is necessarily a task of labor
and difficulty, since it requires us to know the time of high water on
the same day in every part of the world; but in proportion as it is
completed, it supplies steps between our general view of the movements
of the ocean and the phenomena of particular ports.
108 Essay towards a First
Approximation to a Map of Cotidal Lines. Phil. Trans. 1833,
1836.
Looking at this subject by the light which the example of the
history of astronomy affords, we may venture to repeat, that it will
never have justice done it till it is treated as other parts of
astronomy are treated; that is, till Tables of all the phenomena which
can be observed, are calculated by means of the best knowledge which
we at present possess, and till these tables are constantly improved
by a comparison of the predicted with the observed fact. A set of
Tide-observations and Tide-ephemerides of this kind, would soon give
to this subject that precision which marks the other parts of
astronomy; and would leave an assemblage of unexplained residual
phenomena, in which a careful research might find the materials of
other truths as yet unsuspected.
[2d Ed.] [That there would be, in the tidal movements of the ocean,
inequalities of the heights and times of high and low water 461
corresponding to those which the equilibrium theory gives,
could be considered only as a conjecture, till the comparison with
observation was made. It was, however, a natural conjecture; since the
waters of the ocean are at every moment tending to acquire
the form assumed in the equilibrium theory: and it may be considered
likely that the causes which prevent their assuming this form produce
an effect nearly constant for each place. Whatever be thought of this
reasoning, the conjecture is confirmed by observation with curious
exactness. The laws of a great number of the tidal
phenomena—namely, of the Semi-mensual Inequality of the Heights,
of the Semi-mensual Inequality of the Times, of the Diurnal
Inequality, of the effect of the Moon’s Declination, of the effect of
the Moon’s Parallax—are represented very closely by formulæ
derived from the equilibrium theory. The hydrodynamical mode of
treating the subject has not added any thing to the knowledge of the
laws of the phenomena to which the other view had conducted us.
We may add, that Laplace’s assumption, that in the moving fluid the
motions must have a periodicity corresponding to that of the
forces, is also a conjecture. And though this conjecture may, in some
cases of the problem, be verified, by substituting the resulting
expressions in the equations of motion, this cannot be done in the
actual case, where the revolving motion of the ocean is prevented by
the intrusion of tracts of land running nearly from pole to pole.
Yet in Mr. Airy’s Treatise On Tides and Waves (in the
Encyclopædia Metropolitana) much has been done to bring the
hydrodynamical theory of oceanic tides into agreement with
observation. In this admirable work, Mr. Airy has, by peculiar
artifices, solved problems which come so near the actual cases that
they may represent them. He has, in this way, deduced the laws of the
semi-diurnal and the diurnal tide, and the other features of the tides
which the equilibrium theory in some degree imitates; but he has also,
taking into account the effect of friction, shown that the actual tide
may be represented as the tide of an earlier epoch;—that the
relative mass of the moon and sun, as inferred from the tides, would
depend upon the depth of the ocean (Art. 455);—with many other
results remarkably explaining the observed phenomena. He has also
shown that the relation of the cotidal lines to the tide waves really
propagated is, in complex cases, very obscure, because different waves
of different magnitudes, travelling in different directions, may
coexist, and the cotidal line is the compound result of all these.
462
With reference to the Maps of Cotidal Lines, mentioned in
the text, I may add, that we are as yet destitute of observations
which should supply the means of drawing such lines on a large scale
in the Pacific Ocean. Admiral Lütke has however supplied us with some
valuable materials and remarks on this subject in his Notice sur
les Marées Périodiques dans le grand Océan Boréal et dans la Mer
Glaciale; and has drawn them, apparently on sufficient data, in
the White Sea.] ~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~
</div></body></text></TEI>