<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="13">

BOOK V.

FORMAL ASTRONOMY.

CHAPTER I.
Prelude to Copernicus.

Nicolas of Cus.
I WILL quote the passage, in
the writings of this author, which bears upon the subject in question.
I translate it from the edition of his book De Docta
Ignorantia, from his works published at Basil in 1565. He praises
Learned Ignorance—that is, Acknowledged
Ignorance—as the source of knowledge. His ground for asserting
the motions of the earth is, that there is no such thing as perfect
rest, or an exact centre, or a perfect circle, nor perfect uniformity
of motion. “Neque verus circulus dabilis est, quinetiam verior dari
possit, neque unquam uno tempore sicut alio æqualiter præcisè, aut
movetur, aut circulum veri similem, æqualem describit, etiamsi nobis
hoc non appareat. Et ubicumque quis fuerit, se in centro esse credit.”
(Lib. i. cap. xi. p. 39.) He adds, “The Ancients did not attain to
this knowledge, because they were wanting in Learned Ignorance. Now it
is manifest to us that the Earth is truly in motion, although this do
not appear to us; since we do not apprehend motion except by
comparison with something fixed. For if any one were in a boat in the
middle of a river, ignorant that the water was flowing, and not seeing
the banks, how could he apprehend that the boat was moving? And thus
since every one, whether he be in the Earth, or in the Sun, or in any
other star, thinks that he is in an immovable centre, and that
everything else is moving; he would assign different poles for
himself, others as being in the Sun, others in the Earth, and others
in the Moon, and so of the rest. Whence the machine of the world is as
if it had its centre everywhere and its circumference nowhere.” This
train of thought 524 might be a preparation for the reception
of the Copernican system; but it is very different from the doctrine
that the Sun is the centre of the Planetary Motions.

CHAPTER II.
The Copernican Theory.

The Moon’s Rotation.
I HAVE said, in page 264, that a confusion of mind produced by
the double reference of motion to absolute space, and to a centre of
revolution, often leads persons to dispute whether the Moon, while she
revolves about the Earth, always turning to it the same face, revolves
about her axis or not.
This dispute has been revived very lately, and has been conducted
in a manner which shows that popular readers and writers have made
little progress in the clearness of their notions during the last two
or three centuries; and that they have accepted the Newtonian
doctrines in words with a very dim apprehension of their real
import.
If the Moon were carried round the Earth by a rigid arm revolving
about the Earth as a centre, being rigidly fastened to this arm, as a
mimic Moon might be, in a machine constructed to represent her
motions, this contrivance, while it made her revolve round the Earth
would make her also turn the same face to the Earth: and if we were to
make such a machine the standard example of rotation, the Moon might
be said not to rotate on her axis.
But we are speedily led to endless confusion by taking this case as
the standard of rotation. For the selection of the centre of rotation
in a system which includes several bodies is arbitrary. The Moon turns
all her faces successively to the Sun, and therefore with regard to
the Sun, she does rotate on her axis; and yet she revolves round the
Sun as truly as she revolves round the Earth. And the only really
simple and consistent mode of speaking of rotation, is to refer the
motion not to any relative centre, but to absolute space.
This is the argument merely on the ground of simplicity and
consistency. But we find physical reasons, as well as mathematical,
for referring the motion to absolute space. If a cup of water be
carried round a centre so as to describe a circle, a straw floating on
the surface 525 of
the water, if it point to the centre of the circle at first, does not
continue to do so, but remains parallel to itself during the whole
revolution. Now there is no cause to make the water (and therefore the
straw) rotate on its axis; and therefore it is not a clear or
convenient way of speaking, to say that the water in this case does
revolve on its axis. But if the water in this case do not revolve on
its axis, a body in the case of the Moon does revolve on its axis.
The difficulty, as I have said in the text, is of the same nature
as that which the Copernicans at first found in the parallel motion of
the Earth’s axis. In order to make the axis of the Earth’s rotation
remain parallel to itself while the Earth revolves about the Sun, in a
mechanical representation, some machinery is needed in
addition to the machinery which produces the revolution round the
centre (the Sun): but the simplest way of regarding the parallel
motion is, to conceive that the axis has no motion except that which
carries it round the central Sun. And it was seen, when the science of
Mechanics was established, that no force was needed in nature to
produce this parallelism of the Earth’s axis. It was therefore the
only scientific course, to conceive this parallelism as not being a
rotation: and in like manner we are to conceive the parallelism of a
revolving body as not being a rotation.
M. Foucault’s Proofs of the Earth’s Motion.
It was hardly to be expected that we should
discover, in our own day, a new physical proof of the earth’s motion,
yet so it has been. The experiments of M. Foucault have enabled us to
see the Rotation of the Earth on its axis, as taking place, we may
say, before our eyes. These experiments are, in fact, a result of what
has been said in speaking of the Moon’s rotation: namely, That the
mechanical causes of motion operate with reference to absolute, not
relative, space; so that where there is no cause operating to change a
motion, it will retain its direction in absolute space; and
may on that account seem to change, if regarded relatively in a
limited space.
In M. Foucault’s first experiment, the motion employed was that of
a pendulum. If a pendulum oscillate quite freely, there is no cause
acting to change the vertical plane of oscillation
absolutely; for the forces which produce the oscillation are
in the vertical plane. But if the vertical plane remain the
same absolutely, at a spot on the surface of the revolving
Earth, it will change relatively to the spectator. He will
see the pendulum oscillate in a vertical plane which gradually 526 turns away from its
first position. Now this is what really happens; and thus the
revolution of the Earth in absolute space is experimentally
proved.
In subsequent experiments, M. Foucault has used the rotation of a
body to prove the same thing. For when a body rotates freely, acted
upon by no power, there is nothing to change the position of the axis
of rotation in absolute space. But if the position of the axis remain
the same in absolute space, it will, in virtue of its relative motion,
change as seen by a spectator at any spot on the rotating Earth. By
taking a heavy disk or globe and making it rotate on its axis rapidly,
the force of absolute permanence (as compared with the inevitable
casual disturbances arising from the machinery which supports the
revolving disk) becomes considerable  and hence the relative motion
can, in this way also, be made visible.
Mr. De Morgan has said (Comp. to Brit. Alm. 1836, p. 18)
that astronomy does not supply any argument for the earth’s motion
which is absolutely and demonstrably conclusive, till we come to the
Aberration of Light. But we may now venture to say that the
experiments of M. Foucault prove the diurnal motion of the Earth in
the most conclusive manner, by palpable and broad effects, if we
accept the doctrines of the Science of Mechanics: while Aberration
proves the annual motion, if we suppose that we can observe the places
of the fixed stars to the accuracy of a few seconds; and if we accept,
in addition to the doctrines of Mechanics, the doctrine of the motion
of light with a certain great velocity.

CHAPTER III.
Sequel to Copernicus.

English Copernicans.
PROFESSOR DE MORGAN  has made
numerous and interesting contributions to the history of the progress
and reception of the Copernican System. These are given mainly in the
Companion to the British Almanac; especially in his papers
entitled “Old Arguments against the Motion of the Earth” (1836);
“English Mathematical and Astronomical Writers” (1837); “On the
Difficulty of Correct 527 Description of Books” (1853); “The
Progress of the Doctrine of the Earth’s Motion between the Times of
Copernicus and Galileo” (1855). In these papers he insists very
rightly upon the distinction between the mathematical and the
physical aspect of the doctrines of Copernicus: a distinction
corresponding very nearly with the distinction which we have drawn
between Formal and Physical Astronomy; and in accordance with which we
have given the history of the Heliocentric Doctrine as a Formal Theory
in Book v., and as a Physical Theory in Book vii.
Another interesting part of Mr. De Morgan’s researches are the
notices which he has given of the early assertors of the heliocentric
doctrine in England. These make their appearance as soon as it was
well possible they should exist. The work of Copernicus was published,
as we have said, in 1543. In September 1556, John Field published an
Ephemeris for 1557, “juxta Copernici et Reinholdi Canones,” in the
preface to which he avows his conviction of the truth of the
Copernican hypothesis. Robert Recorde, the author of various works on
Arithmetic, published among others, “The Pathway to Knowledge” in
1551. In this book, the author discusses the question of the “quietnes
of the earth,” and professes to leave it undecided: but Mr. De Morgan
(Comp. A. 1837, p. 33) conceives that it appears from what is
said, that he was really a Copernican, but did not think the world
ripe for any such doctrine.
Mr. Joseph Hunter also has brought to notice29 the claims of
Field, whom he designates as the Proto-Copernican of England.
He quotes the Address to the Reader prefixed to his first
Ephemeris, and dated May 31, 1556, in which he says that, since
abler men decline the task, “I have therefore published this Ephemeris
of the year 1557, following in it as my authorities, N. Copernicus and
Erasmus Reinhold, whose writings are established and founded on true,
certain, and authentic demonstrations.” I conceive that this passage,
however, only shows that Field had adopted the Copernican scheme as a
basis for the calculation of Ephemerides; which, as Mr. De Morgan has
remarked, is a very different thing from accepting it as a physical
truth. Field, in this same address, makes mention of the errors
“illius turbæ quæ Alphonsi utitur hypothesi;” but the word
hypothesis is still indecisive.</div></body></text></TEI>