<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="19">
      SECTION 12. OF THE PLAN FOR REFORMING THE SOCIETY.
    

      The indiscriminate admission of every candidate became at last so
      notorious, even beyond the pale of the Society, that some of the members
      began to perceive the inconveniences to which it led. This feeling,
      together with a conviction that other improvements were necessary to
      re-establish the Society in public opinion, induced several of the most
      active members to wish for some reform in its laws and proceedings; and a
      Committee was appointed to consider the subject. It was perfectly
      understood, that the object of this Committee was to inquire,—First,
      as to the means and propriety of limiting the numbers of this Society; and
      then, as to other changes which they might think beneficial. The names of
      the gentlemen composing this Committee were:—
    

     Dr. Wollaston,           Mr. Herschel,
     Dr. Young,               Mr. Babbage,
     Mr. Davies Gilbert,      Captain Beaufort,
     Mr. South,               Captain Kater.


      The importance of the various improvements suggested was different in the
      eyes of different members. The idea of rendering the Society so select as
      to make it an object of ambition to men of science to be elected into it,
      was by no means new, as the following extract from the Minutes of the
      Council will prove:—
    

      "MINUTES OF COUNCIL. August 27, 1674 Present,
    

   Sir W. Petty, Vice-President,
   Sir John Lowther,
   Sir John Cutler,
   Sir Christopher Wren,
   Mr. Oldenburgh,
   Sir Paul Neile.


      "It was considered by this Council, that to make the Society prosper, good
      experiments must be in the first place provided to make the weekly
      meetings considerable, and that the expenses for making these experiments
      must be secured by legal subscriptions for paying the contributors; which
      done, the Council might then with confidence proceed to the EJECTION OF
      USELESS FELLOWS."
    

      The reformers of modern times were less energetic in the measures they
      recommended. Dr. Wollaston and some others thought the limitation of the
      numbers of the Society to be the most essential point, and 400 was
      suggested as a proper number to be recommended, in case a limitation
      should be ultimately resolved upon. I confess, such a limit did not appear
      to me to bring great advantages, especially when I reflected how long a
      time must have elapsed before the 714 members of the Society could be
      reduced by death to that number. And I also thought that as long as those
      who alone sustained the reputation of the Society by their writings and
      discoveries should be admitted into it on precisely the same terms, and on
      the payment of the same sum of money as other gentlemen who contributed
      only with their purse, it could never be an object of ambition to any man
      of science to be enrolled on its list.
    

      With this view, and also to assist those who wished for a limitation, I
      suggested a plan extremely simple in its nature, and which would become
      effective immediately. I proposed that, in the printed list of the Royal
      Society, a star should be placed against the name of each Fellow who had
      contributed two or more papers which had been printed in the Transactions,
      or that such a list should be printed separately at the end.
    

      At that period there were 109 living members who had contributed papers to
      the Transactions, and they were thus arranged:
    

     37 Contributors of.. 1 paper
     21.......... 2 papers
     19.......... 3 ditto
     5 .......... 4 ditto
     3 .......... 5 ditto
     3 .......... 6 ditto
     12....  from 7 to 12 ditto
     14... of more than 12 papers.


      100 Contributing Fellows of the Royal Society. 589 Papers contributed by
      them.
    

      Now the immediate effect of printing such a list would be the division of
      the Society into two classes. Supposing two or more papers necessary for
      placing a Fellow in the first class, that class would only consist of
      seventy-two members, which is nearly the same as the number of those of
      the Institute of France. If only those who had contributed three or more
      were admitted, then this class would be reduced to fifty-one. In either of
      these cases it would obviously become a matter of ambition to belong to
      the first class; and a more minute investigation into the value of each
      paper would naturally take place before it was admitted into the
      Transactions. Or it might be established that such papers only should be
      allowed to count, as the Committee, who reported them as fit to be
      printed, should also certify. The great objection made to such an
      arrangement was, that it would be displeasing to the rest of the Society,
      and that they had a vested right (having entered the Society when no
      distinction was made in the lists) to have them always continued without
      one.
    

      Without replying to this shadow of an argument of vested rights, I will
      only remark that he who maintains this view pays a very ill compliment to
      the remaining 600 members of the Royal Society; since he does, in truth,
      maintain that those gentlemen who, from their position, accidentally
      derive reputation which does not belong to them, are unwilling, when the
      circumstance is pointed out, to allow the world to assign it to those who
      have fairly won it; or else that they are incapable of producing any thing
      worthy of being printed in the Transactions of the Royal Society. Lightly
      as the conduct of the Society, as a body, has compelled me to think of it,
      I do not think so ill of the personal character of its members as to
      believe that if the question were fairly stated to them, many would object
      to it.
    

      Amongst the alterations which I considered most necessary to the
      renovation of the Society, was the recommendation, by the expiring
      Council, of those whom they thought most eligible for that of the ensuing
      year.
    

      The system which had got into practice was radically bad: it is impossible
      to have an INDEPENDENT Council if it is named by ONE PERSON. Our statutes
      were framed with especial regard to securing the fitness of the members
      elected to serve in the Council; and the President is directed, by those
      statutes, at the two ordinary meetings previous to the anniversary, to
      give notice of the elections, and "to declare how much it importeth the
      good of the Society that such persons may be chosen into the Council as
      are most likely to attend the meetings and business of the Council, and
      out of whom may be made the best choice of a President and other
      officers." This is regularly done; and, in mockery of the wisdom of our
      ancestors, the President has perhaps in his pocket the list of the future
      Council he has already fixed upon.
    

      In some other Societies, great advantage is found to arise from the
      discussion of the proper persons to be recommended to the Society for the
      Council of the next year. A list is prepared, by the Secretary, of the old
      Council, and against each name is placed the number of times he has
      attended the meetings of the Council. Those whose attendance has been
      least frequent are presumed to be otherwise engaged, unless absence from
      London, or engagement in some pursuit connected with the Society, are
      known to have interfered. Those members who have been on the Council the
      number of years which is usually allowed, added to those who go out by
      their own wish, and by non-attendance, are, generally, more in number than
      can be spared; and the question is never, who shall retire?—but,
      who, out of the rest of the Society, is most likely to work, if placed on
      the Council?
    

      If any difference of opinion should exist in a society, it is always of
      great importance to its prosperity to have both opinions represented in
      the Council. In this age of discussion it is impossible to stifle
      opinions; and if they are not represented in the Council, there is some
      chance of their being brought before the general body, or, at last, even
      before the public. It is certainly an advantage that questions should be
      put, and even that debates should take place on the days appropriated to
      the anniversaries of societies. This is the best check to the commencement
      of irregularities; and a suspicion may reasonably be entertained of those
      who endeavour to suppress inquiry.
    

      On the other hand, debates respecting the affairs of the Society should
      never be entered on at the ordinary meetings, as they interrupt its
      business, and only a partial attendance can be expected. That the conduct
      of those who have latterly managed the Royal Society has not led to such
      discussions, is to be attributed more to the forbearance of those who
      disapprove of the line of conduct they have pursued, than to the
      discretion of the party in not giving them cause.
    

      The public is the last tribunal; one to which nothing but strong necessity
      should induce an appeal. There are, however, advantages in it which may,
      in some cases, render it better than a public discussion at the
      anniversary. When the cause of complaint is a system rather than any one
      great grievance, it may be necessary to enter more into detail than a
      speech will permit; also the printed statement and arguments will probably
      come under the consideration of a larger number of the members. Another
      and a considerable benefit is, that there is much less danger of any
      expression of temper interrupting or injuring the arguments employed.
    

      There were other points suggested, but I shall subjoin the Report of the
      Committee:—
    

      REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE APPOINTED TO CONSIDER THE BEST MEANS OF LIMITING
      THE MEMBERS ADMITTED INTO THE ROYAL SOCIETY, AS WELL AS TO MAKE SUCH
      SUGGESTIONS ON THAT SUBJECT AS MAY SEEM TO THEM CONDUCIVE TO THE WELFARE
      OF THE SOCIETY.
    

      Your Committee having maturely considered the resolution of the Council
      under which they have been appointed; and having satisfied themselves that
      the progressive increase of the Society has been in a much higher ratio
      than the progressive increase of population, or the general growth of
      knowledge, or the extension of those sciences which it has been the great
      object of the Society to promote, they have agreed to the following
      Report:—
    

      Your Committee assume as indisputable propositions, that the utility of
      the Society is in direct proportion to its respectability. That its
      respectability can only be secured by its comprising men of high
      philosophical eminence; and that the obvious means of associating persons
      of this eminence will be the public conviction, that to belong to the
      Society is an honour. Your Committee, therefore, think themselves fully
      borne out in the conclusion, that it would be expedient to limit the
      Society to such a number as should be a fair representation of the talent
      of the country; the consequence of which will be, that every vacancy would
      become an object of competition among persons of acknowledged merit.
    

      From the returns which have been laid on your table, of the Fellows who
      have contributed papers, and from the best estimate they can make of the
      persons without doors who are engaged in the active pursuit of science,
      your Committee feel justified in recommending that those limits should be
      fixed at four hundred, exclusive of foreign members, and of such royal
      personages as it may be thought proper to admit.
    

      As many years must elapse before the present number of seven hundred and
      fourteen can be reduced to those limits by the course of nature, and as it
      would be prejudicial to the interests of the Society and of science, that
      no fresh accessions should take place during that long period, your
      Committee would further recommend, that till that event takes place, four
      new members should be annually admitted.
    

      With respect to the manner of admission, your Committee are of opinion,
      that there are several inconveniences in the present mode of proceeding to
      a single ballot upon each certificate, according to its seniority. If the
      above limitation should be adopted, it may be presumed, that for every
      vacancy there will be many candidates; from amongst them, it must be the
      general wish to select the most distinguished individuals; but to
      accomplish this, if the present system were to be continued, it would be
      necessary to reject all those candidates whose certificates were of
      earlier date than theirs; a process not only extremely irritating, but
      probably ineffectual from the want of unanimity. Your Committee,
      therefore, most earnestly recommend, that one general election should take
      place every year towards the end of the session, and that this should be
      conducted on the same principles as the present annual election of the
      Council and officers; VIZ. by having lists printed of all the candidates
      (whose certificates had been suspended for the usual time,) in which lists
      each Fellow would mark the requisite number of persons.
    

      As the charter, however, requires the concurrence of two-thirds of the
      Fellows present, your Committee suggest, that after the choice has been
      determined by the plurality of votes by ballot in the above manner, the
      successful candidates should be again submitted to a general vote, in
      accordance with the enactments of the said charter.
    

      In concluding this part of the subject, your Committee beg leave to
      remark, that by the method now proposed, the invidious act of blackballing
      would cease, and with it all feelings of resentment and mortification; as
      the result of such an open competition could only be construed by the
      public into a fair preference of the superior claims of the successful
      few, and not into a direct and disgraceful rejection of the others.
    

      Your Committee are fully aware, that such a reduction in the usual
      admissions would materially affect the pecuniary resources of the Society;
      but they are at the same time convinced, that by a vigorous economy its
      present income might be rendered adequate to all its real wants, and the
      aggregate expenditure might be considerably diminished by many small but
      wholesome retrenchments.
    

      It appears, from the accounts of last year, that although 1200L. was
      received for compositions, in addition to the standing income, and usual
      contributions, &c., and although no money was invested, yet there was
      a balance only of a few pounds at the end of the year. It further appears,
      that 500L. was paid for the paper, 370L. for engravings, and nearly 340L.
      for printing; and from those alarming facts, your Committee submit to your
      consideration, whether the expenditure might not be beneficially
      controlled by a standing Committee of Finance.
    

      In obedience to the latter part of your resolution, your Committee now
      proceed to offer some further suggestions for your consideration. They
      conceive that it would afford a beneficial stimulus to individual
      exertion, if the Fellows who have received the medals of the Society, and
      those who have repeatedly enriched its Transactions, were distinguished by
      being collected into a separate and honourable list. It would also be
      found, perhaps, not less a future incentive than an act of retrospective
      justice, if the names of all those illustrious Fellows who have formerly
      obtained the medals, as well as of all those individuals who have been
      large benefactors to the Society, were recorded at the end of the list. It
      would be a satisfactory addition likewise to the annual list, if all those
      Fellows who have died, or had been admitted within the preceding year,
      were regularly noticed. And your Committee think, that these lists should
      always form part of the Transactions, and be stitched up with the last
      part of the volume.
    

      It requires no argument to demonstrate that the well-being of the Society
      mainly depends on the activity and integrity of its Council; and as their
      selection is unquestionably of paramount importance, your Committee hope
      that our excellent President will not consider it any impeachment of his
      impartiality, or any doubt of his zeal, if they venture to suggest, that
      the usual recommendation to the Society of proper members for the future
      Council should henceforth be considered as a fit subject for the diligent
      and anxious deliberation of the expiring Council.
    

      There is another point of great moment to the character of the Society,
      and to the dignified station it occupies among the learned associations of
      Europe; for its character abroad can only be appreciated by the nature and
      value of its Transactions. Your Committee allude to the important task of
      deciding on what papers should be published; and they are of opinion that
      it would be a material improvement on the present mode, if each paper were
      referred to a separate Committee, who should have sufficient time given
      them to examine it carefully, who should be empowered to communicate on
      any doubtful parts with the author; and who should report, not only their
      opinion, but the grounds on which that opinion is formed, for the ultimate
      decision of the Council.
    

      If it should be thought fit to adopt the suggestions which your Committee
      have now had the honour of proposing, they beg leave to move, that another
      Committee be appointed, with directions to frame or to alter the necessary
      statutes, so that they may be in strict accordance with the charters.
    

      In concluding the Report, your Committee do not wish to disguise the
      magnitude of some of the measures they have thought it their duty to
      propose; on the contrary, they would not only urge the fullest discussion
      of their expediency; but further, that if you should even be unanimously
      disposed to confirm them, your Committee would recommend, that the several
      statutes, when they have been drawn up or modified, should be only entered
      on your minutes, and not finally enacted. All innovations in the
      constitution, or even the habits of the Royal Society, should be
      scrutinized with the most jealous circumspection. It is enough for the
      present Council to have traced the plan; let the Council of the ensuing
      sessions share the credit of carrying that plan into effect.
    

      This Report was presented to the Council very late in the session of 1827,
      and on the 25th of June there occurs the following entry on the
      council-book:—
    

      "The Report of the Committee for considering the best means of limiting
      the number of members, and such other suggestions as they may think
      conducive to the good of the Society, was received and read, and ordered
      to be entered on the minutes; and the Council, regarding the importance of
      the subject, and its bearings on the essential interests of the Society,
      in conformity with the concluding paragraph, and considering also the
      advanced stage of the session, recommend it to the most serious and early
      consideration of the Council for the ensuing year."
    

      Those who advocated these alterations, were in no hurry for their hasty
      adoption; they were aware of their magnitude, and anxious for the fullest
      investigation before one of them should be tried.
    

      Unfortunately, the concluding recommendation of the Committee did not
      coincide with the views of Mr. Gilbert, whom the party had determined to
      make their new President. That gentleman made such arrangements for the
      Council of the succeeding year, that when the question respecting the
      consideration of the Report of that Committee was brought forward, it was
      thrown aside in the manner I have stated. Thus a report, sanctioned by the
      names of such a committee, and recommended by one Council to "THE MOST
      SERIOUS and EARLY consideration of the Council for the ensuing year," was
      by that very Council rejected, without even the ceremony of discussing its
      merits. Was every individual recommendation it contained, not merely unfit
      to be adopted, but so totally deficient in plausibility as to be utterly
      unworthy of discussion? Or did the President and his officers feel, that
      their power rested on an insecure foundation, and that they did not
      possess the confidence of the working members of the Society?
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>