<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="80">INTRODUCTION.
Of the Mechanico-Chemical Sciences.
UNDER the title of
Mechanico-Chemical Sciences, I include the laws of Magnetism,
Electricity, Galvanism, and the other classes of phenomena closely
related to these, as Thermo-electricity. This group of subjects forms
a curious and interesting portion of our physical knowledge; and not
the least of the circumstances which give them their interest, is that
double bearing upon mechanical and chemical principles, which their
name is intended to imply. Indeed, at first sight they appear to be
purely Mechanical Sciences; the attractions and repulsions, the
pressure and motion, which occur in these cases, are referrible to
mechanical conceptions and laws, as completely as the weight or fall
of terrestrial bodies, or the motion of the moon and planets. And if
the phenomena of magnetism and electricity had directed us only to
such laws, the corresponding sciences must have been arranged as
branches of mechanics. But we find that, on the other side, these
phenomena have laws and bearings of a kind altogether different.
Magnetism is associated with Electricity by its mechanical analogies;
and, more recently, has been discovered to be still more closely
connected with it by physical influence; electric is identified with
galvanic agency; but in galvanism, decomposition, or some action of
that kind, universally appears; and these appearances lead to very
general laws. Now composition and decomposition are the subjects of
Chemistry; and thus we find that we are insensibly but irresistibly
led into the domain of that science. The highest generalizations to
which we can look, in advancing from the elementary facts of
electricity and galvanism, must involve chemical notions; we must
therefore, in laying out the platform of these sciences, make
provision for that convergence of mechanical and chemical theory,
which they are to exhibit as we ascend.
We must begin, however, with stating the mechanical phenomena of
these sciences, and the reduction of such phenomena to laws. In this
point of view, the phenomena of which we have to speak are those in
which bodies exhibit attractions and repulsions, peculiarly determined
by their nature and circumstances; as the magnet, and a 192 piece of amber when
rubbed. Such results are altogether different from the universal
attraction which, according to Newton’s discovery, prevails among all
particles of matter, and to which cosmical phenomena are owing. But
yet the difference of these special attractions, and of cosmical
attraction, was at first so far from being recognized, that the only
way in which men could be led to conceive or assent to an action of
one body upon another at a distance, in cosmical cases, was by
likening it to magnetic attraction, as we have seen in the history of Physical Astronomy. And we
shall, in the first part of our account, not dwell much upon the
peculiar conditions under which bodies are magnetic or electric, since
these conditions are not readily reducible to mechanical laws; but,
taking the magnetic or electric character for granted, we shall trace
its effects.
The habit of considering magnetic action as the type or general
case of attractive and repulsive agency, explains the early writers
having spoken of Electricity as a kind of Magnetism. Thus Gilbert, in
his book De Magnete (1600), has a chapter,1 De coitione
Magniticâ, primumque de Succini attractione, sive verius corporum ad
Succinum applicatione. The manner in which he speaks, shows us how
mysterious the fact of attraction then appeared; so that, as he says,
“the magnet and amber were called in aid by philosophers as
illustrations, when our sense is in the dark in abstruse inquiries,
and when our reason can go no further. Gilbert speaks of these
phenomena like a genuine inductive philosopher, reproving2
those who before him had “stuffed the booksellers’ shops by copying
from one another extravagant stories concerning the attraction of
magnets and amber, without giving any reason from experiment.” He
himself makes some important steps in the subject. He distinguishes
magnetic from electric forces,3 and is the
inventor of the latter name, derived from ἤλεκτρον, electron,
amber. He observes rightly, that the electric force attracts all light
bodies, while the magnetic force attracts iron only; and he devises a
satisfactory apparatus by which this is shown. He gives4
a considerable list of bodies which possess the electric property;
“Not only amber and agate attract small bodies, as some think, but
diamond, sapphire, carbuncle, opal, amethyst, Bristol gem, beryli,
crystal, glass, glass of antimony, spar of various kinds, sulphur,
mastic, sealing-wax,” and other substances which he mentions. Even his
speculations on the general laws of these phenomena, though vague and
erroneous, as 193
at that period was unavoidable, do him no discredit when compared with
the doctrines of his successors a century and a half afterwards. But
such speculations belong to a succeeding part of this history.
1 Lib. ii. cap. 2.
2 De Magnete, p. 48.
3 Ib. p. 52.
4 Ib. p. 48.
In treating of these Sciences, I will speak of Electricity in the
first place; although it is thus separated by the interposition of
Magnetism from the succeeding subjects (Galvanism, &c.) with which
its alliance seems, at first sight, the closest, and although some
general notions of the laws of magnets were obtained at an earlier
period than a knowledge of the corresponding relations of electric
phenomena: for the theory of electric attraction and repulsion is
somewhat more simple than of magnetic; was, in fact, the first
obtained; and was of use in suggesting and confirming the
generalization of magnetic laws.
</div></body></text></TEI>