<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Cosmos: A Sketch of the Physical Description of the Universe, Vol. 1</title><author>Humboldt, Alexander von (1769-1859)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1845</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="6">
__________
GIGANTIC BIRDS OF NEW ZEALAND. — Vol. i., p. 287.
An extensive and highly interesting collection of bones, referrible to
several species of the 'Moa' (Dinornis of Owen), and to three or four other
genera of birds, formed by Mr. Walter Mantell, of Wellington, New Zealand,
has recently arrived in England, and is now deposited in the British Museum.
 This series consists of between 700 and 800 speciments, belonging to
different parts of the skeletons of many individuals of various sizes and
ages.  Some of the largest vertebrae, tibiae, and femora equal in magnitude
the most gigantic previously known, while others are not larger than the
corresponding bones of the living apteryx.  Among these relics are the
'skulls' and 'mandibles'  of two genera, the 'Dinornis' and 'Palapteryx';
and of an extinct genus, 'Notornis', allied to the 'Rallidae'; and the
mandibles of a species of 'Nestor', a genus of nocturnal owl-like parrots,
of which only two living species are known.*
[footnote]  *See Professor Owen's Memoir on these fossil remains, in
'Zoological Transactions', 1848.
These osseous remains are in a very different state of preservation from any
previously received from New Zealand; they are light and porous, and of a
light fawn-color; the most delicate processes are entire, and the
articulating surfaces smooth and uninjured; 'fragments of egg-shells', and
even the bony rings of the trachea and air tubes, are preserved'.
The bones were dug up by Mr. Walter Mantell from a bed of marly sand,
containing magnetic iron, crystals of hornblende and augite, and the
detritus of augitic rocks and earthy volcanic tuff.  The sand had filled up
all the cavities and cancelli, but was in no instance consolidated or
aggregated together; it was, therefore, easily removed by a soft brush, and
the bones perfectly cleared without injury.
The spot whence these precious relics of the colossal birds that once
inhabited the islands of New Zealand were obtained, is a flat tract of land,
near the embouchure of a river, named Waingongoro, not far from Wanganui,
which has its rise in the volcanic regions of Mount Egmont.  The natives
affirm that this level tract was one of the places first dwelt upon by their
remote ancestors; and this tradition is corroborated by the existence of
numerous heaps and pits of ashes and charred bones indicating ancient fires,
long burning on the same spot.  In these fire-heaps Mr. Mantell found burned
bones of 'men, moas', and 'dogs'.
The fragments of egg-shells, imbedded in the ossiferous deposits, had
escaped the notice of all previous naturalists.  They are, unfortunately,
very small portions, the largest being only four inches long, but they
afford a chord by which to estimate the size of the original.  Mr. Mantell
observes that the egg of the Moa must have been so large that a hat would
form a good egg-cup for it.  These relics evidently belong to two or more
species, perhaps genera.  In some examples the external
p 362
surface is smooth; in others it is marked with short intercepted linear
grooves, resembling the eggs of some of the Struthiouidae, but distinct from
all known recent types.  In this valuable collection only one bone of a
mammal has been detected, namely, 'the femur of a dog'.
An interesting memoir on the probable geological position and age of the
ornithic bone deposits of New Zealand, by Dr. Mantell, based on the
observations of his enterprising son, it published in the Quarterly Journal
of the Geological Society of London (1848).  It appears that in many
instances the bones are imbedded in sand and clay, which lie beneath a thick
deposit of volcanic detritus, and rest on an argillaceous stratum abounding
in marine shells.  The specimens found in the rivers and streams have been
washed out of their banks by the currents which now flow through channels
from ten to thirty feet deep, formed in the more ancient alluvial soil.  Dr.
Mantell concludes that the islands of New Zealand were densely peopled at a
period geologically recent, though historically remote, by tribes of
gigantic brevi-pennate birds allied to the ostrich tribe, all, or almost
all, of species and genera now extinct; and that, subsequently to the
formation of the most ancient ornithic deposit, the sea-coast has been
elevated from fifty to one hundred feet above its original level; hence the
terraces of shingle and loam which now skirt the maritime districts.  The
existing rivers and mountain torrents flow in deep gulleys which they have
eroded in the course of centuries in these pleistocene strata, in like
manner as the river courses of Auvergne, in Central France, are excavated in
the mammiferous tertiary deposits of that country.  The last of the gigantic
birds were probably exterminated, like the dodo, by human agency:  some
small species allied to the apteryx may possibly be met with in the
unexplored parts of the middle island.
THE DODO. — A most valuable and highly interesting history of the dodo and
its kindred* has recently appeared in which the history, affinities, and
osteology of the 'Dodo, Solitaire', and other extinct birds of the islands
Mauritius, Rodriguez, and Bourbon are admirably elucidated by H. G.
Strickland (of Oxford), and Dr. G. A. Melville.
[footnote]  *'The Dodo and its Kindred'.  By Messrs. Strickland and
Melville.  1 vol. 4to. with numerous plates.  Reeves, London, 1848.
The historical part is by the former, the osteological and physiological
portion by the latter eminent anatomist.  We would earnestly recommend the
reader interested in the most perfect history that has ever appeared, of the
extinction of a race of large animals, of which thousands existed but three
centuries ago, to refer to the original work.  We have only space enough to
state that the authors have proved, upon the most incontrovertible evidence,
that the dodo was neither a vulture, ostrich, nor galline, as previously
anatomists supposed, but a 'frugiverous pigeon'.
This section from pp 363-379 of:
COSMOS: A Sketch of the Physical Description of the Universe, Vol. 1
by Alexander von Humboldt
Translated by E C Otte
from the 1858 Harper & Brothers edition of Cosmos, volume 1
—————————————————————————
p 363
INDEX TO VOL. I.
—————————-
ABICH, Hermana, structural relations of volcanic rocks, 234.
Acosta, Joseph de, Historia Natural de las Indias, 66, 193.
Adams, Mr., planet Neptune.  See note by Translator, 90, 91.
Aegos Potamos, on the aerolite of, 117, 122.
Aelian on Mount Aetna, 227.
Aerolites (shooting stars, meteors, meteoric stones, fire-balls, etc),
general description of, 111-137; physical character, 112-123; dates of
remarkable falls, 114, 115; their planetary velocity, 116-120; ideas of the
ancients on, 115, 116; November and August periodic falls of shooting stars,
118-120, 124-126; their direction from one point in the heavens, 120;
altitude, 120; orbit, 127; Chinese notices of, 128; media of communication
with other planetary bodies, 136; their essential difference from comets,
137; specific weights, 116, 117; large meteoric stones on record, 117;
chemical elements, 117, 129-131; crust, 129, 130; deaths occasioned by, 135.
Aeschylus, "Prometheus Delivered," 115.
Aetna, Mount, its elevation, 28, 229; supposed extinction by the ancients,
227; its eruptions from lateral fissures, 229; similarity of its zones of
vegetation to those of Ararat, 347.
Agassiz, Researches on Fossil Fishes, 46, 273-277.
Alexander, influence of his campaigns on physical science, 353.
Alps, the, elevation of, 28, 29.
Amber, researches on its vegetable origin, 284; Goppert on the amber-tree of
the ancient world (Pinites succifer), 283.
Ampere, Andre Marie, 58, 193, 236.
Anaxagoras on aerolites, 122; on the surrounding ether, 134.
Andes, the, their altitude, etc.  See Cordilleras.
Anghiera, Peter Martyr de, remarked that the palmeta and pineta were found
associated together, 282, 283; first recognized (1510) that the limit of
perpetual snow continues to ascend as we approach the equator, 329.
Animal life, its universality, 342-345; as viewed with microscopic powers of
vision, 341-346; rapid propagation and tenacity of life in animalcules,
344-346; geography of, 341-346.
Anning, Miss Mary, discovery of the ink bag of the sepia, and of coprolites
of fish, in the lias of Lyme Regis, 271, 272.
Austed's, D. R., "Ancient World."  See notes by Translator, 271, 272, 274,
281, 287.
Aplan, Peter, on comets, 101.
Apollonius Myndius, described the paths of comets, 103.
Arago, his ocular micrometer, 39; chromatic polarization, 52; optical
considerations, 85; on comets, 99-106; polarization experiments on the light
of comets, 105; aerolites, 114; on the November fall of meteors, 124;
zodiacal light, 143; motion of the solar system, 146, 147; on the increase
of heat at increasing depths, 173, 174; magnetism of rotation, 179, 180;
horary observations of declination at Paris compared with simultaneous
perturbations at Kasan, 191; discovery of the influence of magnetic storms
on the course of the needle, 194, 195; on south polar bands, 198; on
terrestrial light, 202; phenomenon of supplementary rainbows, 220; observed
the deepest Artesian wells to be the warmest, 223; explanation of the
absence of a refrigeration of temperature in the lower strata of the
Mediterranean, 303; observations on the mean annual quantity of rain in
Paris, 333; his investigations on the evolution of lightning, 337.
Argelander on the comet of 1811, 109; on the motion of the solar system,
146, 149; on the light of the Aurora, 195, 196.
Aristarchus of Samos, the pioneer of the Copernican system, 65.
Aristotle, 65; his definition of Cosmos, 69; use of the term history, 75; on
comets, 103, 104; on the Ligyan field of stones, 115; aerolites, 122; on the
stone of Aegos Potamos, 135; aware that noises sometimes existed without
earthquakes, 209; his account of the upheavals of islands of eruption, 241;
"spontaneous motion," 341; noticed the redness assumed by long fallen snow,
344.
Artesian wells, temperature of, 174, 223.
Astronomy, results of, 38-40; phenomena of physical astronomy, 43, 44.
Atmosphere, the general description of, 311, 316; its composition and
admixture, 312; variation of pressure, 313-317; climatic distribution of
heat, 313, 317-328; distribution of humidity, 313, 328, 334; electric
condition, 314, 335-338.
p 363
August, his psychometer, 332.
Augustine, St., his views on spontaneous generation, 345, 346.
Aurora Borealis, general description of 193-202; origin and course, 195,
196; altitude, 199; brilliancy coincident with the fall of shooting stars,
126, 127; whether attended with crackling sound, 199, 200; intensity of the
light, 201.
Bacon, Lord, 53, 58; Novum Organon, 290.
Baer, Von, 337.
Barometer, the increase of its height attended by a depression of the level
of the sea, 298; horary oscillations of, 314, 315
Batten, Mr., letter on the snow-line of the two sides of the Himalayas, 331,
332.
Beaufort, Capt., observed the emissions of inflammable gas on the Caramanian
coast, as described by Pliny, 223.  See also, note by Translator, 223.
Beaumont, Elie de, on the uplifting of mountain chains, 51, 300; influence
of the rocks of melaphyre and serpentine, on pendulum experiments, 167;
conjectures on the quartz strata of the Col de la Poissoniere, 266.
Baccaria, observation of steady luminous appearance in the clouds, 202; of
lightning clouds, unaccompanied by thunder or indication of storm, 337.
Beechey, Capt., 97; observations on the temperature and density of the water
of the ocean under different zones of longitude and latitude, 306.
Bembo, Cardinal, his observations on the eruptions of Mount Aetna, 229;
theory of the necessity of the proximity of volcanoes to the sea, 243;
vegetation on the declivity of Aetna, 347.
Berard, Capt., shooting stars, 119.
Berton, Count, his barometrical measurements of the Dead Sea, 296.
Berzelins on the chemical elements of aerolites, 130, 131.
Benzenberg on meteors and shooting stars, 119, 120; their periodic return in

Autgust, 125.
Bessel's theory on the oscillations of the pendulum, 44; pendulum
experiments, 64; on the parallax of 61 Cygni, 88; on Halley's comet, 102,
103, 104; on the ascent of shooting stars, 123; on their partial visibility,
128; velocity of the sun's translatory motion, 145; mass of the star 61
Cygni, 148; parallaxes and distances of fixed stars, 153; comparison of
measurements of degrees, 165, 166.
Biot on the phenomenon of twilight, 118; on the zodical light, 141; pendulum
experiments at Bordeaux, 170.
Biot, Edward, Chinese observations of comets, 101, 109; of aerolites, 128.
Bischof on the interior heat of the globe, 217, 219, 235, 244, 294.
Blumenbach, his classification of the races of men, 356.
Bockh, origin of the ancient myth of the Nemean lunar lion, 134, 135.
Boguslawski, falls of shooting stars, 119, 128.
Bonpland, M., and Humboldt, on the pelagic shells found on the ridge of the

Andes, 45.
Boussingault, on the depth at which is found the mean annual temperature
within the tropics, 175; on the volcanoes of New Granada, 217; on the
temperature of the earth in the tropics, 220, 221; temperature of the
thermal springs of Las Trincheras, 222; his investigations on the chemical
analysis of the atmosphere, 311, 312; on the mean annual quantity of rain in
different parts of South America, 333, 334.
Bouvard, M., 105; his observations on that portion of the horary
oscillations of the pressure of the atmosphere, which depends on the
attraction of the moon 313.
Bramidos y truenos of Guanaxuato, 209, 210.
Brandes, falls of shooting stars, 114, 116; height and velocity of shooting
stars, 120; their periodic falls, 125, 126.
Bravais, on the Aurora, 201; on the daily oscillations of the barometer in
70 degrees north latitude, 314; distribution of the quantity of rain in
Central Europe, 334; doubts on the greater dryness of mountain air, 334.
Brewster, Sir David, first detected the connection between the curvature of
magnetic lines and my isothermal lines, 193.
Brongniart, Adolphe, luxuriance of the primitive vegetable world, 218;
fossil flora contained in coal measures, 280.
Brongniart, Alexander, formation of ribbon jasper, 259; one of the founders
of the archaeology of organic life, 273.
Brown, Robert, first discoverer of molecular motion, 341.
Buch's, Leopold von, theory on the elevation of continents and mountain
chains, 45; on the craters and circular form of the island of Palma, 226; on
volcanoes, 234, 238, 242, 243, 247; on metamorphic rocks, 249-252, 260, 263,
264; on the origin of various conglomerates and rocks of detritus, 269;
classification of ammonites, 276, 277; physical causes of the elevation of
continents, 295; on the changes in height of the Swedish coasts, 295.
Buckland, 272; on the fossil flora of the coal measures, 279.
Buffon, his views on the geographical distribution of animals, 348.
Burckhardt, on the volcano of Medina, 246; on the hornitos de Jerullo, see
note by Translator, 230.
Burnes, Sir Alexander, on the purity of the atmosphere in Bokhara, 114;
propagation of shocks of earthquakes, 212.
p 365
Caile, La, pendulum measurements at the Cape of Good Hope, 169.
Caldas, quantity of rain at Santa Fe de Bogota, 334.
Camargo's MS. 'Historia de Tiascala', 140.
Capocci, his observations on periodic falls of aerolites, 126.
Carlini, geodesic experiments in Lombardy, 168; Mount Cenis, 170.
Carrara marble, 262, 263.
Carus, his definition of "Nature," 41.
Caspian Sea, its periodic rise and fall, 297.
Cassini, Dominicus, on the zodiacal light, 139, 140; hypothesis on 141; his
discovery of the spheroidal form of Jupiter, 164.
Cautley, Capt, and Dr. Falconer, discovery of gigantic fossils in the

Himalayas.
Cavanilles, first entertained the idea of seeing grass grow, 149.
Cavendish, use of the torsion balance to determine the mean density of the

Earth, 170.
Challis, Professor, on the Aurora, March 19 and Oct. 24th, 1847, see note by

Translator, 195, 199.
Chardin, noticed in Persia the famous comet of 1608, called "nyzek" or
"petite lance," 139.
Charpentier, M., belemnites found in the primitive limestone of the Col de
la Seigne, 261; glaciers, 329.
Chemistry as distinguished from physics, 62; chemical affinity, 63.
Chevandier, calculations on the carbon contained in the trees of the forests
of our temperate zones, 281.
Childrey first described the zodical light in his Britannia Baconica, 138.
Chinese accounts of comets, 99, 100, 101; shooting stars, 128: "fire
springs," 158; knowledge of the magnetic needle, 180; electro-magnetism,
188, 189.
Chladni on meteoric stones, etc., 118, 135; on the selenic origin of
aerolites, 121; on the supposed phenomenon of ascending shooting stars, 122;
on the obscuration of the Sun's disk, 133; sound-figures, 135; pulsations in
the tails of comets, 143.
Choiseul, his chart of Lemnos, 246.
Chromatic polarization.  See Polarization.
Cirro-cumulus cloud.  See Clouds.
Cirrous Strata.  See Clouds.
Clark, his experiments on the variations of atmospheric electricity, 335,
336.
Clarke, J. G., of Maine, U.S., on the comet of 1843, 100.
Climatic distribution of heat, 313, 317-328; of humidity, 328, 333, 334.
Climatology, 317-329; climate, general sense of, 317, 318.
Clouds, their electric tension, color, and height, 236, 337; connection of
cirrous strata with the Aurora Borealis, 196; cirro-cumulus cloud, phenomena
of, 197; luminous, 202; Dove on their formation and appearance, 315, 316;
often present on a bright summer sky the "projected image" of the soil
below, 316; volcanic, 233.
Coal formations, ancient vegetable remains in, 280, 281.
Coal mines, depth of, 158-160.
Colebrooke on the snow-line of the two sides of the Himalayas, 31.
Colladon, electro-magnetic apparatus, 335.
Columbus, his remark that "the Earth is small and narrow," 164; found the
compass showed no variation in the Azores, 181, 182; of lava streams, 245;
noticed conifers and palms growing together in Cuba, 282; remarks in his
journal on the equatorial currents, 307; of the Sargasso Sea, 308; his
dream, 310, 311.
Comets, general description of, 99-112; Biela's 43, 86, 107, 108; Blaupain's
108; Clausen's 108; Encke's, 43, 64, 86, 107-108; Faye's 107, 108; Halley's,
43, 100, 102-109; Lexell's and Burchardt's 108, 110; Messier's 108;
Olbera's, 109; Pons's 109; famous one of 1608, seen in Persia, called
"nyzek," or "petit lance," 189; comet of 1843, 101; their nucleus and tail,
87, 100; small mass, 100; diversity of form, 100-103; light, 104-106;
velocity, 109; comets of short period, 107-109; long period, 109-110;
number, 99; Chinese observations on, 99-101; value of a knowledge of their
orbits, 43; possibility of collision of Blela's and Encke's comets, 107,
108; hypothesis of a resisting medium conjectured from the diminishing
period of the revolution of Encke's comet, 106; apprehensions of their
collision with the Earth, 108, 110, 111; their popular supposed influence on
the vintage, 111.
Compass, early use of by the Chinese, 180; permanency in the West Indies,
181.
Condamine, La, inscription on a marble tablet at the Jesuit's College, Quito
on the use of the pendulum as a measure of seconds, 166, 167.
Conde, notice of a heavy shower of shooting stars, Oct., 902, 119.
Coraboeuf and Delcrois, geodetic operations, 304.
Cordilleras, scenery of, 26, 29, 33; vegetation, 34, 35; intensity of the
zodiacal light, 137.
Cosmography, physical, its object and ultimate aims, 57-60; materials, 60.
Cosmos, the author's object, 38, 78; primitive signification and precise
definition of the word, 69; how employed by Greek and Roman writers, 69, 60;
derivation, 70.
Craters.  See Volcanoes.
Curtius, Professor, his notes on the temperature of various springs in

Greece, 222, 223.
Cuvier, one of the founders of the archaeology of organic life, 273;
discovery of fossil crocodiles in the tertiary formations, 274.
Dainachos on the phenomena attending the fall of the stone of Aegos Potamos,
133, 134.
Dalman on the existence of Chionaea araneoides in polar snow, 344.
Dalton, observed the southern lights in England, 198.
Dante, quotation from, 322.
Darwin, Charles, fossil vegetation in the travertine of Van Diemen's Land,
224; central volcanoes regarded as volcanic chains of small extent on
parallel fissures, 238; instructive materials in the temperate zones of the
southern hemisphere for the study of the present and past geography of
plants, 282, 283; on the fiord formation at the southeast end of America,
293; on the elevation and depression of the bottom of the South Sea, 297;
rich luxuriance of animal life in the ocean, 309, 310; on the volcano of
Aconcagua, 330.
Daubeney on volcanos.  See Translator's notes, 161, 203, 204, 210, 218, 224,
228, 230, 233, 234, 235, 236, 244, 245.
Daussy, his barometric expriments, 208; observations on the velocity of the
equatorial current, 307.
Davy, Sir Humphrey, hypothesis on active volcanic phenomena, 235; on the low
temperature of water on shoals, 309.
Dead Sea, its depression below the level of the Mediterranean, 296, 297.
Dechen, Von, on the depth of the coal-basin of Liege, 160.
Delcrois.  See Coraboeuf.
Descartes, his fragments of a contemplated work, entitled "Monde," 68; on
comets, 139.
Deshayes and Lyell, their investigations on the numerical relations of
extinct and existing organic life, 275.
Dicaearchus, his "parallel of the diaphragm," 289.
Diogenes Laertius, on the aerolite of Aegos Potamos, 116, 122, 134.
D'Orbigny, fossil remains from the Himalaya and the Indian plains of Cutch,
277.
Dove on the similar action of the declination needle to the atmospheric
electrometer, 194; "law of rotation," 315; on the formation and appearance
of clouds, 316; on the difference between the true temperature of the
surface of the ground and the indications of a thermometer suspended in the
shade, 325; hygrometric windrose, 333.
Doyere, his beautiful experiments on the tenacity of life in animalcules,
345.
Drake, shaking of the earth for successive days in the United States
(1811-12), 211.
Dufrenoy et Elie de Beaumont, Geologie de la France, 253, 258, 259, 260,
262, 266.
Dumas, results of his chemical analysis of the atmosphere, 311.
Dunlop on the comet of 1825, 103.
Duperrey on the configuration of the magnetic equator, 183; pendulum
oscillations, 166.
Duprez, influence of trees on the intensity of electricity in the
atmosphere, 335.
Eandi, Vassalli, electric perturbation during the protracted earthquake of

Pignorol, 206.
Earth, survey of its crust, 72; relative magnitude, etc., in the solar
system, 95-97; general description of terrestrial phenomena, 154-360;
geographical distribution, 161, 162; its mean density, 169-172; internal
heat and temperature, 172-176; electro-magnetic activity, 177-193;
conjectures on its early high temperature, 172; interior increase of heat
with increasing depth, 161; greatest depths reached by human labor, 157-159;
methods employed to investigate the curvature of its surface, 165-168;
reaction of the interior on the external crust, 161, 202-247; general
delineation of its reaction, 204-206; fantastic views on its interior, 171.
Earthquakes, general account of, 204-218; their manifestations, 204-206; of
Riobamba, 204, 206, 208, 212, 214; Lisbon, 210, 211, 213, 214; Calabria,
206; their propagation, 204, 212, 213; waves of commotion, 205, 206, 212;
action on gaseous and aqueous springs, 210, 222, 224; salses and mud
volcanoes, 224-228; erroneous popular belief on, 206-208; noise accompanying
earthquakes, 208-210; their vast destruction of life, 210, 211; volcanic
force, 214, 215; deep and peculiar impression produced on men and animals,
215, 216.
Ehrenberg, his discovery of infusoria in the polishing slate of Bilin, 150;
infusorial deposits, 255, 262; brilliant discovery of microscopic life in
the ocean and in the ice of the polar regions, 342; rapid propogation of
animalcules and their tenacity of life, 343-345; transformation of chalk,
262.
Electricity, magnetic, 188-202; conjectured electric currents, 189, 190;
electric storms, 194; atmospheric 335, 337.
Elevations, comparative, of mountains in the two hemispheres, 28, 29.
Encke, 106; his computation that the showers of meteors, in 1833, proceeded
from the same point of space in the direction in which the earth was moving
at the time, 119, 120.
Ennius, 71.
Epicharmus, writings of, 71.
Equator, advantages of the countries bordering on, 33, 34; their organic
richness and fertility, 34, 35; magnetic equator, 183-185.
Erman, Adolph, on the three cold days of May (11th-13th), 133; lines of
declination in Northern Asia, 182; in the southern parts of the Atlantic,
187; observations during the earthquake of Irkutsk, on the non-disturbance
of the horary changes of the magnetic needle, 207.
Eruptions and exhalations (volcanic), lava, gaseous and liquid fluids, hot
mud, mud mofettes, etc., 161, [other page numbers obscured in paper copy]
p 367
Ethnographical studies, their importance and teaching, 357, 358.
Euripides, his Phaeton, 122.
Falconer, Dr., fossil researches in the Himalayas, 278.
Faraday, radiating heat, electro-magnetism etc., 49, 179, 188; brilliant
discovery of the evolution of light by magnetic forces, 193.
Farquharson on the connection of cirrous clouds with the Aurora, 197; its
altitude, 199.
Federow, his pendulum experiments, 168.
Feldt on the ascent of shooting stars, 123.
Ferdinandes, igneous island of, 242.
Floras, geographical distribution of, 350.
Forbes, Professor E., reference to his Travels in Lycia, 223; account of the
island of Santorino, 241, 242.
Forbes, Professor J., his improved selsmometer, 205; on the correspondence
existing between the distribution of existing floras in the British Islands,
348, 349; on the origin and diffusion of the British flora, 353, 354.
Forster, George, remarked the climatic difference of temperature of the
eastern and western coasts of both continents, 321.
Forster, Dr. Thomas, monkish notice of "Meteorodes," 123.
Fossil remains of tropical plants and animals found in northern regions, 46,
270-284; of extinct vegetation in the travertine of Van Diemen's Land, 224;
fossil human remains, 250.
Foster, Reinhold, pyramidal configuration of the southern extremities of
continents, 290, 291.
Fourier, temperature of our planetary system, 155, 172, 176.
Fracastoro on the direction of the tails of comets from the sun, 101.
Fraehn, fall of stars, 119.
Franklin, Benjamin, existence of sandbanks indicated by the coldness of the
water over them, 308.
Franklin, Capt., on the Aurora, 197, 199, 200, 201; rarity of electric
explosions in high northern regions, 337.
Freycinet, pendulum oscillations, 166.
Fusinieri on meteoric masses, 123.
Galileo, 104, 167.
Galle, Dr., 91.
Galvant, Aloysio, accidental discovery of galvanism, 52.
Gaseous emanations, fluids, mud, and molten earth, 217, 220.
Gasparin, distribution of the quantity of rain in Central Europe, 333.
Gauss, Friedrich, on terrestrial magnetism, 179; his erection. in 1832, of a
magnetic observatory on a new principle, 191, 192.
Gay-Lussac, 204, 233, 234, 266, 267, 311, 312, 334, 336.
Geognostic or geological description of the earth's surface, 202-286.
Geognosy (the study of the textures and position of the earth's surface),
its progress, 203.
Geography, physical, 288-311; of animal life, 341-346; of plants, 346-351.
Geographics, Ritter's (Carl), "Geography in relation to Nature and the

History of Man," 48, 67; Varenius (Bernhard), General and Comparative

Geography, 66, 67.
Gerard, Capts. A. G. and J. G., on the snow-line and vegetation of the

Himalayas, 31, 32, 331, 332.
German scientific works, their defects, 47.
Geyser, intermittent fountains of, 222.
Gieseke on the Aurora, 200.
Gilbert, Sir Humphrey, Gulf Stream, 307.
Gilbert, William, of Colchester, terrestrial magnetism, 158, 159, 177, 179,
182.
Gillies, Dr., on the snow-line of South America, 330, 331.
Gioja, crater of, 98.
Girard, composition and texture of basalt, 253.
Glaisher, James, on the Aurora Borealis of Oct. 24, 1847.  See Translator's
notes, 194, 200.
Goldfuss, Professor, examination of fossil specimens of the flying saurians,
274.
Goppert on the conversion of a fragment of amber-tree into black coal, 281;
eyeadeae, 283; on the amber-tree of the Baltic, 283, 284.
Gothe, 41, 47, 53.
Greek philosophers, their use of the term Cosmos, 69, 70; hypotheses on
aerolites, 122, 123, 134.
Grimm, Jacob, graceful symbolism attached to falling stars in the Lithuanian
mythology, 112, 113.
Gulf Stream, its origin and course, 307.
Gumprecht, pyroxenic nepheline, 253.
Guanaxuato, striking subterranean noise at, 209.
Hall, Sir James, his experiments on mineral fusion, 262.
Halley, comet, 43, 100, 102-109; on the meteor of 1686, 118, 133; on the
light of stars, 152; hypothesis of the earth being a hollow sphere, 171; his
bold conjecture that the Aurora Borealis was a magnetic phenomenon, 193.
Hansteen on magnetic lines of declination in Northern Asia, 182.
Hausen on the material contents of the moon, 96.
Hedenstrom on the so-called "Wood Hills" of New Siberia, 281.
Hegel, quotation from his "Philosophy of History," 76.
Heine, discovery of crystals of feldspar in scoriae, 268.
Hemmer, falling stars, 119.
Hencke, planets discovered by.  See note by Translator, 90, 91.
Henfrey, A., extract from his Outlines of Structural and Physiological

Botany.  See notes by Translator, 341, 342, 351.
p 368
Hensius on the variations of form in the comet of 1744, 102.
Herodotus, described Scythia as free from earthquakes, 204; Scythian saga of
the sacred gold, which fell burning from heaven, 115.
Herschel, Sir William, map of the world, 66; inscription on his monument at
Upton, 87; satellites of Saturn, 96; diameters of comets, 101; on the comet
of 1811, 103; star guagings, 150; starless space, 150, 152; time required
for light to pass to the earth from the remotest luminous vapor, 154.
Herschel, Sir John, letter on Magellanic clouds, 85; satellites of Saturn,
98; diameter of nebulous stars, 141; stellar Milky Way, 150, 151; light of
isolated starry clusters, 151; observed at the Cape, the star pi in Argo
increase in splendor, 153; invariability of the magnetic declination in the
West Indes, 181.
Hesiod, dimensions of the universe, 154.
Hevellus on the comet of 1618, 106.
Hibbert, Dr., on the Lake of Laach.  See note by Translator, 218.
Himalayas, the, their altitude, 28; scenery and vegetation, 29, 30;
temperature, 30, 31; variations of the snow-line on their northern and
southern declivities, 30-33, 331.
Hind, Mr., planets discovered by.  See Translator's note, 90, 91.
Hindoo civilization, its primitive seat, 35, 36.
Hippalos, or monsoons, 316.
Hippocrates, his erroneous supposition that the land of Scythia is an
elevated table-land, 346.
Hoff, numerical inquiries on the distribution of earthquakes throughout the
year, 207.
Hoffman, Friedrich, observations on earthquakes, 206-207; on eruption
fissures in the Lipari Islands, 238.
Holberg, his Satire, "Travels of Nic. Klimius, in the world under ground."

See Translator's note, 171, 172.
Hood on the Aurora, 200, 201.
Hooke, Robert, pulsations in the tails of comets, 143; his anticipation of
the application of botannical and zoological evidence to determine the
relative age of rocks, 270-272.
Ho-tsings, Chinese fire-springs, their depth, 158; chemical composition, 217.
Howard on the climate of London, 125; mean annual quantity of rain in

London, 333.
Hugel, Carl von, on the elevation of the valley of Kashmir, 32, 33; on the
snow-line of the Himalayas, 331.
Humboldt, Alexander von, works by referred to in various notes:

  Annales de Chimie et de Physique, 31, 305.

  Annales des Science Naturelles, 28.

  Ansichten der Natur, 342, 344, 347.

  Asie Centrale, 28, 31, 33, 115, 158, 159, 160, 204, 217, 219, 225, 245,

251, 252, 260, 289, 290, 291, 292, 296, 300, 301, 303-306, 320, 323, 324,

330, 331, 334, 350, 356.

  Atlas Geographique et Physique du Nouveau Continent, 33, 249.

  De distributione Geographica Plantrum, secundum coeli temperiem, et

altitudinem Montium, 33, 291, 324.

  Examen Critique de l'Histoire de la Geographie, 58, 180, 181, 227, 289,

292, 307, 308, 310, 316, 356.

  Essai Geognostique sur le Gisement des Roches, 230, 252, 266, 300.

  Essai Politique sur la Nouvelle Espagne, 129, 240.

  Essai sur la Geographie des Plantes, 33, 230, 315.

  Flora Friburgensis Subterranea, 340, 346.

  Journal de Physique, 178, 292.

  Lettre au Duc de Sussex, sur les Moyens propres a perfectionner la

connaissance du Magnetisme Terrestre, 178, 192.

  Monumens des Peuples Indigenes de l'Amerique, 140.

  Nouvelles Annales des Voyages, 307.

  Recueil d'Observations Astronomiques, 28, 167, 218, 327.

  Recueil d'Observations de Zoologi et d'Anatomie Comparee, 232.

  Relation Historique du Voyage aux Regions Equinoxiales, 113, 119, 123,

127, 130, 186, 206, 207, 220, 221, 225, 252, 292, 299, 300, 302, 305-307,

314, 315, 327, 329, 334, 336.

  Tableau Physique des Regions Equinoxiales, 33, 230.

  Vues des Cordilleres, 225, 230.
Humboldt, Wilhelm von, on the primitive seat of Hindoo civilization, 36;
sonnet, extract from, 154; on the gradual recognition by the human race of
the bond of humanity, 358, 359.
Humidity, 313, 332-335.
Hutton, Capt. Thomas, his paper on the snow-line of the Himalayas, 331, 332.
Huygens, polarization of light, 52; nebulous spots, 138.
Hygrometry, 332, 333; hygrometric wind-rose, 333.
Imagination, abuse of, by half-civilized nations, 37.
Imbert, his account of Chinese "fire-springs," 158.
Ionian school of natural philosophy, 65, 77, 84, 134.
Isogenic, isoclinical, isodynamic, etc.  See Lines.
Jacquemont, Victor, his barometrical observations on the snow-line of the

Himalayas, 32, 231.
Jasper, its formation, 259-261.
Jessen on the gradual rise of the coast of Sweden, 295.
Jorullo, hornitos de, 230.
p 369
Justinian, conjectures on the physical causes of volcanic eruptions, 243.
Kamtz, isobarometric lines, 315; doubts on the greater dryness of mountain
air, 334.
Kant, Emmanuel, "on the theory and structure of the heavens," 50, 65;
earthquake at Lisbon, 210.
Kelihau on the ancient sea-line of the coast of Spitzbergen, 296.
Kepler on the distances of stars, 88; on the density of the planets, 93; law
of progression, 95; on the number of comets, 99; shooting stars, 113; on the
obscuration of the sun's disk, 132; on the radiations of heat from the fixed
stars, 136; on a solar atmosphere, 139.
Kloden, shooting stars, 119, 124.
Knowledge, superficial, evils of, 43.
Krug of Nidda, temperature of the Geyser and the Strokr intermittent
fountains, 222.
Krusenstern, Admiral, on the train of a fire-ball, 114.
Kuopho, a Chinese physicist on the attraction of the magnet, and of amber,
168.
Kupffer, magnetic stations in Northern Asia, 191.
Lamanon, 187.
Lambert, suggestion that the direction of the wind be compared with the
height of the barometer, alterations of temperature, humidity, etc., 315.
Lamont, mass of Uranus, 93; satellites of Saturn, 96.
Language and thought, their mutual alliance, 56; author's praise of his
native language, 56.
Languages, importance of their study, 357, 359.
Laplace, his "Systeme du Monde," 48, 62, 92, 141; mass of the comet of 1770,
107; on the required velocity of masses projected from the Moon, 121, 122;
on the altitude of the boundaries of the atmosphere of cosmical bodies, 141;
zodiacal light, 141; lunar inequalities, 166; the Earth's form and size
inferred from lunar inequalities, 168, 169; his estimate of the mean height
of mountains, 301; density of the ocean required to be less than the earth's
for the stability of its equilibrium, 305; results of his perfect theory of
tides, 306.
Latin writers, their use of the term "Mundus," 70, 71.
Latitudes, Northern, obstacles they present to a discovery of the laws of
Nature, 36; earliest acquaintance with the governing forces of the physical
world, there displayed, 36; spread from thence of the germs of civilization,
36.
Latitudes, tropical, their advantages for the contemplation of nature, 33;
powerful impressions, from their organic richness and fertility, 34;
facilities they present for a knowledge of the laws of nature, 35; brilliant
display of shooting stars, 113.
Laugier, his calculations to prove Halley's comet identical with the comet
of 1378, described in Chinese tables, 109.
Lava, its mineral composition, 234.
Lavoisier, 62.
Lawrence (St.), fiery tears, 124; meteoric stream, 125.
Leibnitz, his conjecture that the planets increase in volume in proportion
to their increase of distance from the Sun, 93.
Lenz, observations on the mean level of the Caspian Sea, 297; maxims of
density of the oceanic temperature, 304; temperature and density of the
ocean under different zones of latitude and longitude, 306.
Leonhard, Karl von, assumption on formations of granular limestone, 263.
Leverrier, planet Neptune.  See Translator's note, 90, 91.
Lewy, observations on the varying quantity of oxygen in the atmosphere,
according to local conditions, or the seasons, 311, 312.
Lichtenberg, on meteoric stones, 118.
Liebig on traces of ammonical vapors in the atmosphere, 311.
Light, chromatic polarization of, 52; transmission, 88; of comets, 104-106;
of fixed stars, 105; extraordinary lightness, instances of, 142-144;
propagation of 153; speed of transit, 153, 154.  See Aurora, Zodiacal Light,
etc.
Lignites or beds of brown coal, 283, 284.
Lines, isogonic (magnetic equal deviation), 177, 181-185; isoclinal
(magnetis equal inclination), 178, 179, 181-185; isodynamic (or magnetic
equal force), 181, 185-194; isogeothermal (chthonisothermal), 219;
isobarometric, 315; isothermal, isotheral, and isochimenal, 317, 327, 328,
358.
Line of no variation of horary declination, 183; lower limit of perpetual
snow, 329-332; phosphorescent, 113.
Lisbon, earthquake of, 210, 211, 213, 214.
Lord on the limits of the snow-line on the Himalayas, 32.
Lottin, his observations of the Aurora, with Bravais and Siljerstrom, on the
coast of Lapland, 195, 200, 201.
Lowenorn, recognized the coruscation of the polar light in bright sunshine,
196.
Lyell, Charles, investigations on the numerical relations of extinct and
organic life, 274, 275; nether-formed or hypogene rocks, 249; uniformity of
the production of erupted rocks, 257.  See notes by Translator, 203, 244,
257.
Mackenzie, description of a remarkable eruption in Iceland, 236.
Maclear on a Centauri, 88; parallaxes and distances of fixed stars, 153;
increase in brightness of 'pi' Argo, 153.
Madler, planetary compression of Uranus, 96; distance of the innermost
satellite of Saturn from the centre of that planet, 97; material contents of
the Moon, 96; its libration, 98; mean depression of temperature on the three
cold days of May (11th-13th), 133; conjecture that the average mass of the
larger number of binary stars exceeds the mass of the Sun, 149.
Magellanic clouds, 85.
Magnetic attraction, 188; declination, 181-183; horary motion, 177-180;
horary variations 183, 190; magnetic storms, 177, 179, 195, 199; their
intimate connection with the Aurora, 193-201; represented by three systems
of lines, see Lines; movement of oval systems, 182; magnetic equator,
183-185; magnetic poles, 183, 184; observatories, 190-192; magnetic
stations, 190, 191, 317.
Magnetism, terrestrial, 177-193, 201; electro, 177-191.
Magnussen, Soemund, description of remarkable eruption in Iceland, 236.
Mahlmann, Wilhelm, south west direction of the aërial current in the middle
latitudes of the temperate zone, 317.
Mairan on the zodiacal light, 138, 139, 142; his opinion that the Sun is a
nebulous star, 141.
Malapert, annular mountain, 98.
Malle, Dureau de la, 223.
Man, general view of, 351-359; proofs of the flexibility of his nature, 27;
results of his intellectual progress, 53, 54; geographical distribution of
races, 351-356; on the assumption of superior and inferior races, 351-358;
his gradual recognition of the bond of humanity, 358, 359.
Mantell, Dr., his "Wonders of Geology," see notes by Translator, 45, 64,
203, 274, 278, 281, 283, 284, 287; "Medals of Creation," 46, 271, 283, 287.
Margarita Philosophica by Gregory Reisch, 58.
Marius, Simon, first described the nebulous spots in Andromeda and Orion,
138.
Martins, observations on polar bands, 198; found that air collected at
Faulhorn contained as much oxygen as the air of Paris, 312; on the
distribution of the quantity of rain in Central Europe, 333; doubts on the
greater dryness of mountain air, 334.
Matthessen, letter to Arago on the zodiacal light, 142.
Mathieu on the augmented intensity of the attraction of gravitation in
volcanic islands, 167.
Mayer, Tobias, on the motion of the solar system, 146, 148.
Mean numerical values, their necessity in modern physical science, 81.
Melloni, his discoveries on radiating heat and electro-magnetism, 49.
Menzel, unedited work by, on the flora of Japan, 347.
Messier, comet, 108; nebulous spot resembling our starry stratum, 151.
Metamorphic Rocks.  See Rocks.
Meteorology, 311-339.
Meteors, see Aërolites; meteoric infusoria, 345, 346.
Methone, Hill of, 240.
Meyen on forming a thermal scale of cultivation, 324; on the reproductive
organs of liverworts and algae, 341.
Meyer, Hermann von, on the organization of flying saurians, 274.
Milky Way, its figure, 89; views of Aristotle on, 103; vast telescopic
breadth, 150; Milky Way of nebulous spots at right angles with that of the
stars, 151.
Minerals, artificially formed, 268, 269.
Mines, greatest depth of, 157, 159; temperature, 158.
Mist, phosphorescent, 142.
Mitchell, protracted earthquake shocks in North America, 211.
Mitscherlich on the chemical origin of iron glance in volcanic masses, 234;
chemical combinations, a means of throwing a clear light on geognosy, 256;
on gypsum, as a uniaxal crystal, 259; experiments on the simultaneously
opposite actions of heat on crystalline bodies, 259; formation of crystals
of mica, 260; on artificial mineral products, 268, 271.
Mofettes (exhalations of carbonic acid gas), 215-219.
Monsoons (Indian), 316, 317.
Monticelli on the current of hydrochloric acid from the crater of Vesuvius,
235; crystals of mica found in the lava of Vesuvius, 260.
Moon, the, its relative magnitude, 96; density, 96; distance from the earth,
97; its libration, 98, 163; its light compared with that of the Aurora, 201,
202; volcanic action in, 228.
Moons or satellites, their diameter, distances, rotation, etc., 95-99.
Morgan, John H. "on the Aurora Borealis of Oct. 24, 1847."  See Translator's
notes, 194, 199.
Morton, Samuel George, his magnificent work on the American Races, 362.
Moser's images, 202.
Mountains, in Asia, America, and Europe, their altitude, scenery, and
vegetation, 27-30, 238, 347; their influence on climate, natural
productions, and on the human race, its trade, civilization, and social
condition, 291, 292, 299, 300, 327; zones of vegetation on the declivities
of 29, 30, 327-329; snow-line of, 30-33, 330, 331.
Mud volcanoes.  See Salses and Volcanoes.
Muller, Johannes, on the modifications of plants and aniimals within certain
limitations, 353.
Muncke on the appearance of Auroras in certain districts, 198.
Murchison, Sir R., account of a large fissure through which melaphyre had
been ejected, 258; classification of fossiliferous strata, 277; on the age
of the Palaeosaurus and Thecodontosaurus of Bristol, 274.
Muschenbroek on the frequency of meteors in August, 125.
Myndius, Apollonius, on the Pythagorean doctrine of comets, 103, 104.
Nature, result of a rational inquiry into, 25; emotions excited by her
contemplation, 25; striking scenes, 26; their sources of enjoyment, 26, 27;
magnificence of the tropical scenery, 33, 34, 35, 344; religious impulses
from a communion with nature, 37; obstacles to an active spirit of inquiry,
37; mischief of inaccurate observations, 38; higher enjoyments of her study,
38; narrow-minded views of nature, 38; lofty impressions produced on the
minds of laborious observers, 40; nature defined, 41; her studies
inexhaustible, 41; general observations, their great advantages, 42; how to
be correctly comprehended, 72; her most vivid impressions earthly, 82.
Nature, philosophy of, 24, 37; physical description of, 66, 67, 73.
Nebulae, 84-86; nebulous Milky Way at right angles with that of the stars,
150-153; nebulous spots, conjectures on, 83-86; nebulous stars and planetary
nebulae, 85, 151, 152; nebulous vapor, 83-86, 87, 152; their supposed
condensation in conformity with the laws of attraction, 84.
Neilson, gradual depression of the southern part of Sweden, 295.
Nericat, Andrea de, popular belief in Syria on the fall of aerolites, 123.
Newton, discussed the question on the difference between the attraction of
masses and molecular attraction, 63; Newtonian axiom confirmed by Bessel,
64; his edition of the Geography of Varenius, 66; Principia Mathematica, 67;
considered the planets to be composed of the same matter with the Earth,
132; compression of the Earth, 165.
Nicholl, J. P., note from his account of the planet Neptune, 90, 91.
Nicholson, observations of lighting clouds, unaccompanied by thunder or
indications of storm, 337.
Nobile, Antonio, experiments of the height of the barometer, and its
influence on the level of the sea, 298.
Noggerath counted 792 annual rings in the trunk of a tree at Bonn, 283.
Nordmann on the existence of animalcules in the fluids of the eyes of
fishes, 345.
Norman, Robert, invented the inclinatorium, 179.
Observations, scientific, mischief of inaccurate, 38; tendency of
unconnected, 40.
Ocean, general view of, 292-311; its extent as compared with the dry land,
288, 289; its depth, 160, 302; tides, 304, 305; decreasing temperature at
increased depths, 302; uniformity and constancy of temperature in the same
spaces, 303; its currents and their various causes, 306-309; its
phosphorescence in the torrid zone, 202; its action on climate, 303,
319-320; influence on the mental and social condition of the human race,
162, 291, 292, 294, 310; richness of its organic life, 300, 310; oceanic
microscopic forms, 342, 343; sentiments excited by its contemplation, 310.
Oersted, electro-magnetic discoveries, 188, 191.
Olbers, comets, 104, 109; aerolites, 114, 118; on their planetary velocity,
121; on the supposed phenomena of ascending shooting stars, 123; their
periodic return in August, 125; November stream, 126; prediction of a
brilliant fall of shooting stars in Nov., 1867, 127; absence of fossil
meteoric stones in secondary and tertiary formations, 131; zodiacal light,
its vibration through the tails of comets, 143; on the transparency of
celestial space, 152.
Olmsted, Denison of New Haven, Connecticut, observations of aerolites, 113,
118, 119, 124.
Oltmanns, Herr, observed continuously with Humboldt, at Berlin, the
movements of the declination needle, 190, 191.
Ovid, his description of the volcanic Hill of Methone, 240.
Oviedo describes the weed of the Gulf Stream as Praderias de yerva (sea weed
meadows), 308.
Palaeontology, 270-284.
Pallas, meteoric iron, 131.
Palmer, New Haven, Connecticut, on the prodigious swarm of shooting stars,

Nov. 12 and 13, 1833, 124; on the non-appearance in certain years of the

August and November fall of aerolites, 129.
Parallaxes of fixed stars, 88, 89; of the solar system, 145, 146.
Perry, Capt., on Auroras, their connection with magnetic perturbations, 197,
201; whether attended with any sound, 200; seen to continue throughout the
day, 197; barometric observation at Port Bowen, 314, 315; rarity of electric
explosions in northern regions, 337.
Patricius, St., his accurate conjectures on the hot springs of Carthage,
223, 224.
Peltier on the actual source of atmospheric electricity, 335, 336.
Pendulum, its scientific uses, 44; experiments with, 64, 166, 169, 170;
employed to investigate the curvature of the earth's surface, 165; local
attraction, its influence on the pendulum, and geognostic knowledge deduced
from, 44, 45, 167, 168; experiments of Bessel, 64.
Pentland, his measurements of the Andes, 28.
Percy, Dr., on minerals artifically produced.  See note by Translator, 268.
Permian system of Murchison, 277.
Perouse, La, expedition of, 186.
Persia, great comet seen in (1608), 139, 140.
Pertz on the large aerolite that fell in the bed of the River Narni, 116.
Peters, Dr., velocity of stones projected from Aetna, 122.
Peucati, Count Mazari, partial infection of calcareous beds by the contact
of syenitic granite in the Tyrol, 262.
Phillips on the temperature of a coalmine at increasing depths, 174.
Philolaus, his astronomical studies, 65; his fragmentary writings, 68-71.
Philosophy of nature, first germ, 37.
Phosphorescence of the sea in the torrid zones, 202.
Physics, their limits, 50; influence of physical science on the wealth and
prosperity of nations, 53; province of physical science, 59; distinction
betweeen the physical 'history' and physical 'description' of the world, 71,
72; physical science, characteristics of its modern progress, 81.
Pindar, 227.
Plans, geodesic experiments in Lombardy, 168.
Planets, 89-99; present number discovered, 90.  (See note by Translator on
the most recent discoveries, 90, 91); Sir Isaac Newton on their composition,
132; limited physical knowledge of, 156, 157; Ceres, 64-92; Earth, 88-99;
Juno, 64, 92-97, 106; Jupiter, 64, 87, 92-98, 202; Mars, 87, 91-94, 132;
Mercury, 87, 92-94; Pallas, 64, 92; Saturn, 87, 92-94; Venus, 91-94, 202;
Uranus, 90-94; planets which have the largest number of moons, 95, 96.
Plants, geographical distribution of, 346-350.
Plato on the heavenly bodies, etc., 69; interpretation of nature, 163; his
geognostic views on hot springs, and volcanic igneous streams, 237, 238.
Pliny the elder, his Natural History, 73; on comets, 104; aerolites, 122,
123, 130; magnetism, 180; attraction of amber, 188; on earthquakes, 205,
207; on the flame of inflammable gas, in the district of Phasells, 223;
rarity of jasper, 261; on the configuration of Africa, 292.
Pliny the younger, his description of the great eruption of Mount Vesuvius,
and the phenomenon of volcanic ashes, 235.
Plutarch, truth of his conjecture that falling stars are celestial bodies,
133, 134.
Poisson on the planet Jupiter, 64; conjecture on the spontaneous ignition of
meteoric stones, 118; zodiacal light, 141; theory on the earth's
temperature, 172, 173, 174, 176, 177.
Polarization, chromatic, results of its discovery, 52; experiments on the
light of comets, 105, 106.
Polybius, 291.
Posidonius on the Ligyran field of stones, 115, 116.
Pouilet on the actual source of atmospheric electricity, 335.
Prejudices against science, how originated, 38; against the study of the
exact sciences, why fallacious, 40-52.
Prichard, his physical history of Mankind, 352.
Pseudo-Plato, 54.
Psychrometer, 332, 338.
Pythagoras, first employed the word Cosmos in its modern sense, 69.
Pythagoreans, their study of the heavenly bodies, 65; doctrine on comets,
103.
Quarterly Review, article on Terrestrial Magnetism, 192.
Quetelet on aerolites, 114; their periodic return in August, 125.
Races, human, their geographical distribution, and unity, 351, 359.
Rain drops, temperature of, 220; mean annual quantity in the two
hemispheres, 333, 334.
Reich, mean density of the earth, as ascertained by the torsion balance,
170; temperature of the mines in Saxony, 174.
Reisch, Gregory, his "Margarita Philosophica," 58.
Remusat, Abel, Mongolian tradition on the fall of an aerolite, 116; active
volcanoes in Central Asia, at great distances from the sea, 245.
Richardson, magnetic phenomena attending the Aurora, 197; whether
accompanied by sound 200; influence on the magnetic needle of the Aurora,
201.
Riohamba, earthquake at, 204, 205, 208, 213, 214.
Ritter, Carl, on his "Geography in relation to Nature and the History of

Man," 48, 67.
Robert, Eugene, on the ancient sea-line on the coast of Spitzbergen, 296.
Robertson on the permanency of the compass in Jamaica, 181.
Rocks, their nature and configuration, 228; geognostical classification into
four groups, 248-251; i. rocks of eruption, 248, 251-253; ii. sedimentary
rocks, 248, 254, 255; iii. transformed, or metamorphic rocks, 248, 259, 255,
256-269; iv. conglomerates, or rocks of detritus, 269, 270; their changes
from the action of heat, 258, 259; phenomena of contact, 258-269; effects of
pressure and the rapidity of cooling, 258, 267.
Rose, Gustav, on the chemical elements, etc., of various aerolites, 131; on
the structural relations of volcanic rocks, 254; on crystals of feldspar and
albite found in granite, 251; relations of position in which granite occurs,
252-269; chemical process in the formation of various minerals, 265-269.
Ross, Sir James, his soundings with 27,000 feet of line, 160; magnetic
observations at the South Pole, 187; important results of the Antarctic
magnetic expedition in 1839, 192; rarity of electric explosions in high
northern regions, 337.
Rossell, M. de, his magnetic oscillation experiments, and their date of
publication, 186, 187.
Rothmann, confounded the setting zodiscal light with the cessation of
twilight, 143.
Rozier, observation of a steady luminous appearance in the clouds, 202.
Rumker, Encke's comet, 106.
Ruppell denies the existence of active volcanoes in Kordofan, 245.
Sabine, Edward, observations on days of unusual magnetic disturbances, 178;
recent magnetic observations, 184, 185, 187, 188.
Sagra, Ramon de la, observations on the mean annual quantity of rain in the

Havana, 333.
Saint Pierre, Bernardin de, Paul and Virginia, 26; Studies of Nature, 347.
Salses or mud volcanoes, 224-228; striking phenomena attending their origin,
224, 225.
Salt works, depth of 158, 159; temperature, 174.
Santorino, the most important of the islands of eruption, 241, 242;
description of.  See note by Translator, 241.
Sargasso Sea, its situation, 308.
Satellites revolving round the primary planets, their diameter, distance,
rotation, etc., 94, 99; Saturn's 96-98, 127' Earth's see Moon, Jupiter's,
96, 97; Uranus, 96-98.
Saurians, flying, fossil remains of, 274, 275.
Saussure, measurements of the marginal ledge of the crater of Mount
Vesuvius, 232; traces of ammoniacal vapors in the atmosphere, 311;
hygrometric measurements with Humboldt, 334-336.
Schayer, microscopic organisms in the ocean, 342, 343.
Scheerer on the identity of eleolite and nepheline, 253.
Schelling on nature, 55; quotation from his Giordino Bruino, 77.
Scheuchzner's fossil salamander, conjectured to be an antediluvian man, 274.
Schiller, quotation from, 36.
Schnurrer on the obscuration of the sun's disk, 133.
Schouten, Cornelius, in 1616 found the declination null in the Pacific, 182.
Schouw, distribution of the quantity of rain in Central Europe, 333.
Schrieber on the fragmentary character of meteoric stones, 117.
Scientific researches, their frequent result, 50; scientific knowledge a
requirement of the present age, 53, 54; scientific terms, their vagueness
and misapplication, 58, 68.
Scina, Abbate, earthquakes unconnected with the state of the weather, 206,
207.
Scoresby, rarity of electric explosions in high northern regions, 337.
Sea.  See Ocean.
Seismometer, the, 205.
Seleucus of Erythrea, his astronomical studies, 65.
Seneca, noticed the direction of the tails of comets, 102; his views on the
nature and paths of comets, 103, 104; omens drawn from their sudden
appearance, 111; the germs of later observations on earthquakes found in his
writings, 207; problematical extinction and sinking of Mount Aetna, 227, 240.
Shoals, atmospheric indications of their vicinity, 309.
Sidereal systems, 89, 90.
Siljerstrom, his observations on the Aurora, with Lottin and Bravais, on the
coast of Lapland, 195.
Sirowatskoi, "Wood Hills" in New Siberia, 281.
Snow-line of the Himalayas, 30-33, 331, 334; of the Andes, 330; redness of
long-fallen snow, 344.
Solar system, general description, 90-154; its position in space, 89; its
transistory motion, 145-150.
Solinus on mud volcanoes, 225.
Sommering on the fossil remains of the large vertebrata, 274.
Somerville, Mrs., on the volume of fire-balls and shooting stars, 116;
faintness of light of planetary nebulae, 141.
Southern celestial hemisphere, its picturesque beauty, 85, 86.
Spontaneous generation, 345, 346.
Springs, hot and cold, 219-225; intermittent, 219; causes of their
temperature, 220-222; thermal, 222, 345; deepest Artesian wells the warmest,
observed by Arago, 223; salses, 224-226; influence of earthquake shocks on
hot springs, 210, 222-224.
Stars, general account of, 85-90; fixed 89, 90, 104; double and multiple,
89, 147; nebulous, 85, 86, 151, 152; their translatory motion, 147-150;
parallaxes and distances, 147-149; computations of Bessel and Herschel on
their diameter and volume, 148; immense number in the Milky Way, 150, 151;
star dust, 85; star gaugings, 150; starless spaces, 150, 152; telescopic
stars, 152; velocity of the propagation of light of, 153, 154; apparition of
new stars, 153.
Storms, magnetic and volcanic.  See Magnetism, Volcanoes.
Strabo, observed the cessation of shocks of erthquake on the eruption of
lava, 215; on the mode in which islands are formed, 227; description of the
Hill of Methone, 240; volcanic theory, 243; divined the existence of a
continent in the northern hemisphere between Theria and Thine, 289; extolled
the varied form of our small continent as favorable to the moral and
intellectual development of its people, 291, 292.
Struve, Otho, on the proper motion of the solar system, 146; investigations
on the propagation of light, 153; parallaxes and distances of fixed stars,
153; observations on Halley's comet, 105.
Studer, Professor, on mineral metamorphism.  See note by Translator, 248.
Sun, magnitude of its volume compared with that of the fixed stars, 136;
obscuration of its disk, 132; rotation round the center of gravity of the
whole solar system, 145; velocity of its translatory motion, 145; narrow
limitations of its atmosphere as compared with the nucleus of other nebulous
stars, 141; "sun stones" of the ancients, 122; views of the Greek
philosophers on the sun, 122.
Symond, Lieut., his trigonometrical survey of the Dead Sea, 296, 297.
Tacitus, distinguished local climatic relations from those of race, 352.
Temperature of the globe, see Earth and Ocean; remarkable uniformity over
the same spaces of the surface of the ocean, 303; zones at which occur the
maxima of the oceanic temperature, 319; causes which lower the temperature,
319, 320; temperature of various places, annual, and in the different
seasons, 322, 323-328; thermic scale of temperature, 324, 325; of
continental climates as compared with insular and littoral climates, 321,
322; law of decrease with increase of elevation, 327; depression of, by
shoals, 309; refrigeration of the lower strata of the ocean, 303.
Teneriffe, Peak of its striking scenery, 26.
Theodectes of Phaselis on the color of the Ethiopians, 353.
Theon of Alexandria described comets as "wandering light clouds," 100.
Theophylactus described Scythia as free from earthquakes, 204.
Thermal scales of cultivated plants, 324, 325.
Thermal springs, their temperature, constancy, and change, 221-224; animal
and vegetable life in, 345.
Thermometer, 338.
Thibet, habitability of its elevated plateaux, 331, 332.
Thienemann on the Aurora, 197, 200.
Thought, results of its free action, 53, 54; union with language, 56.
Tiberias, Sea of, its depression below the level of the Mediterranean, 296.
Tides of the ocean, their phenomena, 305, 306.
Tillard, Capt., on the sudden appearance of the island of Sabrina, 242.
Tournefort, zones of vegetation on Mount Ararat, 347.
Tralles, his notice of the negative electricity of the air near high
waterfalls, 336.
Translator, notes by, 29; on the increase of the earth's internal heat with
increase of depth, 45; silicious infusoria and animalculites, 46; chemical
analysis of an aerolite, 64; on the recent discoveries of planets, 90, 91;
observed the comet of 1843, at New Bedford, Massachusetts, in bright
sunshine, 101; on meteoric stones, 111; on a MS., said to be in the library
of Christ's College, Cambridge, 124; on the term "salses," 161;  on
Holberg's satire, "Travels in the World under Ground," 171; on the Aurora
Borealis of Oct. 24, 1847, 194, 195, 199; on the electricity of the
atmosphere during the Aurora, 200; on volcanic phenomena, 203, 204;
description of the seismometer, 205; on the great earthquake of Lisbon, 210;
impression made on the natives and foreigners by earthquakes in Peru, 215;
earthquakes at Lima, 216, 217; on the gaseous compounds of sulphur, 217,
218; on the Lake of Lasch, its craters, 218; on the emissions of inflammable
gas in the district of Phasells, 233; on true volcanoes as distinguished
from salses, 224; on the volcano of Pichincha, 228; on the hornitos de
Jorullo, as seen by Humboldt, 230; general rule on the dimensions of
craters, 230; on the ejection of fish from the volcano of Imbaburn, 223; on
the little isle of Volcano, 234; volcanic steam of Pantellaria, 235; on
Daubeney's work "On Volcanoes," 236; account of the island of Santorino,
241; on the vicinity of extinct volcanoes to the sea, 244; meaning of the
Chinese term "li," 245; on mineral metamorphism, 248; on fossil human
remains found in Guadaloupe, 250; on minerals artifically produced 267, 268;
fossil organic structures, 271, 272; on Coprolites, 271; geognostic
distribution of fossils, 276; fossil fauna of the Sewalik Hills, 278;
thickness of coal measures, 281; on the amber pine forests of the Baltic,
283, 284; elevation of mountain chains, 286, 287; the dinornis of Owen, 287;
depth of the atmosphere, 302; richness of organic life in the ocean, 309; on
filaments of plants resembling the spermatozoa of animals, 341; on the
Diatomaceae in the South Arctic Ocean, 343; on the distribution of the
floras and faunas of the British Isles, 348, 349; on the origin and
diffusion of the British flora, 353, 354.
Translatory motion of the solar system, 145-150.
Trogus, Pompeius, on the supposed necessity that volcanoes were dependent on
their vicinity to the sea for their continuance, 243, 244; views of the
ancients on spontaneous generation, 346.
Tropical latitudes, their advantages for the contemplation of nature, 33;
powerful impressions from their organic richness and fertility, 34;
facilities they present for a knowledge of the laws of nature 35;
transparency of the atmosphere, 114; phosphorescence of the sea, 202.
Tschudi, Dr., extract from his "Travels in Peru."  See Translator's note,
215, 216, 217.
Turner, note on Sir Isaac Newton, 132.
Universality of animated life, 342, 343.
Valz on the comet of 1618, 106.
Varenius, Bernhard, his excellent general and comparative Geography, 66, 67;
edited by Newton, 66.
Vegetable world, as viewed with microscopic powers of vision, 341; its
predominance over animal life, 343.
Vegetation, its varied distribution on the earth's surface, 29-31, 62;
richness and fertility in the tropics, 33-35; zones of vegetation on the
declivities of mountains, 29-32, 346-350.  See Aetna, Cordilleras,
Himalayas, Mountains.
Vico, satellites of Saturn, 96.
Vigne, measurement of Ladak, 322.
Vine, thermal scale of its cultivation, 324.
Volcanoes, 28, 30, 35, 159, 161, 214, 215, 224-248; author's application of
the term volcanic, 45; active volcanoes, safety-valves for their immediate
neighborhood, 214; volcanic eruptions, 161, 210-270; mud volcanoes or
salses, 224-228; traces of volcanic action on the surface of the earth and
moon, 228; influence of relations of height on the occurrence of eruptions,
228-233; volcanic storm, 233; volcanic ashes, 233; classification of
volcanoes into central and linear, 238; theory of the necessity of their
proximity to the sea, 243-246; geographical distribution of still active
volcanoes, 245-247; metamorphic action on rocks, 247-249.
Vrolik, his anatomical investigations on the form of the pelvis, 352, 353.
Wagner, Rudolph, notes on the races of Africa, 352.
Walter on the decrease of volcanic activity, 215.
Wartmann, meteors, 113, 114.
Weber, his anatomical investigations on the form of the pelvis, 353.
Webster, Dr. (of Harvard College, U.S.), account of the island named

Sabrina.  See note by Translator, 242.
Winds, 315-321; monsoons, 316, 317; trade winds, 32-, 321; law of rotation,
importance of its knowledge, 315-317.
Wine on the temperature required for its cultivation, 324; thermic table of
mean annual heat, 325.
Wolleston on the limitation of the atmosphere, 302.
Wrangel, Admiral, on the brilliancy of the Aurora Borealis, coincident with
the fall of shooting stars, 126, 127; observations of the Aurora, 197, 200;
wood hills of the Siberian Polar Sea, 281.
Xenophanes of Colophon, described comets as wandering light clouds, 100;
marine fossils found in marble quarries, 263.
Young, Thomas, earliest observer of the influence different kinds of rocks
exercise on the vibrations of the pendulum, 168.
Yul-sung, described by Chinese writers as "the realm of pleasure," 332.
Zimmerman, Carl, hypsometrical remarks on the elevation of the Himalayas, 32.
Zodiacal light, conjectures on, 86-92; general account of, 137-144;
beautiful appearance, 137, 138; first described in Childrey's Britannia
Baconica, 138; probable causes, 141; intensity in tropical climates, 142.
Zones, of vegetation, on the declivities of mountains, 29-33; of latitude,
their diversified vegetation, 62; of the southern heavens, their
magnificence, 85, 86; polar, 197, 198.
END OF VOL. I.
*** END OF THE PROJECT GUTENBERG EBOOK COSMOS: A SKETCH OF THE PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION OF THE UNIVERSE, VOL. 1 ***


Updated editions will replace the previous one—the old editions will
be renamed.

Creating the works from print editions not protected by U.S. copyright
law means that no one owns a United States copyright in these works,
so the Foundation (and you!) can copy and distribute it in the United
States without permission and without paying copyright
royalties. Special rules, set forth in the General Terms of Use part
of this license, apply to copying and distributing Project
Gutenberg™ electronic works to protect the PROJECT GUTENBERG™
concept and trademark. Project Gutenberg is a registered trademark,
and may not be used if you charge for an eBook, except by following
the terms of the trademark license, including paying royalties for use
of the Project Gutenberg trademark. If you do not charge anything for
copies of this eBook, complying with the trademark license is very
easy. You may use this eBook for nearly any purpose such as creation
of derivative works, reports, performances and research. Project
Gutenberg eBooks may be modified and printed and given away—you may
do practically ANYTHING in the United States with eBooks not protected
by U.S. copyright law. Redistribution is subject to the trademark
license, especially commercial redistribution.

START: FULL LICENSE
THE FULL PROJECT GUTENBERG LICENSE
PLEASE READ THIS BEFORE YOU DISTRIBUTE OR USE THIS WORK

To protect the Project Gutenberg™ mission of promoting the free
distribution of electronic works, by using or distributing this work
(or any other work associated in any way with the phrase “Project
Gutenberg”), you agree to comply with all the terms of the Full
Project Gutenberg™ License available with this file or online at
www.gutenberg.org/license.

Section 1. General Terms of Use and Redistributing Project Gutenberg™
electronic works

1.A. By reading or using any part of this Project Gutenberg™
electronic work, you indicate that you have read, understand, agree to
and accept all the terms of this license and intellectual property
(trademark/copyright) agreement. If you do not agree to abide by all
the terms of this agreement, you must cease using and return or
destroy all copies of Project Gutenberg™ electronic works in your
possession. If you paid a fee for obtaining a copy of or access to a
Project Gutenberg™ electronic work and you do not agree to be bound
by the terms of this agreement, you may obtain a refund from the person
or entity to whom you paid the fee as set forth in paragraph 1.E.8.

1.B. “Project Gutenberg” is a registered trademark. It may only be
used on or associated in any way with an electronic work by people who
agree to be bound by the terms of this agreement. There are a few
things that you can do with most Project Gutenberg™ electronic works
even without complying with the full terms of this agreement. See
paragraph 1.C below. There are a lot of things you can do with Project
Gutenberg™ electronic works if you follow the terms of this
agreement and help preserve free future access to Project Gutenberg™
electronic works. See paragraph 1.E below.

1.C. The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation (“the
Foundation” or PGLAF), owns a compilation copyright in the collection
of Project Gutenberg™ electronic works. Nearly all the individual
works in the collection are in the public domain in the United
States. If an individual work is unprotected by copyright law in the
United States and you are located in the United States, we do not
claim a right to prevent you from copying, distributing, performing,
displaying or creating derivative works based on the work as long as
all references to Project Gutenberg are removed. Of course, we hope
that you will support the Project Gutenberg™ mission of promoting
free access to electronic works by freely sharing Project Gutenberg™
works in compliance with the terms of this agreement for keeping the
Project Gutenberg™ name associated with the work. You can easily
comply with the terms of this agreement by keeping this work in the
same format with its attached full Project Gutenberg™ License when
you share it without charge with others.

1.D. The copyright laws of the place where you are located also govern
what you can do with this work. Copyright laws in most countries are
in a constant state of change. If you are outside the United States,
check the laws of your country in addition to the terms of this
agreement before downloading, copying, displaying, performing,
distributing or creating derivative works based on this work or any
other Project Gutenberg™ work. The Foundation makes no
representations concerning the copyright status of any work in any
country other than the United States.

1.E. Unless you have removed all references to Project Gutenberg:

1.E.1. The following sentence, with active links to, or other
immediate access to, the full Project Gutenberg™ License must appear
prominently whenever any copy of a Project Gutenberg™ work (any work
on which the phrase “Project Gutenberg” appears, or with which the
phrase “Project Gutenberg” is associated) is accessed, displayed,
performed, viewed, copied or distributed:

    This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere in the United States and most
    other parts of the world at no cost and with almost no restrictions
    whatsoever. You may copy it, give it away or re-use it under the terms
    of the Project Gutenberg License included with this eBook or online
    at www.gutenberg.org. If you
    are not located in the United States, you will have to check the laws
    of the country where you are located before using this eBook.
  
1.E.2. If an individual Project Gutenberg™ electronic work is
derived from texts not protected by U.S. copyright law (does not
contain a notice indicating that it is posted with permission of the
copyright holder), the work can be copied and distributed to anyone in
the United States without paying any fees or charges. If you are
redistributing or providing access to a work with the phrase “Project
Gutenberg” associated with or appearing on the work, you must comply
either with the requirements of paragraphs 1.E.1 through 1.E.7 or
obtain permission for the use of the work and the Project Gutenberg™
trademark as set forth in paragraphs 1.E.8 or 1.E.9.

1.E.3. If an individual Project Gutenberg™ electronic work is posted
with the permission of the copyright holder, your use and distribution
must comply with both paragraphs 1.E.1 through 1.E.7 and any
additional terms imposed by the copyright holder. Additional terms
will be linked to the Project Gutenberg™ License for all works
posted with the permission of the copyright holder found at the
beginning of this work.

1.E.4. Do not unlink or detach or remove the full Project Gutenberg™
License terms from this work, or any files containing a part of this
work or any other work associated with Project Gutenberg™.

1.E.5. Do not copy, display, perform, distribute or redistribute this
electronic work, or any part of this electronic work, without
prominently displaying the sentence set forth in paragraph 1.E.1 with
active links or immediate access to the full terms of the Project
Gutenberg™ License.

1.E.6. You may convert to and distribute this work in any binary,
compressed, marked up, nonproprietary or proprietary form, including
any word processing or hypertext form. However, if you provide access
to or distribute copies of a Project Gutenberg™ work in a format
other than “Plain Vanilla ASCII” or other format used in the official
version posted on the official Project Gutenberg™ website
(www.gutenberg.org), you must, at no additional cost, fee or expense
to the user, provide a copy, a means of exporting a copy, or a means
of obtaining a copy upon request, of the work in its original “Plain
Vanilla ASCII” or other form. Any alternate format must include the
full Project Gutenberg™ License as specified in paragraph 1.E.1.

1.E.7. Do not charge a fee for access to, viewing, displaying,
performing, copying or distributing any Project Gutenberg™ works
unless you comply with paragraph 1.E.8 or 1.E.9.

1.E.8. You may charge a reasonable fee for copies of or providing
access to or distributing Project Gutenberg™ electronic works
provided that:

• You pay a royalty fee of 20% of the gross profits you derive from
        the use of Project Gutenberg™ works calculated using the method
        you already use to calculate your applicable taxes. The fee is owed
        to the owner of the Project Gutenberg™ trademark, but he has
        agreed to donate royalties under this paragraph to the Project
        Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation. Royalty payments must be paid
        within 60 days following each date on which you prepare (or are
        legally required to prepare) your periodic tax returns. Royalty
        payments should be clearly marked as such and sent to the Project
        Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation at the address specified in
        Section 4, “Information about donations to the Project Gutenberg
        Literary Archive Foundation.”
    
• You provide a full refund of any money paid by a user who notifies
        you in writing (or by e-mail) within 30 days of receipt that s/he
        does not agree to the terms of the full Project Gutenberg™
        License. You must require such a user to return or destroy all
        copies of the works possessed in a physical medium and discontinue
        all use of and all access to other copies of Project Gutenberg™
        works.
    
• You provide, in accordance with paragraph 1.F.3, a full refund of
        any money paid for a work or a replacement copy, if a defect in the
        electronic work is discovered and reported to you within 90 days of
        receipt of the work.
    
• You comply with all other terms of this agreement for free
        distribution of Project Gutenberg™ works.
    

1.E.9. If you wish to charge a fee or distribute a Project
Gutenberg™ electronic work or group of works on different terms than
are set forth in this agreement, you must obtain permission in writing
from the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation, the manager of
the Project Gutenberg™ trademark. Contact the Foundation as set
forth in Section 3 below.

1.F.

1.F.1. Project Gutenberg volunteers and employees expend considerable
effort to identify, do copyright research on, transcribe and proofread
works not protected by U.S. copyright law in creating the Project
Gutenberg™ collection. Despite these efforts, Project Gutenberg™
electronic works, and the medium on which they may be stored, may
contain “Defects,” such as, but not limited to, incomplete, inaccurate
or corrupt data, transcription errors, a copyright or other
intellectual property infringement, a defective or damaged disk or
other medium, a computer virus, or computer codes that damage or
cannot be read by your equipment.

1.F.2. LIMITED WARRANTY, DISCLAIMER OF DAMAGES - Except for the “Right
of Replacement or Refund” described in paragraph 1.F.3, the Project
Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation, the owner of the Project
Gutenberg™ trademark, and any other party distributing a Project
Gutenberg™ electronic work under this agreement, disclaim all
liability to you for damages, costs and expenses, including legal
fees. YOU AGREE THAT YOU HAVE NO REMEDIES FOR NEGLIGENCE, STRICT
LIABILITY, BREACH OF WARRANTY OR BREACH OF CONTRACT EXCEPT THOSE
PROVIDED IN PARAGRAPH 1.F.3. YOU AGREE THAT THE FOUNDATION, THE
TRADEMARK OWNER, AND ANY DISTRIBUTOR UNDER THIS AGREEMENT WILL NOT BE
LIABLE TO YOU FOR ACTUAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, CONSEQUENTIAL, PUNITIVE OR
INCIDENTAL DAMAGES EVEN IF YOU GIVE NOTICE OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH
DAMAGE.

1.F.3. LIMITED RIGHT OF REPLACEMENT OR REFUND - If you discover a
defect in this electronic work within 90 days of receiving it, you can
receive a refund of the money (if any) you paid for it by sending a
written explanation to the person you received the work from. If you
received the work on a physical medium, you must return the medium
with your written explanation. The person or entity that provided you
with the defective work may elect to provide a replacement copy in
lieu of a refund. If you received the work electronically, the person
or entity providing it to you may choose to give you a second
opportunity to receive the work electronically in lieu of a refund. If
the second copy is also defective, you may demand a refund in writing
without further opportunities to fix the problem.

1.F.4. Except for the limited right of replacement or refund set forth
in paragraph 1.F.3, this work is provided to you ‘AS-IS’, WITH NO
OTHER WARRANTIES OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT
LIMITED TO WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR ANY PURPOSE.

1.F.5. Some states do not allow disclaimers of certain implied
warranties or the exclusion or limitation of certain types of
damages. If any disclaimer or limitation set forth in this agreement
violates the law of the state applicable to this agreement, the
agreement shall be interpreted to make the maximum disclaimer or
limitation permitted by the applicable state law. The invalidity or
unenforceability of any provision of this agreement shall not void the
remaining provisions.

1.F.6. INDEMNITY - You agree to indemnify and hold the Foundation, the
trademark owner, any agent or employee of the Foundation, anyone
providing copies of Project Gutenberg™ electronic works in
accordance with this agreement, and any volunteers associated with the
production, promotion and distribution of Project Gutenberg™
electronic works, harmless from all liability, costs and expenses,
including legal fees, that arise directly or indirectly from any of
the following which you do or cause to occur: (a) distribution of this
or any Project Gutenberg™ work, (b) alteration, modification, or
additions or deletions to any Project Gutenberg™ work, and (c) any
Defect you cause.

Section 2. Information about the Mission of Project Gutenberg™

Project Gutenberg™ is synonymous with the free distribution of
electronic works in formats readable by the widest variety of
computers including obsolete, old, middle-aged and new computers. It
exists because of the efforts of hundreds of volunteers and donations
from people in all walks of life.

Volunteers and financial support to provide volunteers with the
assistance they need are critical to reaching Project Gutenberg™’s
goals and ensuring that the Project Gutenberg™ collection will
remain freely available for generations to come. In 2001, the Project
Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation was created to provide a secure
and permanent future for Project Gutenberg™ and future
generations. To learn more about the Project Gutenberg Literary
Archive Foundation and how your efforts and donations can help, see
Sections 3 and 4 and the Foundation information page at www.gutenberg.org.

Section 3. Information about the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation

The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation is a non-profit
501(c)(3) educational corporation organized under the laws of the
state of Mississippi and granted tax exempt status by the Internal
Revenue Service. The Foundation’s EIN or federal tax identification
number is 64-6221541. Contributions to the Project Gutenberg Literary
Archive Foundation are tax deductible to the full extent permitted by
U.S. federal laws and your state’s laws.

The Foundation’s business office is located at 809 North 1500 West,
Salt Lake City, UT 84116, (801) 596-1887. Email contact links and up
to date contact information can be found at the Foundation’s website
and official page at www.gutenberg.org/contact

Section 4. Information about Donations to the Project Gutenberg
Literary Archive Foundation

Project Gutenberg™ depends upon and cannot survive without widespread
public support and donations to carry out its mission of
increasing the number of public domain and licensed works that can be
freely distributed in machine-readable form accessible by the widest
array of equipment including outdated equipment. Many small donations
($1 to $5,000) are particularly important to maintaining tax exempt
status with the IRS.

The Foundation is committed to complying with the laws regulating
charities and charitable donations in all 50 states of the United
States. Compliance requirements are not uniform and it takes a
considerable effort, much paperwork and many fees to meet and keep up
with these requirements. We do not solicit donations in locations
where we have not received written confirmation of compliance. To SEND
DONATIONS or determine the status of compliance for any particular state
visit www.gutenberg.org/donate.

While we cannot and do not solicit contributions from states where we
have not met the solicitation requirements, we know of no prohibition
against accepting unsolicited donations from donors in such states who
approach us with offers to donate.

International donations are gratefully accepted, but we cannot make
any statements concerning tax treatment of donations received from
outside the United States. U.S. laws alone swamp our small staff.

Please check the Project Gutenberg web pages for current donation
methods and addresses. Donations are accepted in a number of other
ways including checks, online payments and credit card donations. To
donate, please visit: www.gutenberg.org/donate.

Section 5. General Information About Project Gutenberg™ electronic works

Professor Michael S. Hart was the originator of the Project
Gutenberg™ concept of a library of electronic works that could be
freely shared with anyone. For forty years, he produced and
distributed Project Gutenberg™ eBooks with only a loose network of
volunteer support.

Project Gutenberg™ eBooks are often created from several printed
editions, all of which are confirmed as not protected by copyright in
the U.S. unless a copyright notice is included. Thus, we do not
necessarily keep eBooks in compliance with any particular paper
edition.

Most people start at our website which has the main PG search
facility: www.gutenberg.org.

This website includes information about Project Gutenberg™,
including how to make donations to the Project Gutenberg Literary
Archive Foundation, how to help produce our new eBooks, and how to
subscribe to our email newsletter to hear about new eBooks.
</div></body></text></TEI>