<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="34">CHAPTER XXXII.
Philip the Second, king of Spain, succeeded to the throne
of that monarchy about the close of the year 1555; but
his affairs in England and the Netherlands long withheld
him from visiting his beloved country, and he did not reach
its shores, after a seven years’ absence, till the twenty-ninth
of August, 1559. It may be thought that a public event
of this sort could be little interesting to me, a forgotten
prisoner, immured in the dungeons of the inquisition.
The fact was otherwise. The king was desirous of distinguishing
his arrival on his native soil by some splendid
exhibition or memorable event, that should at once express
his piety to God, and conduce to the felicity of his people:
and he could think of nothing that so signally united
these characters as an Auto de Fé. The Lutheran heresy,
which in the course of forty years had spread its poison so
widely in the different countries of Europe, had not failed
to scatter a few of its noxious seeds even in this, the
purest and most Catholic of all its divisions. But Philip
had early proclaimed his hostility against this innovation;
and, prostrating himself before the image of his Saviour,
had earnestly besought the divine majesty, “that he might
never suffer himself to be, or to be called, the lord of those
in any corner of the globe, who should deny Him the
Lord.” Previously to his arrival in Spain, directions had
been given, and arrangements made, respecting the pious
and solemn exhibition he demanded. Formerly those who
by the fathers of the inquisition had been delivered over to
the secular arm, had been executed in the different places
where their crimes had been committed, or their trials been
held: but now it was proposed that all those throughout
the kingdom, who were found properly qualified to satisfy
by their deaths the sublime taste of the royal saint, should
be divided into two troops, and sent, the one to Seville,
long the capital of an illustrious monarchy, and the other
to Valladolid, which had the honour to be the birthplace
of the present sovereign. The troop destined to feed the[337]
flames at Seville was composed of fifty persons, many of
them distinguished for their rank, their talents, or their
virtues. The troop to be escorted to Valladolid, of which
I was a member, amounted only to thirty: but to compensate
this deficiency, Philip himself had signified his gracious
intention to be present, together with the heir apparent and
his whole court, at that exhibition. The Spanish nation,
rejoicing in the approach of a monarch who was born
among them, whose manners and temper happily accorded
with theirs, and whom they believed about to fix his perpetual
residence in their land, expected him with all the
longings of the most ardent attachment. We, the unhappy
victims of pious and inquisitorial tyranny, also expected him.
Our hearts did not pant with a less beating quickness;
though our anxiety arose from emotions of a different nature.
Valladolid is distant from the metropolis eighty-four
miles. We had already been some weeks prepared for this
journey, and piously directed to hold ourselves in readiness
to take our part in the solemn national sacrifice. We
waited however to receive a previous notice of the day on
which the monarch would enter the place of his birth,
since so great was his royal zeal for the cause of religion
and civil society, that he would not consent to be absent
from any part of the spectacle; and accordingly it was not
allowed us to enter the scene of our final destination, till
the king of Spain and the Indies should be already on the
spot, and prepared to receive us. The auto da fé performed
at Seville had the precedence of ours: it took place
on the twenty-fourth of September; and we were indulged
with an accurate account of it, and were present at a public
reading of the record of the act, in the chapel of our prison,
previously to our removal from the metropolis.
I will not enter into a minute detail of the scene of this
reading, though the recollection will never be effaced from
my memory. Of the persons present who were destined to
suffer capital punishment, eight were women. Four of
them were taken from a single family, being a grandmother,
a mother, and two daughters of the noble house of Alcala.
They had all been beautiful of person, and of a graceful
figure; the youngest of the daughters was in the nineteenth[338]
year of her age. Their crime, together with that of the
majority of their fellow-sufferers, was obstinate and impenitent
Lutheranism. The seats of the women were separated
from the rest, and fronted with a close lattice. The
men were twenty-two in number, and their appearance was
truly impressive. Their persons were neglected, and their
figures emaciated; their eyes were sunk and ghastly, and
their complexions of a sallow and death-like white. Most
of them were crippled by their long confinement and the
severities they had endured, and were supported to their
seats, upon an elevated scaffolding with benches raised one
above another, by two apparators, one on each side of the
condemned heretic. God of mercy and benevolence! is it
possible that this scene should be regarded as thy triumph,
and the execution destined to follow, as a sacrifice acceptable
in thy sight? If these papers of mine are ever produced
to light, may it not happen that they shall first be
read by a distant posterity, who will refuse to believe that
their fathers were ever mad enough to subject each other to
so horrible a treatment, merely because they were unable
to adopt each other’s opinions? Oh, no! human affairs,
like the waves of the ocean, are merely in a state of ebb
and flow: “there is nothing new under the sun:” two
centuries perhaps after Philip the Second shall be gathered
to his ancestors [he died in 1598], men shall learn over
again to persecute each other for conscience sake; other
anabaptists or levellers shall furnish pretexts for new persecutions;
other inquisitors shall arise in the most enlightened
tracts of Europe; and professors from their chair,
sheltering their intolerance under the great names of Aristotle
and Cicero, shall instruct their scholars, that a heterodox
doctrine is the worst of crimes, and that the philanthropy
and purity of heart in which it is maintained, only
render its defenders the more worthy to be extirpated.
What were the ideas and reflections of my fellows, seated
on the benches above, below, and on either side of me, I
am unable to affirm; my own could not fail to be pungent
and distressing. I understood continually more and more
of the mysterious and unuttered history, of the stranger
who died in the summer-house of the lake of Constance:[339]
I found that I was only acting over again what he had
experienced before me. His legacies had served to involve
me in the bitterest and most unheard of miseries, but were
wholly destitute of ability to rescue from the evils themselves
created. Unbounded wealth I found to have no
power to bribe the dastard slaves of religious bigotry; and
the elixir of immortality, though it could cure disease, and
put to flight the approaches of age, was impotent to repel
the fervour of devouring flames. I might have been happy——I
was happy when the stranger found me. I might
have lived to a virtuous and venerable old age, and have
died in the arms of my posterity. The stranger had given
me wealth, and I was now poorer than the peasant who
wanders amidst polar snows. The stranger had given me
immortality, and in a few days I was to expire in excruciating
tortures. He found me tranquil, contented, in the
midst of simple, yet inestimable pleasures; he breathed into
me the restless sentiment of ambition; and it was that sentiment
which at length had placed me on high in the chapel
of the prison of the Catholic Inquisition.
Our progress to Valladolid was slow and solemn, and
occupied a space of no less than four days. On the evening
of the fourth day we approached that city. The king
and his court came out to meet us. He saluted the inquisitor
general with all the demonstrations of the deepest
submission and humility; and then, having yielded him
the place of honour, turned round his horse, and accompanied
us to Valladolid. The cavalcade that attended the
king broke into two files, and received us in the midst of
them. The whole city seemed to empty itself on this memorable
occasion; and the multitudes that crowded along
the road, and were scattered in the neighbouring fields,
were innumerable. The day was now closed; and the procession
went forward amidst the light of a thousand torches.
We, the condemned of the inquisition, had been conducted
from the metropolis upon tumbrils; but, as we arrived at
the gates of Valladolid, we were commanded, for the greater
humiliation, to alight and proceed on foot to the place of
our confinement, as many as could not walk without assistance
being supported by the attendants. We were[340]
neither chained nor bound; the practice of the inquisition
being to deliver the condemned upon such occasions into
the hands of two sureties each, who placed their charge in
the middle between them; and men of the most respectable
characters were accustomed from religious motives to sue
for this melancholy office.
Dejected and despairing I entered the streets of the city,
no object present to the eyes of my mind but that of my
approaching execution. The crowd was vast; the confusion
inexpressible. As we passed by the end of a narrow
lane, the horse of one of the guards who rode exactly in a
line with me, plunged and reared in a violent manner, and
at length threw his rider upon the pavement. Others of
the horse-guards attempted to catch the bridle of the enraged
animal. They rushed against each other. Several
of the crowd were thrown down, and trampled under the
horses’ feet. The shrieks of these, and the loud cries and
exclamations of the bystanders, mingled in confused and
discordant chorus. No sound, no object could be distinguished.
From the excess of the tumult a sudden thought
darted into my mind, where all, an instant before, had been
relaxation and despair. Two or three of the horses pushed
forward in a particular direction. A moment after they
resiled with equal violence, and left a wide, but transitory
gap. My project was no sooner conceived than executed.
Weak as I had just now felt myself, a supernatural tide of
strength seemed to come over me. I sprung away with all
imaginable impetuosity, and rushed down the lane I have
just mentioned. Every one amidst the confusion was attentive
to his personal safety, and several minutes elapsed
before I was missed.
</div></body></text></TEI>