<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="22">
CHAPTER VI.
General Rules for the Construction of the Conception.
Aphorism XXXVIII.
The Construction of the Conception very often includes, in
a great measure, the Determination of the Magnitudes.
Aphorism XXXIX.
When a series of progressive numbers is given as the
result of observation, it may generally be reduced to law by
combinations of arithmetical and geometrical progressions.
Aphorism XL.
A true formula for a progressive series of numbers cannot
commonly be obtained from a narrow range of observations.
Aphorism XLI.
Recurrent series of numbers must, in most cases, be expressed
by circular formulæ.
Aphorism XLII.
The true construction of the conception is frequently suggested
by some hypothesis; and in these cases, the hypothesis
may be useful, though containing superfluous parts.
1. IN
speaking of the discovery of laws of nature,
those which depend upon quantity, as number,
space, and the like, are most prominent and most easily
conceived, and therefore in speaking of such researches,
we shall often use language which applies peculiarly to 196
the cases in which quantities numerically measurable
are concerned, leaving it for a subsequent task to extend
our principles to ideas of other kinds.
Hence we may at present consider the Construction
of a Conception which shall include and connect the
facts, as being the construction of a Mathematical Formula,
coinciding with the numerical expression of the
facts; and we have to consider how this process can be
facilitated, it being supposed that we have already before
us the numerical measures given by observation.
2. We may remark, however, that the construction
of the right Formula for any such case, and the determination
of the Coefficients of such formula, which we
have spoken of as two separate steps, are in practice
almost necessarily simultaneous; for the near coincidence
of the results of the theoretical rule with the
observed facts confirms at the same time the Formula
and its Coefficients. In this case also, the mode of
arriving at truth is to try various hypotheses;—to
modify the hypotheses so as to approximate to the
facts, and to multiply the facts so as to test the hypotheses.
The Independent Variable, and the Formula which
we would try, being once selected, mathematicians have
devised certain special and technical processes by which
the value of the coefficients may be determined. These
we shall treat of in the next Chapter; but in the mean
time we may note, in a more general manner, the mode
in which, in physical researches, the proper formula
may be obtained.
3. A person somewhat versed in mathematics, having before
him a series of numbers, will generally be
able to devise a formula which approaches near to
those numbers. If, for instance, the series is constantly
progressive, he will be able to see whether it
more nearly resembles an arithmetical or a geometrical
progression. For example, MM. Dulong and Petit, in
their investigation of the law of cooling of bodies,
obtained the following series of measures. A thermometer,
made hot, was placed in an enclosure of which
the temperature was 0 degrees, and the rapidity of 197
cooling of the thermometer was noted for many temperatures.
It was found that
For the temperature 240the rapidity of cooling was10·69
〃220〃8·81
〃200〃7·40
〃180〃6·10
〃160〃4·89
〃140〃3·88
and so on. Now this series of numbers manifestly increases
with greater rapidity as we proceed from the
lower to the higher parts of the scale. The numbers
do not, however, form a geometrical series, as we may
easily ascertain. But if we were to take the differences
of the successive terms we should find them to be—
1·88, 1·41, 1·30, 1·21, 1·01, &c.
and these numbers are very nearly the terms of a geometric
series. For if we divide each term by the succeeding one,
we find these numbers,
1·33, 1·09, 1·07, 1·20, 1·27,
in which there does not appear to be any constant tendency
to diminish or increase. And we shall find that
a geometrical series in which the ratio is 1·165, may be
made to approach very near to this series, the deviations
from it being only such as may be accounted for
by conceiving them as errours of observation. In this
manner a certain formula26
is obtained, giving results 198
which very nearly coincide with the observed facts, as
may be seen in the margin.
26
 The formula is v = 2·037(at − 1) where
v is the velocity of cooling, t the
temperature of the thermometer expressed in degrees, and a is the
quantity, 1·0077.
 The degree of coincidence is as follows:—


Excess of temperature of the thermometer, orvalues  of t.
Observed valuesof v.
Calculated valuesof v.
24010·6910·68
220 8·81  8·89
200 7·40  7·34
180 6·10 6·03
160 4·89  4·87
140 3·88 3·89
120 3·02 3·05
100 2·30  2·33
 80 1·74  1·72
The physical law expressed by the formula just
spoken of is this:—that when a body is cooling in an
empty inclosure which is kept at a constant temperature,
the quickness of the cooling, for excesses of temperature
in arithmetical progression, increases as the
terms of a geometrical progression, diminished by a
constant number.
4. In the actual investigation of Dulong and Petit,
however, the formula was not obtained in precisely the
manner just described. For the quickness of cooling
depends upon two elements, the temperature of the hot
body and the temperature of the inclosure; not merely
upon the excess of one of these over the other. And
it was found most convenient, first, to make such experiments
as should exhibit the dependence of the velocity of cooling
upon the temperature of the enclosure;
which dependence is contained in the following law:—The
quickness of cooling of a thermometer in vacuo
for a constant excess of temperature, increases in geometric
progression, when the temperature of the inclosure increases
in arithmetic progression. From this
law the preceding one follows by necessary
consequence27.
27
 For if θ be the temperature of the inclosure,
and t the excess of temperature of the hot body, it appears,
by this law, that the radiation of heat is as aθ. And hence
the quickness of cooling, which is as the excess of radiation,
is as aθ + t − aθ;
that is, as aθ(at − 1)
which agrees with the formula given in the last note.
 The whole of this series of researches of Dulong and Petit is
full of the most beautiful and instructive artifices for the
construction of the proper formulæ in physical research.
This example may serve to show the nature of the
artifices which may be used for the construction of
formulæ, when we have a constantly progressive series
of numbers to represent. We must not only endeavour
by trial to contrive a formula which will answer the
conditions, but we must vary our experiments so as to
determine, first one factor or portion of the formula,
and then the other; and we must use the most
199 probable
hypothesis as means of suggestion for our formulæ.
5. In a progressive series of numbers, unless the
formula which we adopt be really that which expresses
the law of nature, the deviations of the formula from
the facts will generally become enormous, when the
experiments are extended into new parts of the scale.
True formulæ for a progressive series of results can
hardly ever be obtained from a very limited range of
experiments: just as the attempt to guess the general
course of a road or a river, by knowing two or three
points of it in the neighbourhood of one another, would
generally fail. In the investigation respecting the
laws of the cooling of bodies just noticed, one great
advantage of the course pursued by the experimenters
was, that their experiments included so great a range
of temperatures. The attempts to assign the law of
elasticity of steam deduced from experiments made
with moderate temperatures, were found to be enormously
wrong, when very high temperatures were
made the subject of experiment. It is easy to see that
this must be so: an arithmetical and a geometrical
series may nearly coincide for a few terms moderately
near each other: but if we take remote corresponding
terms in the two series, one of these will be very many
times the other. And hence, from a narrow range of
experiments, we may infer one of these series when we
ought to infer the other; and thus obtain a law which
is widely erroneous.
6. In Astronomy, the series of observations which
we have to study are, for the most part, not progressive,
but recurrent. The numbers observed do not go on
constantly increasing; but after increasing up to a certain
amount they diminish; then, after a certain space,
increase again; and so on, changing constantly through
certain cycles. In cases in which the observed numbers
are of this kind, the formula which expresses them
must be a circular function, of some sort or other;
involving, for instance, sines, tangents, and other forms
of calculation, which have recurring values when the
angle on which they depend goes on constantly 200
increasing. The main business of formal astronomy consists
in resolving the celestial phenomena into a series
of terms of this kind, in detecting their arguments, and
in determining their coefficients.
7. In constructing the formulæ by which laws of
nature are expressed, although the first object is to
assign the Law of the Phenomena, philosophers have,
in almost all cases, not proceeded in a purely empirical
manner, to connect the observed numbers by some expression
of calculation, but have been guided, in the
selection of their formula, by some Hypothesis
respecting the mode of connexion of the facts.
Thus the formula of Dulong and Petit above given was suggested
by the Theory of Exchanges; the first attempts at the
resolution of the heavenly motions into circular functions
were clothed in the hypothesis of Epicycles. And
this was almost inevitable. ‘We must confess,’ says
Copernicus28,
‘that the celestial motions are circular,
or compounded of several circles, since their inequalities
observe a fixed law, and recur in value at certain
intervals, which could not be except they were circular:
for a circle alone can make that quantity which
has occurred recur again.’ In like manner the first
publication of the Law of the Sines, the true formula of
optical refraction, was accompanied by Descartes with
an hypothesis, in which an explanation of the law was
pretended. In such cases, the mere comparison of
observations may long fail in suggesting the true formulæ.
The fringes of shadows and other diffracted
colours were studied in vain by Newton, Grimaldi,
Comparetti, the elder Herschel, and Mr. Brougham,
so long as these inquirers attempted merely to trace
the laws of the facts as they appeared in themselves;
while Young, Fresnel, Fraunhofer, Schwerdt, and
others, determined these laws in the most rigorous
manner, when they applied to the observations the
Hypothesis of Interferences.
28
 De Rev. l. i. c. iv.
8. But with all the aid that Hypotheses and Calculation
can afford, the construction of true formulæ, in 201
those cardinal discoveries by which the progress of
science has mainly been caused, has been a matter of
great labour and difficulty, and of good fortune added
to sagacity. In the History of Science, we have seen
how long and how hard Kepler laboured, before he
converted the formula for the planetary motions, from
an epicyclical combination, to a simple ellipse. The same
philosopher, labouring with equal zeal and perseverance
to discover the formula of optical refraction, which
now appears to us so simple, was utterly foiled. Malus
sought in vain the formula determining the Angle at
which a transparent surface polarizes light: Sir D.
Brewster29,
with a happy sagacity, discovered
the formula to be simply this, that the index of refraction is
the tangent of the angle of polarization.
29
 Hist. Ind. Sc. b. ix. c. vi.
Though we cannot give rules which will be of
much service when we have thus to divine the general
form of the relation by which phenomena are connected,
there are certain methods by which, in a narrower field,
our investigations may be materially promoted;—certain
special methods of obtaining laws
from Observations. Of these we shall now proceed to
treat.
</div></body></text></TEI>