<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="15">

BOOK VII.

PHYSICAL ASTRONOMY.

CHAPTER I.
Prelude to Newton.

The Ancients.
EXPRESSIONS in ancient writers
which may be interpreted as indicating a notion of gravitation in the
Newtonian sense, no doubt occur. But such a notion, we may be sure,
must have been in the highest degree obscure, wavering, and partial. I
have mentioned (Book i. Chap. 3) an author who
has fancied that he traces in the works of the ancients the origin of
most of the vaunted discoveries of the moderns. But to ascribe much
importance to such expressions would be to give a false representation
of the real progress of science. Yet some of Newton’s followers put
forward these passages as well deserving notice; and Newton himself
appears to have had some pleasure in citing such expressions; probably
with the feeling that they relieved him of some of the odium which, he
seems to have apprehended, hung over new discoveries. The Preface to
the Principia, begins by quoting40 the authority of
the ancients, as well as the moderns, in favor of applying the science
of Mechanics to Natural Philosophy. In the Preface to David Gregory’s
Astronomiæ Physicæ et Geometricæ Elementa, published in 1702,
is a large array of names of ancient authors, and of quotations, to
prove the early and wide diffusion of the doctrine of the gravity of
the Heavenly Bodies. And it appears to be now made out, that this
collection of ancient authorities 545 was supplied to Gregory by Newton
himself. The late Professor Rigaud, in his Historical Essay on the
First Publication of Sir Isaac Newton’s Principia, says (pp. 80
and 101) that having been allowed to examine Gregory’s papers, he
found that the quotations given by him in his Preface are copied or
abridged from notes which Newton had supplied to him in his own
handwriting. Some of the most noticeable of the quotations are those
taken from Plutarch’s Dialogue on the Face which appears in the
Moon’s Disk: it is there said, for example, by one of the
speakers, that the Moon is perhaps prevented from falling to the earth
by the rapidity of her revolution round it; as a stone whirled in a
sling keeps it stretched. Lucretius also is quoted, as teaching that
all bodies would descend with an equal celerity in a vacuum:</div></body></text></TEI>