<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Personal Narrative of Travels, Volume 1</title><author>Humboldt, Alexander von (1769-1859)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1814</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="14">CHAPTER 1.15.
DEPARTURE FROM CARACAS.
MOUNTAINS OF SAN PEDRO AND OF LOS TEQUES.
LA VICTORIA.
VALLEYS OF ARAGUA.
To take the shortest road from Caracas to the banks of the Orinoco,
we should have crossed the southern chain of mountains between
Baruta, Salamanca, and the savannahs of Ocumare, passed over the
steppes or llanos of Orituco, and embarked at Cabruta, near the
mouth of the Rio Guarico. But this direct route would have deprived
us of the opportunity of surveying the valleys of Aragua, which are
the finest and most cultivated portion of the province; of taking
the level of an important part of the chain of the coast by means
of the barometer; and of descending the Rio Apure as far as its
junction with the Orinoco. A traveller who has the intention of
studying the configuration and natural productions of a country is
not guided by distances, but by the peculiar interest attached to
the regions he may traverse. This powerful motive led us to the
mountains of Los Teques, to the hot springs of Mariara, to the
fertile banks of the lake of Valencia, and through the immense
savannahs of Calabozo to San Fernando de Apure, in the eastern part
of the province of Varinas. Having determined on this route, our
first direction was westward, then southward, and finally to
east-south-east, so that we might enter the Orinoco by the Apure in
latitude 7 degrees 36 minutes 23 seconds.
On the day on which we quitted the capital of Venezuela, we reached
the foot of the woody mountains which close the valley on the
south-west. There we halted for the night, and on the following day
we proceeded along the right bank of the Rio Guayra as far as the
village of Antimano, by a very fine road, partly scooped out of the
rock. We passed by La Vega and Carapa. The church of La Vega rises
very picturesquely above a range of hills covered with thick
vegetation. Scattered houses surrounded with date-trees seem to
denote the comfort of their inhabitants. A chain of low mountains
separates the little river Guayra from the valley of La Pascua* (so
celebrated in the history of the country) (* Valley of Cortes, or
Easter Valley, so called because Diego de Losada, after having
defeated the Teques Indians, and their cacique Guaycaypuro, in the
mountains of San Pedro, spent the Easter there in 1567, before
entering the valley of San Francisco. In the latter place he
founded the city of Caracas.), and from the ancient gold-mines of
Baruta and Oripoto. Ascending in the direction of Carapa, we enjoy
once more the sight of the Silla, which appears like an immense
dome with a cliff on the side next the sea. This rounded summit,
and the ridge of Galipano crenated like a wall, are the only
objects which in this basin of gneiss and mica-slate impress a
peculiar character on the landscape. The other mountains have a
uniform and monotonous aspect.
A little before reaching the village of Antimano we observed on the
right a very curious geological phenomenon. In hollowing the new
road out of the rock, two large veins of gneiss were discovered in
the mica-slate. They are nearly perpendicular, intersecting all the
mica-slate strata, and are from six to eight toises thick. These
veins contain not fragments, but balls or spheres of granular
diabasis,* formed of concentric layers. (* Ur-grunstein. I remember
having seen similar balls filling a vein in transition-slate, near
the castle of Schauenstein in the margravate of Bayreuth. I sent
several balls from Antimano to the collection of the king of Spain
at Madrid.) These balls are composed of lamellar feldspar and
hornblende closely commingled. The feldspar approximates sometimes
to vitreous feldspar when disseminated in very thin laminae in a
mass of granular diabasis, decomposed, and emitting a strong
argillaceous smell. The diameter of the spheres is very unequal,
sometimes four or eight inches, sometimes three or four feet; their
nucleus, which is more dense, is without concentric layers, and of
a very dark green hue, inclining to black. I could not perceive any
mica in them; but, what is very remarkable, I found great
quantities of disseminated garnets. These garnets are of a very
fine red, and are found in the grunstein only. They are neither in
the gneiss, which serves as a cement to the balls, nor in the
mica-slate, which the veins traverse. The gneiss, the constituent
parts of which are in a state of considerable disintegration,
contains large crystals of feldspar; and, though it forms the body
of the vein in the mica-slate, it is itself traversed by threads of
quartz two inches thick, and of very recent formation. The aspect
of this phenomenon is very curious: it appears as if cannon-balls
were embedded in a wall of rock. I also thought I recognized in
these same regions, in the Montana de Avila, and at Cabo Blanco,
east of La Guayra, a granular diabasis, mixed with a small quantity
of quartz and pyrites, and destitute of garnets, not in veins, but
in subordinate strata in the mica-slate. This position is
unquestionably to be found in Europe in primitive mountains; but in
general the granular diabasis is more frequently connected with the
system of transition rocks, especially with a schist
(ubergangs-thonschiefer) abounding in beds of Lydian stone strongly
carburetted, of schistose jasper,* (Kieselschiefer.) ampelites,*
(Alaunschiefer.) and black limestone.
Near Antimano all the orchards were full of peach-trees loaded with
blossom. This village, the Valle, and the banks of the Macarao,
furnish great abundance of peaches, quinces, and other European
fruits for the market of Caracas. Between Antimano and Ajuntas we
crossed the Rio Guayra seventeen times. The road is very fatiguing;
yet, instead of making a new one, it would perhaps be better to
change the bed of the river, which loses a great quantity of water
by the combined effects of filtration and evaporation. Each
sinuosity forms a marsh more or less extensive. This loss of water
is to be regretted in a province, nearly all the cultivated
portions of which are extremely dry. The rains are much less
frequent and less violent in this place than in the interior of New
Andalusia, at Cumanacoa, and on the banks of the Guarapiche. Many
of the mountains of Caracas enter the region of the clouds; but the
strata of primitive rocks dip at an angle of 70 or 80 degrees, and
generally to northwest, so that the waters are either lost in the
interior of the earth, or gush out in copious springs not southward
but northward of the mountains of the coast of Niguatar, Avila, and
Mariara. The rising of the gneiss and mica-slate strata to the
south appears to me to explain in a considerable degree the extreme
humidity of the coast. In the interior of the province we meet with
portions of land, two or three leagues square, in which there are
no springs; consequently sugar-cane, indigo, and coffee, grow only
in places where running waters can be made to supply artificial
irrigation during very dry weather. The early colonists imprudently
destroyed the forests. Evaporation is enormous on a stony soil
surrounded with rocks, which radiate heat on every side. The
mountains of the coast, like a wall, extending east and west from
Cape Codera toward Point Tucacas, prevent the humid air of the
shore (that is to say, those inferior strata of the atmosphere
resting immediately on the sea, and dissolving the largest
proportion of water) from penetrating to the islands. There are few
openings, few ravines, which, like those of Catia or of Tipe, lead
from the coast to the high longitudinal valleys, and there is no
bed of a great river, no gulf allowing the sea to flow inland,
spreading moisture by abundant evaporation. In the eighth and tenth
degrees of latitude, in regions where the clouds do not, as it
were, skim the surface of the soil, many trees are stripped of
their leaves in the months of January and February; not by the
sinking of the temperature as in Europe, but because the air at
this period, the most distant from the rainy season, nearly attains
its maximum of dryness. Only those plants which have very tough and
glossy leaves resist this absence of humidity. Beneath the fine sky
of the tropics the traveller is struck with the almost hibernal
aspect of the country; but the freshest verdure again appears when
he reaches the banks of the Orinoco, where another climate
prevails; and the great forests preserve by their shade a certain
quantity of moisture in the soil, by sheltering it from the
devouring heat of the sun.
Beyond the small village of Antimano the valley becomes much
narrower. The river is bordered with Lata, a fine gramineous plant
with distich leaves, which sometimes reaches the height of thirty
feet.* (* G. saccharoides.) Every hut is surrounded with enormous
trees of persea,* (* Laurus persea (alligator pear).) at the foot
of which the aristolochiae, paullinia, and other creepers vegetate.
The neighbouring mountains, covered with forests, seem to spread
humidity over the western extremity of the valley of Caracas. We
passed the night before our arrival at Las Ajuntas at a sugar-cane
plantation. A square house (the hacienda or farm of Don Fernando
Key-Munoz) contained nearly eighty negroes; they were lying on
skins of oxen spread upon the ground. In each apartment of the
house were four slaves: it looked like a barrack. A dozen fires
were burning in the farm-yard, where people were employed in
dressing food, and the noisy mirth of the blacks almost prevented
us from sleeping. The clouds hindered me from observing the stars;
the moon appeared only at intervals. The aspect of the landscape
was dull and uniform, and all the surrounding hills were covered
with aloes. Workmen were employed at a small canal, intended for
conveying the waters of the Rio San Pedro to the farm, at a height
of more than seventy feet. According to a barometric calculation,
the site of the hacienda is only fifty toises above the bed of the
Rio Guayra at La Noria, near Caracas.
The soil of these countries is found to be but little favourable to
the cultivation of the coffee-tree, which in general is less
productive in the valley of Caracas than was imagined when the
first plantations were made near Chacao. The finest
coffee-plantations are now found in the savannah of Ocumare, near
Salamanca, and at Rincon, in the mountainous countries of Los
Mariches, San Antonio Hatillo, and Los Budares. The coffee of the
three last mentioned places, situated eastward of Caracas, is of a
superior quality; but the trees bear a smaller quantity, which is
attributed to the height of the spot and the coolness of the
climate. The greater plantations of the province of Venezuela (as
Aguacates, near Valencia and Rincon) yield in good years a produce
of three thousand quintals.
The extreme predilection entertained in this province for the
culture of the coffee-tree is partly founded on the circumstance
that the berry can be preserved during a great number of years;
whereas, notwithstanding every possible care, cacao spoils in the
warehouses after ten or twelve months. During the long dissensions
of the European powers, at a time when Spain was too weak to
protect the commerce of her colonies, industry was directed in
preference to productions of which the sale was less urgent, and
could await the chances of political and commercial events. I
remarked that in the coffee-plantations the nurseries are formed
not so much by collecting together young plants, accidentally
rising under trees which have yielded a crop, as by exposing the
seeds of coffee to germination during five days, in heaps, between
plantain leaves. These seeds are taken out of the pulp, but yet
retaining a part of it adherent to them. When the seed has
germinated it is sown, and it produces plants capable of bearing
the heat of the sun better than those which spring up in the shade
in coffee-plantations. In this country five thousand three hundred
coffee-trees are generally planted in a fanega of ground, amounting
to five thousand four hundred and seventy-six square toises. This
land, if it be capable of artificial irrigation, costs five hundred
piastres in the northern part of the province. The coffee-tree
flowers only in the second year, and its flowering lasts only
twenty-four hours. At this time the shrub has a charming
appearance; and, when seen from afar, it appears covered with snow.
The produce of the third year becomes very abundant. In plantations
well weeded and watered, and recently cultivated, trees will bear
sixteen, eighteen, and even twenty pounds of coffee. In general,
however, more than a pound and a half or two pounds cannot be
expected from each plant; and even this is superior to the mean
produce of the West India Islands. The coffee trees suffer much
from rain at the time of flowering, as well as from the want of
water for artificial irrigation, and also from a parasitic plant, a
new species of loranthus, which clings to the branches. When, in
plantations of eighty or a hundred thousand shrubs, we consider the
immense quantity of organic matter contained in the pulpy berry of
the coffee-tree, we may be astonished that no attempts have been
made to extract a spirituous liquor from them.* (* The berries
heaped together produce a vinous fermentation, during which a very
pleasant alcoholic smell is emitted. Placing, at Caracas, the ripe
fruit of the coffee-tree under an inverted jar, quite filled with
water, and exposed to the rays of the sun, I remarked that no
extrication of gas took place in the first twenty-four hours. After
thirty-six hours the berries became brown, and yielded gas. A
thermometer, enclosed in the jar in contact with the fruit, kept at
night 4 or 5 degrees higher than the external air. In the space of
eighty-seven hours, sixty berries, under various jars, yielded me
from thirty-eight to forty cubic inches of a gas, which underwent
no sensible diminution with nitrous gas. Though a great quantity of
carbonic acid had been absorbed by the water as it was produced, I
still found 0.78 in the forty inches. The remainder, or 0.22, was
nitrogen. The carbonic acid had not been formed by the absorption
of the atmospheric oxygen. That which is evolved from the berries
of the coffee-tree slightly moistened, and placed in a phial with a
glass stopple filled with air, contains alcohol in suspension; like
the foul air which is formed in our cellars during the fermentation
of must. On agitating the gas in contact with water, the latter
acquires a decidedly alcoholic flavour. How many substances are
perhaps contained in a state of suspension in those mixtures of
carbonic acid and hydrogen, which are called deleterious miasmata,
and which rise everywhere within the tropics, in marshy grounds, on
the sea-shore, and in forests where the soil is strewed with dead
leaves, rotten fruits, and putrefying insects.)
If the troubles of St. Domingo, the temporary rise in the price of
colonial produce, and the emigration of French planters, were the
first causes of the establishment of coffee plantations on the
continent of America, in the island of Cuba, and in Jamaica; their
produce has far more than compensated the deficiency of the
exportation from the French West India Islands. This produce has
augmented in proportion to the population, the change of customs,
and the increasing luxury of the nations of Europe. The island of
St. Domingo exported, in 1700, at the time of Necker's
administration, nearly seventy-six million pounds of coffee.* (*
French pounds, containing 9216 grains. 112 English pounds = 105
French pounds; and 160 Spanish pounds = 93 French pounds. The
island of St. Domingo was at that time, it must be remembered, a
French colony.)
Tea could be cultivated as well as coffee in the mountainous parts
of the provinces of Caracas and Cumana. Every climate is there
found rising in stages one above another; and this new culture
would succeed there as well as in the southern hemisphere, where
the government of Brazil, protecting at the same time industry and
religious toleration, suffered at once the introduction of Chinese
tea and of the dogmas of Fo. It is not yet a century since the
first coffee-trees were planted at Surinam and in the West India
Islands, and already the produce of America amounts to fifteen
millions of piastres, reckoning the quintal of coffee at fourteen
piastres only.
On the eighth of February we set out at sunrise, to cross the
Higuerote, a group of lofty mountains, separating the two
longitudinal valleys of Caracas and Aragua. After passing, near Las
Ajuntas, the junction of the two small rivers San Pedro and
Macarao, which form the Rio Guayra, we ascended a steep hill to the
table-land of La Buenavista, where we saw a few lonely houses. The
view extends on the north-west to the city of Caracas, and on the
south to the village of Los Teques. The country has a very wild
aspect, and is thickly wooded. We had now gradually lost the plants
of the valley of Caracas.* (* The Flora of Caracas is characterized
chiefly by the following plants, which grow between the heights of
four hundred and six hundred toises. Cipura martinicensis, Panicum
mieranthum, Parthenium hysterophorus, Vernonia odoratissima,
(Pevetera, with flowers having a delicious odour of heliotropium),
Tagetes caracasana, T. scoparia of Lagasca (introduced by M.
Bonpland into the gardens of Spain), Croton hispidus, Smilax
scabriusculus, Limnocharis Humboldti, Rich., Equisetum
ramosissimum, Heteranthera alismoides, Glycine punctata, Hyptis
Plumeri, Pavonia cancellata, Cav., Spermacoce rigida, Crotalaria
acutifolia, Polygala nemorosa, Stachytarpheta mutabilis,
Cardiospermum ulmaceum, Amaranthus caracasanus, Elephantopus
strigosus, Hydrolea mollis, Alternanthera caracasana, Eupatorium
amydalinum, Elytraria fasciculata, Salvia fimbriata, Angelonia
salicaria, Heliotropium strictum, Convolvulus batarilla, Rubus
jamaicensis, Datura arborea, Dalea enneaphylla, Buchnera rosea,
Salix Humboldtiana, Willd., Theophrasta longifolia, Tournefortia
caracasana, Inga cinerea, I. ligustrina, I. sapindioides, I.
fastuosa, Schwenkia patens, Erythrina mitis. The most agreeable
places for herborizing near Caracas are the ravines of Tacagua,
Tipe, Cotecita, Catoche, Anauco, and Chacaito.) We were eight
hundred and thirty-five toises above the level of the ocean, which
is almost the height of Popayan; but the mean temperature of this
place is probably only 17 or 18 degrees. The road over these
mountains is much frequented; we met continually long files of
mules and oxen; it is the great road leading from the capital to La
Victoria, and the valleys of Aragua. This road is cut out of a
talcose gneiss* in a state of decomposition. (* The direction of
the strata of gneiss varies; it is either hor. 3.4, dipping to the
north-west or hor. 8.2, dipping to the south-east.) A clayey soil
mixed with spangles of mica covered the rock, to the depth of three
feet. Travellers suffer from the dust in winter, while in the rainy
season the place is changed into a slough. On descending the
table-land of Buenavista, about fifty toises to the south-east, an
abundant spring, gushing from the gneiss, forms several cascades
surrounded with thick vegetation. The path leading to the spring is
so steep that we could touch with our hands the tops of the
arborescent ferns, the trunks of which reach a height of more than
twenty-five feet. The surrounding rocks are covered with
jungermannias and hypnoid mosses. The torrent, formed by the
spring, and shaded with heliconias, uncovers, as it falls, the
roots of the plumerias,* (* The red jasmine-tree, frangipanier of
the French West India Islands. The plumeria, so common in the
gardens of the Indians, has been very seldom found in a wild state.
It is mixed here with the Piper flagellare, the spadix of which
sometimes reaches three feet long. With the new kind of fig-tree
(which we have called Ficus gigantea, because it frequently attains
the height of a hundred feet), we find in the mountains of
Buenavista and of Los Teques, the Ficus nymphaeifolia of the garden
of Schonbrunn, introduced into our hot-houses by M. Bredemeyer. I
am certain of the identity of the species found in the same places;
but I doubt really whether it be really the F. nymphaeifolia of
Linnaeus, which is supposed to be a native of the East Indies.)
cupeys,* (* In the experiments I made at Caracas, on the air which
circulates in plants, I was struck with the fine appearance
presented by the petioles and leaves of the Clusia rosea, when cut
open under water, and exposed to the rays of the sun. Each trachea
gives out a current of gas, purer by 0.08 than atmospheric air. The
phenomenon ceases the moment the apparatus is placed in the shade.
There is only a very slight disengagement of air at the two
surfaces of the leaves of the clusia exposed to the sun without
being cut open. The gas enclosed in the capsules of the
Cardiospermum vesicarium appeared to me to contain the same
proportion of oxygen as the atmosphere, while that contained
between the knots, in the hollow of the stalk, is generally less
pure, containing only from 0.12 to 0.15 of oxygen. It is necessary
to distinguish between the air circulating in the tracheae, and
that which is stagnant in the great cavities of the stems and
pericarps.) browneas, and Ficus gigantea. This humid spot, though
infested by serpents, presents a rich harvest to the botanist. The
Brownea, which the inhabitants call rosa del monte, or palo de
cruz, bears four or five hundred purple flowers together in one
thyrsus; each flower has invariably eleven stamina, and this
majestic plant, the trunk of which grows to the height of fifty or
sixty feet, is becoming rare, because its wood yields a highly
valued charcoal. The soil is covered with pines (ananas),
hemimeris, polygala, and melastomas. A climbing gramen* (* Carice.
See Chapter 6.) with its light festoons unites trees, the presence
of which attests the coolness of the climate of these mountains.
Such are the Aralia capitata,* (* Candelero. We found it also at La
Cumbre, at a height of 700 toises.) the Vismia caparosa, and the
Clethra fagifolia. Among these plants, peculiar to the fine region
of the arborescent ferns,* (* Called by the inhabitants of the
country Region de los helechos.) some palm-trees rise in the
openings, and some scattered groups of guarumo, or cecropia with
silvery leaves. The trunks of the latter are not very thick, and
are of a black colour towards the summit, as if burnt by the oxygen
of the atmosphere. We are surprised to find so noble a tree, which
has the port of the theophrasta and the palm-tree, bearing
generally only eight or ten terminal leaves. The ants, which
inhabit the trunk of the guarumo, or jarumo, and destroy its
interior cells, seem to impede its growth. We had already made one
herborization in the temperate mountains of the Higuerote in the
month of December, accompanying the capitan-general, Senor de
Guevara, in an excursion with the intendant of the province to the
Valles de Aragua. M. Bonpland then found in the thickest part of
the forest some plants of aguatire, the wood of which, celebrated
for its fine red colour, will probably one day become an article of
exportation to Europe. It is the Sickingia erythroxylon described
by Bredemeyer and Willdenouw.
Descending the woody mountain of the Higuerote to the south-west,
we reached the small village of San Pedro, situated in a basin
where several valleys meet, and almost three hundred toises lower
than the table-land of Buenavista. Plantain-trees, potatoes,* (*
Solanum tuberosum.) and coffee are cultivated together on this
spot. The village is very small, and the church not yet finished.
We met at an inn (pulperia) several European Spaniards employed at
the government tobacco farm. Their dissatisfaction formed a strange
contrast to our feelings. They were fatigued with their journey,
and they vented their displeasure in complaints and maledictions on
the wretched country, or to use their own phrase, estas tierras
infelices, in which they were doomed to live. We, on the other
hand, were enchanted with the wild scenery, the fertility of the
soil, and the mildness of the climate. Near San Pedro, the talcose
gneiss of Buenavista passes into a mica-slate filled with garnets,
and containing subordinate beds of serpentine. Something analogous
to this is met with at Zoblitz in Saxony. The serpentine, which is
very pure and of a fine green, varied with spots of a lighter tint,
often appears only superimposed on the mica-slate. I found in it a
few garnets, but no metaloid diallage.
The valley of San Pedro, through which flows the river of the same
name, separates two great masses of mountains, the Higuerote and
Las Cocuyzas. We ascended westward in the direction of the small
farms of Las Lagunetos and Garavatos. These are solitary houses,
which serve as inns, and where the mule-drivers obtain their
favourite beverage, the guarapo, or fermented juice of the
sugar-cane: intoxication is very common among the Indians who
frequent this road. Near Garavatos there is a mica-slate rock of
singular form; it is a ridge, or steep wall, crowned by a tower. We
opened the barometer at the highest point of the mountain Las
Cocuyzas,* (* Absolute height 845 toises.) and found ourselves
almost at the same elevation as on the table-land of Buenavista,
which is scarcely ten toises higher.
The prospect at Las Lagunetas is extensive, but rather uniform.
This mountainous and uncultivated tract of ground between the
sources of the Guayra and the Tuy is more than twenty-five square
leagues in extent. We there found only one miserable village, that
of Los Teques, south-east of San Pedro. The soil is as it were
furrowed by a multitude of valleys, the smallest of which, parallel
with each other, terminate at right angles in the largest valleys.
The back of the mountains presents an aspect as monotonous as the
ravines; it has no pyramidal forms, no ridges, no steep
declivities. I am inclined to think that the undulation of this
ground, which is for the most part very gentle, is less owing to
the nature of the rocks, (to the decomposition of the gneiss for
instance), than to the long presence of the water and the action of
currents. The limestone mountains of Cumana present the same
phenomenon north of Tumiriquiri.
From Las Lagunetas we descended into the valley of the Rio Tuy.
This western slope of the mountains of Los Teques bears the name of
Las Cocuyzas, and it is covered with two plants with agave leaves;
the maguey of Cocuyza, and the maquey of Cocuy. The latter belongs
to the genus Yucca.* (* Yucca acaulis, Humb.) Its sweet and
fermented juice yields a spirit by distillation; and I have seen
the young leaves of this plant eaten. The fibres of the full-grown
leaves furnish cords of extraordinary strength.* (* At the clock of
the cathedral of Caracas, a cord of maguey, half an inch in
diameter, sustained for fifteen years a weight of 350 pounds.)
Leaving the mountains of the Higuerote and Los Teques, we entered a
highly cultivated country, covered with hamlets and villages;
several of which would in Europe be called towns. From east to
west, on a line of twelve leagues in extent, we passed La Victoria,
San Mateo, Turmero, and Maracay, containing together more than 28,
000 inhabitants. The plains of the Tuy may be considered as the
eastern extremity of the valleys of Aragua, extending from Guigne,
on the borders of the lake of Valencia, as far as the foot of Las
Cocuyzas. A barometrical measurement gave me 295 toises for the
absolute height of the Valle del Tuy, near the farm of Manterola,
and 222 toises for that of the surface of the lake. The Rio Tuy,
flowing from the mountains of Las Cocuyzas, runs first towards the
west, then turning to the south and to the east, it takes its
course along the high savannahs of Ocumare, receives the waters of
the valley of Caracas, and reaches the sea near cape Codera. It is
the small portion of its basin in the westward direction which,
geologically speaking, would seem to belong to the valley of
Aragua, if the hills of calcareous tufa, breaking the continuity of
these valleys between Consejo and La Victoria, did not deserve some
consideration. We shall here again remind the reader that the group
of the mountains of Los Teques, eight hundred and fifty toises
high, separates two longitudinal valleys, formed in gneiss,
granite, and mica-slate. The most eastern of these valleys,
containing the capital of Caracas, is 200 toises higher than the
western valley, which may be considered as the centre of
agricultural industry.
Having been for a long time accustomed to a moderate temperature,
we found the plains of the Tuy extremely hot, although the
thermometer kept, in the day-time, between eleven in the morning
and five in the afternoon, at only 23 or 24 degrees. The nights
were delightfully cool, the temperature falling as low as 17.5
degrees. As the heat gradually abated, the air became more and more
fragrant with the odour of flowers. We remarked above all the
delicious perfume of the Lirio hermoso,* (* Pancratium undulatum.)
a new species of pancratium, of which the flower, eight or nine
inches long, adorns the banks of the Rio Tuy. We spent two very
agreeable days at the plantation of Don Jose de Manterola, who in
his youth had accompanied the Spanish embassy to Russia. The farm
is a fine plantation of sugar-canes; and the ground is as smooth as
the bottom of a drained lake. The Rio Tuy winds through districts
covered with plantains, and a little wood of Hura crepitans,
Erythrina corallodendron, and fig-trees with nymphaea leaves. The
bed of the river is formed of pebbles of quartz. I never met with
more agreeable bathing than in the Tuy. The water, as clear as
crystal, preserves even during the day a temperature of 18.6
degrees; a considerable coolness for these climates, and for a
height of three hundred toises; but the sources of the river are in
the surrounding mountains. The house of the proprietor, situated on
a hillock, of fifteen or twenty toises of elevation, is surrounded
by the huts of the negroes. Those who are married provide food for
themselves; and here, as everywhere else in the valleys of Aragua,
a small spot of ground is allotted to them to cultivate. They
labour on that ground on Saturdays and Sundays, the only days in
the week on which they are free. They keep poultry, and sometimes
even a pig. Their masters boast of their happiness, as in the north
of Europe the great landholders love to descant upon the ease
enjoyed by peasants who are attached to the glebe. On the day of
our arrival we saw three fugitive negroes brought back; they were
slaves newly purchased. I dreaded having to witness one of those
punishments which, wherever slavery prevails, destroys all the
charm of a country life. Happily these blacks were treated with
humanity.
In this plantation, as in all those of the province of Venezuela,
three species of sugar-cane can be distinguished even at a distance
by the colour of their leaves; the old Creole sugar-cane, the
Otaheite cane, and the Batavia cane. The first has a deep-green
leaf, the stem not very thick, and the knots rather near together.
This sugar-cane was the first introduced from India into Sicily,
the Canary Islands, and West Indies. The second is of a lighter
green; and its stem is higher, thicker, and more succulent. The
whole plant exhibits a more luxuriant vegetation. We owe this plant
to the voyages of Bougainville, Cook, and Bligh. Bougainville
carried it to the Mauritius, whence it passed to Cayenne,
Martinique, and, since 1792, to the rest of the West India Islands.
The sugar-cane of Otaheite, called by the people of that island To,
is one of the most important acquisitions for which colonial
agriculture is indebted to the travels of naturalists. It yields
not only one-third more juice than the creolian cane on the same
space of ground; but from the thickness of its stem, and the
tenacity of its ligneous fibres, it furnishes much more fuel. This
last advantage is important in the West Indies, where the
destruction of the forests has long obliged the planters to use
canes deprived of juice, to keep up the fire under the boilers. But
for the knowledge of this new plant, together with the progress of
agriculture on the continent of Spanish America, and the
introduction of the East India and Java sugar, the prices of
colonial produce in Europe would have been much more sensibly
affected by the revolutions of St. Domingo, and the destruction of
the great sugar plantations of that island. The Otaheite sugar-cane
was carried from the island of Trinidad to Caracas, under the name
of Cana solera, and it passed from Caracas to Cucuta and San Gil in
the kingdom of New Grenada. In our days its cultivation during
twenty-five years has almost entirely removed the apprehension at
first entertained, that being transplanted to America, the cane
would by degrees degenerate, and become as slender as the creole
cane. The third species, the violet sugar-cane, called Cana de
Batavia, or de Guinea, is certainly indigenous in the island of
Java, where it is cultivated in preference in the districts of
Japara and Pasuruan.* (* Raffles History of Java tome 1 page 124.)
Its foliage is purple and very broad; and this cane is preferred in
the province of Caracas for rum. The tablones, or grounds planted
with sugar-canes, are divided by hedges of a colossal gramen; the
lata, or gynerium, with distich leaves. At the Tuy, men were
employed in finishing a dyke, to form a canal of irrigation. This
enterprise had cost the proprietor seven thousand piastres for the
expense of labour, and four thousand piastres for the costs of
lawsuits in which he had become engaged with his neighbours. While
the lawyers were disputing about a canal of which only one-half was
finished, Don Jose de Manterola began to doubt even of the
possibility of carrying the plan into execution. I took the level
of the ground with a lunette d'epreuve, on an artificial horizon,
and found, that the dam had been constructed eight feet too low.
What sums of money have I seen expended uselessly in the Spanish
colonies, for undertakings founded on erroneous levelling!
The valley of the Tuy has its 'gold mine,' like almost every part
of America inhabited by whites, and backed by primitive mountains.
I was assured, that in 1780, foreign gold-gatherers had been
engaged in picking up grains of that metal, and had established a
place for washing the sand in the Quebrada del Oro. An overseer of
a neighbouring plantation had followed these indications; and after
his death, a waistcoat with gold buttons being found among his
clothes, this gold, according to the logic of the people here,
could only have proceeded from a vein, which the falling in of the
earth had rendered invisible. In vain I objected, that I could not,
by the mere view of the soil, without digging a large trench in the
direction of the vein, judge of the existence of the mine; I was
compelled to yield to the desire of my hosts. For twenty years past
the overseer's waistcoat had been the subject of conversation in
the country. Gold extracted from the bosom of the earth is far more
alluring in the eyes of the vulgar, than that which is the produce
of agricultural industry, favoured by the fertility of the soil,
and the mildness of the climate.
North-west of the Hacienda del Tuy, in the northern range of the
chain of the coast, we find a deep ravine, called the Quebrada
Seca, because the torrent, by which it was formed, loses its waters
through the crevices of the rock, before it reaches the extremity
of the ravine. The whole of this mountainous country is covered
with thick vegetation. We there found the same verdure as had
charmed us by its freshness in the mountains of Buenavista and Las
Lagunetas, wherever the ground rises as high as the region of the
clouds, and where the vapours of the sea have free access. In the
plains, on the contrary, many trees are stripped of a part of their
leaves during the winter; and when we descend into the valley of
the Tuy, we are struck with the almost hibernal aspect of the
country. The dryness of the air is such that the hygrometer of
Deluc keeps day and night between 36 and 40 degrees. At a distance
from the river scarcely any huras or piper-trees extend their
foliage over thickets destitute of verdure. This seems owing to the
dryness of the air, which attains its maximum in the month of
February; and not, as the European planters assert, "to the seasons
of Spain, of which the empire extends as far as the torrid zone."
It is only plants transported from one hemisphere to the other,
which, in their organic functions, in the development of their
leaves and flowers, still retain their affinity to a distant
climate: faithful to their habits, they follow for a long time the
periodical changes of their native hemisphere. In the province of
Venezuela the trees stripped of their foliage begin to renew their
leaves nearly a month before the rainy season. It is probable, that
at this period the electrical equilibrium of the air is already
disturbed, and the atmosphere, although not yet clouded, becomes
gradually more humid. The azure of the sky is paler, and the
elevated regions are loaded with light vapours, uniformly diffused.
This season may be considered as the awakening of nature; it is a
spring which, according to the received language of the Spanish
colonies, proclaims the beginning of winter, and succeeds to the
heats of summer.* (* That part of the year most abundant in rain is
called winter; so that in Terra Firma, the season which begins by
the winter solstice, is designated by the name of summer; and it is
usual to hear, that it is winter on the mountains, at the time when
summer prevails in the neighbouring plains.)
Indigo was formerly cultivated in the Quebrada Seca; but as the
soil covered with vegetation cannot there concentrate so much heat
as the plains and the bottom of the Tuy valley receive and radiate,
the cultivation of coffee has been substituted in its stead. As we
advanced in the ravine we found the moisture increase. Near the
Hato, at the northern extremity of the Quebrada, a torrent rolls
down over sloping beds of gneiss. An aqueduct was being formed
there to convey the water to the plain. Without irrigation,
agriculture makes no progress in these climates. A tree of
monstrous size fixed our attention.* (* Hura crepitans.) It lay on
the slope of the mountain, above the house of the Hato. On the
least dislodgment of the earth, its fall would have crushed the
habitation which it shaded: it had therefore been burnt near its
foot, and cut down in such a manner, that it fell between some
enormous fig-trees, which prevented it from rolling into the
ravine. We measured the fallen tree; and though its summit had been
burnt, the length of its trunk was still one hundred and fifty-four
feet.* (* French measure, nearly fifty metres.) It was eight feet
in diameter near the roots, and four feet two inches at the upper
extremity.
Our guides, less anxious than ourselves to measure the bulk of
trees, continually pressed us to proceed onward and seek the 'gold
mine.' This part of the ravine is little frequented, and is not
uninteresting. We made the following observations on the geological
constitution of the soil. At the entrance of the Quebrada Seca we
remarked great masses of primitive saccharoidal limestone,
tolerably fine grained, of a bluish tint, and traversed by veins of
calcareous spar of dazzling whiteness. These calcareous masses must
not be confounded with the very recent depositions of tufa, or
carbonate of lime, which fill the plains of the Tuy; they form beds
of mica-slate, passing into talc-slate.* (* Talkschiefer of Werner,
without garnets or serpentine; not eurite or weisstein. It is in
the mountains of Buenavista that the gneiss manifests a tendency to
pass into eurite.) The primitive limestone often simply covers this
latter rock in concordant stratification. Very near the Hato the
talcose slate becomes entirely white, and contains small layers of
soft and unctuous graphic ampelite.* (* Zeichenschiefer.) Some
pieces, destitute of veins of quartz, are real granular plumbago,
which might be of use in the arts. The aspect of the rock is very
singular in those places where thin plates of black ampelite
alternate with thin, sinuous, and satiny plates of a talcose slate
as white as snow. It would seem as if the carbon and iron, which in
other places colour the primitive rocks, are here concentrated in
the subordinate strata.
Turning westward we reached at length the ravine of gold (Quebrada
del Oro). On examining the slope of a hill, we could hardly
recognize the vestige of a vein of quartz. The falling of the earth
caused by the rains had changed the surface of the ground, and
rendered it impossible to make any observation. Great trees were
growing in the places where the gold-washers had worked twenty
years before. It is probable that the mica-slate contains here, as
near Goldcronach in Franconia, and in Salzburgh, auriferous veins;
but how is it possible to judge whether they be worth the expense
of being wrought, or whether the ore is only in nodules, and in the
less abundance in proportion as it is rich? We made a long
herborization in a thick forest, extending beyond the Hato, and
abounding in cedrelas, browneas, and fig-trees with nymphaea
leaves. The trunks of these last are covered with very odoriferous
plants of vanilla, which in general flower only in the month of
April. We were here again struck with those ligneous excrescences,
which in the form of ridges, or ribs, augment to the height of
twenty feet above the ground, the thickness of the trunk of the
fig-trees of America. I found trees twenty-two feet and a half in
diameter near the roots. These ligneous ridges sometimes separate
from the trunk at a height of eight feet, and are transformed into
cylindrical roots two feet thick. The tree looks as if it were
supported by buttresses. This scaffolding however does not
penetrate very deep into the earth. The lateral roots wind at the
surface of the ground, and if at twenty feet distance from the
trunk they are cut with a hatchet, we see gushing out the milky
juice of the fig-tree, which, when deprived of the vital influence
of the organs of the tree, is altered and coagulates. What a
wonderful combination of cells and vessels exist in these vegetable
masses, in these gigantic trees of the torrid zone, which without
interruption, perhaps during the space of a thousand years, prepare
nutritious fluids, raise them to the height of one hundred and
eighty feet, convey them down again to the ground, and conceal,
beneath a rough and hard bark, under inanimate layers of ligneous
matter, all the movements of organic life!
I availed myself of the clearness of the nights, to observe at the
plantation of Tuy two emersions of the first and third satellites
of Jupiter. These two observations gave, according to the tables of
Delambre, longitude 4 hours 39 minutes 14 seconds; and by the
chronometer I found 4 hours 39 minutes 10 seconds. During my stay
in the valleys of the Tuy and Aragua the zodiacal light appeared
almost every night with extraordinary brilliancy. I had perceived
it for the first time between the tropics at Caracas, on the 18th
of January, after seven in the evening. The point of the pyramid
was at the height of 53 degrees. The light totally disappeared at
9 hours 35 minutes (apparent time), nearly 3 hours 50 minutes after
sunset, without any diminution in the serenity of the sky. La Caille,
in his voyage to Rio Janeiro and the Cape, was struck with the
beautiful appearance displayed by the zodiacal light within the
tropics, not so much on account of its less inclined position,
as of the greater transparency of the air.* (* The great serenity
of the air caused this phenomenon to be remarked, in 1668, in the
arid plains of Persia.) It may appear singular, that Childrey and
Dominic Cassini, navigators who were well acquainted with the seas
of the two Indies, did not at a much earlier period direct the
attention of scientific Europe to this light, and its regular form
and progress. Until the middle of the eighteenth century mariners
were little interested by anything not having immediate relation
to the course of a ship, and the demands of navigation.
However brilliant the zodiacal light in the dry valley of Tuy, I
have observed it more beautiful still at the back of the
Cordilleras of Mexico, on the banks of the lake of Tezcuco, eleven
hundred and sixty toises above the surface of the ocean. In the
month of January, 1804, the light rose sometimes to more than 60
degrees above the horizon. The Milky Way appeared to grow pale
compared with the brilliancy of the zodiacal light; and if small,
bluish, scattered clouds were accumulated toward the west, it
seemed as if the moon were about to rise.
I must here relate another very singular fact. On the 18th of
January, and the 15th of February, 1800, the intensity of the
zodiacal light changed in a very perceptible manner, at intervals
of two or three minutes. Sometimes it was very faint, at others it
surpassed the brilliancy of the Milky Way in Sagittarius. The
changes took place in the whole pyramid, especially toward the
interior, far from the edges. During these variations of the
zodiacal light, the hygrometer indicated considerable dryness. The
stars of the fourth and fifth magnitude appeared constantly to the
naked eye with the same degree of light. No stream of vapour was
visible: nothing seemed to alter the transparency of the
atmosphere. In other years I saw the zodiacal light augment in the
southern hemisphere half an hour before its disappearance. Cassini
admitted "that the zodiacal light was feebler in certain years, and
then returned to its former brilliancy." He thought that these slow
changes were connected with "the same emanations which render the
appearance of spots and faculae periodical on the solar disk." But
this excellent observer does not mention those changes of intensity
in the zodiacal light which I have several times remarked within
the tropics, in the space of a few minutes. Mairan asserts, that in
France it is common enough to see the zodiacal light, in the months
of February and March, mingling with a kind of Aurora Borealis,
which he calls 'undecided,' and the nebulous matter of which
spreads itself all around the horizon, or appears toward the west.
I very much doubt, whether, in the observations I have been
describing, there was any mixture of these two species of light.
The variations in intensity took place at considerable altitudes;
the light was white, and not coloured; steady, and not undulating.
Besides, the Aurora Borealis is so seldom visible within the
tropics, that during five years, though almost constantly sleeping
in the open air, and observing the heavens with unremitting
attention, I never perceived the least traces of that phenomenon.
I am rather inclined to think that the variations of the zodiacal
light are not all appearances dependent on certain modifications in
the state of our atmosphere. Sometimes, during nights equally
clear, I sought in vain for the zodiacal light, when, on the
previous night, it had appeared with the greatest brilliancy. Must
we admit that emanations which reflect white light, and seem to
have some analogy with the tails of comets, are less abundant at
certain periods? Researches on the zodiacal light have acquired a
new degree of interest since geometricians have taught us that we
are ignorant of the real causes of this phenomenon. The illustrious
author of "La Mecanique Celeste" has shown that the solar
atmosphere cannot reach even the planet Mercury; and that it could
not in any case display the lenticular form which has been
attributed to the zodiacal light. We may also entertain the same
doubts respecting the nature of this light, as with regard to that
of the tails of comets. Is it in fact a reflected or a direct
light?
We left the plantation of Manterola on the 11th of February, at
sunrise. The road runs along the smiling banks of the Tuy; the
morning was cool and humid, and the air seemed embalmed by the
delicious odour of the Pancratium undulatum, and other large
liliaceous plants. In our way to La Victoria, we passed the pretty
village of Mamon or of Consejo, celebrated in the country for a
miraculous image of the Virgin. A little before we reached Mamon,
we stopped at a farm belonging to the family of Monteras. A negress
more than a hundred years old was seated before a small hut built
of earth and reeds. Her age was known because she was a creole
slave. She seemed still to enjoy very good health. "I keep her in
the sun" (la tengo al sol), said her grandson; "the heat keeps her
alive." This appeared to us not a very agreeable mode of prolonging
life, for the sun was darting his rays almost perpendicularly. The
brown-skinned nations, blacks well seasoned, and Indians,
frequently attain a very advanced age in the torrid zone. A native
of Peru named Hilario Pari died at the extraordinary age of one
hundred and forty-three years, after having been ninety years
married.
Don Francisco Montera and his brother, a well-informed young
priest, accompanied us with the view of conducting us to their
house at La Victoria. Almost all the families with whom we had
lived in friendship at Caracas were assembled in the fine valleys
of Aragua, and they vied with each other in their efforts to render
our stay agreeable. Before we plunged into the forests of the
Orinoco, we enjoyed once more all the advantages which advanced
civilization affords.
The road from Mamon to La Victoria runs south and south-west. We
soon lost sight of the river Tuy, which, turning eastward, forms an
elbow at the foot of the high mountains of Guayraima. As we drew
nearer to Victoria the ground became smoother; it seemed like the
bottom of a lake, the waters of which had been drained off. We
might have fancied ourselves in the valley of Hasli, in the canton
of Berne. The neighbouring hills, only one hundred and forty toises
in height, are composed of calcareous tufa; but their abrupt
declivities project like promontories on the plain. Their form
indicates the ancient shore of the lake. The eastern extremity of
this valley is parched and uncultivated. No advantage has been
derived from the ravines which water the neighbouring mountains;
but fine cultivation is commencing in the proximity of the town. I
say of the town, though in my time Victoria was considered only as
a village (pueblo).
The environs of La Victoria present a very remarkable agricultural
aspect. The height of the cultivated ground is from two hundred and
seventy to three hundred toises above the level of the ocean, and
yet we there find fields of corn mingled with plantations of
sugar-cane, coffee, and plantains. Excepting the interior of the
island of Cuba,* (* The district of Quatro Villas.) we scarcely
find elsewhere in the equinoctial regions European corn cultivated
in large quantities in so low a region. The fine fields of wheat in
Mexico are between six hundred and twelve hundred toises of
absolute elevation; and it is rare to see them descend to four
hundred toises. We shall soon perceive that the produce of grain
augments sensibly, from high latitudes towards the equator, with
the mean temperature of the climate, in comparing spots of
different elevations. The success of agriculture depends on the
dryness of the air; on the rains distributed through different
seasons, or accumulated in one season; on winds blowing constantly
from the east; or bringing the cold air of the north into very low
latitudes, as in the gulf of Mexico; on mists, which for whole
months diminish the intensity of the solar rays; in short, on a
thousand local circumstances which have less influence on the mean
temperature of the whole year than on the distribution of the same
quantity of heat through the different parts of the year. It is a
striking spectacle to see the grain of Europe cultivated from the
equator as far as Lapland in the latitude of 69 degrees, in regions
where the mean heat is from 22 to-2 degrees, in every place where
the temperature of summer is above 9 or 10 degrees. We know the
minimum of heat requisite to ripen wheat, barley, and oats; but we
are less certain in respect to the maximum which these species of
grain, accommodating as they are, can support. We are even ignorant
of all the circumstances which favour the culture of corn within
the tropics at very small heights. La Victoria and the neighbouring
village of San Mateo yield an annual produce of four thousand
quintals of wheat. It is sown in the month of December, and the
harvest is reaped on the seventieth or seventy-fifth day. The grain
is large, white, and abounding in gluten; its pellicle is thinner
and not so hard as that of the wheat of the very cold table-lands
of Mexico. An acre* (* An arpent des eaux et forets, or legal acre
of France, of which 1.95 = 1 hectare. It is about 1 1/4 acre
English.) near Victoria generally yields from three thousand to
three thousand two hundred pounds weight of wheat. The average
produce is consequently here, as at Buenos Ayres, three or four
times as much as that of northern countries. Nearly sixteenfold of
the quantity of seed is reaped; while, according to Lavoisier, the
surface of France yields on an average only five or six for one, or
from one thousand to twelve hundred pounds per acre.
Notwithstanding this fecundity of the soil, and this happy
influence of the climate, the culture of the sugar-cane is more
productive in the valleys of Aragua than that of corn.
La Victoria is traversed by the little river Calanchas, running,
not into the Tuy, but into the Rio Aragua: it thence results that
this fine country, producing at once sugar and corn, belongs to the
basin of the lake of Valencia, to a system of interior rivers not
communicating with the sea. The quarter of the town west of the Rio
Calanchas is called la otra banda; it is the most commercial part;
merchandize is everywhere exhibited, and ranges of shops form the
streets. Two commercial roads pass through La Victoria, that of
Valencia, or of Porto Cabello, and the road of Villa de Cura, or of
the plains, called camino de los Llanos. We here find more whites
in proportion than at Caracas. We visited at sunset the little hill
of Calvary, where the view is extremely fine and extensive. We
discover on the west the lovely valleys of Aragua, a vast space
covered with gardens, cultivated fields, clumps of wild trees,
farms, and hamlets. Turning south and south-east, we see, extending
as far as the eye can reach, the lofty mountains of La Palma,
Guayraima, Tiara, and Guiripa, which conceal the immense plains or
steppes of Calabozo. This interior chain stretches westward along
the lake of Valencia, towards the Villa de Cura, the Cuesta de
Yusma, and the denticulated mountains of Guigne. It is very steep,
and constantly covered with that light vapour which in hot climates
gives a vivid blue tint to distant objects, and, far from
concealing their outlines, marks them the more strongly. It is
believed that among the mountains of the interior chain, that of
Guayraima reaches an elevation of twelve hundred toises. I found in
the night of the eleventh of February the latitude of La Victoria
10 degrees 13 minutes 35 seconds, the magnetic dip 40.8 degrees, the
intensity of the forces equal to 236 oscillations in ten minutes of
time, and the variation of the needle 4.4 degrees north-east.
We proceeded slowly on our way by the villages of San Mateo,
Turmero, and Maracay, to the Hacienda de Cura, a fine plantation
belonging to Count Tovar, where we arrived on the evening of the
fourteenth of February. The valley, which gradually widens, is
bordered with hills of calcareous tufa, called here tierra blanca.
The scientific men of the country have made several attempts to
calcine this earth, mistaking it for the porcelain earth proceeding
from decomposed strata of feldspar. We stayed some hours with a
very intelligent family, named Ustariz, at Concesion. Their house,
which contains a collection of choice books, stands on an eminence,
and is surrounded by plantations of coffee and sugar-cane. A grove
of balsam-trees (balsamo* (* Amyris elata.)) gives coolness and
shade to this spot. It was gratifying to observe the great number
of scattered houses in the valley inhabited by freedmen. In the
Spanish colonies, the laws, the institutions, and the manners, are
more favourable to the liberty of the negroes than in other
European settlements.
San Mateo, Turmero, and Maracay, are charming villages, where
everything denotes the comfort of the inhabitants. We seemed to be
transported to the most industrious districts of Catalonia. Near
San Mateo we find the last fields of wheat, and the last mills with
horizontal hydraulic wheels. A harvest of twenty for one was
expected; and, as if that produce were but moderate, I was asked
whether corn yielded more in Prussia and in Poland. By an error
generally prevalent under the tropics, the produce of grain is
supposed to degenerate in advancing towards the equator, and
harvests are believed to be more abundant in northern climates.
Since calculations have been made on the progress of agriculture in
the different zones, and on the temperatures under the influence of
which corn will flourish, it has been found that, beyond the
latitude of 45 degrees, the produce of wheat is nowhere so
considerable as on the northern coasts of Africa, and on the
table-lands of New Grenada, Peru, and Mexico. Without comparing the
mean temperature of the whole year, but only the mean temperature
of the season which embraces the corn cycle of vegetation, we find
for three months of summer,* in the north of Europe, from 15 to 19
degrees; in Barbary and in Egypt, from 27 to 29 degrees; within the
tropics, between fourteen and three hundred toises of height, from
14 to 25.5 degrees of the centigrade thermometer. (* The mean heat
of the summers of Scotland in the environs of Edinburgh, (latitude
56 degrees), is found again on the table-lands of New Grenada, so
rich in wheat, at 1400 toises of elevation, and at 4 degrees north
latitude. On the other hand, we find the mean temperature of the
valleys of Aragua, latitude 10 degrees 13 minutes, and of all the
plains which are not very elevated in the torrid zone, in the
summer temperature of Naples and Sicily, latitude 39 to 40 degrees.
These figures indicate the situation of the isotheric lines (lines
of the same summer heat), and not that of the isothermal lines
(those of equal annual temperature). Considering the quantity of
heat received on the same spot of the globe during a whole year,
the mean temperatures of the valleys of Aragua, and the table-lands
of New Grenada, at 300 and 1400 toises of elevation, correspond to
the mean temperatures of the coasts at 23 and 45 degrees of
latitude.)
The fine harvests of Egypt and of Algiers, as well as those of the
valleys of Aragua and the interior of the island of Cuba,
sufficiently prove that the augmentation of heat is not prejudicial
to the harvest of wheat and other alimentary grain, unless it be
attended with an excess of drought or moisture. To this
circumstance no doubt we must attribute the apparent anomalies
sometimes observed within the tropics, in the lower limit of corn.
We are astonished to see, eastward of the Havannah, in the famous
district of Quatro Villas, that this limit descends almost to the
level of the ocean; whilst west of the Havannah, on the slope of
the mountains of Mexico and Xalapa, at six hundred and
seventy-seven toises of height, the luxuriance of vegetation is
such, that wheat does not form ears. At the beginning of the
Spanish conquest, the corn of Europe was cultivated with success in
several regions now supposed to be too hot, or too damp, for this
branch of agriculture. The Spaniards on their first removal to
America were little accustomed to live on maize. They still adhered
to their European habits. They did not calculate whether corn would
be less profitable than coffee or cotton. They tried seeds of every
kind, making experiments the more boldly because their reasonings
were less founded on false theories. The province of Carthagena,
crossed by the chain of the mountains Maria and Guamoco, produced
wheat till the sixteenth century. In the province of Caracas, this
culture is of very ancient date in the mountainous lands of Tocuyo,
Quibor, and Barquisimeto, which connect the littoral chain with the
Sierra Nevada of Merida. Wheat is still successfully cultivated
there, and the environs of the town of Tocuyo alone export annually
more than eight thousand quintals of excellent flour. But, though
the province of Caracas, in its vast extent, includes several spots
very favourable to the cultivation of European corn, I believe that
in general this branch of agriculture will never acquire any great
importance there. The most temperate valleys are not sufficiently
wide; they are not real table-lands; and their mean elevation above
the level of the sea is not so considerable but that the
inhabitants cannot fail to perceive that it is more their interest
to establish plantations of coffee, than to cultivate corn. Flour
now comes to Caracas either from Spain or from the United States.
The village of Turmero is four leagues distant from San Mateo. The
road leads through plantations of sugar, indigo, cotton, and
coffee. The regularity observable in the construction of the
villages, reminded us that they all owe their origin to monks and
missions. The streets are straight and parallel, crossing each
other at right angles; and the church is invariably erected in the
great square, situated in the centre of the village. The church of
Turmero is a fine edifice, but overloaded with architectural
ornaments. Since the missionaries have been replaced by vicars, the
whites have mingled their habitations with those of the Indians.
The latter are gradually disappearing as a separate race; that is
to say, they are represented in the general statement of the
population by the Mestizoes and the Zamboes, whose numbers daily
increase. I still found, however, four thousand tributary Indians
in the valleys of Aragua. Those of Turmero and Guacara are the most
numerous. They are of small stature, but less squat than the
Chaymas; their eyes denote more vivacity and intelligence, owing
less perhaps to a diversity in the race, than to a superior state
of civilization. They work like freemen by the day. Though active
and laborious during the short time they allot to labour, yet what
they earn in two months is spent in one week, in the purchase of
strong liquors at the small inns, of which unhappily the numbers
daily increase.
We saw at Turmero the remains of the assembled militia of the
country, and their appearance alone sufficiently indicated that
these valleys had enjoyed for ages undisturbed peace. The
capitan-general, in order to give a new impulse to the military
service, had ordered a grand review; and the battalion of Turmero,
in a mock fight, had fired on that of La Victoria. Our host, a
lieutenant of the militia, was never weary of describing to us the
danger of these manoeuvres, which seemed more burlesque than
imposing. With what rapidity do nations, apparently the most
pacific, acquire military habits! Twelve years afterwards, those
valleys of Aragua, those peaceful plains of La Victoria and
Turmero, the defile of Cabrera, and the fertile banks of the lake
of Valencia, became the scenes of obstinate and sanguinary
conflicts between the natives and the troops of the mother-country.
South of Turmero, a mass of limestone mountains advances into the
plain, separating two fine sugar-plantations, Guayavita and Paja.
The latter belongs to the family of Count Tovar, who have property
in every part of the province. Near Guayavita, brown iron-ore has
been discovered. To the north of Turmero, a granitic summit (the
Chuao) rises in the Cordillera of the coast, from the top of which
we discern at once the sea and the lake of Valencia. Crossing this
rocky ridge, which runs towards the west farther than the eye can
reach, paths somewhat difficult lead to the rich plantations of
cacao on the coast, to Choroni, Turiamo, and Ocumare, noted alike
for the fertility of the soil and the insalubrity of their climate.
Turmero, Maracay, Cura, Guacara, every point of the valley of
Aragua, has its mountain-road, which terminates at one of the small
ports on the coast.
On quitting the village of Turmero, we discover, at a league
distant, an object, which appears at the horizon like a round
hillock, or tumulus, covered with vegetation. It is neither a hill,
nor a group of trees close to each other, but one single tree, the
famous zamang del Guayre, known throughout the province for the
enormous extent of its branches, which form a hemispheric head five
hundred and seventy-six feet in circumference. The zamang is a fine
species of mimosa, and its tortuous branches are divided by
bifurcation. Its delicate and tender foliage was agreeably relieved
on the azure of the sky. We stopped a long time under this
vegetable roof. The trunk of the zamang del Guayre,* (* The mimos
of La Guayre; zamang being the Indian name for the genera mimosa,
desmanthus, and acacia. The place where the tree is found is called
El Guayre.) which is found on the road from Turmero to Maracay, is
only sixty feet high, and nine thick; but its real beauty consists
in the form of its head. The branches extend like an immense
umbrella, and bend toward the ground, from which they remain at a
uniform distance of twelve or fifteen feet. The circumference of
this head is so regular, that, having traced different diameters, I
found them one hundred and ninety-two and one hundred and
eighty-six feet. One side of the tree was entirely stripped of its
foliage, owing to the drought; but on the other side there remained
both leaves and flowers. Tillandsias, lorantheae, Cactus Pitahaya,
and other parasite plants, cover its branches, and crack the bark.
The inhabitants of these villages, but particularly the Indians,
hold in veneration the zamang del Guayre, which the first
conquerors found almost in the same state in which it now remains.
Since it has been observed with attention, no change has appeared
in its thickness or height. This zamang must be at least as old as
the Orotava dragon-tree. There is something solemn and majestic in
the aspect of aged trees; and the violation of these monuments of
nature is severely punished in countries destitute of monuments of
art. We heard with satisfaction that the present proprietor of the
zamang had brought an action against a cultivator who had been
guilty of cutting off a branch. The cause was tried, and the
tribunal condemned the offender. We find near Turmero and the
Hacienda de Cura other zamangs, having trunks larger than that of
Guayre, but their hemispherical heads are not of equal extent.
The culture and population of the plains augment in the direction
of Cura and Guacara, on the northern side of the lake. The valleys
of Aragua contain more than 52,000 inhabitants, on a space thirteen
leagues in length, and two in width. This is a relative population
of two thousand souls on a square league. The village or rather the
small town of Maracay was heretofore the centre of the indigo
plantations, when this branch of colonial industry was in its
greatest prosperity. The houses are all of masonry, and every court
contains cocoa-trees, which rise above the habitations. The aspect
of general wealth is still more striking at Maracay, than at
Turmero. The anil, or indigo, of these provinces has always been
considered in commerce as equal and sometimes superior to that of
Guatemala. The indigo plant impoverishes the soil, where it is
cultivated during a long series of years, more than any other. The
lands of Maracay, Tapatapa, and Turmero, are looked upon as
exhausted; and indeed the produce of indigo has been constantly
decreasing. But in proportion as it has diminished in the valleys
of Aragua, it has increased in the province of Varinas, and in the
burning plains of Cucuta, where, on the banks of the Rio Tachira,
virgin land yields an abundant produce, of the richest colour.
We arrived very late at Maracay, and the persons to whom we were
recommended were absent. The inhabitants perceiving our
embarrassment, contended with each other in offering to lodge us,
to place our instruments, and take care of our mules. It has been
said a thousand times, but the traveller always feels desirous of
repeating it again, that the Spanish colonies are the land of
hospitality; they are so even in those places where industry and
commerce have diffused wealth and improvement. A family of
Canarians received us with the most amiable cordiality; an
excellent repast was prepared, and everything was carefully avoided
that might act as any restraint on us. The master of the house, Don
Alexandro Gonzales, was travelling on commercial business, and his
young wife had lately had the happiness of becoming a mother. She
was transported with joy when she heard that on our return from the
Rio Negro we should proceed by the banks of the Orinoco to
Angostura, where her husband was. We were to bear to him the
tidings of the birth of his first child. In those countries, as
among the ancients, travellers are regarded as the safest means of
communication. There are indeed posts established, but they make
such great circuits that private persons seldom entrust them with
letters for the llanos or savannahs of the interior. The child was
brought to us at the moment of our departure: we had seen him
asleep at night, but it was deemed indispensable that we should see
him awake in the morning. We promised to describe his features
exactly to his father, but the sight of our books and instruments
somewhat chilled the mother's confidence. She said "that in a long
journey, amidst so many cares of another kind, we might well forget
the colour of her child's eyes."
On the road from Maracay to the Hacienda de Cura we enjoyed from
time to time the view of the lake of Valencia. An arm of the
granitic chain of the coast stretches southward into the plain. It
is the promontory of Portachuelo which would almost close the
valley, were it not separated by a narrow defile from the rock of
La Cabrera. This place has acquired a sad celebrity in the late
revolutionary wars of Caracas; each party having obstinately
disputed its possession, as opening the way to Valencia, and to the
Llanos. La Cabrera now forms a peninsula: not sixty years ago it
was a rocky island in the lake, the waters of which gradually
diminish. We spent seven very agreeable days at the Hacienda da
Cura, in a small habitation surrounded by thickets.
We lived after the manner of the rich in this country; we bathed
twice, slept three times, and made three meals in the twenty-four
hours. The temperature of the water of the lake is rather warm,
being from twenty-four to twenty-five degrees; but there is another
cool and delicious bathing-place at Toma, under the shade of ceibas
and large zamangs, in a torrent gushing from the granitic mountains
of the Rincon del Diablo. In entering this bath, we had not to fear
the sting of insects, but to guard against the little brown hairs
which cover the pods of the Dolichos pruriens. When these small
hairs, well characterised by the name of picapica, stick to the
body, they excite a violent irritation on the skin; the dart is
felt, but the cause is unperceived.
Near Cura we found all the people occupied in clearing the ground
covered with mimosa, sterculia, and Coccoloba excoriata, for the
purpose of extending the cultivation of cotton. This product, which
partly supplies the place of indigo, has succeeded so well during
some years, that the cotton-tree now grows wild on the borders of
the lake of Valencia. We have found shrubs of eight or ten feet
high entwined with bignonia and other ligneous creepers. The
exportation of cotton from Caracas, however, is yet of small
importance. It amounted at an average at La Guayra scarcely to
three or four hundred thousand pounds in a year; but including all
the ports of the Capitania-general, it arose, on account of the
flourishing culture of Cariaco, Nueva Barcelona, and Maracaybo, to
more than 22,000 quintals. The cotton of the valleys of Aragua is
of fine quality, being inferior only to that of Brazil; for it is
preferred to that of Carthagena, St. Domingo, and the Caribbee
Islands. The cultivation of cotton extends on one side of the lake
from Maracay to Valencia; and on the other from Guayca to Guigue.
The large plantations yield from sixty to seventy thousand pounds a
year.
During our stay at Cura we made numerous excursions to the rocky
islands (which rise in the midst of the lake of Valencia,) to the
warm springs of Mariara, and to the lofty granitic mountain called
El Cucurucho de Coco. A dangerous and narrow path leads to the port
of Turiamo and the celebrated cacao-plantations of the coast. In
all these excursions we were agreeably surprised, not only at the
progress of agriculture, but at the increase of a free laborious
population, accustomed to toil, and too poor to rely on the
assistance of slaves. White and mulatto farmers had everywhere
small separate establishments. Our host, whose father had a revenue
of 40,000 piastres, possessed more lands than he could clear; he
distributed them in the valleys of Aragua among poor families who
chose to apply themselves to the cultivation of cotton. He
endeavoured to surround his ample plantations with freemen, who,
working as they chose, either in their own land or in the
neighbouring plantations, supplied him with day-labourers at the
time of harvest. Nobly occupied on the means best adapted gradually
to extinguish the slavery of the blacks in these provinces, Count
Tovar flattered himself with the double hope of rendering slaves
less necessary to the landholders, and furnishing the freedmen with
opportunities of becoming farmers. On departing for Europe he had
parcelled out and let a part of the lands of Cura, which extend
towards the west at the foot of the rock of Las Viruelas. Four
years after, at his return to America, he found on this spot,
finely cultivated in cotton, a little hamlet of thirty or forty
houses, which is called Punta Zamuro, and which we visited with
him. The inhabitants of this hamlet are almost all mulattos,
Zamboes, or free blacks. This example of letting out land has been
happily followed by several other great proprietors. The rent is
ten piastres for a fanega of ground, and is paid in money or in
cotton. As the small farmers are often in want, they sell their
cotton at a very moderate price. They dispose of it even before the
harvest: and the advances, made by rich neighbours, place the
debtor in a situation of dependence, which frequently obliges him
to offer his services as a labourer. The price of labour is cheaper
here than in France. A freeman, working as a day-labourer (peon),
is paid in the valleys of Aragua and in the llanos four or five
piastres per month, not including food, which is very cheap on
account of the abundance of meat and vegetables. I love to dwell on
these details of colonial industry, because they serve to prove to
the inhabitants of Europe, a fact which to the enlightened
inhabitants of the colonies has long ceased to be doubtful, namely,
that the continent of Spanish America can produce sugar, cotton,
and indigo by free hands, and that the unhappy slaves are capable
of becoming peasants, farmers, and landholders.
END OF VOLUME 1.
</div></body></text></TEI>