<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="28">CHAPTER XXVI.
It was no long time after the death of Charon, that Hector
came home one evening in a state of the most violent
anxiety and trepidation. He burst upon me in my study,
where I was sitting alone, buried in one of those deep
reveries which, especially since the legacy of the stranger,
had been among the most frequent habits of my mind.
His perturbation was such as to render it impossible for
him to impose on himself the smallest degree of caution
and restraint. The noise he made in entering the apartment
startled me. I looked up, and perceived his features
swelled, his face bruised, and his garments disfigured with
blood.
“For heaven’s sake, Hector,” exclaimed I, “what is
the matter?”
He answered not. He advanced towards the upper end
of the room, he took down a pistol, one of those which I
always kept loaded in my apartment, he came towards me,
he fell upon his knees, he tendered the pistol to my acceptance.
“Hector!” cried I, “what am I to understand? what
is the meaning of this?”
“Kill me, dear master! For Christ’s sake I entreat
you to kill me!”
I took the pistol from his hand; it pointed towards
the floor.
“And will you not kill me?” in a mournful accent
exclaimed he.
“What have you done, that deserves that I should kill
you?”
[276]
“Kill me! only kill me! pray kill me!” He spread
out his hands towards me with a gesture of intreaty.
“Hector, what means this agitation? what has happened?
You terrify me beyond expression.”
“Must I speak?” replied he. “Must I be the accuser
of my guilty self?” He burst into an agony of tears.
“Would I were dead! Would I had been torn into a
thousand pieces, before this had happened! Indeed, sir,
I am innocent! I thought no harm! Indeed it is not
my fault!”
“What have you done? Whence come these bruises
and this wound?”
“It is all my fault! It is all my doing,—nobody
else! Why will you not kill me?”
“Hector, I cannot bear this uncertainty. Recollect
yourself! Be pacified! and tell your story!”
“Will you forgive me?”
“Forgive you what? What have you done to deserve
my anger?”
“No, no, I do not wish to be forgiven! I only wish
you to abhor, to detest, to curse and to kill me!”
“This is beyond all patience.”
“I never loved any body but you, and my mistress, and
my dear young ladies. I never did any body else the
least atom of mischief; and now my folly will be the ruin
of you all!
“Pardon me, sir! I will torment you no longer. I
will get the better of myself, and tell you all that has happened.”
He then informed me, though with many breaks and
passionate interruptions, of what he had just discovered,
my evil repute as a necromancer, the many strange and
terrible stories that were circulated of me, the antipathy
universally entertained against me, the active ferociousness
with which this antipathy was accompanied, and the
consequences that he feared would result. He ascribed
the whole to his own imprudence, and to the particulars
which the superior cunning of the donzella, in spite of his
invincible refusal to acquaint her with a single circumstance,
had wrung from him. Hector had collected several[277]
of these particulars accidentally from a neighbouring rustic,
and had been vehement in my defence. While they were
eager in debate, others had joined them, but Hector had
found them all opponents, not one a supporter. Irritated
with the contest, and the opprobrious language heaped
upon himself and his master, Hector had been provoked to
strike the most insolent of the disputants. Immediately
several had fallen upon him at once, and it was owing to
the uncommon strength and dexterity he possessed, that
he had escaped alive out of their hands. Beside innumerable
blows with fist, foot, and stick, he had received
two or three stabs in different parts of the body, from the
knives with which the Italian is too much accustomed to
assail his adversary. It was easy to see that the gallant
and generous defence of Hector had considerably augmented
the danger of my situation. They dismissed him with a
thousand execrations against both him and myself, and
vows that they would signalise their vengeance by setting
fire to my house. Having related his story, Hector concluded
with again earnestly conjuring me to kill him, that
so he might expiate the imprudence and folly by which he
had made himself the author of my calamity.
The excessiveness of the poor fellow’s distress excited
me to employ every effort to pacify his mind. “Hector,”
said I, “you have been very imprudent, but I foresee no
such consequences as your terrified imagination has led
you to forebode. The idle threats of clowns in the midst
of their brawls are entitled to little regard. I am not so
weak and infirm of soul as to be moved from my tranquillity
by their senseless prate. I entertain no doubt of
your fidelity and affection. I am not angry with you.
The fault you have been guilty of, arose from no defect of
vigilance or attachment. You did what you could, and
where you failed, it was only in that to which your powers
were not commensurate. You have done well and wisely
now, in acquainting me with particulars and the whole
extent of the danger: doubt not but I will employ such
precautions and be so awake to my situation, as to forestall
the possibility of mischief.”
Thus I endeavoured to assuage honest Hector’s perturbation,[278]
but with no adequate effect. He hung his head
in sorrow, and refused to be comforted. Shame and terror
assailed him together, and he knew not how to support
their united pressure. He intreated me not to lull myself
in fancied security, and fall blindfold on my ruin. He entreated
me not to forgive him. My clemency and forbearance
served only to make him regard with greater
horror the crime of which he had been guilty. If however
I refused to punish him, and by penance or death to lighten
the remorse that hung upon his heart, he would at least
devote himself in opposition to the evil he had created,
and die rather than it should touch a hair of our heads.
This idea he seemed to view with some complacency; but
the pleasure it gave was a glimmering and momentary
light; he could not remain in any place for an instant;
he wrung his hands with anguish, and exhibited every
feature of the deepest despair. I examined his bruises and
wounds, the latter of which, though attended with a copious
effusion of blood, did not appear to be dangerous. I warned
him to be guilty of no further indiscretion, to betray nothing
of what had happened to any one of my family, and
to engage in no further controversies and broils in my
vindication.
Though I endeavoured to make light of what I heard
in compassion to the distress of my servant, yet, when I
came to reconsider the subject in solitude, it by no means
appeared to me in a light and trivial point of view. One
part of Hector’s story had related to the death of Charon,
who, I now found, had owed his fate to the superstition
of my uncultivated neighbours. I had always entertained
a formidable idea of the character of an Italian populace,
whom I regarded as more suspicious, sanguinary, and
violent than any other race of men in the world. I deplored
my fate that exposed me to their rage. I deplored
my folly that had admitted any confidant into my
individual pursuits, though my confidence had been so
limited, and its receiver so trustworthy, that I could not
have imagined any evil would have resulted. I determined
that I would not expose myself to the risk of such
sinister consequences, as in my opinion might in my present[279]
situation easily overtake me. I grieved for the tender
health and the doubtful state of mind of my beloved
Marguerite, which alone opposed themselves to the adoption
of an immediate change of scene. In the state of her
health I had been grievously disappointed. I had looked
for amendment; I found decay. The decay however was
gradual, almost imperceptible; from time to time I had
even flattered myself that the progress was in an opposite
direction; but the delusion was soon banished. Another
difficulty arose in addition to the rest; Marguerite appeared
pregnant; a circumstance that now first presented
itself after a cessation of ten years.
The morning after the accident and disclosure of Hector
I went to Pisa, determined to consult with the marchese
Filosanto, elder brother of the unfortunate Andrea, who
was probably more accurately acquainted with the Italian
character than myself, and understood the shades of that
character, as they were modified in the particular territory
in which I resided. The marchese was a man universally
admired for subtlety of reasoning, vigorousness of comprehension,
and refinement of taste. In the structure of his
mind he was scarcely an Italian. He had resided several
years in England, and was the intimate friend of Henry
Howard earl of Surrey, who some time after fell a victim
to the jealous tyranny of his native sovereign, king Henry
the Eighth. The marchese was frank, generous and disinterested,
and possessed more fully the affections of every one
within the circle of his friendship than any other man I ever
knew. He was of a sanguine temper, always contemplating
the world on its brightest side; and, from the generosity
of his own heart, incapable of crediting a distant danger,
or of discerning the storm in the embryo cloud where it
was silently engendering.
In the conference we held, I was influenced too implicitly
by my consciousness of his integrity and the gigantic
powers of his mind, and did not sufficiently advert to
those peculiarities in his temper which I have now described.
The external facts with which the narrative of Hector had
furnished me I fully detailed to him; as to my particular
pursuits, I contented myself with stating that I indulged[280]
freely in the study of chemistry, and was of those persons,
ordinarily accounted visionaries, who amused themselves
with the expectation of finding the philosopher’s stone.
Having heard my story to an end, the marchese ridiculed
my apprehensions. He saw nothing in the facts that
alarmed me, but a cowardly superstition whose utmost flight
reached no higher than the shooting a dog, and a squabble
between a boisterous rustic, and a servant too acutely sensitive
for the reputation of his master. He assured me
that the days of such superstition as I contemplated were
long since past, and that his countrymen less deserved the
imputation than any others, as, living at the very centre
and source of catholic imposition, they saw deeper into the
mystery, and were not exposed to the advantage which distance
possesses for augmenting our reverence. He expatiated
with great eloquence on the vice of a suspicious
temper. A spirit of alarm and continual apprehension,
like the jealousy of lovers, he said, made the meat it fed
on. It brooded over plots that had no existence but in the
wanderings of a disturbed imagination. It was continually
interrupting the quiet of its owner, and the tranquillity of
society; and, for the sake of avoiding imaginary evils,
often plunged into such as were real. He advised me to
go home and be contented. He recommended to me to
clear up the clouds of my mind, and cultivate a light
heart, a cheerful temper, and a generous confidence in the
honest sympathies of mankind. In fine, he bade me continue
my pursuits, avoid éclat, and trust in his sagacity
that no ill consequences would ensue.
The remonstrances of the marchese Filosanto led me to
suspect that I had been idly credulous. I had too easily
participated the feelings and apprehensions of a poor uninstructed
negro, and had suffered the secret griefs that
brooded in my heart, to discolour my perceptions, and
aggravate the features of circumstances in themselves trifling
or indifferent. I began to be half ashamed of the
gloominess of my conceptions. I could not, alas! follow
the advice of the marchese as to the cheerfulness of my
heart; but I could exert myself to prevent my present
melancholy from disfiguring to me every thing I saw. The[281]
influence exercised over my conceptions by persons of eminent
intellect has always been great. Not that the judgment
I formed of the powers of my own mind was peculiarly
humble; but I reasoned thus. Perhaps the person I
consult is as well informed in the subject under consideration
as I am, in that case his decision is as fully entitled
to attention as my own; and thus, without cowardly self-contempt
on my part, the general balance of the argument
was materially altered. Perhaps, without being on the
whole my superior, he may be more competent to this particular
question. In either case my idea of its merits became
perceptibly modified. I never listened to the sentiments
of a man of talents when they differed from my own,
unless where he was evidently visionary and irrational,
without being shaken as to the credit due to my own view
of the subject.
Such then was the effect produced on me by the marchese’s
expostulation. I shook off my apprehensions, and
laughed at my fears. I was ashamed of the want of gallantry
that had possessed me, when I meditated flight
from so trivial a menace. I concluded that dangers, particularly
such as arise from the irrational passions of a capricious
multitude, were increased when symptoms of apprehension
discovered themselves, and abated, when received
with neglect or repelled with a magnanimous serenity.
</div></body></text></TEI>