<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="57">DICTIONARY OF ARTS, MANUFACTURES AND MINES.
 Containing a clear Exposition of their principles and practice.
Illustrated with nearly 1,600 engravings. Complete in two large 8vo.
volumes; counts over 2,000 pages. Price $5.00. 
This new edition is nearly a quarter of a century in advance of any
previous one. It contains one third more matter than the latest previous
one. The statistics, inventions, and improvements, are all brought down
to the present time.
The results of the London Exhibition on the respective subjects of which
the Dictionary treats, are presented with great fulness and accurracy.
The numerous errors in the typography of the London edition have been
corrected in this.
SIR CHARLES LYELL'S
PRINCIPLES OF GEOLOGY;
 Or, the Modern Changes of the Earth and its Inhabitants, considered as
illustrative of Geology. A new and much enlarged edition. Illustrated
with maps, plates, and wood-cuts. 1 vol. 8vo., of 850 pages. Price
$2.25. 
SIR CHARLES LYELL'S
MANUAL OF ELEMENTARY GEOLOGY;
 Or, the Ancient Changes of the Earth and its Inhabitants, as
illustrated by Geological Monuments. A new and greatly enlarged edition.
Illustrated with 500 wood-cuts. 1 vol. 8vo. Price $1.75. 
*** The author of these works, stands in the very front rank of
scientific men, and his works upon the science to which he has devoted
his great powers and his indefatigable study, are the standard books
upon these subjects.
APPLETON'S
MODERN ATLAS OF THE EARTH.
 With an Alphabetical Index of the Latitudes and Longitudes of 18,000
places. Thirty-four beautifully engraved and colored maps, with
Temperature Scales. 4to. size, bound in 1 vol., royal 8vo. Price $3.50. 
This is the only complete portable Modern Atlas yet published. The maps
are engraved on steel, and executed with great clearness, distinctness
and accuracy. The delineations of mountainous districts, the sources of
rivers and boundary lines, have been made with great care. It is
designed for the table of the Student and the office of the Professional
Man and is issued in a very finished and elegant style, and embraces
extensive details of all the important parts of the Earth.
</div></body></text></TEI>