<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 166, folios 76-79</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 166, folios 76-79.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1843">undated [8 October 1843]</date>
          <note type="place">Clifton</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 166, folios 76-79</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_166_folios_76-79.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Clifton Sunday Eveg. 8 o'clock</p>
      <p>Dearest W. Today has been detestable, tho' fine. A biting North wind, very strong. I have had a very long ramble this afternoon, somewhat exploring &amp; adventurous; &amp; I think it has been beneficial. I sadly feel the want of you however, when I explore</p>
      <p>&amp; go adventuring. There is no companion so agreeable; &amp; the bird flies along (when exploring without you) in a skimming hurried way, like a poor thing that wants something or other, without exactly knowing what.</p>
      <p>I think this excursion will answer, &amp; will give me a lift; perhaps not the less that it is far from being a mere pleasuring expedition, for there are many little things I do not fancy. Clifton is not the Clifton</p>
      <p>of the little girl of 12 years old. Staring rows of white houses, &amp; many other emblems of the watering-place genus, by no means now pass either unheeded, or else present attractions as they perhaps did to a childish creature sucking in novelties of any kind. Then the rocks &amp; some of the neighbouring scenery, altho' far from contemptible, are to me now, much less the fairyland region of romance &amp; imagination, the</p>
      <p>paradise &amp; the El-Dorado which any rock or ruin or mountain, anything that was not a positive dead flat, certainly constituted to me between the ages of 10 &amp; 18 years [two words crossed out].</p>
      <p>By the bye, the Hen is anxious you should a little look after the quantity &amp; degree of Byron's walking exercise. She says she thinks him constantly much overdone, altho' not aware of it himself; &amp; on the contrary anxious to</p>
      <p>be manly. She fancies that his energies for study are much injured occasionally, in consequence. She feels sure he is far from very powerful, &amp; that if much is taken out of him in any one way, he will always fail in some other. Not so Annabella, whom she considers to require enormous work in every way. So pray don't let any such idea be applied to</p>
      <p>her.</p>
      <p>Send me the Athenaeum &amp; Examiner, when done with.</p>
      <p>When we next go to Ashley, will you my Dear take me from Bath via Cheddar, to Bridgwater. I long for that excursion. It must be done by a fly from Bath, the valley I hear being had for a carriage.</p>
      <p>I write in a hurry. Am I illegible?--</p>
      <p>I believe I am to ride the hen's new grey pony. He is a very handsome little animal.--</p>
      <p>The Hen amazes me by her strength, &amp; her endurance in all respects. I am delighted about it. She certainly gains in health.</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
