<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="70">

CHAPTER II.
Of the Three Members of a Palætiological Science.


1. Divisions of such Sciences.—In each of the Sciences of this class we consider some particular order
of phenomena now existing:—from our knowledge of
the causes of change among such phenomena, we endeavour to infer the causes which have made this order of
things what it is:—we ascend in this manner to some
previous stage of such phenomena;—and from that, by
a similar course of inference, to a still earlier stage,
and to its causes. Hence it will be seen that each
such science will consist of two parts,—the knowledge
of the Phenomena, and the knowledge of their Causes.
And such a division is, in fact, generally recognized
in such sciences: thus we have History, and the Philosophy of History; we have Comparison of Languages, and the Theories of the Origin and Progress
of Language; we have Descriptive Geology, and
Theoretical or Physical Geology. In all these cases,
the relation between the two parts in these several
provinces of knowledge is nearly the same; and it may,
on some occasions at least, be useful to express the
distinction in a uniform or general manner. The investigation of Causes has been termed Ætiology by
philosophical writers, and this term we may use, in
contradistinction to the mere Phenomenology of each
such department of knowledge. And thus we should
have Phenomenal Geology and Ætiological Geology, for
the two divisions of the science which we have above
termed Descriptive and Theoretical Geology.
2. The Study of Causes.—But our knowledge respecting the causes which actually have produced any 264 order of phenomena must be arrived at by ascertaining what the causes of change in such matters can
do. In order to learn, for example, what share earthquakes, and volcanoes, and the beating of the ocean
against its shores, ought to have in our Theory of
Geology, we must make out what effects these agents
of change are able to produce. And this must be
done, not hastily, or unsystematically, but in a careful and connected manner; in short, this study of
the causes of change in each order of phenomena must
become a distinct body of Science, which must include
a large amount of knowledge, both comprehensive and
precise, before it can be applied to the construction of
a theory. We must have an Ætiology corresponding
to each order of phenomena.
3. Ætiology.—In the History of Geology, I have
spoken of the necessity for such an Ætiology with
regard to geological phenomena: this necessity I have
compared with that which, at the time of Kepler, required the formation of a separate science of Dynamics
(the doctrine of the Causes of Motion), before Physical
Astronomy could grow out of Phenomenal Astronomy.
In pursuance of this analogy, I have there given the
name of Geological Dynamics to the science which
treats of the causes of geological change in general.
But, as I have there intimated, in a large portion of
the subject the changes are so utterly different in their
nature from any modification of motion, that the term
Dynamics, so applied, sounds harsh and strange. For
in this science we have to treat, not only of the subterraneous forces by which parts of the earth’s crust are
shaken, elevated, or ruptured, but also of the causes
which may change the climate of a portion of the
earth’s surface, making a country hotter or colder than
in former ages; again, we have to treat of the causes
which modify the forms and habits of animals and
vegetables, and of the extent to which the effects of
such causes can proceed; whether, for instance, they
can extinguish old species and produce new. These
and other similar investigations would not be naturally
included in the notion of Dynamics; and therefore it 265 might perhaps be better to use the term Ætiology
when we wish to group together all those researches
which have it for their object to determine the laws
of such changes. In the same manner the Comparison
and History of Languages, if it is to lead to any
stable and exact knowledge, must have appended to
it an Ætiology, which aims at determining the nature
and the amount of the causes which really do produce
changes in language; as colonization, conquest, the
mixture of races, civilization, literature, and the like.
And the same rule applies to all sciences of this class.
We shall now make a few remarks on the characteristics of such branches of science as those to which
we are led by the above considerations.
4. Phenomenology requires Classification. Phenomenal Geology.—The Phenomenal portions of each science
imply Classification, for no description of a large and
varied mass of phenomena can be useful or intelligible
without classification. A representation of phenomena, in order to answer the purposes of science, must
be systematic. Accordingly, in giving the History of
Descriptive or Phenomenal Geology, I have called it
Systematic Geology, just as Classificatory Botany is
termed Systematic Botany. Moreover, as we have
already seen, Classification can never be an arbitrary
process, but always implies some natural connexion
among the objects of the same Class; for if this connexion did not exist, the Classes could not be made the
subjects of any true assertion. Yet though the classes
of phenomena which our system acknowledges must be
such as already exist in nature, the discovery of these
classes is, for the most part, very far from obvious or
easy. To detect the true principles of Natural Classes,
and to select marks by which these may be recognized,
are steps which require genius and good fortune, and
which fall to the lot only of the most eminent persons
in each science. In the History, I have pointed out
Werner, William Smith, and Cuvier, as the three
great authors of Systematic Geology of Europe. The
mode of classifying the materials of the earth’s surface which was found, by these philosophers, fitted to 266 enunciate such general facts as came under their notice, was to consider the rocks and other materials as
divided into successive layers or strata, superimposed
one on another, and variously inclined and broken.
The German geologist distinguished his strata for the
most part by their mineralogical character; the other
two, by the remains of animals and plants which the
rocks contained. After a beginning had thus been
made in giving a genuine scientific form to phenomenal
geology, other steps followed in rapid succession, as has
already been related in the History5. The Classification of the Strata was fixed by a suitable Nomenclature. Attempts were made to apply to other countries
the order of strata which had been found to prevail in
that first studied: and in this manner it was ascertained what rocks in distant regions are the synonyms,
or Equivalents6,—of each other. The knowledge thus
collected and systematized was exhibited in the form
of Geological Maps.</div></body></text></TEI>