<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="37">CHAPTER V.
Discoveries added to the Newtonian
Theory.

Sect. 1.—Tables of Astronomical
Refraction.
WE have travelled over an
immense field of astronomical and mathematical labor in the last few
pages, and have yet, at the end of every step, still found ourselves
under the jurisdiction of the Newtonian laws. We are reminded of the
universal monarchies, where a man could not escape from the empire
without quitting the world. We have now to notice some other
discoveries, in which this reference to the law of universal
gravitation is less immediate and obvious; I mean the astronomical
discoveries respecting Light.
The general truths to which the establishment of the true laws of
Atmospheric Refraction led astronomers, were the law of Deflection of
the rays of light, which applies to all refractions, and the real
structure and size of the Atmosphere, so far as it became known. The
great discoveries of Römer and Bradley, namely, the Velocity of Light,
the Aberration of Light, and the Nutation of the earth’s axis, gave a
new distinctness to the conceptions of the propagation of light in the
minds of philosophers, and confirmed the doctrines of Copernicus,
Kepler, and Newton, respecting the motions which belong to the
earth.
The true laws of Atmospheric Refraction were slowly discovered.
Tycho attributed the apparent displacement of the heavenly bodies to
the low and gross part of the atmosphere only, and hence made it cease
at a point half-way to the zenith; but Kepler rightly extended it to
the zenith itself. Dominic Cassini endeavored to discover the law of
this correction by observation, and gave his result in the form 463 which, as we have
said, sound science prescribes, a Table to be habitually used for all
observations. But great difficulties at this time embarrassed this
investigation, for the parallaxes of the sun and of the planets were
unknown, and very diverse values had been assigned them by different
astronomers. To remove some of these difficulties, Richer, in 1762,
went to observe at the equator; and on his return, Cassini was able to
confirm and amend his former estimations of parallax and refraction.
But there were still difficulties. According to La Hire, though the
phenomena of twilight give an altitude of 34,000 toises to the
atmosphere,109 those of refraction make it only 2000.
John Cassini undertook to support and improve the calculations of his
father Dominic, and took the true supposition, that the light follows
a curvilinear path through the air. The Royal Society of London had
already ascertained experimentally the refractive power of air.110 Newton calculated a Table of
Refractions, which was published under Halley’s name in the Philosophical Transactions for
1721, without any indication of the method by which it was
constructed. But M. Biot has recently shown,111 by means of
the published correspondence of Flamsteed, that Newton had solved the
problem in a manner nearly corresponding to the most improved methods
of modern analysis.
109 Bailly, ii. 612.
110 Ibid. ii. 607.
111 Biot, Acad. Sc. Compte
Rendu, Sept. 5, 1836.
Dominic Cassini and Picard proved,112 Le Monnier in
1738 confirmed more fully, the fact that the variations of the
Thermometer affect the Refraction. Mayer, taking into account both
these changes, and the changes indicated by the Barometer, formed a
theory, which Lacaille, with immense labor, applied to the
construction of a Table of Refractions from observation. But Bradley’s
Table (published in 1763 by Maskelyne) was more commonly adopted in
England; and his formula, originally obtained empirically, has been
shown by Young to result from the most probable suppositions we can
make respecting the atmosphere. Bessel’s Refraction Tables are now
considered the best of those which have appeared.
112 Bailly, iii. 92.
Sect. 2.—Discovery of the Velocity of
Light.—Römer.
The astronomical history of Refraction is
not marked by any great discoveries, and was, for the most part, a
work of labor only. The progress of the other portions of our
knowledge respecting light is 464 more striking. In 1676, a great number
of observations of eclipses of Jupiter’s satellites were accumulated,
and could be compared with Cassini’s Tables. Römer, a Danish
astronomer, whom Picard had brought to Paris, perceived that these
eclipses happened constantly later than the calculated time at one
season of the year, and earlier at another season;—a difference
for which astronomy could offer no account. The error was the same for
all the satellites; if it had depended on a defect in the Tables of
Jupiter, it might have affected all, but the effect would have had a
reference to the velocities of the satellites. The cause, then, was
something extraneous to Jupiter. Römer had the happy thought of
comparing the error with the earth’s distance from Jupiter, and it was
found that the eclipses happened later in proportion as Jupiter was
further off.113 Thus we see the eclipse later, as it
is more remote; and thus light, the messenger which brings us
intelligence of the occurrence, travels over its course in a
measurable time. By this evidence, light appeared to take about eleven
minutes in describing the diameter of the earth’s orbit.
113 Bailly, ii. 17.
This discovery, like so many others, once made, appears easy and
inevitable; yet Dominic Cassini had entertained the idea for a
moment,114 and had rejected it; and Fontenelle
had congratulated himself publicly on having narrowly escaped this
seductive error. The objections to the admission of the truth arose
principally from the inaccuracy of observation, and from the
persuasion that the motions of the satellites were circular and
uniform. Their irregularities disguised the fact in question. As these
irregularities became clearly known, Römer’s discovery was finally
established, and the “Equation of Light” took its place in the
Tables.
114 Ib. ii. 419.
Sect. 3.—Discovery of
Aberration.—Bradley.
Improvements in instruments, and in the art
of observing, were requisite for making the next great step in tracing
the effect of the laws of light. It appears clear, on consideration,
that since light and the spectator on the earth are both in motion,
the apparent direction of an object will be determined by the
composition of these motions. But yet the effect of this composition
of motions was (as is usual in such cases) traced as a fact in
observation, before it was clearly seen as a consequence of reasoning.
This fact, the Aberration of Light, the greatest astronomical
discovery of the eighteenth century, belongs to Bradley, 465 who was then
Professor of Astronomy at Oxford, and afterwards Astronomer Royal at
Greenwich. Molyneux and Bradley, in 1725, began a series of
observations for the purpose of ascertaining, by observations near the
zenith, the existence of an annual parallax of the fixed stars, which
Hooke had hoped to detect, and Flamsteed thought he had discovered.
Bradley115 soon found that the star observed by
him had a minute apparent motion different from that which the annual
parallax would produce. He thought of a nutation of the earth’s axis
as a mode of accounting for this; but found, by comparison of a star
on the other side of the pole, that this explanation would not apply.
Bradley and Molyneux then considered for a moment an annual alteration
of figure in the earth’s atmosphere, such as might affect the
refractions, but this hypothesis was soon rejected.116 In 1727, Bradley resumed his
observations, with a new instrument, at Wanstead, and obtained
empirical rules for the changes of declination of different stars. At
last, accident turned his thoughts to the direction in which he was to
find the cause of the variations which he had discovered. Being in a
boat on the Thames, he observed that the vane on the top of the mast
gave a different apparent direction to the wind, as the boat sailed
one way or the other. Here was an image of his case: the boat
represented the earth moving in different directions at different
seasons, and the wind represented the light of a star. He had now to
trace the consequences of this idea; he found that it led to the
empirical rules, which he had already discovered, and, in 1729, he
gave his discovery to the Royal Society. His paper is a very happy
narrative of his labors and his thoughts. His theory was so sound that
no astronomer ever contested it; and his observations were so
accurate, that the quantity which he assigned as the greatest amount
of the change (one nineteenth of a degree) has hardly been corrected
by more recent astronomers. It must be noticed, however, that he
considered the effects in declination only; the effects in right
ascension required a different mode of observation, and a consummate
goodness in the machinery of clocks, which at that time was hardly
attained.
115 Rigaud’s Bradley.
116 Rigaud, p. xxiii.
Sect. 4.—Discovery of Nutation.
When Bradley went to Greenwich as
Astronomer Royal, he continued with perseverance observations of the
same kind as those by which he had detected Aberration. The result of
these was another 466 discovery; namely, that very Nutation
which he had formerly rejected. This may appear strange, but it is
easily explained. The aberration is an annual change, and is detected
by observing a star at different seasons of the year: the Nutation is
a change of which the cycle is eighteen years; and which, therefore,
though it does not much change the place of a star in one year, is
discoverable in the alterations of several successive years. A very
few years’ observations showed Bradley the effect of this change;117 and long before the half cycle of nine
years had elapsed, he had connected it in his mind with the true
cause, the motion of the moon’s nodes. Machin was then Secretary to
the Royal Society,118 and was “employed in considering the
theory of gravity, and its consequences with regard to the celestial
motions:” to him Bradley communicated his conjectures; from him he
soon received a Table containing the results of his calculations; and
the law was found to be the same in the Table and in observation,
though the quantities were somewhat different. It appeared by both,
that the earth’s pole, besides the motion which the precession of the
equinoxes gives it, moves, in eighteen years, through a small
circle;—or rather, as was afterwards found by Bradley, an
ellipse, of which the axes are nineteen and fourteen seconds.119
117 Rigaud, lxiv.
118 Ib. 25.
119 Ib. lxvi.
For the rigorous establishment of the mechanical theory of that
effect of the moon’s attraction from which the phenomena of Nutation
flow, Bradley rightly and prudently invited the assistance of the
great mathematicians of his time. D’Alembert, Thomas Simpson, Euler,
and others, answered this call, and the result was, as we have already
said in the last chapter (Sect. 7), that this
investigation added another to the recondite and profound evidences of
the doctrine of universal gravitation.
It has been said120 that Bradley’s discoveries “assure him
the most distinguished place among astronomers after Hipparchus and
Kepler.” If his discoveries had been made before Newton’s, there could
have been no hesitation as to placing him on a level with those great
men. The existence of such suggestions as the Newtonian theory offered
on all astronomical subjects, may perhaps dim, in our eyes, the
brilliance of Bradley’s achievements; but this circumstance cannot
place any other person above the author of such discoveries, and
therefore we may consider Delambre’s adjudication of precedence as
well warranted, and deserving to be permanent.
120 Delambre, Ast. du 18
Sièc. p. 420. Rigaud, xxxvii. 467
Sect. 5.—Discovery of the Laws of Double
Stars.—The two Herschels.
No truth, then, can be more certainly
established, than that the law of gravitation prevails to the very
boundaries of the solar system. But does it hold good further? Do the
fixed stars also obey this universal sway? The idea, the question, is
an obvious one—but where are we to find the means of submitting
it to the test of observation?
If the Stars were each insulated from the rest, as our Sun appears
to be from them, we should have been quite unable to answer this
inquiry. But among the stars, there are some which are called
Double Stars, and which consist of two stars, so near to each
other that the telescope alone can separate them. The elder Herschel
diligently observed and measured the relative positions of the two
stars in such pairs; and as has so often happened in astronomical
history, pursuing one object he fell in with another. Supposing such
pairs to be really unconnected, he wished to learn, from their
phenomena, something respecting the annual parallax of the earth’s
orbit. But in the course of twenty years’ observations he made the
discovery (in 1803) that some of these couples were turning round each
other with various angular velocities. These revolutions were for the
most part so slow that he was obliged to leave their complete
determination as an inheritance to the next generation. His son was
not careless of the bequest, and after having added an enormous mass
of observations to those of his father, he applied himself to
determine the laws of these revolutions. A problem so obvious and so
tempting was attacked also by others, as Savary and Encke, in 1830 and
1832, with the resources of analysis. But a problem in which the data
are so minute and inevitably imperfect, required the mathematician to
employ much judgment, as well as skill in using and combining these
data; and Sir John Herschel, by employing positions only of the line
joining the pair of stars (which can be observed with comparative
exactness), to the exclusion of their distances (which cannot be
measured with much correctness), and by inventing a method which
depended upon the whole body of observations, and not upon selected
ones only, for the determination of the motion, has made his
investigations by far the most satisfactory of those which have
appeared. The result is, that it has been rendered very probable, that
in several of the double stars the two stars describe ellipses about
each other; and therefore that here also, at an 468 immeasurable distance
from our system, the law of attraction according to the inverse square
of the distance, prevails. And, according to the practice of
astronomers when a law has been established, Tables have been
calculated for the future motions; and we have Ephemerides of the
revolutions of suns round each other, in a region so remote, that the
whole circle of our earth’s orbit, if placed there, would be
imperceptible by our strongest telescopes. The permanent comparison of
the observed with the predicted motions, continued for more than one
revolution, is the severe and decisive test of the truth of the
theory; and the result of this test astronomers are now awaiting.
[2d Ed.] [In calculating the orbits of revolving systems of double
stars, there is a peculiar difficulty, arising from the plane of the
orbit being in a position unknown, but probably oblique, to the visual
ray. Hence it comes to pass that even if the orbit be an ellipse
described about the focus by the laws of planetary motion, it will
appear otherwise; and the true orbit will have to be deduced from the
apparent one.
With regard to a difficulty which has been mentioned, that the two
stars, if they are governed by gravity, will not revolve the one about
the other, but both about their common centre of gravity;—this
circumstance adds little difficulty to the problem. Newton has shown
(Princip. lib. i. Prop. 61) in the problem of two
bodies, the relation between the relative orbits and the orbit
about the common centre of gravity.
How many of the apparently double stars have orbitual
motions? Sir John Herschel in 1833 gave, in his Astronomy
(Art. 606), a list of nine stars, with periods extending from 43 years
(η Coronæ) to 1200 years (γ Leonis), which he presented as the chief
results then obtained in this department. In his work on Double Stars,
the fruit of his labors in both hemispheres, which the astronomical
world are looking for with eager expectation, he will, I believe, have
a few more to add to these.
Is it well established that such double stars attract each
other according to the law of the inverse square of the distance?
The answer to this question must be determined by ascertaining whether
the above cases are regulated by the laws of elliptical motion. This
is a matter which it must require a long course of careful observation
to determine in such a number of cases as to prove the universality of
the rule. Perhaps the minds of astronomers are still in suspense upon
the subject. When Sir John Herschel’s work shall appear, it will
probably 469 be
found that with regard to some of these stars, and γ Virginis in
particular, the conformity of the observations with the laws of
elliptical motion amounts to a degree of exactness which must give
astronomers a strong conviction of the truth of the law. For since Sir
W. Herschel’s first measures in 1781, the arc described by one star
about the other is above 305 degrees; and during this period the
angular annual motion has been very various, passing through all
gradations from about 20 minutes to 80 degrees. Yet in the whole of
this change, the two curves constructed, the one from the
observations, the other from the elliptical elements, for the purpose
of comparison, having a total ordinate of 305 parts, do not, in any
part of their course, deviate from each other so much as two
such parts.]
The verification of Newton’s discoveries was sufficient employment
for the last century; the first step in the extension of them belongs
to this century. We cannot at present foresee the magnitude of this
task, but every one must feel that the law of gravitation, before
verified in all the particles of our own system, and now probably
extended to the all but infinite distance of the fixed stars, presses
upon our minds with a strong claim to be accepted as a universal law
of the whole material creation.
Thus, in this and the preceding chapter, I have given a brief
sketch of the history of the verification and extension of Newton’s
great discovery. By the mass of labor and of skill which this head of
our subject includes, we may judge of the magnitude of the advance in
our knowledge which that discovery made. A wonderful amount of talent
and industry have been requisite for this purpose; but with these,
external means have co-operated. Wealth, authority, mechanical skill,
the division of labor, the power of associations and of governments,
have been largely and worthily applied in bringing astronomy to its
present high and flourishing condition. We must consider briefly what
has thus been done. ~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~ 470</div></body></text></TEI>