<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol I</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1794</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="24">SECT. XXIV.
OF THE SECRETIONS OF SALIVA, AND OF TEARS, AND OF
THE LACRYMAL SACK.

I. Secretion of saliva increased by
  mercury in the blood. 1. By the food
  in the mouth. Dryness of the mouth not from a deficiency of saliva.
2. By Sensitive ideas. 3. By volition. 4. By distasteful substances. It is secreted
  in a dilute and saline state. It then becomes more viscid. 5. By ideas of distasteful substances.
6. By nausea. 7. By aversion. 8. By catenation with stimulating substances
  in the ear. II. 1. Secretion of tears less in sleep. From
  stimulation of their excretory duct. 2.
  Lacrymal sack is a gland. 3. Its
  uses. 4. Tears are secreted, when the
  nasal duct is stimulated. 5. Or when
  it is excited by sensation. 6. Or by
  volition. 7. The lacrymal sack can
  regurgitate its contents into the eye. 8. More tears are secreted by association
  with the irritation of the nasal duct of the lacrymal sack, than the
  puncta lacrymalia can imbibe. Of the gout in the liver and
  stomach.

I. The salival glands drink up a certain
  fluid from the circumfluent blood, and pour it into the mouth. They are
  sometimes stimulated into action by the blood, that surrounds their
  origin, or by some part of that heterogeneous fluid: for when mercurial
  salts, or oxydes, are mixed with the blood, they stimulate these glands
  into unnatural exertions; and then an unusual quantity of saliva is
  separated.
1. As the saliva secreted by these glands
  is most wanted during the mastication of our food, it happens, when the
  terminations of their ducts in the mouth are stimulated into action, the
  salival glands themselves are brought into increased action at the same
  time by association, and separate a greater quantity of their juices from
  the blood; in the same manner as tears are produced in greater abundance
  during the stimulus of the vapour of onions, or of any other acrid
  material in the eye.
The saliva is thus naturally poured into the mouth only during the
  stimulus of our food in mastication; for when there is too great an
  exhalation of the mucilaginous secretion from the membranes, which line
  the mouth, or too great an absorption of it, the mouth becomes dry,
  though there is no deficiency in the quantity of saliva; as in those who
  sleep with their mouths open, and in some fevers.
2. Though during the mastication of our
  natural food the salival glands are excited into action by the stimulus
  on their excretory ducts, and a due quantity of saliva is separated from
  the blood, and poured into the mouth; yet as this mastication of our food
  is always attended with a degree of pleasure; and that pleasurable
  sensation is also connected with our ideas of certain kinds of aliment;
  it follows, that when these ideas are reproduced, the pleasurable
  sensation arises along with them, and the salival glands are excited into
  action, and fill the mouth with saliva from this sensitive association,
  as is frequently seen in dogs, who slaver at the sight of food.
3. We have also a voluntary power over the
  action of these salival glands, for we can at any time produce a flow of
  saliva into our mouth, and spit out, or swallow it at will.
4. If any very acrid material be held in
  the mouth, as the root of pyrethrum, or the leaves of tobacco, the
  salival glands are stimulated into stronger action than is natural, and
  thence secrete a much larger quantity of saliva; which is at the same
  time more viscid than in its natural state; because the lymphatics, that
  open their mouths into the ducts of the salival glands, and on the
  membranes, which line the mouth, are likewise stimulated into stronger
  action, and absorb the more liquid parts of the saliva with greater
  avidity; and the remainder is left both in greater quantity and more
  viscid.
The increased absorption in the mouth by some stimulating substances,
  which are called astringents, as crab juice, is evident from the instant
  dryness produced in the mouth by a small quantity of them.
As the extremities of the glands are of exquisite tenuity, as appears
  by their difficulty of injection, it was necessary for them to secrete
  their fluids in a very dilute state; and, probably for the purpose of
  stimulating them into action, a quantity of neutral salt is likewise
  secreted or formed by the gland. This aqueous and saline part of all
  secreted fluids is again reabsorbed into the habit. More than half of
  some secreted fluids is thus imbibed from the reservoirs, into which they
  are poured; as in the urinary bladder much more than half of what is
  secreted by the kidneys becomes reabsorbed by the lymphatics, which are
  thickly dispersed around the neck of the bladder. This seems to be the
  purpose of the urinary bladders of fish, as otherwise such a receptacle
  for the urine could have been of no use to an animal immersed in
  water.
5. The idea of substances disagreeably
  acrid will also produce a quantity of saliva in the mouth; as when we
  smell very putrid vapours, we are induced to spit out our saliva, as if
  something disagreeable was actually upon our palates.
6. When disagreeable food in the stomach
  produces nausea, a flow of saliva is excited in the mouth by association;
  as efforts to vomit are frequently produced by disagreeable drugs in the
  mouth by the same kind of association.
7. A preternatural flow of saliva is
  likewise sometimes occasioned by a disease of the voluntary power; for if
  we think about our saliva, and determine not to swallow it, or not to
  spit it out, an exertion is produced by the will, and more saliva is
  secreted against our wish; that is, by our aversion, which bears the same
  analogy to desire, as pain does to pleasure; as they are only
  modifications of the same disposition of the sensorium. See Class IV. 3.
  2. 1.
8. The quantity of saliva may also be
  increased beyond what is natural, by the catenation of the motions of
  these glands with other motions, or sensations, as by an extraneous body
  in the ear; of which I have known an instance; or by the application of
  stizolobium, siliqua hirsuta, cowhage, to the seat of the parotis, as
  some writers have affirmed.
II. 1. The
  lacrymal gland drinks up a certain fluid from the circumfluent blood, and
  pours it on the ball of the eye, on the upper part of the external corner
  of the eyelids. Though it may perhaps be stimulated into the performance
  of its natural action by the blood, which surrounds its origin, or by
  some part of that heterogeneous fluid; yet as the tears secreted by this
  gland are more wanted at some times than at others, its secretion is
  variable, like that of the saliva above mentioned, and is chiefly
  produced when its excretory duct is stimulated; for in our common sleep
  there seems to be little or no secretion of tears; though they are
  occasionally produced by our sensations in dreams.
Thus when any extraneous material on the eye-ball, or the dryness of
  the external covering of it, or the coldness of the air, or the acrimony
  of some vapours, as of onions, stimulates the excretory duct of the
  lacrymal gland, it discharges its contents upon the ball; a quicker
  secretion takes place in the gland, and abundant tears succeed, to
  moisten, clean, and lubricate the eye. These by frequent nictitation are
  diffused over the whole ball, and as the external angle of the eye in
  winking is closed sooner than the internal angle, the tears are gradually
  driven forwards, and downwards from the lacrymal gland to the puncta
  lacrymalia.
2. The lacrymal sack, with its puncta
  lacrymalia, and its nasal duct, is a complete gland; and is singular in
  this respect, that it neither derives its fluid from, nor disgorges it
  into the circulation. The simplicity of the structure of this gland, and
  both the extremities of it being on the surface of the body, makes it
  well worthy our minuter observation; as the actions of more intricate and
  concealed glands may be better understood from their analogy to this.
3. This simple gland consists of two
  absorbing mouths, a belly, and an excretory duct. As the tears are
  brought to the internal angle of the eye, these two mouths drink them up,
  being stimulated into action by this fluid, which they absorb. The belly
  of the gland, or lacrymal sack, is thus filled, in which the saline part
  of the tears is absorbed, and when the other end of the gland, or nasal
  duct, is stimulated by the dryness, or pained by the coldness of the air,
  or affected by any acrimonious dust or vapour in the nostrils, it is
  excited into action together with the sack, and the tears are disgorged
  upon the membrane, which lines the nostrils; where they serve a second
  purpose to moisten, clean, and lubricate, the organ of smell.
4. When the nasal duct of this gland is
  stimulated by any very acrid material, as the powder of tobacco, or
  volatile spirits, it not only disgorges the contents of its belly or
  receptacle (the lacrymal sack), and absorbs hastily all the fluid, that
  is ready for it in the corner of the eye; but by the association of its
  motions with those of the lacrymal gland, it excites that also into
  increased action, and a large flow of tears is poured into the eye.
5. This nasal duct is likewise excited
  into strong action by sensitive ideas, as in grief, or joy, and then also
  by its associations with the lacrymal gland it produces a great flow of
  tears without any external stimulus; as is more fully explained in Sect.
  XVI. 8. on Instinct.
6. There are some, famous in the arts of
  exciting compassion, who are said to have acquired a voluntary power of
  producing a flow of tears in the eye; which, from what has been said in
  the section on Instinct above mentioned, I should suspect, is performed
  by acquiring a voluntary power over the action of this nasal duct.
7. There is another circumstance well
  worthy our attention, that when by any accident this nasal duct is
  obstructed, the lacrymal sack, which is the belly or receptacle of this
  gland, by slight pressure of the finger is enabled to disgorge its
  contents again into the eye; perhaps the bile in the same manner, when
  the biliary ducts are obstructed, is returned into the blood by the
  vessels which secrete it?
8. A very important though minute
  occurrence must here be observed, that though the lacrymal gland is only
  excited into action, when we weep at a distressful tale, by its
  association with this nasal duct, as is more fully explained in Sect. XVI. 8; yet the quantity of tears secreted at once
  is more than the puncta lacrymalia can readily absorb; which shews
  that the motions occasioned by associations are frequently more
  energetic than the original motions, by which they were occasioned.
  Which we shall have occasion to mention hereafter, to illustrate, why
  pains frequently exist in a part distant from the cause of them, as in
  the other end of the urethra, when a stone stimulates the neck of the
  bladder. And why inflammations frequently arise in parts distant from
  their cause, as the gutta rosea of drinking people, from an inflamed
  liver.
The inflammation of a part is generally preceded by a torpor or
  quiescence of it; if this exists in any large congeries of glands, as in
  the liver, or any membranous part, as the stomach, pain is produced and
  chilliness in consequence of the torpor of the vessels. In this situation
  sometimes an inflammation of the parts succeeds the torpor; at other
  times a distant more sensible part becomes inflamed; whose actions have
  previously been associated with it; and the torpor of the first part
  ceases. This I apprehend happens, when the gout of the foot succeeds a
  pain of the biliary duct, or of the stomach. Lastly, it sometimes
  happens, that the pain of torpor exists without any consequent
  inflammation of the affected part, or of any distant part associated with
  it, as in the membranes about the temple and eye-brows in hemicrania, and
  in those pains, which occasion convulsions; if this happens to gouty
  people, when it affects the liver, I suppose epileptic fits are produced;
  and, when it affects the stomach, death is the consequence. In these
  cases the pulse is weak, and the extremities cold, and such medicines as
  stimulate the quiescent parts into action, or which induce inflammation
  in them, or in any distant part, which is associated with them, cures the
  present pain of torpor, and saves the patient.
I have twice seen a gouty inflammation of the liver, attended with
  jaundice; the patients after a few days were both of them affected with
  cold fits, like ague-fits, and their feet became affected with gout, and
  the inflammation of their livers ceased. It is probable, that the uneasy
  sensations about the stomach, and indigestion, which precedes gouty
  paroxysms, are generally owing to torpor or slight inflammation of the
  liver, and biliary ducts; but where great pain with continued sickness,
  with feeble pulse, and sensation of cold, affect the stomach in patients
  debilitated by the gout, that it is a torpor of the stomach itself, and
  destroys the patient from the great connexion of that viscus with the
  vital organs. See Sect. XXV. 17.

</div></body></text></TEI>