<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol I</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1794</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="21">SECT. XXI.
OF DRUNKENNESS.

1. Sleep from satiety of hunger. From
  rocking children. From uniform sounds. 2.
  Intoxication from common food after fatigue and inanition. 3. From wine or of opium. Chilness after meals.
  Vertigo. Why pleasure is produced by intoxication, and by swinging and
  rocking children. And why pain is relieved by it. 4. Why drunkards stagger and stammer, and are
  liable to weep. 5. And become delirious,
  sleepy, and stupid. 6. Or make pale
  urine and vomit. 7. Objects are seen
  double. 8. Attention of the mind
  diminishes drunkenness. 9. Disordered
  irritative motions of all the senses. 10.
  Diseases from drunkenness. 11.
  Definition of drunkenness.

1. In the state of nature when the sense of
  hunger is appeased by the stimulus of agreeable food, the business of the
  day is over, and the human savage is at peace with the world, he then
  exerts little attention to external objects, pleasing reveries of
  imagination succeed, and at length sleep is the result: till the
  nourishment which he has procured, is carried over every part of the
  system to repair the injuries of action, and he awakens with fresh
  vigour, and feels a renewal of his sense of hunger.
The juices of some bitter vegetables, as of the poppy and the
  laurocerasus, and the ardent spirit produced in the fermentation of the
  sugar found in vegetable juices, are so agreeable to the nerves of the
  stomach, that, taken in a small quantity, they instantly pacify the sense
  of hunger; and the inattention to external stimuli with the reveries of
  imagination, and sleep, succeeds, in the same manner as when the stomach
  is filled with other less intoxicating food.
This inattention to the irritative motions occasioned by external
  stimuli is a very important circumstance in the approach of sleep, and is
  produced in young children by rocking their cradles: during which all
  visible objects become indistinct to them. An uniform soft repeated
  sound, as the murmurs of a gentle current, or of bees, are said to
  produce the same effect, by presenting indistinct ideas of
  inconsequential sounds, and by thus stealing our attention from other
  objects, whilst by their continued reiterations they become familiar
  themselves, and we cease gradually to attend to any thing, and sleep
  ensues.
2. After great fatigue or inanition, when the
  stomach is suddenly filled with flesh and vegetable food, the inattention
  to external stimuli, and the reveries of imagination, become so
  conspicuous as to amount to a degree of intoxication. The same is at any
  time produced by superadding a little wine or opium to our common meals;
  or by taking these separately in considerable quantity; and this more
  efficaciously after fatigue or inanition; because a less quantity of any
  stimulating material will excite an organ into energetic action, after it
  has lately been torpid from defect of stimulus; as objects appear more
  luminous, after we have been in the dark; and because the suspension of
  volition, which is the immediate cause of sleep, is sooner induced, after
  a continued voluntary exertion has in part exhausted the sensorial power
  of volition; in the same manner as we cannot contract a single muscle
  long together without intervals of inaction.
3. In the beginning of intoxication we are
  inclined to sleep, as mentioned above, but by the excitement of external
  circumstances, as of noise, light, business, or by the exertion of
  volition, we prevent the approaches of it, and continue to take into our
  stomach greater quantities of the inebriating materials. By these means
  the irritative movements of the stomach are excited into greater action
  than is natural; and in consequence all the irritative tribes and trains
  of motion, which are catenated with them, become susceptible of stronger
  action from their accustomed stimuli; because these motions are excited
  both by their usual irritation, and by their association with the
  increased actions of the stomach and lacteals. Hence the skin glows, and
  the heat of the body is increased, by the more energetic action of the
  whole glandular system; and pleasure is introduced in consequence of
  these increased motions from internal stimulus. According to Law 5. Sect.
  IV. on Animal Causation.
From this great increase of irritative motions from internal stimulus,
  and the increased sensation introduced into the system in consequence;
  and secondly, from the increased sensitive motions in consequence of this
  additional quantity of sensation, so much sensorial power is expended,
  that the voluntary power becomes feebly exerted, and the irritation from
  the stimulus of external objects is less forcible; the external parts of
  the eye are not therefore voluntarily adapted to the distances of
  objects, whence the apparent motions of those objects either are seen
  double, or become too indistinct for the purpose of balancing the body,
  and vertigo is induced.
Hence we become acquainted with that very curious circumstance, why
  the drunken vertigo is attended with an increase of pleasure; for the
  irritative ideas and motions occasioned by internal stimulus, that were
  not attended to in our sober hours, are now just so much increased as to
  be succeeded by pleasurable sensation, in the same manner as the more
  violent motions of our organs are succeeded by painful sensation. And
  hence a greater quantity of pleasurable sensation is introduced into the
  constitution; which is attended in some people with an increase of
  benevolence and good humour.
If the apparent motions of objects is much increased, as when we
  revolve on one foot, or are swung on a rope, the ideas of these apparent
  motions are also attended to, and are succeeded with pleasureable
  sensation, till they become familiar to us by frequent use. Hence
  children are at first delighted with these kinds of exercise, and with
  riding, and failing, and hence rocking young children inclines them to
  sleep. For though in the vertigo from intoxication the irritative ideas
  of the apparent motions of objects are indistinct from their decrease of
  energy: yet in the vertigo occasioned by rocking or swinging the
  irritative ideas of the apparent motions of objects are increased in
  energy, and hence they induce pleasure into the system, but are equally
  indistinct, and in consequence equally unfit to balance ourselves by.
  This addition of pleasure precludes desire or aversion, and in
  consequence the voluntary power is feebly exerted, and on this account
  rocking young children inclines them to sleep.
In what manner opium and wine act in relieving pain is another
  article, that well deserves our attention. There are many pains that
  originate from defect as well as from excess of stimulus; of these are
  those of the six appetites of hunger, thirst, lust, the want of heat, of
  distention, and of fresh air. Thus if our cutaneous capillaries cease to
  act from the diminished stimulus of heat, when we are exposed to cold
  weather, or our stomach is uneasy for want of food; these are both pains
  from defect of stimulus, and in consequence opium, which stimulates all
  the moving system into increased action, must relieve them. But this is
  not the case in those pains, which arise from excess of stimulus, as in
  violent inflammations: in these the exhibition of opium is frequently
  injurious by increasing the action of the system already too great, as in
  inflammation of the bowels mortification is often produced by the
  stimulus of opium. Where, however, no such bad consequences follow; the
  stimulus of opium, by increasing all the motions of the system, expends
  so much of the sensorial power, that the actions of the whole system soon
  become feebler, and in consequence those which produced the pain and
  inflammation.
4. When intoxication proceeds a little
  further, the quantity of pleasurable sensation is so far increased, that
  all desire ceases, for there is no pain in the system to excite it. Hence
  the voluntary exertions are diminished, staggering and stammering
  succeed; and the trains of ideas become more and more inconsistent from
  this defect of voluntary exertion, as explained in the sections on sleep
  and reverie, whilst those passions which are unmixed with volition are
  more vividly felt, and shewn with less reserve; hence pining love, or
  superstitious fear, and the maudling tear dropped on the remembrance of
  the most trifling distress.
5. At length all these circumstances are
  increased; the quantity of pleasure introduced into the system by the
  increased irritative muscular motions of the whole sanguiferous, and
  glandular, and absorbent systems, becomes so great, that the organs of
  sense are more forcibly excited into action by this internal pleasurable
  sensation, than by the irritation from the stimulus of external objects.
  Hence the drunkard ceases to attend to external stimuli, and as volition
  is now also suspended, the trains of his ideas become totally
  inconsistent as in dreams, or delirium: and at length a stupor succeeds
  from the great exhaustion of sensorial power, which probably does not
  even admit of dreams, and in which, as in apoplexy, no motions continue
  but those from internal stimuli, from sensation, and from
  association.
6. In other people a paroxysm of drunkenness
  has another termination; the inebriate, as soon as he begins to be
  vertiginous, makes pale urine in great quantities and very frequently,
  and at length becomes sick, vomits repeatedly, or purges, or has profuse
  sweats, and a temporary fever ensues with a quick strong pulse. This in
  some hours is succeeded by sleep; but the unfortunate bacchanalian does
  not perfectly recover himself till about the same time of the succeeding
  day, when his course of inebriation began. As shewn in Sect. XVII. 1. 7. on Catenation. The temporary fever
  with strong pulse is owing to the same cause as the glow on the skin
  mentioned in the third paragraph of this Section: the flow of urine and
  sickness arises from the whole system of irritative motions being thrown
  into confusion by their associations with each other; as in sea-sickness,
  mentioned in Sect. XX. 4. on Vertigo; and which
  is more fully explained in Section XXIX. on
  Diabetes.
7. In this vertigo from internal causes we
  see objects double, as two candles instead of one, which is thus
  explained. Two lines drawn through the axes of our two eyes meet at the
  object we attend to: this angle of the optic axes increases or diminishes
  with the less or greater distances of objects. All objects before or
  behind the place where this angle is formed, appear double; as any one
  may observe by holding up a pen between his eyes and the candle; when he
  looks attentively at a spot on the pen, and carelessly at the candle, it
  will appear double; and the reverse when he looks attentively at the
  candle and carelessly at the pen; so that in this case the muscles of the
  eye, like those of the limbs, stagger and are disobedient to the expiring
  efforts of volition. Numerous objects are indeed sometimes seen by the
  inebriate, occasioned by the refractions made by the tears, which stand
  upon his eye-lids.
8. This vertigo also continues, when the
  inebriate lies in his bed, in the dark, or with his eyes closed; and this
  more powerfully than when he is erect, and in the light. For the
  irritative ideas of the apparent motions of objects are now excited by
  irritation from internal stimulus, or by association with other
  irritative motions; and the inebriate, like one in a dream, believes the
  objects of these irritative motions to be present, and feels himself
  vertiginous. I have observed in this situation, so long as my eyes and
  mind were intent upon a book, the sickness and vertigo ceased, and were
  renewed again the moment I discontinued this attention; as was explained
  in the preceding account of sea-sickness. Some drunken people have been
  known to become sober instantly from some accident, that has strongly
  excited their attention, as the pain of a broken bone, or the news of
  their house being on fire.
9. Sometimes the vertigo from internal
  causes, as from intoxication, or at the beginning of some fevers, becomes
  so universal, that the irritative motions which belong to other organs of
  sense are succeeded by sensation or attention, as well as those of the
  eye. The vertiginous noise in the ears has been explained in Section XX. on Vertigo. The taste of the saliva, which in
  general is not attended to, becomes perceptible, and the patients
  complain of a bad taste in their mouth.
The common smells of the surrounding air sometimes excite the
  attention of these patients, and bad smells are complained of, which to
  other people are imperceptible. The irritative motions that belong to the
  sense of pressure, or of touch, are attended to, and the patient
  conceives the bed to librate, and is fearful of falling out of it. The
  irritative motions belonging to the senses of distention, and of heat,
  like those above mentioned, become attended to at this time: hence we
  feel the pulsation of our arteries all over us, and complain of heat, or
  of cold, in parts of the body where there is no accumulation or
  diminution of actual heat. All which are to be explained, as in the last
  paragraph, by the irritative ideas belonging to the various senses being
  now excited by internal stimuli, or by their associations with other
  irritative motions. And that the inebriate, like one in a dream, believes
  the external objects, which usually caused these irritative ideas, to be
  now present.
10. The diseases in consequence of frequent
  inebriety, or of daily taking much vinous spirit without inebriety,
  consist in the paralysis, which is liable to succeed violent stimulation.
  Organs, whose actions are associated with others, are frequently more
  affected than the organ, which is stimulated into too violent action. See
  Sect. XXIV. 2. 8. Hence in drunken people it
  generally happens, that the secretory vessels of the liver become first
  paralytic, and a torpor with consequent gall-stones or schirrus of this
  viscus is induced with concomitant jaundice; otherwise it becomes
  inflamed in consequence of previous torpor, and this inflammation is
  frequently transferred to a more sensible part, which is associated with
  it, and produces the gout, or the rosy eruption of the face, or some
  other leprous eruption on the head, or arms, or legs. Sometimes the
  stomach is first affected, and paralysis of the lacteal system is
  induced: whence a total abhorrence from flesh-food, and general
  emaciation. In others the lymphatic system is affected with paralysis,
  and dropsy is the consequence. In some inebriates the torpor of the liver
  produces pain without apparent schirrus, or gall stones, or inflammation,
  or consequent gout, and in these epilepsy or insanity are often the
  consequence. All which will be more fully treated of in the course of the
  work.
I am well aware, that it is a common opinion, that the gout is as
  frequently owing to gluttony in eating, as to intemperance in drinking
  fermented or spirituous liquors. To this I answer, that I have seen no
  person afflicted with the gout, who has not drank freely of fermented
  liquor, as wine and water, or small beer; though as the disposition to
  all the diseases, which have originated from intoxication, is in some
  degree hereditary, a less quantity of spirituous potation will induce the
  gout in those, who inherit the disposition from their parents. To which I
  must add, that in young people the rheumatism is frequently mistaken for
  the gout.
Spice is seldom taken in such quantity as to do any material injury to
  the system, flesh-meats as well as vegetables are the natural diet of
  mankind; with these a glutton may be crammed up to the throat, and fed
  fat like a stalled ox; but he will not be diseased, unless he adds
  spirituous or fermented liquor to his food. This is well known in the
  distilleries, where the swine, which are fattened by the spirituous
  sediments of barrels, acquire diseased livers. But mark what happens to a
  man, who drinks a quart of wine or of ale, if he has not been habituated
  to it. He loses the use both of his limbs and of his understanding! He
  becomes a temporary idiot, and has a temporary stroke of the palsy! And
  though he slowly recovers after some hours, is it not reasonable to
  conclude, that a perpetual repetition of so powerful a poison must at
  length permanently affect him?—If a person accidentally becomes
  intoxicated by eating a few mushrooms of a peculiar kind, a general alarm
  is excited, and he is said to be poisoned, and emetics are exhibited; but
  so familiarised are we to the intoxication from vinous spirit, that it
  occasions laughter rather than alarm.
There is however considerable danger in too hastily discontinuing the
  use of so strong a stimulus, lest the torpor of the system, or paralysis,
  should sooner be induced by the omission than by the continuance of this
  habit, when unfortunately acquired. A golden rule for determining the
  quantity, which may with safety be discontinued, is delivered in Sect. XII. 7. 8.
11. Definition of drunkenness. Many of the
  irritative motions are much increased in energy by internal
  stimulation.
2. A great additional quantity of pleasurable sensation is occasioned
  by this increased exertion of the irritative motions. And many sensitive
  motions are produced in consequence of this increased sensation.
3. The associated trains and tribes of motions, catenated with the
  increased irritative and sensitive motions, are disturbed, and proceed in
  confusion.
4. The faculty of volition is gradually impaired, whence proceeds the
  instability of locomotion, inaccuracy of perception, and inconsistency of
  ideas; and is at length totally suspended, and a temporary apoplexy
  succeeds.

</div></body></text></TEI>