<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="117">CHAPTER III.
Formation of a System of Arrangement of
Plants.
Sect. 1.—Prelude to the Epoch of
Cæsalpinus.
THE arrangement of plants in
the earliest works was either arbitrary, or according to their use, or
some other extraneous circumstance, as in Pliny. This and the division
of vegetables by Dioscorides into aromatic, alimentary,
medicinal, vinous, is, as will be easily seen, a merely
casual distribution. The Arabian writers, and those of the middle
ages, showed still more clearly their insensibility to the nature of
system, by adopting an alphabetical arrangement; which was employed
also in the Herbals of the sixteenth century. Brunfels, as we have
said, adopted no principle of order; nor did his successor, Fuchs. Yet
the latter writer urged his countrymen to put aside their Arabian and
barbarous Latin doctors, and to observe the vegetable kingdom for
themselves; and he himself set the example of doing this, examined
plants with zeal and accuracy, and made above fifteen hundred drawings
of them.36
36 His Historia Stirpium was
published at Basil in 1542.
370 The
difficulty of representing plants in any useful way by means of
drawings, is greater, perhaps, than it at first appears. So long as no
distinction was made of the importance of different organs of the
plant, a picture representing merely the obvious general appearance
and larger parts, was of comparatively small value. Hence we are not
to wonder at the slighting manner in which Pliny speaks of such
records. “Those who gave such pictures of plants,” he says, “Crateuas,
Dionysius, Metrodorus, have shown nothing clearly, except the
difficulty of their undertaking. A picture may be mistaken, and is
changed and disfigured by copyists; and, without these imperfections,
it is not enough to represent the plant in one state, since it has
four different aspects in the four seasons of the year.”
The diffusion of the habit of exact drawing, especially among the
countrymen of Albert Durer and Lucas Cranach, and the invention of
wood-cuts and copper-plates, remedied some of these defects. Moreover,
the conviction gradually arose in men’s minds that the structure of
the flower and the fruit are the most important circumstances in
fixing the identity of the plant. Theophrastus speaks with precision
of the organs which he describes, but these are principally the
leaves, roots, and stems. Fuchs uses the term apices for the
anthers, and gluma for the blossom of grasses, thus showing
that he had noticed these parts as generally present.
In the next writer whom we have to mention, we find some traces of
a perception of the real resemblances of plants beginning to appear.
It is impossible to explain the progress of such views without
assuming in the reader some acquaintance with plants; but a very few
words may suffice to convey the requisite notions. Even in plants
which most commonly come in our way, we may perceive instances of the
resemblances of which we speak. Thus, Mint, Marjoram, Basil, Sage,
Lavender, Thyme, Dead-nettle, and many other plants, have a tubular
flower, of which the mouth is divided into two lips; hence they are
formed into a family, and termed Labiatæ. Again, the Stock, the
Wall-flower, the Mustard, the Cress, the Lady-smock, the Shepherd’s
purse, have, among other similarities, their blossoms with four petals
arranged crosswise; these are all of the order Cruciferæ. Other
flowers, apparently more complex, still resemble each other, as Daisy.
Marigold, Aster, and Chamomile; these belong to the order
Compositæ. And though the members of each such family may
differ widely in their larger parts, their stems and leaves, the close
study of nature leads the botanist irresistibly to consider their
resemblances as 371
occupying a far more important place than their differences. It is the
general establishment of this conviction and its consequences which we
have now to follow.
The first writer in whom we find the traces of an arrangement
depending upon these natural resemblances, is Hieronymus Tragus,
(Jerom Bock,) a laborious German botanist, who, in 1551, published a
herbal. In this work, several of the species included in those natural
families to which we have alluded,37 as for instance
the Labiatæ, the Cruciferæ, the Compositæ, are for the most part
brought together; and thus, although with many mistakes as to such
connexions, a new principle of order is introduced into the
subject.
37 Sprengel, i. 270.
In pursuing the development of such principles of natural order, it
is necessary to recollect that the principles lead to an assemblage of
divisions and groups, successively subordinate, the lower to the
higher, like the brigades, regiments, and companies of an army, or the
provinces, towns, and parishes of a kingdom. Species are included in
Genera, Genera in Families or Orders, and orders in Classes. The
perception that there is some connexion among the species of plants,
was the first essential step; the detection of different marks and
characters which should give, on the one hand, limited groups, on the
other, comprehensive divisions, were other highly important parts of
this advance. To point out every successive movement in this progress
would be a task of extreme difficulty, but we may note, as the most
prominent portions of it, the establishment of the groups which
immediately include Species, that is, the formation of Genera;
and the invention of a method which should distribute into consistent
and distinct divisions the whole vegetable kingdom, that is, the
construction of a System.
To the second of these two steps we have no difficulty in assigning
its proper author. It belongs to Cæsalpinus, and marks the first great
epoch of this science. It is less easy to state to what botanist is
due the establishment of Genera; yet we may justly assign the greater
part of the merit of this invention, as is usually done, to Conrad
Gessner of Zurich. This eminent naturalist, after publishing his great
work on animals, died38 of the plague in 1565, at the age of
forty-nine, while he was preparing to publish a History of Plants, a
sequel to his History of Animals. The fate of the work thus left 372 unfinished was
remarkable. It fell into the hands of his pupil, Gaspard Wolf, who was
to have published it, but wanting leisure for the office, sold it to
Joachim Camerarius, a physician and botanist of Nuremberg, who made
use of the engravings prepared by Gessner, in an Epitome which he
published in 1586. The text of Gessner’s work, after passing through
various hands, was published in 1754 under the title of Gessneri
Opera Botanica per duo Sæcula desiderata, &c., but is very
incomplete.
38 Cuvier, Leçons sur l’Hist. des
Sciences Naturelles, partie ii. p. 193.
The imperfect state in which Gessner left his botanical labors,
makes it necessary to seek the evidence of his peculiar views in
scattered passages of his correspondence and other works. One of his
great merits was, that he saw the peculiar importance of the flower
and fruit as affording the characters by which the affinities of
plants were to be detected; and that he urged this view upon his
contemporaries. His plates present to us, by the side of each plant,
its flower and its fruit, carefully engraved. And in his
communications with his botanical correspondents, he repeatedly
insists on these parts. Thus39 in 1565 he
writes to Zuinger concerning some foreign plants which the latter
possessed: “Tell me if your plants have fruit and flower, as well as
stalk and leaves, for those are of much the greater consequence. By
these three marks,—flower, fruit, and seed,—I find that
Saxifraga and Consolida Regalis are related to Aconite.” These
characters, derived from the fructification (as the assemblage
of flower and fruit is called), are the means by which genera are
established, and hence, by the best botanists, Gessner is declared to
be the inventor of genera.40
39 Epistolæ, fol. 113 a; see
also fol. 65 b.
40 Haller, Biblio Botanica, i.
284. Methodi Botanicæ rationem primus pervidit;—dari nempe et
genera quæ plures species comprehenderent et classes quæ multa genera.
Varias etiam classes naturales expressit. Characterem in flore inque
semine posuit, &c.—Rauwolfio Socio Epist. Wolf, p.
39.
 Linnæus, Genera Plantarum, Pref. xiii. “A fructificatione
plantas distinguere in genera, infinitæ sapientiæ placuisse, detexit
posterior ætas, et quidem primus, sæculi sui ornamentum, Conradus
Gessnerus, uti patet ex Epistolis ejus postremis, et Tabulis per
Carmerarium editis.”
 Cuvier says (Hist. des Sc. Nat. 2e
pe, p. 193), after speaking to the same effect, “Il fit
voir encore que toutes les plantes qui ont des fleurs et des fruits
semblables se ressemblent par leurs propriétés, et que quand on
rapproche ces plantes on obtient ainsi une classification naturelle.”
I do not know if he here refers to any particular passages of
Gessner’s work.
373 The labors
of Gessner in botany, both on account of the unfinished state in which
he left the application of his principles, and on account of the
absence of any principles manifestly applicable to the whole extent of
the vegetable kingdom, can only be considered as a prelude to the
epoch in which those defects were supplied. To that epoch we now
proceed.
Sect. 2.—Epoch of
Cæsalpinus.—Formation of a System of Arrangement.
If any one were disposed to
question whether Natural History truly belongs to the domain of
Inductive Science;—whether it is to be prosecuted by the same
methods, and requires the same endowments of mind as those which lead
to the successful cultivation of the Physical Sciences,—the
circumstances under which Botany has made its advance appear fitted to
remove such doubts. The first decided step in this study was merely
the construction of a classification of its subjects. We shall, I
trust, be able to show that such a classification includes, in
reality, the establishment of one general principle, and leads to
more. But without here dwelling on this point, it is worth notice that
the person to whom we owe this classification, Andreas Cæsalpinus of
Arezzo, was one of the most philosophical men of his time, profoundly
skilled in the Aristotelian lore which was then esteemed, yet gifted
with courage and sagacity which enabled him to weigh the value of the
Peripatetic doctrines, to reject what seemed error, and to look
onwards to a better philosophy. “How are we to understand,” he
inquires, “that we must proceed from universals to particulars (as
Aristotle directs), when particulars are better known?”41 Yet he treats the Master with
deference, and, as has been observed,42 we see in his
great botanical work deep traces of the best features of the
Aristotelian school, logic and method; and, indeed, in this work he
frequently refers to his Quæstiones Peripateticæ. His book,
entitled De Plantis libri xvi. appeared at Florence in 1583.
The aspect under which his task presented itself to his mind appears
to me to possess so much interest, that I will transcribe a few of his
reflections. After speaking of the splendid multiplicity of the
productions of nature, and the confusion which has hitherto prevailed
among writers on plants, 374 the growing treasures of the botanical
world; he adds,43 “In this immense multitude of plants, I
see that want which is most felt in any other unordered crowd: if such
an assemblage be not arranged into brigades like an army, all must be
tumult and fluctuation. And this accordingly happens in the treatment
of plants: for the mind is overwhelmed by the confused accumulation of
things, and thus arise endless mistake and angry altercation.” He then
states his general view, which, as we shall see, was adopted by his
successors. “Since all science consists in the collection of
similar, and the distinction of dissimilar things, and since the
consequence of this is a distribution into genera and species, which
are to be natural classes governed by real differences, I have
attempted to execute this task in the whole range of plants;—ut
si quid pro ingenii mei tenuitate in hujusmodi studio profecerim, ad
communem utilitatem proferam.” We see here how clearly he claims for
himself the credit of being the first to execute this task of
arrangement.
41 Quæstiones Peripateticæ,
(1569,) lib. i. quæst. i.
42 Cuvier, p. 198.
43 Dedicatio, a 2.
After certain preparatory speculations, he says,44 “Let us now endeavor to mark the kinds
of plants by essential circumstances in the fructification.” He then
observes, “In the constitution of organs three things are mainly
important—the number, the position, the figure.” And he then
proceeds to exemplify this: “Some have under one flower, one seed, as Amygdala, or one seed-receptacle, as Rosa; or two seeds, as Ferularia, or two seed-receptacles, as Nasturtium;
or three, as the Tithymalum kind have three seeds, the Bulbaceæ three receptacles; or four, as
Marrubium, four seeds,
Siler four receptacles; or more,
as Cicoraceæ, and Acanaceæ have more seeds, Pinus, more receptacles.”
44 Lib. i. c. 13, 14.
It will be observed that we have here ten classes made out by means
of number alone, added to the consideration of whether the seed is
alone in its covering, as in a cherry, or contained in a receptacle
with several others, as in a berry, pod, or capsule. Several of these
divisions are, however, further subdivided according to other
circumstances, and especially according as the vital part of the seed,
which he called the heart (cor45), is situated
in the upper or lower part of the seed. As our object here is only to
indicate the principle of the method of Cæsalpinus, I need not further
dwell on the details, and still less on the defects by which it is
disfigured, as, for instance, the retention of the old distinction of
Trees, Shrubs, and Herbs.
45 Corculum, of Linnæus.
375 To some
persons it may appear that this arbitrary distribution of the
vegetable kingdom, according to the number of parts of a particular
kind, cannot deserve to be spoken of as a great discovery. And if,
indeed, the distribution had been arbitrary, this would have been
true; the real merit of this and of every other system is, that while
it is artificial in its form, it is natural in its results. The plants
which are associated by the arrangement of Cæsalpinus, are those which
have the closest resemblances in the most essential points. Thus, as
Linnæus says, though the first in attempting to form natural orders,
he observed as many as the most successful of later writers. Thus his
Legumina46 correspond to the natural order
Leguminosæ; his genus Ferulaceum47 to the
Umbellatæ; his Bulbaceæ48 to
Liliaceæ; his Anthemides49 to the
Compositæ; in like manner, the Boragineæ are brought
together,50 and the Labiatæ. That such
assemblages are produced by the application of his principles, is a
sufficient evidence that they have their foundation in the general
laws of the vegetable world. If this had not been the case, the mere
application of number or figure alone as a standard of arrangement,
would have produced only intolerable anomalies. If, for instance,
Cæsalpinus had arranged plants by the number of flowers on the same
stalk, he would have separated individuals of the same species; if he
had distributed them according to the number of leaflets which compose
the leaves, he would have had to place far asunder different species
of the same genus. Or, as he himself says,51 “If we make one
genus of those which have a round root, as Rapum, Aristolochia,
Cyclaminus, Aton, we shall separate from this genus those which most
agree with it, as Napum and Raphanum, which resemble Rapum, and the
long Aristolochia, which resembles the round; while we shall join the
most remote kinds, for the nature of Cyclaminus and Rapum is
altogether diverse in all other respects. Or if we attend to the
differences of stalk, so as to make one genus of those which have a
naked stalk, as the Junci, Cæpe, Aphacæ, along with Cicoraceæ, Violæ,
we shall still connect the most unlike things, and disjoin the closest
affinities. And if we note the differences of leaves, or even flowers,
we fall into the same difficulty; for many plants very different in
kind have leaves very similar, as Polygonum and Hypericum, Ernea and
Sesamois, Apium and Ranunculus; and plants of the same genus have
sometimes very different 376 leaves, as the several species of
Ranunculus and of Lactuca. Nor will color or shape of the flowers help
us better; for what has Vitis in common with Œnanthe, except the
resemblance of the flower?” He then goes on to say, that if we seek a
too close coincidence of all the characters we shall have no Species;
and thus shows us that he had clearly before his view the difficulty,
which he had to attack, and which it is his glory to have overcome,
that of constructing Natural Orders.
46 Lib. vi.
47 Lib. vii.
48 Lib. x.
49 Lib. xii.
50 Lib. xi.
51 Lib. i. cap. xii. p. 25.
But as the principles of Cæsalpinus are justified, on the one hand,
by their leading to Natural Orders, they are recommended on the
other by their producing a System which applies through the
whole extent of the vegetable kingdom. The parts from which he takes
his characters must occur in all flowering-plants, for all such plants
have seeds. And these seeds, if not very numerous for each flower,
will be of a certain definite number and orderly distribution. And
thus every plant will fall into one part or other of the same
system.
It is not difficult to point out, in this induction of Cæsalpinus,
the two elements which we have so often declared must occur in all
inductive processes; the exact acquaintance with facts, and
the general and applicable ideas by which these facts are
brought together. Cæsalpinus was no mere dealer in intellectual
relations or learned traditions, but a laborious and persevering
collector of plants and of botanical knowledge. “For many years,” he
says in his Dedication, “I have been pursuing my researches in various
regions, habitually visiting the places in which grew the various
kinds of herbs, shrubs, and trees; I have been assisted by the labors
of many friends, and by gardens established for the public benefit,
and containing foreign plants collected from the most remote regions.”
He here refers to the first garden directed to the public study of
Botany, which was that of Pisa,52 instituted in
1543, by order of the Grand Duke Cosmo the First. The management of it
was confided first to Lucas Ghini, and afterwards to Cæsalpinus. He
had collected also a herbarium of dried plants, which he calls the
rudiment of his work. “Tibi enim,” he says, in his dedication to
Francis Medici, Grand Duke of Etruria, “apud quem extat ejus
rudimentum ex plantis libro agglutinatis a me compositum.” And,
throughout, he speaks with the most familiar and vivid acquaintance of
the various vegetables which he describes.
52 Cuv. 187.
But Cæsalpinus also possessed fixed and general views concerning
the relation and functions of the parts of plants, and ideas of
symmetry 377 and
system; without which, as we see in other botanists of his and
succeeding times, the mere accumulation of a knowledge of details does
not lead to any advance in science. We have already mentioned his
reference to general philosophical principles, both of the
Peripatetics and of his own. The first twelve chapters of his work are
employed in explaining the general structure of plants, and especially
that point to which he justly attaches so much importance, the results
of the different situation of the cor or corculum of the
seed. He shows53 that if we take the root, or stem, or
leaves, or blossom, as our guide in classification, we shall separate
plants obviously alike, and approximate those which have merely
superficial resemblances. And thus we see that he had in his mind
ideas of fixed resemblance and symmetrical distribution, which he
sedulously endeavored to apply to plants; while his acquaintance with
the vegetable kingdom enabled him to see in what manner these ideas
were not, and in what manner they were, really applicable.
53 Lib. i. cap. xii.
The great merit and originality of Cæsalpinus have been generally
allowed, by the best of the more modern writers on Botany. Linnæus
calls him one of the founders of the science; “Primus verus
systematicus;”54 and, as if not satisfied with the
expression of his admiration in prose, hangs a poetical garland on the
tomb of his hero. The following distich concludes his remarks on this
writer:

Quisquis hic extiterit primos concedet
honores
Cæsalpine tibi; primaque serta dabit:

and similar language of praise has been applied to
him by the best botanists up to Cuvier,55 who justly
terms his book “a work of genius.”
54 Philosoph. Bot. p.
19.
55 Cuv. Hist. 193.
Perhaps the great advance made in this science by Cæsalpinus, is
most strongly shown by this; that no one appeared, to follow the path
which he had opened to system and symmetry, for nearly a century.
Moreover, when the progress of this branch of knowledge was resumed,
his next successor, Morison, did not choose to acknowledge that he had
borrowed so much from so old a writer; and thus, hardly mentions his
name, although he takes advantage of his labors, and even transcribes
his words without acknowledgement, as I shall show. The pause between
the great invention of Cæsalpinus, and its natural sequel, the
developement and improvement of his method, is so marked, that I 378 will, in order to
avoid too great an interruption of chronological order, record some of
its circumstances in a separate section.
Sect. 3.—Stationary Interval.
The method of Cæsalpinus was
not, at first, generally adopted. It had, indeed, some disadvantages.
Employed in drawing the boundary-lines of the larger divisions of the
vegetable kingdom, he had omitted those smaller groups, Genera, which
were both most obvious to common botanists, and most convenient in the
description and comparison of plants. He had also neglected to give
the Synonyms of other authors for the plants spoken of by him; an
appendage to botanical descriptions, which the increase of botanical
information and botanical books had now rendered indispensable. And
thus it happened, that a work, which must always be considered as
forming a great epoch in the science to which it refers, was probably
little read, and in a short time could be treated as if it were quite
forgotten.
In the mean time, the science was gradually improved in its
details. Clusius, or Charles de l’Ecluse, first taught botanists to
describe well. “Before him,” says Mirbel,56 “the
descriptions were diffuse, obscure, indistinct; or else concise,
incomplete, vague. Clusius introduced exactitude, precision, neatness,
elegance, method: he says nothing superfluous; he omits nothing
necessary.” He travelled over great part of Europe, and published
various works on the more rare of the plants which he had seen. Among
such plants, we may note now one well known, the potato; which he
describes as being commonly used in Italy in 1586;57 thus throwing doubt, at least, on the
opinion which ascribes the first introduction of it into Europe to Sir
Walter Raleigh, on his return from Virginia, about the same period. As
serving to illustrate, both this point, and the descriptive style of
Clusius, I quote, in a note, his description of the flower of this
plant.58
56 Physiol. Veg. p. 525.
57 Clusius. Exotic. iv. c. 52,
p. lxxix.
58 “Papas Peruanorum. Arachidna,
Theoph. forte. Flores elegantes, uncialis amplitudinis aut majores,
angulosi, singulari folio constantes, sed ita complicato ut quinque
folia discreta videantur, coloris exterius ex purpura candicantis,
interius purpurascentis, radiis quinque herbaceis ex umbilico stellæ
instar prodeuntibus, et totidem staminibus flavis in umbonem
coeuntibus.”
 He says that the Italians do not know whence they had the plant,
and that they call it Taratouffli. The name Potato was,
in England, previously applied to the Sweet Potato (Convolvulus
batatas), which was the common Potato, in distinction to
the Virginian Potato, at the time of Gerard’s Herbal. (1597?)
Gerard’s figures of both plants are copied from those of Clusius.
 It may be seen by the description of Arachidna, already quoted
from Theophrastus, (above,) that there is
little plausibility in Clusius’s conjecture of the plant being known
to the ancients. I need not inform the botanist that this opinion is
untenable.
379 The addition
of exotic species to the number of known plants was indeed going on
rapidly during the interval which we are now considering. Francis
Hernandez, a Spaniard, who visited America towards the end of the
sixteenth century, collected and described many plants of that
country, some of which were afterwards published by Recchi.59 Barnabas Cobo, who went as a missionary
to America in 1596, also described plants.60 The Dutch,
among other exertions which they made in their struggle with the
tyranny of Spain, sent out an expedition which, for a time, conquered
the Brazils; and among other fruits of this conquest, they published
an account of the natural history of the country.61 To avoid
interrupting the connexion of such labors, I will here carry them on a
little further in the order of time. Paul Herman, of Halle, in Saxony,
went to the Cape of Good Hope and to Ceylon; and on his return,
astonished the botanists of Europe by the vast quantity of remarkable
plants which he introduced to their knowledge.62 Rheede, the
Dutch governor of Malabar, ordered descriptions and drawings to be
made of many curious species, which were published in a large work in
twelve folio volumes.63 Rumphe, another Dutch consul at
Amboyna,64 labored with zeal and success upon the
plants of the Moluccas. Some species which occur in Madagascar figured
in a description of that island composed by the French Commandant
Flacourt.65 Shortly afterwards, Engelbert
Kæmpfer,66 a Westphalian of great acquirements and
undaunted courage, visited Persia, Arabia Felix, the Mogul Empire,
Ceylon, Bengal, Sumatra, Java, Siam, Japan; Wheler travelled in Greece
and Asia Minor; and Sherard, the English consul, published an account
of the plants of the neighborhood of Smyrna.
59 Nova Plantarum Regni Mexicana
Historia, Rom. 1651, fol.
60 Sprengel, Gesch. der
Botanik, ii. 62.
61 Historia Naturalis
Brasiliæ, L. B. 1648, fol. (Piso and Maregraf).
62 Museum Zeylanicum, L. B.
1726.
63 Hortus Malabaricus,
1670–1703.
64 Herbarium Amboinense,
Amsterdam, 1741–51, fol.
65 Histoire de la grande Isle
Madagascar, Paris, 1661.
66 Amœnitates Exoticæ, Lemgov.
1712. 4to.
380 At the same
time, the New World excited also the curiosity of botanists. Hans
Sloane collected the plants of Jamaica; John Banister those of
Virginia; William Vernon, also an Englishman, and David Kriege, a
Saxon, those of Maryland; two Frenchmen, Surian and Father Plumier,
those of Saint Domingo.
We may add that public botanical gardens were about this time
established all over Europe. We have already noticed the institution
of that of Pisa in 1543; the second was that of Padua in 1545; the
next, that of Florence in 1556; the fourth, that of Bologna, 1568;
that of Rome, in the Vatican, dates also from 1568.
The first transalpine garden of this kind arose at Leyden in 1577;
that of Leipzig in 1580. Henry the Fourth of France established one at
Montpellier in 1597. Several others were instituted in Germany; but
that of Paris did not begin to exist till 1626; that of Upsal,
afterwards so celebrated, took its rise in 1657, that of Amsterdam in
1684. Morison, whom we shall soon have to mention, calls himself, in
1680, the first Director of the Botanical Garden at Oxford.
[2nd Ed.] [To what is above said of Botanical Gardens and Botanical
Writers, between the times of Cæsalpinus and Morison, I may add a few
circumstances. The first academical garden in France was that at
Montpellier, which was established by Peter Richier de Belleval, at
the end of the sixteenth century. About the same period, rare flowers
were cultivated at Paris, and pictures of them made, in order to
supply the embroiderers of the court-robes with new patterns. Thus
figures of the most beautiful flowers in the garden of Peter Robins
were published by the court-embroiderer Peter Vallet, in 1608, under
the title of Le Jardin du Roi Henry IV. But Robins’ works were
of great service to botany; and his garden assisted the studies of
Renealmus (Paul Reneaulme), whose Specimen Historiæ Plantarum
(Paris, 1611), is highly spoken of by the best botanists. Recently,
Mr. Robert Brown has named after him a new genus of Irideæ
(Renealmia); adding, “Dixi in memoriam Pauli Renealmi, botanici sui ævi accuratissimi,
atque staminum primi scrutatoris; qui non modo eorum numerum et situm,
sed etiam filamentorum proportionem passim descripsit, et characterem
tetradynamicum siliquosarum perspexit.” (Prodromus Floræ Novæ
Hollandiæ, p. 448.)
The oldest Botanical Garden in England is that at Hampton Court,
founded by Queen Elizabeth, and much enriched by Charles II. and
William III. (Sprengel, Gesch. d. Bot. vol. ii. p. 96.)]
In the mean time, although there appeared no new system which 381 commanded the
attention of the botanical world, the feeling of the importance of the
affinities of plants became continually more strong and distinct.
Lobel, who was botanist to James the First, and who published his
Stirpium Adversaria Nova in 1571, brings together the natural
families of plants more distinctly than his predecessors, and even
distinguishes (as Cuvier states,67)
monocotyledonous from dicotyledonous plants; one of the most
comprehensive division-lines of botany, of which succeeding times
discovered the value more completely. Fabius Columna,68 in 1616, gave figures of the
fructification of plants on copper, as Gessner had before done on
wood. But the elder Bauhin (John), notwithstanding all that Cæsalpinus
had done, retrograded, in a work published in 1619, into the less
precise and scientific distinctions of—trees with nuts; with
berries; with acorns; with pods; creeping plants, gourds, &c.: and
no clear progress towards a system was anywhere visible among the
authors of this period.
67 Cuv. Leçons, &c.
198.
68 Ib. 206.
While this continued to be the case, and while the materials, thus
destitute of order, went on accumulating, it was inevitable that the
evils which Cæsalpinus had endeavored to remedy, should become more
and more grievous. “The nomenclature of the subject69 was in such disorder, it was so
impossible to determine with certainty the plants spoken of by
preceding writers, that thirty or forty different botanists had given
to the same plant almost as many different names. Bauhin called by one
appellation, a species which Lobel or Matheoli designated by another.
There was an actual chaos, a universal confusion, in which it was
impossible for men to find their way.” We can the better understand
such a state of things, from having, in our own time, seen another
classificatory science, Mineralogy, in the very condition thus
described. For such a state of confusion there is no remedy but the
establishment of a true system of classification; which by its real
foundation renders a reason for the place of each species; and which,
by the fixity of its classes, affords a basis for a standard
nomenclature, as finally took place in Botany. But before such a
remedy is obtained, men naturally try to alleviate the evil by
tabulating the synonyms of different writers, as far as they are able
to do so. The task of constructing such a Synonymy of botany at
the period of which we speak, was undertaken by Gaspard Bauhin, the
brother of John, but nineteen years younger. This work, the Pinax
Theatri Botanici, was printed 382 at Basil in 1623. It was a useful
undertaking at the time; but the want of any genuine order in the
Pinax itself, rendered it impossible that it should be of great
permanent utility.
69 Ib. 212.
After this period, the progress of almost all the sciences became
languid for a while; and one reason of this interruption was, the wars
and troubles which prevailed over almost the whole of Europe. The
quarrels of Charles the First and his parliament, the civil wars and
the usurpation, in England; in France, the war of the League, the
stormy reign of Henry the Fourth, the civil wars of the minority of
Louis the Thirteenth, the war against the Protestants and the war of
the Fronde in the minority of Louis the Fourteenth; the bloody and
destructive Thirty Years’ War in Germany; the war of Spain with the
United Provinces and with Portugal;—all these dire agitations
left men neither leisure nor disposition to direct their best thoughts
to the promotion of science. The baser spirits were brutalized; the
better were occupied by high practical aims and struggles of their
moral nature. Amid such storms, the intellectual powers of man could
not work with their due calmness, nor his intellectual objects shine
with their proper lustre.
At length a period of greater tranquillity gleamed forth, and the
sciences soon expanded in the sunshine. Botany was not inert amid this
activity, and rapidly advanced in a new direction, that of physiology;
but before we speak of this portion of our subject, we must complete
what we have to say of it as a classificatory science.
Sect. 4.—Sequel to the Epoch of Cæsalpinus.
Further Formation and Adoption of Systematic Arrangement.
Soon after the period of
which we now speak, that of the restoration of the Stuarts to the
throne of England, systematic arrangements of plants appeared in great
numbers; and in a manner such as to show that the minds of botanists
had gradually been ripening for this improvement, through the
influence of preceding writers, and the growing acquaintance with
plants. The person whose name is usually placed first on this list,
Robert Morison, appears to me to be much less meritorious than many of
those who published very shortly after him; but I will give him the
precedence in my narrative. He was a Scotchman, who was wounded
fighting on the royalist side in the civil wars of England. On the
triumph of the republicans, he withdrew to France, when he became
director of the garden of Gaston, Duke of Orléans at Blois; and there
he came under the notice of our Charles 383 the Second; who, on his restoration,
summoned Morison to England, where he became Superintendent of the
Royal Gardens, and also of the Botanic Garden at Oxford. In 1669, he
published Remarks on the Mistakes of the two Bauhins, in which
he proves that many plants in the Pinax are erroneously placed,
and shows considerable talent for appreciating natural families and
genera. His great systematic work appeared from the University press
at Oxford in 1680. It contains a system, but a system, Cuvier says,70 which approaches rather to a natural
method than to a rigorous distribution, like that of his predecessor
Cæsalpinus, or that of his successor Ray. Thus the herbaceous plants
are divided into climbers, leguminous, siliquose,
unicapsalar, bicapsular, tricapsular,
quadricapsular, quinquecapsular; this division being
combined with characters derived from the number of petals. But along
with these numerical elements, are introduced others of a loose and
heterogeneous kind, for instance, the classification of herbs as
lactescent and emollient. It is not unreasonable to say,
that such a scheme shows no talent for constructing a complete system;
and that the most distinct part of it, that dependent on the fruit,
was probably borrowed from Cæsalpinus. That this is so, we have, I
think, strong proof; for though Morison nowhere, I believe, mentions
Cæsalpinus, except in one place in a loose enumeration of botanical
writers,71 he must have made considerable use of
his work. For he has introduced into his own preface a passage copied
literally72 from the dedication of Cæsalpinus;
which passage we have already quoted (p.
374,) beginning, “Since all science consists in the collection of
similar, and the distinction of dissimilar things.” And that the
mention of the original is not omitted by accident, appears from this;
that Morison appropriates also the conclusion of the passage, which
has a personal reference, “Conatus sum id præstare in universa
plantarum historia, ut si quid pro ingenii mei tenuitate in hujusmodi
studio profecerim, ad communem utilitatem proferrem.” That
Morison, thus, at so long an interval after the publication of the
work of Cæsalpinus, borrowed from him without acknowledgement, and
adopted his system so as to mutilate it, proves that he had neither
the temper nor the talent of a discoverer; and justifies us
withholding from him the credit which belongs to those, who, in his
time, resumed the great undertaking of constructing a vegetable
system.
70 Cuv. Leçons, &c. p.
486.
71 Pref. p. i.
72 Ib. p. ii.
Among those whose efforts in this way had the greatest and earliest
384 influence, was
undoubtedly our countryman, John Ray, who was Fellow of Trinity
College, Cambridge, at the same time with Isaac Newton. But though
Cuvier states73 that Ray was the model of the
systematists during the whole of the eighteenth century, the Germans
claim a part of his merit for one of their countrymen, Joachim Jung,
of Lubeck, professor at Hamburg.74 Concerning the
principles of this botanist, little was known during his life. But a
manuscript of his book was communicated75 to Ray in 1660,
and from this time forwards, says Sprengel, there might be noticed in
the writings of Englishmen, those better and clearer views to which
Jung’s principles gave birth. Five years after the death of Jung, his
Doxoscopia Physica was published, in 1662; and in 1678, his
Isagoge Phytoscopica. But neither of these works was ever much
read; and even Linnæus, whom few things escaped which concerned
botany, had, in 1771, seen none of Jung’s works.
73 Leçons Hist. Sc. p.
487.
74 Sprengel, ii. 27.
75 Ray acknowledges this in his
Index Plant. Agri Cantab. p. 87, and quotes from it the
definition of caulis.
I here pass over Jung’s improvements of botanical language, and
speak only of those which he is asserted to have suggested in the
arrangement of plants. He examines, says Sprengel,76 the value of characters of species,
which, he holds, must not be taken from the thorns, nor from color,
taste, smell, medicinal effects, time and place of blossoming. He
shows, in numerous examples, what plants must be separated, though
called by a common name, and what most be united, though their names
are several.
76 Sprengel, ii. 29.
I do not see in this much that interferes with the originality of
Ray’s method,77 of which, in consequence of the
importance ascribed to it by Cuvier, as we have already seen, I shall
give an account, following that great naturalist.78 I confine
myself to the ordinary plants, and omit the more obscure vegetables,
as mushrooms, mosses, ferns, and the like.
77 Methodus Plantarum Nova,
1682. Historia Plantarum, 1686.
78 Cuv.  Leçons Hist. Sc.
488.
Such plants are composite or simple. The
composite flowers are those which contain many florets in the
same calyx.79 These are subdivided according as they
are composed altogether of complete florets, 385 or of half florets, or of a centre of
complete florets, surrounded by a circumference or ray of
demi-florets. Such are the divisions of the corymbiferæ, or
compositæ.
79 Involucrum, in modern
terminology.
In the simple flowers, the seeds are naked, or in a
pericarp. Those with naked seeds are arranged according
to the number of the seeds, which may be one, two, three, four, or
more. If there is only one, no subdivision is requisite: if there are
two, Ray makes a subdivision, according as the flower has five petals,
or a continuous corolla. Here we come to several natural families.
Thus, the flowers with two seeds and five petals are the
Umbelliferous plants; the monopetalous flowers with two seeds
are the Stellatæ. He founds the division of four-seeded flowers
on the circumstance of the leaves being opposite, or alternate; and
thus again, we have the natural families of Asperifoliæ, as
Echium, &c., which have the leaves alternate, and the
Verticillatæ, as Salvia, in which the leaves are
opposite. When the flower has more than four seeds, he makes no
subdivision.
So much for simple flowers with naked seeds. In those where the
seeds are surrounded by a pericarp, or fruit, this fruit is
large, soft, and fleshy, and the plants are pomiferous; or it
is small and juicy, and the fruit is a berry, as a Gooseberry.
If the fruit is not juicy, but dry, it is multiple or
simple. If it be simple, we have the leguminose plants. If it
be multiple, the form of the flower is to be attended to. The flower
may be monopetalous, or tetrapetalous, or
pentapetalous, or with still more divisions. The
monopetalous may be regular or irregular; so may the
tetrapetalous. The regular tetrapetalous flowers are, for example, the
Cruciferæ, as Stock and Cauliflower; the irregular, are the
papilionaceous plants, Peas, Beans, and Vetches; and thus we
again come to natural families. The remaining plants are divided in
the same way, into those with imperfect, and those with
perfect, flowers. Those with imperfect flowers are the
Grasses, the Rushes (Junci), and the like; among
those with perfect flowers, are the Palmaceæ, and the
Liliaceæ.
We see that the division of plants is complete as a system; all
flowers must belong to one or other of the divisions. Fully to explain
the characters and further subdivisions of these families, would be to
write a treatise on botany; but it is easily seen that they exhaust
the subject as far as they go.
Thus Ray constructed his system partly on the fruit and partly on
the flower; or more properly, according to the expression of Linnæus,
386 comparing his
earlier with his later system, he began by being a fructicist,
and ended by being a corollist.80 ~Additional
material in the 3rd edition.~
80 Ray was a most industrious
herbalizer, and I cannot understand on what ground Mirbel asserts
(Physiol. Veg., tom. ii. p. 531,) that he was better acquainted
with books than with plants.
As we have said, a number of systems of arrangement of plants were
published about this time, some founded on the fruit, some on the
corolla, some on the calyx, and these employed in various ways.
Rivinus81 (whose real name was Bachman,)
classified by the flower alone; instead of combining it with the
fruit, as Ray had done.82 He had the further merit of being the
first who rejected the old division, of woody and
herbaceous plants; a division which, though at variance with
any system founded upon the structure of the plants was employed even
by Tournefort, and only finally expelled by Linnæus.
81 Cuv. Leçons, 491.
82 Historia Generalis ad rem
Herbariam, 1690.
It would throw little light upon the history of botany, especially
for our purpose, to dwell on the peculiarities of these transitory
systems. Linnæus,83 after his manner, has given a
classification of them. Rivinus, as we have just seen, was a
corollist, according to the regularity and number of the
petals; Hermann was a fructicist. Christopher Knaut84 adopted the system of Ray, but inverted
the order of its parts; Christian Knaut did nearly the same with
regard to that of Rivinus, taking number before regularity in the
flower.85
83 Philos. Bot. p. 21.
84 Enumeratio Plantarum,
&c., 1687.
85 Linn.
Of the systems which prevailed previous to that of Linnæus,
Tournefort’s was by far the most generally accepted. Joseph Pitton de
Tournefort was of a noble family in Provence, and was appointed
professor at the Jardin du Roi in 1683. His well-known travels in the
Levant are interesting on other subjects, as well as botany. His
Institutio Rei Herbariæ, published in 1700, contains his
method, which is that of a corollist. He is guided by the
regularity or irregularity of the flowers, by their form, and by the
situation of the receptacle of the seeds below the calyx, or within
it. Thus his classes are—those in which the flowers are
campaniform, or bell-shaped; those in which they are
infundibuliform, or funnel-shaped, as Tobacco; then the
irregular flowers, as the Personatæ, which resemble an ancient
mask; the Labiatæ, with their two lips; the Cruciform;
the Rosaceæ, with flowers like a rose; the Umbelliferæ;
the Caryophylleæ, as the 387 Pink; the Liliaceæ, with six
petals, as the Tulip, Narcissus, Hyacinth, Lily; the
Papilionaceæ, which are leguminous plants, the flower of which
resembles a butterfly, as Peas and Beans; and finally, the
Anomalous, as Violet, Nasturtium, and others.
Though this system was found to be attractive, as depending, in an
evident way, on the most conspicuous part of the plant, the flower, it
is easy to see that it was much less definite than systems like that
of Rivinus, Hermann, and Ray, which were governed by number. But
Tournefort succeeded in giving to the characters of genera a degree of
rigor never before attained, and abstracted them in a separate form.
We have already seen that the reception of botanical Systems has
depended much on their arrangement into Genera.
Tournefort’s success was also much promoted by the author inserting
in his work a figure of a flower and fruit belonging to each genus;
and the figures, drawn by Aubriet, were of great merit. The study of
botany was thus rendered easy, for it could be learned by turning over
the leaves of a book. In spite of various defects, these advantages
gave this writer an ascendancy which lasted, from 1700, when his book
appeared, for more than half a century. For though Linnæus began to
publish in 1735, his method and his nomenclature were not generally
adopted till 1760.
</div></body></text></TEI>