<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="7">CHAPTER VII.
FARTHER EXAMINATION OF THE QUESTION AS TO THE ASSUMED DISCORDANCE
OF THE ANCIENT AND MODERN CAUSES OF CHANGE.
On the causes of vicissitudes in climate—Remarks on the present diffusion of heat
over the globe—On the dependence of the mean temperature on the relative
position of land and sea—Isothermal Lines—Currents from equatorial regions—Drifting
of icebergs—Different temperature of Northern and Southern hemispheres—Combination
of causes which might produce the extreme cold of which
the earth's surface is susceptible—Conditions necessary for the production of
the extreme of heat, and its probable effects on organic life.
Causes of Vicissitudes in Climate.165—As the proofs enumerated in the
last chapter indicate that the earth's surface has experienced great changes
of climate since the deposition of the older sedimentary strata, we have
next to inquire how such vicissitudes can be reconciled with the existing
order of nature. The cosmogonist has availed himself of this, as of every
obscure problem in geology, to confirm his views concerning a period
when the planet was in a nascent or half-formed state, or when the laws
of the animate and inanimate world differed essentially from those now
established; and he has in this, as in many other cases, succeeded so far,
as to divert attention from that class of facts which, if fully understood,
might probably lead to an explanation of the phenomena. At first it was
imagined that the earth's axis had been for ages perpendicular to the
plane of the ecliptic, so that there was a perpetual equinox, and uniformity
of seasons throughout the year;—that the planet enjoyed this
"paradisiacal" state until the era of the great flood; but in that catastrophe,
whether by the shock of a comet, or some other convulsion, it
lost its equal poise, and hence the obliquity of its axis, and with that the
varied seasons of the temperate zone, and the long nights and days of
the polar circles.
When the progress of astronomical science had exploded this theory,
it was assumed, that the earth at its creation was in a state of fluidity,
and red-hot, and that ever since that era, it had been cooling down, contracting
its dimensions, and acquiring a solid crust,—an hypothesis hardly
less arbitrary, yet more calculated for lasting popularity; because, by referring
the mind directly to the beginning of things, it requires no support
from observation, nor from any ulterior hypothesis. But if, instead
93of forming vague conjectures as to what might have been the state of
the planet at the era of its creation, we fix our thoughts on the connection
at present existing between climate and the distribution of land and sea;
and then consider what influence former fluctuations in the physical
geography of the earth must have had on superficial temperature, we may
perhaps approximate to a true theory. If doubts and obscurities still
remain, they should be ascribed to our limited acquaintance with the
laws of Nature, not to revolutions in her economy;—they should stimulate
us to farther research, not tempt us to indulge our fancies respecting
the imaginary changes of internal temperature in an embryo world.
Diffusion of Heat over the Globe.—In considering the laws which regulate
the diffusion of heat over the globe, we must be careful, as Humboldt
well remarks, not to regard the climate of Europe as a type of the
temperature which all countries placed under the same latitude enjoy.
The physical sciences, observes this philosopher, always bear the impress
of the places where they began to be cultivated; and as, in geology, an
attempt was at first made to refer all the volcanic phenomena to those
of the volcanoes in Italy, so in meteorology, a small part of the old world,
the centre of the primitive civilization of Europe, was for a long time
considered a type to which the climate of all corresponding latitudes
might be referred. But this region, constituting only one-seventh of the
whole globe, proved eventually to be the exception to the general rule.
For the same reason, we may warn the geologist to be on his guard, and
not hastily to assume that the temperature of the earth in the present
era is a type of that which most usually obtains, since he contemplates
far mightier alterations in the position of land and sea, at different epochs,
than those which now cause the climate of Europe to differ from that of
other countries in the same parallels.
It is now well ascertained that zones of equal warmth, both in the
atmosphere and in the waters of the ocean, are neither parallel to the
equator nor to each other.166 It is also known that the mean annual
temperature may be the same in two places which enjoy very different
climates, for the seasons may be nearly uniform, or violently contrasted,
so that the lines of equal winter temperature do not coincide with those
of equal annual heat or isothermal lines. The deviations of all these
lines from the same parallel of latitude are determined by a multitude
of circumstances, among the principal of which are the position, direc94tion,
and elevation of the continents and islands, the position and depths
of the sea, and the direction of currents and of winds.
On comparing the two continents of Europe and America, it is found
that places in the same latitudes have sometimes a mean difference of
temperature amounting to 11°, or even in a few cases to 17° Fahr.; and
some places on the two continents, which have the same mean temperature,
differ from 7° to 17° in latitude. Thus, Cumberland House, in
North America, having the same latitude (54° N.) as the city of York
in England, stands on the isothermal line of 32°, which in Europe rises
to the North Cape, in lat. 71°, but its summer heat exceeds that of
Brussels or Paris.167 The principal cause of greater intensity of cold in
corresponding latitudes of North America, as contrasted with Europe,
is the connection of America with the polar circle, by a large tract of
land, some of which is from three to five thousand feet in height; and,
on the other hand, the separation of Europe from the arctic circle by an
ocean. The ocean has a tendency to preserve everywhere a mean temperature,
which it communicates to the contiguous land, so that it tempers
the climate, moderating alike an excess of heat or cold. The elevated
land, on the other hand, rising to the colder regions of the atmosphere,
becomes a great reservoir of ice and snow, arrests, condenses,
and congeals vapor, and communicates its cold to the adjoining country.
For this reason, Greenland, forming part of a continent which stretches
northward to the 82d degree of latitude, experiences under the 60th
parallel a more rigorous climate than Lapland under the 72d parallel.
But if land be situated between the 40th parallel and the equator, it
produces, unless it be of extreme height, exactly the opposite effect;
for it then warms the tracts of land or sea that intervene between it and
the polar circle. For the surface being in this case exposed to the vertical,
or nearly vertical rays of the sun, absorbs a large quantity of heat,
which it diffuses by radiation into the atmosphere. For this reason, the
western parts of the old continent derive warmth from Africa, "which,
like an immense furnace, distributes its heat to Arabia, to Turkey in
Asia, and to Europe."168 On the contrary, the northeastern extremity
of Asia experiences in the same latitude extreme cold; for it has land
on the north between the 60th and 70th parallel, while to the south it
is separated from the equator by the Pacific Ocean.
In consequence of the more equal temperature of the waters of the
ocean, the climate of islands and of coasts differs essentially from that
of the interior of continents, the more maritime climate being characterized
by mild winters, and more temperate summers; for the sea-breezes
moderate the cold of winter, as well as the heat of summer. When,
therefore, we trace round the globe those belts in which the mean annual
temperature is the same, we often find great differences in climate; for
there are insular climates in which the seasons are nearly equalized, and
95excessive climates, as they have been termed, where the temperature of
winter and summer is strongly contrasted. The whole of Europe, compared
with the eastern parts of America and Asia, has an insular climate.
The northern part of China, and the Atlantic region of the United States,
exhibit "excessive climates." We find at New York, says Humboldt,
the summer of Rome and the winter of Copenhagen; at Quebec, the
summer of Paris and the winter of Petersburg. At Pekin, in China,
where the mean temperature of the year is that of the coasts of Brittany,
the scorching heats of summer are greater than at Cairo, and the winters
as rigorous as at Upsala.169
If lines be drawn round the globe through all those places which
have the same winter temperature, they are found to deviate from the
terrestrial parallels much farther than the lines of equal mean annual
heat. The lines of equal winter in Europe, for example, are often
curved so as to reach parallels of latitude 9° or 10° distant from each
other, whereas the isothermal lines, or those passing through places
having the same mean annual temperature, differ only from 4° to 5°
in Europe.
Influence of currents and drift ice on temperature.—Among other influential
causes, both of remarkable diversity in the mean annual heat,
and of unequal division of heat in the different seasons, are the direction
of currents and the accumulation and drifting of ice in high latitudes.
The temperature of the Lagullas current is 10° or 12° Fahr.
above that of the sea at the Cape of Good Hope; for it derives the
greater part of its waters from the Mozambique channel, and southeast
coast of Africa, and from regions in the Indian Ocean much nearer
the line, and much hotter than the Cape.170 An opposite effect is produced
by the "equatorial" current, which crosses the Atlantic from
Africa to Brazil, having a breadth varying from 160 to 450 nautical
miles. Its waters are cooler by 3° or 4° Fahr. than those of the ocean
under the line, so that it moderates the heat of the tropics.171
But the effects of the Gulf stream on the climate of the North Atlantic
Ocean are far more remarkable. This most powerful of known
currents has its source in the Gulf or Sea of Mexico, which, like the
Mediterranean and other close seas in temperate or low latitudes, is
warmer than the open ocean in the same parallels. The temperature
of the Mexican sea in summer is, according to Rennell, 86° Fahr., or at
least 7° above that of the Atlantic in the same latitude.172 From this
great reservoir or caldron of warm water, a constant current pours
forth through the straits of Bahama at the rate of 3 or 4 miles an hour;
it crosses the ocean in a northeasterly direction, skirting the great
bank of Newfoundland, where it still retains a temperature of 8° above
that of the surrounding sea. It reaches the Azores in about 78 days,
after flowing nearly 3000 geographical miles, and from thence it some96times
extends its course a thousand miles farther, so as to reach the
Bay of Biscay, still retaining an excess of 5° above the mean temperature
of that sea. As it has been known to arrive there in the months
of November and January, it may tend greatly to moderate the cold
of winter in countries on the west of Europe.
.
There is a large tract in the centre of the North Atlantic, between
the parallels of 33° and 45° N. lat., which Rennell calls the "recipient
of the gulf water." A great part of it is covered by the weed called
sargasso (Sargassum bacciferum), which the current floats in abundance
from the Gulf of Mexico. This mass of water is nearly stagnant, is
warmer by 7° or 10° than the waters of the Atlantic, and may be compared
to the fresh water of a river overflowing the heavier salt water
of the sea. Rennell estimates the area of the "recipient," together
with that covered by the main current, as being 2000 miles in length
from E. to W., and 350 in breadth from N. to S., which, he remarks,
is a larger area than that of the Mediterranean. The heat of this great
body of water is kept up by the incessant and quick arrivals of fresh
supplies of warm water from the south; and there can be no doubt
that the general climate of parts of Europe and America is materially
affected by this cause.
It is considered probable by Scoresby that the influence of the Gulf
stream extends even to the sea near Spitzbergen, where its waters may
pass under those of melted ice; for it has been found that in the neighborhood
of Spitzbergen, the water is warmer by 6° or 7° at the depth
of one hundred and two hundred fathoms than at the surface. This
might arise from the known law that fresh water passes the point of
greatest density when cooled down below 40°, and between that and
the freezing point expands again. The water of melted ice might be
lighter, both as being fresh (having lost its salt in the decomposing
process of freezing), and because its temperature is nearer the freezing
point than the inferior water of the Gulf stream.
The great glaciers generated in the valleys of Spitzbergen, in the 79°
of north latitude, are almost all cut off at the beach, being melted by
the feeble remnant of heat still retained by the Gulf stream. In
Baffin's Bay, on the contrary, on the west coast of Old Greenland,
where the temperature of the sea is not mitigated by the same cause,
and where there is no warmer under-current, the glaciers stretch out
from the shore, and furnish repeated crops of mountainous masses of
ice which float off into the ocean.173 The number and dimensions of
these bergs is prodigious. Captain Sir John Ross saw several of them
together in Baffin's Bay aground in water fifteen hundred feet deep!
Many of them are driven down into Hudson's Bay, and accumulating
there, diffuse excessive cold over the neighboring continent; so that
Captain Franklin reports, that at the mouth of Hayes' River, which
97lies in the same latitude as the north of Prussia or the south of Scotland,
ice is found everywhere in digging wells, in summer, at the depth
of four feet! Other bergs have been occasionally met with, at midsummer,
in a state of rapid thaw, as far south as lat. 40° and longitude
about 60° west, where they cool the water sensibly to the distance of
forty or fifty miles around, the thermometer sinking sometimes 17°, or
even 18°, Fahrenheit, in their neighborhood.174 It is a well-known fact
that every four or five years a large number of icebergs, floating from
Greenland, double Cape Langaness, and are stranded on the west coast
of Iceland. The inhabitants are then aware that their crops of hay
will fail, in consequence of fogs which are generated almost incessantly;
and the dearth of food is not confined to the land, for the temperature
of the water is so changed that the fish entirely desert the coast.
Difference of climate of the Northern and Southern hemispheres.—When
we compare the climate of the northern and southern hemispheres,
we obtain still more instruction in regard to the influence of the distribution
of land and sea on climate. The dry land in the southern hemisphere
is to that of the northern in the ratio only of one to three, excluding
from our consideration that part which lies between the pole and
the 78° of south latitude, which has hitherto proved inaccessible. And
whereas in the northern hemisphere, between the pole and the thirtieth
parallel of north latitude, the land and sea occupy nearly equal areas,
the ocean in the southern hemisphere covers no less than fifteen parts
in sixteen of the entire space included between the antarctic circle and
the thirtieth parallel of south latitude.
This great extent of sea gives a particular character to climates south
of the equator, the winters being mild and the summers cool. Thus, in
Van Dieman's Land, corresponding nearly in latitude to Rome, the
winters are more mild than at Naples, and the summers not warmer than
those at Paris, which is 7° farther from the equator.175 The effects on
animal and vegetable life are remarkable. Capt. King observed large
shrubs of Fuchsia and Veronica, which in England are treated as tender
plants, thriving and in full flower in Tierra del Fuego with the temperature
at 36°. He states also that humming birds were seen sipping the
sweets of the flowers "after two or three days of constant rain, snow,
and sleet, during which time the thermometer had been at the freezing
point." Mr. Darwin also saw parrots feeding on the seeds of a tree
called the winter's bark, south of lat. 55°, near Cape Horn.176
So the orchideous plants which are parasitical on trees, and are generally
characteristic of the tropics, advance to the 38th and 42d degree
of S. lat., and even beyond the 45th degree in New Zealand, where
they were found by Forster. In South America also arborescent grasses
abound in the dense forests of Chiloe, in lat. 42° S., where "they entwine
the trees into one entangled mass to the height of thirty or forty
98feet above the ground. Palm-trees in the same quarter of the globe
grow in lat. 37°, an arborescent grass very like a bamboo in 40°, and
another closely allied kind, of great length, but not erect, even as far
south as 45°."177
It has long been supposed that the general temperature of the southern
hemisphere was considerably lower than that of the northern, and that
the difference amounted to at least 10° Fahrenheit. Baron Humboldt,
after collecting and comparing a great number of observations, came to
the conclusion that even a much larger difference existed, but that none
was to be observed within the tropics, and only a small difference as far
as the thirty-fifth and fortieth parallel. Captain Cook was of opinion
that the ice of the antarctic predominated greatly over that of the arctic
region, that encircling the southern pole coming nearer to the equator
by 10° than the ice around the north pole. All the recent voyages of
discovery have tended to confirm this opinion, although Capt. Weddel
penetrated, in 1823, three degrees farther south than Capt. Cook, reaching
lat. 74° 15' South, long. 34° 17' West, and Sir James Ross, in 1842,
arrived at lat. 78° 10' S., as high a latitude, within three degrees, as
the farthest point attained by Captain Parry in the arctic circle, or lat.
81° 12' North.
The description given by ancient as well as modern navigators of the
sea and land in high southern latitudes, clearly attests the greater severity
of the climate as compared to arctic regions. In Sandwich Land,
in lat. 59° S., or in nearly the same parallel as the north of Scotland,
Capt. Cook found the whole country, from the summits of the mountains
down to the very brink of the sea-cliffs, "covered many fathoms thick
with everlasting snow," and this on the 1st of February, the hottest time
of the year; and what is still more astonishing, in the island of S. Georgia,
which is in the 54° south latitude, or the same parallel as Yorkshire, the
line of perpetual snow descends to the level of the ocean.178 When we
consider this fact, and then recollect that the highest mountains in Scotland,
which ascend to an elevation of nearly 5000 feet, and are four degrees
farther to the north, do not attain the limit of perpetual snow on
our side of the equator, we learn that latitude is one only of many powerful
causes, which determine the climate of particular regions of the
globe. Capt. Sir James Ross, in his exploring expedition in 1841-3,
found that the temperature south of the 60th degree of latitude seldom
rose above 32° Fahr. During the two summer months of the year 1841
(January and February) the range of the thermometer was between 11°
and 32° Fahr.; and scarcely once rose above the freezing point. The
permanence of snow in the southern hemisphere, is in this instance partly
due to the floating ice, which chills the atmosphere and condenses the
99vapor, so that in summer the sun cannot pierce through the foggy air.
But besides the abundance of ice which covers the sea to the south of
Georgia and Sandwich Land, we may also, as Humboldt suggests, ascribe
the cold of those countries in part to the absence of land between
them and the tropics.
If Africa and New Holland extended farther to the south, a diminution
of ice would take place in consequence of the radiation of heat from
these continents during summer, which would warm the contiguous sea
and rarefy the air. The heated aerial currents would then ascend and
flow more rapidly towards the south pole, and moderate the winter.
In confirmation of these views, it is stated that the ice, which extends as
far as the 68° and 71° of south latitude, advances more towards the
equator whenever it meets an open sea; that is, where the extremities
of the present continents are not opposite to it; and this circumstance
seems explicable only on the principle above alluded to, of the radiation
of heat from the lands so situated.
The cold of the antarctic regions was conjectured by Cook to be due
to the existence of a large tract of land between the seventieth degree
of south latitude and the pole. The justness of these and other speculations
of that great navigator have since been singularly confirmed by
the investigation made by Sir James Ross in 1841. He found Victoria
Land, extending from 71° to 79° S. latitude, skirted by a great barrier
of ice, the height of the land ranging from 4000 to 14,000 feet,
the whole entirely covered with snow, except a narrow ring of black
earth surrounding the huge crater of the active volcano of Mount
Erebus, rising 12,400 feet above the level of the sea. The position of
a mountainous territory of such altitude, so near the pole, and so obvious
a source of intense cold, fully explains why Graham's and Enderby's
Land, discovered by Captain Biscoe in 1831-2 (between lat. 64° and
68° S.), presented a most wintry aspect, covered even in summer with
ice and snow, and nearly destitute of animal life. In corresponding
latitudes of the northern hemisphere we not only meet with herds of
wild herbivorous animals, but with land which man himself inhabits,
and where he has even built ports and inland villages.179
The distance to which icebergs float from the polar regions on the
opposite sides of the line is, as might have been anticipated, very different.
Their extreme limit in the northern hemisphere is lat. 40°, as
before mentioned, and they are occasionally seen in lat. 42° N., near
the termination of the great bank of Newfoundland, and at the Azores,
lat. 42° N., to which they are sometimes drifted from Baffin's Bay.
But in the other hemisphere they have been seen, within the last few
years, at different points off the Cape of Good Hope, between lat.
10036° and 39°.180 One of these (see fig. 2.) was two miles in circumference,
and 150 feet high, appearing like chalk when the sun was obscured,
and having the lustre of refined sugar when the sun was shining
on it. Others rose from 250 to 300 feet above the level of the sea, and
were therefore of great volume below; since it is ascertained by experiments
on the buoyancy of ice floating in sea-water, that for every cubic
foot seen above, there must at least be eight cubic feet below water.181
If ice islands from the north polar regions floated as far, they might
reach Cape St. Vincent, and there, being drawn by the current that
always sets in from the Atlantic through the Straits of Gibraltar, be
drifted into the Mediterranean, so that the serene sky of that delightful
region might soon be deformed by clouds and mists.
Fig. 2.
Iceberg seen off the Cape of Good Hope, April, 1829.
Lat. 89º 18' S. Long. 48° 46' E.
Before the amount of difference between the temperature of the two
hemispheres was ascertained, it was referred by many astronomers to
the precession of the equinoxes, or the acceleration of the earth's motion
in its perihelium; in consequence of which the spring and summer
of the southern hemisphere are now shorter, by nearly eight days, than
those seasons north of the equator. But Sir J. Herschel reminds us
that the excess of eight days in the duration of the sun's presence in
the northern hemisphere is not productive of an excess of annual light
and heat; since, according to the laws of elliptic motion, it is demonstrable
that whatever be the ellipticity of the earth's orbit, the two
hemispheres must receive equal absolute quantities of light and heat
per annum, the proximity of the sun in perigee exactly compensating
the effect of its swifter motion.182 Humboldt, however, observes, that
there must be a greater loss of heat by radiation in the southern hemi101sphere
during a winter longer by eight days than that on the other side
of the equator.183
Perhaps no very sensible effect may be produced by this source of
disturbance; yet the geologist should bear in mind that to a certain
extent it operates alternately on each of the two hemispheres for a
period of upwards of 10,000 years, dividing unequally the times during
which the annual supply of solar light and heat is received. This
cause may sometimes tend to counterbalance inequalities of temperature
resulting from other far more influential circumstances; but, on the
other hand, it must sometimes tend to increase the extreme of deviation
arising from particular combinations of causes.
But whatever may be at present the inferiority of heat in the temperate
and frigid zones south of the line, it is quite evident that the cold
would be far more intense if there happened, instead of open sea, to be
tracts of elevated land between the 55th and 70th parallel; and, on the
other hand, the cold would be moderated if there were more land between
the line and the forty-fifth degree of south latitude.
Changes in the position of land and sea may give rise to vicissitudes
in climate.—Having offered these brief remarks on the diffusion of heat
over the globe in the present state of the surface, I shall now proceed
to speculate on the vicissitudes of climate, which must attend those
endless variations in the geographical features of our planet which are
contemplated in geology. That our speculations may be confined within
the strict limits of analogy, I shall assume, 1st, That the proportion
of dry land to sea continues always the same. 2dly, That the volume
of the land rising above the level of the sea is a constant quantity; and
not only that its mean, but that its extreme height, is liable only to
trifling variations. 3dly, That both the mean and extreme depth of
the sea are invariable; and 4thly, It may be consistent with due caution
to assume that the grouping together of the land in continents is a
necessary part of the economy of nature; for it is possible that the
laws which govern the subterranean forces, and which act simultaneously
along certain lines, cannot but produce, at every epoch, continuous
mountain-chains; so that the subdivision of the whole land into
innumerable islands may be precluded.
If it be objected, that the maximum of elevation of land and depth
of sea are probably not constant, nor the gathering together of all the
land in certain parts, nor even perhaps the relative extent of land
and water, I reply, that the arguments about to be adduced will be
strengthened if, in these peculiarities of the surface, there be considerable
deviations from the present type. If, for example, all other circumstances
being the same, the land is at one time more divided into
islands than at another, a greater uniformity of climate might be produced,
the mean temperature remaining unaltered; or if, at another era,
there were mountains higher than the Himalaya, these, when placed in
102high latitudes, would cause a greater excess of cold. Or, if we suppose
that at certain periods no chain of hills in the world rose beyond the
height of 10,000 feet, a greater heat might then have prevailed than is
compatible with the existence of mountains thrice that elevation.
However constant may be the relative proportion of sea and land, we
know that there is annually some small variation in their respective
geographical positions, and that in every century the land is in some
parts raised, and in others depressed in level, and so likewise is the bed
of the sea. By these and other ceaseless changes, the configuration of
the earth's surface has been remodelled again and again, since it was
the habitation of organic beings, and the bed of the ocean has been
lifted up to the height of some of the loftiest mountains. The imagination
is apt to take alarm when called upon to admit the formation of
such irregularities in the crust of the earth, after it had once become
the habitation of living creatures; but, if time be allowed, the operation
need not subvert the ordinary repose of nature; and the result is
in a general view insignificant, if we consider how slightly the highest
mountain-chains cause our globe to differ from a perfect sphere.
Chimborazo, though it rises to more than 21,000 feet above the sea,
would be represented, on a globe of about six feet in diameter, by a
grain of sand less than one-twentieth of an inch in thickness.
The superficial inequalities of the earth, then, may be deemed minute
in quantity, and their distribution at any particular epoch must be regarded
in geology as temporary peculiarities, like the height and outline
of the cone of Vesuvius in the interval between two eruptions.
But although, in reference to the magnitude of the globe, the unevenness
of the surface is so unimportant, it is on the position and direction
of these small inequalities that the state of the atmosphere, and both
the local and general climate, are mainly dependent.
Before considering the effect which a material change in the distribution
of land and sea must occasion, it may be well to remark, how
greatly organic life may be affected by those minor variations, which
need not in the least degree alter the general temperature. Thus, for
example, if we suppose, by a series of convulsions, a certain part of
Greenland to become sea, and, in compensation, a tract of land to rise
and connect Spitzbergen with Lapland,—an accession not greater in
amount than one which the geologist can prove to have occurred in certain
districts bordering the Mediterranean, within a comparatively modern
period,—this altered form of the land might cause an interchange
between the climate of certain parts of North America and of Europe,
which lie in corresponding latitudes. Many European species of plants
and animals would probably perish in consequence, because the mean
temperature would be greatly lowered; and others would fail in America,
because it would there be raised. On the other hand, in places
where the mean annual heat remained unaltered, some species which
flourish in Europe, where the seasons are more uniform, would be unable
to resist the greater heat of the North American summer, or the103
intenser cold of the winter; while others, now fitted by their habits for
the great contrast of the American seasons, would not be fitted for the
insular climate of Europe. The vine, for example, according to Humboldt,
can be cultivated with advantage 10° farther north in Europe
than in North America. Many plants endure severe frost, but cannot
ripen their seeds without a certain intensity of summer heat and a certain
quantity of light; others cannot endure a similar intensity either of
heat or cold.
It is now established that many of the existing species of animals
have survived great changes in the physical geography of the globe. If
such species be termed modern, in comparison to races which preceded
them, their remains, nevertheless, enter into submarine deposits many
hundred miles in length, and which have since been raised from the deep
to no inconsiderable altitude. When, therefore, it is shown that changes
in the temperature of the atmosphere may be the consequence of such
physical revolutions of the surface, we ought no longer to wonder that
we find the distribution of existing species to be local, in regard to longitude
as well as latitude. If all species were now, by an exertion of
creative power, to be diffused uniformly throughout those zones where
there is an equal degree of heat, and in all respects a similarity of climate,
they would begin from this moment to depart more and more from
their original distribution. Aquatic and terrestrial species would be displaced,
as Hooke long ago observed, so often as land and water exchanged
places; and there would also, by the formation of new mountains and
other changes, be transpositions of climate, contributing, in the manner
before alluded to, to the local extermination of species.184
If we now proceed to consider the circumstances required for a general
change of temperature, it will appear, from the facts and principles
already laid down, that whenever a greater extent of high land is collected
in the polar regions, the cold will augment; and the same result
will be produced when there is more sea between or near the tropics;
while, on the contrary, so often as the above conditions are reversed,
the heat will be greater. (See figs. 5 and 6, p. 111.) If this be admitted,
it will follow, that unless the superficial inequalities of the earth be
fixed and permanent, there must be never-ending fluctuations in the mean
temperature of every zone; and that the climate of one era can no more
be a type of every other; than is one of our four seasons of all the rest.
It has been well said, that the earth is covered by an ocean, in the
midst of which are two great islands, and many smaller ones; for the
whole of the continents and islands occupy an area scarcely exceeding
one-fourth of the whole superficies of the spheroid. Now, according to
this analogy, we may fairly speculate on the probability that there would
not be usually, at any given epoch of the past, more than about one-fourth
dry land in a particular region; as, for example, near the poles,
104
or between them and the 75th parallels of N. and S. latitude. If, therefore,
at present there should happen to be, in both these quarters of the
globe, much more than this average proportion of land, some of it in the
arctic region, being above, five thousand feet in height, and if in antarctic
latitudes a mountainous country has been found varying from 4000 to
14,000 feet in height, this alone affords ground for concluding that, in
the present state of things, the mean heat of the climate is below that
which the earth's surface, in its more ordinary state, would enjoy. This
presumption is heightened when we reflect on the results of the recent
soundings made by Sir James Ross, in the Southern Ocean, and continued
for four successive years, ending 1844, which seem to prove that
the mean depth of the Atlantic and Pacific is as great as Laplace and
other eminent astronomers had imagined;185 for then we might look not
only for more than two-thirds sea in the frigid zones, but for water of
great depth, which could not readily be reduced to the freezing point.
The same opinion is confirmed, when we compare the quantity of land
lying between the poles and the 30th parallels of north and south latitude,
with the quantity placed between those parallels and the equator;
for, it is clear, that we have at present not only more than the usual degree
of cold in the polar regions, but also less than the average quantity
of heat within the tropics.
105Position of land and sea which might produce the extreme of cold of
which the earth's surface is susceptible.—To simplify our view of the
various changes in climate, which different combinations of geographical
circumstances may produce, we shall first consider the conditions necessary
for bringing about the extreme of cold, or what would have been
termed in the language of the old writers the winter of the "great
year," or geological cycle, and afterwards, the conditions requisite to
produce the maximum of heat, or the summer of the same year.
To begin with the northern hemisphere. Let us suppose those hills
of the Italian peninsula and of Sicily, which are of comparatively modern
origin, and contain many fossil shells identical with living species, to
subside again into the sea, from which they have been raised, and that an
extent of land of equal area and height (varying from one to three
thousand feet) should rise up in the Arctic Ocean between Siberia and
the north pole. In speaking of such changes, I shall not allude to the
manner in which I conceive it possible that they may be brought about,
nor of the time required for their accomplishment—reserving for a future
occasion, not only the proofs that revolutions of equal magnitude have
taken place, but that analogous operations are still in gradual progress.
The alteration now supposed in the physical geography of the northern
regions, would cause additional snow and ice to accumulate where now
there is usually an open sea; and the temperature of the greater part
of Europe would be somewhat lowered, so as to resemble more nearly
that of corresponding latitudes of North America: or, in other words,
it might be necessary to travel about 10° farther south in order to meet
with the same climate which we now enjoy. No compensation would
be derived from the disappearance of land in the Mediterranean countries;
but the contrary, since the mean heat of the soil in those latitudes
probably exceeds that which would belong to the sea, by which
we imagine it to be replaced.
But let the configuration of the surface be still farther varied, and let
some large district within or near the tropics, such as Brazil, with its
plains and hills of moderate height, be converted into sea, while lands
of equal elevation and extent rise up in the arctic circle. From this
change there would, in the first place, result a sensible diminution of
temperature near the tropic, for the Brazilian soil would no longer be
heated by the sun; so that the atmosphere would be less warm, as also
the neighboring Atlantic. On the other hand, the whole of Europe,
Northern Asia, and North America, would be chilled by the enormous
quantity of ice and snow, thus generated on the new arctic continent.
If, as we have already seen, there are now some points in the southern
hemisphere where snow is perpetual down to the level of the sea, in
latitudes as low as central England, such might assuredly be the case
throughout a great part of Europe, under the change of circumstances
above supposed: and if at present the extreme range of drifted icebergs
is the Azores, they might easily reach the equator after the assumed
alteration. But to pursue the subject still farther, let the Himalaya106
mountains, with the whole of Hindostan, sink down, and their place be
occupied by the Indian Ocean, while an equal extent of territory and
mountains, of the same vast height, rise up between North Greenland
and the Orkney Islands. It seems difficult to exaggerate the amount
to which the climate of the northern hemisphere would then be cooled.186
But the refrigeration brought about at the same time in the southern
hemisphere, would be nearly equal, and the difference of temperature
between the arctic and equatorial latitudes would not be much greater
than at present; for no important disturbance can occur in the climate
of a particular region without its immediately affecting all other latitudes,
however remote. The heat and cold which surround the globe
are in a state of constant and universal flux and reflux. The heated
and rarefied air is always rising and flowing from the equator towards
the poles in the higher regions of the atmosphere; while in the lower,
the colder air is flowing back to restore the equilibrium. That this circulation
is constantly going on in the aerial currents is not disputed; it
is often proved by the opposite course of the clouds at different heights,
and the fact has been farther illustrated in a striking manner by two
recent events. The trade wind continually blows with great force from
the island of Barbadoes to that of St. Vincent; notwithstanding which,
during the eruption of the volcano in the island of St. Vincent, in 1812,
ashes fell in profusion from a great height in the atmosphere upon
Barbadoes.187 In like manner, during the great eruption of Sumbawa,
in 1815, ashes were carried to the islands of Amboyna and Banda,
which last is about 800 miles east from the site of the volcano. Yet
the southeast monsoon was then at its height.188 This apparent transposition
of matter against the wind, confirmed the opinion of the existence
of a counter-current in the higher regions, which had previously
rested on theoretical conclusions only.
That a corresponding interchange takes place in the seas, is demonstrated,
according to Humboldt, by the cold which is found to exist at
great depths within the tropics; and, among other proofs, may be mentioned
the mass of warmer water which the Gulf stream is constantly
bearing northwards, while a cooler current flows from the north along
the coast of Greenland and Labrador, and helps to restore the equilibrium.189
107Currents of colder and therefore specifically heavier water pass from
the poles towards the equator, which cool the inferior parts of the
ocean; so that the heat of the torrid zone and the cold of the polar
circle balance each other. The refrigeration, therefore, of the polar regions,
resulting from the supposed alteration in the distribution of land
and sea, would be immediately communicated to the tropics, and from
them its influence would extend to the antarctic circle, where the atmosphere
and the ocean would be cooled, so that ice and snow would augment.
Although the mean temperature of higher latitudes in the
southern hemisphere is, as before stated, for the most part, lower than
that of the same parallels in the northern, yet, for a considerable space
on each side of the line, the mean annual heat of the waters is found
to be the same in corresponding parallels. If, therefore, by the new
position of the land, the formation of icebergs had become of common
occurrence in the northern temperate zone, and if these were frequently
drifted as far as the equator, the same degree of cold which they generated
would immediately be communicated as far as the tropic of Capricorn,
and from thence to the lands or ocean to the south.
The freedom, then, of the circulation of heat and cold from pole to
pole being duly considered, it will be evident that the mean temperature
which may prevail at the same point at two distinct periods, may
differ far more widely than that of any two points in the same parallels
of latitude, at one and the same period. For the range of temperature,
or in other words, the curvature of the isothermal lines in a given zone,
and at a given period, must always be circumscribed within narrow
limits, the climate of each place in that zone being controlled by the
combined influence of the geographical peculiarities of all other parts
of the earth. Whereas, if we compare the state of things at two distinct
and somewhat distant epochs, a particular zone may at one time
be under the influence of one class of disturbing causes, and at another
time may be affected by an opposite combination. The lands, for example,
to the north of Greenland cause the present climate of North
America to be colder than that of Europe in the same latitudes; but
the excess of cold is not so great as it would have been if the western
hemisphere had been entirely isolated, or separated from the eastern
like a distinct planet. For not only does the refrigeration produced by
Greenland chill to a certain extent the atmosphere of northern and western
Europe, but the mild climate of Europe reacts also upon North America,
and moderates the chilling influence of the adjoining polar lands.
To return to the state of the earth after the changes above supposed,
we must not omit to dwell on the important effects to which a wide
expanse of perpetual snow would give rise. It is probable that nearly
the whole sea, from the poles to the parallels of 45°, would be frozen
over; for it is well known that the immediate proximity of land is not
108essential to the formation and increase of field ice, provided there be in
some part of the same zone a sufficient quantity of glaciers generated
on or near the land, to cool down the sea. Captain Scoresby, in his
account of the arctic regions, observes, that when the sun's rays "fall
upon the snow-clad surface of the ice or land, they are in a great measure
reflected, without producing any material elevation of temperature;
but when they impinge on the black exterior of a ship, the pitch on
one side occasionally becomes fluid while ice is rapidly generated at
the other."190
Now field ice is almost always covered with snow;191 and thus not
only land as extensive as our existing continents, but immense tracts of
sea in the frigid and temperate zones, might present a solid surface
covered with snow, and reflecting the sun's rays for the greater part of
the year. Within the tropics, moreover, where the ocean now predominates,
the sky would no longer be serene and clear, as in the present
era; but masses of floating ice would cause quick condensations of
vapor, so that fogs and clouds would deprive the vertical rays of the
sun of half their power. The whole planet, therefore, would receive
annually a smaller portion of the solar influence, and the external crust
would part, by radiation, with some of the heat which had been accumulated
in it, during a different state of the surface. This heat would
be dissipated in the spaces surrounding our atmosphere, which, according
to the calculations of M. Fourier, have a temperature much inferior
to that of freezing water.
After the geographical revolution above assumed, the climate of
equinoctial lands might be brought at last to resemble that of the present
temperate zone, or perhaps be far more wintry. They who should
then inhabit such small isles and coral reefs as are now seen in the
Indian Ocean and South Pacific, would wonder that zoophytes of large
dimensions had once been so prolific in their seas; or if, perchance,
they found the wood and fruit of the cocoa-nut tree or the palm silicified
by the waters of some ancient mineral spring, or incrusted with
calcareous matter, they would muse on the revolutions which had annihilated
such genera, and replaced them by the oak, the chestnut, and
the pine. With equal admiration would they compare the skeletons of
their small lizards with the bones of fossil alligators and crocodiles more
than twenty feet in length, which, at a former epoch, had multiplied
between the tropics: and when they saw a pine included in an iceberg,
drifted from latitudes which we now call temperate, they would be astonished
at the proof thus afforded, that forests had once grown where
nothing could be seen in their own times but a wilderness of snow.
If the reader hesitate to suppose so extensive an alteration of temperature
as the probable consequence of geographical changes, confined to
one hemisphere, he should remember how great are the local anomalies
in climate now resulting from the peculiar distribution of land and sea
109in certain regions. Thus, in the island of South Georgia, before mentioned
(p. 98), Captain Cook found the everlasting snows descending
to the level of the sea, between lat. 54° and 55° S.; no trees or shrubs
were to be seen, and in summer a few rocks only, after a partial melting
of the ice and snow, were scantily covered with moss and tufts of
grass. If such a climate can now exist at the level of the sea in a latitude
corresponding to that of Yorkshire in spite of all those equalizing
causes before enumerated, by which the mixture of the temperatures of
distant regions is facilitated throughout the globe, what rigors might
we not anticipate in a winter generated by the transfer of the mountains
of India to our arctic circle!
But we have still to contemplate the additional refrigeration which
might be effected by changes in the relative position of land and sea in
the southern hemisphere. If the remaining continents were transferred
from the equatorial and contiguous latitudes to the south polar regions,
the intensity of cold produced might, perhaps, render the globe uninhabitable.
We are too ignorant of the laws governing the direction of
subterranean forces, to determine whether such a crisis be within the
limits of possibility. At the same time, it may be observed, that no
distribution of land can well be imagined more irregular, or, as it were,
capricious, than that which now prevails; for at present, the globe may
be divided into two equal parts, in such a manner, that one hemisphere
shall be almost entirely covered with water, while the other shall contain
less water than land (see figs. 3 and 4);192 and, what is still more
extraordinary, on comparing the extratropical lands in the northern and
southern hemispheres, the lands in the northern are found to be to those
in the southern in the proportion of thirteen to one!193 To imagine all
the lands, therefore, in high, and all the sea in low latitudes, as delineated
in fig. 6. p. 111, would scarcely be a more anomalous state of the
surface.
110
Map showing the present unequal Distribution of Land and Water on the
Surface of the Globe.


Fig. 3.




Fig. 4.




Fig. 3. Here London is taken as a centre, and we behold the greatest quantity of land
existing in one hemisphere.
Fig. 4. Here the centre is the antipodal point to London, and we see the greatest
quantity of water existing in one hemisphere.
The black shading expresses land having land opposite or antipodal to it.

111
Maps showing the position of Land and Sea which might produce the Extremes
of Heat and Cold in the Climates of the Globe.
Fig. 5.
Extreme of Heat.
Fig. 6.
Extreme of Cold.
Observations.—These maps are intended to show that continents and islands having the same
shape and relative dimensions as those now existing, might be placed so as to occupy either the
equatorial or polar regions.
In fig. 5, scarcely any of the land extends from the equator towards the poles beyond the 30th
parallel of latitude; and fig. 6, a very small proportion of it extends from the poles towards the
Equator beyond the 40th parallel of latitude.
Position of land and sea which might give rise to the extreme of heat.—Let
us now turn from the contemplation of the winter of the "great year,"
and consider the opposite train of circumstances which would bring on
the spring and summer. To imagine all the lands to be collected together
in equatorial latitudes, and a few promontories only to project
112
beyond the thirtieth parallel, as represented in the annexed maps (figs.
5 and 6), would be undoubtedly to suppose an extreme result of geological
change. But if we consider a mere approximation to such a state
of things, it would be sufficient to cause a general elevation of temperature.
Nor can it be regarded as a visionary idea, that amidst the revolutions
of the earth's surface, the quantity of land should, at certain periods,
have been simultaneously lessened in the vicinity of both the poles,
and increased within the tropics. We must recollect that even now it
is necessary to ascend to the height of fifteen thousand feet in the Andes
under the line, and in the Himalaya mountains, which are without the tropic,
to seventeen thousand feet, before we reach the limit of perpetual snow.
On the northern slope, indeed, of the Himalaya range, where the heat radiated
from a great continent moderates the cold, there are meadows and
cultivated land at an elevation equal to the height of Mont
Blanc.194 If then
there were no arctic lands to chill the atmosphere, and freeze the sea, and
if the loftiest chains were near the line, it seems reasonable to imagine that
the highest mountains might be clothed with a rich vegetation to their
summits, and that nearly all signs of frost would disappear from the earth.
When the absorption of the solar rays was in no region impeded, even
in winter, by a coat of snow, the mean heat of the earth's crust would
augment to considerable depths, and springs, which we know to be in
general an index of the mean temperature of the climate, would be
warmer in all latitudes. The waters of lakes, therefore, and rivers,
would be much hotter in winter, and would be never chilled in summer
by melted snow and ice. A remarkable uniformity of climate would prevail
amid the archipelagoes of the temperate and polar oceans, where the
tepid waters of equatorial currents would freely circulate. The general humidity
of the atmosphere would far exceed that of the present period, for
increased heat would promote evaporation in all parts of the globe. The
winds would be first heated in their passage over the tropical plains, and
would then gather moisture from the surface of the deep, till, charged with
vapor, they arrived at extreme northern and southern regions, and there
encountering a cooler atmosphere, discharged their burden in warm rain.
If, during the long night of a polar winter, the snows should whiten the
summits of some arctic islands, they would be dissolved as rapidly by the
returning sun, as are the snows of Etna by the blasts of the sirocco.
We learn from those who have studied the geographical distribution of
plants, that in very low latitudes, at present, the vegetation of small islands remote
from continents has a peculiar character; the ferns and allied families,
in particular, bearing a great proportion to the total number of other plants.
Other circumstances being the same, the more remote the isles are from
the continents, the greater does this proportion become. Thus, in the continent
of India, and the tropical parts of New Holland, the proportion of
ferns to the phænogamous plants is only as one to twenty-six; whereas,
in the South-Sea Islands, it is as one to four, or even as one to three.195
113We might expect, therefore, in the summer of the "great year," or
cycle of climate, that there would be a predominance of tree ferns and
plants allied to genera now called tropical, in the islands of the wide
ocean, while many forms now confined to arctic and temperate regions,
or only found near the equator on the summit of the loftiest mountains,
would almost disappear from the earth. Then might those genera of
animals return, of which the memorials are preserved in the ancient rocks
of our continents. The pterodactyle might flit again through the air,
the huge iguanodon reappear in the woods, and the ichthyosaurs swarm
once more in the sea. Coral reefs might be prolonged again beyond
the arctic circle, where the whale and the narwal now abound; and
droves of turtles might begin again to wander through regions now tenanted
by the walrus and the seal.
But not to indulge too far in these speculations, I may observe, in
conclusion, that however great, during the lapse of ages, may be the
vicissitudes of temperature in every zone, it accords with this theory that
the general climate should not experience any sensible change in the
course of a few thousand years; because that period is insufficient to
affect the leading features of the physical geography of the globe.
Notwithstanding the apparent uncertainty of the seasons, it is found
that the mean temperature of particular localities is very constant, when
observations made for a sufficient series of years are compared.
Yet there must be exceptions to this rule; and even the labors of
man have, by the drainage of lakes and marshes, and the felling of extensive
forests, caused such changes in the atmosphere as greatly to raise
our conception of the more important influence of those forces to which,
in certain latitudes, even the existence of land or water, hill or valley,
lake or sea, must be ascribed. If we possessed accurate information of
the amount of local fluctuation in climate in the course of twenty centuries,
it would often, undoubtedly, be considerable. Certain tracts, for
example, on the coast of Holland and of England consisted of cultivated
land in the time of the Romans, which the sea, by gradual encroachments,
has at length occupied. Here, at least, a slight alteration has
been effected; for neither the distribution of heat in the different seasons,
nor the mean annual temperature of the atmosphere investing the sea, is
precisely the same as that which rests upon the land.
In those countries, also, where earthquakes and volcanoes are in full
activity, a much shorter period may produce a sensible variation. The
climate of the great table-land of Malpais in Mexico, must differ materially
from that which prevailed before the middle of the last century; for,
since that time, six mountains, the highest of them rising sixteen hundred
feet above the plateau, have been thrown up by volcanic eruptions.
It is by the repetition of an indefinite number of such local revolutions,
and by slow movements extending simultaneously over wider areas, as
will be afterwards shown, that a general change of climate may finally
be brought about.

114</div></body></text></TEI>