<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="36">CHAPTER XXXIV.
The first employment in which I purposed to engage my
new-found liberty and youth, was a visit to my daughters.
I now carried a disguise perpetually about with me, that
would render my journey incapable of proving injurious to
them. My daughters were all that remained, if indeed they
still remained, of my once idolised family. For twelve
years I had continued totally ignorant of their fortune, and
even of their existence. Part of the plan I had adopted
for their advantage necessarily precluded me from all correspondence
or communication with them or any one near
them, that might satisfy and tranquillise the anxieties of a
father. If it had been otherwise, deprived, as I had been,
of the common benefits of light and air, and cast out from
the society of mankind, I could have obtained no intelligence
of their welfare. In visiting, I determined not to
make myself known to them; yet, notwithstanding the
greatness of this disadvantage, I felt that one of the most
exquisite gratifications the earth could afford me was to
behold my children. What a multitude of adventures and
incidents might they not have encountered in the space of
twelve years! Imagination and affection dwell impatiently
on the interval; nor can any thing quiet the conjectures of[354]
him that loves, short of the most complete information.
What a difference must twelve years have produced in the
very persons and figures of creatures so young? With what
mingled and exquisite emotions does the father contemplate
his daughter, whom he left a child, grown up into a woman?
He sees her with astonishment and rapture, displaying
maturer beauties, discovering in her countenance new traces
of knowledge and sentiment, and in her gesture and manners
a character finished, matronly, and sedate. The very
circumstance that I should visit them unknown, and converse
intimately with them without being discovered, while
it cut me off from many pure and ingenuous pleasures,
added in some respects a new relish to the indulgence; for
it gave it a character, singular, and perhaps unprecedented,
in the history of mankind. I anticipated with eager transport
the hour at which I should revisit the place of my
birth, wander amidst the shades where my careless infancy
had strayed, recognise objects made sacred to my heart by
associations with my venerable mother and my adorable
wife, now illumined with the presence of my children,
and steal a joy, unsuspected and unknown, to which the
very secrecy with which it was ravished would give a
tenfold gust.
I embraced the nearest route, by Pampeluna and the
Pyrenees, to the banks of the Garonne. One particular
pleasure that I reaped during this tour, which the climate
and scenery might alone have rendered delightful, consisted
in the youthful sensation with which every thing I saw
was enjoyed. Every one who can call to mind the amusements
of his childhood will be conscious that during that
period all his senses were in a tone adapted to convey the
most exquisite gratification. This is not merely, as is
vulgarly supposed, the result of the novelty and freshness
with which at that time every thing strikes us. The extremities
of the nerves are in a state of the most delicate
susceptibility, upon which no touch, however slight and
evanescent, is lost, and which makes us, upon every occasion
favourable to enjoyment, gasp and tremble with the
pleasure we imbibe. We feel it thrilling through every
pulse, and communicating its tone to every part. Our attention[355]
is engrossed by a single object; or, if we are
sensible to accompanying incidents, it spreads over them
an animating sunshine, and totally varies their appearance
and hue. Age, on the contrary, imperceptibly brings
along with it callosity and sluggishness of sensation, our
gratifications are coldly relished, and our desires feebly
awakened. Such is the difference in our perception, of
delicious fruits, of fragrant smells, of smooth and glossy
surfaces, of the vividness of colour, and the heavenly
sweetness of sound. If this be a just account, I leave the
reader to imagine how I enjoyed my tour from Valladolid
to the beautiful and romantic retirement of St. Leon.
There was however one sentiment with which I was at
this time impressed, that I shall find it difficult to make
the reader understand in the extent in which I felt it, and
that formed a powerful drawback upon the pleasures I have
just described. A short time ago I had been old; now I
was young: I had quaffed of the elixir of immortality.
The revolution this had produced in my sentiments was
not less memorable than that which it had effected in my
corporeal lineaments and my mental elasticity. It is so
different a thing to conceive a proposition theoretically,
and to experience it in practice! The case is parallel to
that of the expectation which an ordinary Christian entertains
of eternal bliss. It is an article in his creed; he
repeats it every night when he lies down, and every morning
when he rises. He would be both offended and surprised
if you told him he was not persuaded of it; and
yet how faint and indistinct a picture it produces in his
intellectual retina! The affairs of the world strike him
with all the force of vision; to them he cannot make himself
a stranger and a pilgrim; he cannot transfer all his
affections to the mere creature of his imagination, engendered
in solitude, and nurtured by enthusiasm,—heaven.
How different must have been the feelings of the celebrated
apostle, who had been taken up into the third heaven, and
had beheld the new Jerusalem with all its jaspers, its chrysolites,
its emeralds, and its sapphires!
My situation was similar to this. I had long known, as
far as reflection could assure me of it, that I possessed the[356]
elixir of immortality. But never till now had I felt the
julep tingling in my veins, and known the effects of it in
every joint and articulation of my frame. I before believed,
I now felt, that I was immortal. The consequence of this
intimate persuasion was not without its portion of melancholy.
I still bore the figure and lineaments of a human
creature; but I knew that I was not what I seemed. There
was a greater distance between me and the best constructed
and most consummate of the human species, than there is
between him and an ant or a muskito, crushed by the first
accidental tread, or consumed by the first spark wafted by
the wind. I can no longer cheat my fancy; I know that
I am alone. The creature does not exist with whom I have
any common language, or any genuine sympathies. Society
is a bitter and galling mockery to my heart; it only shows
in more glaring colours my desolate condition. The nearer
I attempt to draw any of the nominal ties of our nature,
the more they start and shrink from my grasp. From this
moment I could not shake off the terrible impression of my
loneliness; no, not for an hour. Often does this impression
induce me to regard my immortality with loathing indescribable;
often do I wish to shelter myself from it in the
sweet oblivion of the grave. From this hour I had no
passions, no interests, no affections; my heart has never
expanded with one natural emotion; I have never delivered
myself up to the repose of one genuine amusement. If at
any time I have had a glimpse of pleasure, it has irritated,
only to deceive; it has increased the appetite, while it displayed
in stronger colours my impotence to gratify it.
What is worse, every added year has still subtracted something
from the little poignancy and relish which the bowl
of human life continued to retain. I have the power of
assuming a youthful and glossy appearance whenever I think
proper; but this is only a bitter mockery of the furrows
ploughed in my heart. In so much of my adventures as
remains for me to describe, I feel that I shall be obliged to
employ the established terms of human description. I cannot
interrupt the history of my sensations, by a recital of
those pangs by which they have been every moment interrupted.
The terms I must use may delude the reader into[357]
an imagination that I still participate of enjoyment and of
hope. Be it so; they may cheat the reader; they cannot
cheat myself!
Previously to my arrival in the vicinity of the Garonne,
I equipped myself in the habit of an Armenian, and assumed
the character of a merchant travelling from country
to country for the sale of his commodities.
It was in the close of a wintry day in the bleak and
cheerless month of December, that I first viewed from a
distance the turrets of St. Leon. I procured myself accommodations
for the night in the adjoining village. Being
now, after so long an absence, within reach of the residence
of these lovely treasures, I sought, without any direct consciousness
of the sentiment, to delay our interview. When
I entered the little auberge, sheltered under a small plantation
of olives, I dreaded to hear the repetition of my family
name. I longed most fervently to be informed of the welfare
of my daughters, yet I could have died sooner than
utter a single question on the subject. I found that that
ardent love which had urged me with rapid steps from Valladolid
to St. Leon, gradually, as the distance grew little,
changed from an impetuous vehemence to hear of, and to
see them, to fearful, awe-struck, motionless anxiety. Their
light and airy figures, as I last saw them at Montauban in
1547, danced before the eyes of my imagination: what
casualties, what calamities might not have overtaken them
since! I was afraid almost to breathe, lest I should dissolve
the unreal scene that played around me. How did I know
that I did not indulge this cheerful imagination for the last
time? Again and again in the course of the evening, I felt
as if I could have wasted ages in this auberge and the
neighbouring fields, still believing that my daughters inhabited
yonder towers, still hovering round their fancied
residence, but never daring to utter their name, lest it should
be found the prelude to some fatal intelligence. How rich
and refined a repast in some cases is uncertainty! It had the
power to impart to these precious pledges a share of that immortality
of which I was the destined monopolist.
Why had I not the courage never to overpass the limit
at which I was now arrived, and, wherever I afterwards[358]
wandered on the various surface of the globe, still to be
able to repeat to myself the complacent whisper, “I have
visited my daughters in their separated abode, and my visit
was productive of none but agreeable sensations?” My
passions were too much afloat to suffer me really to rest in
this patient, contemplative gratification. Before the morning’s
dawn, I walked forth, and turned my eyes towards
the castle. I loitered from bank to bank, and from point
to point. Daylight slowly broke in upon me, but all was
silent and quiet in my paternal château. “The family is
not yet stirring,” said I to myself. I turned my steps to
the spot where the ashes of my mother were mingled with
their parent earth. The time that had intervened since
her decease, the various fortunes and impressions I had
experienced, had somewhat obliterated the vividness of her
picture in my memory, and deadened the tremblingness of
sensation with which I once thought of her. Yet enough
was left, to make it an interesting moment to me, when I
kneeled at her tomb. Why, oh why, as it had been with
my great forefathers, was it not a moment of exultation to
me, when I thus feelingly saluted the shade of a parent!
He that exults in such an hour, must feel that he has
illustrated his birth, and honoured his progenitors. I had
done nothing of this: I was an exile on the face of the
earth, had acquired no trophies, and accumulated no fame.
I had none to honour, none even to know me; I had no
family, I had no friend! These bitter recollections started
up in array before me, and cut me to the heart. The spirit
of my mother frowned upon her son; and I returned along
the path by which I came, disgraced and disconsolate.
“I am now,” said I, “in a fit temper to learn intelligence
of my daughters: if they have been unhappy, to
hear it will not make me more forlorn; if they have been
fortunate, that knowledge, and that alone, may revive my
courage.” I hastened towards the avenue. I looked into
the thickets and winding paths, as I passed. They communicated
to me mingled pictures of my own boyish days,
and of the amusements of the present inhabitants.
I told the nature of my pretended traffic to the servants
of the house, and proposed an exhibition of my commodities;[359]
I was admitted, as I desired, to the apartment of
their mistresses. I saw two young ladies, who appeared
to be respectively about twenty-eight and twenty-four years
of age, and whom without much difficulty I recognised for
my daughters Louisa and Marguerite. Their situation and
their ages identified them; and when afterwards I came to
peruse their features attentively, I could easily discover
traits of the amiable young woman and the playful child
they had been when last we parted. I found them employed
upon a piece of embroidery; a comely and respectable
looking young woman, a servant, was sewing in another
part of the room. Every thing about the ladies
bespoke the ease of their circumstances, and the propriety
of their sentiments. Both had on an elegant morning-habit;
both had an air of sedateness and sobriety, that to
my apprehension told that they had not lived unchastened
by misfortune.
They each slightly looked up, as I was ushered into the
apartment; they saluted me with a graceful and condescending
bend of the head, such as we are accustomed to
use to an inferior whom we are willing to put at his ease.
What were my sensations, a father, disguised and unknown,
in the presence of his children! I attempted to stand, as
is usual for a tradesman, when he waits on his customers
at their own house. I attempted to speak. My tongue
refused its office; my legs tottered as if sustaining an unusual
weight. Louisa observed me, and desired me to be
seated. I had no power of choice; I accepted her civility.
No sooner was I seated, than in spite of myself a flood of
tears gushed from my eyes. She was astonished; she
begged to know if I were indisposed; she requested me to
make use of every assistance the house could afford. I now
found my speech. I apologised for my behaviour; said I
had felt suddenly ill, but that the tears I shed would prove
the most effectual relief to me. My appearance, it may be
proper to mention, was not that of a vulgar pedlar; it was
tall, graceful, and ingenuous, with a certain air of refinement
and politeness; my Armenian dress, though formed
of uncostly materials, was such as to display my person to
considerable advantage. Both the young ladies showed[360]
themselves interested in the symptoms of my distress.
After a few minutes internal struggle, I rose, made an excuse
for the abruptness of my departure, and requested
permission to repeat my visit in the afternoon, when I
should have something not unimportant to communicate to
them.
I had seen two of my daughters; I had been satisfied
that they still existed; I had witnessed their exterior health
and beauty. As I withdrew, I laid my hand upon my heart,
and congratulated myself: “Thus far,” said I, “it is well!”
I felt relieved from part of the weight that lay there. With
my right hand I struck upon my forehead: “but, oh, where,”
cried I, “is my other daughter?” The thought came over
me with the force of a demonstration: she is dead! A
servant was attending me to the door; I requested to speak
to the housekeeper; I was introduced to Mariana Chabot.
She was struck with my appearance, as I believe my daughters
had been, as if my features were those of some person
with whom she was intimately acquainted. She would
probably have mistaken me for my own son, but that I
looked considerably too young. I intreated her to pardon
my curiosity; but, I assured her, I had a particular reason to
interest myself in the family of Monsieur St. Leon, and I
therefore requested that she would have the goodness to
inform me of their affairs, as far as she could with propriety
communicate them to a person who was not so
happy as to be in the catalogue of their acquaintance. I
told her that I had just seen two of her ladies, but that I
had understood there had been three, and I particularly desired
some information as to the young lady who had not
made her appearance in the parlour. My presentiment was
true; the impression that smote me when I left the parlour,
was her funeral knell; my beloved Julia was dead;
she had been dead four years! If it had not been for the
agitation of my mind when I visited the tomb of my
venerable parent, I should have discovered her monument
near that of her grandmother. That would have been too
overwhelming a mode of learning the painful intelligence;
I was glad at least to have escaped that!
In this and some subsequent conversations I held with[361]
this respectable matron, I learned a variety of particulars
respecting my daughters. Madame Chabot expressed herself
sorry that she had nothing pleasing to communicate.
Her young ladies had been pursued by a train of misfortunes,
though, heaven knew, they had merited every happiness.
A few years after they had been settled at St. Leon,
Julia had been addressed by a lover in every sense worthy
of her. He was rich, noble, of a gallant spirit, of a cultivated
understanding, and a truly kind and affectionate
heart. Their attachment had been long and tried; habit
and experience of each other’s virtues had caused it to take
a deep root. The father of the young man had destined
him to marry the daughter of a duke and peer of the
kingdom; but, finding his affections unalterably fixed, he
had at length yielded, and sanctioned their mutual passion
with his consent. Every thing was now prepared for the
nuptials; a day was fixed, and the appointed time was fast
approaching. Just at this juncture, the father changed his
mind, and became more obstinate and inexorable than ever.
A report had begun to be circulated that monsieur St. Leon,
the father of the young ladies, was still alive. Madame
Chabot expressed her fear that this report had originated in
some indiscretion of Bernardin, who, however, had always
proved himself a most zealous and faithful servant, and who
had since paid the debt of nature. Be that as it might,
the father of the lover of Julia was found no longer accessible
to expostulation or entreaty. He was of an avaricious
disposition, and he regarded the fortune of the young lady,
which would otherwise have been considerable, as entirely
alienated and annihilated by this flaw in the title. But
what was more material, it by no means accorded with his
ideas of nobility and honour, that the father-in-law of his
only son should be a fugitive and a wanderer, with whose
residence no one was acquainted, and of whom no one
could tell whether he were living or dead. The manner
in which the ladies had entered into the repossession of
their paternal estate, when minutely investigated, was
thought to have something in it of an ambiguous and unpleasant
nature. It was well known that monsieur St. Leon
had left the country in consequence of his having ruined[362]
himself by the vice of gaming. “Surely,” said some, “it is
a little mysterious, how his children came, after an interval
of nine years, to be able to repurchase all he ever possessed.”
In short, the more the old vicomte was reasoned with, the
more furious he grew. At length he made use of the
power which the government of France vests in the father
of a family, and shut up his son in one of the royal prisons.
This was a fatal blow both to the chevalier and his
mistress. Disappointed in the object of his warmest affections,
maltreated and disgraced by the severity of a father,
his health sensibly declined. Nothing however could shake
the inflexibility of the vicomte; he would release his son
upon no other terms than a renunciation of his love, terms
which the sense of dignity and honour in the young gentleman,
equally with his passion, forbade him to accept. To
all representations of the necessity of granting liberty to
his son, if he would not make himself answerable for his
death, the vicomte sternly replied, “that he preferred his
dying to the idea of his connecting himself with a family
of dishonour.” It was not till a few weeks before he expired,
that the father had consented to his release from
prison, and had removed him to one of his castles in a
remote province. But the malady of the chevalier was
found incurable; the vital principles of the system were
fatally deranged. The lover died; and the consequences
of this unhappy affair had put a premature close to the
existence of the unfortunate Julia. Madame Chabot added
that, the circumstance of this story having become a subject
of public animadversion, it had had a most unfavourable
effect on the prospects of the surviving sisters. They bore
their situation with dignity; but they could not but feel
the unhappy coincidence, which cut them off from the
happiest condition of human life, an honourable and well
assorted settlement in marriage.
While madame Chabot related to me the tragical history
of Julia, I felt convulsed with passion, and more than once
burst into an agony of tears. Fatal legacy! atrocious secrets
of medicine and chemistry! every day opened to my astonished
and terrified sight a wider prospect of their wasteful
effects! A common degree of penetration might have[363]
shown me, that secrets of this character cut off their possessor
from the dearest ties of human existence, and render
him a solitary, cold, self-centered individual; his heart no
longer able to pour itself into the bosom of a mistress or a
friend; his bosom no longer qualified to receive upon equal
terms the overflowing of a kindred heart. But no mere
exercise of imagination, nothing short of the actual experience
through which I had passed, could have adequately
represented the mischiefs of a thousand various
names, that issued from this Pandora’s box, this extract of
a universal panacea. I regarded myself as the murderer of
these two lovers, than whom I concluded, from my personal
observation of the one, and all that I heard of the
other, two purer and more affectionate beings, more singularly
qualified to form each other’s happiness, had never
existed. I felt as truly haunted with the ghosts of those I
had murdered, as Nero or Caligula might have been; my
wife, my son, my faithful negro; and now, in addition to
these, the tender Julia and her unalterable admirer. I possessed
the gift of immortal life; but I looked on myself as
a monster that did not deserve to exist.
It is with difficulty that I shall be able to make the
reader understand how much more severe the impression
of this last catastrophe was made to me, by the place and
time in which I received the intelligence. We are creatures
of sensation: our worst calamities derive as much of their
pungency from the accessories by which they are accompanied,
as they do from their intrinsic evil. If I had heard
this story at any other period, I am persuaded its effects
would not have been half so painful. The idea of my
daughters was faded in my sensorium, and whatever related
to them, though really felt, and felt like a father,
would have been felt with a less overpowering interest.
But now I had journeyed from Valladolid to the Garonne
to behold them; I had surveyed the castle they inhabited;
I had viewed the garden which they arranged
with their hands; I had entered the parlour which they
adorned with their presence. All this controlled the operation
of absence and of distance; I felt at this moment
as if I had been accustomed to see them every day, and to[364]
regard them as inseparable from my existence. I experienced,
as it were, the united effect of familiarity and
novelty; I felt the melancholy fate of Julia, with all the
keenness of an inmate, and all the surprise of a long absent
traveller. The very metamorphosis I had undergone gave
new poignancy to my distress. Madame Chabot tortured
me deliberately and at leisure, without the slightest consciousness
of what she was doing; she believed she was
pouring a tale of persons unknown into the ears of a native
of the other hemisphere, at the moment that she was calling
up in arms the strongest and most excruciating feelings of
a father for his child. I on the other hand had the most
violent struggle with myself, while I endeavoured to suppress
the appearances of an emotion, which to the person
who witnessed them must have been for ever unaccountable.
As it was, and in spite of all my efforts, madame Chabot
betrayed no little amazement at the agitation with which I
listened to a story, in which, as she apprehended, I could
have no personal interest.
What I heard from madame Chabot suggested to me a
conduct, which I resolved to adopt under the present circumstances.
In my next interview I told Louisa that I
would now account to her for emotions which, at the time
they occurred, must have appeared somewhat extraordinary.
I owned that I had been acquainted with her father; I said
that I had first met with him in a journey, in which I was
then engaged through the province of Mesopotamia; that
I had received from him, though a stranger, a singular
obligation; that a sincere friendship between us had been
the result of this event; that he died about two years since;
that I had attended him in his last moments; that he had
charged me with his dying recommendations and requests;
and that my present journey into France had principally
been instigated by a desire to visit his children. I then
delivered into her hands various letters and papers, which I
had counterfeited chiefly with the intention of supplying my
daughters with legal evidence of the decease of their father.
Louisa listened to what I related with those marks of affection
and sorrow, which are inseparable from the habits
of a well constituted mind. The emotion she discovered[365]
led me farther than I first intended. I was urged by an
irresistible impulse to practise, beyond what the occasion
demanded, upon the feelings of her virtuous mind. I know
not whether this is to be considered as a vain refinement
and a criminal curiosity; but—I think—every generous
spirit will excuse me, when it is recollected that this covert
and imperfect proceeding was all that was left me to soothe
the impatient cravings of a father’s heart. From time to
time I reminded her of particulars that it was scarcely possible
any one but her father should know; I conjured up
past scenes; I made all the revolutions of her youth pass
successively in review before her; I touched all the pulses
of her soul. Sometimes she was fixed in mute astonishment
at the exactness of my information, and was ready to
do me homage as some aerial genius, who condescended to
clothe himself in this earthly figure; at other times astonishment
was swallowed up in feeling, her soul dissolved in tenderness,
and she appeared ready to faint into my arms. It is
scarcely possible to depict the pleasurable sensations I drew
from these intercourses; I know not whether they were
entirely innocent; but this I know, that in me they produced
a sentiment of innocence, and a sentiment of paradise.
I felt sometimes as if I could have wasted ages in this sort
of gratification.
As the executor of their father, my daughters received
me with every mark of respect; but, after having already
protracted my visit to them for the space of many days, I
felt that I should be guilty of something alike hostile to
their decorum and reputation, if I did not speedily bring it
to a termination. I was a person unknown and almost
without a name; nor could it be proper for a young woman
to continue to receive the visits of a person of her own age
and a different sex, upon the intimate and confidential
footing upon which my visits were paid, except in the case
of him whom she intends to make her husband. To considerations
of this sort I was obliged to sacrifice the gratifications
in which I had lately been indulging. My principal
concern at St. Leon, from the time in which madame
Chabot had communicated to me the real nature of my
daughter’s situation, was to remove those disadvantages in[366]
which my destiny and my errors had involved them: it
would therefore have been the extreme of inconsistency in
me, while I was healing one mischief, to prepare for them
another. It is not indeed probable that I should long have
been contented for myself with this anomalous and neutral
situation, in which I more resembled a piece of furniture
endowed with the faculty of noting the sensations of those
around me, than the member of any human society. It
was high time, as I thought, even in this point of view,
that I should put an end to the inglorious scene, should appear
in some real character, and engage in some real undertaking.
Influenced by these considerations, I now quitted the residence
of my daughters. I had satisfied the longing curiosity
of a father, had seen their situation, had witnessed
their beauty, their accomplishments, and their virtues. If
I had been afflicted at hearing of the premature fate of my
eldest daughter, if I had been agonised by the reflection
that I might justly regard myself as her murderer, who was
so fitted to suffer this anguish as myself? The outcast of my
species, what right had I to expect to be happy in my own
person, or prosperous in any of my relations? The guilty
cause of all this mischief, it was but suitable that it should
be brought home to my own bosom, that it should tear and
distract my own brain! Add to this, I was not without a
hope that my journey would not be found useless to the
survivors. By furnishing to them the proper documents to
certify the death of their father, I flattered myself that I
had cut them off more effectually than before from all connection
with my unpropitious destiny, and had placed them
nearly upon a footing with the other noble and unmarried
heiresses of their native country. I have nothing further
to relate in regard to these two amiable and excellent sisters.
From the time that I quitted St. Leon upon this occasion,
to the time in which I am now writing, the opportunity of
making further enquiries respecting them has not occurred
to me. If ever it does occur, I have only this one wish to
entertain, which, if granted, will, I am sure, satisfy my
fondest hopes,—May I find they have been as happy, as
they so well deserve to be!
[367]
The parting between me and my daughters was not an
unaffecting one. On my part, whose bosom was fraught
with a thousand tender feelings, to which I could give no
language, and of which those whom they principally concerned
had not the slightest suspicion, it could not be unaffecting.
Nor did Louisa and her younger sister look with
an indifferent eye upon the bearer of the last sentiments of
their father, the witness of his death, the executor of his
will. There was something in the features of my countenance,
a peculiar sort of conformation, a family resemblance
to themselves, which it is probable they did not advert to,
but which I am persuaded wrought within them to the full
extent of the mysterious sympathies of our nature. I pretended
to have been the familiar confident of their father; I
told them of things at which they started and almost blushed
to think that any one beyond the circuit of their dearest
relations should have been privy. In the hour of our separation,
they shed many tears, and embraced me with a
warmth that might have well become sisters to a brother.
Yet, shall I confess my weakness, a weakness in which I
do not apprehend myself to be singular? It happens to
few men to witness the manner in which the story of their
own deaths is received. If it did, I believe we all of us
have enough of vanity and personal feeling, however sincere
a grief might show itself in the demeanour of survivors, to
find it falling short of our appetites and demand. This I
know, I was myself a party to this unreasonableness. My
daughters received the intelligence of my death with a decorum
and sensibility, which in the eyes of every impartial
spectator would have reflected honour on their characters,
a sensibility beyond what could have been imagined in
daughters who now had not seen their father for twelve
years. Yet it was an unpleasing reflection to me, thus to
have occasion to gauge their love, and to say, This is the
exact measure of their affection. I remained in this part of
the world long enough to see my children consoled, and
myself forgotten. Self-importance of man, upon how slight
a basis do thy gigantic erections repose!

[368]</div></body></text></TEI>