<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="121">CHAPTER VII.
The Progress of Ichthyology.
IF it had been already
observed and admitted that sciences of the same kind follow, and must
follow, the same course in the order of their development, it would be
unnecessary to give a history of any special branch of Systematic
Zoology; since botany has already afforded us a sufficient example of
the progress of the classificatory sciences. But we may be excused for
introducing a sketch of the advance of one department of zoology,
since we are led to the attempt by the peculiar advantage we possess
in having a complete history of the subject written with great care,
and brought up to the present time, by a naturalist of unequalled
talents and knowledge. I speak of Cuvier’s Historical View of
Ichthyology, which forms the first chapter of his great work on
that part of natural history. The place and office in the progress of
this science, which is assigned to each person by Cuvier, will
probably not be lightly contested. It will, therefore, be no small
confirmation of the justice of the views on which the 420 distribution of the
events in the history of botany was founded, if Cuvier’s
representation of the history of ichthyology offers to us obviously a
distribution almost identical.
We shall find that this is so;—that we have, in zoology as in
botany, a period of unsystematic knowledge; a period of misapplied
erudition; an epoch of the discovery of fixed characters; a period in
which many systems were put forward; a struggle of an artificial and a
natural method; and a gradual tendency of the natural method to a
manifestly physiological character. A few references to Cuvier’s
history will enable us to illustrate these and other analogies.
Period of Unsystematic Knowledge.—It would be easy to
collect a number of the fabulous stories of early times, which formed
a portion of the imaginary knowledge of men concerning animals as well
as plants. But passing over these, we come to a long period and a
great collection of writers, who, in various ways, and with various
degrees of merit, contributed to augment the knowledge which existed
concerning fish, while as yet there was hardly ever any attempt at a
classification of that province of the animal kingdom. Among these
writers, Aristotle is by far the most important. Indeed he carried on
his zoological researches under advantages which rarely fall to the
lot of the naturalist; if it be true, as Athenæus and Pliny state,140 that Alexander gave him sums which
amounted to nine hundred talents, to enable him to collect materials
for his history of animals, and put at his disposal several thousands
of men to be employed in hunting, fishing, and procuring information
for him. The works of his on Natural History which remain to us are,
nine Books Of the History of Animals; four, On the Parts of
Animals; five, On the Generation of Animals; one, On the
Going of Animals; one, Of the Sensations, and the Organs of
them; one, On Sleeping and Waking; one, On the Motion of
Animals; one, On the Length and Shortness of Life; one,
On Youth and Old Age; one, On Life and Death; one, On
Respiration. The knowledge of the external and internal
conformation of animals, their habits, instincts, and uses, which
Aristotle displays in these works, is spoken of as something wonderful
even to the naturalists of our own time. And he may be taken as a
sufficient representative of the whole of the period of which we
speak; for he is, says Cuvier,141 not only the
first, but the only one of the ancients who has treated of the natural
history of fishes (the province to which 421 we now confine ourselves,) in a
scientific point of view, and in a way which shows genius.
140 Cuv. Hist. Nat. des
Poissons, i. 13.
141 Cuv. p. 18.
We may pass over, therefore, the other ancient authors from whose
writings Cuvier, with great learning and sagacity, has levied
contributions to the history of ichthyology; as Theophrastus, Ovid,
Pliny, Oppian, Athenæus, Ælian, Ausonius, Galen. We may, too, leave
unnoticed the compilers of the middle ages, who did little but
abstract and disfigure the portions of natural history which they
found in the ancients. Ichthyological, like other knowledge, was
scarcely sought except in books, and on that very account was not
understood when it was found.
Period of Erudition.—Better times at length came, and
men began to observe nature for themselves. The three great authors
who are held to be the founders of modern ichthyology, appeared in the
middle of the sixteenth century; these were Bélon, Rondelet, and
Salviani, who all published about 1555. All the three, very different
from the compilers who filled the interval from Aristotle to them,
themselves saw and examined the fishes which they describe, and have
given faithful representations of them. But, resembling in that
respect the founders of modern botany, Briassavola, Ruellius, Tragus,
and others, they resembled them in this also, that they attempted to
make their own observations a commentary upon the ancient writers.
Faithful to the spirit of their time, they are far more careful to
make out the names which each fish bore in the ancient world, and to
bring together scraps of their history from the authors in whom these
names occur, than to describe them in a lucid manner; so that without
their figures, says Cuvier, it would be almost as difficult to
discover their species as those of the ancients.
The difficulty of describing and naming species so that they can be
recognized, is little appreciated at first, although it is in reality
the main-spring of the progress of the sciences of classification.
Aristotle never dreamt that the nomenclature which was in use in his
time could ever become obscure;142 hence he has
taken no precaution to enable his readers to recognize the species of
which he speaks; and in him and in other ancient authors, it requires
much labor and great felicity of divination to determine what the
names mean. The perception of this difficulty among modern naturalists
led to systems, and to nomenclature founded upon system; but these did
not come into 422
being immediately at the time of which we speak; nor till the evil had
grown to a more inconvenient magnitude.
142 Cuvier, p. 17.
Period of Accumulation of Materials. Exotic
Collections.—The fishes of Europe were for some time the
principal objects of study; but those of distant regions soon came
into notice.143 In the seventeenth century the Dutch
conquered Brazil, and George Margrave, employed by them, described the
natural productions of the country, and especially the fishes.
Bontius, in like manner, described some of those of Batavia. Thus
these writers correspond to Romphius and Rheede in the history of
botany. Many others might be mentioned; but we must hasten to the
formation of systems, which is our main object of attention.
143 Cuv. p. 43.
Epoch of the Fixation of Characters. Ray and
Willoughby.—In botany, as we have seen, though Ray was one
of the first who invented a connected system, he was preceded at a
considerable interval by Cæsalpinus, who had given a genuine solution
of the same problem. It is not difficult to assign reasons why a sound
classification should be discovered for plants at an earlier period
than for fishes. The vastly greater number of the known species, and
the facilities which belong to the study of vegetables, give the
botanist a great advantage; and there are numerical relations of a
most definite kind (for instance, the number of parts of the
seed-vessel employed by Cæsalpinus as one of the bases of his system),
which are tolerably obvious in plants, but which are not easily
discovered in animals. And thus we find that in ichthyology, Ray, with
his pupil and friend Willoughby, appears as the first founder of a
tenable system.144
144 Francisci Willoughbeii,
Armigeri, de Historia Piscium, libri iv. jussu et sumptibus
Societatis Regiæ Londinensis editi, &c. Totum opus recognovit,
coaptavit, supplevit, librum etiam primum et secundum adjecit Joh.
Raius. Oxford, 1668.
The first great division in this system is into
cartilaginous and bony fishes; a primary division, which
had been recognized by Aristotle, and is retained by Cuvier in his
latest labors. The subdivisions are determined by the general form of
the fish (as long or flat), by the teeth, the presence or absence of
ventral fins, the number of dorsal fins, and the nature of the spines
of the fins, as soft or prickly. Most of these characters have
preserved their importance in later systems; especially the last,
which, under the terms malacopterygian and
acanthopterygian, holds a place in the best recent
arrangements. 423
That this system was a true first approximation to a solution of
the problem, appears to be allowed by naturalists. Although, says
Cuvier,145 there are in it no genera well defined
and well limited, still in many places the species are brought
together very naturally, and in such a way that a few words of
explanation would suffice to form, from the groups thus presented to
us, several of the genera which have since been received. Even in
botany, as we have seen, genera were hardly maintained with any degree
of precision, till the binary nomenclature of Linnæus made this
division a matter of such immense convenience.
145 Cuvier, p. 57.
The amount of this convenience, the value of a brief and sure
nomenclature, had not yet been duly estimated. The work of Willoughby
forms an epoch,146 and a happy epoch, in the history of
ichthyology; for the science, once systematized, could distinguish the
new from the old, arrange methodically, describe clearly. Yet, because
Willoughby had no nomenclature of his own, and no fixed names for his
genera, his immediate influence was not great. I will not attempt to
trace this influence in succeeding authors, but proceed to the next
important step in the progress of system.
146 p. 58.
Improvement of the System. Artedi.—Peter Artedi was a
countryman and intimate friend of Linnæus; and rendered to ichthyology
nearly the same services which Linnæus rendered to botany. In his
Philosophia Ichthyologica, he analysed147 all the
interior and exterior parts of animals; he created a precise
terminology for the different forms of which these parts are
susceptible; he laid down rules for the nomenclature of genera and
species; besides his improvements of the subdivisions of the class. It
is impossible not to be struck with the close resemblance between
these steps, and those which are due to the Fundamenta
Botanica. The latter work appeared in 1736, the former was
published by Linnæus, after the death of the author, in 1738; but
Linnæus had already, as early as 1735, made use of Artedi’s
manuscripts in the ichthyological part of his Systema Naturæ.
We cannot doubt that the two young naturalists (they were nearly of
the same age), must have had a great influence upon each other’s views
and labors; and it would be difficult now to ascertain what portion of
the peculiar merits of the Linnæan reform was derived from Artedi. But
we may remark that, in ichthyology at least, Artedi appears to have
been a naturalist of more original views and profounder philosophy
than his friend and editor, who afterwards himself took up the
subject. 424 The
reforms of Linnæus, in all parts of natural history, appear as if they
were mainly dictated by a love of elegance, symmetry, clearness, and
definiteness; but the improvement of the ichthyological system by
Artedi seems to have been a step in the progress to a natural
arrangement. His genera,148 which are
forty-five in number, are so well constituted, that they have almost
all been preserved; and the subdivisions which the
constantly-increasing number of species has compelled his successors
to introduce, have very rarely been such that they have led to the
transposition of his genera.
147 p. 20.
148 Cuvier, p. 71.
In its bases, however, Artedi’s was an artificial system. His
characters were positive and decisive, founded in general upon the
number of rays of the membrane of the gills, of which he was the first
to mark the importance;—upon the relative position of the fins,
upon their number, upon the part of the mouth where the teeth are
found, upon the conformation of the scales. Yet, in some cases, he has
recourse to the interior anatomy.
Linnæus himself at first did not venture to deviate from the
footsteps of a friend, who, in this science, had been his master. But
in 1758, in the tenth edition of the Systema Naturæ, he chose
to depend upon himself and devised a new ichthyological method. He
divided some genera, united others, gave to the species trivial names
and characteristic phrases, and added many species to those of Artedi.
Yet his innovations are for the most part disapproved of by Cuvier; as
his transferring the chondropterygian fishes of Artedi to the
class of reptiles, under the title of Amphybia nantes; and his
rejecting the distinction of acanthopterygian and malacopterygian,
which, as we have seen, had prevailed from the time of Willoughby, and
introducing in its stead a distribution founded on the presence or
absence of the ventral fins, and on their situation with regard to the
pectoral fins. “Nothing,” says Cuvier, “more breaks the true
connexions of genera than these orders of apodes,
jugulares, thoracici, and abdominales.”
Thus Linnæus, though acknowledging the value and importance of
natural orders, was not happy in his attempts to construct a system
which should lead to them. In his detection of good characters for an
artificial system he was more fortunate. He was always attentive to
number, as a character; and he had the very great merit149 of introducing into the classification
the number of rays of the fins of each species. This mark is one of
great importance and use. And this, as well as 425 other branches of
natural history, derived incalculable advantages from the more general
merits of the illustrious Swede;150—the
precision of the characters, the convenience of a well-settled
terminology, the facility afforded by the binary nomenclature. These
recommendations gave him a pre-eminence which was acknowledged by
almost all the naturalists of his time, and displayed by the almost
universal adoption of his nomenclature, in zoology, as well as in
botany; and by the almost exclusive employment of his distributions of
classes, however imperfect and artificial they might be.
149 p. 74.
150 Cuvier, p. 85.
And even151 if Linnæus had had no other merit than
the impulse he gave to the pursuit of natural science, this alone
would suffice to immortalize his name. In rendering natural history
easy, or at least in making it appear so, he diffused a general taste
for it. The great took it up with interest; the young, full of ardor,
rushed forwards in all directions, with the sole intention of
completing his system. The civilized world was eager to build the
edifice which Linnæus had planned.
151 Ib. p. 88.
This spirit, among other results, produced voyages of natural
historical research, sent forth by nations and sovereigns. George the
Third of England had the honor of setting the example in this noble
career, by sending out the expeditions of Byron, Wallis, and Carteret,
in 1765. These were followed by those of Bougainville, Cook, Forster,
and others. Russia also scattered several scientific expeditions
through her vast dominions; and pupils of Linnæus sought the icy
shores of Greenland and Iceland, in order to apply his nomenclature to
the productions of those climes. But we need not attempt to convey any
idea of the vast stores of natural historical treasures which were
thus collected from every part of the globe.
I shall not endeavor to follow Cuvier in giving an account of the
great works of natural history to which this accumulation of materials
gave rise; such as the magnificent work of Bloch on Fishes, which
appeared in 1782–1785; nor need I attempt, by his assistance, to
characterize or place in their due position the several systems of
classification proposed about this time. But in the course of these
various essays, the distinction of the artificial and natural methods
of classification came more clearly into view than before; and this is
a point so important to the philosophy of the subject, that we must
devote a few words to it. 426
Separation of the Artificial and Natural Methods in
Ichthyology.—It has already been said that all so-called
artificial methods of classification must be natural, at least
as to the narrowest members of the system; thus the artificial Linnæan
method is natural as to species, and even as to genera. And on the
other hand, all proposed natural methods, so long as they remain
unmodified, are artificial as to their characteristic marks. Thus a
Natural Method is an attempt to provide positive and distinct
characters for the wider as well as for the narrower
natural groups. These considerations are applicable to
zoology as well as to botany. But the question, how we know natural
groups before we find marks for them, was, in botany, as we have seen,
susceptible only of vague and obscure answers:—the mind forms
them, it was said, by taking the aggregate of all the characters; or
by establishing a subordination of characters. And each of these
answers had its difficulty, of which the solution appeared to be, that
in attempting to form natural orders we are really guided by a latent
undeveloped estimate of physiological relations. Now this principle,
which was so dimly seen in the study of vegetables, shines out with
much greater clearness when we come to the study of animals, in which
the physiological relations of the parts are so manifest that they
cannot be overlooked, and have so strong an attraction for our
curiosity that we cannot help having our judgments influenced by them.
Hence the superiority of natural systems in zoology would probably be
far more generally allowed than in botany; and no arrangement of
animals which, in a large number of instances, violated strong and
clear natural affinities, would be tolerated because it answered the
purpose of enabling us easily to find the name and place of the animal
in the artificial system. Every system of zoological arrangement may
be supposed to aspire to be a natural system. But according to the
various habits of the minds of systematizers, this object was pursued
more or less steadily and successfully; and these differences came
more and more into view with the increase of knowledge and the
multiplication of attempts.
Bloch, whose ichthyological labors have been mentioned, followed in
his great work the method of Linnæus. But towards the end of his life
he had prepared a general system, founded upon one single numerical
principle;—the number of fins; just as the sexual system of
Linnæus is founded upon the number of stamina; and he made his
subdivisions according to the position of the ventral and pectoral
fins; the same character which Linnæus had employed for his primary
427 division. He
could not have done better, says Cuvier,152 if his object
had been to turn into ridicule all artificial methods, and to show to
what absurd combinations they may lead.
152 p. 108.
Cuvier himself who always pursued natural systems with a singularly
wise and sagacious consistency, attempted to improve the
ichthyological arrangements which had been proposed before him. In his
Règne Animal, published in 1817, he attempts the problem of
arranging this class; and the views suggested to him, both by his
successes and his failures, are so instructive and philosophical, that
I cannot illustrate the subject better than by citing some of
them.
“The class of fishes,” he says,153 “is, of all,
that which offers the greatest difficulties, when we wish to subdivide
it into orders, according to fixed and obvious characters. After many
trials, I have determined on the following distribution, which in some
instances is wanting in precision, but which possesses the advantage
of keeping the natural families entire.
153 Règne Animal, vol. ii. p.
110.
“Fish form two distinct series;—that of
chondropterygians or cartilaginous fish, and that of
fish properly so called.
“The first of these series has for its character, that the
palatine bones replace, in it, the bones of the upper jaw: moreover
the whole of its structure has evident analogies, which we shall
explain.
“It divides itself into three orders:
“The Cyclostomes, in which the jaws are
soldered (soudées) into an immovable ring, and the bronchiæ are
open in numerous holes.
“The Selacians, which have the bronchiæ
like the preceding, but not the jaws.
“The Sturonians, in which the bronchiæ are
open as usual by a slit furnished with an operculum.
“The second series, or that of ordinary fishes, offers me,
in the first place, a primary division, into those of which the
maxillary bone and the palatine arch are dovetailed (engrenés)
to the skull. Of these I make an order of Pectognaths, divided into two families; the
gymnodonts and the scleroderms.
“After these I have the fishes with complete jaws, but with
bronchiæ which, instead of having the form of combs, as in all the
others, have the form of a series of little tufts (houppes). Of
these I again form an order, which I call Lophobranchs, which only includes one family. 428
“There then remains an innumerable quantity of fishes, to which we
can no longer apply any characters except those of the exterior organs
of motion. After long examination, I have found that the least bad of
these characters is, after all, that employed by Ray and Artedi, taken
from the nature of the first rays of the dorsal and of the anal fin.
Thus ordinary fishes are divided into Malacopterygians, of which all the rays are soft,
except sometimes the first of the dorsal fin or the
pectorals;—and Acanthopterygians, which
have always the first portion of the dorsal, or of the first dorsal
when there are two, supported by spinous rays, and in which the anal
has also some such rays, and the ventrals, at least, each one.
“The former may be subdivided without inconvenience, according to
their ventral fins, which are sometimes situate behind the abdomen,
sometimes adherent to the apparatus of the shoulder, or, finally, are
sometimes wanting altogether.
“We thus arrive at the three orders of Abdominal
Malacopterygians, of Subbrachians, and
of Apodes; each of which includes some natural
families which we shall explain: the first, especially, is very
numerous.
“But this basis of division is absolutely impracticable with the
Acanthopterygians; and the problem of establishing among these any
other subdivision than that of the natural families has hitherto
remained for me insoluble. Fortunately several of these families offer
characters almost as precise as those which we could give to true
orders.
“In truth, we cannot assign to the families of fishes, ranks as
marked, as for example, to those of mammifers. Thus the
Chondropterygians on the one hand hold to reptiles by the organs of
the senses, and by those of generation in some; and they are related
to mollusks and worms by the imperfection of the skeleton in
others.
“As to Ordinary Fishes, if any part of the organization is found
more developed in some than in others, there does not result from this
any pre-eminence sufficiently marked, or of sufficient influence upon
their whole system, to oblige us to consult it in the methodical
arrangement.
“We shall place them, therefore, nearly in the order in which we
have just explained their characters.”
I have extracted the whole of this passage, because, though it is
too technical to be understood in detail by the general reader, those
who have followed with any interest the history of the attempts at a
natural classification in any department in nature, will see here a
fine example of the problems which such attempts propose, of the 429 difficulties which it
may present, and of the reasonings, labors, cautions, and varied
resources, by means of which its solution is sought, when a great
philosophical naturalist girds himself to the task. We see here, most
instructively, how different the endeavor to frame such a natural
system, is from the procedure of an artificial system, which carries
imperatively through the whole of a class of organized beings, a
system of marks either arbitrary, or conformable to natural affinities
in a partial degree. And we have not often the advantage of having the
reasons for a systematic arrangement so clearly and fully indicated,
as is done here, and in the descriptions of the separate orders.
This arrangement Cuvier adhered to in all its main points, both in
the second edition of the Règne Animal, published in 1821, and
in his Histoire Naturelle des Poissons, of which the first
volume was published in 1828, but which unfortunately was not
completed at the time of his death. It may be supposed, therefore, to
be in accordance with those views of zoological philosophy, which it
was the business of his life to form and to apply; and in a work like
the present, where, upon so large a question of natural history, we
must be directed in a great measure by the analogy of the history of
science, and by the judgments which seem most to have the character of
wisdom, we appear to be justified in taking Cuvier’s ichthyological
system as the nearest approach which has yet been made to a natural
method in that department.
The true natural method is only one: artificial methods, and even
good ones, there may be many, as we have seen in botany; and each of
these may have its advantages for some particular use. On some methods
of this kind, on which naturalists themselves have hardly yet had time
to form a stable and distinct opinion, it is not our office to decide.
But judging, as I have already said, from the general analogy of the
natural sciences, I find it difficult to conceive that the
ichthyological method of M. Agassiz, recently propounded with an
especial reference to fossil fishes, can be otherwise than an
artificial method. It is founded entirely on one part of the animal,
its scaly covering, and even on a single scale. It does not conform to
that which almost all systematic ichthyologists hitherto have
considered as a permanent natural distinction of a high order; the
distinction of bony and cartilaginous fishes; for it is stated that
each order contains examples of both.154 I do not know
what general anatomical or physiological 430 truths it brings into view; but they
ought to be very important and striking ones, to entitle them to
supersede those which led Cuvier to his system. To this I may add,
that the new ichthyological classification does not seem to form, as
we should expect that any great advance towards a natural system would
form, a connected sequel to the past history of ichthyology;—a
step to which anterior discoveries and improvements have led, and in
which they are retained.
154 Dr. Buckland’s Bridgewater
Treatise, p. 270.
But notwithstanding these considerations, the method of M. Agassiz
has probably very great advantages for his purpose; for in the case of
fossil fish, the parts which are the basis of his system often remain,
when even the skeleton is gone. And we may here again refer to a
principle of the classificatory sciences which we cannot make too
prominent;—all arrangements and nomenclatures are good, which
enable us to assert general propositions. Tried by this test, we
cannot fail to set a high value on the arrangement of M. Agassiz; for
propositions of the most striking generality respecting fossil remains
of fish, of which geologists before had never dreamt, are enunciated
by means of his groups and names. Thus only the two first orders, the
Placoïdians and Ganoïdians, existed before the
commencement of the cretaceous formation: the third and fourth orders,
the Ctenoïdians and Cycloïdians, which contain
three-fourths of the eight thousand known species of living Fishes,
appear for the first time in the cretaceous formation: and other
geological relations of these orders, no less remarkable, have been
ascertained by M. Agassiz.
But we have now, I trust, pursued these sciences of classification
sufficiently far; and it is time for us to enter upon that higher
domain of Physiology to which, as we have said. Zoology so
irresistibly directs us.
[2nd Ed.] [I have retained the remarks which I ventured at first to
make on the System of M. Agassiz; but I believe the opinion of the
most philosophical ichthyologists to be that Cuvier’s System was too
exclusively based on the internal skeleton, as Agassiz’s was on the
external skeleton. In some degree both systems have been superseded,
while all that was true in each has been retained. Mr. Owen, in his
Lectures on Vertebrata (1846), takes Cuvierian characters from
the endo-skeleton, Agassizian ones from the exo-skeleton, Linnæan ones
from the ventral fins, Müllerian ones from the air-bladder, and
combines them by the light of his own researches, with the view of
forming a system more truly natural than any preceding one.
As I have said above, naturalists, in their progress towards a
Natural 431 System,
are guided by physiological relations, latently in Botany, but
conspicuously in Zoology. From the epoch of Cuvier’s Règne
Animal, the progress of Systematic Zoology is inseparably
dependent on the progress of Comparative Anatomy. Hence I have placed
Cuvier’s Classification of animal forms in the next Book, which treats
of Physiology.]


BOOK XVII.

ORGANICAL SCIENCES.

HISTORY OF PHYSIOLOGY
AND
COMPARATIVE ANATOMY.

Fearful and wondrous is the skill which
moulds
  Our body’s vital plan,
And from the first dim hidden germ unfolds
  The perfect limbs of man.
Who, who can pierce the secret? tell us how
  Something is drawn from naught,
Life from the inert mass? Who, Lord! but
thou,
  Whose hand the whole has wrought?
Of this corporeal substance, still to be,
  Thine eye a survey took;
And all my members, yet unformed by thee,
  Were written in thy book.
Psalm cxxxix.
13–16.   

</div></body></text></TEI>