<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="77">CHAPTER II.
The Laws of Changes occasioned by Heat.

Sect. 1.—Expansion by Heat.—The
Law of Dalton and Gay-Lussac for Gases.
ALMOST all bodies expand by
heat; solids, as metals, in a small degree; fluids, as water, oil,
alcohol, mercury, in a greater degree. This was one of the facts first
examined by those who studied the nature of heat, because this
property was used for the measure of heat. In the Philosophy of the
Inductive Sciences, Book iv., Chap. iv., I have stated that
secondary qualities, such as Heat, must be measured by their effects:
and in Sect. 4 of that Chapter I have given an account of the
successive attempts which have been made to obtain measures of heat. I
have there also spoken of the results which were obtained by comparing
the rate at which the expansion of different substances went on, under
the same degrees of heat; or as it was called, the different
thermometrical march of each substance. Mercury appears to be
the liquid which is most uniform in its thermometrical march; and it
has been taken as the most common material of our thermometers; but
the expansion of mercury is not proportional to the heat. De Luc was
led, by his experiments, to conclude “that the dilatations of mercury
follow an accelerated march for equal augmentations of heat.” Dalton
conjectured that water and mercury both expand as the square of the
real temperature from the point of greatest contraction: the
real temperature being measured so as to lead to such a result. But
none of the rules thus laid down for the expansion of solids and
fluids appear to have led, as yet, to any certain general laws.
With regard to gases, thermotical inquirers have been more
successful. Gases expand by heat; and their expansion is governed by a
law which applies alike to all degrees of heat, and to all gaseous
fluids. The law is this: that for equal increments of temperature
they expand by the same fraction of their own bulk; which fraction
is three-eights 158 in proceeding from freezing to boiling
water. This law was discovered by Dalton and M. Gay-Lussac
independently of each other;32 and is usually
called by both their names, the law of Dalton and Gay-Lussac.
The latter says,33 “The experiments which I have
described, and which have been made with great care, prove
incontestably that oxygen, hydrogen, azotic acid, nitrous acid,
ammoniacal acid, muriatic acid, sulphurous acid, carbonic acid, gases,
expand equally by equal increments of heat.” “Therefore,” he adds with
a proper inductive generalization, “the result does not depend upon
physical properties, and I collect that all gases expand equally by
heat.” He then extends this to vapors, as ether. This must be one
of the most important foundation-stones of any sound theory of
heat.
32 Manch. Mem. vol. v. 1802;
and Ann. Chim. xliii. p. 137.
33 Ib. p. 272.
[2nd Ed.] Yet MM. Magnus and Regnault conceive that they have
overthrown this law of Dalton and Gay-Lussac, and shown that the
different gases do not expand alike for the same increment of heat.
Magnus found the ratio to be for atmospheric air, 1∙366; for hydrogen,
1∙365; for carbonic acid, 1∙369; for sulphurous-acid gas, 1∙385. But
these differences are not greater than the differences obtained for
the same substances by different observers; and as this law is
referred to in Laplace’s hypothesis, hereafter to be discussed, I do not treat
the law as disproved.
Yet that the rate of expansion of gas in certain circumstances is
different for different substances, must be deemed very probable,
after Dr. Faraday’s recent investigations On the Liquefaction and
Solidification of Bodies generally existing as Gases,34 by which it appears that the elasticity
of vapors in contact with their fluids increases at different
rates in different substances. “That the force,” he says, “of vapor
increases in a geometrical ratio for equal increments of heat is true
for all bodies, but the ratio is not the same for all. . . . For an
increase of pressure from two to six atmospheres, the following number
of degrees require to be added to the bodies named:—water 69°,
sulphureous acid 63°, cyanogen 64°∙5, ammonia 60°, arseniuretted
hydrogen 54°, sulphuretted hydrogen 56°∙5, muriatic acid 43°, carbonic
acid 32°∙5, nitrous oxide 30°.”]
34 Phil. Trans. 1845, Pt.
1.
We have already seen that the opinion that
the air-thermometer is a true measure of heat, is strongly
countenanced by the symmetry which, by using it, we introduce into the
laws of radiation. If we 159 accept the law of Dalton and Gay-Lussac,
it follows that this result is independent of any peculiar properties
in the air employed; and thus this measure has an additional character
of generality and simplicity which make it still more probable that it
is the true standard. This opinion is further supported by the
attempts to include such facts in a theory; but before we can treat of
such theories, we must speak of some other doctrines which have been
introduced.
Sect. 2.—Specific Heat.—Change of
Consistence.
In the attempts to obtain
measures of heat, it was found that bodies had different capacities
for heat; for the same quantity of heat, however measured, would
raise, in different degrees, the temperature of different substances.
The notion of different capacities for heat was thus introduced, and
each body was thus assumed to have a specific capacity for
heat, according to the quantity of heat which it required to raise
it through a given scale of heat.35 The term
“capacity for heat” was introduced by Dr. Irvine, a pupil of Dr.
Black. For this term, Wilcke, the Swedish physicist, substituted
“specific heat;” in analogy with “specific gravity.”
35 See Crawford, On Heat, for
the History of Specific Heat.
It was found, also, that the capacity of the same substance was
different in the same substance at different temperatures. It appears
from experiments of MM. Dulong and Petit, that, in general, the
capacity of liquids and solids increases as we ascend in the scale of
temperature.
But one of the most important thermotic facts is, that by the
sudden contraction of any mass, its temperature is increased. This is
peculiarly observable in gases, as, for example, common air. The
amount of the increase of temperature by sudden condensation, or of
the cold produced by sudden rarefaction, is an important datum,
determining the velocity of sound, as we have already seen, and affecting many points of
meteorology. The coefficient which enters the calculation in the
former case depends on the ratio of two specific heats of air under
different conditions; one belonging to it when, varying in density,
the pressure is constant by which the air is contained; the other,
when, varying in density, it is contained in a constant space.
A leading fact, also, with regard to the operation of heat on
bodies 160 is, that
it changes their form, as it is often called, that is, their
condition as solid, liquid, or air. Since the term “form” is employed
in too many and various senses to be immediately understood when it is
intended to convey this peculiar meaning, I shall use, instead of it,
the term consistence, and shall hope to be excused, even when I
apply this word to gases, though I must acknowledge such phraseology
to be unusual. Thus there is a change of consistence when solids
become liquid, or liquids gaseous; and the laws of such changes must
be fundamental facts of our thermotical theories. We are still in the
dark as to many of the laws which belong to this change; but one of
them, of great importance, has been discovered, and to that we must
now proceed.
Sect. 3.—The Doctrine of Latent Heat.
The Doctrine of Latent Heat
refers to such changes of consistence as we have just spoken of. It is
to this effect; that during the conversion of solids into liquids, or
of liquids into vapors, there is communicated to the body heat which
is not indicated by the thermometer. The heat is absorbed, or becomes
latent; and, on the other hand, on the condensation of the
vapor to a liquid, or the liquid to a solid consistency, this heat is
again given out and becomes sensible. Thus a pound of ice requires
twenty times as long a time, in a warm room, to raise its temperature
seven degrees, as a pound of ice-cold water does. A kettle placed on a
fire, in four minutes had its temperature raised to the boiling point,
212°: and this temperature continued stationary for twenty minutes,
when the whole was boiled away. Dr. Black inferred from these facts
that a large quantity of heat is absorbed by the ice in becoming
water, and by the water in becoming steam. He reckoned from the above
experiments, that ice, in melting, absorbs as much heat as would raise
ice-cold water through 140° of temperature: and that water, in
evaporating, absorbs as much heat as would raise it through 940°.
That snow requires a great quantity of heat to melt it; that water
requires a great quantity of heat to convert it into steam; and that
this heat is not indicated by a rise in the thermometer, are facts
which it is not difficult to observe; but to separate these from all
extraneous conditions, to group the cases together, and to seize upon
the general law by which they are connected, was an effort of
inductive insight, which has been considered, and deservedly, as one
of the most striking 161 events in the modern history of physics.
Of this step the principal merit appears to belong to Black.
[2nd Ed.] [In the first edition I had mentioned the names of De Luc
and of Wilcke, in connexion with the discovery of Latent Heat, along
with the name of Black. De Luc had observed, in 1755, that ice, in
melting, did not rise above the freezing-point of temperature till the
whole was melted. De Luc has been charged with plagiarizing Black’s
discovery, but, I think, without any just ground. In his Idées sur
la Météorologique (1787), he spoke of Dr. Black as “the first who
had attempted the determinations of the quantities of latent heat.”
And when Mr. Watt pointed out to him that from this expression it
might be supposed that Black had not discovered the fact itself, he
acquiesced, and redressed the equivocal expression in an Appendix to
the volume.36
36 See his Letter to the
Editors of the Edinburgh Review, No. xii. p. 502, of the
Review.
Black never published his own account of the doctrine of Latent
Heat: but he delivered it every year after 1760 in his Lectures. In
1770, a surreptitious publication of his Lectures was made by a London
bookseller, and this gave a view of the leading points of Dr. Black’s
doctrine. In 1772, Wilcke, of Stockholm, read a paper to the Royal
Society of that city, in which the absorption of heat by melting ice
is described; and in the same year, De Luc of Geneva published his
Recherches sur les Modifications de l’Atmosphère, which has
been alleged to contain the doctrine of latent heat, and which the
author asserts to have been written in ignorance of what Black had
done. At a later period, De Luc, adopting, in part. Black’s
expression, gave the name of latent fire to the heat
absorbed.37
37 See Ed. Rev. No. vi. p.
20.
It appears that Cavendish determined the amount of heat produced by
condensing steam, and by thawing snow, as early as 1765. He had
perhaps already heard something of Black’s investigations, but did not
accept his term “latent heat”.38]
38 See Mr. V. Harcourt’s
Address to the Brit. Assoc. in 1839, and the
Appendix.
The consequences of Black’s principle are very important, for upon
it is founded the whole doctrine of evaporation; besides which, the
principle of latent heat has other applications. But the relations of
aqueous vapor to air are so important, and have been so long a 162 subject of
speculation, that we may with advantage dwell a little upon them. The
part of science in which this is done may be called, as we have said,
Atmology; and to that division of Thermotics the following chapters
belong.


ATMOLOGY.
</div></body></text></TEI>