<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="41">

CHAPTER XXXII.
OF TRUE AND FALSE IDEAS.

1. Truth and Falsehood properly belong to Propositions, not to Ideas.


Though truth and falsehood belong, in propriety of speech, only to
PROPOSITIONS: yet IDEAS are oftentimes termed true or false (as what words are
there that are not used with great latitude, and with some deviation from their
strict and proper significations?) Though I think that when ideas themselves
are termed true or false, there is still some secret or tacit proposition,
which is the foundation of that denomination: as we shall see, if we examine
the particular occasions wherein they come to be called true or false. In all
which we shall find some kind of affirmation or negation, which is the reason
of that denomination. For our ideas, being nothing but bare APPEARANCES, or
perceptions in our minds, cannot properly and simply in themselves be said to
be true or false, no more than a single name of anything can be said to be true
or false.


2. Ideas and words may be said to be true, inasmuch as they really are ideas
and words.


Indeed both ideas and words may be said to be true, in a metaphysical sense of
the word truth; as all other things that any way exist are said to be true,
i.e. really to be such as they exist. Though in things called true, even in
that sense, there is perhaps a secret reference to our ideas, looked upon as
the standards of that truth; which amounts to a mental proposition, though it
be usually not taken notice of.


3. No Idea, as an Appearance in the Mind, either true or false.


But it is not in that metaphysical sense of truth which we inquire here, when
we examine, whether our ideas are capable of being true or false, but in the
more ordinary acceptation of those words: and so I say that the ideas in our
minds, being only so many perceptions or appearances there, none of them are
false; the idea of a centaur having no more falsehood in it when it appears in
our minds, than the name centaur has falsehood in it, when it is pronounced by
our mouths, or written on paper. For truth or falsehood lying always in some
affirmation or negation, mental or verbal, our ideas are not capable, any of
them, of being false, till the mind passes some judgment on them; that is,
affirms or denies something of them.


4. Ideas referred to anything extraneous to them may be true or false.


Whenever the mind refers any of its ideas to anything extraneous to them, they
are then capable to be called true or false. Because the mind, in such a
reference, makes a tacit supposition of their conformity to that thing; which
supposition, as it happens to be true or false, so the ideas themselves come to
be denominated. The most usual cases wherein this happens, are these following:


5. Other Men’s Ideas; real Existence; and supposed real Essences, are what Men
usually refer their Ideas to.


First, when the mind supposes any idea it has CONFORMABLE to that in OTHER
MEN’S MINDS, called by the same common name; v.g. when the mind intends or
judges its ideas of justice, temperance, religion, to be the same with what
other men give those names to.


Secondly, when the mind supposes any idea it has in itself to be CONFORMABLE to
some REAL EXISTENCE. Thus the two ideas of a man and a centaur, supposed to be
the ideas of real substances, are the one true and the other false; the one
having a conformity to what has really existed, the other not. Thirdly, when
the mind REFERS any of its ideas to that REAL constitution and ESSENCE of
anything, whereon all its properties depend: and thus the greatest part, if not
all our ideas of substances, are false.


6. The cause of such Reference.


These suppositions the mind is very apt tacitly to make concerning its own
ideas. But yet, if we will examine it, we shall find it is chiefly, if not
only, concerning its ABSTRACT complex ideas. For the natural tendency of the
mind being towards knowledge; and finding that, if it should proceed by and
dwell upon only particular things, its progress would be very slow, and its
work endless; therefore, to shorten its way to knowledge, and make each
perception more comprehensive, the first thing it does, as the foundation of
the easier enlarging its knowledge, either by contemplation of the things
themselves that it would know, or conference with others about them, is to bind
them into bundles, and rank them so into sorts, that what knowledge it gets of
any of them it may thereby with assurance extend to all of that sort; and so
advance by larger steps in that which is its great business, knowledge. This,
as I have elsewhere shown, is the reason why we collect things under
comprehensive ideas, with names annexed to them, into genera and species; i.e.
into kinds and sorts.


7. Names of things supposed to carry in them knowledge of their essences.


If therefore we will warily attend to the motions of the mind, and observe what
course it usually takes in its way to knowledge, we shall I think find, that
the mind having got an idea which it thinks it may have use of either in
contemplation or discourse, the first thing it does is to abstract it, and then
get a name to it; and so lay it up in its storehouse, the memory, as containing
the essence of a sort of things, of which that name is always to be the mark.
Hence it is, that we may often observe that, when any one sees a new thing of a
kind that he knows not, he presently asks, what it is; meaning by that inquiry
nothing but the name. As if the name carried with it the knowledge of the
species, or the essence of it; whereof it is indeed used as the mark, and is
generally supposed annexed to it.


8. How men suppose that their ideas must correspond to things, and to the
customary meanings of names.


But this ABSTRACT IDEA, being something in the mind, between the thing that
exists, and the name that is given to it; it is in our ideas that both the
rightness of our knowledge, and the propriety and intelligibleness of our
speaking, consists. And hence it is that men are so forward to suppose, that
the abstract ideas they have in their minds are such as agree to the things
existing without them, to which they are referred; and are the same also to
which the names they give them do by the use and propriety of that language
belong. For without this double conformity of their ideas, they find they
should both think amiss of things in themselves, and talk of them
unintelligibly to others.


9. Simple Ideas may be false, in reference to others of the same Name, but are
least liable to be so.


First, then, I say, that when the truth of our ideas is judged of by the
conformity they have to the ideas which other men have, and commonly signify by
the same name, they may be any of them false. But yet SIMPLE IDEAS are least of
all liable to be so mistaken. Because a man, by his senses and every day’s
observation, may easily satisfy himself what the simple ideas are which their
several names that are in common use stand for; they being but few in number,
and such as, if he doubts or mistakes in, he may easily rectify by the objects
they are to be found in. Therefore it is seldom that any one mistakes in his
names of simple ideas, or applies the name red to the idea green, or the name
sweet to the idea bitter: much less are men apt to confound the names of ideas
belonging to different senses, and call a colour by the name of a taste,
&c. Whereby it is evident that the simple ideas they call by any name are
commonly the same that others have and mean when they use the same names.


10. Ideas of mixed Modes most liable to be false in this Sense.


Complex ideas are much more liable to be false in this respect; and the complex
ideas of MIXED MODES, much more than those of substances; because in substances
(especially those which the common and unborrowed names of any language are
applied to) some remarkable sensible qualities, serving ordinarily to
distinguish one sort from another, easily preserve those who take any care in
the use of their words, from applying them to sorts of substances to which they
do not at all belong. But in mixed modes we are much more uncertain; it being
not so easy to determine of several actions, whether they are to be called
JUSTICE or CRUELTY, LIBERALITY or PRODIGALITY. And so in referring our ideas to
those of other men, called by the same names, ours may be false; and the idea
in our minds, which we express by the word JUSTICE, may perhaps be that which
ought to have another name.


11. Or at least to be thought false.


But whether or no our ideas of mixed modes are more liable than any sort to be
different from those of other men, which are marked by the same names, this at
least is certain. That this sort of falsehood is much more familiarly
attributed to our ideas of mixed modes than to any other. When a man is thought
to have a false idea of JUSTICE, or GRATITUDE, or GLORY, it is for no other
reason, but that his agrees not with the ideas which each of those names are
the signs of in other men.


12. And why.


The reason whereof seems to me to be this: That the abstract ideas of mixed
modes, being men’s voluntary combinations of such a precise collection of
simple ideas, and so the essence of each species being made by men alone,
whereof we have no other sensible standard existing anywhere but the name
itself, or the definition of that name; we having nothing else to refer these
our ideas of mixed modes to, as a standard to which we would conform them, but
the ideas of those who are thought to use those names in their most proper
significations; and, so as our ideas conform or differ from THEM, they pass for
true or false. And thus much concerning the truth and falsehood of our ideas,
in reference to their names.


13. As referred to Real Existence, none of our Ideas can be false but those of
Substances.


Secondly, as to the truth and falsehood of our ideas, in reference to the real
existence of things. When that is made the standard of their truth, none of
them can be termed false but only our complex ideas of substances.


14. First, Simple Ideas in this Sense not false and why.


First, our simple ideas, being barely such perceptions as God has fitted us to
receive, and given power to external objects to produce in us by established
laws and ways, suitable to his wisdom and goodness, though incomprehensible to
us, their truth consists in nothing else but in such appearances as are
produced in us, and must be suitable to those powers he has placed in external
objects or else they could not be produced in us: and thus answering those
powers, they are what they should be, true ideas. Nor do they become liable to
any imputation of falsehood, if the mind (as in most men I believe it does)
judges these ideas to be in the things themselves. For God in his wisdom having
set them as marks of distinction in things, whereby we may be able to discern
one thing from another, and so choose any of them for our uses as we have
occasion; it alters not the nature of our simple idea, whether we think that
the idea of blue be in the violet itself, or in our mind only; and only the
power of producing it by the texture of its parts, reflecting the particles of
light after a certain manner, to be in the violet itself. For that texture in
the object, by a regular and constant operation producing the same idea of blue
in us, it serves us to distinguish, by our eyes, that from any other thing;
whether that distinguishing mark, as it is really in the violet, be only a
peculiar texture of parts, or else that very colour, the idea whereof (which is
in us) is the exact resemblance. And it is equally from that appearance to be
denominated blue, whether it be that real colour, or only a peculiar texture in
it, that causes in us that idea: since the name, BLUE, notes properly nothing
but that mark of distinction that is in a violet, discernible only by our eyes,
whatever it consists in; that being beyond our capacities distinctly to know,
and perhaps would be of less use to us, if we had faculties to discern.


15. Though one Man’s Idea of Blue should be different from another’s.


Neither would it carry any imputation of falsehood to our simple ideas, if by
the different structure of our organs it were so ordered, that THE SAME OBJECT
SHOULD PRODUCE IN SEVERAL MEN’S MINDS DIFFERENT IDEAS at the same time; v.g. if
the idea that a violet produced in one man’s mind by his eyes were the same
that a marigold produced in another man’s, and vice versa. For, since this
could never be known, because one man’s mind could not pass into another man’s
body, to perceive what appearances were produced by those organs; neither the
ideas hereby, nor the names, would be at all confounded, or any falsehood be in
either. For all things that had the texture of a violet, producing constantly
the idea that he called blue, and those which had the texture of a marigold,
producing constantly the idea which he as constantly called yellow, whatever
those appearances were in his mind; he would be able as regularly to
distinguish things for his use by those appearances, and understand and signify
those distinctions marked by the name blue and yellow, as if the appearances or
ideas in his mind received from those two flowers were exactly the same with
the ideas in other men’s minds. I am nevertheless very apt to think that the
sensible ideas produced by any object in different men’s minds, are most
commonly very near and undiscernibly alike. For which opinion, I think, there
might be many reasons offered: but that being besides my present business, I
shall not trouble my reader with them; but only mind him, that the contrary
supposition, if it could be proved, is of little use, either for the
improvement of our knowledge, or conveniency of life, and so we need not
trouble ourselves to examine it.


16. Simple Ideas can none of them be false in respect of real existence.


From what has been said concerning our simple ideas, I think it evident that
our simple ideas can none of them be false in respect of things existing
without us. For the truth of these appearances or perceptions in our minds
consisting, as has been said, only in their being answerable to the powers in
external objects to produce by our senses such appearances in us, and each of
them being in the mind such as it is, suitable to the power that produced it,
and which alone it represents, it cannot upon that account, or as referred to
such a pattern, be false. Blue and yellow, bitter or sweet, can never be false
ideas: these perceptions in the mind are just such as they are there, answering
the powers appointed by God to produce them; and so are truly what they are,
and are intended to be. Indeed the names may be misapplied, but that in this
respect makes no falsehood in the ideas; as if a man ignorant in the English
tongue should call purple scarlet.


17. Secondly, Modes not false cannot be false in reference to essences of
things.


Secondly, neither can our complex ideas of modes, in reference to the essence
of anything really existing, be false; because whatever complex ideas I have of
any mode, it hath no reference to any pattern existing, and made by nature; it
is not supposed to contain in it any other ideas than what it hath; nor to
represent anything but such a complication of ideas as it does. Thus, when I
have the idea of such an action of a man who forbears to afford himself such
meat, drink, and clothing, and other conveniences of life, as his riches and
estate will be sufficient to supply and his station requires, I have no false
idea; but such an one as represents an action, either as I find or imagine it,
and so is capable of neither truth nor falsehood. But when I give the name
FRUGALITY or VIRTUE to this action, then it may be called a false idea, if
thereby it be supposed to agree with that idea to which, in propriety of
speech, the name of frugality doth belong, or to be conformable to that law
which is the standard of virtue and vice.


18. Thirdly, Ideas of Substances may be false in reference to existing things.


Thirdly, our complex ideas of substances, being all referred to patterns in
things themselves, may be false. That they are all false, when looked upon as
the representations of the unknown essences of things, is so evident that there
needs nothing to be said of it. I shall therefore pass over that chimerical
supposition, and consider them as collections of simple ideas in the mind,
taken from combinations of simple ideas existing together constantly in things,
of which patterns they are the supposed copies; and in this reference of them
to the existence of things, they are false ideas:—(1) When they put
together simple ideas, which in the real existence of things have no union; as
when to the shape and size that exist together in a horse, is joined in the
same complex idea the power of barking like a dog: which three ideas, however
put together into one in the mind, were never united in nature; and this,
therefore, may be called a false idea of a horse. (2) Ideas of substances are,
in this respect, also false, when, from any collection of simple ideas that do
always exist together, there is separated, by a direct negation, any other
simple idea which is constantly joined with them. Thus, if to extension,
solidity, fusibility, the peculiar weightiness, and yellow colour of gold, any
one join in his thoughts the negation of a greater degree of fixedness than is
in lead or copper, he may be said to have a false complex idea, as well as when
he joins to those other simple ones the idea of perfect absolute fixedness. For
either way, the complex idea of gold being made up of such simple ones as have
no union in nature, may be termed false. But, if he leaves out of this his
complex idea that of fixedness quite, without either actually joining to or
separating it from the rest in his mind, it is, I think, to be looked on as an
inadequate and imperfect idea, rather than a false one; since, though it
contains not all the simple ideas that are united in nature, yet it puts none
together but what do really exist together.


19. Truth or Falsehood always supposes Affirmation or Negation.


Though, in compliance with the ordinary way of speaking, I have shown in what
sense and upon what ground our ideas may be sometimes called true or false; yet
if we will look a little nearer into the matter, in all cases where any idea is
called true or false, it is from some JUDGMENT that the mind makes, or is
supposed to make, that is true or false. For truth or falsehood, being never
without some affirmation or negation, express or tacit, it is not to be found
but where signs are joined or separated, according to the agreement or
disagreement of the things they stand for. The signs we chiefly use are either
ideas or words; wherewith we make either mental or verbal propositions. Truth
lies in so joining or separating these representatives, as the things they
stand for do in themselves agree or disagree; and falsehood in the contrary, as
shall be more fully shown hereafter.


20. Ideas in themselves neither true nor false.


Any idea, then, which we have in our minds, whether conformable or not to the
existence of things, or to any idea in the minds of other men, cannot properly
for this alone be called false. For these representations, if they have nothing
in them but what is really existing in things without, cannot be thought false,
being exact representations of something: nor yet if they have anything in them
differing from the reality of things, can they properly be said to be false
representations, or ideas of things they do not represent. But the mistake and
falsehood is:


21. But are false—1. When judged agreeable to another Man’s Idea, without
being so.


First, when the mind having any idea, it JUDGES and concludes it the same that
is in other men’s minds, signified by the same name; or that it is conformable
to the ordinary received signification or definition of that word, when indeed
it is not: which is the most usual mistake in mixed modes, though other ideas
also are liable to it.


22. Secondly, When judged to agree to real Existence, when they do not.


(2) When it having a complex idea made up of such a collection of simple ones
as nature never puts together, it JUDGES it to agree to a species of creatures
really existing; as when it joins the weight of tin to the colour, fusibility,
and fixedness of gold.


23. Thirdly, When judged adequate, without being so.


(3) When in its complex idea it has united a certain number of simple ideas
that do really exist together in some sort of creatures, but has also left out
others as much inseparable, it JUDGES this to be a perfect complete idea of a
sort of things which really it is not; v.g. having joined the ideas of
substance, yellow, malleable, most heavy, and fusible, it takes that complex
idea to be the complete idea of gold, when yet its peculiar fixedness, and
solubility in AQUA REGIA, are as inseparable from those other ideas, or
qualities, of that body as they are one from another.


24. Fourthly, When judged to represent the real Essence.


(4) The mistake is yet greater, when I JUDGE that this complex idea contains in
it the real essence of any body existing; when at least it contains but some
few of those properties which flow from its real essence and constitution. I
say only some few of those properties; for those properties consisting mostly
in the active and passive powers it has in reference to other things, all that
are vulgarly known of any one body, of which the complex idea of that kind of
things is usually made, are but a very few, in comparison of what a man that
has several ways tried and examined it knows of that one sort of things; and
all that the most expert man knows are but a few, in comparison of what are
really in that body, and depend on its internal or essential constitution. The
essence of a triangle lies in a very little compass, consists in a very few
ideas: three lines including a space make up that essence: but the properties
that flow from this essence are more than can be easily known or enumerated. So
I imagine it is in substances; their real essences lie in a little compass,
though the properties flowing from that internal constitution are endless.


25. Ideas, when called false.


To conclude, a man having no notion of anything without him, but by the idea he
has of it in his mind, (which idea he has a power to call by what name he
pleases,) he may indeed make an idea neither answering the reason of things,
nor agreeing to the idea commonly signified by other people’s words; but cannot
make a wrong or false idea of a thing which is no otherwise known to him but by
the idea he has of it: v.g. when I frame an idea of the legs, arms, and body of
a man, and join to this a horse’s head and neck, I do not make a false idea of
anything; because it represents nothing without me. But when I call it a MAN or
TARTAR, and imagine it to represent some real being without me, or to be the
same idea that others call by the same name; in either of these cases I may
err. And upon this account it is that it comes to be termed a false idea;
though indeed the falsehood lies not in the idea, but in that tacit mental
proposition, wherein a conformity and resemblance is attributed to it which it
has not. But yet, if, having framed such an idea in my mind, without thinking
either that existence, or the name MAN or TARTAR, belongs to it, I will call it
MAN or TARTAR, I may be justly thought fantastical in the naming; but not
erroneous in my judgment; nor the idea any way false.


26. More properly to be called right or wrong.


Upon the whole matter, I think that our ideas, as they are considered by the
mind,—either in reference to the proper signification of their names; or
in reference to the reality of things,—may very fitly be called RIGHT or
WRONG ideas, according as they agree or disagree to those patterns to which
they are referred. But if any one had rather call them true or false, it is fit
he use a liberty, which every one has, to call things by those names he thinks
best; though, in propriety of speech, TRUTH or FALSEHOOD will, I think, scarce
agree to them, but as they, some way or other, virtually contain in them some
mental proposition. The ideas that are in a man’s mind, simply considered,
cannot be wrong; unless complex ones, wherein inconsistent parts are jumbled
together. All other ideas are in themselves right, and the knowledge about them
right and true knowledge; but when we come to refer them to anything, as to
their patterns and archetypes then they are capable of being wrong, as far as
they disagree with such archetypes.


</div></body></text></TEI>