<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="9">
CHAPTER IX.

The Laws of Heat with respect to Water.

The manner in which heat is transmitted through
fluids is altogether different from the mode in which
it passes through solids; and hence the waters of the
earth’s surface produce peculiar effects upon its condition
as to temperature. Moreover, water is susceptible
of evaporation in a degree depending upon
the increase of heat; and in consequence of this property
it has most extensive and important functions
to discharge in the economy of nature. We will
consider some of the offices of this fluid.
1. Heat is communicated through water, not by
being conducted from one part of the fluid to another,
as in solid bodies, but (at least principally) by being
carried with the parts of the fluid by means of an intestine
motion. Water expands and becomes lighter
by heat, and, therefore, if the upper parts be cooled
below the subjacent temperature, this upper portion
will become heavier than that below, bulk for bulk,
and will descend through it, while the lower portion
rises to take the upper place. In this manner the
colder parts descend, and the warmer parts ascend
by contrary currents, and by their interchange and
mixture, reduce the whole to a temperature at least
as low as that of the surface. And this equalization
of temperature by means of such currents, is an operation
of a much more rapid nature than the slow
motion of conduction by which heat creeps through
a solid body. Hence, alternations of heat and cold,[71]
as day and night, summer and winter, produce in
water, inequalities of temperature much smaller than
those which occur in a solid body. The heat communicated
is less, for transparent fluids imbibe heat
very slowly; and the cold impressed on the surface
is soon diffused through the mass by internal circulation.
Hence it follows that the ocean, which covers so
large a portion of the earth, and affects the temperature
of the whole surface by its influence, produces
the effect of making the alternations of heat and
cold much less violent than they would be if it were
absent. The different temperatures of its upper and
lower parts produce a current which draws the seas,
and by means of the seas, the air, towards the mean
temperature. And this kind of circulation is produced,
not only between the upper and lower parts,
but also between distant tracts of the ocean. The
great Gulf Stream which rushes out of the Gulf of
Mexico, and runs across the Atlantic to the western
shores of Europe, carries with it a portion of the
tropical heat into northern regions: and the returning
current which descends along the coast of Africa,
tends to cool the parts nearer the equator. Great as
the difference of temperature is in different climates,
it would be still greater if there were not this equalizing
and moderating power exerted constantly over
the whole surface. Without this influence, it is probable
that the two polar portions of the earth, which
are locked in perpetual ice and snow, and almost destitute
of life, would be much increased.
We find an illustration of this effect of the ocean
on temperature, in the peculiarities of the climates of
maritime tracts and islands. The climate of such
portions of the earth, corrected in some measure by
the temperature of the neighbouring sea, is more
equable than that of places in the same latitudes differently
situated. London is cooler in summer and
warmer in winter than Paris.
2. Water expands by heat and contracts by cold,[72]
as has been already said; and in consequence of this
property, the coldest portions of the fluid generally
occupy the lower parts. The continued progress of
cold produces congelation. If, therefore, the law just
mentioned had been strictly true, the lower parts of
water would have been first frozen; and being once
frozen, hardly any heat applied at the surface could
have melted them, for the warm fluid could not have
descended through the colder parts. This is so far
the case, that in a vessel containing ice at the bottom
and water at the top, Rumford made the upper
fluid boil without thawing the congealed cake below.
Now, a law of water with respect to heat operating
in this manner, would have been very inconvenient
if it had obtained in our lakes and seas. They
would all have had a bed of ice, increasing with
every occasion, till the whole was frozen. We could
have had no bodies of water, except such pools on
the surfaces of these icy reservoirs as the summer
sun could thaw, to be again frozen to the bottom
with the first frosty night. The law of the regular
contraction of water by cold till it became ice, would,
therefore, be destructive of all the utility of our seas
and lakes. How is this inconvenience obviated?
It 
is obviated by a modification of the law which
takes place when the temperature approaches this
limit. Water contracts by the increase of cold,
till we come near the freezing temperature; but then,
by a further increase of cold, it contracts no more,
but expands till the point at which it becomes ice. It
contracts in cooling down to 40 degrees of Fahrenheit’s
thermometer; in cooling further it expands,
and when cooled to 32 degrees, it freezes. Hence,
the greatest density of the fluid is at 40 degrees, and
water of this temperature, or near it, will lie at the
bottom with cooler water or with ice floating above
it. However much the surface be cooled, water
colder than 40 cannot descend to displace water
warmer than itself. Hence we can never have ice
formed at the bottom of deep water. In approaching[73]
the freezing point, the coldest water will rise to the
surface, and the congelation will take place there;
and the ice so formed will remain at the surface, exposed
to the warmth of the sunbeams and the air,
and will not survive any long continuance of such
action.
Another peculiarity in the laws which regulate the
action of cold on water is, that in the very act of
freezing a further sudden and considerable expansion
takes place. Many persons will have known instances
of vessels burst by the freezing of water in
them. The consequence of this expansion is, that the
specific gravity of ice is less than that of water of any
temperature; and it therefore always floats in the
unfrozen fluid. If this expansion of crystallization
did not exist, ice would float in water which was below
forty degrees, but would sink when the fluid was
above that temperature: as the case is, it floats
under all circumstances. The icy remnants of the
effects of winter, which the river carries down its
stream, are visible on its surface till they melt away;
and the icebergs which are detached from the shores
of the polar seas, drift along, exposed to the sun and
air, as well as to the water in which they are immersed.
These laws of the effect of temperature on water
are truly remarkable in their adaptation to the beneficial
course of things at the earth’s surface. Water
contracts by cold; it thus equalizes the temperature
of various times and places; but if its contraction
were continued all the way to the freezing point, it
would bind a great part of the earth in fetters of ice.
The contraction then is here replaced by expansion,
in a manner which but slightly modifies the former
effects, while it completely obviates the bad consequences.
The further expansion which takes place
at the point of freezing, still further facilitates the
rapid removal of the icy chains, in which parts of
the earth’s surface are at certain seasons bound.
We do not know how far these laws of expansion[74]
are connected with and depend on more remote and
general properties of this fluid, or of all fluids. But
we have no reason to believe that, by whatever
means they operate, they are not laws selected from
among other laws which might exist, as in fact for
other fluids other laws do exist. And we have all
the evidence, which the most remarkable furtherance
of important purposes can give us, that they are selected,
and selected with a beneficial design.
3. As water becomes ice by cold, it becomes steam
by heat. In common language, steam is the name
given to the vapour of hot water; but in fact a vapour
or steam rises from water at all temperatures,
however low, and even from ice. The expansive
force of this vapour increases rapidly as the heat increases;
so that when we reach the heat of boiling
water, it operates in a far more striking manner than
when it is colder; but in all cases the surface of water
is covered with an atmosphere of aqueous vapour,
the pressure or tension of which is limited by
the temperature of the water. To each degree of
pressure in steam there is a constituent temperature
corresponding. If the surface of water is not pressed
by vapour with the force thus corresponding to its
temperature, an immediate evaporation will supply
the deficiency. We can compare the tension of such
vapour with that of our common atmosphere; the
pressure of the latter is measured by the barometrical
column, about thirty inches of mercury; that of
watery vapour is equal to one inch of mercury at
the constituent temperature of 80 degrees, and to one-fifth
of an inch, at the temperature of 32 degrees.
Hence, if that part of the atmosphere which consists
of common air were annihilated, there would
still remain an atmosphere of aqueous vapour, arising
from the waters and moist parts of the earth;
and in the existing state of things this vapour rises
in the atmosphere of dry air. Its distribution and
effects are materially influenced by the vehicle in
which it is thus carried, as we shall hereafter notice;[75]
but at present we have to observe the exceeding
utility of water in this shape. We remark how suitable
and indispensable to the well-being of the creation
it is, that the fluid should possess the property
of assuming such a form under such circumstances.
The moisture which floats in the atmosphere is of
most essential use to vegetable life.[7] “The leaves
of living plants appear to act upon this vapour in its
elastic form, and to absorb it. Some vegetables increase
in weight from this cause when suspended in
the atmosphere and unconnected with the soil, as the
house-leek and the aloe. In very intense heats, and
when the soil is dry, the life of plants seems to be
preserved by the absorbent power of their leaves.”
It follows from what has already been said, that, with
an increasing heat of the atmosphere, an increasing
quantity of vapour will rise into it, if supplied from
any quarter. Hence it appears that aqueous vapour
is most abundant in the atmosphere when it is most
needed for the purposes of life; and that when other
sources of moisture are cut off, this is most copious.
4. Clouds are produced by aqueous vapour when
it returns to the state of water. This process is condensation,
the reverse of evaporation. When vapour
exists in the atmosphere, if in any manner the temperature
becomes lower than the constituent temperature,
requisite for the maintenance of the vapoury
state, some of the steam will be condensed and will
become water. It is in this manner that the curl of
steam from the spout of a boiling tea-kettle becomes
visible, being cooled down as it rushes to the air.
The steam condenses into a fine watery powder,
which is carried about by the little aerial currents.
Clouds are of the same nature with such curls, the
condensation being generally produced when air,
charged with aqueous vapour, is mixed with a colder
current, or has its temperature diminished in any
other manner.
[76]
Clouds, while they retain that shape, are of the
most essential use to vegetable and animal life. They
moderate the fervour of the sun, in a manner agreeable,
to a greater or less degree, in all climates, and
grateful no less to vegetables than to animals. Duhamel
says that plants grow more during a week of
cloudy weather than a month of dry and hot. It
has been observed that vegetables are far more refreshed
by being watered in cloudy than in clear
weather. In the latter case, probably the supply of
fluid is too rapidly carried off by evaporation. Clouds
also moderate the alternations of temperature, by
checking the radiation from the earth. The coldest
nights are those which occur under a cloudless winter
sky.
The uses of clouds, therefore, in this stage of their
history, are by no means inconsiderable, and seem
to indicate to us that the laws of their formation
were constructed with a view to the purposes of organized
life.
5. Clouds produce rain. In the formation of a
cloud the precipitation of moisture probably forms a
fine watery powder, which remains suspended in the
air in consequence of the minuteness of its particles:
but if from any cause the precipitation is collected
in larger portions, and becomes drops, these descend
by their weight and produce a shower.
However rain is formed, it is one of the consequences
of the capacity of evaporation and condensation
which belongs to water, and its uses are the
result of the laws of those processes. Its uses to
plants are too obvious and too numerous to be described.
It is evident that on its quantity and distribution
depend in a great measure the prosperity of
the vegetable kingdom: and different climates are
fitted for different productions, no less by the relations
of dry weather and showers, than by those of
hot and cold.
6. Returning back still further in the changes
which cold can produce on water, we come to snow[77]
and ice: snow being apparently frozen vapour, aggregated
by a confused action of crystalline laws;
and ice being water in its fluid state, solidified by the
same crystalline forces. The impression of these
agents on the animal feelings is generally unpleasant,
and we are in the habit of considering them as symptoms
of the power of winter to interrupt that state
of the elements in which they are subservient to life.
Yet, even in this form, they are not without their
uses.[8] “Snow and ice are bad conductors of cold;
and when the ground is covered with snow, or the
surface of the soil or of water is frozen, the roots
or bulbs of plants beneath are protected by the congealed
water from the influence of the atmosphere,
the temperature of which, in northern winters, is
usually very much below the freezing point; and
this water becomes the first nourishment of the plant
in early spring. The expansion of water during its
congelation, at which time its volume increases one-twelfth,
and its contraction in bulk during a thaw,
tend to pulverize the soil, to separate its parts from
each other, and to make it more permeable to the
influence of the air.” In consequence of the same
slowness in the conduction of heat which snow thus
possesses, the arctic traveller finds his bed of snow
of no intolerable coldness; the Esquimaux is sheltered
from the inclemency of the season in his snow
hut, and travels rapidly and agreeably over the
frozen surface of the sea. The uses of those arrangements,
which at first appear productive only
of pain and inconvenience, are well suited to give
confidence and hope to our researches for such usefulness
in every part of the creation. They have
thus a peculiar value in adding connexion and universality
to our perception of beneficial design.
7. There is a peculiar circumstance still to be
noticed in the changes from ice to water and from
water to steam. These changes take place at a[78]
particular and invariable degree of heat; yet they
do not take place suddenly when we increase the
heat to this degree. This is a very curious arrangement.
The temperature makes a stand, as it were,
at the point where thaw, and where boiling take
place. It is necessary to apply a considerable quantity
of heat to produce these effects; all which heat
disappears, or becomes latent, as it is called. We
cannot raise the temperature of a thawing mass of
ice till we have thawed the whole. We cannot raise
the temperature of boiling water, or of steam rising
from it, till we have converted all the water into
steam. Any heat that we apply while these changes
are going on is absorbed in producing the changes.
The consequences of this property of latent heat
are very important. It is on this account that the
changes now spoken of necessarily occupy a considerable
time. Each part in succession must have a
proper degree of heat applied to it. If it were
otherwise, thaw and evaporation must be instantaneous:
at the first touch of warmth, all the snow
which lies on the roofs of our houses would descend
like a waterspout into the streets: all that which
rests on the ground would rush like an inundation
into the water courses. The hut of the Esquimaux
would vanish like a house in a pantomime: the icy
floor of the river would be gone without giving any
warning to the skaiter or the traveller: and when, in
heating our water, we reached the boiling point, the
whole fluid would “flash into steam,” (to use the expression
of engineers,) and dissipate itself in the atmosphere,
or settle in dew on the neighbouring
objects.
It is obviously necessary for the purposes of human
life, that these changes should be of a more
gradual and manageable kind than such as we have
now described. Yet this gradual progress of freezing
and thawing, of evaporation and condensation, is
produced, so far as we can discover, by a particular
contrivance. Like the freezing of water from the[79]
top, or the floating of ice, the moderation of the rate
of these changes seems to be the result of a violation
of a law: that is, the simple rule regarding the effects
of change of temperature, which at first sight appears
to be the law, and which, from its simplicity, would
seem to us the most obvious laws for these as well
as other cases, is modified at certain critical points,
so as to produce these advantageous effects:—why
may we not say in order to produce such effects?
8. Another office of water which it discharges by
means of its relations to heat, is that of supplying
our springs. There can be no doubt that the old hypotheses
which represent springs as drawing their
supplies from large subterranean reservoirs of water,
or from the sea by a process of subterraneous
filtration, are erroneous and untenable. The quantity
of evaporation from water and from wet ground is
found to be amply sufficient to supply the requisite
drain. Mr. Dalton calculated[9] that the quantity of
rain which falls in England is thirty-six inches a year.
Of this he reckoned that thirteen inches flow off to
the sea by the rivers, and that the remaining twenty-three
inches are raised again from the ground by
evaporation. The thirteen inches of water are of
course supplied by evaporation from the sea, and
are carried back to the land through the atmosphere.
Vapour is perpetually rising from the ocean,
and is condensed in the hills and high lands, and
through their pores and crevices descends, till it is
deflected, collected, and conducted out to the bay,
by some stratum or channel which is watertight.
The condensation which takes place in the higher
parts of the country, may easily be recognised in the
mists and rains which are the frequent occupants of
such regions. The coldness of the atmosphere and
other causes precipitate the moisture in clouds and
showers, and in the former as well as in the latter
shape, it is condensed and absorbed by the cool[80]
ground. Thus a perpetual and compound circulation
of the waters is kept up; a narrower circle between
the evaporation and precipitation of the land itself,
the rivers and streams only occasionally and partially
forming a portion of the circuit; and a wider
interchange between the sea and the lands which
feed the springs, the water ascending perpetually by
a thousand currents through the air, and descending
by the gradually converging branches of the rivers,
till it is again returned into the great reservoir of the
ocean.
In every country, these two portions of the aqueous
circulation have their regular, and nearly constant,
proportion. In this kingdom the relative quantities
are, as we have said, twenty-three and thirteen.
A due distribution of these circulating fluids in each
country appears to be necessary to its organic
health; to the habits of vegetables, and of man. We
have every reason to believe that it is kept up from
year to year as steadily as the circulation of the
blood in the veins and arteries of man. It is maintained
by a machinery very different, indeed, from
that of the human system, but apparently as well,
and, therefore, we may say as clearly, as that, adapted
to its purposes.
By this machinery, we have a connexion established
between the atmospheric changes of remote
countries. Rains in England are often introduced
by a south-east wind. “Vapour brought to
us by such a wind, must have been generated in
countries to the south and east of our island. It is,
therefore, probably, in the extensive valleys watered
by the Meuse, the Moselle, and the Rhine, if not
from the more distant Elbe, with the Oder and the
Weser, that the water rises, in the midst of sunshine,
which is soon afterwards to form our clouds, and
pour down our thunder-showers.” “Drought and
sunshine in one part of Europe may be as necessary
to the production of a wet season in another, as it is
on the great scale of the continents of Africa and[81]
South America; where the plains, during one-half
the year, are burnt up, to feed the springs of the
mountain; which in their turn contribute to inundate
the fertile valleys and prepare them for a luxuriant
vegetation.”[10] The properties of water which regard
heat make one vast watering-engine of the
atmosphere.
</div></body></text></TEI>