<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="144">GENERAL REMARKS.
ELECTRICITY in the form in
which it was originally studied—Franklinic, frictional, or
statical electricity—has been so completely identified with
electricity in its more comprehensive form—Voltaic, chemical, or
dynamical electricity—that any additions we might have to make
to the history of the earlier form of the subject are included in the
later science.
There are, however, several subjects which may still be regarded
rather as branches of Electricity than of the Cognate Sciences. Such
are, for instance, Atmospheric Electricity, with all that belongs to
Thunderstorms and Lightning Conductors. The observation of Atmospheric
Electricity has been prosecuted with great zeal at various
meteorological observatories; and especially at the Observatory
established by the British Association at Kew. The Aurora Borealis,
again, is plainly an electrical phenomenon; but probably belonging
rather to dynamical than to statical electricity. For it strongly
affects the magnetic needle, and its position has reference to the
direction of magnetism; but it has not been observed to affect the
electroscope. The general features of this phenomenon have been
described by M. de Humboldt, and more recently by M. de Bravais; and
theories of the mode of its production have been propounded by MM.
Biot, De la Rive, Kaemtz, and others.
Again, there are several fishes which have the power of giving an
electrical shock:—the torpedo, the gymnotus, and the silurus.
The agency of these creatures has been identified with electricity in
the most general sense. The peculiar energy of the animal has been
made to produce the effects which are produced by an electrical
discharge or a voltaic current:—not only to destroy life in
small animals, but to 611 deflect a magnet, to make a magnet, to
decompose water, and to produce a spark.
Dr. Faraday’s Views of Statical Electric Induction.
According to the theories of electricity of Æpinus and Coulomb,
which in this Book of our History are regarded as constituting a main
part of the progress of this portion of science, the particles of the
electric fluid or fluids exert forces, attractive and repulsive, upon
each other in straight lines at a distance, in the same way in which,
in the Newtonian theory of the universe, the particles of matter are
conceived as exerting attractive forces upon each other. An electrized
body presented a conducting body of any form, determines a new
arrangement of the electric fluids in the conductor, attracting the
like fluid to its own side, and repelling the opposite fluid to the
opposite side. This is Electrical Induction. And as, by the
theory, the attraction is greater at the smaller distances, the
distribution of the fluid upon the conductor in virtue of this
Induction will not be symmetrical, but will be governed by laws which
it will require a complex and difficult calculation to
determine—as we have seen was the case in the investigations of
Coulomb, Poisson, and others.
Instead of this action at a distance. Dr. Faraday has been led to
conceive Electrical Induction to be the result of an action taking
place between the electrized body and the conductor through lines of
contiguous particles in the mass of the intermediate body, which he
calls the Dielectric. And the irregularities of the
distribution of the electricity in these cases of Induction, and
indeed the existence of an action in points protected from direct
action by the protuberant sides of the conductor, are the causes, I
conceive, which lead him to the conclusion that Induction takes place
in curved lines17 of such contiguous particles.
17 Researches, 1165,
&c.
With reference to this, I may remark that, as I have said, the
distribution of electricity on a conductor in the presence of an
electrized body is so complex a mathematical problem that I do not
conceive any merely popular way of regarding the result can entitle us
to say, that the distribution which we find cannot be explained by the
Coulombian theory, and must force us upon the assumption of an action
in curved lines:—which is, indeed, itself a theory, and so vague
a one 612 that it
requires to be made much more precise before we can say what
consequences it does or does not lead to. Professor W. Thomson has
arrived at a mathematical proof that the effect of induction on the
view of Coulomb and of Faraday must, under certain conditions, be
necessarily and universally the same.
With regard to the influence of different Dielectrics upon
Induction, the inquiry appears to be of the highest importance; and
may certainly necessitate some addition to the theory.


BOOK XII.

MAGNETISM.

Recent Progress of Terrestrial Magnetism.
IN Chapter II., I have noticed the history of Terrestrial Magnetism;
Hansteen’s map published in 1819; the discovery of “magnetic storms”
about 1825; the chain of associated magnetic observations, suggested
by M. de Humboldt, and promoted by the British Association and the
Royal Society; the demand for the continuation of these till 1848; the
magnetic observations made in several voyages; the magnetic surveys of
various countries. And I have spoken also of Gauss’s theory of
Terrestrial Magnetism, and his directions and requirements concerning
the observations to be made. I may add a few words with regard to the
more recent progress of the subject.
The magnetic observations made over large portions of the Earth’s
surface by various persons, and on the Ocean by British officers, have
been transmitted to Woolwich, where they have been employed by General
Sabine in constructing magnetic maps of the Earth for the year 1840.18 Following the course of inquiry
described in the part of the history referred to, these maps exhibit
the declination, inclination, and intensity of the magnetic force at
every point of the earth’s surface. The curves which mark equal
amounts of each of these three elements (the lines of equal
declination, inclination, and force:—the
isogonal, the isoclinal, and the isodynamic
lines,) are, in their general form, complex and irregular; and it has
been made a matter of question (the facts being agreed upon) whether
it be more proper to say that they indicate four poles, as Halley and
as Hansteen said, or only two poles, as Gauss asserts. The matter
appears to become more clear if we draw magnetic meridians;
that is, lines obtained by following the directions, or pointings, of
the magnetic needle to the north or to 614 the south, till we arrive at the points
of convergence of all their directions; for there are only two such
poles, one in the Arctic and one in the Antarctic region. But in
consequence of the irregularity of the magnetic constitution of the
earth, if we follow the inclination of the magnetic force round the
earth on any parallel of latitude, we find that it has two
maxima and two minima, as if there were four magnetic
poles. The isodynamic map is a new presentation of the facts of this
subject; the first having been constructed by Colonel Sabine in
1837.
18 These maps are published in Mr.
Keith Johnstone’s Physical Atlas.
I have stated also that the magnetic elements at each place are to
be observed in such a manner as to bring into view both their
periodical, their secular, and their irregular or
occasional changes. The observations made at Toronto in Canada,
and at Hobart Town in Van Diemen’s Land, two stations at equal
distances from the two poles of the earth, and also at St Helena, a
station within the tropics, have been discussed by General Sabine with
great care, and with an amount of labor approaching to that employed
upon reductions of astronomical observations. And the results have
been curious and unexpected.
The declination was first examined.19 This magnetical
element is, as we have already seen (p. 232),
liable both to a diurnal and to an annual inequality; and also to
irregular perturbations which have been termed magnetic storms. Now it
was found that all these inequalities went on increasing gradually and
steadily from 1843 to 1848, so as to become, at the end of that time,
above twice as large as they were at the beginning of it. A new
periodical change in all these elements appeared to be clearly
established by this examination. M. Lamont, of Munich, had already
remarked indications of a decennial period in the diurnal variation of
the declination of the needle. The duration of the period from minimum
to maximum being about five years, and therefore the whole period
about ten years. The same conclusion was found to follow still more
decidedly from the observations of the dip and intensity.
19 Phil. Trans. 1852 and
1856.
This period of ten years had no familiar meaning in astronomy; and
if none such had been found for it, its occurrence as a magnetic
period must have been regarded, as General Sabine says,20 in the light of a fragmentary fact. But
it happened about this time that the scientific world was made aware
of the existence of a like period in a 615 phenomenon which no one would have
guessed to be connected with terrestrial magnetism, namely, the spots
in the Sun. M. Schwabe, of Dessau, had observed the Sun’s disk with
immense perseverance for 24 years:—often examining it more than
300 days in the year; and had found that the spots had, as to their
quantity and frequency, a periodical character. The years of maximum
are 1828, 1838, 1848, in which there were respectively 225,21 282, 330 groups of spots. The minimum
years, 1833, 1843, had only 33 and 34 such groups. This curious fact22 was first made public by M. de
Humboldt, in the third volume of his Kosmos (1850). The
coincidence of the periods and epochs of these two classes of facts
was pointed out by General Sabine in a Memoir presented to the Royal
Society in March, 1852.
20 Phil. Trans. 1856, p.
382.
21 In 1837 there were 333.
22 The observations up to 1844 were
published in Poggendorf’s Annalen.
Of course it was natural to suppose, even before this discovery,
that the diurnal and annual inequalities of the magnetic element at
each place depend upon the action of the sun, in some way or
other.
Dr. Faraday had endeavored to point out how the effect of the solar
heat upon the atmosphere would, according to the known relations of
heat and magnetism, explain many of the phenomena. But this new
feature of the phenomena, their quinquennial increase and decrease,
makes us doubt whether such an explanation can really be the true
one.
Of the secular changes in the magnetic elements, not much
more is known than was known some years ago. These changes go on, but
their laws are imperfectly known, and their causes not even
conjectured. M. Hansteen, in a recent memoir,23 says that the
decrease of the inclination goes on progressively diminishing. With us
this rate of decrease appears to be at present nearly uniform. We
cannot help conjecturing that the sun, which has so plain a connexion
with the diurnal, annual, and occasional movements of the needle, must
also have some connexion with its secular movements.
23 See K. Johnstone’s Physical
Atlas.
In 1840 the observations made at various places had to a great
extent enabled Gauss, in connexion with W. Weber, to apply his Theory
to the actual condition of the Earth;24  and he
calculated the Declination, Inclination, and Intensity at above 100
places, and found 616 the agreement, as he says, far beyond
his hopes. They show, he says, that the Theory comes near to the
Truth.
24 Atlas des Erdmagnetismus nach
den Elementen der Theorie Entworfen. See Preface.
Correction of Ship’s Compasses.
The magnetic needle had become of importance when it was found that
it always pointed to the North. Since that time the history of
magnetism has had its events reflected in the history of navigation.
The change of the declination arising from a change of place terrified
the companions of Columbus. The determination of the laws of this
change was the object of the voyage of Halley; and has been pursued
with the utmost energy in the Arctic and Antarctic regions by
navigators up to the present time. Probably the dependence of the
magnetic declination upon place is now known well enough for the
purposes of navigation. But a new source of difficulty has in the
meantime come into view; the effect of the iron in the ship upon the
Compass. And this has gone on increasing as guns, cables, stays,
knees, have been made of iron; then steam-engines with funnels,
wheels, and screws, have been added; and finally the whole ship has
been made of iron. How can the compass be trusted in such cases?
I have already said in the history that
Mr. Barlow proposed to correct the error of the compass by placing
near to the compass an iron plate, which from its proximity to the
compass might counterbalance magnetically the whole effect of the
ship’s iron upon the compass. This correction was not effectual,
because the magnetic forces of the plate and of the ship do not change
their direction and value according to the same law, with the change
of position. I have further stated that Mr. Airy devised other means
of correcting the error. I may add a few words on the subject; for the
subject has been further examined by Mr. Airy25 and by
others.
25 Phil. Trans. 1856.
It appears, by mathematical reasoning, that the magnetic effect of
the iron in a ship may be regarded as producing two kinds of deviation
which are added together;—a “polar-magnet deviation,” which
changes from positive to negative as the direction of the ship’s keel,
in a horizontal revolution, passes from semicircle to semicircle; and
a “quadrantal deviation,” which changes from positive to negative as
the keel turns from quadrant to quadrant. The latter deviation may be
remedied completely by a mass of unmagnetized iron placed on a level
617 with the
compass, either in the athwartship line or in the fore-and-aft line,
according to circumstances. “The polar-magnet-deviation” may be
corrected at any given place by a magnet or magnets, but the
magnets thus applied at one place will not always correct the
deviation in another magnetic latitude. For it appears that this
deviation arises partly from a magnetism inherent in the materials of
the ship, not changing with the change of magnetic position, and
partly from the effect of terrestrial magnetism upon the ship’s iron.
But the errors arising from both sources may be remedied by adjusting,
at a new locality, the positions of the corrective magnets.
The inherent magnetism of the ship, of which I have spoken, may be
much affected by the position in which the ship was built; and may
change from time to time; for instance, by the effect of the battering
of the waves, and other causes. Hence it is called by Mr. Airy
“sub-permanent magnetism.”
Another method of correcting the errors of a ship’s compass has
been proposed, and is used to some extent; namely, by swinging
the ship round (in harbor) to all points of azimuth, and thus
constructing a Table of Compass Errors for that particular
ship. But to this method it is objected that the Table loses its value
in a new magnetic latitude much more than the correction by magnets
does; besides the inconveniences of steering a ship by a Table.


BOOK XIII.

VOLTAIC ELECTRICITY.
</div></body></text></TEI>