<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="11">
      SECTION 4. OF THE SCIENTIFIC ADVISERS.
    

      Whether it was feared by the PARTY who govern the Royal Society, that its
      Council would not be sufficiently tractable, or whether the Admiralty
      determined to render that body completely subservient to them, or whether
      both these motives concurred, I know not; but, low as has been for years
      its character for independence, and fallen as the Royal Society is in
      public estimation, it could scarcely be prepared for this last insult. In
      order to inform the public and the Society, (for I believe the fact is
      known to few of the members,) it will be necessary to trace the history of
      those circumstances which led to the institution of the offices of
      Scientific Advisers, from the time of the existence of the late Board of
      Longitude.
    

      That body consisted, according to the act of parliament which established
      it, of certain official members, who usually possessed no knowledge of the
      subjects it was the duty of the Board to discuss—of certain
      professors of the two universities, and the Astronomer Royal, who had some
      knowledge, and who were paid 100L. a year for their attendance;—of
      three honorary members of the Royal Society, who combined the
      qualifications of the two preceding classes; and, lastly, of "three other
      persons," named Resident Commissioners, who were supposed to be "WELL
      VERSED IN THE SCIENCES OF MATHEMATICS, ASTRONOMY, OR NAVIGATION," and who
      were paid a hundred a year to do the work of the Board.
    

      The first three classes were permanent members, but the "three other
      persons" only held the appointment for ONE YEAR, and were renewable at the
      pleasure of the Admiralty. This Board was abolished by another act of
      parliament, on the ground that it was useless. Shortly after, the
      Secretary of the Admiralty communicated to the Council of the Royal
      Society, the copy of an Order in Council:
    

      ADMIRALTY OFFICE,
    

      November 1, 1828.
    

      SIR, I am commanded by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty, to send
      herewith, for the information of the President and Council of the Royal
      Society, a copy of His Majesty's Order in Council of the 27th of last
      month; explaining that the salaries heretofore allowed to the Resident
      Commissioners of the Board of Longitude, and to the Superintendents of the
      Nautical Almanac, and of Chronometers, shall be continued to them,
      notwithstanding the abolition of the Board of Longitude. And I am to
      acquaint you, that the necessary orders have been given to the Navy Board
      for the payment of the said salaries.
    

      I am, Sir,
    

      Your most obedient humble servant,
    

      JOHN BARROW. AT THE COURT AT WINDSOR,
    

      27th October, 1828.
    

      PRESENT,
    

      The King's most Excellent Majesty in Council,
    

      Whereas, there was this day read at the Board a Memorial from the Right
      Honourable the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty, dated 4th of this
      instant, in the words following, viz.—
    

      Whereas, by an Act of the 58th of his late Majesty's reign, cap. 20,
      instituted "An Act for the more effectually discovering the Longitude at
      sea, and encouraging attempts to find a Northern passage between the
      Atlantic and Pacific Oceans, and to approach the North Pole," three
      persons well versed in the sciences of Mathematics, Astronomy, or
      Navigation, were appointed as a Resident Committee of the Board of
      Commissioners for discovery of the Longitude at sea, and a Superintendent
      of the Nautical Almanac and of Chronometers was also appointed, with such
      salaries for the execution of those services as his Majesty might, by any
      Order in Council, be pleased to direct; and, whereas, your Majesty was in
      consequence, by your Order in Council of the 27th of May, 1828, most
      graciously pleased to direct, that the three said Resident Commissioners
      should be paid at the rate of 100L. a year each; and by your further Order
      in Council, of the 31st October, 1818, that the Superintendent of the
      Nautical Almanac should be allowed a salary of 300L., and the
      Superintendent of Chronometers 100L. a year; and, whereas, the act above
      mentioned has been repealed, and the Board of Longitude abolished; and
      doubts have therefore arisen, whether the said Orders in Council shall
      still continue in force; and whereas it is expedient that the said
      appointments be continued; We beg leave most humbly to submit to your
      Majesty, that your Majesty may be graciously pleased, by your Order in
      Council, to direct that the said offices of Superintendent of the Nautical
      Almanac, and of Superintendent of Chronometers; and also the three persons
      before-mentioned as a Resident Committee, to advise with the Commissioners
      for executing the Office of Lord High Admiral, on all questions of
      discoveries, inventions, calculations, and other scientific subjects, be
      continued, with the same duties and salaries, and under the same
      regulations as heretofore; and further beg most humbly to propose, that
      such three persons to form the Resident Committee, be chosen annually by
      the Commissioners for executing the office of Lord High Admiral, from
      among the Council of the Royal Society.
    

      His Majesty, having taken the said Memorial into consideration, was
      pleased, by and with the advice of his Privy Council, to approve thereof
      and the Right Honourable the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty are to
      give the necessary directions herein accordingly.
    

      (Signed) JAMES HILLER.
    

      Thus, it appeared that the Admiralty were to choose three persons from
      among the Council of the Royal Society, who were to have a hundred a year
      each during the pleasure of the Admiralty.
    

      Such an open attack on the independence of the Council could not escape
      the remarks of some of the members, and a kind of mild remonstrance was
      made, in which the real ground of complaint was omitted.
    

      MINUTE OF COUNCIL OF THE ROYAL SOCIETY. December 18, 1823.
    

      RESOLVED, That in acknowledging the communication of the Lords
      Commissioners of the Admiralty, made to the Council of the Royal Society,
      on the 20th of November last, it be represented to them that inconvenience
      may arise from the plan therein specified, from the circumstance of all
      the members of the Council being annually elected by the Society at large;
      and that body being consequently subject to continual changes from year to
      year.
    

      This was answered by the following letter from the Secretary of the
      Admiralty:
    

      ADMIRALTY OFFICE, DEC. 30, 1828.
    

      SIR, Having submitted to my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty your
      Letter of the 18th instant, subjoining an extract from the Minutes of the
      proceedings of the Council of the Royal Society, arising out of the
      communication made to them by their Lordships, on the subject of his
      Majesty's Order in Council, of the fifth of October last, I have their
      Lordships' command to acquaint you, for the information of the President
      and Council, and with reference to what they have stated as to the
      inconvenience which may arise from the intended plan of limiting their
      Lordships' choice of members of the Resident Committee of Scientific
      Advice to the Council of the Royal Society, that their Lordships were
      induced to recommend this plan to his Majesty as a mark of respect to the
      Society, and as a pledge to the public of the qualification of the persons
      chosen. Nor did their Lordships apprehend any inconvenience from the
      circumstance stated in the Minute of the Council, of the Members being
      annually elected, as the Resident Committee is also annually appointed;
      and, in point of fact, no practical inconvenience has been felt during the
      ten years that the Committee has been in existence, as four of the
      distinguished gentlemen whom their Lordships have successively appointed
      to this office, have continued during the whole period to be members of
      the Council; and if any such difficulty or inconvenience should hereafter
      arise, their Lordships will be ready to take proper measures for remedying
      it.
    

      Their Lordships' intention therefore is, to propose to Captain Kater and
      Mr. Herschel, to continue to fill this office; and to Dr. Young, who had
      resigned it, on receiving the appointment of Secretary to the late Board
      of Longitude, to be appointed.
    

      I am, Sir, Your obedient servant,
    

      JOHN BARROW.
    

      The representation made by the Council was not calculated to produce much
      effect; but the Secretary of the Admiralty, who knew well the stuff of
      which Councils of the Royal Society are composed, might have spared the
      bitter irony of making their Lordships say, that they recommended this
      plan "AS A MARK OF RESPECT TO THE SOCIETY," and "AS A PLEDGE TO THE PUBLIC
      OF THE QUALIFICATIONS OF THE PERSONS CHOSEN," whilst he delicately hints
      to them their dependent situation, by observing, that the "RESIDENT
      COMMITTEE IS ALSO ANNUALLY APPOINTED."
    

      The Secretary knew that, PRACTICALLY speaking, it had been the custom for
      years for the President of the Royal Society to nominate the Council, and
      consequently he knew that every scientific adviser must first be indebted
      to the President for being qualified to advise, and then to the Admiralty
      for deriving profit from his counsel. Thus then their Lordships, as a
      "MARK OF RESPECT FOR THE SOCIETY" confirm the dependence of the Council on
      the President, by making his nomination a qualification for place, and
      establish a new dependence of the same Council on themselves, by giving a
      hundred pounds each year to such three members of that Council as they may
      select. "THE PLEDGE" they offer "TO THE PUBLIC, OF THE QUALIFICATIONS OF
      THE PERSONS CHOSEN," is, that Mr. Davies Gilbert had previously thought
      they would do for his Council.
    

      What the Society, when they are acquainted with it, may think of this mark
      of respect, or what value the public may put upon this pledge, must be
      left to themselves to express.
    

      In looking over the list of officers and Council of the Royal Society the
      weakest perhaps (for purposes of science) which was ever made, a
      consolation arises from the possibility of some of those who were placed
      there by way of compliment, occasionally attending. In that contracted
      field Lord Melville's penetration may not be uselessly employed; and the
      soldier who presides over our colonies may judge whether the principles
      which pervade it are open and liberal as his own.
    

      The inconvenience to the public service from such an arrangement is, that
      the number out of which the advisers are selected must, in any case, be
      very small; and may, from several circumstances, be considerably reduced.
      In a council fairly selected, to judge of the merits of the various
      subjects likely to be brought under the consideration of the Society,
      anatomy, chemistry, and the different branches of natural history, will
      share with the numerous departments of physical science, in claiming to be
      represented by persons competently skilled in those subjects. These claims
      being satisfied, but few places will be left to fill up with
      mathematicians, astronomers, and persons conversant with nautical
      astronomy.
    

      Let us look at the present Council. Is there a single mathematician
      amongst them, if we except Mr Barlow, whose deservedly high reputation
      rests chiefly on his physical and experimental inquiries, and whom the
      President and the Admiralty have clearly shown they do not look upon as a
      mathematician, by not appointing him an adviser?
    

      Small as the number of those persons on the Council, who are conversant
      with the three subjects named in the Act of Parliament, must usually be,
      it may be still further diminished. The President, when he forms his
      Council, may decline naming those members who are most fit for such
      situations. Or, on the other hand, some of those members who are best
      qualified for them, from their knowledge, may decline the honour of being
      the nominees of Mr. Gilbert, as Vice Presidents, Treasurers, or
      Councillors, and thus lending their names to support a system of which
      they disapprove.
    

      Whether the first of these causes has ever operated can be best explained
      by those gentlemen who have been on the Council. The refusals are,
      notwithstanding the President's taciturnity on the subject, better known
      than he is willing that they should be.
    

      Having discussed the general policy of the measure, with reference both to
      the Society and to the public, and without the slightest reference to the
      individuals who may have refused or accepted those situations, I shall now
      examine the propriety of the appointments that have been made.
    

      Doubtless the gentlemen who now hold those situations either have never
      considered the influence such a mode of selection would have on the
      character of the Council; or, having considered it, they must have arrived
      at a different conclusion from mine. There may, however, be arguments
      which I have overlooked, and a discussion of them must ultimately lead to
      truth: but I confess that it appears to me the objections which have been
      stated rest on principles of human nature, too deeply seated to be easily
      removed.
    

      That I am not singular in the view I have taken of this subject, appears
      from several circumstances. A question was asked respecting these
      appointments at the Anniversary before the last; and, from the nature of
      the answer, many of the members of the Society have been led to believe
      the objections have been removed. Several Fellows of the Society, who knew
      these facts, thought it inexpedient ever to vote for placing any gentleman
      on the Council who had accepted these situations; and, having myself the
      same view of the case, I applied to the Council to be informed of the
      names of the present Scientific Advisers. But although they remonstrated
      against the PRINCIPLE, they replied that they had "NO COGNIZANCE" of the
      fact.
    

      The two first members of the Council, Mr. Herschel and Captain Kater, who
      were so appointed, and who had previously been Resident Commissioners
      under the Act, immediately refused the situations. Dr. Young became one of
      the Advisers; and Captain Sabine and Mr. Faraday were appointed by the
      Admiralty as the two remaining ones. Of Dr. Young, who died shortly after,
      I shall only observe that he possessed knowledge which qualified him for
      the situation.
    

      Whether those who at present fill these offices can be said to belong to
      that class of persons which the Order in Council and the Act of Parliament
      point out, is a matter on which doubt may reasonably be entertained. The
      Order in Council speaks of these three persons as being the same, and
      having the "SAME DUTIES" as those mentioned in the Act; and it recites the
      words of the Act, that they shall be persons "WELL VERSED IN THE SCIENCES
      OF MATHEMATICS ASTRONOMY, AND NAVIGATION." Of the fitness of the gentlemen
      who now hold those situations to pronounce judgment on mathematical
      questions, the public will be better able to form an opinion when they
      shall have communicated to the world any of their own mathematical
      inquiries. Although it is the practice to consider that acceptance of
      office is alone necessary to qualify a man for a statesman, a similar
      doctrine has not yet prevailed in the world of science. One of these
      gentlemen, who has established his reputation as a chemist, stands in the
      same predicament with respect to the other two sciences. It remains then
      to consider Captain Sabine's claims, which must rest on his skill in
      "PRACTICAL ASTRONOMY AND NAVIGATION,"—a claim which can only be
      allowed when the scientific world are set at rest respecting the
      extraordinary nature of those observations contained in his work on the
      Pendulum.
    

      That volume, printed under the authority of the Board of Longitude,
      excited at its appearance considerable attention. The circumstance of the
      Government providing instruments and means of transport for the purpose of
      these inquiries, placed at Captain Sabine's disposal means superior to
      those which amateurs can generally afford, whilst the industry with which
      he availed himself of these opportunities, enabled him to bring home
      multitudes of observations from situations rarely visited with such
      instruments, and for such purposes.
    

      The remarkable agreement with each other, which was found to exist amongst
      each class of observations, was as unexpected by those most conversant
      with the respective processes, as it was creditable to one who had devoted
      but a few years to the subject, and who, in the course of those voyages,
      used some of the instruments for the first time in his life.
    

      This accordance amongst the results was such, that naval officers of the
      greatest experience, confessed themselves unable to take such lunars;
      whilst other observers, long versed in the use of the transit instrument,
      avowed their inability to take such transits. Those who were conversant
      with pendulums, were at a loss how to make, even under more favourable
      circumstances, similarly concordant observations. The same opinion
      prevailed on the continent as well as in England. On whatever subject
      Captain Sabine touched, the observations he published seemed by their
      accuracy to leave former observers at a distance. The methods of using the
      instruments scarcely differed in any important point from those before
      adopted; and, but for a fortunate discovery, which I shall presently
      relate, the world must have concluded that Captain Sabine possessed some
      keenness of vision, or acuteness of touch, which it would be hopeless for
      any to expect to rival.
    

      The Council of the Royal Society spared no pains to stamp the accuracy of
      these observations with their testimony. They seem to have thrust Captain
      Sabine's name perpetually on their minutes, and in a manner which must
      have been almost distressing: they recommend him in a letter to the
      Admiralty, then in another to the Ordnance; and several of the same
      persons, in their other capacity, as members of the Board of Longitude,
      after voting him a THOUSAND POUNDS for these observations, are said to
      have again recommended him to the Master-General of the Ordnance. That an
      officer, commencing his scientific career, should be misled by such
      praises, was both natural and pardonable; but that the Council of the
      Royal Society should adopt their opinion so heedlessly, and maintain it so
      pertinaciously, was as cruel to the observer as it was injurious to the
      interests of science.
    

      It might have been imagined that such praises, together with the Copley
      medal, presented to Captain Sabine by the Royal Society, and the medal of
      Lalande, given to him by the Institute of France, had arisen from such a
      complete investigation of his observations, as should place them beyond
      the reach even of criticism. But, alas! the Royal Society may write, and
      nobody will attend; its medals have lost their lustre; and even the
      Institute of France may find that theirs cannot confer immortality. That
      learned body is in the habit of making most interesting and profound
      reports on any memoirs communicated to it; nothing escapes the penetration
      of their committees appointed for such purposes. Surely, when they enter
      on the much more important subject of the award of a medal, unusual pains
      must be taken with the previous report, and it might, perhaps, be of some
      advantage to science, and might furnish their admirers with arguments in
      their defence, if they would publish that on which the decree of their
      Lalande's medal to Captain Sabine was founded.
    

      It is far from necessary to my present object, to state all that has been
      written and said respecting these pendulum experiments: I shall confine
      myself merely to two points; one, the transit observations, I shall allude
      to, because I may perhaps show the kind of feeling that exists respecting
      them, and possibly enable Captain Sabine to explain them. The other point,
      the error in the estimation of the division of the level, I shall discuss,
      because it is an admitted fact.
    

      Some opinion may be formed of transit observations, by taking the
      difference of times of the passage of any star between the several wires;
      supposing the distances of those wires equal, the intervals of time
      occupied by the star in passing from one to the other, ought to be
      precisely the same. As those times of passing from one wire to another are
      usually given to seconds and tenths of seconds, it rarely happens that the
      accordance is perfect.
    

      The transit instrument used by Captain Sabine was thirty inches in length,
      and the wires are stated to be equi-distant. Out of about 370 transits,
      there are eighty-seven, or nearly one-fourth, which have the intervals
      between all the wires agreeing to the same, the tenth of a second. At
      Sierra Leone, nineteen out of seventy-two have the same accordance; and of
      the moon culminating stars, p. 409, twelve out of twenty-four are equally
      exact. With larger instruments, and in great observatories, this is not
      always the case.
    

      Captain Kater has given, in the Philosophical Transactions, 1819, p. 427,
      a series of transits, with a three and a half foot transit, in which about
      one-eleventh part of them only have this degree of accuracy; and it should
      be observed that not merely the instrument, but the stars selected, have,
      in this instance, an advantage over Captain Sabine's.
    

      The transit of M. Bessel is five feet in length, made by Frauenhofer, and
      the magnifying power employed is 182; yet, out of some observations of his
      in January, 1826, only one-eleventh have this degree of accordance. In
      thirty-three of the Greenwich observations of January, 1828, fifteen have
      this agreement, or five-elevenths; but this is with a ten-feet transit.
      Now in none of these instances do the times agree within a tenth of a
      second between all the wires; but I have accounted those as agreeing in
      all the wires in which there is not more than four-tenths of a second
      between the greatest and least.
    

      This superior accuracy of the small instrument requires some explanation.
      One which has been suggested is, that Captain Sabine employs a chronometer
      to observe transits with; and that since it beats five times in two
      seconds, each beat will give four-tenths of a second; and this being the
      smallest quantity registered, the agreement becomes more probable than if
      tenths were the smallest quantities noticed. In general, the larger the
      lowest unity employed the greater will be the apparent agreement amongst
      the differences. Thus, if, in the transit of stars near the pole, the
      times of passing the wires were only registered to the nearest minute, the
      intervals would almost certainly be equal. There is another circumstance,
      about which there is some difficulty. It is understood that the same
      instrument,—the thirty-inch transit, was employed by Lieutenant
      Foster; and it has not been stated that the wires were changed, although
      this has most probably been the case. Now, in the transits which the later
      observer has given, he has found it necessary to correct for a
      considerable inequality between the first and second wires (See Phil.
      Trans. 1827). If an erroneous impression has gone abroad on this subject,
      it is doing a service to science to insure its correction, by drawing
      attention to it.
    

      Should these observations be confirmed by other observers, it would seem
      to follow that the use of a chronometer renders a transit more exact, and
      therefore that it ought to be used in observatories.
    

      Among the instruments employed by Captain Sabine, was a repeating circle
      of six inches diameter, made by order of the Board of Longitude, for the
      express purpose of ascertaining how far repeating instruments might be
      diminished in size:—a most important subject, on which the Board
      seem to have entertained a very commendable degree of anxiety.
    

      The following extract from the "Pendulum Experiments" is important:
    

      "The repeating circle was made by the direction, and at the expense of the
      Board of Longitude, for the purpose of exemplifying the principle of
      repetition when applied to a circle of so small a diameter as six inches,
      carrying a telescope of seven inches focal length, and one inch aperture;
      and of practically ascertaining the degree of accuracy which might be
      retained, whilst the portability of the instrument should be increased, by
      a reduction in the size to half the amount which had been previously
      regarded by the most eminent artists as the extreme limit of diminution to
      which repeating circles, designed for astronomical purposes, ought to be
      carried.
    

      "The practical value of the six-inch repeating circle may be estimated, by
      comparing the differences of the partial results from the mean at each
      station, with the correspondence of any similar collection of observations
      made with a circle, on the original construction, and of large dimensions;
      such, for instance, as the latitudes of the stations of the French are,
      recorded in the Base du Systeme Metrique: when, if due allowance be made
      for the extensive experience and great skill of the distinguished persons
      who conducted the French observations, the comparison will scarcely appear
      to the disadvantage of the smaller circle, even if extended generally
      through all the stations of the present volume; but if it be particularly
      directed to Maranham and Spitzbergen,—at which stations the partial
      results were more numerous than elsewhere, and obtained with especial
      regard to every circumstance by which their accuracy might be affected,
      the performance of the six-inch circle will appear fully equal to that of
      circles of the larger dimension. The comparison with the two stations, at
      which a more than usual attention was bestowed, is the more appropriate,
      because it was essential to the purposes for which the latitudes of the
      French stations were required, that the observations should always be
      conducted with the utmost possible regard to accuracy.
    

      "It would appear, therefore, that in a repeating circle of six inches, the
      disadvantages of a smaller image enabling a less precise contact or
      bisection, and of an arch of less radius admitting of a less minute
      subdivision, may be compensated by the principle of repetition."
    

      Captain Sabine has pointed out Maranham and Spitzbergen as places most
      favourable to the comparison. Let us take the former of these places, and
      compare the observations made there with the small repeating instrument of
      six inches diameter, with those made by the French astronomers at
      Formentera, with a repeating circle of forty-one centi-metres, or about
      sixteen inches in diameter, made by Fortin. It is singular that this
      instrument was directed, by the French Board of Longitude, to be made
      expressly for this survey, and the French astronomers paid particular
      attention to it, from the circumstance of some doubts having been
      entertained respecting the value of the principle of repetition.
    

      The following series of observations were made with the two instruments.
      [I have chosen the inferior meridian altitude of Polaris, merely because
      the number of sets of observations are rather fewer. The difference
      between the extremes of the altitude of Polaris, deduced from sets taken
      above the pole by the same observers, amounts to seven seconds and a
      half.]
    

      Latitude deduced from Polaris, with a repeating circle, 16 inches
      diameter.—BASE DU SYSTEME METRIQUE, tom. iv. p. 376. 1807.
    

     Number of           Latitude              Names of Observers.
     Observations.       of Formentera.

                         deg. min. sec.
      64                  38  39  55.3         Biot
     100                          54.7         Arago
      10                          56.2         Biot
      88                          56.9         Biot
     120                          56.7         Arago
      84                          54.9         Biot
     100                          56.5         Arago
     102                          57.1         Arago
      80                          54.5         Biot
      88                          53.3         Arago
      90                          53.6         Arago
      88                          53.8         Arago
      92                          53.7         Arago
      42                          55.6         Chaix
      90                          54.1         Chaix
      80                          53.9         Arago

     Mean of 1318 Observations, 38deg. 39min. 54.93sec.


      Sets of Observations made with a six-inch repeating circle, at Maranham.
    

   Star.               Number of         Latitude       Observer.
                       Observations.     deduced.

                                      deg. min. sec.
   alpha Lyrae             8           2    31  42.4    Capt. Sabine
   alpha Lyrae            12                    43.8     Ditto
   alpha Pavonis          10                    44.5     Ditto
   alpha Lyrae            12                    44.6     Ditto
   alpha Cygni            12                    42.1     Ditto
   alpha Gruris           12                    42.2     Ditto

   Mean latitude deduced from 66 observations 2deg. 31min 43.3sec.


      In comparing these results, although the French observations were more
      than twenty times as numerous as the English, yet the deviations of the
      individual sets from the mean are greater. One second and three-tenths is
      the greatest deviation from the mean of the Maranham observations; whilst
      the greatest deviation of those of Formentera, is two seconds and
      two-tenths. If this mode of comparison should be thought unfair, on
      account of the greater number of the sets in the French observations, let
      any six, in succession, of those sets be taken, and compared with the six
      English sets; and it will be found that in no one instance is the greatest
      deviation from the mean of the whole of the observations less than in
      those of Maranham. It must also be borne in mind, that by the latitude
      deduced by the mean of 1250 superior culminations of Polaris by the same
      observers, the latitude of Formentera was found to be 38deg. 39min
      57.07sec., a result differing by 2.14sec. from the mean of the 1318
      inferior culminations given above. [This difference cannot be accounted
      for by any difference in the tables of refraction, as neither the
      employment of those of Bradley, of Piazzi, of the French, of Groombridge,
      of Young, of Ivory, of Bessel, or of Carlini, would make a difference of
      two-tenths of a second.]
    

      These facts alone ought to have awakened the attention of Captain Sabine,
      and of those who examined and officially pronounced on the merits of his
      observations; for, supposing the skill of the observers equal, it seems a
      necessary consequence that "the performance of the six-inch circle is" not
      merely "fully equal to that of circles of larger dimensions," but that it
      is decidedly SUPERIOR to one of sixteen inches in diameter.
    

      This opinion did indeed gain ground for a time; but, fortunately for
      astronomy, long after these observations were made, published, and
      rewarded, Captain Kater, having borrowed the same instrument, discovered
      that the divisions of its level, which Captain Sabine had considered to be
      equal to one second each, were, in fact, more nearly equal to eleven
      seconds, each one being 10.9sec. This circumstance rendered necessary a
      recalculation of all the observations made with that instrument: a
      re-calculation which I am not aware Captain Sabine has ever thought it
      necessary to publish. [Above two hundred sets of observations with this
      instrument are given in the work alluded to. It can never be esteemed
      satisfactory merely to state the mean results of the corrections arising
      from this error: for the confidence to be attached to that mean will
      depend on the nature of the deviations from it.]
    

      This is the more to be regretted, as it bears upon a point of considerable
      importance to navigation; and if it should have caused any alteration in
      his opinion as to the comparative merits of great and small instruments,
      it might have been expected from a gentleman, who was expressly directed
      by the Board of Longitude, to try the question with an instrument
      constructed for that especial purpose.
    

      Finding that this has not been done by the person best qualified for the
      task, perhaps a few remarks from one who has no pretensions to familiarity
      with the instrument, may tend towards elucidating this interesting
      question.
    

      The following table gives the latitudes as corrected for the error of
      level:
    

 Station.       Star              Latitude      Latitude        Diffe-
                                   by Capt.    corrected for     rence
                                   Sabine      error of level.

                                 deg.min.sec.   deg.min.sec.    sec.

 Sierra Leone  Sirius             8  29  27.9    8  29  34.7    6.8

 Ascension     Alph.Centuri       7  55  46.7    7  55  40.1    6.6

 Bahia         Alph.Lyrae        12  59  19.4   12  59  21.4    2.0
               Alph.Lyrae                21.2       58  49.8   31.4
               Alph.Pavonis              22.4       59   5.1   17.3

 Maranham      Alph.Lyrae         2  31  42.4    2  31  22     20.4
               Alph.Lyrae                43.8           31.8   12.0
               Alph.Pavonis              44.5           44      .5
               Alph.Lyrae                44.6           42.6    2.0
               Alph.Cygni                42.1           39.2    2.9
               Alph.Gruris               42.2           27.4   14.8

 Trinidad      Achernar          10  38  56.1   10  38  58.2    2.1
               Alph.Gruris               52.2           50.8    1.4
               Achernar                  59.3           56.6    2.7

 Jamaica       Polaris           17  56   8.6   17  56   4.6    4.0
                                          6.6            3.3    3.3

 New York      Sun               40  42  40.1   40  42  44.6    4.5
               Polaris                   48.9           38.2   10.7
               Sun                       41.4           47.2    5.8
               Beta Urs.Min.             42.3           58.4   16.1

 Hammerfest    Sun               70  40   5.3   70  40   7.2    1.9

 Spitzbergen   Sun               79  49  56.1   79  49  58.6    2.5
               Sun                       55.9           44.8   11.1
               Sun                       58.6           52.7    5.9
               Sun                       59.3           51.6    7.7
               Sun                       55.8           51.6    4.2
               Sun                   50   1.5           57.0    4.5

 Greenland     Sun               74  32  19.9   74  32  32.4   12.4
               Sun                       17.9           18.7    0.8

 Drontheim     Sun               63  25  51.3   63  26   6.1   14.8
               Alph.Urs.Min.             57.2           49.4    7.8


      This presents a very different view of the latitudes as determined by the
      small repeating circle, from that in Captain Sabine's book; and confining
      ourselves still to Maranham, where the latitudes "WERE OBTAINED, WITH
      ESPECIAL REGARD TO EVERY CIRCUMSTANCE BY WHICH THEIR ACCURACY MIGHT BE
      AFFECTED," and where "A MORE THAN USUAL ATTENTION WAS BESTOWED," it
      appears, that if we take Captain Sabine's own test, namely, "the
      differences of the partial results from the mean at each station," the
      deviations become nearly ten times as large as they were before; a
      circumstance which might be expected to have some influence in the
      decision of the question.
    

      There is, however, another light in which it is impossible to avoid
      looking at this singular oversight. The second column of the table of
      latitudes must now be considered the true one, as that which really
      resulted from the observations. Now, on examining the column of true
      latitudes, the differences between the different sets of observations is
      so considerable as naturally to excite some fear of latent error, more
      especially as nearly the greatest discordance arises from the same star,
      Alph.Lyrae, observed after an interval of only three days. It becomes
      interesting to every person engaged in making astronomical observations,
      to know what is the probability of his being exposed to an error so little
      to be guarded against, and so calculated to lull the suspicions of the
      unfortunate astronomer to whom it may happen.
    

      In fact, the question resolves itself into this: the true latitude of a
      place being determined by sets of observations as in the first of the
      following columns—
    

                                                     Latitudes as
     True latitudes observed.                    computed by a mistake
                                                   of Capt. Sabine's.

                                 deg.min.sec.       deg.min.sec.
     Alph.Lyrae, 28th Aug....  2  31  22.0        2  31  42.4
     Alph.Lyrae, 29th Aug....         31.8               43.8
     Alph.Pavonis, 29th Aug...         44,0               44.5
     Alph.Lyrae, 31st Aug....         42.6               44.6
     Alph.Cygni, 31st Aug....         39.2               42.0
     Alph.Gruris, 2d Sept....         27.4               42.2


      what are the chances that, by one error all the latitudes in the first
      column should be brought so nearly to an agreement as they are in the
      second column? The circumstance of the number of divisions of the level
      being almost arbitrary within limits, might perhaps be alleged as
      diminishing this extraordinary improbability: but let any one consider, if
      he choose the error of each set, as independent of the others, still he
      will find the odds against it enormous.
    

      When it is considered that an error, almost arbitrary in its law, has thus
      had the effect of bringing discordant observations into an almost
      unprecedented accordance, as at Maranham; and not merely so, but that at
      eight of the nine stations it has uniformly tended to diminish the
      differences between the partial results, and that at the ninth station it
      only increased it by a small fraction of a second, I cannot help feeling
      that it is more probable even that Captain Kater, with all his admitted
      skill, and that Captain Sabine himself, should have been both mistaken in
      their measures of the divisions of the level, than that so singular an
      effect should have been produced by one error; and I cannot bring myself
      to believe that such an anticipation is entirely without foundation.
    

      Whatever may be the result of a re-examination, it was a singular
      oversight NOT TO MEASURE the divisions of a level intended to be used for
      determining so important a question; more particularly as, in the very
      work to which reference was made by Captain Sabine for the purpose of
      comparing the observations, it was the very first circumstance which
      occupied the French philosophers, and several pages [See pages 265 to 275
      of the RECUEIL D'OBSERVATIONS GEODESIQUES, &c. PAR MM. BIOT ET ARAGO,
      which forms the fourth volume of the BASE DU SYSTEME METRIQUE.] are filled
      with the details relative to the determination of the value of the
      divisions of the level. It would also have been satisfactory, with such an
      important object in view, to have read off some of the sets after each
      pair of observations, in order to see how far the system of repetition
      made the results gradually converge to a limit, and in order to know how
      many repetitions were sufficient. Such a course would almost certainly
      have led to a knowledge of the true value of the divisions of the level;
      for the differences in the altitude of the same star, after a few minutes
      of time, must, in many instances, have been far too great to have arisen
      from the change of its altitude: and had these been noticed, they must
      have been referred to some error in the instrument, which could scarcely,
      in such circumstances, have escaped detection.
    

      I have now mentioned a few of the difficulties which attend Captain
      Sabine's book on the pendulum, difficulties which I am far from saying are
      inexplicable. He would be bold indeed who, after so wonderful an instance
      of the effect of chance as I have been just discussing, should venture to
      pronounce another such accident impossible; but I think enough has been
      said to show, that the feeling which so generally prevails relative to it,
      is neither captious nor unreasonable.
    

      Enough also has appeared to prove, that the conduct of the Admiralty in
      appointing that gentleman one of their scientific advisers, was, under the
      peculiar circumstances, at least, unadvised. They have thus lent, as far
      as they could, the weight of their authority to support observations which
      are now found to be erroneous. They have thus held up for imitation
      observations which may induce hundreds of meritorious officers to throw
      aside their instruments, in the despair of ever approaching a standard
      which is since admitted to be imaginary; and they have ratified the
      doctrine, for I am not aware their official adviser has ever even modified
      it, that diminutive instruments are equal almost to the largest.
    

      To what extent this doctrine is correct, may perhaps yet admit of doubt.
      It cannot, however, admit of a doubt, that it is unwise to crown it with
      official authority, and thus expose the officers of their service to
      depend on means which may be quite insufficient for their purpose.
    

      How the Board of Longitude, after EXPRESSLY DIRECTING THIS INSTRUMENT TO
      BE MADE AND TRIED, could come to the decision at which they arrived,
      appears inexplicable. The known difference of opinion amongst the best
      observers respecting the repeating principle, ought to have rendered them
      peculiarly cautious, nor ought the opinion of a Troughton, that
      instruments of less than one foot in diameter may be considered, "FOR
      ASTRONOMY, AS LITTLE BETTER THAN PLAYTHINGS," [Memoirs of the Astronomical
      Society, Vol.I. p.53.] to have been rejected without the most carefully
      detailed experiments. There were amongst that body, persons who must have
      examined minutely the work on the Pendulum. Captain Kater must have felt
      those difficulties in the perusal of it which other observers have
      experienced; and he who was placed in the Board of Longitude especially
      for his knowledge of instruments, might, in a few hours, have arrived at
      more decisive facts. But perhaps I am unjust. Captain Kater's knowledge
      rendered it impossible for him to have been ignorant of the difficulties,
      and his candour would have prevented him from concealing them: he must,
      therefore, after examining the subject, have been outvoted by his
      lay-brethren who had dispensed with that preliminary.
    

      It would be unjust, before quitting this subject, not to mention with
      respect the acknowledgment made by an officer of the naval service of the
      errors into which he also fell from this same level. Lieutenant Foster,
      aware of the many occasions on which Captain Sabine had employed this
      instrument, and knowing that he considered each division as equal to one
      second, never thought that a doubt could exist on the subject, and made
      all his calculations accordingly. When Captain Kater made him acquainted
      with the mistake, Lieutenant Foster immediately communicated a paper [The
      paper of Lieutenant Foster is printed in the Philosophical Transactions,
      1827, p.122, and is worth consulting.] to the Royal Society, in which he
      states the circumstance most fully, and recomputed all the observations in
      which that instrument was used. Unfortunately, from the original
      observations of Mr. Ross being left on board the Fury at the time of her
      loss, the transcripts of his results could not be recomputed like the
      rest, and were consequently useless.
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>