<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 165, folios 178-183</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 165, folios 178-183.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1840">undated (estimated from box 165 date range)</date>
          <note type="place">[no place]</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 165, folios 178-183</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_165_folios_178-183.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Saturday</p>
      <p>Dearest W. I have given your letters to the Hen, who has been with me this afternoon.</p>
      <p>From the enclosed (received from her on Thursday), you will perceive that I had stated to you quite correctly what she told me about Lady</p>
      <p>H, but that her opinion subsequently altered, on re-consideration.</p>
      <p>I am in great delight &amp; excitement, at finding I am to learn singing of Herr Staudigl, when he arrives for the German Opera. There is no such singer &amp; dramatist I believe in Europe.</p>
      <p>Mr Rousselet has decided this choice of a master for me.-- I had left it to Rousselet, knowing that</p>
      <p>he is the best of judges on such a subject.--</p>
      <p>Rousselet is astonished at my powers, both musical &amp; dramatic, &amp; says that I must sing Scenas by &amp; bye; as such a genius must not be lost to my friends &amp; society. In scena - singing you know there is real acting , just as on the stage. For example I should sing a scena</p>
      <p>from Norma, (one of those between her &amp; Pollio say), in the little-library at Ockham, I &amp; my Pollio being in our ordinary dresses, but doing it exactly as is done on the stage; &amp; the audience sitting in the large library, we merely placing ourselves so as to be seen thro' the folding-doors.--</p>
      <p>This would be to me the greatest of enjoyments,</p>
      <p>&amp; will give you much to be proud &amp; fond of. They all say that my dramatic genius is something wonderful; &amp; the more scope I have in prospect for it, the more settled, calm, &amp; happy, does my mind become. The style of song that best suits me is that in which there is the expression of deep &amp; stirring &amp; generous sentiments, like those</p>
      <p>in Norma for instance; &amp; also those in which there is vengeance [very thick underline] scorn &amp; indignation. Perhaps the latter you would not have imagined would be my line.</p>
      <p>But it is marvellous, they tell me, how powerfully I can express scorn &amp; fury, &amp; get my action being all the while so tranquil &amp; so removed from the</p>
      <p>stage . But it is with a glance, on the motion of an arm or hand, that I [two words crossed out] so naturally &amp; so powerfully give those feelings. There is a famous song of Norma's in which she says the single words "Indegno," (to Pollio), "tu preghi alfine."</p>
      <p>The manner in which I do this is I believe admirable, in its mixture of scornful pride and indignation. I don't think</p>
      <p>I am growing conceited, pray. But I speak of myself as I should of another; &amp; rejoice in the pleasure I think my rare musical genius will by &amp; bye be able to afford to you, &amp; others.</p>
      <p>A singing &amp; acting Avis, would be delightful. Think how mwerrily &amp; joyously evenings would go; &amp; how delightful when we have company, to be able to inspire them a little, as I know I could, thro' song!</p>
      <p>It is a great &amp; glorious gift to have, where as with me it results from deep &amp; powerful &amp; generous feelings. For there is a mysterious kind of mesmerism in such expression as I am likely to be able to give, which ennobles the hearts of those who listen .--</p>
      <p>May I be one day worthy of the name of Phoenix, which you now bestow on</p>
      <p>one who as yet has done little to deserve it.--</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
