<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="40">

BOOK XII.

MAGNETISM.

Recent Progress of Terrestrial Magnetism.
IN Chapter II., I have noticed the history of Terrestrial Magnetism;
Hansteen’s map published in 1819; the discovery of “magnetic storms”
about 1825; the chain of associated magnetic observations, suggested
by M. de Humboldt, and promoted by the British Association and the
Royal Society; the demand for the continuation of these till 1848; the
magnetic observations made in several voyages; the magnetic surveys of
various countries. And I have spoken also of Gauss’s theory of
Terrestrial Magnetism, and his directions and requirements concerning
the observations to be made. I may add a few words with regard to the
more recent progress of the subject.
The magnetic observations made over large portions of the Earth’s
surface by various persons, and on the Ocean by British officers, have
been transmitted to Woolwich, where they have been employed by General
Sabine in constructing magnetic maps of the Earth for the year 1840.18 Following the course of inquiry
described in the part of the history referred to, these maps exhibit
the declination, inclination, and intensity of the magnetic force at
every point of the earth’s surface. The curves which mark equal
amounts of each of these three elements (the lines of equal
declination, inclination, and force:—the
isogonal, the isoclinal, and the isodynamic
lines,) are, in their general form, complex and irregular; and it has
been made a matter of question (the facts being agreed upon) whether
it be more proper to say that they indicate four poles, as Halley and
as Hansteen said, or only two poles, as Gauss asserts. The matter
appears to become more clear if we draw magnetic meridians;
that is, lines obtained by following the directions, or pointings, of
the magnetic needle to the north or to 614 the south, till we arrive at the points
of convergence of all their directions; for there are only two such
poles, one in the Arctic and one in the Antarctic region. But in
consequence of the irregularity of the magnetic constitution of the
earth, if we follow the inclination of the magnetic force round the
earth on any parallel of latitude, we find that it has two
maxima and two minima, as if there were four magnetic
poles. The isodynamic map is a new presentation of the facts of this
subject; the first having been constructed by Colonel Sabine in
1837.</div></body></text></TEI>