<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="22">CHAPTER XX.
The morning after my return to my family, as I sat surrounded
with my girls, and endeavouring to make myself
their playmate and companion, certain officers of justice
belonging to the supreme tribunal of the city entered my
apartment. They were sent, as they informed me, to conduct
me to prison. My blood at this intelligence mounted
into my face.
“To prison?” cried I—“wherefore?—what have I
done?—I am no citizen of your state. What is the charge
against me? Lead me not to prison: lead me to your
chief magistrate!”
“You will be called up for examination, when his honour
is at leisure to hear you: in the mean time you must
go to prison.”
“Do those who sent you know that I am a native and
a gentleman of France? They will be made to repent this
insolence. Upon what pretence do they dare to act thus?”
“You will please not to talk of insolence to us. If you
do not demean yourself quietly——”
“Silence, fellow!” answered I fiercely. “Lead the
way!”
[215]
By this time the children, astonished at a scene so alarming
and unintelligible to them, began to express their terror
in various ways. Julia, who was ready to faint, occupied
the attention of her mother. The little Marguerite clung
round my knees, and expressed her emotions by shrieks and
cries. To see her father about to be torn from her by four
strangers, the peculiarity of whose garb of office aggravated
the rudeness of their countenances and the peremptoriness
of their behaviour, was a spectacle which the affectionateness
of her nature was unable to endure.
“I will go with you presently,” said I to the officers.
“See, how you have terrified the children!”
“Nay, sir, if you will behave civilly, and make it worth
our while, we do not desire to hurry you.”
I was stung with the brutal assurance with which they
thus set the liberty of a few moments at a price to me. But
I checked my impatience. I felt that it would be both
foolish and degrading to enter into contention with such
wretches. I turned from them proudly, and took my child
in my arms.
“I will not be long gone, my love!” said I. “These
people have made a mistake, and I shall soon be able to
rectify it.”
“I fancy not,” muttered one of them surlily.
“They shall not take you away, papa; that they shall
not! I will hold you, and will not let you go!”
“You are a good girl, Marguerite! But I know best
what is proper, and you must not think to control me.
The men will not do me any harm, child; they dare not.
Perhaps I shall be back to dinner, and mamma will then
tell me how good you have been.”
As I spoke, she looked steadfastly in my face; and then,
flinging her arms round my neck, cried, “Good-by, papa!”
and burst into a flood of tears.
I embraced the other children and their mother; and,
saying to the latter significantly, “Fear nothing; you
know I have nothing to fear!”—departed with my conductors.
The way to the citadel lay through the market-place.
The scene was already crowded; and I had the mortification[216]
to be led along as a criminal, in the midst of a thousand
gazing eyes and enquiring tongues. New as every
thing connected with my present situation was to me, I had
not anticipated this vexation. I was stung with shame and
impatience. “To my dungeon!” said I to my conductors
sternly. “If you had shown yourself better humoured,”
cried the most brutal of them, “we would have led you
round by the back way.”
The master of the prison was somewhat less a savage
than his officers. He knew my person, and had heard of
my wealth. “Does monsieur choose the best apartment?”
said he. “Any where that I can be alone!” answered
I hastily. He hesitated a moment. I looked in his face:
“Oh, yes, you will be paid!” He bowed, and showed
me to a room.
I shut the door as he retired. What had happened to
me was of little importance in itself. The impertinence of
bailiffs and thief-takers is of no more real moment than the
stinging of a gnat. But I was so utterly unacquainted with
scenes of this nature! The pride of rank that swelled
within me made every appearance of restraint galling to
my sense. From the instant I was able to write, man, no
one, except in the voluntary compact of military service,
had ever said to me, Go there! or, Do this! And now,
was I to be directed by the very refuse of the species? Was
I to learn the prudence of not replying to their insults?
Was I to purchase, at a stipulated price, their patience and
forbearance?—I request the reader to pardon me for troubling
him with my noviciate feelings: I soon learned to
understand the world—the world of a prison—better!
But, what was of more importance, I was apprehended
as a criminal: I had been dragged a prisoner of justice
through the streets of Constance; I was, by and by, to be
subjected to the interrogatories of the municipal tribunal.
I could scarcely credit my senses, that such an indignity
had happened to the blood of St. Leon. It is true, I was
innocent. I was conscious, whatever might be my imprudences
and offences towards my own family, that I had
done nothing to merit the animadversion of public justice.
But this was of no consequence. Nothing, in my opinion,[217]
could wipe away the disgrace of being interrogated, examined!
of having for an instant imputed to me the possibility
of being a criminal! I writhed under this dishonour,
and felt it as a severer attack than the question, which was
comparatively of ceremony and etiquette, that had oppressed
me in my residence at Dresden.
The next day, when I was brought up for examination,
I had expected to be the complainant, in demanding redress
for the injury I had sustained. But I was mistaken.
I entered the room haughtily, and with the air of a man
that felt himself aggrieved. Of this however the magistrate
took no notice. “Do you know, sir,” said I, “that I am
a citizen and a gentleman of France? Are you acquainted
with the treatment I have experienced? Have you lent
your authority to that treatment?”
“Wait a few minutes,” replied he with an imperious
tone, “and I shall be at leisure to attend to you.”
I was silent. After the interval of nearly a quarter of
an hour, he resumed—
“You call yourself the count de St. Leon!”
“I do.”
“Perhaps, sir, you are uninformed of the purity with
which justice is administered in the city within whose jurisdiction
you now stand. Our state is a small one, and its
magistrates are therefore enabled to discharge the office of
a parent, not only to its proper citizens, but to all strangers
that place themselves under its protection.”
“I remember, sir, that seven years ago, I and my wife
and four children, sick and unfriended, were upon the
point of perishing with hunger within the walls of this
city!”—The fact I mentioned was wholly foreign to the
point with which I was at present concerned; but the
parading arrogance of the man brought it forcibly to my
memory, and wrung it from my lips.
“Monsieur le comte,” replied he, “you are petulant.
It is not the office of a state to feed the souls it contains;
it could not do that without making them slaves. Its
proper concern is to maintain them in that security and
freedom of action, which may best enable them to support
themselves.”
[218]
I suppressed the emotions which the tone of this speech
excited. I was unwilling to enter into contention with a man
whom I regarded as inexpressibly my inferior.
“Is it,” cried I sternly, “a part of the justice you boast
of, to drag a man of rank and a stranger from his home,
without any intimation of the cause of his being so treated,
and then, instead of investigating immediately the charge
against him, to send him to prison unheard? I disdain to
mention the behaviour of your officers: those things naturally
grow out of the abuses practised by their superiors.”
“The mode of our proceeding,” replied he, “depends
upon the seriousness of the crime imputed. If a man of
distinction labours under a slight accusation only, we then
treat him with all proper forbearance and respect. But,
when he is suspected of a crime of more than ordinary
magnitude, that alters the case. The man who has ceased
to respect himself, must look for no respect from others.”
I was for a moment thunderstruck and speechless. At
length fiercely I cried, “Produce my accusers!”
“That is not the mode of proceeding in Constance. I
have certain questions to propound to you. When you have
answered them, we shall see what is to be done next.”
“Carry me before the prince-bishop of your city! If I
am to be examined further, let it be by your sovereign!”
“The prince-bishop, moved by the state of our affairs in
matters of religion, has been prevailed on to delegate his
juridical authority. I am the person to whom the cognisance
of your business belongs; and at certain times, aided
by my assessors, have the power of life and death within
this city. You have had every indulgence to which you
are entitled, and it will be your wisdom to be no further
refractory.”
“Propose your questions!”
“A person, apparently greatly advanced in years, arrived
in the autumn of last year at a miserable farm you at that
time cultivated, called the Cottage of the Lake. It is to
him that my questions will principally relate.”
I stood aghast. The words of the magistrate were most
unwelcome sounds. I remembered that the stranger had
said to me, “When I am once buried, speak of me, and,[219]
if possible, think of me no more.” I replied with eagerness
and alarm—
“Of that person I have nothing to say. Spare your
questions: I have no answer to return you!”
“What was his name?”
“I know not.”
“His country?”
“I cannot inform you.”
“It is understood that he died, or in some manner disappeared,
while under your protection. Yet in the registers
of the church there is no notice of that event. If he
died, no application was made for the rites of religion to
him dying, or to his body when his spirit had deserted it.
You are required to answer, what became of him or his
remains?”
“I have already told you, that from me you will obtain
no information.”
“One question more, sir. Seven years ago, you tell me,
you and your family were perishing with hunger. Soon
after, you removed from obscure lodgings in this city to
the cottage of the lake, and seemed to be laudably employed
in earning for yourself a scanty livelihood with the labour
of your hands. But within the last six months the scene
is wholly changed. You appear to have suddenly grown
rich, and here, and in other parts of Germany, have actually
disbursed considerable sums. Whence comes this
change?”
The train of questions thus proposed to me, impelled me
to a serious reply.
“Monsieur le juge,” said I, “I am a stranger, a native
of France, and a man of rank in my own country. I have
paid your state the compliment of choosing it for my residence.
I have expended my industry, I expend my wealth
among you. I have comported myself as a peaceable inhabitant.
No action of my life has brought scandal upon
your state, or disturbed the peace and tranquillity of your
affairs. I cannot collect from any thing you have said,
that I have any accuser, or that any charge has been alleged
against me. Till that happens, I cannot fall under
your animadversion. I am a man of generous birth and[220]
honourable sentiments. To myself and my own conscience
only am I accountable for my expenditure and my income.
I disdain to answer to any tribunal on earth an enquiry of
this sort. And now, sir, in conclusion, what I demand of
you is, first, my liberty; and secondly, an ample reparation
for the interruption I have sustained, and the insults to
which I have causelessly been exposed.”
“You are mistaken, sir,” said the magistrate. “What
you mention may be the rule of administering justice in
some states. They may decide, if they think proper, that
some open act, apparently of a criminal description, must
be alleged against a man, before he can become an object of
animadversion to the state. But in Constance, as I have
already told you, the government assumes to act the part of
a parent to its subjects. I sit here, not merely to investigate
and examine definite acts, but as a censor morum; and
I should violate the oath of my office, if I did not lend a
vigilant attention to the behaviour and conduct of every one
within my jurisdiction. The city of Constance requires
that nothing immoral, licentious, or of suspicious character,
shall be transacted within its walls. Your proceedings
have escaped notice too long; much longer than they would
have done but for your late absence. In cases where what
is committed is merely immoral or licentious, we content
ourselves with sending the offender out of our walls. But
your case is of a complicated nature. It has scandalised
all the inhabitants of our virtuous and religious city. Unless
you answer my enquiries, and give a clear and satisfactory
account of your wealth, I am bound to believe that
there is something in the business that will not bear the
light. The coincidence of times obliges me to connect the
disappearance of your guest, and the sudden growth of your
fortune. This connection gives rise to the most alarming
suspicions. I have therefore to inform you that, unless
you honourably clear up these suspicions by the most ample
communication, my duty directs me to remand you to
prison, and to assure you that you will not be liberated
thence till you have satisfied the whole of my interrogatories.”
“Think deliberately,” answered I, “of your decision[221]
before you form it. Your prisons I despise; but I will
not suffer my reputation and my honour to be trifled with.
I came before you willingly, though I could easily have
avoided doing so; because I was eager to clear my fame.
I expected accusers, and I knew I could confound accusation.
But what is this that you call justice? You put
together circumstances in your own mind: you form conjectures;
and then, without information, accuser, or oath,
without the semblance of guilt, you condemn me to prison,
and expect to extort from me confession. In defect of
articles of charge I disdain to answer: the only return a
man of honour should make to loose conjectures and random
calumnies is silence. I am descended from a race of
heroes, knights of the cross, and champions of France; and
their blood has not degenerated in my veins. I feel myself
animated by the soul of honour, and incapable of crime.
I know my innocence, and I rest upon it with confidence.
Your vulgar citizens, habituated to none but the groveling
notions of traffic and barter, are not the peers of St. Leon,
nor able to comprehend the views and sentiments by which
he is guided.”
“You are mighty well-spoken, monsieur St. Leon,” replied
the magistrate, “and your words are big and sounding;
but we know that the devil can assume the form of an angel,
and that the most infamous and profligate character can
pronounce with emphasis sentiments of the purest virtue.
You are pleased to decide that the presumptions against you
are nothing but calumnies. Is it nothing that, having received
a stranger and retained him with you for months,
you endeavoured to conceal this fact, and never suffered
him to be seen by a human creature? Is his final disappearance
nothing? Is it nothing that, supposing him to be
dead, as he probably is, you denied to his remains the rites
of funeral, and refuse to tell what is become of the body?
Is it nothing that, upon the death of this stranger, you,
who were before in a state almost of penury, suddenly appear
to be possessed of unbounded riches? Where is the
will of this stranger? In what archives have you deposited
the declaration of his wealth? Let me tell you, sir, that
these presumptions, which you call nothing, form a body of[222]
circumstantial evidence that, in many countries, would have
led you to the scaffold as a murderer. But the laws of
Constance, which you audaciously revile, are the mildest in
the universe. Here we never put a man to death but on
his own confession. We simply condemn him to perpetual
imprisonment, or until he makes a declaration of his guilt.
You refuse to declare the name or country of the man
whom you are suspected of murdering, and then have the
assurance to boast that no private accuser rises against you.
No, sir, we know there can be no private accuser, where the
connections of the party can be successfully concealed. But
shall this concealment, which is an aggravation of the murder,
prove its security? In conclusion, you boast of your
blood and heroic sentiments, and rail at our citizens as
shopkeepers and merchants. Let me tell you, sir, shopkeepers
and merchants though we are, we should scorn to
conduct ourselves in the obscure and suspicious manner
that you have done. And, now I have taken the trouble
to refute your flimsy pretences, which it was wholly unnecessary
for me to do, I have done with you. You know
your destination, unless you are prepared immediately to give
a satisfactory account of yourself and your proceedings.”
Finding it impossible to make on this man the impression
I desired, I declined entering into further parley; and,
telling him that I should convey a representation of my
case to my native sovereign, and did not doubt soon to
make him feel the rashness of his proceeding, I withdrew,
in the custody of the officers who had conducted me to the
scene of audience. I was, I confess, struck with the coincidence
of circumstances, which the magistrate had placed
in a fight equally unexpected and forcible, and which I
now saw calculated to subject me to the most injurious
suspicions. I was not disposed in the smallest degree to
yield to the attack, but I felt a desire to act deliberately
and with caution. The whole of what I had heard was
utterly unforeseen, and it was with peculiar anguish that I
became aware of this new consequence of the stranger’s pernicious
donation. This was a consequence that no resignation,
no abjuration of his bequests could cure; and that
must be stood up to with manly courage, if any hope were
entertained of averting it.

[223]</div></body></text></TEI>