<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="12">

CHAPTER III.
OF SIMPLE IDEAS OF SENSE.

1. Division of simple ideas.


The better to conceive the ideas we receive from sensation, it may not be amiss
for us to consider them, in reference to the different ways whereby they make
their approaches to our minds, and make themselves perceivable by us.


FIRST, then, There are some which come into our minds BY ONE SENSE ONLY.


SECONDLY, There are others that convey themselves into the mind BY MORE SENSES
THAN ONE.


THIRDLY, Others that are had from REFLECTION ONLY.


FOURTHLY, There are some that make themselves way, and are suggested to the
mind BY ALL THE WAYS OF SENSATION AND REFLECTION.


We shall consider them apart under these several heads.


Ideas of one Sense.


There are some ideas which have admittance only through one sense, which is
peculiarly adapted to receive them. Thus light and colours, as white, red,
yellow, blue; with their several degrees or shades and mixtures, as green,
scarlet, purple, sea-green, and the rest, come in only by the eyes. All kinds
of noises, sounds, and tones, only by the ears. The several tastes and smells,
by the nose and palate. And if these organs, or the nerves which are the
conduits to convey them from without to their audience in the brain,—the
mind’s presence-room (as I may so call it)—are any of them so disordered
as not to perform their functions, they have no postern to be admitted by; no
other way to bring themselves into view, and be perceived by the understanding.


The most considerable of those belonging to the touch, are heat and cold, and
solidity: all the rest, consisting almost wholly in the sensible configuration,
as smooth and rough; or else, more or less firm adhesion of the parts, as hard
and soft, tough and brittle, are obvious enough.


2. Few simple Ideas have Names.


I think it will be needless to enumerate all the particular simple ideas
belonging to each sense. Nor indeed is it possible if we would; there being a
great many more of them belonging to most of the senses than we have names for.
The variety of smells, which are as many almost, if not more, than species of
bodies in the world, do most of them want names. Sweet and stinking commonly
serve our turn for these ideas, which in effect is little more than to call
them pleasing or displeasing; though the smell of a rose and violet, both
sweet, are certainly very distinct ideas. Nor are the different tastes, that by
our palates we receive ideas of, much better provided with names. Sweet,
bitter, sour, harsh, and salt are almost all the epithets we have to denominate
that numberless variety of relishes, which are to be found distinct, not only
in almost every sort of creatures, but in the different parts of the same
plant, fruit, or animal. The same may be said of colours and sounds. I shall,
therefore, in the account of simple ideas I am here giving, content myself to
set down only such as are most material to our present purpose, or are in
themselves less apt to be taken notice of though they are very frequently the
ingredients of our complex ideas; amongst which, I think, I may well account
solidity, which therefore I shall treat of in the next chapter.


</div></body></text></TEI>