<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="110">CHAPTER VI.
Correction of the Law of the same Angle for the same
Substance.
DISCOVERY of Isomorphism.
Mitscherlich.—The discovery of which we now have to speak
may appear at first sight too large to be included in the history of
crystallography, and may seem to belong rather to chemistry. But it is
to be recollected that crystallography, from the time of its first
assuming importance in the hands of Haüy, founded its claim to notice
entirely upon its connexion with chemistry; crystalline forms were
properties of something; but what that something
was, and how it might be modified without becoming something else, no
crystallographer could venture to decide, without the aid of chemical
analysis. Haüy had assumed, as the general result of his researches,
that the same chemical elements, combined in the same proportions,
would always exhibit the same crystalline form; and reciprocally, that
the same form and angles (except in the obvious case of the tessular
system, in which the angles are determined by its being the
tessular system,) implied the same chemical constitution. But this
dogma could only be considered as an approximate conjecture; for there
were many glaring and unexplained exceptions to it. The explanation of
several of these was beautifully described by the discovery that there
are various elements which are isomorphous to each other; that
is, such that one may take the place of another without altering the
crystalline form; and thus the chemical composition may be much
changed, while the crystallographic character is undisturbed.
This truth had been caught sight of, probably as a guess only, by
Fuchs as early as 1815. In speaking of a mineral which had been called
Gehlenite, he says, “I hold the oxide of iron, not for an essential
component part of this genus, but only as a vicarious
element, replacing so much lime. We shall find it necessary to
consider the results of several analyses of mineral bodies in this
point of view, if we wish, on the one hand, to bring them into
agreement with the doctrine of chemical proportions, and on the other,
to avoid unnecessarily splitting up genera.” In a lecture On the
Mutual Influence of 335 Chemistry and Mineralogy,36 he again draws attention to his term
vicarious (vicarirende), which undoubtedly expresses the
nature of the general law afterwards established by Mitscherlich in
1822.
36 Munich, 1820.
But Fuchs’s conjectural expression was only a prelude to
Mitscherlich’s experimental discovery of isomorphism. Till many
careful analyses had given substance and signification to this
conception of vicarious elements, it was of small value. Perhaps no
one was more capable than Berzelius of turning to the best advantage
any ideas which were current in the chemical world; yet we find him,37 in 1820, dwelling upon a certain vague
view of these cases,—that “oxides which contain equal doses of
oxygen must have their general properties common;” without tracing it
to any definite conclusions. But his scholar, Mitscherlich, gave this
proposition a real crystallographical import. Thus he found that the
carbonates of lime (calcspar,) of magnesia, of protoxide of iron, and
of protoxide of manganese, agree in many respects of form, while the
homologous angles vary through one or two degrees only; so again the
carbonates of baryta, strontia, lead, and lime (arragonite), agree
nearly; the different kinds of felspar vary only by the substitution
of one alkali for another; the phosphates are almost identical with
the arseniates of several bases. These, and similar results, were
expressed by saying that, in such cases, the bases, lime, protoxide of
iron, and the rest, are isomorphous; or in the latter instance,
that the arsenic and phosphoric acids are isomorphous.
37 Essay on the Theory of Chemical
Proportions, p. 122.
Since, in some of these cases, the substitution of one element of
the isomorphous group for another does alter the angle, though
slightly, it has since been proposed to call such groups
plesiomorphous.
This discovery of isomorphism was of great importance, and excited
much attention among the chemists of Europe. The history of its
reception, however, belongs, in part, to the classification of
minerals; for its effect was immediately to metamorphose the existing
chemical systems of arrangement. But even those crystallographers and
chemists who cared little for general systems of classification,
received a powerful impulse by the expectation, which was now excited,
of discovering definite laws connecting chemical constitution with
crystalline form. Such investigations were soon carried on with great
activity. Thus, at a recent period, Abich analysed a number of
tessular minerals, spinelle, pleonaste, gahnite, franklinite, and
chromic iron oxide; and 336 seems to have had some success in giving a common
type to their chemical formulæ, as there is a common type in their
crystallization.
[2nd Ed.] [It will be seen by the above account that Prof.
Mitscherlich’s merit in the great discovery of Isomorphism is not at
all narrowed by the previous conjectures of M. Fuchs. I am informed,
moreover, that M. Fuchs afterwards (in Schweigger’s Journal)
retracted the opinions he had put forward on this subject.]
Dimorphism.—My business is, to point out the connected
truths which have been obtained by philosophers, rather than insulated
difficulties which still stand out to perplex them. I need not,
therefore, dwell on the curious cases of dimorphism; cases in
which the same definite chemical compound of the same elements appears
to have two different forms; thus the carbonate of lime has two forms,
calcspar and arragonite, which belong to different
systems of crystallization. Such facts may puzzle us; but they hardly
interfere with any received general truths, because we have as yet no
truths of very high order respecting the connexion of chemical
constitution and crystalline form. Dimorphism does not interfere with
isomorphism; the two classes of facts stand at the same stage of
inductive generalization, and we wait for some higher truth which
shall include both, and rise above them.
[2nd Ed.] [For additions to our knowledge of the Dimorphism of
Bodies, see Professor Johnstone’s valuable Report on that
subject in the Reports of the British Association for 1837.
Substances have also been found which are trimorphous. We owe
to Professor Mitscherlich the discovery of dimorphism, as well as of
isomorphism: and to him also we owe the greater part of the knowledge
to which these discoveries have led.]
</div></body></text></TEI>