<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Vestiges of the Natural History of Creation</title><author>Chambers, Robert (1802-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="7">p. 94ERA OF
THE NEW RED SANDSTONE.
TERRESTRIAL ZOOLOGY COMMENCES
WITH REPTILES.
FIRST TRACES OF BIRDS.
The next volume of the rock series
refers to an era distinguished by an event of no less importance
than the commencement of land animals.  The New Red
Sandstone System is subdivided into groups, some of which are
wanting in some places; they are pretty fully developed in the
north of England, in the following ascending
order:—1.  Lower red sandstone; 2.  Magnesian
limestone; 3.  Red and white sandstones and conglomerate;
4.  Variegated marls.  Between the third and fourth
there is, in Germany, another group, called the Muschelkalk, a
word expressing a limestone full of shells.
The first group, containing the conglomerates already adverted
to, seems to have been produced during the time of disturbance
which occurred so generally after the carbonigenous era. 
This new era is distinguished by a paucity of organic remains, as
might partly be expected from the appearances of disturbance, and
the red tint of the rocks, the latter being communicated by a
solution of oxide of iron, a substance unfavourable to animal
life.
The second group is a limestone with an infusion of
magnesia.  It is developed less generally than some others,
but occurs conspicuously in England and Germany.  Its place,
above the red sandstone, shews the recurrence of circumstances
favourable to animal life, and we accordingly find in it not only
zoophytes, conchifera, and a few tribes of fish, but some faint
traces of land plants, and a new and startling appearance—a
reptile of saurian (lizard) character, analogous to the now
existing family called monitors.  Remains of this creature
are found in cupriferous (copper-bearing) slate connected with
the mountain limestone, at Mansfield and Glucksbrunn, in Germany,
which may be taken as evidence that dry land existed in that age
near those places.  The magnesia limestone is also
remarkable as the last rock in which appears the leptæna,
or producta, a conchifer of numerous species which makes a
conspicuous appearance in all previous seas.  It is likewise
to be observed, that the fishes of this age, to the genera of
which the names palæoniscus, catopterus, platysomus,
&c., have been applied, vanish, and henceforth appear no
more.
The third group, chiefly sandstones, variously coloured
according to the amount and nature of the metallic oxide infused
into them, shews a recurrence of agitation, and a consequent
diminution of the amount of animal life.  In the upper part,
however, of this group, there are abundant symptoms of a revival
of proper conditions for such life.  There are marl beds,
the origin of which substance in decomposed shells is obvious;
and in Germany, though not in England, here occurs the
muschelkalk, containing numerous organic remains, (generally
different from those of the magnesian limestone,) and noted for
the specimens of land animals, which it is the first to present
in any considerable abundance to our notice.
These animals are of the vertebrate sub-kingdom, but of its
lowest class next after fishes,—namely, reptiles,—a
portion of the terrestrial tribes whose imperfect respiratory
system perhaps fitted them for enduring an atmosphere not yet
quite suitable for birds or mammifers. [97]  The specimens found in the
muschelkalk are allied to the crocodile and lizard tribes of the
present day, but in the latter instance are upon a scale of
magnitude as much superior to present forms as the lepidodendron
of the coal era was superior to the dwarf club-mosses of our
time.  These saurians also combine some peculiarities of
structure of a most extraordinary character.
The animal to which the name ichthyosaurus has been
given, was as long as a young whale, and it was fitted for living
in the water, though breathing the atmosphere.  It had the
vertebral column and general bodily form of a fish, but to that
were added the head and breast-bone of a lizard, and the paddles
of the whale tribes.  The beak, moreover, was that of a
porpoise, and the teeth were those of a crocodile.  It must
have been a most destructive creature to the fish of those early
seas.
The plesiosaurus was of similar bulk, with a
turtle-like body and paddles, shewing that the sea was its
element, but with a long serpent-like neck, terminating in a
saurian head, calculated to reach prey at a considerable
distance.  These two animals, of which many varieties have
been discovered, constituting distinct species, are supposed to
have lived in the shallow borders of the seas of this and
subsequent formations, devouring immense quantities of the finny
tribes.  It was at first thought that no creatures
approaching them in character now inhabit the earth; but latterly
Mr. Darwin has discovered, in the reptile-peopled Galapagos
Islands, in the South Sea, a marine saurian from three to four
feet long.
The megalosaurus was an enormous lizard—a land
creature, also carnivorous.  The pterodactyle was
another lizard, but furnished with wings to pursue its prey in
the air, and varying in size between a cormorant and a
snipe.  Crocodiles abounded, and some of these were
herbivorous.  Such was the iguanodon, a creature of the
character of the iguana of the Ganges, but reaching a hundred
feet in length, or twenty times that of its modern
representative.
There were also numerous tortoises, some of them
reaching a great size; and Professor Owen has found in
Warwickshire some remains of an animal of the batrachian order,
[99] to which, from the peculiar form of the
teeth, he has given the name of labyrinthidon.  Thus, three
of Cuvier’s four orders of reptilia (sauria,
chelonia, and batrachia) are represented in this
formation, the serpent order (ophidia) being alone
wanting.
The variegated marl beds which constitute the uppermost group
of the formation, present two additional genera of huge
saurians,—the phytosaurus and mastodonsaurus.
It is in the upper beds of the red sandstone that beds of salt
first occur.  These are sometimes of such thickness, that
the mine from which the material has been excavated looks like a
lofty church.  We see in the present world no circumstances
calculated to produce the formation of a bed of rock salt; yet it
is not difficult to understand how such strata were formed in an
age marked by ultra-tropical heat and frequent volcanic
disturbances.  An estuary, cut off by an upthrow of trap, or
a change of level, and left to dry up under the heat of the sun,
would quickly become the bed of a dense layer of rock salt. 
A second shift of level, or some other volcanic disturbance,
connecting it again with the sea, would expose this stratum to
being covered over with a layer of sand or mud, destined in time
to form the next stratum of rock above it.
The plants of this era are few and unobtrusive. 
Equiseta, calamites, ferns, Voltzia, and a few of the other
families found so abundantly in the preceding formation, here
present themselves, but in diminished size and quantity.
This seems to be the proper place to advert to certain
memorials of a peculiar and unexpected character respecting these
early ages in the sandstones.  So low as the bottom of the
carboniferous system, slabs are found marked over a great extent
of surface with that peculiar corrugation or wrinkling which the
receding tide leaves upon a sandy beach when the sea is but
slightly agitated; and not only are these ripple-marks, as they
are called, found on the surfaces, but casts of them are found on
the under sides of slabs lying above.  The phenomena
suggests the time when the sand ultimately formed into these
stone slabs, was part of the beach of a sea of the carbonigenous
era; when, left wavy by one tide, it was covered over with a thin
layer of fresh sand by the next, and so on, precisely as such
circumstances might be expected to take place at the present
day.  Sandstone surfaces, ripple-marked, are found
throughout the subsequent formations: in those of the new red, at
more than one place in England, they further bear impressions of
rain-drops which have fallen upon them—the rain, of course,
of the inconceivably remote age in which the sandstones were
formed.  In the Greensill sandstone, near Shrewsbury, it has
even been possible to tell from what direction the shower came
which impressed the sandy surface, the rims of the marks being
somewhat raised on one side, exactly as might be expected from a
slanting shower falling at this day upon one of our
beaches.  These facts have the same sort of interest as the
season rings of the Craigleith conifers, as speaking of a parity
between some of the familiar processes of nature in those early
ages and our own.
In the new red sandstone, impressions still more important in
the inferences to which they tend, have been
observed,—namely, the footmarks of various animals. 
In a quarry of this formation, at Corncockle Muir, in
Dumfriesshire, where the slabs incline at an angle of
thirty-eight degrees, the vestiges of an animal supposed to have
been a tortoise are distinctly traced up and down the slope, as
if the creature had had occasion to pass backwards and forwards
in that direction only, possibly in its daily visits to the
sea.  Some slabs similarly impressed, in the Stourton
quarries in Cheshire, are further marked with a shower of rain
which we know must have fallen afterwards, for its little
hollows are impressed in the footmarks also, though more slightly
than on the rest of the surface, the comparative hardness of a
trodden place having apparently prevented so deep an impression
being made.  At Hessberg, in Saxony, the vestiges of four
distinct animals have been traced, one of them a web-footed
animal of small size, considered as a congener of the crocodile;
another, whose footsteps having a resemblance to an impression of
a swelled human hand, has caused it to be named the
cheirotherium.  The footsteps of the cheirotherium
have been found also in the Stourton quarries above
mentioned.  Professor Owen, who stands at the head of
comparative anatomy in the present day, has expressed his belief
that this last animal was the same batrachian of which he has
found fragments in the new red sandstone of Warwickshire. 
At Runcorn, near Manchester, and elsewhere, have been discovered
the tracks of an animal which Mr. Owen calls the rynchosaurus,
uniting with the body of a reptile the beak and feet of a bird,
and which clearly had been a link between these two
classes.
If geologists shall ultimately give their approbation to the
inferences made from a recent discovery in America, we shall have
the addition of perfect birds, though probably of a low type, to
the animal forms of this era.  It is stated to be in
quarries of this rock, in the valley of Connecticut, that
footprints have been found, apparently produced by birds of the
order grallæ, or waders.  “The footsteps appear
in regular succession on the continuous track of an animal, in
the act of walking or running, with the right and left foot
always in their relative places.  The distance of the
intervals between each footstep on the same track is occasionally
varied, but to no greater amount than may be explained by the
bird having altered its pace.  Many tracks of different
individuals and different species are often found crossing each
other, and crowded, like impressions of feet upon the shores of a
muddy stream, where ducks and geese resort.” [103]  Some of these prints indicate
small animals, but others denote birds of what would now be an
unusually large size.  One animal, having a foot fifteen
inches in length, (one-half more than that of the ostrich,) and a
stride of from four to six feet, has been appropriately entitled,
ornithichnites giganteus.</div></body></text></TEI>