<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="5">CHAPTER III.
The lists of military ambition then being closed, if not
permanently, at least for a time, my mind took a new bias;
and, without dismissing its most cherished and darling passion,
pursued a path in the present emergency, to which
the accidents of my youth had also guided me. If my
mother had survived, she would probably either not have consented
to my serving at the siege of Pavia, or at least would
have recalled me to the obscurity of my paternal château
as soon as the campaign was at an end. I had not fully
completed the twentieth year of my age, at the period of the
memorable battle in which my sovereign was made prisoner.
I was left without adviser or guide; even the Marquis de
Villeroy, my mother’s brother, of whatever consequence his
admonitions to me might have proved, was taken from me
in this fatal engagement. The king himself, perhaps, had
it not been for the dreadful calamities in which he was now
involved, might have condescended to interest himself in
some degree in my welfare. By the course of events, I
was left, yet a minor, and with an ample revenue at my
disposition, to be wholly guided by the suggestions of my
own mind.
In the portion of his reign already elapsed, the splendid
and interesting qualities of Francis had given a new spring
to the sentiments of the nation. He was the most accomplished
and amiable prince of the time in which he lived.
There was but one of all the sovereigns of Christendom that
could cope with him in power,—the Emperor Charles; and
as Charles’s peculiarities were of a sort that Frenchmen
were accustomed to regard with aversion and contempt, so[27]
there had not been a doubt among my compatriots, of the
side upon which the superiority would ultimately rest. By
the events of the day of Pavia they were confounded and
overwhelmed. They did not despair of their country; they
soon felt, and felt to its utmost extent, the rank which
France held among the European states. But the chain of
their ideas was interrupted; they could not but be conscious
that the fortune of the kingdom had received a grievous
check. The illustrious career which they had in fancy
already traversed, was postponed to a distant period.
The consequences which flow from a suppressed ambition
may easily be imagined. The nobility of France exchanged
the activity of the field for the indulgences of the table:
that concentrated spirit which had sought to expand itself
upon the widest stage, now found vent in the exhibition of
individual expense: and, above all, the sordid and inglorious
passion for gaming, a vice eminently characteristic of the
age, now especially gained strength, and drew multitudes
into its destructive vortex. It was, perhaps, impossible for
a young man to have entered the theatre of the world under
less favourable auspices.
In what I have already written, I felt myself prompted
to enlarge with complacency upon the sentiments and scenes
of my youth; and I have yielded to the suggestion. The
same internal admonition makes me shrink from entering
with minuteness into the detail of my ruin. I recollect my
infatuation with abhorrence; I fly from the memory with
sensations inexpressibly painful; I regard it as a cloud that
overshadowed and blackened for ever the fair prospects of
my earlier years.
I shall not enumerate all my youthful companions, or all
my youthful follies. I committed a mistake obvious enough,
at this immature period of my existence, when I mistook
profusion and extravagance for splendour and dignity; and
the prudent economy which my mother had practised, served,
in the present instance, as the pander to my vices. The
whole tendency of my education had been to inspire me
with a proud and restless desire of distinction; and I was
not content to play a second part in the career of my vices,
as I should not have been content to play a second part in[28]
the genuine theatre of honour and fame. In all that was
thoughtlessly spirited and gaily profligate, I led the way to
my compeers, and was constantly held up by them as an
example. By this conduct I incurred the censure of the
rigorous and the old; but the voice of censure reached me
much seldomer than that of adulation. My person and
demeanour were the topics of general applause. I was tall
and well-proportioned; my frame was slender and agile,
but with an appearance of the fullest health; my countenance
was open, commanding, and animated: my rank and
situation in the world gave me confidence; the fire and
impetuosity of my temper rendered my gestures easy, rapid,
expressive, and graceful. The consequence of all this was,
to confirm me in a plan of life which I early laid down to
myself, and from which I never in any instance deviated.
I put aside those rules, as splenetic and hypercritical, which
confessors preach, and with which the preceptors of young
men are accustomed to weary and alienate the minds of
their pupils. The charge of being disorderly and unthinking
I despised; that of imprudence, even when meant for
blame, sounded in my ear like the voice of encomium. But,
accustomed from education to sentiments of honour, and
from habit to the language of eulogy, it is difficult for any
man to be more firmly bent than I was to incur no breath
of dishonour, or to draw the line more peremptorily between
the follies of youth and the aberrations of a gross
and unprincipled spirit.
It may be alleged, indeed, and with considerable justice,
that the habit of gaming is an exception to this statement.
It was with hesitation and reluctance that I entered into
this habit. I saw it as it was, and as every ingenuous and
undebauched mind must see it, base and sordid. The possession
of some degree of wealth I regarded, indeed, as indispensable
to a man who would fill a lofty and respectable
character in the world; a character that, by uniting the
advantages of exterior appearance with the actions of a hero,
should extort the homage of his species. But, in the picture
I drew of this man in my mind, I considered wealth
as an accident, the attendant on his birth, to be dispensed
with dignity, not to be adverted to with minuteness of attention.[29]
Deep play is certainly sufficiently inconsistent with
this character. The direct purpose of the gamester is to
transfer money from the pocket of his neighbour into his
own. He rouses his sleepy and wearied attention by the
most sordid of all motives. The fear of losing pierces his
heart with anguish; and to gain—to obtain an advantage
for himself which can scarcely exceed, and which seldom
equals, the injury his competitor suffers,—is the circumstance
which most transports his heart with delight. For this he
watches; for this he calculates. An honourable gamester
does not seize with premeditation the moment when his
adversary is deprived, by wine or any other cause, of his
usual self-possession. He does not seek with sober malice
to play upon his passions. He does not enter with avidity
into the contest with an unpractised but presuming rival:
but he cannot avoid rejoicing, when he finds that accident
has given him an unusual advantage. I have often thought
that I could better understand how a man of honour could
reconcile himself to the accursed and murderous trade of
war, than to the system of the gaming table. In war, he
fights with a stranger, a man with whom he has no habits
of kindness, and who is fairly apprised that he comes against
him with ruinous intent. But in play, he robs, perhaps,
his brother, his friend, the partner of his bosom; or, in
every event, a man seduced into the snare with all the
arts of courtesy, and whom he smiles upon, even while he
stabs.
I am talking here the mere reason and common sense of
the question as it relates to mankind in general. But it is
with other feelings that I reflect upon the concern I have
myself individually in the subject. Years roll on in vain;
ages themselves are useless here; looking forward, as I do,
to an existence that shall endure till time shall be no more;
no time can wipe away the remembrance of the bitter
anguish that I have endured, the consequence of gaming.
It is torture! It is madness! Poverty, I have drained thy
cup to the dregs! I have seen my wife and my children
looking to me in vain for bread! Which is the most intolerable
distress?—that of the period, in which all the comforts
of life gradually left me; in which I caught at every[30]
fragment of promise, and every fragment failed; in which
I rose every morning to pamper myself with empty delusions;
in which I ate the apples of purgatory, fair without,
but within bitterness and ashes; in which I tossed, through
endless, sightless nights, upon the couch of disappointment
and despair?—or the period, when at length all my hopes
were at an end; when I fled with horror to a foreign
climate; when my family, that should have been my comfort,
gave me my most poignant agony; when I looked
upon them, naked, destitute, and exiles, with the tremendous
thought, what and who it was that had caused their
ruin? Adversity, without consolation,—adversity, when its
sting is remorse, self-abhorrence and self-contempt,—hell
has no misery by which it can be thrown into shade or
exceeded!
Why do I dwell upon, or at least why do I anticipate,
this detested circumstance of my story? Let me add one
remark in this place, and pass on to the other particulars
of this epoch of my prodigality. It is true, I must take
this shameful appellation to myself—I was a gamester.
But, in the beginning, I took no concern in that species of
science which is often implied in the appellation. My
games were games of hazard, not of skill. It appeared to
my distempered apprehension to be only a mode in which
for a man to display his fortitude and philosophy; I was
flattered with the practice of gaming, because I saw in it,
when gracefully pursued, the magnanimity of the stoic,
combined with the manners of a man of the world; a magnanimity
that no success is able to intoxicate, and no vicissitude
to subvert. I committed my property to the hazard
of the die; and I placed my ambition in laughing alike at
the favours of fortune and her frowns. In the sequel,
however, I found myself deceived. The fickle goddess
sufficiently proved that she had the power of making me
serious. But in her most tremendous reverses, I was never
influenced to do any thing that the most scrupulous gamester
regards as dishonourable. I say not this for the purpose
of giving colour and speciousness to my tale. I say
it, because I have laid it down to myself in this narrative
as a sacred principle, to relate the simple, unaltered truth.
[31]
Another characteristic of the reign of Francis the First,
is its gallantries. It is well known how much the king was
himself occupied with attachments of this sort; his government
was rather the government of women than of politicians;
and the manners of the sovereign strongly tended to
fix the habits of his subjects. A very young man rather
takes the tone of his passions from those about him, than
forms one that is properly his own; and this was my case
in the present instance as well as in the preceding. Originally
of an amorous constitution, I should perhaps have
quieted the restlessness of my appetites without ostentation
and éclat, had not the conduct of my youthful associates in
general led me to regard gallantry as an accomplishment
indispensably necessary in a young man of rank. It must
be confessed, indeed, that this offence against the rigour of
discipline has a thousand advantages over that of gaming.
Few women of regular and reputable lives have that ease of
manners, that flow of fancy, and that graceful intrepidity
of thinking and expressing themselves, that is sometimes to
be found among those who have discharged themselves from
the tyranny of custom. There is something irresistibly
captivating in that voluptuousness which, while it assumes
a certain air of freedom, uniformly and with preference
conforms itself to the dictates of unsophisticated delicacy.
A judicious and limited voluptuousness is necessary to the
cultivation of the mind, to the polishing of the manners, to
the refining of sentiment and the developement of the understanding;
and a woman deficient in this respect may be
of use for the government of our families, but can neither
add to the enjoyments, nor fix the partiality, of a man of
animation and taste.
But whatever there may be in these considerations, certain
it is that the conduct I pursued in matters of gallantry
led me into great and serious expenses. The mistresses
with whom I chanced to associate had neither the inexpressible
captivation of madame de Chateaubriant, nor the
aspiring and impressive manners of the duchess d’Etampes[7].
They had, however, beauty and vivacity, frolic without
rudeness, and softness without timidity. They had paid[32]
some regard to points of knowledge and taste, considering
these as additional means for fixing the partiality of their
paramours, and knowing that they had no security for the
permanence of their prosperity but in the variety of their
attractions. In their society I was led into new trains
of reflection, a nicer consideration of human passion and
the varieties of human character, and, above all, into a
greater quickness and delicacy in matters of intellectual taste.
My hours, for the most part, rolled swiftly and easily away,
sometimes in the society of the young, the gay and the ambitious
of my own sex, and sometimes in the softer and
more delicious intercourse of the fair. I lived in the midst
of all that Paris could at that time furnish of splendid and
luxurious. This system of living was calculated to lull
me in pleasing dreams, and to waste away existence in delirious
softness. It sufficiently accorded with the sad
period of our sovereign’s captivity, when my young compatriots
sought to drown the sense of public and patriotic
considerations in copious draughts of pleasure; nor did the
monarch’s return immediately restore to France her former
haughtiness and pride.
The course of sensuality in which I was now engaged,
though it did not absolutely sink into grossness, may
well be supposed to have trodden upon the very edge of
licence. I and my companions were young; we were made
fearless and presuming by fortune and by rank; we had
laid aside those more rigorous restraints which render the
soberer part of mankind plausible and decent, by making
them timid and trite. I will not contaminate the minds of
my innocent and inexperienced readers by entering into the
detail of the follies in which I engaged.
One thing it is necessary to remark, as essential to the
main thread of my story. My expenses of all kinds, during
this period of self-desertion, drained my resources, but did
not tarnish my good name. My excesses were regarded by
some as ornamental and becoming, but by all were admitted
as venial. The laurels I had won in the field of military
honour were not obscured by my subsequent conduct. I
was universally ranked among the most promising and
honourable of the young noblemen of France. I had some[33]
rivals; I did not pass through this turbulent and diversified
scene without disputes; but no one cast a reflection
upon my name, no one ventured to speak of me with superciliousness
and opprobrium. Nor was my temper more injured
than my reputation. From every dispute I extricated
myself with grace and propriety; I studied the pleasure and
ease of all with whom I associated; and no man enjoyed
more extensively than I did the sweets of friendship, as far
as the sweets of friendship can be extensively enjoyed.
</div></body></text></TEI>