<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="114">INTRODUCTION.
WE now arrive at that study
which offers the most copious and complete example of the sciences of
classification, I mean Botany. And in this case, we have before us a
branch of knowledge of which we may say, more properly than of any of
the sciences which we have reviewed since Astronomy, that it has been
constantly advancing, more or less rapidly, from the infancy of the
human race to the present day. One of the reasons of this resemblance
in the fortunes of two studies so widely dissimilar, is to be found in
a simplicity of principle which they have in common; the ideas of
Likeness and Difference, on which the knowledge of plants depends,
are, like the ideas of Space and Time, which are the foundation of
astronomy, readily apprehended with clearness and precision, even
without any peculiar culture of the intellect. But another reason why,
in the history of Botany, as in that of Astronomy, the progress of
knowledge forms an unbroken line from the earliest times, is precisely
the great difference of the kind of knowledge which has been attained
in the two cases. In Astronomy, the discovery of general truths began
at an early period of civilization; in Botany, it has hardly yet
begun; and thus, in each of these departments of study, the lore of
the ancient is homogeneous with that of the modern times, though in
the one case it is science, in the other, the absence of science,
which pervades all ages. The resemblance of the form of their history
arises from the diversity of their materials.
I shall not here dwell further upon this subject, but proceed to
trace rapidly the progress of Systematic Botany, as the
classificatory science is usually denominated, when it is requisite to
distinguish between that and Physiological Botany. My own imperfect
acquaintance with this study admonishes me not to venture into its
details, further than my purpose absolutely requires. I trust that, by
taking my views principally from writers who are generally allowed to
possess the best insight into the science, I may be able to draw the
larger features of its history with tolerable correctness; and if I
succeed in this, I shall attain an object of great importance in my
general scheme. 358</div></body></text></TEI>