<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="39">

BOOK XI.

ELECTRICITY.

GENERAL REMARKS.
ELECTRICITY in the form in
which it was originally studied—Franklinic, frictional, or
statical electricity—has been so completely identified with
electricity in its more comprehensive form—Voltaic, chemical, or
dynamical electricity—that any additions we might have to make
to the history of the earlier form of the subject are included in the
later science.
There are, however, several subjects which may still be regarded
rather as branches of Electricity than of the Cognate Sciences. Such
are, for instance, Atmospheric Electricity, with all that belongs to
Thunderstorms and Lightning Conductors. The observation of Atmospheric
Electricity has been prosecuted with great zeal at various
meteorological observatories; and especially at the Observatory
established by the British Association at Kew. The Aurora Borealis,
again, is plainly an electrical phenomenon; but probably belonging
rather to dynamical than to statical electricity. For it strongly
affects the magnetic needle, and its position has reference to the
direction of magnetism; but it has not been observed to affect the
electroscope. The general features of this phenomenon have been
described by M. de Humboldt, and more recently by M. de Bravais; and
theories of the mode of its production have been propounded by MM.
Biot, De la Rive, Kaemtz, and others.
Again, there are several fishes which have the power of giving an
electrical shock:—the torpedo, the gymnotus, and the silurus.
The agency of these creatures has been identified with electricity in
the most general sense. The peculiar energy of the animal has been
made to produce the effects which are produced by an electrical
discharge or a voltaic current:—not only to destroy life in
small animals, but to 611 deflect a magnet, to make a magnet, to
decompose water, and to produce a spark.
Dr. Faraday’s Views of Statical Electric Induction.
According to the theories of electricity of Æpinus and Coulomb,
which in this Book of our History are regarded as constituting a main
part of the progress of this portion of science, the particles of the
electric fluid or fluids exert forces, attractive and repulsive, upon
each other in straight lines at a distance, in the same way in which,
in the Newtonian theory of the universe, the particles of matter are
conceived as exerting attractive forces upon each other. An electrized
body presented a conducting body of any form, determines a new
arrangement of the electric fluids in the conductor, attracting the
like fluid to its own side, and repelling the opposite fluid to the
opposite side. This is Electrical Induction. And as, by the
theory, the attraction is greater at the smaller distances, the
distribution of the fluid upon the conductor in virtue of this
Induction will not be symmetrical, but will be governed by laws which
it will require a complex and difficult calculation to
determine—as we have seen was the case in the investigations of
Coulomb, Poisson, and others.
Instead of this action at a distance. Dr. Faraday has been led to
conceive Electrical Induction to be the result of an action taking
place between the electrized body and the conductor through lines of
contiguous particles in the mass of the intermediate body, which he
calls the Dielectric. And the irregularities of the
distribution of the electricity in these cases of Induction, and
indeed the existence of an action in points protected from direct
action by the protuberant sides of the conductor, are the causes, I
conceive, which lead him to the conclusion that Induction takes place
in curved lines17 of such contiguous particles.</div></body></text></TEI>