<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="11">
CHAPTER VI.
Of the Logic of Induction.
Aphorism XVII.
The Logic of Induction consists in stating the Facts and
the Inference in such a manner, that the Evidence of the Inference
is manifest: just as the Logic of Deduction consists
in stating the Premises and the Conclusion in such a manner
that the Evidence of the Conclusion is manifest.
Aphorism XVIII.
The Logic of Deduction is exhibited by means of a certain
Formula; namely, a Syllogism; and every train of deductive
reasoning, to be demonstrative, must be capable of resolution
into a series of such Formulæ legitimately constructed. In
like manner, the Logic of Induction may be exhibited by
means of certain Formulæ; and every train of inductive
inference to be sound, must be capable of resolution into a
scheme of such Formulæ, legitimately constructed.
Aphorism XIX.
The inductive act of thought by which several Facts are
colligated into one Proposition, may be expressed by saying:
The several Facts are exactly expressed as one Fact, if,
and only if, we adopt the Conceptions and the Assertion
of the Proposition.
Aphorism XX.
The One Fact, thus inductively obtained from several
Facts, may be combined with other Facts, and colligated
with them by a new act of Induction. This process may be 98
indefinitely repeated: and these successive processes are the
Steps of Induction, or of Generalization, from the lowest to
the highest.
Aphorism XXI.
The relation of the successive Steps of Induction may be
exhibited by means of an Inductive Table, in which the
several Facts are indicated, and tied together by a Bracket,
and the Inductive Inference placed on the other side of the
Bracket; and this arrangement repeated, so as to form a
genealogical Table of each Induction, from the lowest to the
highest.
Aphorism XXII.
The Logic of Induction is the Criterion of Truth inferred
from Facts, as the Logic of Deduction is the Criterion of
Truth deduced from necessary Principles. The Inductive
Table enables us to apply such a Criterion; for we can determine
whether each Induction is verified and justified by
the Facts which its Bracket includes; and if each induction
in particular be sound, the highest, which merely combines
them all, must necessarily be sound also.
Aphorism XXIII.
The distinction of Fact and Theory is only relative.
Events and phenomena, considered as Particulars which may
be colligated by Induction, are Facts; considered as Generalities
already obtained by colligation of other Facts, they are
Theories. The same event or phenomenon is a Fact or a
Theory, according as it is considered as standing on one side
or the other of the Inductive Bracket.

1. THE
subject to which the present chapter refers
is described by phrases which are at the present
day familiarly used in speaking of the progress of
knowledge. We hear very frequent mention of ascending
from particular to general propositions, and
from these to propositions still more general;—of 99
truths included in other truths of a higher degree of
generality;—of different stages of generalization;—and
of the highest step of the process of discovery, to
which all others are subordinate and preparatory. As
these expressions, so familiar to our ears, especially
since the time of Francis Bacon, denote, very significantly,
processes and relations which are of great importance in
the formation of science, it is necessary for
us to give a clear account of them, illustrated with
general exemplifications; and this we shall endeavour
to do.
We have, indeed, already explained that science consists
of Propositions which include the Facts from which
they were collected; and other wider Propositions, collected
in like manner from the former, and including
them. Thus, that the stars, the moon, the sun, rise,
culminate, and set, are facts included in the proposition
that the heavens, carrying with them all the celestial
bodies, have a diurnal revolution about the axis of the
earth. Again, the observed monthly motions of the
moon, and the annual motions of the sun, are included
in certain propositions concerning the movements of
those luminaries with respect to the stars. But all
these propositions are really included in the doctrine
that the earth, revolving on its axis, moves round the
sun, and the moon round the earth. These movements, again,
considered as facts, are explained and
included in the statement of the forces which the earth
exerts upon the moon, and the sun upon the earth.
Again, this doctrine of the forces of these three bodies
is included in the assertion, that all the bodies of the
solar system, and all parts of matter, exert forces, each
upon each. And we might easily show that all the
leading facts in astronomy are comprehended in the
same generalization. In like manner with regard to
any other science, so far as its truths have been well
established and fully developed, we might show that it
consists of a gradation of propositions, proceeding from
the most special facts to the most general theoretical
assertions. We shall exhibit this gradation in some of
the principal branches of science. 100
2. This gradation of truths, successively included
in other truths, may be conveniently represented by
Tables resembling the genealogical tables by which the
derivation of descendants from a common ancestor is
exhibited; except that it is proper in this case to invert
the form of the Table, and to make it converge to
unity downwards instead of upwards, since it has for
its purpose to express, not the derivation of many from
one, but the collection of one truth from many things.
Two or more co-ordinate facts or propositions may be
ranged side by side, and joined by some mark of connexion,
(a bracket, as ⏟ or ⎵,) beneath
which may be placed the more general proposition
which is collected by induction from the former. Again,
propositions co-ordinate with this more general one
may be placed on a level with it; and the combination
of these, and the result of the combination, may be
indicated by brackets in the same manner; and so on,
through any number of gradations. By this means
the streams of knowledge from various classes of facts
will constantly run together into a smaller and smaller
number of channels; like the confluent rivulets of a
great river, coming together from many sources, uniting
their ramifications so as to form larger branches, these
again uniting in a single trunk. The genealogical tree
of each great portion of science, thus formed, will
contain all the leading truths of the science arranged
in their due co-ordination and subordination. Such
Tables, constructed for the sciences of Astronomy and
of Optics, will be given at the end of this chapter.
3. The union of co-ordinate propositions into a proposition
of a higher order, which occurs in this Tree of
Science wherever two twigs unite in one branch, is, in
each case, an example of Induction. The single proposition
is collected by the process of induction from
its several members. But here we may observe, that
the image of a mere union of the parts at each of these
points, which the figure of a tree or a river presents, is
very inadequate to convey the true state of the case;
for in Induction, as we have seen, besides mere collection
of particulars, there is always a new conception, a 101
principle of connexion and unity, supplied by the
mind, and superinduced upon the particulars. There
is not merely a juxta-position of materials, by which
the new proposition contains all that its component
parts contained; but also a formative act exerted by
the understanding, so that these materials are contained
in a new shape. We must remember, therefore, that our
Inductive Tables, although they represent the elements
and the order of these inductive
steps, do not fully represent the whole signification of
the process in each case.
4. The principal features of the progress of science
spoken of in the last chapter are clearly exhibited in
these Tables; namely, the Consilience of Inductions
and the constant Tendency to Simplicity observable in
true theories. Indeed in all cases in which, from
propositions of considerable generality, propositions of a
still higher degree are obtained, there is a convergence
of inductions; and if in one of the lines which thus
converge, the steps be rapidly and suddenly made in
order to meet the other line, we may consider that we
have an example of Consilience. Thus when Newton
had collected, from Kepler’s Laws, the Central Force of
the sun, and from these, combined with other facts,
the Universal Force of all the heavenly bodies, he
suddenly turned round to include in his generalization
the Precession of the Equinoxes, which he declared to
arise from the attraction of the sun and moon upon
the protuberant part of the terrestrial spheroid. The
apparent remoteness of this fact, in its nature, from the
other facts with which he thus associated it, causes this
part of his reasoning to strike us as a remarkable example
of Consilience. Accordingly, in the Table of
Astronomy we find that the columns which contain
the facts and theories relative to the sun and planets,
after exhibiting several stages of induction within
themselves, are at length suddenly connected with
a column till then quite distinct, containing the
precession of the equinoxes. In like manner, in the Table
of Optics, the columns which contain the facts and
theories relative to double refraction, and those which
102 include
polarization by crystals, each go separately
through several stages of induction; and then these
two sets of columns are suddenly connected by Fresnel’s
mathematical induction, that double refraction and
polarization arise from the same cause: thus
exhibiting a remarkable Consilience.
5. The constant Tendency to Simplicity in the
sciences of which the progress is thus represented,
appears from the form of the Table itself; for the
single trunk into which all the branches converge,
contains in itself the substance of all the propositions
by means of which this last generalization was arrived
at. It is true, that this ultimate result is sometimes
not so simple as in the Table it appears: for instance,
the ultimate generalization of the Table exhibiting the
progress of Physical Optics,—namely, that Light consists
in Undulations,—must be understood as including some other
hypotheses; as, that the undulations
are transverse, that the ether through which they are
propagated has its elasticity in crystals and other
transparent bodies regulated by certain laws; and the
like. Yet still, even acknowledging all the complication
thus implied, the Table in question evidences
clearly enough the constant advance towards unity,
consistency, and simplicity, which have marked the
progress of this Theory. The same is the case in the
Inductive Table of Astronomy in a still greater
degree.
6. These Tables naturally afford the opportunity of
assigning to each of the distinct steps of which the
progress of science consists, the name of the Discoverer
to whom it is due. Every one of the inductive
processes which the brackets of our Tables mark,
directs our attention to some person by whom the induction
was first distinctly made. These names I
have endeavoured to put in their due places in the
Tables; and the Inductive Tree of our knowledge in
each science becomes, in this way, an exhibition of the
claims of each discoverer to distinction, and, as it
were, a Genealogical Tree of scientific nobility. It is
by no means pretended that such a tree includes the 103
names of all the meritorious labourers in each department
of science. Many persons are most usefully
employed in collecting and verifying truths, who do
not advance to any new truths. The labours of a
number of such are included in each stage of our
ascent. But such Tables as we have now before us
will present to us the names of all the most eminent
discoverers: for the main steps of which the progress
of science consists, are transitions from more particular
to more general truths, and must therefore be
rightly given by these Tables; and those must be the
greatest names in science to whom the principal events
of its advance are thus due.
7. The Tables, as we have presented them, exhibit
the course by which we pass from Particular to General
through various gradations, and so to the most general.
They display the order of discovery. But by reading
them in an inverted manner, beginning at the single
comprehensive truths with which the Tables end, and
tracing these back into the more partial truths, and
these again into special facts, they answer another
purpose;—they exhibit the process of verification of
discoveries once made. For each of our general propositions
is true in virtue of the truth of the narrower
propositions which it involves; and we cannot satisfy
ourselves of its truth in any other way than by ascertaining
that these its constituent elements are true.
To assure ourselves that the sun attracts the planets
with forces varying inversely as the square of the distance,
we must analyse by geometry the motion of a
body in an ellipse about the focus, so as to see that such
a motion does imply such a force. We must also verify
those calculations by which the observed places of each
planet are stated to be included in an ellipse. These
calculations involve assumptions respecting the path which
the earth describes about the sun, which assumptions
must again be verified by reference to observation. And
thus, proceeding from step to step, we resolve the most
general truths into their constituent parts; and these
again into their parts; and by testing, at each step, both
the reality of the asserted ingredients and the propriety 104
of the conjunction, we establish the whole system of
truths, however wide and various it may be.
8. It is a very great advantage, in such a mode of
exhibiting scientific truths, that it resolves the verification
of the most complex and comprehensive theories,
into a number of small steps, of which almost any one
falls within the reach of common talents and industry.
That if the particulars of any one step be true, the
generalization also is true, any person with a mind
properly disciplined may satisfy himself by a little
study. That each of these particular propositions is
true, may be ascertained, by the same kind of attention,
when this proposition is resolved into its constituent
and more special propositions. And thus we
may proceed, till the most general truth is broken up
into small and manageable portions. Of these portions,
each may appear by itself narrow and easy; and
yet they are so woven together, by hypothesis and conjunction,
that the truth of the parts necessarily assures
us of the truth of the whole. The verification is of
the same nature as the verification of a large and complex
statement of great sums received by a mercantile
office on various accounts from many quarters. The
statement is separated into certain comprehensive heads,
and these into others less extensive; and these again
into smaller collections of separate articles, each of
which can be inquired into and reported on by separate
persons. And thus at last, the mere addition of
numbers performed by these various persons, and the
summation of the results which they obtain, executed
by other accountants, is a complete and entire security
that there is no errour in the whole of the process.
9. This comparison of the process by which we
verify scientific truth to the process of Book-keeping
in a large commercial establishment, may appear to
some persons not sufficiently dignified for the subject.
But, in fact, the possibility of giving this formal and
business-like aspect to the evidence of science, as
involved in the process of successive generalization, is an
inestimable advantage. For if no one could pronounce
concerning a wide and profound theory except he who 105
could at once embrace in his mind the whole range of
inference, extending from the special facts up to the
most general principles, none but the greatest geniuses
would be entitled to judge concerning the truth or
errour of scientific discoveries. But, in reality, we
seldom need to verify more than one or two steps of
such discoveries at one time; and this may commonly
be done (when the discoveries have been fully established
and developed,) by any one who brings to the
task clear conceptions and steady attention. The progress
of science is gradual: the discoveries which are
successively made, are also verified successively. We
have never any very large collections of them on our
hands at once. The doubts and uncertainties of any
one who has studied science with care and perseverance
are generally confined to a few points. If he can
satisfy himself upon these, he has no misgivings respecting
the rest of the structure; which has indeed
been repeatedly verified by other persons in like manner.
The fact that science is capable of being resolved
into separate processes of verification, is that which
renders it possible to form a great body of scientific
truth, by adding together a vast number of truths, of
which many men, at various times and by multiplied
efforts, have satisfied themselves. The treasury of
Science is constantly rich and abundant, because it
accumulates the wealth which is thus gathered by so
many, and reckoned over by so many more: and the
dignity of Knowledge is no more lowered by the multiplicity
of the tasks on which her servants are employed, and the
narrow field of labour to which some
confine themselves, than the rich merchant is degraded
by the number of offices which it is necessary for him
to maintain, and the minute articles of which he requires
an exact statement from his accountants.
10. The analysis of doctrines inductively obtained,
into their constituent facts, and the arrangement of
them in such a form that the conclusiveness of the
induction may be distinctly seen, may be termed the
Logic of Induction. By Logic has generally been
meant a system which teaches us so to arrange our 106
reasonings that their truth or falsehood shall be evident
in their form. In deductive reasonings, in which
the general principles are assumed, and the question is
concerning their application and combination in particular
cases, the device which thus enables us to judge
whether our reasonings are conclusive is the Syllogism;
and this form, along with the rules which belong to it,
does in fact supply us with a criterion of deductive or
demonstrative reasoning. The Inductive Table, such
as it is presented in the present chapter, in like manner
supplies the means of ascertaining the truth of our
inductive inferences, so far as the form in which our
reasoning may be stated can afford such a criterion. Of
course some care is requisite in order to reduce a train
of demonstration into the form of a series of syllogisms;
and certainly not less thought and attention are required
for resolving all the main doctrines of any great
department of science into a graduated table of co-ordinate
and subordinate inductions. But in each
case, when this task is once executed, the evidence or
want of evidence of our conclusions appears immediately
in a most luminous manner. In each step of
induction, our Table enumerates the particular facts,
and states the general theoretical truth which includes
these and which these constitute. The special act of
attention by which we satisfy ourselves that the facts
are so included,—that the general truth is so
constituted,—then affords little room for errour, with
moderate attention and clearness of thought.
11. We may find an example of this act of attention
thus required, at any one of the steps of induction
in our Tables; for instance, at the step in the early
progress of astronomy at which it was inferred, that
the earth is a globe, and that the sphere of the heavens
(relatively) performs a diurnal revolution round this
globe of the earth. How was this established in the belief
of the Greeks, and how is it fixed in our conviction?
As to the globular form, we find that as we travel to
the north, the apparent pole of the heavenly motions,
and the constellations which are near it, seem to mount
higher, and as we proceed southwards they descend. 107
Again, if we proceed from two different points considerably
to the east and west of each other, and travel
directly northwards from each, as from the south of
Spain to the north of Scotland, and from Greece to
Scandinavia, these two north and south lines will be
much nearer to each other in their northern than in
their southern parts. These and similar facts, as soon
as they are clearly estimated and connected in the
mind, are seen to be consistent with a convex surface of
the earth, and with no other: and this notion is further
confirmed by observing that the boundary of the earth’s
shadow upon the moon is always circular; it being
supposed to be already established that the moon receives
her light from the sun, and that lunar eclipses
are caused by the interposition of the earth. As for
the assertion of the (relative) diurnal revolution of the
starry sphere, it is merely putting the visible phenomena
in an exact geometrical form: and thus we establish and
verify the doctrine of the revolution of the sphere of
the heavens about the globe of the earth, by contemplating
it so as to see that it does really and exactly
include the particular facts from which it is collected.
We may, in like manner, illustrate this mode of
verification by any of the other steps of the same Table.
Thus if we take the great Induction of Copernicus, the
heliocentric scheme of the solar system, we find it in the
Table exhibited as including and explaining, first, the
diurnal revolution just spoken of; second, the motions
of the moon among the fixed stars; third, the motions
of the planets with reference to the fixed stars and the
sun; fourth, the motion of the sun in the ecliptic.
And the scheme being clearly conceived, we see that all
the particular facts are faithfully represented by it;
and this agreement, along with the simplicity of the
scheme, in which respect it is so far superior to any
other conception of the solar system, persuade us that
it is really the plan of nature.
In exactly the same way, if we attend to any of the
several remarkable discoveries of Newton, which form
the principal steps in the latter part of the Table, as
for instance, the proposition that the sun attracts all 108
the planets with a force which varies inversely as the
square of the distance, we find it proved by its including
three other propositions previously established;—first,
that the sun’s mean force on different planets
follows the specified variation (which is proved from
Kepler’s third law); second, that the force by which
each planet is acted upon in different parts of its orbit
tends to the sun (which is proved by the equable description
of areas); third, that this force in different
parts of the same orbit is also inversely as the square
of the distance (which is proved from the elliptical
form of the orbit). And the Newtonian generalization,
when its consequences are mathematically traced,
is seen to agree with each of these particular propositions,
and thus is fully established.
12. But when we say that the more general proposition
includes the several more particular ones, we
must recollect what has before been said, that these
particulars form the general truth, not by being merely
enumerated and added together, but by being seen in a
new light. No mere verbal recitation of the particulars
can decide whether the general proposition is true;
a special act of thought is requisite in order to determine
how truly each is included in the supposed induction.
In this respect the Inductive Table is not
like a mere schedule of accounts, where the rightness
of each part of the reckoning is tested by mere addition
of the particulars. On the contrary, the Inductive
truth is never the mere sum of the facts. It is made
into something more by the introduction of a new
mental element; and the mind, in order to be able to
supply this element, must have peculiar endowments
and discipline. Thus looking back at the instances
noticed in the last article, how are we to see that a
convex surface of the earth is necessarily implied by
the convergence of meridians towards the north, or by
the visible descent of the north pole of the heavens as
we travel south? Manifestly the student, in order to
see this, must have clear conceptions of the relations
of space, either naturally inherent in his mind, or
established there by geometrical cultivation,—by 109
studying the properties of circles and spheres. When he
is so prepared, he will feel the force of the expressions
we have used, that the facts just mentioned are seen to
be consistent with a globular form of the earth; but
without such aptitude he will not see this consistency:
and if this be so, the mere assertion of it in words
will not avail him in satisfying himself of the truth of
the proposition.
In like manner, in order to perceive the force of the
Copernican induction, the student must have his mind
so disciplined by geometrical studies, or otherwise, that
he sees clearly how absolute motion and relative motion
would alike produce apparent motion. He must have
learnt to cast away all prejudices arising from the seeming
fixity of the earth; and then he will see that there
is nothing which stands in the way of the induction,
while there is much which is on its side. And in the
same manner the Newtonian induction of the law of
the sun’s force from the elliptical form of the orbit,
will be evidently satisfactory to him only who has such
an insight into Mechanics as to see that a curvilinear
path must arise from a constantly deflecting force;
and who is able to follow the steps of geometrical
reasoning by which, from the properties of the ellipse,
Newton proves this deflection to be in the proportion
in which he asserts the force to be. And thus in all
cases the inductive truth must indeed be verified by
comparing it with the particular facts; but then this
comparison is possible for him only whose mind is
properly disciplined and prepared in the use of those
conceptions, which, in addition to the facts, the act of
induction requires.
13. In the Tables some indication is given, at
several of the steps, of the act which the mind must
thus perform, besides the mere conjunction of facts, in
order to attain to the inductive truth. Thus in the
cases of the Newtonian inductions just spoken of, the
inferences are stated to be made ‘By Mechanics;’
and in the case of the Copernican induction, it is said
that, ‘By the nature of motion, the apparent motion is
the same, whether the heavens or the earth have a 110
diurnal motion; and the latter is more simple.’ But
these verbal statements are to be understood as mere
hints22:
they cannot supersede the necessity of the student’s
contemplating for himself the mechanical principles and the
nature of motion thus referred to.
22
 In the Inductive Tables they are marked by an asterisk.

14. In the common or Syllogistic Logic, a certain
Formula of language is used in stating the reasoning,
and is useful in enabling us more readily to apply the
Criterion of Form to alleged demonstrations. This
formula is the usual Syllogism; with its members,
Major Premiss, Minor Premiss, and Conclusion. It
may naturally be asked whether in Inductive Logic
there is any such Formula? whether there is any
standard form of words in which we may most properly
express the inference of a general truth from
particular facts?
At first it might be supposed that the formula of
Inductive Logic need only be of this kind: ‘These
particulars, and all known particulars of the same
kind, are exactly included in the following general
proposition.’ But a moment’s reflection on what has
just been said will show us that this is not sufficient:
for the particulars are not merely included in the
general proposition. It is not enough that they appertain
to it by enumeration. It is, for instance, no adequate
example of Induction to say, ‘Mercury describes
an elliptical path, so does Venus, so do the Earth,
Mars, Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus; therefore all the
Planets describe elliptical paths.’ This is, as we have
seen, the mode of stating the evidence when the proposition
is once suggested; but the Inductive step consists in the
suggestion of a conception not before
apparent. When Kepler, after trying to connect the
observed places of the planet Mars in many other
ways, found at last that the conception of an ellipse
would include them all, he obtained a truth by induction:
for this conclusion was not obviously included
in the phenomena, and had not been applied to these 111
facts previously. Thus in our Formula, besides stating
that the particulars are included in the general proposition,
we must also imply that the generality is constituted by
a new Conception,—new at least in its
application.
Hence our Inductive Formula might be something
like the following: ‘These particulars, and all known
particulars of the same kind, are exactly expressed by
adopting the Conceptions and Statement of the following
Proposition.’ It is of course requisite that the
Conceptions should be perfectly clear, and should precisely
embrace the facts, according to the explanation
we have already given of those conditions.
15. It may happen, as we have already stated, that
the Explication of a Conception, by which it acquires
its due distinctness, leads to a Definition, which Definition
may be taken as the summary and total result
of the intellectual efforts to which this distinctness is
due. In such cases, the Formula of Induction may be
modified according to this condition; and we may state
the inference by saying, after an enumeration and
analysis of the appropriate facts, ‘These facts are
completely and distinctly expressed by adopting the
following Definition and Proposition.’
This Formula has been adopted in stating the Inductive
Propositions which constitute the basis of the
science of Mechanics, in a work intitled The Mechanical
Euclid. The fundamental truths of the subject
are expressed in Inductive Pairs of Assertions, consisting
each of a Definition and a Proposition, such as
the following:
 Def.—A Uniform Force
is that which acting in the
direction of the body’s motion, adds or subtracts equal
velocities in equal times.
 Prop.—Gravity is a Uniform Force.
 Again,
 Def.—Two Motions are
compounded when each
produces its separate effect in a direction parallel to
itself.
 Prop.—When any Force acts upon a body in motion,
the motion which the Force would produce in the 112
body at rest is compounded with the previous motion
of the body.
 And in like manner in other cases.
In these cases the proposition is, of course, established,
and the definition realized, by an enumeration
of the facts. And in the case of inferences made in
such a form, the Definition of the Conception and the
Assertion of the Truth are both requisite and are correlative
to one another. Each of the two steps contains the verification
and justification of the other.
The Proposition derives its meaning from the Definition;
the Definition derives its reality from the Proposition.
If they are separated, the Definition is arbitrary or empty,
the Proposition vague or ambiguous.
16. But it must be observed that neither of the
preceding Formulæ expresses the full cogency of the
inductive proof. They declare only that the results
can be clearly explained and rigorously deduced by the
employment of a certain Definition and a certain Proposition.
But in order to make the conclusion demonstrative, which in
perfect examples of Induction it is,
we ought to be able to declare that the results can be
clearly explained and rigorously declared only by the
Definition and Proposition which we adopt. And in
reality, the conviction of the sound inductive reasoner
does reach to this point. The Mathematician asserts
the Laws of Motion, seeing clearly that they (or laws
equivalent to them) afford the only means of clearly
expressing and deducing the actual facts. But this
conviction, that the inductive inference is not only
consistent with the facts, but necessary, finds its place
in the mind gradually, as the contemplation of the
consequences of the proposition, and the various relations
of the facts, becomes steady and familiar. It
is scarcely possible for the student at once to satisfy
himself that the inference is thus inevitable. And
when he arrives at this conviction, he sees also, in
many cases at least, that there may be other ways of
expressing the substance of the truth established,
besides that special Proposition which he has under
his notice. 113
We may, therefore, without impropriety, renounce
the undertaking of conveying in our formula this final
conviction of the necessary truth of our inference. We
may leave it to be thought, without insisting upon saying it,
that in such cases what can be true, is true.
But if we wish to express the ultimate significance of
the Inductive Act of thought, we may take as our
Formula for the Colligation of Facts by Induction,
this:—‘The several Facts are exactly expressed as one
Fact if, and only if, we adopt the Conception and the
Assertion’ of the inductive inference.
17. I have said that the mind must be properly
disciplined in order that it may see the necessary
connexion between the facts and the general proposition
in which they are included. And the perception of
this connexion, though treated as one step in our
inductive inference, may imply many steps of demonstrative
proof. The connexion is this, that the particular case
is included in the general one, that is, may
be deduced from it: but this deduction may often
require many links of reasoning. Thus in the case of
the inference of the law of the force from the elliptical
form of the orbit by Newton, the proof that in the
ellipse the deflection from the tangent is inversely as
the square of the distance from the focus of the ellipse,
is a ratiocination consisting of several steps, and
involving several properties of Conic Sections; these
properties being supposed to be previously established by
a geometrical system of demonstration on the special
subject of the Conic Sections. In this and similar
cases the Induction involves many steps of Deduction.
And in such cases, although the Inductive Step, the
Invention of the Conception, is really the most important,
yet since, when once made, it occupies a
familiar place in men’s minds; and since the Deductive
Demonstration is of considerable length and requires
intellectual effort to follow it at every step; men often
admire the deductive part of the proposition, the geometrical
or algebraical demonstration, far more than
that part in which the philosophical merit really resides. 114
18. Deductive reasoning is virtually a collection of
syllogisms, as has already been stated: and in such
reasoning, the general principles, the Definitions and
Axioms, necessarily stand at the beginning of the
demonstration. In an inductive inference, the Definitions
and Principles are the final result of the reasoning,
the ultimate effect of the proof. Hence when an
Inductive Proposition is to be established by a proof
involving several steps of demonstrative reasoning, the
enunciation of the Proposition will contain, explicitly
or implicitly, principles which the demonstration proceeds
upon as axioms, but which are really inductive
inferences. Thus in order to prove that the force
which retains a planet in an ellipse varies inversely as
the square of the distance, it is taken for granted that
the Laws of Motion are true, and that they apply to
the planets. Yet the doctrine that this is so, as well
as the law of the force, were established only by this and
the like demonstrations. The doctrine which is the
hypothesis of the deductive reasoning, is the inference
of the inductive process. The special facts which are
the basis of the inductive inference, are the conclusion
of the train of deduction. And in this manner the
deduction establishes the induction. The principle
which we gather from the facts is true, because the
facts can be derived from it by rigorous demonstration.
Induction moves upwards, and deduction downwards,
on the same stair.
But still there is a great difference in the character
of their movements. Deduction descends steadily and
methodically, step by step: Induction mounts by a
leap which is out of the reach of method. She bounds
to the top of the stair at once; and then it is the
business of Deduction, by trying each step in order, to
establish the solidity of her companion’s footing. Yet
these must be processes of the same mind. The Inductive
Intellect makes an assertion which is subsequently
justified by demonstration; and it shows its
sagacity, its peculiar character, by enunciating the
proposition when as yet the demonstration does not 115
exist: but then it shows that it is sagacity, by also
producing the demonstration.
It has been said that inductive and deductive reasoning
are contrary in their scheme; that in Deduction
we infer particular from general truths; while in
Induction we infer general from particular: that
Deduction consists of many steps, in each of which we apply
known general propositions in particular cases; while
in Induction we have a single step, in which we pass
from many particular truths to one general proposition.
And this is truly said; but though contrary
in their motions, the two are the operation of the same
mind travelling over the same ground. Deduction is
a necessary part of Induction. Deduction justifies by
calculation what Induction had happily guessed. Induction
recognizes the ore of truth by its weight;
Deduction confirms the recognition by chemical analysis.
Every step of Induction must be confirmed by
rigorous deductive reasoning, followed into such detail
as the nature and complexity of the relations (whether
of quantity or any other) render requisite. If not so
justified by the supposed discoverer, it is not Induction.
19. Such Tabular arrangements of propositions as
we have constructed may be considered as the Criterion
of Truth for the doctrines which they include. They
are the Criterion of Inductive Truth, in the same
sense in which Syllogistic Demonstration is the Criterion
of Necessary Truth,—of the certainty of conclusions,
depending upon evident First Principles.
And that such Tables are really a Criterion of the
truth of the propositions which they contain, will be
plain by examining their structure. For if the connexion
which the inductive process assumes be ascertained
to be in each case real and true, the assertion of
the general proposition merely collects together
ascertained truths; and in like manner each of those more
particular propositions is true, because it merely
expresses collectively more special facts: so that the most
general theory is only the assertion of a great body
of facts, duly classified and subordinated. When we 116
assert the truth of the Copernican theory of the motions
of the solar system, or of the Newtonian theory of the
forces by which they are caused, we merely assert the
groups of propositions which, in the Table of Astronomical
Induction, are included in these doctrines; and
ultimately, we may consider ourselves as merely asserting
at once so many Facts, and therefore, of course,
expressing an indisputable truth.
20. At any one of these steps of Induction in the
Table, the inductive proposition is a Theory with
regard to the Facts which it includes, while it is to be
looked upon as a Fact with respect to the higher
generalizations in which it is included. In any other
sense, as was formerly shown, the opposition of Fact
and Theory is untenable, and leads to endless perplexity
and debate. Is it a Fact or a Theory that the
planet Mars revolves in an Ellipse about the Sun?
To Kepler, employed in endeavouring to combine the
separate observations by the Conception of an Ellipse,
it is a Theory; to Newton, engaged in inferring the
law of force from a knowledge of the elliptical motion,
it is a Fact. There are, as we have already seen, no
special attributes of Theory and Fact which distinguish
them from one another. Facts are phenomena apprehended
by the aid of conceptions and mental acts, as
Theories also are. We commonly call our observations
Facts, when we apply, without effort or consciousness,
conceptions perfectly familiar to us: while we speak of
Theories, when we have previously contemplated the
Facts and the connecting Conception separately, and
have made the connexion by a conscious mental act.
The real difference is a difference of relation; as the
same proposition in a demonstration is the premiss of
one syllogism and the conclusion in another;—as the
same person is a father and a son. Propositions are
Facts and Theories, according as they stand above or
below the Inductive Brackets of our Tables.
21. To obviate mistakes I may remark that the
terms higher and lower, when used of generalizations,
are unavoidably represented by their opposites in our
Inductive Tables. The highest generalization is that 117
which includes all others; and this stands the lowest
on our page, because, reading downwards, that is the
place which we last reach.
There is a distinction of the knowledge acquired by
Scientific Induction into two kinds, which is so important
that we shall consider it in the succeeding
chapter.
 

CHAPTER VII.
Of Laws of Phenomena and of Causes.


Aphorism XXIV.
Inductive truths are of two kinds, Laws of Phenomena,
and Theories of Causes. It is necessary to begin in every
science with the Laws of Phenomena; but it is impossible that
we should be satisfied to stop short of a Theory of Causes. In
Physical Astronomy, Physical Optics, Geology, and other
sciences, we have instances showing that we can make a great
advance in inquiries after true Theories of Causes.

1. IN
the first attempts at acquiring an exact and
connected knowledge of the appearances and operations
which nature presents, men went no further
than to learn what takes place, not why it occurs.
They discovered an Order which the phenomena follow,
Rules which they obey; but they did not come in
sight of the Powers by which these rules are determined,
the Causes of which this order is the effect.
Thus, for example, they found that many of the celestial
motions took place as if the sun and stars were
carried round by the revolutions of certain celestial
spheres; but what causes kept these spheres in constant
motion, they were never able to explain. In
like manner in modern times, Kepler discovered that
the planets describe ellipses, before Newton explained
why they select this particular curve, and describe it
in a particular manner. The laws of reflection, refraction,
dispersion, and other properties of light have
long been known; the causes of these laws are at
present under discussion. And the same might be 119
said of many other sciences. The discovery of the
Laws of Phenomena is, in all cases, the first step in
exact knowledge; these Laws may often for a long
period constitute the whole of our science; and it is
always a matter requiring great talents and great efforts,
to advance to a knowledge of the Causes of the
phenomena.
Hence the larger part of our knowledge of nature,
at least of the certain portion of it, consists of the
knowledge of the Laws of Phenomena. In Astronomy
indeed, besides knowing the rules which guide the appearances,
and resolving them into the real motions
from which they arise, we can refer these motions to
the forces which produce them. In Optics, we have
become acquainted with a vast number of laws by
which varied and beautiful phenomena are governed;
and perhaps we may assume, since the evidence of the
Undulatory Theory has been so fully developed, that
we know also the Causes of the Phenomena. But in
a large class of sciences, while we have learnt many
Laws of Phenomena, the causes by which these are
produced are still unknown or disputed. Are we to
ascribe to the operation of a fluid or fluids, and if so,
in what manner, the facts of heat, magnetism, electricity,
galvanism? What are the forces by which the
elements of chemical compounds are held together?
What are the forces, of a higher order, as we cannot
help believing, by which the course of vital action in
organized bodies is kept up? In these and other cases,
we have extensive departments of science; but we are
as yet unable to trace the effects to their causes; and
our science, so far as it is positive and certain, consists
entirely of the laws of phenomena.
2. In those cases in which we have a division of
the science which teaches us the doctrine of the causes,
as well as one which states the rules which the effects
follow, I have, in the History, distinguished the two
portions of the science by certain terms. I have thus
spoken of Formal Astronomy and Physical Astronomy.
The latter phrase has long been commonly employed to
describe that department of Astronomy which deals with 120
those forces by which the heavenly bodies are guided in
their motions; the former adjective appears well suited
to describe a collection of rules depending on those ideas
of space, time, position, number, which are, as we have
already said, the forms of our apprehension of phenomena.
The laws of phenomena may be considered as
formulæ, expressing results in terms of those ideas.
In like manner, I have spoken of Formal Optics and
Physical Optics; the latter division including all
speculations concerning the machinery by which the
effects are produced. Formal Acoustics and Physical
Acoustics may be distinguished in like manner, although
these two portions of science have been a good
deal mixed together by most of those who have treated
of them. Formal Thermotics, the knowledge of the
laws of the phenomena of heat, ought in like manner
to lead to Physical Thermotics, or the Theory of Heat
with reference to the cause by which its effects are
produced;—a branch of science which as yet can hardly
be said to exist.
3. What kinds of cause are we to admit in science?
This is an important, and by no means an easy question.
In order to answer it, we must consider in what
manner our progress in the knowledge of causes has
hitherto been made. By far the most conspicuous instance
of success in such researches, is the discovery
of the causes of the motions of the heavenly bodies.
In this case, after the formal laws of the motions,—their
conditions as to space and time,—had become
known, men were enabled to go a step further; to reduce
them to the familiar and general cause of motion—mechanical
force; and to determine the laws which
this force follows. That this was a step in addition to
the knowledge previously possessed, and that it was a
real and peculiar truth, will not be contested. And a
step in any other subject which should be analogous to
this in astronomy;—a discovery of causes and forces
as certain and clear as the discovery of universal
gravitation;—would undoubtedly be a vast advance upon
a body of science consisting only of the laws of phenomena. 121
4. But although physical astronomy may well be
taken as a standard in estimating the value and magnitude
of the advance from the knowledge of phenomena to the
knowledge of causes; the peculiar features
of the transition from formal to physical science in
that subject must not be allowed to limit too narrowly
our views of the nature of this transition in other
cases. We are not, for example, to consider that the
step which leads us to the knowledge of causes in any
province of nature must necessarily consist in the
discovery of centers of forces, and collections of
such centers, by which the effects are produced. The discovery
of the causes of phenomena may imply the detection
of a fluid by whose undulations, or other operations,
the results are occasioned. The phenomena of acoustics
are, we know, produced in this manner by the air;
and in the cases of light, heat, magnetism, and others,
even if we reject all the theories of such fluids which
have hitherto been proposed, we still cannot deny that
such theories are intelligible and possible, as the
discussions concerning them have shown. Nor can it be
doubted that if the assumption of such a fluid, in any
case, were as well evidenced as the doctrine of universal
gravitation is, it must be considered as a highly
valuable theory.
5. But again; not only must we, in aiming at the
formation of a Causal Section in each Science of Phenomena,
consider Fluids and their various modes of
operation admissible, as well as centers of mechanical
force; but we must be prepared, if it be necessary, to
consider the forces, or powers to which we refer the
phenomena, under still more general aspects, and invested
with characters different from mere mechanical
force. For example; the forces by which the chemical
elements of bodies are bound together, and from which
arise, both their sensible texture, their crystalline form,
and their chemical composition, are certainly forces of
a very different nature from the mere attraction of
matter according to its mass. The powers of assimilation
and reproduction in plants and animals are obviously
still more removed from mere mechanism; yet 122
these powers are not on that account less real, nor a
less fit and worthy subject of scientific inquiry.
6. In fact, these forces—mechanical, chemical and
vital,—as we advance from one to the other, each bring
into our consideration new characters; and what these
characters are, has appeared in the historical survey
which we made of the Fundamental Ideas of the various
sciences. It was then shown that the forces by which
chemical effects are produced necessarily involve the
Idea of Polarity,—they are polar forces; the particles
tend together in virtue of opposite properties which in
the combination neutralize each other. Hence, in attempting
to advance to a theory of Causes in chemistry,
our task is by no means to invent laws of mechanical
force, and collections of forces, by which the effects
may be produced. We know beforehand that no such
attempt can succeed. Our aim must be to conceive
such new kinds of force, including Polarity among
their characters, as may best render the results intelligible.
7. Thus in advancing to a Science of Cause in any
subject, the labour and the struggle is, not to analyse
the phenomena according to any preconceived and
already familiar ideas, but to form distinctly new
conceptions, such as do really carry us to a more intimate
view of the processes of nature. Thus in the case of
astronomy, the obstacle which deferred the discovery
of the true causes from the time of Kepler to that of
Newton, was the difficulty of taking hold of mechanical
conceptions and axioms with sufficient clearness and
steadiness; which, during the whole of that interval,
mathematicians were learning to do. In the question
of causation which now lies most immediately in the
path of science, that of the causes of electrical and
chemical phenomena, the business of rightly fixing and
limiting the conception of polarity, is the proper object
of the efforts of discoverers. Accordingly a large portion
of Mr Faraday’s recent
labours23
is directed, not to 123
the attempt at discovering new laws of phenomena, but
to the task of throwing light upon the conception of
polarity, and of showing how it must be understood, so
that it shall include electrical induction and other phenomena,
which have commonly been ascribed to forces
acting mechanically at a distance. He is by no means
content, nor would it answer the ends of science that
he should be, with stating the results of his experiments;
he is constantly, in every page, pointing out
the interpretation of his experiments, and showing how
the conception of Polar Forces enters into this interpretation.
‘I shall,’ he says24,
‘use every opportunity
which presents itself of returning to that strong test of
truth, experiment; but,’ he adds, ‘I shall necessarily
have occasion to speak theoretically, and even hypothetically.’
His hypothesis that electrical inductive
action always takes place by means of a continuous line
of polarized particles, and not by attraction and repulsion
at a distance, if established, cannot fail to be a
great step on our way towards a knowledge of causes,
as well as phenomena, in the subjects under his consideration.

23 Eleventh, Twelfth,
and Thirteenth Series of Researches, Phil. Trans. 1837 and 8.


24 Art. 1318.

8. The process of obtaining new conceptions is, to
most minds, far more unwelcome than any labour in
employing old ideas. The effort is indeed painful and
oppressive; it is feeling in the dark for an object which
we cannot find. Hence it is not surprising that we
should far more willingly proceed to seek for new causes
by applying conceptions borrowed from old ones. Men
were familiar with solid frames, and with whirlpools of
fluid, when they had not learnt to form any clear conception
of attraction at a distance. Hence they at
first imagined the heavenly motions to be caused by
Crystalline Spheres, and by Vortices. At length they
were taught to conceive Central Forces, and then they
reduced the solar system to these. But having done
this, they fancied that all the rest of the machinery of
nature must be central forces. We find Newton 124
expressing this conviction25,
and the mathematicians of
the last century acted upon it very extensively. We
may especially remark Laplace’s labours in this field.
Having explained, by such forces, the phenomena of
capillary attraction, he attempted to apply the same
kind of explanation to the reflection, refraction, and
double refraction of light;—to the constitution of
gases;—to the operation of heat. It was soon seen that
the explanation of refraction was arbitrary, and that
of double refraction illusory; while polarization entirely
eluded the grasp of this machinery. Centers of force
would no longer represent the modes of causation
which belonged to the phenomena. Polarization required
some other contrivance, such as the undulatory
theory supplied. No theory of light can be of any
avail in which the fundamental idea of Polarity is not
clearly exhibited.
25
Multa me movent, &c.,—Pref. to the Principia, already quoted in the
History.

9. The sciences of magnetism and electricity have
given rise to theories in which this relation of polarity
is exhibited by means of two opposite
fluids26;—a
positive and a negative fluid, or a vitreous and a resinous,
for electricity, and a boreal and an austral fluid
for magnetism. The hypothesis of such fluids gives
results agreeing in a remarkable manner with the
facts and their measures, as Coulomb and others have
shown. It may be asked how far we may, in such a
case, suppose that we have discovered the true cause of
the phenomena, and whether it is sufficiently proved
that these fluids really exist. The right answer seems
to be, that the hypothesis certainly represents the
truth so far as regards the polar relation of the two
energies, and the laws of the attractive and repulsive
forces of the particles in which these energies reside;
but that we are not entitled to assume that the vehicles
of these energies possess other attributes of material
fluids, or that the forces thus ascribed to the
particles are the primary elementary forces from which 125
the action originates. We are the more bound to
place this cautious limit to our acceptance of the Coulombian
theory, since in electricity Faraday has in
vain endeavoured to bring into view one of the polar
fluids without the other: whereas such a result ought
to be possible if there were two separable fluids. The
impossibility of this separate exhibition of one fluid
appears to show that the fluids are real only so far as
they are polar. And Faraday’s view above mentioned,
according to which the attractions at a distance are
resolved into the action of lines of polarized particles
of air, appears still further to show that the conceptions
hitherto entertained of electrical forces, according
to the Coulombian theory, do not penetrate to the real
and intimate nature of the causation belonging to this
case.
26
Hist. Ind. Sc. b. xi. c. ii.

10. Since it is thus difficult to know when we have
seized the true cause of the phenomena in any department
of science, it may appear to some persons that
physical inquirers are imprudent and unphilosophical
in undertaking this Research of Causes; and that it
would be safer and wiser to confine ourselves to the
investigation of the laws of phenomena, in which field
the knowledge which we obtain is definite and certain.
Hence there have not been wanting those who have
laid it down as a maxim that ‘science must study only
the laws of phenomena, and never the mode of
production27.’
But it is easy to see that such a maxim would
confine the breadth and depth of scientific inquiries to
a most scanty and miserable limit. Indeed, such a
rule would defeat its own object; for the laws of phenomena,
in many cases, cannot be even expressed or
understood without some hypothesis respecting their
mode of production. How could the phenomena of
polarization have been conceived or reasoned upon,
except by imagining a polar arrangement of particles,
or transverse vibrations, or some equivalent hypothesis?
The doctrines of fits of easy transmission, the doctrine
of moveable polarization, and the like, even when 126
erroneous as representing the whole of the phenomena,
were still useful in combining some of them into laws;
and without some such hypotheses the facts could not
have been followed out. The doctrine of a fluid caloric
may be false; but without imagining such a fluid, how
could the movement of heat from one part of a body to
another be conceived? It may be replied that Fourier,
Laplace, Poisson, who have principally cultivated the
Theory of Heat, have not conceived it as a fluid, but
have referred conduction to the radiation of the molecules
of bodies, which they suppose to be separate points.
But this molecular constitution of bodies is itself an
assumption of the mode in which the phenomena are
produced; and the radiation of heat suggests inquiries
concerning a fluid emanation, no less than its conduction
does. In like manner, the attempts to connect
the laws of phenomena of heat and of gases, have led
to hypotheses respecting the constitution of gases, and
the combination of their particles with those of caloric,
which hypotheses may be false, but are probably the
best means of discovering the truth.
27
 Comte, Philosophie Positive.

To debar science from inquiries like these, on the
ground that it is her business to inquire into facts,
and not to speculate about causes, is a curious example
of that barren caution which hopes for truth without
daring to venture upon the quest of it. This temper
would have stopped with Kepler’s discoveries, and
would have refused to go on with Newton to inquire
into the mode in which the phenomena are produced.
It would have stopped with Newton’s optical facts,
and would have refused to go on with him and his
successors to inquire into the mode in which these
phenomena are produced. And, as we have abundantly
shown, it would, on that very account, have failed in
seeing what the phenomena really are.
In many subjects the attempt to study the laws of
phenomena, independently of any speculations respecting
the causes which have produced them, is neither
possible for human intelligence nor for human temper.
Men cannot contemplate the phenomena without
clothing them in terms of some hypothesis, and will 127
not be schooled to suppress the questionings which at
every moment rise up within them concerning the
causes of the phenomena. Who can attend to the
appearances which come under the notice of the geologist;—strata
regularly bedded, full of the remains of
animals such as now live in the depths of the ocean,
raised to the tops of mountains, broken, contorted,
mixed with rocks such as still flow from the mouths of
volcanos,—who can see phenomena like these, and
imagine that he best promotes the progress of our
knowledge of the earth’s history, by noting down the
facts, and abstaining from all inquiry whether these
are really proof of past states of the earth and of
subterraneous forces, or merely an accidental imitation of
the effects of such causes? In this and similar cases,
to proscribe the inquiry into causes would be to annihilate the science.
Finally, this caution does not even gain its own
single end, the escape from hypotheses. For, as we
have said, those who will not seek for new and appropriate
causes of newly-studied phenomena, are almost
inevitably led to ascribe the facts to modifications of
causes already familiar. They may declare that they
will not hear of such causes as vital powers, elective
affinities, electric, or calorific, or luminiferous ethers or
fluids; but they will not the less on that account
assume hypotheses equally unauthorized;—for instance—universal
mechanical forces; a molecular constitution of bodies;
solid, hard, inert matter;—and will
apply these hypotheses in a manner which is arbitrary
in itself as well as quite insufficient for its purpose.
11. It appears, then, to be required, both by the
analogy of the most successful efforts of science in past
times and by the irrepressible speculative powers of
the human mind, that we should attempt to discover
both the laws of phenomena, and their causes. In every
department of science, when prosecuted far enough,
these two great steps of investigation must succeed
each other. The laws of phenomena must be known
before we can speculate concerning causes; the causes
must be inquired into when the phenomena have been 128
reduced to rule. In both these speculations the suppositions
and conceptions which occur must be constantly tested by
reference to observation and experiment. In both we must,
as far as possible, devise
hypotheses which, when we thus test them, display
those characters of truth of which we have already
spoken;—an agreement with facts such as will stand
the most patient and rigid inquiry; a provision for
predicting truly the results of untried cases; a consilience
of inductions from various classes of facts; and
a progressive tendency of the scheme to simplicity and
unity.
We shall attempt hereafter to give several rules of a
more precise and detailed kind for the discovery of the
causes, and still more, of the laws of phenomena. But
it will be useful in the first place to point out the
Classification of the Sciences which results from the
principles already established in this
work. And for
this purpose we must previously decide the question,
whether the practical Arts, as Medicine and Engineering,
must be included in our list of Sciences.
 

CHAPTER VIII.
Of Art and Science.


Aphorism XXV.
Art and Science differ. The object of Science is Knowledge;
the objects of Art, are Works. In Art, truth is a
means to an end; in Science, it is the only end. Hence the
Practical Arts are not to be classed among the Sciences.
Aphorism XXVI.
Practical Knowledge, such as Art implies, is not Knowledge
such as Science includes. Brute animals have a practical
knowledge of relations of space and force; but they have
no knowledge of Geometry or Mechanics.

1. THE
distinction of Arts and Sciences very materially
affects all classifications of the departments
of Human Knowledge. It is often maintained, expressly or
tacitly, that the Arts are a part of our
knowledge, in the same sense in which the Sciences
are so; and that Art is the application of Science to the
purposes of practical life. It will be found that these
views require some correction, when we understand
Science in the exact sense in which we have throughout
endeavoured to contemplate it, and in which alone
our examination of its nature can instruct us in the
true foundations of our knowledge.
When we cast our eyes upon the early stages of
the histories of nations, we cannot fail to be struck
with the consideration, that in many countries the
Arts of life already appear, at least in some rude form
or other, when, as yet, nothing of science exists. A 130
practical knowledge of Astronomy, such as enables them
to reckon months and years, is found among all nations
except the mere savages. A practical knowledge of
Mechanics must have existed in those nations which
have left us the gigantic monuments of early architecture.
The pyramids and temples of Egypt and Nubia,
the Cyclopean walls of Italy and Greece, the temples
of Magna Græcia and Sicily, the obelisks and edifices
of India, the cromlechs and Druidical circles of countries
formerly Celtic,—must have demanded no small
practical mechanical skill and power. Yet those
modes of reckoning time must have preceded the rise
of speculative Astronomy; these structures must have
been erected before the theory of Mechanics was
known. To suppose, as some have done, a great body
of science, now lost, to have existed in the remote
ages to which these remains belong, is not only quite
gratuitous, and contrary to all analogy, but is a
supposition which cannot be extended so far as to explain
all such cases. For it is impossible to imagine that
every art has been preceded by the science which
renders a reason for its processes. Certainly men formed
wine from the grape, before they possessed a Science of
Fermentation; the first instructor of every artificer in
brass and iron can hardly be supposed to have taught
the Chemistry of metals as a Science; the inventor
of the square and the compasses had probably no more
knowledge of demonstrated Geometry than have the
artisans who now use those implements; and finally,
the use of speech, the employment of the inflections
and combinations of words, must needs be assumed as
having been prior to any general view of the nature
and analogy of Language. Even at this moment, the
greater part of the arts which exist in the world are
not accompanied by the sciences on which they theoretically
depend. Who shall state to us the general
chemical truths to which the manufactures of glass,
and porcelain, and iron, and brass, owe their existence?
Do not almost all artisans practise many successful
artifices long before science explains the ground of the
process? Do not arts at this day exist, in a high state 131
of perfection, in countries in which there is no science,
as China and India? These countries and many others
have no theories of mechanics, of optics, of chemistry,
of physiology; yet they construct and use mechanical
and optical instruments, make chemical combinations,
take advantage of physiological laws. It is too evident
to need further illustration that Art may exist without
Science;—that the former has usually been anterior to
the latter, and even now commonly advances independently,
leaving science to follow as it can.
2. We here mean by Science, that exact, general,
speculative knowledge, of which we have, throughout
this work, been endeavouring to exhibit the nature
and rules. Between such Science and the practical
Arts of life, the points of difference are sufficiently
manifest. The object of Science is Knowledge; the
object of Art are Works. The latter is satisfied with
producing its material results; to the former, the
operations of matter, whether natural or artificial, are
interesting only so far as they can be embraced by
intelligible principles. The End of Art is the Beginning
of Science; for when it is seen what is done, then
comes the question why it is done. Art may have
fixed general rules, stated in words; but she has
these merely as means to an end: to Science, the propositions
which she obtains are each, in itself, a sufficient end of
the effort by which it is acquired. When
Art has brought forth her product, her task is finished;
Science is constantly led by one step of her path to
another: each proposition which she obtains impels
her to go onwards to other propositions more general,
more profound, more simple. Art puts elements together,
without caring to know what they are, or why
they coalesce. Science analyses the compound, and at
every such step strives not only to perform, but to
understand the analysis. Art advances in proportion
as she becomes able to bring forth products more
multiplied, more complex, more various; but Science,
straining her eyes to penetrate more and more deeply
into the nature of things, reckons her success in
proportion as she sees, in all the phenomena, however 132
multiplied; complex, and varied, the results of one or
two simple and general laws.
3. There are many acts which man, as well as
animals, performs by the guidance of nature, without
seeing or seeking the reason why he does so; as, the
acts by which he balances himself in standing or
moving, and those by which he judges of the form and
position of the objects around him. These actions
have their reason in the principles of geometry and
mechanics; but of such reasons he who thus acts is
unaware: he works blindly, under the impulse of an
unknown principle which we call Instinct. When
man’s speculative nature seeks and finds the reasons
why he should act thus or thus;—why he should
stretch out his arm to prevent his falling, or assign a
certain position to an object in consequence of the
angles under which it is seen;—he may perform the
same actions as before, but they are then done by the
aid of a different faculty, which, for the sake of
distinction, we may call Insight. Instinct is a purely
active principle; it is seen in deeds alone; it has no
power of looking inwards; it asks no questions; it has
no tendency to discover reasons or rules; it is the
opposite of Insight.
4. Art is not identical with Instinct: on the contrary,
there are broad differences. Instinct is stationary;
Art is progressive. Instinct is mute; it acts,
but gives no rules for acting: Art can speak; she can
lay down rules. But though Art is thus separate
from Instinct, she is not essentially combined with
Insight. She can see what to do, but she needs not
to see why it is done. She may lay down Rules, but it
is not her business to give Reasons. When man makes
that his employment, he enters upon the domain of
Science. Art takes the phenomena and laws of nature
as she finds them: that they are multiplied, complex,
capricious, incoherent, disturbs her not. She is content
that the rules of nature’s operations should be
perfectly arbitrary and unintelligible, provided they
are constant, so that she can depend upon their effects.
But Science is impatient of all appearance of caprice, 133
inconsistency, irregularity, in nature. She will not
believe in the existence of such characters. She resolves
one apparent anomaly after another; her task is
not ended till every thing is so plain and simple, that
she is tempted to believe that she sees that it could by
no possibility have been otherwise than it is.
5. It may be said that, after all, Art does really
involve the knowledge which Science delivers;—that
the artisan who raises large weights, practically knows
the properties of the mechanical powers;—that he
who manufactures chemical compounds is virtually
acquainted with the laws of chemical combination.
To this we reply, that it might on the same grounds
be asserted, that he who acts upon the principle that
two sides of a triangle are greater than the third is
really acquainted with geometry; and that he who
balances himself on one foot knows the properties of
the center of gravity. But this is an acquaintance
with geometry and mechanics which even brute animals
possess. It is evident that it is not of such
knowledge as this that we have here to treat. It is
plain that this mode of possessing principles is
altogether different from that contemplation of them on
which science is founded. We neglect the most essential
and manifest differences, if we confound our unconscious
assumptions with our demonstrative reasonings.
6. The real state of the case is, that the principles
which Art involves, Science alone evolves. The truths
on which the success of Art depends, lurk in the
artist’s mind in an undeveloped state; guiding his
hand, stimulating his invention, balancing his judgment;
but not appearing in the form of enunciated
Propositions. Principles are not to him direct objects
of meditation: they are secret Powers of Nature, to
which the forms which tenant the world owe their
constancy, their movements, their changes, their luxuriant
and varied growth, but which he can nowhere
directly contemplate. That the creative and directive
Principles which have their lodgment in the artist’s
mind, when unfolded by our speculative powers into 134
systematic shape, become Science, is true; but it is
precisely this process of development which gives to
them their character of Science. In practical Art,
principles are unseen guides, leading us by invisible
strings through paths where the end alone is looked
at: it is for Science to direct and purge our vision so
that these airy ties, these principles and laws,
generalizations and theories, become distinct objects of vision.
Many may feel the intellectual monitor, but it is only
to her favourite heroes that the Goddess of Wisdom
visibly reveals herself.
7. Thus Art, in its earlier stages at least, is widely
different from Science, is independent of it, and is
anterior to it. At a later period, no doubt, Art may borrow
aid from Science; and the discoveries of the philosopher
may be of great value to the manufacturer and
the artist. But even then, this application forms no
essential part of the science: the interest which belongs
to it is not an intellectual interest. The augmentation
of human power and convenience may impel
or reward the physical philosopher; but the processes
by which man’s repasts are rendered more delicious,
his journeys more rapid, his weapons more terrible,
are not, therefore, Science. They may involve principles
which are of the highest interest to science; but
as the advantage is not practically more precious because
it results from a beautiful theory, so the theoretical
principle has no more conspicuous place in science
because it leads to convenient practical consequences.
The nature of Science is purely intellectual; Knowledge
alone,—exact general Truth,—is her object; and we
cannot mix with such material, as matters of the same
kind, the merely Empirical maxims of Art, without
introducing endless confusion into the subject, and
making it impossible to attain any solid footing in our
philosophy.
8. I shall therefore not place, in our Classification
of the Sciences, the Arts, as has generally been done;
nor shall I notice the applications of sciences to art,
as forming any separate portion of each science. The
sciences, considered as bodies of general speculative 135
truths, are what we are here concerned with; and
applications of such truths, whether useful or useless,
are important to us only as illustrations and examples.
Whatever place in human knowledge the Practical
Arts may hold, they are not Sciences. And it is only
by this rigorous separation of the Practical from the
Theoretical, that we can arrive at any solid conclusions
respecting the nature of Truth, and the mode of arriving
at it, such as it is our object to attain.
 

CHAPTER IX.
Of the Classification of Sciences.



1. THE
Classification of Sciences has its chief use in
pointing out to us the extent of our powers of
arriving at truth, and the analogies which may obtain
between those certain and lucid portions of knowledge
with which we are here concerned, and those other
portions, of a very different interest and evidence,
which we here purposely abstain to touch upon. The
classification of human knowledge will, therefore, have
a more peculiar importance when we can include in it
the moral, political, and metaphysical, as well as the
physical portions of our knowledge. But such a survey
does not belong to our present undertaking: and
a general view of the connexion and order of the
branches of sciences which our review has hitherto included,
will even now possess some interest; and may
serve hereafter as an introduction to a more complete
scheme of the general body of human knowledge.
2. In this, as in any other case, a sound classification
must be the result, not of any assumed principles
imperatively applied to the subject, but of an examination
of the objects to be classified;—of an analysis of
them into the principles in which they agree and differ.
The Classification of Sciences must result from the
consideration of their nature and contents. Accordingly,
that review of the Sciences in which the History of
the Sciences engaged us, led to a Classification, of which
the main features are indicated in that work. The
Classification thus obtained, depends neither upon the
faculties of the mind to which the separate parts of
our knowledge owe their origin, nor upon the objects
which each science contemplates; but upon a more 137
natural and fundamental element;—namely, the Ideas
which each science involves. The Ideas regulate and
connect the facts, and are the foundations of the reasoning,
in each science: and having in another work
more fully examined these Ideas, we are now prepared
to state here the classification to which they lead. If
we have rightly traced each science to the Conceptions
which are really fundamental with regard to it, and
which give rise to the first principles on which it
depends, it is not necessary for our purpose that we
should decide whether these Conceptions are absolutely
ultimate principles of thought, or whether, on the contrary,
they can be further resolved into other Fundamental Ideas.
We need not now suppose it determined whether or not Number
is a mere modification
of the Idea of Time, and Force a mere modification of
the Idea of Cause: for however this may be, our Conception
of Number is the foundation of Arithmetic,
and our Conception of Force is the foundation of Mechanics.
It is to be observed also that in our classification,
each Science may involve, not only the Ideas
or Conceptions which are placed opposite to it in the
list, but also all which precede it. Thus Formal Astronomy
involves not only the Conception of Motion, but
also those which are the foundation of Arithmetic and
Geometry. In like manner. Physical Astronomy employs the
Sciences of Statics and Dynamics, and thus,
rests on their foundations; and they, in turn, depend
upon the Ideas of Space and of Time, as well as of
Cause.
3. We may further observe, that this arrangement
of Sciences according to the Fundamental Ideas which
they involve, points out the transition from those parts
of human knowledge which have been included in our
History and Philosophy, to other regions of speculation
into which we have not entered. We have repeatedly
found ourselves upon the borders of inquiries of a
psychological, or moral, or theological nature. Thus
the History of Physiology28
led us to the consideration 138
of Life, Sensation, and Volition; and at these Ideas we
stopped, that we might not transgress the boundaries of
our subject as then predetermined. It is plain that
the pursuit of such conceptions and their consequences,
would lead us to the sciences (if we are allowed to call
them sciences) which contemplate not only animal, but
human principles of action, to Anthropology, and Psychology.
In other ways, too, the Ideas which we hare
examined, although manifestly the foundations of sciences
such as we have here treated of also plainly
pointed to speculations of a different order; thus the
Idea of a Final Cause is an indispensable guide in
Biology, as we have seen; but the conception of Design
as directing the order of nature, once admitted, soon
carries us to higher contemplations. Again, the Class
of Palætiological Sciences which we were in the History
led to construct, although we there admitted only
one example of the Class, namely Geology, does in
reality include many vast lines of research; as the
history and causes of the division of plants and animals,
the history of languages, arts, and consequently
of civilization. Along with these researches, comes
the question how far these histories point backwards to
a natural or a supernatural origin; and the Idea of a
First Cause is thus brought under our consideration.
Finally, it is not difficult to see that as the Physical
Sciences have their peculiar governing Ideas, which
support and shape them, so the Moral and Political
Sciences also must similarly have their fundamental
and formative Ideas, the source of universal and certain
truths, each of their proper kind. But to follow
out the traces of this analogy, and to verify the
existence of those Fundamental Ideas in Morals and
Politics, is a task quite out of the sphere of the work
in which we are here engaged.
28
 Hist. Ind. Sc. b. xvii. c. v. sect. 2.

4. We may now place before the reader our Classification
of the Sciences. I have added to the list of
Sciences, a few not belonging to our present subject,
that the nature of the transition by which we are to
extend our philosophy into a wider and higher region
may be in some measure perceived. 139
The Classification of the Sciences is given over leaf.
A few remarks upon it offer themselves.
The Pure Mathematical Sciences can hardly be called
Inductive Sciences. Their principles are not obtained
by Induction from Facts, but are necessarily assumed
in reasoning upon the subject matter which those
sciences involve.
The Astronomy of the Ancients aimed only at explaining
the motions of the heavenly bodies, as a mechanism.
Modern Astronomy, explains these motions on
the principles of Mechanics.
The term Physics, when confined to a peculiar
class of Sciences, is usually understood to exclude the
Mechanical Sciences on the one side, and Chemistry
on the other; and thus embraces the Secondary Mechanical
and Analytico-Mechanical Sciences. But the adjective
Physical applied to any science and opposed
to Formal, as in Astronomy and Optics, implies those
speculations in which we consider not only the Laws
of Phenomena but their Causes; and generally, as
in those cases, their Mechanical Causes.
The term Metaphysics is applied to subjects in which
the Facts examined are emotions, thoughts and mental
conditions; subjects not included in our present survey. 140


Fundamental Ideas or
Conceptions.Sciences.Classification.


SpaceGeometry⎫


Time⎪Pure Mathematical


NumberArithmetic⎬


SignAlgebra⎪ Sciences.


LimitDifferentials⎭


MotionPure Mechanism⎱Pure Motional


Formal Astronomy⎰Sciences.





Cause


ForceStatics⎫


MatterDynamics⎪Mechanical


Inertia Hydrostatics⎬


Fluid PressureHydrodynamics⎪Sciences.


Physical Astronomy⎭


Outness


Medium of SensationAcoustics⎫


Intensity of QualitiesFormal Optics⎪Secondary


Scales of QualitiesPhysical Optics⎬Mechanical


Thermotics⎪Sciences.


Atmology⎭(Physics.)


PolarityElectricity⎫Analytico-Mecha-


Magnetism⎬nical Sciences.


Galvanism⎭(Physics.)


Element (Composition)


Chemical Affinity


Substance (Atoms)ChemistryAnalytical Science.


SymmetryCrystallography⎱Analytico-Classifi-


LikenessSystematic Mineralogy⎰catory Sciences.


Degrees of LikenessSystematic Botany⎫Classificatory


Systematic Zoology⎬


Natural AffinityComparative Anatomy⎭Sciences.


(Vital Powers)


Assimilation


Irritability


(Organization)BiologyOrganical Sciences.


Final Cause


Instinct


EmotionPsychology(Metaphysics.)


Thought


Historical CausationGeology⎫


Distribution of⎪Palætiological


 Plants and Animals⎬


Glossology⎪Sciences.


Ethnography⎭


First CauseNatural Theology.


 

INDUCTIVE CHARTS

[Transcriber's note: Two large charts were inserted into the book at this point. Here
they have been reproduced as tables. But since the originals were much wider than the book
pages they are somewhat unwieldy tables. They are omitted in ePub and Kindle files.
In the lines containing brackets, vertical lines
are used to indicate the range of columns thus brought together, where this is not obvious.
To move on to the text of Book III., click here.]
</div></body></text></TEI>