<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="4">CHAPTER III.
Failure of the Physical Philosophy of the Greek
Schools.

Sect. 1.—Result of the Greek School
Philosophy.
THE methods and forms of
philosophizing which we have described as employed by the Greek
Schools, failed altogether in their application to physics. No
discovery of general laws, no explanation of special phenomena,
rewarded the acuteness and boldness of these early students of nature.
Astronomy, which made considerable progress during the existence of
the sects of Greek philosophers, gained perhaps something by the
authority with which Plato taught the supremacy and universality of
mathematical rule and order; and the truths of Harmonics, which had
probably given rise to the Pythagorean passion for numbers, were
cultivated with much care by that school. But after these first
impulses, the sciences owed nothing to the philosophical sects; and
the vast and complex accumulations and apparatus of the Stagirite do
not appear to have led to any theoretical physical truths.
This assertion hardly requires proof, since in the existing body of
science there are no doctrines for which we are indebted to the
Aristotelian School. Real truths, when once established, remain to the
end of time a part of the mental treasure of man, and may be discerned
through all the additions of later days. But we can point out no
physical doctrine now received, of which we trace the anticipation in
Aristotle, in the way in which we see the Copernican system
anticipated by Aristarchus, the resolution of the heavenly appearances
into circular motions suggested by Plato, and the numerical relations
of musical intervals ascribed to Pythagoras. But it may be worth while
to look at this matter more closely.
Among the works of Aristotle are thirty-eight chapters of
“Problems,” which may serve to exemplify the progress he had really
made in the reduction of phenomena to laws and causes. Of these
Problems, a large proportion are physiological, and these I here pass
by, as not illustrative of the state of physical knowledge. But those
which are properly physical are, for the most part, questions
concerning such 81
facts and difficulties as it is the peculiar business of theory to
explain. Now it may be truly said, that in scarcely any one instance
are the answers, which Aristotle gives to his questions, of any value.
For the most part, indeed, he propounds his answer with a degree of
hesitation or vacillation which of itself shows the absence of all
scientific distinctness of thought; and the opinions so offered never
appear to involve any settled or general principle.
We may take, as examples of this, the problems of the simplest
kind, where the principles lay nearest at hand—the mechanical
ones. “Why,” he asks,43 “do small forces move great weights by
means of a lever, when they have thus to move the lever added to the
weight? Is it,” he suggests, “because a greater radius moves faster?”
“Why does a small wedge split great weights?44 Is it because
the wedge is composed of two opposite levers?” “Why,45 when a man rises from a chair, does he
bend his leg and his body to acute angles with his thigh? Is it
because a right angle is connected with equality and rest?” “Why46 can a man throw a stone further with a
sling than with his hand? Is it that when he throws with his hand he
moves the stone from rest, but when he uses the sling he throws it
already in motion?” “Why,47 if a circle be thrown on the ground,
does it first describe a straight line and then a spiral, as it falls?
Is it that the air first presses equally on the two sides and supports
it, and afterwards presses on one side more?” “Why48 is it difficult
to distinguish a musical note from the octave above? Is it that
proportion stands in the place of equality?” It must be allowed that
these are very vague and worthless surmises; for even if we were, as
some commentators have done, to interpret some of them so as to agree
with sound philosophy, we should still be unable to point out, in this
author’s works, any clear or permanent apprehension of the general
principles which such an interpretation implies.
43 Mech. Prob. 4.
44 Ib. 18.
45 Ib. 31.
46 Ib. 13.
47 Περὶ Ἄψυχα. 11.
48 Περὶ Ἁρμον. 14.
Thus the Aristotelian physics cannot be considered as otherwise
than a complete failure. It collected no general laws from facts; and
consequently, when it tried to explain facts, it had no principles
which were of any avail.
The same may be said of the physical speculations of the other
schools of philosophy. They arrived at no doctrines from which they
could deduce, by sound reasoning, such facts as they saw; though they
82 often venture so
far to trust their principles as to infer from them propositions
beyond the domain of sense. Thus, the principle that each element
seeks its own place, led to the doctrine that, the place of
fire being the highest, there is, above the air, a Sphere of
Fire—of which doctrine the word Empyrean, used by our
poets, still conveys a reminiscence. The Pythagorean tenet that ten is
a perfect number,49 led some persons to assume that the
heavenly bodies are in number ten; and as nine only were known to
them, they asserted that there was an antichthon, or
counter-earth, on the other side of the sun, invisible to us.
Their opinions respecting numerical ratios, led to various other
speculations concerning the distances and positions of the heavenly
bodies: and as they had, in other cases, found a connection between
proportions of distance and musical notes, they assumed, on this
suggestion, the music of the spheres.
49 Arist. Metaph. i. 5.
Although we shall look in vain in the physical philosophy of the
Greek Schools for any results more valuable than those just mentioned,
we shall not be surprised to find, recollecting how much an admiration
for classical antiquity has possessed the minds of men, that some
writers estimate their claims much more highly than they are stated
here. Among such writers we may notice Dutens, who, in 1766, published
his “Origin of the Discoveries attributed to the Moderns; in which it
is shown that our most celebrated Philosophers have received the
greatest part of their knowledge from the Works of the Ancients.” The
thesis of this work is attempted to be proved, as we might expect, by
very large interpretations of the general phrases used by the
ancients. Thus, when Timæus, in Plato’s dialogue, says of the Creator
of the world,50 “that he infused into it two powers,
the origins of motions, both of that of the same thing and of that of
different things;” Dutens51 finds in this a clear indication of the
projectile and attractive forces of modern science. And in some of the
common declamation of the Pythagoreans and Platonists concerning the
general prevalence of numerical relations in the universe, he
discovers their acquaintance with the law of the inverse square of the
distance by which gravitation is regulated, though he allows52 that it required all the penetration of
Newton and his followers to detect this law in the scanty fragments by
which it is transmitted.
50 Tim. 96.
51 3d ed. p. 83.
52 Ib. p. 88.
Argument of this kind is palpably insufficient to cover the failure
of the Greek attempts at a general physical philosophy; or rather we
83 may say, that
such arguments, since they are as good as can be brought in favor of
such an opinion, show more clearly how entire the failure was. I
proceed now to endeavor to point out its causes.
Sect. 2.—Cause of the Failure of the Greek
Physical Philosophy.
The cause of the failure of so many of the
attempts of the Greeks to construct physical science is so important,
that we must endeavor to bring it into view here; though the full
development of such subjects belongs rather to the Philosophy of
Induction. The subject must, at present, be treated very briefly.
I will first notice some errors which may naturally occur to the
reader’s mind, as possible causes of failure, but which, we shall be
able to show, were not the real reasons in this case.
The cause of failure was not the neglect of facts. It is
often said that the Greeks disregarded experience, and spun their
philosophy out of their own thoughts alone; and this is supposed by
many to be their essential error. It is, no doubt, true, that the
disregard of experience is a phrase which may be so interpreted as to
express almost any defect of philosophical method; since coincidence
with experience is requisite to the truth of all theory. But if we fix
a more precise sense on our terms, I conceive it may be shown that the
Greek philosophy did, in its opinions, recognize the necessity and
paramount value of observations; did, in its origin, proceed upon
observed facts; and did employ itself to no small extent in
classifying and arranging phenomena. We must endeavor to illustrate
these assertions, because it is important to show that these steps
alone do not necessarily lead to science.
1. The acknowledgment of experience as the main ground of physical
knowledge is so generally understood to be a distinguishing feature of
later times, that it may excite surprise to find that Aristotle, and
other ancient philosophers, not only asserted in the most pointed
manner that all our knowledge must begin from experience, but also
stated in language much resembling the habitual phraseology of the
most modern schools of philosophizing, that particular facts must be
collected; that from these, general principles must be
obtained by induction; and that these principles, when of the
most general kind, are axioms. A few passages will show
this.
“The way53 must be the same,” says Aristotle, in
speaking of the rules of reasoning, “with respect to philosophy, as it
is with respect to 84 any art or science whatever; we must
collect the facts, and the things to which the facts happen, in each
subject, and provide as large a supply of these as possible.” He then
proceeds to say that “we are not to look at once at all this collected
mass, but to consider small and definite portions” . . . “And thus it
is the office of observation to supply principles in each subject; for
instance, astronomical observation supplies the principles of
astronomical science. For the phenomena being properly assumed, the
astronomical demonstrations were from these discovered. And the same
applies to every art and science. So that if we take the facts (τὰ
ὑπάρχοντα) belonging to each subject, it is our task to mark
out clearly the course of the demonstrations. For if in our
natural history (κατὰ τὴν ἱστορίαν) we have omitted nothing of
the facts and properties which belong to the subject, we shall learn
what we can demonstrate and what we cannot.”
53 Anal. Prior. i. 30.
These facts, τὰ ὑπάρχοντα, he, at other times, includes in the term
sensation. Thus, he says,54 “It is obvious
that if any sensation is wanting, there must be also some knowledge
wanting which we are thus prevented from having, since we arrive at
knowledge either by induction or by demonstration. Demonstration
proceeds from universal propositions, Induction from particulars. But
we cannot have universal theoretical propositions except from
induction; and we cannot make inductions without having sensation; for
sensation has to do with particulars.”
54 Anal. Post. i. 18.
In another place,55 after stating that principles must be
prior to, and better known than conclusions, he distinguishes such
principles into absolutely prior, and prior relative to us: “The prior
principles, relative to us, are those which are nearer to the
sensation; but the principles absolutely prior are those which are
more remote from the sensation. The most general principles are the
more remote, the more particular are nearer. The general principles
which are necessary to knowledge are axioms.”
55 Ib. i. 2.
We may add to these passages, that in which he gives an account of
the way in which Leucippus was led to the doctrine of atoms. After
describing the opinions of some earlier philosophers, he says,56 “Thus, proceeding in violation of
sensation, and disregarding it, because, as they held, they must
follow reason, some came to the conclusion that the universe was one,
and infinite, and at rest. As it appeared, however, that though this
ought to be by reasoning, it 85 would go near to madness to hold such
opinions in practice (for no one was ever so mad as to think fire and
ice to be one), Leucippus, therefore, pursued a line of reasoning
which was in accordance with sensation, and which was not
irreconcilable with the production and decay, the motion and multitude
of things.” It is obvious that the school to which Leucippus belonged
(the Eclectic) must have been, at least in its origin, strongly
impressed with the necessity of bringing its theories into harmony
with the observed course of nature.
56 De Gen. et Cor. i. 8.
2. Nor was this recognition of the fundamental value of experience
a mere profession. The Greek philosophy did, in its beginning, proceed
upon observation. Indeed it is obvious that the principles which it
adopted were, in the first place, assumed in order to account for some
classes of facts, however imperfectly they might answer their purpose.
The principle of things seeking their own places, was invented in
order to account for the falling and floating of bodies. Again,
Aristotle says, that heat is that which brings together things of the
same kind, cold is that which brings together things whether of the
same or of different kinds: it is plain that in this instance he
intended by his principle to explain some obvious facts, as the
freezing of moist substances, and the separation of heterogeneous
things by fusion; for, as he adds, if fire brings together things
which are akin, it will separate those which are not akin. It would be
easy to illustrate the remark further, but its truth is evident from
the nature of the case; for no principles could be accepted for a
moment, which were the result of an arbitrary caprice of the mind, and
which were not in some measure plausible, and apparently confirmed by
facts.
But the works of Aristotle show, in another way, how unjust it
would be to accuse him of disregarding facts. Many large treatises of
his consist almost entirely of collections of facts, as for instance,
those “On Colors,” “On Sounds,” and the collection of Problems to
which we have already referred; to say nothing of the numerous
collection of facts bearing on natural history and physiology, which
form a great portion of his works, and are even now treasuries of
information. A moment’s reflection will convince us that the physical
sciences of our own times, for example. Mechanics and Hydrostatics,
are founded almost entirely upon facts with which the ancients were as
familiar as we are. The defect of their philosophy, therefore,
wherever it may lie, consists neither in the speculative depreciation
of the value of facts, nor in the practical neglect of their use.
3. Nor again, should we hit upon the truth, if we were to say that
86 Aristotle, and
other ancient philosophers, did indeed collect facts; but that they
took no steps in classifying and comparing them; and that thus they
failed to obtain from them any general knowledge. For, in reality, the
treatises of Aristotle which we have mentioned, are as remarkable for
the power of classifying and systematizing which they exhibit, as for
the industry shown in the accumulation. But it is not classification
of facts merely which can lead us to knowledge, except we adopt that
special arrangement, which, in each case, brings into view the
principles of the subject. We may easily show how unprofitable an
arbitrary or random classification is, however orderly and systematic
it may be.
For instance, for a long period all unusual fiery appearances in
the sky were classed together as meteors. Comets,
shooting-stars, and globes of fire, and the aurora borealis in all its
forms, were thus grouped together, and classifications of considerable
extent and minuteness were proposed with reference to these objects.
But this classification was of a mixed and arbitrary kind. Figure,
color, motion, duration, were all combined as characters, and the
imagination lent its aid, transforming these striking appearances into
fiery swords and spears, bears and dragons, armies and chariots. The
facts so classified were, notwithstanding, worthless; and would not
have been one jot the less so, had they and their classes been ten
times as numerous as they were. No rule or law that would stand the
test of observation was or could be thus discovered. Such
classifications have, therefore, long been neglected and forgotten.
Even the ancient descriptions of these objects of curiosity are
unintelligible, or unworthy of trust, because the spectators had no
steady conception of the usual order of such phenomena. For, however
much we may fear to be misled by preconceived opinions, the caprices
of imagination distort our impressions far more than the anticipations
of reason. In this case men had, indeed we may say with regard to many
of these meteors, they still have, no science: not for want of facts,
nor even for want of classification of facts; but because the
classification was one in which no real principle was contained.
4. Since, as we have said before, two
things are requisite to science,—Facts and Ideas; and since, as
we have seen. Facts were not wanting in the physical speculations of
the ancients, we are naturally led to ask, Were they then deficient in
Ideas? Was there a want among them of mental activity, and logical
connection of thought? But it is so obvious that the answer to this
inquiry must be in the negative, that we need not dwell upon it. No
one who knows any thing of the 87 history of the ancient Greek mind, can
question, that in acuteness, in ingenuity, in the power of close and
distinct reasoning, they have never been surpassed. The common
opinion, which considers the defect of their philosophical character
to reside rather in the exclusive activity of such qualities, than in
the absence of them, is at least so far just.
5. We come back again, therefore, to the question, What was the
radical and fatal defect in the physical speculations of the Greek
philosophical schools?
To this I answer: The defect was, that though they had in their
possession Facts and Ideas, the Ideas were not distinct and
appropriate to the Facts.
The peculiar characteristics of scientific ideas, which I have
endeavored to express by speaking of them as distinct and
appropriate to the facts, must be more fully and formally set
forth, when we come to the philosophy of the subject. In the mean
time, the reader will probably have no difficulty in conceiving that,
for each class of Facts, there is some special set of Ideas, by means
of which the facts can be included in general scientific truths; and
that these Ideas, which may thus be termed appropriate, must be
possessed with entire distinctness and clearness, in order that they
may be successfully applied. It was the want of Ideas having this
reference to material phenomena, which rendered the ancient
philosophers, with very few exceptions, helpless and unsuccessful
speculators on physical subjects.
This must be illustrated by one or two examples. One of the facts
which Aristotle endeavors to explain is this; that when the sun’s
light passes through a hole, whatever be the form of the hole, the
bright image, if formed at any considerable distance from the hole, is
round, instead of imitating the figure of the hole, as shadows
resemble their objects in form. We shall easily perceive this
appearance to be a necessary consequence of the circular figure of the
sun, if we conceive light to be diffused from the luminary by means of
straight rays proceeding from every point of the sun’s disk and
passing through every point within the boundary of the hole. By
attending to the consequences of this mode of conception, it will be
seen that each point of the hole will be the vertex of a double cone
of rays which has the sun’s disk for its base on one side and an image
of the sun on the other; and the figure of the image of the hole will
be determined by supposing a series of equal bright circles, images of
the sun, to be placed along the boundary of an image equal to the hole
itself. The figure of the image thus determined will partake of the
form of the hole, and 88 of the circular form of the sun’s image:
but these circular images become larger and larger as they are further
from the hole, while the central image of the hole remains always of
the original size; and thus at a considerable distance from the hole,
the trace of the hole’s form is nearly obliterated, and the image is
nearly a perfect circle. Instead of this distinct conception of a cone
of rays which has the sun’s disk for its basis, Aristotle has the
following loose conjecture.57 “Is it because light is emitted in a
conical form; and of a cone, the base is a circle; so that on whatever
the rays of the sun fall, they appear more circular?” And thus though
he applies the notion of rays to this problem, he possesses this
notion so indistinctly that his explanation is of no value.
He does not introduce into his explanation the consideration of the
sun’s circular figure, and is thus prevented from giving a true
account of this very simple optical phenomenon.
57 Problem. 15, ὁσα μαθηματίκης,
&c.
6. Again, to pass to a more extensive failure: why was it that
Aristotle, knowing the property of the lever, and many other
mechanical truths, was unable to form them into a science of
mechanics, as Archimedes afterwards did?
The reason was, that, instead of considering rest and motion
directly, and distinctly, with reference to the Idea of Cause, that is
Force, he wandered in search of reasons among other ideas and notions,
which could not be brought into steady connection with the
facts;—the ideas of properties of circles, of proportions of
velocities,—the notions of “strange” and “common,” of “natural”
and “unnatural.” Thus, in the Proem to his Mechanical Problems, after
stating some of the difficulties which he has to attack, he says, “Of
all such cases, the circle contains the principle of the cause. And
this is what might be looked for; for it is nothing absurd, if
something wonderful is derived from something more wonderful
still. Now the most wonderful thing is, that opposites should be
combined; and the circle is constituted of such combinations of
opposites. For it is constructed by a stationary point and a moving
line, which are contrary to each other in nature; and hence we may the
less be surprised at the resulting contrarieties. And in the first
place, the circumference of the circle, though a line without breadth,
has opposite qualities; for it is both convex and
concave. In the next place, it has, at the same time, opposite
motions, for it moves forward and backward at the same time. For the
circumference, setting out from any point, comes to the same point
again, so 89 that by
a continuous progression, the last point becomes the first. So that,
as was before stated, it is not surprising that the circle should be
the principle of all wonderful properties.”
Aristotle afterwards proceeds to explain more specially how he
applies the properties of the circle in this case. “The reason,” he
says, in his fourth Problem, “why a force, acting at a greater
distance from the fulcrum, moves a weight more easily, is, that it
describes a greater circle.” He had already asserted that when a body
at the end of a lever is put in motion, it may be considered as having
two motions; one in the direction of the tangent, and one in the
direction of the radius; the former motion is, he says, according
to nature, the latter, contrary to nature. Now in the
smaller circle, the motion, contrary to nature, is more considerable
than it is in the larger circle. “Therefore,” he adds, “the mover or
weight at the larger arm will be transferred further by the same force
than the weight moved, which is at the extremity of the shorter
arm.”
These loose and inappropriate notions of “natural” and “unnatural”
motions, were unfit to lead to any scientific truths; and, with the
habits of thought which dictated these speculations a perception of
the true grounds of mechanical properties was impossible.
7. Thus, in this instance, the error of Aristotle was the neglect
of the Idea appropriate to the facts, namely, the Idea of
Mechanical Cause, which is Force; and the substitution of vague or
inapplicable notions involving only relations of space or emotions of
wonder. The errors of those who failed similarly in other instances,
were of the same kind. To detail or classify these would lead us too
far into the philosophy of science; since we should have to enumerate
the Ideas which are appropriate, and the various classes of Facts on
which the different sciences are founded,—a task not to be now
lightly undertaken. But it will be perceived, without further
explanation, that it is necessary, in order to obtain from facts any
general truth, that we should apply to them that appropriate Idea, by
which permanent and definite relations are established among them.
In such Ideas the ancients were very poor, and the stunted and
deformed growth of their physical science was the result of this
penury. The Ideas of Space and Time, Number and Motion, they did
indeed possess distinctly; and so far as these went, their science was
tolerably healthy. They also caught a glimpse of the Idea of a Medium
by which the qualities of bodies, as colors and sounds, are perceived.
But the idea of Substance remained barren in their hands; 90 in speculating about
elements and qualities, they went the wrong way, assuming that the
properties of Compounds must resemble those of the Elements
which determine them; and their loose notions of Contrariety never
approached the form of those ideas of Polarity, which, in modern
times, regulate many parts of physics and chemistry.
If this statement should seem to any one to be technical or
arbitrary, we must refer, for the justification of it, to the
Philosophy of Science, of which we hope hereafter to treat. But it
will appear, even from what has been here said, that there are certain
Ideas or Forms of mental apprehension, which may be applied to Facts
in such a manner as to bring into view fundamental principles of
science; while the same Facts, however arrayed or reasoned about, so
long as these appropriate ideas are not employed, cannot give rise to
any exact or substantial knowledge.
[2d Ed.] This account of the cause of failure in the physical
speculations of the ancient Greek philosophers has been objected to as
unsatisfactory. I will offer a few words in explanation of it.
The mode of accounting for the failure of the Greeks in physics is,
in substance;—that the Greeks in their physical speculations
fixed their attention upon the wrong aspects and relations of the
phenomena; and that the aspects and relations in which phenomena are
to be viewed in order to arrive at scientific truths may be arranged
under certain heads, which I have termed Ideas; such as Space,
Time, Number, Cause, Likeness. In every case, there is an Idea to
which the phenomena may be referred, so as to bring into view the Laws
by which they are governed; this Idea I term the appropriate
Idea in such case; and in order that the reference of the phenomena to
the Law may be clearly seen, the Idea must be distinctly
possessed.
Thus the reason of Aristotle’s failure in his attempts at
Mechanical Science is, that he did not refer the facts to the
appropriate Idea, namely Force, the Cause of Motion, but to relations
of Space and the like; that is, he introduces Geometrical
instead of Mechanical Ideas. It may be said that we learn
little by being told that Aristotle’s failure in this and the like
cases arose from his referring to the wrong class of Ideas; or, as I
have otherwise expressed it, fixing his attention upon the wrong
aspects and relations of the facts; since, it may be said, this is
only to state in other words that he did fail. But this
criticism is, I think, ill-founded. The account which I have given is
not only a statement that Aristotle, and others who took a like
course, did fail; but also, that they failed in one certain point out
of several 91 which
are enumerated. They did not fail because they neglected to observe
facts; they did not fail because they omitted to class facts; they did
not fail because they had not ideas to reason from; but they failed
because they did not take the right ideas in each case. And so long as
they were in the wrong in this point, no industry in collecting facts,
or ingenuity in classing them and reasoning about them, could lead
them to solid truth.
Nor is this account of the nature of their mistake without its
instruction for us; although we are not to expect to derive from the
study of their failure any technical rule which shall necessarily
guide us to scientific discovery. For their failure teaches us that,
in the formation of science, an Error in the Ideas is as fatal to the
discovery of Truth as an Error in the Facts; and may as completely
impede the progress of knowledge. I have in Books ii. to x. of the
Philosophy, shown historically how large a portion of the
progress of Science consists in the establishment of Appropriate Ideas
as the basis of each science. Of the two main processes by which
science is constructed, as stated in Book xi.
of that work, namely the Explication of Conceptions and the
Colligation of Facts, the former must precede the latter. In
Book xii. chap. 5, of the Philosophy, I
have stated the maxim concerning appropriate Ideas in this form, that
the Idea and the Facts must be homogeneous.
When I say that the failure of the Greeks in physical science arose
from their not employing appropriate Ideas to connect the
facts, I do not use the term “appropriate” in a loose popular sense;
but I employ it as a somewhat technical term, to denote the
appropriate Idea, out of that series of Ideas which have been made (as
I have shown in the Philosophy) the foundation of sciences;
namely, Space, Time, Number, Cause, Likeness, Substance, and the rest.
It appears to me just to say that Aristotle’s failure in his attempts
to deal with problems of equilibrium, arose from his referring to
circles, velocities, notions of natural and unnatural, and the
like,—conceptions depending upon Ideas of Space, of Nature,
&c.—which are not appropriate to these problems, and from
his missing the Idea of Mechanical Force or Pressure, which is the
appropriate Idea.
I give this, not as an account of all failures in attempts
at science, but only as the account of such radical and fundamental
failures as this of Aristotle; who, with a knowledge of the facts,
failed to connect them into a really scientific view. If I had to
compare rival theories of a more complex kind, I should not
necessarily say that one involved 92 an appropriate Idea and the other did not,
though I might judge one to be true and the other to be false. For
instance, in comparing the emissive and the undulatory theory of
light, we see that both involve the same Idea;—the Idea of a
Medium acting by certain mechanical properties. The question there is,
What is the true view of the mechanism of the Medium?
It may be remarked, however, that the example of Aristotle’s
failure in physics, given in p. 87, namely,
his attempted explanation of the round image of a square hole, is a
specimen rather of indistinct than of inappropriate
ideas.
The geometrical explanation of this phenomenon, which I have there
inserted, was given by Maurolycus, and before him, by Leonardo da
Vinci.
We shall, in the next  Book, see the
influence of the appropriate general Ideas, in the formation of
various sciences. It need only be observed, before we proceed, that,
in order to do full justice to the physical knowledge of the Greek
Schools of philosophy, it is not necessary to study their course after
the time of their founders. Their fortunes, in respect of such
acquisitions as we are now considering, were not progressive. The
later chiefs of the Schools followed the earlier masters; and though
they varied much, they added little. The Romans adopted the philosophy
of their Greek subjects; but they were always, and, indeed,
acknowledged themselves to be, inferior to their teachers. They were
as arbitrary and loose in their ideas as the Greeks, without
possessing their invention, acuteness, and spirit of system.
In addition to the vagueness which was combined with the more
elevated trains of philosophical speculation among the Greeks, the
Romans introduced into their treatises a kind of declamatory rhetoric,
which arose probably from their forensic and political habits, and
which still further obscured the waning gleams of truth. Yet we may
also trace in the Roman philosophers to whom this charge mostly
applies (Lucretius, Pliny, Seneca), the national vigor and ambition.
There is something Roman in the public spirit and anticipation of
universal empire which they display, as citizens of the intellectual
republic. Though they speak sadly or slightingly of the achievements
of their own generation, they betray a more abiding and vivid belief
in the dignity and destined advance of human knowledge as a whole,
than is obvious among the Greeks.
We must, however, turn back, in order to describe steps
of more definite value to the progress of science than those which we
have hitherto noticed.  ~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~


BOOK II.

HISTORY
OF THE
PHYSICAL
SCIENCES
IN
ANCIENT GREECE.


Ναρθηκοπλήρωτον δὲ θηρῶμαι πυρὸς
Πηγὴν κλοπαίαν, ἣ διδάσκαλος τέχνης
Πάσης βροτοῖς πεφῆνε καὶ μέγας πόρος.
Prom. Vinct. 109.

I brought to earth the spark of heavenly
fire,
Concealed at first, and small, but spreading
soon
Among the sons of men, and burning on,
Teacher of art and use, and fount of
power.

</div></body></text></TEI>