<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="10">CHAPTER VIII.
While I murmured in bitterness of soul at the lowness to
which my family was reduced, a still heavier calamity impended,
as if in vengeance against the fantastic refinements
of distress over which I brooded.
I was wandering, as I had often done, with a gloomy
and rebellious spirit, among the rocks, a few miles distant
from the place of our habitation. It was the middle of
summer. The weather had been remarkably fine; but I
disdained to allow the gratifications which arise from a pure
atmosphere and a serene sky to find entrance in my soul.
My excursions had for some days been incessant; and the
sun, which matured the corn and blackened the grapes[88]
around, had imbrowned my visage, and boiled in my blood.
I drank in fierceness and desperation from the fervour of
his beams. One night, as in sullen mood I watched his
setting from a point of the rock, I perceived the clearness
of the day subsiding in a threatening evening. The
clouds gathered in the west; and, as night approached, were
overspread with a deep dye of the fiercest crimson. The
wind rose; and, during the hours of darkness, its roarings
were hollow and tempestuous.
In the morning the clouds were hurried rapidly along,
and the air was changed from a long series of sultriness to
a nipping cold. This change of the atmosphere I disregarded,
and pursued my rambles. A little before noon,
however, the air suddenly grew so dark, as to produce a
sensation perfectly tremendous. I felt as if the darkest
night had never exceeded it. The impetuous motion to
which I had been impelled, partly by the fever in my blood,
and partly by the turbulence of the season, was suspended.
Mechanically I looked round me for shelter. But I could
ill distinguish the objects that were near me, when a flash
of lightning, blue and sulphureous, came directly in my
face, with a brightness that threatened to extinguish the
organ of vision. The thunder that followed was of a
length and loudness to admit of no comparison from any
object with which I am acquainted. The bursts were so
frequent as almost to confound themselves with each other.
At present I thought only of myself; and the recent habits
of my mind were not calculated to make me peculiarly accessible
to fear. I stood awe-struck; but rather with the awe
that inheres to a cultivated imagination, than that which
consists in apprehension. I seemed ready to mount amidst
the clouds, and penetrate the veil with which nature conceals
her operations. I would have plunged into the recesses
in which the storm was engendered, and bared my bosom
to the streaming fire. Meanwhile my thoughts were solemnised
and fixed by observing the diversified dance of the
lightnings upon the points of the rocks, contrasting as they
did in the strongest manner with the darkness in which
the rest of the scene was enveloped. This added contention
of the elements did not, however, suspend the raging[89]
of the wind. Presently a storm of mingled hail and rain
poured from the clouds, and was driven with inconceivable
impetuosity. The hailstones were of so astonishing a magnitude,
that, before I was aware, I was beaten by them to
the ground. Not daring to attempt to rise again, I simply
endeavoured to place myself in such a manner as might best
protect me from their violence. I therefore remained prostrate,
listening to the force with which they struck upon the
earth, and feeling the rebound of their blows from different
parts of my body.
In about twenty minutes the shower abated, and in half
an hour was entirely over. When I began to move, I was
surprised at the sensation of soreness which I felt in every
part of me. I raised myself upon my elbow, and saw the
hailstones, in some places lying in heaps like hillocks of
ice, while in others they had ploughed up the surface, and
buried themselves in the earth. As I looked further, I perceived
immense trees torn from their roots, and thrown to
a great distance upon the declivity. To the noise that they
made in their descent, which must have been astonishingly
great, I had been at the time insensible. Such were the
marks which the tempest had left upon the mountains.
In the plain it was still worse. I could perceive the soil
for long spaces together converted into a morass, the standing
corn beaten down and buried in the mud, the vines
torn into a thousand pieces, the fruit trees demolished, and
even in some places the animals themselves, lambs, sheep, and
cows, strewing the fields with their mangled carcasses. The
whole hopes of the year over which my eyes had glanced a
few minutes before, for it was near the period of harvest,
were converted into the most barren and dreary scene that
any quarter of the globe ever witnessed. I was mounted
upon a considerable eminence, and had an extensive prospect
of this horrible devastation.
As I stood gazing in mute astonishment, suddenly a fear
came over me that struck dampness to my very heart.
What was the situation of my own family and their little
remaining property, amidst this dreadful ruin? I was in
a position where, though I nearly faced our habitation, a
point of the rock intercepted it from my sight. The obstacle[90]
was but a small one, yet it would require a considerable
circuit to overcome. I flew along the path with a
speed that scarcely permitted me to breathe. When I had
passed the upper rock, the whole extensive scene opened
upon me in an instant. What were my sensations, when
I perceived that the devastation had been even more complete
here than on the side where I first viewed it! My
own cottage in particular, which that very morning had
contained, and I hoped continued to contain, all that was
most dear to my heart, seemed to stand an entire solitude
in the midst of an immense swamp.
Marguerite, whose idea, upon our retreat into Switzerland,
had been that of conforming without reserve to the new
situation that was allotted us, had immediately expended
the whole of what remained from the shipwreck of our fortune,
in the purchase of the cottage in which we dwelt, and
a small portion of land around it, sufficient with economy
for the support of our family. Under her direction the
hills had been covered with vines, and the fields with corn.
She had purchased cows to furnish us with milk, and sheep
with their fleeces, and had formed her establishment upon
the model of the Swiss peasantry in our neighbourhood.
Reverting to the simplicity of nature, appeared to her like
building upon an immovable basis, which the clash of nations
could not destroy, and which was too humble to
fear the treachery of courts, or the caprice of artificial refinement.
It was all swept away in a moment. Our little property
looked as if it had been particularly a mark for the vengeance
of Heaven, and was more utterly destroyed than any
of the surrounding scenes. There was not a tree left
standing; there was not a hedge or a limit that remained
within or around it; chaos had here resumed his empire,
and avenged himself of the extraordinary order and beauty
it had lately displayed.
I was not overwhelmed with this astonishing spectacle.
At that moment nature found her way to my heart, and
made a man of me. I made light of these petty accessories
of our existence; and the thought of my wife and my
children, simply as they were in themselves, filled every[91]
avenue of my heart. For them, and them alone, I was
interested: it was a question for their lives. To conceive
what they might personally have sustained was a horror
that seemed to freeze up all the arteries of my heart. I
descended from the mountain. It was with the greatest
difficulty, and not without many circuitous deviations, that
I proceeded; so much was the surface changed, and so
deep and miry the swamps. My terror increased, as I
passed near to the carcasses of the animals who had fallen
victims to this convulsion of the elements. I observed,
with inconceivable alarm, that the dead or wounded bodies
of some human beings were intermingled with the brute
destruction. I stayed not to enquire whether they were yet
in a state to require assistance; the idea that had taken
possession of me left no room for the sentiment of general
humanity.
A little further on I distinctly remarked the body of a
woman at some distance from any habitation, who appeared
to be dead, destroyed by the storm. Near her lay a female
infant, apparently about six years of age. My attention
was involuntarily arrested; I thought of Louisa, that sweet
and amiable child, so like her admirable mother. The
figure was hers; the colour of the robe corresponded to
that in which I last saw her. The child was lying on her
face. With all the impatient emotions of a father, I stooped
down. I turned over the body, that I might identify my
child. It was still warm; life had scarcely deserted it. I
gazed upon the visage; it was distorted with the agonies of
death: but enough to convince me still remained discernible;
it was not Louisa!
I can scarcely recollect a period through all the strange
vicissitudes of my existence to be compared with this. If
I had not felt what I then felt, I could never have conceived
it. Human nature is so constituted, that the highest
degree of anguish, an anguish in which the heart stretches
itself to take in the mightiness of its woe, can be felt but
for a few instants. When the calamity we feared is already
arrived, or when the expectation of it is so certain as to
shut out hope, there seems to be a principle within us by
which we look with misanthropic composure on the state[92]
to which we are reduced, and the heart sullenly contracts
and accommodates itself to what it most abhorred. Our
hopes wither; and our pride, our self-complacence, all that
taught us to rejoice in existence, wither along with them.
But, when hope yet struggles with despair, or when the calamity
abruptly announces itself, then is the true contention,
the tempest and uproar of the soul too vast to be endured.
This sentiment of ineffable wretchedness I experienced,
when I stooped down over the body of the imaginary
Louisa, and when I hastened to obtain the certainty which
was of all things most terrible to me. The termination of
such a moment of horror is scarcely less memorable than its
intrinsic greatness. In an instant the soul recovers its
balance, and the thought is as if it has never been. I
clapped my hands in an ecstasy at once of joy and astonishment,
so sure did I seem to have made myself of my misfortune;
I quitted the body with an unburdened heart; I
flew towards my home, that I might ascertain whether I
was prematurely speaking comfort to my spirit.
At length I reached it. I saw the happy group assembled
at the door. Marguerite had entertained the same
terrors for me, with which I had myself so lately been impressed.
We flew into each other’s arms. She hid her
face in my neck, and sobbed audibly. I embraced each of
the children in turn, but Louisa with the most heartfelt delight.
“Are you safe, papa?”—“Are you safe, my child?”
were echoed on every side. A spectator, unacquainted with
what was passing in our hearts, would certainly have stood
astonished to see the transport with which we exulted, surrounded
as we were with desolation and ruin.
After an interval, however, we opened our eyes, and began
to ruminate upon the new condition in which we were
placed. Marguerite and myself watched each other’s countenances
with anxiety, to discover what were likely to be
the feelings of either in this terrible crisis. “Be of good
heart, my love,” said Marguerite; “do not suffer the accident
which has happened entirely to overcome you.” There
was a mixed compassion, tenderness, and anxiety in the
tone of voice with which she uttered these words, that was
inexpressibly delightful.
[93]
“No, Marguerite,” replied I, with enthusiastic impetuosity,
“I am not cast down; I never shall be cast down
again. Ruin is nothing to me, so long as I am surrounded
with you and our dear children. I have for some time
been a fool. In the midst of every real blessing, I have
fashioned for myself imaginary evils. But my eyes are
now opened. How easily is the human mind induced to
forget those benefits with which we are constantly surrounded,
and our possession of which we regard as secure!
The feelings of this morning have awakened me. I am
now cured of my folly. I have learned to value my domestic
blessings as I ought. Having preserved them, I
esteem myself to have lost nothing. What are gold and
jewels and precious utensils? Mere dross and dirt. The
human face and the human heart, reciprocations of kindness
and love, and all the nameless sympathies of our nature,—these
are the only objects worth being attached to. What
are rank and station?—the homage of the multitude and
the applause of fools. Let me judge for myself! The value
of a man is in his intrinsic qualities; in that of which
power cannot strip him, and which adverse fortune cannot
take away. That for which he is indebted to circumstances,
is mere trapping and tinsel. I should love these precious
and ingenuous creatures before me better, though in rags,
than the children of kings in all the pomp of ornament. I
am proud to be their father. Whatever may be my personal
faults, the world is my debtor for having been the
occasion of their existence. But they are endeared to me
by a better principle than pride. I love them for their qualities.
He that loves, and is loved by, a race of pure and
virtuous creatures, and that lives continually in the midst of
them, is an idiot, if he does not think himself happy. Surrounded
as I am now surrounded, I feel as irremovable as
the pillars of creation. Nothing that does not strike at their
existence can affect me with terror.”
Marguerite viewed me with surprise and joy. “Now indeed,”
said she, “you are the man I took you for, and the
man I shall henceforth be prouder than ever to call my
husband. The sorrow in which you lately indulged was
a luxury; and we must have done with luxuries. You will
be our protector and our support.”
[94]
Thus saying, she took me by the hand, and motioned
me to view with her the devastation that had been committed.
There was one path I had discovered, in which
we might proceed some way with tolerable ease. The
scene was terrible. We were indeed beggars. A whole
province had been destroyed: all the corn and the fruits
of the earth; most of the trees; in many places cattle;
in some places men. Persons who had been rich in the
morning saw all the produce of their fields annihilated,
and were unable even to guess by what process fertility
was to be re-established. The comparatively wealthy
scarcely knew how they were to obtain immediate subsistence;
the humbler class, who always live by the expedients
of the day, saw nothing before them but the prospect of
perishing with hunger. We witnessed, in one or two instances,
the anguish of their despair.
Our prospect was scarcely in any respect better than
theirs; yet we felt differently. We were more impressed
with the joy of our personal escape. As my error respecting
the value of externals had been uncommonly great, the
sudden revolution of opinion I experienced was equally memorable.
The survey, indeed, that we took of the general
distress somewhat saddened our hearts; but the sadness it
gave was that of sobriety, not of dejection.
It was incumbent upon us to make a strict examination
into the amount of our property, and our immediate resources;
and in this office I united myself with Marguerite,
not only with a degree of cheerfulness and application, the
perfect contrast of my whole conduct ever since our arrival
in Switzerland, but which greatly exceeded any thing I had
ever before exhibited in a business of this nature. We
found that, though all our hopes of a harvest were annihilated,
yet we were not destitute of the instant means of
subsistence. The resources we possessed, whether in money
or provisions, that were our dependence till the period when
the new produce should supply their place, were uninjured.
Our implements of husbandry remained as before. The
land was not impoverished, but had rather derived additional
fertility from the effects of the storm. What we
had lost was chiefly the produce of our capital for one year,[95]
together with a part of that capital itself in the live stock
that had been destroyed. This was a loss which a certain
degree of care and scope in our external circumstances
might easily have enabled us to supply. But the principle
of supply was denied us. It was with considerable difficulty
that all the economy of Marguerite had enabled her
to support our family establishment, while every thing of
this kind had gone on prosperously. Such a shock as the
present we were totally disqualified to surmount. It compelled
us to a complete revolution of our affairs.
Many indeed of our neighbours had scarcely any greater
advantage in their private affairs than ourselves. But they
possessed one superiority that proved of the greatest importance
in this conjuncture; they were natives of the state
in which they resided. In the cantons of Switzerland, the
destruction of the fruits of the earth, occasioned by inclement
seasons and tempests, is by no means unfrequent; and
it is therefore customary, in plentiful years, to lay up corn
in public magazines, that the people may not perish in periods
of scarcity. These magazines are placed under the
inspection and disposal of the magistracy; and the inhabitants
looked to them with confidence for the supply of their
need. No storm, however, had occurred in the memory of
man so terrible and ruinous as the present; and it became
evident that the magazines would prove a resource too
feeble for the extent of the emergency.
The storm had spread itself over a space of many leagues
in circumference, not only in the canton of Soleure, but in
the neighbouring cantons, particularly that of Berne. The
sufferers, in our own canton only, amounted to scarcely less
than ten thousand. While the women and children, for
the most part, remained at home, the houses having in
general suffered little other damage than the destruction of
their windows, the fathers of families repaired to the seat
of government to put in their claims for national relief;
and these alone formed an immense troop, that threatened
little less than to besiege the public magazines and the magistrates.
An accurate investigation was entered into of the
losses of each, it being the purpose of government, as far as
its power extended, not only to supply the people with the[96]
means of immediate subsistence, but also, by disbursements
from the public treasury, to recruit the stock of cattle, and
to assist every one to return, with revived hopes and expectation,
to the sphere of his industry. The purpose was no
doubt benevolent; but, in the mean time, the unhappy
victims found in uncertainty and expectation a real and
corroding anguish.
I advanced my claim with the rest, but met with a
peremptory refusal. The harsh and rigorous answer I
received was, that they had not enough for their own
people, and could spare nothing to strangers. Upon this
occasion I was compelled to feel what it was to be an alien,
and how different the condition in which I was now placed
from that I had filled in my native country. There I had
lived in the midst of a people, to whom the veneration of
my ancestry and name seemed a part of their nature. They
had witnessed for several years the respectable manner in
which I lived; the virtues of Marguerite were familiar to
them; and they took an interest in every thing that concerned
us, a sentiment that confessed us at once for kindred
and patrons. It was the turn of mind only which is
generated by rank, that had compelled us to quit their
vicinity; we might have continued in it, if not in affluence,
at least enjoying the gratifications that arise from general
affection and respect. But here we were beheld with an
eye of jealousy and distaste. We had no prejudice of birth
and habit in our favour; indeed, in the reverse of fortune
which had brought us hither, Marguerite had been less desirous
of obtruding, than of withdrawing from the public
eye, the circumstance of our rank. We were too recent
inmates to have secured, by any thing of a personal nature,
an advantageous opinion among our neighbours. They saw
only a miserable and distracted father of a family, and a
mother who, in spite of the simplicity she cultivated, sufficiently
evinced that she had been accustomed to a more
elevated situation. The prepossessions of mankind are
clearly unfavourable to a new-comer, an emigrant who has
quitted his former connections and the scenes of his youth.
They are unavoidably impelled to believe, that his taking
up his abode in another country must be owing to a weak[97]
and discreditable caprice, if it be not owing to something
still more disadvantageous to his character.
The calamity therefore which we had suffered in common
with most of the inhabitants of the province, finally
reduced us to the necessity of a second emigration. The
jealousy with which we were regarded, daily became more
visible and threatening. Though, in consequence of the
distribution made by order of the state, the price of commodities
was not so much increased as might have been expected,
we were considered as interlopers upon the portion
of the natives; the sellers could with difficulty be persuaded
to accommodate us, and the bystanders treated us
with murmurs and reviling. While we were deliberating
what course to pursue in this emergency, certain officers of
government one morning entered our habitation, producing
an order of the senate for our immediate removal out of the
territory. It is of the essence of coercive regulations, to
expel, to imprison, and turn out of prison, the individuals
it is thought proper to control, without any care as to the
mischiefs they may suffer, and whether they perish under
or survive the evil inflicted on them. We were accordingly
allowed only from six in the morning till noon, to prepare
for our departure. Our guards indeed offered to permit
me to remain three days to wind up my affairs, upon condition
that my wife and children were instantly removed into
another country, as a sort of hostages for my own departure.
This indulgence however would have been useless. In the
present state of the country no purchaser could be found
for the little estate I possessed; and if there could, it must
doubtless have been disposed of to great disadvantage at
such an emergency. I know not how we should have extricated
ourselves out of these difficulties, if a member of
the senate, who, being one of my nearest neighbours, had
been struck with admiration of the virtues of Marguerite,
and with compassion for my family, had not paid me a visit
shortly after the arrival of the officers, and generously offered
to take upon himself the care of my property, and to
advance me what money might be necessary for my emigration.
This offer, which at any other time might have
been regarded as purely a matter of course, under the[98]
present circumstances, when capital was so necessary for
the revival of agriculture in the desolated country, implied
a liberal and disinterested spirit. I accepted the kindness
of my neighbour in both its parts, but for the reimbursement
of his loan referred him to the French minister to
the United Cantons, who, under all the circumstances of
the case, and taking my estate as security for the money
advanced, I thought it reasonable to believe would attend
to my application.
</div></body></text></TEI>