<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 166, folios 95-98</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 166, folios 95-98.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1844">10 April [1844]</date>
          <note type="place">St. James's Square</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 166, folios 95-98</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_166_folios_95-98.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>St James' Sqre Weddy-- 10th April 1 o'clock</p>
      <p>I have thought of you with no small distress, dearest W--, &amp; I feel I have not one word to say for myself. I hope you will not fail to see me on Friday, before you go to Ashley.</p>
      <p>I have had no intention, I can truly &amp; honestly say, of teasing &amp; hurting you. The consequence was that when I found I had (most undesignedly) had those effects, I felt beyong measure exasperated with you for having felt hurt.-- I am not pleading for the justice or fairness of this. Far from it. I merely mention it as a</p>
      <p>fact.</p>
      <p>Now one word about the children. I shall make it a rule henceforward that they always come to spend a little time with you, previous to any absence you are to make.</p>
      <p>You may depend on me for this. Had I known your wish in good time yesterday, they would have been all ready for you to see comfortably &amp; at leisure.</p>
      <p>You must allow me to point out to you that you do not always give sufficient notice of your wishes &amp; orders.</p>
      <p>You cannot imaging, for instance, the inconvenience of a sudden announcement that you want to have the children down. It has not be expected, &amp; perhaps it occurs while a master or other appointment is</p>
      <p>going on. The child gets ready with what haste he or she can; but still it is probably a little after date; which inconveniences you, puts you out of temper, &amp; then follows disagreements &amp; all sorts of mischief.</p>
      <p>Had I but known yesterday, you might have had the three children, (&amp; heard that masterly music also, &amp; enjoyed it thoroughly), all quite in early time &amp; at ease.</p>
      <p>I must endeavour to impress on you the great importance of telling me things beforehand. If they are distasteful to me, I then at least am able to make them less so, or even agreeable, by arrangement.</p>
      <p>I do not feel I am fairly dealt with in this. Either thro'</p>
      <p>negligence or intention on your part, you give me no notice of anything scarcely. I then find suddenly some arrangement made of which I knew nothing, &amp; which consequently happens often to be at direct variance with some unwitting plan of my own. But I am expected to make no objections &amp; manifest no surpise, however impromptu the thing may be, &amp; however unpleasant for what I had planned.</p>
      <p>I can safely promise you that a little more forethought &amp; notice on your part, would most materially alter everything you now compain of. You would find things &amp; tastes of yours consulted &amp; provided for, as if by magic, &amp; without any trouble to yourself.</p>
      <p>It is my first wish, dearest Mate, to make your happiness</p>
      <p>&amp; comfort; but I assure you it is not easy; simply because you give me no helping hand. I know this is from diffidence on your part, to a certain extent. But it is a diffidence very pernicious to our mutual happiness, &amp; which makes my game a difficult one.</p>
      <p>I am glad to have the occasion of stating this to you clearly, in writing. You will get it tomorrow morning I hope. A line by return of post would be a great relief to me. And say in it when you are likely to return on Friday, what time you wish dinner &amp;c.</p>
      <p>Now here is just an occasion when you would probably inform me of nothing in a usual way. The consequence would be I might be out or engaged; &amp; you think what an indifferent unfeeling wife you</p>
      <p>had. Whereas she could not know by intuition when to expect you, or what you would wish; (&amp; ten to one I should have preferred being tout a [accent mark over the a] vous, to what I might be doing).</p>
      <p>I should always prefer being with you to any plans of my own. But then I must have notice, of course. And sometimes it will occur that other engagements are of real importance to me, or indirectly to yourself, &amp; must command me in preference.</p>
      <p>I have bought a thrush. Only 18 pence he is. The poor fellow took my fancy in the street. He has a large wicker cage, &amp; lives in the School-room. I thought you too, would be pleased with me for this.--</p>
      <p>I am very busy, with my music, &amp; with looking after the young, who go on nicely.</p>
      <p>I rose at 7 this morning, &amp; practised for one hour before breakfast. Dr L-- wishes me to get up at seven; &amp; also advises me to practise a good deal at present.</p>
      <p>I do not neglect the riding &amp; walking. But as I find the sun affects my head too much in the middle of the day, &amp; do not like just now to ride at the fashionably late hour, I take my 2 chestnuts to the Riding-School instead, on hot days like this. The expense is next to nothing, as I do not require the master's presence or us his horses; &amp; it enables me to derive healthy &amp; effective exercise, &amp; does the horses great good. Tag Rag</p>
      <p>has a corn, which was why he stumbled. I insisted on his being examined without his shoes. It is not much, but he is better for riding-school ground just for a few days.</p>
      <p>So I hope you will approve altogether; &amp; do believe me your own nice Bird, my Dear.</p>
      <p>Pray write to me, if only 6 words. I am quite miserable about you, because I know you are unhappy, &amp; fancy you have an unkind bird.</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
