<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="91">CHAPTER VII.
Consequences of the Electrodynamic
Theory.
IT is not necessary to state
the various applications which were soon made of the electro-magnetic
discoveries. But we may notice one 251 of the most important,—the
Galvanometer, an instrument which, by enabling the philosopher
to detect and to measure extremely minute electrodynamic actions, gave
an impulse to the subject similar to that which it received from the
invention of the Leyden Phial, or the Voltaic Pile. The strength of
the voltaic current was measured, in this instrument, by the
deflection produced in a compass-needle; and its sensibility was
multiplied by making the wire pass repeatedly above and below the
needle. Schweigger, of Halle, was one of the first devisers of this
apparatus.
The substitution of electro-magnets, that is, of spiral tubes
composed of voltaic wires, for common magnets, gave rise to a variety
of curious apparatus and speculations, some of which I shall hereafter
mention.
[2nd Ed.] [When a voltaic apparatus is in action, there may be
conceived to be a current of electricity running through its various
elements, as stated in the text. The force of this current in various
parts of the circuit has been made the subject of mathematical
investigation by M. Ohm.18 The problem is in every respect similar
to that of the flow of heat through a body, and taken generally, leads
to complex calculations of the same kind. But Dr. Ohm, by limiting the
problem in the first place by conditions which the usual nature and
form of voltaic apparatus suggest, has been able to give great
simplicity to his reasonings. These conditions are, the linear form of
the conductors (wires) and the steadiness of the electric state. For
this part of the problem Dr. Ohm’s reasonings are as simple and as
demonstrative as the elementary propositions of Mechanics. The formulæ
for the electric force of a voltaic current to which he is led have
been experimentally verified by others, especially Fechner,19 Gauss,20 Lenz, Jacobi,
Poggendorf, and Pouillet.
18 Die Galvanische Kette
Mathematisch bearbeitet von Dr. G. S. Ohm, Berlin, 1827.
19 Mass-bestimmungen über
die Galvanische Kette. Leipzig, 1831.
20 Results of the Magnetic
Association.
Among ourselves, Mr. Wheatstone has confirmed and applied the views
of M. Ohm, in a Memoir21 On New Instruments and Processes for
determining the Constants of a Voltaic Circuit. He there remarks
that the clear ideas of electromotive forces and resistances,
substituted by Ohm for the vague notions of quantity and intensity
which have long been prevalent, give satisfactory explanations of the
most important difficulties, and express the laws of a vast number of
phenomena 252 in
formulæ of remarkable simplicity and generality. In this Memoir,
Professor Wheatstone describes an instrument which he terms
Rheostat, because it brings to a common standard the voltaic
currents which are compared by it. He generalizes the language of the
subject by employing the term rheomotor for any apparatus which
originates an electric current (whether voltaic or thermoelectric,
&c.) and rheometer for any instrument to measure the force
of such a current. It appears that the idea of constructing an
instrument of the nature of the Rheostat had occurred also to Prof.
Jacobi, of St Petersburg.]
21 Phil. Trans. 1843. Pt.
11.
The galvanometer led to the discovery of another class of cases in
which the electrodynamical action was called into play, namely, those
in which a circuit, composed of two metals only, became
electro-magnetic by heating one part of it. This discovery of
thermo-electricity was made by Professor Seebeck of Berlin, in
1822, and prosecuted by various persons; especially by Prof. Cumming22 of Cambridge, who, early in 1823,
extended the examination of this property to most of the metals, and
determined their thermo-electric order. But as these investigations
exhibited no new mechanical effects of electromotive forces, they do
not now further concern us; and we pass on, at present, to a case in
which such forces act in a manner different from any of those already
described.
22 Camb. Trans. vol. ii. p.
62. On the Development of Electro-Magnetism by Heat.
Discovery of
Diamagnetism.
[2nd Ed.] [By the discoveries just related, a cylindrical spiral of
wire through which an electric current is passing is identified with a
magnet; and the effect of such a spiral is increased by placing in it
a core of soft iron. By the use of such a combination under the
influence of a voltaic battery, magnets are constructed far more
powerful than those which depend upon the permanent magnetism of iron.
The electro-magnet employed by Dr. Faraday in some of his experiments
would sustain a hundred-weight at either end.
By the use of such magnets Dr. Faraday discovered that, besides
iron, nickel and cobalt, which possess magnetism in a high degree,
many bodies are magnetic in a slight degree. And he made the further
very important discovery, that of those substances which are not
magnetic, many, perhaps all, possess an opposite property, in virtue
of which he terms them diamagnetic. The opposition is of this
253
kind;—that magnetic bodies in the form of bars or needles, if
free to move, arrange themselves in the axial line joining
the poles; diamagnetic bodies under the same circumstances arrange
themselves in an equatorial position, perpendicular to the
axial line. And this tendency he conceives to be the result of one
more general; that whereas magnetic bodies are attracted to the poles
of a magnet, diamagnetic bodies are repelled from the poles. The list
of diamagnetic bodies includes all kinds of substances; not only
metals, as antimony, bismuth, gold, silver, lead, tin, zinc, but many
crystals, glass, phosphorus, sulphur, sugar, gum, wood, ivory; and
even flesh and fruit.
It appears that M. le Bailli had shown, in 1829, that both bismuth
and antimony and bismuth repelled the magnetic needle; and as Dr.
Faraday remarks, it is astonishing that such an experiment should have
remained so long without further results. M. Becquerel in 1827
observed, and quoted Coulomb as having also observed, that a needle of
wood under certain conditions pointed across the magnetic curves; and
also stated that he had found a needle of wood place itself parallel
to the wires of a galvanometer. This he referred to a magnetism
transverse to the length. But he does not refer the phenomena to
elementary repulsive action, nor show that they are common to an
immense class of bodies, nor distinguish this diamagnetic from the
magnetic class, as Faraday has taught us to do.
I do not dwell upon the peculiar phenomena of copper which, in the
same series of researches, are traced by Dr. Faraday to the combined
effect of its diamagnetic character, and the electric currents excited
in it by the electro-magnet; nor to the optical phenomena manifested
by certain transparent diamagnetic substances under electric action;
as already stated in Book ix.23] ~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~
23 See the Twentieth Series of
Experimental Researches in Electricity, read to the Royal Society,
Dec. 18, 1845.
</div></body></text></TEI>