<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="66">CHAPTER V.
Discovery of the Laws of Double
Refraction.
THE laws of refraction which
we have hitherto described, were simple and uniform, and had a
symmetrical reference to the surface of the refracting medium. It
appeared strange to men, when their attention was drawn to a class of
phenomena in which this symmetry was wanting, and in which a
refraction took place which was not even in the plane of incidence.
The subject was not unworthy the notice and admiration it attracted;
for the prosecution of it ended in the discovery of the general laws
of light. The phenomena of which I now speak, are those exhibited by
various kinds of crystalline bodies; but observed for a long time in
one kind only, namely, the rhombohedral calc-spar; or, as it was
usually termed, from the country which supplied the largest and
clearest crystals, Iceland spar. These 70 rhombohedral crystals are usually very
smooth and transparent, and often of considerable size; and it was
observed, on looking through them, that all objects appeared double.
The phenomena, even as early as 1669, had been considered so curious,
that Erasmus Bartholin published a work upon them at Copenhagen,36 (Experimenta Crystalli
Islandici, Hafniæ, 1669.) He analysed the phenomena into their
laws, so far as to discover that one of the two images was produced by
refraction after the usual rule, and the other by an unusual
refraction. This latter refraction Bartholin found to vary in
different positions; to be regulated by a line parallel to the sides
of the rhombohedron; and to be greatest in the direction of a line
bisecting two of the angles of the rhombic face of the crystal.
36 Priestley’s Optics, p.
550.
These rules were exact as far as they went; and when we consider
how geometrically complex the law is, which really regulates the
unusual or extraordinary refraction;—that Newton altogether
mistook it, and that it was not verified till the experiments of Haüy
and Wollaston in our own time;—we might expect that it would not
be soon or easily detected. But Huyghens possessed a key to the
secret, in the theory, which he had devised, of the propagation of
light by undulations, and which he conceived with perfect distinctness
and correctness, so far as its application to these phenomena is
concerned. Hence he was enabled to lay down the law of the phenomena
(the only part of his discovery which we have here to consider), with
a precision and success which excited deserved admiration, when the
subject, at a much later period, regained its due share of attention.
His Treatise was written37 in 1678, but not published till
1690.
37 See his Traité de la
Lumière. Preface.
The laws of the ordinary and the extraordinary
refraction in Iceland spar are related to each other; they are, in
fact, similar constructions, made, in the one case, by means of an
imaginary sphere, in the other, by means of a spheroid; the spheroid
being of such oblateness as to suit the rhombohedral form of the
crystal, and the axis of the spheroid being the axis of symmetry of
the crystal. Huyghens followed this general conception into particular
positions and conditions; and thus obtained rules, which he compared
with observation, for cutting the crystal and transmitting the rays in
various manners. “I have examined in detail,” says he,38 “the properties of the 71 extraordinary
refraction of this crystal, to see if each phenomenon which is deduced
from theory, would agree with what is really observed. And this being
so, it is no slight proof of the truth of our suppositions and
principles; but what I am going to add here confirms them still more
wonderfully; that is, the different modes of cutting this crystal, in
which the surfaces produced give rise to refractions exactly such as
they ought to be, and as I had foreseen them, according to the
preceding theory.”
38 See Maseres’s Tracts on
Optics, p. 250; or Huyghens, Tr. sur la Lum. ch. v. Art.
43.
Statements of this kind, coming from a philosopher like Huyghens,
were entitled to great confidence; Newton, however, appears not to
have noticed, or to have disregarded them. In his Opticks, he
gives a rule for the extraordinary refraction of Iceland spar which is
altogether erroneous, without assigning any reason for rejecting the
law published by Huyghens; and, so far as appears, without having made
any experiments of his own. The Huyghenian doctrine of double
refraction fell, along with his theory of undulations, into temporary
neglect, of which we shall have hereafter to
speak. But in 1788, Haüy showed that Huyghens’s rule agreed much
better than Newton’s with the phenomena: and in 1802, Wollaston,
applying a method of his own for measuring refraction, came to the
same result. “He made,” says Young,39 “a number of
accurate experiments with an apparatus singularly well calculated to
examine the phenomena, but could find no general principle to connect
them, until the work of Huyghens was pointed out to him.” In 1808, the
subject of double refraction was proposed as a prize-question by the
French Institute; and Malus, whose Memoir obtained the prize, says, “I
began by observing and measuring a long series of phenomena on natural
and artificial faces of Iceland spar. Then, testing by means of these
observations the different laws proposed up to the present time by
physical writers, I was struck with the admirable agreement of the law
of Huyghens with the phenomena, and I was soon convinced that it is
really the law of nature.” Pursuing the consequences of the law, he
found that it satisfied phenomena which Huyghens himself had not
observed. From this time, then, the truth of the Huyghenian law was
universally allowed, and soon afterwards, the theory by which it had
been suggested was generally received.
39 Quart. Rev. 1809, Nov. p.
338.
The property of double refraction had been first studied only in
Iceland spar, in which it is very obvious. The same property belongs,
72 though less
conspicuously, to many other kinds of crystals. Huyghens had noticed
the same fact in rock-crystal;40 and Malus found
it to belong to a large list of bodies besides; for instance,
arragonite, sulphate of lime, of baryta, of strontia, of iron;
carbonate of lead; zircon, corundum, cymophane, emerald, euclase,
felspar, mesotype, peridote, sulphur, and mellite. Attempts were made,
with imperfect success, to reduce all these to the law which had been
established for Iceland spar. In the first instance, Malus took for
granted that the extraordinary refraction depended always upon an
oblate spheroid; but M. Biot41 pointed out a
distinction between two classes of crystals in which this spheroid was
oblong and oblate respectively, and these he called attractive
and repulsive crystals. With this correction, the law could be
extended to a considerable number of cases; but it was afterwards
proved by Sir D. Brewster’s discoveries, that even in this form, it
belonged only to substances of which the crystallization has relation
to a single axis of symmetry, as the rhombohedron, or the square
pyramid. In other cases, as the rhombic prism, in which the form,
considered with reference to its crystalline symmetry, is
biaxal, the law is much more complicated. In that case, the
sphere and the spheroid, which are used in the construction for
uniaxal crystals, transform themselves into the two successful
convolutions of a single continuous curve surface; neither of the two
rays follows the law of ordinary refraction; and the formula which
determines their position is very complex. It is, however, capable of
being tested by measures of the refractions of crystals cut in a
peculiar manner for the purpose, and this was done by MM. Fresnel and
Arago. But this complex law of double refraction was only discovered
through the aid of the theory of a luminiferous ether, and therefore
we must now return to the other facts which led to such a theory.
40  Traité de la Lumière, ch.
v. Art. 20
41 Biot, Traité de Phys. iii.
330.
</div></body></text></TEI>