<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 165, folios 13-16</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 165, folios 13-16.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1835">7 October 1835</date>
          <note type="place">Southhampton</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 165, folios 13-16</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_165_folios_13-16.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Southampton Wednesday Evening 7th Octr 1835</p>
      <p>My dearest Cock. Our dear Hen seems to me much better today, &amp; says she is so herself. Her little nasty cough is not so bad.-- I am delightfully well myself, &amp; in all aspects like a dear &amp; good little Bird.-- I have not yet succeeded in getting any horse. Joseph has been looking out for one, but</p>
      <p>doubts if he shall find what he thinks suitable.-- He seems so exceedingly cautious about it, that I cannot help thinking he suspects there is good reason to be so. At all events, I am not inclined to be otherwise than very cautious myself.-- The Hen thought the Bird should take a drive this afternoon, since it could not ride; so I had a nice pair of post horses to the Britska &amp; Mrs. Henry Siddons &amp; I took a very pretty &amp; pleasant drive together. I have also walked today for about</p>
      <p>half an hour, &amp; in short am a dear little bird.--</p>
      <p>I have hired a very nice harp, which is just come, &amp; is gone up into my room, where it is to live, since this tiny house has but little spare space.--</p>
      <p>I have been lamentably idle today. What else could be expected, the first Hen-day?--</p>
      <p>My dearest, I am longing to hear from you tomorrow morning.-- The Hen says she always knows when I am writing to you, by my countenance-- the Cock countenance.-- I think</p>
      <p>it is almost worth this little absence, in order to feel more forcibly how very very much I love you. You are indeed a dear good master, &amp; so kind to your little own Bird. It makes the poor little thing very happy to think of its Cock.--</p>
      <p>Miss Montgomery was here yesterday when I came, but has left Southampton today. I was glad to see her, &amp; so was she to see the Bird.--</p>
      <p>I forgot to tell you that Tubbs is rather in tribulation about your hats. He consulted me yesterday morning before I came away, &amp; so I sat</p>
      <p>in judgment on this momentous subject. I decreed that I certainly would not bring one down here for you, as I was sure you would return to Ockham [diagonal line crossed out] before you came, &amp; could get what you wanted for yourself.--</p>
      <p>Tubbs says we want a new dining-room tray-stand, the one there is being unsafe.--</p>
      <p>The Coachman &amp;c were so exact yesterday morning, that I kept them waiting. But I believe you have not threatened to dismiss</p>
      <p>the poor Bird for this crime.--</p>
      <p>My dearest husband, the poor little thing wants her master sadly. How she will chirp at him, when he comes!-- I send you now six good chirps.--</p>
      <p>Believe me, Your very affecte Birdie, A. Ada King</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
