<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Chambers Robert</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="11">p. 134ERA
OF THE SUPERFICIAL FORMATIONS.
COMMENCEMENT OF PRESENT
SPECIES.
We have now completed our survey of
the series of stratified rocks, and traced in their fossils the
progress of organic creation down to a time which seems not long
antecedent to the appearance of man.  There are,
nevertheless, monuments of still another era or space of time
which it is all but certain did also precede that event.
Over the rock formations of all eras, in various parts of the
globe, but confined in general to situations not very elevated,
there is a layer of stiff clay, mostly of a blue colour, mingled
with fragments of rock of all sizes, travel-worn, and otherwise,
and to which geologists give the name of diluvium, as being
apparently the produce of some vast flood, or of the sea thrown
into an unusual agitation.  It seems to indicate that, at
the time when it was laid down, much of the present dry land was
under the ocean, a supposition which we shall see supported by
other evidence.  The included masses of rock have been
carefully inspected in many places, and traced to particular
parent beds at considerable distances.  Connected with these
phenomena are certain rock surfaces on the slopes of hills and
elsewhere, which exhibit groovings and scratchings, such as we
might suppose would be produced by a quantity of loose blocks
hurried along over them by a flood.  Another associated
phenomenon is that called crag and tail, which exists in
many places,—namely, a rocky mountain, or lesser elevation,
presenting on one side the naked rock in a more or less abrupt
form, and on the other a gentle slope; the sites of Windsor,
Edinburgh, and Stirling, with their respective castles, are
specimens of crag and tail.  Finally, we may advert to
certain long ridges of clay and gravel which arrest the attention
of travellers on the surface of Sweden and Finland, and which are
also found in the United States, where, indeed, the whole of
these phenomena have been observed over a large surface, as well
as in Europe.  It is very remarkable that the direction from
which the diluvial blocks have generally come, the lines of the
grooved rock surfaces, the direction of the crag and tail
eminences, and that of the clay and gravel
ridges—phenomena, be it observed, extending over the
northern parts of both Europe and America—are all from
the north and north-west towards the south-east.  We
thus acquire the idea of a powerful current moving in a direction
from north-west to south-east, carrying, besides mud, masses of
rock which furrowed the solid surfaces as they passed along,
abrading the north-west faces of many hills, but leaving the
slopes in the opposite direction uninjured, and in some instances
forming long ridges of detritus along the surface.  These
are curious considerations, and it has become a question of much
interest, by what means, and under what circumstances, was such a
current produced.  One hypothetical answer has some
plausibility about it.  From an investigation of the nature
of glaciers, and some observations which seem to indicate that
these have at one time extended to lower levels, and existed in
regions (the Scottish Highlands an example) where there is now no
perennial snow, it has been surmised that there was a time,
subsequent to the tertiary era, when the circumpolar ice extended
far into the temperate zone, and formed a lofty, as well as
extensive accumulation.  A change to a higher temperature,
producing a sudden thaw of this mass, might set free such a
quantity of water as would form a large flood, and the southward
flow of this deluge, joined to the direction which it would
obtain from the rotatory motion of the globe, would of course
produce that compound or south-easterly direction which the
phenomena require.  All of these speculations are as yet far
too deficient in facts to be of much value; and I must freely own
that, for one, I attach little importance to them.  All that
we can legitimately infer from the diluvium is, that the northern
parts of Europe and America were then under the sea, and that a
strong current set over them.
Connected with the diluvium is the history of ossiferous
caverns, of which specimens singly exist at Kirkdale in
Yorkshire, Gailenreuth in Franconia, and other places.  They
occur in the calcareous strata, as the great caverns generally
do, but have in all instances been naturally closed up till the
recent period of their discovery.  The floors are covered
with what appears to be a bed of the diluvial clay, over which
rests a crust of stalagmite, the result of the droppings from the
roof since the time when the clay-bed was laid down.  In the
instances above specified, and several others, there have been
found, under the clay bed, assemblages of the bones of animals,
of many various kinds.  At Kirkdale, for example, the
remains of twenty-four species were ascertained—namely,
pigeon, lark, raven, duck, and partridge; mouse, water-rat,
rabbit, hare, deer, (three species,) ox, horse, hippopotamus,
rhinoceros, elephant, weazel, fox, wolf, bear, tiger,
hyena.  From many of the bones of the gentler of these
animals being found in a broken state, it is supposed that the
cave was a haunt of hyenas and other predaceous animals, by which
the smaller ones were here consumed.  This must have been at
a time antecedent to the submersion which produced the diluvium,
since the bones are covered by a bed of that formation.  It
is impossible not to see here a very natural series of
incidents.  First, the cave is frequented by wild beasts,
who make it a kind of charnel-house.  Then, submerged in the
current which has been spoken of, it receives a clay flooring
from the waters containing that matter in suspension. 
Finally, raised from the water, but with no mouth to the open
air, it remains unintruded on for a long series of ages, during
which the clay flooring receives a new calcareous covering, from
the droppings of the roof.  Dr. Buckland, who examined and
described the Kirkdale cave, was at first of opinion that it
presented a physical evidence of the Noachian deluge; but he
afterwards saw reason to consider its phenomena as of a time far
apart from that event, which rests on evidence of an entirely
different kind.
Our attention is next drawn to the erratic blocks or boulders,
which in many parts of the earth are thickly strewn over the
surface, particularly in the north of Europe.  Some of these
blocks are many tons in weight, yet are clearly ascertained to
have belonged originally to situations at a great distance. 
Fragments, for example, of the granite of Shap Fell are found in
every direction around to the distance of fifty miles, one piece
being placed high upon Criffel Mountain, on the opposite side of
the Solway estuary; so also are fragments of the Alps found far
up the slopes of the Jura.  There are even blocks on the
east coast of England, supposed to have travelled from
Norway.  The only rational conjecture which can be formed as
to the transport of such masses from so great a distance, is one
which presumes them to have been carried and dropped by icebergs,
while the space between their original and final sites was under
ocean.  Icebergs do even now carry off such masses from the
polar coasts, which, falling when the retaining ice melts, must
take up situations at the bottom of the sea analogous to those in
which we find the erratic blocks of the present day.
As the diluvium and erratic blocks clearly suppose one last
long submersion of the surface, (last, geologically
speaking,) there is another set of appearances which as
manifestly shew the steps by which the land was made afterwards
to reappear.  These consist of terraces, which have
been detected near, and at some distance inland from, the coast
lines of Scandinavia, Britain, America, and other regions; being
evidently ancient beaches, or platforms, on which the margin of
the sea at one time rested.  They have been observed at
different heights above the present sea-level, from twenty to
above twelve hundred feet; and in many places they are seen
rising above each other in succession, to the number of three,
four, and even more.  The smooth flatness of these terraces,
with generally a slight inclination towards the sea, the sandy
composition of many of them, and, in some instances, the
preservation of marine shells in the ground, identify them
perfectly with existing sea-beaches, notwithstanding the cuts and
scoopings which have every here and there been effected in them
by water-courses.  The irresistible inference from the
phenomena is, that the highest was first the coast line; then an
elevation took place, and the second highest became so, the first
being now raised into the air and thrown inland.  Then, upon
another elevation, the sea began to form, at its new point of
contact with the land, the third highest beach, and so on down to
the platform nearest to the present sea-beach.  Phenomena of
this kind become comparatively familiar to us, when we hear of
evidence that the last sixty feet of the elevation of Sweden, and
the last eighty-five of that of Chili, have taken place since man
first dwelt in those countries; nay, that the elevation of the
former country goes on at this time at the rate of about
forty-five inches in a century, and that a thousand miles of the
Chilian coast rose four feet in one night, under the influence of
a powerful earthquake, so lately as 1822.  Subterranean
forces, of the kind then exemplified in Chili, supply a ready
explanation of the whole phenomena, though some other operating
causes have been suggested.  In an inquiry on this point, it
becomes of consequence to learn some particulars respecting the
levels.  Taking a particular beach, it is generally observed
that the level continues the same along a considerable number of
miles, and nothing like breaks or hitches has as yet been
detected in any case.  A second and a third beach are also
observed to be exactly parallel to the first.  These facts
would seem to indicate quiet elevating movements, uniform over a
large tract.  It must, however, be remarked that the raised
beaches at one part of a coast rarely coincide with those at
another part forty or fifty miles off.  We might suppose
this to indicate a limit in that extent of the uniformity of the
elevating cause, but it would be rash to conclude positively that
such is the case.  In the present sea, as is well known,
there are different levels at different places, owing to the
operation of peculiar local causes, as currents, evaporation, and
the influx of large rivers into narrow-mouthed estuaries. 
The differences of level in the ancient beaches might be
occasioned by some such causes.  But, whatever doubt may
rest on this minor point, enough has been ascertained to settle
the main one, that we have in these platforms indubitable
monuments of the last rise of the land from the sea, and the
concluding great event of the geological history.
The idea of such a wide-spread and possibly universal
submersion unavoidably suggests some considerations as to the
effect which it might have upon terrestrial animal life.  It
seems likely that this would be, on such an occasion,
extensively, if not universally destroyed.  Nor does the
idea of its universal destruction seem the less plausible, when
we remark, that none of the species of land animals heretofore
discovered can be detected at a subsequent period.  The
whole seem to have been now changed.  Some geologists appear
much inclined to think that there was at this time a new
development of terrestrial animal life upon the globe, and M.
Agassiz, whose opinion on such a subject must always be worthy of
attention, speaks all but decidedly for such a conclusion. 
It must, however, be owned, that proofs for it are still scanty,
beyond the bare fact of a submersion which appears to have had a
very wide range.  I must therefore be content to leave this
point, as far as geological evidence is concerned, for future
affirmation.
There are some other superficial deposits, of less consequence
on the present occasion than the diluvium—namely,
lacustrine deposits, or filled-up lakes; alluvium, or the
deposits of rivers beside their margins; deltas, the deposits
made by great ones at their efflux into the sea; peat mosses; and
the vegetable soil.  The animal remains found in these
generally testify to a zoology on the verge of that which still
exists, or melting into it, there being included many species
which still exist.  In a lacustrine deposit at
Market-Weighton, in the Vale of York, there have been found bones
of the elephant, rhinoceros, bison, wolf, horse, felis, deer,
birds, all or nearly all extinct species; associated with
thirteen species of land and fresh water shells, “exactly
identical with types now living in the vicinity.”  In
similar deposits in North America, are remains of the mammoth,
mastodon, buffalo, and other animals of extinct and living
types.  In short, these superficial deposits shew precisely
such remains as might be expected from a time at which the
present system of things (to use a vague but not unexpressive
phrase) obtained, but yet so far remote in chronology as to allow
of the dropping of many species, through familiar causes, in the
interval.  Still, however, there is no authentic or
satisfactory instance of human remains being found, except in
deposits obviously of very modern date; a tolerably strong proof
that the creation of our own species is a comparatively recent
event, and one posterior (generally speaking) to all the great
natural transactions chronicled by geology.</div></body></text></TEI>