<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="65">CHAPTER IV.
Discovery of Achromatism.
THE discovery that the laws of
refractive dispersion of different substances were such as to allow of
combinations which neutralised the dispersion without neutralizing the
refraction, is one which has hitherto been of more value to art than
to science. The property has no definite bearing, which has yet been
satisfactorily explained, upon the theory of light; but it is
of the greatest importance in its application to the construction of
telescopes; and it excited the more notice, in consequence of the
prejudices and difficulties which for a time retarded the
discovery.
Newton conceived that he had proved by experiment,31 that light 67 is white after refraction, when the
emergent rays are parallel to the incident, and in no other case. If
this were so, the production of colorless images by refracting media
would be impossible; and such, in deference to Newton’s great
authority, was for some time the general persuasion. Euler32 observed, that a combination of lenses
which does not color the image must be possible, since we have an
example of such a combination in the human eye; and he investigated
mathematically the conditions requisite for such a result.
Klingenstierna,33 a Swedish mathematician, also showed
that Newton’s rule could not be universally true. Finally, John
Dollond,34 in 1757, repeated Newton’s experiment,
and obtained an opposite result. He found that when an object was seen
through two prisms, one of glass and one of water, of such angles that
it did not appear displaced by refraction, it was colored. Hence it
followed that, without being colored, the rays might be made to
undergo refraction; and that thus, substituting lenses for prisms, a
combination might be formed, which should produce an image without
coloring it, and make the construction of an achromatic
telescope possible.
31 Opticks, B. i. p. ii. Prop.
3.
32 Ac. Berlin. 1747.
33 Swedish Trans. 1754.
34 Phil. Trans. 1758.
Euler at first hesitated to confide in Dollond’s experiments; but
he was assured of their correctness by Clairaut, who had throughout
paid great attention to the subject; and those two great
mathematicians, as well as D’Alembert, proceeded to investigate
mathematical formulæ which might be useful in the application of the
discovery. The remainder of the deductions, which were founded upon
the laws of dispersion of various refractive substances, belongs
rather to the history of art than of science. Dollond used at first,
for his achromatic object-glass, a lens of crown-glass, and one of
flint-glass. He afterwards employed two lenses of the former
substance, including between them one of the latter, adjusting the
curvatures of his lenses in such a way as to correct the imperfections
arising from the spherical form of the glasses, as well as the fault
of color. Afterwards, Blair used fluid media along with glass lenses,
in order to produce improved object-glasses. This has more recently
been done in another form by Mr. Barlow. The inductive laws of
refraction being established, their results have been deduced by
various mathematicians, as Sir J. Herschel and Professor Airy among
ourselves, who have simplified and extended the investigation of the
formulæ which determine the best combination of lenses in the
object-glasses and eye-glasses of 68 telescopes, both with reference to
spherical and to chromatic aberrations.
According to Dollond’s discovery, the colored spectra produced by
prisms of two substances, as flint-glass and crown-glass, would be of
the same length when the refraction was different. But a question then
occurred: When the whole distance from the red to the violet in one
spectrum was the same as the whole distance in the other, were the
intermediate colors, yellow, green, &c., in corresponding places
in the two? This point also could not be determined any otherwise than
by experiment. It appeared that such a correspondence did not exist;
and, therefore, when the extreme colors were corrected by combinations
of the different media, there still remained an uncorrected residue of
color arising from the rest of the spectrum. This defect was a
consequence of the property, that the spectra belonging to different
media were not divided in the same ratio by the same colors,
and was hence termed the irrationality of the spectrum. By
using three prisms, or three lenses, three colors may be made to
coincide instead of two, and the effects of this irrationality greatly
diminished.
For the reasons already mentioned, we do not pursue this subject
further,35 but turn to those optical facts which
finally led to a great and comprehensive theory.
35 The discovery of the fixed
lines in the spectrum, by Wollaston and Fraunhofer, has more
recently supplied the means of determining, with extreme accuracy, the
corresponding portions of the spectrum in different refracting
substances.
[2nd Ed.] [Mr. Chester More Hall, of More Hall, in Essex, is said
to have been led by the study of the human eye, which he conceived to
be achromatic, to construct achromatic telescopes as early as 1729.
Mr. Hall, however, kept his invention a secret. David Gregory, in his
Catoptrics (1713), had suggested that it would perhaps be an
improvement of telescopes, if, in imitation of the human eye, the
object-glass were composed of different media. Encyc. Brit.
art. Optics.
It is said that Clairaut first discovered the irrationality of the
colored spaces in the spectrum. In consequence of this irrationality,
it follows that when two refracting media are so combined as to
correct each other’s extreme dispersion, (the separation of the red
and violet rays,) this first step of correction still leaves a residue
of 69 coloration
arising from the unequal dispersion of the intermediate rays (the
green, &c.). These outstanding colors, as they were termed
by Professor Robison, form the residual, or secondary
spectrum.
Dr. Blair, by very ingenious devices, succeeded in producing an
object-glass, corrected by a fluid lens, in which this aberration of
color was completely corrected, and which performed wonderfully
well.
The dispersion produced by a prism may be corrected by another
prism of the same substance and of a different angle. In this
case also there is an irrationality in the colored spaces, which
prevents the correction of color from being complete; and hence, a new
residuary spectrum, which has been called the tertiary
spectrum, by Sir David Brewster, who first noticed it.
I have omitted, in the notice of discoveries respecting the
spectrum, many remarkable trains of experimental research, and
especially the investigations respecting the power of various media to
absorb the light of different parts of the spectrum, prosecuted by Sir
David Brewster with extraordinary skill and sagacity. The observations
are referred to in chapter iii. Sir John
Herschel, Prof. Miller, Mr. Daniel, Dr. Faraday, and Mr. Talbot, have
also contributed to this part of our knowledge.]
</div></body></text></TEI>