<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="82">CHAPTER II.
The Progress of Electrical Theory.
THE cause of electrical
phenomena, and the mode of its operation, were naturally at first
spoken of in an indistinct and wavering manner. It was called the
electric fire, the electric fluid; its effects were
attributed to virtues, effluvia, atmospheres.
When men’s mechanical ideas became somewhat more distinct, the motions
and tendencies to motion were ascribed to currents, in the same
manner as the cosmical motions had been in the Cartesian system. This
doctrine of currents was maintained by Nollet, who ascribed all the
phenomena of electrized bodies to the contemporaneous afflux and
efflux of electrical matter. It was an important step towards sound
theory, to get rid of this notion of moving fluids, and to consider
attraction and repulsion as statical forces; and this appears to have
been done by others about the same time. Dufay23 considered that
he had proved the existence of two electricities, the vitreous and the
resinous, and conceived each 202 of these to be a fluid which repelled
its own parts and attracted those of the other: this is, in fact, the
outline of the theory which recently has been considered as the best
established; but from various causes it was not at once, or at least
not generally adopted. The hypothesis of the excess and defect of a
single fluid is capable of being so treated as to give the same
results with the hypothesis of two opposite fluids and happened to
obtain the preference for some time. We have already seen that this
hypothesis, according to which electric phenomena arose from the
excess and defect of a generally diffused fluid, suggested itself to
Watson and Franklin about 1747. Watson found that when an electric
body was excited, the electricity was not created, but collected; and
Franklin held, that when the Leyden jar was charged, the quantity of
electricity was unaltered, though its distribution was changed.
Symmer24 maintained the existence of two fluids;
and Cigna supplied the main defect which belonged to this tenet in the
way in which Dufay held it, by showing that the two opposite
electricities were usually produced at the same time. Still the
apparent simplicity of the hypothesis of one fluid procured it many
supporters. It was that which Franklin adopted, in his explanation of
the Leyden experiment; and though after the first conception of an
electrical charge as a disturbance of equilibrium, there was nothing
in the development or details of Franklin’s views which deserved to
win for them any peculiar authority, his reputation, and his skill as
a writer, gave a considerable influence to his opinions. Indeed, for a
time he was considered, over a large part of Europe, as the creator of
the science, and the terms25
Franklinism, Franklinist, Franklinian system,
occur in almost every page of continental publications on the subject.
Yet the electrical phenomena to the knowledge of which Franklin added
least, those of induction, were those by which the progress of the
theory was most promoted. These, as we have already said, were at
first explained by the hypothesis of electrical atmospheres. Lord
Mahon wrote a treatise, in which this hypothesis was mathematically
treated; yet the hypothesis was very untenable, for it would not
account for the most obvious cases of induction, such as the Leyden
jar, except the atmosphere was supposed to penetrate glass.
23 Ac. Par. 1733, p.
467.
24 Phil. Trans. 1759.
25 Priestley, p. 160.
The phenomena of electricity by induction, when fairly considered
by a person of clear notions of the relations of space and force, were
seen to accommodate themselves very generally to the conception 203 introduced by
Dufay;26 of two electricities each repelling
itself and attracting the other. If we suppose that there is only one
fluid, which repels itself and attracts all other matter, we obtain,
in many cases, the same general results as if we suppose two fluids;
thus, if an electrized body, overcharged with the single fluid, act
upon a ball, it drives the electric fluid in the ball to the further
side by its repulsion, and then attracts the ball by attracting the
matter of the ball more than it repels the fluid which is upon the
ball. If we suppose two fluids, the positively electrized body draws
the negative fluid to the nearer side of the ball, repels the positive
fluid to the opposite side, and attracts the ball on the whole,
because the attracted fluid is nearer than that which is repelled. The
verification of either of these hypotheses, and the determination of
their details, depended necessarily upon experiment and calculation.
It was under the hypothesis of a single fluid that this trial was
first properly made. Æpinus of Petersburg published, in 1759, his
Tentamen Theoriæ Electricitatis et Magnetismi; in which he
traces mathematically the consequences of the hypothesis of an
electric fluid, attracting all other matter, but repelling itself; the
law of force of this repulsion and attraction he did not pretend to
assign precisely, confining himself to the supposition that the mutual
force of the particles increases as the distance decreases. But it was
found, that in order to make this theory tenable, an additional
supposition was required, namely, that the particles of bodies repel
each other as much as they attract the electric fluid.27 For if two bodies, A and B, be in their
natural electrical condition, they neither attract nor repel each
other. Now, in this case, the fluid in A attracts the matter in B and
repels the fluid in B with equal energy, and thus no tendency to
motion results from the fluid in A; and if we further suppose that the
matter in A attracts the fluid in B and repels the
matter in B with equal energy, we have the resulting mutual
inactivity of the two bodies explained; but without the latter
supposition, there would be a mutual attraction: or we may put the
truth more simply thus; two negatively electrized bodies repel each
other; if negative electrization were merely the abstraction of the
fluid which is the repulsive element, this result could not follow
except there were a repulsion in the bodies themselves, independent of
the fluid. And thus Æpinus found himself compelled to assume this
mutual repulsion of material particles; he had, in fact, the 204 alternative of this
supposition, or that of two fluids, to choose between, for the
mathematical results of both hypotheses are the same. Wilcke, a Swede,
who had at first asserted and worked out the Æpinian theory in its
original form, afterwards inclined to the opinion of Symmer; and
Coulomb, when, at a later period, he confirmed the theory by his
experiments and determined the law of force, did not hesitate to
prefer28 the theory of two fluids, “because,” he
says, “it appears to me contradictory to admit at the same time, in
the particles of bodies, an attractive force in the inverse ratio of
the squares of the distances, which is demonstrated by universal
gravitation, and a repulsive force in the same inverse ratio of the
squares of the distances; a force which would necessarily be
infinitely great relatively to the action of gravitation.” We may add,
that by forcing us upon this doctrine of the universal repulsion of
matter, the theory of a single fluid seems quite to lose that
superiority in the way of simplicity which had originally been its
principal recommendation.
26 Mém. A. P. 1733, p.
467.
27 Robison, vol. iv. p. 18.
28 Mém. Ac. P. 1788, p.
671.
The mathematical results of the supposition of Æpinus, which are,
as Coulomb observes,29 the same as of that of the two fluids,
were traced by the author himself in the work referred to, and shown
to agree, in a great number of cases, with the observed facts of
electrical induction, attraction, and repulsion. Apparently this work
did not make its way very rapidly through Europe; for in 1771, Henry
Cavendish stated30 the same hypothesis in a paper read
before the Royal Society; which he prefaces by saying, “Since I first
wrote the following paper, I find that this way of accounting for the
phenomena of electricity is not new. Æpinus, in his Tentamen
Theoriæ Electricitatis et Magnetismi, has made use of the same, or
nearly the same hypothesis that I have; and the conclusions he draws
from it agree nearly with mine as far as he goes.”
29 Ac. P. 1788, p. 672.
30 Phil. Trans. 1771, vol.
lxi.
The confirmation of the theory was, of course, to be found in the
agreement of its results with experiment; and in particular, in the
facts of electrical induction, attraction, and repulsion, which
suggested the theory. Æpinus showed that such a confirmation appeared
in a number of the most obvious cases; and to these, Cavendish added
others, which, though not obvious, were of such a nature that the
calculations, in general difficult or impossible, could in these
instances be easily performed; as, for example, cases in which there
are plates or globes at the two extremities of a long wire. In all
these cases of 205
electrical action the theory was justified. But in order to give it
full confirmation, it was to be considered whether any other facts,
not immediately assumed in the foundation of the theory, were
explained by it; a circumstance which, as we have seen, gave the final
stamp of truth to the theories of astronomy and optics. Now we appear
to have such confirmation, in the effect of points, and in the
phenomena of the electrical discharge. The theory of neither of these
was fully understood by Cavendish, but he made an approach to the true
view of them. If one part of a conducting body be a sphere of small
radius, the electric fluid upon the surface of this sphere will, it
appears by calculation, be more dense, and tend to escape more
energetically, in proportion as the radius of the sphere is smaller;
and, therefore, if we consider a point as part of the surface of a
sphere of imperceptible radius, it follows from the theory that the
effort of the fluid to escape at that place will be enormous; so that
it may easily be supposed to overcome the resisting causes. And the
discharge may be explained in nearly the same manner; for when a
conductor is brought nearer and nearer to an electrized body, the
opposite electricity is more and more accumulated by attraction on the
side next to the electrized body; its tension becomes greater by the
increase of its quantity and the diminution of the distance, and at
last it is too strong to be contained, and leaps out in the form of a
spark.
The light, sound, and mechanical effects produced by the electric
discharge, made the electric fluid to be not merely considered
as a mathematical hypothesis, useful for reducing phenomena to formulæ
(as for a long time the magnetic fluid was), but caused it to be at
once and universally accepted as a physical reality, of which we learn
the existence by the common use of the senses, and of which measures
and calculations are only wanted to teach us the laws.
The applications of the theory of electricity which I have
principally considered above, are those which belong to conductors, in
which the electric fluid is perfectly moveable, and can take that
distribution which the forces require. In non-conducting or electric
bodies, the conditions to which the fluid is subject are less easy to
determine; but by supposing that the fluid moves with great difficulty
among the particles of such bodies,—that nevertheless it may be
dislodged and accumulated in parts of the surface of such bodies, by
friction and other modes of excitement; and that the earth is an
inexhaustible reservoir of electric matter,—the principal facts
of excitation and the like receive a tolerably satisfactory
explanation. 206
The theory of Æpinus, however, still required to have the law of
action of the particles of the fluid determined. If we were to call to
mind how momentous an event in physical astronomy was the
determination of the law of the cosmical forces, the inverse square of
the distance, and were to suppose the importance and difficulty of the
analogous step in this case to be of the same kind, this would be to
mistake the condition of science at that time. The leading idea, the
conception of the possibility of explaining natural phenomena by means
of the action of forces, on rigorously mechanical principles, had
already been promulgated by Newton, and was, from the first, seen to
be peculiarly applicable to electrical phenomena; so that the very
material step of clearly proposing the problem, often more important
than the solution of it, had already been made. Moreover the
confirmation of the truth of the assumed cause in the astronomical
case depended on taking the right law; but the electrical theory could
be confirmed, in a general manner at least, without this restriction.
Still it was an important discovery that the law of the inverse square
prevailed in these as well as in cosmical attractions.
It was impossible not to conjecture beforehand that it would be so.
Cavendish had professed in his calculations not to take the exponent
of the inverse power, on which the force depended, to be strictly 2,
but to leave it indeterminate between 1 and 3; but in his applications
of his results, he obviously inclines to the assumption that it is 2.
Experimenters tried to establish this in various ways. Robison,31 in 1769, had already proved that the
law of force is very nearly or exactly the inverse square; and Meyer32 had discovered, but not published, the
same result. The clear and satisfactory establishment of this truth is
due to Coulomb, and was one of the first steps in his important series
of researches on this subject. In his first paper33 in the
Memoirs of the Academy for 1785, he proves this law for small
globes; in his second Memoir he shows it to be true for globes one and
two feet in diameter. His invention of the torsion-balance,
which measures very small forces with great certainty and exactness,
enabled him to set this question at rest for ever.
31 Works, iv. p. 68.
32 Biog. Univ. art.
Coulumb, by Biot.
33 Mém. A. P. 1785, pp. 569,
578.
The law of force being determined for the particles of the electric
fluid, it now came to be the business of the experimenter and the
207 mathematician
to compare the results of the theory in detail with those of
experimental measures. Coulomb undertook both portions of the task. He
examined the electricity of portions of bodies by means of a little
disk (his tangent plane) which he applied to them and then
removed, and which thus acted as a sort of electric taster. His
numerical results (the intensity being still measured by the
torsion-balance) are the fundamental facts of the theory of the
electrical fluid. Without entering into detail, we may observe that he
found the electricity to be entirely collected at the surface of
conductors (which Beccaria had before shown to be the case), and that
he examined and recorded the electric intensity at the surface of
globes, cylinders, and other conducting bodies, placed within each
other’s influence in various ways.
The mathematical calculation of the distribution of two fluids, all
the particles of which attract and repel each other according to the
above law, was a problem of no ordinary difficulty; as may easily be
imagined, when it is recollected that the attraction and repulsion
determine the distribution, and the distribution reciprocally
determines the attraction and repulsion. The problem was of the same
nature as that of the figure of the earth; and its rigorous solution
was beyond the powers of the analysis of Coulomb’s time. He obtained,
however, approximate solutions with much ingenuity; for instance, in a
case in which it was obvious that the electric fluid would be most
accumulated at and near the equator of a certain sphere, he calculated
the action of the sphere on two suppositions: first, that the fluid
was all collected precisely at the equator; and next, that it was
uniformly diffused over the surface; and he then assumed the actual
case to be intermediate between these two. By such artifices he was
able to show that the results of his experiments and of his
calculations gave an agreement sufficiently near to entitle him to
consider the theory as established on a solid basis.
Thus, at this period, mathematics was behind experiment; and a
problem was proposed, in which theoretical numerical results were
wanted for comparison with observation, but could not be accurately
obtained; as was the case in astronomy also, till the time of the
approximate solution of the Problem of Three Bodies, and the
consequent formation of the Tables of the Moon and Planets on the
theory of universal gravitation. After some time, electrical theory
was relieved from this reproach, mainly in consequence of the progress
which astronomy had occasioned in pure mathematics. About 1801, 208 there appeared in the
Bulletin des Sciences,34 an exact
solution of the problem of the distribution of electric fluid on a
spheroid, obtained by M. Biot, by the application of the peculiar
methods which Laplace had invented for the problem of the figure of
the planets. And in 1811, M. Poisson applied Laplace’s artifices to
the case of two spheres acting upon one another in contact, a case to
which many of Coulomb’s experiments were referrible; and the agreement
of the results of theory and observation, thus extricated from
Coulomb’s numbers, obtained above forty years previously, was very
striking and convincing.35 It followed also from Poisson’s
calculations, that when two electrized spheres are brought near each
other, the accumulation of the opposite electricities on their nearest
points increases without limit as the spheres approach to contact; so
that before the contact takes place, the external resistance will be
overcome, and a spark will pass.
34 No. li.
35 Mém. A. P. 1811.
Though the relations of non-conductors to electricity, and various
other circumstances, leave many facts imperfectly explained by the
theory, yet we may venture to say that, as a theory which gives the
laws of the phenomena, and which determines the distribution of those
elementary forces, on the surface of electrized bodies, from which
elementary forces (whether arising from the presence of a fluid or
not,) the total effects result, the doctrine of Dufay and Coulomb, as
developed in the analysis of Poisson, is securely and permanently
established. This part of the subject has been called statical
electricity. In the establishment of the theory of this branch of
science, we must, I conceive, allow to Dufay more merit than is
generally ascribed to him; since he saw clearly, and enunciated in a
manner which showed that he duly appreciated their capital character,
the two chief principles,—the conditions of electrical
attraction and repulsion, and the apparent existence of two kinds of
electricity. His views of attraction are, indeed, partly expressed in
terms of the Cartesian hypothesis of vortices, then prevalent in
France; but, at the time when he wrote, these forms of speech
indicated scarcely anything besides the power of attraction.
Franklin’s real merit as a discoverer was, that he was one of the
first who distinctly conceived the electrical charge as a
derangement of equilibrium. The great fame which, in his day, he
enjoyed, arose from the clearness and spirit with which he narrated
his discoveries; from his dealing with electricity in the imposing
form of thunder and lightning; and partly, perhaps, from his character
as an 209 American
and a politician; for he was already, in 1736, engaged in public
affairs as clerk to the General Assembly of Pennsylvania, though it
was not till a later period of his life that his admirers had the
occasion of saying of him

Eripuit cœlis fulmen sceptrumque tyrannis;

Born to control all lawless force, all fierce and
baleful sway,
The thunder’s bolt, the tyrant’s rod, alike he
wrenched away.
Æpinus and Coulomb were two of the most eminent physical
philosophers of the last century, and labored in the way peculiarly
required by that generation; whose office it was to examine the
results, in particular subjects, of the general conception of
attraction and repulsion, as introduced by Newton. The reasonings of
the Newtonian period had, in some measure, anticipated all possible
theories resembling the electrical doctrine of Æpinus and Coulomb;
and, on that account, this doctrine could not be introduced and
confirmed in a sudden and striking manner, so as to make a great
epoch. Accordingly, Dufay, Symmer, Watson, Franklin, Æpinus and
Coulomb, have all a share in the process of induction. With reference
to these founders of the theory of electricity, Poisson holds the same
place which Laplace holds with reference to Newton.
The reception of the Coulombian theory (so we most call
it, for the Æpinian theory implies one fluid only,) has hitherto not
been so general as might have been reasonably expected from its very
beautiful accordance with the facts which it contemplates. This has
partly been owing to the extreme abstruseness of the mathematical
reasoning which it employs, and which put it out of the reach of most
experimenters and writers of works of general circulation. The theory
of Æpinus was explained by Robison in the Encyclopædia
Britannica; the analysis of Poisson has recently been presented to
the public in the Encyclopædia Metropolitana, but is of a kind
not easily mastered even by most mathematicians. On these accounts
probably it is, that in English compilations of science, we find, even
to this day, the two theories of one and of two fluids stated as if
they were nearly on a par in respect of their experimental evidence.
Still we may say that the Coulombian theory is probably assented to by
all who have examined it, at least as giving the laws of phenomena;
and I have not heard of any denial of it from such a quarter, or of
any attempt to show it to be erroneous by detailed and measured
experiments. Mr. Snow Harris 210 has recently36 described some
important experiments and measures; but his apparatus was of such a
kind that the comparison of the results with the Coulombian theory was
not easy; and indeed the mathematical problems which Mr. Harris’s
combinations offered, require another Poisson for their solution.
Still the more obvious results are such as agree with the theory, even
in the cases in which their author considered them to be inexplicable.
For example, he found that by doubling the quantity of electricity of
a conductor, it attracted a body with four times the force; but the
body not being insulated, would have its electricity also doubled by
induction, and thus the fact was what the theory required.
36 Phil. Trans. 1834, p.
2.
Though it is thus highly probable that the Coulombian theory of
electricity (or the Æpinian, which is mathematically equivalent) will
stand as a true representation of the law of the elementary actions,
we must yet allow that it has not received that complete evidence, by
means of experiments and calculations added to those of its founders,
which the precedents of other permanent sciences have led us to look
for. The experiments of Coulomb, which he used in the establishment of
the theory, were not very numerous, and they were limited to a
peculiar form of bodies, namely spheres. In order to form the proper
sequel to the promulgation of this theory, to give a full
confirmation, and to ensure its general reception, we
ought to have experiments more numerous and more varied (such as those
of Mr. Harris are) shown to agree in all respects with results
calculated from the theory. This would, as we have said, be a task of
labor and difficulty; but the person who shall execute it will deserve
to be considered as one of the real founders of the true doctrine of
electricity. To show that the coincidence between theory and
observation, which has already been proved for spherical conductors,
obtains also for bodies of other forms, will be a step in electricity
analogous to what was done in astronomy, when it was shown that the
law of gravitation applied to comets as well as to planets.
But although we consider the views of Æpinus or Coulomb in a very
high degree probable as a formal theory, the question is very
different when we come to examine them as a physical
theory;—that is, when we inquire whether there really is a
material electric fluid or fluids.
Question of One or Two Fluids.—In the first place as
to the question whether the fluids are one or two;—Coulomb’s
introduction of 211
the hypothesis of two fluids has been spoken of as a reform of the
theory of Æpinus; it would probably have been more safe to have called
his labors an advance in the calculation, and in the comparison of
hypothesis with experiment, than to have used language which implied
that the question, between the rival hypotheses of one or two fluids,
could be treated as settled. For, in reality, if we assume, as Æpinus
does, the mutual repulsion of all the particles of matter, in addition
to the repulsion of the particles of the electric fluid for one
another and their attraction for the particles of matter, the one
fluid of Æpinus will give exactly the same results as the two fluids
of Coulomb. The mathematical formulæ of Coulomb and of Poisson express
the conditions of the one case as well as of the other; the
interpretation only being somewhat different. The place of the forces
of the resinous fluid is supplied by the excess of the forces ascribed
to the matter above the forces of the fluid, in the parts where the
electric fluid is deficient.
The obvious argument against this hypothesis is, that we ascribe to
the particles of matter a mutual repulsion, in addition to the mutual
attraction of universal gravitation, and that this appears
incongruous. Accordingly, Æpinus says, that when he was first driven
to this proposition it horrified him.37 But we may
answer it in this way very satisfactorily:—If we suppose the
mutual repulsion of matter to be somewhat less than the mutual
attraction of matter and electric fluid, it will follow, as a
consequence of the hypothesis, that besides all obvious electrical
action, the particles of matter would attract each other with forces
varying inversely as the square of the distance. Thus gravitation
itself becomes an electrical phenomenon, arising from the residual
excess of attraction over repulsion; and the fact which is urged
against the hypothesis becomes a confirmation of it. By this
consideration the prerogative of simplicity passes over to the side of
the hypothesis of one fluid; and the rival view appears to lose at
least all its superiority.
37 Neque diffiteor cum ipsa se mihi
offerret . . . . me ad ipsam quodammodo  exhorruisse. Tentamen
Theor. Elect. p. 39.
Very recently, M. Mosotti38 has calculated
the results of the Æpinian theory in a far more complete manner than
had previously been performed; using Laplace’s coefficients, as
Poisson had done for the 212 Coulombian theory. He finds that, from
the supposition of a fluid and of particles of matter exercising such
forces as that theory assumes (with the very allowable additional
supposition that the particles are small compared with their
distances), it follows that the particles would exert a force,
repulsive at the smallest distances, a little further on vanishing,
afterwards attractive, and at all sensible distances attracting in
proportion to the inverse square of the distance. Thus there would be
a position of stable equilibrium for the particles at a very small
distance from each other, which may be, M. Mosotti suggests, that
equilibrium on which their physical structure depends. According to
this view, the resistance of bodies to compression and to extension,
as well as the phenomena of statical electricity and the mutual
gravitation of matter, are accounted for by the same hypothesis of a
single fluid or ether. A theory which offers a prospect of such a
generalization is worth attention; but a very clear and comprehensive
view of the doctrines of several sciences is requisite to prepare us
to estimate its value and probable success.
38 Sur les Forces qui régissent la
Constitution Intérieure des Corps. Turin. 1836.
Question of the Material Reality of the Electric
Fluid.—At first sight the beautiful accordance of the
experiments with calculations founded upon the attractions and
repulsions of the two hypothetical fluids, persuade us that the
hypotheses must be the real state of things. But we have already
learned that we must not trust to such evidence too readily. It is a
curious instance of the mutual influence of the histories of two
provinces of science, but I think it will be allowed to be just, to
say that the discovery of the polarization of heat has done much to
shake the theory of the electric fluids as a physical reality. For the
doctrine of a material caloric appeared to be proved (from the laws of
conduction and radiation) by the same kind of mathematical evidence
(the agreement of laws respecting the elementary actions with those of
fluids), which we have for the doctrine of material electricity. Yet
we now seem to see that heat cannot be matter, since its rays have
sides, in a manner in which a stream of particles of matter
cannot have sides without inadmissible hypotheses. We see, then, that
it will not be contrary to precedent, if our electrical theory,
representing with perfect accuracy the laws of the actions,
in all their forms, simple and complex, should yet be fallacious as a
view of the cause of the actions.
Any true view of electricity must include, or at least be
consistent with, the other classes of the phenomena, as well as this
statical electrical action; such as the conditions of excitation and
retention of 213
electricity; to which we may add, the connexion of electricity with
magnetism and with chemistry;—a vast field, as yet dimly seen.
Now, even with regard to the simplest of these questions, the cause of
the retention of electricity at the surface of bodies, it appears to
be impossible to maintain Coulomb’s opinion, that this is effected by
the resistance of air to the passage of electricity. The other
questions are such as Coulomb did not attempt to touch; they refer,
indeed, principally to laws not suspected at his time. How wide and
profound a theory must be which deals worthily with these, we shall
obtain some indications in the succeeding part of our history.
But it may be said on the other side, that we have the evidence of
our senses for the reality of an electric fluid;—we see it in
the spark; we hear it in the explosion; we feel it in the shock; and
it produces the effects of mechanical violence, piercing and tearing
the bodies through which it passes. And those who are disposed to
assert a real fluid on such grounds, may appear to be justified in
doing so, by one of Newton’s “Rules of Philosophizing,” in which he
directs the philosopher to assume, in his theories, “causes which are
true.” The usual interpretation of a “vera causa,” has been, that it
implies causes which, independently of theoretical calculations, are
known to exist by their mechanical effects; as gravity was familiarly
known to exist on the earth, before it was extended to the heavens.
The electric fluid might seem to be such a vera causa.
To this I should venture to reply, that this reasoning shows how
delusive the Newtonian rule, so interpreted, may be. For a moment’s
consideration will satisfy us that none of the circumstances, above
adduced, can really prove material currents, rather than vibrations,
or other modes of agency. The spark and shock are quite insufficient
to supply such a proof. Sound is vibrations,—light is
vibrations; vibrations may affect our nerves, and may rend a body, as
when glasses are broken by sounds. Therefore all these supposed
indications of the reality of the electric fluid are utterly
fallacious. In truth, this mode of applying Newton’s rule consists in
elevating our first rude and unscientific impressions into a supremacy
over the results of calculation, generalization, and systematic
induction.39
39 On the subject of this
Newtonian Rule of Philosophizing, see further Phil. Ind. Sc. B.
xii. c. 13. I have given an account of the history and evidence of the
Theory of Electricity in the Reports of the British Association
for 1835. I may seem there to have spoken more favorably of the Theory
as a Physical Theory than I have done here. This difference is
principally due to a consideration of the present aspect of the Theory
of Heat.
214 Thus our
conclusion with regard to this subject is, that if we wish to form a
stable physical theory of electricity, we must take into account not
only the laws of statical electricity, which we have been chiefly
considering, but the laws of other kinds of agency, different from the
electric, yet connected with it. For the electricity of which we have
hitherto spoken, and which is commonly excited by friction, is
identical with galvanic action, which is a result of chemical
combinations, and belongs to chemical philosophy. The connexion of
these different kinds of electricity with one another leads us into a
new domain; but we must, in the first place, consider their mechanical
laws. We now proceed to another branch of the same subject,
Magnetism.
~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~


BOOK XII.

MECHANICO-CHEMICAL SCIENCES.
(CONTINUED.)

HISTORY OF MAGNETISM.

Effice, ut interea fera
munera militiaï
Per maria ac terras omneis sopita
quiescant.
Nam tu sola potes tranquilla pace juvare
Mortales; quoniam belli fera munera Mavors
Armipotens regit, in gremium qui sæpe tuum
se
Rejicit, æterno devictus vulnere amoris;
Atque ita suspiciens tereti cervice
reposta,
Pascit amore avidos inhians in te, Dea,
visus,
Eque tuo pendet resupini spiritus ore.
Hunc tu, Diva, tuo recubantem corpore
sancto
Circumfusa super, suaves ex ore loquelas
Funde, petens placidam Romanis, incluta,
pacem.
Lucret. i.
31.

O charming Goddess, whose mysterious sway
The unseen hosts of earth and sky obey;
To whom, though cold and hard to all
besides,
The Iron God by strong affection glides.
Flings himself eager to thy close embrace,
And bends his head to gaze upon thy face;
Do thou, what time thy fondling arms are
thrown
Around his form, and he is all thy own,
Do thou, thy Rome to save, thy power to
prove,
Beg him to grant a boon for thy dear love;
Beg him no more in battle-fields to deal.
Or crush the nations with his mailed heel.
But, touched and softened by a worthy
flame,
Quit sword and spear, and seek a better
fame.
Bid him to make all war and slaughter
cease,
And ply his genuine task in arts of peace;
And by thee guided o’er the trackless
surge,
Bear wealth and joy to ocean’s farthest
verge.

</div></body></text></TEI>