<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="40">
[267]
CHAPTER VIII.

On the Physical Agency of the Deity.

1. We are not to expect that physical investigation
can enable us to conceive the manner in which
God acts upon the members of the universe. The
question, “Canst thou by searching find out God?”
must silence the boastings of science as well as the
repinings of adversity. Indeed, science shows us,
far more clearly than the conceptions of every day
reason, at what an immeasurable distance we are
from any faculty of conceiving how the universe, material
and moral, is the work of the Deity. But with
regard to the material world, we can at least go so
far as this;—we can perceive that events are brought
about, not by insulated interpositions of divine power
exerted in each particular case, but by the establishment
of general laws. This, which is the view of the
universe proper to science, whose office it is to search
out these laws, is also the view which, throughout
this work, we have endeavoured to keep present to
the mind of the reader. We have attempted to show
that it combines itself most readily and harmoniously
with the doctrines of Natural Theology; that the
arguments for those doctrines are strengthened, the
difficulties which affect them removed, by keeping it
steadily before us. We conceive, therefore, that the
religious philosopher will do well to bear this conception
in his mind. God is the author and governor
of the universe through the laws which he has given
to its parts, the properties which he has impressed
upon its constituent elements; these laws and properties
are, as we have already said, the instruments
with which he works; the institution of such laws,[268]
the selection of the quantities which they involve,
their combination and application, are the modes in
which he exerts and manifests his power, his wisdom,
his goodness: through these attributes, thus exercised,
the Creator of all, shapes, moves, sustains, and guides
the visible creation.
This has been the view of the relation of the Deity
to the universe entertained by the most sagacious
and comprehensive minds ever since the true object
of natural philosophy has been clearly and steadily apprehended.
The great writer who was the first to give
philosophers a distinct and commanding view of this
object, thus expresses himself in his “Confession of
Faith:” “I believe—that notwithstanding God hath
rested and ceased from creating since the first Sabbath,
yet, nevertheless, he doth accomplish and fulfil
his divine will in all things, great and small, singular
and general, as fully and exactly by providence, as
he could by miracle and new creation, though his
working be not immediate and direct, but by compass;
not violating nature, which is his own law upon
the creature.”
And one of our own time, whom we can no longer
hesitate to place among the worthiest disciples of the
school of Bacon, conveys the same thought in the
following passage: “The Divine Author of the universe
cannot be supposed to have laid down particular
laws, enumerating all individual contingencies,
which his materials have understood and obey—this
would be to attribute to him the imperfections of
human legislation;—but rather, by creating them
endued with certain fixed qualities and powers, he
has impressed them in their origin with the spirit,
not the letter of his law, and made all their subsequent
combinations and relations inevitable consequences
of this first impression.”[43]
2. This, which thus appears to be the mode of the
Deity’s operation in the material world, requires[269]
some attention on our part in order to understand it
with proper clearness. One reason of this is, that it
is a mode of operation altogether different from that
in which we are able to make matter fulfil our designs.
Man can construct exquisite machines, can
call in vast powers, can form extensive combinations,
in order to bring about results which he has in view.
But in all this he is only taking advantage of laws of
nature which already exist; he is applying to his use
qualities which matter already possesses. Nor can he
by any effort do more. He can establish no new law
of nature which is not a result of the existing ones.
He can invest matter with no new properties which
are not modifications of its present attributes. His
greatest advances in skill and power are made when
he calls to his aid forces which before existed unemployed,
or when he discovers so much of the habits
of some of the elements as to be able to bend them
to his purpose. He navigates the ocean by the assistance
of the winds which he cannot raise or still:
and even if we suppose him able to control the course
of these, his yet unsubjugated ministers, this could
only be done by studying their characters, by learning
more thoroughly the laws of air and heat and
moisture. He cannot give the minutest portion of the
atmosphere new relations, a new course of expansion,
new laws of motion. But the Divine operations,
on the other hand, include something much higher.
They take in the establishment of the laws of the
elements, as well as the combination of these laws
and the determination of the distribution and quantity
of the materials on which they shall produce
their effect. We must conceive that the Supreme
Power has ordained that air shall be rarefied, and
water turned into vapour, by heat; no less than that
he has combined air and water so as to sprinkle the
earth with showers, and determined the quantity of
heat and air and water, so that the showers shall be
as beneficial as they are.
We may and must, therefore, in our conceptions[270]
of the Divine purpose and agency, go beyond the
analogy of human contrivances. We must conceive
the Deity, not only as constructing the most refined
and vast machinery, with which, as we have already
seen, the universe is filled; but we must also imagine
him as establishing those properties by which such
machinery is possible: as giving to the materials of
his structure the qualities by which the material is
fitted to its use. There is much to be found, in natural
objects, of the same kind of contrivance which
is common to these and to human inventions; there
are mechanical devices, operations of the atmospheric
elements, chemical processes;—many such
have been pointed out, many more exist. But besides
these cases of the combination of means, which,
we seem able to understand without much difficulty,
we are led to consider the Divine Being as the author
of the laws of chemical, of physical, and of mechanical
action, and of such other laws as make matter
what it is;—and this is a view which no analogy of
human inventions, no knowledge of human powers,
at all assists us to embody or understand. Science,
therefore, as we have said, while it discloses to us
the mode of instrumentality employed by the Deity,
convinces us, more effectually than ever, of the impossibility
of conceiving God’s actions by assimilating
them to our own.
3. The laws of material nature, such as we have
described them, operate at all times, and in all places;
affect every province of the universe, and involve
every relation of its parts. Wherever these laws appear,
we have a manifestation of the intelligence
by which they were established. But a law supposes
an agent, and a power; for it is the mode according
to which the agent proceeds, the order according to
which the power acts. Without the presence of such
an agent, of such a power, conscious of the relations
on which the law depends, producing the effects which
the law prescribes, the law can have no efficacy, no
existence. Hence we infer that the intelligence by[271]
which the law is ordained, the power by which it is
put in action, must be present at all times and in all
places where the effects of the law occur; that thus
the knowledge and the agency of the Divine Being
pervade every portion of the universe, producing all
action and passion, all permanence and change. The
laws of nature are the laws which he, in his wisdom,
prescribes to his own acts; his universal presence is
the necessary condition of any course of events, his
universal agency the only origin of any efficient
force.
This view of the relation of the universe to God
has been entertained by many of the most eminent of
those who have combined the consideration of the
material world with the contemplation of God himself.
It may therefore be of use to illustrate it by a
few quotations, and the more so, as we find this idea
remarkably dwelt upon in the works of that writer
whose religious views must always have a peculiar
interest for the cultivators of physical science, the
great Newton.
Thus, in the observations on the nature of the
Deity with which he closes the “Opticks,” he declares
the various portions of the world, organic and
inorganic, “can be the effect of nothing else than the
wisdom and skill of a powerful ever living Agent,
who being in all places, is more able by his will to
move the bodies within his boundless uniform sensorium,
and thereby to form and reform the parts of
the universe, than we are by our will to move the
parts of our own bodies.” And in the Scholium at
the end of the “Principia,” he says, “God is one and
the same God always and every where. He is omnipresent,
not by means of his virtue alone, but also by
his substance, for virtue cannot subsist without substance.
In him all things are contained, and move,
but without mutual passion: God is not acted upon
by the motions of bodies; and they suffer no resistance
from the omnipresence of God.” And he refers
to several passages confirmatory of this view, not[272]
only in the Scriptures, but also in writers who hand
down to us the opinions of some of the most philosophical
thinkers of the pagan world. He does not
disdain to quote the poets, and among the rest, the
verses of Virgil;</div></body></text></TEI>