<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="128">CHAPTER VI.
Introduction of the Principle of Developed and
Metamorphosed Symmetry

Sect. 1.—Vegetable Morphology. Göthe.
De Candolle.
BEFORE we proceed to consider
the progress of principles which belong to animal and human life, such
as have just been pointed at, we must look round for such doctrines,
if any such there be, as apply alike to all organized beings,
conscious or unconscious, fixed or locomotive;—to the laws which
regulate vegetable as well as animal forms and functions. Though we
are very far from being able to present a 469 clear and connected code of such laws,
we may refer to one law, at least, which appears to be of genuine
authority and validity; and which is worthy our attention as an
example of a properly organical or physiological principle, distinct
from all mechanical, chemical, or other physical forces; and such as
cannot even be conceived to be resolvable into those. I speak of the
tendency which produces such results as have been brought together in
recent speculations upon Morphology.
It may perhaps be regarded as indicating how peculiar are the
principles of organic life, and how far removed from any mere
mechanical action, that the leading idea in these speculations was
first strongly and effectively apprehended, not by a laborious
experimenter and reasoner, but by a man of singularly brilliant and
creative fancy; not by a mathematician or chemist, but by a poet. And
we may add further, that this poet had already shown himself incapable
of rightly apprehending the relation of physical facts to their
principles; and had, in trying his powers on such subjects, exhibited
a signal instance of the ineffectual and perverse operation of the
method of philosophizing to which the constitution of his mind led
him. The person of whom we speak, is John Wolfgang Göthe, who is held,
by the unanimous voice of Europe, to have been one of the greatest
poets of our own, or of any time, and whose Doctrine of Colors
we have already had to describe, in the
History of Optics, as an entire failure. Yet his views on the laws
which connect the forms of plants into one simple system, have been
generally accepted and followed up. We might almost be led to think
that this writer’s poetical endowments had contributed to this
scientific discovery;—the love of beauty of form, by fixing the
attention upon the symmetry of plants; and the creative habit of
thought, by making constant developement of a familiar process.80
80 We may quote some of the poet’s
own verses as an illustration of his feelings on this subject. They
are addressed to a lady.

Dich verwirret, geliebte, die tausendfältige
mischung
  Dieses blumengewühls über dem garten
umher;
Viele namen hörest du an, und immer
verdränget,
  Mit barbarischem klang, einer den andern im
ohr.
Alle gestalten sind ähnlich und keine gleichet der
andern;
  Und so deutet das chor auf ein geheimes
gesetz,
Auf ein heiliges räthsel. O! könnte ich dich,
liebliche freundinn,
  Ueberliefern so gleich glücklich das lösende
wort.

Thou, my love, art perplext with the endless seeming
confusion
  Of the luxuriant wealth which in the garden is
spread;
Name upon name thou hearest, and in thy dissatisfied
hearing,
  With a barbarian noise one drives another
along.
All the forms resemble, yet none is the same as
another;
  Thus the whole of the throng points at a deep
hidden law.
Points at a sacred riddle. Oh! could I to thee, my
beloved friend,
  Whisper the fortunate word by which the riddle is
read!


470 But though
we cannot but remark the peculiarity of our being indebted to a poet
for the discovery of a scientific principle, we must not forget that
he himself held, that in making this step, he had been guided, not by
his invention, but by observation. He repelled, with extreme
repugnance, the notion that he had substituted fancy for fact, or
imposed ideal laws on actual things. While he was earnestly pursuing
his morphological speculations, he attempted to impress them upon
Schiller. “I expounded to him, in as lively a manner as possible, the
metamorphosis of plants, drawing on paper, with many characteristic
strokes, a symbolic plant before his eyes. He heard me,” Göthe says,81 “with much interest and distinct
comprehension; but when I had done, he shook his head, and said, ‘That
is not Experience; that is an Idea:’ I stopt with some degree of
irritation; for the point which separated us was marked most
luminously by this expression.” And in the same work he relates his
botanical studies and his habit of observation, from which it is
easily seen that no common amount of knowledge and notice of details,
were involved in the course of thought which led him to the principle
of the Metamorphosis of Plants.
81 Zur Morphologie, p.
24.
Before I state the history of this principle, I may be allowed to
endeavor to communicate to the reader, to whom this subject is new,
some conception of the principle itself. This will not be difficult,
if he will imagine to himself a flower, for instance, a common
wild-rose, or the blossom of an apple-tree, as consisting of a series
of parts disposed in whorls, placed one over another on an
axis. The lowest whorl is the calyx with its five sepals; above
this is the corolla with its five petals; above this are a multitude
of stamens, which may be considered as separate whorls of five each,
often repeated; above these is a whorl composed of the ovaries, or
what become the seed-vessels in the fruit, which are five united
together in the apple, but indefinite in number and separate in the
rose. Now the morphological view is 471 this;—that the members of each of
these whorls are in their nature identical, and the same as if they
were whorls of ordinary leaves, brought together by the shortening
their common axis, and modified in form by the successive elaboration
of their nutriment. Further, according to this view, a whorl of leaves
itself is to be considered as identical with several detached leaves
dispersed spirally along the axis, and brought together because the
axis is shortened. Thus all the parts of a plant are, or at least
represent, the successive metamorphoses of the same elementary member.
The root-leaves thus pass into the common leaves;—these into
bracteæ;—these into the sepals;—these into the
petals;—these into the stamens with their anthers;—these
into the ovaries with their styles and stigmas;—these ultimately
become the fruit; and thus we are finally led to the seed of a new
plant.
Moreover the same notion of metamorphosis may be applied to explain
the existence of flowers which are not symmetrical like those we have
just referred to, but which have an irregular corolla or calyx. The
papilionaceous flower of the pea tribe, which is so markedly
irregular, may be deduced by easy gradations from the regular flower,
(through the mimoseæ,) by expanding one petal, joining one or
two others, and modifying the form of the intermediate ones.
Without attempting to go into detail respecting the proofs of that
identity of all the different organs, and all the different forms of
plants, which is thus asserted, we may observe, that it rests on such
grounds as these;—the transformations which the parts of flowers
undergo by accidents of nutriment or exposure. Such changes,
considered as monstrosities where they are very remarkable, show the
tendencies and possibilities belonging to the organization in which
they occur. For instance, the single wild-rose, by culture, transforms
many of its numerous stamens into petals, and thus acquires the deeply
folded flower of the double garden-rose. We cannot doubt of the
reality of this change, for we often see stamens in which it is
incomplete. In other cases we find petals becoming leaves, and a
branch growing out of the centre of the flower. Some pear-trees, when
in blossom, are remarkable for their tendencies to such
monstrosities.82 Again, we find that flowers which are
usually irregular, occasionally become regular, and conversely. The
common snap-dragon (Linaria vulgaris) affords a curious
instance of this.83 The usual form of this plant is
“personate,” the corolla being divided into two lobes, which differ in
form, and 472
together present somewhat the appearance of an animal’s face; and the
upper portion of the corolla is prolonged backwards into a tube-like
“spur.” No flower can be more irregular; but there is a singular
variety of this plants termed Peloria, in which the corolla is
strictly symmetrical, consisting of a conical tube, narrowed in front,
elongated behind into five equal spurs, and containing five stamens of
equal length, instead of the two unequal pairs of the didynamous
Linaria. These and the like appearances show that there is in nature a
capacity for, and tendency to, such changes as the doctrine of
metamorphosis asserts.
82 Lindley, Nat. Syst. p.
84.
83 Henslow, Principles of
Botany, p. 116.
Göthe’s Metamorphosis of Plants was published 1790: and his
system was the result of his own independent course of thoughts. The
view which it involved was not, however, absolutely new, though it had
never before been unfolded in so distinct and persuasive a manner.
Linnæus considered the leaves, calyx, corolla, stamens, each as
evolved in succession from the other; and spoke of it as
prolepsis or anticipation,84 when the leaves
changed accidentally into bracteæ, these into a calyx, this into a
corolla, the corolla into stamens, or these into the pistil. And
Caspar Wolf apprehended in a more general manner the same principle.
“In the whole plant,” says he,85 “we see nothing
but leaves and stalk;” and in order to prove what is the situation of
the leaves in all their later forms, he adduces the cotyledons as the
first leaves.
84 Sprengel, Bot. ii. 302.
Amœn. Acad. vi. 324, 365.
85 Nov. Con. Ac. Petrop. xii.
403, xiii. 478.
Göthe was led to his system on this subject by his general views of
nature. He saw, he says,86 that a whole life of talent and labor
was requisite to enable any one to arrange the infinitely copious
organic forms of a single kingdom of nature. “Yet I felt,” he adds,
“that for me there must be another way, analogous to the rest of my
habits. The appearance of the changes, round and round, of organic
creatures had taken strong hold on my mind. Imagination and Nature
appeared to me to vie with each other which could go on most boldly
yet most consistently.” His observation of nature, directed by such a
thought, led him to the doctrine of the metamorphosis.
86 Zur Morph. i. 30.
In a later republication of his work (Zur Morphologie,
1817,) he gives a very agreeable account of the various circumstances
which affected the reception and progress of his doctrine. Willdenow87 quoted 473 him thus:—“The life of plants is,
as Mr. Göthe very prettily says, an expansion and contraction, and
these alternations make the various periods of life.” “This
‘prettily,’” says Göthe, “I can be well content with, but the
‘egregie,’ of Usteri is much more pretty and obliging.”
Usteri had used this term respecting Göthe in an edition of
Jussieu.
87 Zur Morph. i. 121.
The application of the notion of metamorphosis to the explanation
of double and monstrous flowers had been made previously by
Jussieu. Göthe’s merit was, to have referred to it the regular
formation of the flower. And as Sprengel justly says,88 his view had so profound a meaning,
made so strong an appeal by its simplicity, and was so fruitful in the
most valuable consequences, that it was not to be wondered at if it
occasioned further examination of the subject; although many persons
pretend to slight it. The task of confirming and verifying the
doctrine by a general application of it to all cases,—a labor so
important and necessary after the promulgation of any great
principle,—Göthe himself did not execute. At first he collected
specimens and made drawings with some such view,89 but he was
interrupted and diverted to other matters. “And now,” says he, in his
later publication, “when I look back on this undertaking, it is easy
to see that the object which I had before my eyes was, for me, in my
position, with my habits and mode of thinking, unattainable. For it
was no less than this: that I was to take that which I had stated in
general, and presented to the conception, to the mental intuition, in
words; and that I should, in a particularly visible, orderly, and
gradual manner, present it to the eye; so as to show to the outward
sense that out of the germ of this idea might grow a tree of
physiology fit to overshadow the world.”
88 Gesch. Botan. ii.
304.
89 Zur Morph. i. 129".
Voigt, professor at Jena, was one of the first who adopted Göthe’s
view into an elementary work, which he did in 1808. Other botanists
labored in the direction which had thus been pointed out. Of those who
have thus contributed to the establishment and developement of the
metamorphic doctrine. Professor De Candolle, of Geneva, is perhaps the
most important. His Theory of Developement rests upon two main
principles, abortion and adhesion. By considering some
parts as degenerated or absent through the abortion of the buds which
might have formed them, and other parts as adhering together, he holds
that all plants may be reduced to perfect symmetry: and the actual and
constant occurrence of such incidents is shown beyond 474 all doubt. And thus
the snap-dragon, of which we have spoken above, is derived from the
Peloria, which is the normal condition of the flower, by the abortion
of one stamen, and the degeneration of two others. Such examples are
too numerous to need to be dwelt on.
Sect. 2.—Application of Vegetable
Morphology.
The doctrine, being thus
fully established, has been applied to solve different problems in
botany; for instance, to explain the structure of flowers which appear
at first sight to deviate widely from the usual forms of the vegetable
world. We have an instance of such an application in Mr. Robert
Brown’s explanation of the real structure of various plants which had
been entirely misunderstood: as, for example, the genus
Euphorbia. In this plant he showed that what had been held to
be a jointed filament, was a pedicel with a filament above it, the
intermediate corolla having evanesced. In Orchideæ (the orchis
tribe), he showed that the peculiar structure of the plant arose from
its having six stamens (two sets of three each), of which five are
usually abortive. In Coniferæ (the cone-bearing trees), it was
made to appear that the seed was naked, while the accompanying
appendage, corresponding to a seed-vessel, assumed all forms, from a
complete leaf to a mere scale. In like manner it was proved that the
pappus, or down of composite plants (as thistles), is a
transformed calyx.
Along with this successful application of a profound principle, it
was natural that other botanists should make similar attempts. Thus
Mr. Lindley was led to take a view90 of the
structure of Reseda (mignonette) different from that usually
entertained; which, when published, attracted a good deal of
attention, and gained some converts among the botanists of Germany and
France. But in 1833, Mr. Lindley says, with great candor, “Lately,
Professor Henslow has satisfactorily proved, in part by the aid of a
monstrosity in the common Mignonette, in part by a severe
application of morphological rules, that my hypothesis must
necessarily be false.” Such an agreement of different botanists
respecting the consequences of morphological rules, proves the reality
and universality of the rules.
90 Lindley, Brit. Assoc.
Report, iii. 50.
We find, therefore, that a principle which we may call the
Principle of Developed and Metamorphosed Symmetry, is firmly
established 475 and
recognized, and familiarly and successfully applied by botanists. And
it will be apparent, on reflection, that though symmetry is a
notion which applies to inorganic as well as to organic things, and
is, in fact, a conception of certain relations of space and position,
such developement and metamorphosis as are here spoken
of, are ideas entirely different from any of those to which the
physical sciences have led us in our previous survey; and are, in
short, genuine organical or physiological
ideas;—real elements of the philosophy of life.
We must, however imperfectly, endeavor to trace the application of
this idea in the other great department of the world of life; we must
follow the history of Animal Morphology.
~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~
</div></body></text></TEI>