<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="76">CHAPTER I.
The Doctrines of Conduction and
Radiation.

Section 1.—Introduction of the
Doctrine of Conduction.
BY conduction is meant
the propagation of heat from one part to another of a continuous body;
or from one body to another in contact with it; as when one end of a
poker stuck in the fire heats the other end, or when this end heats
the hand which takes hold of it. By radiation is meant the
diffusion of heat from the surface of a body to points not in contact.
It is clear in both these cases, that, in proportion as the hot
portion is hotter, it produces a greater effect in warming the cooler
portion; that is, it communicates more Heat to it, if
Heat be the abstract conception of which this effect is the
measure. The simplest rule which can be proposed is, that the heat
thus communicated in a given instant is proportional to the excess of
the heat of the hot body over that of the contiguous bodies; there are
no obvious phenomena which contradict the supposition that this is the
true law; and it was thence assumed by Newton as the true law for
radiation and by other writers for conduction. This assumption was
confirmed approximately, and afterwards corrected, for the case of
Radiation; in its application to Conduction, it has been made the
basis of calculation up to the present time. We may observe that this
statement takes for granted that we have attained to a measure of heat
(or of temperature, as heat thus measured is termed),
corresponding to the law thus assumed; and, in fact, as we shall have
occasion to explain in speaking of the measures of sensible
qualities, 140 the
thermometrical scale of heat according to the expansion of liquids
(which is the measure of temperature here adopted), was constructed
with a reference to Newton’s law of radiation of heat; and thus the
law is necessarily consistent with the scale.
In any case in which the parts of a body are unequally hot, the
temperature will vary continuously in passing from one part of
the body to another; thus, a long bar of iron, of which one end is
kept red hot, will exhibit a gradual diminution of temperature at
successive points, proceeding to the other end. The law of temperature
of the parts of such a bar might be expressed by the ordinates of a
curve which should run alongside the bar. And, in order to
trace mathematically the consequences of the assumed law, some of
those processes would be necessary, by which mathematicians are
enabled to deal with the properties of curves; as the method of
infinitesimals, or the differential calculus; and the truth or
falsehood of the law would be determined, according to the usual rules
of inductive science, by a comparison of results so deduced from the
principle, with the observed phenomena.
It was easily perceived that this comparison was the task which
physical inquirers had to perform; but the execution of it was delayed
for some time; partly, perhaps, because the mathematical process
presented some difficulties. Even in a case so simple as that above
mentioned, of a linear bar with a stationary temperature at one end,
partial differentials entered; for there were three variable
quantities, the time, as well as the place of each point and its
temperature. And at first, another scruple occurred to M. Biot when,
about 1804, he undertook this problem.1 “A difficulty,”
says Laplace,2 in 1809, “presents itself, which has not
yet been solved. The quantities of heat received and communicated in
an instant (by any point of the bar) must be infinitely small
quantities of the same order as the excess of the heat of a slice of
the body over that of the contiguous slice; therefore the
excess of the heat received by any slice over the heat
communicated, is an infinitely small quantity of the second order; and
the accumulation in a finite time (which depends on this excess)
cannot be finite.” I conceive that this difficulty arises entirely
from an arbitrary and unnecessary assumption concerning the relation
of the infinitesimal parts of the body. Laplace resolved the
difficulty by further reasoning founded upon the same assumption which
occasioned 141 it;
but Fourier, who was the most distinguished of the cultivators of this
mathematical doctrine of conduction, follows a course of reasoning in
which the difficulty does not present itself. Indeed it is stated by
Laplace, in the Memoir above quoted,3 that Fourier had
already obtained the true fundamental equations by views of his
own.
1 Biot, Traité de Phys. iv. p.
669.
2 Laplace, Mém. Inst. for 1809,
p. 332.
3 Laplace, Mém. Inst. for 1809,
p. 538.
The remaining part of the history of the doctrine of conduction is
principally the history of Fourier’s labors. Attention having been
drawn to the subject, as we have mentioned, the French Institute, in
January, 1810, proposed, as their prize question, “To give the
mathematical theory of the laws of the propagation of heat, and to
compare this theory with exact observations.” Fourier’s Memoir (the
sequel of one delivered in 1807,) was sent in September, 1811; and the
prize (3000 francs) adjudged to it in 1812. In consequence of the
political confusion which prevailed in France, or of other causes,
these important Memoirs were not published by the Academy till 1824;
but extracts had been printed in the Bulletin des Sciences in
1808, and in the Annales de Chimie in 1816; and Poisson and M.
Cauchy had consulted the manuscript itself.
It is not my purpose to give, in this place,4 an account of the
analytical processes by which Fourier obtained his results. The skill
displayed in these Memoirs is such as to make them an object of just
admiration to mathematicians; but they consist entirely of deductions
from the fundamental principle which I have noticed,—that the
quantity of heat conducted from a hotter to a colder point is
proportional to the excess of heat, modified by the
conductivity, or conducting power of each substance. The
equations which flow from this principle assume nearly the same forms
as those which occur in the most general problems of hydrodynamics.
Besides Fourier’s solution, Laplace, Poisson, and M. Cauchy have also
exercised their great analytical skill in the management of these
formulæ. We shall briefly speak of the comparison of the results of
these reasonings with experiment, and notice some other consequences
to which they lead. But before we can do this, we must pay some
attention to the subject of radiation.
4 I have given an account of Fourier’s
mathematical results in the Reports of the British Association
for 1835. 142
Sect. 2.—Introduction of the Doctrine of
Radiation.
A hot body, as a mass of
incandescent iron, emits heat, as we perceive by our senses when we
approach it; and by this emission of heat the hot body cools down. The
first step in our systematic knowledge of the subject was made in the
Principia. “It was in the destiny of that great work,” says
Fourier, “to exhibit, or at least to indicate, the causes of the
principal phenomena of the universe.” Newton assumed, as we have already said, that the rate at which a body
cools, that is, parts with its heat to surrounding bodies, is
proportional to its heat; and on this assumption he rested the
verification of his scale of temperatures. It is an easy deduction
from this law, that if times of cooling be taken in arithmetical
progression, the heat will decrease in geometrical progression. Kraft,
and after him Richman, tried to verify this law by direct experiments
on the cooling of vessels of warm water; and from these experiments,
which have since been repeated by others, it appears that for
differences of temperature which do not exceed 50 degrees (boiling
water being 100), this geometrical progression represents, with
tolerable (but not with complete) accuracy, the process of
cooling.
This principle of radiation, like that of conduction, required to
be followed out by mathematical reasoning. But it required also to be
corrected in the first place, for it was easily seen that the rate of
cooling depended, not on the absolute temperature of the body, but on
the excess of its temperature above the surrounding objects to which
it communicated its heat in cooling. And philosophers were naturally
led to endeavor to explain or illustrate this process by some physical
notions. Lambert in 1765 published5 an Essay on
the Force of Heat, in which he assimilates the communication of
heat to the flow of a fluid out of one vessel into another by an
excess of pressure; and mathematically deduces the laws of the process
on this ground. But some additional facts suggested a different view
of the subject. It was found that heat is propagated by radiation
according to straight lines, like light; and that it is, as light is,
capable of being reflected by mirrors, and thus brought to a focus of
intenser action. In this manner the radiative effect of a body could
be more precisely traced. A fact, however, came under notice, which,
at first sight, appeared to 143 offer some difficulty. It appeared that
cold was reflected no less than heat. A mass of ice, when its effect
was concentrated on a thermometer by a system of mirrors, made the
thermometer fall, just as a vessel of hot water placed in a similar
situation made it rise. Was cold, then, to be supposed a real
substance, no less than heat?
5 Act. Helvet. tom. ii. p.
172.
The solution of this and similar difficulties was given by Pierre
Prevost, professor at Geneva, whose theory of radiant heat was
proposed about 1790. According to this theory, heat, or
caloric, is constantly radiating from every point of the
surface of all bodies in straight lines; and it radiates the more
copiously, the greater is the quantity of heat which the body
contains. Hence a constant exchange of heat is going on among
neighboring bodies; and a body grows hotter or colder, according as it
receives more caloric than it emits, or the contrary. And thus a body
is cooled by rectilinear rays from a cold body, because along these
paths it sends rays of heat in greater abundance than those which
return the same way. This theory of exchanges is simple and
satisfactory, and was soon generally adopted; but we must consider it
rather as the simplest mode of expressing the dependence of the
communication of heat on the excess of temperature, than as a
proposition of which the physical truth is clearly established.
A number of curious researches on the effect of the different kinds
of surface of the heating and of the heated body, were made by Leslie
and others. On these I shall not dwell; only observing that the
relative amount of this radiative and receptive energy may be
expressed by numbers, for each kind of surface; and that we shall have
occasion to speak of it under the term exterior conductivity;
it is thus distinguished from interior conductivity, which is
the relative rate at which heat is conducted in the interior of
bodies.6
6 The term employed by Fourier,
conductibility or conducibility, suggests expressions
altogether absurd, as if the bodies could be called
conductible, or conducible, with respect to heat: I have
therefore ventured upon a slight alteration of the word, and have used
the abstract term which analogy would suggest, if we suppose bodies to
be conductive in this respect.
Sect. 3.—Verifications of the Doctrines of
Conduction and Radiation.
The interior and exterior
conductivity of bodies are numbers, which enter as elements, or
coefficients, into the mathematical calculations founded on the
doctrines of conduction and radiation. These 144 coefficients are to be determined for
each case by appropriate experiments: when the experimenters had
obtained these data, as well as the mathematical solutions of the
problems, they could test the truth of their fundamental principles by
a comparison of the theoretical and actual results in
properly-selected cases. This was done for the law of conduction in
the simple cases of metallic bars heated at one end, by M. Biot,7
and the accordance with experiment was sufficiently close. In the more
complex cases of conduction which Fourier considered, it was less easy
to devise a satisfactory mode of comparison. But some rather curious
relations which he demonstrated to exist among the temperatures at
different points of an armille, or ring, afforded a good
criterion of the value of the calculations, and confirmed their
correctness.8
7 Tr. de Phys. iv. 671.
8 Mém. Inst. 1819, p. 192,
published 1824.
We may therefore presume these doctrines of radiation and
conduction to be sufficiently established; and we may consider their
application to any remarkable case to be a portion of the history of
science. We proceed to some such applications.
Sect. 4.—The Geological and Cosmological
Application of Thermotics.
By far the most important
case to which conclusions from these doctrines have been applied, is
that of the globe of the earth, and of those laws of climate to which
the modifications of temperature give rise; and in this way we are led
to inferences concerning other parts of the universe. If we had any
means of observing these terrestrial and cosmical phenomena to a
sufficient extent, they would be valuable facts on which we might
erect our theories; and they would thus form part, not of the
corollaries, but of the foundations of our doctrine of heat. In such a
case, the laws of the propagation of heat, as discovered from
experiments on smaller bodies, would serve to explain these phenomena
of the universe, just as the laws of motion explain the celestial
movements. But since we are almost entirely without any definite
indications of the condition of the other bodies in the solar system
as to heat; and since, even with regard to the earth, we know only the
temperature of the parts at or very near the surface, our knowledge of
the part which heat plays in the earth and the heavens must be in a
great measure, not a generalization of observed facts, but a deduction
from theoretical principles. Still, such knowledge, whether obtained
145 from
observation or from theory, must possess great interest and
importance. The doctrines of this kind which we have to notice refer
principally to the effect of the sun’s heat on the earth, the laws of
climate,—the thermotical condition of the interior of the
earth,—and that of the planetary spaces.
1. Effect of Solar Heat on the Earth.—That the sun’s
heat passes into the interior of the earth in a variable manner,
depending upon the succession of days and nights, summers and winters,
is an obvious consequence of our first notions on this subject. The
mode in which it proceeds into the interior, after descending below
the surface, remained to be gathered, either from the phenomena, or
from reasoning. Both methods were employed.9 Saussure
endeavored to trace its course by digging, in 1785, and thus found
that at the depth of about thirty-one feet, the annual variation of
temperature is about 1⁄12th what it is at the
surface. Leslie adopted a better method, sinking the bulbs of
thermometers deep in the earth, while their stems appeared above the
surface. In 1813, ’16, and ’17, he observed thus the temperatures at
the depths of one, two, four, and eight feet, at Abbotshall, in
Fifeshire. The results showed that the extreme annual oscillations of
the temperature diminish as we descend. At the depth of one foot, the
yearly range of oscillation was twenty-five degrees (Fahrenheit); at
two feet it was twenty degrees; at four feet it was fifteen degrees;
at eight feet it was only nine degrees and a half. And the time at
which the heat was greatest was later and later in proceeding to the
lower points. At one foot, the maximum and minimum were three weeks
after the solstice of summer and of winter; at two feet, they were
four or five weeks; at four feet, they were two months; and at eight
feet, three months. The mean temperature of all the thermometers was
nearly the same. Similar results were obtained by Ott at Zurich in
1762, and by Herrenschneider at Strasburg in 1821, ’2, ’3.10
9 Leslie, art. Climate, Supp.
Enc. Brit. 179.
10 Pouillet, Météorol. t. ii.
p. 643.
These results had already been explained by Fourier’s theory of
conduction. He had shown11 that when the surface of a sphere is
affected by a periodical heat, certain alternations of heat travel
uniformly into the interior, but that the extent of the alternation
diminishes in geometrical progression in this descent. This conclusion
applies to the effect of days and years on the temperature of the
earth, and shows that such facts as those observed by Leslie are both
exemplifications of 146 the general circumstances of the earth,
and are perfectly in accordance with the principles on which Fourier’s
theory rests.
11 Mém. Inst. for 1821
(published 1826), p. 162.
2. Climate.—The term climate, which means
inclination, was applied by the ancients to denote that
inclination of the axis of the terrestrial sphere from which result
the inequalities of days in different latitudes. This inequality is
obviously connected also with a difference of thermotical condition.
Places near the poles are colder, on the whole, than places near the
equator. It was a natural object of curiosity to determine the law of
this variation.
Such a determination, however, involves many difficulties, and the
settlement of several preliminary points. How is the temperature of
any place to be estimated? and if we reply, by its mean
temperature, how are we to learn this mean? The answers to such
questions require very multiplied observations, exact instruments, and
judicious generalizations; and cannot be given here. But certain first
approximations may be obtained without much difficulty; for instance,
the mean temperature of any place may be taken to be the temperature
of deep springs, which is probably identical with the temperature of
the soil below the reach of the annual oscillations. Proceeding on
such facts, Mayer found that the mean temperature of any place was
nearly proportional to the square of the cosine of the latitude. This,
as a law of phenomena, has since been found to require considerable
correction; and it appears that the mean temperature does not depend
on the latitude alone, but on the distribution of land and water, and
on other causes. M. de Humboldt has expressed these deviations12 by his map of isothermal lines,
and Sir D. Brewster has endeavored to reduce them to a law by assuming
two poles of maximum cold.
12 British Assoc. 1833. Prof.
Forbes’s Report on Meteorology, p. 215.
The expression which Fourier finds13 for the
distribution of heat in a homogeneous sphere, is not immediately
comparable with Mayer’s empirical formula, being obtained on a certain
hypothesis, namely, that the equator is kept constantly at a fixed
temperature. But there is still a general agreement; for, according to
the theory, there is a diminution of heat in proceeding from the
equator to the poles in such a case; the heat is propagated from the
equator and the neighboring parts, and radiates out from the poles
into the surrounding space. And thus, in the case of the earth, the
solar heat enters in the tropical 147 parts, and constantly flows towards the
polar regions, by which it is emitted into the planetary spaces.
13 Fourier. Mém. Inst. tom. v.
p. 173.
Climate is affected by many thermotic influences, besides the
conduction and radiation of the solid mass of the earth. The
atmosphere, for example, produces upon terrestrial temperatures
effects which it is easy to see are very great; but these it is not
yet in the power of calculation to appreciate;14 and it is clear
that they depend upon other properties of air besides its power to
transmit heat. We must therefore dismiss them, at least for the
present.
14 Mém. Inst. tom. vii. p.
584
3. Temperature of the Interior of the Earth.—The
question of the temperature of the interior of the earth has excited
great interest, in consequence of its bearing on other branches of
knowledge. The various facts which have been supposed to indicate the
fluidity of the central parts of the terrestrial globe, belong, in
general, to geological science; but so far as they require the light
of thermotical calculations in order to be rightly reasoned upon, they
properly come under our notice here.
The principal problem of this kind which has been treated of is
this:—If in the globe of the earth there be a certain original
heat, resulting from its earlier condition, and independent of the
action of the sun, to what results will this give rise? and how far do
the observed temperatures of points below the surface lead us to such
a supposition? It has, for instance, been asserted, that in many parts
of the world the temperature, as observed in mines and other
excavations, increases in descending, at the rate of one degree
(centesimal) in about forty yards. What inference does this
justify?
The answer to this question was given by Fourier and by Laplace.
The former mathematician had already considered the problem of the
cooling of a large sphere, in his Memoirs of 1807, 1809, and 1811.
These, however, lay unpublished in the archives of the Institute for
many years. But in 1820, when the accumulation of observations which
indicated an increase of the temperature of the earth as we descend,
had drawn observation to the subject, Fourier gave, in the Bulletin of
the Philomathic Society,15 a summary of his results, as far as
they bore on this point. His conclusion was, that such an increase of
temperature in proceeding towards the centre of the earth, can arise
from nothing but the remains of a primitive heat;—that the heat
which the sun’s action would communicate, would, in its final and
148 permanent
state, be uniform in the same vertical line, as soon as we get beyond
the influence of the superficial oscillations of which we have
spoken;—and that, before the distribution of temperature reaches
this limit, it will decrease, not increase, in descending. It appeared
also, by the calculation, that this remaining existence of the
primitive heat in the interior of the earth’s mass, was quite
consistent with the absence of all perceptible traces of it at the
surface; and that the same state of things which produces an increase
of one degree of heat in descending forty yards, does not make the
surface a quarter of a degree hotter than it would otherwise be.
Fourier was led also to some conclusions, though necessarily very
vague ones, respecting the time which the earth must have taken to
cool from a supposed original state of incandescence to its present
condition, which time it appeared must have been very great; and
respecting the extent of the future cooling of the surface, which it
was shown must be insensible. Everything tended to prove that, within
the period which the history of the human race embraces, no
discoverable change of temperature had taken place from the progress
of this central cooling. Laplace further calculated the effect16 which any contraction of the globe of
the earth by cooling would produce on the length of the day. He had
already shown, by astronomical reasoning, that the day had not become
shorter by 1⁄200th of a second, since the
time of Hipparchus; and thus his inferences agreed with those of
Fourier. As far as regards the smallness of the perceptible effect due
to the past changes of the earth’s temperature, there can be no doubt
that all the curious conclusions just stated are deduced in a manner
quite satisfactory, from the fact of a general increase of heat in
descending below the surface of the earth; and thus our principles of
speculative science have a bearing upon the history of the past
changes of the universe, and give us information concerning the state
of things in portions of time otherwise quite out of our reach.
15 Bullet. des Sc. 1820, p.
58.
16 Conn. des Tems, 1823.
4. Heat of the Planetary Spaces.—In the same manner,
this portion of science is appealed to for information concerning
parts of space which are utterly inaccessible to observation. The
doctrine of heat leads to conclusions concerning the temperatures of
the spaces which surround the earth, and in which the planets of the
solar system revolve. In his Memoir, published in 1827,17 Fourier states that he conceives it to
follow from his principles, that these planetary spaces 149 are not absolutely
cold, but have a “proper heat” independent of the sun and of the
planets. If there were not such a heat, the cold of the polar regions
would be much more intense than it is, and the alternations of cold
and warmth, arising from the influence of the sun, would be far more
extreme and sudden than we find them. As the cause of this heat in the
planetary spaces, he assigns the radiation of the innumerable stars
which are scattered through the universe.
17 Mém. Inst. tom. vii. p.
580.
Fourier says,18 “We conclude from these various
remarks, and principally from the mathematical examination of the
question,” that this is so. I am not aware that the mathematical
calculation which bears peculiarly upon this point has anywhere been
published. But it is worth notice, that Svanberg has been led19 to the opinion of the same temperature
in these spaces which Fourier had adopted (50 centigrade below zero),
by an entirely different course of reasoning, founded on the relation
of the atmosphere to heat.
18 Mém. Inst. tom. vii. p.
581.
19 Berzel. Jahres Bericht, xi.
p. 50.
In speaking of this subject, I have been led to notice incomplete
and perhaps doubtful applications of the mathematical doctrine of
conduction and radiation. But this may at least serve to show that
Thermotics is a science, which, like Mechanics, is to be established
by experiments on masses capable of manipulation, but which, like
that, has for its most important office the solution of geological and
cosmological problems. I now return to the further progress of our
thermotical knowledge.
Sect. 5.—Correction of Newton’s Law of
Cooling.
In speaking of the
establishment of Newton’s assumption, that the temperature
communicated is proportional to the excess of temperature, we stated
that it was approximately verified, and afterwards corrected (chap.
i., sect. 1.). This correction was the result of the
researches of MM. Dulong and Petit in 1817, and the researches by
which they were led to the true law, are an admirable example both of
laborious experiment and sagacious induction. They experimented
through a very great range of temperature (as high as two hundred and
forty degrees centigrade), which was necessary because the inaccuracy
of Newton’s law becomes considerable only at high temperatures. They
removed the effect of the surrounding medium, by making their
experiments in a vacuum. They selected with great 150 judgment the
conditions of their experiments and comparisons, making one quantity
vary while the others remained constant. In this manner they found,
that the quickness of cooling for a constant excess of temperature,
increases in geometrical progression, when the temperature of the
surrounding space increases in arithmetical progression; whereas,
according to the Newtonian law, this quickness would not have varied
at all. Again, this variation being left out of the account, it
appeared that the quickness of cooling, so far as it depends on the
excess of temperature of the hot body, increases as the terms of a
geometrical progression diminished by a constant number, when the
temperature of the hot body increases in arithmetical progression.
These two laws, with the coefficients requisite for their application
to particular substances, fully determine the conditions of cooling in
a vacuum.
Starting from this determination, MM. Dulong and Petit proceeded to
ascertain the effect of the medium, in which the hot body is placed,
upon its rate of cooling; for this effect became a residual
phenomenon,20 when the cooling in the vacuum was
taken away. We shall not here follow this train of research; but we
may briefly state, that they were led to such laws as this;—that
the rapidity of cooling due to any gaseous medium in which the body is
placed, is the same, so long as the excess of the body’s temperature
is the same, although the temperature itself vary;—that the
cooling power of a gas varies with the elasticity, according to a
determined law; and other similar rules.
20 See Phil. Ind. Sciences, B.
xiii. c. 7, Sect. iv.
In reference to the process of their induction, it is worthy of
notice, that they founded their reasonings upon Prevost’s law of
exchanges; and that, in this way, the second of their laws above
stated, respecting the quickness of cooling, was a mathematical
consequence of the first. It may be observed also, that their
temperatures are measured by means of the air-thermometer, and that if
they were estimated on another scale, the remarkable simplicity and
symmetry of their results would disappear. This is a strong argument
for believing such a measure of temperature to have a natural
prerogative of simplicity. This belief is confirmed by other
considerations; but these, depending on the laws of expansion by heat,
cannot be here referred to; and we must proceed to finish our survey
of the mathematical theory of heat, as founded on the phenomena of
radiation and conduction, which alone have as yet been traced up to
general principles.
We may observe, before we quit this subject, that this correction
of 151 Newton’s law
will materially affect the mathematical calculations on the subject,
which were made to depend on that law both by Fourier, Laplace, and
Poisson. Probably, however, the general features of the results will
be the same as on the old supposition. M. Libri, an Italian
mathematician, has undertaken one of the problems of this kind, that
of the armil, with Dulong and Petit’s law for his basis, in a Memoir
read to the Institute of France in 1825, and since published at
Florence.21
21 Mém. de Math. et de Phys.
1829.
Sect. 6.—Other Laws of Phenomena with respect to
Radiation.
The laws of radiation as
depending upon the surface of radiating bodies, and as affecting
screens of various kinds interposed between the hot body and the
thermometer, were examined by several inquirers. I shall not attempt
to give an account of the latter course of research, and of the
different laws which luminous and non-luminous heat have been found to
follow in reference to bodies, whether transparent or opaque, which
intercept them. But there are two or three laws of the phenomena,
depending upon the effects of the surfaces of bodies, which are
important.
1. In the first place, the powers of bodies to emit and to
absorb heat, as far as depends upon their surface, appear to be
in the same proportion. If we blacken the surface of a canister of hot
water, it radiates heat more copiously; and in the same measure, it is
more readily heated by radiation.
2. In the next place, as the radiative power increases, the power
of reflection diminishes, and the contrary. A bright metal vessel
reflects much heat; on this very account it does not emit much; and
hence a hot fluid which such a vessel contains, remains hot longer
than it does in an unpolished case.
3. The heat is emitted from every point of the surface of a hot
body in all directions; but by no means in all directions with equal
intensity. The intensity of the heating ray is as the sine of the
angle which it makes with the surface.
The last law is entirely, the two former in a great measure, due to
the researches of Leslie, whose Experimental Inquiry into the
Nature and Propagation of Heat, published in 1804, contains a
great number of curious and striking results and speculations. The
laws now just 152
stated bear, in a very important manner, upon the formation of the
theory; and we must now proceed to consider what appears to have been
done in this respect; taking into account, it must still be borne in
mind, only the phenomena of conduction and radiation.
Sect. 7.—Fourier’s Theory of Radiant
Heat.
The above laws of phenomena
being established, it was natural that philosophers should seek to
acquire some conception of the physical action by which they might
account, both for these laws, and for the general fundamental facts of
Thermotics; as, for instance, the fact that all bodies placed in an
inclosed space assume, in time, the temperature of the inclosure.
Fourier’s explanation of this class of phenomena must be considered as
happy and successful; for he has shown that the supposition to which
we are led by the most simple and general of the facts, will explain,
moreover, the less obvious laws. It is an obvious and general fact,
that bodies which are included in the space tend to acquire the same
temperature. And this identity of temperature of neighboring bodies
requires an hypothesis, which, it is found, also accounts for Leslie’s
law of the sine, in radiation.
This hypothesis is, that the radiation takes place, not from the
surface alone of the hot body, but from all particles situated within
a certain small depth of the surface. It is easy to see22 that, on this supposition, a ray
emitted obliquely from an internal particle, will be less intense than
one sent forth perpendicular to the surface, because the former will
be intercepted in a greater degree, having a greater length of path
within the body; and Fourier shows, that whatever be the law of this
intercepting power, the result will be, that the radiative intensity
is as the sine of the angle made by the ray with the surface.
22 Mém. Inst. t. v. 1821, p.
204.
But this law is, as I have said, likewise necessary, in order that
neighboring bodies may tend to assume the same temperature: for
instance, in order that a small particle placed within a spherical
shell, should finally assume the temperature of the shell. If the law
of the sines did not obtain, the final temperature of such a particle
would depend upon its place in the inclosure;23 and within a
shell of ice we should have, at certain points, the temperature of
boiling water and of melting iron.
23 An. Chim. iv. 1817, p.
129.
This proposition may at first appear strange and unlikely; but it
may 153 be shown to
be a necessary consequence of the assumed principle, by very simple
reasoning, which I shall give in a general form in a Note.24
24 The following reasoning may show
the connexion of the law of the sines in radiant heat with the general
principle of ultimate identity of neighboring temperatures. The
equilibrium and identity of temperature between an including shell and
an included body, cannot obtain upon the whole, except it obtain
between each pair of parts of the two surfaces of the body and of the
shell; that is, any part of the one surface, in its exchanges with any
part of the other surface, must give and receive the same quantity of
heat. Now the quantity exchanged, so far as it depends on the
receiving surface, will, by geometry, be proportional to the sine of
the obliquity of that surface: and as, in the exchanges, each may be
considered as receiving, the quantity transferred must be proportional
to the sines of the two obliquities; that is, to that of the giving as
well as of the receiving surface.
 Nor is this conclusion disturbed by the consideration, that all
the rays of heat which fall upon a surface are not absorbed, some
being reflected according to the nature of the surface. For, by the
other above-mentioned laws of phenomena, we know that, in the same
measure in which the surface loses the power of admitting, it loses
the power of emitting, heat; and the superficial parts gain, by
absorbing their own radiation, as much as they lose by not absorbing
the incident heat; so that the result of the preceding reasoning
remains unaltered.
This reasoning is capable of being
presented in a manner quite satisfactory, by the use of mathematical
symbols, and proves that Leslie’s law of the sines is rigorously and
mathematically true on Fourier’s hypothesis. And thus Fourier’s theory
of molecular extra-radiation acquires great consistency.
Sect. 8.—Discovery of the Polarization of
Heat.
The laws of which the
discovery is stated in the preceding Sections of this Chapter, and the
explanations given of them by the theories of conduction and
radiation, all tended to make the conception of a material heat, or
caloric, communicated by an actual flow and emission, familiar
to men’s minds; and, till lately, had led the greater part of
thermotical philosophers to entertain such a view, as the most
probable opinion concerning the nature of heat. But some steps have
recently been made in thermotics, which appear to be likely to
overturn this belief, and to make the doctrine of emission as
untenable with regard to heat, as it had been found to be with regard
to light. I speak of the discovery of the polarization of heat. It
being ascertained that rays of heat are polarized in the same manner
as rays of 154
light, we cannot retain the doctrine that heat radiates by the
emanation of material particles, without supposing those particles of
caloric to have poles; an hypothesis which probably no one would
embrace; for, besides that the ill fortune which attended that
hypothesis in the case of light must deter speculators from it, the
intimate connexion of heat and light would hardly allow us to suppose
polarization in the two cases to be produced by two different kinds of
machinery.
But, without here tracing further the influence which the
polarization of heat must exercise upon the formation of our theories
of heat, we must briefly notice this important discovery, as a law of
phenomena.
The analogies and connexions between light and heat are so strong,
that when the polarization of light had been discovered, men were
naturally led to endeavor to ascertain whether heat possessed any
corresponding property. But partly from the difficulty of obtaining
any considerable effect of heat separated from light, and partly from
the want of a thermometrical apparatus sufficiently delicate, these
attempts led, for some time, to no decisive result. M. Berard took up
the subject in 1813. He used Malus’s apparatus, and conceived that he
found heat to be polarized by reflection at the surface of glass, in
the same manner as light, and with the same circumstances.25 But when Professor Powell, of Oxford, a
few years later (1830), repeated these experiments with a similar
apparatus, he found26 that though the heat which is conveyed
along with light is, of course, polarizable, “simple radiant heat,” as
he terms it, did not offer the smallest difference in the two
rectangular azimuths of the second glass, and thus showed no trace of
polarization.
25 Ann. Chim. March,
1813.
26 Edin. Journ. of Science,
1830, vol. ii. p. 303.
Thus, with the old thermometers, the point remained doubtful. But
soon after this time, MM. Melloni and Nobili invented an apparatus,
depending on certain galvanic laws, of which we shall have to speak
hereafter, which they called a thermomultiplier; and which was
much more sensitive to changes of temperature than any
previously-known instrument. Yet even with this instrument, M. Melloni
failed; and did not, at first, detect any perceptible polarization of
heat by the tourmaline;27 nor did M. Nobili,28 in repeating M.
Berard’s experiment. But in this experiment the attempt was made to
polarize heat by reflection from glass, as light is polarized: and the
quantity 155
reflected is so small that the inevitable errors might completely
disguise the whole difference in the two opposite positions. When
Prof. Forbes, of Edinburgh, (in 1834,) employed mica in the like
experiments, he found a very decided polarizing effect; first, when
the heat was transmitted through several films of mica at a certain
angle, and afterwards, when it was reflected from them. In this case,
he found that with non-luminous heat, and even with the heat of water
below the boiling point, the difference of the heating power in the
two positions of opposite polarity (parallel and crossed) was
manifest. He also detected by careful experiments,29 the polarizing effect of tourmaline.
This important discovery was soon confirmed by M. Melloni. Doubts were
suggested whether the different effect in the opposite positions might
not be due to other circumstances; but Professor Forbes easily showed
that these suppositions were inadmissible; and the property of a
difference of sides, which at first seemed so strange when
ascribed to the rays of light, also belongs, it seems to be proved, to
the rays of heat. Professor Forbes also found, by interposing a plate
of mica to intercept the ray of heat in an intermediate point, an
effect was produced in certain positions of the mica analogous to what
was called depolarization in the case of light; namely, a
partial destruction of the differences which polarization
establishes.
27 Ann. de Chimie, vol.
lv.
28 Bibliothèque
Universelle.
29 Ed. R. S. Transactions,
vol. xiv.; and Phil. Mag. 1835, vol. v. p. 209. Ib. vol. vii.
p. 349.
Before this discovery, M. Melloni had already proved by experiment
that heat is refracted by transparent substances as light is.
In the case of light, the depolarizing effect was afterwards
found to be really, as we have seen, a dipolarizing effect, the
ray being divided into two rays by double refraction. We are
naturally much tempted to put the same interpretation upon the
dipolarizing effect in the case of heat; but perhaps the assertion of
the analogy between light and heat to this extent is as yet
insecure.
It is the more necessary to be cautious in our attempt to identify
the laws of light and heat, inasmuch as along with all the
resemblances of the two agents, there are very important differences.
The power of transmitting light, the diaphaneity of bodies, is
very distinct from their power of transmitting heat, which has been
called diathermancy by M. Melloni. Thus both a plate of alum
and a plate of rock-salt transmit nearly the whole light; but while
the first stops nearly the whole heat, the second stops very little of
it; and a plate of opake 156 quartz, nearly impenetrable by light,
allows a large portion of the heat to pass. By passing the rays
through various media, the heat may be, as it were, sifted
from the light which accompanies it.
[2nd Ed.] [The diathermancy of bodies is distinct from their
diaphaneity, in so far that the same bodies do not exercise the same
powers of selection and suppression of certain rays on heat and on
light; but it appears to be proved by the investigations of modern
thermotical philosophers (MM. De la Roche, Powell, Melloni, and
Forbes), that there is a close analogy between the absorption of
certain colors by transparent bodies, and the absorption of certain
kinds of heat by diathermanous bodies. Dark sources of heat emit rays
which are analogous to blue and violet rays of light; and highly
luminous sources emit rays which are analogous to red rays. And by
measuring the angle of total reflection for heat of different kinds,
it has been shown that the former kind of calorific rays are really
less refrangible than the latter.30
30 See Prof. Forbes’s Third Series
of Researches on Heat, Edinb. R.S. Trans. vol. xiv.
M. Melloni has assumed this analogy as so completely established,
that he has proposed for this part of thermotics the name
Thermochroology (Qu. Chromothermotics?); and along with
this term, many others derived from the Greek, and founded on the same
analogy. If it should appear, in the work which he proposes to publish
on this subject, that the doctrines which he has to state cannot
easily be made intelligible without the use of the terms he suggests,
his nomenclature will obtain currency; but so large a mass of
etymological innovations is in general to be avoided in scientific
works.
M. Melloni’s discovery of the extraordinary power of
rock-salt to transmit heat, and Professor Forbes’s discovery of
the extraordinary power of mica to polarize and depolarize
heat, have supplied thermotical inquirers with two new and most
valuable instruments.31]
31 For an account of many thermotical
researches, which I have been obliged to pass unnoticed here, see two
Reports by Prof. Powell on the present state of our knowledge
respecting Radiant Heat, in the Reports of the British
Association for 1832 and 1840.
Moreover, besides the laws of conduction and radiation, many other
laws of the phenomena of heat have been discovered by philosophers;
and these must be taken into account in judging any theory of heat. To
these other laws we must now turn our attention. 157</div></body></text></TEI>