<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="14">
CHAPTER XIV.

Sound.

Besides the function which air discharges as the
great agent in the changes of meteorology and vegetation,
it has another office, also of great and extensive
importance, as the vehicle of sound.
1. The communication of sound through the air
takes place by means of a process altogether different
from anything of which we have yet spoken:
namely, by the propagation of minute vibrations of
the particles from one part of the fluid mass to another,
without any local motion of the fluid itself.
Perhaps we may most distinctly conceive the kind
of effect here spoken of, by comparing it to the motion
produced by the wind in a field of standing
corn; grassy waves travel visibly over the field, in
the direction in which the wind blows, but this appearance
of an object moving is delusive. The only
real motion is that of the ears of grain, of which
each goes and returns, as the stalk stoops and recovers
itself. This motion affects successively a line
of ears in the direction of the wind, and affects simultaneously
all those ears of which the elevation or
depression forms one visible wave. The elevations
and depressions are propagated in a constant direction,
while the parts with which the space is filled
only vibrate to and fro. Of exactly such a nature is
the propagation of sound through the air. The particles
of air go and return through very minute[97]
spaces, and this vibratory motion runs through the
atmosphere from the sounding body to the ear.
Waves, not of elevation and depression, but of condensation
and rarefaction, are transmitted; and the
sound thus becomes an object of sense to the organ.
Another familiar instance of the propagation of
vibrations we have in the circles on the surface of
smooth water, which diverge from the point where
it is touched by a small object, as a drop of rain. In
the beginning of a shower, for instance, when the
drops come distinct, though frequent, we may see
each drop giving rise to a ring, formed of two or
three close concentric circles, which grow and
spread, leaving the interior of the circles smooth,
and gradually reaching parts of the surface more
and more distant from their origin. In this instance,
it is clearly not a portion of the water which flows
onwards; but the disturbance, the rise and fall of the
surface which makes the ring-formed waves, passes
into wider and wider circles, and thus the undulation
is transmitted from its starting-place, to points in all
directions on the surface of the fluid.
The diffusion of these ring-formed undulations
from their centre resembles the diffusion of a sound
from the place where it is produced to the points
where it is heard. The disturbance, or vibration, by
which it is conveyed, travels at the same rate in all
directions, and the waves which are propagated are
hence of a circular form. They differ, however,
from those on the surface of water; for sound is
communicated upwards and downwards, and in all
intermediate directions, as well as horizontally;
hence the waves of sound are spherical, the point
where the sound is produced being the centre of the
sphere.
This diffusion of vibrations in spherical shells of
successive condensation and rarefaction, will easily
be seen to be different from any local motion of the
air, as wind, and to be independent of that. The circles
on the surface of water will spread on a river[98]
which is flowing, provided it be smooth, as well as
on a standing canal.
Not only are such undulations propagated almost
undisturbed by any local motion of the fluid in which
they take place, but also, many may be propagated
in the same fluid at the same time, without disturbing
each other. We may see this effect on water. When
several drops fall near each other, the circles which
they produce cross each other, without either of
them being lost, and the separate courses of the
rings may still be traced.
All these consequences, both in water, in air, and
in any other fluid, can be very exactly investigated
upon mechanical principles, and the greater part of
the phenomena can thus be shown to result from the
properties of the fluids.
There are several remarkable circumstances in
the way in which air answers its purpose as the vehicle
of sound, of which we will now point out a few.
2. The loudness of sound is such as is convenient
for common purposes. The organs of speech can, in
the present constitution of the air, produce, without
fatigue, such a tone of voice as can be heard with
distinctness and with comfort. That any great alteration
in this element might be incommodious, we
may judge from the difficulties to which persons are
subject who are dull of hearing, and from the disagreeable
effects of a voice much louder than usual,
or so low as to be indistinct. Sounds produced by
the human organs, with other kinds of air, are very
different from those in our common air. If a man
inhale a quantity of hydrogen gas, and then speak,
his voice is scarcely audible.
The loudness of sounds become smaller in proportion
as they come from a greater distance. This
enables us to judge of the distance of objects, in
some degree at least, by the sounds which proceed
from them. Moreover, it is found that we can judge
of the position of objects by the ear: and this judgment
seems to be formed by comparing the loudness[99]
of the impression of the same sound on the two ears
and two sides of the head.[14]
The loudness of sounds appears to depend on the
extent of vibration of the particles of air, and this is
determined by the vibrations of the sounding body.
3. The pitch, or the differences of acute and grave,
in sounds, form another important property, and one
which fits them for a great part of their purposes.
By the succession of different notes, we have all the
results of melody and harmony in musical sound;
and of intonation and modulation of the voice, of
accent, cadence, emphasis, expression, passion, in
speech. The song of birds, which is one of their
principal modes of communication, depends chiefly
for its distinctions and its significance upon the combinations
of acute and grave.
These differences are produced by the different
rapidity of vibration of the particles of air. The
gravest sound has about eighty vibrations in a second,
the most acute about one thousand. Between these
limits each sound has a musical character, and from
the different relations of the number of vibrations in
a second arise all the differences of musical intervals,
concords and discords.
4. The quality of sounds is another of their differences.
This is the name given to the difference of
notes of the same pitch, that is the same note as to
acute and grave, when produced by different instruments.
If a flute and a violin be in unison, the notes
are still quite different sounds. It is this kind of difference
which distinguishes the voice of one man
from that of another: and it is manifestly therefore
one of great consequence; since it connects the
voice with the particular person, and is almost necessary
in order that language may be a medium of
intercourse between men.
5. The articulate character of sounds is for us one
of the most important arrangements which exist in[100]
the world; for it is by this that they become the interpreters
of thought, will and feeling, the means
by which a person can convey his wants, his instructions,
his promises, his kindness, to others;
by which one man can regulate the actions and influence
the convictions and judgments of another.
It is in virtue of the possibility of shaping air into
words, that the imperceptible vibrations which a
man produces in the atmosphere, become some of
his most important actions; the foundations of the
highest moral and social relations; and the condition
and instrument of all the advancement and improvement
of which he is susceptible.
It appears that the differences of articulate sound
arise from the different form of the cavity through
which the sound is made to proceed immediately
after being produced. In the human voice the sound
is produced in the larynx, and modified by the cavity
of the mouth, and the various organs which surround
this cavity. The laws by which articulate sounds are
thus produced have not yet been fully developed,
but appear to be in the progress of being so.
The properties of sounds which have been mentioned,
differences of loudness, of pitch, of quality,
and articulation, appear to be all requisite in order
that sound shall answer its purposes in the economy
of animal and of human life. And how was the air
made capable of conveying these four differences, at
the same time that the organs were made capable of
producing them? Surely by a most refined and skilful
adaptation, applied with a most comprehensive
design.
6. Again; is it by chance that the air and the ear
exist together? Did the air produce the organization
of the ear? or the ear, independently organized, anticipate
the constitution of the atmosphere? Or is
not the only intelligible account of the matter, this,
that one was made for the other: that there is a mutual
adaptation produced by an Intelligence which
was acquainted with the properties of both; which[101]
adjusted them to each other as we find them adjusted,
in order that birds might communicate by song,
that men might speak and hear, and that language
might play its extraordinary part in its operation
upon men’s thoughts, actions, institutions, and fortunes?
The vibrations of an elastic fluid like the air, and
their properties, follow from the laws of motion; and
whether or not these laws of the motion of fluids
might in reality have been other than they are, they
appear to us inseparably connected with the existence
of matter, and as much a thing of necessity as we
can conceive any thing in the universe to be. The
propagation of such vibrations, therefore, and their
properties, we may at present allow to be a necessary
part of the constitution of the atmosphere. But
what is it that makes these vibrations become sound?
How is it that they produce such an effect on our
senses, and, through those, on our minds? The vibrations
of the air seem to be of themselves no more
fitted to produce sound, than to produce smell. We
know that such vibrations do not universally produce
sound, but only between certain limits. When the
vibrations are fewer than eighty in a second, they
are perceived as separate throbs, and not as a continued
sound; and there is a certain limit of rapidity,
beyond which the vibrations become inaudible. This
limit is different to different ears, and we are thus
assured by one person’s ear that there are vibrations,
though to that of another they do not produce sound.
How was the human ear adapted so that its perception
of vibrations as sounds should fall within these
limits?—the very limits within which the vibrations
fall, which it most concerns us to perceive: those of
the human voice for instance? How nicely are the
organs adjusted with regard to the most minute mechanical
motions of the elements?
</div></body></text></TEI>