<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="42">INTRODUCTION.
THE mathematical opinions of
Plato respecting the philosophy of nature, and especially respecting
what we commonly call “the heavenly bodies,” the Sun, Moon, and
Planets, were founded upon the view which I have already described:
namely, that it is the business of philosophy to aim at a truth higher
than observation can teach; and to solve problems which the phenomena
of the universe only suggest. And though the students of nature in
more recent times have learnt that this is too presumptuous a notion
of human knowledge, yet the very boldness and hopefulness which it
involved impelled men in the pursuit of truth, with more vigor than a
more timorous temper could have done; and the belief that there must
be, in nature, mathematical laws more exact than experience could
discover, stimulated men often to discover true laws, though often
also to invent false laws. Plato’s writings, supplying examples of
both these processes, belong to the Prelude of true Astronomy, as well
as to the errors of false philosophy. We may find specimens of both
kinds in those parts of his Dialogues to which we have referred in the
preceding Book of our History.
To Plato’s merits in preparing the way for the Theory of Epicycles,
I have already referred in Chapter ii. of
this Book. I conceive that he had a great share in that which is an
important step in every discovery, the proposing distinctly the
problem to be solved; which was, in this case, as he states it, To
account for the apparent movements of the planets by a combination of
two circular motions for each:—the motion of identity, and the
motion of difference. (Tim. 39, a.) In
the tenth Book of the Republic, quoted in our text, the spindle
which Destiny or Necessity holds between her knees, and on which are
rings, by means of which the planets revolve round it as an axis, is a
step towards the conception of the problem, as the construction of a
machine.
It will not be thought surprising that Plato expected that 504 Astronomy, when
further advanced, would be able to render an account of many things
for which she has not accounted even to this day. Thus, in the passage
in the seventh Book of the Republic, he says that the
philosopher requires a reason for the proportion of the day to the
month, and the month to the year, deeper and more substantial than
mere observation can give. Yet Astronomy has not yet shown us any
reason why the proportion of the times of the earth’s rotation on its
axis, the moon’s revolution round the earth, and the earth’s
revolution round the sun, might not have been made by the Creator
quite different from what they are. But in thus asking Mathematical
Astronomy for reasons which she cannot give, Plato was only doing what
a great astronomical discoverer, Kepler, did at a later period. One of
the questions which Kepler especially wished to have answered was, why
there are five planets, and why at such particular distances from the
sun? And it is still more curious that he thought he had found the
reason of these things, in the relations of those Five Regular Solids
which, as we have seen, Plato was desirous of
introducing into the philosophy of the universe. We have Kepler’s
account of this, his imaginary discovery, in the Mysterium
Cosmographicum, published in 1596, as stated in our History, Book
v. Chap. iv. Sect. 2.
Kepler regards the law which thus determines the number and
magnitude of the planetary orbits by means of the five regular solids
as a discovery no less remarkable and certain than the Three Laws
which give his name its imperishable place in the history of
astronomy.
We are not on this account to think that there is no steady
criterion of the difference between imaginary and real discoveries in
science. As discovery becomes possible by the liberty of guessing, it
becomes real by allowing observation constantly and authoritatively to
determine the value of guesses. Kepler added to Plato’s boldness of
fancy his own patient and candid habit of testing his fancies by a
rigorous and laborious comparison with the phenomena; and thus his
discoveries led to those of Newton. 505</div></body></text></TEI>