<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol I</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1794</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="5">SECT. V.
OF THE FOUR FACULTIES OR MOTIONS OF THE SENSORIUM.

1. Four sensorial powers. 2. Irritation, sensation, volition, association
  defined. 3. Sensorial motions
  distinguished from fibrous motions.

1. The spirit of animation has four different
  modes of action, or in other words the animal sensorium possesses four
  different faculties, which are occasionally exerted, and cause all the
  contractions of the fibrous parts of the body. These are the faculty of
  causing fibrous contractions in consequence of the irritations excited by
  external bodies, in consequence of the sensations of pleasure or pain, in
  consequence of volition, and in consequence of the associations of
  fibrous contractions with other fibrous contractions, which precede or
  accompany them.
These four faculties of the sensorium during their inactive state are
  termed irritability, sensibility, voluntarity, and associability; in
  their active state they are termed as above, irritation, sensation,
  volition, association.
2. IRRITATION is an
  exertion or change of some extreme part of the sensorium residing in the
  muscles or organs of sense, in consequence of the appulses of external
  bodies.
SENSATION is an exertion or change of the
  central parts of the sensorium, or of the whole of it, beginning
  at some of those extreme parts of it, which reside in the muscles or
  organs of sense.
VOLITION is an exertion or change of the
  central parts of the sensorium, or of the whole of it, terminating
  in some of those extreme parts of it, which reside in the muscles or
  organs of sense.
ASSOCIATION is an exertion or change of some
  extreme part of the sensorium residing in the muscles or organs of sense,
  in consequence of some antecedent or attendant fibrous contractions.
3. These four faculties of the animal sensorium
  may at the time of their exertions be termed motions without impropriety
  of language; for we cannot pass from a state of insensibility or inaction
  to a state of sensibility or of exertion without some change of the
  sensorium, and every change includes motion. We shall therefore sometimes
  term the above described faculties sensorial motions to
  distinguish them from fibrous motions; which latter expression
  includes the motions of the muscles and organs of sense.
The active motions of the fibres, whether those of the muscles or
  organs of sense, are probably simple contractions; the fibres being again
  elongated by antagonist muscles, by circulating fluids, or sometimes by
  elastic ligaments, as in the necks of quadrupeds. The sensorial motions,
  which constitute the sensations of pleasure or pain, and which constitute
  volition, and which cause the fibrous contractions in consequence of
  irritation or of association, are not here supposed to be fluctuations or
  refluctuations of the spirit of animation; nor are they supposed to be
  vibrations or revibrations, nor condensations or equilibrations of it;
  but to be changes or motions of it peculiar to life.

</div></body></text></TEI>