<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 165, folios 19-20</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 165, folios 19-20.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1835">9 October 1835</date>
          <note type="place">Southhampton</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 165, folios 19-20</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_165_folios_19-20.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Southampton Friday Evening, 9th Octr. 1835.</p>
      <p>My Own Dearest. If I could only impart to you how happy it makes the poor Bird to receive your letters, long or short, you would be quite happy. The poor thing feels grateful even for a few lines, from her dear cock.--</p>
      <p>I have been riding today in a fair interval, for it has been rainy. I hope</p>
      <p>that you have had better weather for your Germany.--</p>
      <p>My Hen objects to my walking at all, at present. In this stage of the business she thinks that kind of exercise hazardous for me. This will not be the case at a later period she says.</p>
      <p>She thinks my cold was connected with the commencement of the hatching, &amp; was not of an ordinary nature. It must have been about that time that I began to be a "hatch-bird".--</p>
      <p>Tomorrow is no-post day, so</p>
      <p>that I cannot write. If I were to write to you on Sunday, you might get it at Ockham on Tuesday; but as I do not know what hour you purpose having it, &amp; also hope to see you that evening, I think I shall not write to you again. But I should like to hear from you on Tuesday Mrng, as on all other possible mornings.--</p>
      <p>The Siddons's go on Tuesday so that we three shall be alone. I hope you &amp; the Hen won't take to abusing the Bird.-- I went to</p>
      <p>the Ladies Committee for the Prison Discipline this morning. It is quite in its infancy as yet.-- It was too damp for the Hen to venture out today.--</p>
      <p>I want my Cock at night, to keep me warm.--</p>
      <p>And now, my dearest, I shall wish you Good Bye, &amp; you must believe me,</p>
      <p>Most affecy, The Little Bird. A. A. K.</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
