<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="61">INTRODUCTION.
Formal and Physical Optics.
THE history of the science of
Optics, written at length, would be  very voluminous; but we shall not
need to make our history so; since our main object is to illustrate
the nature of science and the conditions of its progress. In this way
Optics is peculiarly instructive; the more so, as its history has
followed a course in some respects different from both the sciences
previously reviewed. Astronomy, as we have seen, advanced with a
steady and continuous movement from one generation to another, from
the earliest time, till her career was crowned by the great unforeseen
discovery of Newton; Acoustics had her extreme generalization in view
from the first, and her history consists in the correct application of
it to successive problems; Optics advanced through a scale of
generalizations as remarkable as those of Astronomy; but for a long
period she was almost stationary; and, at last, was rapidly impelled
through all those stages by the energy of two or three discoverers.
The highest point of generality which Optics has reached is little
different from that which Acoustics occupied at once; but in the older
and earlier science we still want that palpable and pointed
confirmation of the general principle, which the undulatory theory
receives from optical phenomena. Astronomy has amassed her vast
fortune by long-continued industry and labor; Optics has obtained hers
in a few years by sagacious and happy speculations; Acoustics, having
early acquired a competence, has since been employed rather in
improving and adorning than in extending her estate.
The successive inductions by which Optics made her advances, might,
of course, be treated in the same manner as those of Astronomy, each
having its prelude and its sequel. But most of the discoveries in
Optics are of a smaller character, and have less employed the minds of
men, than those of Astronomy; and it will not be necessary to exhibit
them in this detailed manner, till we come to the great generalization
by which the theory was established. I shall, therefore, now pass
rapidly in review the earlier optical discoveries, without any such
division of the series. 52
Optics, like Astronomy, has for its object of inquiry, first, the
laws of phenomena, and next, their causes; and we may hence divide
this science, like the other, into Formal Optics and
Physical Optics. The distinction is clear and substantive, but
it is not easy to adhere to it in our narrative; for, after the theory
had begun to make its rapid advance, many of the laws of phenomena
were studied and discovered in immediate reference to the theoretical
cause, and do not occupy a separate place in the history of science,
as in Astronomy they do. We may add, that the reason why Formal
Astronomy was almost complete before Physical Astronomy began to
exist, was, that it was necessary to construct the science of
Mechanics in the mean time, in order to be able to go on; whereas, in
Optics, mathematicians were able to calculate the results of the
undulatory theory as soon as it had suggested itself from the earlier
facts, and while the great mass of facts were only becoming known.
We shall, then, in the first nine chapters of the History of
Optics treat of the Formal Science, that is, the discovery of the laws
of phenomena. The classes of phenomena which will thus pass under oar
notice are numerous; namely, reflection, refraction, chromatic
dispersion, achromatization, double refraction, polarization,
dipolarization, the colors of thin plates, the colors of thick plates,
and the fringes and bands which accompany shadows. All these cases had
been studied, and, in most of them, the laws had been in a great
measure discovered, before the physical theory of the subject gave to
our knowledge a simpler and more solid form.

FORMAL OPTICS.
</div></body></text></TEI>