<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="20"> 

CHAPTER X.
Of the Induction of Causes.


Aphorism LX.
In the Induction of Causes the principal Maxim is, that
we must be careful to possess, and to apply, with perfect
clearness, the Fundamental Idea on which the Induction depends.
Aphorism LXI.
The Induction of Substance, of Force, of Polarity, go
beyond mere laws of phenomena, and may be considered as
the Induction of Causes.
Aphorism LXII.
The Cause of certain phenomena being inferred, we are
led to inquire into the Cause of this Cause, which inquiry
must be conducted in the same manner as the previous one;
and thus we have the Induction of Ulterior Causes.
Aphorism LXIII.
In contemplating the series of Causes which are themselves
the effects of other causes, we are necessarily led to assume a
Supreme Cause in the Order of Causation, as we assume a
First Cause in Order of Succession.

1. WE
formerly53
stated the objects of the researches
of Science to be Laws of Phenomena and
Causes; and showed the propriety and the necessity of
not resting in the former object, but extending our 248
inquiries to the latter also. Inductions, in which phenomena
are connected by relations of Space, Time,
Number and Resemblance, belong to the former class;
and of the Methods applicable to such Inductions we
have treated already. In proceeding to Inductions
governed by any ulterior Ideas, we can no longer lay
down any Special Methods by which our procedure
may be directed. A few general remarks are all that
we shall offer.</div></body></text></TEI>