<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Chambers Robert</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="10">p. 125ERA
OF THE TERTIARY FORMATION.—
MAMMALIA ABUNDANT.
The chalk-beds are the highest
which extend over a considerable space; but in hollows of these
beds, comparatively limited in extent, there have been formed
series of strata—clays, limestones, marls,
alternating—to which the name of the Tertiary
Formation has been applied.  London and Paris alike rest
on basins of this formation, and another such basin extends from
near Winchester, under Southampton, and re-appears in the Isle of
Wight.  There is a patch, or fragment of the formation in
one of the Hebrides.  A stripe of it extends along the east
coast of North America, from Massachusetts to Florida.  It
is also found in Sicily and Italy, insensibly blended with
formations still in progress.  Though comparatively a local
formation, it is not of the less importance as a record of the
condition of the earth during a certain period.  As in other
formations, it is marked, in the most distant localities, by
identity of organic remains.
The hollows filled by the tertiary formation must be
considered as the beds of estuaries left at the conclusion of the
cretaceous period.  We have seen that an estuary, either by
the drifting up of its mouth, or a change of level in that
quarter, may be supposed to have become an inland sheet of water,
and that, by another change, of the reverse kind, it may be
supposed to have become an estuary again.  Such changes the
Paris basin appears to have undergone oftener than once, for,
first, we have there a fresh-water formation of clay and
limestone beds; then, a marine-limestone formation; next, a
second fresh water formation, in which the material of the
celebrated plaster of Paris (gypsum) is included; then, a
second marine formation of sandy and limy beds; and finally, a
third series of fresh-water strata.  Such alternations occur
in other examples of the tertiary formation likewise.
The tertiary beds present all but an entirely new set of
animals, and as we ascend in the series, we find more and more of
these identical with species still existing upon earth, as if we
had now reached the dawn of the present state of the zoology of
our planet.  By the study of the shells alone, Mr. Lyell has
been enabled to divide the whole term into four sub-periods, to
which he has given names with reference to the proportions which
they respectively present of surviving species—first, the
eocene, (from ’ηως, the dawn;
χαινος, recent;) second, the
miocene, (μειων, less;) third, older
pliocene, (πλειων, more;) fourth,
newer pliocene.
EOCENE SUB-PERIOD.
The eocene period presents, in three continental groups, 1238
species of shells, of which forty-two, or 3.5 per cent, yet
flourish.  Some of these are remarkable enough; but they all
sink into insignificance beside the mammalian remains which the
lower eocene deposits of the Paris basin present to us, shewing
that the land had now become the theatre of an extensive creation
of the highest class of animals.  Cuvier ascertained about
fifty species of these, all of them long since extinct.  A
considerable number are pachydermata, [127] of a character approximating to the
South American tapir: the names, palæotherium,
anthracotherium, anoplotherium, lophiodon, &c., have been
applied to them with a consideration of more or less conspicuous
peculiarities; but a description of the first may give some
general idea of the whole.  It was about the size of a
horse, but more squat and clumsy, and with a heavier head, and a
lower jaw shorter than the upper; the feet, also, instead of
hooves, presented three large toes, rounded, and unprovided with
claws.  These animals were all herbivorous.  Amongst an
immense number of others are found many new reptiles, some of
them adapted for fresh water; species of birds allied to the
sea-lark, curlew, quail, buzzard, owl, and pelican; species
allied to the dormouse and squirrel; also the opossum and racoon;
and species allied to the genette, fox, and wolf.
MIOCENE SUB-PERIOD.
In the miocene sub-period, the shells give eighteen per cent.
of existing species, shewing a considerable advance from the
preceding era, with respect to the inhabitants of the sea. 
The advance in the land animals is less marked, but yet
considerable.  The predominating forms are still
pachydermatous, and the tapir type continues to be
conspicuous.  One animal of this kind, called the
dinotherium, is supposed to have been not less than
eighteen feet long; it had a mole-like form of the
shoulder-blade, conferring the power of digging for food, and a
couple of tusks turning down from the lower jaw, by which it
could have attached itself, like the walrus, to a shore or bank,
while its body floated in the water.  Dr. Buckland considers
this and some similar miocene animals, as adapted for a
semi-aquatic life, in a region where lakes abounded. 
Besides the tapirs, we have in this era animals allied to the
glutton, the bear, the dog, the horse, the hog, and lastly,
several felinæ, (creatures of which the lion is the type;)
all of which are new forms, as far as we know.  There was
also an abundance of marine mammalia, seals, dolphins, lamantins,
walruses, and whales, none of which had previously appeared.
PLIOCENE SUB-PERIOD.
The shells of the older pliocene give from thirty-five to
fifty; those of the newer, from ninety to ninety-five per cent.
of existing species.  The pachydermata of the preceding era
now disappear, and are replaced by others belonging to still
existing families—elephant, hippopotamus,
rhinoceros—though now extinct as species.  Some of
these are startling, from their enormous magnitude.  The
great mastodon, whose remains are found in abundance in America,
was a species of elephant, judged, from peculiarities of its
teeth, to have lived on aquatic plants, and reaching the height
of twelve feet.  The mammoth was another elephant, but
supposed to have survived till comparatively recent times, as a
specimen, in all respects entire, was found in 1801, preserved in
ice, in Siberia.  We are more surprised by finding such
gigantic proportions in an animal called the megatherium, which
ranks in an order now assuming much humbler forms—the
edentata—to which the sloth, ant-eater, and armadillo
belong.  The megatherium had a skeleton of enormous
solidity, with an armour-clad body, and five toes, terminating in
huge claws, wherewith to grasp the branches, from which, like its
existing congener, the sloth, it derived its food.  The
megalonyx was a similar animal, only somewhat less than the
preceding.  Finally, the pliocene gives us for the first
time, oxen, deer, camels, and other specimens of the
ruminantia.
Such is an outline of the fauna of the tertiary era, as
ascertained by the illustrious naturalists who first devoted
their attention to it.  It will be observed that it brings
us up to the felinæ, or carnivora, a considerably elevated
point in the animal scale, but still leaving a blank for the
quadrumana (monkeys) and for man, who collectively form, as will
be afterwards seen, the first group in that scale.  It
sometimes happens, however, as we have seen, that a few rare
traces of a particular class of animals are in time found in
formations originally thought to be destitute of them, displaying
as it were a dawn of that department of creation.  Such
seems to be the case with at least the quadrumana.  A
jaw-bone and tooth of an animal of this order, and belonging to
the genus macacus, were found in the London clay, (eocene,) at
Kyson, near Woodbridge, in 1839.  Another jaw-bone,
containing several teeth, supposed to have belonged to a species
of monkey about three feet high, was discovered about the same
time in a stratum of marl surmounted by compact limestone, in the
department of Gers, at the foot of the Pyrenees.  Associated
with this last were remains of not less than thirty mammiferous
quadrupeds, including three species of rhinoceros, a large
anoplotherium, three species of deer, two antelopes, a true dog,
a large cat, an animal like a weasel, a small hare, and a huge
species of the edentata.  Both of these places are
considerably to the north of any region now inhabited by the
monkey tribes.  Fossil remains of quadrumana have been found
in at least two other parts of the earth,—namely, the
sub-Himalayan hills, near the Sutlej, and in Brazil, (both in the
tertiary strata;) the first being a large species of
semnopithecus, and the second, a still larger animal belonging to
the American group of monkeys, but a new genus, and denominated
by its discoverer, Dr. Lund, protopithecus.  The latter
would be four feet in height.
One remarkable circumstance connected with the tertiary
formation remains to be noticed,—namely, the prevalence of
volcanic action at that era.  In Auvergne, in Catalonia,
near Venice, and in the vicinity of Rome and Naples, lavas
exactly resembling the produce of existing volcanoes, are
associated and intermixed with the lacustrine as well as marine
tertiaries.  The superficies of tertiaries in England is
disturbed by two great swells, forming what are called anticlinal
axes, one of which divides the London from the Hampshire basin,
while the other passes through the Isle of Wight, both throwing
the strata down at violent inclination towards the north, as if
the subterranean disturbing force had waved forward in
that direction.  The Pyrenees, too, and Alps, have both
undergone elevation since the deposition of the tertiaries; and
in Sicily there are mountains which have risen three thousand
feet since the deposition of some of the most recent of these
rocks.  The general effect of these operations was of course
to extend the land surface, and to increase the variety of its
features, thus improving the natural drainage, and generally
adapting the earth for the reception of higher classes of
animals.</div></body></text></TEI>