<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="14">CHAPTER XIV.
Division of the subject into changes of the organic and inorganic world—Inorganic
causes of change divided into aqueous and igneous—Aqueous causes first
considered—Fall of rain—Recent rain-prints in mud—Destroying and transporting
power of running water—Newly formed valleys in Georgia—Sinuosities
of rivers—Two streams when united do not occupy a bed of double surface—Inundations
in Scotland—Floods caused by landslips in the White
Mountains—Bursting
of a lake in Switzerland—Devastations caused by the Anio at
Tivoli—Excavations in the lavas of Etna by Sicilian rivers—Gorge of the
Simeto—Gradual recession of the cataract of Niagara.
Division of the subject.—Geology was defined to be the science
which investigates the former changes that have taken place in the
organic as well as in the inorganic kingdoms of nature. As vicissitudes
in the inorganic world are most apparent, and as on them all fluctuations
in the animate creation must in a great measure depend, they
may claim our first consideration. The great agents of change in the
inorganic world may be divided into two principal classes, the aqueous
and the igneous. To the aqueous belong Rain, Rivers, Torrents,
Springs, Currents, and Tides; to the igneous, Volcanoes, and Earthquakes.
Both these classes are instruments of decay as well as of
reproduction; but they may also be regarded as antagonist forces.
For the aqueous agents are incessantly laboring to reduce the inequalities
of the earth's surface to a level; while the igneous are equally
active in restoring the unevenness of the external crust, partly by heaping
up new matter in certain localities, and partly by depressing one
portion, and forcing out another, of the earth's envelope.
It is difficult, in a scientific arrangement, to give an accurate view
of the combined effects of so many forces in simultaneous operation;
because, when we consider them separately, we cannot easily estimate
either the extent of their efficacy, or the kind of results which they
produce. We are in danger, therefore, when we attempt to examine
the influence exerted singly by each, of overlooking the modifications
which they produce on one another; and these are so complicated,
that sometimes the igneous and aqueous forces co-operate to produce
a joint effect, to which neither of them unaided by the other could
199
give rise,—as when repeated earthquakes unite with running water
to widen a valley; or when a thermal spring rises up from a great
depth, and conveys the mineral ingredients with which it is impregnated
from the interior of the earth to the surface. Sometimes the
organic combine with the inorganic causes; as when a reef, composed
of shells and corals, protects one line of coast from the destroying
power of tides or currents, and turns them against some other point;
or when drift timber, floated into a lake, fills a hollow to which the
stream would not have had sufficient velocity to convey earthy sediment.
It is necessary, however, to divide our observations on these various
causes, and to classify them systematically, endeavoring as much as
possible to keep in view that the effects in nature are mixed and not
simple, as they may appear in an artificial arrangement.
In treating, in the first place, of the aqueous causes, we may consider
them under two divisions; first, those which are connected with
the circulation of water from the land to the sea, under which are included
all the phenomena of rain, rivers, glaciers, and springs; secondly,
those which arise from the movements of water in lakes, seas, and
the ocean, wherein are comprised the phenomena of waves, tides, and
currents. In turning our attention to the former division, we find that
the effects of rivers may be subdivided into, first, those of a destroying
and transporting, and, secondly, those of a renovating nature; in the
former are included the erosion of rocks and the transportation of matter
to lower levels; in the renovating class, the formation of deltas by
the influx of sediment, and the shallowing of seas; but these processes
are so intimately related to each other, that it will not always be possible
to consider them under their separate heads.
Fall of Rain.—It is well known that the capacity of the atmosphere
to absorb aqueous vapor, and hold it in suspension, increases with every
increment of temperature. This capacity is also found to augment in a
higher ratio than the augmentation of the heat. Hence, as was first
suggested by the geologist, Dr. Hutton, when two volumes of air, of
different temperatures, both saturated with moisture, mingle together,
clouds and rain are produced, for a mean degree of heat having resulted
from the union of the two moist airs, the excess of vapor previously
held in suspension by the warmer of the two is given out, and if it be in
sufficient abundance is precipitated in the form of rain.
As the temperature of the atmosphere diminishes gradually from the
equator towards the pole, the evaporation of water and the quantity of
rain diminish also. According to Humboldt's computation, the average
annual depth of rain at the equator is 96 inches, while in lat. 45°
it is only 29 inches, and in lat. 60° not more than 17 inches. But
there are so many disturbing causes, that the actual discharge, in any
given locality, may deviate very widely from this rule. In England, for
example, where the average fall at London is 24½ inches, as ascertained
at the Greenwich Observatory, there is such irregularity in some districts,
200
that while at Whitehaven, in Cumberland, there fell in 1849, 32
inches, the quantity of rain in Borrowdale, near Keswick (only 15 miles
to the westward), was no less than 142 inches!262 In like manner, in
India, Colonel Sykes found by observations made in 1847 and 1848,
that at places situated between 17° and 18° north lat., on a line drawn
across the Western Ghauts in the Deccan, the fall of rain varied from
21 to 219 inches.263 The annual average in Bengal is probably below
80 inches, yet Dr. G. Hooker witnessed at Churrapoonjee, in the year
1850, a fall of 30 inches in 24 hours, and in the same place during a
residence of six months (from June to November) 530 inches! This
occurred on the south face of the Khasia (or Garrow) mountains in
Eastern Bengal (see map, Chap. XVIII.), where the depth during the
whole of the same year probably exceeded 600 inches. So extraordinary
a discharge of water, which, as we shall presently see, is very local,
may be thus accounted for. Warm, southerly winds, blowing over
the Bay of Bengal, and becoming laden with vapor during their passage,
reach the low level delta of the Ganges and Brahmapootra, where
the ordinary heat exceeds that of the sea, and where evaporation is constantly
going on from countless marshes and the arms of the great
rivers. A mingling of two masses of damp air of different temperatures
probably causes the fall of 70 or 80 inches of rain, which takes place
on the plains. The monsoon having crossed the delta, impinges on the
Khasia mountains, which rise abruptly from the plain to a mean elevation
of between 4000 and 5000 feet. Here the wind not only encounters
the cold air of the mountains, but, what is far more effective as a
refrigerating cause, the aerial current is made to flow upwards, and to
ascend to a height of several thousand feet above the sea. Both the
air and the vapor contained in it, being thus relieved of much atmospheric
pressure, expand suddenly, and are cooled by rarefaction. The
vapor is condensed, and about 500 inches of rain are thrown down annually,
nearly twenty times as much as falls in Great Britain in a year,
and almost all of it poured down in six months. The channel of every
torrent and river is swollen at this season, and much sandstone horizontally
stratified, and other rocks are reduced to sand and gravel by the
flooded streams. So great is the superficial waste (or denudation), that
what would otherwise be a rich and luxuriantly wooded region, is converted
into a wild and barren moorland.
After the current of warm air has been thus drained of a large portion
of its moisture, it still continues its northerly course to the opposite
flank of the Khasia range, only 20 miles farther north, and here the
fall of rain is reduced to 70 inches in the year. The same wind then
blows northwards across the valley of the Brahmapootra, and at length
arrives so dry and exhausted at the Bhootan Himalaya (lat. 28° N.), that
those mountains, up to the height of 5000 feet, are naked and sterile,
and all their outer valleys arid and dusty. The aerial current still continuing
201
its northerly course and ascending to a higher region, becomes
further cooled, condensation again ensues, and Bhootan, above 5000
feet, is densely clothed with vegetation.264
In another part of India, immediately to the westward, similar phenomena
are repeated. The same warm and humid winds, copiously
charged with aqueous vapor from the Bay of Bengal, hold their course
due north for 300 miles across the flat and hot plains of the Ganges,
till they encounter the lofty Sikkim mountains. (See map, Chap.
XVIII.) On the southern flank of these they discharge such a deluge
of rain that the rivers in the rainy season rise twelve feet in as many
hours. Numerous landslips, some of them extending three or four
thousand feet along the face of the mountains, composed of granite,
gneiss, and slate, descend into the beds of streams, and dam them up
for a time, causing temporary lakes, which soon burst their barriers.
"Day and night," says Dr. Hooker, "we heard the crashing of falling
trees, and the sound of boulders thrown violently against each other in
the beds of torrents. By such wear and tear rocky fragments swept
down from the hills are in part converted into sand and fine mud; and
the turbid Ganges, during its annual inundation, derives more of its
sediment from this source than from the waste of the fine clay of the
alluvial plains below.265
On the verge of the tropics a greater quantity of rain falls annually
than at the equator. Yet parts even of the tropical latitudes are entirely
destitute of rain: Peru, for example, which owes its vegetation
solely to rivers and nightly dews. In that country easterly winds prevail,
blowing from the Pacific, and these being intercepted by the Andes,
and cooled as they rise, are made to part with all their moisture before
reaching the low region to the leeward. The desert zone of North
Africa, between lat. 15° and 30° N., is another instance of a rainless
region. Five or six consecutive years may pass in Upper Egypt, Nubia,
and Dongola, or in the Desert of Sahara, without rain.
From the facts above mentioned, the reader will infer that in the
course of successive geological periods there will be great variations in
the quantity of rain falling in one and the same region. At one time
there may be none whatever during the whole year; at another a fall
of 100 or 500 inches; and these two last averages may occur on the
two opposite flanks of a mountain-chain, not more than 20 miles wide.
While, therefore, the valleys in one district are widened and deepened
annually, they may remain stationary in another, the superficial soil
being protected from waste by a dense covering of vegetation. This
diversity depends on many geographical circumstances, but principally
on the height of the land above the sea, the direction of the prevailing
winds, and the relative position, at the time being, of the plains, hills,
and the ocean, conditions all of which are liable in the course of ages to
undergo a complete revolution.
202
Recent rain-prints.—When examining, in 1842, the extensive mud-flats
of Nova Scotia, which are exposed at low tide on the borders of
the Bay of Fundy, I observed not only the foot-prints of birds which
had recently passed over the mud, but also very distinct impressions of
rain-drops. A peculiar combination of circumstances renders these
mud-flats admirably fitted to receive and retain any markings which
may happen to be made on their surface. The sediment with which
the waters are charged is extremely fine, being derived from the destruction
of cliffs of red sandstone and shale, and as the tides rise fifty feet
and upwards, large areas are laid dry for nearly a fortnight between the
spring and neap tides. In this interval the mud is baked in summer
by a hot sun, so that it solidifies and becomes traversed by cracks,
caused by shrinkage. Portions of the hardened mud between these
cracks may then be taken up and removed without injury. On examining
the edges of each slab, we observe numerous layers, formed by
successive tides, each layer being usually very thin, sometimes only
one-tenth of an inch thick. When a shower of rain falls, the highest
portion of the mud-covered flat is usually too hard to receive any impressions;
while that recently uncovered by the tide near the water's
edge is too soft. Between these areas a zone occurs, almost as smooth
and even as a looking-glass, on which every drop forms a cavity of circular
or oval form, and, if the shower be transient, these pits retain
their shape permanently, being dried by the sun, and being then too
firm to be effaced by the action of the succeeding tide, which deposits
upon them a new layer of mud. Hence we often find, in splitting open
a slab an inch or more thick, on the upper surface of which the marks
of recent rain occur, that an inferior layer, deposited during some previous
rise of the tide, exhibits on its under side perfect casts of rain-prints,
which stand out in relief, the moulds of the same being seen on
the layer below. But in some cases, especially in the more sandy
layers, the markings have been somewhat blunted by the tide, and by
several rain-prints having been joined into one by a repetition of drops
falling on the same spot; in which case the casts present a very irregular
and blistered appearance.
The finest examples which I have seen of these rain-prints were sent
to me by Dr. Webster, from Kentville, on the borders of the Bay of
Mines, in Nova Scotia. They were made by a heavy shower which
fell on the 21st of July, 1849, when the rise and fall of the tides were
at their maximum. The impressions (see fig. 13) consist of cup-shaped
or hemispherical cavities, the average size of which is from one-eighth
to one-tenth of an inch across, but the largest are fully half an inch in
diameter, and one-tenth of an inch deep. The depth is chiefly below
the general surface or plane of stratification, but the walls of the cavity
consist partly of a prominent rim of sandy mud, formed of the matter
which has been forcibly expelled from the pit. All the cavities having
an oval form are deeper at one end, where they have also a higher rim,
and all the deep ends have the same direction, showing towards which
203
quarter the wind was blowing. Two or more drops are sometimes seen
to have interfered with each other; in which case it is usually possible
to determine which drop fell last, its rim being unbroken.
Fig. 13.
Recent rain-prints, formed July 21, 1849, at Kentville, Bay of Fundy, Nova Scotia.
The arrow represents the direction of the shower.
On some of the specimens the winding tubular tracks of worms are
seen, which have been bored just beneath the surface (see fig. 13, left
side). They occasionally pass under the middle of a rain-mark, having
been formed subsequently. Sometimes the worms have dived beneath
the surface, and then reappeared. All these appearances, both of rain-prints
and worm-tracks, are of great geological interest, as their exact
counterparts are seen in rocks of various ages, even in formations of
very high antiquity.266 Small cavities, often corresponding in size to
those produced by rain, are also caused by air-bubbles rising up through
sand or mud; but these differ in character from rain-prints, being usually
deeper than they are wide, and having their sides steeper. These,
indeed, are occasionally vertical, or overarching, the opening at the
top being narrower than the pit below. In their mode, also, of mutual
interference they are unlike rain-prints.267
In consequence of the effects of mountains in cooling currents of moist
air, and causing the condensation of aqueous vapor in the manner above
described, it follows that in every country, as a general rule, the more
elevated regions become perpetual reservoirs of water, which descends
and irrigates the lower valleys and plains. The largest quantity of
water is first carried to the highest region, and then made to descend
by steep declivities towards the sea; so that it acquires superior velocity,
and removes more soil, than it would do if the rain had been distributed
over the plains and mountains equally in proportion to their relative
204
areas. The water is also made by these means to pass over the greatest
distances before it can regain the sea.
It has already been observed that in higher latitudes, where the atmosphere
being colder is capable of holding less water in suspension,
a diminished fall of rain takes place. Thus at St. Petersburg, the
amount is only 16 inches, and at Uleaborg in the Gulf of Bothnia (N.
lat. 65°), only 13½ inches, or less than half the average of England, and
even this small quantity descends more slowly in the temperate zone,
and is spread more equally over the year than in tropical climates. But
in reference to geological changes, frost in the colder latitude acts as a
compensating power in the disintegration of rocks, and the transportation
of stones to lower levels.
Water when converted into ice augments in bulk more than one-twentieth
of its volume, and owing to this property it widens the minute
crevices (or joints) of rocks into which it penetrates. Ice also in various
ways, as will be shown in the next chapter, gives buoyancy to mud and
sand, even to huge blocks of stone, enabling rivers of moderate size and
velocity to carry them to a great distance.
The mechanical force exerted by running water in undermining cliffs,
and rounding off the angles of hard rock, is mainly due to the intermixture
of foreign ingredients. Sand and pebbles, when hurried along by
the violence of the stream, are thrown against every obstacle lying in
their way, and thus a power of attrition is acquired, capable of wearing
through the hardest siliceous stones, on which water alone could make
no impression.
Newly formed valleys.—When travelling in Georgia and Alabama, in
1846, I saw in both those States the commencement of hundreds of
valleys in places where the native forest had recently been removed.
One of these newly formed gulleys or ravines is represented in the annexed
woodcut (fig. 14), from a drawing which I made on the spot.
It occurs three miles and a half due west of Milledgeville, the capital
of Georgia, and is situated on the farm of Pomona, on the direct road
to Macon.268
Twenty years ago, before the land was cleared, it had no existence;
but when the trees of the forest were cut down, cracks three feet deep
were caused by the sun's heat in the clay; and, during the rains, a sudden
rush of water through the principal crack deepened it at its lower
extremity, from whence the excavating power worked backwards, till,
in the course of twenty years, a chasm, measuring no less than 55 feet
in depth, 300 yards in length, and varying in width from 20 to 180
feet, was the result. The high road has been several times turned to
avoid this cavity, the enlargement of which is still proceeding, and the
old line of road may be seen to have held its course directly over what
is now the wildest part of the ravine. In the perpendicular walls of this
great chasm appear beds of clay and sand, red, white, yellow, and
green, produced by the decomposition in situ of hornblendic gneiss, with
layers and veins of quartz, which remain entire, to prove that the whole
mass was once solid and crystalline.
205
Fig. 14.
Ravine on the farm of Pomona, near Milledgeville, Georgia, as it appeared January, 1846.
Excavated in twenty years, 55 feet deep, and 180 feet broad.
I infer, from the rapidity of the denudation which only began here
after the removal of the native wood, that this spot, elevated about
600 feet above the sea, has been always covered with a dense forest,
from the remote time when it first emerged from the sea. The termination
of the cavity on the right hand in the foreground is the head
or upper end of the ravine, and in almost every case, such gulleys are
lengthened by the streams cutting their way backwards. The depth
at the upper end is often, as in this case, considerable, and there is
usually at this point, during floods, a small cascade.
Sinuosities of rivers.—In proportion as such valleys are widened,
sinuosities are caused by the deflection of the stream first to one side
206
and then to the other. The unequal hardness of the materials through
which the channel is eroded tends partly to give new directions to the
lateral force of excavation. When by these, or by accidental shiftings
of the alluvial matter in the channel, the current is made to cross its
general line of descent, it eats out a curve in the opposite bank, or in
the side of the hills bounding the valley, from which curve it is turned
back again at an equal angle, so that it recrosses the line of descent,
and gradually hollows out another curve lower down in the opposite
bank, till the whole sides of the valley, or river bed, present a succession
of salient and retiring angles. Among the causes of deviation
from a straight course, by which torrents and rivers tend in mountainous
regions to widen the valleys through which they flow, may be mentioned
the confluence of lateral torrents, swollen irregularly at different
seasons by partial storms, and discharging at different times unequal
quantities of sand, mud, and pebbles, into the main channel.
Fig. 15.

When the tortuous flexures of a river are extremely great, as often
happens in alluvial plains, the aberration from the direct line of descent
may be restored by the river cutting through the isthmus which separates
two neighboring curves. Thus in the annexed diagram, the
extreme sinuosity of the river has caused it to return for a brief space
in a contrary direction to its main course, so that a peninsula is formed,
and the isthmus (at a) is consumed on both sides by currents flowing in
opposite directions. In this case an island is soon formed,—on either
side of which a portion of the stream usually remains.
Transporting power of water.—In regard to the transporting power
of water, we may often be surprised at the facility with which
streams of a small size, and descending a slight declivity, bear along
coarse sand and gravel; for we usually estimate the weight of rocks
in air, and do not reflect on their comparative buoyancy when submerged
in a denser fluid. The specific gravity of many rocks is not
more than twice that of water, and very rarely more than thrice, so
that almost all the fragments propelled by a stream have lost a third,
and many of them a half, of what we usually term their weight.
It has been proved by experiment, in contradiction to the theories
of the earlier writers on hydrostatics, to be a universal law, regulating
the motion of running water, that the velocity at the bottom of the
stream is everywhere less than in any part above it, and is greatest at
the surface. Also that the superficial particles in the middle of the
stream move swifter than those at the sides. This retardation of the
lowest and lateral currents is produced by friction; and when the
velocity is sufficiently great, the soil composing the sides and bottom
207
gives way. A velocity of three inches per second at the bottom is
ascertained to be sufficient to tear up fine clay,—six inches per second,
fine sand,—twelve inches per second, fine gravel,—and three feet per
second, stones of the size of an egg.269
When this mechanical power of running water is considered, we are
prepared for the transportation before alluded to of large quantities of
gravel, sand, and mud, by torrents which descend from mountainous
regions. But a question naturally arises, How the more tranquil rivers
of the valleys and plains, flowing on comparatively level ground, can
remove the prodigious burden which is discharged into them by their
numerous tributaries, and by what means they are enabled to convey
the whole mass to the sea? If they had not this removing power,
their channels would be annually choked up, and the valleys of the
lower country, and plains at the base of mountain-chains, would be
continually strewed over with fragments of rock and sterile sand. But
this evil is prevented by a general law regulating the conduct of running
water,—that two equal streams do not, when united, occupy a
bed of double surface. Nay, the width of the principal river, after the
junction of a tributary, sometimes remains the same as before, or is
even lessened. The cause of this apparent paradox was long ago
explained by the Italian writers, who had studied the confluence of the
Po and its feeders in the plains of Lombardy.
The addition of a smaller river augments the velocity of the main
stream, often in the same proportion as it does the quantity of water.
Thus the Venetian branch of the Po swallowed up the Ferranese
branch and that of Panaro without any enlargement of its own dimensions.
The cause of the greater velocity is, first, that after the union
of two rivers the water, in place of the friction of four shores, has
only that of two to surmount; 2dly, because the main body of the
stream being farther distant from the banks, flows on with less interruption;
and lastly, because a greater quantity of water moving more
swiftly, digs deeper into the river's bed. By this beautiful adjustment,
the water which drains the interior country is made continually to
occupy less room as it approaches the sea; and thus the most valuable
part of our continents, the rich deltas and great alluvial plains, are prevented
from being constantly under water.
River floods in Scotland, 1829.—Many remarkable illustrations of
the power of running water in moving stones and heavy materials were
afforded by the storm and floods which occurred on the 3d and 4th
of August, 1829, in Aberdeenshire and other counties in Scotland.
The elements during this storm assumed all the characters which mark
the tropical hurricanes; the wind blowing in sudden gusts and whirlwinds,
the lightning and thunder being such as is rarely witnessed in
our climate, and heavy rain falling without intermission. The floods
extended almost simultaneously, and with equal violence over that part
208
of the northeast of Scotland which would be cut off by two lines
drawn from the head of Lochrannoch, one towards Inverness and the
other to Stonehaven. The united line of the different rivers which
were flooded, could not be less than from five to six hundred miles in
length; and the whole of their courses were marked by the destruction
of bridges, roads, crops, and buildings. Sir T. D. Lauder has
recorded the destruction of thirty-eight bridges, and the entire obliteration
of a great number of farms and hamlets. On the Nairn, a fragment
of sandstone, fourteen feet long by three feet wide and one foot
thick, was carried above 200 yards down the river. Some new ravines
were formed on the sides of mountains where no streams had previously
flowed, and ancient river-channels, which had never been filled from
time immemorial, gave passage to a copious flood.270
The bridge over the Dee at Ballater consisted of five arches, having
upon the whole a water-way of 260 feet. The bed of the river, on which
the piers rested, was composed of rolled pieces of granite and gneiss.
The bridge was built of granite, and had stood uninjured for twenty
years; but the different parts were swept away in succession by the
flood, and the whole mass of masonry disappeared in the bed of the
river. "The river Don," observes Mr. Farquharson, in his account of
the inundations, "has upon my own premises forced a mass of four or
five hundred tons of stones, many of them two or three hundred pounds'
weight, up an inclined plane, rising six feet in eight or ten yards, and
left them in a rectangular heap, about three feet deep on a flat ground:—the
heap ends abruptly at its lower extremity."271
The power even of a small rivulet, when swollen by rain, in removing
heavy bodies, was exemplified in August, 1827, in the College, a
small stream which flows at a slight declivity from the eastern watershed
of the Cheviot Hills. Several thousand tons' weight of gravel and
sand were transported to the plain of the Till, and a bridge, then in
progress of building, was carried away, some of the arch-stones of
which, weighing from half to three quarters of a ton each, were propelled
two miles down the rivulet. On the same occasion, the current
tore away from the abutment of a mill-dam a large block of greenstone-porphyry,
weighing nearly two tons, and transported it to the distance
of a quarter of a mile. Instances are related as occurring repeatedly,
in which from one to three thousand tons of gravel are, in like manner,
removed by this streamlet to still greater distances in one day.272
Floods caused by landslips, 1826.—The power which running water
may exert in the lapse of ages, in widening and deepening a valley,
does not so much depend on the volume and velocity of the stream
usually flowing in it, as on the number and magnitude of the obstructions
which have, at different periods, opposed its free passage. If a
torrent, however small, be effectually dammed up, the size of the valley
209
above the barrier, and its declivity below, and not the dimensions of
the torrent, will determine the violence of the débâcle. The most universal
source of local deluges, are landslips, slides, or avalanches, as
they are sometimes called, when great masses of rock and soil, or sometimes
ice and snow, are precipitated into the bed of a river, the boundary
cliffs of which have been thrown down by the shock of an earthquake,
or undermined by springs or other causes. Volumes might be
filled with the enumeration of instances on record of these terrific catastrophes;
I shall therefore select a few examples of recent occurrence,
the facts of which are well authenticated.
Two dry seasons in the White Mountains, in New Hampshire (United
States), were followed by heavy rains on the 28th August, 1826, when
from the steep and lofty declivities which rise abruptly on both sides of
the river Saco, innumerable rocks and stones, many of sufficient size to
fill a common apartment, were detached, and in their descent swept
down before them, in one promiscuous and frightful ruin, forests, shrubs,
and the earth which sustained them. Although there are numerous
indications on the steep sides of these hills of former slides of the same
kind, yet no tradition had been handed down of any similar catastrophe
within the memory of man, and the growth of the forest on the very
spots now devastated, clearly showed that for a long interval nothing
similar had occurred. One of these moving masses was afterwards
found to have slid three miles, with an average breadth of a quarter of
a mile. The natural excavations commenced generally in a trench a few
yards in depth and a few rods in width, and descended the mountains,
widening and deepening till they became vast chasms. At the base of
these hollow ravines was seen a confused mass of ruins, consisting of
transported earth, gravel, rocks, and trees. Forests of spruce-fir and
hemlock, a kind of fir somewhat resembling our yew in foliage, were
prostrated with as much ease as if they had been fields of grain; for,
where they disputed the ground, the torrent of mud and rock accumulated
behind, till it gathered sufficient force to burst the temporary barrier.
The valleys of the Amonoosuck and Saco presented, for many miles,
an uninterrupted scene of desolation; all the bridges being carried away,
as well as those over their tributary streams. In some places, the road
was excavated to the depth of from fifteen to twenty feet; in others, it
was covered with earth, rocks, and trees, to as great a height. The
water flowed for many weeks after the flood, as densely charged with
earth as it could be without being changed into mud, and marks were
seen in various localities of its having risen on either side of the valley to
more than twenty-five feet above its ordinary level. Many sheep and
cattle were swept away, and the Willey family, nine in number, who in
alarm had deserted their house, were destroyed on the banks of the
Saco; seven of their mangled bodies were afterwards found near the
river, buried beneath drift-wood and mountain ruins.273 Eleven years
210
after the event, the deep channels worn by the avalanches of mud and
stone, and the immense heaps of boulders and blocks of granite in the
river channel, still formed, says Professor Hubbard, a picturesque feature
in the scenery.274
When I visited the country in 1845, eight years after Professor
Hubbard, I found the signs of devastation still very striking; I also particularly
remarked that although the surface of the bare granitic rocks
had been smoothed by the passage over them of so much mud and stone,
there were no continuous parallel and rectilinear furrows, nor any of the
fine scratches or striæ which characterize glacial action. The absence
of these is nowhere more clearly exemplified than in the bare rocks over
which passed the great "Willey slide" of 1826.275
But the catastrophes in the White Mountains are insignificant, when
compared to those which are occasioned by earthquakes, when the
boundary hills, for miles in length, are thrown down into the hollow of
a valley. I shall have opportunities of alluding to inundations of this
kind, when treating expressly of earthquakes, and shall content myself
at present with selecting an example of a flood due to a different cause.
Flood in the valley of Bagnes, 1818.—The valley of Bagnes is one of
the largest of the lateral embranchments of the main valley of the Rhone,
above the Lake of Geneva. Its upper portion was, in 1818, converted
into a lake by the damming up of a narrow pass, by avalanches of snow
and ice, precipitated from an elevated glacier into the bed of the river
Dranse. In the winter season, during continued frost, scarcely any
water flows in the bed of this river to preserve an open channel, so that
the ice barrier remained entire until the melting of the snows in spring,
when a lake was formed above, about half a league in length, which
finally attained in some parts a depth of about two hundred feet, and a
width of about seven hundred feet. To prevent or lessen the mischief
apprehended from the sudden bursting of the barrier, an artificial gallery,
seven hundred feet in length, was cut through the ice, before the waters
had risen to a great height. When at length they accumulated and
flowed through this tunnel, they dissolved the ice, and thus deepened
their channel, until nearly half of the whole contents of the lake were
slowly drained off. But at length, on the approach of the hot season,
the central portion of the remaining mass of ice gave way with a tremendous
crash, and the residue of the lake was emptied in half an hour.
In the course of its descent, the waters encountered several narrow
gorges, and at each of these they rose to a great height, and then burst
with new violence into the next basin, sweeping along rocks, forests,
houses, bridges, and cultivated land. For the greater part of its course
the flood resembled a moving mass of rock and mud, rather than of
water. Some fragments of granitic rocks, of enormous magnitude, and
which from their dimensions, might be compared without exaggeration
211
to houses, were torn out of a more ancient alluvion, and borne down
for a quarter of a mile. One of the fragments moved was sixty paces
in circumference.276 The velocity of the water, in the first part of its
course, was thirty-three feet per second, which diminished to six feet
before it reached the Lake of Geneva, where it arrived in six hours and
a half, the distance being forty-five miles.277
This flood left behind it, on the plains of Martigny, thousands of trees
torn up by the roots, together with the ruins of buildings. Some of the
houses in that town were filled with mud up to the second story. After
expanding in the plain of Martigny, it entered the Rhone, and did no
farther damage; but some bodies of men, who had been drowned above
Martigny, were afterwards found, at the distance of about thirty miles,
floating on the farther side of the Lake of Geneva, near Vevay.
The waters, on escaping from the temporary lake, intermixed with
mud and rock, swept along, for the first four miles, at the rate of above
twenty miles an hour; and M. Escher, the engineer, calculated that the
flood furnished 300,000 cubic feet of water every second—an efflux
which is five times greater than that of the Rhine below Basle. Now,
if part of the lake had not been gradually drained off, the flood would
have been nearly double, approaching in volume to some of the largest
rivers in Europe. It is evident, therefore, that when we are speculating
on the excavating force which a river may have exerted in any particular
valley, the most important question is, not the volume of the existing
stream, nor the present levels of its channel, nor even the nature of the
rocks, but the probability of a succession of floods at some period since
the time when the valley may have been first elevated above the sea.
For several months after the débâcle of 1818, the Dranse, having no
settled channel, shifted its position continually from one side to the
other of the valley, carrying away newly-erected bridges, undermining
houses, and continuing to be charged with as large a quantity of earthy
matter as the fluid could hold in suspension. I visited this valley four
months after the flood, and was witness to the sweeping away of a
bridge, and the undermining of part of a house. The greater part of
the ice-barrier was then standing, presenting vertical cliffs 150 feet high,
like ravines in the lava-currents of Etna or Auvergne, where they are
intersected by rivers.
Inundations, precisely similar, are recorded to have occurred at former
periods in this district, and from the same cause. In 1595, for example,
a lake burst, and the waters, descending with irresistible fury,
destroyed the town of Martigny, where from sixty to eighty persons
perished. In a similar flood, fifty years before, 140 persons were
drowned.
Flood at Tivoli, 1826.—I shall conclude with one more example
derived from a land of classic recollections, the ancient Tibur, and which,
212
like all the other inundations above alluded to, occurred within the
present century. The younger Pliny, it will be remembered, describes
a flood on the Anio, which destroyed woods, rocks, and houses, with
the most sumptuous villas and works of arts.278 For four or five centuries
consecutively, this "headlong stream," as Horace truly called it,
has often remained within its bounds, and then, after so long an interval
of rest, has at different periods inundated its banks again, and widened
its channel. The last of these catastrophes happened 15th Nov. 1826,
after heavy rains, such as produced the floods before alluded to in Scotland.
The waters appear also to have been impeded by an artificial
dike, by which they were separated into two parts, a short distance
above Tivoli. They broke through this dike; and leaving the left trench
dry, precipitated themselves, with their whole weight, on the right side.
Here they undermined, in the course of a few hours, a high cliff, and
widened the river's channel about fifteen paces. On this height stood
the church of St. Lucia, and about thirty-six houses of the town of
Tivoli, which were all carried away, presenting as they sank into the
roaring flood, a terrific scene of destruction to the spectators on the opposite
bank. As the foundations were gradually removed, each building,
some of them edifices of considerable height, was first traversed
with numerous rents, which soon widened into large fissures, until at
length the roofs fell in with a crash, and then the walls sunk into the
river, and were hurled down the cataract below.279
The destroying agency of the flood came within two hundred yards
of the precipice on which the beautiful temple of Vesta stands; but
fortunately this precious relic of antiquity was spared, while the wreck
of modern structures was hurled down the abyss. Vesta, it will be
remembered, in the heathen mythology, personified the stability of the
earth; and when the Samian astronomer, Aristarchus, first taught that
the earth revolved on its axis, and round the sun, he was publicly accused
of impiety, "for removing the everlasting Vesta from her place."
Playfair observed, that when Hutton ascribed instability to the earth's
surface, and represented the continents which we inhabit as the theatre
of incessant change and movement, his antagonists, who regarded them
as unalterable, assailed him in a similar manner with accusations founded
on religious prejudices.280 We might appeal to the excavating power of
the Anio as corroborative of one of the most controverted parts of the
Huttonian theory; and if the days of omens had not gone by, the geologists
who now worship Vesta might regard the late catastrophe as
portentous. We may, at least, recommend the modern votaries of the
goddess to lose no time in making a pilgrimage to her shrine, for the
next flood may not respect the temple.
Excavation of rocks by running water.—The rapidity with which
213
even the smallest streams hollow out deep channels in soft and destructible
soils is remarkably exemplified in volcanic countries, where the sand
and half-consolidated tuffs opposed but a slight resistance to the torrents
which descend the mountain-side. After the heavy rains which followed
the eruption of Vesuvius in 1824, the water flowing from the Atrio del
Cavallo cut, in three days, a new chasm through strata of tuff and
ejected volcanic matter, to the depth of twenty-five feet. I found the
old mule-road, in 1828, intersected by this new ravine.
The gradual erosion of deep chasms through some of the hardest rocks,
by the constant passage of running water, charged with foreign matter,
is another phenomenon of which striking examples may be adduced.
Illustrations of this excavating power are presented by many valleys in
central France where the channels of rivers have been barred up by
solid currents of lava, through which the streams have re-excavated a
passage, to the depth of from twenty to seventy feet and upwards, and
often of great width. In these cases there are decisive proofs that
neither the sea, nor any denuding wave or extraordinary body of water,
has passed over the spot since the melted lava was consolidated. Every
hypothesis of the intervention of sudden and violent agency is entirely
excluded, because the cones of loose scoriæ, out of which the lavas
flowed, are oftentimes at no great elevation above the rivers, and have
remained undisturbed during the whole period which has been sufficient
for the hollowing out of such enormous ravines.
Recent excavation by the Simeto.—But I shall at present confine myself
to examples derived from events which have happened since the
time of history.
Fig. 16.
Recent excavation of lava at the foot of Etna by the river Simeto.
At the western base of Etna, a current of lava (A A, fig. 16), descending
from near the summit of the great volcano, has flowed to the
distance of five or six miles, and then reached the alluvial plain of the
Simeto, the largest of the Sicilian rivers, which skirts the base of Etna,
and falls into the sea a few miles south of Catania. The lava entered
the river about three miles above the town of Aderno, and not only occupied
its channel for some distance, but, crossing to the opposite side
of the valley, accumulated there in a rocky mass. Gemmellaro gives
the year 1603 as the date of the eruption.281 The appearance of the
214
current clearly proves, that it is one of the most modern of those of
Etna; for it has not been covered or crossed by subsequent streams or
ejections, and the olives which had been planted on its surface were all
of small size, when I examined the spot in 1828, yet they were older
than the natural wood on the same lava. In the course, therefore, of
about two centuries, the Simeto has eroded a passage from fifty to several
hundred feet wide, and in some parts from forty to fifty feet deep.
The portion of lava cut through is in no part porous or scoriaceous,
but consists of a compact homogeneous mass of hard blue rock, somewhat
inferior in weight to ordinary basalt, and containing crystals of
olivine and glassy felspar. The general declivity of this part of the bed
of the Simeto is not considerable; but, in consequence of the unequal
waste of the lava, two water-falls occur at Passo Manzanelli, each about
six feet in height. Here the chasm (B, fig. 16) is about forty feet deep,
and only fifty broad.
The sand and pebbles in the river-bed consist chiefly of a brown
quartzose sandstone, derived from the upper country; but the materials
of the volcanic rock itself must have greatly assisted the attrition. This
river, like the Caltabiano on the eastern side of Etna, has not yet cut
down to the ancient bed of which it was dispossessed, and of which
the probable position is indicated in the annexed diagram (C, fig. 16).
On entering the narrow ravine where the water foams down the two
cataracts, we are entirely shut out from all view of the surrounding
country; and a geologist who is accustomed to associate the characteristic
features of the landscape with the relative age of certain rocks, can
scarcely dissuade himself from the belief that he is contemplating a
scene in some rocky gorge of a primary district. The external forms of
the hard blue lava are as massive as any of the most ancient trap-rocks
of Scotland. The solid surface is in some parts smoothed and almost
polished by attrition, and covered in others with a white lichen, which
imparts to it an air of extreme antiquity, so as greatly to heighten the
delusion. But the moment we reascend the cliff the spell is broken;
for we scarcely recede a few paces, before the ravine and river disappear,
and we stand on the black and rugged surface of a vast current of
lava, which seems unbroken, and which we can trace up nearly to the
distant summit of that majestic cone which Pindar called "the pillar of
heaven," and which still continues to send forth a fleecy wreath of vapor,
reminding us that its fires are not extinct, and that it may again
give out a rocky stream, wherein other scenes like that now described
may present themselves to future observers.
215


Fig. 17.
Lake Erie.
The Falls.
 



Limestone Shale.

Lewiston.
Niagara River.
Queenstown.
 


Falls of Niagara.—The falls of Niagara afford a magnificent example
of the progressive excavation of a deep valley in solid rock. That
river flows over a flat table-land, in a depression of which Lake Erie
is situated. Where it issues from the lake, it is nearly a mile in width,
and 330 feet above Lake Ontario, which is about 30 miles distant. For
the first fifteen miles below Lake Erie the surrounding country, comprising
Upper Canada on the west, and the state of New York on the
216
east, is almost on a level with its banks, and nowhere more than thirty
or forty feet above them.282 (See fig. 17.) The river being occasionally
interspersed with low wooded islands, and having sometimes a width of
three miles, glides along at first with a clear, smooth, and tranquil current,
falling only fifteen feet in as many miles, and in this part of its
course resembling an arm of Lake Erie. But its character is afterwards
entirely changed, on approaching the Rapids, where it begins to rush
and foam over a rocky and uneven limestone bottom, for the space of
nearly a mile, till at length it is thrown down perpendicularly 165 feet
at the Falls. Here the river is divided into two sheets of water by an
island, the largest cataract being more than a third of a mile broad, the
smaller one having a breadth of six hundred feet. When the water has
precipitated itself into an unfathomable pool, it rushes with great velocity
down the sloping bottom of a narrow chasm, for a distance of
seven miles. This ravine varies from 200 to 400 yards in width from
cliff to cliff; contrasting, therefore, strongly in its breadth with that of
the river above. Its depth is from 200 to 300 feet, and it intersects
for about seven miles the table-land before described, which terminates
suddenly at Queenstown in an escarpment or long line of inland cliff
facing northwards, towards Lake Ontario. The Niagara, on reaching
the escarpment and issuing from the gorge, enters the flat country,
which is so nearly on a level with Lake Ontario, that there is only a fall
of about four feet in the seven additional miles which intervene between
Queenstown and the shores of that lake.
It has long been the popular belief that the Niagara once flowed in a
shallow valley across the whole platform, from the present site of the
Falls to the escarpment (called the Queenstown heights), where it is
supposed that the cataract was first situated, and that the river has
been slowly eating its way backwards through the rocks for the distance
of seven miles. This hypothesis naturally suggests itself to every
observer, who sees the narrowness of the gorge at its termination, and
throughout its whole course, as far up as the Falls, above which
point the river expands as before stated. The boundary cliffs of the
ravine are usually perpendicular, and in many places undermined on
one side by the impetuous stream. The uppermost rock of the table-land
at the Falls consists of hard limestone (a member of the Silurian
series), about ninety feet thick, beneath which lie soft shales of
equal thickness, continually undermined by the action of the spray,
which rises from the pool into which so large a body of water is projected,
and is driven violently by gusts of wind against the base of the
217
precipice. In consequence of this action, and that of frost, the shale
disintegrates and crumbles away, and portions of the incumbent rock
overhang 40 feet, and often when unsupported tumble down, so that
the Falls do not remain absolutely stationary at the same spot, even for
half a century. Accounts have come down to us, from the earliest period
of observation, of the frequent destruction of these rocks, and the
sudden descent of huge fragments in 1818 and 1828, are said to have
shaken the adjacent country like an earthquake. The earliest travellers,
Hennepin and Kalm, who in 1678 and 1751 visited the Falls, and
published views of them, attest the fact, that the rocks have been suffering
from dilapidation for more than a century and a half, and that
some slight changes, even in the scenery of the cataract have been
brought about within that time. The idea, therefore, of perpetual and
progressive waste is constantly present to the mind of every beholder;
and as that part of the chasm, which has been the work of the last
hundred and fifty years resembles precisely, in depth, width, and character,
the rest of the gorge which extends seven miles below, it is most
natural to infer, that the entire ravine has been hollowed out in the same
manner, by the recession of the cataract.
It must at least be conceded, that the river supplies an adequate
cause for executing the whole task thus assigned to it, provided we
grant sufficient time for its completion. As this part of the country
was a wilderness till near the end of the last century, we can obtain
no accurate data for estimating the exact rate at which the cataract has
been receding. Mr. Bakewell, son of the eminent geologist of that
name, who visited the Niagara in 1829, made the first attempt to calculate
from the observations of one who had lived forty years at the
Falls, and who had been the first settler there, that the cataract had
during that period gone back about a yard annually. But after the
most careful inquiries which I was able to make, during my visit to
the spot in 1841-2, I came to the conclusion that the average of one
foot a year would be a much more probable conjecture. In that case,
it would have required thirty-five thousand years for the retreat of the
Falls, from the escarpment of Queenstown to their present site. It
seems by no means improbable that such a result would be no exaggeration
of the truth, although we cannot assume that the retrograde
movement has been uniform. An examination of the geological structure
of the district, as laid open in the ravine, shows that at every step
in the process of excavation, the height of the precipice, the hardness
of the materials at its base, and the quantity of fallen matter to be
removed, must have varied. At some points it may have receded much
faster than at present, but in general its progress was probably slower,
because the cataract, when it began to recede, must have had nearly
twice its present height.
From observations made by me in 1841, when I had the advantage
of being accompanied by Mr. Hall, state geologist of New York, and
in 1842, when I re-examined the Niagara district, I obtained
geological218
evidence of the former existence of an old river-bed, which, I have
no doubt, indicates the original channel through which the waters once
flowed from the Falls to Queenstown, at the height of nearly three
hundred feet above the bottom of the present gorge. The geological
monuments alluded to, consist of patches of sand and gravel, forty feet
thick, containing fluviatile shells of the genera Unio, Cyclas, Melania,
&c., such as now inhabit the waters of the Niagara above the Falls.
The identity of the fossil species with the recent is unquestionable, and
these freshwater deposits occur at the edge of the cliffs bounding the
ravine, so that they prove the former extension of an elevated shallow
valley, four miles below the falls, a distinct prolongation of that now
occupied by the Niagara, in the elevated region intervening between
Lake Erie and the Falls. Whatever theory be framed for the hollowing
out of the ravine further down, or for the three miles which intervene
between the whirlpool and Queenstown, it will always be necessary
to suppose the former existence of a barrier of rock, not of loose and
destructible materials, such as those composing the drift in this district,
somewhere immediately below the whirlpool. By that barrier the
waters were held back for ages, when the fluviatile deposit, 40 feet in
thickness, and 250 feet above the present channel of the river, originated.
If we are led by this evidence to admit that the cataract has
cut back its way for four miles, we can have little hesitation in referring
the excavation of the remaining three miles below to a like agency, the
shape of the chasm being precisely similar.
There have been many speculations respecting the future recession
of the Falls, and the deluge that might be occasioned by the sudden
escape of the waters of Lake Erie, if the ravine should ever be prolonged
16 miles backwards. But a more accurate knowledge of the
geological succession of the rocks, brought to light by the State Survey,
has satisfied every geologist that the Falls would diminish gradually
in height before they travelled back two miles, and in consequence
of a gentle dip of the strata to the south, the massive limestone now at
the top would then be at their base, and would retard, and perhaps put
an effectual stop to, the excavating process.

219</div></body></text></TEI>