<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="120">CHAPTER VI.
The Progress of Systematic Zoology.
THE history of Systematic
Botany, as we have presented it, may be considered as a sufficient
type of the general order of progression in the sciences of
classification. It has appeared, in the survey which we have had to
give, that this science, no less than those which we first considered,
has been formed by a series of inductive processes, and has, in its
history, Epochs at which, by such processes, decided advances were
made. The important step in such cases is, the seizing upon some
artificial mark which conforms to natural resemblances;—some
basis of arrangement and nomenclature by means of which true
propositions of considerable generality can be enunciated. The advance
of other classificatory sciences, as well as botany, must consist of
such steps; and their course, like that of botany, must (if we attend
only to the real additions made to knowledge,) be gradual and
progressive, from the earliest times to the present.
To exemplify this continued and constant progression in the whole
range of Zoology, would require vast knowledge and great labor; and
is, perhaps, the less necessary, after we have dwelt so long on the
history of Botany, considered in the same point of view. But there are
a few observations respecting Zoology in general which we are led to
make in consequence of statements recently promulgated; for these
statements seem to represent the history of Zoology as having followed
a course very different from that which we have just ascribed to the
classificatory sciences in general. It is held by some naturalists,
that not only the formation of a systematic classification in Zoology
dates as far back as Aristotle; but that his classification is, in
many respects, superior to some of the most admired and recent
attempts of modern times.
If this were really the case, it would show that at least the idea
of a Systematic Classification had been formed and developed long
previous to the period to which we have assigned such a step; and it
would be difficult to reconcile such an early maturity of Zoology with
the conviction, which we have had impressed upon us by the other 413 parts of our history,
that not only labor but time, not only one man of genius but several,
and those succeeding each other, are requisite to the formation of any
considerable science.
But, in reality, the statements to which we refer, respecting the
scientific character of Aristotle’s Zoological system, are altogether
without foundation; and this science confirms the lessons taught us by
all the others. The misstatements respecting Aristotle’s doctrines are
on this account so important, and are so curious in themselves, that I
must dwell upon them a little.
Aristotle’s nine Books On Animals are a work enumerating the
differences of animals in almost all conceivable respects;—in
the organs of sense, of motion, of nutrition, the interior anatomy,
the exterior covering, the manner of life, growth, generation, and
many other circumstances. These differences are very philosophically
estimated. “The corresponding parts of animals,” he says,126 “besides the differences of quality
and circumstance, differ in being more or fewer, greater or smaller,
and, speaking generally, in excess and defect. Thus some animals have
crustaceous coverings, others hard shells; some have long beaks, some
short; some have many wings, some have few; Some again have parts
which others want, as crests and spurs.” He then makes the following
important remark: “Some animals have parts which correspond to those
of others, not as being the same in species, nor by excess and defect,
but by analogy; thus a claw is analogous to a thorn, and a
nail to a hoof, and a hand to the nipper of a lobster, and a feather
to a scale; for what a feather is in a bird, that is a scale in a
fish.”
126 Lib. i. c. i.
It will not, however, be necessary, in order to understand
Aristotle for our present purpose, that we should discuss his notion
of Analogy. He proceeds to state his object,127 which is, as
we have said, to describe the differences of animals in their
structure and habits. He then observes, that for structure, we may
take Man for our type,128 as being best known to us; and the
remainder of the first Book is occupied with a description of man’s
body, beginning from the head, and proceeding to the extremities.
127 Lib. i. c. ii.
128 c. iii.
In the next Book, (from which are taken the principal passages in
which his modern commentators detect his system,) he proceeds to
compare the differences of parts in different animals, according to
the order which he had observed in man. In the first chapter he speaks
414 of the head and
neck of animals; in the second, of the parts analogous to arms and
hands; in the third, of the breast and paps, and so on; and thus he
comes, in the seventh chapter, to the legs, feet, and toes: and in the
eleventh, to the teeth, and so to other parts.
The construction of a classification consists in the selection of
certain parts, as those which shall eminently and peculiarly determine
the place of each species in our arrangement. It is clear, therefore,
that such an enumeration of differences as we have described,
supposing it complete, contains the materials of all possible
classifications. But we can with no more propriety say that the author
of such an enumeration of differences is the author of any
classification which can be made by means of them, than we can say
that a man who writes down the whole alphabet writes down the solution
of a given riddle or the answer to a particular question.
Yet it is on no other ground than this enumeration, so far as I can
discover, that Aristotle’s “System” has been so decidedly spoken of,129 and exhibited in the most formal
tabular shape. The authors of this Systema Aristotelicum, have
selected, I presume, the following passages from the work On
Animals, as they might have selected any other; and by arranging
them according to a subordination unknown to Aristotle himself have
made for him a scheme which undoubtedly bears a great resemblance to
the most complete systems of modern times.
129 Linnæan Transactions,
vol. xvi. p. 24.
Book I., chap. v.—“Some animals are viviparous, some
oviparous, some vermiparous. The viviparous are such as man, and the
horse, and all those animals which have hair; and of aquatic animals,
the whale kind, as the dolphin and cartilaginous fishes.”
Book II., chap. vii.—“Of quadrupeds which have blood and are
viviparous, some are (as to their extremities,) many-cloven, as the
hands and feet of man. For some are many-toed, as the lion, the dog,
the panther; some are bifid, and have hoofs instead of nails, as the
sheep, the goat, the elephant, the hippopotamus; and some have
undivided feet, as the solid-hoofed animals, the horse and ass. The
swine kind share both characters.”
Chap. ii.—“Animals have also great differences in the teeth,
both when compared with each other and with man. For all quadrupeds
which have blood and are viviparous, have teeth. And in the first
place, some are ambidental,130 (having teeth
in both jaws;) and some 415 are not so, wanting the front teeth in
the upper jaw. Some have neither front teeth nor horns, as the camel;
some have tusks,131 as the boar, some have not. Some have
serrated132 teeth, as the lion, the panther, the
dog; some have the teeth unvaried,133 as the horse
and the ox; for the animals which vary their cutting-teeth have all
serrated teeth. No animal has both tusks and horns; nor has any animal
with serrated teeth either of those weapons. The greater part have the
front teeth cutting, and those within broad.”
130 Ἀμφόδοντα.
131 Χαυλιόδοντα.
132 Καρχαρόδοντα.
133 Ἀνεπάλλακτα.
These passages undoubtedly contain most of the differences on which
the asserted Aristotelian classification rests; but the classification
is formed by using the characters drawn from the teeth, in order to
subdivide those taken from the feet; whereas in Aristotle these two
sets of characters stand side by side, along with dozens of others;
any selection of which, employed according to any arbitrary method of
subordination, might with equal justice be called Aristotle’s
system.
Why, for instance, in order to form subdivisions of animals, should
we not go on with Aristotle’s continuation of the second of the above
quoted passages, instead of capriciously leaping to the third? “Of
these some have horns, some have none . . . Some have a
fetlock-joint,134 some have none . . . Of those which
have horns, some have them solid throughout, as the stag; others, for
the most part, hollow . . . Some cast their horns, some do not.” If it
be replied, that we could not, by means of such characters, form a
tenable zoological system; we again ask by what right we assume
Aristotle to have made or attempted a systematic arrangement, when
what he has written, taken in its natural order, does not admit of
being construed into a system.
134 Ἀστράγαλον.
Again, what is the object of any classification? This, at least,
among others. To enable the person who uses it to study and describe
more conveniently the objects thus classified. If, therefore,
Aristotle had formed or adopted any system of arrangement, we should
see it in the order of the subjects in his work. Accordingly, so far
as he has a system, he professes to make this use of it. At the
beginning of the fifth Book, where he is proceeding to treat of the
different modes of generation of animals, he says, “As we formerly
made a Division of animals according to their kinds, we must now, in
the same manner, give a general survey of their History (θεωρίαν).
Except, indeed, that in the former case we made our commencement by a
description 416 of
man, but in the present instance we must speak of him last, because he
requires most study. We must begin then with those animals which have
shells; we must go on to those which have softer coverings, as
crustacea, soft animals, and insects; after these, fishes, both
viviparous and oviparous; then birds; then land animals, both
viviparous and oviparous.”
It is clear from this passage that Aristotle had certain wide and
indefinite views of classification, which though not very exact, are
still highly creditable to him; but it is equally clear that he was
quite unconscious of the classification that has been ascribed to him.
If he had adopted that or any other system, this was precisely the
place in which he must have referred to and employed it.
The honor due to the stupendous accumulation of zoological
knowledge which Aristotle’s works contain, cannot be tarnished by our
denying him the credit of a system which he never dreamt of and which,
from the nature of the progress of science, could not possibly be
constructed at that period. But, in reality, we may exchange the
mistaken claims which we have been contesting for a better, because a
truer praise. Aristotle does show, as far as could be done at his
time, a perception of the need of groups, and of names of groups, in
the study of the animal kingdom; and thus may justly be held up as the
great figure in the Prelude to the Formation of Systems which took
place in more advanced scientific times.
This appears, in some measure, from the passage last quoted. For
not only is there, in that, a clear recognition of the value and
object of a method in natural history; but the general arrangement of
the animal kingdom there proposed has considerable scientific merit,
and is, for the time, very philosophical. But there are passages in
his work in which he shows a wish to carry the principle of
arrangement more into detail. Thus, in the first Book, before
proceeding to his survey of the differences of animals,135 after speaking of such classes as
Quadrupeds. Birds, Fishes, Cetaceous, Testaceous, Crustaceous Animals,
Mollusks, Insects, he says, (chap. vii.)
“Animals cannot be divided into large genera, in which
one kind includes many kinds. For some kinds are unique, and have no
difference of species, as man. Some have such kinds, but have
no names for them. Thus all quadrupeds which have not wings, have
blood. But of these, some are viviparous, some oviparous. Those which
are 417 viviparous
have not all hair; those which are oviparous have scales.” We have
here a manifestly intentional subordination of characters: and a kind
of regret that we have not names for the classes here indicated; such,
for instance, as viviparous quadrupeds having hair. But he follows the
subject into further detail. “Of the class of viviparous quadrupeds,”
he continues, “there are many genera,136 but these
again are without names, except specific names, such as man,
lion, stag, horse, dog, and the like. Yet
there is a genus of animals that have names, as the horse, the ass,
the oreus, the ginnus, the innus, and the animal
which in Syria is called heminus (mule); for these are called
mules, from their resemblance only; not being mules, for they
breed of their own kind. Wherefore,” he adds, that is, because we do
not possess recognized genera and generic names of this kind, “we must
take the species separately, and study the nature of each.”
135 Γένη.
136 Εἴδη.
These passages afford us sufficient ground for placing Aristotle at
the head of those naturalists to whom the first views of the necessity
of a zoological system are due. It was, however, very long before any
worthy successor appeared, for no additional step was made till modern
times. When Natural History again came to be studied in Nature, the
business of Classification, as we have seen, forced itself upon men’s
attention, and was pursued with interest in animals, as in plants. The
steps of its advance were similar in the two cases;—by
successive naturalists, various systems of artificial marks were
selected with a view to precision and convenience;—and these
artificial systems assumed the existence of certain natural groups,
and of a natural system to which they gradually tended. But there was
this difference between botany and zoology:—the reference to
physiological principles, which, as we have remarked, influenced the
natural systems of vegetables in a latent and obscure manner,
botanists being guided by its light, but hardly aware that they were
so, affected the study of systematic zoology more directly and
evidently. For men can neither overlook the general physiological
features of animals, nor avoid being swayed by them in their judgments
of the affinities of different species. Thus the classifications of
zoology tended more and more to a union with comparative anatomy, as
the science was more and more improved.137 But
comparative anatomy belongs to the subject of the next Book; and
anything it may be proper to say respecting its influence upon
zoological arrangements, will properly find a place there.
137 Cuvier, Leç. d’Anat.
Comp. vol. i. p. 17.
418 It will
appear, and indeed it hardly requires to be proved, that those steps
in systematic zoology which are due to the light thrown upon the
subject by physiology, are the result of a long series of labors by
various naturalists, and have been, like other advances in science,
led to and produced by the general progress of such knowledge. We can
hardly expect that the classificatory sciences can undergo any
material improvement which is not of this kind. Very recently,
however, some authors have attempted to introduce into these sciences
certain principles which do not, at first sight, appear as a
continuation and extension of the previous researches of comparative
anatomists. I speak, in particular, of the doctrines of a Circular
Progression in the series of affinity; of a Quinary
Division of such circular groups; and of a relation of
Analogy between the members of such groups, entirely distinct
from the relation of Affinity.
The doctrine of Circular Progression has been propounded
principally by Mr. Macleay; although, as he has shown,138 there are suggestions of the same kind
to be found in other writers. So far as this view negatives the
doctrine of a mere linear progression in nature, which would place
each genus in contact only with the preceding and succeeding ones, and
so far as it requires us to attend to more varied and ramified
resemblances, there can be no doubt that it is supported by the result
of all the attempts to form natural systems. But whether that
assemblage of circles of arrangement which is now offered to
naturalists, be the true and only way of exhibiting the natural
relations of organized bodies, is a much more difficult question, and
one which I shall not here attempt to examine; although it will be
found, I think, that those analogies of science which we have had to
study, would not fail to throw some light upon such an inquiry. The
prevalence of an invariable numerical law in the divisions of natural
groups, (as the number five is asserted to prevail by Mr.
Macleay, the number ten by Fries, and other numbers by other
writers), would be a curious fact, if established; but it is easy to
see that nothing short of the most consummate knowledge of natural
history, joined with extreme clearness of view and calmness of
judgment, could enable any one to pronounce on the attempts which have
been made to establish such a principle. But the doctrine of a
relation of Analogy distinct from Affinity, in the manner which
has recently been taught, seems to be obviously at variance with that
gradual approximation of the classificatory to the 419 physiological
sciences, which has appeared to us to be the general tendency of real
knowledge. It seems difficult to understand how a reference to such
relations as those which are offered as examples of analogy139 can be otherwise than a retrograde
step in science.
138 Linn. Trans. vol. xvi. p.
9.
139 For example, the goatsucker has
an affinity with the swallow; but it has an analogy
with the bat, because both fly at the same hour of the day, and feed
in the same manner.—Swainson, Geography and Classification of
Animals, p. 129.
Without, however, now dwelling upon these points, I will treat a
little more in detail of one of the branches of Zoology.
[2nd Ed.] [For the more recent progress of Systematic Zoology, see
in the Reports of the British Association, in 1834, Mr. L.
Jenyns’s Report an the Recent Progress and Present State of
Zoology, and in 1844, Mr. Strickland’s Report on the Recent
Progress and Present State of Ornithology. In these Reports, the
questions of the Circular Arrangement, the Quinary System, and the
relation of Analogy and Affinity are discussed.]
~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~
</div></body></text></TEI>