<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="146">CHAPTER IX.
The Electro-chemical Theory.
AMONG the consequences of the
Electro-chemical Theory, must be ranged the various improvements which
have been made in the voltaic battery. Daniel introduced between the
two metals a partition permeable by chemical action, but such as to
allow of two different acid solutions being in contact with the two
metals. Mr. Grove’s battery, in which the partition is of porous
porcelain, and the metals are platinum and amalgamated zinc, is one of
the most powerful hitherto known. Another has been constructed by Dr.
Callan, in which the negative or conducting plate is a cylinder of
cast iron, and the positive element a cylinder of amalgamated zinc
placed in a porous cell. This also has great energy.
The Number of Elementary Substances.
There have not been, I believe, any well-established additions to
the list of the simple substances recognized by chemists. Indeed the
tendency at present appears to be rather to deny the separate
elementary character of some already announced as such substances.
Pelopium and Niobium were, as I have said, two of the new metals. But
Naumann, in his Elemente der Mineralogie (4th ed. 1855), says,
in a foot note (page 25): “Pelopium is happily again got rid
of; for Pelopic Acid and Niobic Acid possess the same Radical.
Donarium had a still shorter existence.”
In the same way, when Hermann imagined that he had discovered a new
simple metallic substance in the mineral Samarskite from Miask, the
discovery was disproved by H. Rose (Pogg. Ann. B. 73, s. 449).
626
In general the insulation of the new simple substances, the
metallic bases of the earths, and the like,—their separation
from their combinations, and the exhibition of them in a metallic
form—has been a difficult chemical process, and has rarely been
executed on any considerable scale. But in the case of
Aluminium, the basis of the earth Alumina, the process of its
extraction has recently been so much facilitated, that the metal can
be produced in abundance. This being the case, it will probably soon
be applied to special economical uses, for which it is fitted by
possessing special properties.


BOOK XV.

MINERALOGY.

BY the kindness of W. H.
Miller, Esq., Professor of Mineralogy in the University of Cambridge,
I am able to add to this part the following notices of books and
memoirs.
1. Crystallography.
Elemente der Krystallographie, nebst einer tabellarischen
Uebersicht der Mineralien nach der Krystallformen, von Gustav
Rose. 2. Auflage. Berlin, 1838. The crystallographic method here
adopted is, for the most part, that of Weiss. The method of this work
has been followed in
A System of Crystallography, with its Applications to
Mineralogy. By John Joseph Griffin. Glasgow, 1841. Mr. Griffin
has, however, modified the notation of Rose. He has constructed a
series of models of crystalline forms.
Frankenheim’s System der Krystalle. 1842. This work adopts
nearly the Mohsian systems of crystallization. It contains Tables of
the chemical constitution, inclinations of the axis, and magnitude of
the axes of all the crystals of which a description was to be found,
including those formed in the laboratory, as well as those usually
called minerals; 713 in all.
Fr. Aug. Quenstedt, Methode der Krystallographie, 1840,
employs a fanciful method of representing a crystal by projecting upon
one face of the crystal all the other faces. This invention appears to
be more curious than useful.
Dr. Karl Naumann, who is spoken of in Chap. ix. of this Book, as the
author of the best of the Mixed Systems of Classification, published
also Grundriss der Krystallographie, Leipzig, 1826. In this and
other works he modifies the notation of Mohs in a very advantageous
manner. 628
Professor Dana, in his System of Mineralogy, New Haven
(U.S.), 1837, follows Naumann for the most part, both in
crystallography and in mineral classification. In the latter part of
the subject, he has made the attempt, which in all cases is a source
of confusion and of failure, to introduce a whole system of new names
of the members of his classification.
The geometry of crystallography has been investigated in a very
original manner by M. Bravais, in papers published in the Journal of
the Ecole Polytechnique, entitled Mémoires sur les Systèmes formés
par des Points. 1850. Etudes Crystallographiques. 1851.
Hermann Kopp (Einleitung in die Krystallographie,
Braunschweig. 1849) has given the description and measurement of the
angles of a large number of laboratory crystals.
Rammelsberg (Krystallographische Chemie, Berlin, 1855) has
collected an account of the systems, simple forms and angles of all
the laboratory crystals of which he could obtain descriptions.
Schabus of Vienna (Bestimmung der Krystallgestalten in Chemischen
Laboratorien erzeugten Producte, Wien, 1855; a successful Prize
Essay) has given a description, accompanied by measurements, of 90
crystalline species from his own observations.
To these attempts made in other countries to simplify and improve
crystallography, I may add a remarkable Essay very recently made here
by Mr. Brooke, and suggested to him by his exact and familiar
knowledge of Mineralogy. It is to this effect. All the crystalline
forms of any given mineral species are derived from the primitive
form of that species; and the degree of symmetry, and the
parameters, of this form determine the angles of all derivative
forms. But how is this primitive form selected and its parameters
determined? The selection of the kind of the primitive form depends
upon the degree of symmetry which appears in all the derivative
forms; according to which they belong to the rhombohedral,
prismatic, square pyramidal, or some other
system: and this determination is commonly clear. But the
parameters, or the angles, of the primitive form, are commonly
determined by the cleavage of the mineral. Is this a sufficient
and necessary ground of such determination? May not a simplification
be effected, in some cases, by taking some other parameters? by taking
a primitive form which belongs to the proper system, but which has
some other angles than those given by cleavage? Mr. Brooke has tried
whether, for instance, crystals of the rhombohedral system may not be
referred with advantage to primitive rhombohedrons which have, in all
629 the species,
nearly the same angles. The advantage to be obtained by such a change
would be the simplification of the laws of derivation in the
derivative forms: and therefore we have to ask, whether the indices of
derivation are smaller numbers in this way or with the hitherto
accepted fundamental angles. It appears to me, from the examples
given, that the advantage of simplicity in the indices is on the side
of the old system: but whether this be so or not, it was a great
benefit to crystallography to have the two methods compared. Mr.
Brooke’s Essay is a Memoir presented to the Royal Society in 1856.
2. Optical Properties of Minerals.
The Handbuch der Optik, von F. W. G. Radicke, Berlin, 1839,
contains a chapter on the optical properties of crystals. The author’s
chief authority is Sir D. Brewster, as might be expected.
M. Haidinger has devoted much attention to experiments on the
pleochroism of minerals. He has invented an instrument which
makes the dichroism of minerals more evident by exhibiting the two
colors side by side.
The pleochroism of minerals, and especially the remarkable clouds
that in the cases of Iolite, Andalusite, Augite, Epidote, and Axinite,
border the positions of either optical axis, have been most
successfully imitated by M. de Senarmont by means of artificial
crystallizations. (Ann. de Chim. 3 Ser. xli. p.
319.)
M. Pasteur has found that Racemic Acid consists of two different
acids, having the same density and composition. The salts of these
acids, with bases of Ammonia and of Potassa, are hemihedral, the
hemihedral faces which occur in the one being wanting in the other.
The acids of these different crystals have circular polarization of
opposite kinds. (Ann. de Chim. 3 Ser. xxviii. 56, 99.)
This discovery was marked by the assignation of the Rumford Medal to
M. Pasteur in 1856.
M. Marbach has discovered that crystals of chlorate of soda, which
apparently belongs to the cubic or tessular system, exhibit hemihedral
faces of a peculiar character; and that the crystals have circular
polarization of opposite kinds in accordance with the differences of
the plagihedral faces. (Poggendorf’s Annalen, xci. 482.)
M. Seybolt of Vienna has found a means of detecting plagihedral
faces in quartz crystals which do not reveal them externally.
(Akad. d. Wissenschaft zu Wien, B. xv. s. 59.) 630
3. Classification of Minerals.
In the Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences, B. viii. C. iii., I have treated of the Application of
the Natural-history Method of Classification to Mineralogy, and have
spoken of the Systems of this kind which have been proposed. I have
there especially discussed the system proposed in the treatise of M.
Necker, Le Règne Minéral ramené aux Méthodes d’Histoire
Naturelle (Paris, 1835). More recently have been published M.
Beudant’s Cours élémentaire d’Histoire Naturelle, Minéralogie
(Paris, 1841); and M. A. Dufresnoy’s Traité de Minéralogie
(Paris, 1845). Both these works are so far governed by mere chemical
views that they lapse into the inconveniences and defects which are
avoided in the best systems of German mineralogists.
The last mineral system of Berzelius has been developed by M.
Rammelsberg (Nürnberg, 1847). It is in principle such as we have
described it in the history.
M. Nordenskiöld’s system (3rd Ed. 1849,) has been
criticised by G. Rose, who observes that it removes the defects of the
system of Berzelius only in part. He himself proposes what he calls a
“Krystallo-Chemisches System,” in which the crystalline form
determines the genus and the chemical composition the species. His
classes are—
1. Simple Substances.
2. Combinations of Sulphur, Selenium, Titanium, Arsenic,
Antimony.
3. Chlorides, Fluorides, Bromides, Iodides.
4. Combinations with Oxygen.
We have already said that for us, all chemical compounds are
minerals, in so far that they are included in our
classifications. The propriety of this mode of dealing with the
subject is confirmed by our finding that there is really no tenable
distinction between native minerals and the products of the
laboratory. A great number of eminent chemists have been employed in
producing, by artificial means, crystals which had before been known
only as native products.


BOOK XVI.

CLASSIFICATORY SCIENCES.
</div></body></text></TEI>