<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="30">CHAPTER IV.
Discovery of the Mechanical Principles of
Fluids.

Sect. 1.—Rediscovery of the Laws of
Equilibrium of Fluids.
WE have already said, that the true laws of the
equilibrium of fluids were discovered by Archimedes, and rediscovered
by Galileo and Stevinus; the intermediate time having been occupied by
a vagueness and confusion of thought on physical subjects, which made
it impossible for men to retain such clear views as Archimedes had
disclosed. Stevinus must be considered as the earliest of the authors
of this rediscovery; for his work (Principles of Statik and
Hydrostatik) was published in Dutch about 1585; and in this, his
views are perfectly distinct and correct. He restates the doctrines of
Archimedes, and shows that, as a consequence of them, it follows that
the pressure of a fluid on the bottom of a vessel may be much greater
than the weight of the fluid itself: this he proves, by imagining some
of the upper portions of the vessel to be filled with fixed solid
bodies, which take the place of the fluid, and yet do not alter the
pressure on the base. He also shows what will be the pressure on any
portion of a base in an oblique position; and hence, by certain
mathematical artifices which make an approach to the Infinitesimal
Calculus, he finds the whole pressure on the base in such cases. This
mode of treating the subject would take in a large portion of our
elementary Hydrostatics as the science now stands. Galileo saw the
properties of fluids no less clearly, and explained them very
distinctly, in 1612, in his Discourse on Floating Bodies. It
had been maintained by the Aristotelians, that form was the
cause of bodies floating; and collaterally, that ice was
condensed water; apparently from a confusion of thought
between rigidity and density. Galileo asserted, on
the contrary, that ice is rarefied water, as appears by its
floating: and in support of this, he proved, by various experiments,
that the floating of bodies does not depend on their form. The happy
genius of Galileo is the more remarkable in this case, as the
controversy was a good deal perplexed by the mixture of phenomena of
another kind, due to what is usually called capillary or
molecular attraction. Thus it is a fact, that a ball
346 of ebony sinks
in water, while a flat slip of the same material lies on the
surface; and it required considerable sagacity to separate such cases
from the general rule. Galileo’s opinions were attacked by various
writers, as Nozzolini, Vincenzio di Grazia, Ludovico delle Colombe;
and defended by his pupil Castelli, who published a reply in 1615.
These opinions were generally adopted and diffused; but somewhat
later, Pascal pursued the subject more systematically, and wrote his
Treatise of the Equilibrium of Fluids in 1653; in which he
shows that a fluid, inclosed in a vessel, necessarily presses equally
in all directions, by imagining two pistons or sliding plugs,
applied at different parts, the surface of one being centuple that of
the other: it is clear, as he observes, that the force of one man
acting at the first piston, will balance the force of one hundred men
acting at the other. “And thus,” says he, “it appears that a vessel
full of water is a new Principle of Mechanics, and a new Machine which
will multiply force to any degree we choose.” Pascal also referred the
equilibrium of fluids to the “principle of virtual velocities,” which
regulates the equilibrium of other machines. This, indeed, Galileo had
done before him. It followed from this doctrine, that the pressure
which is exercised by the lower parts of a fluid arises from the
weight of the upper parts.
In all this there was nothing which was not easily assented to; but
the extension of these doctrines to the air required an additional
effort of mechanical conception. The pressure of the air on all sides
of us, and its weight above us, were two truths which had never yet
been apprehended with any kind of clearness. Seneca, indeed,29 talks of the “gravity of the air,” and
of its power of diffusing itself when condensed, as the causes of
wind; but we can hardly consider such propriety of phraseology in him
as more than a chance; for we see the value of his philosophy by what
he immediately adds: “Do you think that we have forces by which we
move ourselves, and that the air is left without any power of moving?
when even water has a motion of its own, as we see in the growth of
plants.” We can hardly attach much value to such a recognition of the
gravity and elasticity of the air.
29 Quæst. Nat. v. 5.
Yet the effects of these causes were so numerous and obvious, that
the Aristotelians had been obliged to invent a principle to account
for them; namely, “Nature’s Horror of a Vacuum.” To this principle
were referred many familiar phenomena, as suction, breathing, the
347 action of a
pair of bellows, its drawing water if immersed in water, its refusing
to open when the rent is stopped up. The action of a cupping
instrument, in which the air is rarefied by fire; the fact that water
is supported when a full inverted bottle is placed in a basin; or when
a full tube, open below and closed above, is similarly placed; the
running out of the water, in this instance, when the top is opened;
the action of a siphon, of a syringe, of a pump; the adhesion of two
polished plates, and other facts, were all explained by the fuga
vacui. Indeed, we must contend that the principle was a very good
one, inasmuch as it brought together all these facts which are really
of the same kind, and referred them to a common cause. But when urged
as an ultimate principle, it was not only unphilosophical,
but imperfect and wrong. It was
unphilosophical, because it introduced the notion of an
emotion, Horror, as an account of physical facts; it was
imperfect, because it was at best only a law of phenomena,
not pointing out any physical cause; and it was wrong,
because it gave an unlimited extent to the effect. Accordingly, it led
to mistakes. Thus Mersenne, in 1644, speaks of a siphon which shall go
over a mountain, being ignorant then that the effect of such an
instrument was limited to a height of thirty-four feet. A few years
later, however, he had detected this mistake; and in his third volume,
published in 1647, he puts his siphon in his emendanda, and
speaks correctly of the weight of air as supporting the mercury in the
tube of Torricelli. It was, indeed, by finding this horror of a vacuum
to have a limit at the height of thirty-four feet, that the true
principle was suggested. It was discovered that when attempts were
made to raise water higher than this. Nature tolerated a vacuum above
the water which rose. In 1643, Torricelli tried to produce this vacuum
at a smaller height, by using, instead of water, the heavier fluid,
quicksilver; an attempt which shows that the true explanation, the
balance of the weight of the water by another pressure, had already
suggested itself. Indeed, this appears from other evidence. Galileo
had already taught that the air has weight; and Baliani, writing to
him in 1630, says,30 “If we were in a vacuum, the weight of
the air above our heads would be felt.” Descartes also appears to have
some share in this discovery; for, in a letter of the date of 1631, he
explains the suspension of mercury in a tube, closed at top, by the
pressure of the column of air reaching to the clouds.
30 Drinkwater’s Galileo, p.
90.
348 Still men’s
minds wanted confirmation in this view; and they found such
confirmation, when, in 1647, Pascal showed practically, that if we
alter the length of the superincumbent column of air by going to a
high place, we alter the weight which it will support. This celebrated
experiment was made by Pascal himself on a church-steeple in Paris,
the column of mercury in the Torricellian tube being used to compare
the weights of the air; but he wrote to his brother-in-law, who lived
near the high mountain of Puy de Dôme in Auvergne, to request him to
make the experiment there, where the result would be more decisive.
“You see,” he says, “that if it happens that the height of the mercury
at the top of the hill be less than at the bottom (which I have many
reasons to believe, though all those who have thought about it are of
a different opinion), it will follow that the weight and pressure of
the air are the sole cause of this suspension, and not the horror of a
vacuum: since it is very certain that there is more air to weigh on it
at the bottom than at the top; while we cannot say that nature abhors
a vacuum at the foot of a mountain more than on its summit.”—M.
Perrier, Pascal’s correspondent, made the observation as he had
desired, and found a difference of three inches of mercury, “which,”
he says, “ravished us with admiration and astonishment.”
When the least obvious case of the operation of the pressure and
weight of fluids had thus been made out, there were no further
difficulties in the progress of the theory of Hydrostatics. When
mathematicians began to consider more general cases than those of the
action of gravity, there arose differences in the way of stating the
appropriate principles: but none of these differences imply any
different conception of the fundamental nature of fluid
equilibrium.
Sect. 2.—Discovery of the Laws of Motion of
Fluids.
The art of conducting water in pipes, and
of directing its motion for various purposes, is very old. When
treated systematically, it has been termed Hydraulics: but
Hydrodynamics is the general name of the science of the laws of
the motions of fluids, under those or other circumstances. The Art is
as old as the commencement of civilization: the Science does not
ascend higher than the time of Newton, though attempts on such
subjects were made by Galileo and his scholars.
When a fluid spouts from an orifice in a vessel, Castelli saw that
the velocity of efflux depends on the depth of the orifice below the
349 surface: but he
erroneously judged the velocity to be exactly proportional to the
depth. Torricelli found that the fluid, under the inevitable causes of
defect which occur in the experiment, would spout nearly to the height
of the surface: he therefore inferred, that the full velocity is that
which a body would acquire in falling through the depth; and that it
is consequently proportional to the square root of the
depth.—This, however, he stated only as a result of experience,
or law of phenomena, at the end of his treatise, De Motu
Naturaliter Accelerato, printed in 1643.
Newton treated the subject theoretically in the Principia
(1687); but we must allow, as Lagrange says, that this is the least
satisfactory passage of that great work. Newton, having made his
experiments in another manner than Torricelli, namely, by measuring
the quantity of the efflux instead of its velocity, found a result
inconsistent with that of Torricelli. The velocity inferred from the
quantity discharged, was only that due to half the depth of
the fluid.
In the first edition of the Principia,31 Newton gave a
train of reasoning by which he theoretically demonstrated his own
result, going upon the principle, that the momentum of the issuing
fluid is equal to the momentum which the column vertically over the
orifice would generate by its gravity. But Torricelli’s experiments,
which had given the velocity due to the whole depth, were confirmed on
repetition: how was this discrepancy to be explained?
31 B. ii. Prop. xxxvii.
Newton explained the discrepancy by observing the contraction which
the jet, or vein of water, undergoes, just after it leaves the
orifice, and which he called the vena contracta. At the
orifice, the velocity is that due to half the height; at the vena
contracta it is that due to the whole height. The former velocity
regulates the quantity of the discharge; the latter, the path of the
jet.
This explanation was an important step in the subject; but it made
Newton’s original proof appear very defective, to say the least. In
the second edition of the Principia (1714), Newton attacked the
problem in a manner altogether different from his former
investigation. He there assumed, that when a round vessel, containing
fluid, has a hole in its bottom, the descending fluid may be conceived
to be a conoidal mass, which has its base at the surface of the fluid,
and its narrow end at the orifice. This portion of the fluid he calls
the cataract; and supposes that while this part descends, the
surrounding 350
parts remain immovable, as if they were frozen; in this way he finds a
result agreeing with Torricelli’s experiments on the velocity of the
efflux.
We must allow that the assumptions by which this result is obtained
are somewhat arbitrary; and those which Newton introduces in
attempting to connect the problem of issuing fluids with that of the
resistance to a body moving in a fluid, are no less so. But even up to
the present time, mathematicians have not been able to reduce problems
concerning the motions of fluids to mathematical principles and
calculations, without introducing some steps of this arbitrary kind.
And one of the uses of experiments on this subject is, to suggest
those hypotheses which may enable us, in the manner most consonant
with the true state of things, to reduce the motions of fluids to
those general laws of mechanics, to which we know they must be
subject.
Hence the science of the Motion of Fluids, unlike all the other
primary departments of Mechanics, is a subject on which we still need
experiments, to point out the fundamental principles. Many such
experiments have been made, with a view either to compare the results
of deduction and observation, or, when this comparison failed, to
obtain purely empirical rules. In this way the resistance of fluids,
and the motion of water in pipes, canals, and rivers, has been
treated. Italy has possessed, from early times, a large body of such
writers. The earlier works of this kind have been collected in sixteen
quarto volumes. Lecchi and Michelotti about 1765, Bidone more
recently, have pursued these inquiries. Bossut, Buat, Hachette, in
France, have labored at the same task, as have Coulomb and Prony,
Girard and Poncelet. Eytelwein’s German treatise (Hydraulik)
contains an account of what others and himself have done. Many of
these trains of experiments, both in France and Italy, were made at
the expense of governments, and on a very magnificent scale. In
England less was done in this way during the last century, than in
most other countries. The Philosophical Transactions, for
instance, scarcely contain a single paper on this subject founded on
experimental investigations.32 Dr. Thomas
Young, who was at the head of his countrymen in so many branches of
science, was one of the first to call back attention to this: and Mr.
Rennie and others have recently made valuable experiments. In many of
the questions now spoken of, the accordance which engineers are able
to obtain, between their calculated and observed results, 351 is very great: but
these calculations are performed by means of empirical formulæ, which
do not connect the facts with their causes, and still leave a wide
space to be traversed, in order to complete the science.
32 Rennie, Report to Brit.
Assoc.
In the mean time, all the other portions of Mechanics were reduced
to general laws, and analytical processes; and means were found of
including Hydrodynamics, notwithstanding the difficulties which attend
its special problems, in this common improvement of form. This
progress we must relate.
[2d Ed.] [The hydrodynamical problems referred to above are, the
laws of a fluid issuing from a vessel, the laws of the motion of water
in pipes, canals, and rivers, and the laws of the resistance of
fluids. To these may be added, as an hydrodynamical problem important
in theory, in experiment, and in the comparison of the two, the laws
of waves. Newton gave, in the Principia, an explanation of the
waves of water (Lib. ii. Prop. 44), which appears to proceed upon an
erroneous view of the nature of the motion of the fluid: but in his
solution of the problem of sound, appeared, for the first time, a
correct view of the propagation of an undulation in a fluid. The
history of this subject, as bearing upon the theory of sound, is given
in Book viii.: but I may here remark, that the
laws of the motion of waves have been pursued experimentally by
various persons, as Bremontier (Recherches sur le Mouvement des
Ondes, 1809), Emy (Du Mouvement des Ondes, 1831), the
Webers (Wellenlehre, 1825); and by Mr. Scott Russell
(Reports of the British Association, 1844). The analytical
theory has been carried on by Poisson, Cauchy, and, among ourselves,
by Prof. Kelland (Edin. Trans.) and Mr. Airy (in the article
Tides, in the Encyclopædia Metropolitana). And though
theory and experiment have not yet been brought into complete
accordance, great progress has been made in that work, and the
remaining chasm between the two is manifestly due only to the
incompleteness of both.]
Perhaps the most remarkable case of fluid motion recently
discussed, is one which Mr. Scott Russell has presented
experimentally; and which, though novel, is easily seen to follow from
known principles; namely, the Great Solitary Wave. A wave may
be produced, which shall move along a canal unaccompanied by any other
wave: and the simplicity of this case makes the mathematical
conditions and consequences more simple than they are in most other
problems of Hydrodynamics. 352</div></body></text></TEI>