<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="33">CHAPTER XXXIII.
CHANGES OF THE ORGANIC WORLD NOW IN PROGRESS.
Division of the subject—Examination of the question, Whether species have a
real existence in nature?—Importance of this question in geology—Sketch of
Lamarck's arguments in favor of the transmutation of species, and his conjectures
respecting the origin of existing animals and plants—His theory of the transformation
of the orang-outang into the human species.
The last book, from chapters fourteen to thirty-three inclusive, was occupied
with the consideration of the changes brought about on the
earth's surface, within the period of human observation, by inorganic
agents; such, for example, as rivers, marine currents, volcanoes, and
earthquakes. But there is another class of phenomena relating to the
organic world, which have an equal claim on our attention, if we desire
to obtain possession of all the preparatory knowledge respecting the existing
course of nature, which may be available in the interpretation of
geological monuments. It appeared from our preliminary sketch of the
progress of the science, that the most lively interest was excited among
its earlier cultivators, by the discovery of the remains of animals and
plants in the interior of mountains frequently remote from the sea.
Much controversy arose respecting the nature of these remains, the
causes which may have brought them into so singular a position, and the
want of a specific agreement between them and known animals and
plants. To qualify ourselves to form just views on these curious questions,
we must first study the present condition of the animate creation
on the globe.
This branch of our inquiry naturally divides itself into two parts: first,
we may examine the vicissitudes to which species are subject; secondly,
the processes by which certain individuals of these species occasionally
become fossil. The first of these divisions will lead us, among other
topics, to inquire, first, whether species have a real and permanent existence
in nature? or whether they are capable, as some naturalists pretend,
of being indefinitely modified in the course of a long series of
generations? Secondly, whether, if species have a real existence, the
individuals composing them have been derived originally from many
similar stocks, or each from one only, the descendants of which have
spread themselves gradually from a particular point over the habitable
lands and waters? Thirdly, how far the duration of each species of
animal and plant is limited by its dependence on certain fluctuating and
temporary conditions in the state of the animate and inanimate world?
Fourthly, whether there be proofs of the successive extermination of
567
species in the ordinary course of nature, and whether there be any reason
for conjecturing that new animals and plants are created from time
to time, to supply their place?
Whether species have a real existence in nature.—Before we can advance
a step in our proposed inquiry, we must be able to define precisely
the meaning which we attach to the term species. This is even
more necessary in geology than in the ordinary studies of the naturalist;
for they who deny that such a thing as a species exists, concede nevertheless
that a botanist or zoologist may reason as if the specific character
were constant, because they confine their observations to a brief period
of time. Just as the geographer, in constructing his maps from century
to century, may proceed as if the apparent places of the fixed stars remained
absolutely the same, and as if no alteration were brought about
by the precession of the equinoxes; so, it is said, in the organic world,
the stability of a species may be taken as absolute, if we do not extend
our views beyond the narrow period of human history; but let a sufficient
number of centuries elapse, to allow of important revolutions in
climate, physical geography, and other circumstances, and the characters,
say they, of the descendants of common parents may deviate indefinitely
from their original type.
Now, if these doctrines be tenable, we are at once presented with a
principle of incessant change in the organic world; and no degree of
dissimilarity in the plants and animals which may formerly have existed,
and are found fossil, would entitle us to conclude that they may not have
been the prototypes and progenitors of the species now living. Accordingly
M. Geoffroy St. Hilaire has declared his opinion, that there has
been an uninterrupted succession in the animal kingdom, effected by
means of generation, from the earliest ages of the world up to the
present day, and that the ancient animals whose remains have been
preserved in the strata, however different, may nevertheless have been
the ancestors of those now in being. This notion is not very generally
received, but we are not warranted in assuming the contrary,
without fully explaining the data and reasoning by which it may be
refuted.
I shall begin by stating as concisely as possible all the facts and ingenious
arguments by which the theory has been supported; and for
this purpose I cannot do better than offer the reader a rapid sketch of
Lamarck's statement of the proofs which he regards as confirmatory of
the doctrine, and which he has derived partly from the works of his
predecessors and in part from original investigations.
His proofs and inferences will be best considered in the order in which
they appear to have influenced his mind, and I shall then point out some
of the results to which he was led while boldly following out his principles
to their legitimate consequences.
Lamarck's arguments in favor of the transmutation of species.—The
name of species, observes Lamarck, has been usually applied to "every
collection of similar individuals produced by other individuals like themselves."790
568
This definition, he admits, is correct; because every living
individual bears a very close resemblance to those from which it springs.
But this is not all which is usually implied by the term species; for the
majority of naturalists agree with Linnæus in supposing that all the individuals
propagated from one stock have certain distinguishing characters
in common, which will never vary, and which have remained the
same since the creation of each species.
In order to shake this opinion, Lamarck enters upon the following line
of argument:—The more we advance in the knowledge of the different
organized bodies which cover the surface of the globe, the more our embarrassment
increases, to determine what ought to be regarded as a
species, and still more how to limit and distinguish genera. In proportion
as our collections are enriched, we see almost every void filled up,
and all our lines of separation effaced! We are reduced to arbitrary determinations,
and are sometimes fain to seize upon the slight differences
of mere varieties, in order to form characters for what we choose to call
a species; and sometimes we are induced to pronounce individuals but
slightly differing, and which others regard as true species, to be varieties.
The greater the abundance of natural objects assembled together, the
more do we discover proofs that every thing passes by insensible shades
into something else; that even the more remarkable differences are
evanescent, and that nature has, for the most part, left us nothing at our
disposal for establishing distinctions, save trifling, and, in some respects,
puerile particularities.
We find that many genera amongst animals and plants are of such an
extent, in consequence of the number of species referred to them, that
the study and determination of these last has become almost impracticable.
When the species are arranged in a series, and placed near to
each other, with due regard to their natural affinities, they each differ
in so minute a degree from those next adjoining, that they almost melt
into each other, and are in a manner confounded together. If we see
isolated species, we may presume the absence of some more closely connected,
and which have not yet been discovered. Already are there
genera, and even entire orders—nay, whole classes, which present an
approximation to the state of things here indicated.
If, when species have been thus placed in a regular series, we select
one, and then, making a leap over several intermediate ones, we take a
second, at some distance from the first, these two will, on comparison,
be seen to be very dissimilar; and it is in this manner that every naturalist
begins to study the objects which are at his own door. He then
finds it an easy task to establish generic and specific distinctions; and it
is only when his experience is enlarged, and when he has made himself
master of the intermediate links, that his difficulties and ambiguities begin.
But while we are thus compelled to resort to trifling and minute
characters in our attempt to separate the species, we find a striking disparity
569
between individuals which we know to have descended from a
common stock; and these newly acquired peculiarities are regularly
transmitted from one generation to another, constituting what are called
races.
From a great number of facts, continues the author, we learn that
in proportion as the individuals of one of our species change their situation,
climate, and manner of living, they change also, by little and little,
the consistence and proportions of their parts, their form, their faculties,
and even their organization, in such a manner that every thing in them
comes at last to participate in the mutations to which they have been
exposed. Even in the same climate, a great difference of situation and
exposure causes individuals to vary; but if these individuals continue
to live and to be reproduced under the same difference of circumstances,
distinctions are brought about in them which become in some degree
essential to their existence. In a word, at the end of many successive
generations, these individuals, which originally belonged to another
species, are transformed into a new and distinct species.791
Thus, for example, if the seeds of a grass, or any other plant which
grows naturally in a moist meadow, be accidentally transported, first to
the slope of some neighboring hill, where the soil, although at a greater
elevation, is damp enough to allow the plant to live; and if, after having
lived there, and having been several times regenerated, it reaches by
degrees the drier and almost arid soil of a mountain declivity, it will
then, if it succeeds in growing, and perpetuates itself for a series of generations,
be so changed that botanists who meet with it will regard it as
a particular species.792 The unfavorable climate in this case, deficiency
of nourishment, exposure to the winds, and other causes, give rise to a
stunted and dwarfish race, with some organ more developed than others,
and having proportions often quite peculiar.
What nature brings about in a great lapse of time, we occasion suddenly
by changing the circumstances in which a species has been accustomed
to live. All are aware that vegetables taken from their birthplace,
and cultivated in gardens, undergo changes which render them
no longer recognizable as the same plants. Many which were naturally
hairy become smooth, or nearly so; a great number of such as were
creepers and trailed along the ground, rear their stalks and grow erect.
Others lose their thorns or asperities; others, again, from the ligneous
state which their stem possessed in hot climates, where they were indigenous,
pass to the herbaceous; and, among them, some which were
perennials become mere annuals. So well do botanists know the effects
of such changes of circumstances, that they are averse to describe species
from garden specimens, unless they are sure that they have been cultivated
for a very short period.
"Is not the cultivated wheat" (Triticum sativum), asks Lamarck, "a
vegetable brought by man into the state in which we now see it? Let
570
any one tell me in what country a similar plant grows wild, unless where
it has escaped from cultivated fields? Where do we find in nature our
cabbages, lettuces, and other culinary vegetables, in the state in which
they appear in our gardens? Is it not the same in regard to a great
quantity of animals which domesticity has changed or considerably modified?"793
Our domestic fowls and pigeons are unlike any wild birds.
Our domestic ducks and geese have lost the faculty of raising themselves
into the higher regions of the air, and crossing extensive countries
in their flight, like the wild ducks and wild geese from which they were
originally derived. A bird which we breed in a cage cannot, when restored
to liberty, fly like others of the same species which have been
always free. This small alteration of circumstances, however, has only
diminished the power of flight, without modifying the form of any part
of the wings. But when individuals of the same race are retained in
captivity during a considerable length of time, the form even of their
parts is gradually made to differ, especially if climate, nourishment, and
other circumstances be also altered.
The numerous races of dogs which we have produced by domesticity
are nowhere to be found in a wild state. In nature we should seek in
vain for mastiffs, harriers, spaniels, greyhounds, and other races, between
which the differences are sometimes so great that they would be readily
admitted as specific between wild animals; "yet all these have sprung
originally from a single race, at first approaching very near to a wolf,
if, indeed, the wolf be not the true type which at some period or other
was domesticated by man."
Although important changes in the nature of the places which they
inhabit modify the organization of animals as well as vegetables; yet the
former, says Lamarck, require more time to complete a considerable
degree of transmutation; and, consequently, we are less sensible of such
occurrences. Next to a diversity of the medium in which animals or
plants may live, the circumstances which have most influence in modifying
their organs are differences in exposure, climate, the nature of the
soil, and other local particulars. These circumstances are as varied as
are the characters of the species, and, like them, pass by insensible shades
into each other, there being every intermediate gradation between the
opposite extremes. But each locality remains for a very long time the
same, and is altered so slowly that we can only become conscious of the
reality of the change by consulting geological monuments, by which we
learn that the order of things which how reigns in each place has not
always prevailed, and by inference anticipate that it will not always continue
the same.794
Every considerable alteration in the local circumstances in which each
race of animals exists causes a change in their wants, and these new
wants excite them to new actions and habits. These actions require the
more frequent employment of some parts before but slightly exercised,
571
and then greater development follows as a consequence of their more
frequent use. Other organs no longer in use are impoverished and
diminished in size, nay, are sometimes entirely annihilated, while in their
place new parts are insensibly produced for the discharge of new functions.795
I must here interrupt the author's argument, by observing, that no
positive fact is cited to exemplify the substitution of some entirely new
sense, faculty, or organ, in the room of some other suppressed as
useless. All the instances adduced go only to prove that the dimensions
and strength of members and the perfection of certain attributes
may, in a long succession of generations, be lessened and enfeebled by
disuse; or, on the contrary, be matured and augmented by active exertion;
just as we know that the power of scent is feeble in the greyhound,
while its swiftness of pace and its acuteness of sight are remarkable—that
the harrier and stag-hound, on the contrary, are comparatively
slow in their movements, but excel in the sense of smelling.
It was necessary to point out to the reader this important chasm in
the chain of evidence, because he might otherwise imagine that I had
merely omitted the illustrations for the sake of brevity; but the plain
truth is, that there were no examples to be found; and when Lamarck
talks "of the efforts of internal sentiment," "the influence of subtle
fluids," and "acts of organization," as causes whereby animals and plants
may acquire new organs, he substitutes names for things; and, with a
disregard to the strict rules of induction, resorts to fictions, as ideal as
the "plastic virtue," and other phantoms of the geologists of the middle
ages.
It is evident that, if some well-authenticated facts could have been
adduced to establish one complete step in the process of transformation,
such as the appearance, in individuals descending from a common stock,
of a sense or organ entirely new, and a complete disappearance of some
other enjoyed by their progenitors, time alone might then be supposed
sufficient to bring about any amount of metamorphosis. The gratuitous
assumption, therefore, of a point so vital to the theory of transmutation,
was unpardonable on the part of its advocate.
But to proceed with the system: it being assumed as an undoubted
fact, that a change of external circumstances may cause one organ to
become entirely obsolete, and a new one to be developed, such as never
before belonged to the species, the following proposition is announced,
which, however staggering and absurd it may seem, is logically deduced
from the assumed premises. It is not the organs, or, in other words,
the nature and form of the parts of the body of an animal, which have
given rise to its habits, and its particular faculties; but, on the contrary,
its habits, its manner of living, and those of its progenitors, have in the
course of time determined the form of its body, the number and condition
of its organs—in short, the faculties which it enjoys. Thus otters,
572
beavers, waterfowl, turtles, and frogs, were not made web-footed in
order that they might swim; but their wants having attracted them to
the water in search of prey, they stretched out the toes of their feet to
strike the water and move rapidly along its surface. By the repeated
stretching of their toes, the skin which united them at the base acquired
a habit of extension, until, in the course of time, the broad membranes
which now connect their extremities were formed.
In like manner, the antelope and the gazelle were not endowed with
light agile forms, in order that they might escape by flight from carnivorous
animals; but, having been exposed to the danger of being
devoured by lions, tigers, and other beasts of prey, they were compelled
to exert themselves in running with great celerity; a habit which, in the
course of many generations, gave rise to the peculiar slenderness of their
legs, and the agility and elegance of their forms.
The camelopard was not gifted with a long flexible neck because it
was destined to live in the interior of Africa, where the soil was arid
and devoid of herbage; but, being reduced by the nature of that
country to support itself on the foliage of lofty trees, it contracted a
habit of stretching itself up to reach the high boughs, until its neck
became so elongated that it could raise its head to the height of twenty
feet above the ground.
Another line of argument is then entered upon, in farther corroboration
of the instability of species. In order, it is said, that individuals
should perpetuate themselves unaltered by generation, those belonging
to one species ought never to ally themselves to those of
another; but such sexual unions do take place, both among plants and
animals; and although the offspring of such irregular connections are
usually sterile, yet such is not always the case. Hybrids have sometimes
proved prolific, where the disparity between the species was not
too great; and by this means alone, says Lamarck, varieties may gradually
be created by near alliances, which would become races, and in the
course of time would constitute what we term species.796
But if the soundness of all these arguments and inferences be admitted,
we are next to inquire, what were the original types of form,
organization, and instinct, from which the diversities of character, as
now exhibited by animals and plants, have been derived? We know
that individuals which are mere varieties of the same species would, if
their pedigree could be traced back far enough, terminate in a single
stock; so, according to the train of reasoning before described, the
species of a genus, and even the genera of a great family, must have
had a common point of departure. What, then, was the single stem
from which so many varieties of form have ramified? Were there
many of these, or are we to refer the origin of the whole animate
creation, as the Egyptian priests did that of the universe, to a single
egg?
573
In the absence of any positive data for framing a theory on so obscure
a subject, the following considerations were deemed of importance to
guide conjecture.
In the first place, if we examine the whole series of known animals,
from one extremity to the other, when they are arranged in the order
of their natural relations, we find that we may pass progressively, or, at
least, with very few interruptions, from beings of more simple to those
of a more compound structure; and, in proportion as the complexity of
their organization increases, the number and dignity of their faculties
increase also. Among plants, a similar approximation to a graduated
scale of being is apparent, Secondly, it appears, from geological observations,
that plants and animals of more simple organization existed on
the globe before the appearance of those of more compound structure,
and the latter were successively formed at more modern periods; each
new race being more fully developed than the most perfect of the preceding
era.
Of the truth of the last-mentioned geological theory, Lamarck seems
to have been fully persuaded; and he also shows that he was deeply
impressed with a belief prevalent amongst the older naturalists, that the
primeval ocean invested the whole planet long after it became the habitation
of living beings; and thus he was inclined to assert the priority of
the types of marine animals to those of the terrestrial, so as to fancy, for
example, that the testacea of the ocean existed first, until some of them,
by gradual evolution, were improved into those inhabiting the land.
These speculative views had already been, in a great degree, anticipated
by Demaillet in his Telliamed, and by several modern writers; so that
the tables were completely turned on the philosophers of antiquity, with
whom it was a received maxim, that created things were always most
perfect when they came first from the hands of their Maker; and that
there was a tendency to progressive deterioration in sublunary things
when left to themselves—


————omnia fatis
In pejus ruere, ac retrò sublapsa referri.


So deeply was the faith of the ancient schools of philosophy imbued
with this dóctrine, that, to check this universal proneness to degeneracy,
nothing less than the reintervention of the Deity was thought adequate;
and it was held, that thereby the order, excellence, and pristine energy
of the moral and physical world had been repeatedly restored.
But when the possibility of the indefinite modification of individuals
descending from common parents was once assumed, as also the geological
inference respecting the progressive development of organic life,
it was natural that the ancient dogma should be rejected, or rather reversed,
and that the most simple and imperfect forms and faculties should
be conceived to have been the originals whence all others were developed.
Accordingly, in conformity to these views, inert matter was supposed to
have been first endowed with life; until, in the course of ages, sensation
574
was superadded to mere vitality: sight, hearing, and the other senses
were afterwards acquired; then instinct and the mental faculties; until,
finally, by virtue of the tendency of things to progressive improvement,
the irrational was developed in the rational.
The reader, however, will immediately perceive that when all the
higher orders of plants and animals were thus supposed to be comparatively
modern, and to have been derived in a long series of generations
from those of more simple conformation, some farther hypothesis became
indispensable, in order to explain why, after an indefinite lapse of ages,
there were still so many beings of the simplest structure. Why have
the majority of existing creatures remained stationary throughout this
long succession of epochs, while others have made such prodigious
advances? Why are there such multitudes of infusoria and polyps, or
of confervæ and other cryptogamic plants? Why, moreover, has the
process of development acted with such unequal and irregular force on
those classes of beings which have been greatly perfected, so that there
are wide chasms in the series; gaps so enormous, that Lamarck fairly
admits we can never expect to fill them up by future discoveries?
The following hypothesis was provided to meet these objections.
Nature, we are told, is not an intelligence, nor the Deity; but a delegated
power—a mere instrument—a piece of mechanism acting by
necessity—an order of things constituted by the Supreme Being, and
subject to laws which are the expressions of his will. This Nature is
obliged to proceed gradually in all her operations; she cannot produce
animals and plants of all classes at once, but must always begin by the
formation of the most simple kinds, and out of them elaborate the more
compound, adding to them, successively, different systems of organs, and
multiplying more and more their number and energy.
This nature is daily engaged in the formation of the elementary rudiments
of animal and vegetable existence, which correspond to what the
ancients termed spontaneous generation. She is always beginning anew,
day by day, the work of creation, by forming monads, or "rough
draughts" (ébauches), which are the only living things she gives birth
to directly.
There are distinct primary rudiments of plants and animals, and
probably of each of the great divisions of the animal and vegetable
kingdoms.797 These are gradually developed into the higher and more
perfect classes by the slow but unceasing agency of two influential
principles: first, the tendency to progressive advancement in organization,
accompanied by greater dignity in instinct, intelligence, &c.; secondly,
the force of external circumstances, or of variations in the physical condition
of the earth, or the mutual relations of plants and animals. For,
as species spread themselves gradually over the globe, they are exposed
from time to time to variations in climate, and to changes in the quantity
and quality of their food; they meet with new plants and animals which
575
assist or retard their development, by supplying them with nutriment,
or destroying their foes. The nature, also, of each locality, is in itself
fluctuating; so that, even if the relation of other animals and plants were
invariable, the habits and organization of species would be modified by
the influence of local revolutions.
Now, if the first of these principles, the tendency to progressive development,
were left to exert itself with perfect freedom, it would give rise,
says Lamarck, in the course of ages, to a graduated scale of being,
where the most insensible transition might be traced from the simplest
to the most compound structure, from the humblest to the most exalted
degree of intelligence. But, in consequence of the perpetual interference
of the external causes before mentioned, this regular order is greatly
interfered with, and an approximation only to such a state of things is
exhibited by the animate creation, the progress of some races being
retarded by unfavorable, and that of others accelerated by favorable,
combinations of circumstances. Hence, all kinds of anomalies interrupt
the continuity of the plan; and chasms, into which whole genera or
families might be inserted, are seen to separate the nearest existing portions
of the series.
Lamarck's theory of the transformation of the orang-outang into the
human species.—Such is the machinery of the Lamarckian system; but
the reader will hardly, perhaps, be able to form a perfect conception of
so complicated a piece of mechanism, unless it is exhibited in motion,
so that we may see in what manner it can work out, under the author's
guidance, all the extraordinary effects which we behold in the present
state of the animate creation. I have only space for exhibiting a small
part of the entire process by which a complete metamorphosis is
achieved, and shall therefore omit the mode by which, after a countless
succession of generations, a small gelatinous body is transformed into
an oak or an ape; passing on at once to the last grand step in the
progressive scheme, by which the orang-outang, having been already
evolved out of a monad, is made slowly to attain the attributes and
dignity of man.
One of the races of quadrumanous animals which had reached the
highest state of perfection, lost, by constraint of circumstances (concerning
the exact nature of which tradition is unfortunately silent), the
habit of climbing trees, and of hanging on by grasping the boughs with
their feet as with hands. The individuals of this race being obliged,
for a long series of generations, to use their feet exclusively for walking,
and ceasing to employ their hands as feet, were transformed into
bimanous animals, and what before were thumbs became mere toes, no
separation being required when their feet were used solely for walking.
Having acquired a habit of holding themselves upright, their legs and
feet assumed, insensibly, a conformation fitted to support them in an
erect attitude, till at last these animals could no longer go on all-fours
without much inconvenience.
The Angola orang (Simia troglodytes, Linn.) is the most perfect of
576
animals; much more so than the Indian orang (Simia Satyrus), which
has been called the orang-outang, although both are very inferior to
man in corporeal powers and intelligence. These animals frequently
hold themselves upright; but their organization has not yet been sufficiently
modified to sustain them habitually in this attitude, so that the
standing posture is very uneasy to them. When the Indian orang is
compelled to take flight from pressing danger, he immediately falls
down upon all-fours, showing clearly that this was the original position
of the animal. Even in man, whose organization, in the course of a
long series of generations, has advanced so much farther, the upright
posture is fatiguing, and can be supported only for a limited time, and
by aid of the contraction of many muscles. If the vertebral column
formed the axis of the human body, and supported the head and all
the other parts in equilibrium, then might the upright position be a
state of repose: but, as the human head does not articulate in the centre
of gravity, as the chest, belly, and other parts press almost entirely
forward with their whole weight, and as the vertebral column reposes
upon an oblique base, a watchful activity is required to prevent the
body from falling. Children who have large heads and prominent bellies
can hardly walk at the end even of two years; and their frequent
tumbles indicate the natural tendency in man to resume the quadrupedal
state.
Now, when so much progress had been made by the quadrumanous
animals before mentioned, that they could hold themselves habitually
in an erect attitude, and were accustomed to a wide range of vision, and
ceased to use their jaws for fighting and tearing, or for clipping herbs
for food, their snout became gradually shorter, their incisor teeth became
vertical, and the facial angle grew more open.
Among other ideas which the natural tendency to perfection engendered,
the desire of ruling suggested itself, and this race succeeded at
length in getting the better of the other animals, and made themselves
masters of all those spots on the surface of the globe which best suited
them. They drove out the animals which approached nearest them in
organization and intelligence, and which were in a condition to dispute
with them the good things of this world, forcing them to take refuge in
deserts, woods, and wildernesses, where their multiplication was checked,
and the progressive development of their faculties retarded; while, in
the mean time, the dominant race spread itself in every direction, and
lived in large companies, where new wants were successively created,
exciting them to industry, and gradually perfecting their means and
faculties.
In the supremacy and increased intelligence acquired by the ruling
race, we see an illustration of the natural tendency of the organic world
to grow more perfect; and, in their influence in repressing the advance
of others, an example of one of those disturbing causes before enumerated,
that force of external circumstances which causes such wide chasms
in the regular series of animated being.
577
When the individuals of the dominant race became very numerous,
their ideas greatly increased in number, and they felt the necessity of
communicating them to each other, and of augmenting and varying the
signs proper for the communication of ideas. Meanwhile the inferior
quadrumanous animals, although most of them were gregarious, acquired
no new ideas, being persecuted and restless in the deserts, and obliged
to fly and conceal themselves, so that they conceived no new wants.
Such ideas as they already had remained unaltered, and they could dispense
with the communication of the greater part of these. To make
themselves, therefore, understood by their fellows, required merely a
few movements of the body or limbs—whistling, and the uttering of
certain cries varied by the inflexions of the voice.
On the contrary, the individuals of the ascendant race, animated with
a desire of interchanging their ideas, which became more and more
numerous, were prompted to multiply the means of communication, and
were no longer satisfied with mere pantomimic signs, nor even with all
the possible inflexions of the voice, but made continual efforts to acquire
the power of uttering articulate sounds, employing a few at first, but
afterwards varying and perfecting them according to the increase of their
wants. The habitual exercise of their throat, tongue, and lips, insensibly
modified the conformation of these organs, until they became fitted for
the faculty of speech.798
In effecting this mighty change, "the exigencies of the individuals
were the sole agents; they gave rise to efforts, and the organs proper
for articulating sounds were developed by their habitual employment."
Hence, in this peculiar race, the origin of the admirable faculty of speech;
hence also the diversity of languages, since the distance of places where
the individuals composing the race established themselves soon favored
the corruption of conventional signs.799
In conclusion, it may be proper to observe that the above sketch of
the Lamarckian theory is no exaggerated picture, and those passages
which have probably excited the greatest surprise in the mind of the
reader are literal translations from the original.

578</div></body></text></TEI>