<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="10">CHAPTER I.
Earliest Stages of Astronomy.

Sect. 1.—Formation of the Notion of a
Year.
THE notion of a Day is
early and obviously impressed upon man in almost any condition in
which we can imagine him. The recurrence of light and darkness, of
comparative warmth and cold, of noise and silence, of the activity and
repose of animals;—the rising, mounting, descending, and setting
of the sun;—the varying colors of the clouds, generally,
notwithstanding their variety, marked by a daily progression of
appearances;—the calls of the desire of food and of sleep in man
himself, either exactly adjusted to the period of this change, or at
least readily capable of being accommodated to it;—the
recurrence of these circumstances at intervals, equal, so far as our
obvious judgment of the passage of time can decide; and these
intervals so short that the repetition is noticed with no effort of
attention or memory;—this assemblage of suggestions makes the
notion of a Day necessarily occur to man, if we suppose him to have
the conception of Time, and of Recurrence. He naturally marks by a
term such a portion of time, and such a cycle of recurrence; he calls
each portion of time, in which this series of appearances and
occurrences come round, a Day; and such a group of particulars
are considered as appearing or happening in the same day.
A Year is a notion formed in the same manner; implying in
the same way the notion of recurring facts; and also the faculty of
arranging facts in time, and of appreciating their recurrence. But the
notion of a Year, though undoubtedly very obvious, is, on many
accounts, less so than that of a Day. The repetition of similar
circumstances, at equal intervals, is less manifest in this case, and
the intervals being much longer, some exertion of memory becomes
requisite in order that the recurrence may be perceived. A child might
easily be persuaded that successive years were of unequal length; or,
if the summer were cold, and the spring and autumn warm, might be made
to believe, if all who spoke in its hearing agreed to support the
delusion, that one year was two. It would be impossible to practise
such a deception with regard to the day, without the use of some
artifice beyond mere words. 113
Still, the recurrence of the appearances which suggest the notion
of a Year is so obvious, that we can hardly conceive man without it.
But though, in all climes and times, there would be a recurrence, and
at the same interval in all, the recurring appearances would be
extremely different in different countries; and the contrasts and
resemblances of the seasons would be widely varied. In some places the
winter utterly alters the face of the country, converting grassy
hills, deep leafy woods of various hues of green, and running waters,
into snowy and icy wastes, and bare snow-laden branches; while in
others, the field retains its herbage, and the tree its leaves, all
the year; and the rains and the sunshine alone, or various
agricultural employments quite different from ours, mark the passing
seasons. Yet in all parts of the world the yearly cycle of changes has
been singled out from all others, and designated by a peculiar name.
The inhabitant of the equatorial regions has the sun vertically over
him at the end of every period of six months, and similar trains of
celestial phenomena fill up each of these intervals, yet we do not
find years of six months among such nations. The Arabs alone,1
who practise neither agriculture nor navigation, have a year depending
upon the moon only; and borrow the word from other languages, when
they speak of the solar year.
1 Ideler, Berl. Trans. 1813, p.
51.
In general, nations have marked this portion of time by some word
which has a reference to the returning circle of seasons and
employments. Thus the Latin annus signified a ring, as we see
in the derivative annulus: the Greek term ἐνιαυτὸς implies
something which returns into itself: and the word as it exists
in Teutonic languages, of which our word year is an example, is
said to have its origin in the word yra which means a ring in
Swedish, and is perhaps connected with the Latin gyrus.
Sect. 2.—Fixation of the Civil Year.
The year, considered as a recurring cycle
of seasons and of general appearances, must attract the notice of man
as soon as his attention and memory suffice to bind together the parts
of a succession of the length of several years. But to make the same
term imply a certain fixed number of days, we must know how many days
the cycle of the seasons occupies; a knowledge which requires
faculties and artifices beyond what we have already mentioned. For
instance, men cannot reckon as far as any number at all approaching
the number of days in the year, without possessing a system of numeral
terms, and methods 114 of practical numeration on which such a
system of terms is always founded.2 The South American
Indians, the Koussa Caffres and Hottentots, and the natives of New
Holland, all of whom are said to be unable to reckon further than the
fingers of their hands and feet,3 cannot, as we do,
include in their notion of a year the fact of its consisting of 365
days. This fact is not likely to be known to any nation except those
which have advanced far beyond that which may be considered as the
earliest scientific process which we can trace in the history of the
human race, the formation of a method of designating the successive
numbers to an indefinite extent, by means of names, framed according
to the decimal, quinary, or vigenary scale.
2 Arithmetic in Encyc.
Metrop. (by Dr. Peacock), Art. 8.
3 Ibid. Art. 32.
But even if we suppose men to have the habit of recording the
passage of each day, and of counting the score thus recorded, it would
be by no means easy for them to determine the exact number of days in
which the cycle of the seasons recurs; for the indefiniteness of the
appearances which mark the same season of the year, and the changes to
which they are subject as the seasons are early or late, would leave
much uncertainty respecting the duration of the year. They would not
obtain any accuracy on this head, till they had attended for a
considerable time to the motions and places of the sun; circumstances
which require more precision of notice than the general facts of the
degrees of heat and light. The motions of the sun, the succession of
the places of his rising and setting at different times of the year,
the greatest heights which he reaches, the proportion of the length of
day and night, would all exhibit several cycles. The turning back of
the sun, when he had reached the greatest distance to the south or to
the north, as shown either by his rising or by his height at noon,
would perhaps be the most observable of such circumstances.
Accordingly the τροπαὶ ἠελίοιο, the turnings of the sun, are used
repeatedly by Hesiod as a mark from which he reckons the seasons of
various employments. “Fifty days,” he says, “after the turning of the
sun, is a seasonable time for beginning a voyage.”4
4


Ἤματα πεντήκοντα μετὰ τροπὰς ἠελίοιο 
Ἐς τέλος ἐλθόντος θέρεος.—Op. et
Dies, 661.


The phenomena would be different
in different climates, but the recurrence would be common to all. Any
one of these kinds of phenomena, noted with moderate care for a year,
would show what was the number of days of which a year consisted; and
if several years 115 were included in the interval through
which the scrutiny extended, the knowledge of the length of the year
so acquired would be proportionally more exact.
Besides those notices of the sun which offered exact indications of
the seasons, other more indefinite natural occurrences were used; as
the arrival of the swallow (χελιδών) and the kite (ἰκτίν), The birds,
in Aristophanes’ play of that name, mention it as one of their offices
to mark the seasons; Hesiod similarly notices the cry of the crane as
an indication of the departure of winter.5
5 Ideler, i. 240.
Among the Greeks the seasons were at first only summer and winter
(θέρος and χειμών), the latter including all the rainy and cold
portion of the year. The winter was then subdivided into the χειμών
and ἔαρ (winter proper and spring), and the summer, less definitely,
into θέρος and ὀπώρα (summer and autumn). Tacitus says that the
Germans knew neither the blessings nor the name of autumn, “Autumni
perinde nomen ac bona ignorantur.” Yet harvest, herbst,
is certainly an old German word.6
6 Ib. i. 243.
In the same period in which the sun goes through his cycle of
positions, the stars also go through a cycle of appearances belonging
to them; and these appearances were perhaps employed at as early a
period as those of the sun, in determining the exact length of the
year. Many of the groups of fixed stars are readily recognized, as
exhibiting always the same configuration; and particular bright stars
are singled out as objects of attention. These are observed, at
particular seasons, to appear in the west after sunset; but it is
noted that when they do this, they are found nearer and nearer to the
sun every successive evening, and at last disappear in his light. It
is observed also, that at a certain interval after this, they rise
visibly before the dawn of day renders the stars invisible; and after
they are seen to do this, they rise every day at a longer interval
before the sun. The risings and settings of the stars under these
circumstances, or under others which are easily recognized, were, in
countries where the sky is usually clear, employed at an early period
to mark the seasons of the year. Eschylus7 makes Prometheus
mention this among the benefits of which 116 he, the teacher of arts to the earliest
race of men, was the communicator.
7 

Οὔκ ἤν γαρ αὐτοῖς οὔτε χείματος τέκμαρ,
Οὔτ’ ἀνθεμώδους ἦρος, οὔδε καρπίμου
Θέρους βέβαιον· ἀλλ’ ἄτερ γνώμης τὸ πᾶν
Ἔπρασσον, ἔστε δή σφιν ἀνατολὰς ἐγὼ
Ἄστρων ἔδειξα, τάς τε δυσκρίτους
δύσεις.—Prom. V. 454.
 Thus, for instance, the rising8
of the Pleiades in the evening was a mark of the approach of winter.
The rising of the waters of the Nile in Egypt coincided with the
heliacal rising of Sirius, which star the Egyptians called Sothis.
Even without any artificial measure of time or position, it was not
difficult to carry observations of this kind to such a degree of
accuracy as to learn from them the number of days which compose the
year; and to fix the precise season from the appearance of the
stars.
8 Ideler (Chronol. i. 242) says that
this rising of the Pleiades took place at a time of the year
which corresponds to our 11th May, and the setting to the 20th
October; but this does not agree with the forty days of their being
“concealed,” which, from the context, must mean, I conceive, the
interval between their setting and rising. Pliny, however, says,
“Vergiliarum exortu æstas incipit, occasu hiems; semestri
spatio intra se messes vindemiasque et omnium maturitatem complexæ.”
(H. N. xviii. 69.)
 The autumn of the Greeks, ὀπώρα, was earlier than our autumn,
for Homer calls Sirius ἀστὴρ ὀπωρινός, which rose at the end of
July.
A knowledge concerning the stars appears to have been first
cultivated with the last-mentioned view, and makes its first
appearance in literature with this for its object. Thus Hesiod directs
the husbandman when to reap by the rising, and when to plough by the
setting of the Pleiades.9 In like manner Sirius,10 Arcturus,11 the Hyades and
Orion,12 are noticed.
9 

Πληίαδων Ἀτλαγενέων ἐπιτελλομενάων.
Ἄρχεσθ’ ἀμητοῦ· ἀρότοιο δὲ, δυσομενάων.
Αἵ δή τοι νύκτας τε καὶ ἤματα τεσσεράκοντα
Κεκρύφαται, αὔτις δὲ περιπλομένου ἐνιαυτοῦ
Φαίνονται. Op. et
Dies, l. 381. 

10 Ib. l. 413.
11

Εὖτ’ ἂν δ’ ἑξήκοντα μετὰ τροπὰς ἠελίοιο
Χειμέρι’, ἐκτελέσῃ Ζεὺς ἤματα, δή ῥα τότ’
ἀστὴρ
Ἀρκτοῦρος, προλιπὼν ἱερὸν ῥόον Ὠκεανοῖο
Πρῶτον παμφαίνων ἐπιτέλλεται ἀκροκνέφαιος.
 Op. et
Dies, l. 562.
 
 Εὖτ’ ἂν δ’ Ὠρίων καὶ Σείριος ἐς μέσον
ἔλθῃ
Οὐρανὸν, Ἀρκτοῦρον δ’ ἐσὶδῃ ῥοδοδάκτυλος
ἠὼς.
            Ib. 607.
12



. . . . . . .  αὐτὰρ ἐπὴν
δὴ
Πληϊάδες Ὑάδες τε τὸ τε σθένος Ὠρίωνος
Δύνωσιν. Ib.
612.  
 These methods were
employed to a late period, because the Greek months, being lunar, did
not correspond to the seasons. Tables of such motions were called
παραπήγματα.—Ideler, Hist. Untersuchungen, p. 209.
117 By such
means it was determined that the year consisted, at least, nearly, of
365 days. The Egyptians, as we learn from Herodotus,13 claimed the honor of this discovery.
The priests informed him, he says, “that the Egyptians were the first
men who discovered the year, dividing it into twelve equal parts; and
this they asserted that they discovered from the stars.” Each of these
parts or months consisted of 30 days, and they added 5 days more at
the end of the year, “and thus the circle of the seasons come round.”
It seems, also, that the Jews, at an early period, had a similar
reckoning of time, for the Deluge which continued 150 days (Gen. vii.
24), is stated to have lasted from the 17th day of the second month
(Gen. vii. 11) to the 17th day of the seventh month (Gen. viii. 4),
that is, 5 months of 30 days.
13 Ib. ii. 4.
A year thus settled as a period of a certain number of days is
called a Civil Year. It is one of the earliest discoverable
institutions of States possessing any germ of civilization; and one of
the earliest portions of human systematic knowledge is the discovery
of the length of the civil year, so that it should agree with the
natural year, or year of the seasons.
Sect. 3.—Correction of the Civil Year.
(Julian Calendar.)
In reality, by such a mode of reckoning as
we have described, the circle of the seasons would not come round
exactly. The real length of the year is very nearly 365 days and a
quarter. If a year of 365 days were used, in four years the year would
begin a day too soon, when considered with reference to the sun and
stars; and in 60 years it would begin 15 days too soon: a quantity
perceptible to the loosest degree of attention. The civil year would
be found not to coincide with the year of the seasons; the beginning
of the former would take place at different periods of the latter; it
would wander into various seasons, instead of remaining fixed
to the same season; the term year, and any number of years,
would become ambiguous: some correction, at least some comparison,
would be requisite.
We do not know by whom the insufficiency of the year of 365 days
was first discovered;14 we find this knowledge diffused among
all civilized nations, and various artifices used in making the
correction. The method which we employ, and which consists in
reckoning an 118
additional day at the end of February every fourth or leap
year, is an example of the principle of intercalation, by which
the correction was most commonly made. Methods of intercalation for
the same purpose were found to exist in the new world. The Mexicans
added 13 days at the end of every 52 years. The method of the Greeks
was more complex (by means of the octaëteris or cycle of 8
years); but it had the additional object of accommodating itself to
the motions of the moon, and therefore must be treated of hereafter.
The Egyptians, on the other hand, knowingly permitted their civil year
to wander, at least so far as their religious observances were
concerned. “They do not wish,” says Geminus,15 “the same
sacrifices of the gods to be made perpetually at the same time of the
year, but that they should go through all the seasons, so that the
same feast may happen in summer and winter, in spring and autumn.” The
period in which any festival would thus pass through all the seasons
of the year is 1461 years; for 1460 years of 365¼ days are equal to
1461 years of 365 days. This period of 1461 years is called the
Sothic Period, from Sothis, the name of the Dog-star, by which
their fixed year was determined; and for the same reason it
is called the Canicular Period.16
14 Syncellus (Chronographia, p.
123) says that according to the legend, it was King Aseth who first
added the 5 additional days to 360, for the year, in the eighteenth
century, b. c.
15 Uranol. p. 33.
16 Censorinus de Die Natali, c.
18.
Other nations did not regulate their civil year by intercalation at
short intervals, but rectified it by a reform when this
became necessary. The Persians are said to have added a month of 30
days every 120 years. The Roman calendar, at first very rude in its
structure, was reformed by Numa, and was directed to be kept in order
by the perpetual interposition of the augurs. This, however, was, from
various causes, not properly done; and the consequence was, that the
reckoning fell into utter disorder, in which state it was found by
Julius Cæsar, when he became dictator. By the advice of Sosigenes, he
adopted the mode of intercalation of one day in 4 years, which we
still retain; and in order to correct the derangement which had
already been produced, he added 90 days to a year of the usual length,
which thus became what was called the year of confusion. The
Julian Calendar, thus reformed, came into use, January 1, b. c. 45.
Sect. 4.—Attempts at the Fixation of the
Month.
The circle of changes through which the
moon passes in about thirty days, is marked, in the earliest stages of
language, by a word which implies the space of time which one such
circle occupies; just 119 as the circle of changes of the seasons
is designated by the word year. The lunar changes are, indeed,
more obvious to the sense, and strike a more careless person, than the
annual; the moon, when the sun is absent, is almost the sole natural
object which attracts our notice; and we look at her with a far more
tranquil and agreeable attention than we bestow on any other celestial
object. Her changes of form and place are definite and striking to all
eyes; they are uninterrupted, and the duration of their cycle is so
short as to require no effort of memory to embrace it. Hence it
appears to be more easy, and in earlier stages of civilization more
common, to count time by moons than by years.
The words by which this period of time is designated in various
languages, seem to refer us to the early history of language. Our word
month is connected with the word moon, and a similar
connection is noticeable in the other branches of the Teutonic. The
Greek word μὴν in like manner is related to μήνη, which though not the
common word for the moon, is found in Homer with that signification.
The Latin word mensis is probably connected with the same
group.17
17 Cicero derives this word from the
verb to measure: “quia mensa spatia conficiunt,
menses nominantur;” and other etymologists, with similar views,
connect the above-mentioned words with the Hebrew manah, to
measure (with which the Arabic word almanach is connected).
Such a derivation would have some analogy with that of annus,
&c., noticed above: but if we are to
attempt to ascend to the earliest condition of language, we must
conceive it probable that men would have a name for a most conspicuous
visible object, the moon, before they would have a verb
denoting the very abstract and general notion, to
measure.
The month is not any exact number of days, being more than 29, and
less than 30. The latter number was first tried, for men more readily
select numbers possessing some distinction of regularity. It existed
for a long period in many countries. A very few months of 30 days,
however, would suffice to derange the agreement between the days of
the months and the moon’s appearance. A little further trial would
show that months of 29 and 30 days alternately, would preserve, for a
considerable period, this agreement.
The Greeks adopted this calendar, and, in consequence, considered
the days of their month as representing the changes of the moon: the
last day of the month was called ἔνη καὶ νέα, “the old and new” as
belonging to both the waning and the reappearing moon:18 and their 120 festivals and sacrifices, as determined
by the calendar, were conceived to be necessarily connected with the
same periods of the cycles of the sun and moon. “The laws and the
oracles,” says Geminus, “which directed that they should in sacrifices
observe three things, months, days, years, were so understood.” With
this persuasion, a correct system of intercalation became a religious
duty.
18 Aratus says of the moon, in a
passage quoted by Geminus, p. 33:

Αἴει δ’ ἄλλοθεν ἄλλα παρακλίνουσα
μετωπὰ
Εἴρῃ, ὁποσταίη μήνος περιτέλλεται ἡὼς
As still her shifting visage changing
turns,
By her we count the monthly round of
morns.
The above rule of alternate months of 29 and 30 days, supposes the
length of the months 29 days and a half, which is not exactly the
length of a lunar month. Accordingly the Months and the Moon were soon
at variance. Aristophanes, in “The Clouds,” makes the Moon complain of
the disorder when the calendar was deranged.


       Οὐκ ἄγειν τὰς
ἡμέρας
Οὐδὲν ὀρθῶς, ἀλλ’ ἀνω τε καὶ κάτω
κυδοιδοπᾶν
 Ὥστ’ ἀπειλεῖν φησὶν αὐτῇ τοὐς θεοὺς
ἑκάστοτε
 Ἡνίκ’ ἂν ψευσθῶσι δείπνου κἀπίωσιν οἴκαδε
 Τῆς ἑορτῆς μὴ τυχόντες κατὰ λόγον τῶν
ἡμερῶν.
Nubes, 615–19.
Chorus of Clouds.


The Moon by us to you her greeting
sends,
But bids us say that she’s an ill-used
moon,
And takes it much amiss that you should
still
Shuffle her days, and turn them
topsy-turvy:
And that the gods (who know their feast-days
well)
By your false count are sent home
supperless,
And scold and storm at her for your neglect.19
19 This passage is supposed by the
commentators to be intended as a satire upon those who had introduced
the cycle of Meton (spoken of in Sect. 5),
which had been done at Athens a few years before “The Clouds” was
acted.
The correction of this inaccuracy, however, was not pursued
separately, but was combined with another object, the securing a
correspondence between the lunar and solar years, the main purpose of
all early cycles.
Sect. 5.—Invention of Lunisolar Years.
There are 12 complete lunations in a year;
which according to the above rule (of 29½ days to a lunation) would
make 354 days, leaving 12¼ days of difference between such a lunar
year and a solar year. It is said that, at an early period, this was
attempted to be corrected by interpolating a month of 30 days every
alternate year; and Herodotus20 relates a
conversation of Solon, implying a still ruder mode of 121 intercalation. This
can hardly be considered as an improvement in the Greek calendar
already described.
20 B. i. c. 15.
The first cycle which produced any near correspondence of the
reckoning of the moon and the sun, was the Octaëteris, or
period of 8 years: 8 years of 354 days, together with 3 months of 30
days each, making up (in 99 lunations) 2922 days; which is exactly the
amount of 8 years of 365¼ days each. Hence this period would answer
its purpose, so far as the above lengths of the lunar and solar cycles
are exact; and it might assume various forms, according to the manner
in which the three intercalary months were distributed. The customary
method was to add a thirteenth month at the end of the third, fifth,
and eighth year of the cycle. This period is ascribed to various
persons and times; probably different persons proposed different forms
of it. Dodwell places its introduction in the 59th Olympiad, or in the
6th century, b. c.: but Ideler thinks the
astronomical knowledge of the Greeks of that age was too limited to
allow of such a discovery.
This cycle, however, was imperfect. The duration of 99 lunations is
something more than 2922 days; it is more nearly 2923½; hence in 16
years there was a deficiency of 3 days, with regard to the motions of
the moon. This cycle of 16 years (Heccædecaëteris), with 3
interpolated days at the end, was used, it is said, to bring the
calculation right with regard to the moon; but in this way the origin
of the year was displaced with regard to the sun. After 10 revolutions
of this cycle, or 160 years, the interpolated days would amount to 30,
and hence the end of the lunar year would be a month in advance of the
end of the solar. By terminating the lunar year at the end of the
preceding month, the two years would again be brought into agreement:
and we have thus a cycle of 160 years.21
21 Geminus. Ideler.
This cycle of 160 years, however, was calculated from the cycle of
16 years; and it was probably never used in civil reckoning; which the
others, or at least that of 8 years, appear to have been.
The cycles of 16 and 160 years were corrections of
the cycle of 8 years; and were readily suggested, when the length of
the solar and lunar periods became known with accuracy. But a much
more exact cycle, independent of these, was discovered and introduced
by Meton,22 432 years b. c.
This cycle consisted of 19 years, and is so correct and convenient,
that it is in use among ourselves to this day. The time occupied by 19
years, and by 235 lunations, is very nearly the same; 122 (the former time is
less than 6940 days by 9½ hours, the latter, by 7½ hours). Hence, if
the 19 years be divided into 235 months, so as to agree with the
changes of the moon, at the end of that period the same succession may
begin again with great exactness.
22 Ideler, Hist. Unters. p.
208.
In order that 235 months, of 30 and 29 days, may make up 6940 days,
we must have 125 of the former, which were called full months,
and 110 of the latter, which were termed hollow. An artifice
was used in order to distribute 110 hollow months among 6940 days. It
will be found that there is a hollow month for each 63 days nearly.
Hence if we reckon 30 days to every month, but at every 63d day leap
over a day in the reckoning, we shall, in the 19 years, omit 110 days;
and this accordingly was done. Thus the 3d day of the 3d month, the
6th day of the 5th month, the 9th day of the 7th, must be omitted, so
as to make these months “hollow.” Of the 19 years, seven must consist
of 13 months; and it does not appear to be known according to what
order these seven years were selected. Some say they were the 3d, 6th,
8th, 11th, 14th, 17th, and 19th; others, the 3d, 5th, 8th, 11th, 13th,
16th, and 19th.
The near coincidence of the solar and lunar periods in this cycle
of 19 years, was undoubtedly a considerable discovery at the time when
it was first accomplished. It is not easy to trace the way in which
such a discovery was made at that time; for we do not even know the
manner in which men then recorded the agreement or difference between
the calendar day and the celestial phenomenon which ought to
correspond to it. It is most probable that the length of the month was
obtained with some exactness by the observation of eclipses, at
considerable intervals of time from each other; for eclipses are very
noticeable phenomena, and must have been very soon observed to occur
only at new and full moon.23
23 Thucyd. vii. 50. Ἡ σελήνη ἐκλείπει·
ἐτύγχανε γὰρ πανσέληνος οὖσα. iv. 52, Τοῦ
ἡλίου ἐκλιπές τι ἐγένετο περὶ νουμηνίαν. ii.
28. Νουμηνίᾳ κατὰ σελήνην (ὥσπερ καὶ μόνον
δοκεῖ εἶναι γίγνεσθαι δυνατὸν) ὁ ἡλίος ἐξέλιπε μετὰ μεσημβρίαν καὶ
πάλιν ἀν ἐπληρώθη, γενόμενος μηνοειδὴς καὶ ἀστέρων τινῶν
ἐκφανέντων.
The exact length of a certain number of months being thus known,
the discovery of a cycle which should regulate the calendar with
sufficient accuracy would be a business of arithmetical skill, and
would depend, in part, on the existing knowledge of arithmetical
methods; but in making the discovery, a natural arithmetical sagacity
was probably more efficacious than method. It is very possible that
the Cycle of Meton is correct more nearly than its author was
aware, and 123
nearly than he could ascertain from any evidence and calculation known
to him. It is so exact that it is still used in calculating the new
moon for the time of Easter; and the Golden Number, which is
spoken of in stating such rules, is the number of this Cycle
corresponding to the current year.24
24 The same cycle of 19 years has been
used by the Chinese for a very great length of time; their civil year
consisting, like that of the Greeks, of months of 29 and 30 days. The
Siamese also have this period. (Astron. Lib. U. K.)
Meton’s Cycle was corrected a hundred years later (330 b. c.), by Calippus, who discovered the error of it
by observing an eclipse of the moon six years before the death of
Alexander.25 In this corrected period, four cycles
of 19 years were taken, and a day left out at the end of the 76 years,
in order to make allowance for the hours by which, as already
observed, 6940 days are greater than 19 years, and than 235 lunations:
and this Calippic period is used in Ptolemy’s Almagest, in
stating observations of eclipses.
25 Delamb. A. A. p. 17.
The Metonic and Calippic periods undoubtedly imply a very
considerable degree of accuracy in the knowledge which the
astronomers, to whom they are due, had of the length of the month; and
the first is a very happy invention for bringing the solar and lunar
calendars into agreement.
The Roman Calendar, from which our own is derived, appears to have
been a much less skilful contrivance than the Greek; though scholars
are not agreed on the subject of its construction, we can hardly doubt
that months, in this as in other cases, were intended originally to
have a reference to the moon. In whatever manner the solar and lunar
motions were intended to be reconciled, the attempt seems altogether
to have failed, and to have been soon abandoned. The Roman months,
both before and after the Julian correction, were portions of the
year, having no reference to full and new moons; and we, having
adopted this division of the year, have thus, in our common calendar,
the traces of one of the early attempts of mankind to seize the law of
the succession of celestial phenomena, in a case where the attempt was
a complete failure.
Considered as a part of the progress of our astronomical knowledge,
improvements in the calendar do not offer many points to our
observation, but they exhibit a few very important steps. Calendars
which, belonging apparently to unscientific ages and nations, possess
a great degree of accordance with the true motions of the sun and moon
(like 124 the solar
calendar of the Mexicans, and the lunar calendar of the Greeks),
contain the only record now extant of discoveries which must have
required a great deal of observation, of thought, and probably of
time. The later improvements in calendars, which take place when
astronomical observation has been attentively pursued, are of little
consequence to the history of science; for they are generally founded
on astronomical determinations, and are posterior in time, and
inferior in accuracy, to the knowledge on which they depend. But
cycles of correction, which are both short and close to exactness,
like that of Meton, may perhaps be the original form of the knowledge
which they imply; and certainly require both accurate facts and
sagacious arithmetical reasonings. The discovery of such a cycle must
always have the appearance of a happy guess, like other discoveries of
laws of nature. Beyond this point, the interest of the study of
calendars, as bearing on our subject, ceases: they may be considered
as belonging rather to Art than to Science; rather as an application
of a part of our knowledge to the uses of life, than a means or an
evidence of its extension.
Sect. 6.—The Constellations.
Some tendency to consider the stars as
formed into groups, is inevitable when men begin to attend to them;
but how men were led to the fanciful system of names of Stars and of
Constellations, which we find to have prevailed in early times, it is
very difficult to determine. Single stars, and very close groups, as
the Pleiades, were named in the time of Homer and Hesiod, and at a
still earlier period, as we find in the book of Job.26
26 Job xxxviii. 31. “Canst thou bind
the sweet influences of Chima (the Pleiades), or loose the bands of
Kesil (Orion)? Canst thou bring forth Mazzaroth (Sirius) in his
season? or canst thou guide Ash (or Aisch) (Arcturus) with his
sons?”
 And ix. 9. “Which maketh Arcturus, Orion, and Pleiades, and the
chambers of the south.”
 Dupuis, vi. 545, thinks that Aisch was αἴξ, the goat and kids.
See Hyde, Ulughbeigh.
Two remarkable circumstances with respect to the Constellations
are, first, that they appear in most cases to be arbitrary
combinations; the artificial figures which are made to include the
stars, not having any resemblance to their obvious configurations; and
second, that these figures, in different countries, are so far
similar, as to imply some communication. The arbitrary nature of these
figures shows that they 125 were rather the work of the imaginative
and mythological tendencies of man, than of mere convenience and love
of arrangement. “The constellations,” says an astronomer of our own
time,27 “seem to have been almost purposely
named and delineated to cause as much confusion and inconvenience as
possible. Innumerable snakes twine through long and contorted areas of
the heavens, where no memory can follow them: bears, lions, and
fishes, large and small, northern and southern, confuse all
nomenclature. A better system of constellations might have been a
material help as an artificial memory.” When men indicate the stars by
figures, borrowed from obvious resemblances, they are led to
combinations quite different from the received constellations. Thus
the common people in our own country find a wain or wagon, or a
plough, in a portion of the great bear.28
27 Sir J. Herschel.
28 So also the Greeks, Homer,
Il. xviii. 487.


Ἄρκτον ἢν καὶ ἄμαξαν ἐπίκλησιν
καλέουσιν.
The Northern Bear which oft the Wain they
call.
Ἄρκτος was the traditional name; ἄμαξα, that suggested by the
form.
The similarity of the constellations recognized in different
countries is very remarkable. The Chaldean, the Egyptian, and the
Grecian skies have a resemblance which cannot be overlooked. Some have
conceived that this resemblance may be traced also in the Indian and
Arabic constellations, at least in those of the zodiac.29 But while the figures are the same, the
names and traditions connected with them are different, according to
the histories and localities of each country;30 the river among
the stars which the Greeks called the Eridanus, the Egyptians asserted
to be the Nile. Some conceive that the Signs of the Zodiac, or
path along which the sun and moon pass, had its divisions marked by
signs which had a reference to the course of the seasons, to the
motion of the sun, or the employments of the husbandman. If we take
the position of the heavens, which, from the knowledge we now possess,
we are sure they must have had 15,000 years ago, the significance of
the signs of the zodiac, in which the sun was, as referred to the
Egyptian year, becomes very marked,31 and has led some
to suppose that the zodiac was invented at such a period. Others have
rejected this as an improbably great antiquity, and have thought it
more likely that the constellation assigned to each season was that
which, at that season, rose at the beginning of the night: 126 thus the balance
(which is conceived to designate the equality of days and nights) was
placed among the stars which rose in the evening when the spring
began: this would fix the origin of these signs 2500 years before our
era.
29 Dupuis, vi. 548. The Indian zodiac
contains, in the place of our Capricorn, a ram and a fish,
which proves the resemblance without chance of mistake. Bailly, i. p.
157.
30 Dupuis, vi. 549.
31 Laplace, Hist. Astron. p.
8.
It is clear, as has already been said, that Fancy, and probably
Superstition, had a share in forming the collection of constellations.
It is certain that, at an early period, superstitious notions were
associated with the stars.32 Astrology is of very high antiquity in
the East. The stars were supposed to influence the character and
destiny of man, and to be in some way connected with superior natures
and powers.
32 Dupuis, vi. 546.
We may, I conceive, look upon the formation of the constellations,
and the notions thus connected with them, as a very early attempt to
find a meaning in the relations of the stars; and as an utter failure.
The first effort to associate the appearances and motions of the skies
by conceptions implying unity and connection, was made in a wrong
direction, as may very easily be supposed. Instead of considering the
appearances only with reference to space, time, number, in a manner
purely rational, a number of other elements, imagination, tradition,
hope, fear, awe of the supernatural, belief in destiny, were called
into action. Man, still young, as a philosopher at least, had yet to
learn what notions his successful guesses on these subjects must
involve, and what they must exclude. At that period, nothing could be
more natural or excusable than this ignorance; but it is curious to
see how long and how obstinately the belief lingered (if indeed it be
yet extinct) that the motions of the stars, and the dispositions and
fortunes of men, may come under some common conceptions and laws, by
which a connection between the one and the other may be
established.
We cannot, therefore, agree with those who consider Astrology in
the early ages as “only a degraded Astronomy, the abuse of a more
ancient science.”33 It was the first step to astronomy by
leading to habits and means of grouping phenomena; and, after a while,
by showing that pictorial and mythological relations among the stars
had no very obvious value. From that time, the inductive process went
on steadily in the true road, under the guidance of ideas of space,
time, and number.
33 Ib. vi. 546.
Sect. 7.—The Planets.
While men were becoming familiar with the
fixed stars, the planets must have attracted their notice. Venus, from
her brightness, and 127 from her accompanying the sun at no
great distance, and thus appearing as the morning and evening star,
was very conspicuous. Pythagoras is said to have maintained that the
evening and morning star are the same body, which certainly must have
been one of the earliest discoveries on this subject; and indeed we
can hardly conceive men noticing the stars for a year or two without
coming to this conclusion.
Jupiter and Mars, sometimes still brighter than Venus, were also
very noticeable. Saturn and Mercury were less so, but in fine climates
they and their motion would soon be detected by persons observant of
the heavens. To reduce to any rule the movements of these luminaries
must have taken time and thought; probably before this was done,
certainly very early, these heavenly bodies were brought more
peculiarly under those views which we have noticed as leading to
astrology.
At a time beyond the reach of certain history, the planets, along
with the sun and moon, had been arranged in a certain recognized order
by the Egyptians or some other ancient nation. Probably this
arrangement had been made according to the slowness of their motions
among the stars; for though the motion of each is very variable, the
gradation of their velocities is, on the whole, very manifest; and the
different rate of travelling of the different planets, and probably
other circumstances of difference, led, in the ready fancy of early
times, to the attribution of a peculiar character to each luminary.
Thus Saturn was held to be of a cold and gelid nature; Jupiter, who,
from his more rapid motion, was supposed to be lower in place, was
temperate; Mars, fiery, and the like.34
34 Achilles Tatius (Uranol. pp.
135, 136), gives the Grecian and Egyptian names of the planets.



 Egyptian.
 Greek.



Saturn 
Νεμεσέως
Κρόνου ἀστὴρ
φαίνων


Jupiter 
Ὀσίριδος
Δῖος
φαέθων
MarsἩρακλεοῦςἈρέοςπυρόεις
VenusἈφροδίτηςἑώσφορος
MercuryἈπόλλωνοςἙρμοῦστίλβων


It is not necessary to dwell on the details of these speculations,
but we may notice a very remarkable evidence of their antiquity and
generality in the structure of one of the most familiar of our
measures of time, the Week. This distribution of time according
to periods of seven days, comes down to us, as we learn from the
Jewish scriptures, from the beginning of man’s existence on the earth.
The same usage is found over all the East; it existed among the
Arabians, Assyrians, 128 Egyptians.35 The same week is
found in India among the Bramins; it has there, also, its days marked
by those of the heavenly bodies; and it has been ascertained that the
same day has, in that country, the name corresponding with its
designation in other nations.
35 Laplace, Hist. Astron. p.
16.
The notion which led to the usual designations of the days of the
week is not easily unravelled. The days each correspond to one of the
heavenly bodies, which were, in the earliest systems of the world,
conceived to be the following, enumerating them in the order of their
remoteness from the earth:36 Saturn, Jupiter, Mars, the Sun, Venus,
Mercury, the Moon. At a later period, the received systems placed the
seven luminaries in the seven spheres. The knowledge which was
implied in this view, and the time when it was obtained, we must
consider hereafter. The order in which the
names are assigned to the days of the week (beginning with Saturday)
is, Saturn, the Sun, the Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus; and
various accounts are given of the manner in which one of these orders
is obtained from the other; all the methods proceeding upon certain
arbitrary arithmetical processes, connected in some way with
astrological views. It is perhaps not worth our while here to examine
further the steps of this process; it would be difficult to determine
with certainty why the former order of the planets was adopted, and
how and why the latter was deduced from it. But there is something
very remarkable in the universality of the notions, apparently so
fantastic, which have produced this result; and we may probably
consider the Week, with Laplace,37 as “the most
ancient monument of astronomical knowledge.” This period has gone on
without interruption or irregularity from the earliest recorded times
to our own days, traversing the extent of ages and the revolutions of
empires; the names of the ancient deities which were associated with
the stars have been replaced by those of the objects of the worship of
our Teutonic ancestors, according to their views of the correspondence
of the two mythologies; and the Quakers, in rejecting these names of
days, have cast aside the most ancient existing relic of astrological
as well as idolatrous superstition.
36 Philol. Mus. No. 1.
37 Hist. Ast. p. 17.
Sect. 8.—The Circles of the Sphere.
The inventions hitherto noticed, though
undoubtedly they were steps in astronomical knowledge, can hardly be
considered as purely abstract and scientific speculations; for the
exact reckoning of time is one of 129 the wants, even of the least civilized
nations. But the distribution of the places and motions of the
heavenly bodies by means of a celestial sphere with imaginary lines
drawn upon it, is a step in speculative astronomy, and was
occasioned and rendered important by the scientific propensities of
man.
It is not easy to say with whom this notion originated. Some parts
of it are obvious. The appearance of the sky naturally suggests the
idea of a concave Sphere, with the stars fixed on its surface. Their
motions during any one night, it would be readily seen, might be
represented by supposing this Sphere to turn round a Pole or Axis; for
there is a conspicuous star in the heavens which apparently stands
still (the Pole-star); all the others travel round this in circles,
and keep the same positions with respect to each other. This
stationary star is every night the same, and in the same place; the
other stars also have the same relative position; but their general
position at the same time of night varies gradually from night to
night, so as to go through its cycle of appearances once a year. All
this would obviously agree with the supposition that the sky is a
concave sphere or dome, that the stars have fixed places on this
sphere, and that it revolves perpetually and uniformly about the Pole
or fixed point.
But this supposition does not at all explain the way in which the
appearances of different nights succeed each other. This, however, may
be explained, it appears, by supposing the sun also to
move among the stars on the surface of the concave sphere. The
sun by his brightness makes the stars invisible which are on his side
of the heavens: this we can easily believe; for the moon, when bright,
also puts out all but the largest stars; and we see the stars
appearing in the evening, each in its place, according to their degree
of splendor, as fast as the declining light of day allows them to
become visible. And as the sun brings day, and his absence night, if
he move through the circuit of the stars in a year, we shall have, in
the course of that time, every part of the starry sphere in succession
presented to us as our nocturnal sky.
This notion, that the sun moves round among the stars in a
year, is the basis of astronomy, and a considerable part of the
science is only the development and particularization of this general
conception. It is not easy to ascertain either the exact method by
which the path of the sun among the stars was determined, or the
author and date of the discovery. That there is some difficulty in
tracing the course of the sun among the stars will be clearly seen,
when it is considered that no 130 star can ever be seen at the same time
with the sun. If the whole circuit of the sky be divided into twelve
parts or signs, it is estimated by Autolycus, the oldest writer
on these subjects whose works remain to us,38 that the stars
which occupy one of these parts are absorbed by the solar rays, so
that they cannot be seen. Hence the stars which are seen nearest to
the place of the setting and the rising sun in the evening and in the
morning, are distant from him by the half of a sign: the evening stars
being to the west, and the morning stars to the east of him. If the
observer had previously obtained a knowledge of the places of all the
principal stars, he might in this way determine the position of the
sun each night, and thus trace his path in a year.
38 Delamb. A. A. p. xiii.
In this, or some such way, the sun’s path was determined by the
early astronomers of Egypt. Thales, who is mentioned as the father of
Greek astronomy, probably learnt among the Egyptians the results of
such speculations, and introduced them into his own country. His
knowledge, indeed, must have been a great deal more advanced than that
which we are now describing, if it be true, as is asserted, that he
predicted an eclipse. But his having done so is not very consistent
with what we are told of the steps which his successors had still to
make.
The Circle of the Signs, in which the sun moves among the stars, is
obliquely situated with regard to the circles in which the stars move
about the poles. Pliny39 states that Anaximander,40 a scholar of Thales, was the first
person who pointed out this obliquity, and thus, as he says, “opened
the gate of nature.” Certainly, the person who first had a clear view
of the nature of the sun’s path in the celestial sphere, made that
step which led to all the rest; but it is difficult to conceive that
the Egyptians and Chaldeans had not already advanced so far.
39 Lib. ii. c. (viii.)
40 Plutarch, De Plac. Phil.
lib. ii. cap. xii. says Pythagoras was the author of this
discovery.
The diurnal motion of the celestial sphere, and the motion of the
moon in the circle of the signs, gave rise to a mathematical science,
the Doctrine of the Sphere, which was one of the earliest
branches of applied mathematics. A number of technical conceptions and
terms were soon introduced. The Sphere of the heavens was
conceived to be complete, though we see but a part of it; it was
supposed to turn about the visible pole and another pole
opposite to this, and these poles were connected by an imaginary
Axis. The circle which divided the sphere exactly midway
between these poles was called the Equator (ἰσημέρινος). 131 The two circles
parallel to this which bounded the sun’s path among the stars were
called Tropics (τροπικαί), because the sun turns back
again towards the equator when he reaches them. The stars which never
set are bounded by a circle called the Arctic Circle (ἄρκτικος,
from ἄρκτος, the Bear, the constellation to which some of the
principal stars within that circle belong.) A circle about the
opposite pole is called Antarctic, and the stars which are
within it can never rise to us.41 The sun’s path
or circle of the signs is called the Zodiac, or circle of
animals; the points where this circle meets the equator are the
Equinoctial Points, the days and nights being equal when the
sun is in them; the Solstitial Points are those where the sun’s
path touches the tropics; his motion to the south or to the north
ceases when he is there, and he appears in that respect to stand
still. The Colures (κόλουροι, mutilated) are circles which pass
through the poles and through the equinoctial and solstitial points;
they have their name because they are only visible in part, a portion
of them being below the horizon.
41 The Arctic and Antarctic Circles of
modern astronomers are different from these.
The Horizon (ὁρίζων) is commonly understood as the boundary
of the visible earth and heaven. In the doctrine of the sphere, this
boundary is a great circle, that is, a circle of which the
plane passes through the centre of the sphere; and, therefore, an
entire hemisphere is always above the horizon. The term occurs for the
first time in the work of Euclid, called Phænomena (Φαινόμενα).
We possess two treatises written by Autolycus42 (who lived about
300 b. c.) which trace deductively the
results of the doctrine of the sphere. Supposing its diurnal motion to
be uniform, in a work entitled Περὶ Κινουμένης Σφαῖρας, “On the Moving
Sphere,” he demonstrates various properties of the diurnal risings,
settings, and motions of the stars. In another work, Περὶ Ἐπιτολῶν καὶ
Δύσεων, “On Risings and Settings,”43 tacitly
assuming the sun’s motion in his circle to be uniform, he proves
certain propositions, with regard to those risings and settings of the
stars, which take place at the same time when the sun rises and
sets,44 or vice versâ;45 and also their apparent risings
and settings when they cease to be visible after sunset, or begin to
be visible after sunrise.46 132 Several of the propositions contained in
the former of these treatises are still necessary to be understood, as
fundamental parts of astronomy.
42 Delambre, Astron. Ancienne,
p. 19.
43 Delambre, Astron. Anc. p.
25.
44 Cosmical rising and
setting.
45 Acronycal rising and
setting; (ἀκρονυκίος, happening at the extremity of the night.)
46 Heliacal rising and
setting.
The work of Euclid, just mentioned, is of the same kind. Delambre47 finds in it evidence that Euclid was
merely a book-astronomer, who had never observed the heavens.
47 Ast. Anc. p. 53.
We may here remark the first instance of that which we shall find
abundantly illustrated in every part of the history of science; that
man is prone to become a deductive reasoner;—that as
soon as he obtains principles which can be traced to details by
logical consequence, he sets about forming a body of science, by
making a system of such reasonings. Geometry has always been a
favorite mode of exercising this propensity: and that science, along
with Trigonometry, Plane and Spherical, to which the early problems of
astronomy gave rise, have, up to the present day, been a constant
field for the exercise of mathematical ingenuity; a few simple
astronomical truths being assumed as the basis of the reasoning.
Sect. 9.—The Globular Form of the Earth.
The establishment of the globular form of
the earth is an important step in astronomy, for it is the first of
those convictions, directly opposed to the apparent evidence of the
senses, which astronomy irresistibly proves. To make men believe that
up and down are different directions in different
places; that the sea, which seems so level, is, in fact, convex; that
the earth, which appears to rest on a solid foundation, is, in fact,
not supported at all; are great triumphs both of the power of
discovering and the power of convincing. We may readily allow this,
when we recollect how recently the doctrine of the antipodes,
or the existence of inhabitants of the earth, who stand on the
opposite side of it, with their feet turned towards ours, was
considered both monstrous and heretical.
Yet the different positions of the horizon at different places,
necessarily led the student of spherical astronomy towards this notion
of the earth as a round body. Anaximander48 is said by some
to have held the earth to be globular, and to be detached or
suspended; he is also stated to have constructed a sphere, on which
were shown the extent of land and water. As, however, we do not know
the arguments upon which he maintained the earth’s globular form, we
cannot judge of the 133 value of his opinion; it may have been
no better founded than a different opinion ascribed to him by
Laertius, that the earth had the shape of a pillar. Probably, the
authors of the doctrine of the globular form of the earth were led to
it, as we have said, by observing the different height of the pole at
different places. They would find that the space which they passed
over from north to south on the earth, was proportional to the change
of place of the horizon in the celestial sphere; and as the horizon
is, at every place, in the direction of the earth’s apparently level
surface, this observation would naturally suggest to them the opinion
that the earth is placed within the celestial sphere, as a small globe
in the middle of a much larger one.
48 See Brucker, Hist. Phil.
vol. i. p. 486.
We find this doctrine so distinctly insisted on by Aristotle, that
we may almost look on him as the establisher of it.49 “As to the figure of the earth, it must
necessarily be spherical.” This he proves, first by the tendency of
things, in all places, downwards. He then adds,50 “And, moreover,
from the phenomena according to the sense: for if it were not so, the
eclipses of the moon would not have such sections as they have. For in
the configurations in the course of a month, the deficient part takes
all different shapes; it is straight, and concave, and convex; but in
eclipses it always has the line of division convex; wherefore, since
the moon is eclipsed in consequence of the interposition of the earth,
the periphery of the earth must be the cause of this by having a
spherical form. And again, from the appearances of the stars, it is
clear, not only that the earth is round, but that its size is not very
large: for when we make a small removal to the south or the north, the
circle of the horizon becomes palpably different, so that the stars
overhead undergo a great change, and are not the same to those that
travel to the north and to the south. For some stars are seen in Egypt
or at Cyprus, but are not seen in the countries to the north of these;
and the stars that in the north are visible while they make a complete
circuit, there undergo a setting. So that from this it is manifest,
not only that the form of the earth is round, but also that it is a
part of not a very large sphere: for otherwise the difference would
not be so obvious to persons making so small a change of place.
Wherefore we may judge that those persons who connect the region
in the neighborhood of the pillars of Hercules with that towards
India, and who assert that in this way the sea is one, do not assert things very improbable. They
confirm this conjecture moreover by the 134 elephants, which are said to be of the
same species (γένος) towards each extreme; as if this circumstance was
a consequence of the conjunction of the extremes. The mathematicians,
who try to calculate the measure of the circumference, make it amount
to 400,000 stadia; whence we collect that the earth is not only
spherical, but is not large compared with the magnitude of the other
stars.”
49 Arist. de Cœlo, lib. ii.
cap. xiv. ed. Casaub. p. 290.
50 p. 291 C.
When this notion was once suggested, it was defended and confirmed
by such arguments as we find in later writers: for instance,51 that the tendency of all things was to
fall to the place of heavy bodies, and that this place being the
centre of the earth, the whole earth had no such tendency; that the
inequalities on the surface were so small as not materially to affect
the shape of so vast a mass; that drops of water naturally form
themselves into figures with a convex surface; that the end of the
ocean would fall if it were not rounded off; that we see ships, when
they go out to sea, disappearing downwards, which shows the surface to
be convex. These are the arguments still employed in impressing the
doctrines of astronomy upon the student of our own days; and thus we
find that, even at the early period of which we are now speaking,
truths had begun to accumulate which form a part of our present
treasures.  ~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~
51 Pliny, Nat. Hist. ii. lxv.
Sect. 10.—The Phases of the Moon.
When men had formed a steady notion of the
Moon as a solid body, revolving about the earth, they had only further
to conceive it spherical, and to suppose the sun to be beyond the
region of the moon, and they would find that they had obtained an
explanation of the varying forms which the bright part of the moon
assumes in the course of a month. For the convex side of the
crescent-moon, and her full edge when she is gibbous, are always
turned towards the sun. And this explanation, once suggested, would be
confirmed, the more it was examined. For instance, if there be near us
a spherical stone, on which the sun is shining, and if we place
ourselves so that this stone and the moon are seen in the same
direction (the moon appearing just over the top of the stone), we
shall find that the visible part of the stone, which is then
illuminated by the sun, is exactly similar in form to the moon, at
whatever period of her changes she may be. The stone and the moon
being in the same position with respect to us, and both being
enlightened by the sun, the bright parts are the same in figure; 135 the only difference
is, that the dark part of the moon is usually not visible at all.
This doctrine is ascribed to Anaximander. Aristotle was fully aware
of it.52 It could not well escape the Chaldeans
and Egyptians, if they speculated at all about the causes of the
appearances in the heavens.
52 Probl. Cap. xv. Art. 7.
Sect. 11.—Eclipses.
Eclipses of the sun and moon were from the
earliest tunes regarded with a peculiar interest. The notions of
superhuman influences and relations, which, as we have seen, were
associated with the luminaries of the sky, made men look with alarm at
any sudden and striking change in those objects; and as the constant
and steady course of the celestial revolutions was contemplated with a
feeling of admiration and awe, any marked interruption and deviation
in this course, was regarded with surprise and terror. This appears to
be the case with all nations at an early stage of their
civilization.
This impression would cause Eclipses to be noted and remembered;
and accordingly we find that the records of Eclipses are the earliest
astronomical information which we possess. When men had discovered
some of the laws of succession of other astronomical phenomena, for
instance, of the usual appearances of the moon and sun, it might then
occur to them that these unusual appearances also might probably be
governed by some rule.
The search after this rule was successful at an early period. The
Chaldeans were able to predict Eclipses of the Moon. This they did,
probably, by means of their Cycle of 223 months, or about 18 years;
for at the end of this time, the eclipses of the moon begin to return,
at the same intervals and in the same order as at the beginning.53 Probably this was the first instance of
the prediction of peculiar astronomical phenomena. The Chinese have,
indeed, a legend, in which it is related that a solar eclipse happened
in the reign of Tchongkang, above 2000 years before Christ, and that
the emperor was so much irritated against two great officers of state,
who had neglected to predict this eclipse, that he put them to death.
But this cannot be accepted as a real event: for, during the next ten
centuries, we find no single observation or fact connected with
astronomy in the Chinese 136 histories; and their astronomy has never
advanced beyond a very rude and imperfect condition.
53 The eclipses of the sun are more
difficult to calculate; since they depend upon the place of the
spectator on the earth.
We can only conjecture the mode in which the Chaldeans discovered
their Period of 18 years; and we may make very different suppositions
with regard to the degree of science by which they were led to it. We
may suppose, with Delambre,54 that they carefully recorded the
eclipses which happened, and then, by the inspection of their
registers, discovered that those of the moon recurred after a certain
period. Or we may suppose, with other authors, that they sedulously
determined the motions of the moon, and having obtained these with
considerable accuracy, sought and found a period which should include
cycles of these motions. This latter mode of proceeding would imply a
considerable degree of knowledge.
54 A. A. p. 212.
It appears probable rather that such a period was discovered by
noticing the recurrence of eclipses, than by studying the
moon’s motions. After 6585⅓ days, or 223 lunations, the same
eclipses nearly will recur. It is not contested that the Chaldeans
were acquainted with this period, which they called Saros; or
that they calculated eclipses by means of it.
Sect. 12.—Sequel to the Early Stages of
Astronomy.
Every stage of science has its train of
practical applications and systematic inferences, arising both from
the demands of convenience and curiosity, and from the pleasure which,
as we have already said, ingenuous and active-minded men feel in
exercising the process of deduction. The earliest condition of
astronomy, in which it can be looked upon as a science, exhibits
several examples of such applications and inferences, of which we may
mention a few.
Prediction of Eclipses.—The Cycles which served to
keep in order the Calendar of the early nations of antiquity, in some
instances enabled them also, as has just been stated, to predict
Eclipses; and this application of knowledge necessarily excited great
notice. Cleomedes, in the time of Augustus, says, “We never see an
eclipse happen which has not been predicted by those who made use of
the Tables.” (ὑπὸ τῶν κανονικῶν.)
Terrestrial Zones.—The globular form of the earth
being assented to, the doctrine of the sphere was applied to the earth
as well as the heavens; and the earth’s surface was divided by various
imaginary 137
circles; among the rest, the equator, the tropics, and circles, at the
same distance from the poles as the tropics are from the equator. One
of the curious consequences of this division was the
assumption that there must be some marked difference in the
stripes or zones into which the earth’s surface was thus divided. In
going to the south, Europeans found countries hotter and hotter, in
going to the north, colder and colder; and it was supposed that the
space between the tropical circles must be uninhabitable from heat,
and that within the polar circles, again, uninhabitable from cold.
This fancy was, as we now know, entirely unfounded. But the principle
of the globular form of the earth, when dealt with by means of
spherical geometry, led to many true and important propositions
concerning the lengths of days and nights at different places. These
propositions still form a part of our Elementary Astronomy.
Gnomonic.—Another important result of the doctrine of
the sphere was Gnomonic or Dialling. Anaximenes is said
by Pliny to have first taught this art in Greece; and both he and
Anaximander are reported to have erected the first dial at Lacedemon.
Many of the ancient dials remain to us; some of these are of complex
forms, and must have required great ingenuity and considerable
geometrical knowledge in their construction.
Measure of the Sun’s Distance.—The explanation of the
phases of the moon led to no result so remarkable as the attempt of
Aristarchus of Samos to obtain from this doctrine a measure of the
Distance of the Sun as compared with that of the Moon. If the moon was
a perfectly smooth sphere, when she was exactly midway between the new
and full in position (that is, a quadrant from the sun), she would be
somewhat more than a half moon; and the place when she was
dichotomized, that is, was an exact semicircle, the bright part
being bounded by a straight line, would depend upon the sun’s distance
from the earth. Aristarchus endeavored to fix the exact place of this
Dichotomy; but the irregularity of the edge which bounds the bright
part of the moon, and the difficulty of measuring with accuracy, by
means then in use, either the precise time when the boundary was most
nearly a straight line, or the exact distance of the moon from the sun
at that time, rendered his conclusion false and valueless. He
collected that the sun is at 18 times the distance of the moon from
us; we now know that he is at 400 times the moon’s distance.
It would be easy to dwell longer on subjects of this kind; but we
have already perhaps entered too much in detail. We have been 138 tempted to do this by
the interest which the mathematical spirit of the Greeks gave to the
earliest astronomical discoveries, when these were the subjects of
their reasonings; but we must now proceed to contemplate them engaged
in a worthier employment, namely, in adding to these discoveries.
~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~
</div></body></text></TEI>