<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="20">CHAPTER XX.
ACTION OF TIDES AND CURRENTS—continued.
Inroads of the sea at the mouths of the Rhine in Holland—Changes in the arms
of the Rhine—Proofs of subsidence of land—Estuary of the Bies Bosoh, formed
in 1421—Zuyder Zee, in the 13th century—Islands destroyed—Delta of the
Ems converted into a bay—Estuary of the Dollart
formed—Encroachment of
the sea on the coast of Sleswick—On shores of North America—Tidal wave,
called the Bore—Influence of tides and currents on the mean level of seas—Action
of currents in inland lakes and seas—Baltic—Cimbrian
deluge—Straits
of Gibraltar—No under-current there—Whether salt is precipitated in the
Mediterranean—Waste of shores of Mediterranean.
Inroads of the sea at the mouths of the Rhine.—The line of British
coast considered in the preceding chapter offered no example of the
conflict of two great antagonist forces; the influx, on the one hand, of
a river draining a large continent, and, on the other, the action of the
waves, tides, and currents of the ocean. But when we pass over by
the Straits of Dover to the Continent, and proceed northeastwards, we
find an admirable illustration of such a contest, where the ocean and the
Rhine are opposed to each other, each disputing the ground now occupied
by Holland; the one striving to shape out an estuary, the other
to form a delta. There was evidently a period when the river obtained
the ascendancy, when the shape and perhaps the relative level of the
coast and set of the tides were very different; but for the last two
thousand years, during which man has witnessed and actively participated
in the struggle, the result has been in favor of the ocean; the
area of the whole territory having become more and more circumscribed;
natural and artificial barriers having given away, one after another;
and many hundred thousand human beings having perished in the
waves.
Changes in the arms of the Rhine.—The Rhine, after flowing from
the Grison Alps, copiously charged with sediment, first purifies itself in
the Lake of Constance, where a large delta is formed; then swelled by
the Aar and numerous other tributaries, it flows for more than six hundred
miles towards the north; when, entering a low tract, it divides into
two arms, about ten miles northeast of Cleves,—a point which must
therefore be considered the head of its delta. (See *, map, fig. 38.) In
speaking of the delta, I do not mean to assume that all that part of
Holland which is comprised within the several arms of the Rhine can
be called a delta in the strictest sense of the term; because some portion
of the country thus circumscribed, as, for example, a part of Gelderland
and Utrecht, consists of strata which may have been deposited
in the sea before the Rhine existed. These older tracts may either have
been raised like the Ullah Bund in Cutch, during the period when the
326
sediment of the Rhine was converting a part of the sea into land, or
they may have constituted islands previously.
Fig. 38.
The dark tint between Antwerp and Nieuport, represents part of the Netherlands which was
land in the time of the Romans, then overflowed by the sea before and during the 5th century,
and afterwards reconverted into land.
When the river divides north of Cleves, the left arm takes the name
of the Waal; and the right, retaining that of the Rhine, is connected, a
little farther to the north, by an artificial canal with the river Yssel.
The Rhine then flowing westward divides again southeast of Utrecht,
and from this point it takes the name of the Leck, a name which was
given to distinguish it from the northern arm called the old Rhine,
which was sanded up until the year 1825, when a channel was cut for
it, by which it now enters the sea at Catwyck. It is common, in all
great deltas, that the principal channels of discharge should shift from
time to time, but in Holland so many magnificent canals have been
constructed, and have so diverted, from time to time, the course of the
waters, that the geographical changes in this delta are endless, and
their history, since the Roman era, forms a complicated topic of antiquarian
research. The present head of the delta is about forty geographical
miles from the nearest part of the gulf called the Zuyder Zee,
and more than twice that distance from the general coast-line. The
present head of the delta of the Nile is about 80 or 90 geographical
miles from the sea; that of the Ganges, as before stated, 220; and
that of the Mississippi about 180, reckoning from the point where the
Atchafalaya branches off to the extremity of the new tongue of land in
the Gulf of Mexico. But the comparative distance between the heads
327
of deltas and the sea affords no positive data for estimating the relative
magnitude of the alluvial tracts formed by their respective rivers, for
the ramifications depend on many varying and temporary circumstances,
and the area over which they extend does not hold any constant
proportion to the volume of water in the river.
The Rhine therefore has at present three mouths. About two-thirds
of its waters flow to the sea by the Waal, and the remainder is carried
partly to the Zuyder Zee by the Yssel, and partly to the ocean by the
Leck. As the whole coast to the south as far as Ostend, and on the
north to the entrance of the Baltic, has, with few exceptions, from time
immemorial, yielded to the force of the waves, it is evident that the
common delta of the Rhine, Meuse, and Scheldt, for these three rivers
may all be considered as discharging their waters into the same part of
the sea, would, if its advance had not been checked, have become extremely
prominent; and even if it had remained stationary, would long
ere this have projected far beyond the rounded outline of the coast, like
that strip of land already described at the mouth of the Mississippi.
But we find, on the contrary, that the islands which skirt the coast
have not only lessened in size, but in number also, while great bays
have been formed in the interior by incursions of the sea.
In order to explain the incessant advance of the ocean on the shores
and inland country of Holland, M. E. de Beaumont has suggested that
there has in all probability been a general depression or sinking of the
land below its former level over a wide area. Such a change of level
would enable the sea to break through the ancient line of sand-banks
and islands which protected the coast,—would lead to the enlargement
of bays, the formation of new estuaries, and ultimately to the entire
submergence of land. These views appear to be supported by the fact
that several peat-mosses of fresh-water origin now occur under the
level of the sea, especially on the site of the Zuyder Zee and Lake
Flevo, presently to be mentioned. Several excavations also made for
wells at Utrecht, Amsterdam, and Rotterdam have proved, that below
the level of the ocean, the soil near the coast consists of alternations of
sand with marine shells, and beds of peat and clay, which have been
traced to the depth of fifty feet and upwards.443
I have said that the coast to the south as far as Ostend has given
way. This statement may at first seem opposed to the fact, that the
tract between Antwerp and Nieuport, shaded black in the annexed map
(fig. 38), although now dry land, and supporting a large population,
has, within the historical period, been covered with the sea. This
region, however, consisted, in the time of the Romans, of woods,
marshes, and peat-mosses, protected from the ocean by a chain of
sandy dunes, which were afterwards broken through during storms,
especially in the fifth century. The waters of the sea during these
irruptions threw down upon the barren peat a horizontal bed of fertile
328
clay, which is in some places three yards thick, full of recent shells and
works of art. The inhabitants, by the aid of embankments and the
sand dunes of the coast, have succeeded, although not without frequent
disasters, in defending the soil thus raised by the marine deposit.444
Inroads of the Sea in Holland.—If we pass to the northward of the
territory just alluded to, and cross the Scheldt, we find that between
the fourteenth and eighteenth centuries parts of the islands Walcheren
and Beveland were swept away, and several populous districts of Kadzand,
losses which far more than counterbalance the gain of land caused
by the sanding up of some pre-existing creeks. In 1658 the Island
Orisant was annihilated. One of the most memorable inroads of the
sea occurred in 1421, when the tide, pouring into the mouth of the
united Meuse and Waal, burst through a dam in the district between
Dort and Gertrudenberg, and overflowed seventy-two villages, forming
a large sheet of water called the Bies Bosch. (See map, fig. 38.)
Thirty-five of the villages were irretrievably lost, and no vestige, even
of their ruins, was afterwards seen. The rest were redeemed, and the
site of the others, though still very generally represented on maps as
an estuary, has in fact been gradually filled up by alluvial deposits, and
had become in 1835, as I was informed by Professor Moll, an immense
plain, yielding abundant crops of hay, though still uninhabited. To
the north of the Meuse is a long line of shore covered with sand dunes,
where great encroachments have taken place from time to time, in consequence
chiefly of the prevalence of southeasterly winds, which blow
down the sands towards the sea. The church of Scheveningen, not far
from the Hague, was once in the middle of the village, and now stands
on the shore, half the place having been overwhelmed by the waves in
1570. Catwyck, once far from the sea, is now upon the shore; two
of its streets having been overflowed, and land torn away to the extent
of 200 yards, in 1719. It is only by the aid of embankments that
Petten, and several other places farther north, have been defended
against the sea.
Formation of the Zuyder Zee and Straits of Staveren.—Still more
important are the changes which have taken place on the coast opposite
the right arm of the Rhine, or the Yssel, where the ocean has
burst through a large isthmus, and entered the inland lake Flevo,
which, in ancient times, was, according to Pomponius Mela, formed by
the overflowing of the Rhine over certain lowlands. It appears that,
in the time of Tacitus, there were several lakes on the present site of
the Zuyder Zee, between Friesland and Holland. The successive inroads
by which these and a great part of the adjoining territory, were
transformed into a great gulf, began about the commencement, and
were completed towards the close, of the thirteenth century. Alting
gives the following relation of the occurrence, drawn from manuscript
documents of contemporary inhabitants of the neighboring provinces.
329
In the year 1205, the island now called Wieringen, to the south
of the Texel, was still a part of the mainland, but during several high
floods, of which the dates are given, ending in December, 1251, it was
separated from the continent. By subsequent incursions the sea consumed
great parts of the rich and populous isthmus, a low tract which
stretched on the north of Lake Flevo, between Staveren in Friesland
and Medemblick in Holland, till at length a breach was completed
about the year 1282, and afterwards widened. Great destruction of
land took place when the sea first broke in, and many towns were
swept away; but there was afterwards a reaction to a certain extent,
large tracts, at first submerged, having been gradually redeemed.
The new straits south of Staveren are more than half the width of
those of Dover, but are very shallow, the greatest depth not exceeding
two or three fathoms. The new bay is of a somewhat circular form,
and between thirty and forty miles in diameter. How much of this
space may formerly have been occupied by Lake Flevo is unknown.
(See map, fig. 38.)
Destruction of islands.—A series of islands stretching from the Texel
to the mouths of the Weser and Elbe are probably the last relics of a
tract once continuous. They have greatly diminished in size, and
have lost about a third of their number, since the time of Pliny; for
that naturalist counted twenty-three islands between the Texel and
Eider, whereas there are now only sixteen, including Heligoland and
Neuwerk.445 The island of Heligoland, at the mouth of the Elbe, consists
of a rock of red marl of the Keuper formation (of the Germans),
and is bounded by perpendicular red cliffs, above 200 feet high. Although,
according to some accounts, it has been greatly reduced in
size since the year 800, M. Wiebel assures us, that the ancient map by
Meyer cannot be depended upon, and that the island, according to the
description still extant by Adam of Bremen, was not much larger than
now, in the time of Charlemagne. On comparing the map made in
the year 1793 by the Danish engineer Wessel, the average encroachment
of the sea on the cliffs, between that period and the year 1848
(or about half a century), did not amount to more than three feet.446
On the other hand, some few islands have extended their bounds in
one direction, or become connected with others, by the sanding-up
of channels; but even these, like Juist, have generally given way as
much on the north towards the sea as they have gained on the south,
or land side.
The Dollart formed.—While the delta of the Rhine has suffered so
materially from the movements of the ocean, it can hardly be supposed
that minor rivers on the same coast should have been permitted to extend
their deltas. It appears that in the time of the Romans there
was an alluvial plain of great fertility, where the Ems entered the sea
330
by three arms. This low country stretched between Groningen and
Friesland, and sent out a peninsula to the northeast towards Emden. A
flood in 1277 first destroyed part of the peninsula. Other inundations
followed at different periods throughout the fifteenth century. In
1507, a part only of Torum, a considerable town, remained standing;
and in spite of the erection of dams, the remainder of that place, together
with market-towns, villages, and monasteries, to the number of
fifty, were finally overwhelmed. The new gulf, which was called the
Dollart, although small in comparison to the Zuyder Zee, occupied no
less than six square miles at first; but part of this space was, in the
course of the two following centuries, again redeemed from the sea.
The small bay of Leybucht, farther north, was formed in a similar manner
in the thirteenth century; and the bay of Harlbucht in the middle
of the sixteenth. Both of these have since been partially reconverted
into dry land. Another new estuary, called the Gulf of Jahde, near
the mouth of the Weser, scarcely inferior in size to the Dollart, has
been gradually hollowed out since the year 1016, between which era
and 1651 a space of about four square miles has been added to the
sea. The rivulet which now enters this inlet is very small; but
Arens conjectures that an arm of the Weser had once an outlet in
that direction.
Coast of Sleswick.—Farther north we find so many records of waste
on the western coast of Sleswick, as to lead us to anticipate that, at no
distant period in the history of the physical geography of Europe, Jutland
may become an island, and the ocean may obtain a more direct
entrance into the Baltic. Indeed, the temporary insulation of the
northern extremity of Jutland has been affected no less than four times
within the records of history, the ocean having as often made a breach
through the bar of sand, which usually excludes it from the Lym Fiord.
This long frith is 120 miles in length including its windings, and communicates
at its eastern end with the Baltic. The last irruption of salt
water happened in 1824, and the fiord was still open in 1837, when
some vessels of thirty tons' burden passed through.
The Marsh islands between the rivers Elbe and Eider are mere banks,
like the lands formed of the "warp" in the Humber, protected by dikes.
Some of them, after having been inhabited with security for more than
ten centuries, have been suddenly overwhelmed. In this manner, in
1216, no less than ten thousand of the inhabitants of Eiderstede and
Ditmarsch perished; and on the 11th of October, 1634, the islands
and the whole coast, as far as Jutland, suffered by a dreadful deluge.
Destruction of Northstrand by the sea.—Northstrand, up to the year
1240, was, with the islands Sylt and Föhr, so nearly connected with the
mainland as to appear a peninsula, and was called North Friesland, a
highly cultivated and populous district. It measured from nine to
eleven geographical miles from north to south, and six to eight from
east to west. In the above-mentioned year it was torn asunder from
the continent, and in part overwhelmed. The Isle of Northstrand,
331
thus formed, was, towards the end of the sixteenth century, only four
geographical miles in circumference, and was still celebrated for its
cultivation and numerous population. After many losses, it still contained
nine thousand inhabitants. At last, in the year 1634, on the
evening of the 11th of October, a flood passed over the whole island,
whereby 1300 houses, with many churches, were lost; fifty thousand
head of cattle perished, and above six thousand men. Three small
islets, one of them still called Northstrand, alone remained, which are
now continually wasting.
The redundancy of river water in the Baltic, especially during the
melting of ice and snow in spring, causes in general an outward current
through the channel called the Cattegat. But after a continuance of
northwesterly gales, especially during the height of the spring-tides, the
Atlantic rises, and pouring a flood of water into the Baltic, commits
dreadful devastations on the isles of the Danish Archipelago. This
current even acts, though with diminished force, as far eastward as the
vicinity of Dantzic.447 Accounts written during the last ten centuries
attest the wearing down of promontories on the Danish coast, the deepening
of gulfs, the severing of peninsulas from the mainland, and the
waste of islands, while in several cases marsh land, defended for centuries
by dikes, has at last been overflowed, and thousands of the
inhabitants whelmed in the waves. Thus the island Barsoe, on the
coast of Sleswick, has lost, year after year, an acre at a time, and the
island Alsen suffers in like manner.
Cimbrian deluge.—As we have already seen that during the flood
before mentioned, 6000 men and 50,000 head of cattle perished on
Northstrand on the western coast of Jutland, we are all well prepared
to find that this peninsula, the Cimbrica Chersonesus of the ancients,
has from a remote period been the theatre of like catastrophes. Accordingly,
Strabo records a story, although he treats it as an incredible
fiction, that, during a high tide, the ocean rose upon this coast so rapidly,
that men on horseback were scarcely able to escape.448 Florus,
alluding to the same tradition, says, "Cimbri, Teutoni, atque Tigurini,
ab extremis Galliæ profugi, cùm terras eorum inundasset Oceanus, novas
sedes toto orbe quærebant."449 This event, commonly called the
"Cimbrian Deluge," is supposed to have happened about three centuries
before the Christian era; but it is not improbable that the principal
catastrophe was preceded and followed by many devastations like those
experienced in modern times on the islands and shores of Jutland, and
such calamities may well be conceived to have forced on the migration
of some maritime tribes.
Inroads of the sea on the eastern shores of North America.—After so
many authentic details respecting the destruction of the coast in parts
of Europe best known, it will be unnecessary to multiply examples of
332
analogous changes in more distant regions of the world. It must not,
however, be imagined that our own seas form any exception to the
general rule. Thus, for example, if we pass over to the eastern coast
of North America, where the tides rise, in the Bay of Fundy, to a great
elevation, we find many facts attesting the incessant demolition of land.
Cliffs, often several hundred feet high, composed of sandstone, red marl,
and other rocks, which border that bay and its numerous estuaries, are
perpetually undermined. The ruins of these cliffs are gradually carried,
in the form of mud, sand, and large boulders, into the Atlantic by powerful
currents, aided at certain seasons by drift ice, which forms along
the coast, and freezes round large stones.
At Cape May, on the north side of Delaware Bay, in the United
States, the encroachment of the sea was shown by observations made
consecutively for sixteen years, from 1804 to 1820, to average about
nine feet a year;450 and at Sullivan's Island, which lies on the north
side of the entrance of the harbor of Charleston, in South Carolina,
the sea carried away a quarter of a mile of land in three years, ending
in 1786.451
Tidal wave called "the Bore."—Before concluding my remarks on
the action of the tides, I must not omit to mention the wave called "the
Bore," which is sometimes produced in a river where a large body of
water is made to rise suddenly, in consequence of the contraction of the
channel. This wave terminates abruptly on the inland side; because
the quantity of water contained in it is so great, and its motion so rapid,
that time is not allowed for the surface of the river to be immediately
raised by means of transmitted pressure. A tide wave thus rendered
abrupt has a close analogy, observes Mr. Whewell, to the waves which
curl over and break on a shelving shore.452
The Bore which enters the Severn, where the phenomenon is of almost
daily occurrence, is sometimes nine feet high, and at spring-tides
rushes up the estuary with extraordinary rapidity. The finest example
which I have seen of this wave was at Nova Scotia,453 where the tide is
said to rise in some places seventy feet perpendicular, and to be the
highest in the world. In the large estuary of the Shubenacadie, which
connects with another estuary called the Basin of Mines, itself an embranchment
of the Bay of Fundy, a vast body of water comes rushing
up, with a roaring noise, into a long narrow channel, and while it is
ascending, has all the appearance of pouring down a slope as steep
as that of the celebrated rapids of the St. Lawrence. In picturesque
effect, however, it bears no comparison, for instead of the transparent
green water and snow-white foam of the St. Lawrence, the whole current
of the Shubenacadie is turbid and densely charged with red mud.
The same phenomenon is frequently witnessed in the principal branches
of the Ganges and in the Megna as before mentioned (p. 279). "In
333
the Hoogly," says Rennell, "the Bore commences at Hoogly Point, the
place where the river first contracts itself, and is perceptible above
Hoogly Town; and so quick is its motion, that it hardly employs four
hours in travelling from one to the other, though the distance is nearly
seventy miles. At Calcutta it sometimes occasions an instantaneous
rise of five feet; and both here, and in every other part of its track,
the boats, on its approach, immediately quit the shore, and make for
safety to the middle of the river. In the channels, between the islands
in the mouth of the Megna, the height of the Bore is said to exceed
twelve feet; and is so terrific in its appearance, and dangerous in its consequences,
that no boat will venture to pass at spring-tide."454 These
waves may sometimes cause inundations, undermine cliffs, and still
more frequently sweep away trees and land animals from low shores, so
that they may be carried down, and ultimately imbedded in fluviatile or
submarine deposits.
CURRENTS IN INLAND LAKES AND SEAS.
In such large bodies of water as the North American lakes, the continuance
of a strong wind in one direction often causes the elevation of
the water, and its accumulation on the leeward side; and while the
equilibrium is restoring itself, powerful currents are occasioned. In
October, 1833, a strong current in Lake Erie, caused partly by the set
of the waters towards the outlet of the lake, and partly by the prevailing
wind, burst a passage through the extensive peninsula called Long
Point, and soon excavated a channel more than nine feet deep and nine
hundred feet wide. Its width and depth have since increased, and a
new and costly pier has been erected; for it is hoped that this event will
permanently improve the navigation of Lake Erie for steamboats.455 On
the opposite, or southern coast of this lake, in front of the town of Cleveland,
the degradation of the cliffs had been so rapid for several years
preceding a survey made in 1837, as to threaten many towns with demolition.456
In the Black Sea, also, although free from tides, we learn from
Pallas that there is a sufficiently strong current to undermine the cliffs
in many parts, and particularly in the Crimea.
Straits of Gibraltar.—It is well known that a powerful current sets
constantly from the Atlantic into the Mediterranean, and its influence
extends along the whole southern borders of that sea, and even to the
shores of Asia Minor. Captain Smyth found, during his survey, that
the central current ran constantly at the rate of from three to six miles
an hour eastward into the Mediterranean, the body of water being three
miles and a half wide. But there are also two lateral currents—one on
the European, and one on the African side; each of them about two
miles and a half broad, and flowing at about the same rate as the central
stream. These lateral currents ebb and flow with the tide, setting alternately
334
into the Mediterranean and into the Atlantic. The excess of
water constantly flowing in is very great, and there is only one cause to
which this can be attributed, the loss of water in the Mediterranean by
evaporation. That the level of this sea should be considerably depressed
by this cause is quite conceivable, since we know that the winds
blowing from the shores of Africa are hot and dry; and hygrometrical
experiments recently made in Malta and other places, show that the
mean quantity of moisture in the air investing the Mediterranean is equal
only to one half of that in the atmosphere of England. The temperature
also of the great inland sea is upon an average higher, by 3½° of Fahrenheit,
than the eastern part of the Atlantic Ocean in the same latitude,
which must greatly promote its evaporation. The Black Sea being
situated in a higher latitude, and being the receptacle of rivers flowing
from the north, is much colder, and its expenditure far less; accordingly
it does not draw any supply from the Mediterranean, but, on the contrary,
contributes to it by a current flowing outwards, for the most part
of the year, through the Dardanelles. The discharge, however, at the
Bosphorus is so small, when compared to the volume of water carried in
by rivers, as to imply a great amount of evaporation in the Black Sea.
Whether salt be precipitated in the Mediterranean.—It is, however,
objected, that evaporation carries away only fresh water, and that the
current from the Atlantic is continually bringing in salt water: why,
then, do not the component parts of the waters of the Mediterranean
vary? or how can they remain so nearly the same as those of the ocean?
Some have imagined that the excess of salt might be carried away by
an under-current running in a contrary direction to the superior; and
this hypothesis appeared to receive confirmation from a late discovery,
that the water taken up about fifty miles within the Straits, from a depth
of 670 fathoms, contained a quantity of salt four times greater than the
water of the surface. Dr. Wollaston,457 who analyzed this water obtained
by Captain Smyth, truly inferred that an under-current of such
denser water flowing outward, if of equal breadth and depth with the
current near the surface, would carry out as much salt below as is brought
in above, although it moved with less than one-fourth part of the velocity,
and would thus prevent a perpetual increase of saltness in the
Mediterranean beyond that existing in the Atlantic. It was also remarked
by others, that the result would be the same, if the swiftness being
equal, the inferior current had only one-fourth of the volume of the
superior. At the same time there appeared reason to conclude that this
great specific gravity was only acquired by water at immense depths;
for two specimens of the water, taken within the Mediterranean, at the
distance of some hundred miles from the Straits, and at depths of 400
and even 450 fathoms, were found by Dr. Wollaston not to exceed in
density that of many ordinary samples of sea-water. Such being the
case, we can now prove that the vast amount of salt brought into the
335
Mediterranean does not pass out again by the Straits; for it appears by
Captain Smyth's soundings, which Dr. Wallaston had not seen, that
between the capes of Trafalgar and Spartel, which are twenty-two miles
apart, and where the Straits are shallowest, the deepest part, which is
on the side of Cape Spartel, is only 220 fathoms. It is therefore evident,
that if water sinks in certain parts of the Mediterranean, in consequence
of the increase of its specific gravity, to greater depths than 220
fathoms, it can never flow out again into the Atlantic, since it must be
stopped by the submarine barrier which crosses the shallowest part of
the Straits of Gibraltar.
The idea of the existence of a counter-current, at a certain depth,
first originated in the following circumstances:—M. De l'Aigle, commander
of a privateer called the Phœnix of Marseilles, gave chase to a
Dutch merchant-ship, near Ceuta Point, and coming up with her in the
middle of the gut, between Tariffa and Tangier, gave her one broadside,
which directly sunk her. A few days after, the sunken ship, with her
cargo of brandy and oil, was cast ashore near Tangier, which is at least
four leagues to the westward of the place where she went down, and
to which she must have floated in a direction contrary to the course of
the central current.458 This fact, however, affords no evidence of an
under-current, because the ship, when it approached the coast, would
necessarily be within the influence of a lateral current, which running
westward twice every twenty-four hours, might have brought back the
vessel to Tangier.
What, then, becomes of the excess of salt?—for this is an inquiry of
the highest geological interest. The Rhone, the Po, the Nile, and
many hundred minor streams and springs, pour annually into the Mediterranean
large quantities of carbonate of lime, together with iron, magnesia,
silica, alumina, sulphur, and other mineral ingredients in a state of
chemical solution. To explain why the influx of this matter does not
alter the composition of this sea has never been regarded as a difficulty;
for it is known that calcareous rocks are forming in the delta of the
Rhone, in the Adriatic, on the coast of Asia Minor, and in other localities.
Precipitation is acknowledged to be the means whereby the surplus
mineral matter is disposed of, after the consumption of a certain
portion in the secretions of testacea, zoophytes, and other marine animals.
But before muriate of soda can, in like manner, be precipitated,
the whole Mediterranean ought, according to the received principles of
chemistry, to become as much saturated with salt as Lake Aral, the
Dead Sea, or the brine-springs of Cheshire.
It is undoubtedly true, in regard to small bodies of water, that every
particle must be fully saturated with muriate of soda before a single
crystal of salt can be formed; such is probably the case in all natural
salterns: such, for example, as those described by travellers as occurring
on the western borders of the Black Sea, where extensive marshes
336
are said to be covered by thin films of salt after a rapid evaporation of
sea-water. The salt étangs of the Rhone, where salt has sometimes
been precipitated in considerable abundance, have been already mentioned.
In regard to the depth of the Mediterranean, it appears that
between Gibraltar and Ceuta, Captain Smyth sounded to the enormous
depth of 950 fathoms, and found there a gravelly bottom, with fragments
of broken shells. Saussure sounded to the depth of two thousand
feet, within a few yards of the shore, at Nice; and M. Bérard has
lately fathomed to the depth of more than six thousand feet in several
places without reaching the bottom.459
The central abysses, therefore, of this sea are, in all likelihood, at least
as deep as the Alps are high; and, as at the depth of seven hundred
fathoms only, water has been found to contain a proportion of salt four
times greater than at the surface, we may presume that the excess of
salt may be much greater at the depth of two or three miles. After
evaporation, the surface water becomes impregnated with a slight excess
of salt, and its specific gravity being thus increased, it instantly
falls to the bottom, while lighter water rises to the top, or flows in laterally,
being always supplied by rivers and the current from the Atlantic.
The heavier fluid, when it arrives at the bottom, cannot stop if it
can gain access to any lower part of the bed of the sea, not previously
occupied by water of the same density.
How far this accumulation of brine can extend before the inferior
strata of water will part with any of their salt, and what difference in
such a chemical process the immense pressure of the incumbent ocean,
or the escape of heated vapors, thermal springs, or submarine volcanic
eruptions, might occasion, are questions which cannot be answered in
the present state of science.
The Straits of Gibraltar are said to become gradually wider by the
wearing down of the cliffs on each side at many points; and the current
sets along the coast of Africa, so as to cause considerable inroads
in various parts, particularly near Carthage. Near the Canopic mouth
of the Nile, at Aboukir, the coast was greatly devastated in the year
1784, when a small island was nearly consumed. By a series of similar
operations, the old site of the cities of Nicropolis, Taposiris, Parva
and Canopus, have become a sand-bank.460

337</div></body></text></TEI>