<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="13">

CHAPTER IV.
Of the Definitions and Axioms which relate to Space.



1. THE
relations of space have been apprehended with
peculiar distinctness and clearness from the very first
unfolding of man’s speculative powers. This was a
consequence of the circumstance which we have just noticed,
that the simplest of these relations, and those on which the
others depend, are seen by intuition. Hence, as soon as men
were led to speculate concerning the relations of space,
they assumed just principles, and obtained true results. It
is said that the science of geometry had its origin
in Egypt, before the dawn of the Greek philosophy: but the
knowledge of the early Egyptians (exclusive of their
mythology) appears to have been purely practical; and,
probably, their geometry consisted only in some maxims of
land-measuring, which is what the term implies. The
Greeks of the time of Plato, had, however, not only
possessed themselves of many of the most remarkable
elementary theorems of the science; but had, in several
instances, reached the boundary of the science in its
elementary form; as when they proposed to themselves the
problems of doubling the cube and squaring the circle.
But the deduction of these theorems by a systematic process,
and the primary exhibition of the simplest principles
involved in the idea of space, which such a deduction
requires, did not take place, so far as we are aware, till a
period somewhat later. The Elements of Geometry of
Euclid, in which this task was performed, are to this day
the standard work on the subject: the author of this work
taught mathematics with great applause at Alexandria, in the
reign of Ptolemy Lagus, 99 about 280 years before Christ.
The principles which Euclid makes the basis of his system
have been very little simplified since his time; and all the
essays and controversies which bear upon these principles,
have had a reference to the form in which they are stated by
him.
2. Definitions.—The first principles of Euclid’s
geometry are, as the first principles of any system of
geometry must be, definitions and axioms respecting the
various ideal conceptions which he introduces; as straight
lines, parallel lines, angles, circles, and the like. But it
is to be observed that these definitions and axioms are very
far from being arbitrary hypotheses and assumptions. They
have their origin in the idea of space, and are merely modes
of exhibiting that idea in such a manner as to make it
afford grounds of deductive reasoning. The axioms are
necessary consequences of the conceptions respecting which
they are asserted; and the definitions are no less necessary
limitations of conceptions; not requisite in order to arrive
at this or that consequence; but necessary in order that it
may be possible to draw any consequences, and to establish
any general truths.
For example, if we rest the end of one straight staff upon
the middle of another straight staff, and move the first
staff into various positions, we, by so doing, alter the
angles which the first staff makes with the other to the
right hand and to the left. But if we place the staff in
that special position in which these two angles are equal,
each of them is a right angle, according to Euclid; and this
is the definition of a right angle, except that
Euclid employs the abstract conception of straight lines,
instead of speaking, as we have done, of staves. But this
selection of the case in which the two angles are equal is
not a mere act of caprice; as it might have been if he had
selected a case in which these angles are unequal in any
proportion. For the consequences which can be drawn
concerning the cases of unequal angles, do not lead to
general truths, without some reference to that peculiar case
in which the angles are equal: and thus it becomes necessary
to 100 single out and define that special case, marking it
by a special phrase. And this definition not only gives
complete and distinct knowledge what a right angle is, to
any one who can form the conception of an angle in general;
but also supplies a principle from which all the properties
of right angles may be deduced.
3. Axioms.—With regard to other conceptions also, as
circles, squares, and the like, it is possible to lay down
definitions which are a sufficient basis for our reasoning,
so far as such figures are concerned. But, besides these
definitions, it has been found necessary to introduce
certain axioms among the fundamental principles of geometry.
These are of the simplest character; for instance, that two
straight lines cannot cut each other in more than one point,
and an axiom concerning parallel lines. Like the
definitions, these axioms flow from the Idea of Space, and
present that idea under various aspects. They are different
from the definitions; nor can the definitions be made to
take the place of the axioms in the reasoning by which
elementary geometrical properties are established. For
example, the definition of parallel straight lines is, that
they are such as, however far continued, can never meet:
but, in order to reason concerning such lines, we must
further adopt some axiom respecting them: for example, we
may very conveniently take this axiom; that two straight
lines which cut one another are not both of them parallel to
a third straight line1. The definition and the axiom are
seen to be inseparably connected by our intuition of the
properties of space; but the axiom cannot be proved from the
definition, by any rigorous deductive demonstration. And if
we were to take any other definition of two parallel
straight lines, (as that they are both perpendicular to a
third straight line,) we should still, at some point or
other of our progress, fall in with the same difficulty of
demonstratively establishing their properties without some
further assumption.</div></body></text></TEI>