<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="36">
[223]
CHAPTER IV.

On the Impression produced by the Contemplation of
Laws of Nature;
or, on the Conviction that Law
implies Mind.

The various trains of thought and reasoning which
lead men from a consideration of the natural world
to the conviction of the existence, the power, the
providence of God, do not require, for the most part,
any long or laboured deduction, to give them their
effect on the mind. On the contrary, they have, in
every age and country, produced their impression
on multitudes who have not instituted any formal
reasonings upon the subject, and probably upon
many who have not put their conclusions in the
shape of any express propositions. The persuasion
of a superior intelligence and will, which manifests
itself in every part of the material world, is, as is
well known, so widely diffused and deeply infixed, as
to have made it a question among speculative men
whether the notion of such a power is not universal
and innate. It is our business to show only how
plainly and how universally such a belief results from
the study of the appearances about us. That in many
nations, in many periods, this persuasion has been
mixed up with much that was erroneous and perverse
in the opinions of the intellect or the fictions of
fancy, does not weaken the force of such consent.
The belief of a supernatural and presiding power
runs through all these errors: and while the perversions
are manifestly the work of caprice and illusion,
and vanish at the first ray of sober inquiry, the belief
itself is substantial and consistent, and grows in
strength upon every new examination. It was the
firmness and solidity of the conviction of something[224]
Divine which gave a hold and permanence to the
figments of so many false divinities. And those who
have traced the progress of human thought on other
subjects, will not think it strange, that while the fundamental
persuasion of a Deity was 
thus irremovably seated in the human mind, the developement of
this conception into a consistent, pure, and steadfast
belief in one Almighty and Holy Father and God,
should be long missed, or never attained, by the
struggle of the human faculties; should require long
reflection to mature it, and the aid of revelation to
establish it in the world.
The view of the universe which we have principally
had occasion to present to the reader, is that
in which we consider its appearances as reducible to
certain fixed and general laws. Availing ourselves
of some of the lights which modern science supplies,
we have endeavoured to show that the adaptation of
such laws to each other, and their fitness to promote
the harmonious and beneficial course of the world,
may be traced, wherever we can discover the laws
themselves; and that the conceptions of the Divine
Power, Goodness and Superintendence which we
thus form, agree in a remarkable manner with the
views of the Supreme Being, to which reason, enlightened
by the divine revelation, has led.
But we conceive that the general impressions of
mankind would go further than a mere assent to the
argument as we have thus stated it. To most persons
it appears that the mere existence of a law connecting
and governing any class of phenomena, implies
a presiding intelligence which has preconceived
and established the law. When events are regulated
by precise rules of time and space, of number and
measure, men conceive these rules to be the evidence
of thought and mind, even without discovering in the
rules any peculiar adaptations, or without supposing
their purpose to be known.
The origin and the validity of such an impression
on the human mind may appear to some matters of[225]
abstruse and doubtful speculation: yet the tendency
to such a belief prevails strongly and widely, both
among the common class of minds whose thoughts
are casually and unsystematically turned to such
subjects, and among philosophers to whom laws of
nature are habitual subjects of contemplation. We
conceive therefore that such a tendency may deserve
to be briefly illustrated; and we trust also that some
attention to this point may be of service in throwing
light upon the true relation of the study of nature to
the belief in God.
1. A very slight attention shows us how readily
order and regularity suggest to a common apprehension
the operation of a calm and untroubled intelligence
presiding over the course of events. Thus the
materialist poet, in accounting for the belief in the
Gods, though he does not share it, cannot deny the
habitual effect of this manifestation.</div></body></text></TEI>