<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="4">CHAPTER IV.
HISTORY OF THE PROGRESS OF GEOLOGY—continued.
Werner's application of geology to the art of mining—Excursive character of his
lectures—Enthusiasm of his pupils—His authority—His theoretical errors—Desmarest's
Map and Description of Auvergne—Controversy between the Vulcanists
and Neptunists—Intemperance of the rival sects—Hutton's Theory of the
earth—His discovery of granite veins—Originality of his views—Why opposed—Playfair's
illustrations—Influence of Voltaire's writings on geology—Imputations
cast on the Huttonians by Williams, Kirwan, and De Luc—Smith's Map
of England—Geological Society of London—Progress of the science in France—Growing
importance of the study of organic remains.
Werner.—The art of mining has long been taught in France, Germany,
and Hungary, in scientific institutions established for that purpose,
where mineralogy has always been a principal branch of instruction.
Werner was named, in 1775, professor of that science in the "School
of Mines," at Freyberg, in Saxony. He directed his attention not
merely to the composition and external characters of minerals, but also
to what he termed "geognosy," or the natural position of minerals in
particular rocks, together with the grouping of those rocks, their geographical
distribution, and various relations. The phenomena observed
in the structure of the globe had hitherto served for little else than to
furnish interesting topics for philosophical discussion; but when Werner
pointed out their application to the practical purposes of mining, they
were instantly regarded by a large class of men as an essential part of
their professional education, and from that time the science was cultivated
in Europe more ardently and systematically. Werner's mind was
at once imaginative and richly stored with miscellaneous knowledge.
He associated every thing with his favorite science, and in his excursive
47lectures, he pointed out all the economical uses of minerals, and their
application to medicine; the influence of the mineral composition of
rocks upon the soil, and of the soil upon the resources, wealth, and civilization
of man. The vast sandy plains of Tartary and Africa, he
would say, retained their inhabitants in the shape of wandering shepherds;
the granitic mountains and the low calcareous and alluvial plains
gave rise to different manners, degrees of wealth, and intelligence. The
history even of languages, and the migration of tribes, had been determined
by the direction of particular strata. The qualities of certain stones
used in building would lead him to descant on the architecture of different
ages and nations; and the physical geography of a country frequently
invited him to treat of military tactics. The charm of his manners
and his eloquence kindled enthusiasm in the minds of his pupils; and
many, who had intended at first only to acquire a slight knowledge of
mineralogy, when they had once heard him, devoted themselves to it as
the business of their lives. In a few years, a small school of mines,
before unheard of in Europe, was raised to the rank of a great university;
and men already distinguished in science studied the German
language, and came from the most distant countries to hear the great
oracle of geology.97
Werner had a great antipathy to the mechanical labor of writing, and,
with the exception of a valuable treatise on metalliferous veins, he could
never be persuaded to pen more than a few brief memoirs, and those
containing no development of his general views. Although the natural
modesty of his disposition was excessive, approaching even to timidity,
he indulged in the most bold and sweeping generalizations, and he inspired
all his scholars with a most implicit faith in his doctrines. Their
admiration of his genius, and the feelings of gratitude and friendship
which they all felt for him, were not undeserved; but the supreme authority
usurped by him over the opinions of his contemporaries, was
eventually prejudicial to the progress of the science; so much so, as
greatly to counterbalance the advantages which it derived from his exertions.
If it be true that delivery be the first, second, and third requisite
in a popular orator, it is no less certain, that to travel is of first,
second, and third importance to those who desire to originate just and
comprehensive views concerning the structure of our globe. Now Werner
had not travelled to distant countries; he had merely explored a
small portion of Germany, and conceived, and persuaded others to believe,
that the whole surface of our planet, and all the mountain chains
in the world, were made after the model of his own province. It became
a ruling object of ambition in the minds of his pupils to confirm
the generalizations of their great master, and to discover in the most
distant parts of the globe his "universal formations," which he supposed
had been each in succession simultaneously precipitated over the whole
earth from a common menstruum, or "chaotic fluid." It now appears
48that the Saxon professor had misinterpreted many of the most important
appearances even in the immediate neighborhood of Freyberg. Thus,
for example, within a day's journey of his school, the porphyry, called
by him primitive, has been found not only to send forth veins or dikes
through strata of the coal formation, but to overlie them in mass. The
granite of the Hartz mountains, on the other hand, which he supposed
to be the nucleus of the chain, is now well known to traverse the other
beds, as near Goslar; and still nearer Freyberg, in the Erzgebirge, the
mica slate does not mantle round the granite as was supposed, but abuts
abruptly against it. Fragments, also, of the greywacké slate, containing
organic remains, have recently been found entangled in the granite of
the Hartz, by M. de Seckendorf.98
The principal merit of Werner's system of instruction consisted in
steadily directing the attention of his scholars to the constant relations
of superposition of certain mineral groups; but he had been anticipated,
as has been shown in the last chapter, in the discovery of this general
law, by several geologists in Italy and elsewhere; and his leading divisions
of the secondary strata were at the same time, and independently,
made the basis of an arrangement of the British strata by our countryman,
William Smith, to whose work I shall refer in the sequel.
Controversy between the Vulcanists and Neptunists.—In regard to
basalt and other igneous rocks, Werner's theory was original, but it was
also extremely erroneous. The basalts of Saxony and Hesse, to which
his observations were chiefly confined, consisted of tabular masses capping
the hills, and not connected with the levels of existing valleys, like many
in Auvergne and the Vivarais. These basalts, and all other rocks of
the same family in other countries, were, according to him, chemical
precipitates from water. He denied that they were the products of
submarine volcanoes; and even taught that, in the primeval ages of the
world, there were no volcanoes. His theory was opposed, in a twofold
sense, to the doctrine of the permanent agency of the same causes in
nature; for not only did he introduce, without scruple, many imaginary
causes supposed to have once effected great revolutions in the earth, and
then to have become extinct, but new ones also were feigned to have
come into play in modern times; and, above all, that most violent instrument
of change, the agency of subterranean heat.
So early as 1768, before Werner had commenced his mineralogical
studies, Raspe had truly characterized the basalts of Hesse as of igneous
origin. Arduino, we have seen, had pointed out numerous varieties of
trap-rock in the Vicentin as analogous to volcanic products, and as distinctly
referable to ancient submarine eruptions. Desmarest, as before
stated, had, in company with Fortis, examined the Vicentin in 1766, and
confirmed Arduino's views. In 1772, Banks, Solander, and Troil compared
the columnar basalt of Hecla with that of the Hebrides. Collini,
49in 1774, recognized the true nature of the igneous rocks on the Rhine,
between Andernach and Bonn. In 1775, Guettard visited the Vivarais,
and established the relation of basaltic currents to lavas. Lastly, in
1779, Faujas published his description of the volcanoes of the Vivarais
and Velay, and showed how the streams of basalt had poured out from
craters which still remain in a perfect state.99
Desmarest.—When sound opinions had thus for twenty years prevailed
in Europe concerning the true nature of the ancient trap-rocks,
Werner by his simple dictum caused a retrograde movement, and not
only overturned the true theory, but substituted for it one of the most
unphilosophical that can well be imagined. The continued ascendancy
of his dogmas on this subject was the more astonishing, because a variety
of new and striking facts were daily accumulated in favor of the
correct opinions previously entertained. Desmarest, after a careful
examination of Auvergne, pointed out, first, the most recent volcanoes
which had their craters still entire, and their streams of lava conforming
to the level of the present river-courses. He then showed that there
were others of an intermediate epoch, whose craters were nearly effaced,
and whose lavas were less intimately connected with the present valleys;
and, lastly, that there were volcanic rocks, still more ancient, without
any discernible craters or scoriæ, and bearing the closest analogy to
rocks in other parts of Europe, the igneous origin of which was denied
by the school of Freyberg.100
Desmarest's map of Auvergne was a work of uncommon merit. He
first made a trigonometrical survey of the district, and delineated its
physical geography with minute accuracy and admirable graphic power.
He contrived, at the same time, to express without the aid of colors,
many geological details, including the different ages and sometimes even
the structure, of the volcanic rocks, and distinguishing them from the
fresh-water and the granitic. They alone who have carefully studied
Auvergne, and traced the different lava streams from their craters to
their termination,—the various isolated basaltic cappings,—the relation
of some lavas to the present valleys,—-the absence of such relations
in others,—can appreciate the extraordinary fidelity of this elaborate
work. No other district of equal dimensions in Europe exhibits, perhaps,
so beautiful and varied a series of phenomena; and, fortunately,
Desmarest possessed at once the mathematical knowledge required for
the construction of a map, skill in mineralogy, and a power of original
generalization.
Dolomieu—Montlosier.—Dolomieu, another of Werner's contemporaries,
had found prismatic basalt among the ancient lavas of Etna; and,
in 1784, had observed the alternations of submarine lavas and calcareous
strata in the Val di Noto, in Sicily.101 In 1790, also, he described similar
phenomena in the Vicentin and in the Tyrol.102 Montlosier published,
50in 1788, an essay on the theories of volcanoes of Auvergne, combining
accurate local observations with comprehensive views. Notwithstanding
this mass of evidence the scholars of Werner were prepared to
support his opinions to their utmost extent; maintaining, in the fulness
of their faith, that even obsidian was an aqueous precipitate. As they
were blinded by their veneration for the great teacher, they were impatient
of opposition, and soon imbibed the spirit of a faction; and their
opponents, the Vulcanists, were not long in becoming contaminated with
the same intemperate zeal. Ridicule and irony were weapons more
frequently employed than argument by the rival sects, till at last the
controversy was carried on with a degree of bitterness almost unprecedented
in questions of physical science. Desmarest alone, who had
long before provided ample materials for refuting such a theory, kept
aloof from the strife; and whenever a zealous Neptunist wished to draw
the old man into an argument, he was satisfied with replying, "Go and
see."103
Hutton, 1788.—It would be contrary to all analogy, in matters of
graver import, that a war should rage with such fury on the Continent,
and that the inhabitants of our island should not mingle in the affray.
Although in England the personal influence of Werner was wanting to
stimulate men to the defence of the weaker side of the question, they
contrived to find good reason for espousing the Wernerian errors with
great enthusiasm. In order to explain the peculiar motives which led
many to enter, even with party feeling, into this contest, it will be necessary
to present the reader with a sketch of the views unfolded by
Hutton, a contemporary of the Saxon geologist. The former naturalist
had been educated as a physician, but declining the practice of medicine,
he resolved, when young, to remain content with the small independence
inherited from his father, and thenceforth to give his undivided
attention to scientific pursuits. He resided at Edinburgh, where
he enjoyed the society of many men of high attainments, who loved
him for the simplicity of his manners, and the sincerity of his character.
His application was unwearied; and he made frequent tours through
different parts of England and Scotland, acquiring considerable skill as
a mineralogist, and consequently arriving at grand and comprehensive
views in geology. He communicated the results of his observations
unreservedly, and with the fearless spirit of one who was conscious
that love of truth was the sole stimulus of his exertions. When at
length he had matured his views, he published, in 1788, his "Theory
of the Earth,"104 and the same, afterwards more fully developed in a
separate work, in 1795. This treatise was the first in which geology
was declared to be in no way concerned about "questions as to the origin
of things;" the first in which an attempt was made to dispense entirely
with all hypothetical causes, and to explain the former changes
of the earth's crust by reference exclusively to natural agents. Hutton
51labored to give fixed principles to geology, as Newton had succeeded
in doing to astronomy; but, in the former science, too little progress
had been made towards furnishing the necessary data, to enable any
philosopher, however great his genius, to realize so noble a project.
Huttonian theory.—"The ruins of an older world," said Hutton,
"are visible in the present structure of our planet; and the strata
which now compose our continents have been once beneath the sea, and
were formed out of the waste of pre-existing continents. The same
forces are still destroying, by chemical decomposition or mechanical
violence, even the hardest rocks, and transporting the materials to the
sea, where they are spread out, and form strata analogous to those of
more ancient date. Although loosely deposited along the bottom of the
ocean, they become afterwards altered and consolidated by volcanic
heat, and then heaved up, fractured, and contorted."
Although Hutton had never explored any region of active volcanoes,
he had convinced himself that basalt and many other trap-rocks were of
igneous origin, and that many of them had been injected in a melted state
through fissures in the older strata. The compactness of these rocks,
and their different aspect from that of ordinary lava, he attributed to
their having cooled down under the pressure of the sea; and in order to
remove the objections started against this theory, his friend, Sir James
Hall, instituted a most curious and instructive series of chemical experiments,
illustrating the crystalline arrangement and texture assumed by
melted matter cooled under high pressure.
The absence of stratification in granite, and its analogy, in mineral
character, to rocks which he deemed of igneous origin, led Hutton to conclude
that granite also must have been formed from matter in fusion;
and this inference he felt could not be fully confirmed, unless he discovered
at the contact of granite and other strata a repetition of the
phenomena exhibited so constantly by the trap-rocks. Resolved to try
his theory by this test, he went to the Grampians, and surveyed the line
of junction of the granite and superincumbent stratified masses, until he
found in Glen Tilt, in 1785, the most clear and unequivocal proofs in
support of his views. Veins of red granite are there seen branching out
from the principal mass, and traversing the black micaceous schist and
primary limestone. The intersected stratified rocks are so distinct in
color and appearance as to render the example in that locality most
striking, and the alteration of the limestone in contact was very analogous
to that produced by trap veins on calcareous strata. This verification of
his system filled him with delight, and called forth such marks of joy
and exultation, that the guides who accompanied him, says his biographer,
were convinced that he must have discovered a vein of silver or
gold.105 He was aware that the same theory would not explain the origin
of the primary schists, but these he called primary, rejecting the term
primitive, and was disposed to consider them as sedimentary rocks
al52tered by heat, and that they originated in some other form from the waste
of previously existing rocks.
By this important discovery of granite veins, to which he had been
led by fair induction from an independent class of facts, Hutton prepared
the way for the greatest innovation of the systems of his predecessors.
Vallisneri had pointed out the general fact that there were certain fundamental
rocks which contained no organic remains, and which he supposed
to have been formed before the creation of living beings. Moro, Generelli,
and other Italian writers, embraced the same doctrine; and Lehman regarded
the mountains called by him primitive, as parts of the original
nucleus of the globe. The same tenet was an article of faith in the
school of Freyberg; and if any one ventured to doubt the possibility of
our being enabled to carry back our researches to the creation of the
present order of things, the granitic rocks were triumphantly appealed
to. On them seemed written, in legible characters, the memorable inscription—

"Dinanzi a me non fur cose create
Se non eterne;"106

and no small sensation was excited when Hutton seemed, with unhallowed
hand, desirous to erase characters already regarded by many as
sacred. "In the economy of the world," said the Scotch geologist, "I
can find no traces of a beginning, no prospect of an end;" a declaration
the more startling when coupled with the doctrine, that all past ages
on the globe had been brought about by the slow agency of existing
causes. The imagination was first fatigued and overpowered by endeavoring
to conceive the immensity of time required for the annihilation
of whole continents by so insensible a process; and when the thoughts
had wandered through these interminable periods, no resting-place was
assigned in the remotest distance. The oldest rocks were represented
to be of a derivative nature, the last of an antecedent series, and that,
perhaps, one of many pre-existing worlds. Such views of the immensity
of past time, like those unfolded by the Newtonian philosophy in regard
to space, were too vast to awaken ideas of sublimity unmixed with
a painful sense of our incapacity to conceive a plan of such infinite extent.
Worlds are seen beyond worlds immeasurably distant from each
other, and, beyond them all, innumerable other systems are faintly traced
on the confines of the visible universe.
The characteristic feature of the Huttonian theory was, as before
hinted, the exclusion of all causes not supposed to belong to the present
order of nature. But Hutton had made no step beyond Hooke, Moro,
and Raspe, in pointing out in what manner the laws now governing subterranean
movements might bring about geological changes, if sufficient
time be allowed. On the contrary, he seems to have fallen far short of
some of their views, especially when he refused to attribute any part
53of the external configuration of the earth's crust to subsidence. He
imagined that the continents were first gradually destroyed by aqueous
degradation; and when their ruins had furnished materials for new
continents, they were upheaved by violent convulsions. He therefore
required alternate periods of general disturbance and repose; and such
he believed had been, and would forever be, the course of nature.
Generelli, in his exposition of Moro's system, had made a far nearer
approximation towards reconciling geological appearances with the state
of nature as known to us; for while he agreed with Hutton, that the
decay and reproduction of rocks were always in progress, proceeding
with the utmost uniformity, the learned Carmelite represented the repairs
of mountains by elevation from below to be effected by an equally
constant and synchronous operation. Neither of these theories, considered
singly, satisfies all the conditions of the great problem, which a
geologist, who rejects cosmological causes, is called upon to solve; but
they probably contain together the germs of a perfect system. There
can be no doubt, that periods of disturbance and repose have followed
each other in succession in every region of the globe; but it may be
equally true, that the energy of the subterranean movements has been
always uniform as regards the whole earth. The force of earthquakes
may for a cycle of years have been invariably confined, as it is now, to
large but determinate spaces, and may then have gradually shifted its
position, so that another region, which had for ages been at rest, became
in its turn the grand theatre of action.
Playfair's illustrations of Hutton.—The explanation proposed by
Hutton, and by Playfair, the illustrator of his theory, respecting the
origin of valleys and of alluvial accumulations, was also very imperfect.
They ascribed none of the inequalities of the earth's surface to movements
which accompanied the upheaving of the land, imagining that
valleys in general were formed in the course of ages by the rivers now
flowing in them; while they seem not to have reflected on the excavating
and transporting power which the waves of the ocean might exert
on land during its emergence.
Although Hutton's knowledge of mineralogy and chemistry was considerable,
he possessed but little information concerning organic remains;
they merely served him, as they did Werner, to characterize certain
strata, and to prove their marine origin. The theory of former revolutions
in organic life was not yet fully recognized; and without this class
of proofs in support of the antiquity of the globe, the indefinite periods
demanded by the Huttonian hypothesis appeared visionary to many;
and some, who deemed the doctrine inconsistent with revealed truths,
indulged very uncharitable suspicions of the motives of its author.
They accused him of a deliberate design of reviving the heathen dogma
of an "eternal succession," and of denying that this world ever had a
beginning. Playfair, in the biography of his friend, has the following
comment on this part of their theory:—"In the planetary motions,
where geometry has carried the eye so far, both into the future and the54
past, we discover no mark either of the commencement or termination
of the present order. It is unreasonable, indeed, to suppose that such
marks should anywhere exist. The Author of Nature has not given
laws to the universe, which, like the institutions of men, carry in themselves
the elements of their own destruction. He has not permitted in
His works any symptom of infancy or of old age, or any sign by which
we may estimate either their future or their past duration. He may
put an end, as he no doubt gave a beginning, to the present system, at
some determinate period of time; but we may rest assured that this
great catastrophe will not be brought about by the laws now existing,
and that it is not indicated, by any thing which we perceive."107
The party feeling excited against the Huttonian doctrines, and the
open disregard of candor and temper in the controversy, will hardly be
credited by the reader, unless he recalls to his recollection that the mind of
the English public was at that time in a state of feverish excitement.
A class of writers in France had been laboring industriously for many
years, to diminish the influence of the clergy, by sapping the foundations
of the Christian faith; and their success, and the consequences of
the Revolution, had alarmed the most resolute minds, while the imagination
of the more timid was continually haunted by dread of innovation,
as by the phantom of some fearful dream.
Voltaire.—Voltaire had used the modern discoveries in physics as
one of the numerous weapons of attack and ridicule directed by him
against the Scriptures. He found that the most popular systems of
geology were accommodated to the sacred writings, and that much ingenuity
had been employed to make every fact coincide exactly with
the Mosaic account of the creation and deluge. It was, therefore, with no
friendly feelings that he contemplated the cultivators of geology in general,
regarding the science as one which had been successfully enlisted
by theologians as an ally in their cause.108 He knew that the majority
of those who were aware of the abundance of fossil shells in the interior
of continents, were still persuaded that they were proofs of the universal
deluge; and as the readiest way of shaking this article of faith, he
endeavored to inculcate skepticism as to the real nature of such shells,
and to recall from contempt the exploded dogma of the sixteenth century,
that they were sports of nature. He also pretended that vegetable
impressions were not those of real plants.109 Yet he was perfectly
convinced that the shells had really belonged to living testacea, as may
55be seen in his essay "On the formation of Mountains."110 He would
sometimes, in defiance of all consistency, shift his ground when addressing
the vulgar; and, admitting the true nature of the shells collected in
the Alps and other places, pretend that they were Eastern species,
which had fallen from the hats of pilgrims coming from Syria. The
numerous essays written by him on geological subjects were all calculated
to strengthen prejudices, partly because he was ignorant of the
real state of the science, and partly from his bad faith.111 On the other
hand, they who knew that his attacks were directed by a desire to invalidate
Scripture, and who were unacquainted with the true merits of
the question, might well deem the old diluvian hypothesis incontrovertible,
if Voltaire could adduce no better argument against it than to deny
the true nature of organic remains.
It is only by careful attention to impediments originating in extrinsic
causes, that we can explain the slow and reluctant adoption of the simplest
truths in geology. First, we find many able naturalists adducing
the fossil remains of marine animals as proofs of an event related in
Scripture. The evidence is deemed conclusive by the multitude for a
century or more; for it favors opinions which they entertained before,
and they are gratified by supposing them confirmed by fresh and unexpected
proofs. Many who see through the fallacy have no wish to undeceive
those who are influenced by it, approving the effect of the delusion,
and conniving at it as a pious fraud; until, finally, an opposite party,
who are hostile to the sacred writings, labor to explode the erroneous
opinion, by substituting for it another dogma, which they know to be
equally unsound.
The heretical Vulcanists were soon after openly assailed in England,
by imputations of the most illiberal kind. We cannot estimate the malevolence
of such a persecution, by the pain which similar insinuations
might now inflict; for although charges of infidelity and atheism must
always be odious, they were injurious in the extreme at that moment of
political excitement; and it was better, perhaps, for a man's good reception
in society, that his moral character should have been traduced, than
that he should become a mark for these poisoned weapons.
I shall pass over the works of numerous divines, who may be excused
for sensitiveness on points which then excited so much uneasiness in the
public mind; and shall say nothing of the amiable poet Cowper,112 who
56could hardly be expected to have inquired into the merit of doctrines in
physics. But in the foremost ranks of the intolerant are found several
laymen who had high claims to scientific reputation. Among these appears
Williams, a mineral surveyor of Edinburgh, who published a
"Natural History of the Mineral Kingdom," in 1789; a work of great
merit, for that day, and of practical utility, as containing the best account
of the coal strata. In his preface he misrepresents Hutton's theory
altogether, and charges him with considering all rocks to be lavas
of different colors and structure; and also with "warping every thing to
support the eternity of the world."113 He descants on the pernicious
influence of such skeptical notions, as leading to downright infidelity
and atheism, "and as being nothing less than to depose the Almighty
Creator of the universe from his office."114
Kirwan—De Luc.—Kirwan, president of the Royal Academy of
Dublin, a chemist and mineralogist of some merit, but who possessed
much greater authority in the scientific world than he was entitled by
his talents to enjoy, said, in the introduction to his "Geological Essays,
1799," "that sound geology graduated into religion, and was required
to dispel certain systems of atheism or infidelity, of which they had had
recent experience."115 He was an uncompromising defender of the aqueous
theory of all rocks, and was scarcely surpassed by Burnet and
Whiston, in his desire to adduce the Mosaic writings in confirmation of
his opinions.
De Luc, in the preliminary discourse to his Treatise on Geology,116
says, "The weapons have been changed by which revealed religion is
attacked; it is now assailed by geology, and the knowledge of this
science has become essential to theologians." He imputes the failure
of former geological systems to their having been anti-Mosaical, and
directed against a "sublime tradition." These and similar imputations,
reiterated in the works of De Luc, seem to have been taken for granted
by some modern writers: it is therefore necessary to state, in justice to
the numerous geologists of different nations, whose works have been
considered, that none of them were guilty of endeavoring, by arguments
drawn from physics, to invalidate scriptural tenets. On the contrary,
the majority of those who were fortunate enough "to discover the true
causes of things," rarely deserved another part of the poet's panegyric,
"Atque metus omnes subjecit pedibus." The caution and even timid reserve,
of many eminent Italian authors of the earlier period is very apparent;
and there can hardly be a doubt, that they subscribed to certain
dogmas, and particularly to the first diluvian theory, out of deference
to popular prejudices, rather than from conviction. If they were
guilty of dissimulation, we may feel regret, but must not blame their
want of moral courage, reserving rather our condemnation for the intol57erance
of the times, and that inquisitorial power which forced Galileo to
abjure, and the two Jesuits to disclaim the theory of Newton.117
Hutton answered Kirwan's attacks with great warmth, and with the
indignation justly excited by unmerited reproach. "He had always
displayed," says Playfair, "the utmost disposition to admire the beneficent
design manifested in the structure of the world; and he contemplated
with delight those parts of his theory which made the greatest
additions to our knowledge of final causes." We may say with equal
truth, that in no scientific works in our language can more eloquent
passages be found, concerning the fitness, harmony, and grandeur of all
parts of the creation, than in those of Playfair. They are evidently the
unaffected expressions of a mind, which contemplated the study of
nature, as best calculated to elevate our conceptions of the attributes of
the First Cause. At any other time the force and elegance of Playfair's
style must have insured popularity to the Huttonian doctrines;
but by a singular coincidence, Neptunianism and orthodoxy were now
associated in the same creed; and the tide of prejudice ran so strong,
that the majority were carried far away into the chaotic fluid, and other
cosmological inventions of Werner. These fictions the Saxon professor
had borrowed with little modification, and without any improvement,
from his predecessors. They had not the smallest foundation either in
Scripture or in common sense, and were probably approved of by many
as being so ideal and unsubstantial, that they could never come into
violent collision with any preconceived opinions.
According to De Luc, the first essential distinction to be made between
the various phenomena exhibited on the surface of the earth was,
to determine which were the results of causes still in action, and which
had been produced by causes that had ceased to act. The form and
composition of the mass of our continents, he said, and their existence
above the level of the sea, must be ascribed to causes no longer in
action. These continents emerged, at no very remote period, on the
sudden retreat of the ocean, the waters of which made their way into
subterranean caverns. The formation of the rocks which enter into the
crust of the earth began with the precipitation of granite from a primordial
liquid, after which other strata containing the remains of or58ganized
bodies were deposited, till at last the present sea remained as
the residuum of the primordial liquid, and no longer continued to produce
mineral strata.118
William Smith, 1790.—While the tenets of the rival schools of
Freyberg and Edinburgh were warmly espoused by devoted partisans,
the labors of an individual, unassisted by the advantages of wealth or
station in society, were almost unheeded. Mr. William Smith, an English
surveyor, published his "Tabular View of the British Strata" in
1790, wherein he proposed a classification of the secondary formations
in the West of England. Although he had not communicated with
Werner, it appeared by this work that he had arrived at the same views
respecting the laws of superposition of stratified rocks; that he was
aware that the order of succession of different groups was never inverted;
and that they might be identified at very distant points by their
peculiar organized fossils.
From the time of the appearance of the "Tabular View," the author
labored to construct a geological map of the whole of England; and
with the greatest disinterestedness of mind, communicated the results of
his investigations to all who desired information, giving such publicity
to his original views, as to enable his contemporaries almost to compete
with him in the race. The execution of his map was completed in
1815, and remains a lasting monument of original talent and extraordinary
perseverance; for he had explored the whole country on foot,
without the guidance of previous observers, or the aid of fellow-laborers,
and had succeeded in throwing into natural divisions the whole complicated
series of British rocks. D'Aubuisson, a distinguished pupil of
Werner, paid a just tribute of praise to this remarkable performance,
observing, that "what many celebrated mineralogists had only accomplished
for a small part of Germany in the course of half a century, had
been effected by a single individual for the whole of England."119
Werner invented a new language to express his divisions of rocks,
and some of his technical terms, such as grauwacke, gneiss, and others,
passed current in every country in Europe. Smith adopted for the most
part English provincial terms, often of barbarous sound, such as gault,
cornbrash, clunch clay; and affixed them to subdivisions of the British
series. Many of these still retain their place in our scientific classifications,
and attest his priority of arrangement.
MODERN PROGRESS OF GEOLOGY.
The contention of the rival factions of the Vulcanists and Neptunists
had been carried to such a height, that these names had become terms
of reproach; and the two parties had been less occupied in searching
for truth, than for such arguments as might strengthen their own cause
or serve to annoy their antagonists. A new school at last arose, who
59professed the strictest neutrality, and the utmost indifference to the
systems of Werner and Hutton, and who resolved diligently to devote
their labors to observation. The reaction, provoked by the intemperance
of the conflicting parties, now produced a tendency to extreme
caution. Speculative views were discountenanced, and, through fear of
exposing themselves to the suspicion of a bias towards the dogmas of a
party, some geologists became anxious to entertain no opinion whatever
on the causes of phenomena, and were inclined to skepticism even where
the conclusions deducible from observed facts scarcely admitted of reasonable
doubt.
Geological Society of London.—But although the reluctance to theorize
was carried somewhat to excess, no measure could be more salutary
at such a moment than a suspension of all attempts to form what were
termed "theories of the earth." A great body of new data were required;
and the Geological Society of London, founded in 1807, conduced
greatly to the attainment of this desirable end. To multiply and
record observations, and patiently to await the result at some future
period, was the object proposed by them; and it was their favorite
maxim that the time was not yet come for a general system of geology,
but that all must be content for many years to be exclusively engaged
in furnishing materials for future generalizations. By acting up to these
principles with consistency, they in a few years disarmed all prejudice,
and rescued the science from the imputation of being a dangerous, or at
best but a visionary pursuit.
A distinguished modern writer has with truth remarked, that the advancement
of three of the main divisions of geological inquiry have during
the last half century been promoted successively by three different nations
of Europe,—the Germans, the English, and the French.120 We have seen
that the systematic study of what may be called mineralogical geology
had its origin and chief point of activity in Germany, where Werner first
described with precision the mineral characters of rocks. The classification
of the secondary formations, each marked by their peculiar fossils,
belongs, in a great measure, to England, where the labors before alluded
to of Smith, and those of the most active members of the Geological
Society of London, were steadily directed to these objects. The foundation
of the third branch, that relating to the tertiary formations, was laid
in France by the splendid work of Cuvier and Brongniart, published in
1808, "On the Mineral Geography and Organic Remains of the Neighborhood
of Paris."
We may still trace, in the language of the science and our present
methods of arrangement, the various countries where the growth of these
several departments of geology was at different times promoted. Many
names of simple minerals and rocks remain to this day German; while
the European divisions of the secondary strata are in great part English,
and are, indeed, often founded too exclusively on English types. Lastly,
the subdivisions first established of the succession of strata in the Paris
60basin have served as normal groups to which other tertiary deposits
throughout Europe have been compared, even in cases where this
standard was wholly inapplicable.
No period could have been more fortunate for the discovery, in the
immediate neighborhood of Paris, of a rich store of well-preserved fossils,
than the commencement of the present century; for at no former
era had Natural history been cultivated with such enthusiasm in the
French metropolis. The labors of Cuvier in comparative osteology, and
of Lamarck in recent and fossil shells, had raised these departments of
study to a rank of which they had never previously been deemed susceptible.
Their investigations had eventually a powerful effect in dispelling
the illusion which had long prevailed concerning the absence of
analogy between the ancient and modern state of our planet. A close
comparison of the recent and fossil species and the inferences drawn in
regard to their habits, accustomed the geologist to contemplate the
earth as having been at successive periods the dwelling-place of animals
and plants of different races, some terrestrial, and others aquatic—some
fitted to live in seas, others in the waters of lakes and rivers. By the
consideration of these topics, the mind was slowly and insensibly withdrawn
from imaginary pictures of catastrophes and chaotic confusion,
such as haunted the imagination of the early cosmogonists. Numerous
proofs were discovered of the tranquil deposition of sedimentary matter,
and the slow development of organic life. If many writers, and Cuvier
himself in the number, still continued to maintain, that "the thread of
induction was broken,"121 yet, in reasoning by the strict rules of induction
from recent to fossil species, they in a great measure disclaimed
the dogma which in theory they professed. The adoption of the same
generic, and, in some cases, even of the same specific, names for the
exuviæ of fossil animals and their living analogues, was an important step
towards familiarizing the mind with the idea of the identity and unity of
the system in distant eras. It was an acknowledgment, as it were, that
part at least of the ancient memorials of nature were written in a living
language. The growing importance, then, of the natural history of organic
remains may be pointed out as the characteristic feature of the
progress of the science during the present century. This branch of
knowledge has already become an instrument of great utility in geological
classification, and is continuing daily to unfold new data for grand and
enlarged views respecting the former changes of the earth.
When we compare the result of observations in the last fifty years
with those of the three preceding centuries, we cannot but look forward
with the most sanguine expectations to the degree of excellence to which
geology may be carried, even by the labors of the present generation.
Never, perhaps, did any science, with the exception of astronomy, unfold,
in an equally brief period, so many novel and unexpected truths,
and overturn so many preconceived opinions. The senses had for ages
declared the earth to be at rest, until the astronomer taught that it was
61carried through space with inconceivable rapidity. In like manner was
the surface of this planet regarded as having remained unaltered since
its creation, until the geologist proved that it had been the theatre of
reiterated change, and was still the subject of slow but never-ending
fluctuations. The discovery of other systems in the boundless regions
of space was the triumph of astronomy; to trace the same system
through various transformations—to behold it at successive eras adorned
with different hills and valleys, lakes and seas, and peopled with new inhabitants,
was the delightful meed of geological research. By the
geometer were measured the regions of space, and the relative distances
of the heavenly bodies;—by the geologist myriads of ages were
reckoned, not by arithmetical computation, but by a train of physical
events—a succession of phenomena in the animate and inanimate worlds—signs
which convey to our minds more definite ideas than figures can
do of the immensity of time.
Whether our investigation of the earth's history and structure will
eventually be productive of as great practical benefits to mankind as a
knowledge of the distant heavens, must remain for the decision of posterity.
It was not till astronomy had been enriched by the observations
of many centuries, and had made its way against popular prejudices to
the establishment of a sound theory, that its application to the useful
arts was most conspicuous. The cultivation of geology began at a later
period; and in every step which it has hitherto made towards sound
theoretical principles, it had to contend against more violent prepossessions.
The practical advantages already derived from it have not been
inconsiderable; but our generalizations are yet imperfect, and they
who come after us may be expected to reap the most valuable fruits of
our labor. Meanwhile, the charm of first discovery is our own; and, as
we explore this magnificent field of inquiry, the sentiment of a great
historian of our times may continually be present to our minds, that "he
who calls what has vanished back again into being, enjoys a bliss like
that of creating."122
</div></body></text></TEI>