<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="48">CHAPTER III.
Sequel to Copernicus.

English Copernicans.
PROFESSOR DE MORGAN  has made
numerous and interesting contributions to the history of the progress
and reception of the Copernican System. These are given mainly in the
Companion to the British Almanac; especially in his papers
entitled “Old Arguments against the Motion of the Earth” (1836);
“English Mathematical and Astronomical Writers” (1837); “On the
Difficulty of Correct 527 Description of Books” (1853); “The
Progress of the Doctrine of the Earth’s Motion between the Times of
Copernicus and Galileo” (1855). In these papers he insists very
rightly upon the distinction between the mathematical and the
physical aspect of the doctrines of Copernicus: a distinction
corresponding very nearly with the distinction which we have drawn
between Formal and Physical Astronomy; and in accordance with which we
have given the history of the Heliocentric Doctrine as a Formal Theory
in Book v., and as a Physical Theory in Book vii.
Another interesting part of Mr. De Morgan’s researches are the
notices which he has given of the early assertors of the heliocentric
doctrine in England. These make their appearance as soon as it was
well possible they should exist. The work of Copernicus was published,
as we have said, in 1543. In September 1556, John Field published an
Ephemeris for 1557, “juxta Copernici et Reinholdi Canones,” in the
preface to which he avows his conviction of the truth of the
Copernican hypothesis. Robert Recorde, the author of various works on
Arithmetic, published among others, “The Pathway to Knowledge” in
1551. In this book, the author discusses the question of the “quietnes
of the earth,” and professes to leave it undecided: but Mr. De Morgan
(Comp. A. 1837, p. 33) conceives that it appears from what is
said, that he was really a Copernican, but did not think the world
ripe for any such doctrine.
Mr. Joseph Hunter also has brought to notice29 the claims of
Field, whom he designates as the Proto-Copernican of England.
He quotes the Address to the Reader prefixed to his first
Ephemeris, and dated May 31, 1556, in which he says that, since
abler men decline the task, “I have therefore published this Ephemeris
of the year 1557, following in it as my authorities, N. Copernicus and
Erasmus Reinhold, whose writings are established and founded on true,
certain, and authentic demonstrations.” I conceive that this passage,
however, only shows that Field had adopted the Copernican scheme as a
basis for the calculation of Ephemerides; which, as Mr. De Morgan has
remarked, is a very different thing from accepting it as a physical
truth. Field, in this same address, makes mention of the errors
“illius turbæ quæ Alphonsi utitur hypothesi;” but the word
hypothesis is still indecisive.
29 Ast. Soc. Notices, vol. iii.
p. 3 (1833).
As evidence that Field was regarded in his own day as a man who
528 had rendered
good service to science, Mr. Hunter notices that, in 1558, the Heralds
granted to him the right of using, with his arms, the crest or
additional device of a red right arm issuing from the clouds, and
presenting a golden armillary sphere.
Recorde’s claims depend upon a passage in a Dialogue between
Master and Scholar, in which the Master expounds the
doctrine of Copernicus, and the authorities against it; to which the
Scholar answers, taking the common view: “Nay, sir, in good faith I
desire not to hear such vaine phantasies, so far against common
reason, and repugnant to all the learned multitude of wryters, and
therefore let it passe for ever and a day longer.” The Master, more
sagely, warns him against a hasty judgment, and says, “Another time I
will so declare his supposition, that you shall not only wonder to
hear it, but also peradventure be as earnest then to credit it, as you
now are now to condemne it.” I conceive that this passage proves Mr.
De Morgan’s assertion, that Recorde was a Copernican, and very likely
the first in England.
In 1555, also, Leonard Digges published his “Prognostication
Everlasting;” but this is, as Mr. De Morgan says (Comp. A.
1837, p. 40) a meteorological work. It was republished in 1592 by his
son Thomas Digges with additions; and as these have been the occasion
of some confusion among those who have written on the history of
astronomy, I am glad to be able, through the kindness of Professor
Walker of Oxford, to give a distinct account of the editions of the
work.
In the Bodleian Library, besides the editions of 1555 and 1592 of
the “Prognostication Everlasting,” there is an edition of 1564. It is
still decidedly Ptolemaic, and contains a Diagram representing a
number of concentric circles, which are marked, in order, as—
 “The Earth,
   Moone,
   Venus,
   Mercury,
   Sunne,
   Mars,
   Jupiter,
   Saturne,
 The Starrie Firmament,
 The Crystalline Heavens,
 The First Mover,
 The Abode of God and the Elect. Here the Learned do approve.”
529
The third edition, of 1592, contains an Addition, by the son, of
twenty pages. He there speaks of having found, apparently among his
father’s papers, “A description or modile of the world and situation
of Spheres Cœlestiall and elementare according to the doctrine of
Ptolemie, whereunto all universities (led thereunto chiefly by the
authoritie of Aristotle) do consent.” He adds: “But in this our age,
one rare witte (seeing the continuall errors that from time to time
more and more continually have been discovered, besides the infinite
absurdities in their Theoricks, which they have been forced to admit
that would not confesse any Mobilitie in the ball of the Earth) hath
by long studye, paynfull practise, and rare invention, delivered a new
Theorick or Model of the world, shewing that the Earth resteth not in
the Center of the whole world or globe of elements, which encircled
and enclosed in the Moone’s orbe, and together with the whole globe of
mortalitye is carried yearely round about the Sunne, which like a king
in the middest of all, raygneth and giveth lawes of motion to all the
rest, sphærically dispersing his glorious beames of light through all
this sacred cœlestiall Temple. And the Earth itselfe to be one of the
Planets, having his peculiar and strange courses, turning every 24
hours rounde upon his owne centre, whereby the Sunne and great globe
of fixed Starres seem to sway about and turne, albeit indeed they
remaine fixed—So many ways is the sense of mortal man
abused.”
This Addition is headed:
 “A Perfit Description of the Cœlestiall Orbes, according to the
most ancient doctrine of the Pythagoreans: lately revived by
Copernicus, and by Geometrical Demonstrations approved.” Mr. De
Morgan, not having seen this edition, and knowing the title-page only
as far as the word “Pythagoreans,” says “their astrological
doctrines we presume, not their reputed Copernican ones.” But
it now appears that in this, as in other cases, the authority of the
Pythagoreans was claimed for the Copernican system. Antony a Wood
quotes the latter part of the title thus: “Cui subnectitur
orbium Copernicarum accurata descriptio;” which is inaccurate.
Weidler, still more inaccurately, cites it, “Cui subnectitur
operum Copernici accurata descriptio.” Lalande goes still
further, attempting, it would seem, to recover the English title-page
from the Latin: we find in the Bibl. Astron. the following:
“1592 . . Leonard Digges, Accurate Description of the Copernican
System to the Astronomical perpetual Prognostication.”
Thomas Digges appears, by others also of his writings, to have been
530 a clear and
decided Copernican. In his “Alæ sive Scalæ Mathematicæ,” 1573, he
bestows high praise upon Copernicus and upon his system: and appears
to have been a believer in the real motion of the Earth, and not
merely an admirer of the system of Copernicus as an explanatory
hypothesis.
Giordano Bruno.
The complete title of the work referred to
is:
 “Jordani Bruni Nolani De Monade Numero et Figura liber
consequens Quinque De Minimo Magno et Mensura, item De
Innumerabilibus, Immenso et Infigurabili; seu De Universo et Mundis
libri octo. (Francofurti, 1591.)”
That the Reader may judge of the value of Bruno’s speculations, I
give the following quotations:
Lib. iv. c. 11 (Index). “Tellurem totam habitabilem esse
intus et extra, et innumerabilia animantium complecti tum
nobis sensibilium tum occultorum genera.”
C. 13. “Ut Mundorum Synodi in Universo et particulares Mundi in
Synodis ordinentur,’ &c.
He says (Lib. v. c. 1, p. 461): “Besides the stars and the great
worlds there are smaller living creatures carried through the etherial
space, in the form of a small sphere which has the aspect of a bright
fire, and is by the vulgar regarded as a fiery beam. They are below
the clouds, and I saw one which seemed to touch the roofs of the
houses. Now this sphere, or beam as they call it, was really a living
creature (animal), which I once saw moving in a straight path,
and grazing as it were the roofs of the city of Nola, as if it were
going to impinge on Mount Cicada; which however it went over.”
There are two recent editions of the works of Giordano Bruno; by
Adolf Wagner, Leipsick, 1830, in two volumes; and by Gfrörer, Berlin,
1833. Of the latter I do not know that more than one volume (vol. ii.)
has appeared.
Did Francis Bacon reject the Copernican System?
Mr. De Morgan has very properly remarked
(Comp. B. A. 1855, p. 11) that the notice of the heliocentric
question in the Novum Organon must be considered one of the
most important passages in his works upon this point, as being
probably the latest written and best 531 matured. It occurs in Lib. ii. Aphorism
xxxvi., in which he is speaking of Prerogative Instances, of
which he gives twenty-seven species. In the passage now referred to,
he is speaking of a kind of Prerogative Instances, better known to
ordinary readers than most of the kinds by name, the Instantia
Crucis: though probably the metaphor from which this name is
derived is commonly wrongly apprehended. Bacon’s meaning is
Guide-Post Instances: and the Crux which he alludes to
is not a Cross, but a Guide-Post at Cross-roads. And among the cases
to which such Instances may be applied, he mentions the diurnal motion
of the heavens from east to west, and the special motion of the
particular heavenly bodies from west to east. And he suggests what he
conceives may be an Instantia Crucis in each case. If, he says,
we find any motion from east to west in the bodies which surround the
earth, slow in the ocean, quicker in the air, quicker still in comets,
gradually quicker in planets according to their greater distance from
the earth: then we may suppose that there is a cosmical
diurnal motion, and the motion of the earth must be denied.
With regard to the special motions of the heavenly bodies, he first
remarks that each body not coming quite so far westwards as before,
after one revolution of the heavens, and going to the north or the
south, does not imply any special motion; since it may be accounted
for by a modification of the diurnal motion in each, which produces a
defect of the return, and a spiral path; and he says that if we look
at the matter as common people30 and disregard
the devices of astronomers, the motion is really so to the senses; and
that he has made an imitation of it by means of wires. The
instantia crucis which he here suggests is, to see if we can
find in any credible history an account of any comet which did not
share in the diurnal revolution of the skies.
30 Et certissimum est si paulisper pro
plebeiis nos geramus (missis astronomorum et scholæ commentis, quibus
illud in more est, ut sensui in multis immerito vim faciant et
obscuriora malint) talem esse motum istum ad sensum qualem
diximus.
On his assertion that the motion of each separate planet is, to
sense, a spiral, we may remark that it is certainly true; but that the
business of science, here, as elsewhere, consists in
resolving the complex phenomenon into simple phenomena; the
complex spiral motion into simple circular motions.
With regard to the diurnal motion of the earth, it would seem as if
Bacon himself had a leaning to believe it when he wrote this passage;
for neither is he himself, nor are any of the Anticopernicans, 532 accustomed to assert
that the immensely rapid motion of the sphere of the Fixed Stars
graduates by a slower and slower motion of Planets, Comets, Air, and
Ocean, into the immobility of the Earth. So that the conditions are
not satisfied on which he hypothetically says, “tum abnegandus est
motus terræ.”
With regard to the proper motions of the planets, this passage
seems to me to confirm what I have already said of him; that he does
not appear to have seen the full value and meaning of what had been
done, up to his time, in Formal Astronomy.
We may however fully agree with Mr. De Morgan; that the whole of
what he has said on this subject, when put together, does not justify
Hume’s assertion that he rejected the Copernican system “with the most
positive disdain.”
Mr. De Morgan, in order to balance the Copernican argument derived
from the immense velocity of the stars in their diurnal velocity on
the other supposition, has reminded us that those who reject this
great velocity as improbable, accept without scruple the greater
velocity of light. It is curious that Bacon also has made this
comparison, though using it for a different purpose; namely, to show
that the transmission of the visual impression may be instantaneous.
In Aphorism xlvi. of Book ii. of the Novum Organon he is
speaking of what he calls Instantiæ curriculi, or Instantiæ
ad aquam, which we may call Instances by the clock: and he
says that the great velocity of the diurnal sphere makes the
marvellous velocity of the rays of light more credible.
“Immensa illa velocitas in ipso corpore, quæ cernitur in motu
diurno (quæ etiam viros graves ita obstupefecit ut mallent credere
motum terræ), facit motum illum ejaculationis ab ipsis [stellis]
(licet celeritate ut diximus admirabilem) magis credibilem.” This
passage shows an inclination towards the opinion of the earth’s being
at rest, but not a very strong conviction.
Kepler persecuted.
We have seen (p.
280) that Kepler writes to Galileo in 1597—“Be trustful and
go forwards. If Italy is not a convenient place for the publication of
your views, and if you are likely to meet with any obstacles, perhaps
Germany will grant us the necessary liberty.” Kepler however had soon
afterwards occasion to learn that in Germany also, the cultivators of
science were exposed to persecution. It is true that 533 in his case the
persecution went mainly on the broad ground of his being a Protestant,
and extended to great numbers of persons at that time. The
circumstances of this and other portions of Kepler’s life have been
brought to light only recently through an examination of public
documents in the Archives of Würtemberg and unpublished letters of
Kepler. (Johann Keppler’s Leben und Wirken, nach neuerlich
aufgefundenen Manuscripten bearbeitet von J. L. C. Freiherrn v.
Breitschwart, K. Würtemberg. Staats-Rath. Stuttgart, 1831.)
Schiller, in his History of the Thirty Years’ War, says that
when Ferdinand of Austria succeeded to the Archduchy of Stiria, and
found a great number of Protestants among his subjects, he suppressed
their public worship without cruelty and almost without noise. But it
appears now that the Protestants were treated with great severity.
Kepler held a professorship in Stiria, and had married, in 1507,
Barbara Müller, who had landed property in that province. On the 11th
of June, 1598, he writes to his friend Mæstlin that the arrival of the
Prince out of Italy is looked forwards to with terror. In December he
writes that the Protestants had irritated the Catholics by attacks
from the pulpit and by caricatures; that hereupon the Prince, at the
prayer of the Estates, had declared the Letter of License granted by
his father to be forfeited, and had ordered all the Evangelical
Teachers to leave the country on pain of death. They went to the
frontiers of Hungary and Croatia; but after a month, Kepler was
allowed to return, on condition of keeping quiet. His discoveries
appear to have operated in his favor. But the next year he found his
situation in Stiria intolerable, and longed to return to his native
country of Würtemberg, and to find some position there. This he did
not obtain. He wrote a circular letter to his Brother Protestants, to
give them consolation and courage; and this was held to be a violation
of the conditions on which his residence was tolerated. Fortunately,
at this time he was invited to join Tycho Brahe, who had also been
driven from his native country, and was living at Prague. The two
astronomers worked together under the patronage of the Emperor Rudolph
II.; and when Tycho died in 1601, Kepler became the Imperial
Mathematicus.
We are not to imagine that even among Protestants, astronomical
notions were out of the sphere of religious considerations. When
Kepler was established in Stiria, his first official business was the
calculation of the Calendar for the Evangelical Community. They
protested against the new Calendar, as manifestly calculated for the
furtherance of an impious papistry: and, say they, “We hold the Pope
for a 534 horrible
roaring Lion. If we take his Calendar, we must needs go into the
church when he rings us in.” Kepler however did not fail to see, and
to say, that the Papal Reformation of the Calendar was a vast
improvement.
Kepler, as court-astronomer, was of course required to provide such
observations of the heavens as were requisite for the calculations of
the Astrologers. That he considered Astrology to be valuable only as
the nurse of Astronomy, he did not hesitate to reveal. He wrote a work
with a title of which the following is the best translation which I
can give: “Tertius interveniens, or: A Warning to certain
Theologi, Medici, Philosophi, that while they
reasonably reject star-gazing superstition, they do not throw away the
kernel with the shell.31 1610.” In this he says, “You
over-clever Philosophers blame this Daughter of Astronomy more than is
reasonable. Do you not know that she must maintain her mother with her
charms? How many men would be able to make Astronomy their business,
if men did not cherish the hope to read the Future in the skies?”
31 The German passage involves a
curious image, borrowed, I suppose, from some odd story: “dass sie mit
billiger Verwerfung des sternguckerischen Aberglaubens das Kind nicht
mit dem Bade ausschütten.” “That they do not throw away the child
along with the dirty water of his bath.”
Were the Papal Edicts against the Copernican System
repealed?
Admiral Smyth, in his Cycle of Celestial
Objects, vol. i. p. 65, says—“At length, in 1818, the voice
of truth was so prevailing that Pius VII. repealed the edicts against
the Copernican system, and thus, in the emphatic words of Cardinal
Toriozzi, ‘wiped off this scandal from the Church.’”
A like story is referred to by Sir Francis Palgrave, in his
entertaining and instructive fiction, The Merchant and the
Friar.
Having made inquiry of persons most likely to be well informed on
this subject, I have not been able to learn that there is any further
foundation for these statements than this: In 1818, on the revisal of
the Index Expurgatorius, Galileo’s writings were, after some
opposition, expunged from that Catalogue.
Monsignor Marino Marini, an eminent Roman Prelate, had addressed to
the Romana Accademia di Archeologia, certain historico-critical
Memoirs, which he published in 1850, with the title Galileo e
l’Inquisizione. In these, he confirms the conclusion which, I
think, almost 535
all persons who have studied the facts have arrived at;32 that Galileo trifled with authority to
which he professed to submit, and was punished for obstinate
contumacy, not for heresy. M. Marini renders full justice to Galileo’s
ability, and does not at all hesitate to regard his scientific
attainments as among the glories of Italy. He quotes, what Galileo
himself quoted, an expression of Cardinal Baronius, that “the
intention of the Holy Spirit was to teach how to go to heaven, not how
heaven goes.”33 He shows that Galileo pleaded (p. 62)
that he had not held the Copernican opinion after it had been
intimated to him (by Bellarmine in 1616), that he was not to hold it;
and that his breach of promise in this respect was the cause of the
proceedings against him.
32 M. Marini (p. 29) mentions
Leibnitz, Guizot, Spittler, Eichhorn, Raumer, Ranke, among the
“storici eterodossi” who have at last done justice to the Roman
Church.
33 Come si vada al Cielo, e non come
vada il Cielo.
Those who admire Galileo and regard him as a
martyr because, after escaping punishment by saying “It does
not move,” he forthwith said “And yet it does move,”
will perhaps be interested to know that the former answer was
suggested to him by friends anxious for his safety. Niccolini writes
to Bali Cioli (April 9, 1633) that Galileo continued to be so
persuaded of the truth of his opinions that “he was resolved (some
moments before his sentence) to defend them stoutly; but I (continues
Niccolini) exhorted him to make an end of this; not to mind defending
them; and to submit himself to that which he sees that they may desire
him to believe or to hold about this matter of the motion of the
earth. He was extremely afflicted.” But the Inquisition was satisfied
with his answers, and required no more.34
34 Marini, p. 61.


BOOK VI.

MECHANICS.
</div></body></text></TEI>