<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="25">
CHAPTER IX.
Of the Application of Inductive Truths.
Aphorism LIII.
When the theory of any subject is established, the observations
and experiments which are made in applying the
science to use and to instruction, supply a perpetual verification
of the theory.
Aphorism LIV.
Such observations and experiments, when numerous and
accurate, supply also corrections of the constants involved
in the theory; and sometimes, (by the Method of Residues,)
additions to the theory.
Aphorism LV.
It is worth considering, whether a continued and connected
system of observation and calculation, like that of
astronomy, might not be employed with advantage in improving
our knowledge of other subjects; as Tides, Currents,
Winds, Clouds, Rain, Terrestrial Magnetism, Aurora Borealis,
Composition of Crystals, and many other subjects.
Aphorism LVI.
An extension of a well-established theory to the explanation
of new facts excites admiration as a discovery; but it is a
discovery of a lower order than the theory itself.
Aphorism LVII.
The practical inventions which are most important in
Art may be either unimportant parts of Science, or results
not explained by Science. 234
Aphorism LVIII.
In modern times, in many departments. Art is constantly
guided, governed and advanced by Science.
Aphorism LIX.
Recently several New Arts have been invented, which may
be regarded as notable verifications of the anticipations of
material benefits to be derived to man from the progress of
Science.
1. BY the
application of inductive truths, we here
mean, according to the arrangement given in
chap. I. of this book, those steps, which in the natural
order of science, follow the discovery of each truth.
These steps are, the verification of the discovery by additional
experiments and reasonings, and its extension
to new cases, not contemplated by the original discoverer.
These processes occupy that period, which,
in the history of each great discovery, we have termed
the Sequel of the epoch; as the collection of facts, and
the elucidation of conceptions, form its Prelude.
2. It is not necessary to dwell at length on the
processes of the Verification of Discoveries. When the
Law of Nature is once stated, it is far easier to devise
and execute experiments which prove it, than it was
to discern the evidence before. The truth becomes
one of the standard doctrines of the science to which it
belongs, and is verified by all who study or who teach
the science experimentally. The leading doctrines of
Chemistry are constantly exemplified by each chemist
in his Laboratory; and an amount of verification is
thus obtained of which books give no adequate conception.
In Astronomy, we have a still stronger example
of the process of verifying discoveries. Ever since the
science assumed a systematic form, there have been
Observatories, in which the consequences of the theory
were habitually compared with the results of observation.
And to facilitate this comparison, Tables of
great extent have been calculated, with immense labour,
from each theory, showing the place which the 235
theory assigned to the heavenly bodies at successive
times; and thus, as it were, challenging nature to
deny the truth of the discovery. In this way, as I
have elsewhere stated, the continued prevalence of an
errour in the systematic parts of astronomy is
impossible49.
An errour, if it arise, makes its way into the
tables, into the ephemeris, into the observer’s nightly
list, or his sheet of reductions; the evidence of sense
flies in its face in a thousand Observatories; the
discrepancy is traced to its source, and soon disappears
for ever.
49
 Hist. Ind. Sc. b. vii. c. vi. sect. 6.
3. In these last expressions, we suppose the theory,
not only to be tested, but also to be corrected when it
is found to be imperfect. And this also is part of the
business of the observing astronomer. From his accumulated
observations, he deduces more exact values than
had previously been obtained, of the Constants or
Coefficients of these Inequalities of which the Argument is
already known. This he is enabled to do by the methods
explained in the fifth chapter of this book; the Method
of Means, and especially the Method of Least Squares.
In other cases, he finds, by the Method of Residues,
some new Inequality; for if no change of the Coefficients
will bring the Tables and the observation to a
coincidence, he knows that a new Term is wanting in
his formula. He obtains, as far as he can, the law of
this unknown Term; and when its existence and its
law have been fully established, there remains the
task of tracing it to its cause.
4. The condition of the science of Astronomy, with
regard to its security and prospect of progress, is one of
singular felicity. It is a question well worth our consideration,
as regarding the interests of science, whether, in other branches
of knowledge also, a continued
and corrected system, of observation and calculation,
imitating the system employed by astronomers, might
not be adopted. But the discussion of this question
would involve us in a digression too wide for the present occasion. 236
5. There is another mode of application of true
theories after their discovery, of which we must also
speak; I mean the process of showing that facts, not
included in the original induction, and apparently of a
different kind, are explained by reasonings founded
upon the theory:—extensions of the theory as we may
call them. The history of physical astronomy is full
of such events. Thus after Bradley and Wargentin
had observed a certain cycle among the perturbations
of Jupiter’s satellites, Laplace explained this cycle by
the doctrine of universal
gravitation50. The long
inequality of Jupiter and Saturn, the diminution of the
obliquity of the ecliptic, the acceleration of the moon’s
mean motion, were in like manner accounted for by
Laplace. The coincidence of the nodes of the moon’s
equator with those of her orbit was proved to result
from mechanical principles by Lagrange. The motions
of the recently-discovered planets, and of comets, shown
by various mathematicians to be in exact accordance
with the theory, are Verifications and Extensions still
more obvious.
50
 Hist. Ind. Sc. b. vii. c. iv. sect. 3.
6. In many of the cases just noticed, the consistency
between the theory, and the consequences thus proved
to result from it, is so far from being evident, that the
most consummate command of all the powers and aids
of mathematical reasoning is needed, to enable the philosopher
to arrive at the result. In consequence of
this circumstance, the labours just referred to, of Laplace,
Lagrange, and others, have been the object of
very great and very just admiration. Moreover, the
necessary connexion of new facts, at first deemed inexplicable,
with principles already known to be true;—a
connexion utterly invisible at the outset, and yet at
last established with the certainty of demonstration;—strikes
us with the delight of a new discovery; and at
first sight appears no less admirable than an original
induction. Accordingly, men sometimes appear tempted
to consider Laplace and other great mathematicians as
persons of a kindred genius to Newton. We must not 237
forget, however, that there is a great and essential difference
between inductive and deductive processes of
the mind. The discovery of a new theory, which is
true, is a step widely distinct from any mere development
of the consequences of a theory already invented
and established.
7. In the other sciences also, which have been
framed by a study of natural phenomena, we may find
examples of the explanation of new phenomena by
applying the principles of the science when once
established. Thus, when the laws of the reflection
and refraction of light had been established, a new
and poignant exemplification of them was found in
the explanation of the Rainbow by the reflection and
refraction of light in the spherical drops of a shower;
and again, another, no less striking, when the intersecting
Luminous Circles and Mock Suns, which are
seen in cold seasons, were completely explained by the
hexagonal crystals of ice which float in the upper
regions of the atmosphere. The Darkness of the space
between the primary and secondary rainbow is another
appearance which optical theory completely explains.
And when we further include in our optical theory
the doctrine of interferences, we find the explanation
of other phenomena; for instance, the Supernumerary
Rainbows which accompany the primary rainbow on
its inner side, and the small Halos which often surround
the sun and moon. And when we come to
optical experiments, we find many instances in which
the doctrine of interferences and of undulations have
been applied to explain the phenomena by calculations
almost as complex as those which we have mentioned
in speaking of astronomy: with results as little foreseen
at first and as entirely satisfactory in the end.
Such are Schwerdt’s explanation of the diffracted
images of a triangular aperture by the doctrine of
interferences, and the explanation of the coloured
Lemniscates seen by polarized light in biaxal crystals,
given by Young and by Herschel: and still more
marked is another case, in which the curves are
unsymmetrical, namely, the curves seen by passing polarized 238
light through plates of quartz, which agree in a wonderful manner
with the calculations of Airy. To these
we may add the curious phenomena, and equally
curious mathematical explanation, of Conical Refraction,
as brought to view by Professor Lloyd and Sir
W. Hamilton. Indeed, the whole history both of
Physical Optics and of Physical Astronomy is a series
of felicities of this kind, as we have elsewhere
observed. Such applications of theory, and unforeseen
explanations of new facts by complicated trains of reasoning
necessarily flowing from the theory, are strong proof
of the truth of the theory, while it is in the course of
being established; but we are here rather speaking of
them as applications of the theory after it has been
established.
Those who thus apply principles already discovered
are not to be ranked in their intellectual achievements
with those who discover new principles; but still,
when such applications are masked by the complex
relations of space and number, it is impossible not to
regard with admiration the clearness and activity of
intellect which thus discerns in a remote region the
rays of a central truth already unveiled by some great
discoverer.
8. As examples in other fields of the application
of a scientific discovery to the explanation of natural
phenomena, we may take the identification of Lightning
with electricity by Franklin, and the explanation
of Dew by Wells. For Wells’s Inquiry into the
Cause of Dew, though it has sometimes been praised
as an original discovery, was, in fact, only resolving
the phenomenon into principles already discovered.
The atmologists of the last century were
aware51 that
the vapour which exists in air in an invisible state
may be condensed into water by cold; and they had
noticed that there is always a certain temperature,
lower than that of the atmosphere, to which if we
depress bodies, water forms upon them in fine drops.
This temperature is the limit of that which
is 239 necessary
to constitute vapour, and is hence called the constituent
temperature. But these principles were not
generally familiar in England till Dr. Wells introduced
them into his Essay on Dew, published in 1814; having
indeed been in a great measure led to them by his
own experiments and reasonings. His explanation of
Dew,—that it arises from the coldness of the bodies
on which it settles,—was established with great ingenuity;
and is a very elegant confirmation of the Theory
of Constituent Temperature.
51
Hist. Ind. Sc. b. x. c. iii. sect. 5.
9. As other examples of such explanations of new
phenomena by a theory, we may point out Ampère’s
Theory that Magnetism is transverse voltaic currents,
applied to explain the rotation of a voltaic wire round
a magnet, and of a magnet round a voltaic wire. And
again, in the same subject, when it had been proved
that electricity might be converted into magnetism, it
seemed certain that magnetism might be converted
into electricity; and accordingly Faraday found under
what conditions this may be done; though indeed
here, the theory rather suggested the experiment than
explained it when it had been independently observed.
The production of an electric spark by a magnet was
a very striking exemplification of the theory of the
identity of these different polar agencies.
10. In Chemistry such applications of the principles of
the science are very frequent; for it is the
chemist’s business to account for the innumerable
changes which take place in material substances by
the effects of mixture, heat, and the like. As a marked
instance of such an application of the science, we
may take the explanation of the explosive force of
gunpowder52,
from the conversion of its materials
into gases. In Mineralogy also we have to apply the 240
principles of Chemistry to the analysis of bodies: and
I may mention, as a case which at the time excited
much notice, the analysis of a mineral called Heavy
Spar. It was found that different specimens of this
mineral differed in their crystalline angles about three
degrees and a half; a difference which was at variance
with the mineralogical discovery then recently made,
of the constancy of the angle of the same substance.
Vauquelin solved this difficulty by discovering that
the crystals with the different angles were really
minerals chemically different; the one kind being sulphate
of barytes, and the other, sulphate of strontian.
52
 The explanation is, that the force is due to the
sudden development of a large volume of nitrogen and carbonic
acid gases, which at the ordinary temperature of the air would
occupy a space equal to about 300 times the bulk of the powder
used, but from the intense heat developed at the moment of the
explosion, the dilatation amounts to at least 1500 times
the volume of the gunpowder employed.
11. In this way a scientific theory, when once established,
is perpetually finding new applications in the
phenomena of nature; and those who make such
applications, though, as we have said, they care not to
be ranked with the great discoverers who establish
theories new and true, often receive a more prompt
and general applause than great discoverers do; because
they have not to struggle with the perplexity
and averseness which often encounter the promulgation
of new truths.
12. Along with the verification and extension of
scientific truths, we are naturally led to consider the
useful application of them. The example of all the
best writers who have previously treated of the philosophy
of sciences, from Bacon to Herschel, draws our
attention to those instances of the application of scientific
truths, which are subservient to the uses of
practical life; to the support, the safety, the pleasure
of man. It is well known in how large a degree
the furtherance of these objects constituted the merit
of the Novum Organon in the eyes of its author;
and the enthusiasm with which men regard these
visible and tangible manifestations of the power and
advantage which knowledge may bring, has gone on
increasing up to our own day. And undoubtedly such
applications of the discoveries of science to promote
the preservation, comfort, power and dignity of man,
must always be objects of great philosophical as well
as practical interest. Yet we may observe that those 241
practical inventions which are of most importance in
the Arts, have not commonly, in the past ages of the
world, been the results of theoretical knowledge, nor
have they tended very greatly to the promotion of such
knowledge. The use of bread and of wine has existed
from the first beginning of man’s social history; yet men
have not had—we may question whether they yet have—a
satisfactory theory of the constitution and fabrication
of bread and of wine. From a very early period
there have been workers in metal: yet who could tell
upon what principles depended the purifying of gold
and silver by the fire, or the difference between iron
and steel? In some cases, as in the story of the brass
produced by the Corinthian conflagration, some particular
step in art is ascribed to a special accident; but
hardly ever to the thoughtful activity of a scientific
speculator. The Dyeing of cloths, the fabrication and
colouring of earthenware and glass vessels was carried
to a very high degree of completeness; yet who had
any sound theoretical knowledge respecting these processes?
Are not all these arts still practised with
a degree of skill which we can hardly or not at all
surpass, by nations which have, properly speaking, no
science? Till lately, at least, if even now the case
be different, the operations by which man’s comforts,
luxuries, and instruments were produced, were either
mere practical processes, which the artist practises, but
which the scientist cannot account for; or, as in astronomy
and optics, they depended upon a small portion
only of the theoretical sciences, and did not tend to
illustrate, or lead to, any larger truths. Bacon mentions
as recent discoveries, which gave him courage
and hope with regard to the future progress of human
knowledge, the invention of gunpowder, glass, and
printing, the introduction of silk, and the discovery of
America. Yet which of these can be said to have been
the results of a theoretical enlargement of human
knowledge? except perhaps the discovery of the New
World, which was in some degree the result of Columbus’s
conviction of the globular form of the earth.
This, however, was not a recent, but a very ancient 242
doctrine of all sound astronomers. And which of these
discoveries has been the cause of a great enlargement
of our theoretical knowledge?—except any one claims
such a merit for the discovery of printing; in which
sense the result is brought about in a very indirect
manner, in the same way in which the progress of
freedom and of religion may be ascribed as consequences
to the same discovery. However great or
striking, then, such discoveries have been, they have
not, generally speaking, produced any marked advance
of the Inductive Sciences in the sense in which we
here speak of them. They have increased man’s
power, it may be: that is, his power of adding to his
comforts and communicating with his fellow-men.
But they have not necessarily or generally increased
his theoretical knowledge. And, therefore, with whatever
admiration we may look upon such discoveries as
these, we are not to admire them as steps in Inductive
Science.
And on the other hand, we are not to ask of Inductive Science,
as a necessary result of her progress,
such additions as these to man’s means of enjoyment
and action. It is said, with a feeling of triumph, that
Knowledge is Power: but in whatever sense this may
truly be said, we value Knowledge, not because it is
Power but because it is Knowledge; and we estimate
wrongly both the nature and the dignity of that kind
of science with which we are here concerned, if we
expect that every new advance in theory will forthwith
have a market value:—that science will mark
the birth of a new Truth with some new birthday
present, such as a softer stuff to wrap our limbs, a
brighter vessel to grace our table, a new mode of
communication with our friends and the world, a new
instrument for the destruction of our enemies, or a new
region which may be the source of wealth and interest.
13. Yet though, as we have said, many of the most
remarkable processes which we reckon as the triumphs
of Art did not result from a previous progress of Science,
we have, at many points of the history of Science,
applications of new views, to enable man to do
as well 243
as to see. When Archimedes had obtained clear views
of the theory of machines, he forthwith expressed them
in his bold practical boast; ‘Give me whereon to stand,
and I will move the earth.’ And his machines with
which he is said to have handled the Roman ships
like toys, and his burning mirrors with which he is
reported to have set them on fire, are at least possible
applications of theoretical principles. When he saw
the waters rising in the bath as his body descended,
and rushed out crying, ‘I have found the way;’ what
he had found was the solution of the practical
question of the quantity of silver mixed with the gold of
Hiero’s crown. But the mechanical inventions of Hero
of Alexandria, which moved by the force of air or of
steam, probably involved no exact theoretical notions
of the properties of air or of steam. He devised a toy
which revolved by the action of steam; but by the force
of steam exerted in issuing from an orifice, not by its
pressure or condensation. And the Romans had no arts
derived from science in addition to those which they
inherited from the Greeks. They built aqueducts, not
indeed through ignorance of the principles of hydrostatics,
as has sometimes been said; for we, who know our
hydrostatics, build aqueducts still; but their practice
exemplified only Archimedean hydrostatics. Their
clepsydras or water-clocks were adjusted by trial only.
They used arches and vaults more copiously than the
Greeks had done, but the principle of the arch appears,
by the most recent researches, to have been known to
the Greeks. Domes and groined arches, such as we have
in the Pantheon and in the Baths of Caracalla, perhaps
they invented; certainly they practised them on
a noble scale. Yet this was rather practical skill
than theoretical knowledge; and it was pursued by
their successors in the middle ages in the same manner,
as practical skill rather than theoretical knowledge.
Thus were produced flying buttresses, intersecting
pointed vaults, and the other wonders of mediæval
architecture. The engineers of the fifteenth century,
as Leonardo da Vinci, began to convert their practical
into theoretical knowledge of Mechanics; but still 244
clocks and watches, flying machines and printing
presses involved no new mechanical principle.
14. But from this time the advances in Science
generally produced, as their result, new inventions of
a practical kind. Thus the doctrine of the weight of
air led to such inventions as the barometer used as
a Weather-glass, the Air-pump with its train of curious
experiments, the Diving-Bell, the Balloon. The
telescope was perhaps in some degree a discovery due
to accident, but its principles had been taught by
Roger Bacon, and still more clearly by Descartes.
Newton invented a steady thermometer by attending
to steady laws of nature. And in the case of the improvements
of the steam engine made by Watt, we
have an admirable example how superior the method
of improving Art by Science is, to the blind gropings
of mere practical habit.
Of this truth, the history of most of the useful arts
in our time offers abundant proofs and illustrations.
All improvements and applications of the forces and
agencies which man employs for his purposes are now
commonly made, not by blind trial but with the
clearest theoretical as well as practical insight which
he can obtain, into the properties of the agents which
he employs. In this way he has constructed, (using
theory and calculation at every step of his construction,)
steam engines, steam boats, screw-propellers,
locomotive engines, railroads and bridges and structures
of all kinds. Lightning-conductors have been
improved and applied to the preservation of buildings,
and especially of ships, with admirable effect, by Sir
Wm. Snow Harris, an experimenter who has studied
with great care the theory of electricity. The measurement
of the quantity of oxygen, that is, of vital
power, in air, has been taught by Cavendish, and by
Dr Ure a skilful chemist of our time. Methods for
measuring the bleaching power of a substance have
been devised by eminent chemical philosophers, Gay
Lussac and Mr Graham. Davy used his discoveries
concerning the laws of flame in order to construct his
Safety Lamp:—his discoveries concerning the galvanic 245
battery in order to protect ships’ bottoms from corrosion.
The skilled geologist has repeatedly given to
those who were about to dig for coal where it could
have no geological place, advice which has saved them
from ruinous expence. Sir Roderick Murchison, from
geological evidence, declared the likelihood of gold
being found abundantly in Australia, many years before
the diggings began.
Even the subtle properties of light as shewn in the
recent discoveries of its interference and polarization,
have been applied to useful purposes. Young invented
an Eriometer, an instrument which should measure the
fineness of the threads of wool by the coloured fringes
which they produce; and substances which it is important
to distinguish in the manufacture of sugar,
are discriminated by their effect in rotating the plane
of polarization of light. One substance has been termed
Dextrin, from its impressing a right-handed rotation
on the plane of polarization.
And in a great number of Arts and Manufactures,
the necessity of a knowledge of theory to the right
conduct of practice is familiarly acknowledged and
assumed. In the testing and smelting of metals, in the
fabrication of soap, of candles, of sugar; in the dyeing
and printing of woollen, linen, cotton and silken stuffs;
the master manufacturer has always the scientific chemist
at his elbow;—either a ‘consulting chemist’ to
whom he may apply on a special occasion, (for such is
now a regular profession;) or a chemist who day by
day superintends, controls, and improves the processes
which his workmen daily carry on. In these cases,
though Art long preceded Science, Science now guides,
governs and advances Art.
15. Other Arts and manufactures which have arisen
in modern times have been new creations produced by
Science, and requiring a complete acquaintance with
scientific processes to conduct them effectually and
securely. Such are the photographic Arts, now so
various in their form; beginning with those which,
from their authors, are called Daguerrotype and Talbotype.
Such are the Arts of Electrotype modelling 246
and Electrotype plating. Such are the Arts of preparing
fulminating substances; gun-cotton; fulminate
of silver, and of mercury; and the application of those
Arts to use, in the fabrication of percussion-caps for
guns. Such is the Art of Electric Telegraphy, from its
first beginning to its last great attempt, the electric
cord which connects England and America. Such is
the Art of imitating by the chemistry of the laboratory
the vegetable chemistry of nature, and thus producing
the flavour of the pear, the apple, the pine-apple, the
melon, the quince. Such is the Art of producing in
man a temporary insensibility to pain, which was
effected first through the means of sulphuric ether by
Dr Jackson of America, and afterwards through the
use of chloroform by Dr Simpson of Edinburgh. In
these cases and many others Science has endowed
man with New Arts. And though even in these Arts,
which are thus the last results of Science, there is
much which Science cannot fully understand and explain;
still, such cases cannot but be looked upon as
notable verifications of the anticipations of those who
in former times expected from the progress of Science
a harvest of material advantages to man.
We must now conclude our task by a few words on
the subject of inductions involving Ideas ulterior to
those already considered.
</div></body></text></TEI>