<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="21">
CHAPTER II.

The Circular Orbits of the Planets round the Sun.

The orbit which the earth describes round the sun
is very nearly a circle: the sun is about one thirtieth
nearer to us in winter than in summer. This nearly
circular form of the orbit, on a little consideration,
will appear to be a remarkable circumstance.
Supposing the attraction of a planet towards the
sun to exist, if the planet were put in motion in any
part of the solar system, it would describe about the
sun an orbit of some kind; it might be a long oval, or[124]
a shorter oval, or an exact circle. But if we suppose
the result left to chance, the chances are infinitely
against the last mentioned case. There is but one
circle; there are an infinite number of ovals. Any
original impulse would give some oval, but only one
particular impulse, determinate in velocity and direction,
will give a circle. If we suppose the planet
to be originally projected, it must be projected perpendicularly
to its distance from the sun, and with a
certain precise velocity, in order that the motion
may be circular.
In the basin to which we have compared the solar
system, the adjustment requisite to produce circular
motion would require us to project our pellet so that
after running half round the surface it should touch
a point exactly at an equal distance from the centre,
on the other side, passing neither too high nor too
low. And the pellet, it may be observed, should be
in size only one ten thousandth part of the distance
from the centre, to make the dimensions correspond
with the cast of the earth’s orbit. If the mark were
set up and hit, we should hardly attribute the result
to chance.
The earth’s orbit, however, is not exactly a circle.
The mark is not precisely a single point, but is a
space of the breadth of one thirtieth of the distance
from the centre. Still this is much too near an agreement
with the circle to be considered as the work of
chance. The chances were great against the ball
passing so nearly at the same distance, for there
were twenty-nine equal spaces through which it
might have gone, between the mark and the centre,
and an indefinite number outside the mark.
But it is not the earth’s orbit alone which is nearly
a circle: the rest of the planets also approach very
nearly to that form: Venus more nearly still than
the earth: Jupiter, Saturn, and Uranus have a difference
of about one tenth, between their greatest and
least distances from the sun: Mars has his extreme
distances in the proportion of five to six nearly; and[125]
Mercury in the proportion of two to three. The last
mentioned case is a considerable deviation, and two
of the small planets which lie between Mars and Jupiter,
namely Juno and Pallas, exhibit an inequality
somewhat greater still; but the smallness of these
bodies, and other circumstances, make it probable
that there may be particular causes for the exception
in their case. The orbits of the satellites of the
Earth, of Jupiter and of Saturn, are also nearly circular.
Taking the solar system altogether, the regularity
of its structure is very remarkable. The diagram
which represents the orbits of the planets might have
consisted of a number of ovals, narrow and wide in
all degrees, intersecting and interfering with each
other in all directions. The diagram does consist,
as all who have opened a book of astronomy know,
of a set of figures which appear at first sight concentric
circles, and which are very nearly so; no
where approaching to any crossing or interfering,
except in the case of the small planets, already noticed
as irregular. No one, looking at this common
diagram, can believe that the orbits were made to
be so nearly circles by chance; any more than he
can believe that a target, such as archers are accustomed
to shoot at, was painted in concentric circles
by the accidental dashes of a brush in the hands of a
blind man.
The regularity, then, of the solar system excludes
the notion of accident in the arrangement of the orbits
of the planets. There must have been an express
adjustment to produce this circular character
of the orbits. The velocity and direction of the motion
of each planet must have been subject to some
original regulation; or, as it is often expressed, the
projectile force must have been accommodated to
the centripetal force. This once done, the motion of
each planet, taken by itself, would go on for ever,
still retaining its circular character, by the laws of
motion.
[126]
If some original cause adjusted the orbits of the
planets to their circular form and regular arrangement,
we can hardly avoid including in our conception
of this cause, the intention and will of a Creating
Power. We shall consider this argument more fully
in a succeeding chapter; only observing here, that
the presiding Intelligence, which has selected and
combined the properties of the organic creation, so
that they correspond so remarkably with the arbitrary
quantities of the system of the universe, may
readily be conceived also to have selected the arbitrary
velocity and direction of each planet’s motion,
so that the adjustment should produce a close approximation
to a circular motion.
We have argued here only from the regularity of
the solar system; from the selection of the single
symmetrical case and the rejection of all the unsymmetrical
cases. But this subject may be considered
in another point of view. The system thus selected
is not only regular and symmetrical, but also it is, so
far as we can judge, the only one which would answer
the purpose of the earth, perhaps of the other
planets, as the seat of animal and vegetable life. If
the earth’s orbit were more eccentric, as it is called,
if for instance the greatest and least distances were
as three to one, the inequality of heat at two seasons
of the year would be destructive to the existing species
of living creatures. A circular, or nearly circular,
orbit, is the only case in which we can have a
course of seasons such as we have at present, the
only case in which the climates of the northern and
southern hemispheres are nearly the same; and what
is more clearly important, the only case in which the
character of the seasons would not vary from century
to century. For if the eccentricity of the earth’s
orbit were considerable, the difference of heat at different
seasons, arising from the different distances of
the sun, would be combined with the difference, now
the only considerable one, which depends on the
position of the earth’s axis. And as by the motion[127]
of the perihelion, or place of the nearest distance of
the earth to the sun, this nearest distance would fall
in different ages at different parts of the year, the
whole distribution of heat through the year would
thus be gradually subverted. The summer and winter
of the tropical year, as we have it now, being
combined with the heat and cold of the anomalistic
year, a period of different length, the difference of
the two seasons might sometimes be neutralized altogether,
and at other times exaggerated by the accumulation
of the inequalities, so as to be intolerable.
The circular form of the orbit therefore, which,
from its unique character, appears to be chosen with
some design, from its effects on the seasons appears
to be chosen with this design, so apparent in other
parts of creation, of securing the welfare of organic
life, by a steadfast and regular order of the solar influence
upon the planet.
</div></body></text></TEI>