<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 166, folios 169-173</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 166, folios 169-173.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1851">24 July [1851]</date>
          <note type="place">[no place]</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 166, folios 169-173</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_166_folios_169-173.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Thursdy. 24th July</p>
      <p>Dearest L--.</p>
      <p>I am very glad of yr letter,-- &amp; perhaps a little glad that you "miss me"!--</p>
      <p>It shows at least that I have not become irksome or odious to you. If you will have patience yet a little longer, you will rejoice that you had patience.--</p>
      <p>Now as to my health: I do not agree with you that</p>
      <p>the progress is slow. When we consider that I have not been quite 2 months under treatment, for a most serious complaint which had existed (more or less) for upwards of a year,-- I think we cannot call the present state other than very satisfactory. Not only is there an improvement in nerves &amp; in general health which is obvious to everyone, &amp; is most of all</p>
      <p>felt &amp; known to myself,-- but the local condition is no longer vicious . Dr Locock explained to me yesterday how threatening &amp; how morbid it had been.-- He said that tho' now there is still an extensive &amp; deep-seated sore, yet it is a healthy sore that is not pressing hourly on the vital system. When he first saw me, he says he feared almost lest the constitution might not</p>
      <p>have power to aid the remedies &amp; to restore parts that were so un-vitalized as it were. Now he says he has no shadow of doubt or anxiety.</p>
      <p>He is shortly going away, &amp; will have to leave me under Dr Cape's care,-- &amp; this is one reason why my peculiar attention from him (Dr L--) is right at this time, in order that he may leave Dr Cape in full possession of all that is desirable</p>
      <p>2/ during the 5 or 6 weeks of Dr. L's absence. This transfer to Dr Cape is to me extremely distressing &amp; unpleasant, but it is inevitable.--</p>
      <p>I may tell you that there is a possibility of my going down on Satdy, till Mondy. But as it is so entirely uncertain, I have not liked even to mention it,-- &amp; you had better not think of it as likely.</p>
      <p>One comfort is that the drive to &amp; fro is rather good for me. And I think no harm for the horses either, with discretion.</p>
      <p>As to Nelson: will you explain to Kayes that 1stly, the nature of the wound did not seem to admit of the solution of a bite. It had not the character of a bite. 2ndly, that last year in the autumn (It might have</p>
      <p>been Novr or Decr) when the same thing occured, the accident was seen , for the Coachman was looking at the dog at the time, &amp; heard him yell at the momeent he saw the stone hit his foot. The stone was then thrown either from the garden or [two words crossed out] from some of the side nooks &amp; covers &amp; alleys that may border the road to the Tunnel. No other dog, nor any</p>
      <p>(visible) person was near at the time.</p>
      <p>I do not believe that any dog was near Nelson this time either. A fight &amp; quarrel would have ensued &amp; been heard, &amp; there is no doubt it would have been notorious enough.</p>
      <p>I will try &amp; get the Coachman to say on whom his suspicions fall. Meanwhile please to state the above facts. I examined the wound both times, &amp;</p>
      <p>3/ it certainly was very different from any bite I ever saw, &amp; was not on a spot where the teeth of an antagonist could well have found purchase. There was a cut &amp; bruise laying the claw bare, on the broad part of the foot. A dog would bite higher.</p>
      <p>Is the enclosed the Nicholson marriage?--</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
