<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="38">

CHAPTER II.
On Peculiarities in the Perceptions of the Different Senses.



1. WE
cannot doubt that we perceive all secondary qualities
by means of immediate impressions made, through the proper
medium of sensation, upon our organs. Hence all the senses
are sometimes vaguely spoken of as modifications of the
sense of feeling. It will, however, be seen, on reflection,
that this mode of speaking identifies in words things which
in our conceptions have nothing in common. No impression on
the organs of touch can be conceived as having any
resemblance to colour or smell. No effort, no ingenuity, can
enable us to describe the impressions of one sense in terms
borrowed from another.
The senses have, however, each its peculiar powers, and
these powers may be in some respects compared, so as to show
their leading resemblances and differences, and the
characteristic privileges and laws of each. This is what we
shall do as briefly as possible.
Sect. I.—Prerogatives of Sight.
The sight distinguishes colours, as the hearing
distinguishes tones; the sight estimates degrees of
brightness, the ear, degrees of loudness; but with several
resemblances, there are most remarkable differences between
these two senses.
2. Position.—The sight has this peculiar
prerogative, that it apprehends the place of its
objects directly and primarily. We see where an
object is at the same instant that we see what it is. If we
see two objects, we see their relative position. We cannot
help 303 perceiving that one is above or below, to the
right or to the left of the other, if we perceive them at
all.
There is nothing corresponding to this in sound. When we
hear a noise, we do not necessarily assign a place to it. It
may easily happen that we cannot tell from which side a
thunder-clap comes. And though we often can judge in what
direction a voice is heard, this is a matter of secondary
impression, and of inference from concomitant circumstances,
not a primary fact of sensation. The judgments which we form
concerning the position of sounding bodies are obtained by
the conscious or unconscious comparison of the impressions
made on the two ears, and on the bones of the head in
general; they are not inseparable conditions of hearing. We
may hear sounds, and be uncertain whether they are ‘above,
around, or underneath!’ but the moment anything visible
appears, however unexpected, we can say, ‘see where
it comes!’
Since we can see the relative position of things, we can see
figure, which is but the relative position of the
different parts of the boundary of the object. And thus the
whole visible world exhibits to us a scene of various
shapes, coloured and shaded according to their form and
position, but each having relations of position to all the
rest; and altogether, entirely filling up the whole range
which the eye can command.
3. Distance.—The distance of objects from us is no
matter of immediate perception, but is a judgment and
inference formed from our sensations, in something of the
same way as our judgment of position by the ear, though more
precise. That this is so, was most distinctly shown by
Berkeley, in his New Theory of Vision. The elements
on which we form our judgment are, the effort by which we
fix both eyes on the same object, the effort by which we
adjust each eye to distinct vision, and the known forms,
colours, and parts of objects, as compared with their
appearance. The right interpretation of the information
which these circumstances give us respecting the true
distances and forms of things, is gradually learnt by
experience, the lesson being begun in our earliest infancy,
and inculcated upon us every hour during which we 304 use
our eyes. The completeness with which the lesson is learnt
is truly admirable; for we forget that our conclusion is
obtained indirectly, and mistake a judgment on evidence for
an intuitive perception. This, however, is not more
surprizing than the rapidity and unconsciousness of effort
with which we understand the meaning of the speech that we
hear, or the book that we read. In both cases, the habit of
interpretation is become as familiar as the act of
perception. And this is the case with regard to vision. We
see the breadth of the street as clearly and readily as we
see the house on the other side of it. We see the house to
be square, however obliquely it be presented to us. Indeed
the difficulty is, to recover the consciousness of our real
and original sensations;—to discover what is the
apparent relation of the lines which appear before
us. As we have already said, (book ii. chap. 6) in the
common process of vision we suppose ourselves to see that
which cannot be seen; and when we would make a picture of an
object, the difficulty is to represent what is visible and
no more.
But perfect as is our habit of interpreting what we
perceive, we could not interpret if we did not perceive. If
the eye did not apprehend visible position, it could not
infer actual position, which is collected from visible
position as a consequence: if we did not see apparent
figure, we could not arrive at any opinion concerning real
form. The perception of place, which is the prerogative of
the eye, is the basis of all its other superiority.
The precision with which the eye can judge of apparent
position is remarkable. If we had before us two stars
distant from each other by one-twentieth of the moon’s
diameter, we could easily decide the apparent direction of
the one from the other, as above or below, to the right or
left. Yet eight millions of stars might be placed in the
visible hemisphere of the sky at such distances from each
other; and thus the eye would recognize the relative
position in a portion of its range not greater than one
eight-millionth of the whole. Such is the accuracy of the
sense of vision in this 305 respect; and, indeed, we might
with truth have stated it much higher. Our judgment of the
position of distant objects in a landscape depends upon
features far more minute than the magnitude we have here
described.
As our object is to point out principally the differences of
the senses, we do not dwell upon the delicacy with which we
distinguish tints and shades, but proceed to another sense.
Sect. II.—Prerogatives of Hearing.
The sense of hearing has two remarkable prerogatives; it can
perceive a definite and peculiar relation between certain
tones, and it can clearly perceive two tones together; in
both these circumstances it is distinguished from vision,
and from the other senses.
4. Musical intervals.—We perceive that two tones
have, or have not, certain definite relations to each other,
which we call Concords: one sound is a Fifth,
an Octave, &c., above the other. And when this is the
case, our perception of the relation is extremely precise.
It is easy to perceive when a fifth is out of tune by
one-twentieth of a tone; that is, by one-seventieth of
itself. To this there is nothing analogous in vision.
Colours have certain vague relations to one another; they
look well together, by contrast or by resemblance; but this
is an indefinite, and in most cases a casual and variable
feeling. The relation of complementary colours to
one another, as of red to green, is somewhat more definite;
but still, has nothing of the exactness and peculiarity
which belongs to a musical concord. In the case of the two
sounds, there is an exact point at which the relation
obtains; when by altering one note we pass this point, the
concord does not gradually fade away, but instantly becomes
a discord; and if we go further still, we obtain another
concord of quite a different character.
We learn from the theory of sound that concords occur when
the times of vibration of the notes have exact simple
ratios; an octave has these times as 1 to 306 2; a fifth,
as 2 to 3. According to the undulatory theory of light, such
ratios occur in colours, yet the eye is not affected by them
in any peculiar way. The times of the undulations of certain
red and certain violet rays are as 2 to 3, but we do not
perceive any peculiar harmony or connexion between those
colours.
5. Chords.—Again, the ear has this prerogative, that
it can apprehend two notes together, yet distinct. If two
notes, distant by a fifth from each other, are sounded on
two wind instruments, both they and their musical relation
are clearly perceived. There is not a mixture, but a
concord, a musical interval. In colours, the case is
otherwise. If blue and yellow fall on the same spot, they
form green; the colour is simple to the eye; it can no more
be decomposed by the vision than if it were the simple green
of the prismatic spectrum: it is impossible for us, by
sight, to tell whether it is so or not.
These are very remarkable differences of the two senses: two
colours can be compounded into an apparently simple one; two
sounds cannot: colours pass into each other by gradations
and intermediate tints; sounds pass from one concord to
another by no gradations: the most intolerable discord is
that which is near a concord. We shall hereafter see how
these differences affect the scales of sound and of
colour.
6. Rhythm.—We might remark, that as we see objects
in space, we hear sounds in time; and that
we thus introduce an arrangement among sounds which has
several analogies with the arrangement of objects in space.
But the conception of time does not seem to be peculiarly
connected with the sense of hearing; a faculty of
apprehending tone and time, or in musical phraseology
tune and rhythm, are certainly very distinct.
I shall not, therefore, here dwell upon such analogies.
The other Senses have not any peculiar prerogatives, at
least none which bear on the formation of science. I may,
however, notice, in the feeling of heat, this circumstance;
that it presents us with two opposites, heat and cold, which
graduate into each other. This 307 is not quite peculiar,
for vision also exhibits to us white and black, which are
clearly opposites, and which pass into each other by the
shades of gray.
Sect. III.—The Paradoxes of Vision.
7. First Paradox of Vision. Upright Vision.—All our
senses appear to have this in common; That they act by means
of organs, in which a bundle of nerves receives the
impression of the appropriate medium of the sense. In the
construction of these organs there are great differences and
peculiarities, corresponding, in part at least, to the
differences in the information given. Moreover, in some
cases, as we have noted in the case of audible position and
visible distance, that which seems to be a perception is
really a judgment founded on perceptions of which we are not
directly aware. It will be seen, therefore, that with
respect to the peculiar powers of each sense, it may be
asked;—whether they can be explained by the construction of
the peculiar organ;—whether they are acquired judgments and
not direct perceptions;—or whether they are inexplicable in
either of these ways, and cannot, at present at least, be
resolved into anything but conditions of the intellectual
act of perception.
Two of these questions with regard to vision, have been much
discussed by psychological writers: the cause of our seeing
objects upright by inverted images on the retina; and of our
seeing single with two such images.
Physiologists have very completely explained the exquisitely
beautiful mechanism of the eye, considered as analogous to
an optical instrument; and it is indisputable that by means
of certain transparent lenses and humours, an inverted image
of the objects which are looked at is formed upon the
retina, or fine net-work of nerve, with which the
back of the eye is lined. We cannot doubt that the
impression thus produced on these nerves is essential to the
act of vision; and so far as we consider the nerves 308
themselves to feel or perceive by contact, we may say that
they perceive this image, or the affections of light which
it indicates. But we cannot with any propriety say that
we perceive, or that our mind perceives, this
image; for we are not conscious of it, and none but
anatomists are aware of its existence: we perceive by
means of it.
A difficulty has been raised, and dwelt upon in a most
unaccountable manner, arising from the neglect of this
obvious distinction. It has been asked, how is it that we
see an object, a man for instance, upright, when the
immediate object of our sensation, the image of the man on
our retina, is inverted? To this we must answer, that we see
him upright because the image is inverted; that the
inverted image is the necessary means of seeing an upright
object. This is granted, and where then is the difficulty?
Perhaps it may be put thus: How is it that we do not judge
the man to be inverted, since the sensible image is so? To
this we may reply, that we have no notion of
upright or inverted, except that which is founded
on experience, and that all our experience, without
exception, must have taught us that such a sensible image
belongs to a man who is in an upright position. Indeed, the
contrary judgment is not conceivable; a man is upright whose
head is upwards and his feet downwards. But what are the
sensible images of upwards and downwards?
Whatever be our standard of up and down, the sensible
representation of up will be an image moving on the
retina towards the lower side, and the sensible
representation of down will be a motion towards the
upper side. The head of the man’s image is towards the image
of the sky, its feet are towards the image of the ground;
how then should it appear otherwise than upright? Do we
expect that the whole world should appear inverted? Be it
so: but if the whole be inverted, how is the relation of the
parts altered? Do we expect that we should think our own
persons in particular? This cannot be, for we look at them
as we do at other objects. Do we expect that things should
appear to fall 309 upwards? Surely not. For what do we
know of upwards, except that it is the direction in which
bodies do not fall? In short, the whole of this
difficulty, though it has in no small degree embarrassed
metaphysicians, appears to result from a very palpable
confusion of ideas; from an attempt at comparison of what
we see, with that which the retina feels, as if
they were separately presentable. It is a sufficient
explanation to say, that we do not see the image on the
retina, but see by means of it. The perplexity does
not require much more skill to disentangle, than it does to
see that a word written in black ink, may signify
white8.</div></body></text></TEI>