<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="5">

CHAPTER I.
INTRODUCTION.

1. An Inquiry into the Understanding pleasant and useful.


Since it is the UNDERSTANDING that sets man above the rest of sensible beings,
and gives him all the advantage and dominion which he has over them; it is
certainly a subject, even for its nobleness, worth our labour to inquire into.
The understanding, like the eye, whilst it makes us see and perceive all other
things, takes no notice of itself; and it requires and art and pains to set it
at a distance and make it its own object. But whatever be the difficulties that
lie in the way of this inquiry; whatever it be that keeps us so much in the
dark to ourselves; sure I am that all the light we can let in upon our minds,
all the acquaintance we can make with our own understandings, will not only be
very pleasant, but bring us great advantage, in directing our thoughts in the
search of other things.


2. Design.


This, therefore, being my purpose—to inquire into the original,
certainty, and extent of HUMAN KNOWLEDGE, together with the grounds and degrees
of BELIEF, OPINION, and ASSENT;—I shall not at present meddle with the
physical consideration of the mind; or trouble myself to examine wherein its
essence consists; or by what motions of our spirits or alterations of our
bodies we come to have any SENSATION by our organs, or any IDEAS in our
understandings; and whether those ideas do in their formation, any or all of
them, depend on matter or not. These are speculations which, however curious
and entertaining, I shall decline, as lying out of my way in the design I am
now upon. It shall suffice to my present purpose, to consider the discerning
faculties of a man, as they are employed about the objects which they have to
do with. And I shall imagine I have not wholly misemployed myself in the
thoughts I shall have on this occasion, if, in this historical, plain method, I
can give any account of the ways whereby our understandings come to attain
those notions of things we have; and can set down any measures of the certainty
of our knowledge; or the grounds of those persuasions which are to be found
amongst men, so various, different, and wholly contradictory; and yet asserted
somewhere or other with such assurance and confidence, that he that shall take
a view of the opinions of mankind, observe their opposition, and at the same
time consider the fondness and devotion wherewith they are embraced, the
resolution and eagerness wherewith they are maintained, may perhaps have reason
to suspect, that either there is no such thing as truth at all, or that mankind
hath no sufficient means to attain a certain knowledge of it.


3. Method.


It is therefore worth while to search out the bounds between opinion and
knowledge; and examine by what measures, in things whereof we have no certain
knowledge, we ought to regulate our assent and moderate our persuasion. In
order whereunto I shall pursue this following method:— First, I shall
inquire into the original of those ideas, notions, or whatever else you please
to call them, which a man observes, and is conscious to himself he has in his
mind; and the ways whereby the understanding comes to be furnished with them.


Secondly, I shall endeavour to show what knowledge the understanding hath by
those ideas; and the certainty, evidence, and extent of it.


Thirdly, I shall make some inquiry into the nature and grounds of FAITH or
OPINION: whereby I mean that assent which we give to any proposition as true,
of whose truth yet we have no certain knowledge. And here we shall have
occasion to examine the reasons and degrees of ASSENT.


4. Useful to know the Extent of our Comprehension.


If by this inquiry into the nature of the understanding, I can discover the
powers thereof; how far they reach; to what things they are in any degree
proportionate; and where they fail us, I suppose it may be of use to prevail
with the busy mind of man to be more cautious in meddling with things exceeding
its comprehension; to stop when it is at the utmost extent of its tether; and
to sit down in a quiet ignorance of those things which, upon examination, are
found to be beyond the reach of our capacities. We should not then perhaps be
so forward, out of an affectation of an universal knowledge, to raise
questions, and perplex ourselves and others with disputes about things to which
our understandings are not suited; and of which we cannot frame in our minds
any clear or distinct perceptions, or whereof (as it has perhaps too often
happened) we have not any notions at all. If we can find out how far the
understanding can extend its view; how far it has faculties to attain
certainty; and in what cases it can only judge and guess, we may learn to
content ourselves with what is attainable by us in this state.


5. Our Capacity suited to our State and Concerns.


For though the comprehension of our understandings comes exceeding short of the
vast extent of things, yet we shall have cause enough to magnify the bountiful
Author of our being, for that proportion and degree of knowledge he has
bestowed on us, so far above all the rest of the inhabitants of this our
mansion. Men have reason to be well satisfied with what God hath thought fit
for them, since he hath given them (as St. Peter says) [words in Greek],
whatsoever is necessary for the conveniences of life and information of virtue;
and has put within the reach of their discovery, the comfortable provision for
this life, and the way that leads to a better. How short soever their knowledge
may come of an universal or perfect comprehension of whatsoever is, it yet
secures their great concernments, that they have light enough to lead them to
the knowledge of their Maker, and the sight of their own duties. Men may find
matter sufficient to busy their heads, and employ their hands with variety,
delight, and satisfaction, if they will not boldly quarrel with their own
constitution, and throw away the blessings their hands are filled with, because
they are not big enough to grasp everything. We shall not have much reason to
complain of the narrowness of our minds, if we will but employ them about what
may be of use to us; for of that they are very capable. And it will be an
unpardonable, as well as childish peevishness, if we undervalue the advantages
of our knowledge, and neglect to improve it to the ends for which it was given
us, because there are some things that are set out of the reach of it. It will
be no excuse to an idle and untoward servant, who would not attend his business
by candle light, to plead that he had not broad sunshine. The Candle that is
set up in us shines bright enough for all our purposes. The discoveries we can
make with this ought to satisfy us; and we shall then use our understandings
right, when we entertain all objects in that way and proportion that they are
suited to our faculties, and upon those grounds they are capable of being
proposed to us; and not peremptorily or intemperately require demonstration,
and demand certainty, where probability only is to be had, and which is
sufficient to govern all our concernments. If we will disbelieve everything,
because we cannot certainly know all things, we shall do much—what as wisely as
he who would not use his legs, but sit still and perish, because he had no
wings to fly.


6. Knowledge of our Capacity a Cure of Scepticism and Idleness.


When we know our own strength, we shall the better know what to undertake with
hopes of success; and when we have well surveyed the POWERS of our own minds,
and made some estimate what we may expect from them, we shall not be inclined
either to sit still, and not set our thoughts on work at all, in despair of
knowing anything; nor on the other side, question everything, and disclaim all
knowledge, because some things are not to be understood. It is of great use to
the sailor to know the length of his line, though he cannot with it fathom all
the depths of the ocean. It is well he knows that it is long enough to reach
the bottom, at such places as are necessary to direct his voyage, and caution
him against running upon shoals that may ruin him. Our business here is not to
know all things, but those which concern our conduct. If we can find out those
measures, whereby a rational creature, put in that state in which man is in
this world, may and ought to govern his opinions, and actions depending
thereon, we need not to be troubled that some other things escape our
knowledge.


7. Occasion of this Essay.


This was that which gave the first rise to this Essay concerning the
understanding. For I thought that the first step towards satisfying several
inquiries the mind of man was very apt to run into, was, to take a survey of
our own understandings, examine our own powers, and see to what things they
were adapted. Till that was done I suspected we began at the wrong end, and in
vain sought for satisfaction in a quiet and sure possession of truths that most
concerned us, whilst we let loose our thoughts into the vast ocean of Being; as
if all that boundless extent were the natural and undoubted possession of our
understandings, wherein there was nothing exempt from its decisions, or that
escaped its comprehension. Thus men, extending their inquiries beyond their
capacities, and letting their thoughts wander into those depths where they can
find no sure footing, it is no wonder that they raise questions and multiply
disputes, which, never coming to any clear resolution, are proper only to
continue and increase their doubts, and to confirm them at last in perfect
scepticism. Whereas, were the capacities of our understandings well considered,
the extent of our knowledge once discovered, and the horizon found which sets
the bounds between the enlightened and dark parts of things; between what is
and what is not comprehensible by us, men would perhaps with less scruple
acquiesce in the avowed ignorance of the one, and employ their thoughts and
discourse with more advantage and satisfaction in the other.


8. What Idea stands for.


Thus much I thought necessary to say concerning the occasion of this inquiry
into human Understanding. But, before I proceed on to what I have thought on
this subject, I must here in the entrance beg pardon of my reader for the
frequent use of the word IDEA, which he will find in the following treatise. It
being that term which, I think, serves best to stand for whatsoever is the
OBJECT of the understanding when a man thinks, I have used it to express
whatever is meant by PHANTASM, NOTION, SPECIES, or WHATEVER IT IS WHICH THE
MIND CAN BE EMPLOYED ABOUT IN THINKING; and I could not avoid frequently using
it. I presume it will be easily granted me, that there are such IDEAS in men’s
minds: every one is conscious of them in himself; and men’s words and actions
will satisfy him that they are in others.


Our first inquiry then shall be,—how they come into the mind.


</div></body></text></TEI>