<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="23">

CHAPTER XIII.
The Doctrine of Motion.


1. Pure Mechanism.—The doctrine of Motion, of which
we have here to speak, is that in which motion is considered
quite independently of its cause, force; for all
consideration of force belongs to a class of ideas entirely
different from those with which we are here concerned. In
this view it may be termed the pure doctrine of
motion, since it has to do solely with space and time, which
are the subjects of pure mathematics. (See c. i. of this
book.) Although the doctrine of motion in connexion with
force, which is the subject of mechanics, is by far the most
important form in which the consideration of motion enters
into the formation of our sciences, the Pure Doctrine of
Motion, which treats of space, time, and velocity, might be
followed out so as to give rise to a very considerable and
curious body of science. Such a science is the science of
Mechanism, independent of force, and considered as the
solution of a problem which may be thus enunciated: ‘To
communicate any given motion from a first mover to a given
body.’ The science which should have for its object to solve
all the various cases into which this problem would ramify,
might be termed Pure Mechanism, in contradistinction
to Mechanics Proper, or Machinery, in which
Force is taken into consideration. The greater part of the
machines which have been constructed for use in manufactures
have been practical solutions of some of the cases of this
problem. We have also important contributions to such a
science in the works of Mathematicians; for example, the
various investigations and demonstrations which have been
published respecting the form of the Teeth 157 of Wheels,
and Mr. Babbage’s memoir15 on the Language of Machinery.
There are also several works which contain collections of
the mechanical contrivances which have been invented for the
purpose of transmitting and modifying motion, and these
works may be considered as treatises on the science of Pure
Mechanism. But this science has not yet been reduced to the
systematic simplicity which is desirable, nor indeed
generally recognized as a separate science. It has been
confounded, under the common name of Mechanics, with
the other science, Mechanics Proper, or Machinery, which
considers the effect of force transmitted by
Mechanism from one part of a material combination to
another. For example, the Mechanical Powers, as they
are usually termed, (the Lever, the Wheel and Axle, the
Inclined Plane, the Wedge, and the Screw,) have almost
always been treated with reference to the relation between
the Power and the Weight, and not primarily as
a mode of changing the velocity and kind of the motion. The
science of pure motion has not generally been separated from
the science of motion viewed with reference to its causes.</div></body></text></TEI>