<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="136">CHAPTER V.
Inorganic Geological Dynamics.

Sect. 1.—Necessity and Object of a
Science of Geological Dynamics.
WHEN the structure and
arrangement which men observed in the materials of the earth
instigated them to speculate concerning the past changes and
revolutions by which such results had been produced, they at first
supposed themselves sufficiently able to judge what would be the
effects of any of the obvious agents of change, as water or volcanic
fire. It did not at once occur to them to suspect, that their common
and extemporaneous judgment on such points was far from sufficient for
sound knowledge;—they did not foresee that they must create a
special science, whose object should be to estimate the general laws
and effects of assumed causes, before they could pronounce whether
such causes had actually produced the particular facts which their
survey of the earth had disclosed to them.
Yet the analogy of the progress of knowledge on other subjects
points out very clearly the necessity of such a science. When
phenomenal astronomy had arrived at a high point of completeness, by
the labors of ages, and especially by the discovery of Kepler’s laws,
astronomers were vehemently desirous of knowing the causes of these
motions; and sanguine men, such as Kepler, readily conjectured that
the motions were the effects of certain virtues and influences, by
which the heavenly bodies acted upon each other. But it did not at
first occur to him and his fellow-speculators, that they had not
ascertained what motions the influences of one body upon another could
produce: and that, therefore, they were not prepared to judge whether
such causes as they spoke of, did really regulate the motions of the
planets. Yet such was found to be the necessary course of sound
inference. Men needed a science of motion, in order to arrive at a
science of the 543
heavenly motions: they could not advance in the study of the Mechanics
of the heavens, till they had learned the Mechanics of terrestrial
bodies. And thus they were, in such speculations, at a stand for
nearly a century, from the time of Kepler to the time of Newton, while
the science of Mechanics was formed by Galileo and his successors.
Till that task was executed, all the attempts to assign the causes of
cosmical phenomena were fanciful guesses and vague assertions; after
that was done, they became demonstrations. The science of
Dynamics enabled philosophers to pass securely and completely
from Phenomenal Astronomy to Physical Astronomy.
In like manner, in order that we may advance from Phenomenal
Geology to Physical Geology, we need a science of Geological
Dynamics;—that is, a science which shall investigate and
determine the laws and consequences of the known causes of changes
such as those which Geology considers:—and which shall do this,
not in an occasional, imperfect, and unconnected manner, but by
systematic, complete, and conclusive methods;—shall, in short,
be a Science, and not a promiscuous assemblage of desultory
essays.
The necessity of such a study, as a distinct branch of geology, is
perhaps hardly yet formally recognized, although the researches which
belong to it have, of late years, assumed a much more methodical and
scientific character than they before possessed. Mr. Lyell’s work
(Principles of Geology), in particular, has eminently
contributed to place Geological Dynamics in its proper prominent
position. Of the four books of his Treatise, the second and third are
upon this division of the subject; the second book treating of aqueous
and igneous causes of change, and the third, of changes in the organic
world.
There is no difficulty in separating this auxiliary geological
science from theoretical Geology itself, in which we apply our
principles to the explanation of the actual facts of the earth’s
surface. The former, if perfected, would be a demonstrative science
dealing with general cases; the latter is an ætiological view having
reference to special facts; the one attempts to determine what always
must be under given conditions; the other is satisfied with knowing
what is and has been, and why it has been; the first study has a
strong resemblance to Mechanics, the other to philosophical
Archæology.
Since this portion of science is still so new, it is scarcely
possible to give any historical account of its progress, or any
complete survey of its shape and component parts. I can only attempt a
few notices, 544
which may enable us in some measure to judge to what point this
division of our subject is tending.
We may remark, in this as in former cases, that since we have here
to consider the formation and progress of a science, we must
treat as unimportant preludes to its history, the detached and casual
observations of the effects of causes of change which we find in older
writers. It is only when we come to systematic collections of
information, such as may afford the means of drawing general
conclusions; or to rigorous deductions from known laws of
nature;—that we can recognise the separate existence of
geological dynamics, as a path of scientific research.
The following may perhaps suffice, for the present, as a sketch of
the subjects of which this science treats:—the aqueous causes of
change, or those in which water adds to, takes from, or transfers, the
materials of the land:—the igneous causes; volcanoes, and,
closely connected with them, earthquakes, and the forces by which they
are produced;—the calculations which determine, on physical
principles, the effects of assumed mechanical causes acting upon large
portions of the crust of the earth;—the effect of the forces,
whatever they be, which produce the crystalline texture of rocks,
their fissile structure, and the separation of materials, of which we
see the results in metalliferous veins. Again, the estimation of the
results of changes of temperature in the earth, whether operating by
pressure, expansion, or in any other way;—the effects of assumed
changes in the superficial condition, extent, and elevation, of
terrestrial continents upon the climates of the earth;—the
effect of assumed cosmical changes upon the temperature of this
planet;—and researches of the same nature as these.
These researches are concerned with the causes of change in the
inorganic world; but the subject requires no less that we should
investigate the causes which may modify the forms and conditions of
organic things; and in the large sense in which we have to use the
phrase, we may include researches on such subjects also as parts of
Geological Dynamics; although, in truth, this department of physiology
has been cultivated, as it well deserves to be, independently of its
bearing upon geological theories. The great problem which offers
itself here, in reference to Geology, is, to examine the value of any
hypotheses by which it may be attempted to explain the succession of
different races of animals and plants in different strata; and though
it may be difficult, in this inquiry, to arrive at any positive
result, we 545 may
at least be able to show the improbability of some conjectures which
have been propounded.
I shall now give a very brief account of some of the attempts made
in these various departments of this province of our knowledge; and in
the present chapter, of Inorganic Changes.
Sect. 2.—Aqueous Causes of Change.
The controversies to which
the various theories of geologists gave rise, proceeding in various
ways upon the effects of the existing causes of change, led men to
observe, with some attention and perseverance, the actual operation of
such causes. In this way, the known effect of the Rhine, in filling up
the Lake of Geneva at its upper extremity, was referred to by De Luc,
Kirwan, and others, in their dispute with the Huttonians; and attempts
were even made to calculate how distant the period was, when this
alluvial deposit first began. Other modern observers have attended to
similar facts in the natural history of rivers and seas. But the
subject may be considered as having first assumed its proper form,
when taken up by Mr. Von Hoff; of whose History of the Natural
Changes of the Earth’s surface which are proved by Tradition, the
first part, treating of aqueous changes, appeared in 1822. This work
was occasioned by a Prize Question of the Royal Society of Göttingen,
promulgated in 1818; in which these changes were proposed as the
subject of inquiry, with a special reference to geology. Although Von
Hoff does not attempt to establish any general inductions upon the
facts which his book contains, the collection of such a body of facts
gave almost a new aspect to the subject, by showing that changes in
the relative extent of land and water were going on at every time, and
almost at every place; and that mutability and fluctuation in the form
of the solid parts of the earth, which had been supposed by most
persons to be a rare exception to the common course of events, was, in
fact, the universal rule. But it was Mr. Lyell’s Principles of
Geology, being an attempt to explain the former Changes of the Earth’s
Surface by the Causes now in action (of which the first volume was
published in 1830), which disclosed the full effect of such researches
on geology; and which attempted to present such assemblages of special
facts, as examples of general laws. Thus this work may, as we have
said, be looked upon as the beginning of Geological Dynamics, at least
among us. Such generalizations and applications as it contains give
the most lively 546
interest to a thousand observations respecting rivers and floods,
mountains and morasses, which otherwise appear without aim or meaning;
and thus this department of science cannot fail to be constantly
augmented by contributions from every side. At the same time it is
clear, that these contributions, voluminous as they must become, must,
from time to time, be resolved into laws of greater and greater
generality; and that thus alone the progress of this, as of all other
sciences, can be furthered.
I need not attempt any detailed enumeration of the modes of aqueous
action which are here to be considered. Some are destructive, as when
the rivers erode the channels in which they flow; or when the waves,
by their perpetual assault, shatter the shores, and carry the ruins of
them into the abyss of the ocean. Some operations of the water, on the
other hand, add to the land; as when deltas are formed at the
mouths of rivers or when calcareous springs form deposits of
travertin. Even when bound in icy fetters, water is by no mean
deprived of its active power; the glacier carries into the
valley masses of its native mountain, and often, becoming ice-bergs,
float with a lading of such materials far into the seas of the
temperate zone. It is indisputable that vast beds of worn down
fragments of the existing land are now forming into strata at the
bottom of the ocean; and that many other effects are constantly
produced by existing aqueous causes, which resemble some, at least, of
the facts which geology has to explain.
[2nd Ed.] [The effects of glaciers above mentioned are obvious; but
the mechanism of these bodies,—the mechanical cause of their
motions,—was an unsolved problem till within a very few years.
That they slide as rigid masses;—that they advance by the
expansion of their mass;—that they advance as a collection of
rigid fragments; were doctrines which were held by eminent physicists;
though a very slight attention to the subject shows these opinions to
be untenable. In Professor James Forbes’s theory on the subject
(published in his Travels through the Alps, 1843,) we find a
solution of the problem, so simple, and yet so exact, as to produce
the most entire conviction. In this theory, the ice of a glacier is,
on a great scale, supposed to be a plastic or viscous mass, though
small portions of it are sensibly rigid. It advances down the slope of
the valley in which it lies as a plastic mass would do, accommodating
itself to the varying shape and size of its bed, and showing by its
crevasses its mixed character between fluid and rigid. It shows this
character still more curiously by a ribboned 547 structure on a
small scale, which is common in the solid ice of the glacier. The
planes of these ribbons are, for the most part, at right angles
to the crevasses, near the sides of the glacier, while, near its
central line, they dip towards the upper part of the glacier.
This structure appears to arise from the difference of velocities of
contiguous moving filaments of the icy mass, as the crevasses
themselves arise from the tension of larger portions. Mr. Forbes has,
in successive publications, removed the objections which have been
urged against this theory. In the last of them, a Memoir in the
Phil. Trans., 1846, (Illustrations of the Viscous Theory of
Glacier Motion,) he very naturally expresses astonishment at the
opposition which has been made to the theory on the ground of the
rigidity of small pieces of ice. He has himself shown that the ice of
glaciers has a plastic flexibility, by marking forty-five points in a
transverse straight line upon the Mer de Glace, and observing them for
several days. The straight line in that time not only became oblique
to the side, but also became visibly curved.
Both Mr. Forbes and other philosophers have made it in the highest
degree probable that glaciers have existed in many places in which
they now exist no longer, and have exercised great powers in
transporting large blocks of rock, furrowing and polishing the rocks
along which they slide, and leaving lines and masses of detritus or
moraine which they had carried along with them or pushed before
them. It cannot be doubted that extinct glaciers have produced some of
the effects which the geologist has to endeavor to explain. But this
part of the machinery of nature has been worked by some theorists into
an exaggerated form, in which it cannot, as I conceive, have any place
in an account of Geological Dynamics which aims at being
permanent.
The great problem of the diffusion of drift and erratic blocks from
their parent rocks to great distances, has driven geologists to the
consideration of other hypothetical machinery by which the effects may
be accounted for: especially the great northern drift and
boulders,—the rocks from the Scandinavian chain which
cover the north of Europe on a vast area, having a length of 2000 and
breadth of from 400 to 800 miles. The diffusion of these blocks has
been accounted for by supposing them to be imbedded in icebergs,
detached from the shore, and floated into oceanic spaces, where they
have grounded and been deposited by the melting of the ice. And this
mode of action may to some extent be safely admitted into geological
speculation. For it is a matter of fact, that our navigators in arctic
and antarctic regions have 548 repeatedly seen icebergs and icefloes
sailing along laden with such materials.
The above explanation of the phenomena of drift supposes the land
on which the travelled materials are found to have been the bottom of
a sea where they were deposited. But it does not, even granting the
conditions, account for some of the facts observed;—that the
drift and the boulders are deposited in “trainées” or streaks, which,
in direction, diverge from the parent rock;—and that the
boulders are of smaller and smaller size, as they are found more
remote from that centre. These phenomena rather suggest the notion of
currents of water as the cause of the distribution of the materials
into their present situations. And though the supposition that the
whole area occupied by drift and boulders was a sea-bottom when they
were scattered over it much reduces the amount of violence which it is
necessary to assume in order to distribute the loose masses, yet still
the work appears to be beyond the possible effect of ordinary marine
currents, or any movements which would be occasioned by a slow and
gradual rising of the centre of distribution.
It has been suggested that a sudden rise of the centre of
distribution would cause a motion in the surrounding ocean sufficient
to produce such an effect: and in confirmation of this reference has
been made to Mr. Scott Russell’s investigations with respect to waves,
already referred to. (Book viii.) The wave in this case would be the wave
of translation, in which the motion of the water is as great at the
bottom as at the top; and it has hence been asserted that by
paroxysmal elevations of 100 or 200 feet, a current of 25 or 30 miles
an hour might be accounted for. But I think it has not been
sufficiently noted that at each point this “current” is transient: it
lasts only while the wave is passing over the point, and therefore it
would only either carry a single mass the whole way with its own
velocity, or move through a short distance a series of masses over
which it successively passed. It does not appear, therefore, that we
have here a complete account of the transport of a collection of
materials, in which each part is transferred through great
distances:—except, indeed, we were to suppose a numerous
succession of paroxysmal elevations. Such a battery might, by
successive shocks, transmitting their force through the water, diffuse
the fragments of the central mass over any area, however wide.
The fact that the erratic blocks are found to rest on the lower
drift, is well explained by supposing the latter to have been spread
on the 549 sea
bottom while rock-bearing ice-masses floated on the surface till they
deposited their lading.
Sir R. Murchison has pointed out another operation of ice in
producing mounds of rocky masses; namely, the effects of rivers and
lakes, in climates where, as in Russia, the waters carry rocky
fragments entangled in the winter ice, and leave them in heaps at the
highest level which the waters attain.
The extent to which the effects of glaciers, now vanished, are
apparent in many places, especially in Switzerland and in England, and
other phenomena of the like tendency, have led some of the most
eminent geologists to the conviction that, interior to the period of
our present temperature, there was a Glacial Period, at which
the temperature of Europe was lower than it now is.]
Although the study of the common operations of water may give the
geologist such an acquaintance with the laws of his subject as may
much aid his judgment respecting the extent to which such effects may
proceed, a long course of observation and thought must be requisite
before such operations can be analysed into their fundamental
principles, and become the subjects of calculation, or of rigorous
reasoning in any manner which is as precise and certain as
calculation. Various portions of Hydraulics have an important bearing
upon these subjects, including some researches which have been pursued
with no small labor by engineers and mathematicians; as the effects of
currents and waves, the laws of tides and of rivers, and many similar
problems. In truth, however, such subjects have not hitherto been
treated by mathematicians with much success; and probably several
generations must elapse before this portion of geological dynamics can
become an exact science.
Sect. 3.—Igneous Causes of Change.—Motions
of the Earth’s Surface.
The effects of volcanoes have
long been noted as important and striking features in the physical
history of our globe; and the probability of their connexion with many
geological phenomena, had not escaped notice at an early period. But
it was not till more recent times, that the full import of these
phenomena was apprehended. The person who first looked at such
operations with that commanding general view which showed their
extensive connexion with physical geology, was Alexander von Humboldt,
who explored the volcanic phenomena 550 of the New World, from 1799 to 1804. He
remarked64 the linear distribution of volcanic
domes, considering them as vents placed along the edge of vast
fissures communicating with reservoirs of igneous matter, and
extending across whole continents. He observed, also, the frequent
sympathy of volcanic and terremotive action in remote districts of the
earth’s surface, thus showing how deeply seated must be the cause of
these convulsions. These views strongly excited and influenced the
speculations of geologists; and since then, phenomena of this kind
have been collected into a general view as parts of a
natural-historical science. Von Hoff, in the second volume of the work
already mentioned, was one of the first who
did this; “At least,” he himself says,65 (1824,) “it was
not known to him that any one before him had endeavored to combine so
large a mass of facts with the general ideas of the natural
philosopher, so as to form a whole.” Other attempts were, however,
soon made. In 1825, M. von Ungern-Sternberg published his book On
the Nature and Origin of Volcanoes,66 in which, he
says, his object is, to give an empirical representation of these
phenomena. In the same year, Mr. Poulett Scrope published a work in
which he described the known facts of volcanic action; not, however,
confining himself to description; his purpose being, as his title
states, to consider “the probable causes of their phenomena, the laws
which determine their march, the disposition of their products, and
their connexion with the present state and past history of the globe;
leading to the establishment of a new theory of the earth.” And in
1826, Dr. Daubeny, of Oxford, produced A Description of Active
and Extinct Volcanoes, including in the latter phrase the
volcanic rocks of central France, of the Rhine, of northern and
central Italy, and many other countries. Indeed, the near connexion
between the volcanic effects now going on, and those by which the
basaltic rocks of Auvergne and many other places had been produced,
was, by this time, no longer doubted by any; and therefore the line
which here separates the study of existing causes from that of past
effects may seem to melt away. But yet it is manifest that the
assumption of an identity of scale and mechanism between volcanoes now
active, and the igneous catastrophes of which the products have 551 survived great
revolutions on the earth’s surface, is hypothetical; and all which
depends on this assumption belongs to theoretical geology.
64 Humboldt, Relation
Historique; and his other works.
65 Vol. ii. Prop. 5.
66 Werden und Seyn des
Vulkanischen Gebirges. Carlsruhe, 1825.
Confining ourselves, then, to volcanic effects, which have been
produced, certainly or probably, since the earth’s surface assumed its
present form, we have still an ample exhibition of powerful causes of
change, in the streams of lava and other materials emitted in
eruptions; and still more in the earthquakes which, as men easily
satisfied themselves, are produced by the same causes as the eruptions
of volcanic fire.
Mr. Lyell’s work was important in this as in other portions of this
subject. He extended the conceptions previously entertained of the
effects which such causes may produce, not only by showing how great
these operations are historically known to have been, and how
constantly they are going on, if we take into our survey the whole
surface of the earth; but still more, by urging the consequences which
would follow in a long course of time from the constant repetition of
operations in themselves of no extraordinary amount. A lava-stream
many miles long and wide, and several yards deep, a subsidence or
elevation of a portion of the earth’s surface of a few feet, are by no
means extraordinary facts. Let these operations, said Mr. Lyell, be
repeated thousands of times; and we have results of the same order
with the changes which geology discloses.
The most mitigated earthquakes have, however, a character of
violence. But it has been thought by many philosophers that there is
evidence of a change of level of the land in cases where none of these
violent operations are going on. The most celebrated of these cases is
Sweden; the whole of the land from Gottenburg to the north of the Gulf
of Bothnia has been supposed in the act of rising, slowly and
insensibly, from the surrounding waters. The opinion of such a change
of level has long been the belief of the inhabitants; and was
maintained by Celsius in the beginning of the eighteenth century. It
has since been conceived to be confirmed by various observations of
marks cut on the face of the rock; beds of shells, such as now live in
the neighboring seas, raised to a considerable height; and other
indications. Some of these proofs appear doubtful; but Mr. Lyell,
after examining the facts upon the spot in 1834, says, “In regard to
the proposition that the land, in certain parts of Sweden, is
gradually rising, I have no hesitation in assenting to it, after my
visit to the districts above alluded to.”67 If this
conclusion be generally accepted by 552 geologists, we have here a daily example
of the operation of some powerful agent which belongs to geological
dynamics; and which, for the purposes of the geological theorist, does
the work of the earthquake upon a very large scale, without assuming
its terrors.
67 Phil. Trans. 1835, p.
32.
[2nd Ed.] [Examples of changes of level of large districts
occurring at periods when the country has been agitated by earthquakes
are well ascertained, as the rising of the coast of Chili in 1822, and
the subsidence of the district of Cutch, in the delta of the Indus, in
1819. (Lyell, B. ii. c. xv.) But the cases of
more slow and tranquil movement seem also to be established. The
gradual secular rise of the shore of the Baltic, mentioned in the
text, has been confirmed by subsequent investigation. It appears that
the rate of elevation increases from Stockholm, where it is only a few
inches in a century, to the North Cape, where it is several feet. It
appears also that several other regions are in a like state of secular
change. The coast of Greenland is sinking. (Lyell, B. ii. c. xviii.) And the existence of “raised beaches”
along various coasts is now generally accepted among geologists. Such
beaches, anciently forming the margin of the sea, but now far above
it, exist in many places; for instance, along a great part of the
Scotch coast; and among the raised beaches of that country we ought
probably, with Mr. Darwin, to include the “parallel roads” of Glenroy,
the subject, in former days, of so much controversy among geologists
and antiquaries.
Connected with the secular rise and fall of large portions of the
earth’s surface, another agency which plays an important part in
Geological dynamics has been the subject of some bold yet singularly
persuasive speculations by Mr. Darwin. I speak of the formation of
Coral, and Coral Reefs. He says that the coral-building animal works
only at small and definite distances below the surface. How then are
we to account for the vast number of coral islands, rings, and reefs,
which are scattered over the Pacific and Indian Oceans! Can we suppose
that there are so many mountains, craters, and ridges, all exactly
within a few feet of the same height through this vast portion of the
globe’s surface? This is incredible. How then are we to explain the
facts? Mr. Darwin replies, that if we suppose the land to subside
slowly beneath the sea, and at the same time suppose the coralline
zoophytes to go on building, so that their structure constantly rises
nearly to the surface of the water, we shall have the facts explained.
A submerged island will produce a ring; a long coast, a barrier reef;
and so on. Mr. Darwin also notes other phenomena, as 553 elevated beds of
coral, which, occurring in other places, indicate a recent rising of
the land; and on such grounds as these he divides the surface of those
parts of the ocean into regions of elevation and of depression.
The labors of coralline zoophytes, as thus observed, form masses of
coral, such as are found fossilized in the strata of the earth. But
our knowledge of the laws of life which have probably affected the
distribution of marine remains in strata, has received other very
striking accessions by the labors of Prof. Edward Forbes in observing
the marine animals of the Ægean Sea. He found that, even in their
living state, the mollusks and zoophytes are already distributed into
strata. Dividing the depth into eight regions, from 2 to 230 fathoms,
he found that each region had its peculiar inhabitants, which
disappeared speedily either in ascending or in descending. The zero of
animal life appeared to occur at about 300 fathoms. This curious
result bears in various ways upon geology. Mr. Forbes himself has
given an example of the mode in which it may be applied, by
determining the depth at which the submarine eruption took place which
produced the volcanic isle of Neokaimeni in 1707. By an examination of
the fossils embedded in the pumice, he showed that it came from the
fourth region.68
68 British Assoc. Reports,
1843, p. 177.
To the modes in which organized beings operate in producing the
materials of the earth, we must add those pointed out by the
extraordinary microscopic discoveries of Professor Ehrenberg. It
appears that whole beds of earthy matter consist of the cases of
certain infusoria, the remains of these creatures being accumulated in
numbers which it confounds our thoughts to contemplate.]
Speculations concerning the causes of volcanoes and
earthquakes, and of the rising and sinking of land, are a highly
important portion of this science, at least as far as the calculation
of the possible results of definite causes is concerned. But the
various hypotheses which have been propounded on this subject can
hardly be considered as sufficiently matured for such calculation. A
mass of matter in a state of igneous fusion, extending to the centre
of the earth, even if we make such an hypothesis, requires some
additional cause to produce eruption. The supposition that this fire
may be produced by intense chemical action between combining elements,
requires further, not only some agency to bring together such
elements, but some reason why 554 they should be originally separate. And
if any other causes have been suggested, as electricity or magnetism,
this has been done so vaguely as to elude all possibility of rigorous
deduction from the hypothesis. The doctrine of a Central Heat,
however, has occupied so considerable a place in theoretical geology,
that it ought undoubtedly to form an article in geological
dynamics.
Sect. 4.—The Doctrine of Central Heat.
The early geological
theorists who, like Leibnitz and Buffon, assumed that the earth was
originally a mass in a state of igneous fusion, naturally went on to
deduce from this hypothesis, that the crust consolidated and cooled
before the interior, and that there might still remain a central heat,
capable of producing many important effects. But it is in more recent
times that we have measures of such effects, and calculations which we
can compare with measures. It was found, as we have said, that in
descending below the surface of the earth, the temperature of its
materials increased. Now it followed from Fourier’s mathematical
investigations of the distribution of heat in the earth, that if there
be no primitive heat (chaleur d’origine), the temperature, when
we descend below the crust, will be constant in each vertical line.
Hence an observed increase of temperature in descending, appeared to
point out a central heat resulting from some cause now no longer in
action.
The doctrine of a central heat has usually been combined with the
supposition of a central igneous fluidity; for the heat in the
neighborhood of the centre must be very intense, according to any law
of its increase in descending which is consistent with known
principles. But to this central fluidity it has been objected that
such a fluid must be in constant circulation by the cooling of its
exterior. Mr. Daniell found this to be the case in all fused metals.
It has also been objected that there must be, in such a central fluid,
tides produced by the moon and sun; but this inference would
require several additional suppositions and calculations to give it a
precise form.
Again, the supposition of a central heat of the earth, considered
as the effect of a more ancient state of its mass, appeared to
indicate that its cooling must still be going on. But if this were so,
the earth might contract, as most bodies do when they cool; and this
contraction might lead to mechanical results, as the shortening of the
day. Laplace satisfied himself, by reference to ancient astronomical
records, that no such 555 alteration in the length of the day had
taken place, even to the amount of one two-hundredth of a second; and
thus, there was here no confirmation of the hypothesis of a primitive
heat of the earth.
Though we find no evidence of the secular contraction of the earth
in the observations with which astronomy deals, there are some
geological facts which at first appear to point to the reality of a
refrigeration within geological periods; as the existence of the
remains of plants and shells of tropical climates, in the strata of
countries which are now near to or within the frigid zones. These
facts, however, have given rise to theories of the changes of climate,
which we must consider separately.
But we may notice, as connected with the doctrine of central heat,
the manner in which this hypothesis has been applied to explain
volcanic and geological phenomena. It does not enter into my plan, to
consider explanations in which this central heat is supposed to give
rise to an expansive force,69 without any
distinct reference to known physical laws. But we may notice; as more
likely to become useful materials of the science now before us, such
speculations as those of Mr. Babbage; in which he combines the
doctrine of central heat with other physical laws;70 as, that solid rocks expand by
being heated, but that clay contracts; that different rocks and strata
conduct heat differently; that the earth radiates heat
differently, or at different parts of its surface, according as it is
covered with forests, with mountains, with deserts, or with water.
These principles, applied to large masses, such as those which
constitute the crust of the earth, might give rise to changes as great
as any which geology discloses. For example: when the bed of a sea is
covered by a thick deposit of new matter worn from the shores, the
strata below the bed, being protected by a bad conductor of heat, will
be heated, and, being heated, maybe expanded; or, as Sir J. Herschel
has observed, may produce explosion by the conversion of their
moisture into steam. Such speculations, when founded on real data and
sound calculations, may hereafter be of material use in geology.
69 Scrope On Volcanoes, p.
192.
70 On the Temple of Serapis,
1834. See also Journal of the Royal Inst. vol.  ii., quoted in
Conyb. and Ph. p. xv. Lyell, B. ii. c. xix. p. 383, (4th ed.) on
Expansion of Stone.
The doctrine of central heat and fluidity has been rejected by some
eminent philosophers. Mr. Lyell’s reasons for this rejection belong
556 rather to
Theoretical Geology; but I may here notice M. Poisson’s opinion. He does not
assent to the conclusion of Fourier, that once the temperature
increases in descending, there must be some primitive central heat. On
the contrary, he considers that such an increase may arise from
this;—that the earth, at some former period, passed (by the
motion of the solar system in the universe,) through a portion of space which
was warmer than the space in which it now revolves (by reason, it may
be, of the heat of other stars to which it was then nearer). He
supposes that, since such a period, the surface has cooled down by the
influence of the surrounding circumstances; while the interior, for a
certain unknown depth, retains the trace of the former elevation of
temperature. But this assumption is not likely to expel the belief is
the terrestrial origin of the subterraneous heat. For the supposition
of such an inequality in the temperature of the different regions in
which the solar system is placed at different times, is altogether
arbitrary; and, if pushed to the amount to which it must be carried,
in order to account for the phenomenon, is highly improbable.71 The doctrine of central heat, on the
other hand, (which need not be conceived as implying the
universal fluidity of the mass,) is not only naturally
suggested by the subterraneous increase of temperatures, but explains
the spheroidal figure of the earth; and falls in with almost any
theory which can be devised, of volcanoes, earthquakes, and great
geological changes.
71 For this hypothesis would make it
necessary to suppose that the earth has, at some former period,
derived from some other star or stars more heat than she now derives
from the sun. But this would imply, as highly probable, that at some
period some other star or stars must have produced also a
mechanical effect upon the solar system, greater than the
effect of the sun. Now such a past operation of forces, fitted to
obliterate all order and symmetry, is quite inconsistent with the
simple, regular, and symmetrical relation which the whole solar
system, as far as Uranus, bears to the present central body.
Sect. 5.—Problems respecting Elevations and
Crystalline Forces.
Other problems respecting the
forces by which great masses of the earth’s crust have been displaced,
have also been solved by various mathematicians. It has been
maintained by Von Buch that there occur, in various places, craters
of elevation; that is, mountain-masses resembling the craters of
volcanoes, but really produced by an expansive force from below,
bursting an aperture through horizontal strata, 557 and elevating them in
a conical form. Against this doctrine, as exemplified in the most
noted instances, strong arguments have been adduced by other
geologists. Yet the protrusion of fused rock by subterraneous forces
upon a large scale is not denied: and how far the examples of such
operations may, in any cases, be termed craters of elevation, must be
considered as a question not yet decided. On the supposition of the
truth of Von Buch’s doctrine, M. de Beaumont has calculated the
relations of position, the fissures, &c., which would arise. And
Mr. Hopkins,72 of Cambridge, has investigated in a
much more general manner, upon mechanical principles, the laws of the
elevations, fissures, faults, veins, and other phenomena which would
result from an elevatory force, acting simultaneously at every point
beneath extensive portions of the crust of the earth. An application
of mathematical reasoning to the illustration of the phenomena of
veins had before been made in Germany by Schmidt and Zimmerman.73 The conclusion which Mr. Hopkins has
obtained, respecting the two sets of fissures, at right angles to each
other, which would in general be produced by such forces as he
supposes, may suggest interesting points of examination respecting the
geological phenomena of fissured districts.
72 Trans. Camb. Phil. Soc.
vol. vi. 1836.
73 Phil. Mag. July, 1836, p.
2.
[2nd Ed.] [The theory of craters of elevation probably errs rather
by making the elevation of a point into a particular class of volcanic
agency, than by giving volcanic agency too great a power of
elevation.
A mature consideration of the subject will make us hesitate to
ascribe much value to the labors of those writers who have applied
mathematical reasoning to geological questions. Such reasoning, when
it is carried to the extent which requires symbolical processes, has
always been, I conceive, a source, not of knowledge, but of error, and
confusion; for in such applications the real questions are slurred
over in the hypothetical assumptions of the mathematician, while the
calculation misleads its followers by a false aspect of demonstration.
All symbolical reasonings concerning the fissures of a semi-rigid mass
produced by elevatory or other forces, appear to me to have turned out
valueless. At the same time it cannot be too strongly borne in mind,
that mathematical and mechanical habits of thought are requisite to
all clear thinking on such subjects.]
Other forces, still more secure in their nature and laws, have
played a very important part in the formation of the earth’s crust. I
speak of the forces by which the crystalline, slaty, and jointed
structure of 558
mineral masses has been produced. These forces are probably identical,
on the one hand, with the cohesive forces from which rocks derive
their solidity and their physical properties; while, on the other
hand, they are closely connected with the forces of chemical
attraction. No attempts, of any lucid and hopeful kind, have yet been
made to bring such forces under definite mechanical conceptions: and
perhaps mineralogy, to which science, as the point of junction of
chemistry and crystallography, such attempts would belong, is hardly
yet ripe for such speculations. But when we look at the universal
prevalence of crystalline forms and cleavages, at the extent of the
phenomena of slaty cleavage, and at the segregation of
special minerals into veins and nodules, which has taken place in some
unknown manner, we cannot doubt that the forces of which we now speak
have acted very widely and energetically. Any elucidation of their
nature would be an important step in Geological Dynamics.
[2nd Ed.] [A point of Geological Dynamics of great importance is,
the change which rocks undergo in structure after they are deposited,
either by the action of subterraneous heat, or by the influence of
crystalline or other corpuscular forces. By such agencies, sedimentary
rocks may be converted into crystalline, the traces of organic fossils
may be obliterated, a slaty cleavage may be produced, and other like
effects. The possibility of such changes was urged by Dr. Hutton in
his Theory; and Sir James Hall’s very instructive and striking
experiments were made for the purpose of illustrating this theory. In
these experiments, powdered chalk was, by the application of heat
under pressure, converted into crystalline calcspar. Afterwards Dr.
McCulloch’s labors had an important influence in satisfying geologists
of the reality of corresponding changes in nature. Dr. McCulloch, by
his very lively and copious descriptions of volcanic regions, by his
representations of them, by his classification of igneous rocks, and
his comprehensive views of the phenomena which they exhibit, probably
was the means of converting many geologists from the Wernerian
opinions.
Rocks which have undergone changes since they were deposited are
termed by Mr. Lyell metamorphic. The great extent of
metamorphic rock changed by heat is now uncontested. The internal
changes which are produced by the crystalline forces of mountain
masses have been the subjects of important and comprehensive
speculations by Professor Sedgwick.] 559
Sect. 6.—Theories of Changes of Climate.
As we have already stated,
Geology offers to us strong evidence that the climate of the ancient
periods of the earth’s history was hotter than that which now exists
in the same countries. This, and other circumstances, have led
geologists to the investigation of the effects of any hypothetical
causes of such changes of condition in respect of heat.
The love of the contemplation of geometrical symmetry, as well as
other reasons, suggested the hypothesis that the earth’s axis had
originally no obliquity, but was perpendicular to the equator. Such a
construction of the world had been thought of before the time of
Milton,74 as what might be supposed to have
existed when man was expelled from Paradise; and Burnet, in his
Sacred Theory of the Earth (1690), adopted this notion of the
paradisiacal condition of the globe:

     The spring
Perpetual smiled on earth with verdant
flowers,
Equal in days and nights.

74


Some said he bade his angels turn askance
The poles of earth twice ten degrees and
more
From the sun’s axle, &c.—Paradise
Lost, x. 214.


In modern times, too, some persons have been disposed to adopt this
hypothesis, because they have conceived that the present polar
distribution of light is inconsistent with the production of the
fossil plants which are found in those regions,75 even if we
could, in some other way, account for the change of temperature. But
this alteration in the axes of a revolution could not take place
without a subversion of the equilibrium of the surface, such as does
not appear to have occurred; and the change has of late been generally
declared impossible by physical astronomers.
75 Lyell, i. 155. Lindley, Fossil
Flora.
The effects of other astronomical changes have been calculated by
Sir John Herschel. He has examined, for instance, the thermotical
consequences of the diminution of the eccentricity of the earth’s
orbit, which has been going on for ages beyond the records of history.
He finds76 that, on this account, the annual
effect of solar radiation would increase as we go back to remoter
periods of the past; but (probably at least) not in a degree
sufficient to account for the apparent past 560 changes of climate. He finds, however,
that though the effect of this change on the mean temperature of the
year may be small, the effect on the extreme temperature of the
seasons will be much more considerable; “so as to produce alternately,
in the same latitude of either hemisphere, a perpetual spring, or the
extreme vicissitudes of a burning summer and a rigorous winter.”77
76 Geol. Trans. vol. iii. p.
295.
77 Geol. Trans. vol. iii. p.
298.
Mr. Lyell has traced the consequences of another hypothesis on this
subject, which appears at first sight to promise no very striking
results, but which yet is found, upon examination, to involve adequate
causes of very great changes: I refer to the supposed various
distribution of land and water at different periods of the earth’s
history. If the land were all gathered into the neighborhood of the
poles, it would become the seat of constant ice and snow, and would
thus very greatly reduce the temperature of the whole surface of the
globe. If, on the other hand, the polar regions were principally
water, while the tropics were occupied with a belt of land, there
would be no part of the earth’s surface on which the frost could
fasten a firm hold, while the torrid zone would act like a furnace to
heat the whole. And, supposing a cycle of terrestrial changes in which
these conditions should succeed each other, the winter and summer of
this “great year” might differ much more than the elevated temperature
which we are led to ascribe to former periods of the globe, can be
judged to have differed from the present state of things.
The ingenuity and plausibility of this theory cannot be doubted:
and perhaps its results may hereafter be found not quite out of the
reach of calculation. Some progress has already been made in
calculating the movement of heat into, through, and out of the earth;
but when we add to this the effects of the currents of the ocean and
the atmosphere, the problem, thus involving so many thermotical and
atmological laws, operating under complex conditions, is undoubtedly
one of extreme difficulty. Still, it is something, in this as in all
cases, to have the problem even stated; and none of the elements of
the solution appears to be of such a nature that we need allow
ourselves to yield to despair, respecting the possibility of dealing
with it in a useful manner, as our knowledge becomes more complete and
definite. 561</div></body></text></TEI>