<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="147">BOTANY.
FOR the purpose of giving to
my reader some indication of the present tendency of Botanical
Science, I conceive that I cannot do better than direct his attention
to the reflections, procedure, and reasonings which have been
suggested by the most recent extensions of man’s knowledge of the
vegetable world. And as a specimen of these, I may take the labors of
Dr. Joseph Hooker, on the Flora of the Antarctic Regions,41 and especially of New Zealand. Dr.
Hooker was the Botanist to an expedition commanded by Sir James Ross,
sent out mainly for the purpose of investigating the phenomena of
Terrestrial Magnetism near the South Pole; but directed also to the
improvement of Natural History. The extension of botanical
descriptions and classifications to a large mass of new objects
necessarily suggests wider views of the value of classes (genera,
species, &c.,) and the conclusions to be drawn from their
constancy or inconstancy. A few of Dr. Hooker’s remarks may show the
nature of the views taken under such circumstances.
41 The Botany of the Antarctic
Voyage of H. M. Discovery Ships Erebus and Terror, in the years
1839–40. Published 1847. Flora Novæ Zelandiæ. 1853.
I may notice, in the first place, (since this work is intended for
general rather than for scientific readers,) Dr. Hooker’s testimony to
the value of a technical descriptive language for a classificatory
science—a Terminology, as it is called. He says, “It is
impossible to write Botanical descriptions which a person ignorant of
Botany can understand, although it is supposed by many unacquainted
with science that this can and should be done.” And hence, he says,
the state of botanical science demands Latin descriptions of the
plants; and this is a lesson which he especially urges upon the
Colonists who study the indigenous plants. 632
Dr. Hooker’s remarks on the limits of species, their dispersion and
variation, are striking and instructive. He is of opinion that species
vary more, and are more widely diffused, than is usually supposed.
Hence he conceives that the number of species has been needlessly and
erroneously multiplied, by distinguishing the specimens which occur in
different places, and vary in unessential features. He says that
though, according to the lowest estimate of compilers, 100,000 is the
commonly received number of known plants, he thinks that half that
number is much nearer the truth. “This,” he says, “may be well
conceived, when it is notorious that nineteen species have been made
of the Common Potatoe, and many more of Solanum nigrum alone.
Pteris aquilina has given rise to numerous book species;
Vernonia cinerea of India to fifteen at least. . . . . . . Many
more plants are common to most countries than is supposed; I have
found 60 New Zealand flowering plants and 9 Ferns to be European ones,
besides inhabiting numerous intermediate countries. . . . . . So long
ago as 1814, Mr. Brown drew attention to the importance of such
considerations, and gave a list of 150 European plants common to
Australia.”
As an example of the extent to which unessential differences may
go, he says (p. xvii.,) “The few remaining native Cedars of Lebanon
may be abnormal states of the tree which was once spread over the
whole of the Lebanon; for there are now growing in England varieties
of it which have no existence in a wild state. Some of them closely
resemble the Cedars of Atlas and of the Himalayas (Deodar;) and
the absence of any valid botanical differences tends to prove that
all, though generally supposed to be different species, are one.”
Still the great majority of the species of plants in those Southern
regions are peculiar. “There are upwards of 100 genera, subgenera, or
other well marked groups of plants, entirely or nearly confined to New
Zealand, Australia, and extra-tropical South America. They are
represented by one or more species in two or more of those countries,
and thus effect a botanical relationship or affinity between them all
which every botanist appreciates.”
In reference to the History of Botany, I have received corrections
and remarks from Dr. Hooker, with which I am allowed to enrich my
pages.
“P. 359. Note 3. Nelumbium speciosum, the Lotus
of India. The Nelumbium does not float, but raises both leaf
and flower several feet above the water: the Nymphæa Lotus has
floating leaves. Both enter largely into the symbolism of the Hindoos,
and are often confounded. 633
“P. 362. Note 5. For Arachnis read
Arachis. The Arachidna of Theophrastus cannot, however,
be the Arachis or ground-nut.
“Pp. 388 and 394. For Harlecamp read Hartecamp.
“P. 394. For Kerlen read Kalm.
“P. 394. For Asbech read Osbeck.
“P. 386. John Ray. Ray was further the author of the present
Natural System in its most comprehensive sense. He first divided
plants into Flowerless and Flowering; and the latter into
Monocotyledonous and Dicotyledonous:—’Floriferas dividemus in
Dicotyledones, quarum semina sata binis
foliis, seminalibus dictis, quæ cotyledonorum usum præstant, e terra
exeunt, vel in binos saltem lobos dividuntur, quamvis eos supra terram
foliorum specie non efferant; et Monocotyledones, quæ nec folia bina seminalia
efferunt nec lobos binos condunt. Hæc divisio ad arbores etiam extendi
potest; siquidem Palmæ et congeneres hoc respectu eodem modo a
reliquis arboribus differunt quo Monocotyledones a reliquis
herbis.’
“P. 408. Endogenous and Exogenous Growth. The exact course
of the wood fibres which traverse the stems of both Monocotyledonous
and Dicotyledonous plants has been only lately discovered. In the
Monocotyledons, those fibres are collected in bundles, which follow a
very peculiar course:—from the base of each leaf they may be
followed downwards and inwards, towards the axis of the trunk, when
they form an arch with the convexity to the centre; and curving
outwards again reach the circumference, where they are lost amongst
the previously deposited fibres. The intrusion of the bases of these
bundles amongst those already deposited, causes the circumference of
the stem to be harder than the centre; and as all these arcs have a
short course (their chords being nearly equal), the trunk does not
increase in girth, and grows at the apex only. The wood-bundles are
here definite. In the Dicotyledonous trunks, the layers of wood run in
parallel courses from the base to the top of the trunk, each
externally to that last formed, and the trunk increases both in height
and girth; the wood-bundles are here indefinite.
“With regard to the Cotyledons, though it is often difficult to
distinguish a Monocotyledonous Embryo from a Dicotyledonous, they may
always be discriminated when germinating. The Cotyledons, when two or
more, and primordial leaves (when no Cotyledons are visible) of a
Monocotyledon, are alternate; those of a Dicotyledon are opposite.
“A further physiological distinction between Monocotyledons and
634 Dicotyledons is
observed in germination, when the Dicotyledonous radicle elongates and
forms the root of the young plant; the Monocotyledonous radicle does
not elongate, but pushes out rootlets from itself at once. Hence the
not very good terms, exorhizal for Dicotyledonous, and
endorhizal for Monocotyledonous.
“The highest physiological generalization in the vegetable kingdom
is between Phænogama and Cryptogama. In the former,
fertilization is effected by a pollen-tube touching the nucleus of an
ovule; in Cryptogams, the same process is effected by the contact of a
sperm-cell, usually ciliated (antherozoid), upon another kind
of cell called a germ-cell. In Phænogams, further, the organs of
fructification are all modified leaves; those of Cryptogams are not
homologous.” (J. D. H.)</div></body></text></TEI>