<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="58">CHAPTER IV.
Problem of different Sounds of the same
String.
IT had been observed at an
early period of acoustical knowledge, that one string might give
several sounds. Mersenne and others 37 had noticed21 that when a
string vibrates, one which is in unison with it vibrates without being
touched. He was also aware that this was true if the second string was
an octave or a twelfth below the first. This was observed as a new
fact in England in 1674, and communicated to the Royal Society by
Wallis.22 But the later observers ascertained
further, that the longer string divides itself into two, or into three
equal parts, separated by nodes, or points of rest; this they
proved by hanging bits of paper on different parts of the string. The
discovery so modified was again made by Sauveur23 about 1700. The
sounds thus produced in one string by the vibration of another, have
been termed Sympathetic Sounds. Similar sounds are often
produced by performers on stringed instruments, by touching the string
at one of its aliquot divisions, and are then called the Acute
harmonics. Such facts were not difficult to explain on Taylor’s
view of the mechanical condition of the string; but the difficulty was
increased when it was noticed that a sounding body could produce these
different notes at the same time. Mersenne had remarked this,
and the fact was more distinctly observed and pursued by Sauveur. The
notes thus produced in addition to the genuine note of the string,
have been called Secondary Notes; those usually heard are, the
Octave, the Twelfth, and the Seventeenth above the note itself. To
supply a mode of conceiving distinctly, and explaining mechanically,
vibrations which should allow of such an effect, was therefore a
requisite step in acoustics.
21 Harm. lib. iv. Prop. 28
(1636).
22 Ph. Tr. 1677, April.
23 A. P. 1701.
This task was performed by Daniel Bernoulli in a memoir published
in 1755.24 He there stated and proved the
Principle of the coexistence of small vibrations. It was
already established, that a string might vibrate either in a single
swelling (if we use this word to express the curve between two
nodes which Bernoulli calls a ventre), or in two or three or
any number of equal swellings with immoveable nodes between. Daniel
Bernoulli showed further, that these nodes might be combined, each
taking place as if it were the only one. This appears sufficient to
explain the coexistence of the harmonic sounds just noticed.
D’Alembert, indeed, in the article Fundamental in the French
Encyclopédie, and Lagrange in his Dissertation on Sound
in the Turin Memoirs,25 offer several
objections to this explanation; and it cannot be denied that the
subject has its difficulties; but 38 still these do not deprive Bernoulli of
the merit of having pointed out the principle of Coexistent
Vibrations, or divest that principle of its value in physical
science.
24 Berlin Mem. 1753, p.
147.
25 T. i. pp. 64, 103.
Daniel Bernoulli’s Memoir, of which we speak, was published at a
period when the clouds which involve the general analytical treatment
of the problem of vibrating strings, were thickening about Euler and
D’Alembert, and darkening into a controversial hue; and as Bernoulli
ventured to interpose his view, as a solution of these difficulties,
which, in a mathematical sense, it is not, we can hardly be surprised
that he met with a rebuff. The further prosecution of the different
modes of vibration of the same body need not be here considered.
The sounds which are called Grave Harmonics, have no analogy
with the Acute Harmonics above-mentioned; nor do they belong to this
section; for in the case of Grave Harmonics, we have one sound from
the co-operation of two strings, instead of several sounds from one
string. These harmonics are, in fact, connected with beats, of which
we have already spoken; the beats becoming so
close as to produce a note of definite musical quality. The discovery
of the Grave Harmonics is usually ascribed to Tartini, who mentions
them in 1754; but they are first noticed26 in the work of
Sorge On tuning Organs, 1744. He there expresses this discovery
in a query. “Whence comes it, that if we tune a fifth (2 : 3), a
third sound is faintly heard, the octave below the lower of
the two notes? Nature shows that with 2 : 3, she still requires the
unity, to perfect the order 1, 2, 3.” The truth is, that these numbers
express the frequency of the vibrations, and thus there will be
coincidences of the notes 2 and 3, which are of the frequency 1, and
consequently give the octave below the sound 2. This is the
explanation given by Lagrange,27 and is indeed
obvious.
26 Chladni. Acoust. p.
254.
27 Mem. Tur. i. p. 104.
</div></body></text></TEI>