<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="22">CHAPTER II.
Induction of Copernicus.—The Heliocentric
Theory asserted on formal grounds.
IT will be recollected that
the formal are opposed to the physical grounds of a
theory; the former term indicating that it gives a satisfactory
account of the relations of the phenomena in Space and Time, that is,
of the Motions themselves; while the latter expression implies further
that we include in our explanation the Causes of the motions, the laws
of Force and Matter. The strongest of the considerations by which
Copernicus was led to invent and adopt his system of the universe were
of the former kind. He was dissatisfied, he says, in his Preface
addressed to the Pope, with the want of symmetry in the Eccentric
Theory, as it prevailed in his days; and weary of the uncertainty of
the mathematical traditions. He then sought through all the works of
philosophers, whether any had held opinions concerning the motions of
the world, different from those received in the established
mathematical schools. He found, in ancient authors, accounts of
Philolaus and others, who had asserted the motion of the earth.
“Then,” he adds, “I, too, began to meditate concerning the motion of
the earth; and though it appeared an absurd opinion, yet since I knew
that, in previous times, others had been allowed the privilege of
feigning what circles they chose, in order to explain the phenomena, I
conceived that I also might take the liberty of trying whether, on the
supposition of the earth’s motion, it was possible to find better
explanations than the ancient ones, of the revolutions of the
celestial orbs.
“Having then assumed the motions of the earth, which are hereafter
explained, by laborious and long observation I at length found, that
if the motions of the other planets be compared with the revolution of
the earth, not only their phenomena follow from the suppositions, but
also that the several orbs, and the whole system, are so connected in
order and magnitude, that no one part can be transposed without
disturbing the rest, and introducing confusion into the whole
universe.”
Thus the satisfactory explanation of the apparent motions of the
planets, and the simplicity and symmetry of the system, were the 263 grounds on which
Copernicus adopted his theory; as the craving for these qualities was
the feeling which led him to seek for a new theory. It is manifest
that in this, as in other cases of discovery, a clear and steady
possession of abstract Ideas, and an aptitude in comprehending real
Facts under these general conceptions, must have been leading
characters in the discoverer’s mind. He must have had a good
geometrical head, and great astronomical knowledge. He must have seen,
with peculiar distinctness, the consequences which flowed from his
suppositions as to the relations of space and time,—the apparent
motions which resulted from the assumed real ones; and he must also
have known well all the irregularities of the apparent motions for
which he had to account. We find indications of these qualities in his
expressions. A steady and calm contemplation of the theory is what he
asks for, as the main requisite to its reception. If you suppose the
earth to revolve and the heaven to be at rest, you will find, he says,
“si serio animadvertas,” if you think steadily, that the
apparent diurnal motion will follow. And after alleging his reasons
for his system, he says,7 “We are, therefore, not ashamed to
confess, that the whole of the space within the orbit of the moon,
along with the centre of the earth, moves round the sun in a year
among the other planets; the magnitude of the world being so great,
that the distance of the earth from the sun has no apparent magnitude
when compared with the sphere of the fixed stars.” “All which things,
though they be difficult and almost inconceivable, and against the
opinion of the majority, yet, in the sequel, by God’s favor, we will
make clearer than the sun, at least to those who are not ignorant of
mathematics.”
7 Nicolai Copernici Torinensis de
Revolutionibus Orbium Cœlestium Libri VI. Norimbergæ, m.d.xliii. p. 9.
It will easily be understood, that since the ancient geocentric
hypothesis ascribed to the planets those motions which were apparent
only, and which really arose from the motion of the earth round the
sun in the new hypothesis, the latter scheme must much simplify the
planetary theory. Kepler8 enumerates eleven motions of the
Ptolemaic system, which are at once exterminated and rendered
unnecessary by the new system. Still, as the real motions, both of the
earth and the planets, are unequable, it was requisite to have some
mode of representing their inequalities; and, accordingly, the ancient
theory of eccentrics and epicycles was retained, so far as was
requisite for this purpose. The planets revolved round the sun by
means of a Deferent, and a 264 great and small Epicycle; or else by
means of an Eccentric and Epicycle, modified from Ptolemy’s, for
reasons which we shall shortly mention. This mode of representing the
motions of the planets continued in use, until it was expelled by the
discoveries of Kepler.
8 Myst. Cosm. cap. 1.
Besides the daily rotation of the earth on its axis, and its annual
circuit about the sun, Copernicus attributed to the axis a “motion of
declination,” by which, during the whole annual revolution, the pole
was constantly directed towards the same part of the heavens. This
constancy in the absolute direction of the axis, or its moving
parallel to itself, may be more correctly viewed as not indicating any
separate motion. The axis continues in the same direction, because
there is nothing to make it change its direction; just as a straw,
lying on the surface of a cup of water, continues to point nearly in
the same direction when the cup is carried round a room. And this was
noticed by Copernicus’s adherent, Rothman,9 a few years after
the publication of the work De Revolutionibus. “There is no
occasion,” he says, in a letter to Tycho Brahe, “for the triple motion
of the earth: the annual and diurnal motions suffice.” This error of
Copernicus, if it be looked upon as an error, arose from his referring
the position of the axis to a limited space, which he conceived to be
carried round the sun along with the earth, instead of referring it to
fixed or absolute space. When, in a Planetarium (a machine in which
the motions of the planets are imitated), the earth is carried round
the sun by being fastened to a material radius, it is requisite to
give a motion to the axis by additional machinery, in order
to enable it to preserve its parallelism. A similar confusion
of geometrical conception, produced by a double reference to absolute
space and to the centre of revolution, often leads persons to dispute
whether the moon, which revolves about the earth, always turning to it
the same face, revolves about her axis or not.
9 Tycho. Epist. i. p. 184, a. d. 1590.
It is also to be noticed that the precession of the equinoxes made
it necessary to suppose the axis of the earth to be not
exactly parallel to itself, but to deviate from that position
by a slight annual difference. Copernicus erroneously supposes the
precession to be unequable; and his method of explaining this change,
which is simpler than that of the ancients, becomes more simple still,
when applied to the true state of the facts.
The tendencies of our speculative nature, which carry us onwards in
265 pursuit of
symmetry and rule, and which thus produced the theory of Copernicus,
as they produce all theories, perpetually show their vigor by
overshooting their mark. They obtain something by aiming at much more.
They detect the order and connection which exist, by imagining
relations of order and connection which have no existence. Real
discoveries are thus mixed with baseless assumptions; profound
sagacity is combined with fanciful conjecture; not rarely, or in
peculiar instances, but commonly, and in most cases; probably in all,
if we could read the thoughts of the discoverers as we read the books
of Kepler. To try wrong guesses is apparently the only way to hit upon
right ones. The character of the true philosopher is, not that he
never conjectures hazardously, but that his conjectures are clearly
conceived and brought into rigid contact with facts. He sees and
compares distinctly the ideas and the things,—the relations of
his notions to each other and to phenomena. Under these conditions it
is not only excusable, but necessary for him, to snatch at every
semblance of general rule;—to try all promising forms of
simplicity and symmetry.
Copernicus is not exempt from giving us, in his work, an example of
this character of the inventive spirit. The axiom that the celestial
motions must be circular and uniform, appeared to him to
have strong claims to acceptation; and his theory of the inequalities
of the planetary motions is fashioned upon it. His great desire was to
apply it more rigidly than Ptolemy had done. The time did not come for
rejecting this axiom, till the observations of Tycho Brahe and the
calculations of Kepler had been made.
I shall not attempt to explain, in detail, Copernicus’s system of
the planetary inequalities. He retained epicycles and eccentrics,
altering their centres of motion; that is, he retained what was
true in the old system, translating it into his own.
The peculiarities of his method consisted in making such a combination
of epicycles as to supply the place of the equant,10 and to make all the motions equable
about the centres of motion. This device was admired for a time, till
Kepler’s elliptic theory expelled it, with all other forms of the
theory of epicycles: but we must observe that Copernicus was aware of
some of the discrepancies which belonged to that theory as it had, up
to that time, been propounded. In the case of Mercury’s orbit, which
is more eccentric than that of the other planets, he makes
suppositions which are complex indeed, but which show his perception
of the imperfection of 266 the common theory; and he proposes a new
theory of the moon, for the very reason which did at last overturn the
doctrine of epicycles, namely, that the ratio of their distances from
the earth at different times was inconsistent with the circular
hypothesis.11
10 See B. iii. Chap. iv. Sect. 7.
11 De Rev. iv. c. 2.
It is obvious, that, along with his mathematical clearness of view,
and his astronomical knowledge, Copernicus must have had great
intellectual boldness and vigor, to conceive and fully develop a
theory so different as his was from all received doctrines. His pupil
and expositor, Rheticus, says to Schener, “I beg you to have this
opinion concerning that learned man, my Preceptor; that he was an
ardent admirer and follower of Ptolemy; but when he was compelled by
phenomena and demonstration, he thought he did well to aim at the same
mark at which Ptolemy had aimed, though with a bow and shafts of a
very different material from his. We must recollect what Ptolemy says,
Δεῖ δ’ ἐλευθέρον εἶναι τῇ γνώμῃ τὸν μέλλοντα φιλοσοφεῖν. ‘He who is to
follow philosophy must be a freeman in mind.’” Rheticus then goes on
to defend his master from the charge of disrespect to the ancients:
“That temper,” he says, “is alien from the disposition of every good
man, and most especially from the spirit of philosophy, and from no
one more utterly than from my Preceptor. He was very far from rashly
rejecting the opinions of ancient philosophers, except for weighty
reasons and irresistible facts, through any love of novelty. His
years, his gravity of character, his excellent learning, his
magnanimity and nobleness of spirit, are very far from having any
liability to such a temper, which belongs either to youth, or to
ardent and light minds, or to those τῶν μέγα φρονούντων ἐπὶ θεωρίᾳ
μικρῂ, ‘who think much of themselves and know little,’ as Aristotle
says.” Undoubtedly this deference for the great men of the past,
joined with the talent of seizing the spirit of their methods when the
letter of their theories is no longer tenable, is the true
mental constitution of discoverers.
Besides the intellectual energy which was requisite in order to
construct a system of doctrines so novel as those of Copernicus, some
courage was necessary to the publication of such opinions; certain, as
they were, to be met, to a great extent, by rejection and dispute, and
perhaps by charges of heresy and mischievous tendency. This last
danger, however, must not be judged so great as we might infer from
the angry controversies and acts of authority which occurred in 267 Galileo’s time. The
Dogmatism of the stationary period, which identified the cause of
philosophical and religious truth, had not yet distinctly felt itself
attacked by the advance of physical knowledge; and therefore had not
begun to look with alarm on such movements. Still, the claims of
Scripture and of ecclesiastical authority were asserted as paramount
on all subjects; and it was obvious that many persons would be
disquieted or offended with the new interpretation of many scriptural
expressions, which the true theory would make necessary. This evil
Copernicus appears to have foreseen; and this and other causes long
withheld him from publication. He was himself an ecclesiastic; and, by
the patronage of his maternal uncle, was prebendary of the church of
St. John at Thorn, and a canon of the church of Frauenburg, in the
diocese of Ermeland.12 He had been a student at Bologna, and
had taught mathematics at Rome in the year 1500; and he afterwards
pursued his studies and observations at his residence near the mouth
of the Vistula.13 His discovery of his system must have
occurred before 1507, for in 1543 he informs Pope Paulus the Third, in
his dedication, that he had kept his book by him for four times the
nine years recommended by Horace, and then only published it at the
earnest entreaty of his friend Cardinal Schomberg, whose letter is
prefixed to the work. “Though I know,” he says, “that the thoughts of
a philosopher do not depend on the judgment of the many, his study
being to seek out truth in all things as far as that is permitted by
God to human reason: yet when I considered,” he adds, “how absurd my
doctrine would appear, I long hesitated whether I should publish my
book, or whether it were not better to follow the example of the
Pythagoreans and others, who delivered their doctrines only by
tradition and to friends.” It will be observed that he speaks here of
the opposition of the established school of Astronomers, not of
Divines. The latter, indeed, he appears to consider as a less
formidable danger. “If perchance,” he says at the end of his preface,
“there be ματαιολόγοι, vain babblers, who knowing nothing of
mathematics, yet assume the right of judging on account of some place
of Scripture perversely wrested to their purpose, and who blame and
attack my undertaking; I heed them not, and look upon their judgments
as rash and contemptible.” He then goes on to show that the globular
figure of the earth (which was, of course, at that time, an undisputed
point among astronomers), had been opposed on similar grounds by
Lactantius, who, 268 though a writer of credit in other
respects, had spoken very childishly in that matter. In another
epistle prefixed to the work (by Andreas Osiander), the reader is
reminded that the hypotheses of astronomers are not necessarily
asserted to be true, by those who propose them, but only to be a way
of representing facts. We may observe that, in the time of
Copernicus, when the motion of the earth had not been connected with
the physical laws of matter and motion, it could not be considered so
distinctly real as it necessarily was held to be in after times.
12 Rheticus, Nar. p. 94.
13 Riccioli.
The delay of the publication of Copernicus’s work brought it to the
end of his life; he died in the year 1543, in which it was published.
It was entitled De Revolutionibus Orbium Cœlestium Libri VI. He
received the only copy he ever saw on the day of his death, and never
opened it: he had then, says Gassendi, his biographer, other cares.
His system was, however, to a certain extent, promulgated, and his
fame diffused before that time. Cardinal Schomberg, in his letter of
1536, which has been already mentioned, says, “Some years ago, when I
heard tidings of your merit by the constant report of all persons, my
affection for you was augmented, and I congratulated the men of our
time, among whom you flourish in so much honor. For I had understood
that you were not only acquainted with the discoveries of ancient
mathematicians, but also had formed a new system of the world, in
which you teach that the Earth moves, the Sun occupies the lowest, and
consequently, the middle place, the sphere of the fixed stars remains
immovable and fixed, and the Moon, along with the elements included in
her sphere, placed between the orbits (cœlum) of Mars and
Venus, travels round the sun in a yearly
revolution.”14
The writer goes on to say that he has
heard that Copernicus has written a book (Commentarios), in
which this system is applied to the construction of Tables of the
Planetary Motions (erraticarum stellarum). He then proceeds to
entreat him earnestly to publish his lucubrations.
14 This passage has so important a
place in the history, that I will give it in the
original:—“Intellexeram te non modo veterum mathematicorum
inventa egregie callere sed etiam novam mundi rationem constituisse:
Qua doceas terram moveri: solem imum mundi, atque medium locum
obtinere: cœlum octavum immotum atque fixum perpetuo manere: Lunam se
una cum inclusis suæ spheræ elementis, inter Martis et Veneris cœlum
sitam, anniversario cursu circum solem convertere. Atque de hac tota
astronomiæ ratione commentarios a te confectos esse, ac erraticarum
stellarum motus calculis subductos tabulis te contulisse, maxima
omnium cum admiratione. Quamobrem vir doctissime, nisi tibi molestus
sum, te etiam atque etiam oro vehementer ut hoc tuum inventum
studiosis communices, et tuas de mundi sphæra lucubrationes, una cum
Tabulis et si quid habes præterea quod ad eandem rem pertineat primo
quoque tempore ad me mittas.”
269 This letter
is dated 1536, and implies that the work of Copernicus was then
written, and known to persons who studied astronomy. Delambre says
that Achilles Gassarus of Lindau, in a letter dated 1540, sends to his
friend George Vogelin of Constance, the book De Revolutionibus.
But Mr. De Morgan15 has pointed out that the printed work
which Gassarus sent to Vogelin was the Narratio by Rheticus of
Feldkirch, a eulogium of Copernicus and his system prefixed to the
second edition of the De Revolutionibus, which appeared in
1566. In this Narration, Rheticus speaks of the work of Copernicus as
a Palingenesia, or New Birth of astronomy. Rheticus, it appears, had
gone to Copernicus for the purpose of getting knowledge about
triangles and trigonometrical tables, and had had his attention called
to the heliocentric theory, of which he became an ardent admirer. He
speaks of his “Preceptor” with strong admiration, as we have seen. “He
appears to me,” says he, “more to resemble Ptolemy than any other
astronomers.” This, it must be recollected, was selecting the highest
known subject of comparison.  ~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~
15 Ast. Mod. i. p. 138. I owe
this and many other corrections to the personal kindness of Mr. De
Morgan.
</div></body></text></TEI>