<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="38">CHAPTER VI.
The Instruments and Aids of Astronomy during the
Newtonian Period.

Sect. 1.—Instruments.
SOME instruments or other were
employed at all periods of astronomical observation. But it was only
when observation had attained a considerable degree of delicacy, that
the exact construction of instruments became an object of serious
care. Gradually, as the possibility and the value of increased
exactness became manifest, it was seen that every thing which could
improve the astronomer’s instruments was of high importance to him.
And hence in some cases a vast increase of size and of expense was
introduced; in other cases new combinations, or the result of
improvements in other sciences, were brought into play. Extensive
knowledge, intense thought, and great ingenuity, were requisite in the
astronomical instrument maker. Instead of ranking with artisans, he
became a man of science, sharing the honor and dignity of the
astronomer himself.
1. Measure of Angles.—Tycho Brahe was the first
astronomer who acted upon a due appreciation of the importance of good
instruments. The collection of such at Uraniburg was by far the finest
which had ever existed. He endeavored to give steadiness to the frame,
and accuracy to the divisions of his instruments. His Mural Quadrant
was well adapted for this purpose; its radius was five cubits: it is
clear, that as we enlarge the instrument we are enabled to measure
smaller arcs. On this principle many large gnomons were
erected. Cassini’s celebrated one in the church of St. Petronius at
Bologna, was eighty-three feet (French) high. But this mode of
obtaining accuracy was soon abandoned for better methods. Three great
improvements were introduced about the same time. The application of
the Micrometer to the telescope, by Huyghens, Malvasia, and Auzout;
the application of the Telescope to the astronomical quadrant; and the
fixation of the centre of its field by a Cross of fine wires placed in
the focus by Gascoigne, and afterwards by Picard. We may judge how
great was the improvement which these contrivances introduced into the
art of 471
observing, by finding that Hevelius refused to adopt them because they
would make all the old observations of no value. He had spent a
laborious and active life in the exercise of the old methods, and
could not bear to think that all the treasures which he had
accumulated had lost their worth by the discovery of a new mine of
richer ore.
[2d Ed.] [Littrow, in his Die Wunder des Himmels, Ed. 2, pp.
684, 685, says that Gascoigne invented and used the telescope with
wires in the common focus of the lenses in 1640. He refers to Phil.
Trans. xxx. 603. Picard reinvented this arrangement in 1667. I
have   already spoken of Gascoigne as the
inventor of the micrometer.
Römer (already mentioned, p. 464) brought
into use the Transit Instrument, and the employment of complete
Circles, instead of the Quadrants used till then; and by these means
gave to practical astronomy a new form, of which the full value was
not discovered till long afterwards.]
The apparent place of the object in the instrument being so
precisely determined by the new methods, the exact Division of the arc
into degrees and their subdivisions became a matter of great
consequence. A series of artists, principally English, have acquired
distinguished places in the lists of scientific fame by their
performances in this way; and from that period, particular instruments
have possessed historical interest and individual reputation. Graham
was one of the first of these artists. He executed a great Mural Arc
for Halley at Greenwich; for Bradley he constructed the Sector which
detected aberration. He also made the Sector which the French
academicians carried to Lapland; and probably the goodness of this
instrument, compared with the imperfection of those which were sent to
Peru, was one main cause of the great difference of duration in the
two series of observations. Bird, somewhat later121 (about 1750),
divided several Quadrants for public observatories. His method of
dividing was considered so perfect, that the knowledge of it was
purchased by the English government, and published in 1767. Ramsden
was equally celebrated. The error of one of his best Quadrants (that
at Padua) is said to be never greater than two seconds. But at a later
period, Ramsden constructed Mural Circles only, holding this to be a
kind of instrument far superior to the quadrant. He made one of five
feet diameter, in 1788, for M. Piazzi at Palermo; and one of eight
feet for the observatory of Dublin. Troughton, a worthy successor of
the 472 artists we
have mentioned, has invented a method of dividing the circle still
superior to the former ones; indeed, one which is theoretically
perfect, and practically capable of consummate accuracy. In this way,
circles have been constructed for Greenwich, Armagh, Cambridge, and
many other places; and probably this method, carefully applied, offers
to the astronomer as much exactness as his other implements allow him
to receive; but the slightest casualty happening to such an
instrument, after it has been constructed, or any doubt whether the
method of graduation has been rightly applied, makes it unfit for the
jealous scrupulosity of modern astronomy.
121 Mont. iv. 337.
The English artists sought to attain accurate measurements by
continued bisection and other aliquot subdivision of the limb of their
circle; but Mayer proposed to obtain this end otherwise, by
repeating the measure on different parts of the circumference
till the error of the division becomes unimportant, instead of
attempting to divide an instrument without error. This invention of
the Repeating Circle was zealously adopted by the French, and the
relative superiority of the rival methods is still a matter of
difference of opinion.
[2d Ed.] [In the series of these great astronomical mechanists, we
must also reckon George Reichenbach. He was born Aug. 24, 1772, at
Durlach; became Lieutenant of Artillery in the Bavarian service in
1794; (Salinenrath) Commissioner of Salt-works in 1811; and in 1820,
First Commissioner of Water-works and Roads. He became, with
Fraunhofer, the ornament of the mechanical and optical Institute
erected in 1805 at Benedictbeuern by Utzschneider; and his
astronomical instruments, meridian circles, transit instruments,
equatorials, heliometers, make an epoch in Observing Astronomy. His
contrivances in the Salt-works at Berchtesgaden and Reichenhall, in
the Arms Manufactory at Amberg, and in the works for boring cannon at
Vienna, are enduring monuments of his rare mechanical talent. He died
May 21, 1826, at Munich.]
2. Clocks.—The improvements in the
measures of space require corresponding improvements in the measure of
time. The beginning of any thing which we can call accuracy, in this
subject, was the application of the Pendulum to clocks, by Huyghens,
in 1656. That the successive oscillations of a pendulum occupy equal
times, had been noticed by Galileo; but in order to take advantage of
this property, the pendulum must be connected with machinery by which
its motion is kept from languishing, and by which the number of its
swings is recorded. By inventing such machinery, Huyghens at once
obtained 473 a
measure of time more accurate than the sun itself. Hence astronomers
were soon led to obtain the right ascension of a star, not directly,
by measuring a Distance in the heavens, but indirectly, by observing
the Moment of its Transit. This observation is now made with a degree
of accuracy which might, at first sight, appear beyond the limits of
human sense, being noted to a tenth of a second of time: but we
may explain this, by remarking that though the number of the second at
which the transit happens is given by the clock, and is reckoned
according to the course of time, the subdivision of the second of time
into smaller fractions is performed by the eye,—by seeing the
space described by the heavenly body in a whole second, and hence
estimating a smaller time, according to the space which its
description occupies.
But in order to make clocks so accurate as to justify this degree
of precision, their construction was improved by various persons in
succession. Picard soon found that Huyghens’ clocks were affected in
their going by temperature, for heat caused expansion of the metallic
pendulum. This cause of error was remedied by combining different
metals, as iron and copper, which expand in a different degree, in
such a way that their effects compensate each other. Graham afterwards
used quicksilver for the same purpose. The Escapement too
(which connects the force which impels the clock with the pendulum
which regulates it), and other parts of the machinery, had the most
refined mechanical skill and ingenuity of the best artists constantly
bestowed upon then. The astronomer of the present day, constantly
testing the going of such a clock by the motions of the fixed stars,
has a scale of time as stable and as minutely exact as the scales on
which he measures distance.
The construction of good Watches, that is, portable or marine
clocks, was important on another account, namely, because they might
be used in determining the longitude of places. Hence the improvement
of this little machine became an object of national interest, and was
included in the reward of 20,000l., which we have already noticed as offered by the English parliament for
the discovery of the longitude. Harrison,122 originally a
carpenter, turned his mind to this subject with success. After thirty
years of labor, in which he was encouraged by many eminent persons, he
produced, in 1758, a time-keeper, which was sent on a voyage to
Jamaica for trial. After 161 days, the error 474 of the watch was only one minute five
seconds, and the artist received from the nation 5000l. At a
later period,123 at the age of seventy-five years,
after a life devoted to this object, having still further satisfied
the commissioners, he received, in 1765, 10,000l., at the same
time that Euler and the heirs of Mayer received each 3000l. for
the lunar tables which they had constructed.
122 Mont. iv. 554.
123 Mont. iv. 560.
The two methods of finding the longitude, by Chronometers and by
Lunar Observations, have solved the problem for all practical
purposes; but the latter could not have been employed at sea without
the aid of that invaluable instrument, the Sextant, in which the
distance of two objects is observed, by bringing one to coincide
apparently with the reflected image of the other. This instrument was
invented by Hadley, in 1731. Though the problem of finding the
longitude be, in fact, one of geography rather than astronomy, it is
an application of astronomical science which has so materially
affected the progress of our knowledge, that it deserves the notice we
have bestowed upon it.
3. Telescopes.—We have spoken of the application of
the telescope to astronomical measurements, but not of the improvement
of the telescope itself. If we endeavor to augment the optical power
of this instrument, we run, according to the path we take, into
various inconveniences;—distortion, confusion, want of light, or
colored images. Distortion and confusion are produced, if we increase
the magnifying power, retaining the length and the aperture of the
object-glass. If we diminish the aperture we suffer from loss of
light. What remains then is to increase the focal length. This was
done to an extraordinary extent, in telescopes constructed in the
beginning of the last century. Huyghens, in his first attempts, made
them 22 feet long;124 afterwards, Campani, by order of Louis
the Fourteenth, made them of 86, 100, and 136 feet. Huyghens, by new
exertions, made a telescope 210 feet long. Auzout and Hartsoecker are
said to have gone much further, and to have succeeded in making an
object-glass of 600 feet focus. But even such telescopes as those of
Campani are almost unmanageable: in that of Huyghens, the object-glass
was placed on a pole, and the observer was placed at the focus with an
eye-glass.
124 Bailly, ii. 253.
The most serious objection to the increase of the aperture of
object-glasses, was the coloration of the image produced, in
consequence of the unequal refrangibility of differently colored rays.
Newton, who discovered the principle of this defect in lenses, had
maintained that 475
the evil was irremediable, and that a compound lens could no more
refract without producing color, than a single lens could. Euler and
Klingenstierna doubted the exactness of Newton’s proposition; and, in
1755, Dollond disproved it by experiment. This discovery pointed out a
method of making object-glasses which should give no
color;—which should be achromatic. For this purpose
Dollond fabricated various kinds of glass (flint and crown glass); and
Clairaut and D’Alembert calculated formulæ. Dollond and his son125 succeeded in constructing telescopes
of three feet long (with a triple object-glass) which produced an
effect as great as those of forty-five feet on the ancient principles.
At first it was conceived that these discoveries opened the way to a
vast extension of the astronomer’s power of vision; but it was found
that the most material improvement was the compendious size of the new
instruments; for, in increasing the dimensions, the optician was
stopped by the impossibility of obtaining lenses of flint-glass of
very large dimensions. And this branch of art remained long
stationary; but, after a time, its epoch of advance again arrived. In
the present century, Fraunhofer, at Munich, with the help of Guinand
and the pecuniary support of Utzschneider, succeeded in forming lenses
of flint-glass of a magnitude till then unheard of. Achromatic
object-glasses, of a foot in diameter, and twenty feet focal length,
are now no longer impossible; although in such attempts the artist
cannot reckon on certain success.
125 Bailly, iii. 118.
[2d Ed.] [Joseph Fraunhofer was born March 6, 1787, at Straubing in
Bavaria, the son of a poor glazier. He was in his earlier years
employed in his father’s trade, so that he was not able to attend
school, and remained ignorant of writing and arithmetic till his
fourteenth year. At a later period he was assisted by Utzschneider,
and tried rapidly to recover his lost ground. In the year 1806 he
entered the establishment of Utzschneider as an optician. In this
establishment (transferred from Benedictbeuern to Munich in 1819) he
soon came to be the greatest Optician of Germany. His excellent
telescopes and microscopes are known throughout Europe. His greatest
telescope, that in the Observatory at Dorpat, has an object-glass of 9
inches diameter, and a focal length of 13⅓ feet. His written
productions are to be found in the Memoirs of the Bavarian
Academy, in Gilbert’s Annalen der Physik, and in Schumacher’s
Astronomische Nachrichten. He died the 7th of June, 1826.]
476
Such telescopes might be expected to add something to our knowledge
of the heavens, if they had not been anticipated by reflectors of an
equal or greater scale. James Gregory had invented, and Newton had
more efficaciously introduced, reflecting telescopes. But these were
not used with any peculiar effect, till the elder Herschel made them
his especial study. His skill and perseverance in grinding specula,
and in contriving the best apparatus for their use, were rewarded by a
number of curious and striking discoveries, among which, as we have already related, was the discovery of a new planet
beyond Saturn. In 1789, Herschel surpassed all his former attempts, by
bringing into action a reflecting telescope of forty feet length, with
a speculum of four feet in diameter. The first application of this
magnificent instrument showed a new satellite (the sixth) of Saturn.
He and his son have, with reflectors of twenty feet, made a complete
survey of the heavens, so far as they are visible in this country; and
the latter is now in a distant region completing this survey, by
adding to it the other hemisphere.
In speaking of the improvements of telescopes we ought to notice,
that they have been pursued in the eye-glasses as well as in the
object-glasses. Instead of the single lens, Huyghens substituted an
eye-piece of two lenses, which, though introduced for another purpose,
attained the object of destroying color.126 Ramsden’s
eye-piece is one fit to be used with a micrometer, and others of more
complex construction have been used for various purposes. ~Additional
material in the 3rd edition.~
126 Coddington’s Optics, ii.
21.
Sect. 2.—Observatories.
Astronomy, which is thus benefited by the
erection of large and stable instruments, requires also the
establishment of permanent Observatories, supplied with funds for
their support, and for that of the observers. Such observatories have
existed at all periods of the history of the science; but from the
commencement of the period which we are now reviewing, they multiplied
to such an extent that we cannot even enumerate them. Yet we must
undoubtedly look upon such establishments, and the labors of which
they have been the scene, as important and essential parts of the
history of the progress of astronomy. Some of the most distinguished
of the observatories of modern times we may mention. The first of
these were that of Tycho Brahe 477 at Uraniburg, and that of the Landgrave
of Hesse Cassel, at Cassel, where Rothman and Byrgius observed. But by
far the most important observations, at least since those of Tycho,
which were the basis of the discoveries of Kepler and Newton, have
been made at Paris and Greenwich. The Observatory of Paris was built
in 1667. It was there that the first Cassini made many of his
discoveries; three of his descendants have since labored in the same
place, and two others of his family, the Maraldis;127 besides many other eminent
astronomers, as Picard, La Hire, Lefêvre, Fouchy, Legentil, Chappe,
Méchain, Bouvard. Greenwich Observatory was built a few years later
(1675); and ever since its erection, the observations there made have
been the foundation of the greatest improvements which astronomy, for
the time, received. Flamsteed, Halley, Bradley, Bliss, Maskelyne,
Pond, have occupied the place in succession: on the retirement of the
last-named astronomer in 1835, Professor Airy was removed thither from
the Cambridge Observatory. In every state, and in almost every
principality in Europe, Observatories have been established; but these
have often fallen speedily into inaction, or have contributed little
to the progress of astronomy, because their observations have not been
published. From the same causes, the numerous private observatories
which exist throughout Europe have added little to our knowledge,
except where the attention of the astronomer has been directed to some
definite points; as, for instance, the magnificent labors of the
Herschels, or the skilful observations made by Mr. Pond with the
Westbury circle, which first pointed out the error of graduation of
the Greenwich quadrants. The Observations, now regularly published,128 are those of Greenwich, begun by
Maskelyne, and continued quarterly by Mr. Pond; those of Königsberg,
published by Bessel since 1814; of Vienna, by Littrow since 1820; of
Speier, by Schwerd since 1826; those of Cambridge, commenced by Airy
in 1828; of Armagh, by Robinson in 1829. Besides these, a number of
useful observations have been published in journals and occasional
forms; as, for instance, those of Zach, made by Seeberg, near Gotha,
since 1788; and others have been employed in forming catalogues, of
which we shall speak shortly.
127 Mont. iv. 346.
128 Airy, Rep. p. 128.
[2d Ed.] [I have left the statement of published Observations in
the text as it stood originally. I believe that at present (1847) the
twelve places contained in the following list publish their
Observations quite regularly, or nearly so;—Greenwich, Oxford,
Cambridge, Vienna, 478 Berlin, Dorpat, Munich, Geneva, Paris,
Königsberg, Madras, the Cape of Good Hope.
Littrow, in his translation, adds to the publications noticed in
the text as containing astronomical Observations, Zach’s Monatliche
Correspondenz, Lindenau and Bohnenberger’s Zeitschrift für
Astronomie, Bode’s Astronomisches Jahrbuch, Schumacher’s
Astronomische Nachrichten.]
Nor has the establishment of observatories been confined to Europe.
In 1786, M. de Beauchamp, at the expense of Louis the Sixteenth,
erected an observatory at Bagdad, “built to restore the Chaldean and
Arabian observations,” as the inscription stated; but, probably, the
restoration once effected, the main intention had been fulfilled, and
little perseverance in observing was thought necessary. In 1828, the
British government completed the building of an observatory at the
Cape of Good Hope, which Lacaille had already made an astronomical
station by his observations there at an earlier period (1750); and an
observatory formed in New South Wales by Sir T. M. Brisbane in 1822,
and presented by him to the government, is also in activity. The East
India Company has founded observatories at Madras, Bombay, and St.
Helena; and observations made at the former of these places, and at
St. Helena, have been published.
The bearing of the work done at such observatories upon the past
progress of astronomy, has already been seen in the preceding
narrative. Their bearing upon the present condition of the science
will be the subject of a few remarks hereafter.
Sect. 3.—Scientific Societies.
The influence of Scientific Societies, or
Academical Bodies, has also been very powerful in the subject before
us. In all branches of knowledge, the use of such associations of
studious and inquiring men is great; the clearness and coherence of a
speculator’s ideas, and their agreement with facts (the two main
conditions of scientific truth), are severally but beneficially tested
by collision with other minds. In astronomy, moreover, the vast extent
of the subject makes requisite the division of labor and the support
of sympathy. The Royal Societies of London and of Paris were founded
nearly at the same time as the metropolitan Observatories of the two
countries. We have seen what constellations of philosophers, and what
activity of research, existed at those periods; these philosophers
appear in the lists, their discoveries 479 in the publications, of the
above-mentioned eminent Societies. As the progress of physical
science, and principally of astronomy, attracted more and more
admiration, Academies were created in other countries. That of Berlin
was founded by Leibnitz in 1710; that of St Petersburg was established
by Peter the Great in 1725; and both these have produced highly
valuable Memoirs. In more modern times these associations have
multiplied almost beyond the power of estimation. They have been
formed according to divisions, both of locality and of subject,
conformable to the present extent of science, and the vast population
of its cultivators. It would be useless to attempt to give a view
either of their number or of the enormous mass of scientific
literature which their Transactions present. But we may notice, as
especially connected with our present subject, the Astronomical
Society of London, founded in 1820, which gave a strong impulse to the
pursuit of the science in England.
Sect. 4.—Patrons of Astronomy.
The advantages which letters and philosophy
derive from the patronage of the great have sometimes been questioned;
that love of knowledge, it has been thought, cannot be genuine which
requires such stimulation, nor those speculations free and true which
are thus forced into being. In the sciences of observation and
calculation, however, in which disputed questions can be
experimentally decided, and in which opinions are not disturbed by
men’s practical principles and interests, there is nothing necessarily
operating to poison or neutralize the resources which wealth and power
supply to the investigation of truth.
Astronomy has, in all ages, flourished under the favor of the rich
and powerful; in the period of which we speak, this was eminently the
case. Louis the Fourteenth gave to the astronomy of France a
distinction which, without him, it could not have attained. No step
perhaps tended more to this than his bringing the celebrated Dominic
Cassini to Paris. This Italian astronomer (for he was born at
Permaldo, in the county of Nice, and was professor at Bologna), was
already in possession of a brilliant reputation, when the French
ambassador, in the name of his sovereign, applied to Pope Clement the
Ninth, and to the senate of Bologna, that he should be allowed to
remove to Paris. The request was granted only so far as an absence of
six years; but at the end of that time, the benefits and honors which
480 the king had
conferred upon him, fixed him in France. The impulse which his arrival
(in 1669) and his residence gave to astronomy, showed the wisdom of
the measure. In the same spirit, the French government drew to Paris
Römer from Denmark, Huyghens from Holland, and gave a pension to
Hevelius, and a large sum when his observatory at Dantzic had been
destroyed by fire in 1679.
When the sovereigns of Prussia and Russia were exerting themselves
to encourage the sciences in their countries, they followed the same
course which had been so successful in France. Thus, as we have said, the Czar Peter took Delisle to Petersburg
in 1725; the celebrated Frederick the Great drew to Berlin, Voltaire
and Maupertuis, Euler and Lagrange; and the Empress Catharine obtained
in the same way Euler, two of the Bernoulli’s, and other
mathematicians. In none of these instances, however, did it happen
that “the generous plant did still its stock renew,” as we have seen
was the case at Paris, with the Cassinis, and their kinsmen the
Maraldis.
[2d Ed.] [I may notice among instances of the patronage of
Astronomy, the reward at present offered by the King of Denmark for
the discovery of a Comet.]
It is not necessary to mention here the more recent cases in which
sovereigns or statesmen have attempted to patronize individual
astronomers.
Sect. 5.—Astronomical Expeditions.
Besides the pensions thus bestowed upon
resident mathematicians and astronomers, the governments of Europe
have wisely and usefully employed considerable sums upon expeditions
and travels undertaken by men of science for some appropriate object.
Thus Picard, in 1671, was sent to Uraniburg, the scene of Tycho’s
observations, to determine its latitude and its longitude. He found
that “the City of the Skies” had utterly disappeared from the earth;
and even its foundations were retraced with difficulty. With the same
object, that of accurately connecting the labors of the places which
had been at different periods the metropolis of astronomy, Chazelles
was sent, in 1693, to Alexandria. We have already mentioned Richer’s
astronomical expedition to Cayenne in 1672. Varin and Deshayes129 were sent a few years later into the
same regions for similar purposes. Halley’s expedition to St. 481 Helena in 1677, with
the view of observing the southern stars, was at his own expense; but
at a later period (in 1698), he was appointed to the command of a
small vessel by King William the Third, in order that he might make
his magnetical observations in all parts of the world. Lacaille was
maintained by the French government four years at the Cape of Good
Hope (1750–4), for the purpose of observing the stars of the
southern hemisphere. The two transits of Venus in 1761 and 1769,
occasioned expeditions to be sent to Kamtschatka and Tobolsk by the
Russians; to the Isle of France, and to Coromandel, by the French;130 to the isles of St. Helena and
Otaheite by the English; to Lapland and to Drontheim, by the Swedes
and Danes. I shall not here refer to the measures of degrees executed
by various nations, still less the innumerable surveys by land and
sea; but I may just notice the successive English expeditions of
Captains Basil Hall, Sabine, and Foster, for the purpose of
determining the length of the seconds’ pendulum in different
latitudes; and the voyages of M. Biot and others, sent by the French
government for the same purpose. Much has been done in this way, but
not more than the progress of astronomy absolutely required; and only
a small portion of that which the completion of the subject calls
for.
129 Bailly, ii. 374.
130 Bailly, iii. 107.
Sect. 6.—Present State of Astronomy.
Astronomy, in its present condition, is not
only much the most advanced of the sciences, but is also in far more
favorable circumstances than any other science for making any future
advance, as soon as this is possible. The general methods and
conditions by which such an advantage is to be obtained for the
various sciences, we shall endeavor hereafter to throw some light
upon; but in the mean time, we may notice here some of the
circumstances in which this peculiar felicity of the present state of
astronomy may be traced.
The science is cultivated by a number of votaries, with an
assiduity and labor, and with an expenditure of private and public
resources, to which no other subject approaches; and the mode of its
cultivation in all public and most private observatories, has this
character—that it forms, at the same time, a constant process of
verification of existing discoveries, and a strict search for any new
discoverable laws. The observations made are immediately referred to
the best tables, and 482 corrected by the best formulæ which are
known; and if the result of such a reduction leaves any thing
unaccounted for, the astronomer is forthwith curious and anxious to
trace this deviation from the expected numbers to its rule and its
origin; and till the first, at least, of these things is performed, he
is dissatisfied and unquiet. The reference of observations to the
state of the heavens as known by previous researches, implies a great
amount of calculation. The exact places of the stars at some standard
period are recorded in Catalogues; their movements, according
to the laws hitherto detected, are arranged in Tables; and if
these tables are applied to predict the numbers which observation on
each day ought to give, they form Ephemerides. Thus the
catalogues of fixed stars of Flamsteed, of Piazzi, of Maskelyne, of
the Astronomical Society, are the basis of all observation. To these
are applied the Corrections for Refraction of Bradley or Bessel, and
those for Aberration, for Nutation, for Precession, of the best modern
astronomers. The observations so corrected enable the observer to
satisfy himself of the delicacy and fidelity of his measures of time
and space; his Clocks and his Arcs. But this being done, different
stars so observed can be compared with each other, and the astronomer
can then endeavor further to correct his fundamental
Elements;—his Catalogue, or his Tables of Corrections. In these
Tables, though previous discovery has ascertained the law, yet the
exact quantity, the constant or coefficient of the
formula, can be exactly fixed only by numerous observations and
comparisons. This is a labor which is still going on, and in which
there are differences of opinion on almost every point; but the amount
of these differences is the strongest evidence of the certainty and
exactness of those doctrines in which all agree. Thus Lindenau makes
the coefficient of Nutation rather less than nine seconds, which other
astronomers give as about nine seconds and three-tenths. The Tables of
Refraction are still the subject of much discussion, and of many
attempts at improvement. And after or amid these discussions, arise
questions whether there be not other corrections of which the law has
not yet been assigned. The most remarkable example of such questions
is the controversy concerning the existence of an Annual Parallax of
the fixed stars, which Brinkley asserted, and which Pond denied. Such
a dispute between two of the best modern observers, only proves that
the quantity in question, if it really exist, is of the same order as
the hitherto unsurmounted errors of instruments and corrections.
[2d Ed.] [The belief in an appreciable parallax of some of the
fixed 483 stars
appears to gain ground among astronomers. The parallax of 61
Cygni, as determined by Bessel, is 0″·34; about one-third of a
second, or 1⁄10000 of a degree. That of
α Centauri, as determined by Maclear, is 0″·9, or 1⁄4000 of a
degree.]
But besides the fixed stars and their corrections, the astronomer
has the motions of the planets for his field of action. The
established theories have given us tables of these, from which their
daily places are calculated and given in our Ephemerides, as the
Berliner Jahrbuch of Encke, or the Nautical Almanac,
published by the government of this country, the Connaissance des
Tems which appears at Paris, or the Effemeridi di Milano.
The comparison of the observed with the tabular place, gives us the
means of correcting the coefficients of the tables; and thus of
obtaining greater exactness in the constants of the solar system. But
these constants depend upon the mass and form of the bodies of which
the system is composed; and in this province, as well as in sidereal
astronomy, different determinations, obtained by different paths, may
be compared; and doubts may be raised and may be solved. In this way,
the perturbations produced by Jupiter on different planets gave rise
to a doubt whether his attraction be really proportional to his mass,
as the law of universal gravitation asserts. The doubt has been solved
by Nicolai and Encke in Germany, and by Airy in England. The mass of
Jupiter, as shown by the perturbations of Juno, of Vesta, and of
Encke’s Comet, and by the motion of his outermost Satellite, is found
to agree, though different from the mass previously received on the
authority of Laplace. Thus also Burckhardt, Littrow, and Airy, have
corrected the elements of the Solar Tables. In other cases, the
astronomer finds that no change of the coefficients will bring the
Tables and the observations to a coincidence;—that a new term in
the formula is wanting. He obtains, as far as he can, the law of this
unknown term; if possible, he traces it to some known or probable
cause. Thus Mr. Airy, in his examination of the Solar Tables, not only
found that a diminution of the received mass of Mars was necessary,
but perceived discordances which led him to suspect the existence of a
new inequality. Such an inequality was at length found to result
theoretically from the attraction of Venus. Encke, in his examination
of his comet, found a diminution of the periodic time in the
successive revolutions; from which he inferred the existence of a
resisting medium. Uranus still deviates from his tabular place, and
the cause remains yet to be discovered. (But see the Additions to this volume.) 484
Thus it is impossible that an assertion, false to any amount which
the existing state of observation can easily detect, should have any
abiding prevalence in astronomy. Such errors may long keep their
ground in any science which is contained mainly in didactic works, and
studied in the closet, but not acted upon elsewhere;—which is
reasoned upon much, but brought to the test of experiment rarely or
never. Here, on the contrary, an error, if it arise, makes its way
into the Tables, into the Ephemeris, into the observer’s nightly List,
or his sheet of Reductions; the evidence of sense flies in its face in
a thousand observatories; the discrepancy is traced to its source, and
soon disappears forever.
In this favored branch of knowledge, the most recondite and
delicate discoveries can no more suffer doubt or contradiction, than
the most palpable facts of sense which the face of nature offers to
our notice. The last great discovery in astronomy—the motion of
the stars arising from Aberration—is as obvious to the vast
population of astronomical observers in all parts of the world, as the
motion of the stars about the pole is to the casual night wanderer.
And this immunity from the danger of any large error in the received
doctrines, is a firm platform on which the astronomer can stand and
exert himself to reach perpetually further and further into the region
of the unknown.
The same scrupulous care and diligence in recording all that has
hitherto been ascertained, has been extended to those departments of
astronomy in which we have as yet no general principles which serve to
bind together our acquired treasures. These records may be considered
as constituting a Descriptive Astronomy; such are, for
instance, Catalogues of Stars, and Maps of the Heavens, Maps of the
Moon, representations of the appearance of the Sun and Planets as seen
through powerful telescopes, pictures of Nebulæ, of Comets, and the
like. Thus, besides the Catalogue of Fundamental Stars which may be
considered as standard points of reference for all observations of the
Sun, Moon, and Planets, there exist many large catalogues of smaller
stars. Flamsteed’s Historia Celestis, which much surpassed any
previous catalogue, contained above 3000 stars. But in 1801, the
French Histoire Céleste appeared, comprising observations of
50,000 stars. Catalogues or charts of other special portions of the
sky have been published more recently; and in 1825, the Berlin Academy
proposed to the astronomers of Europe to carry on this work by
portioning out the heavens among them.
[2d Ed.] [Before Flamsteed, the best Catalogue of the Stars was
485 Tycho Brahe’s,
containing the places of about 1000 stars, determined very roughly
with the naked eye. On the occasion of a project of finding the
longitude, which was offered to Charles II., in 1674, Flamsteed
represented that the method was quite useless, in consequence, among
other things, of the inaccuracy of Tycho’s places of the stars.
Flamsteed’s letters being shown King Charles, he was startled at the
assertion of the fixed stars’ places being false in the Catalogue, and
said, with some vehemence, “He must have them anew observed, examined,
and corrected for the use of his seamen.” This was the immediate
occasion of building Greenwich Observatory, and placing Flamsteed
there as an observer. Flamsteed’s Historia Celestis contained
above 3000 stars, observed with telescopic sights. It has recently
been republished with important improvements by Mr. Baily. See Baily’s
Flamsteed, p. 38.
The French Histoire Céleste was published in 1801 by
Lalande, containing 50,000 stars, simply as observed by himself and
other French astronomers. The reduction of the observations contained
in this Catalogue to the mean places at the beginning of the year 1800
may be effected by means of Tables published by Schumacher for that
purpose in 1825.
In 1807, Piazzi’s Catalogue of 6748 stars, founded on Maskelyne’s
Catalogue of 1700, was published; afterwards extended to 7646 stars in
1814. This is considered as the greatest work undertaken by any modern
astronomer; the observations being well made, reduced, and compared
with those of former astronomers. Piazzi’s Catalogue is the standard
and accurate Catalogue, as the Histoire Céleste is the standard
approximate Catalogue for small stars. But the new planets were
discovered mostly by a comparison of the heavens with Bode’s (Berlin)
Catalogue.
I may mention other Catalogues of Stars which have recently been
published. Pond’s Catalogue contains 1112 Northern stars; Johnson’s,
606; Wrottesley’s, 1318 (in Right Ascension only); Airy’s First
Cambridge Catalogue, 726; his Greenwich Catalogue, 1439. Pearson’s has
520 zodiacal stars; Groombridge’s, 4243 circumpolar stars as far as 50
degrees of North Polar distance; Santini’s, a zone 18 degrees North of
the equator. Besides these, Mr. Taylor has published, by order of the
Madras government, a Catalogue of 11,000 stars observed by him at
Madras; and Rumker, who observed in the Observatory established by Sir
Thomas Brisbane at Paramatta (in Australia), has commenced a Catalogue
which is to contain 12,000. Mr. Baily 486 published two Standard Catalogues; that
of the Royal Astronomical Society, containing 2881 stars; and that of
the British Association, containing 8377 stars. I omit other
Catalogues, as those of Argelander, &c., and Catalogues of
Southern Stars.
Of the Berlin Maps, fourteen hours in Right Ascension have been
published; and their value may be judged of by this circumstance, that
it was in a great measure by comparing the heavens with these Maps
that the new planet Astræa was discovered. The Zone observations made
at Königsberg, by the late illustrious astronomer Bessel, deserve to
be mentioned, as embracing a vast number of stars.
The common mode of designating the Stars is founded upon the
ancient constellations as given by Ptolemy; to which Bayer, of
Augsburg, in his Uranometria, added the artifice of designating
the brightest stars in each constellation by the Greek letters, α, β,
γ, &c., applied in order of brightness, and when these were
exhausted, the Latin letters. Flamsteed used numbers. As the number of
observed stars increased, various methods were employed for
designating them; and the confusion which has been thus introduced,
both with regard to the boundaries of the constellations and the
nomenclature of the stars in each, has been much complained of lately.
Some attempts have been made to remedy this variety and disorder. Mr.
Argelander has recently recorded stars, according to their magnitudes
as seen by the naked eye, in a Neue Uranometrie.
Among representations of the Moon I may mention Hevelius’s
Selenographia, a work of former times, and Beer and Madler’s
Map of the Moon, recently published.]
I have already said something of the
observations of the two Herschels on Double Stars, which have
led to a knowledge of the law of the revolution of such systems. But
besides these, the same illustrious astronomers have accumulated
enormous treasures of observations of Nebulæ; the materials, it
may be, hereafter, of some vast new generalization with respect to the
history of the system of the universe.
[2d Ed.] [A few measures of Double Stars are to be found in
previous astronomical records. But the epoch of the creation of this
part of the science of astronomy must be placed at the beginning of
the present century, when Sir William Herschel (in 1802) published in
the Phil. Trans. a Catalogue of 500 new Nebulæ of various
classes, and in the Phil. Trans. 1803, a paper “On the changes
in the relative situation of the Double Stars in 25 years.” In
succeeding papers he pursued the subject. In one in 1814 he noticed
the breaking up of the 487 Milky Way in different places,
apparently from some principle of Attraction; and in this, and in one
in 1817, he published those remarkable views on the distribution of
the stars in our own cluster as forming a large stratum, and on the
connection of stars and nebulæ (the stars appearing sometimes to be
accompanied by nebulæ, sometimes to have absorbed a part of the
nebula, and sometimes to have been formed from nebulæ), which have
been accepted and propounded by others as the Nebular Theory.
Sir William Herschel’s last paper was a Catalogue of 145 new Double
Stars communicated to the Astronomical Society in 1822. In 1827 M.
Struve, of Dorpat (in Russia), published his Catalogus Novus,
containing the places of 3112 double stars. While this was going on,
Sir John Herschel and Sir James South published (in the Phil.
Trans. 1824) accurate measures of 380 Double and Triple Stars, to
which Sir J. South afterwards added 458. Mr. Dunlop published measures
of 253 Southern Double Stars. Other Observations have been published
by Capt. Smyth, Mr. Dawes, &c. The great work of Struve,
Mensuræ Micrometricæ, &c., contains 3134 such objects,
including most of Sir W. Herschel’s Double Stars. Sir J. Herschel in
1826, 7, and 8 presented to the Astronomical Society about 1000
measures of Double Stars; and in 1830, good measures of 1236, made
with his 20-feet reflector. His paper in vol. v. of the Ast. Soc.
Mem., besides measures of 364 such stars, exhibits all the most
striking results, as to the motion of Double Stars, which have yet
been obtained. In 1835 he carried his 20-feet reflector to the Cape of
Good Hope for the purpose of completing the survey of Double Stars and
Nebulæ in the southern hemisphere with the same instruments which had
explored the northern skies. He returned from the Cape in 1838, and is
now (1846) about to give the world the results of his labors. Besides
the stars just mentioned, his work will contain from 1500 to 2000
additional double stars; making a gross number of above 8000; in which
of course are included a number of objects of no great scientific
interest, but in which also are contained the materials of the most
important discoveries which remain to be made by astronomers. The
publication of Sir John Herschel’s great work upon Double Stars and
Nebulæ is looked for with eager interest by astronomers.
Of the observations of Nebulæ we may say what has just been said of
the observations of Double Stars;—that they probably contain the
materials of important future discoveries. It is impossible not to
regard these phenomena with reference to the Nebular
Hypothesis, which has been propounded by Laplace, and much more
strongly 488
insisted upon by other persons;—namely, the hypothesis that
systems of revolving planets, of which the Solar System is an example,
arise from the gradual contraction and separation of vast masses of
nebulous matter. Yet it does not appear that any changes have been
observed in nebulæ which tend to confirm this hypothesis; and the most
powerful telescope in the world, recently erected by the Earl of
Rosse, has given results which militate against the hypothesis;
inasmuch as it has shown that what appeared a diffused nebulous mass
is, by a greater power of vision, resolved, in all cases yet examined,
into separate stars.
When astronomical phenomena are viewed with reference to the
Nebular Hypothesis, they do not belong so properly to Astronomy, in
the view here taken of it, as to Cosmogony. If such speculations
should acquire any scientific value, we shall have to arrange them
among those which I have called Palætiological Sciences;
namely, those Sciences which contemplate the universe, the earth, and
its inhabitants, with reference to their historical changes and the
causes of those changes.]


ADDITIONS TO THE THIRD EDITION.
</div></body></text></TEI>