<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="150">CHAPTER VII.
Animal Morphology.
THE subject of Animal
Morphology has recently been expanded into a form strikingly
comprehensive and systematic by Mr. Owen; and supplied by him with a
copious and carefully-chosen language; which in his hands facilitates
vastly the comparison and appreciation of the previous labors of
physiologists, and opens the way to new truths and philosophical
generalizations. Though the steps which have been made had been
prepared by previous anatomists, I will borrow my view of them mainly
from him; with the less scruple, inasmuch as he has brought into full
view the labors of his predecessors.
I have stated in the History that the
skeletons of all vertebrate animals are conceived to be reducible to a
single Type, and the skull reducible to a series of vertebræ. But
inasmuch as this reduction includes not only a detailed correspondence
of the bones of man with those of beasts, but also with those of
birds, fishes, and reptiles, it may easily be conceived that the
similarities and connexions are of a various and often remote kind.
The views of such relations, held by previous Comparative Anatomists,
have led to the designations of the bones of animals which have been
employed in anatomical descriptions; and these designations having
been framed and adopted by anatomists looking at the subject from
different sides, and having different views of analogies and
relations, have been very various and unstable; besides being often of
cumbrous length and inconvenient form.
The corresponding parts in different animals are called
homologues, 639 a term first applied to anatomy by the
philosophers of Germany; and this term Mr. Owen adopts, to the
exclusion of terms more loosely denoting identity or similarity. And
the Homology of the various bones of vertebrates having been in a
great degree determined by the labors of previous anatomists, Mr. Owen
has proposed names for each of the bones: the condition of such names
being, that the homologues in all vertebrates shall be called by the
same name, and that these names shall be founded upon the terms and
phrases in which the great anatomists of the 16th, 17th, and 18th
centuries expressed the results of their researches respecting the
human skeleton. These names, thus selected, so far as concerned the
bones of the Head of Fishes, one of the most difficult cases of this
Special Homology, he published in a Table,44 in which they
were compared, in parallel columns, with the names or phrases used for
the like purpose by Cuvier, Agassiz, Geoffroy, Hallman, Sœmmering,
Meckel, and Wagner. As an example of the considerations by which this
selection of names was determined, I may quote what he says with
regard to one of these bones of the skull.
44 Lectures on Vertebrates.
1846, p. 158. And On the Archetype and Homologies of the Vertebrate
Skeleton. 1848, p. 172.
“With regard to the ‘squamosal’ (squamosum. Lat. pars
squamosa ossis temporis.—Sœmmering), it might be asked why the
term ‘temporal’ might not be retained for this bone. I reply, because
that term has long been, and is now universally, understood in human
anatomy to signify a peculiarly anthropotomical coalesced congeries of
bones, which includes the ‘squamosal’ together with the ‘petrosal,’
the ‘tympanic,’ the ‘mastoid,’ and the ‘stylohyal.’ It seems
preferable, therefore, to restrict the signification of the term
‘temporal’ to the whole (in Man) of which the ‘squamosal’ is a part.
To this part Cuvier has unfortunately applied the term ‘temporal’ in
one class, and ‘jugal’ in another; and he has also transferred the
term ‘temporal’ to a third equally distinct bone in fishes; while to
increase the confusion M. Agassiz has shifted the name to a fourth
different bone in the skull of fishes. Whatever, therefore, may be the
value assigned to the arguments which will be presently set forth, as
to the special homologies of the ‘pars squamosa ossis temporis,’ I
have felt compelled to express the conclusion by a definite term, and
in the present instance, have selected that which recalls the best
accepted anthropomorphical designation of the part; although
‘squamosal’ must be understood and applied in an arbitrary sense; and
not as descriptive of a scale-like 640 form; which in reference to the bone so
called, is rather its exceptional than normal figure in the vertebrate
series.”
The principles which Mr. Owen here adopts in the selection of names
for the parts of the skeleton are wise and temperate. They agree with
the aphorisms concerning the language of science which I published in
the Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences; and Mr. Owen does me
the great honor of quoting with approval some of those Aphorisms. I
may perhaps take the liberty of remarking that the system of terms
which he has constructed, may, according to our principles, be called
rather a Terminology than a Nomenclature: that is, they are
analogous more nearly to the terms by which botanists describe
the parts and organs of plants, than to the names by which they
denote genera and species. As we have seen in the History, plants as
well as animals are subject to morphological laws; and the names which
are given to organs in consequence of those laws are a part of the
Terminology of the science. Nor is this distinction between
Terminology and Nomenclature without its use; for the rules of
prudence and propriety in the selection of words in the two cases are
different. The Nomenclature of genera and species may be arbitrary and
casual, as is the case to a great extent in Botany and in Zoology,
especially of fossil remains; names being given, for instance, simply
as marks of honor to individuals. But in a Terminology, such a mode of
derivation is not admissible: some significant analogy or idea must be
adopted, at least as the origin of the name, though not necessarily
true in all its applications, as we have seen in the case of the
“squamosal” just quoted. This difference in the rules respecting two
classes of scientific words is stated in the Aphorisms xiii.
and xiv. concerning the Language of Science.
Such a Terminology of the bones of the skeletons of all vertebrates
as Mr. Owen has thus propounded, cannot be otherwise than an immense
acquisition to science, and a means of ascending from what we know
already to wider truths and new morphological doctrines.
With regard to one of these doctrines, the resolution of the human
head into vertebræ, Mr. Owen now regards it as a great truth, and
replies to the objections of Cuvier and M. Agassiz, in detail.45 He gives a Table in which the Bones of
the Head are resolved into four vertebræ, which he terms the
Occipital, Parietal, Frontal, and Nasal Vertebra, respectively. These
four vertebræ agree in general with what Oken called the Ear-vertebra,
the Jaw-vertebra, the Eye-vertebra, and 641 the Nose-vertebra, in his work On the
Signification of the Bones of the Skull, published in 1807: and in
various degrees, with similar views promulgated by Spix (1815),
Bojanus (1818), Geoffroy (1824), Carus (1828). And I believe that
these views, bold and fanciful as they at first appeared, have now
been accepted by most of the principal physiologists of our time.
45 Archetype and Homologies of the
Vertebrate Skeleton. 1848, p. 141.
But another aspect of this generalization has been propounded among
physiologists; and has, like the others, been extended, systematized,
and provided with a convenient language by Mr. Owen. Since animal
skeletons are thus made up of vertebræ and their parts are to be
understood as developements of the parts of vertebræ, Geoffroy (1822),
Carus (1828), Müller (1834), Cuvier (1836), had employed certain terms
while speaking of such developements; Mr. Owen in the Geological
Transactions in 1838, while discussing the osteology of certain
fossil Saurians, used terms of this kind, which are more systematic
than those of his predecessors, and to which he has given currency by
the quantity of valuable knowledge and thought which he has embodied
in them.
According to his Terminology,46 a vertebra, in
its typical completeness, consists of a central part or
centrum; at the back of this, two plates (the neural
apophyses) and a third outward projecting piece (the neural
spine), which three, with the centrum, form a canal for the spinal
marrow; at the front of the centrum two other plates (the hæmal
apophyses) and a projecting piece, forming a canal for a vascular
trunk. Further lateral elements (pleuro-apophyses) and other
projections, are in a certain sense dependent on these principal
bones; besides which the vertebra may support diverging
appendages. These parts of the vertebra are fixed together, so
that a vertebra is by some anatomists described as a single bone; but
the parts now mentioned are usually developed from distinct and
independent centres, and are therefore called by Mr. Owen “autogenous”
elements.
46 Archetype and Homologies of the
Vertebrate Skeleton. 1848, p. 81.
The General Homology of the vertebral skeleton is the
reference of all the parts of a skeleton to their true types in a
series of vertebræ: and thus, as special homology refers all
the parts of skeletons to a given type of skeleton, say that of Man,
general homology refers all the parts of every skeleton, say
that of Man, to the parts of a series of Vertebræ. And thus as Oken
propounded his views of the Head as a resolution of the Problem of
the Signification of the Bones of the Head, 642 so have we in like
manner, for the purposes of General Homology, to solve the Problem of
the Signification of Limbs. The whole of the animal being a
string of vertebræ, what are arms and legs, hands and paws, claws and
fingers, wings and fins, and the like? This inquiry Mr. Owen has
pursued as a necessary part of his inquiries. In giving a public
lecture upon the subject in 1849,47 he conceived
that the phrase which I have just employed would not be clearly
apprehended by an English Audience, and entitled his Discourse “On the
Nature of Limbs:” and in this discourse he explained the
modifications by which the various kinds of limbs are derived from
their rudiments in an archetypal skeleton, that is, a mere series of
vertebræ without head, arms, legs, wings, or fins.
47 On the Nature of Limbs, a
discourse delivered at a Meeting of the Royal Institution, 1849.
Final Causes
It has been mentioned in the History that in the discussions which
took place concerning the Unity of Plan of animal structure, this
principle was in some measure put in opposition to the principle of
Final Causes: Morphology was opposed to Teleology. It is natural to
ask whether the recent study of Morphology has affected this
antithesis.
If there be advocates of Final Causes in Physiology who would push
their doctrines so far as to assert that every feature and every
relation in the structure of animals have a purpose discoverable by
man, such reasoners are liable to be perpetually thwarted and
embarrassed by the progress of anatomical knowledge; for this progress
often shows that an arrangement which had been explained and admired
with reference to some purpose, exists also in cases where the purpose
disappears; and again, that what had been noted as a special
teleological arrangement is the result of a general morphological law.
Thus to take an example given by Mr. Owen: that the ossification of
the head originates in several centres, and thus in its early stages
admits of compression, has been pointed out as a provision to
facilitate the birth of viviparous animals; but our view of this
provision is disturbed, when we find that the same mode of the
formation of the bony framework takes place in animals which are born
from an egg. And the number of points from which ossification begins,
depends in a wider sense on the general homology of the animal frame,
according to which each part is composed of a certain number of
autogenous vertebral elements. In this 643 way, the admission of a new view as to
Unity of Plan will almost necessarily displace or modify some of the
old views respecting Final Causes.
But though the view of Final Causes is displaced, it is not
obliterated; and especially if the advocate of Purpose is also ready
to admit visible correspondences which have not a discoverable object,
as well as contrivances which have. And in truth, how is it possible
for the student of anatomy to shut his eyes to either of these two
evident aspects of nature? The arm and hand of man are made for taking
and holding, the wing of the sparrow is made for flying; and each is
adapted to its end with subtle and manifest contrivance. There is
plainly Design. But the arm of man and the wing of the sparrow
correspond to each other in the most exact manner, bone for bone.
Where is the Use or the Purpose of this correspondence? If it be said
that there may be a purpose though we do not see it, that is granted.
But Final Causes for us are contrivances of which we
see the end; and nothing is added to the evidence of Design by
the perception of a unity of plan which in no way tends to promote the
design.
It may be said that the design appears in the modification of the
plan in special ways for special purposes;—that the vertebral
plan of an animal being given, the fore limbs are modified in Man and
in Sparrow, as the nature and life of each require. And this is truly
said; and is indeed the truth which we are endeavoring to bring into
view:—that there are in such speculations, two elements; one
given, the other to be worked out from our examination of the case;
the datum and the problem; the homology and the
teleology.
Mr. Owen, who has done so much for the former of these portions of
our knowledge, has also been constantly at the same time contributing
to the other. While he has been aiding our advances towards the Unity
of Nature, he has been ever alive to the perception of an Intelligence
which pervades Nature. While his morphological doctrines have moved
the point of view from which he sees Design, they have never obscured
his view of it, but, on the contrary, have led him to present it to
his readers in new and striking aspects. Thus he has pointed out the
final purposes in the different centres of ossification of the long
bones of the limbs of mammals, and shown how and why they differ in
this respect from reptiles (Archetype, p. 104). And in this way
he has been able to point out the insufficiency of the rule laid down
both by Geoffroy St. Hilaire and Cuvier, for ascertaining the true
number of bones in each species. 644
Final Causes, or Evidences of Design, appear, as we have said, not
merely as contrivances for evident purposes, but as modifications of a
given general Plan for special given ends. If the general Plan be
discovered after the contrivance has been noticed, the discovery may
at first seem to obscure our perception of Purpose; but it will soon
be found that it merely transfers us to a higher point of view. The
adaptation of the Means to the End remains, though the Means are parts
of a more general scheme than we were aware of. No generalization of
the Means can or ought permanently to shake our conviction of the End;
because we must needs suppose that the Intelligence which contemplates
the End is an intelligence which can see at a glance along a vista of
Means, however long and complex. And on the other hand, no special
contrivance, however clear be its arrangement, can be unconnected with
the general correspondences and harmonies by which all parts of nature
are pervaded and bound together. And thus no luminous teleological
point can be extinguished by homology; nor, on the other hand, can it
be detached from the general expanse of homological light.
The reference to Final Causes is sometimes spoken of as
unphilosophical, in consequence of Francis Bacon’s comparison of Final
Causes in Physics to Vestal Virgins devoted to God, and barren. I have
repeatedly shown that, in Physiology, almost all the great discoveries
which have been made, have been made by the assumption of a purpose in
animal structures. With reference to Bacon’s simile, I have elsewhere
said that if he had had occasion to develope its bearings, full of
latent meaning as his similes so often are, he would probably have
said that to those Final Causes barrenness was no reproach, seeing
they ought to be not the Mothers but the Daughters of our Natural
Sciences; and that they were barren, not by imperfection of their
nature, but in order that they might be kept pure and undefiled, and
so fit ministers in the temple of God. I might add that in Physiology,
if they are not Mothers, they are admirable Nurses; skilful and
sagacious in perceiving the signs of pregnancy, and helpful in
bringing the Infant Truth into the light of day.
There is another aspect of the doctrine of the Archetypal Unity of
Composition of Animals, by which it points to an Intelligence from
which the frame of nature proceeds; namely this:—that the
Archetype of the Animal Structure being of the nature of an
Idea, implies a mind in which this Idea existed; and that thus
Homology itself points the way to the Divine Mind. But while we
acknowledge the full 645 value of this view of theological
bearing of physiology, we may venture to say that it is a view quite
different from that which is described by speaking of “Final Causes,”
and one much more difficult to present in a lucid manner to ordinary
minds.


BOOK XVIII.


GEOLOGY.

WITH regard to Geology, as a
Palætiological Science, I do not know that any new light of an
important kind has been thrown upon the general doctrines of the
science. Surveys and examinations of special phenomena and special
districts have been carried on with activity and intelligence; and the
animals of which the remains people the strata, have been
reconstructed by the skill and knowledge of zoologists:—of such
reconstructions we have, for instance, a fine assemblage in the
publications of the Palæontological Society. But the great questions
of the manner of the creation and succession of animal and vegetable
species upon the earth remain, I think, at the point at which they
were when I published the last edition of the History.
I may notice the views propounded by some chemists of certain
bearings of Mineralogy upon Geology. As we have, in mineral masses,
organic remains of former organized beings, so have we crystalline
remains of former crystals; namely, what are commonly called
pseudomorphoses—the shape of one crystal in the substance
of another. M. G. Bischoff48 considers the study of pseudomorphs as
important in geology, and as frequently the only means of tracing
processes which have taken place and are still going on in the mineral
kingdom.
48 Chemical and Physical
Geology.
I may notice also Professor Breithaupt’s researches on the order of
succession of different minerals, by observing the mode in which they
occur and the order in which different crystals have been deposited,
promise to be of great use in following out the geological changes
which the crust of the globe has undergone. (Die Paragenesis der
Mineralien. Freiberg. 1849.)
In conjunction with these may be taken M. de Senarmont’s
experiments on the formation of minerals in veins; and besides
Bischoff’s 647
Chemical Geology, Sartorius von Walterhausen’s Observations on
the occurrence of minerals in Amygdaloid.
As a recent example of speculations concerning Botanical
Palætiology, I may give Dr. Hooker’s views of the probable history of
the Flora of the Pacific.
In speculating upon this question, Dr. Hooker is led to the
discussion of geological doctrines concerning the former continuity of
tracts of land which are now separate, the elevation of low lands into
mountain ranges in the course of ages, and the like. We have already
seen, in the speculations of the late lamented Edward Forbes, (see
Book xviii. chap. vi. of this History,) an
example of a hypothesis propounded to account for the existing Flora
of England: a hypothesis, namely, of a former Connexion of the West of
the British Isles with Portugal, of the Alps of Scotland with those of
Scandinavia, and of the plains of East Anglia with those of Holland.
In like manner Dr. Hooker says (p. xxi.) that he was led to speculate
on the possibility of the plants of the Southern Ocean being the
remains of a Flora that had once spread over a larger and more
continuous tract of land than now exists in the ocean; and that the
peculiar Antarctic genera and species may be the vestiges of a Flora
characterized by the predominance of plants which are now scattered
throughout the Southern islands. He conceives this hypothesis to be
greatly supported by the observations and reasonings of Mr. Darwin,
tending to show that such risings and sinkings are in active progress
over large portions of the continents and islands of the Southern
hemisphere: and by the speculations of Sir C. Lyell respecting the
influence of climate on the migrations of plants and animals, and the
influence of geological changes upon climate.
In Zoology I may notice (following Mr. Owen)49 recent
discoveries of the remains of the animals which come nearest to man in
their structure. At the time of Cuvier’s death, in 1832, no evidence
had been obtained of fossil Quadrumana; and he supposed that these, as
well as Bimana, were of very recent introduction. Soon after, in the
oldest (eocene) tertiary deposits of Suffolk, remains were found
proving the existence of a monkey of the genus Macacus. In the
Himalayan tertiaries were found petrified bones of a Semnopithecus; in
Brazil, remains of an extinct platyrhine monkey of great size; and
lastly, in the middle tertiary series of the South of France, was
discovered a fragment of the jaw of the long-armed ape
(Hylobates). But no fossil human 648 remains have been discovered in the
regularly deposited layers of any divisions (not even the pleiocene) of
the tertiary series; and thus we have evidence that the placing of man
on the earth was the last and peculiar act of Creation.
49 Brit. Asso. 1854, p.
112.
THE END.

Transcriber’s Notes
Whewell’s book was originally published in 3 volumes in London in
1837. A second edition appeared in 1847, and a third in 1857. A
2-volume version of the 3rd edition was published in New York in 1858,
reprinted 1875. This Project Gutenberg text, combining both volumes in
sequence, was derived from the 1875 version, relying upon resources
kindly provided by the Internet Archive. In so doing, the Contents of
Volume 2 have been moved to follow the Contents of Volume 1.
Three items have been added to the Contents of the First Volume;
they are marked off by ~ ~. Whewell’s additions to the 3rd edition
were printed by way of appendices to the volumes. An indication that
such an addition may be found has been given, again marked off by ~ ~,
and linked to the relevant text. Any infelicities in these and other
internal links are the transcriber’s responsibility.
Where ditto signs were used in the text, the material has been
repeated in full.
Printed page numbers have been transcribed in colour. Where words
were hyphenated across pages, the number has been placed before the word.
Fractions have been transcribed as numerator⁄denominator,
occasionally using parentheses to disambiguate. The original sometimes
has numerator over a line with denominator below, at other times
numerator hyphen denominator.
Footnotes in the original text were numbered by chapter; here they
have been numbered by Book (counting the preface and the appendices to
each volume as a separate book and incorporating the Introduction with
Book I). They are placed after the paragraph in which they occur.
Corrections to the text are flagged in the .htm version by dotted red
underline, on mouse-over revealing the nature of the change. They were
usually confirmed by reference to English printings of the text.
Inconsistencies, especially with respect to accents and formatting,
are numerous and have in general not been adjusted, though Greek
quotations have been checked against other versions where
available. Nor have Whewell's unbalanced quotation marks been modernised.
The English versions have been used to restore Whewell’s “gesperrt” emphases
in some Greek passages.

</div></body></text></TEI>