<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="15">CHAPTER I.
On the Indistinctness of Ideas of the Middle
Ages.
THAT firm and entire
possession of certain clear and distinct general ideas which is
necessary to sound science, was the character of the minds of those
among the ancients who created the several sciences which arose among
them. It was indispensable that such inventors should have a luminous
and steadfast apprehension of certain general relations, such as those
of space and number, order and cause; and should be able to apply
these notions with perfect readiness and precision to special facts
and cases. It is necessary that such scientific notions should be more
definite and precise than those which common language conveys; and in
this state of unusual clearness, they must be so familiar to the
philosopher, that they are the language in which he thinks. The
discoverer is thus led to doctrines which other men adopt and follow
out, in proportion as they seize the fundamental ideas, and become
acquainted with the leading facts. Thus Hipparchus, conceiving clearly
the motions and combinations of motion which enter into his theory,
saw that the relative lengths of the seasons were sufficient data for
determining the form of the sun’s orbit; thus Archimedes, possessing a
steady notion of mechanical pressure, was able, not only to deduce the
properties of the lever and of the centre of gravity, but also to see
the truth of those principles respecting the distribution of pressure
in fluids, on which the science of hydrostatics depends.
With the progress of such distinct ideas, the inductive sciences
rise and flourish; with the decay and loss of such distinct ideas,
these sciences become stationary, languid, and retrograde. When men
merely repeat the terms of science, without attaching to them any
clear conceptions;—when their apprehensions become vague and
dim;—when they assent to scientific doctrines as a matter of
tradition, rather than of conviction, on trust rather than on
sight;—when science is considered as a collection of opinions,
rather than a record of laws by which the universe is really
governed;—it must inevitably happen, that men will lose their
hold on the knowledge which the great discoverers who preceded them
have brought to light. They are not able to push forwards the truths
on which they lay so 187 feeble and irresolute a hand; probably
they cannot even prevent their sliding back towards the obscurity from
which they had been drawn, or from being lost altogether. Such
indistinctness and vacillation of thought appear to have prevailed in
the stationary period, and to be, in fact, intimately connected with
its stationary character. I shall point out some indications of the
intellectual peculiarity of which I speak.
1. Collections of Opinions.—The fact, that mere
Collections of the opinions of physical philosophers came to hold a
prominent place in literature, already indicated a tendency to an
indistinct and wandering apprehension of such opinions. I speak of
such works as Plutarch’s five Books “on the Opinions of Philosophers,”
or the physical opinions which Diogenes Laërtius gives in his “Lives
of the Philosophers.” At an earlier period still, books of this kind
appear; as for instance, a large portion of Pliny’s Natural History, a
work which has very appropriately been called the Encyclopædia of
Antiquity; even Aristotle himself is much in the habit of enumerating
the opinions of those who had preceded him. To present such statements
as an important part of physical philosophy, shows an erroneous and
loose apprehension of its nature. For the only proof of which its
doctrines admit, is the possibility of applying the general theory to
each particular case; the authority of great men, which in moral and
practical matters may or must have its weight, is here of no force;
and the technical precision of ideas which the terms of a sound
physical theory usually demand, renders a mere statement of the
doctrines very imperfectly intelligible to readers familiar with
common notions only. To dwell upon such collections of opinions,
therefore, both implies, and produces, in writers and readers, an
obscure and inadequate apprehension of the full meaning of the
doctrines thus collected; supposing there be among them any which
really possess such a clearness, solidity, and reality, as to make
them important in the history of science. Such diversities of opinion
convey no truth; such a multiplicity of statements of what has been
said, in no degree teaches us what is; such
accumulations of indistinct notions, however vast and varied, do not
make up one distinct idea. On the contrary, the habit of dwelling upon
the verbal expressions of the views of other persons, and of being
content with such an apprehension of doctrines as a transient notice
can give us, is fatal to firm and clear thought: it indicates wavering
and feeble conceptions, which are inconsistent with speculation. 188
We may, therefore, consider the prevalence of Collections of the
kind just referred to, as indicating a deficiency of philosophical
talent in the ages now under review. As evidence of the same
character, we may add the long train of publishers of Abstracts,
Epitomes, Bibliographical Notices, and similar writers. All such
writers are worthless for all purposes of science, and their
labors may be considered as dead works; they have in them no principle
of philosophical vitality; they draw their origin and nutriment from
the death of true physical knowledge; and resemble the swarms of
insects that are born from the perishing carcass of some noble
animal.
2. Indistinctness of Ideas in Mechanics.—But the
indistinctness of thought which is so fatal a feature in the intellect
of the stationary period, may be traced more directly in the works,
even of the best authors, of those times. We find that they did not
retain steadily the ideas on which the scientific success of the
previous period had depended. For instance, it is a remarkable
circumstance in the history of the science of Mechanics, that it did
not make any advance from the time of Archimedes to that of Stevinus
and Galileo. Archimedes had established the doctrine of the lever;
several persons tried, in the intermediate time, to prove the property
of the inclined plane, and none of them succeeded. But let us look to
the attempts; for example, that of Pappus, in the eighth Book of his
Mathematical Collections, and we may see the reason of the failure.
His Problem shows, in the very terms in which it is propounded, the
want of a clear apprehension of the subject. “Having given the power
which will draw a given weight along the horizontal plane, to find the
additional power which will draw the same weight along a given
inclined plane.” This is proposed without previously defining how
Powers, producing such effects, are to be measured; and as if the
speed with which the body were drawn, and the nature of the surface of
the plane, were of no consequence. The proper elementary Problem is,
To find the force which will support a body on a smooth
inclined plane; and no doubt the solution of Pappus has more reference
to this problem than to his own. His reasoning is, however, totally at
variance with mechanical ideas on any view of the problem. He supposes
the weight to be formed into a sphere; and this sphere being placed in
contact with the inclined plane, he assumes that the effect will be
the same as if the weight were supported on a horizontal lever, the
fulcrum being the point of contact of the sphere with the plane, and
the power acting at the circumference of the sphere. Such an
assumption implies an entire 189 absence of those distinct ideas of force
and mechanical pressure, on which our perception of the identity or
difference of different modes of action must depend;—of those
ideas by the help of which Archimedes had been able to demonstrate the
properties of the lever, and Stevinus afterwards discovered the true
solution of the problem of the inclined plane. The motive to Pappus’s
assumption was probably no more than this;—he perceived that the
additional power, which he thus obtained, vanished when the plane
became horizontal, and increased as the inclination became greater.
Thus his views were vague; he had no clear conception of mechanical
action, and he tried a geometrical conjecture. This is not the way to
real knowledge.
Pappus (who lived about a. d. 400) was one
of the best mathematicians of the Alexandrian school; and, on subjects
where his ideas were so indistinct, it is not likely that any much
clearer were to be found in the minds of his contemporaries.
Accordingly, on all subjects of speculative mechanics, there appears
to have been an entire confusion and obscurity of thought till modern
times. Men’s minds were busy in endeavoring to systematize the
distinctions and subtleties of the Aristotelian school, concerning
Motion and Power; and, being thus employed among doctrines in which
there was involved no definite meaning capable of real
exemplification, they, of course, could not acquire sound physical
knowledge. We have already seen that the physical opinions of
Aristotle, even as they came from him, had no proper scientific
precision. His followers, in their endeavors to perfect and develop
his statements, never attempted to introduce clearer ideas than those
of their master; and as they never referred, in any steady manner, to
facts, the vagueness of their notions was not corrected by any
collision with observation. The physical doctrines which they
extracted from Aristotle were, in the course of time, built up into a
regular system; and though these doctrines could not be followed into
a practical application without introducing distinctions and changes,
such as deprived the terms of all steady signification, the dogmas
continued to be repeated, till the world was persuaded that they were
self-evident; and when, at a later period, experimental philosophers,
such as Galileo and Boyle, ventured to contradict these current
maxims, their new principles sounded in men’s ears as strange as they
now sound familiar. Thus Boyle promulgated his opinions on the
mechanics of fluids, as “Hydrostatical Paradoxes, proved and
illustrated by experiments.” And the opinions which he there opposes,
are those which the Aristotelian philosophers habitually propounded as
certain 190 and
indisputable; such, for instance, as that “in fluids the upper parts
do not gravitate on the lower;” that “a lighter fluid will not
gravitate on a heavier;” that “levity is a positive quality of bodies
as well as gravity.” So long as these assertions were left uncontested
and untried, men heard and repeated them, without perceiving the
incongruities which they involved: and thus they long evaded
refutation, amid the vague notions and undoubting habits of the
stationary period. But when the controversies of Galileo’s time had
made men think with more acuteness and steadiness, it was discovered
that many of these doctrines were inconsistent with themselves, as
well as with experiment. We have an example of the confusion of
thought to which the Aristotelians were liable, in their doctrine
concerning falling bodies. “Heavy bodies,” said they, “must fall
quicker than light ones; for weight is the cause of their fall, and
the weight of the greater bodies is greater.” They did not perceive
that, if they considered the weight of the body as a power acting to
produce motion, they must consider the body itself as offering a
resistance to motion; and that the effect must depend on the
proportion of the power to the resistance; in short, they had no clear
idea of accelerating force. This defect runs through all
their mechanical speculations, and renders them entirely
valueless.
We may exemplify the same confusion of thought on mechanical
subjects in writers of a less technical character. Thus, if men had
any distinct idea of mechanical action, they could not have accepted
for a moment the fable of the Echineis or Remora, a little fish which
was said to be able to stop a large ship merely by sticking to it.1
Lucan refers to this legend in a poetical manner, and notices this
creature only in bringing together a collection of monstrosities; but
Pliny relates the tale gravely, and moralizes upon it after his
manner. “What,” he cries,2 “is more violent than the sea and the
winds? what a greater work of art than a ship? Yet one little fish
(the Echineis) can hold back all these when they all strain the same
way. The winds may 191 blow, the waves may rage; but this small
creature controls their fury, and stops a vessel, when chains and
anchors would not hold it: and this it does, not by hard labor, but
merely by adhering to it. Alas, for human vanity! when the turreted
ships which man has built, that he may fight from castle-walls, at sea
as well as at land, are held captive and motionless by a fish a foot
and a half long! Such a fish is said to have stopped the admiral’s
ship at the battle of Actium, and compelled Antony to go into another.
And in our own memory, one of these animals held fast the ship of
Caius, the emperor, when he was sailing from Astura to Antium. The
stopping of this ship, when all the rest of the fleet went on, caused
surprise; but this did not last long, for some of the men jumped into
the water to look for the fish, and found it sticking to the rudder;
they showed it to Caius, who was indignant that this animal should
interpose its prohibition to his progress, when impelled by four
hundred rowers. It was like a slug; and had no power, after it was
taken into the ship.”
1 Lucan is describing one of the
poetical compounds produced in incantations.


Huc quicquid fœtu genuit Natura sinistro
Miscetur: non spuma canum quibus unda timori
est,
Viscera non lyncis, non duræ nodus hyænæ
Defuit, et cervi pasti serpente medullæ;
Non puppes retinens, Euro tendente rudentes
In mediis Echineis aquis, oculique
draconum.
Etc.
          
Pharsalia, vi. 670.


2 Plin. Hist. N. xxxii. 5.
A very little advance in the power of thinking clearly on the force
which it exerted in pulling, would have enabled the Romans to see that
the ship and its rowers must pull the adhering fish by the hold the
oars had upon the water; and that, except the fish had a hold equally
strong on some external body, it could not resist this force.
3. Indistinctness of Ideas shown in
Architecture.—Perhaps it may serve to illustrate still
further the extent to which, under the Roman empire, men’s notions of
mechanical relations became faint, wavered, and disappeared, if we
observe the change which took place in architecture. All architecture,
to possess genuine beauty, must be mechanically consistent. The
decorative members must represent a structure which has in it a
principle of support and stability. Thus the Grecian colonnade was a
straight horizontal beam, resting on vertical props; and the pediment
imitated a frame like a roof, where oppositely inclined beams support
each other. These forms of building were, therefore, proper models of
art, because they implied supporting forces. But to be content with
colonnades and pediments, which, though they imitated the forms of the
Grecian ones, were destitute of their mechanical truth, belonged to
the decline of art; and showed that men had lost the idea of force,
and retained only that of shape. Yet this was what the architects of
the Roman empire did. Under their hands, the pediment was severed at
its vertex, and divided into separate halves, so that it was no longer
a mechanical possibility. The entablature no longer lay straight from
pillar to pillar, but, projecting over each 192 column, turned back to the wall, and
adhered to it in the intervening space. The splendid remains of
Palmyra, Balbec, Petra, exhibit endless examples of this kind of
perverse inventiveness; and show us, very instructively, how the decay
of art and of science alike accompany this indistinctness of ideas
which we are now endeavoring to illustrate.
4. Indistinctness of Ideas in Astronomy.—Returning to
the sciences, it may be supposed, at first sight, that, with regard to
astronomy, we have not the same ground for charging the stationary
period with indistinctness of ideas on that subject, since they were
able to acquire and verify, and, in some measure, to apply, the
doctrines previously established. And, undoubtedly, it must be
confessed that men’s notions of the relations of space and number are
never very indistinct. It appears to be impossible for these chains of
elementary perception ever to be much entangled. The later Greeks, the
Arabians, and the earliest modern astronomers, must have conceived the
hypotheses of the Ptolemaic system with tolerable completeness. And
yet, we may assert, that during the stationary period, men did not
possess the notions, even of space and number, in that vivid and
vigorous manner which enables them to discover new truths. If they had
perceived distinctly that the astronomical theorist had merely to do
with relative motions, they must have been led to see the
possibility, at least, of the Copernican system; as the Greeks, at an
earlier period, had already perceived it. We find no trace of this.
Indeed, the mode in which the Arabian mathematicians present the
solutions of their problems, does not indicate that clear apprehension
of the relations of space, and that delight in the contemplation of
them, which the Greek geometrical speculations imply. The Arabs are in
the habit of giving conclusions without demonstrations, precepts
without the investigations by which they are obtained; as if their
main object were practical rather than speculative,—the
calculation of results rather than the exposition of theory.
Delambre3 has been obliged to exercise great
ingenuity, in order to discover the method by which Ibn Iounis proved
his solution of certain difficult problems.
3 Delamb. M. A. p.
125–8.
5. Indistinctness of Ideas shown by Skeptics.—The same
unsteadiness of ideas which prevents men from obtaining clear views,
and steady and just convictions, on special subjects, may lead them to
despair of or deny the possibility of acquiring certainty at all, and
may thus make them skeptics with regard to all knowledge. Such
skeptics 193 are
themselves men of indistinct views, for they could not otherwise avoid
assenting to the demonstrated truths of science; and, so far as they
may be taken as specimens of their contemporaries, they prove that
indistinct ideas prevail in the age in which they appear. In the
stationary period, moreover, the indefinite speculations and
unprofitable subtleties of the schools might further impel a man of
bold and acute mind to this universal skepticism, because they offered
nothing which could fix or satisfy him. And thus the skeptical spirit
may deserve our notice as indicative of the defects of a system of
doctrine too feeble in demonstration to control such resistance.
The most remarkable of these philosophical skeptics is Sextus
Empiricus; so called, from his belonging to that medical sect which
was termed the empirical, in contradistinction to the
rational and methodical sects. His works contain a
series of treatises, directed against all the divisions of the science
of his time. He has chapters against the Geometers, against the
Arithmeticians, against the Astrologers, against the Musicians, as
well as against Grammarians, Rhetoricians, and Logicians; and, in
short, as a modern writer has said, his skepticism is employed as a
sort of frame-work which embraces an encyclopedical view of human
knowledge. It must be stated, however, that his objections are rather
to the metaphysical grounds, than to the details of the sciences; he
rather denies the possibility of speculative truth in general, than
the experimental truths which had been then obtained. Thus his
objections to geometry and arithmetic are founded on abstract cavils
concerning the nature of points, letters, unities, &c. And when he
comes to speak against astrology, he says, “I am not going to consider
that perfect science which rests upon geometry and arithmetic; for I
have already shown the weakness of those sciences: nor that faculty of
prediction (of the motions of the heavens) which belongs to the pupils
of Eudoxus, and Hipparchus, and the rest, which some call Astronomy;
for that is an observation of phenomena, like agriculture or
navigation: but against the Art of Prediction from the time of birth,
which the Chaldeans exercise.” Sextus, therefore, though a skeptic by
profession, was not insensible to the difference between experimental
knowledge and mystical dogmas, though even the former had nothing
which excited his admiration.
The skepticism which denies the evidence of the truths of which the
best established physical sciences consist, must necessarily involve a
very indistinct apprehension of those truths; for such truths,
properly exhibited, contain their own evidence, and are the best
antidote 194 to
this skepticism. But an incredulity or contempt towards the asserted
truths of physical science may arise also from the attention being
mainly directed to the certainty and importance of religious truths. A
veneration for revealed religion may thus assume the aspect of a
skepticism with regard to natural knowledge. Such appears to be the
case with Algazel or Algezeli, who is adduced by Degerando4
as an example of an Arabian skeptic. He was a celebrated teacher at
Bagdad in the eleventh century, and he declared himself the enemy, not
only of the mixed Peripatetic and Platonic philosophy of the time, but
of Aristotle himself. His work entitled The Destructions of the
Philosophers, is known to us by the refutation of it which
Averrhoes published, under the title of Destruction of Algazel’s
Destructions of the Philosophers. It appears that he contested the
fundamental principles both of the Platonic and of the Aristotelian
schools, and denied the possibility of a known connection between
cause and effect; thus making a prelude, says Degerando, to the
celebrated argumentation of Hume.
4 Degerando, Hist. Comp. de
Systèmes, iv. 224.
[2d Ed.] Since the publication of my first edition, an account of
Algazel or Algazzali and his works has been published under the title
of Essai sur les Ecoles Philosophiques chez les Arabes, et
notamment sur la Doctrine d’Algazzali, par August Schmölders.
Paris. 1842. From this book it appears that Degerando’s account of
Algazzali is correct, when he says5 that “his
skepticism seems to have essentially for its object to destroy all
systems of merely rational theology, in order to open an indefinite
career, not only to faith guided by revelation, but also to the free
exaltation of a mystical enthusiasm.” It is remarked by Dr.
Schmölders, following M. de Hammer-Purgstall, that the title of the
work referred to in the text ought rather to be Mutual Refutation
of the Philosophers: and that its object is to show that
Philosophy consists of a mass of systems, each of which overturns the
others. The work of Algazzali which Dr. Schmölders has published,
On the Errors of Sects, &c., contains a kind of
autobiographical account of the way in which the author was led to his
views. He does not reject the truths of science, but he condemns the
mental habits which are caused by laying too much stress upon science.
Religious men, he says, are, by such a course, led to reject all
science, even what relates to eclipses of the moon and sun; and men of
science are led to hate religion.6
5 Hist. Comp. iv. p. 227.
6 Essai, p. 33.
195 6.
Neglect of Physical Reasoning in Christendom.—If the
Arabians, who, during the ages of which we are speaking, were the most
eminent cultivators of science, entertained only such comparatively
feeble and servile notions of its doctrines, it will easily be
supposed, that in the Christendom of that period, where physical
knowledge was comparatively neglected, there was still less
distinctness and vividness in the prevalent ideas on such subjects.
Indeed, during a considerable period of the history of the Christian
Church, and by many of its principal authorities, the study of natural
philosophy was not only disregarded but discommended. The great
practical doctrines which were presented to men’s minds, and the
serious tasks, of the regulation of the will and affections, which
religion impressed upon them, made inquiries of mere curiosity seem to
be a reprehensible misapplication of human powers; and many of the
fathers of the Church revived, in a still more peremptory form, the
opinion of Socrates, that the only valuable philosophy is that which
teaches us our moral duties and religious hopes.7 Thus Eusebius
says,8 “It is not through ignorance of the
things admired by them, but through contempt of their useless labor,
that we think little of these matters, turning our souls to the
exercise of better things.” When the thoughts were thus intentionally
averted from those ideas which natural philosophy involves, the ideas
inevitably became very indistinct in their minds; and they could not
conceive that any other persons could find, on such subjects, grounds
of clear conviction and certainty. They held the whole of their
philosophy to be, as Lactantius9 asserts it to be,
“empty and false.” “To search,” says he, “for the causes of natural
things; to inquire whether the sun be as large as he seems, whether
the moon is convex or concave, whether the stars are fixed in the sky
or float freely in the air; of what size and of what material are the
heavens; whether they be at rest or in motion; what is the magnitude
of the earth; on what foundations it is suspended and
balanced;—to dispute and conjecture on such matters, is just as
if we chose to discuss what we think of a city in a remote country, of
which we never heard but the name.” It is impossible to express more
forcibly that absence of any definite notions on physical subjects
which led to this tone of thought.
7 Brucker, iii. 317.
8 Præp. Ev. xv. 61.
9 Inst. 1. iii. init.
7. Question of Antipodes.—With such habits of thought,
we are not to be surprised if the relations resulting from the best
established theories were apprehended in an imperfect and incongruous
manner. 196 We have
some remarkable examples of this; and a very notable one is the
celebrated question of the existence of Antipodes, or persons
inhabiting the opposite side of the globe of the earth, and
consequently having the soles of their feet directly opposed to ours.
The doctrine of the globular form of the earth results, as we have
seen, by a geometrical necessity, from a clear conception of the
various points of knowledge which we obtain, bearing upon that
subject. This doctrine was held distinctly by the Greeks; it was
adopted by all astronomers, Arabian and European, who followed them;
and was, in fact, an inevitable part of every system of astronomy
which gave a consistent and intelligible representation of phenomena.
But those who did not call before their minds any distinct
representation at all, and who referred the whole question to other
relations than those of space, might still deny this doctrine; and
they did so. The existence of inhabitants on the opposite side of the
terraqueous globe, was a fact of which experience alone could teach
the truth or falsehood; but the religious relations, which extend
alike to all mankind, were supposed to give the Christian philosopher
grounds for deciding against the possibility of such a race of men.
Lactantius,10 in the fourth century, argues this
matter in a way very illustrative of that impatience of such
speculations, and consequent confusion of thought, which we have
mentioned. “Is it possible,” he says, “that men can be so absurd as to
believe that the crops and trees on the other side of the earth hang
downwards, and that men there have their feet higher than their heads?
If you ask of them how they defend these monstrosities—how
things do not fall away from the earth on that side—they reply,
that the nature of things is such that heavy bodies tend towards the
centre, like the spokes of a wheel, while light bodies, as clouds,
smoke, fire, tend from the centre towards the heavens on all sides.
Now I am really at a loss what to say of those who, when they have
once gone wrong, steadily persevere in their folly, and defend one
absurd opinion by another.” It is obvious that so long as the writer
refused to admit into his thoughts the fundamental conception of their
theory, he must needs be at a loss what to say to their arguments
without being on that account in any degree convinced of their
doctrines.
10 Inst. 1. iii. 23.
In the sixth century, indeed, in the reign of Justinian, we find a
writer (Cosmas Indicopleustes11) who does not
rest in this obscurity of 197 representation; but in this case, the
distinctness of the pictures only serves to show his want of any clear
conception as to what suppositions would explain the phenomena. He
describes the earth as an oblong floor, surrounded by upright walls,
and covered by a vault, below which the heavenly bodies perform their
revolutions, going round a certain high mountain, which occupies the
northern parts of the earth, and makes night by intercepting the light
of the sun. In Augustin12 (who flourished a.
d. 400) the opinion is treated on other grounds; and without
denying the globular form of the earth, it is asserted that there are
no inhabitants on the opposite side, because no such race is recorded
by Scripture among the descendants of Adam.13 Considerations
of the same kind operated in the well-known instance of Virgil, Bishop
of Salzburg, in the eighth century. When he was reported to Boniface,
Archbishop of Mentz, as holding the existence of Antipodes, the
prelate was shocked at the assumption, as it seemed to him, of a world
of human beings, out of the reach of the conditions of salvation; and
application was made to Pope Zachary for a censure of the holder of
this dangerous doctrine. It does not, however, appear that this led to
any severity; and the story of the deposition of Virgil from his
bishopric, which is circulated by Kepler and by more modern writers,
is undoubtedly altogether false. The same scruples continued to
prevail among Christian writers to a later period; and Tostatus14 notes the opinion of the rotundity of
the earth as an “unsafe” doctrine, only a few years before Columbus
visited the other hemisphere.
11 Montfaucon, Collectio Nova
Patrum, t. ii. p. 113. Cosmas Indicopleustes. Christianorum
Opiniones de Mundo, sive Topographia Christiana.
12 Civ. D. xvi. 9.
13 It appears, however, that
scriptural arguments were found on the other side. St. Jerome says
(Comm. in Ezech. i. 6), speaking of the two cherubims with four
faces, seen by the prophet, and the interpretation of the vision:
“Alii vero qui philosophorum stultam sequuntur sapientiam, duo
hemispheria in duobus templi cherubim, nos et antipodes, quasi supinos
et cadentes homines suspicantur.”
14 Montfauc. Patr. t. ii.
8. Intellectual Condition of the Religious Orders.—It
must be recollected, however, that though these were the views and
tenets of many religious writers, and though they may be taken as
indications of the prevalent and characteristic temper of the times of
which we speak, they never were universal. Such a confusion of thought
affects the minds of many persons, even in the most enlightened times;
and in what we call the Dark Ages, though clear views on such subjects
might be more rare, those who gave their minds to science, entertained
the true opinion of the figure of the earth. Thus Boëthius15 (in the sixth century) urges the
smallness of the globe of the earth, 198 compared with the heavens, as a reason
to repress our love of glory. This work, it will be recollected, was
translated into the Anglo-Saxon by our own Alfred. It was also
commented on by Bede, who, in what he says on this passage, assents to
the doctrine, and shows an acquaintance with Ptolemy and his
commentators, both Arabian and Greek. Gerbert, in the tenth century,
went from France to Spain to study astronomy with the Arabians, and
soon surpassed his masters. He is reported to have fabricated clocks,
and an astrolabe of peculiar construction. Gerbert afterwards (in the
last year of the first thousand from the birth of Christ) became pope,
by the name of Sylvester II. Among other cultivators of the sciences,
some of whom, from their proficiency, must have possessed with
considerable clearness and steadiness the elementary ideas on which it
depends, we may here mention, after Montucla,16 Adelbold, whose
work On the Sphere was addressed to Pope Sylvester, and whose
geometrical reasonings are, according to Montucla,17 vague and
chimerical; Hermann Contractus, a monk of St Gall, who, in 1050,
published astronomical works; William of Hirsaugen, who followed his
example in 1080; Robert of Lorraine, who was made Bishop of Hereford
by William the Conqueror, in consequence of his astronomical
knowledge. In the next century, Adelhard Goth, an Englishman,
travelled among the Arabs for purposes of study, as Gerbert had done
in the preceding age; and on his return, translated the Elements of
Euclid, which he had brought from Spain or Egypt. Robert Grostête,
Bishop of Lincoln, was the author of an Epitome on the Sphere; Roger
Bacon, in his youth the contemporary of Robert, and of his brother
Adam Marsh, praises very highly their knowledge in mathematics.
15 Boëthius, Cons. ii. pr.
7.
16 Mont. i. 502.
17 Ib. i. 503.
“And here,” says the French historian of mathematics, whom I have
followed in the preceding relation, “it is impossible not to reflect
that all those men who, if they did not augment the treasure of the
sciences, at least served to transmit it, were monks, or had been such
originally. Convents were, during these stormy ages, the asylum of
sciences and letters. Without these religious men, who, in the silence
of their monasteries, occupied themselves in transcribing, in
studying, and in imitating the works of the ancients, well or ill,
those works would have perished; perhaps not one of them would have
come down to us. The thread which connects us with the Greeks and
Romans would have been snapt asunder; the precious productions of
199 ancient
literature would no more exist for us, than the works, if any there
were, published before the catastrophe that annihilated that highly
scientific nation, which, according to Bailly, existed in remote ages
in the centre of Tartary, or at the roots of Caucasus. In the sciences
we should have had all to create; and at the moment when the human
mind should have emerged from its stupor and shaken off its slumbers,
we should have been no more advanced than the Greeks were after the
taking of Troy.” He adds, that this consideration inspires feelings
towards the religious orders very different from those which, when he
wrote, were prevalent among his countrymen.
Except so far as their religious opinions interfered, it was
natural that men who lived a life of quiet and study, and were
necessarily in a great measure removed from the absorbing and blinding
interests with which practical life occupies the thoughts, should
cultivate science more successfully than others, precisely because
their ideas on speculative subjects had time and opportunity to become
clear and steady. The studies which were cultivated under the name of
the Seven Liberal Arts, necessarily tended to favor this effect. The
Trivium,18 indeed, which consisted of Grammar,
Logic, and Rhetoric, had no direct bearing upon those ideas with which
physical science is concerned; but the Quadrivium, Music,
Arithmetic, Geometry, Astronomy, could not be pursued with any
attention, without a corresponding improvement of the mind for the
purposes of sound knowledge.19
18 Bruck. iii. 597.
19 Roger Bacon, in his Specula
Mathematica, cap. i., says “Harum scientiarum porta et clavis est
mathematica, quam sancti a principio mundi invenerunt, etc. Cujus
negligentia jam per triginta vel quadraginta annos destruxit
totum studium Latinorum.” I do not know on what occasion this neglect
took place.
9. Popular Opinions.—That, even in the best
intellects, something was wanting to fit them for scientific progress
and discovery, is obvious from the fact that science was so long
absolutely stationary. And I have endeavored to show that one part of
this deficiency was the want of the requisite clearness and vigor of
the fundamental scientific ideas. If these were wanting, even in the
most powerful and most cultivated minds, we may easily conceive that
still greater confusion and obscurity prevailed in the common class of
mankind. They actually adopted the belief, however crude and
inconsistent, that the form of the earth and heavens really is what at
any place it appears to be; that the earth is flat, and the waters of
the sky sustained above a material floor, through which in showers
they descend. Yet the true doctrines of 200 astronomy appear to have had some
popular circulation. For instance, a French poem of the time of Edward
the Second, called Ymage du Monde, contains a metrical account
of the earth and heavens, according to the Ptolemaic views; and in a
manuscript of this poem, preserved in the library of the University of
Cambridge, there are representations, in accordance with the text, of
a spherical earth, with men standing upright upon it on every side;
and by way of illustrating the tendency of all things to the centre,
perforations of the earth, entirely through its mass, are described
and depicted; and figures are exhibited dropping balls down each of
these holes, so as to meet in the interior. And, as bearing upon the
perplexity which attends the motions of up and down,
when applied to the globular earth, and the change of the direction of
gravity which would occur in passing the centre, the readers of Dante
will recollect the extraordinary manner in which the poet and his
guide emerge from the bottom of the abyss; and the explanation which
Virgil imparts to him of what he there sees. After they have crept
through the aperture in which Lucifer is placed, the poet says,


“Io levai gli occhi e credetti vedere
Lucifero com’ io l’ avea lasciato,
E vidile le gambe in su tenere.”
.  .  .  .  “Questi come è
fitto
Si sottasopra!” .  .  .  . 
.
“Quando mi volsi, tu passast’ il punto
Al qual si traggon d’ ogni parte i pesi.”
Inferno, xxxiv. 

 .  .  .  . “I raised mine
eyes,
Believing that I Lucifer should see
Where he was lately left, but saw him now
With legs held upward.” .  .  . .

“How standeth he in posture thus reversed?”
.  .  .  .  .  . 
.  .  .  .  .  .  .  .
“Thou wast on the other side so long as I
Descended; when I turned, thou didst
o’erpass
That point to which from every part is
dragged
All heavy substance.” Cary.      

This is more philosophical than Milton’s representation, in a more
scientific age, of Uriel sliding to the earth on a sunbeam, and
sliding back again, when the sun had sunk below the horizon.


.  .  .  .  .  “Uriel to his
charge
Returned on that bright beam whose point now
raised,
Bore him slope downward to the sun, now
fallen
Beneath the Azores.”  Par. Lost, B.
iv.    201
The philosophical notions of up and down are too much at variance
with the obvious suggestions of our senses, to be held steadily and
justly by minds undisciplined in science. Perhaps it was some
misunderstood statement of the curved surface of the ocean, which gave
rise to the tradition of there being a part of the sea directly over
the earth, from which at times an object has been known to fall or an
anchor to be let down. Even such whimsical fancies are not without
instruction, and may serve to show the reader what that vagueness and
obscurity of ideas is, of which I have been endeavoring to trace the
prevalence in the dark ages.
We now proceed to another of the features which appears to me to
mark, in a very prominent manner, the character of the stationary
period.
</div></body></text></TEI>