<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="6">
NOVUM ORGANON RENOVATUM.

BOOK II.
OF THE CONSTRUCTION OF SCIENCE.


CHAPTER I.
Of two principal Processes by which Science is constructed.
Aphorism I.
THE two processes by which Science is constructed are
the Explication of Conceptions, and the Colligation of
Facts.
TO the subject of the present and next Book all that
has preceded is subordinate and preparatory. In
former works we have treated of the History of Scientific
Discoveries and of the History of Scientific Ideas. We
have now to attempt to describe the manner in which
discoveries are made, and in which Ideas give rise to
knowledge. It has already been stated that Knowledge
requires us to possess both Facts and Ideas;—that
every step in our knowledge consists in applying the
Ideas and Conceptions furnished by our minds to the
Facts which observation and experiment offer to us.
When our Conceptions are clear and distinct, when our
Facts are certain and sufficiently numerous, and when
the Conceptions, being suited to the nature of the 28
Facts, are applied to them so as to produce an exact
and universal accordance, we attain knowledge of a
precise and comprehensive kind, which we may term
Science. And we apply this term to our knowledge
still more decidedly when, Facts being thus included
in exact and general Propositions, such Propositions
are, in the same manner, included with equal rigour
in Propositions of a higher degree of Generality; and
these again in others of a still wider nature, so as to
form a large and systematic whole.
But after thus stating, in a general way, the nature
of science, and the elements of which it consists, we
have been examining with a more close and extensive
scrutiny, some of those elements; and we must now
return to our main subject, and apply to it the results
of our long investigation. We have been exploring
the realm of Ideas; we have been passing in review
the difficulties in which the workings of our own minds
involve us when we would make our conceptions consistent
with themselves: and we have endeavoured to
get a sight of the true solutions of these difficulties.
We have now to inquire how the results of these long
and laborious efforts of thought find their due place in
the formation of our Knowledge. What do we gain
by these attempts to make our notions distinct and
consistent; and in what manner is the gain of which
we thus become possessed, carried to the general treasure-house
of our permanent and indestructible knowledge? After all this
battling in the world of ideas,
all this struggling with the shadowy and changing
forms of intellectual perplexity, how do we secure to
ourselves the fruits of our warfare, and assure ourselves
that we have really pushed forwards the frontier of
the empire of Science? It is by such an appropriation,
that the task which we have had in our hands
during the two previous works, (the History of the
Inductive Sciences and the History of Scientific Ideas,)
must acquire its real value and true place in our design.
In order to do this, we must reconsider, in a more
definite and precise shape, the doctrine which has
already been laid down;—that our Knowledge consists 29
in applying Ideas to Facts; and that the conditions of
real knowledge are that the ideas be distinct and appropriate,
and exactly applied to clear and certain
facts. The steps by which our knowledge is advanced
are those by which one or the other of these two processes
is rendered more complete;—by which Conceptions are made more
clear in themselves, or by which
the Conceptions more strictly bind together the Facts.
These two processes may be considered as together constituting
the whole formation of our knowledge; and
the principles which have been established in the History of
Scientific Ideas bear principally upon the former
of these two operations;—upon the business of elevating
our conceptions to the highest possible point of precision
and generality. But these two portions of the
progress of knowledge are so clearly connected with
each other, that we shall deal with them in immediate
succession. And having now to consider these operations
in a more exact and formal manner than it was
before possible to do, we shall designate them by certain
constant and technical phrases. We shall speak
of the two processes by which we arrive at science, as
the Explication of Conceptions and the Colligation of
Facts: we shall show how the discussions in which we
have been engaged have been necessary in order to
promote the former of these offices; and we shall
endeavour to point out modes, maxims, and principles
by which the second of the two tasks may also be furthered.
</div></body></text></TEI>