<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="1">CHAPTER I.
Geology defined—Compared to History—Its relation to other Physical Sciences—Not
to be confounded with Cosmogony.
Geology is the science which investigates the successive changes that
have taken place in the organic and inorganic kingdoms of nature; it
inquires into the causes of these changes, and the influence which they
have exerted in modifying the surface and external structure of our planet.
By these researches into the state of the earth and its inhabitants at
former periods, we acquire a more perfect knowledge of its present condition,
and more comprehensive views concerning the laws now governing
its animate and inanimate productions. When we study history, we
obtain a more profound insight into human nature, by instituting a comparison
between the present and former states of society. We trace the
long series of events which have gradually led to the actual posture of
affairs; and by connecting effects with their causes, we are enabled to
classify and retain in the memory a multitude of complicated relations—the
various peculiarities of national character—the different degrees of
moral and intellectual refinement, and numerous other circumstances,
which, without historical associations, would be uninteresting or imperfectly
understood. As the present condition of nations is the result of
many antecedent changes, some extremely remote, and others recent,
some gradual, others sudden and violent; so the state, of the natural
world is the result of a long succession of events; and if we would enlarge
our experience of the present economy of nature, we must investigate
the effects of her operations in former epochs.
We often discover with surprise, on looking back into the chronicles
of nations, how the fortune of some battle has influenced the fate of
millions of our contemporaries, when it has long been forgotten by the
mass of the population. With this remote event we may find inseparably
connected the geographical boundaries of a great state, the language
now spoken by the inhabitants, their peculiar manners, laws, and
religious opinions. But far more astonishing and unexpected are the
connections brought to light, when we carry back our researches into
the history of nature. The form of a coast, the configuration of the in2terior
of a country, the existence and extent of lakes, valleys, and mountains,
can often be traced to the former prevalence of earthquakes and
volcanoes in regions which have long been undisturbed. To these remote
convulsions the present fertility of some districts, the sterile character of
others, the elevation of land above the sea, the climate, and various peculiarities,
may be distinctly referred. On the other hand, many distinguishing
features of the surface may often be ascribed to the operation,
at a remote era, of slow and tranquil causes—to the gradual deposition
of sediment in a lake or in the ocean, or to the prolific increase of testacea
and corals.
To select another example, we find in certain localities subterranean
deposits of coal, consisting of vegetable matter, formerly drifted into
seas and lakes. These seas and lakes have since been filled up, the lands
whereon the forests grew have disappeared or changed their form, the
rivers and currents which floated the vegetable masses can no longer be
traced, and the plants belonged to species which for ages have passed
away from the surface of our planet. Yet the commercial prosperity,
and numerical strength of a nation, may now be mainly dependent on
the local distribution of fuel determined by that ancient state of things.
Geology is intimately related to almost all the physical sciences, as
history is to the moral. An historian should, if possible, be at once profoundly
acquainted with ethics, politics, jurisprudence, the military art,
theology; in a word, with all branches of knowledge by which any insight
into human affairs, or into the moral and intellectual nature of man,
can be obtained. It would be no less desirable that a geologist should
be well versed in chemistry, natural philosophy, mineralogy, zoology,
comparative anatomy, botany; in short, in every science relating to organic
and inorganic nature. With these accomplishments, the historian
and geologist would rarely fail to draw correct and philosophical conclusions
from the various monuments transmitted to them of former occurrences.
They would know to what combination of causes analogous
effects were referable, and they would often be enabled to supply, by
inference, information concerning many events unrecorded in the defective
archives of former ages. But as such extensive acquisitions are
scarcely within the reach of any individual, it is necessary that men who
have devoted their lives to different departments should unite their
efforts; and as the historian receives assistance from the antiquary, and
from those who have cultivated different branches of moral and political
science, so the geologist should avail himself of the aid of many naturalists,
and particularly of those who have studied the fossil remains of lost
species of animals and plants.
The analogy, however, of the monuments consulted in geology, and
those available in history, extends no farther than to one class of historical
monuments—those which may be said to be undesignedly commemorative
of former events. The canoes, for example, and stone hatchets
found in our peat bogs, afford an insight into the rude arts and manners
of the earliest inhabitants of our island; the buried coin fixes the date3
of the reign of some Roman emperor; the ancient encampment indicates
the districts once occupied by invading armies, and the former method
of constructing military defences; the Egyptian mummies throw light
on the art of embalming, the rites of sepulture, or the average stature
of the human race in ancient Egypt. This class of memorials yields to
no other in authenticity, but it constitutes a small part only of the resources
on which the historian relies, whereas in geology it forms the
only kind of evidence which is at our command. For this reason we
must not expect to obtain a full and connected account of any series of
events beyond the reach of history. But the testimony of geological
monuments, if frequently imperfect, possesses at least the advantage of
being free from all intentional misrepresentation. We may be deceived
in the inferences which we draw, in the same manner as we often mistake
the nature and import of phenomena observed in the daily course of nature;
but our liability to err is confined to the interpretation, and, if this
be correct, our information is certain.
It was long before the distinct nature and legitimate objects of geology
were fully recognized, and it was at first confounded with many other
branches of inquiry, just as the limits of history, poetry, and mythology
were ill-defined in the infancy of civilization. Even in Werner's time,
or at the close of the eighteenth century, geology appears to have been
regarded as little other than a subordinate department of mineralogy;
and Desmarest included it under the head of Physical Geography. But
the most common and serious source of confusion arose from the notion,
that it was the business of geology to discover the mode in which the
earth originated, or, as some imagined, to study the effects of those cosmological
causes which were employed by the Author of Nature to
bring this planet out of a nascent and chaotic state into a more perfect
and habitable condition. Hutton was the first who endeavored to draw
a strong line of demarcation between his favorite science and cosmogony,
for he declared that geology was in nowise concerned "with questions
as to the origin of things."
An attempt will be made in the sequel of this work to demonstrate
that geology differs as widely from cosmogony, as speculations concerning
the mode of the first creation of man differ from history. But, before
entering more at large on this controverted question, it will be desirable
to trace the progress of opinion on this topic, from the earliest
ages to the commencement of the present century.

4</div></body></text></TEI>