<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 168, folios 107-112</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 168, folios 107-112.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to Louisa Barwell</title>
          <date when="1841">5 January [1841]</date>
          <note type="place">Ockam</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 168, folios 107-112</note>
          <note type="recipient">Louisa Barwell</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_168_folios_107-112.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Ockham Tuesdy. 5th Jany</p>
      <p>My Dear Mrs. Barwell. I have long delayed replying to your last letter. Partly I have been this last fortnight much engaged with company. Partly I have been digesting in my large Causality the affairs of my children.-- I certainly do wish to make general enquiry for the great unknown whom we have agreed to be the grand desideratum. But I</p>
      <p>have given up any hope or indeed intention of finding such a person until July next. We intend to go to Town the end of Feby, &amp; even were I now immediately to meet with a desirable &amp; likely person, I could not feel satisfied to confide my children while in Town to her after a trial so short as 7 or 8 weeks. In London I can scarcely see them at all. The very construction of the house renders it next to impossible for me to do so, &amp; when to this we add my numerous</p>
      <p>engagements, I may say that the luncheon time is nearly the amount of attention I can give them there.-- I must therefore this year manage as I can, &amp; they will derive less mischief from too little superintendence than they would from improper superintendance.</p>
      <p>Anne Harmes, as far as she goes, is excellent; &amp; as there will be some regular occupations begun in Town this year which will occupy idle energies &amp; promote both health &amp; amusement, I think we may manage to jig on, especially with the assistance</p>
      <p>of the Miss Kings, who will I am sure bestow at any rate some attention on them.-- The occupations I intend trying for them are the Riding School, for both the elder ones; &amp; for Byron a commencement of the Piano-Forte. I believe I know of a young lady well adapted to teach the latter to a young child like Byron, &amp; I have reason to think he will be likely to take to it.--</p>
      <p>During the next 5 or 6 months we must endeavour to find a suitable assistant, &amp; I think we may in time succeed.-- I could tell you</p>
      <p>much about Byron that is most interesting. I wish you could now see him. He is altered wonderfully. An observation made by me during the last 3 weeks, on the very remarkable &amp; beneficial effects of company upon him, will not be lost on me.--</p>
      <p>Varied &amp; exciting social intercourse act like magic with him. His affable, communicative, manly, &amp; I may say elegant manners, charm people much; &amp; I have been pleased &amp; surprised with his whole</p>
      <p>deportment this last fortnight, &amp; that too at a time when the habits of his father &amp; mother, were as I thought producing a sad relapse into Self-Concentration, &amp; I was becoming very uneasy for a change. He takes much pleasure in relating things to others &amp; in receiving their sympathy; &amp; I also observe a spontaneous politeness towards Annabella occasionally, which is pleasing. If he hears her trying to open the door outside, he will generally run to do it for her, &amp; this quite unprompted.</p>
      <p>He is really sometimes very charming; but still the main thing for him is a constant gentle rousing &amp; excitement. I feel tht I have great influence with him, especially on all moral subjects. You know we are both of us to a certain extent philosophical, &amp; we understand each other exceedingly well;-- I believe children are often more philosophical than we suppose, if we only treat them as having at any rate the germs of common sense.</p>
      <p>Byron nearly upset all my</p>
      <p>philosophy however yesterday; for I was lecturing him on some improper conduct, of which he was explaining to me the motives; &amp; I remarked to him "But do you think that "was a good reason?" After a moment he answered very decisively, "No, do "think it was a naughty "reason", and he said it so very oddly, with such a comical mixture of candour, simplicity, &amp; earnestness, that I barely managed to be grave.--</p>
      <p>He is altogether a most singular child, &amp; I cannot but hope</p>
      <p>he has grand elements in him. By the bye I should remark that of late I think he is much more passionate than he used to be, which I do not regret. One wished to see a little more impulse &amp; laissez-aller about him.--</p>
      <p>I think you may be of essential service in writing to Miss King, to impress upon her the immense value she may be to Byron. It is not that she is backward in attending to</p>
      <p>him. Far from it;-- but it would be desirable that she should feel the whole of her importance, &amp; that is no little.--</p>
      <p>I expect the Miss Kings here about the 14th. They are now just returned to Town from visits in Sussex.</p>
      <p>Pray believe me</p>
      <p>Yours most sincerely A. A. Lovelace</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
