<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="46">CHAPTER XLVI.
BURYING OF FOSSILS IN ALLUVIAL DEPOSITS AND IN CAVES.
Fossils in alluvium—Effects of sudden inundations—terrestrial animals most
abundantly preserved in alluvium where earthquakes prevail—Marine alluvium—Buried
town—Effects of Landslips—Organic remains in fissures and
caves—Form and dimensions of caverns—their probable origin—Closed basins
and subterranean rivers of the Morea—Katavothra—Formation of breccias
with red cement—Human remains imbedded in Morea—Intermixture, in caves
of South of France and elsewhere, of human remains and bones of extinct
quadrupeds, no proof of former co-existence of man with those lost species.
Fossils in alluvium.—The next subject for our consideration, according
to the division before proposed, is the embedding of organic bodies
in alluvium.
The gravel, sand, and mud in the bed of a river does not often contain
any animal or vegetable remains; for the whole mass is so continually
shifting its place, and the attrition of the various parts is so great,
that even the hardest rocks contained in it are, at length, ground down
to powder. But when sand and sediment are suddenly swept by a flood,
and then let fall upon the land, such an alluvium may envelop trees or
the remains of animals, which, in this manner, are often permanently
preserved. In the mud and sand produced by the floods in Scotland, in
1829, the dead and mutilated bodies of hares, rabbits, moles, mice, partridges,
and even the bodies of men, were found partially buried.1034 But
in these and similar cases one flood usually effaces the memorials left by
another, and there is rarely a sufficient depth of undisturbed transported
matter, in any one spot, to preserve the organic remains for ages from
destruction.
Where earthquakes prevail, and the levels of a country are changed
from time to time, the remains of animals may more easily be inhumed
and protected from disintegration. Portions of plains, loaded with alluvial
accumulations by transient floods, may be gradually upraised; and,
if any organic remains have been imbedded in the transported materials,
they may, after such elevation, be placed beyond the reach of the erosive
power of streams. In districts where the drainage is repeatedly deranged
by subterranean movements, every fissure, every hollow caused by the
sinking in of land, becomes a depository of organic and inorganic substances,
hurried along by transient floods.
Marine alluvium.—In May, 1787, a dreadful inundation of the sea
was caused at Coringa, Ingeram, and other places, on the coast of Coromandel,
in the East Indies, by a hurricane blowing from the N. E., which
raised the waters so that they rolled inland to the distance of about
twenty miles from the shore, swept away many villages, drowned more
731
than 10,000 people, and left the country covered with marine mud, on
which the carcasses of about 100,000 head of cattle were strewed. An old
tradition of the natives of a similar flood, said to have happened about a
century before, was, till this event, regarded as fabulous by the European
settlers.1035 The same coast of Coromandel was, so late as May, 1832, the
scene of another catastrophe of the same kind; and when the inundation
subsided, several vessels were seen grounded in the fields of the low
country about Coringa.
Many of the storms termed hurricanes have evidently been connected
with submarine earthquakes, as is shown by the atmospheric phenomena
attendant on them, and by the sounds heard in the ground and the odors
emitted. Such were the circumstances which accompanied the swell of
the sea in Jamaica, in 1780, when a great wave desolated the western
coast, and bursting upon Savanna la Mar, swept away the whole town in
an instant, so that not a vestige of man, beast, or habitation, was seen
upon the surface.1036
Houses and works of art in alluvial deposits.—A very ancient subterranean
town, apparently of Hindoo origin, was discovered in India in
1833, in digging the Doab canal. Its site is north of Saharunpore, near
the town of Behat, and seventeen feet below the present surface of the
country. More than 170 coins of silver and copper have already been
found, and many articles in metal and earthenware. The overlying
deposit consisted of about five feet of river sand, with a substratum about
twelve feet thick of red alluvial clay. In the neighborhood are several
rivers and torrents, which descend from the mountains charged with vast
quantities of mud, sand, and shingle; and within the memory of persons
now living the modern Behat has been threatened by an inundation,
which, after retreating, left the neighboring country strewed over with
a superficial covering of sand several feet thick. In sinking wells in the
environs, masses of shingle and boulders have been reached resembling
those now in the river-channels of the same district, under a deposit of
thirty feet of reddish loam. Captain Cautley, therefore, who directed the
excavations, supposes that the matter discharged by torrents has gradually
raised the whole country skirting the base of the lower hills; and that the
ancient town, having been originally built in a hollow, was submerged by
floods, and covered over with sediment seventeen feet in thickness.1037
We are informed, by M. Boblaye, that in the Morea, the formation
termed céramique, consisting of pottery, tiles, and bricks, intermixed
with various works of art, enters so largely into the alluvium and vegetable
soil upon the plains of Greece, and into hard and crystalline breccias
which have been formed at the foot of declivities, that it constitutes
an important stratum which might, in the absence of zoological characters,
serve to mark our epoch in a most indestructible manner.1038
732
Landslips.—The landslip, by suddenly precipitating large masses of
rock and soil into a valley, overwhelms a multitude of animals, and
sometimes buries permanently whole villages, with their inhabitants and
large herds of cattle. Thus three villages, with their entire population,
were covered, when the mountain of Piz fell in 1772, in the district of
Treviso, in the state of Venice,1039 and part of Mount Grenier, south of
Chambery, in Savoy, which fell down in the year 1248, buried five
parishes, including the town and church of St. André, the ruins occupying
an extent of about nine square miles.1040
The number of lives lost by the slide of the Rossberg, in Switzerland,
in 1806, was estimated at more than 800, a great number of the bodies,
as well as several villages and scattered houses, being buried deep under
mud and rock. In the same country, several hundred cottages, with
eighteen of their inhabitants and a great number of cows, goats, and
sheep, were victims to the sudden fall of a bed of stones, thirty yards
deep, which descended from the summits of the Diablerets in Vallais.
In the year 1618, a portion of Mount Conto fell, in the county of Chiavenna,
in Switzerland, and buried the town of Pleurs with all its inhabitants,
to the number of 2430.
It is unnecessary to multiply examples of similar local catastrophes,
which however numerous they may have been in mountainous parts of
Europe, within the historical period, have been, nevertheless, of rare occurrence
when compared to events of the same kind which have taken place
in regions convulsed by earthquakes. It is then that enormous masses
of rock and earth, even in comparatively low and level countries, are
detached from the sides of valleys, and cast down into the river courses,
and often so unexpectedly that they overwhelm, even in the daytime,
every living thing upon the plains.
Preservation of Organic Remains in Fissures and Caves.
In the history of earthquakes it was shown that many hundreds of
new fissures and chasms had opened in certain regions during the last
150 years, some of which are described as being of unfathomable depth.
We also perceive that mountain masses have been violently fractured and
dislocated, during their rise above the level of the sea; and thus we may
account for the existence of many cavities in the interior of the earth by
the simple agency of earthquakes; but there are some caverns, especially
in limestone rocks, which, although usually, if not always, connected
with rents, are nevertheless of such forms, and dimensions, alternately
expanding into spacious chambers, and then contracting again into narrow
passages, that it is difficult to conceive that they can owe their origin
to the mere fracturing and displacement of solid masses.
In the limestone of Kentucky, in the basin of Green River, one of the
733
tributaries of the Ohio, a line of underground cavities has been traced
in one direction for a distance of ten miles, without any termination; and
one of the chambers, of which there are many, all connected by narrow
tunnels, is no less than ten acres in area and 150 feet in its greatest
height. Besides the principal series of "antres vast," there are a great
many lateral embranchments not yet explored.1041
The cavernous structure here alluded to is not altogether confined to
calcareous rocks; for it has lately been observed in micaceous and argillaceous
schist in the Grecian island of Thermia (Cythnos of the ancients),
one of the Cyclades. Here also spacious halls, with rounded and irregular
walls, are connected together by narrow passages or tunnels, and
there are many lateral branches which have no outlet. A current of
water has evidently at some period flowed through the whole, and left a
muddy deposit of bluish clay upon the floor; but the erosive action of
the stream cannot be supposed to have given rise to the excavations in
the first instance. M. Virlet suggests that fissures were first caused by
earthquakes, and that these fissures became the chimneys or vents for
the disengagement of gas, generated below by volcanic heat. Gases, he
observes, such as the muriatic, sulphuric, fluoric, and others, might, if
raised to a high temperature, alter and decompose the rocks which they
traverse. There are signs of the former action of such vapors in rents
of the micaceous schist of Thermia, and thermal springs now issue from
the grottoes of that island. We may suppose that afterwards the elements
of the decomposed rocks were gradually removed in a state of solution
by mineral waters; a theory which, according to M. Virlet, is confirmed
by the effect of heated gases which escape from rents in the isthmus of
Corinth, and which have greatly altered and corroded the hard siliceous
and jaspideous rocks.1042
When we reflect on the quantity of carbonate of lime annually poured
out by mineral waters, we are prepared to admit that large cavities must,
in the course of ages, be formed at considerable depths below the surface
in calcareous rocks.1043 These rocks, it will be remembered, are at once
more soluble, more permeable, and more fragile, than any others, at least
all the compact varieties are very easily broken by the movements of
earthquakes, which would produce only flexures in argillaceous strata.
Fissures once formed in limestone are not liable, as in many other formations,
to become closed up by impervious clayey matter, and hence a
stream of acidulous water might for ages obtain a free and unobstructed
passage.1044
Morea.—Nothing is more common in limestone districts than the
engulfment of rivers, which after holding a subterranean course for many
miles escape again by some new outlet. As they are usually charged
734
with fine sediment, and often with sand and pebbles where they enter,
whereas they are usually pure and limpid where they flow out again,
they must deposit much matter in empty spaces in the interior of the
earth. In addition to the materials thus introduced, stalagmite, or carbonate
of lime, drops from the roofs of caverns, and in this mixture the
bones of animals washed in by rivers are often entombed. In this manner
we may account for those bony breccias which we often find in caves,
some of which are of high antiquity while others are very recent and
in daily progress. In no district are engulfed streams more conspicuous
than in the Morea, where the phenomena attending them have been
lately studied and described in great detail by M. Boblaye and his fellow-laborers
of the French expedition to Greece.1045 Their account is peculiarly
interesting to geologists, because it throws light on the red osseous
breccias containing the bones of extinct quadrupeds which are so common
in almost all the countries bordering the Mediterranean. It appears that
the numerous caverns of the Morea occur in a compact limestone, of the
age of the English chalk, immediately below which are arenaceous strata
referred to the period of our greensand. In the more elevated districts
of that peninsula there are many deep land-locked valleys, or basins,
closed round on all sides by mountains of fissured and cavernous limestone.
The year is divided almost as distinctly as between the tropics
into a rainy season, which lasts upwards of four months, and a season of
drought of nearly eight months' duration. When the torrents are
swollen by the rains, they rush from surrounding heights into the inclosed
basins; but, instead of giving rise to lakes, as would be the case in most
other countries, they are received into gulfs or chasms, called by the
Greeks "Katavothra," and which correspond to what are termed "swallow-holes"
in the north of England. The water of these torrents is
charged with pebbles and red ochreous earth, resembling precisely the
well-known cement of the osseous breccias of the Mediterranean. It
dissolves in acids with effervescence, and leaves a residue of hydrated
oxide of iron, granular iron, impalpable grains of silex, and small crystals
of quartz. Soil of the same description abounds everywhere on the
surface of the decomposing limestone in Greece, that rock containing in
it much siliceous and ferruginous matter.
Many of the Katavothra being insufficient to give passage to all the
water in the rainy season, a temporary lake is formed round the mouth
of the chasm, which then becomes still farther obstructed by pebbles,
sand, and red mud, thrown down from the turbid waters. The lake
being thus raised, its waters generally escape through other openings, at
higher levels, around the borders of the plain, constituting the bottom of
the closed basin.
In some places, as at Kavaros and Tripolitza, where the principal discharge
is by a gulf in the middle of the plain, nothing can be seen over
the opening in summer, when the lake dries up, but a deposit of red
735
mud, cracked in all directions. But the Katavothron is more commonly
situated at the foot of the surrounding escarpment of limestone; and in
that case there is sometimes room enough to allow a person to enter, in
summer, and even to penetrate far into the interior. Within is seen a
suite of chambers, communicating with each other by narrow passages;
and M. Virlet relates, that in one instance he observed, near the entrance,
human bones imbedded in recent red mud, mingled with the remains of
plants and animals of species now inhabiting the Morea. It is not
wonderful, he says, that the bones of man should be met with in such
receptacles; for so murderous have been the late wars in Greece, that
skeletons are often seen lying exposed on the surface of the country.1046
In summer, when no water is flowing into the Katavothron, its mouth,
half closed up with red mud, is masked by a vigorous vegetation, which
is cherished by the moisture of the place. It is then the favorite hiding-place
and den of foxes and jackals; so that the same cavity serves at one
season of the year for the habitation of carnivorous beasts, and at another
as the channel of an engulfed river. Near the mouth of one chasm, M.
Boblaye and his companions saw the carcass of a horse, in part devoured,
the size of which seemed to have prevented the jackals from dragging it
in: the marks of their teeth were observed on the bones, and it was
evident that the floods of the ensuing winter would wash in whatsoever
might remain of the skeleton.
It has been stated that the waters of all these torrents of the Morea are
turbid where they are engulfed; but when they come out again, often at
the distance of many leagues, they are perfectly clear and limpid, being
only charged occasionally with a slight quantity of calcareous sand. The
points of efflux are usually near the sea-shores of the Morea, but sometimes
they are submarine; and when this is the case, the sands are seen
to boil up for a considerable space, and the surface of the sea, in calm
weather, swells in large convex waves. It is curious to reflect, that when
this discharge fails in seasons of drought, the pressure of the sea may
force its salt waters into subterraneous caverns, and carry in marine sand
and shells, to be mingled with ossiferous mud, and the remains of terrestrial
animals.
In general, however, the efflux of water at these inferior openings is
surprisingly uniform. It seems, therefore, that the large caverns in the
interior must serve as reservoirs, and that the water escapes gradually
from them, in consequence of the smallness of the rents and passages by
which they communicate with the surface.
The phenomena above described are not confined to the Morea, but
occur in Greece generally, and in those parts of Italy, Spain, Asia Minor,
and Syria, where the formations of the Morea extend. The Copaic lake
in Bœotia has no outlet, except by underground channels; and hence
we can explain those traditional and historical accounts of its having
gained on the surrounding plains and overflowed towns, as such floods
736
must have happened whenever the outlet was partially choked up by mud,
gravel, or the subsidence of rocks, caused by earthquakes. When speaking
of the numerous fissures in the limestone of Greece, M. Boblaye
reminds us of the famous earthquake of 469 B. C., when, as we learn from
Cicero, Plutarch, Strabo, and Pliny, Sparta was laid in ruins, part of the
summit of Mount Taygetus torn off, and numerous gulfs and fissures
caused in the rocks of Laconia.
During the great earthquake of 1693, in Sicily, several thousand people
were at once entombed in the ruins of caverns in limestone, at Sortino
Vecchio; and, at the same time, a large stream, which had issued for
ages from one of the grottoes below that town, changed suddenly its subterranean
course, and came out from the mouth of a cave lower down
the valley, where no water had previously flowed. To this new point
the ancient water-mills were transferred, as I learnt when I visited the
spot in 1829.
When the courses of engulfed rivers are thus liable to change, from
time to time, by alterations in the levels of a country, and by the rending
and shattering of mountain masses, we must suppose that the dens of
wild beasts will sometimes be inundated by subterranean floods, and their
carcasses buried under heaps of alluvium. The bones, moreover, of individuals
which have died in the recesses of caves, or of animals which have
been carried in for prey, may be drifted along, and mixed up with mud,
sand, and fragments of rocks, so as to form osseous breccias.
In 1833 I had an opportunity of examining the celebrated caves of
Franconia, and among others that of Rabenstein, newly discovered. Their
general form, and the nature and arrangement of their contents, appeared
to me to agree perfectly with the notion of their having once served as
the channels of subterranean rivers. This mode of accounting for the
introduction of transported matter into the Franconian and other caves,
filled up as they often are even to their roofs with osseous breccia, was
long ago proposed by M. C. Prevost,1047 and seems at length to be very
generally adopted. But I do not doubt that bears inhabited some of the
German caves, or that the cavern of Kirkdale, in Yorkshire, was once the
den of hyænas. The abundance of bony dung, associated with hyænas'
bones, has been pointed out by Dr. Buckland, and with reason, as confirmatory
of this opinion.
The same author observed in every cave examined by him in Germany,
that deposits of mud and sand, with or without rolled pebbles and angular
fragments of rock, were covered over with a single crust of stalagmite.1048
In the English caves he remarked a similar absence of alterations of alluvium
and stalagmite. But Dr. Schmerling has discovered in a cavern at
Chockier, about two leagues from Liège, three distinct beds of stalagmite,
and between each of them a mass of breccia, and mud mixed with quartz
pebbles, and in the three deposits the bones of extinct quadrupeds.1049
737
This exception does not invalidate the generality of the phenomenon
pointed out by Dr. Buckland, one cause of which may perhaps be this,
that if several floods pass at different intervals of time through a subterranean
passage, the last, if it has power to drift along fragments of rock,
will also tear up any alternating stalagmitic and alluvial beds that may
have been previously formed. Another cause may be, that a particular
line of caverns will rarely be so situated, in relation to the lowest levels
of a country, as to become, at two distinct epochs, the receptacle of engulfed
rivers; and if this should happen, some of the caves, or at least
the tunnels of communication, may at the first period be entirely choked
up with transported matter, so as not to allow the subsequent passage of
water in the same direction.
As the same chasms may remain open throughout periods of indefinite
duration, the species inhabiting a country may in the meantime be greatly
changed, and thus the remains of animals belonging to very different
epochs may become mingled together in a common tomb. For this
reason it is often difficult to separate the monuments of the human epoch
from those relating to periods long antecedent, and it was not without
great care and skill that Dr. Buckland was enabled to guard against such
anachronisms in his investigations of several of the English caves. He
mentions that human skeletons were found in the cave of Wokey Hole,
near Wells, in the Mendips, dispersed through reddish mud and clay,
and some of them united by stalagmite into a firm osseous breccia.
"The spot on which they lie is within reach of the highest floods of the
adjacent river, and the mud in which they are buried is evidently
fluviatile."1050
In speaking of the cave of Paviland on the coast of Glamorganshire
the same author states that the entire mass through which bones were
dispersed appeared to have been disturbed by ancient diggings, so that
the remains of extinct animals had become mixed with recent bones and
shells. In the same cave was a human skeleton, and the remains of recent
testacea of eatable species, which may have been carried in by man.
In several caverns on the banks of the Meuse, near Liège, Dr. Schmerling
has found human bones in the same mud and breccia with those of
the elephant, rhinoceros, bear, and other quadrupeds of extinct species.
He has observed none of the dung of any of these animals: and from
this circumstance, and the appearance of the mud and pebbles, he concludes
that these caverns were never inhabited by wild beasts, but washed
in by a current of water. As the human skulls and bones were in fragments,
and no entire skeleton had been found, he does not believe that
these caves were places of sepulture, but that the human remains were
washed in at the same time as the bones of extinct quadrupeds, and that
these lost species of mammalia co-existed on the earth with man.
Caverns in the south of France.—Similar associations in the south
of France, of human bones and works of art, with remains of extinct
quadrupeds, have induced other geologists to maintain that man was an
738
inhabitant of that part of Europe before the rhinoceros, hyæna, tiger,
and many fossil species disappeared. I may first mention the cavern of
Bize, in the department of Aude, where M. Marcel de Serres met with a
small number of human bones mixed with those of extinct animals and
with land shells. They occur in a calcareous stony mass, bound together
by a cement of stalagmite. On examining the same caverns, M. Tournal
found not only in these calcareous beds, but also in a black mud which
overlies a red osseous mud, several human teeth, together with broken
angular fragments of a rude kind of pottery, and also recent marine and
terrestrial shells. The teeth preserve their enamel; but the fangs are so
much altered as to adhere strongly when applied to the tongue. Of the
terrestrial shells thus associated with the bones and pottery, the most
common are Cyclostoma elegans, Bulimus decollatus, Helix nemoralis,
and H. nitida. Among the marine are found Pecten jacobæus, Mytilus
edulis, and Natica mille-punctata, all of them eatable kinds, and which
may have been brought there for food. Bones were found in the same
mass belonging to three new species of deer, the brown bear (Ursus
arctoïdeus), and the wild bull (Bos urus), formerly a native of
Germany.1051
In the same parts of France, M. de Christol has found in caverns in a
tertiary limestone at Pondres and Souvignargues, two leagues north of
Lunel-viel, in the department of Herault, human bones and pottery confusedly
mixed with remains of the rhinoceros, bear, hyæna, and other
terrestrial mammifers. They were imbedded in alluvial mud, of the solidity
of calcareous tufa, and containing some flint pebbles and fragments
of the limestone of the country. Beneath this mixed accumulation,
which sometimes attained a thickness of thirteen feet, is the original
floor of the cavern, about a foot thick, covered with bones and the dung
of animals (album græcum), in a sandy and tufaceous cement.
The human bones in these caverns of Pondres and Souvignargues
were found, upon a careful analysis, to have parted with their animal
matter to as great a degree as those of the hyæna which accompany
them, and are equally brittle, and adhere as strongly to the tongue.
In order to compare the degree of alteration of these bones with those
known to be of high antiquity, M. Marcel de Serres and M. Ballard,
chemists of Montpelier, procured some from a Gaulish sarcophagus, in
the plain of Lunel, supposed to have been buried for fourteen or fifteen
centuries at least. In these the cellular tissue was empty, but they were
more solid than fresh bones. They did not adhere to the tongue in the
same manner as those of the caverns of Bize and Pondres, yet they
had lost at least three fourths of their original animal matter.
The superior solidity of the Gaulish bones to those in a fresh skeleton
is a fact in perfect accordance with the observations made by Dr. Mantell
on bones taken from a Saxon tumulus near Lewes.
M. Tessier has also described a cavern near Mialet, in the department
739
of Gard, where the remains of the bear and other animals were mingled
confusedly with human bones, coarse pottery, teeth pierced for amulets,
pointed fragments of bone, bracelets of bronze, and a Roman urn. Part
of this deposit reached to the roof of the cavity, and adhered firmly to it.
The author suggests that the exterior portion of the grotto may at one
period have been a den of bears, and that afterwards the aboriginal inhabitants
of the country took possession of it either for a dwelling or a burial-place,
and left there the coarse pottery, amulets, and pointed pieces of
bone. At a third period the Romans may have used the cavern as a
place of sepulture or concealment, and to them may have belonged the
urn and bracelets of metal. If we then suppose the course of the neighboring
river to be impeded by some temporary cause, a flood would be
occasioned, which, rushing into the open grotto, may have washed all
the remains into the interior caves and tunnels, heaping the whole confusedly
together.1052
In the controversy which has arisen on this subject, MM. Marcel de
Serres, De Christol, Tournal, and others, have contended, that the phenomena
of this and other caverns in the south of France prove that the
fossil rhinoceros, hyæna, bear, and several other lost species, were once
contemporaneous inhabitants of the country, together with man; while
M. Desnoyers has supported the opposite opinion. The flint hatchets and
arrow-heads, he says, and the pointed bones and coarse pottery of many
French and English caves, agree precisely in character with those found
in the tumuli, and under the dolmens (rude altars of unhewn stone) of
the primitive inhabitants of Gaul, Britain, and Germany. The human
bones, therefore, in the caves which are associated with such fabricated
objects, must belong not to antediluvian periods, but to a people in the
same stage of civilization as those who constructed the tumuli and
altars.
In the Gaulish monuments we find, together with the objects of industry
above mentioned, the bones of wild and domestic animals of species
now inhabiting Europe, particularly of deer, sheep, wild-boars, dogs,
horses, and oxen. This fact has been ascertained in Quercy, and other
provinces; and it is supposed by antiquaries that the animals in question
were placed beneath the Celtic altars in memory of sacrifices offered to
the Gaulish divinity Hesus, and in the tombs to commemorate funeral
repasts, and also from a supposition prevalent among savage nations,
which induces them to lay up provisions for the manes of the dead in a
future life. But in none of these ancient monuments have any bones
been found of the elephant, rhinoceros, hyæna, tiger, and other quadrupeds,
such as are found in caves, as might certainly have been expected
had these species continued to flourish at the time that this part of Gaul
was inhabited by man.1053
We are also reminded by M. Desnoyers of a passage in Florus, in which
it is related that Cæsar ordered the caves into which the Aquitanian
740
Gauls had retreated to be closed up.1054 It is also on record, that so late
as the eighth century, the Aquitanians defended themselves in caverns
against King Pepin. As many of these caverns, therefore, may have
served in succession as temples and habitations, as places of sepulture,
concealment, or defence, it is easy to conceive that human bones, and
those of animals, in osseous breccias of much older date, may have been
swept away together, by inundations, and then buried in one promiscuous
heap.
It is not on the evidence of such intermixtures that we ought readily
to admit either the high antiquity of the human race, or the recent date
of certain lost species of quadrupeds.
Among the various modes in which the bones of animals become preserved,
independently of the agency of land floods and engulfed rivers, I
may mention that open fissures often serve as natural pitfalls in which
herbivorous animals perish. This may happen the more readily when
they are chased by beasts of prey, or when surprised while carelessly
browsing on the shrubs which so often overgrow and conceal the edges
of fissures.1055
During the excavations recently made near Behat in India, the bones
of two deer were found at the bottom of an ancient well which had
been filled up with alluvial loam. Their horns were broken to pieces,
but the jaw bones and other parts of the skeleton remained tolerably
perfect. "Their presence," says Captain Cautley, "is easily accounted
for, as a great number of these and other animals are constantly lost in
galloping over the jungles and among the high grass by falling into
deserted wells."1056
Above the village of Selside, near Ingleborough in Yorkshire, a
chasm of enormous but unknown depth occurs in the scar-limestone, a
member of the carboniferous series. "The chasm," says Professor Sedgwick,
"is surrounded by grassy shelving banks, and many animals,
tempted towards its brink, have fallen down and perished in it. The
approach of cattle is now prevented by a strong lofty wall; but there
can be no doubt that, during the last two or three thousand years, great
masses of bony breccia must have accumulated in the lower parts of the
great fissure, which probably descends through the whole thickness of the
scar-limestone, to the depth of perhaps five or six hundred feet."1057
When any of these natural pit-falls happen to communicate with lines
of subterranean caverns, the bones, earth, and breccia, may sink by
their own weight, or be washed into the vaults below.
At the north extremity of the rock of Gibraltar are perpendicular
fissures, on the ledges of which a number of hawks nestle and rear their
young in the breeding season. They throw down from their nests the
bones of small birds, mice, and other animals, on which they feed, and
741
these are gradually united into a breccia of angular fragments of the
decomposing limestone with a cement of red earth.
At the pass of Escrinet in France, on the northern escarpment of the
Coiron hills, near Aubenas, I have seen a breccia in the act of forming.
Small pieces of disintegrating limestone are transported, during heavy
rains, by a streamlet, to the foot of the declivity, where land shells are
very abundant. The shells and pieces of stone soon become cemented
together by stalagmite into a compact mass, and the talus thus formed
is in one place fifty feet deep, and five hundred yards wide. So firmly
is the lowest portion consolidated, that it is quarried for mill-stones.
Recent, stalagmitic limestone of Cuba.—One of the most singular
examples of the recent growth of stalagmitic limestone in caves and
fissures is that described by Mr. R. C. Taylor, as observable on the
north-east part of the island of Cuba.1058 The country there is composed
of a white marble, in which are numerous cavities, partially filled with
a calcareous deposit of a brick-red color. In this red deposit are
shells, or often the hollow casts of shells, chiefly referable to eight or
nine species of land snails, a few scattered bones of quadrupeds, and,
what is still more singular, marine univalve shells, often at the height
of many hundred, or even one thousand feet above the sea. The following
explanation is given of the gradual increase of this deposit. Land
snails of the genera Helix, Cyclostoma, Pupa, and Clausilia, retire into
the caves, the floors of which are strewed with myriads of their dead
and unoccupied shells, at the same time that water infiltered through
the mountain throws down carbonate of lime, enveloping the shells,
together with fragments of the white limestone which occasionally falls
from the roof. Multitudes of bats resort to the caves; and their dung,
which is of a bright red color, (probably derived from the berries on
which they feed,) imparts its red hue to the mass. Sometimes also the
Hutia, or great Indian rat of the island, dies and leaves its bones in the
caves. "At certain seasons the soldier-crabs resort to the sea-shore, and
then return from their pilgrimage, each carrying with them, or rather
dragging, the shell of some marine univalve for many a weary mile.
They may be traced even at the distance of eight or ten miles from the
shore, on the summit of mountains 1200 feet high, like the pilgrims of
the olden times, each bearing his shell to denote the character and
extent of his wanderings." By this means several species of marine
testacea of the genera Trochus, Turbo, Littorina, and Monodonta, are
conveyed into inland caverns, and enter into the composition of the
newly formed rock.

742</div></body></text></TEI>