<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="52">CHAPTER IV.
Verification and Completion of the Newtonian
Theory.

Tables of the Moon and
Planets.
THE Newtonian discovery of
Universal Gravitation, so remarkable in other respects, is also
remarkable as exemplifying the immense extent to which the
verification of a great truth may be carried, the amount of human
labor which may be requisite to do it justice, and the striking
extension of human knowledge to which it may lead. I have said that it
is remarked as a beauty in the first fixation of a theory that its
measures or elements are established by means of a few 551 data; but that its
excellence when established is in the number of observations which it
explains. The multiplicity of observations which are explained by
astronomy, and which are made because astronomy explains them, is
immense, as I have noted in the text. And the multitude of
observations thus made is employed for the purpose of correcting the
first adopted elements of the theory. I have mentioned some of the
examples of this process: I might mention many others in order to
continue the history of this part of Astronomy up to the present time.
But I will notice only those which seem to me the most remarkable.
In 1812, Burckhardt’s Tables de la Lune were published by
the French Bureau des Longitudes. A comparison of these and Burg’s
with a considerable number of observations, gave 9⁄100ths of
a second as the mean error of the former in the Moon’s longitude,
while the mean error of Burg’s was 18⁄100ths. The preference was
therefore accorded to Burckhardt’s.
Yet the Lunar Tables were still as much as thirty seconds wrong in
single observations. This circumstance, and Laplace’s expressed wish,
induced the French Academy to offer a prize for a complete and purely
theoretical determination of the Lunar path, instead of determinations
resting, as hitherto, partly upon theory and partly upon observations.
In 1820, two prize essays appeared, the one by Damoiseau, the other by
Plana and Carlini. And some years afterwards (in 1824, and again in
1828), Damoiseau published Tables de la Lune formées sur la seule
Théorie d’Attraction. These agree very closely with observation.
That we may form some notion of the complexity of the problem, I may
state that the longitude of the Moon is in these Tables affected by no
fewer than forty-seven equations; and the other quantities
which determine her place are subject to inequalities not much less in
number.
Still I had to state in the second Edition, published in 1847, that
there remained an unexplained discordance between theory and
observation in the motions of the Moon; an inequality of long period
as it seemed, which the theory did not give.
A careful examination of a long series of the best observations of
the Moon, compared throughout with the theory in its most perfect
form, would afford the means both of correcting the numerical elements
of the theory, and of detecting the nature, and perhaps the law, of
any still remaining discrepancies. Such a work, however, required vast
labor, as well as great skill and profound mathematical knowledge.
552 Mr. Airy
undertook the task; employing for that purpose, the Observations of
the Moon made at Greenwich from 1750 to 1830. Above 8000 observed
places of the Moon were compared with theory by the computation of the
same number of places, each separately and independently calculated
from Plana’s Formulæ. A body of calculators (sometimes sixteen), at
the expense of the British Government, was employed for about eight
years in this work. When we take this in conjunction with the labor
which the observations themselves imply, it may serve to show on what
a scale the verification of the Newtonian theory has been conducted.
The first results of this labor were published in two quarto volumes;
the final deductions as to correction of elements, &c., were given
in the Memoirs of the Astronomical Society in 1848.48
48 The total expense of computers, to
the end of reading the proof-sheets, was 4300l.
 Mr. Airy’s estimate of days’ works [made before beginning], for
the heavy part of calculations only, was thirty-six years of one
computer. This was somewhat exceeded, but not very greatly, in that
part.
Even while the calculations were going on, it became apparent that
there were some differences between the observed places of the Moon,
and the theory so far as it had then been developed. M. Hansen, an
eminent German mathematician who had devised new and powerful methods
for the mathematical determination of the results of the law of
gravitation, was thus led to explore still further the motions of the
Moon in pursuance of this law. The result was that he found there must
exist two lunar inequalities, hitherto not known; the one of 273, and
the other of 239 years, the coefficients of which are respectively 27
and 23 seconds. Both these originate in the attraction of Venus; one
of them being connected with the long inequality in the Solar Tables,
of which Mr. Airy had already proved the existence, as stated in Chap.
vi. Sect. 6 of this Book.
These inequalities fell in with the discrepancies between the
actual observations and the previously calculated Tables, which Mr.
Airy had discovered. And again, shortly afterwards, M. Hansen found
that there resulted from the theory two other new equations of the
Moon; one in latitude and one in longitude, agreeing with two which
were found by Mr. Airy in deducing from the observations the
correction of the elements of the Lunar Tables. And again, a little
later, there was detected by these mathematicians a theoretical
correction for the 553 motion of the Node of the Moon’s orbit,
coinciding exactly with one which had been found to appear in the
observations.
Nothing can more strikingly exhibit the confirmation which
increased scrutiny brings to light between the Newtonian theory on the
one hand, and the celestial motions on the other. We have here a very
large mass of the best observations which have ever been made,
systematically examined, with immense labor, and with the set purpose
of correcting at once all the elements of the Lunar Tables. The
corrections of the elements thus deduced imply of course some error in
the theory as previously developed. But at the same time, and with the
like determination thoroughly to explore the subject, the theory is
again pressed to yield its most complete results, by the invention of
new and powerful mathematical methods; and the event is, that residual
errors of the old Tables, several in number, following the most
diverse laws, occurring in several detached parts, agree with the
residual results of the Theory thus newly extracted from it. And thus
every additional exactness of scrutiny into the celestial motions on
the one hand and the Newtonian theory on the other, has ended, sooner
or later, in showing the exactness of their coincidence.
The comparison of the theory with observation in the case of the
motions of the Planets, the motion of each being disturbed by the
attraction of all the others, is a subject in some respects still more
complicated and laborious. This work also was undertaken by the same
indefatigable astronomer; and here also his materials belonged to the
same period as before; being the admirable observations made at
Greenwich from 1750 to 1830, during the time that Bradley, Maskelyne,
and Pond were the Astronomers Royal.49 These Planetary
observations were deduced, and the observed places were compared with
the tabular places: with Lindenau’s Tables of Mercury, Venus, and
Mars; and with Bouvard’s Tables of Jupiter, Saturn, and Uranus; and
thus, while the received theory and its elements were confirmed, the
means of testing any improvement which may hereafter be proposed,
either in the form of the theoretical results or in the constant
elements which they involved, was placed within the reach of the 554 astronomers of all
future time. The work appeared in 1845; the expense of the
compilations and the publication being defrayed by the British
Government.
49 The observations of stars made by
Bradley, who preceded Maskelyne at Greenwich, had already been
discussed by Bessel, a great German astronomer; and the results
published in 1818, with a title that well showed the estimation in
which he held those materials: Fundamenta Astronomiæ pro anno
1775, deducta ex Ohservationibus viri incomparabilis James Bradley
in specula Astronomica Grenovicensi per annos 1750–1762
institutis.
The Discovery of Neptune.
The theory of gravitation was destined to receive a confirmation
more striking than any which could arise from any explanation, however
perfect, given by the motions of a known planet; namely, in revealing
the existence of an unknown planet, disclosed to astronomers by the
attraction which it exerted upon a known one. The story of the
discovery of Neptune by the calculations of Mr. Adams and M. Le
Verrier was partly told in the former edition of this History. I had
there stated (vol. ii. p. 306) that “a deviation of observation from
the theory occurs at the very extremity of the solar system, and that
its existence appears to be beyond doubt. Uranus does not conform to
the Tables calculated for him on the theory of gravitation. In 1821,
Bouvard said in the Preface to the Tables of this Planet, “the
formation of these Tables offers to us this alternative, that we
cannot satisfy modern observations to the requisite degree of
precision without making our Tables deviate from the ancient
observations.” But when we have done this, there is still a
discordance between the Tables and the more modern observations, and
this discordance goes on increasing. At present the Tables make the
Planet come upon the meridian about eight seconds later than he really
does. This discrepancy has turned the thoughts of astronomers to the
effects which would result from a planet external to Uranus. It
appears that the observed motion would be explained by applying a
planet at twice the distance of Uranus from the Sun to exercise a
disturbing force, and it is found that the present longitude of this
disturbing body must be about 325 degrees.
I added, “M. Le Verrier (Comptes Rendus, Jan. 1, 1846) and,
as I am informed by the Astronomer Royal, Mr. Adams, of St. John’s
College, Cambridge, have both arrived independently at this
result.”
To this Edition I added a Postscript, dated, Nov. 7, 1846, in which
I said:
“The planet exterior to Uranus, of which the existence was inferred
by M. Le Verrier and Mr. Adams from the motions of Uranus (vol. ii.
Note (l.)), has since been discovered. This
confirmation of calculations founded upon the doctrine of universal
gravitation, may be looked upon as the most remarkable event of the
kind since the return of Halley’s comet in 1757  and in some respects,
as a more striking event 555 even than that; inasmuch as the new
planet had never been seen at all, and was discovered by
mathematicians entirely by their feeling of its influence, which they
perceived through the organ of mathematical calculation.
“There can be no doubt that to M. Le Verrier belongs the glory of
having first published a prediction of the place and appearance of the
new planet, and of having thus occasioned its discovery by
astronomical observers. M. Le Verrier’s first prediction was published
in the Comptes Rendus de l’Acad. des Sciences, for June
1, 1846 (not Jan. 1, as erroneously printed in my Note). A
subsequent paper on the subject was read Aug. 31. The planet was seen
by M. Galle, at the Observatory of Berlin, on September 23, on which
day he had received an express application from M. Le Verrier,
recommending him to endeavor to recognize the stranger by its having a
visible disk. Professor Challis, at the Observatory of Cambridge, was
looking out for the new planet from July 29, and saw it on August 4,
and again on August 12, but without recognizing it, in consequence of
his plan of not comparing his observations till he had accumulated a
greater number of them. On Sept. 29, having read for the first time M.
Le Verrier’s second paper, he altered his plan, and paid attention to
the physical appearance rather than the position of the star. On that
very evening, not having then heard of M. Galle’s discovery, he
singled out the star by its seeming to have a disk.
“M. Le Verrier’s mode of discussing the circumstances of Uranus’s
motion, and inferring the new planet from these circumstances, is in
the highest degree sagacious and masterly. Justice to him cannot
require that the contemporaneous, though unpublished, labors of Mr.
Adams, of St John’s College, Cambridge, should not also be recorded.
Mr. Adams made his first calculations to account for the anomalies in
the motion of Uranus, on the hypothesis of a more distant planet, in
1843. At first he had not taken into account the earlier Greenwich
observations; but these were supplied to him by the Astronomer Royal,
in 1844. In September, 1845, Mr. Adams communicated to Professor
Challis values of the elements of the supposed disturbing body;
namely, its mean distance, mean longitude at a given epoch, longitude
of perihelion, eccentricity of orbit, and mass. In the next month, he
communicated to the Astronomer Royal values of the same elements,
somewhat corrected. The note (l.), vol. ii.,
of the present work (2d Ed.), in which the names of MM. Le Verrier and
Adams are mentioned in conjunction, was in the press in August, 1846,
a 556 month before
the planet was seen. As I have stated in the text, Mr. Adams and M. Le
Verrier assigned to the unseen planet nearly the same position; they
also assigned to it nearly the same mass; namely, 2½ times the mass of
Uranus. And hence, supposing the density to be not greater than that
of Uranus, it followed that the visible diameter would be about 3”, an
apparent magnitude not much smaller than Uranus himself.
“M. Le Verrier has mentioned for the new planet the name
Neptunus; and probably, deference to his authority as its
discoverer, will obtain general currency for this name.”
Mr. Airy has given a very complete history of the circumstances
attending the discovery of Neptune, in the Memoirs of the Astronomical
Society (read November 13, 1846). In this he shows that the
probability of some disturbing body beyond Uranus had suggested itself
to M. A. Bouvard and Mr. Hussey as early as 1834. Mr. Airy himself
then thought that the time was not ripe for making out the nature of
any external action on the planets. But Mr. Adams soon afterwards
proceeded to work at the problem. As early as 1841 (as he himself
informs me) he conjectured the existence of a planet exterior to
Uranus, and recorded in a memorandum his design of examining its
effect; but deferred the calculations till he had completed his
preparations for the University examination which he was to undergo in
January, 1843, in order to receive the Degree of Bachelor of Arts. He
was the Senior Wrangler of that occasion, and soon afterwards
proceeded to carry his design into effect; applying to the Astronomer
Royal for recorded observations which might aid him in his task. On
one of the last days of October, 1845, Mr. Adams went to the
Observatory at Greenwich; and finding the Astronomer Royal abroad, he
left there a paper containing the elements of the extra-Uranian
Planet: the longitude was in this paper stated as 323½ degrees. It
was, as we have seen, in June, 1846, that M. Le Verrier’s Memoir
appeared, in which he assigned to the disturbing body a longitude of
325 degrees. The coincidence was striking. “I cannot sufficiently
express,” says Mr. Airy, “the feeling of delight and satisfaction
which I received from the Memoir of M. Le Verrier.” This feeling
communicated itself to others. Sir John Herschel said in September,
1846, at a meeting of the British Association at Southampton, “We see
it (the probable new planet) as Columbus saw America from the shores
of Spain. Its movements have been felt, trembling along the
far-reaching line of our analysis, with a certainty hardly inferior to
that of ocular demonstration.” 557
In truth, at the moment when this was uttered, the new Planet had
already been seen by Professor Challis; for, as we have said, he had
seen it in the early part of August. He had included it in the net
which he had cast among the stars for this very purpose; but employing
a slow and cautious process, he had deferred for a time that
examination of his capture which would have enabled him to detect the
object sought. As soon as he received M. Le Verrier’s paper of August
31 on September 29, he was so much impressed with the sagacity and
clearness of the limitations of the field of observation there laid
down, that he instantly changed his plan of observation, and noted the
planet, as an object having a visible disk, on the evening of the same
day.
In this manner the theory of gravitation predicted and produced the
discovery. Thus to predict unknown facts found afterwards to be true,
is, as I have said, a confirmation of a theory which in impressiveness
and value goes beyond any explanation of known facts. It is a
confirmation which has only occurred a few times in the history of
science; and in the case only of the most refined and complete
theories, such as those of Astronomy and Optics. The mathematical
skill which was requisite in order to arrive at such a discovery, may
in some measure be judged of by the account which we have had to give
of the previous mathematical progress of the theory of gravitation. It
there appeared that the lives of many of the most acute,
clear-sighted, and laborious of mankind, had been employed for
generations in solving the problem. Given the planetary bodies, to
find their mutual perturbations: but here we have the inverse
problem—Given the perturbations, to find the planets.50
50 This may be called the
inverse problem with reference to the older and more familiar
problem; but we may remark that the usual phraseology of the Problem
of Central Forces differs from this analogy. In Newton’s
Principia, the earlier Sections, in which the motion is given
to find the force, are spoken of as containing the Direct Problem of
Central Forces: the Eighth Section of the First Book, where the Force
is given to find the orbit, is spoken of as containing the
Inverse Problem of Central Forces.
The Minor Planets.
The discovery of the Minor Planets which revolve between the orbits
of Mars and Jupiter was not a consequence or confirmation of the
Newtonian theory. That theory gives no reason for the distance of
558 the Planets
from the Sun; nor does any theory yet devised give such reason. But an
empirical formula proposed by the Astronomer Bode of Berlin, gives a
law of these distances (Bode’s Law), which, to make it
coherent, requires a planet between Mars and Jupiter. With such an
addition, the distance of Mercury, Venus, Earth, Mars, the Missing
Planet, Jupiter, Saturn, and Uranus, are nearly as the numbers 4, 7, 10, 16, 28, 52, 100, 196,in which the excesses of each number above the preceding are
the series 3, 3, 6, 12, 24, 48, 96.On the strength of this law the Germans wrote on
the long-expected Planet, and formed themselves into associations
for the discovery of it.
Not only did this law stimulate the inquiries for the Missing
Planet, and thus lead to the discovery of the Minor Planets, but it
had also a share in the discovery of Neptune. According to the law, a
planet beyond Uranus may be expected to be at the distance represented
by 388. Mr. Adams and M. Le Verrier both of them began by assuming a
distance of nearly this magnitude for the Planet which they sought;
that is, a distance more than 38 times the earth’s distance. It was
found afterwards that the distance of Neptune is only 30 times that of
the earth; yet the assumption was of essential use in obtaining the
result  and Mr. Airy remarks that the history of the discovery shows
the importance of using any received theory as far as it will go, even
if the theory can claim no higher merit than that of being
plausible.51
51 Account of the Discovery of
Neptune, &c., Mem. Ast. Soc., vol. xvi. p. 414.
The discovery of Minor Planets in a certain region of the interval
between Mars and Jupiter has gone on to such an extent, that their
number makes them assume in a peculiar manner the character of
representatives of a Missing Planet. At first, as I have said in the
text, it was supposed that all these portions
must pass through or near a common node; this opinion being founded on
the very bold doctrine, that the portions must at one time have been
united in one Planet, and must then have separated. At this node, as I
have stated, Olbers lay in wait for them, as for a hostile army at a
defile. Ceres, Pallas, and Juno had been discovered in this way in the
period from 1801 to 1804; and Vesta was caught in 1807. For a time the
chase for new planets in this region seemed to have exhausted the
stock. But after thirty-eight years, to the astonishment of
astronomers, they began to be again detected in extraordinary numbers.
In 1845, M. Hencke of 559 Driessen discovered a fifth of these
planets, which was termed Astræa. In various quarters the chase was
resumed with great ardor. In 1847 were found Hebe, Iris, and Flora; in
1848, Metis; in 1849, Hygæa; in 1850, Parthenope, Victoria, and
Egeria; in 1861, Irene and Eunomia; in 1852, Psyche, Thetis,
Melpomene, Fortuna, Massilia, Lutetia, Calliope. To these we have now
(at the close of 1856) to add nineteen others; making up the
whole number of these Minor Planets at present known to
forty-two.
As their enumeration will show, the ancient practice has been
continued of giving to the Planets mythological names. And for a time,
till the numbers became too great, each of the Minor Planets was
designated in astronomical books by some symbol appropriate to the
character of the mythological person; as from ancient times Mars has
been denoted by a mark indicating a spear, and Venus by one
representing a looking-glass. Thus, when a Minor Planet was discovered
at London in 1851, the year in which the peace of the world was, in a
manner, celebrated by the Great Exhibition of the Products of All
Nations, held at that metropolis, the name Irene was given to
the new star, as a memorial of the auspicious time of its discovery.
And it was agreed, for awhile, that its symbol should be a dove with
an olive-branch. But the vast multitude of the Minor Planets, as
discovery went on, made any mode of designation, except a numerical
one, practically inconvenient. They are now denoted by a small circle
inclosing a figure in the order of their discovery. Thus, Ceres
is ⓵, Irene is ⑭, and Isis is ㊷.
The rapidity with which these discoveries were made was owing in
part to the formation of star-maps, in which all known fixed stars
being represented, the existence of a new and movable star might be
recognized by comparison of the sky with the map. These maps were
first constructed by astronomers of different countries at the
suggestion of the Academy of Berlin; but they have since been greatly
extended, and now include much smaller stars than were originally laid
down.
I will mention the number of planets discovered in each year. After
the start was once made, by Hencke’s discovery of Astræa in 1845, the
same astronomer discovered Hebe in 1847; and in the same year Mr.
Hind, of London, discovered two others, Iris and Flora. The years 1848
and 1849 each supplied one; the year 1850, three; 1851, two; 1852 was
marked by the extraordinary discovery of eight new members of
the planetary system. The year 1853 supplied four; 1854, six; 1855,
four; and 1856 has already given us five. 560
These discoveries have been distributed among the observatories of
Europe. The bright sky of Naples has revealed seven new planets to the
telescope of Signer Gasparis. Marseilles has given us one; Germany,
four, discovered by M. Luther at Bilk; Paris has furnished seven; and
Mr. Hind, in Mr. Bishop’s private observatory in London,
notwithstanding our turbid skies, has discovered no less than ten
planets; and there also Mr. Marth discovered ㉙ Amphitrite. Mr.
Graham, at the private observatory of Mr. Cooper, in Ireland,
discovered ⓽ Metis.
America has supplied its planet, namely ㉛ Euphrosyne,
discovered by Mr. Ferguson at Washington  and the most recent of these
discoveries is that by Mr. Pogson, of Oxford, who has found the
forty-second of these Minor Planets, which has been named Isis.52
52 I take this list from a Memoir of
M. Bruhns, Berlin, 1856.
I may add that it appears to follow from the best calculations that
the total mass of all these bodies is very small. Herschel reckoned
the diameters of Ceres at 35, and of Pallas at 26 miles. It has since
been calculated53 that some of them are smaller still;
Victoria having a diameter of 9 miles, Lutetia of 8, and Atalanta of
little more than 4. It follows from this that the whole mass would
probably be less than the sixth part of our moon. Hence their
perturbing effects on each other or on other planets are null; but
they are not the less disturbed by the action of the other planets,
and especially of Jupiter.
53 Bruhns, as above.
Anomalies in the Action of Gravitation.
The complete and exact manner in which the doctrine of gravitation
explains the motions of the Comets as well as of the Planets, has made
astronomers very bold in proposing hypotheses to account for any
deviations from the motion which the theory requires. Thus Encke’s
Comet is found to have its motion accelerated by about one-eighth of a
day in every revolution. This result was conceived to be established
by former observations, and is confirmed by the facts of the
appearance of 1852.54 The hypothesis which is proposed in
order to explain this result is, that the Comet moves in a resisting
medium, which makes it fall inwards from its path, towards the Sun,
and thus, by narrowing its orbit, diminishes its periodic time. On the
other hand, M. Le Verrier has found that Mercury’s mean motion has
gone on diminishing; 561 as if the planet were, in the progress
of his revolutions, receding further from the Sun. This is explained,
if we suppose that there is, in the region of Mercury, a resisting
medium which moves round the Sun in the same direction as the Planets
move. Evidence of a kind of nebulous disk surrounding the Sun, and
extending beyond the orbits of Mercury and Venus, appears to be
afforded us by the phenomenon called the Zodiacal Light; and as
the Sun itself rotates on its axis, it is most probable that this kind
of atmosphere rotates also.55 On the other hand, M. Le Verrier
conceives that the Comets which now revolve within the ordinary
planetary limits have not always done so, but have been caught and
detained by the Planets among which they move. In this way the action
of Jupiter has brought the Comets of Faye and Vico into their present
limited orbits, as it drew the Comet of Lexell out of its known orbit,
when the Comet passed over the Planet in 1779, since which time it has
not been seen.
54 Berlin Memoirs, 1854.
55 M. Le Verrier, Annales de l’Obs.
de Paris, vol. i. p. 89.
Among the examples of the boldness with which astronomers assume
the doctrine of gravitation even beyond the limits of the solar system
to be so entirely established, that hypotheses may and must be assumed
to explain any apparent irregularity of motion, we may reckon the mode
of accounting for certain supposed irregularities in the proper motion
of Sirius, which has been proposed by Bessel, and which M. Peters
thinks is proved to be true by his recent researches (Astr.
Nach. xxxi. p. 219, and xxxii. p. 1). The hypothesis is, that
Sirius has a companion star, dark, and therefore invisible to us; and
that the two, revolving round their common centre as the system moves
on, the motion of Sirius is seen to be sometimes quicker and sometimes
slower.
The Earth’s Density.
“Cavendish’s experiment,” as it is commonly called—the
measure of the attractions of manageable masses by the torsion
balance, in order to determine the density of the Earth—has been
repeated recently by Professor Reich at Freiberg, and by Mr. Baily in
England, with great attention to the means of attaining accuracy.
Professor Reich’s result for the density of the Earth is 5·44; Mr.
Baily’s is 5·92. Cavendish’s result was 5·48; according to recent
revisions56 it is 5·52.
56 The calculation has been revised by
M. Edward Schmidt. Humboldt’s Kosmos, ii. p. 425.
562 But the
statical effect of the attraction of manageable masses, or even of
mountains, is very small. The effect of a small change in gravity may
be accumulated by being constantly repeated in the oscillations of a
pendulum, and thus may become perceptible. Mr. Airy attempted to
determine the density of the Earth by a method depending on this view.
A pendulum oscillating at the surface was to be compared with an equal
pendulum at a great depth below the surface. The difference of their
rates would disclose the different force of gravity at the two
positions; and hence, the density of the Earth. In 1826 and 1828, Mr.
Airy attempted this experiment at the copper mine of Dolcoath in
Cornwall, but failed from various causes. But in 1854, he resumed it
at the Harton coal mine in Durham, the depth of which is 1260 feet;
having in this new trial, the advantage of transmitting the time from
one station to the other by the instantaneous effect of galvanism,
instead of by portable watches. The result was a density of 6·56;
which is much larger than the preceding results, but, as Mr. Airy
holds, is entitled to compete with the others on at least equal
terms.
Tides.
I should be wanting in the expression of gratitude to those who
have practically assisted me in Researches on the Tides, if I did not
mention the grand series of Tide Observations made on the coast of
Europe and America in June, 1835, through the authority of the Board
of Admiralty, and the interposition of the late Duke of Wellington, at
that time Foreign Secretary. Tide observations were made for a
fortnight at all the Coast-guard stations of Great Britain and Ireland
in June, 1834; and these were repeated in June, 1835, with
corresponding observations on all the coasts of Europe, from the North
Cape of Norway to the Straits of Gibraltar; and from the mouth of the
St. Lawrence to the mouth of the Mississippi. The results of these
observations, which were very complete so far as the coast tides were
concerned, were given in the Philosophical Transactions for
1836.
Additional accuracy respecting the Tides of the North American
coast may be expected from the survey now going on under the direction
of Superintendent A. Bache. The Tides of the English Channel have been
further investigated, and the phenomena presented under a new point of
view by Admiral Beechey. 563
The Tides of the Coast of Ireland have been examined with great
care by Mr. Airy. Numerous and careful observations were made with a
view, in the first instance, of determining what was to be regarded as
“the Level of the Sea;” but the results were discussed so as to bring
into view the laws and progress, on the Irish coast, of the various
inequalities of the Tides mentioned in Chap. iv. Sect. 9 of this Book.
I may notice as one of the curious results of the Tide Observations
of 1836, that it appeared to me, from a comparison of the
Observations, that there must be a point in the German Ocean, about
midway between Lowestoft on the English coast, and the Brill on the
Dutch coast, where the tide would vanish: and this was ascertained to
be the case by observation; the observations being made by Captain
Hewett, then employed in a survey of that sea.
Cotidal Lines supply, as I conceive, a good and simple
method of representing the progress and connection of
littoral tides. But to draw cotidal lines across oceans, is a
very precarious mode of representing the facts, except we had much
more knowledge on the subject than we at present possess. In the
Phil. Trans. for 1848, I have resumed the subject of the Tides
of the Pacific; and I have there expressed my opinion, that while the
littoral tides are produced by progressive waves, the oceanic tides
are more of the nature of stationary undulations.
But many points of this kind might be decided, and our knowledge on
this subject might be brought to a condition of completeness, if a
ship or ships were sent expressly to follow the phenomena of the Tides
from point to point, as the observations themselves might suggest a
course. Till this is done, our knowledge cannot be completed. Detached
and casual observations, made aliud agendo, can never carry us
much beyond the point where we at present are.
Double Stars.
Sir John Herschel’s work, referred to in
the History (2d Ed.) as then about to appear, was published in 1847.57 In this work, besides a vast amount of
valuable observations and reasonings on other subjects 564 (as Nebulæ, the
Magnitude of Stars, and the like), the orbits of several double stars
are computed by the aid of the new observations. But Sir John
Herschel’s conviction on the point in question, the operation of the
Newtonian law of gravitation in the region of the stars, is expressed
perhaps more clearly in another work which he published in 1849.58 He there speaks of Double Stars, and
especially of gamma Virginis, the one which has been most
assiduously watched, and has offered phenomena of the greatest
interest.59 He then finds that the two components
of this star revolve round each other in a period of 182 years; and
says that the elements of the calculated orbit represent the whole
series of recorded observations, comprising an angular movement of
nearly nine-tenths of a complete circuit, both in angle and distance,
with a degree of exactness fully equal to that of observation itself.
“No doubt can therefore,” he adds, “remain as to the prevalence
in this remote system of the Newtonian Law of Gravitation.”
57 Results of Astronomical
Observations made during the years 1834, 5, 6, 7, 8, at the
Cape of Good Hope, being the completion of a Telescopic Survey of the
whole Surface of the visible Heavens commenced in 1825.
58 Outlines of Astronomy.
59 Out. 844.
Yet M. Yvon de Villarceau has endeavored to show60 that this conclusion, however probable,
is not yet proved. He holds, even for the Double Stars, which have
been most observed, the observations are only equivalent to seven or
eight really distinct data, and that seven data are not sufficient to
determine that an ellipse is described according to the Newtonian law.
Without going into the details of this reasoning, I may remark, that
the more rapid relative angular motion of the components of a Double
Star when they are more near each other, proves, as is allowed on all
hands, that they revolve under the influence of a mutual attractive
force, obeying the Keplerian Law of Areas. But that, whether this
force follows the law of the inverse square or some other law, can
hardly have been rigorously proved as yet, we may easily conceive,
when we recollect the manner in which that law was proved for the
Solar System. It was by means of an error of eight minutes,
observed by Tycho, that Kepler was enabled, as he justly boasted, to
reform the scheme of the Solar System,—to show, that is, that
the planetary orbits are ellipses with the sun in the focus. Now, the
observations of Double Stars cannot pretend to such accuracy as this;
and therefore the Keplerian theorem cannot, as yet, have been fully
demonstrated from those observations. But when we know 565 that Double Stars are
held together by a central force, to prove that this force follows a
different law from the only law which has hitherto been found to
obtain in the universe, and which obtains between all the known masses
of the universe, would require very clear and distinct evidence, of
which astronomers have as yet seen no trace.
60 Connaissance des Temps, for
1852; published in 1849.
</div></body></text></TEI>