<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="28">CHAPTER XXVIII.
EARTHQUAKE IN CALABRIA, 1783.
Earthquake in Calabria, February 5, 1783—Shocks continued to the end of the
year 1786—Authorities—Area convulsed—Geological structure of the district—Difficulty
of ascertaining changes of level—Subsidence of the quay at Messina—Movement
in the stones of two obelisks—Shift or fault in the Round Tower
of Terranuova—Opening and closing of fissures—Large edifices engulfed—Dimensions
of new caverns and fissures—Gradual closing in of rents—Bounding
of detached masses into the air—Landslips—Buildings transported entire to
great distances—New lakes—Funnel-shaped hollows in alluvial plains—Currents
of mud—Fall of cliffs, and shore near Scilla inundated—State of Stromboli
and Etna during the shocks—How earthquakes contribute to the formation
of valleys—Concluding remarks.
Calabria, 1783.—Of the numerous earthquakes which have occurred
in different parts of the globe, during the last 100 years, that of Calabria,
in 1783, is almost the only one of which the geologist can be said
to have such a circumstantial account as to enable him fully to appreciate
the changes which this cause is capable of producing in the lapse
of ages. The shocks began in February, 1783, and lasted for nearly
four years, to the end of 1786. Neither in duration, nor in violence,
nor in the extent of territory moved, was this convulsion remarkable,
when contrasted with many experienced in other countries, both during
the last and present century; nor were the alterations which it occasioned
in the relative level of hill and valley, land and sea, so great as
those effected by some subterranean movements in South America, in
later times. The importance of the earthquake in question arises from
the circumstance, that Calabria is the only spot hitherto visited, both
472
during and after the convulsions, by men possessing sufficient leisure,
zeal, and scientific information, to enable them to collect and describe
with accuracy the physical facts which throw light on geological questions.
Fig. 74.

Authorities.—Among the numerous authorities, Vivenzio, physician
to the king of Naples, transmitted to the court a regular statement of
his observations during the continuance of the shocks; and his narrative
is drawn up with care and clearness.663 Francesco Antonio Grimaldi,
then secretary of war, visited the different provinces at the king's
command, and published a most detailed description of the permanent
changes in the surface.664 He measured the length, breadth, and depth
of the different fissures and gulfs which opened, and ascertained their
number in many provinces. His comments, moreover, on the reports of
the inhabitants, and his explanations of their relations, are judicious and
instructive. Pignataro, a physician residing at Monteleone, a town
placed in the very centre of the convulsions, kept a register of the
shocks, distinguishing them into four classes, according to their degree
of violence. From his work, it appears that, in the year 1783, the
number was 949, of which 501 were shocks of the first degree of force;
473
and in the following year there were 151, of which 98 were of the first
magnitude.
Count Ippolito, also, and many others, wrote descriptions of the
earthquake; and the Royal Academy of Naples, not satisfied with these
and other observations, sent a deputation from their own body into Calabria,
before the shocks had ceased, who were accompanied by artists instructed
to illustrate by drawings the physical changes of the district,
and the state of ruined towns and edifices. Unfortunately these artists
were not very successful in their representations of the condition of the
country, particularly when they attempted to express, on a large scale,
the extraordinary revolutions which many of the great and minor river-courses
underwent. But many of the plates published by the Academy
are valuable; and as they are little known, I shall frequently avail myself
of them to illustrate the facts about to be described.665
In addition to these Neapolitan sources of information, our countryman,
Sir William Hamilton, surveyed the district, not without some
personal risk, before the shocks had ceased; and his sketch, published
in the Philosophical Transactions, supplies many facts that would otherwise
have been lost. He has explained, in a rational manner, many
events which, as related in the language of some eye-witnesses, appeared
marvellous and incredible. Dolomieu also examined Calabria during
the catastrophe, and wrote an account of the earthquake, correcting a
mistake into which Hamilton had fallen, who supposed that a part of
the tract shaken had consisted of volcanic tuff. It is, indeed, a circumstance
which enhances the geological interest of the commotions which
so often modify the surface of Calabria, that they are confined to a
country where there are neither ancient nor modern rocks of volcanic
or trappean origin; so that at some future time, when the era of disturbance
shall have passed by, the cause of former revolutions will be
as latent as in parts of Great Britain now occupied exclusively by ancient
marine formations.
Extent of the area convulsed.—The convulsion of the earth, sea, and
air extended over the whole of Calabria Ultra, the southeast part of
Calabria Citra, and across the sea to Messina and its environs; a district
lying between the 38th and 39th degrees of latitude. The concussion
was perceptible over a great part of Sicily, and as far north as Naples;
but the surface over which the shocks acted so forcibly as to excite
intense alarm did not generally exceed 500 square miles in area. The
soil of that part of Calabria is composed chiefly, like the southern part
of Sicily, of calcareo-argillaceous strata of great thickness, containing
marine shells. This clay is sometimes associated with beds of sand and
limestone. For the most part these formations resemble in appearance
and consistency the Subapennine marls, with their accompanying sands
and sandstones; and the whole group bears considerable resemblance,
474
in the yielding nature of its materials, to most of our tertiary deposits
in France and England. Chronologically considered, however, the Calabrian
formations are comparatively of modern date, often abounding in
fossil shells referable to species now living in the Mediterranean.
We learn from Vivencio, that on the 20th and 26th of March, 1783,
earthquakes occurred in the islands of Zante, Cephalonia, and St. Maura;
and in the last-mentioned island several public edifices and private
houses were overthrown, and many people destroyed.
If the city of Oppido, in Calabria Ultra, be taken as a centre, and
round that centre a circle be described, with a radius of twenty-two
miles, this space will comprehend the surface of the country which
suffered the greatest alteration, and where all the towns and villages
were destroyed. The first shock, of February 5th, 1783, threw down,
in two minutes, the greater part of the houses in all the cities, towns,
and villages, from the western flanks of the Apennines in Calabria Ultra
to Messina in Sicily, and convulsed the whole surface of the country.
Another occurred on the 28th of March, with almost equal violence.
The granitic chain which passes through Calabria from north to south,
and attains the height of many thousand feet, was shaken but slightly
by the first shock, but more rudely by some which followed.
Some writers have asserted that the wave-like movements which
were propagated through the recent strata, from west to east, became
very violent when they reached the point of junction with the granite,
as if a reaction was produced where the undulatory movement of the
soft strata was suddenly arrested by the more solid rocks. But the
statement of Dolomieu on this subject is most interesting, and perhaps,
in a geological point of view, the most important of all the observations
which are recorded.666 The Apennines, he says, which consist in great
part of hard and solid granite, with some micaceous and argillaceous
schists, form bare mountains with steep sides, and exhibit marks of
great degradation. At their base newer strata are seen of sand and
clay, mingled with shells; a marine deposit containing such ingredients
as would result from the decomposition of granite. The surface of this
newer (tertiary) formation constitutes what is called the plain of Calabria—a
platform which is flat and level, except where intersected by
narrow valleys or ravines, which rivers and torrents have excavated
sometimes to the depth of six hundred feet. The sides of these ravines
are almost perpendicular; for the superior stratum, being bound together
by the roots of trees, prevents the formation of a sloping bank.
The usual effect of the earthquake, he continues, was to disconnect all
those masses which either had not sufficient bases for their bulk, or
which was supported only by lateral adherence. Hence it follows that
throughout almost the whole length of the chain, the soil which adhered
to the granite at the base of the mountains Caulone, Esope, Sagra, and
475
Aspramonte, slid over the solid and steeply inclined nucleus, and descended
somewhat lower, leaving almost uninterruptedly from St.
George to beyond St. Christina, a distance of from nine to ten miles, a
chasm between the solid granitic nucleus and the sandy soil. Many
lands slipping thus were carried to a considerable distance from their
former position, so as entirely to cover others; and disputes arose as to
whom the property which had thus shifted its place should belong.
From this account of Dolomieu we might anticipate, as the result of a
continuance of such earthquakes, first, a longitudinal valley following the
line of junction of the older and newer rocks; secondly, greater disturbance
in the newer strata near the point of contact than at a greater distance
from the mountains; phenomena very common in other parts of
Italy at the junction of the Apennine and Subapennine formations.
Mr. Mallet, in his valuable essay on the Dynamics of Earthquakes,667
offers the following explanation of the fact to which Dolomieu has called
attention. When a wave of elastic compression, of which he considers
the earth-wave to consist, passes abruptly from a body having an extremely
low elasticity, such as clay and gravel, into another like granite,
whose elasticity is remarkably high, it changes not only its velocity but
in part also its course, a portion being reflected and a portion refracted.
The wave being thus sent back again produces a shock in the opposite
direction, doing great damage to buildings on the surface by thus returning
upon itself. At the same time, the shocks are at once eased
when they get into the more elastic materials of the granitic mountains.
The surface of the country during the Calabrian earthquakes often
heaved like the billows of a swelling sea, which produced a swimming
in the head, like sea-sickness. It is particularly stated, in almost all the
accounts, that just before each shock the clouds appeared motionless;
and, although no explanation is offered of this phenomenon, it is obviously
the same as that observed in a ship at sea when it pitches violently.
The clouds seem arrested in their career as often as the vessel rises in a
direction contrary to their course; so that the Calabrians must have experienced
precisely the same motion on the land.
Trees, supported by their trunks, sometimes bent during the shocks
to the earth, and touched it with their tops. This is mentioned as a
well-known fact by Dolomieu; and he assures us that he was always
on his guard against the spirit of exaggeration in which the vulgar are
ever ready to indulge when relating these wonderful occurrences.
It is impossible to suppose that these waves, which are described in
Italy and other regions of earthquakes as passing along the solid surface
of the earth in a given direction like a billow on the sea, have any strict
analogy with the undulations of a fluid. They are doubtless the effects
of vibrations, radiating from some deep-seated point, each of which on
reaching the surface lifts up the ground, and then allows it again to subside.
As the distance between the source of the subterranean move476ment
and the surface must vary according to the outline of the country,
so the vibratory jar will reach different points in succession.
Fig. 75.
Shifts in the stones of two obelisks in the Convent of St Bruno.
The Academicians relate that in some of the cities of Calabria effects
were produced seeming to indicate a whirling or vorticose movement.
Thus, for example, two obelisks (fig. 75) placed at the extremities of a
magnificent façade in the convent of S. Bruno, in a small town called
Stefano del Bosco, were observed to have undergone a movement of a
singular kind. The shock which agitated the building is described as
having been horizontal and vorticose. The pedestal of each obelisk
remained in its original place; but the separate stones above were
turned partially round, and removed sometimes nine inches from their
position without falling.
It has been suggested by Mr. Darwin that this kind of displacement
may be due to a vibratory rather than a whirling motion;668 and more
lately Mr. Mallet, in the paper already cited, has offered a very ingenious
solution of the problem. He refers the twisting simply to an elastic
wave, which has moved the pedestal forwards and back again, by an
alternate horizontal motion within narrow limits, and he has succeeded
in showing that a rectilinear movement in the ground may have sufficed
to cause an incumbent body to turn partially round upon its bed, provided
a certain relation exist between the position of the centre of gravity
of the body and its centre of adherence.669
I shall now consider, in the first place, that class of physical changes
produced by the earthquake which are connected with alterations in the
relative level of the different parts of the land; and afterwards describe
those which are more immediately connected with the derangement of
the regular drainage of the country, and where the force of running water
co-operated with that of the earthquake.
Difficulty of ascertaining changes of level.—In regard to alterations of
477relative level, none of the accounts establish that they were on a considerable
scale; but it must always be remembered that, in proportion
to the area moved is the difficulty of proving that the general level has
undergone any change, unless the sea-coast happens to have participated
in the principal movement. Even then it is often impossible to determine
whether an elevation or depression even of several feet has occurred,
because there is nothing to attract notice in a band of shingle and sand
of unequal breadth above the level of the sea running parallel to a coast;
such bands generally marking the point reached by the waves during
spring tides, or the most violent tempests. The scientific investigator
has not sufficient topographical knowledge to discover whether the extent
of beach has diminished or increased; and he who has the necessary
local information, scarcely ever feels any interest in ascertaining the
amount of the rise or fall of the ground. Add to this the great difficulty
of making correct observations, in consequence of the enormous
waves which roll in upon a coast during an earthquake, and efface every
landmark near the shore.
Subsidence of the quay at Messina.—It is evidently in seaports alone
that we can look for very accurate indications of slight changes of level;
and when we find them, we may presume that they would not be rare
at other points, if equal facilities of comparing relative altitudes were
afforded. Grimaldi states (and his account is confirmed by Hamilton and
others), that at Messina, in Sicily, the shore was rent; and the soil along
the port, which before the shock was perfectly level, was found afterwards
to be inclined towards the sea,—the sea itself near the "Banchina" becoming
deeper, and its bottom in several places disordered. The quay
also sunk down about fourteen inches below the level of the sea, and the
houses in its vicinity were much fissured. (Phil. Trans. 1783.)
Among various proofs of partial elevation and depression in the interior,
the Academicians mention, in their Survey, that the ground was
sometimes on the same level on both sides of new ravines and fissures,
but sometimes there had been a considerable shifting, either by the upheaving
of one side, or the subsidence of the other. Thus, on the sides
of long rents in the territory of Soriano, the stratified masses had altered
their relative position to the extent of from eight to fourteen palms (six
to ten and a half feet).
Polistena.—Similar shifts in the strata are alluded to in the territory
of Polistena, where there appeared innumerable fissures in the earth.
One of these was of great length and depth; and in parts the level of
the corresponding sides was greatly changed. (See fig. 76.)
Terranuova.—In the town of Terranuova some houses were seen uplifted
above the common level, and others adjoining sunk down into the
earth. In several streets the soil appeared thrust up, and abutted
against the walls of houses: a large circular tower of solid masonry,
part of which had withstood the general destruction, was divided by a
vertical rent, and one side was upraised, and the foundations heaved out
of the ground. It was compared by the Academicians to a great tooth
478
half extracted from the alveolus, with the upper part of the fangs exposed.
(See fig. 77.)
Fig. 76.
Deep fissure, near Polistena, caused by the earthquake of 1783.
Along the line of this shift, or "fault," as it would be termed technically
by miners, the walls were found to adhere firmly to each other, and
to fit so well, that the only signs of their having been disunited was the
want of correspondence in the courses of stone on either side of the rent.
Fig. 77.
Shift or "fault" in the Round Tower of Terranuova in Calabria, occasioned by the earthquake of
1783.
Dolomieu saw a stone well in the convent of the Augustins at Terranuova,
which had the appearance of having been driven out of the earth.
It resembled a small tower eight or nine feet in height, and a little inclined.
This effect, he says, was produced by the consolidation and
consequent sinking of the sandy soil in which the well was dug.
479
In some walls which had been thrown down, or violently shaken, in
Monteleone, the separate stones were parted from the mortar, so as to
leave an exact mould where they had rested; whereas in other cases
the mortar was ground to dust between the stones.
It appears that the wave-like motions often produced effects of the
most capricious kind. Thus, in some streets of Monteleone, every house
was thrown down but one; in others, all but two; and the buildings
which were spared were often scarcely in the least degree injured. In
many cities of Calabria, all the most solid buildings were thrown down,
while those which were slightly built escaped; but at Rosarno, as also
at Messina in Sicily, it was precisely the reverse, the massive edifices
being the only ones that stood.
Fissures.—It appears evident that a great part of the rending and
fissuring of the ground was the effect of a violent motion from below
upwards; and in a multitude of cases where the rents and chasms
opened and closed alternately, we must suppose that the earth was by
turns heaved up, and then let fall again.670 We may conceive the same
effect to be produced on a small scale, if, by some mechanical force, a
pavement composed of large flags of stone should be raised up, and
then allowed to fall suddenly, so as to resume its original position. If
any small pebbles happened to be lying on the line of contact of two
flags, they would fall into the opening when the pavement rose, and be
swallowed up, so that no trace of them would appear after the subsidence
of the stones. In the same manner, when the earth was upheaved,
large houses, trees, cattle, and men were engulfed in an instant
in chasms and fissures; and when the ground sank down again, the
earth closed upon them, so that no vestige of them was discoverable
on the surface. In many instances, individuals were swallowed up by
one shock, and then thrown out again alive, together with large jets of
water, by the shock which immediately succeeded.
Fig. 78.
Fissures near Jerocarne, in Calabria, caused by the earthquake of 1783.
480
At Jerocarne, a country which, according to the Academicians, was
lacerated in a most extraordinary manner, the fissures ran in every direction,
"like cracks on a broken pane of glass" (see fig. 78); and as a
great portion of them remained open after the shocks, it is very possible
that this country was permanently upraised. It was usual, as we learn
from Dolomieu, for the chasms and fissures throughout Calabria, to ran
parallel to the course of some pre-existing gorges in their neighborhood.
Houses engulfed.—In the vicinity of Oppido, the central point from
which the earthquake diffused its violent movements, many houses were
swallowed up by the yawning earth, which closed immediately over
them. In the adjacent district, also, of Cannamaria four farm-houses,
several oil-stores, and some spacious dwelling-houses were so completely
engulfed in one chasm, that not a vestige of them was afterwards discernible.
The same phenomena occurred at Terranuova, S. Christina,
and Sinopoli. The Academicians state particularly, that when deep
abysses had opened in the argillaceous strata of Terranuova, and houses
had sunk into them, the sides of the chasms closed with such violence,
that, on excavating afterwards to recover articles of value, the workmen
found the contents and detached parts of the buildings jammed together
so as to become one compact mass. It is unnecessary to accumulate examples
of similar occurrences; but so many are well authenticated during
this earthquake in Calabria, that we may, without hesitation, yield assent
to the accounts of catastrophes of the same kind repeated again and
again in history, where whole towns are declared to have been engulfed,
and nothing but a pool of water or tract of sand left in their place.
Chasm formed near Oppido.—On the sloping side of a hill near
Oppido a great chasm opened; and, although a large quantity of soil
was precipitated into the abyss, together with a considerable number
of olive-trees and part of a vineyard, a great gulf remained after the
shock, in the form of an amphitheatre, 500 feet long and 200 feet deep.
(See fig. 79.)
Fig. 79.
Chasm formed by the earthquake of 1783, near Oppido in Calabria.
481
Dimensions of new fissures and chasms.—According to Grimaldi,
many fissures and chasms, formed by the first shock of February 5th,
were greatly widened, lengthened, and deepened by the violent convulsions
of March 28th. In the territory of San Fili this observer found a
new ravine, half a mile in length, two feet and a half broad, and twenty-five
feet deep; and another of similar dimensions in the territory of
Rosarno. A ravine nearly a mile long, 105 feet broad and thirty feet
deep, opened in the district of Plaisano, where, also, two gulfs were
caused—one in a place called Cerzulle, three-quarters of a mile long,
150 feet broad, and above one hundred feet deep; and another at La
Fortuna, nearly a quarter of a mile long, above thirty feet in breadth,
and no less than 225 feet deep.
Fig. 80.
Chasm in the hill of St. Angelo, near Soriano, in Calabria, caused by the earthquake of 1783.
In the district of Fosolano three gulfs opened: one of these measured
300 feet square, and above thirty feet deep; another was nearly
half a mile long, fifteen feet broad, and above thirty-feet deep; the
third was 750 feet square. Lastly, a calcareous mountain, called
Zefirio, at the southern extremity of the Italian peninsula, was cleft in
two for the length of nearly half a mile, and an irregular breadth of
many feet. Some of these chasms were in the form of a crescent.
The annexed cut (fig. 80) represents one by no means remarkable for
its dimensions, which remained open by the side of a small pass over
the hill of St. Angelo, near Soriano. The small river Mesima is seen
in the foreground.
Formation of circular hollows and new lakes.—In the report of the
Academy, we find that some plains were covered with circular hollows,
for the most part about the size of carriage-wheels, but often somewhat
larger or smaller. When filled with water to within a foot or two of
the surface, they appeared like wells; but, in general, they were filled
with dry sand, sometimes with a concave surface, and at other times
convex. (See fig. 81.) On digging down, they found them to be funnel
482
shaped, and the moist loose sand in the centre marked the tube up
which the water spouted. The annexed cut (fig. 82) represents a section
of one of these inverted cones when the water had disappeared, and
nothing but dry micaceous sand remained.
Fig. 81.
Circular hollows in the plain of Rosarno, formed by the earthquake of 1783.

Fig. 82.
Section of one of the circular hollows formed in the plain of Rosarno.
A small circular pond of similar character was formed not far from
Polistena (see fig. 83); and in the vicinity of Seminara, a lake was suddenly
caused by the opening of a great chasm, from the bottom of which
water issued. This lake was called Lago del Tolfilo. It extended 1785
feet in length, by 937 in breadth, and 52 in depth. The inhabitants,
dreading the miasma of this stagnant pool, endeavored, at great cost, to
drain it by canals, but without success, as it was fed by springs issuing
from the bottom of the deep chasm.
Vivenzio states, that near Sitizzano a valley was nearly filled up to a
level with the high grounds on each side, by the enormous masses detached
483
from the boundary hills, and cast down into the course of two
streams. By this barrier a lake was formed of great depth, about two
miles long and a mile broad. The same author mentions that, upon the
whole, there were fifty lakes occasioned during the convulsions: and he
assigns localities to all of these. The government surveyors enumerated
215 lakes; but they included in this number many small ponds.
Fig. 83.
Circular pond near Polistena, in Calabria, caused by the earthquake in 1783.
Cones of sand thrown up.—Many of the appearances exhibited in the
alluvial plains, such as springs spouting up their water like fountains at
the moment of the shock, have been supposed to indicate the alternate
rising and sinking of the ground. The first effect of the more violent
shocks was usually to dry up the rivers, but they immediately afterwards
overflowed their banks. In marshy places, an immense number of cones
of sand were thrown up. These appearances Hamilton explains, by
supposing that the first movement raised the fissured plain from below
upwards, so that the rivers and stagnant waters in bogs sank down, or
at least were not upraised with the soil. But when the ground returned
with violence to its former position, the water was thrown up in jets
through fissures.671
The phenomenon, according to Mr. Mallet, may be simply an accident
contingent on the principal cause of disturbance, the rapid transit of the
earth-wave. "The sources," he says, "of copious springs usually lie in
flat plates or fissures filled with water, whether issuing from solid rock,
or from loose materials; now, if a vein, or thin flat cavity filled with
water, be in such a position that the plane of the plate of water or fissure
be transverse to the line of transit of the earth-wave, the effect of
the arrival of the earth-wave at the watery fissure will be, at the instant,
to compress its walls more or less together, and so squeeze out the water,
which will, for a moment, gush up at the spring-head like a fountain, and
again remain in repose after the transit of the wave."
Gradual closing in of fissures.—Sir W. Hamilton was shown several
484
deep fissures in the vicinity of Mileto, which, although not one of them
was above a foot in breadth, had opened so wide during the earthquake
as to swallow an ox and nearly one hundred goats. The Academicians
also found, on their return through districts which they had passed at
the commencement of their tour, that many rents had, in that short
interval, gradually closed in, so that their width had diminished several
feet, and the opposite walls had sometimes nearly met. It is natural
that this should happen in argillaceous strata, while, in more solid rocks,
we may expect that fissures will remain open for ages. Should this be
ascertained to be a general fact in countries convulsed by earthquakes,
it may afford a satisfactory explanation of a common phenomenon in
mineral veins. Such veins often retain their full size so long as the rocks
consist of limestone, granite, or other indurated materials; but they contract
their dimensions, become mere threads, or are even entirely cut off,
where masses of an argillaceous nature are interposed. If we suppose
the filling up of fissures with metallic and other ingredients to be a process
requiring ages for its completion, it is obvious that the opposite walls
of rents, where strata consist of yielding materials, must collapse or
approach very near to each other before sufficient time is allowed for the
accretion of a large quantity of veinstone.
Thermal waters augmented.—It is stated by Grimaldi, that the thermal
waters of St. Eufemia, in Terra di Amato, which first burst out during
the earthquake of 1638, acquired, in February, 1783, an augmentation
both in quantity and degree of heat. This fact appears to indicate
a connection between the heat of the interior and the fissures caused by
the Calabrian earthquakes, notwithstanding the absence of volcanic rocks,
either ancient or modern, in that district.
Bounding of detached masses into the air.—The violence of the movement
of the ground upwards was singularly illustrated by what the
Academicians call the "sbalzo," or bounding into the air, to the height
of several yards, of masses slightly adhering to the surface. In some
towns a great part of the pavement stones were thrown up, and found
lying with their lower sides uppermost. In these cases, we must suppose
that they were propelled upwards by the momentum which they
had acquired; and that the adhesion of one end of the mass being greater
than that of the other, a rotatory motion had been communicated to them.
When the stone was projected to a sufficient height to perform somewhat
more than a quarter of a revolution in the air, it pitched down on
its edge, and fell with its lower side uppermost.
Effects of earthquakes on the excavations of valleys.—The next class
of effects to be considered, are those more immediately connected with
the formation of valleys, in which the action of water was often combined
with that of the earthquake. The country agitated was composed, as
before stated, chiefly of argillaceous strata, intersected by deep narrow
valleys, sometimes from 500 to 600 feet deep. As the boundary cliffs
were in great part vertical, it will readily be conceived that, amidst the
various movements of the earth, the precipices overhanging rivers, being
485
without support on one side, were often thrown down. We find, indeed,
that inundations produced by obstructions in river-courses are among
the most disastrous consequences of great earthquakes in all parts of the
world, for the alluvial plains in the bottoms of valleys are usually the
most fertile and well-peopled parts of the whole country; and whether
the site of a town is above or below a temporary barrier in the channel
of a river, it is exposed to injury by the waters either of a lake or flood.
Landslips.—From each side of the deep valley or ravine of Terranuova
enormous masses of the adjoining flat country were detached, and
cast down into the course of the river, so as to give rise to great lakes.
Oaks, olive-trees, vineyards, and corn, were often seen growing at the
bottom of the ravine, as little injured as their former companions, which
still continued to flourish in the plain above, at least 500 feet higher,
and at the distance of about three-quarters of a mile. In one part of
this ravine was an enormous mass, 200 feet high and about 400 feet at
its base, which had been detached by some former earthquake. It is
well attested, that this mass travelled down the ravine nearly four miles,
having been put in motion by the earthquake of the 5th of February.
Hamilton, after examining the spot, declared that this phenomenon
might be accounted for by the declivity of the valley, the great abundance
of rain which fell, and the great weight of the alluvial matter
which pressed behind it. Dolomieu also alludes to the fresh impulse
derived from other masses falling, and pressing upon the rear of those
first set in motion.
The first account sent to Naples of the two great slides or landslips
above alluded to, which caused a great lake near Terranuova, was
couched in these words:—"Two mountains on the opposite sides of a
valley walked from their original position until they met in the middle
of the plain, and there joining together, they intercepted the course of
a river," &c. The expressions here used resemble singularly those
applied to phenomena, probably very analogous, which are said to have
occurred at Fez, during the great Lisbon earthquake, as also in Jamaica
and Java at other periods.
Not far from Soriano, which was levelled to the ground by the great
shock of February, a small valley, containing a beautiful olive-grove,
called Fra Ramondo, underwent a most extraordinary revolution. Innumerable
fissures first traversed the river-plain in all directions, and
absorbed the water until the argillaceous substratum became soaked, so
that a great part of it was reduced to a state of fluid paste. Strange
alterations in the outline of the ground were the consequence, as the
soil to a great depth was easily moulded into any form. In addition to
this change, the ruins of the neighboring hills were precipitated into
the hollow; and while many olives were uprooted, others remained
growing on the fallen masses, and inclined at various angles (see fig. 84).
The small river Caridi was entirely concealed for many days; and when
at length it reappeared, it had shaped for itself an entirely new channel.
Buildings transported entire to great distances.—Near Seminara an
486
extensive olive-ground and orchard were hurled to a distance of two
hundred feet, into a valley sixty feet in depth. At the same time a
deep chasm was riven in another part of the high platform from which
the orchard had been detached, and the river immediately entered the
fissure, leaving its former bed completely dry. A small inhabited
house, standing on the mass of earth carried down into the valley, went
along with it entire, and without injury to the inhabitants. The olive-trees,
also, continued to grow on the land which had slid into the valley,
and bore the same year an abundant crop of fruit.
Fig. 84.
Changes of the surface at Fra Ramondo, near Soriano, in Calabria.
1, Portion of a hill covered with olives thrown down.
2, New bed of the river Caridi.
3, Town of Soriano.
Two tracts of land on which a great part of the town of Polistena
stood, consisting of some hundreds of houses, were detached into a contiguous
ravine, and nearly across it, about half a mile from their original
site; and what is most extraordinary, several of the inhabitants were
dug out from the ruins alive and unhurt.
Two tenements, near Mileto, called the Macini and Vaticano, occupying
an extent of ground about a mile long and half a mile broad,
were carried for a mile down a valley. A thatched cottage, together
with large olive and mulberry trees, most of which remained erect, were
carried uninjured to this extraordinary distance. According to Hamilton,
the surface removed had been long undermined by rivulets, which
were afterwards in full view on the bare spot deserted by the tenements.
The earthquake seems to have opened a passage in the adjoining argillaceous
hills, which admitted water charged with loose soil into the
subterranean channels of the rivulets immediately under the tenements,
so that the foundations of the ground set in motion by the earthquake
were loosened. Another example of subsidence, where the edifices
487
were not destroyed, is mentioned by Grimaldi, as having taken place in
the city of Catanzaro, the capital of the province of that name. The
houses in the quarter called San Giuseppe subsided with the ground to
various depths from two to four feet, but the buildings remained uninjured.
Fig. 85.
Landslips near Cinquefrondi, caused by the earthquake of 1783.
It would be tedious, and our space would not permit us, to follow the
different authors through their local details of landslips produced in
minor valleys; but they are highly interesting, as showing to how great
an extent the power of rivers to widen valleys, and to carry away large
portions of soil towards the sea, is increased where earthquakes are of
periodical occurrence. Among other territories, that of Cinquefrondi,
was greatly convulsed, various portions of soil being raised or sunk, and
innumerable fissures traversing the country in all directions (see fig. 85).
Along the flanks of a small valley in this district there appears to have
been an almost uninterrupted line of landslips.
Currents of mud.—Near S. Lucido, among other places, the soil is
described as having been "dissolved," so that large torrents of mud inundated
all the low grounds, like lava. Just emerging from this mud,
the tops only of trees and of the ruins of farm-houses were seen. Two
miles from Laureana, the swampy soil in two ravines became filled with
calcareous matter, which oozed out from the ground immediately before
the first great shock. This mud, rapidly accumulating, began, ere long,
to roll onward, like a flood of lava, into the valley, where the two streams
uniting, moved forward with increased impetus from east to west. It
now presented a breadth of 225 feet by 15 in depth, and, before it ceased
to move, covered a surface equal in length to an Italian mile. In its
progress it overwhelmed a flock of thirty goats, and tore up by the roots
many olive and mulberry trees, which floated like ships upon its surface.
When this calcareous lava had ceased to move, it gradually became dry
and hard, during which process the mass was lowered seven feet and a
488
half. It contained fragments of earth of a ferruginous color, and emitting
a sulphureous smell.
Fall of the sea-cliffs.—Along the sea-coast of the Straits of Messina,
near the celebrated rock of Scilla, the fall of huge masses detached from
the bold and lofty cliffs overwhelmed many villas and gardens. At Gian
Greco, a continuous line of cliff, for a mile in length, was thrown down.
Great agitation was frequently observed in the bed of the sea during
the shocks, and, on those parts of the coast where the movement was
most violent, all kinds of fish were taken in abundance, and with unusual
facility. Some rare species, as that called Cicirelli, which usually lie
buried in the sand, were taken on the surface of the waters in great
quantity. The sea is said to have boiled up near Messina, and to have
been agitated as if by a copious discharge of vapors from its bottom.
Shore near Scilla inundated.—The prince of Scilla had persuaded a
great part of his vassals to betake themselves to their fishing-boats for
safety, and he himself had gone on board. On the night of the 5th of
February, when some of the people were sleeping in the boats, and others
on a level plain slightly elevated above the sea, the earth rocked, and
suddenly a great mass was torn from the contiguous Mount Jaci, and
thrown down with a dreadful crash upon the plain. Immediately afterwards,
the sea, rising more than twenty feet above the level of this low
tract, rolled foaming over it, and swept away the multitude. It then
retreated, but soon rushed back again with greater violence, bringing
with it some of the people and animals it had carried away. At the same
time every boat was sunk or dashed against the beach, and some of them
were swept far inland. The aged prince, with 1430 of his people, was
destroyed.
State of Stromboli and Etna during the shocks.—The inhabitants of
Pizzo remarked that on the 5th of February, 1783, when the first great
shock afflicted Calabria, the volcano of Stromboli, which is in full view
of that town, and at the distance of about fifty miles, smoked less, and
threw up a less quantity of inflamed matter than it had done for some
years previously. On the other hand, the great crater of Etna is said
to have given out a considerable quantity of vapor towards the beginning,
and Stromboli towards the close, of the commotions. But as no
eruption happened from either of these great vents during the whole
earthquake, the sources of the Calabrian convulsions, and of the volcanic
fires of Etna and Stromboli, appear to be very independent of each other;
unless, indeed, they have the same mutual relation as Vesuvius and the
volcanoes of the Phlegræan Fields and Ischia, a violent disturbance in
one district serving as a safety-valve to the other, and both never being
in full activity at once.
Excavation of valleys.—It is impossible for the geologist to consider
attentively the effect of this single earthquake of 1783, and to look forward
to the alterations in the physical condition of the country to which
a continued series of such movements will hereafter give rise, without
perceiving that the formation of valleys by running water can never be
489
understood, if we consider the question independently of the agency of
earthquakes. It must not be imagined that rivers only begin to act when
a country is already elevated far above the level of the sea, for their
action must of necessity be most powerful while land is rising and sinking
by successive movements. Whether Calabria is now undergoing
any considerable change of relative level, in regard to the sea, or is, upon
the whole, nearly stationary, is a question which our observations, confined
almost entirely to the last half century, cannot possibly enable us
to determine. But we know that strata, containing species of shells
identical with those now living in the contiguous parts of the Mediterranean,
have been raised in that country, as they have in Sicily, to the
height of several thousand feet.
Now, those geologists who grant that the present course of Nature
in the inanimate world has continued the same since the existing species
of animals were in being, will not feel surprised that the Calabrian streams
and rivers have cut out of such comparatively modern strata a great system
of valleys, varying in depth from fifty to six hundred feet, and often
several miles wide, if they consider how numerous may have been the
shocks which accompanied the uplifting of those recent marine strata to
so prodigious a height. Some speculators, indeed, who disregard the
analogy of existing nature, and who are always ready to assume that her
forces were more energetic in by-gone ages, may dispense with a long
series of movements, and suppose that Calabria "rose like an exhalation"
from the deep, after the manner of Milton's Pandemonium. But such
an hypothesis would deprive them of that peculiar removing force required
to form a regular system of deep and wide valleys; for time,
which they are so unwilling to assume, is essential to the operation.
Time must be allowed in the intervals between distinct convulsions, for
running water to clear away the ruins caused by landslips, otherwise the
fallen masses will serve as buttresses, and prevent the succeeding earthquake
from exerting its full power. The sides of the valley must be
again cut away by the stream, and made to form precipices and overhanging
cliffs, before the next shock can take effect in the same manner.
Possibly the direction of the succeeding shock may not coincide with
that of the valley, a great extent of adjacent country being equally
shaken. Still it will usually happen that no permanent geographical
change will be produced except in valleys. In them alone will occur
landslips from the boundary cliffs, and these will frequently divert the
stream from its accustomed course, causing the original ravine to become
both wider and more tortuous in its direction.
If a single convulsion of extreme violence should agitate at once an
entire hydrographical basin, or if the shocks should follow each other
too rapidly, the previously existing valleys would be annihilated, instead
of being modified and enlarged. Every stream might in that case be
compelled to begin its operations anew, and to shape out new channels,
instead of continuing to deepen and widen those already excavated. But
if the subterranean movements have been intermittent, and if sufficient
490
periods have always intervened between the severer shocks to allow the
drainage of the country to be nearly restored to its original state, then
are both the kind and degree of force supplied by which running water
may hollow out valleys of any depth or size consistent with the elevation
above the sea which the districts drained by them may have attained.
When we read of the drying up and desertion of the channels of
rivers, the accounts most frequently refer to their deflection into some
other part of the same alluvial plain, perhaps several miles distant. Under
certain circumstances a change of level may undoubtedly force the water
to flow over into some distinct hydrographical basin; but even then it
will fall immediately into some other system of valleys already formed.
We learn from history that, ever since the first Greek colonists settled
in Calabria, that region has been subject to devastation by earthquakes;
and, for the last century and a half, ten years have seldom elapsed without
a shock; but the severer convulsions have not only been separated
by intervals of twenty, fifty, or one hundred years, but have not affected
precisely the same points when they recurred. Thus the earthquake of
1783, although confined within the same geographical limits as that of
1638, and not very inferior in violence, visited, according to Grimaldi,
very different districts. The points where the local intensity of the
force is developed being thus perpetually varied, more time is allowed
for the removal of separate mountain masses thrown into river-channels
by each shock.
Number of persons who perished during the earthquake.—The number
of persons who perished during the earthquake in the two Calabrias and
Sicily, is estimated by Hamilton at about forty thousand; and about
twenty thousand more died by epidemics, which were caused by insufficient
nourishment, exposure to the atmosphere, and malaria, arising
from the new stagnant lakes and pools.
By far the greater number were buried under the ruins of their houses;
but many were burnt to death in the conflagrations which almost invariably
followed the shocks. These fires raged the more violently in
some cities, such as Oppido, from the immense magazines of oil which
were consumed.
Many persons were engulfed in deep fissures, especially the peasants
when flying across the open country, and their skeletons may perhaps
be buried in the earth to this day, at the depth of several hundred feet.
When Dolomieu visited Messina after the shock of Feb. 5th, he describes
the city as still presenting, at least at a distance, an imperfect
image of its ancient splendor. Every house was injured, but the walls
were standing; the whole population had taken refuge in wooden huts
in the neighborhood, and all was solitude and silence in the streets: it
seemed as if the city had been desolated by the plague, and the impression
made upon his feelings was that of melancholy and sadness. "But
when I passed over to Calabria, and first beheld Polistena, the scene of
horror almost deprived me of my faculties; my mind was filled with
mingled compassion and terror; nothing had escaped; all was levelled
491
with the dust; not a single house or piece of wall remained; on all sides
were heaps of stone so destitute of form, that they gave no conception
of there ever having been a town on the spot. The stench of the dead
bodies still rose from the ruins. I conversed with many persons who
had been buried for three, four, and even for five days; I questioned
them respecting their sensations in so dreadful a situation, and they
agreed that of all the physical evils they endured, thirst was the most
intolerable; and that their mental agony was increased by the idea that
they were abandoned by their friends, who might have rendered them
assistance."672
It is supposed that about a fourth part of the inhabitants of Polistena,
and of some other towns, were buried alive, and might have been saved
had there been no want of hands; but in so general a calamity, where
each was occupied with his own misfortunes or those of his family, aid
could rarely be obtained. Neither tears, nor supplications, nor promises
of high rewards were listened to. Many acts of self-devotion, prompted
by parental and conjugal tenderness, or by friendship, or the gratitude
of faithful servants, are recorded; but individual exertions were, for the
most part, ineffectual. It frequently happened, that persons in search
of those most dear to them could hear their moans,—could recognize
their voices—were certain of the exact spot where they lay buried beneath
their feet, yet could afford them no succor. The piled mass
resisted all their strength, and rendered their efforts of no avail.
At Terranuova, four Augustin monks, who had taken refuge in a
vaulted sacristy, the arch of which continued to support an immense pile
of ruins, made their cries heard for the space of four days. One only of
the brethren of the whole convent was saved, and "of what avail was
his strength to remove the enormous weight of rubbish which had overwhelmed
his companions?" He heard their voices die away gradually;
and when afterwards their four corpses were disinterred, they were found
clasped in each other's arms. Affecting narratives are preserved of
mothers saved after the fifth, sixth, and even seventh day of their interment,
when their infants or children had perished with hunger.
It might have been imagined that the sight of sufferings such as these
would have been sufficient to awaken sentiments of humanity and pity in
the most savage breasts; but while some acts of heroism are related,
nothing could exceed the general atrocity of conduct displayed by the
Calabrian peasants: they abandoned the farms, and flocked in great
numbers into the towns—not to rescue their countrymen from a lingering
death, but to plunder. They dashed through the streets, fearless of
danger, amid tottering walls and clouds of dust, trampling beneath their
feet the bodies of the wounded and half-buried, and often stripping them,
while yet living, of their clothes.673
Concluding remarks.—But to enter more fully into these details would
be foreign to the purpose of the present work, and several volumes
492
would be required to give the reader a just idea of the sufferings which
the inhabitants of many populous districts have undergone during the
earthquakes of the last 150 years. A bare mention of the loss of life—as
that fifty or a hundred thousand souls perished in one catastrophe—conveys
to the reader no idea of the extent of misery inflicted: we must
learn, from the narratives of eye-witnesses, the various forms in which
death was encountered, the numbers who escaped with loss of limbs or
serious bodily injuries, and the multitude who were suddenly reduced to
penury and want. It has been often remarked, that the dread of earthquakes
is strongest in the minds of those who have experienced them
most frequently; whereas, in the case of almost every other danger,
familiarity with peril renders men intrepid. The reason is obvious—scarcely
any part of the mischief apprehended in this instance is imaginary;
the first shock is often the most destructive; and, as it may occur
in the dead of the night, or if by day, without giving the least warning
of its approach, no forethought can guard against it; and when the convulsion
has begun, no skill, or courage, or presence of mind, can point
out the path of safety. During the intervals, of uncertain duration,
between the more fatal shocks, slight tremors of the soil are not unfrequent;
and as these sometimes precede more violent convulsions, they
become a source of anxiety and alarm. The terror arising from this
cause alone is of itself no inconsiderable evil.
Although sentiments of pure religion are frequently awakened by these
awful visitations, yet we more commonly find that an habitual state of
fear, a sense of helplessness, and a belief in the futility of all human exertions,
prepare the minds of the vulgar for the influence of a demoralizing
superstition.
Where earthquakes are frequent, there can never be perfect security
of property under the best government; industry cannot be assured of
reaping the fruits of its labor; and the most daring acts of outrage may
occasionally be perpetrated with impunity, when the arm of the law is
paralyzed by the general consternation. It is hardly necessary to add,
that the progress of civilization and national wealth must be retarded by
convulsions which level cities to the ground, destroy harbors, render
roads impassable, and cause the most cultivated valley-plains to be
covered with lakes, or the ruins of adjoining hills.
Those geologists who imagine that, at remote periods ere man became
a sojourner on earth, the volcanic agency was more energetic than now,
should be careful to found their opinion on strict geological evidence, and
not permit themselves to be biased, as they have often been, by a
notion, that the disturbing force would probably be mitigated for the
sake of man.
I shall endeavor to point out in the sequel, that the general tendency
of subterranean movements, when their effects are considered for a sufficient
lapse of ages, is eminently beneficial, and that they constitute an
essential part of that mechanism by which the integrity of the habitable
surface is preserved, and the very existence and perpetuation of dry land
493
secured. Why the working of this same machinery should be attended
with so much evil, is a mystery far beyond the reach of our philosophy,
and must probably remain so until we are permitted to investigate, not
our planet alone and its inhabitants, but other parts of the moral and
material universe with which they may be connected. Could our survey
embrace other worlds, and the events, not of a few centuries only,
but of periods as indefinite as those with which geology renders us
familiar, some apparent contradictions might be reconciled, and some
difficulties would doubtless be cleared up. But even then, as our capacities
are finite, while the scheme of the universe may be infinite, both
in time and space, it is presumptuous to suppose that all sources of doubt
and perplexity would ever be removed. On the contrary, they might,
perhaps, go on augmenting in number, although our confidence in the
wisdom of the plan of Nature should increase at the same time; for it
has been justly said, that the greater the circle of light, the greater the
boundary of darkness by which it is surrounded.674
</div></body></text></TEI>