<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="141">CHAPTER XIII.
Undulatory Theory.

Direction of the Transverse Vibrations in
Polarization.
IN the conclusion of Chapter xiii. I have stated that there is a point
in the undulatory theory which was regarded as left undecided by Young
and Fresnel, and on which the two different opinions have been
maintained by different mathematicians; namely, whether the vibrations
of polarized light are perpendicular to the plane of polarization or
in that plane. Professor Stokes of Cambridge has attempted to solve
this question in a manner which is, theoretically, exceedingly
ingenious, though it is difficult to make the requisite experiments in
a decisive manner. The method may be briefly described.
If polarized light be diffracted (see Chap. xi. sect. 2), each ray will be bent from its position,
but will still be polarized. The original ray and the diffracted ray,
thus forming a broken line, may be supposed to be connected at the
angle by a universal joint (called a Hooke’s Joint), such that
when the original ray turns about its axis, the diffracted ray also
turns about its axis; as in the case of the long handle of a telescope
and the screw which is turned by it. Now if the motion of the original
ray round its axis be uniform, the motion of the diffracted ray round
its axis is not uniform: and hence if, in a series of cases, the
planes of polarization of the original ray differ by equal angles, in
the diffracted ray the planes of polarization will differ by unequal
angles. Then if vibrations be perpendicular to the plane of
polarization, the planes of polarization in the diffracted rays will
be crowded together in the neighborhood of the plane in which the
diffraction takes place, and will be more rarely distributed in the
neighborhood of the plane perpendicular to this, in which is the
diffracting thread or groove.
On making the experiment, Prof. Stokes conceived that he found, in
his experiments, such a crowding of the planes of diffracted
polarization towards the plane of diffraction; and thus he held that
the 604 hypothesis
that the transverse vibrations which constitute polarization are
perpendicularly transverse to the plane of polarization was
confirmed.8
8 Camb. Trans., vol. ix. part i.
1849.
But Mr. Holtzmann,9 who, assenting to the reasoning, has
made the experiment in a somewhat different manner, has obtained an
opposite result; so that the point may be regarded as still
doubtful.
9 Phil. Mag., Feb. 1857.
Final Disproof of the Emission Theory.
As I have stated in the History, we cannot
properly say that there ever was an Emission Theory of Light which was
the rival of the Undulatory Theory: for while the undulatory
theory provided explanations of new classes of phenomena as fast as
they arose, and exhibited a consilience of theories in these
explanations, the hypothesis of emitted particles required new
machinery for every new set of facts, and soon ceased to be capable
even of expressing the facts. The simple cases of the ordinary
reflexion and refraction of light were explained by Newton on the
supposition that the transmission of light is the motion of particles:
and though his explanation includes a somewhat harsh assumption (that
a refracting surface exercises an attractive force through a fixed
finite space), the authority of his great name gave it a sort of
permanent notoriety, and made it to be regarded as a standard point of
comparison between a supposed “Emission Theory” and the undulation
theory. And the way in which the theories were to be tested in this
case was obvious: in the Newtonian theory, the velocity of light is
increased by the refracting medium; in the undulatory theory, it is
diminished. On the former hypothesis the velocity of light in air and
in water is as 3 to 4; in the latter, as 4 to 3.
But the immense velocity of light made it appear impossible to
measure it, within the limits of any finite space which we can occupy
with refracting matter. The velocity of light is known from
astronomical phenomena;—from the eclipses of Jupiter’s
satellites, by which it appears that light occupies 8 minutes in
coming from the sun to the earth; and from the aberration of light, by
which its velocity is shown to be 10,000 times the velocity of the
earth in its orbit. Is it, then, possible to make apparent so small a
difference as that between its passing through a few yards of air and
of water?
Mr. Wheatstone, in 1831, invented a machine by which this could
605 be done. His
object was to determine the velocity of the electric shock. His
apparatus consisted in a small mirror, turning with great velocity
about an axis which is in its own plane, like a coin spinning on its
edge. The velocity of spinning may be made so great, that an object
reflected shall change its place perceptibly after an almost
inconceivably small fraction of a second. The application of this
contrivance to measure the velocity of light, was, at the suggestion
of Arago, who had seen the times of the rival theories of light,
undertaken by younger men at Paris, his eyesight not allowing him to
prosecute such a task himself. It was necessary that the mirrors
should turn more than 1000 times in a second, in order that the two
images, produced, one by light coming through air, and the other by
light coming through an equal length of water, should have places
perceptibly different. The mechanical difficulties of the experiment
consisted in keeping up this great velocity by the machinery without
destroying the machinery, and in transmitting the light without too
much enfeebling it. These difficulties were overcome in 1850, by M.
Fizeau and M. Léon Foucault separately: and the result was, that the
velocity of light was found to be less in water than in air. And thus
the Newtonian explanation of refraction, the last remnant of the
Emission Theory, was proved to be false.


BOOK X.

THERMOTICS.—ATMOLOGY.
</div></body></text></TEI>