<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="2">CHAPTER II.
HISTORICAL SKETCH OF THE PROGRESS OF GEOLOGY.
Oriental Cosmogony—Hymns of the Vedas—Institutes of Menù—Doctrine of the
successive destruction and renovation of the world—Origin of this doctrine—Common
to the Egyptians—Adopted by the Greeks—System of Pythagoras—Of
Aristotle—Dogmas concerning the extinction and reproduction of genera
and species—Strabo's theory of elevation by earthquakes—Pliny—Concluding
Remarks on the knowledge of the Ancients.
Oriental Cosmogony.—The earliest doctrines of the Indian and Egyptian
schools of philosophy agreed in ascribing the first creation of the
world to an omnipotent and infinite Being. They concurred also in representing
this Being, who had existed from all eternity, as having repeatedly
destroyed and reproduced the world and all its inhabitants.
In the sacred volume of the Hindoos, called the Ordinances of Menù,
comprising the Indian system of duties religious and civil, we find a preliminary
chapter treating of the Creation, in which the cosmogony is
known to have been derived from earlier writings and traditions; and
principally from certain hymns of high antiquity, called the Vedas.
These hymns were first put together, according to Mr. Colebrooke,1 in
a connected series, about thirteen centuries before the Christian era, but
they appear from internal evidence to have been written at various antecedent
periods. In them, as we learn from the researches of Professor
Wilson, the eminent Sanscrit scholar, two distinct philosophical systems
are discoverable. According to one of them, all things were originally
brought into existence by the sole will of a single First Cause,
which existed from eternity; according to the other, there have always
existed two principles, the one material, but without form, the other
spiritual and capable of compelling "inert matter to develop its sensible
properties." This development of matter into "individual and visible
existences" is called creation, and is assigned to a subordinate agent, or the
creative faculty of the Supreme Being embodied in the person of Brahma.
In the first chapter of the Ordinances of Menù above alluded to, we
meet with the following passages relating to former destructions and
renovations of the world:—
"The Being, whose powers are incomprehensible, having created me
(Menù) and this universe, again became absorbed in the supreme spirit,
changing the time of energy for the hour of repose.
"When that Power awakes, then has this world its full expansion;
but when he slumbers with a tranquil spirit, then the whole system
fades away..... For while he reposes, as it were, embodied spirits
5endowed with principles of action depart from their several acts, and
the mind itself becomes inert."
The absorption of all beings into the Supreme essence is then described,
and the Divine soul itself is said to slumber, and to remain for
a time immersed in "the first idea, or in darkness." After which the
text thus proceeds (verse fifty-seven), "Thus that immutable power
by waking and reposing alternately, revivifies and destroys, in eternal succession,
this whole assemblage of locomotive and immovable creatures."
It is then declared that there has been a long succession of manwantaras,
or periods, each of the duration of many thousand ages, and—
"There are creations also, and destructions of worlds innumerable:
the Being, supremely exalted, performs all this with as much ease as if
in sport, again and again, for the sake of conferring happiness."2
No part of the Eastern cosmogony, from which these extracts are
made, is more interesting to the geologist than the doctrine, so frequently
alluded to, of the reiterated submersion of the land beneath the
waters of a universal ocean. In the beginning of things, we are told,
the First Sole Cause "with a thought created the waters," and then
moved upon their surface in the form of Brahma the creator, by whose
agency the emergence of the dry land was effected, and the peopling
of the earth with plants, animals, celestial creatures, and man. Afterwards,
as often as a general conflagration at the close of each manwantara
had annihilated every visible and existing thing, Brahma, on
awaking from his sleep, finds the whole world a shapeless ocean. Accordingly,
in the legendary poems called the Puranas, composed at a
later date than the Vedas, the three first Avatars or descents of the
Deity upon earth have for their object to recover the land from the
waters. For this purpose Vishnu is made successively to assume the
form of a fish, a tortoise, and a boar.
Extravagant as may be some of the conceits and fictions which disfigure
these pretended revelations, we can by no means look upon them
as a pure effort of the unassisted imagination, or believe them to have
been composed without regard to opinions and theories founded on the
observation of Nature. In astronomy, for instance, it is declared that,
at the North Pole, the year was divided into a long day and night, and
that their long day was the northern, and their night the southern
course of the sun; and to the inhabitants of the moon, it is said one
day is equal in length to one month of mortals.3 If such statements
cannot be resolved into mere conjectures, we have no right to refer to
mere chance the prevailing notion that the earth and its inhabitants had
formerly undergone a succession of revolutions and aqueous catastrophes
interrupted by long intervals of tranquillity.
Now there are two sources in which such a theory may have originated.
The marks of former convulsions on every part of the surface of
6our planet are obvious and striking. The remains of marine animals
imbedded in the solid strata are so abundant, that they may be expected
to force themselves on the attention of every people who have made
some progress in refinement; and especially where one class of men
are expressly set apart from the rest, like the ancient priesthoods of
India and Egypt, for study and contemplation. If these appearances
are once recognized, it seems natural that the mind should conclude in
favor, not only of mighty changes in past ages, but of alternate periods
of repose and disorder;—of repose, when the animals now fossil lived,
grew, and multiplied—of disorder, when the strata in which they were
buried became transferred from the sea to the interior of continents, and
were uplifted so as to form part of high mountain-chains. Those modern
writers, who are disposed to disparage the former intellectual
advancement and civilization of Eastern nations, may concede some
foundation of observed facts for the curious theories now under consideration,
without indulging in exaggerated opinions of the progress of
science; especially as universal catastrophes of the world, and exterminations
of organic beings, in the sense in which they were understood
by the Brahmins, are untenable doctrines.
We know that the Egyptian priests were aware, not only that
the soil beneath the plains of the Nile, but that also the hills bounding
the great valley, contained marine shells; and Herodotus inferred
from these facts, that all lower Egypt, and even the high lands above
Memphis, had once been covered by the sea.4 As similar fossil
remains occur in all parts of Asia hitherto explored, far in the
interior of the continent as well as near the sea, they could hardly
have escaped detection by some Eastern sages not less capable
than the Greek historian of reasoning philosophically on natural phenomena.
We also know that the rulers of Asia were engaged in very remote
eras in executing great national works, such as tanks and canals, requiring
extensive excavations. In the fourteenth century of our era
(in the year 1360), the removal of soil necessary for such undertakings
brought to light geological facts, which attracted the attention of a people
less civilized than were many of the older nations of the East. The
historian Ferishta relates that fifty thousand laborers were employed
in cutting through a mound, so as to form a junction between the rivers
Selima and Sutlej; and in this mound were found the bones of elephants
and men, some of them petrified, and some of them resembling
bone. The gigantic dimensions attributed to the human bones show
them to have belonged to some of the larger pachydermata.5
But, although the Brahmins, like the priests of Egypt, may have
7
been acquainted with the existence of fossil remains in the strata, it is
possible that the doctrine of successive destructions and renovations of
the world, merely received corroboration from such proofs; and that it
may have been originally handed down, like the religious traditions of
most nations, from a ruder state of society. The system may have had
its source, in part at least, in exaggerated accounts of those dreadful
catastrophes which are occasioned by particular combinations of natural
causes. Floods and volcanic eruptions, the agency of water and fire,
are the chief instruments of devastation on our globe. We shall point
out in the sequel the extent of many of these calamities, recurring at
distant intervals of time, in the present course of nature; and shall only
observe here, that they are so peculiarly calculated to inspire a lasting
terror, and are so often fatal in their consequences to great multitudes
of people, that it scarcely requires the passion for the marvellous, so
characteristic of rude and half-civilized nations, still less the exuberant
imagination of Eastern writers, to augment them into general cataclysms
and conflagrations.
The great flood of the Chinese, which their traditions carry back to
the period of Yaou, something more than 2000 years before our era, has
been identified by some persons with the universal deluge described in
the Old Testament; but according to Mr. Davis, who accompanied two
of our embassies to China, and who has carefully examined their written
accounts, the Chinese cataclysm is therein described as interrupting
the business of agriculture, rather than as involving a general destruction
of the human race. The great Yu was celebrated for having
"opened nine channels to draw off the waters," which "covered the
low hills and bathed the foot of the highest mountains." Mr. Davis
suggests that a great derangement of waters of the Yellow River, one of
the largest in the world, might even now cause the flood of Yaou to be
repeated, and lay the most fertile and populous plains of China under
water. In modern times the bursting of the banks of an artificial canal,
into which a portion of the Yellow River has been turned, has repeatedly
given rise to the most dreadful accidents, and is a source of perpetual
anxiety to the government. It is easy, therefore, to imagine
how much greater may have been the inundation, if this valley was
ever convulsed by a violent earthquake.6
Humboldt relates the interesting fact that, after the annihilation of a
large part of the inhabitants of Cumana, by an earthquake in 1766, a
season of extraordinary fertility ensued, in consequence of the great
rains which accompanied the subterranean convulsions. "The Indians,"
he says, "celebrated, after the ideas of an antique superstition, by festivals
and dancing, the destruction of the world and the approaching
epoch of its regeneration."7
The existence of such rites among the rude nations of South America
8
is most important, as showing what effects may be produced by local
catastrophes, recurring at distant intervals of time, on the minds of
a barbarous and uncultivated race. I shall point out in the sequel how
the tradition of a deluge among the Araucanian Indians may be explained,
by reference to great earthquake-waves which have repeatedly
rolled over part of Chili since the first recorded flood of 1590. (See
chap. 29, Book II.) The legend also of the ancient Peruvians of an
inundation many years before the reign of the Incas, in which only six
persons were saved on a float, relates to a region which has more than
once been overwhelmed by inroads of the ocean since the days of Pizarro.
(Chap. 29, Book II.) I might refer the reader to my account of
the submergence of a wide area in Cutch so lately as the year 1819,
when a single tower only of the fort of Sindree appeared above the
waste of waters (see Chap. 28, Book II.), if it were necessary, to prove
how easily the catastrophes of modern times might give rise to traditionary
narratives, among a rude people, of floods of boundless extent. Nations
without written records, and who are indebted for all their knowledge of
past events exclusively to oral tradition, are in the habit of confounding
in one legend a series of incidents which have happened at various
epochs; nor must we forget that the superstitions of a savage tribe are
transmitted through all the progressive stages of society, till they exert
a powerful influence on the mind of the philosopher. He may find, in
the monuments of former changes on the earth's surface, an apparent
confirmation of tenets handed down through successive generations,
from the rude hunter, whose terrified imagination drew a false picture
of those awful visitations of floods and earthquakes, whereby the whole
earth as known to him was simultaneously devastated.
Egyptian Cosmogony.—Respecting the cosmogony of the Egyptian
priests, we gather much information from writers of the Grecian sects,
who borrowed almost all their tenets from Egypt, and amongst others
that of the former successive destruction and renovation of the
world.8 We learn from Plutarch, that this was the theme of one of
the hymns of Orpheus, so celebrated in the fabulous ages of Greece.
It was brought by him from the banks of the Nile; and we even find
in his verses, as in the Indian systems, a definite period assigned for
the duration of each successive world.9 The returns of great catastrophes
were determined by the period of the Annus Magnus, or
great year,—a cycle composed of the revolutions of the sun, moon,
and planets, and terminating when these return together to the same
sign whence they were supposed at some remote epoch to have set out.
The duration of this great cycle was variously estimated. According to
Orpheus, it was 120,000 years; according to others, 300,000; and by
Cassander it was taken to be 360,000 years.10
9We learn particularly from the Timæus of Plato, that the Egyptians
believed the world to be subject to occasional conflagrations and
deluges, whereby the gods arrested the career of human wickedness,
and purified the earth from guilt. After each regeneration, mankind
were in a state of virtue and happiness, from which they gradually
degenerated again into vice and immorality. From this Egyptian
doctrine, the poets derived the fable of the decline from the golden to
the iron age. The sect of Stoics adopted most fully the system of catastrophes
destined at certain intervals to destroy the world. Those
they taught were of two kinds;—the Cataclysm, or destruction by
water, which sweeps away the whole human race, and annihilates all
the animal and vegetable productions of nature; and the Ecpyrosis, or
destruction by fire, which dissolves the globe itself. From the Egyptians
also they derived the doctrine of the gradual debasement of man
from a state of innocence. Towards the termination of each era, the
gods could no longer bear with the wickedness of men, and a shock of
the elements or a deluge overwhelmed them; after which calamity,
Astrea again descended on the earth to renew the golden age.11
The connection between the doctrine of successive catastrophes and
repeated deteriorations in the moral character of the human race is more
intimate and natural than might at first be imagined. For, in a rude
state of society, all great calamities are regarded by the people as judgments
of God on the wickedness of man. Thus, in our own time, the
priests persuaded a large part of the population of Chili, and perhaps
believed themselves, that the fatal earthquake of 1822 was a sign of the
wrath of Heaven for the great political revolution just then consummated
in South America. In like manner, in the account given to Solon
by the Egyptian priests, of the submersion of the island of Atlantis
under the waters of the ocean, after repeated shocks of an earthquake,
we find that the event happened when Jupiter had seen the moral depravity
of the inhabitants.12 Now, when the notion had once gained
ground, whether from causes before suggested or not, that the earth
had been destroyed by several general catastrophes, it would next be inferred
that the human race had been as often destroyed and renovated.
And since every extermination was assumed to be penal, it could only
be reconciled with divine justice, by the supposition that man, at each
successive creation, was regenerated in a state of purity and innocence.
A very large portion of Asia, inhabited by the earliest nations, whose
traditions have come down to us, has been always subject to tremendous
earthquakes. Of the geographical boundaries of these, and their
effects, I shall speak in the proper place. Egypt has, for the most
part, been exempt from this scourge, and the Egyptian doctrine of great
catastrophes was probably derived in part, as before hinted, from early
geological observations, and in part from Eastern nations.
Pythagorean Doctrines.—Pythagoras, who resided for more than
10
twenty years in Egypt, and, according to Cicero, had visited the East,
and conversed with the Persian philosophers, introduced into his own
country, on his return, the doctrine of the gradual deterioration of the
human race from an original state of virtue and happiness; but if we
are to judge of his theory concerning the destruction and renovation of
the earth from the sketch given by Ovid, we must concede it to have
been far more philosophical than any known version of the cosmogonies
of Oriental or Egyptian sects.
Although Pythagoras is introduced by the poet as delivering his doctrine
in person, some of the illustrations are derived from natural events
which happened after the death of the philosopher. But notwithstanding
these anachronisms, we may regard the account as a true picture of
the tenets of the Pythagorean school in the Augustan age; and although
perhaps partially modified, it must have contained the substance
of the original scheme. Thus considered, it is extremely curious and
instructive; for we here find a comprehensive summary of almost all
the great causes of change now in activity on the globe, and these adduced
in confirmation of a principle of a perpetual and gradual revolution
inherent in the nature of our terrestrial system. These doctrines, it
is true, are not directly applied to the explanation of geological phenomena;
or, in other words, no attempt is made to estimate what may
have been in past ages, or what may hereafter be, the aggregate amount
of change brought about by such never-ending fluctuations. Had this
been the case, we might have been called upon to admire so extraordinary
an anticipation with no less interest than astronomers, when they
endeavor to define by what means the Samian philosopher came to the
knowledge of the Copernican system.
Let us now examine the celebrated passages to which we have been
adverting:13
"Nothing perishes in this world; but things merely vary and change
their form. To be born, means simply that a thing begins to be something
different from what it was before; and dying, is ceasing to be
the same thing. Yet, although nothing retains long the same image,
the sum of the whole remains constant." These general propositions
are then confirmed by a series of examples, all derived from natural
appearances, except the first, which refers to the golden age giving
place to the age of iron. The illustrations are thus consecutively adduced.
1. Solid land has been converted into sea.
2. Sea has been changed into land. Marine shells lie far distant
from the deep, and the anchor has been found on the summit of hills.
3. Valleys have been excavated by running water, and floods have
washed down hills into the sea.14
11
4. Marshes have become dry ground.
5. Dry lands have been changed into stagnant pools.
6. During earthquakes some springs have been closed up, and new
ones have broken out. Rivers have deserted their channels, and have
been re-born elsewhere, as the Erasinus in Greece, and Mysus in Asia.
7. The waters of some rivers, formerly sweet, have become bitter;
as those of the Anigris, in Greece, &c.15
8. Islands have become connected with the mainland by the growth
of deltas and new deposits; as in the case of Antissa joined to Lesbos,
Pharos to Egypt, &c.
9. Peninsulas have been divided from the main land, and have become
islands, as Leucadia; and according to tradition, Sicily, the sea
having carried away the isthmus.
10. Land has been submerged by earthquakes; the Grecian cities of
Helice and Buris, for example, are to be seen under the sea, with their
walls inclined.
11. Plains have been upheaved into hills by the confined air seeking
vent; as at Trœzene in the Peloponnesus.
12. The temperature of some springs varies at different periods. The
waters of others are inflammable.16
13. There are streams which have a petrifying power, and convert
the substances which they touch into marble.
14. Extraordinary medicinal and deleterious effects are produced by
the water of different lakes and springs.17
15. Some rocks and islands, after floating and having been subject
to violent movements, have at length become stationary and immovable;
as Delos and the Cyanean Isles.18
16. Volcanic vents shift their position; there was a time when Etna
was not a burning mountain, and the time will come when it will cease
to burn. Whether it be that some caverns become closed up by the
movements of the earth, and others opened, or whether the fuel is finally
exhausted, &c., &c.
The various causes of change in the inanimate world having been thus
enumerated, the doctrine of equivocal generation is next propounded, as
illustrating a corresponding perpetual flux in the animate creation.19
12In the Egyptian and Eastern cosmogonies, and in the Greek version
of them, no very definite meaning can, in general, be attached to the
term "destruction of the world;" for sometimes it would seem almost
to imply the annihilation of our planetary system, and at others a mere
revolution of the surface of the earth.
Opinions of Aristotle.—From the works now extant of Aristotle, and
from the system of Pythagoras, as above exposed, we might certainly
infer that these philosophers considered the agents of change now operating
in nature, as capable of bringing about in the lapse of ages a complete
revolution; and the Stagyrite even considers occasional catastrophes,
happening at distant intervals of time, as part of the regular and
ordinary course of nature. The deluge of Deucalion, he says, affected
Greece only, and principally the part called Hellas, and it arose from
great inundations of rivers, during a rainy winter. But such extraordinary
winters, he says, though after a certain period they return, do not
always revisit the same places.20
Censorinus quotes it as Aristotle's opinion that there were general
inundations of the globe, and that they alternated with conflagrations;
and that the flood constituted the winter of the great year, or astronomical
cycle, while the conflagration, or destruction by fire, is the
summer, or period of greatest heat.21 If this passage, as Lipsius supposes,
be an amplification, by Censorinus, of what is written in "the
Meteorics," it is a gross misrepresentation of the doctrine of the Stagyrite,
for the general bearing of his reasoning in that treatise tends clearly
in an opposite direction. He refers to many examples of changes now
constantly going on, and insists emphatically on the great results which
they must produce in the lapse of ages. He instances particular cases
of lakes that had dried up, and deserts that had at length become
watered by rivers and fertilized. He points to the growth of the
Nilotic Delta since the time of Homer, to the shallowing of the Palus
Mæotis within sixty years from his own time; and although, in the
same chapter he says nothing of earthquakes, yet in others of the same
treatise he shows himself not unacquainted with their effects.22 He
alludes, for example, to the upheaving of one of the Eolian islands
previous to a volcanic eruption. "The changes of the earth," he says,
"are so slow in comparison to the duration of our lives, that they are overlooked
(λανθανει): and the migrations of people after great catastrophes,
and their removal to other regions, cause the event to be forgotten."23
13When we consider the acquaintance displayed by Aristotle, in his
various works, with the destroying and renovating powers of Nature,
the introductory and concluding passages of the twelfth chapter of his
"Meteorics" are certainly very remarkable. In the first sentence he
says, "The distribution of land and sea in particular regions does not
endure throughout all time, but it becomes sea in those parts where
it was land, and again it becomes land where it was sea: and there is
reason for thinking that these changes take place according to a certain
system, and within a certain period." The concluding observation
is as follows:—"As time never fails, and the universe is eternal, neither
the Tànais, nor the Nile, can have flowed forever. The places where
they rise were once dry, and there is a limit to their operations; but
there is none to time. So also of all other rivers; they spring up, and
they perish; and the sea also continually deserts some lands and invades
others. The same tracts, therefore, of the earth are not, some
always sea, and others always continents, but every thing changes in
the course of time."
It seems, then, that the Greeks had not only derived from preceding
nations, but had also, in some slight degree, deduced from their
own observations, the theory of periodical revolutions in the inorganic
world: there is, however, no ground for imagining that they contemplated
former changes in the races of animals and plants. Even the
fact that marine remains were inclosed in solid rocks, although observed
by some, and even made the groundwork of geological speculation,
never stimulated the industry or guided the inquiries of naturalists.
It is not impossible that the theory of equivocal generation might
have engendered some indifference on this subject, and that a belief in
the spontaneous production of living beings from the earth or corrupt
matter, might have caused the organic world to appear so unstable
and fluctuating, that phenomena indicative of former changes would
not awaken intense curiosity. The Egyptians, it is true, had taught,
and the Stoics had repeated, that the earth had once given birth to
some monstrous animals, which existed no longer; but the prevailing
opinion seems to have been, that after each great catastrophe the same
species of animals were created over again. This tenet is implied in a
passage of Seneca, where, speaking of a future deluge, he says, "Every
animal shall be generated anew, and man free from guilt shall be given
to the earth."24
An old Arabian version of the doctrine of the successive revolutions
of the globe, translated by Abraham Ecchellensis,25 seems to form a
singular exception to the general rule, for here we find the idea of different
genera and species having been created. The Gerbanites, a sect
14of astronomers who flourished some centuries before the Christian era,
taught as follows:—"That after every period of thirty-six thousand
four hundred and twenty-five years, there were produced a pair of
every species of animal, both male and female, from whom animals
might be propagated and inhabit this lower world. But when a circulation
of the heavenly orbs was completed, which is finished in that
space of years, other genera and species of animals are propagated, as
also of plants and other things, and the first order is destroyed, and so
it goes on forever and ever."26
Theory of Strabo.—As we learn much of the tenets of the Egyptian
and Oriental schools in the writings of the Greeks, so, many speculations
of the early Greek authors are made known to us in the works of
the Augustan and later ages. Strabo, in particular, enters largely, in
the second book of his Geography, into the opinions of Eratosthenes and
other Greeks on one of the most difficult problems in geology, viz., by
what causes marine shells came to be plentifully buried in the earth at
such great elevations and distances from the sea.
He notices, amongst others, the explanation of Xanthus the Lydian,
who said that the seas had once been more extensive, and that they had
afterwards been partially dried up, as in his own time many lakes, rivers,
and wells in Asia had failed during a season of drought. Treating this
conjecture with merited disregard, Strabo passes on to the hypothesis
of Strato, the natural philosopher, who had observed that the quantity
of mud brought down by rivers into the Euxine was so great, that its
bed must be gradually raised, while the rivers still continue to pour in
an undiminished quantity of water. He, therefore, conceived that, originally,
when the Euxine was an inland sea, its level had by this means
become so much elevated that it burst its barrier near Byzantium, and
formed a communication with the Propontis; and this partial drainage,
he supposed, had already converted the left side into marshy ground,
and thus, at last, the whole would be choked up with soil. So, it was
argued, the Mediterranean had once opened a passage for itself by the
Columns of Hercules into the Atlantic; and perhaps the abundance of
sea-shells in Africa, near the Temple of Jupiter Ammon, might also be
the deposit of some former inland sea, which had at length forced a
passage and escaped.
15But Strabo rejects this theory, as insufficient to account for all the
phenomena, and he proposes one of his own, the profoundness of which
modern geologists are only beginning to appreciate. "It is not," he
says, "because the lands covered by seas were originally at different
altitudes, that the waters have risen, or subsided, or receded from some
parts and inundated others. But the reason is, that the same land is
sometimes raised up and sometimes depressed, and the sea also is simultaneously
raised and depressed, so that it either overflows or returns
into its own place again. We must, therefore, ascribe the cause to the
ground, either to that ground which is under the sea, or to that which
becomes flooded by it, but rather to that which lies beneath the sea, for
this is more movable and, on account of its humidity, can be altered
with greater celerity.27 "It is proper," he observes in continuation, "to
derive our explanations from things which are obvious, and in some
measure of daily occurrence, such as deluges, earthquakes, and volcanic
eruptions,28 and sudden swellings of the land beneath the sea; for the
last raise up the sea also; and when the same lands subside again, they
occasion the sea to be let down. And it is not merely the small, but
the large islands also, and not merely the islands, but the continents
which can be lifted up together with the sea; and both large and small
tracts may subside, for habitations and cities, like Bure, Bizona, and
many others, have been engulphed by earthquakes."
In another place, this learned geographer, in alluding to the tradition
that Sicily had been separated by a convulsion from Italy, remarks, that
at present the land near the sea in those parts was rarely shaken by
earthquakes, since there were now open orifices whereby fire and ignited
matters, and waters escape; but formerly, when the volcanoes of Etna,
the Lipari Islands, Ischia, and others, were closed up, the imprisoned
fire and wind might have produced far more vehement movements.29
The doctrine, therefore, that volcanoes are safety-valves, and that the
subterranean convulsions are probably most violent when first the volcanic
energy shifts itself to a new quarter, is not modern.
We learn from a passage in Strabo,30 that it was a dogma of the
Gaulish Druids that the universe was immortal, but destined to survive
catastrophes both of fire and water. That this doctrine was communicated
to them from the East, with much of their learning, cannot be
doubted. Cæsar, it will be remembered, says that they made use of
Greek letters in arithmetical computations.31
16Pliny.—This philosopher had no theoretical opinions of his own concerning
changes of the earth's surface; and in this department, as in
others, he restricted himself to the task of a compiler, without reasoning
on the facts stated by him, or attempting to digest them into regular
order. But his enumeration of the new islands which had been formed
in the Mediterranean, and of other convulsions, shows that the ancients
had not been inattentive observers of the changes which had taken place
within the memory of man.
Such, then, appear to have been the opinions entertained before the
Christian era, concerning the past revolutions of our globe. Although
no particular investigations had been made for the express purpose of
interpreting the monuments of ancient changes, they were too obvious
to be entirely disregarded; and the observation of the present course of
nature presented too many proofs of alterations continually in progress
on the earth to allow philosophers to believe that nature was in a state
of rest, or that the surface had remained, and would continue to remain
unaltered. But they had never compared attentively the results of the
destroying and reproductive operations of modern times with those of
remote eras, nor had they ever entertained so much as a conjecture concerning
the comparative antiquity of the human race, or of living species
of animals and plants, with those belonging to former conditions of the
organic world. They had studied the movements and positions of the
heavenly bodies with laborious industry, and made some progress in
investigating the animal, vegetable, and mineral kingdoms; but the ancient
history of the globe was to them a sealed book, and, although
written in characters of the most striking and imposing kind, they were
unconscious even of its existence.

17</div></body></text></TEI>