<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="3">

CHAPTER III.
Of Necessary Truths.



1. EVERY
 advance in human knowledge consists, as we have
seen, in adapting new ideal conceptions to ascertained
facts, and thus in superinducing the Form upon the Matter,
the active upon the passive processes of our minds. Every
such step introduces into our knowledge an additional
portion of the ideal element, and of those relations which
flow from the nature of Ideas. It is, therefore, important
for our purpose to examine more closely this element, and to
learn what the relations are which may thus come to form
part of our knowledge. An inquiry into those Ideas which
form the foundations of our sciences;—into the reality,
independence, extent, and principal heads of the knowledge
which we thus acquire; is a task on which we must now enter,
and which will employ us for several of the succeeding
Books.
In this inquiry our object will be to pass in review all the
most important Fundamental Ideas which our sciences involve;
and to prove more distinctly in reference to each, what we
have already asserted with regard to all, that there are
everywhere involved in our knowledge acts of the mind as
well as impressions of sense; and that our knowledge
derives, from these acts, a generality, certainty, and
evidence which the senses could in no degree have supplied.
But before I proceed to do this in particular cases, I will
give some account of the argument in its general form.
We have already considered the separation of our knowledge
into its two elements,—Impressions of Sense and Ideas,—as
evidently indicated by this; that all knowledge possesses
characters which neither of these 58 elements alone could
bestow. Without our ideas, our sensations could have no
connexion; without external impressions, our ideas would
have no reality; and thus both ingredients of our knowledge
must exist.
2. There is another mode in which the distinction of the two
elements of knowledge appears, as I have already said (c. i.
sect. 2): namely in the distinction of necessary, and
contingent or experiential, truths. For of
these two classes of truths, the difference arises from
this;—that the one class derives its nature from the one,
and the other from the other, of the two elements of
knowledge. I have already stated briefly the difference of
these two kinds of truths:—namely, that the former are
truths which, we see, must be true:—the latter are true,
but so far as we can see, might be otherwise. The former are
true necessarily and universally: the latter are learnt from
experience and limited by experience. Now with regard to the
former kind of truths, I wish to show that the universality
and necessity which distinguish them can by no means be
derived from experience; that these characters do in reality
flow from the ideas which these truths involve; and that
when the necessity of the truth is exhibited in the way of
logical demonstration, it is found to depend upon certain
fundamental principles, (Definitions and Axioms,) which may
thus be considered as expressing, in some measure, the
essential characters of our ideas. These fundamental
principles I shall afterwards proceed to discuss and to
exhibit in each of the principal departments of science.
I shall begin by considering Necessary Truths more fully
than I have yet done. As I have already said, necessary
truths are those in which we not only learn, that the
proposition is true, but see that it must
be true; in which the negation of the truth is not only
false, but impossible; in which we cannot, even by an effort
of imagination, or in a supposition, conceive the reverse of
that which is asserted.
3. That there are such truths cannot be doubted. We may
take, for example, all relations of number. Three and Two
added together make Five. We cannot 59 conceive it to be
otherwise. We cannot, by any freak of thought, imagine Three
and Two to make Seven.
It may be said that this assertion merely expresses what we
mean by our words; that it is a matter of definition; that
the proposition is an identical one.
But this is by no means so. The definition of Five is not
Three and Two, but Four and One. How does it appear that
Three and Two is the same number as Four and One? It is
evident that it is so; but why is it evident?—not
because the proposition is identical; for if that were the
reason, all numerical propositions must be evident for the
same reason. If it be a matter of definition that 3 and 2
make 5, it must be a matter of definition that 39 and 27
make 66. But who will say that the definition of 66 is 39
and 27? Yet the magnitude of the numbers can make no
difference in the ground of the truth. How do we know that
the product of 13 and 17 is 4 less than the product of 15
and 15? We see that it is so, if we perform certain
operations by the rules of arithmetic; but how do we know
the truth of the rules of arithmetic? If we divide 123375 by
987 according to the process taught us at school, how are we
assured that the result is correct, and that the number 125
thus obtained is really the number of times one number is
contained in the other?
The correctness of the rule, it may be replied, can be
rigorously demonstrated. It can be shown that the process
must inevitably give the true quotient.
Certainly this can be shown to be the case. And precisely
because it can be shown that the result must be true, we
have here an example of a necessary truth; and this truth,
it appears, is not therefore necessary because it
is itself evidently identical, however it may be possible to
prove it by reducing it to evidently identical propositions.
And the same is the case with all other numerical
propositions; for, as we have said, the nature of all of
them is the same.
Here, then, we have instances of truths which are not only
true, but demonstrably and necessarily true. Now such truths
are, in this respect at least, altogether 60 different
from truths, which, however certain they may be, are learnt
to be so only by the evidence of observation, interpreted,
as observation must be interpreted, by our own mental
faculties. There is no difficulty in finding examples of
these merely observed truths. We find that sugar dissolves
in water, and forms a transparent fluid, but no one will say
that we can see any reason beforehand why the result
must be so. We find that all animals which chew the
cud have also the divided hoof; but could any one have
predicted that this would be universally the case? or
supposing the truth of the rule to be known, can any one say
that he cannot conceive the facts as occurring otherwise?
Water expands when it crystallizes, some other substances
contract in the same circumstances; but can any one know
that this will be so otherwise than by observation? We have
here propositions rigorously true, (we will
assume,) but can any one say they are necessarily
true? These, and the great mass of the doctrines established
by induction, are actual, but so far as we can see,
accidental laws; results determined by some unknown
selection, not demonstrable consequences of the essence of
things, inevitable and perceived to be inevitable. According
to the phraseology which has been frequently used by
philosophical writers, they are contingent, not
necessary truths.
It is requisite to insist upon this opposition, because no
insight can be obtained into the true nature of knowledge,
and the mode of arriving at it, by any one who does not
clearly appreciate the distinction. The separation of truths
which are learnt by observation, and truths which can be
seen to be true by a pure act of thought, is one of the
first and most essential steps in our examination of the
nature of truth, and the mode of its discovery. If any one
does not clearly comprehend this distinction of necessary
and contingent truths, he will not be able to go along with
us in our researches into the foundations of human
knowledge; nor, indeed, to pursue with success any
speculation on the subject. But, in fact, this distinction
is one that can hardly fail to be at once understood. It
61 is insisted upon by almost all the best modern, as well
as ancient, metaphysicians5, as of primary importance.
And if any person does not fully apprehend, at first, the
different kinds of truth thus pointed out, let him study, to
some extent, those sciences which have necessary truth for
their subject, as geometry, or the properties of numbers, so
as to obtain a familiar acquaintance with such truth; and he
will then hardly fail to see how different the evidence of
the propositions which occur in these sciences, is from the
evidence of the facts which are merely learnt from
experience. That the year goes through its course in 365
days, can only be known by observation of the sun or stars:
that 365 days is 52 weeks and a day, it requires no
experience, but only a little thought to perceive. That bees
build their cells in the form of hexagons, we cannot know
without looking at them; that regular hexagons may be
arranged so as to fill space, may be proved with the utmost
rigour, even if there were not in existence such a thing as
a material hexagon.</div></body></text></TEI>