<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="43">

CHAPTER II.
Of the Connexion of Polarities.



1. IT
has appeared in the preceding chapter that in cases in
which the phenomena suggest to us the idea of Polarity, we
are also led to assume some material machinery as the mode
in which the polar forces are exerted. We assume, for
instance, globular particles which possess poles, or the
vibrations of a fluid, or two fluids attracting each other;
in every case, in short, some hypothesis by which the
existence and operation of the Polarity is embodied in
geometrical and mechanical properties of a medium; nor is it
possible for us to avoid proceeding upon the conviction that
some such hypothesis must be true; although the nature of
the connexion between the mechanism and the phenomena must
still be indefinite and arbitrary.
But since each class of Polar Phenomena is thus referred to
an ulterior cause, of which we know no more than that it has
a polar character, it follows that different
Polarities may result from the same cause
manifesting its polar character under different aspects.
Taking, for example, the hypothesis of globular particles,
if electricity result from an action dependent upon the
poles of each globule, magnetism may depend upon an
action in the equator of each globule; or taking
the supposition of transverse vibrations, if polarized light
result directly from such vibrations,
crystallization may have reference to the axes of
the elasticity of the medium by which the
vibrations are rendered transverse,—so far as the polar
character only of the phenomena is to be accounted for. I
say this may be so, in so far only as the
polar character of the phenomena is concerned; for whether
the relation of 372 electricity to magnetism, or of
crystalline forces to light, can really be explained by such
hypotheses, remains to be determined by the facts
themselves. But since the first necessary feature of the
hypothesis is, that it shall give polarity, and since an
hypothesis which does this, may, by its mathematical
relations, give polarities of different kinds and in
different directions, any two co-existent kinds of polarity
may result from the same cause, manifesting itself in
various manners.
The conclusion to which we are led by these general
considerations is, that two co-existing classes of polar
phenomena may be effects of the same cause. But
those who have studied such phenomena more deeply and
attentively have, in most or in all cases, arrived at the
conviction that the various kinds of Polarity in such cases
must be connected and fundamentally identical. As
this conviction has exercised a great influence, both upon
the discoveries of new facts and upon the theoretical
speculations of modern philosophers, and has been put
forward by some writers as a universal principle of science,
I will consider some of the cases in which it has been thus
applied.
2. Connexion of Magnetic and Electric Polarity.—The
polar phenomena of electricity and magnetism are clearly
analogous in their laws: and obvious facts showed at an
early period that there was some connexion between the two
agencies. Attempts were made to establish an evident and
definite relation between the two kinds of force, which
attempts proceeded upon the principle now under
consideration;—namely, that in such cases, the two kinds of
Polarity must be connected. Professor Œrsted, of Copenhagen,
was one of those who made many trials founded upon this
conviction: yet all these were long unsuccessful. At length,
in 1820, he discovered that a galvanic current, passing at
right angles near to a magnetic needle, exercises upon it a
powerful deflecting force. The connexion once detected
between magnetism and galvanism was soon recognized as
constant and universal. It was represented in different
hypothetical modes by different persons; some considering
the galvanic 373 current as the primitive axis, and the
magnet as constituted of galvanic currents passing round it
at right angles to the magnetic axis; while others conceived
the magnetic axis as the primitive one, and the electric
current as implying a magnetic current round the wire. So
far as many of the general relations of these two kinds of
force were concerned, either mode of representation served
to express them; and thus the assumption that the two
Polarities, the magnetic and the electric, were
fundamentally identical, was verified, so far as the
phenomena of magnetic attraction, and the like, were
concerned.
I need not here mention how this was further confirmed by
the experiments in which, by means of the forces thus
brought into view, a galvanic wire was made to revolve round
a magnet, and a magnet round a galvanic wire;—in which
artificial magnets were constructed of coils of galvanic
wire;—and finally, in which the galvanic spark was obtained
from the magnet. The identity which sagacious speculators
had divined even before it was discovered, and which they
had seen to be universal as soon as it was brought to light,
was completely manifested in every imaginable form.
The relation of the electric and magnetic Polarities was
found to be, that they were transverse to each
other, and this relation exhibited under various conditions
of form and position of the apparatus, gave rise to very
curious and unexpected perplexities. The degree of
complication which this relation may occasion, may be judged
of from the number of constructions and modes of conception
offered by Œrsted, Wollaston, Faraday, and others, for the
purpose of framing a technical memory of the results. The
magnetic polarity gives us the north and south poles of the
needle; the electric polarity makes the current positive and
negative; and these pairs of opposites are connected by
relations of situation, as above and below, right and left;
and give rise to the resulting motion of the needle one way
or the other. 374
3. Ampère, by framing his hypotheses of the action of
voltaic currents and the constitution of magnets, reduced
all these technical rules to rigorous deductions from one
general principle. And thus the vague and obscure persuasion
that there must be some connexion between
Electricity and Magnetism, so long an idle and barren
conjecture, was unfolded into a complete theory, according
to which magnetic and electromotive actions are only two
different manifestations of the same forces; and all the
above-mentioned complex relations of polarities are reduced
to one single polarity, that of the electro-dynamic current.
4. As the Idea of Polarity was thus firmly established and
clearly developed, it became an instrument of reasoning.
Thus it led Ampère to maintain that the original or
elementary forces in electro-dynamic action could not be as
M. Biot thought they were, a statical couple, but
must be directly opposite to each other. The same idea
enabled Mr. Faraday to carry on with confidence such
reasonings as the following8: ‘No other known power has
like direction with that exerted between an electric current
and a magnetic pole; it is tangential, while all other
forces acting at a distance are direct. Hence if a magnetic
pole on one side of a revolving plate follow its course by
reason of its obedience to the tangential force exerted upon
it by the very current of electricity which it has itself
caused; a similar pole on the other side of the plate should
immediately set it free from this force; for the currents
which have to be formed by the two poles are in contrary
directions.’ And in Article 1114 of his Researches,
the same eminent philosopher infers that if electricity and
magnetism are considered as the results of a peculiar agent
or condition, exerted in determinate directions
perpendicular to each other, one must be by some means
convertible into the other; and this he was afterwards able
to prove to be the case in fact.</div></body></text></TEI>