<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="27">
CHAPTER VIII.

The Existence of a Resisting Medium in the Solar
System.

The question of a plenum and a vacuum was formerly
much debated among those who speculated
concerning the constitution of the universe; that is,
they disputed whether the celestial and terrestrial
spaces are absolutely full, each portion being occupied
by some matter or other; or whether there are,
between and among the material parts of the world,
empty spaces free from all matter, however rare.
This question was often treated by means of abstract
conceptions and à priori reasonings; and was sometimes
considered as one in which the result of the
struggle between rival systems of philosophy, the
Cartesian and Newtonian for instance, was involved.
It was conceived by some that the Newtonian doctrine
of the motions of the heavenly bodies, according
to mechanical laws, required that the space in which[151]
they moved should be, absolutely and metaphysically
speaking, a vacuum.
This, however, is not necessary to the truth of the
Newtonian doctrines, and does not appear to have
been intended to be asserted by Newton himself.
Undoubtedly, according to his theory, the motions
of the heavenly bodies were calculated on the supposition
that they do move in a space void of any resisting
fluid; and the comparison of the places so calculated
with the places actually observed, (continued for a
long course of years, and tried in innumerable cases,)
did not show any difference which implied the existence
of a resisting fluid. The Newtonian, therefore,
was justified in asserting that either there was no
such fluid, or that it was so thin and rarefied, that no
phenomenon yet examined by astronomers was capable
of betraying its effects.
This was all that the Newtonian needed or ought
to maintain; for his philosophy, founded altogether
upon observation, had nothing to do with abstract
possibilities and metaphysical necessities. And in
the same manner in which observation and calculation
thus showed that there could be none but a very
rare medium pervading the solar system, it was left
open to observation and calculation to prove that
there was such a medium, if any facts could be discovered
which offered suitable evidence.
Within the last few years, facts have been observed
which show, in the opinion of some of the best
mathematicians of Europe, that such a very rare
medium does really occupy the spaces in which the
planets move; and it may be proper and interesting
to consider the bearing of this opinion upon the views
and arguments which we have had here to present.
1. Reasons might be offered, founded on the universal
diffusion of light and on other grounds, for believing
that the planetary spaces cannot be entirely
free from matter of some kind; and wherever matter
is, we should expect resistance. But the facts
which have thus led astronomers to the conviction[152]
that such a resisting medium really exists, are certain
circumstances occurring in the motion of a body
revolving round the sun, which is now usually called
Encke’s comet. This body revolves in a very eccentric
or oblong orbit, its greatest or aphelion distance
from the sun, and its nearest, or perihelion distance,
being in the proportion of more than ten to one. In
this respect it agrees with other comets; but its time
of revolution about the sun is much less than that of
the comets which have excited most notice; for
while they appear only at long intervals of years, the
body of which we are now speaking returns to its
perihelion every twelve hundred and eight days, or
in about three years and one-third. Another observable
circumstance in this singular body, is its
extreme apparent tenuity: it appears as a loose
indefinitely formed speck of vapour, through which
the stars are visible with no perceptible diminution
of their brightness. This body was first seen by
Mechain and Messier, in 1786,[21] but they obtained
only two observations, whereas three, at least, are
requisite to determine the path of a heavenly body.
Miss Herschel discovered it again in 1795, and it
was observed by several European astronomers. In
1805 it was again seen, and again in 1819. Hitherto
it was supposed that the four comets thus observed
were all different; Encke, however, showed that the
observations could only be explained by considering
them as returns of the same revolving body; and by
doing this, well merited that his name should be associated
with the subject of his discovery. The return
of this body in 1822, was calculated beforehand,
and observed in New South Wales, the comet being
then in the southern part of the heavens; but on
comparing the calculated and the observed places,
Encke concluded that the observations could not be
exactly explained, without supposing a resisting medium.
This comet was again generally observed in[153]
Europe in 1825 and 1828, and the circumstances of
the last appearance were particularly favourable for
determining the absolute amount of the retardation
arising from the medium, which the other observations
had left undetermined.
The effect of this retarding influence is, as might
be supposed from what has already been said, extremely
slight; and would probably not have been
perceptible at all, but for the loose texture and small
quantity of matter of the revolving body. It will
easily be conceived that a body which has perhaps
no more solidity or coherence than a cloud of dust,
or a wreath of smoke, will have less force to make
its way through a fluid medium, however thin, than
a more dense and compact body would have. In
atmospheric air much rarefied, a bullet might proceed
for miles without losing any of its velocity,
while such a loose mass as the comet is supposed to
be 
would lose its projectile motion in the space of a
few yards. This consideration will account for the
circumstance, that the existence of such a medium
has been detected by observing the motions of
Encke’s comet, though the motions of the heavenly
bodies previously observed showed no trace of such
an impediment.
It will appear perhaps remarkable that a body so
light and loose as we have described this comet to
be, should revolve about the sun by laws as fixed and
certain as those which regulate the motions of those
great and solid masses, the Earth and Jupiter. It is
however certain from observation, that this comet is
acted upon by exactly the same force of solar attraction,
as the other bodies of the system; and not
only so, but that it also experiences the same kind of
disturbing force from the action of the other planets,
which they exercise upon each other. The effect of
all these causes has been calculated with great care
and labour; and the result has been an agreement
with observation sufficiently close to show that these
causes really act, but at the same time a residual[154]
phenomenon (as Sir J. Herschel expresses it) has
come to light: and from this has been collected the
inference of a resisting medium.
This medium produces a very small effect upon
the motion of the comet, as will easily be supposed
from what has been said. By Encke’s calculation,
it appears that the effect of the resistance, supposing
the comet to move in the earth’s orbit, would be
about an eight hundred and fiftieth of the sun’s force
on the body. The effect of such resistance may appear,
at first sight, paradoxical; it would be to make
the comet move more slowly, but perform its revolutions
more quickly. This, however, will perhaps be
understood if it be considered that by moving more
slowly the comet will be more rapidly drawn towards
the centre, and that in this way a revolution will be
described by a shorter path than it was before. It
appears that in getting round the sun, the comet
gains more in this way than it loses by the diminution
of its velocity. The case is much like that of a
stone thrown in the air; the stone moves more
slowly than it would do if there were no air; but yet
it comes to the earth sooner than it would do on that
supposition.
It appears that the effect of the resistance of the
ethereal medium, from the first discovery of the
comet up to the present time, has been to diminish
the time of revolution by about two days: and the
comet is ten days in advance of the place which it
would have reached, if there had been no resistance.
2. The same medium which is thus shown to produce
an effect upon Encke’s comet, must also act
upon the planets which move through the same
spaces. The effect upon the planets, however, must
be very much smaller than the effect upon the comet,
in consequence of their greater quantity of matter.
It is not easy to assign any probable value, or
even any certain limit, to the effect of the resisting
medium upon the planets. We are entirely ignorant[155]
of the comparative mass of the comet, and of any
of the planets; and hence, cannot make any calculation
founded on such a comparison. Newton has
endeavoured to show how small the resistance of the
medium must be, if it exist.[22] The result of his calculation
is, that if we take the density of the medium
to be that which our air will have at two hundred
miles from the earth’s surface, supposing the
law of diminution of density to go on unaltered, and
if we suppose Jupiter to move in such a medium, he
would in a million years lose less than a millionth
part of his velocity. If a planet, revolving about
the sun, were to lose any portion of its velocity by
the effect of resistance, it would be drawn proportionally
nearer the sun, the tendency towards the
centre being no longer sufficiently counteracted by
that centrifugal force which arises from the body’s
velocity. And if the resistance were to continue to
act, the body would be drawn perpetually nearer
and nearer to the centre, and would describe its revolutions
quicker and quicker, till at last it would
reach the central body, and the system would cease
to be a system.
This result is true, however small be the velocity
lost by resistance; the only difference being, that
when the resistance is small, the time requisite to
extinguish the whole motion will be proportionally
longer. In all cases the times which come under
our consideration in problems of this kind, are enormous
to common apprehension. Thus Encke’s
comet, according to the results of the observations
already made, will lose, in ten revolutions, or thirty-three
years, less than one thousandth of its velocity:
and if this law were to continue, the velocity would
not be reduced to one-half its present value in less
than seven thousand revolutions or twenty-three
thousand years. If Jupiter were to lose one-millionth
of his velocity in a million years, (which, as has been[156]
seen, is far more than can be considered in any way
probable,) he would require seventy millions of years
to lose one-thousandth of the velocity; and a period
seven hundred times as long to reduce the velocity
to one-half. These are periods of time which quite
overwhelm the imagination; and it is not pretended
that the calculations are made with any pretensions
to accuracy. But at the same time it is beyond doubt
that though the intervals of time thus assigned to
these changes are highly vague and uncertain, the
changes themselves must, sooner or later, take place,
in consequence of the existence of the resisting medium.
Since there is such a retarding force perpetually
acting, however slight it be, it must in the end
destroy all the celestial motions. It may be millions
of millions of years before the earth’s retardation
may perceptibly affect the apparent motion of the
sun; but still the day will come (if the same Providence
which formed the system, should permit it to
continue so long) when this cause will entirely change
the length of our year and the course of our seasons,
and finally stop the earth’s motion round the sun
altogether. The smallness of the resistance, however
small we choose to suppose it, does not allow
us to escape this certainty. There is a resisting medium;
and, therefore, the movements of the solar
system cannot go on for ever. The moment such a
fluid is ascertained to exist, the eternity of the movements
of the planets becomes as impossible as a perpetual
motion on the earth.
3. The vast periods which are brought under our
consideration in tracing the effects of the resisting
medium, harmonize with all that we learn of the
constitution of the universe from other sources.
Millions, and millions of millions of years are expressions
that at first sight appear fitted only to overwhelm
and confound all our powers of thought; and
such numbers are no doubt beyond the limits of any
thing which we distinctly conceive. But our powers
of conception are suited rather to the wants and[157]
uses of common life, than to a complete survey of
the universe. It is in no way unlikely that the whole
duration of the solar system should be a period immeasurably
great in our eyes, though demonstrably
finite. Such enormous numbers have been brought
under our notice by all the advances we have made
in our knowledge of nature. The smallness of the
objects detected by the microscope and of their
parts;—the multitude of the stars which the best
telescopes of modern times have discovered in the
sky;—the duration assigned to the globe of the earth
by geological investigation;—all these results require
for their probable expression, numbers, which so far
as we see, are on the same gigantic scale as the
number of years in which the solar system will become
entirely deranged. Such calculations depend
in some degree on our relation to the vast aggregate
of the works of our Creator; and no person who is
accustomed to meditate on these subjects will be surprised
that the numbers which such an occasion requires
should oppress our comprehension. No one
who has dwelt on the thought of a universal Creator
and Preserver, will be surprised to find the conviction
forced upon the mind by every new train of
speculation, that viewed in reference to Him, our
space is a point, our time a moment, our millions a
handful, our permanence a quick decay.
Our knowledge of the vast periods, both geological
and astronomical, of which we have spoken, is
most slight. It is in fact little more than that such
periods exist; that the surface of the earth has, at
wide intervals of time, undergone great changes in
the disposition of land and water, and in the forms of
animal life; and that the motions of the heavenly
bodies round the sun are affected, though with inconceivable
slowness, by a force which must end by
deranging them altogether. It would therefore be
rash to endeavour to establish any analogy between
the periods thus disclosed; but we may observe that
they agree in this, that they reduce all things to the[158]
general rule of finite duration. As all the geological
states of which we find evidence in the present state
of the earth, have had their termination, so also the
astronomical conditions under which the revolutions
of the earth itself proceed, involve the necessity of a
future cessation of these revolutions.
The contemplative person may well be struck by
this universal law of the creation. We are in the
habit sometimes of contrasting the transient destiny
of man with the permanence of the forests, the mountains,
the ocean,—with the unwearied circuit of the
sun. But this contrast is a delusion of our own imagination;
the difference is after all but one of degree.
The forest tree endures for its centuries and then
decays; the mountains crumble and change, and
perhaps subside in some convulsion of nature; the
sea retires, and the shore ceases to resound with the
“everlasting” voice of the ocean: such reflections
have already crowded upon the mind of the geologist;
and it now appears that the courses of the heavens
themselves are not exempt from the universal
law of decay; that not only the rocks and the mountains,
but the sun and the moon have the sentence
“to end” stamped upon their foreheads. They enjoy
no privilege beyond man except a longer respite.
The ephemeron perishes in an hour; man endures
for his three score years and ten; an empire, a nation,
numbers its centuries, it may be its thousands of
years; the continents and islands which its dominion
includes have perhaps their date, as those which preceded
them have had; and the very revolutions of
the sky by which centuries are numbered will at last
languish and stand still.
To dwell on the moral and religious reflections suggested
by this train of thought is not to our present
purpose; but we may observe that it introduces a
homogeneity, so to speak, into the government of the
universe. Perpetual change, perpetual progression,
increase and diminution, appear to be the rules of
the material world, and to prevail without exception.[159]
The smaller portions of matter which we have near
us, and the larger, which appear as luminaries at a
vast distance, different as they are in our mode of
conceiving them, obey the same laws of motion; and
these laws produce the same results; in both cases
motion is perpetually destroyed, except it be repaired
by some living power; in both cases the relative rest
of the parts of a material system is the conclusion to
which its motion tends.
4. It may perhaps appear to some, that this acknowledgment
of the tendency of the system to derangement
through the action of a resisting medium
is inconsistent with the argument which we have
drawn in a previous chapter, from the provisions for
its stability. In reality, however, the two views are
in perfect agreement, so far as our purpose is concerned.
The main point which we had to urge, in
the consideration of the stability of the system, was,
not that it is constructed to last for ever, but that
while it lasts, the deviations from its mean condition
are very small. It is this property which fits the
world for its uses. To maintain either the past or
the future eternity of the world, does not appear consistent
with physical principles, as it certainly does
not fall in with the convictions of the religious man,
in whatever way obtained. We conceive that this
state of things has had a beginning; we conceive that
it will have an end. But in the mean time we find
it fitted, by a number of remarkable arrangements,
to be the habitation of living creatures. The conditions
which secure the stability, and the smallness of
the perturbations of the system, are among these provisions.
If the eccentricity of the orbit of Venus, or
of Jupiter, were much greater than it is, not only
might some of the planets, at the close of ages, fall
into the sun or fly off into infinite space, but also, in
the intermediate time, the earth’s orbit might become
much more eccentric; the course of the seasons and
the average of temperature might vary from what
they now are, so as to injure or destroy the whole[160]
organic creation. By certain original arrangements
these destructive oscillations are prevented. So long
as the bodies continue to revolve, their orbits will
not be much different from what they now are. And
this result is not affected by the action of the resisting
medium. Such a medium cannot increase the
small eccentricities of the orbits. The range of the
periodical oscillations of heat and cold will not be
extended by the mechanical effect of the medium,
nor would be, even if its density were incomparably
greater than it is. The resisting medium therefore
does not at all counteract that which is most important
in the provision for the permanency of the solar
system. If the stability of the system had not been
secured by the adjustments which we described in a
former chapter, the course of the seasons might have
been disturbed to an injurious or even destructive
extent in the course of a few centuries, or even within
the limits of one generation; by the effect of the resisting
medium, the order of nature remains unchanged
for a period, compared with which the
known duration of the human race is insignificant.
But, it may be objected, the effect of the medium
must be ultimately to affect, the duration of the earth’s
revolution round the sun, and thus to derange those
adaptations which depend on the length of the year.
And, without question, if we permit ourselves to look
forward to that inconceivably distant period at which
the effect of the medium will become sensible, this
must be allowed to be true, as has been already
stated. Millions, and probably millions of millions,
of years express inadequately the distance of time at
which this cause would produce a serious effect.
That the machine of the universe is so constructed
that it may answer its purposes for such a period, is
surely sufficient proof of the skill of its workmanship,
and of the reality of its purpose: and those persons,
probably, who are best convinced that it is the work
of a wise and good Creator, will be least disposed to[161]
consider the system as imperfect, because in its present
condition it is not fitted for eternity.
5. The doctrine of a Resisting Medium leads us
towards a point which the Nebular Hypothesis assumes;—a
beginning of the present order of things.
There must have been a commencement of the motions
now going on in the solar system. Since these
motions, when once begun, would be deranged and
destroyed in a period which, however large, is yet
finite, it is obvious we cannot carry their origin indefinitely
backwards in a range of past duration.
There is a period in which these revolutions, whenever
they had begun, would have brought the revolving
bodies into contact with the central mass;
and this period has in our system not yet elapsed.
The watch is still going, and therefore it must have
been wound up within a limited time.
The solar system, at this its beginning, must have
been arranged and put in motion by some cause. If
we suppose this cause to operate by means of the
configurations and the properties of previously existing
matter, these configurations must have resulted
from some still previous cause, these properties must
have produced some previous effects. We are thus
led to a condition still earlier than the assumed beginning;—to
an origin of the original state of the
universe; and in this manner we are carried perpetually
further and further back, through a labyrinth
of mechanical causation, without any possibility of
finding any thing in which the mind can acquiesce
or rest, till we admit “a First Cause which is not
mechanical.”
Thus the argument which was before urged against
those in particular, who put forwards the Nebular Hypothesis
in opposition to the admission of an Intelligent
Creator, offers itself again, as cogent in itself,
when we adopt the opinion of a resisting medium,
for which the physical proofs have been found to be
so strong. The argument is indeed forced upon our
minds, whatever view we take of the past history of[162]
the universe. Some have endeavoured to evade its
force by maintaining that the world as it now exists
has existed from eternity. They assert that the present
order of things, or an order of things in some
way resembling the present, produced by the same
causes, governed by the same laws, has prevailed
through an infinite succession of past ages. We shall
not dwell upon any objections to this tenet which
might be drawn from our own conceptions, or from
what may be called metaphysical sources. Nor shall
we refer to the various considerations which history,
geology, and astronomical records supply, and which
tend to show, not only that the past duration of the
present course of things is finite, but that it is short,
compared with such periods as we have had to speak
of. But we may observe, that the doctrine of a resisting
medium once established, makes this imagination
untenable; compels us to go back to the origin,
not only of the present course of the world, not only
of the earth, but of the solar system itself; and thus
sets us forth upon that path of research into the series
of past causation, where we obtain no answer of
which the meaning corresponds to our questions, till
we rest in the conclusion of a most provident and
most powerful Creating Intelligence.
It is related of Epicurus that when a boy, reading
with his preceptor these verses of Hesiod,</div></body></text></TEI>