<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="140">CHAPTER III.
Sound.
The Velocity of Sound in
Water.
THE Science of which the
history is narrated in this Book has for its objects, the minute
Vibrations of the parts of bodies such as those by which Sounds are
produced, and the properties of Sounds. The Vibrations of bodies are
the result of a certain tension of their structure which we term
Elasticity. The Elasticity determines the rate of Vibration:
the rate of Vibration determines the audible note: the Elasticity
determines also the velocity with which the vibration travels through
the substance. These points of the subject, Elasticity, Rate of
Vibration, Velocity of Propagation, Audible Note, are connected in
each substance, and are different in different substances.
In the history of this Science, considered as tending to a
satisfactory general theory, the Problems which have obviously offered
themselves were, to explain the properties of Sounds by the relations
of their constituent vibrations; and to explain the existence of
vibrations by the elasticity of the substances in which they occurred:
as in Optics, philosophers have explained the phenomenon of light and
colors by the Undulatory Theory, and are still engaged in explaining
the requisite modulations by means of the elasticity of the Ether. But
the Undulatory Theory of Sound was seen to be true at an early
period of the Science: and the explanation, in a general way at least,
of all kinds of such undulations by means of the elasticity of the
vibrating substances has been performed by a series of mathematicians
of whom I have given an account in this Book.
Hence the points of the subject already mentioned (Elasticity,
Vibrations and their Propagations, 600 and Note), have a known material
dependence, and each may be employed in determining the other: for
instance, the Note may be employed in determining the velocity of
sound and the elasticity of the vibrating substance.
Chladni,1 and the Webers,2 had made valuable
experimental inquiries on such subjects. But more complete
investigations of this kind have been conducted with care and skill by
M. Wertheim.3 For instance, he has determined the
velocity with which sound travels in water, by making an organ-pipe to
sound by the passage of water through it. This is a matter of some
difficulty; for the mouthpiece of an organ-pipe, if it be not properly
and carefully constructed, produces sounds of its own, which are not
the genuine musical note of the pipe. And though the note depends
mainly upon the length of the pipe, it depends also, in a small
degree, on the breadth of the pipe and the size of the mouthpiece.
1 Traité d’Acoustique,
1809.
2 Wellenlehre, 1852.
3 Mémoires de Physique
Mécanique. Paris, 1848.
If the pipe were a mere line, the time of a vibration would be the
time in which a vibration travels from one end of the pipe to the
other; and thus the note for a given length (which is determined by
the time of vibration), is connected with the velocity of vibration.
He thus found that the velocity of a vibration along the pipe in
sea-water is 1157 mètres per second.
But M. Wertheim conceived that he had previously shown, by general
mathematical reasoning, that the velocity with which sound travels in
an unlimited expanse of any substance, is to the velocity with which
it travels along a pipe or linear strip of the same substance as the
square root of 3 to the square root of 2. Hence the velocity of sound
in sea-water would be 1454 mètres a second. The velocity of
sound in air is 332 mètres.
M. Wertheim also employed the vibrations of rods of steel and other
metals in order to determine their modulus of
elasticity—that is, the quantity which determines for each
substance, the extent to which, in virtue of its elasticity, it is
compressed and expanded by given pressures or tensions. For this
purpose he caused the rod to vibrate near to a tuning-fork of given
pitch, so that both the rod and the tuning-fork by their vibrations
traced undulating curves on a revolving disk. The curves traced by the
two could be compared so as to give their relative rate, and thus to
determine the elasticity of the substance.


BOOK IX.

PHYSICAL OPTICS.

Photography.
I HAVE, at the end of Chapter xi., stated that the theory of which I
have endeavored to sketch the history professes to explain only the
phenomena of radiant visible light; and that though we know that light
has other properties—for instance, that it produces chemical
effects—these are not contemplated as included within the domain
of the theory. The chemical effects of light cannot as yet be included
in exact and general truths, such as those which constitute the
undulatory theory of radiant visible light. But though the present age
has not yet attained to a Science of the chemistry of Light,
it has been enriched with a most exquisite Art, which
involves the principles of such a science, and may hereafter be made
the instrument of bringing them into the view of the philosopher. I
speak of the Art of Photography, in which chemistry has
discovered the means of producing surfaces almost as sensitive to the
modifications of light as the most sensitive of organic textures, the
retina of the eye: and has given permanence to images which in the eye
are only momentary impressions. Hereafter, when the laws shall have
been theoretically established, which connect the chemical
constitution of bodies with the action of light upon them, the
prominent names in the Prelude to such an Epoch must be those who by
their insight, invention, and perseverance, discovered and carried to
their present marvellous perfection the processes of photographic
Art:—Niepce and Daguerre in France, and our own accomplished
countryman, Mr. Fox Talbot.
Fluorescence.
As already remarked, it is not within the province of the
undulatory theory to explain the phenomena of the absorption of light
which take place in various ways when the light is transmitted through
various 602
mediums. I have, at the end of Chapter iii.,
given the reasons which prevent my assenting to the assertion of a
special analysis of light by absorption. In the same manner, with
regard to other effects produced by media upon light, it is sufficient
for the defence of the theory that it should be consistent with the
possibility of the laws of phenomena which are observed, not that it
should explain those laws; for they belong, apparently, to another
province of philosophy.
Some of the optical properties of bodies which have recently
attracted notice appear to be of this kind. It was noticed by Sir John
Herschel,4 that a certain liquid, sulphate of
quinine, which is under common circumstances colorless, exhibits in
certain aspects and under certain incidences of light, a beautiful
celestial blue color. It appeared that this color proceeded from the
surface on which the light first fell; and color thus produced Sir J.
Herschel called epipolic colors, and spoke of the light as
epipolized. Sir David Brewster had previously noted effects of
color in transparent bodies which he ascribed to internal
dispersion:5 and he conceived that the colors
observed by Sir J. Herschel were of the same class. Professor Stokes6
of Cambridge applied himself to the examination of these phenomena,
and was led to the conviction that they arise from a power which
certain bodies possess, of changing the color, and with it, the
refrangibility of the rays of light which fall upon them: and he
traced this property in various substances, into various remarkable
consequences. As this change of refrangibility always makes the rays
less refrangible, it was proposed to call it a
degradation of the light; or again, dependent emission,
because the light is emitted in the manner of self-luminous bodies,
but only in dependence upon the active rays, and so long as the body
is under their influence. In this respect it differs from
phosphorescence, in which light is emitted without such
dependence. The phenomenon occurs in a conspicuous and beautiful
manner in certain kinds of fluor spar: and the term
fluorescence, suggested by Professor Stokes, has the advantage
of inserting no hypothesis, and will probably be found the most
generally acceptable.7
4 Phil. Trans. 1845.
5 Edinb. Trans. 1833.
6 Phil. Trans. 1852 and
1854.
7 Phil. Trans. 1852.
It may be remarked that Professor Stokes rejects altogether the
doctrine that light of definite refrangibility may still be compound,
and maybe analysed by absorption. He says, “I have not overlooked the
remarkable effect of absorbing media in causing apparent changes 603 of color in a pure
spectrum; but this I believe to be a subjective phenomenon depending
upon contrast.”
</div></body></text></TEI>