<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="14">
CHAPTER IX.
Of the Classification of Sciences.
1. THE
Classification of Sciences has its chief use in
pointing out to us the extent of our powers of
arriving at truth, and the analogies which may obtain
between those certain and lucid portions of knowledge
with which we are here concerned, and those other
portions, of a very different interest and evidence,
which we here purposely abstain to touch upon. The
classification of human knowledge will, therefore, have
a more peculiar importance when we can include in it
the moral, political, and metaphysical, as well as the
physical portions of our knowledge. But such a survey
does not belong to our present undertaking: and
a general view of the connexion and order of the
branches of sciences which our review has hitherto included,
will even now possess some interest; and may
serve hereafter as an introduction to a more complete
scheme of the general body of human knowledge.
2. In this, as in any other case, a sound classification
must be the result, not of any assumed principles
imperatively applied to the subject, but of an examination
of the objects to be classified;—of an analysis of
them into the principles in which they agree and differ.
The Classification of Sciences must result from the
consideration of their nature and contents. Accordingly,
that review of the Sciences in which the History of
the Sciences engaged us, led to a Classification, of which
the main features are indicated in that work. The
Classification thus obtained, depends neither upon the
faculties of the mind to which the separate parts of
our knowledge owe their origin, nor upon the objects
which each science contemplates; but upon a more 137
natural and fundamental element;—namely, the Ideas
which each science involves. The Ideas regulate and
connect the facts, and are the foundations of the reasoning,
in each science: and having in another work
more fully examined these Ideas, we are now prepared
to state here the classification to which they lead. If
we have rightly traced each science to the Conceptions
which are really fundamental with regard to it, and
which give rise to the first principles on which it
depends, it is not necessary for our purpose that we
should decide whether these Conceptions are absolutely
ultimate principles of thought, or whether, on the contrary,
they can be further resolved into other Fundamental Ideas.
We need not now suppose it determined whether or not Number
is a mere modification
of the Idea of Time, and Force a mere modification of
the Idea of Cause: for however this may be, our Conception
of Number is the foundation of Arithmetic,
and our Conception of Force is the foundation of Mechanics.
It is to be observed also that in our classification,
each Science may involve, not only the Ideas
or Conceptions which are placed opposite to it in the
list, but also all which precede it. Thus Formal Astronomy
involves not only the Conception of Motion, but
also those which are the foundation of Arithmetic and
Geometry. In like manner. Physical Astronomy employs the
Sciences of Statics and Dynamics, and thus,
rests on their foundations; and they, in turn, depend
upon the Ideas of Space and of Time, as well as of
Cause.
3. We may further observe, that this arrangement
of Sciences according to the Fundamental Ideas which
they involve, points out the transition from those parts
of human knowledge which have been included in our
History and Philosophy, to other regions of speculation
into which we have not entered. We have repeatedly
found ourselves upon the borders of inquiries of a
psychological, or moral, or theological nature. Thus
the History of Physiology28
led us to the consideration 138
of Life, Sensation, and Volition; and at these Ideas we
stopped, that we might not transgress the boundaries of
our subject as then predetermined. It is plain that
the pursuit of such conceptions and their consequences,
would lead us to the sciences (if we are allowed to call
them sciences) which contemplate not only animal, but
human principles of action, to Anthropology, and Psychology.
In other ways, too, the Ideas which we hare
examined, although manifestly the foundations of sciences
such as we have here treated of also plainly
pointed to speculations of a different order; thus the
Idea of a Final Cause is an indispensable guide in
Biology, as we have seen; but the conception of Design
as directing the order of nature, once admitted, soon
carries us to higher contemplations. Again, the Class
of Palætiological Sciences which we were in the History
led to construct, although we there admitted only
one example of the Class, namely Geology, does in
reality include many vast lines of research; as the
history and causes of the division of plants and animals,
the history of languages, arts, and consequently
of civilization. Along with these researches, comes
the question how far these histories point backwards to
a natural or a supernatural origin; and the Idea of a
First Cause is thus brought under our consideration.
Finally, it is not difficult to see that as the Physical
Sciences have their peculiar governing Ideas, which
support and shape them, so the Moral and Political
Sciences also must similarly have their fundamental
and formative Ideas, the source of universal and certain
truths, each of their proper kind. But to follow
out the traces of this analogy, and to verify the
existence of those Fundamental Ideas in Morals and
Politics, is a task quite out of the sphere of the work
in which we are here engaged.
28
 Hist. Ind. Sc. b. xvii. c. v. sect. 2.
4. We may now place before the reader our Classification
of the Sciences. I have added to the list of
Sciences, a few not belonging to our present subject,
that the nature of the transition by which we are to
extend our philosophy into a wider and higher region
may be in some measure perceived. 139
The Classification of the Sciences is given over leaf.
A few remarks upon it offer themselves.
The Pure Mathematical Sciences can hardly be called
Inductive Sciences. Their principles are not obtained
by Induction from Facts, but are necessarily assumed
in reasoning upon the subject matter which those
sciences involve.
The Astronomy of the Ancients aimed only at explaining
the motions of the heavenly bodies, as a mechanism.
Modern Astronomy, explains these motions on
the principles of Mechanics.
The term Physics, when confined to a peculiar
class of Sciences, is usually understood to exclude the
Mechanical Sciences on the one side, and Chemistry
on the other; and thus embraces the Secondary Mechanical
and Analytico-Mechanical Sciences. But the adjective
Physical applied to any science and opposed
to Formal, as in Astronomy and Optics, implies those
speculations in which we consider not only the Laws
of Phenomena but their Causes; and generally, as
in those cases, their Mechanical Causes.
The term Metaphysics is applied to subjects in which
the Facts examined are emotions, thoughts and mental
conditions; subjects not included in our present survey. 140
Fundamental Ideas or
Conceptions.Sciences.Classification.


SpaceGeometry⎫


Time⎪Pure Mathematical


NumberArithmetic⎬


SignAlgebra⎪ Sciences.


LimitDifferentials⎭


MotionPure Mechanism⎱Pure Motional


Formal Astronomy⎰Sciences.





Cause


ForceStatics⎫


MatterDynamics⎪Mechanical


Inertia Hydrostatics⎬


Fluid PressureHydrodynamics⎪Sciences.


Physical Astronomy⎭


Outness


Medium of SensationAcoustics⎫


Intensity of QualitiesFormal Optics⎪Secondary


Scales of QualitiesPhysical Optics⎬Mechanical


Thermotics⎪Sciences.


Atmology⎭(Physics.)


PolarityElectricity⎫Analytico-Mecha-


Magnetism⎬nical Sciences.


Galvanism⎭(Physics.)


Element (Composition)


Chemical Affinity


Substance (Atoms)ChemistryAnalytical Science.


SymmetryCrystallography⎱Analytico-Classifi-


LikenessSystematic Mineralogy⎰catory Sciences.


Degrees of LikenessSystematic Botany⎫Classificatory


Systematic Zoology⎬


Natural AffinityComparative Anatomy⎭Sciences.


(Vital Powers)


Assimilation


Irritability


(Organization)BiologyOrganical Sciences.


Final Cause


Instinct


EmotionPsychology(Metaphysics.)


Thought


Historical CausationGeology⎫


Distribution of⎪Palætiological


 Plants and Animals⎬


Glossology⎪Sciences.


Ethnography⎭


First CauseNatural Theology.
</div></body></text></TEI>