<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="4">
[50]
CHAPTER IV.

The Magnitude of the Ocean.

There are several arbitrary quantities which contribute
to determine the state of things at the earth’s
surface besides those already mentioned. Some of
these we shall briefly refer to, without pursuing the
subject into detail. We wish not only to show that
the properties and processes of vegetable and animal
life must be adjusted to each of these quantities in
particular, but also to point out how numerous and
complicated the conditions of the existence of organized
beings are; and we shall thus be led to think
less inadequately of the intelligence which has embraced
at once, and combined without confusion, all
these conditions. We appear thus to be conducted
to the conviction not only of design and intention,
but of supreme knowledge and wisdom.
One of the quantities which enters into the constitution
of the terrestrial system of things is the bulk of
the waters of the ocean. The mean depth of the sea,
according to the calculations of Laplace, is four or
five miles. On this supposition, the addition to the
sea of one-fourth of the existing waters would drown
the whole of the globe, except a few chains of mountains.
Whether this be exact or no, we can easily
conceive the quantity of water which lies in the cavities
of our globe to be greater or less than it at present
is. With every such addition or subtraction
the form and magnitude of the dry land would vary,
and if this change were considerable, many of the
present relations of things would be altered. It may
be sufficient to mention one effect of such a change.
The sources which water the earth, both clouds,
rains, and rivers, are mainly fed by the aqueous vapour[51]
raised from the sea; and therefore if the sea
were much diminished, and the land increased, the
mean quantity of moisture distributed upon the land
must be diminished, and the character of climates,
as to wet and dry, must be materially affected. Similar,
but opposite changes would result from the increase
of the surface of the ocean.
It appears then that the magnitude of the ocean is
one of the conditions to which the structure of all
organized beings which are dependent upon climate
must be adapted.
</div></body></text></TEI>