<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="47">

CHAPTER II.
Establishment and Development of the Idea of Chemical Affinity.



1. THE earlier chemists did not commonly involve
themselves in the confusion into which the
mechanical philosophers ran, of comparing chemical to
mechanical forces. Their attention was engaged, and
their ideas were moulded, by their own pursuits. They
saw that the connexion of elements and compounds with
which they had to deal, was a peculiar relation which must
be studied directly; and which must be understood, if
understood at all, in itself, and not by comparison with
a different class of relations. At different periods of
the progress of chemistry, the conception of this relation, still vague and obscure, was expressed in various
manners; and at last this conception was clothed in
tolerably consistent phraseology, and the principles
which it involved were, by the united force of thought
and experiment, brought into view.
2. The power by which the elements of bodies
combine chemically, being, as we have seen, a peculiar
agency, different from mere mechanical connexion or
attraction, it is desirable to have it designated by a
distinct and peculiar name; and the term Affinity has
been employed for that purpose by most modern chemists. The word ‘affinity’ in common language means,
sometimes resemblance, and sometimes relationship
and ties of family. It is from the latter sense that the
metaphor is borrowed when we speak of ‘chemical
affinity.’ By the employment of this term we do not indicate a resemblance, but a disposition to unite. Using
the word in a common unscientific manner, we might
say that chlorine, bromine, and iodine, have a great 16 natural affinity with each other, for there are considerable resemblances and analogies among them; but
these bodies have very little chemical Affinity for each
other. The use of the word in the former sense, of resemblance, can be traced in earlier chemists; but the word
does not appear to have acquired its peculiar chemical
meaning till after Boerhaave’s time. Boerhaave, however, is the writer in whom we first find a due apprehension of the peculiarity and importance of the Idea
which it now expresses. When we make a chemical
solution13, he says, not only are the particles of the dissolved body separated from each other, but they are
closely united to the particles of the solvent. When
aqua regia dissolves gold, do you not see, he says to
his hearers, that there must be between each particle
of the solvent and of the metal, a mutual virtue by
which each loves, unites with, and holds the other
(amat, unit, retinet)? The opinion previously prevalent had been that the solvent merely separates the
parts of the body dissolved: and most philosophers
had conceived this separation as performed by mechanical operations of the particles, resembling, for instance, the operation of wedges breaking up a block of
timber. But Boerhaave forcibly and earnestly points
out the insufficiency of the conception. This, he says,
does not account for what we see. We have not only
a separation, but a new combination. There is a force
by which the particles of the solvent associate to themselves the parts dissolved, not a force by which they
repel and dissever them. We are here to imagine not
mechanical action, not violent impulse, not antipathy,
but love, at least if love be the desire of uniting. (Non
igitur hic etiam actiones mechanicæ, non propulsiones
violentæ, non inimicitiæ cogitandæ, sed amicitiæ, si
amor dicendus copulæ cupido.) The novelty of this
view is evidenced by the mode in which he apologizes
for introducing it. ‘Fateor, paradoxa hæc assertio.’
To Boerhaave, therefore, (especially considering his
great influence as a teacher of chemistry,) we may 17 assign the merit of first diffusing a proper view of
Chemical Affinity as a peculiar force, the origin of
almost all chemical changes and operations.</div></body></text></TEI>