<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="16">

CHAPTER VII.
OF SIMPLE IDEAS OF BOTH SENSATION AND REFLECTION.

1. Ideas of Pleasure and Pain.


There be other simple ideas which convey themselves into the mind by all the
ways of sensation and reflection, viz.


Pleasure or Delight, and its opposite,
Pain, or Uneasiness;
Power;
Existence;
Unity mix with almost all our other Ideas.


2. Delight or uneasiness, one or other of them, join themselves to almost all
our ideas both of sensation and reflection: and there is scarce any affection
of our senses from without, any retired thought of our mind within, which is
not able to produce in us pleasure or pain. By pleasure and pain, I would be
understood to signify, whatsoever delights or molests us; whether it arises
from the thoughts of our minds, or anything operating on our bodies. For,
whether we call it; satisfaction, delight, pleasure, happiness, &c., on the
one side, or uneasiness, trouble, pain, torment, anguish, misery, &c., the
other, they are still but different degrees of the same thing, and belong to
the ideas of pleasure and pain, delight or uneasiness; which are the names I
shall most commonly use for those two sorts of ideas.


3. As motives of our actions.


The infinite wise Author of our being, having given us the power over several
parts of our bodies, to move or keep them at rest as we think fit; and also, by
the motion of them, to move ourselves and other contiguous bodies, in which
consist all the actions of our body: having also given a power to our minds, in
several instances, to choose, amongst its ideas, which it will think on, and to
pursue the inquiry of this or that subject with consideration and attention, to
excite us to these actions of thinking and motion that we are capable
of,—has been pleased to join to several thoughts, and several sensations
a perception of delight. If this were wholly separated from all our outward
sensations, and inward thoughts, we should have no reason to prefer one thought
or action to another; negligence to attention, or motion to rest. And so we
should neither stir our bodies, nor employ our minds, but let our thoughts (if
I may so call it) run adrift, without any direction or design, and suffer the
ideas of our minds, like unregarded shadows, to make their appearances there,
as it happened, without attending to them. In which state man, however
furnished with the faculties of understanding and will, would be a very idle,
inactive creature, and pass his time only in a lazy, lethargic dream. It has
therefore pleased our wise Creator to annex to several objects, and the ideas
which we receive from them, as also to several of our thoughts, a concomitant
pleasure, and that in several objects, to several degrees, that those faculties
which he had endowed us with might not remain wholly idle and unemployed by us.


4. An end and use of pain.


Pain has the same efficacy and use to set us on work that pleasure has, we
being as ready to employ our faculties to avoid that, as to pursue this: only
this is worth our consideration, that pain is often produced by the same
objects and ideas that produce pleasure in us. This their near conjunction,
which makes us often feel pain in the sensations where we expected pleasure,
gives us new occasion of admiring the wisdom and goodness of our Maker, who,
designing the preservation of our being, has annexed pain to the application of
many things to our bodies, to warn us of the harm that they will do, and as
advices to withdraw from them. But he, not designing our preservation barely,
but the preservation of every part and organ in its perfection, hath in many
cases annexed pain to those very ideas which delight us. Thus heat, that is
very agreeable to us in one degree, by a little greater increase of it proves
no ordinary torment: and the most pleasant of all sensible objects, light
itself, if there be too much of it, if increased beyond a due proportion to our
eyes, causes a very painful sensation. Which is wisely and favourably so
ordered by nature, that when any object does, by the vehemency of its
operation, disorder the instruments of sensation, whose structures cannot but
be very nice and delicate, we might, by the pain, be warned to withdraw, before
the organ be quite put out of order, and so be unfitted for its proper function
for the future. The consideration of those objects that produce it may well
persuade us, that this is the end or use of pain. For, though great light be
insufferable to our eyes, yet the highest degree of darkness does not at all
disease them: because that, causing no disorderly motion in it, leaves that
curious organ unharmed in its natural state. But yet excess of cold as well as
heat pains us: because it is equally destructive to that temper which is
necessary to the preservation of life, and the exercise of the several
functions of the body, and which consists in a moderate degree of warmth; or,
if you please, a motion of the insensible parts of our bodies, confined within
certain bounds.


5. Another end.


Beyond all this, we may find another reason why God hath scattered up and down
several degrees of pleasure and pain, in all the things that environ and affect
us; and blended them together in almost all that our thoughts and senses have
to do with;—that we, finding imperfection, dissatisfaction, and want of
complete happiness, in all the enjoyments which the creatures can afford us,
might be led to seek it in the enjoyment of Him with whom there is fullness of
joy, and at whose right hand are pleasures for evermore.


6. Goodness of God in annexing pleasure and pain to our other ideas.


Though what I have here said may not, perhaps, make the ideas of pleasure and
pain clearer to us than our own experience does, which is the only way that we
are capable of having them; yet the consideration of the reason why they are
annexed to so many other ideas, serving to give us due sentiments of the wisdom
and goodness of the Sovereign Disposer of all things, may not be unsuitable to
the main end of these inquiries: the knowledge and veneration of him being the
chief end of all our thoughts, and the proper business of all understandings.


7. Ideas of Existence and Unity.


EXISTENCE and UNITY are two other ideas that are suggested to the understanding
by every object without, and every idea within. When ideas are in our minds, we
consider them as being actually there, as well as we consider things to be
actually without us;—which is, that they exist, or have existence. And
whatever we can consider as one thing, whether a real being or idea, suggests
to the understanding the idea of unity.


8. Idea of Power.


POWER also is another of those simple ideas which we receive from sensation and
reflection. For, observing in ourselves that we do and can think, and that we
can at pleasure move several parts of our bodies which were at rest; the
effects, also, that natural bodies are able to produce in one another,
occurring every moment to our senses,—we both these ways get the idea of
power.


9. Idea of Succession.


Besides these there is another idea, which, though suggested by our senses, yet
is more constantly offered to us by what passes in our minds; and that is the
idea of SUCCESSION. For if we look immediately into ourselves, and reflect on
what is observable there, we shall find our ideas always, whilst we are awake,
or have any thought, passing in train, one going and another coming, without
intermission.


10. Simple Ideas the materials of all our Knowledge.


These, if they are not all, are at least (as I think) the most considerable of
those simple ideas which the mind has, out of which is made all its other
knowledge; all which it receives only by the two forementioned ways of
sensation and reflection.


Nor let any one think these too narrow bounds for the capacious mind of man to
expatiate in, which takes its flight further than the stars, and cannot be
confined by the limits of the world; that extends its thoughts often even
beyond the utmost expansion of Matter, and makes excursions into that
incomprehensible Inane. I grant all this, but desire any one to assign any
SIMPLE IDEA which is not received from one of those inlets before mentioned, or
any COMPLEX IDEA not made out of those simple ones. Nor will it be so strange
to think these few simple ideas sufficient to employ the quickest thought, or
largest capacity; and to furnish the materials of all that various knowledge,
and more various fancies and opinions of all mankind, if we consider how many
words may be made out of the various composition of twenty-four letters; or if,
going one step further, we will but reflect on the variety of combinations that
may be made with barely one of the above-mentioned ideas, viz. number, whose
stock is inexhaustible and truly infinite: and what a large and immense field
doth extension alone afford the mathematicians?


</div></body></text></TEI>