<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="8">
CHAPTER VIII.

The Constituents of Climate.

We have spoken of the steady average of the climate
at each place, of the difference of this average
at different places, and of the adaptation of organized
beings to this character in the laws of the elements
by which they are affected. But this steadiness in
the general effect of the elements, is the result of an
extremely complex and extensive machinery. Climate,
in its wider sense, is not one single agent, but
is the aggregate result of a great number of different
agents, governed by different laws, producing effects
of various kinds. The steadiness of this compound
agency is not the steadiness of a permanent condition,
like that of a body at rest; but it is the steadiness
of a state of constant change and movement,
succession and alternation, seeming accident and
irregularity. It is a perpetual repose, combined
with a perpetual motion; an invariable average of
most variable quantities. Now, the manner in which
such a state of things is produced, deserves, we conceive,
a closer consideration. It may be useful to
show how the particular laws of the action of each
of the elements of climate are so adjusted that they
do not disturb this general constancy.
[67]
The principal constituents of climate are the following:—the
temperature of the earth, of the water,
of the air:—the distribution of the aqueous vapour
contained in the atmosphere:—the winds and rains
by which the equilibrium of the atmosphere is restored
when it is in any degree disturbed. The
effects of light, of electricity, probably of other
causes also, are no doubt important in the economy
of the vegetable world, but these agencies have not
been reduced by scientific inquirers to such laws as
to admit of their being treated with the same exactness
and certainty which we can obtain in the case
of those first mentioned.
We shall proceed to trace some of the peculiarities
in the laws of the different physical agents which
are in action at the earth’s surface, and the manner
in which these peculiarities bear upon the general
result.
The Laws of Heat with respect to the Earth.
One of the main causes which determine the temperature
of each climate is the effect of the sun’s
rays on the solid mass of the earth. The laws of
this operation have been recently made out with
considerable exactness, experimentally by Leslie,
theoretically 
by Fourier, and by other inquirers.
The theoretical inquiries have required the application
of very complex and abstruse mathematical investigations;
but the general character of the operation
may, perhaps, be made easily intelligible.
The earth, like all solid bodies, transmits into its
interior the impressions of heat which it receives at
the surface; and throws off the superfluous heat from
its surface into the surrounding space. These processes
are called conduction and radiation, and have
each their ascertained mathematical laws.
By the laws of conduction, the daily impressions
of heat which the earth receives, follow each other[68]
into the interior of the mass, like the waves which
start from the edge of a canal;[6] and like them, become
more and more faint as they proceed, till they
melt into the general level of the internal temperature.
The heat thus transmitted is accumulated in
the interior of the earth, as in a reservoir, and flows
from one part to another of this reservoir. The parts
of the earth near the equator are more heated by the
sun than other parts, and on this account there is a
perpetual internal conduction of heat from the equatorial
to other parts of the sphere. And as all parts
of the surface throw off heat by radiation, in the polar
regions, where the surface receives little in return
from the sun, a constant waste is produced. There
is thus from the polar parts a perpetual dispersion of
heat in the surrounding space, which is supplied by
a perpetual internal flow from the equator towards
each pole.
Here, then, is a kind of circulation of heat; and
the quantity and rapidity of this circulation, determine
the quantity of heat in the solid part of the
earth, and in each portion of it; and through this,
the mean temperature belonging to each point on its
surface.
If the earth conducted heat more rapidly than it
does, the inequalities of temperature would be more
quickly balanced, and the temperature of the ground
(below the reach of annual and diurnal variations)
would differ less than it does. If the surface radiated
more rapidly than it does, the flow of heat from the
polar regions would increase, and the temperature
of the interior of the globe would find a lower level;
the differences of temperature in different latitudes[69]
would increase, but the mean temperature of the
globe 
would diminish.
There is nothing which, so far as we can perceive,
determines necessarily, either the conducting or the
radiating power of the earth to its present value.
The measures of such powers, in different substances,
differ very widely. If the earth were a globe of pure
iron, it would conduct heat, probably, twenty times
as well as it does; if its surface were polished iron,
it would only radiate one-sixth as much as it does.
Changes in the amount of the conduction and radiation
far less than these, would, probably, subvert the
whole thermal constitution of the earth, and make it
uninhabitable by any of its present vegetable, or animal
tenants.
One of the results of the laws of heat, as they exist
in the globe, is, that, by their action, the thermal
state tends to a limiting condition, which, once
reached, remains constant and steady, as it now is.
The oscillations or excursions from the mean condition,
produced by any temporary cause, are rapidly
suppressed; the deviations of seasons from their
usual standard produce only a small and transient
effect. The impression of an extremely hot day
upon the ground melts almost immediately into the
average internal heat. The effect of a hot summer,
in like manner, is soon lost in its progress through
the globe. If this were otherwise, if the inequalities
and oscillations of heat went on, through the interior
of the earth, retaining the same value, or becoming
larger and larger, we might have the extreme heats
or colds of one place making their appearance at
another place after a long interval; like a conflagration
which creeps along a street and bursts out at a
point remote from its origin.
It appears, therefore, that both the present differences
of climate, and the steadiness of the average
at each place, depend upon the form of the present
laws of heat, and on the arbitrary magnitudes which
determine the rate of conduction and radiation. The[70]
laws are such as to secure us from increasing and
destructive inequalities of heat; the arbitrary magnitudes
are elements to which the organic world is adjusted.
</div></body></text></TEI>