<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="19">CHAPTER V.
Progress of the Arts in the Middle Ages.
ART and Science.—I
shall, before I resume the history of science, say a few words on the
subject described in the title of this chapter, both because I might
otherwise be accused of doing injustice to the period now treated of;
and also, because we shall by this means bring under our notice some
circumstances which were important as being the harbingers of the
revival of progressive knowledge.
The accusation of injustice towards the state of science in the
middle ages, if we were to terminate our survey of them with what has
hitherto been said, might be urged from obvious topics. How do we
recognize, it might be asked, in a picture of mere confusion and
mysticism of thought, of servility and dogmatism of character, the
powers and acquirements to which we owe so many of the most important
inventions which we now enjoy? Parchment and paper, printing and
engraving, improved glass and steel, gunpowder, clocks, telescopes,
240 the mariner’s
compass, the reformed calendar, the decimal notation, algebra,
trigonometry, chemistry, counterpoint, an invention equivalent to a
new creation of music;—these are all possessions which we
inherit from that which has been so disparagingly termed the
Stationary Period. Above all, let us look at the monuments of
architecture of this period;—the admiration and the despair of
modern architects, not only for their beauty, but for the skill
disclosed in their construction. With all these evidences before us,
how can we avoid allowing that the masters of the middle ages not only
made some small progress in Astronomy, which has, grudgingly as it
would seem, been admitted in a former Book; but also that they were no
small proficients in other sciences, in Optics, in Harmonics, in
Physics, and, above all, in Mechanics?
If, it may be added, we are allowed, in the present day, to refer
to the perfection of our arts as evidence of the advanced state of our
physical philosophy;—if our steam-engines, our gas-illumination,
our buildings, our navigation, our manufactures, are cited as triumphs
of science;—shall not prior inventions, made under far heavier
disadvantages,—shall not greater works, produced in an earlier
state of knowledge, also be admitted as witnesses that the middle ages
had their share, and that not a small or doubtful one, of science?
To these questions I answer, by distinguishing between Art, and
Science in that sense of general Inductive Systematic Truth, which it
bears in this work. To separate and compare, with precision, these two
processes, belongs to the Philosophy of Induction; and the attempt
must be reserved for another place: but the leading differences are
sufficiently obvious. Art is practical, Science is speculative: the
former is seen in doing; the latter rests in the contemplation of what
is known. The Art of the builder appears in his edifice, though he may
never have meditated on the abstract propositions on which its
stability and strength depends. The Science of the mathematical
mechanician consists in his seeing that, under certain conditions,
bodies must sustain each other’s pressure, though he may never have
applied his knowledge in a single case.
Now the remark which I have to make is this:—in all cases the
Arts are prior to the related Sciences. Art is the parent, not the
progeny, of Science; the realization of principles in practice forms
part of the prelude, as well as of the sequel, of theoretical
discovery. And thus the inventions of the middle ages, which have been
above enumerated, though at the present day they may be portions of
our sciences, are no evidence that the sciences then existed; but only
that 241 those
powers of practical observation and practical skill were at work,
which prepare the way for theoretical views and scientific
discoveries.
It may be urged, that the great works of art do virtually take for
granted principles of science; and that, therefore, it is unreasonable
to deny science to great artists. It may be said, that the grand
structures of Cologne, or Amiens, or Canterbury, could not have been
erected without a profound knowledge of mechanical principles.
To this we reply, that such knowledge is manifestly not of
the nature of that which we call science. If the beautiful
and skilful structures of the middle ages prove that mechanics then
existed as a science, mechanics must have existed as a science also
among the builders of the Cyclopean walls of Greece and Italy, or of
our own Stonehenge; for the masses which are there piled on each
other, could not be raised without considerable mechanical skill. But
we may go much further. The actions of every man who raises and
balances weights, or walks along a pole, take for granted the laws of
equilibrium; and even animals constantly avail themselves of such
principles. Are these, then, acquainted with mechanics as a science?
Again, if actions which are performed by taking advantage of
mechanical properties prove a knowledge of the science of mechanics,
they must also be allowed to prove a knowledge of the science of
geometry, when they proceed on geometrical properties. But the most
familiar actions of men and animals proceed upon geometrical truths.
The Epicureans held, as Proclus informs us, that even asses knew that
two sides of a triangle are greater than the third. And animals may
truly be said to have a practical knowledge of this truth; but they
have not, therefore, a science of geometry. And in like manner among
men, if we consider the matter strictly, a practical assumption of a
principle does not imply a speculative knowledge of it.
We may, in another way also, show how inadmissible are the works of
the Master Artists of the middle ages into the series of events which
mark the advance of Science. The following maxim is applicable to a
history, such as we are here endeavoring to write. We are employed in
tracing the progress of such general principles as constitute each of
the sciences which we are reviewing; and no facts or subordinate
truths belong to our scheme, except so far as they tend to or are
included in these higher principles; nor are they important to us, any
further than as they prove such principles. Now with regard to
processes of art like those which we have referred to, namely, the
inventions of the middle ages, let us ask, what principle
each of them 242
illustrates? What chemical doctrine rests for its support on the
phenomena of gunpowder, or glass, or steel? What new harmonical truth
was illustrated in the Gregorian chant? What mechanical principle
unknown to Archimedes was displayed in the printing-press? The
practical value and use, the ingenuity and skill of these inventions
is not questioned; but what is their place in the history of
speculative knowledge? Even in those cases in which they enter into
such a history, how minute a figure do they make! how great is the
contrast between their practical and theoretical importance! They may
in their operation have changed the face of the world; but in the
history of the principles of the sciences to which they belong, they
may be omitted without being missed.
As to that part of the objection which was stated by asking, why,
if the arts of our age prove its scientific eminence, the arts of the
middle ages should not be received as proof of theirs; we must reply
to it, by giving up some of the pretensions which are often put
forwards on behalf of the science of our times. The perfection of the
mechanical and other arts among us proves the advanced condition of
our sciences, only in so far as these arts have been perfected by the
application of some great scientific truth, with a clear insight into
its nature. The greatest improvement of the steam-engine was due to
the steady apprehension of an atmological doctrine by Watt; but what
distinct theoretical principle is illustrated by the beautiful
manufactures of porcelain, or steel, or glass? A chemical view of
these compounds, which would explain the conditions of success and
failure in their manufacture, would be of great value in art; and it
would also be a novelty in chemical theory; so little is the present
condition of those processes a triumph of science, shedding
intellectual glory on our age. And the same might be said of many, or
of most, of the processes of the arts as now practised.
2. Arabian Science.—Having, I trust, established the
view I have stated, respecting the relation of Art and Science, we
shall be able very rapidly to dispose of a number of subjects which
otherwise might seem to require a detailed notice. Though this
distinction has been recognized by others, it has hardly been
rigorously adhered to, in consequence of the indistinct notion of
science which has commonly prevailed. Thus Gibbon, in speaking
of the knowledge of the period now under our notice, says,88 “Much useful experience had been
acquired in 243 the
practice of arts and manufactures; but the science of
chemistry owes its origin and improvement to the industry of the
Saracens. They,” he adds, “first invented and named the alembic for
the purposes of distillation, analyzed the substances of the three
kingdoms of nature, tried the distinction and affinities of alkalies
and acids, and converted the poisonous minerals into soft and salutary
medicines.” The formation and realization of the notions of
analysis and of affinity, were important steps in
chemical science, which, as I shall hereafter endeavor to show, it
remained for the chemists of Europe to make at a much later period. If
the Arabians had done this, they might with justice have been called
the authors of the science of chemistry; but no doctrines can be
adduced from their works which give them any title to this eminent
distinction. Their claims are dissipated at once by the application of
the maxim above stated. What analysis of theirs tended to
establish any received principle of chemistry? What true
doctrine concerning the differences and affinities of acids and
alkalies did they teach? We need not wonder if Gibbon, whose views of
the boundaries of scientific chemistry were probably very wide and
indistinct, could include the arts of the Arabians within its domain;
but they cannot pass the frontier of science if philosophically
defined, and steadily guarded.
88 Decline and Fall, vol. x. p.
43.
The judgment which we are thus led to form respecting the chemical
knowledge of the middle ages, and of the Arabians in particular, may
serve to measure the condition of science in other departments; for
chemistry has justly been considered one of their strongest points. In
botany, anatomy, zoology, optics, acoustics, we have still the same
observations to make, that the steps in science which, in the order of
progress, next followed what the Greeks had done, were left for the
Europeans of the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries. The merits and
advances of the Arabian philosophers in astronomy and pure
mathematics, we have already described.
3. Experimental Philosophy of the Arabians.—The
estimate to which we have thus been led, of the scientific merits of
the learned men of the middle ages, is much less exalted than that
which has been formed by many writers; and, among the rest, by some of
our own time. But I am persuaded that any attempt to answer the
questions just asked, will expose the untenable nature of the higher
claims which have been advanced in favor of the Arabians. We can
deliver no just decision, except we will consent to use the terms of
science in a strict and precise sense: and if we do this, we shall
find little, either in the 244 particular discoveries or general
processes of the Arabians, which is important in the history of the
Inductive Sciences.89
89 If I might take the liberty of
criticising an author who has given a very interesting view of the
period in question (Mahometanism Unveiled, by the Rev. Charles
Forster, 1829), I would remark, that in his work this caution is
perhaps too little observed. Thus, he says, in speaking of Alhazen
(vol. ii. p. 270), “the theory of the telescope may be found in the
work of this astronomer;” and of another, “the uses of magnifying
glasses and telescopes, and the principle of their construction, are
explained in the Great Work of (Roger) Bacon, with a truth and
clearness which have commanded universal admiration.” Such phrases
would be much too strong, even if used respecting the optical
doctrines of Kepler, which were yet incomparably more true and clear
than those of Bacon. To employ such language, in such cases, is to
deprive such terms as theory and principle of all
meaning.
The credit due to the Arabians for improvements in the general
methods of philosophizing, is a more difficult question; and cannot be
discussed at length by us, till we examine the history of such methods
in the abstract, which, in the present work, it is not our intention
to do.  But we may observe, that we cannot agree with those who rank
their merits high in this respect. We have already seen, that their
minds were completely devoured by the worst habits of the stationary
period,—Mysticism and Commentation. They followed their Greek
leaders, for the most part, with abject servility, and with only that
kind of acuteness and independent speculation which the Commentator’s
vocation implies. And in their choice of the standard subjects of
their studies, they fixed upon those works, the Physical Books of
Aristotle, which have never promoted the progress of science, except
in so far as they incited men to refute them; an effect which they
never produced on the Arabians. That the Arabian astronomers made some
advances beyond the Greeks, we have already stated: the two great
instances are, the discovery of the Motion of the Sun’s Apogee by
Albategnius, and the discovery (recently brought to light) of the
existence of the Moon’s Second Inequality, by Aboul Wefa. But we
cannot but observe in how different a manner they treated these
discoveries, from that with which Hipparchus or Ptolemy would have
done. The Variation of the Moon, in particular, instead of being
incorporated into the system by means of an Epicycle, as Ptolemy had
done with the Evection, was allowed, almost immediately, so far as we
can judge, to fall into neglect and oblivion: so little were the
learned Arabians prepared to take their lessons from observation as
well as from books. That in many subjects they made experiments, may
easily be allowed: there never was a period of the earth’s history,
and least of all a period of commerce 245 and manufactures, luxury and art,
medicine and engineering, in which there were not going on innumerable
processes, which may be termed Experiments; and, in addition to these,
the Arabians adopted the pursuit of alchemy, and the love of exotic
plants and animals. But so far from their being, as has been
maintained,90 a people whose “experimental intellect”
fitted them to form sciences which the “abstract intellect” of the
Greeks failed in producing, it rather appears, that several of the
sciences which the Greeks had founded, were never even comprehended by
the Arabians. I do not know any evidence that these pupils ever
attained to understand the real principles of Mechanics, Hydrostatics,
and Harmonics, which their masters had established. At any rate, when
these sciences again became progressive, Europe had to start where
Europe had stopped. There is no Arabian name which any one has thought
of interposing between Archimedes the ancient, and Stevinus and
Galileo the moderns.
90 Mahometanism Unveiled, ii.
271.
4. Roger Bacon.—There is one writer of the middle
ages, on whom much stress has been laid, and who was certainly a most
remarkable person. Roger Bacon’s works are not only so far beyond his
age in the knowledge which they contain, but so different from the
temper of the times, in his assertion of the supremacy of experiment,
and in his contemplation of the future progress of knowledge, that it
is difficult to conceive how such a character could then exist. That
he received much of his knowledge from Arabic writers, there can be no
doubt; for they were in his time the repositories of all traditionary
knowledge. But that he derived from them his disposition to shake off
the authority of Aristotle, to maintain the importance of experiment,
and to look upon knowledge as in its infancy, I cannot believe,
because I have not myself hit upon, nor seen quoted by others, any
passages in which Arabian writers express such a disposition. On the
other hand, we do find in European writers, in the authors of Greece
and Rome, the solid sense, the bold and hopeful spirit, which suggest
such tendencies. We have already seen that Aristotle asserts, as
distinctly as words can express, that all knowledge must depend on
observation, and that science must be collected from facts by
induction. We have seen, too, that the Roman writers, and Seneca in
particular, speak with an enthusiastic confidence of the progress
which science must make in the course of ages. When Roger Bacon holds
similar language in the thirteenth century, the resemblance is
probably rather a sympathy of character, than a matter of direct
derivation; but I know of nothing 246 which proves even so much as this
sympathy in the case of Arabian philosophers.
A good deal has been said of late of the coincidences between his
views, and those of his great namesake in later times, Francis
Bacon.91 The resemblances consist mainly in such
points as I have just noticed; and we cannot but acknowledge, that
many of the expressions of the Franciscan Friar remind us of the large
thoughts and lofty phrases of the Philosophical Chancellor. How far
the one can be considered as having anticipated the method of the
other, we shall examine more advantageously, when we come to consider
what the character and effect of Francis Bacon’s works really are.92
91 Hallam’s Middle Ages, iii.
549. Forster’s Mahom. U. ii. 313.
92 In the Philosophy of the
Inductive Sciences, I have given an account at considerable length
of Roger Bacon’s mode of treating Arts and Sciences; and have also
compared more fully his philosophy with that of Francis Bacon; and I
have given a view of the bearing of this latter upon the progress of
Science in modern times. See Phil. Ind. Sc. book xii. chaps. 7
and 11. See also the Appendix to this
volume.
5. Architecture of the Middle Ages.—But though we are
thus compelled to disallow several of the claims which have been put
forwards in support of the scientific character of the middle ages,
there are two points in which we may, I conceive, really trace the
progress of scientific ideas among them; and which, therefore, may be
considered as the prelude to the period of discovery. I mean their
practical architecture, and their architectural treatises.
In a previous chapter of this book, we
have endeavored to explain how the indistinctness of ideas, which
attended the decline of the Roman empire, appears in the forms of
their architecture;—in the disregard, which the decorative
construction exhibits, of the necessary mechanical conditions of
support. The original scheme of Greek ornamental architecture had been
horizontal masses resting on vertical columns: when the arch was
introduced by the Romans, it was concealed, or kept in a state of
subordination: and the lateral support which it required was supplied
latently, marked by some artifice. But the struggle between the
mechanical and the decorative construction93 ended in the complete disorganization
of the classical style. The 247 inconsistencies and extravagances of
which we have noticed the occurrence, were results and indications of
the fall of good architecture. The elements of the ancient system had
lost all principle of connection and regard to rule. Building became
not only a mere art, but an art exercised by masters without skill,
and without feeling for real beauty.
93 See Mr. Willis’s admirable
Remarks on the Architecture of the Middle Ages, chap. ii.
 Since the publication of my first edition, Mr. Willis has shown
that much of the “mason-craft” of the middle ages consisted in the
geometrical methods by which the artists wrought out of the blocks the
complex forms of their decorative system.
 To the general indistinctness of speculative notions on
mechanical subjects prevalent in the middle ages, there may have been
some exceptions, and especially so long as there were readers of
Archimedes. Boëthius had translated the mechanical works of Archimedes
into Latin, as we learn from the enumeration of his works by his
friend Cassiodorus (Variar. lib i. cap. 45), “Mechanicum
etiam Archimedem latialem siculis reddidisti.” But Mechanicus
was used in those times rather for one skilled in the art of
constructing wonderful machines than in the speculative theory of
them. The letter from which the quotation is taken is sent by King
Theodoric to Boëthius, to urge him to send the king a
water-clock.
When, after this deep decline, architecture rose again, as it did
in the twelfth and succeeding centuries, in the exquisitely beautiful
and skilful forms of the Gothic style, what was the nature of the
change which had taken place, so far as it bears upon the progress of
science? It was this:—the idea of true mechanical relations in
an edifice had been revived in men’s minds, as far as was requisite
for the purposes of art and beauty: and this, though a very different
thing from the possession of the idea as an element of speculative
science, was the proper preparation for that acquisition. The notion
of support and stability again became conspicuous in the decorative
construction, and universal in the forms of building. The eye which,
looking for beauty in definite and significant relations of parts, is
never satisfied except the weights appear to be duly supported,94 was again gratified. Architecture threw
off its barbarous characters: a new decorative construction was
matured, not thwarting and controlling, but assisting and harmonizing
with the mechanical construction. All the ornamental parts were made
to enter into the apparent construction. Every member, almost every
moulding, became a sustainer of weight; and by the multiplicity of
props assisting each other, and the consequent subdivision of weight,
the eye was satisfied of the stability of the structure,
notwithstanding the curiously-slender forms of the separate parts. The
arch and the vault, no longer trammelled by an incompatible system of
decoration, but favoured by more tractable forms, were only limited by
the skill of the builders. Everything showed that, practically at
least, men possessed and applied, with steadiness and pleasure, the
idea of mechanical pressure and support.
94 Willis, pp. 15–21. I have
throughout this description of the formation of the Gothic style
availed myself of Mr. Willis’s well-chosen expressions.
The possession of this idea, as a principle of art, led, in the
course of time, to its speculative development as the foundation of a
science; 248 and
thus Architecture prepared the way for Mechanics. But this advance
required several centuries. The interval between the admirable
cathedrals of Salisbury, Amiens, Cologne, and the mechanical treatises
of Stevinus, is not less than three hundred years. During this time,
men were advancing towards science; but in the mean time, and perhaps
from the very beginning of the time, art had begun to decline. The
buildings of the fifteenth century, erected when the principles of
mechanical support were just on the verge of being enunciated in
general terms, exhibit those principles with a far less impressive
simplicity and elegance than those of the thirteenth. We may hereafter
inquire whether we find any other examples to countenance the belief,
that the formation of Science is commonly accompanied by the decline
of Art.
The leading principle of the style of the Gothic edifices was, not
merely that the weights were supported, but that they were seen to be
so; and that not only the mechanical relations of the larger masses,
but of the smaller members also, were displayed. Hence we cannot
admit, as an origin or anticipation of the Gothic, a style in which
this principle is not manifested. I do not see, in any of the
representations of the early Arabic buildings, that distribution of
weights to supports, and that mechanical consistency of parts, which
would elevate them above the character of barbarous architecture.
Their masses are broken into innumerable members, without
subordination or meaning, in a manner suggested apparently by caprice
and the love of the marvellous. “In the construction of their mosques,
it was a favorite artifice of the Arabs to sustain immense and
ponderous masses of stone by the support of pillars so slender, that
the incumbent weight seemed, as it were, suspended in the air by an
invisible hand.”95 This pleasure in the contemplation of
apparent impossibilities is a very general disposition among mankind;
but it appears to belong to the infancy, rather than the maturity of
intellect. On the other hand, the pleasure in the contemplation of
what is clear, the craving for a thorough insight into the reasons of
things, which marks the European mind, is the temper which leads to
science.
95 Mahometanism Unveiled, ii.
255.
6. Treatises on Architecture.—No one who has attended
to the architecture which prevailed in England, France, and Germany,
from the twelfth to the fifteenth century, so far as to comprehend its
beauty, harmony, consistency, and uniformity, even in the minutest
parts and most obscure relations, can look upon it otherwise than as a
249 remarkably
connected and definite artificial system. Nor can we doubt that it was
exercised by a class of artists who formed themselves by laborious
study and practice, and by communication with each other. There must
have been bodies of masters and of scholars, discipline, traditions,
precepts of art. How these associated artists diffused themselves over
Europe, and whether history enables us to trace them in a distinct
form, I shall not here discuss. But the existence of a course of
instruction, and of a body of rules of practice, is proved beyond
dispute by the great series of European cathedrals and churches, so
nearly identical in their general arrangements, and in their
particular details. The question then occurs, have these rules and
this system of instruction anywhere been committed to writing? Can we,
by such evidence, trace the progress of the scientific idea, of which
we see the working in these buildings?
We are not to be surprised, if, during the most flourishing and
vigorous period of the art of the middle ages, we find none of its
precepts in books. Art has, in all ages and countries, been taught and
transmitted by practice and verbal tradition, not by writing. It is
only in our own times, that the thought occurs as familiar, of
committing to books all that we wish to preserve and convey. And, even
in our own times, most of the Arts are learned far more by practice,
and by intercourse with practitioners, than by reading. Such is the
case, not only with Manufactures and Handicrafts, but with the Fine
Arts, with Engineering, and even yet, with that art, Building, of
which we are now speaking.
We are not, therefore, to wonder, if we have no treatises on
Architecture belonging to the great period of the Gothic
masters;—or if it appears to have required some other incitement
and some other help, besides their own possession of their practical
skill, to lead them to shape into a literary form the precepts of the
art which they knew so well how to exercise:—or if, when they
did write on such subjects, they seem, instead of delivering their own
sound practical principles, to satisfy themselves with pursuing some
of the frivolous notions and speculations which were then current in
the world of letters.
Such appears to be the case. The earliest treatises on Architecture
come before us under the form which the commentatorial spirit of the
middle ages inspired. They are Translations of Vitruvius, with
Annotations. In some of these, particularly that of Cesare Cesariano,
published at Como, in 1521, we see, in a very curious manner, how the
habit of assuming that, in every department of literature, the
ancients 250 must
needs be their masters, led these writers to subordinate the members
of their own architecture to the precepts of the Roman author. We have
Gothic shafts, mouldings, and arrangements, given as parallelisms to
others, which profess to represent the Roman style, but which are, in
fact, examples of that mixed manner which is called the style of the
Cinque cento by the Italians, of the Renaissance by the
French, and which is commonly included in our Elizabethan. But
in the early architectural works, besides the superstitions and
mistaken erudition which thus choked the growth of real architectural
doctrines, another of the peculiar elements of the middle ages comes
into view;—its mysticism. The dimensions and positions of the
various parts of edifices and of their members, are determined by
drawing triangles, squares, circles, and other figures, in such a
manner as to bound them; and to these geometrical figures were
assigned many abstruse significations. The plan and the front of the
Cathedral at Milan are thus represented in Cesariano’s work, bounded
and subdivided by various equilateral triangles; and it is easy to
see, in the earnestness with which he points out these relations, the
evidence of a fanciful and mystical turn of thought.96
96 The plan which he has given, fol.
14, he has entitled “Ichnographia Fundamenti sacræ Ædis baricephalæ,
Germanico more, à Trigono ac Pariquadrato perstructa, uti etiam ea quæ
nunc Milani videtur.”
 The work of Cesariano was translated into German by Gualter
Rivius, and published at Nuremberg, in 1548, under the title of
Vitruvius Teutsch, with copies of the Italian diagrams. A few
years ago, in an article in the Wiener Jahrbücher
(Oct.–Dec., 1821), the reviewer maintained, on the authority of
the diagrams in Rivius’s book, that Gothic architecture had its origin
in Germany and not in England.
We thus find erudition and mysticism take the place of much of that
development of the architectural principles of the middle ages which
would be so interesting to us. Still, however, these works are by no
means without their value. Indeed many of the arts appear to flourish
not at all the worse, for being treated in a manner somewhat mystical;
and it may easily be, that the relations of geometrical figures, for
which fantastical reasons are given, may really involve principles of
beauty or stability. But independently of this, we find, in the best
works of the architects of all ages (including engineers), evidence
that the true idea of mechanical pressure exists among them more
distinctly than among men in general, although it may not be developed
in a scientific form. This is true up to our own time, and the arts
which such persons cultivate could not be successfully 251 exercised if it were
not so. Hence the writings of architects and engineers during the
middle ages do really form a prelude to the works on scientific
mechanics. Vitruvius, in his Architecture, and Julius
Frontinus, who, under Vespasian, wrote On Aqueducts, of which
he was superintendent, have transmitted to us the principal part of
what we know respecting the practical mechanics and hydraulics of the
Romans. In modern times the series is resumed. The early writers on
architecture are also writers on engineering, and often on
hydrostatics: for example, Leonardo da Vinci wrote on the equilibrium
of water. And thus we are led up to Stevinus of Bruges, who was
engineer to Prince Maurice of Nassau, and inspector of the dykes in
Holland; and in whose work, on the processes of his art, is contained
the first clear modern statement of the scientific principles of
hydrostatics.
Having thus explained both the obstacles and the prospects which
the middle ages offered to the progress of science, I now proceed to
the history of the progress, when that progress was once again
resumed.  ~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~


BOOK V.

HISTORY
OF
FORMAL ASTRONOMY
AFTER THE STATIONARY PERIOD.


.  .  .  Cyclopum educta
caminis
Mœnia conspicio, atque adverso fornice
portas.
   .   .  
.   .   .
His demum exactis, perfecto munere Divæ,
Devenere locos lætos et amœna vireta
Fortunatorum nemorum sedesque beatas.
Largior hic campos æther et lumine vestit
Purpureo: solemque suum, sua sidera norunt.
Virgil, Æn. vi.
630.  

They leave at length the nether gloom, and
stand
Before the portals of a better land:
To happier plains they come, and fairer
groves,
The seats of those whom heaven, benignant,
loves;
A brighter day, a bluer ether, spreads
Its lucid depths above their favored heads;
And, purged from mists that veil our earthly
skies,
Shine suns and stars unseen by mortal eyes.

</div></body></text></TEI>