<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="23">
CHAPTER VII.
Special Methods of Induction applicable to Quantity.
Aphorism XLIII.
There are special Methods of Induction applicable to
Quantity; of which the principal are, the Method of Curves,
the Method of Means, the Method of Least Squares, and
the Method of Residues.
Aphorism XLIV.
The Method of Curves consists in drawing a curve of
which the observed quantities are the Ordinates, the quantity
on which the change of these quantities depends being the
Abscissa. The efficacy of this Method depends upon the
faculty which the eye possesses, of readily detecting regularity
and irregularity in forms. The Method may be used
to detect the Laws which the observed quantities follow: and
also, when the Observations are inexact, it may be used to correct
these Observations, so as to obtain data more true than the
observed facts themselves.
Aphorism XLV.
The Method of Means gets rid of irregularities by taking
the arithmetical mean of a great number of observed quantities.
Its efficacy depends upon this; that in cases in which
observed quantities are affected by other inequalities, besides
that of which we wish to determine the law, the excesses above
and defects below the quantities which the law in question
would produce, will, in a collection of many observations,
balance each other. 203
Aphorism XLVI.
The Method of Least Squares is a Method of Means, in
which the mean is taken according to the condition, that the
sum of the squares of the errours of observation shall be the
least possible which the law of the facts allows. It appears,
by the Doctrine of Chances, that this is the most probable
mean.
Aphorism XLVII.
The Method of Residues consists in subtracting, from
the quantities given by Observation, the quantity given by any
Law already discovered; and then examining the remainder,
or Residue, in order to discover the leading Law which it
follows. When this second Law has been discovered, the
quantity given by it may be subtracted from the first Residue;
thus giving a Second Residue, which may be examined in
the same manner; and so on. The efficacy of this method
depends principally upon the circumstance of the Laws of
variation being successively smaller and smaller in amount
(or at least in their mean effect); so that the ulterior undiscovered
Laws do not prevent the Law in question from being
prominent in the observations.
Aphorism XLVIII.
The Method of Means and the Method of Least Squares
cannot be applied without our knowing the Arguments of
the Inequalities which we seek. The Method of Curves and
the Method of Residues, when the Arguments of the principal
Inequalities are known, often make it easy to find the others.
IN cases where the phenomena admit of numerical
measurement and expression, certain mathematical methods
may be employed to facilitate and give
accuracy to the determination of the formula by which
the observations are connected into laws. Among the
most usual and important of these Methods are the
following:— 204
    I. The Method of Curves.
     II. The Method of Means.
    III. The Method of Least Squares.
    IV. The Method of Residues.
Sect. I.—The Method of Curves.
1. The Method of Curves proceeds upon this basis;
that when one quantity undergoes a series of changes
depending on the progress of another quantity, (as, for
instance, the Deviation of the Moon from her equable
place depends upon the progress of Time,) this dependence
may be expressed by means of a curve. In the
language of mathematicians, the variable quantity,
whose changes we would consider, is made the ordinate
of the curve, and the quantity on which the
changes depend is made the abscissa. In this manner,
the curve will exhibit in its form a series of undulations,
rising and falling so as to correspond with the
alternate Increase and Diminution of the quantity represented,
at intervals of Space which correspond to
the intervals of Time, or other quantity by which the
changes are regulated. Thus, to take another example,
if we set up, at equal intervals, a series of ordinates
representing the Height of all the successive High Waters
brought by the tides at a given place, for a year, the
curve which connects the summits of all these ordinates
will exhibit a series of undulations, ascending
and descending once in about each Fortnight; since, in
that interval, we have, in succession, the high spring
tides and the low neap tides. The curve thus drawn
offers to the eye a picture of the order and magnitude
of the changes to which the quantity under contemplation,
(the height of high water,) is subject.
2. Now the peculiar facility and efficacy of the
Method of Curves depends upon this circumstance;—that
order and regularity are more readily and clearly
recognized, when thus exhibited to the eye in a picture,
than they are when presented to the mind in any other
manner. To detect the relations of Number considered
directly as Number, is not easy: and we might 205
contemplate for a long time a Table of recorded Numbers
without perceiving the order of their increase and
diminution, even if the law were moderately simple;
as any one may satisfy himself by looking at a Tide
Table. But if these Numbers are expressed by the
magnitude of Lines, and if these Lines are arranged in
regular order, the eye readily discovers the rule of
their changes: it follows the curve which runs along
their extremities, and takes note of the order in which
its convexities and concavities succeed each other, if
any order be readily discoverable. The separate observations
are in this manner compared and generalized
and reduced to rule by the eye alone. And the eye,
so employed, detects relations of order and succession
with a peculiar celerity and evidence. If, for example,
we thus arrive as ordinates the prices of corn in each
year for a series of years, we shall see the order,
rapidity, and amount of the increase and decrease of price,
far more clearly than in any other manner. And if
there were any recurrence of increase and decrease at
stated intervals of years, we should in this manner
perceive it. The eye, constantly active and busy, and
employed in making into shapes the hints and traces
of form which it contemplates, runs along the curve
thus offered to it; and as it travels backwards and
forwards, is ever on the watch to detect some resemblance
or contrast between one part and another. And
these resemblances and contrasts, when discovered, are
the images of Laws of Phenomena; which are made
manifest at once by this artifice, although the mind
could not easily catch the indications of their existence,
if they were not thus reflected to her in the clear
mirror of Space.
Thus when we have a series of good Observations,
and know the argument upon which their change of
magnitude depends, the Method of Curves enables us to
ascertain, almost at a glance, the law of the change; and
by further attention, may be made to give us a formula
with great accuracy. The Method enables us to perceive,
among our observations, an order, which without the
method, is concealed in obscurity and perplexity. 206
3. But the Method of Curves not only enables us
to obtain laws of nature from good Observations, but
also, in a great degree, from observations which are
very imperfect. For the imperfection of observations
may in part be corrected by this consideration;—that
though they may appear irregular, the correct facts
which they imperfectly represent, are really regular.
And the Method of Curves enables us to remedy this
apparent irregularity, at least in part. For when
Observations thus imperfect are laid down as Ordinates,
and their extremities connected by a line, we obtain,
not a smooth and flowing curve, such as we should
have if the observations contained only the rigorous
results of regular laws; but a broken and irregular
line, full of sudden and capricious twistings, and
bearing on its face marks of irregularities dependent, not
upon law, but upon chance. Yet these irregular and
abrupt deviations in the curve are, in most cases, but
small in extent, when compared with those bendings
which denote the effects of regular law. And this
circumstance is one of the great grounds of advantage
in the Method of Curves. For when the observations
thus laid down present to the eye such a broken and
irregular line, we can still see, often with great ease
and certainty, what twistings of the line are probably
due to the irregular errours of observation; and can
at once reject these, by drawing a more regular curve,
cutting off all such small and irregular sinuosities,
leaving some to the right and some to the left; and
then proceeding as if this regular curve, and not the
irregular one, expressed the observations. In this
manner, we suppose the errours of observation to
balance each other; some of our corrected measures
being too great and others too small, but with no great
preponderance either way. We draw our main regular
curve, not through the points given by our observations,
but among them: drawing it, as has been said
by one of the philosophers30
who first systematically
used this method, ‘with a bold but careful hand.’ 207
The regular curve which we thus obtain, thus freed
from the casual errours of observation, is that in which
we endeavour to discover the laws of change and succession.
30
 Sir J. Herschel, Ast. Soc. Trans. vol. v. p. 1.
4. By this method, thus getting rid at once, in a
great measure, of errours of observation, we obtain
data which are more true than the individual facts
themselves. The philosopher’s business is to compare
his hypotheses with facts, as we have often said. But
if we make the comparison with separate special facts,
we are liable to be perplexed or misled, to an unknown
amount, by the errours of observation; which may
cause the hypothetical and the observed result to agree,
or to disagree, when otherwise they would not do so.
If, however, we thus take the whole mass of the facts,
and remove the errours of actual
observation31, by
making the curve which expresses the supposed observation
regular and smooth, we have the separate facts
corrected by their general tendency. We are put in
possession, as we have said, of something more true
than any fact by itself is.
31 Ib. vol. v. p. 4.
One of the most admirable examples of the use of
this Method of Curves is found in Sir John Herschel’s
Investigation of the Orbits of Double
Stars32. The author
there shows how far inferior the direct observations of
the angle of position are, to the observations corrected
by a curve in the manner above stated. ‘This curve
once drawn,’ he says, ‘must represent, it is evident,
the law of variation of the angle of position, with the
time, not only for instants intermediate between the
dates of observations, but even at the moments of
observation themselves, much better than the individual
raw observations can possibly (on an average) do.
It is only requisite to try a case or two, to be satisfied
that by substituting the curve for the points, we have
made a nearer approach to nature, and in a great
measure eliminated errours of observation.’ ‘In
following the graphical process,’ he adds, ‘we have a
conviction almost approaching to moral certainty that 208
we cannot be greatly misled.’ Again, having thus
corrected the raw observations, he makes another use
of the graphical method, by trying whether an ellipse
can be drawn ‘if not through, at least among the
points, so as to approach tolerably near them all; and
thus approaching to the orbit which is the subject of
investigation.’
32 Ib.
5. The Obstacles which principally impede the
application of the Method of Curves are (I.) our ignorance
of the arguments of the changes, and (II.) the complication
of several laws with one another.
(I.) If we do not know on what quantity those
changes depend which we are studying, we may fail
entirely in detecting the law of the changes, although
we throw the observations into curves. For the true
argument of the change should, in fact, be made the
abscissa of the curve. If we were to express, by a
series of ordinates, the hour of high water on
successive days, we should not obtain, or should obtain very
imperfectly, the law which these times follow; for the
real argument of this change is not the solar hour, but
the hour at which the moon passes the meridian. But
if we are supposed to be aware that this is the argument,
(which theory suggests and trial instantly confirms) we then do
immediately obtain the primary
Rules of the Time of High Water, by throwing a series
of observations into a Curve, with the Hour of the
Moon’s Transit for the abscissa.
In like manner, when we have obtained the first
great or Semi-mensual Inequality of the tides, if we
endeavour to discover the laws of other Inequalities by
means of curves, we must take from theory the suggestion
that the Arguments of such inequalities will
probably be the parallax and the declination of the
moon. This suggestion again is confirmed by trial;
but if we were supposed to be entirely ignorant of the
dependence of the changes of the tide on the Distance
and Declination of the moon, the curves would exhibit
unintelligible and seemingly capricious changes. For
by the effect of the Inequality arising from the Parallax,
the convexities of the curves which belong to the 209
spring tides, are in some years made alternately greater
and less all the year through; while in other years
they are made all nearly equal. This difference does
not betray its origin, till we refer it to the Parallax;
and the same difficulty in proceeding would arise if we
were ignorant that the moon’s Declination is one of the
Arguments of tidal changes.
In like manner, if we try to reduce to law any meteorological
changes, those of the Height of the Barometer for instance,
we find that we can make little
progress in the investigation, precisely because we do
not know the Argument on which these changes depend.
That there is a certain regular diurnal change
of small amount, we know; but when we have abstracted
this Inequality, (of which the Argument is the time of
day,) we find far greater Changes left behind, from day
to day and from hour to hour; and we express these
in curves, but we cannot reduce them to Rule, because
we cannot discover on what numerical quantity they
depend. The assiduous study of barometrical observations,
thrown into curves, may perhaps hereafter point
out to us what are the relations of time and space by
which these variations are determined; but in the
mean time, this subject exemplifies to us our remark,
that the method of curves is of comparatively small
use, so long as we are in ignorance of the real
Arguments of the Inequalities.
6. (II.) In the next place, I remark that a difficulty
is thrown in the way of the Method of Curves by
the Combination of several laws one with another. It
will readily be seen that such a cause will produce a
complexity in the curves which exhibit the succession
of facts. If, for example, we take the case of the Tides,
the Height of high water increases and diminishes with
the Approach of the sun to, and its Recess from, the
syzygies of the moon. Again, this Height increases
and diminishes as the moon’s Parallax increases and
diminishes; and again, the Height diminishes when
the Declination increases, and vice versa; and all these
Arguments of change, the Distance from Syzygy, the
Parallax, the Declination, complete their circuit and 210
return into themselves in different periods. Hence
the curve which represents the Height of high water
has not any periodical interval in which it completes
its changes and commences a new cycle. The sinuosity
which would arise from each Inequality separately
considered, interferes with, disguises, and conceals the
others; and when we first cast our eyes on the curve
of observation, it is very far from offering any obvious
regularity in its form. And it is to be observed that
we have not yet enumerated all the elements of this
complexity: for there are changes of the tide depending
upon the Parallax and Declination of the Sun as
well as of the Moon. Again; besides these changes, of
which the Arguments are obvious, there are others, as
those depending upon the Barometer and the Wind,
which follow no known regular law, and which constantly
affect and disturb the results produced by other
laws.
In the Tides, and in like manner in the motions of
the Moon, we have very eminent examples of the way
in which the discovery of laws may be rendered difficult
by the number of laws which operate to affect the
same quantity. In such cases, the Inequalities are
generally picked out in succession, nearly in the order
of their magnitudes. In this way there were successively
collected, from the study of the Moon’s motions
by a series of astronomers, those Inequalities which we
term the Equation of the Center, the Evection, the
Variation, and the Annual Equation.
These Inequalities were not, in fact, obtained by the application of
the Method of Curves; but the Method of Curves
might have been applied to such a case with great advantage.
The Method has been applied with great
industry and with remarkable success to the investigation
of the laws of the Tides; and by the use of it,
a series of Inequalities both of the Times and of the
Heights of high water has been detected, which explain
all the main features of the observed facts. 211
Sect. II.—The Method of Means.
7. The Method of Curves, as we have endeavoured
to explain above, frees us from the casual and extraneous
irregularities which arise from the imperfection
of observation; and thus lays bare the results of the
laws which really operate, and enables us to proceed in
search of those laws. But the Method of Curves is
not the only one which effects such a purpose. The
errours arising from detached observations may be got
rid of, and the additional accuracy which multiplied
observations give may be obtained, by operations upon
the observed numbers, without expressing them by
spaces. The process of curves assumes that the errours
of observation balance each other;—that the accidental
excesses and defects are nearly equal in amount;—that
the true quantities which would have been observed
if all accidental causes of irregularity were removed,
are obtained, exactly or nearly, by selecting quantities,
upon the whole, equally distant from the extremes of
great and small, which our imperfect observations offer
to us. But when, among a number of unequal quantities,
we take a quantity equally distant from the
greater and the smaller, this quantity is termed the
Mean of the unequal quantities. Hence the correction
of our observations by the method of curves consists in
taking the Mean of the observations.
8. Now without employing curves, we may proceed
arithmetically to take the Mean of all the observed
numbers of each class. Thus, if we wished to know
the Height of the spring tide at a given place, and if
we found that four different spring tides were measured
as being of the height of ten, thirteen, eleven,
and fourteen feet, we should conclude that the true
height of the tide was the Mean of these numbers,—namely,
twelve feet; and we should suppose that the
deviation from this height, in the individual cases,
arose from the accidents of weather, the imperfections
of observation, or the operation of other laws, besides
the alternation of spring and neap tides. 212
This process of finding the Mean of an assemblage of
observed numbers is much practised in discovering,
and still more in confirming and correcting, laws of
phenomena. We shall notice a few of its peculiarities.
9. The Method of Means requires a knowledge of
the Argument of the changes which we would study;
for the numbers must be arranged in certain Classes,
before we find the Mean of each Class; and the principle
on which this arrangement depends is the Argument. This
knowledge of the Argument is more indispensably necessary
in the Method of Means than in
the Method of Curves; for when Curves are drawn, the
eye often spontaneously detects the law of recurrence in
their sinuosities; but when we have collections of
Numbers, we must divide them into classes by a selection
of our own. Thus, in order to discover the law
which the heights of the tide follow, in the progress
from spring to neap, we arrange the observed tides
according to the day of the moon’s age; and we then
take the mean of all those which thus happen at the
same period of the Moon’s Revolution. In this manner
we obtain the law which we seek; and the process is
very nearly the same in all other applications of this
Method of Means. In all cases, we begin by assuming
the Classes of measures which we wish to compare, the
Law which we could confirm or correct, the Formula
of which we would determine the coefficients.
10. The Argument being thus assumed, the Method
of Means is very efficacious in ridding our inquiry of
errours and irregularities which would impede and perplex
it. Irregularities which are altogether accidental,
or at least accidental with reference to some law which
we have under consideration, compensate each other in
a very remarkable way, when we take the Means of
many observations. If we have before us a collection
of observed tides, some of them may be elevated, some
depressed by the wind, some noted too high and some
too low by the observer, some augmented and some
diminished by uncontemplated changes in the moon’s
distance or motion: but in the course of a year or two
at the longest, all these causes of irregularity balance 213
each other; and the law of succession, which runs
through the observations, comes out as precisely as if
those disturbing influences did not exist. In any particular
case, there appears to be no possible reason why
the deviation should be in one way, or of one moderate
amount, rather than another. But taking the mass of
observations together, the deviations in opposite ways
will be of equal amount, with a degree of exactness
very striking. This is found to be the case in all
inquiries where we have to deal with observed numbers
upon a large scale. In the progress of the population
of a country, for instance, what can appear more
inconstant, in detail, than the causes which produce births
and deaths? yet in each country, and even in each
province of a country, the proportions of the whole
numbers of births and deaths remain nearly constant.
What can be more seemingly beyond the reach of rule
than the occasions which produce letters that cannot
find their destination? yet it appears that the number
of ‘dead letters’ is nearly the same from year to year.
And the same is the result when the deviations arise,
not from mere accident, but from laws perfectly regular,
though not contemplated in our
investigation33.
Thus the effects of the Moon’s Parallax upon the Tides,
sometimes operating one way and sometimes another,
according to certain rules, are quite eliminated by
taking the Means of a long series of observations; the
excesses and defects neutralizing each other, so far as
concerns the effect upon any law of the tides which we
would investigate.
33
 Provided the argument of the law which we
neglect have no coincidence with the argument of the law
which we would determine.
11. In order to obtain very great accuracy, very
large masses of observations are often employed by
philosophers, and the accuracy of the result increases
with the multitude of observations. The immense collections
of astronomical observations which have in
this manner been employed in order to form and correct
the Tables of the celestial motions are perhaps
the most signal instances of the attempts to obtain 214
accuracy by this accumulation of observations. Delambre’s
Tables of the Sun are founded upon nearly 3000
observations; Burg’s Tables of the Moon upon above
4000.
But there are other instances hardly less remarkable.
Mr. Lubbock’s first investigations of the laws of
the tides of London34,
included above 13,000 observations,
extending through nineteen years; it being considered
that this large number was necessary to remove
the effects of accidental causes35.
And the attempts
to discover the laws of change in the barometer have
led to the performance of labours of equal amount:
Laplace and Bouvard examined this question by means
of observations made at the Observatory of Paris, four
times every day for eight years.
34 Phil. Trans. 1831.
35
 This period of nineteen years was also selected for
a reason which is alluded to in a former note. It was thought
that this period secured the inquirer from the errours
which might be produced by the partial coincidence of the
Arguments of different irregularities; for example,
those due to the moon’s Parallax and to the moon’s Declination. It has
since been found (Phil. Tr. 1838. On the Determination
of the Laws of the Tides from Short Series of Observations),
that with regard to Parallax at least, the Means of one year give
sufficient accuracy.
12. We may remark one striking evidence of the
accuracy thus obtained by employing large masses of
observations. In this way we may often detect inequalities
much smaller than the errours by which they are
encumbered and concealed. Thus the Diurnal Oscillations
of the Barometer were discovered by the comparison of
observations of many days, classified according to the
hours of the day; and the result was a clear
and incontestable proof of the existence of such oscillations
although the differences which these oscillations
produce at different hours of the day are far smaller
than the casual changes, hitherto reduced to no law,
which go on from hour to hour and from day to day.
The effect of law, operating incessantly and steadily,
makes itself more and more felt as we give it a longer
range; while the effect of accident, followed out in the 215
same manner, is to annihilate itself, and to disappear
altogether from the result.
Sect. III.—The Method of Least Squares.
13. The Method of Least Squares is in fact a
method of means, but with some peculiar characters.
Its object is to determine the best Mean of a number
of observed quantities; or the most probable Law
derived from a number of observations, of which some,
or all, are allowed to be more or less imperfect. And
the method proceeds upon this supposition;—that all
errours are not equally probable, but that small
errours are more probable than large ones. By reasoning
mathematically upon this ground, we find that
the best result is obtained (since we cannot obtain a
result in which the errours vanish) by making, not the
Errours themselves, but the Sum of their Squares, of
the smallest possible amount.
14. An example may illustrate this. Let a quantity which
is known to increase uniformly, (as the distance of a star
from the meridian at successive instants,) be measured at
equal intervals of time, and be
found to be successively 4, 12, 14. It is plain, upon
the face of these observations, that they are erroneous;
for they ought to form an arithmetical progression, but
they deviate widely from such a progression. But the
question then occurs, what arithmetical progression do
they most probably represent: for we may assume
several arithmetical progressions which more or less
approach the observed series; as for instance, these
three; 4, 9, 14; 6, 10, 14; 5, 10, 15. Now in order
to see the claims of each of these to the truth, we may
tabulate them thus.
Observation 4, 12, 14 Errours
 Sums of Errours Sums of Squares  of Errours

Series (1) 4,  9, 14   0, 3, 0  3 9
 〃  (2) 6, 10, 14   2, 2, 0  4 8
 〃  (3) 5, 10, 15   1, 2, 1  4 6
Here, although the first series gives the sum of the 216
errours less than the others, the third series gives the
sum of the squares of the errours least; and is therefore,
by the proposition on which this Method depends,
the most probable series of the three.
This Method, in more extensive and complex cases,
is a great aid to the calculator in his inferences from
facts, and removes much that is arbitrary in the Method
of Means.
Sect. IV.—The Method of Residues.
15. By either of the preceding Methods we obtain,
from observed facts, such Laws as readily offer themselves;
and by the Laws thus discovered, the most prominent
changes of the observed quantities are accounted
for. But in many cases we have, as we have noticed
already, several Laws of nature operating at the same
time, and combining their influences to modify those
quantities which are the subjects of observation. In
these cases we may, by successive applications of the
Methods already pointed out, detect such Laws one
after another: but this successive process, though only
a repetition of what we have already described, offers
some peculiar features which make it convenient to
consider it in a separate Section, as the Method of
Residues.
16. When we have, in a series of changes of
a variable quantity, discovered one Law which the
changes follow, detected its Argument, and determined
its Magnitude, so as to explain most clearly the course
of observed facts, we may still find that the observed
changes are not fully accounted for. When we compare
the results of our Law with the observations,
there may be a difference, or as we may term it, a
Residue, still unexplained. But this Residue being
thus detached from the rest, may be examined and
scrutinized in the same manner as the whole observed
quantity was treated at first: and we may in this way
detect in it also a Law of change. If we can do this,
we must accommodate this new found Law as nearly
as possible to the Residue to which it belongs; and 217
this being done, the difference of our Rule and of the
Residue itself, forms a Second Residue. This Second
Residue we may again bring under our consideration;
and may perhaps in it also discover some Law of change
by which its alterations may be in some measure accounted for.
If this can be done, so as to account for
a large portion of this Residue, the remaining unexplained part
forms a Third Residue; and so on.
17. This course has really been followed in various
inquiries, especially in those of Astronomy and Tidology.
The Equation of the Center, for the Moon, was
obtained out of the Residue of the Longitude, which
remained when the Mean Anomaly was taken away.
This Equation being applied and disposed of, the Second
Residue thus obtained, gave to Ptolemy the Evection.
The Third Residue, left by the Equation of the Center
and the Evection, supplied to Tycho the Variation
and the Annual Equation. And the Residue, remaining
from these, has been exhausted by other Equations,
of various arguments, suggested by theory or by observation.
In this case, the successive generations of
astronomers have gone on, each in its turn executing
some step in this Method of Residues. In the examination
of the Tides, on the other hand, this method
has been applied systematically and at once. The
observations readily gave the Semimensual Inequality;
the Residue of this supplied the corrections due to the
Moon’s Parallax and Declination; and when these
were determined, the remaining Residue was explored
for the law of the Solar Correction.
18. In a certain degree, the Method of Residues and
the Method of Means are opposite to each other. For
the Method of Residues extricates Laws from their
combination, bringing them into view in succession;
while the Method of Means discovers each Law, not by
bringing the others into view, but by destroying their
effect through an accumulation of observations. By
the Method of Residues we should first extract the
Law of the Parallax Correction of the Tides, and then,
from the Residue left by this, obtain the Declination
Correction. But we might at once employ the Method 218
of Means, and put together all the cases in which the
Declination was the same; not allowing for the Parallax
in each case, but taking for granted that the
Parallaxes belonging to the same Declination would
neutralize each other; as many falling above as below
the mean Parallax. In cases like this, where the
Method of Means is not impeded by a partial coincidence
of the Arguments of different unknown Inequalities,
it may be employed with almost as much success
as the Method of Residues. But still, when the Arguments
of the Laws are clearly known, as in this instance,
the Method of Residues is more clear and
direct, and is the rather to be recommended.
19. If for example, we wish to learn whether the
Height of the Barometer exerts any sensible influence
on the Height of the Sea’s Surface, it would appear
that the most satisfactory mode of proceeding, must be
to subtract, in the first place, what we know to be the
effects of the Moon’s Age, Parallax and Declination,
and other ascertained causes of change; and to search
in the unexplained Residue for the effects of
barometrical pressure. The contrary course has, however,
been adopted, and the effect of the Barometer on the
ocean has been investigated by the direct application
of the Method of Means, classing the observed heights
of the water according to the corresponding heights of
the Barometer without any previous reduction. In
this manner, the suspicion that the tide of the sea is
affected by the pressure of the atmosphere, has been
confirmed. This investigation must be looked upon
as a remarkable instance of the efficacy of the Method
of Means, since the amount of the barometrical effect
is much smaller than the other changes from among
which it was by this process extricated. But an
application of the Method of Residues would still
be desirable on a subject of such extent and difficulty.
20. Sir John Herschel, in his Discourse on the
Study of Natural Philosophy (Articles 158–161), has
pointed out the mode of making discoveries by studying
Residual Phenomena; and has given several illustrations
of the process. In some of these, he has also 219
considered this method in a wider sense than we have
done; treating it as not applicable to quantity only,
but to properties and relations of different kinds.
We likewise shall proceed to offer a few remarks on
Methods of Induction applicable to other relations than
those of quantity.
</div></body></text></TEI>