<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="88">CHAPTER IV.
Discovery of Electro-magnetic
Action.—Oersted.
THE impulse which the
discovery of galvanism, in 1791, and that of the voltaic pile, in
1800, had given to the study of electricity as a mechanical science,
had nearly died away in 1820. It was in that year that M. Oersted, of
Copenhagen, announced that the conducting 244 wire of a voltaic circuit, acts upon a
magnetic needle; and thus recalled into activity that endeavor to
connect magnetism with electricity, which, though apparently on many
accounts so hopeful, had hitherto been attended with no success.
Oersted found that the needle has a tendency to place itself at
right angles to the wire;—a kind of action altogether
different from any which had been suspected.
This observation was of vast importance; and the analysis of its
conditions and consequences employed the best philosophers in Europe
immediately on its promulgation. It is impossible, without great
injustice, to refuse great merit to Oersted as the author of the
discovery. We have already said that men appear generally inclined to
believe remarkable discoveries to be accidental, and the discovery of
Oersted has been spoken of as a casual insulated experiment.12 Yet Oersted had been looking for such
an accident probably more carefully and perseveringly than
any other person in Europe. In 1807, he had published13 a work, in which he professed that his
purpose was “to ascertain whether electricity, in its most latent
state, had any effect on the magnet.” And he, as I know from his own
declaration, considered his discovery as the natural sequel and
confirmation of his early researches; as, indeed, it fell in readily
and immediately with speculations on these subjects then very
prevalent in Germany. It was an accident like that by which a man
guesses a riddle on which his mind has long been employed.
12 See Schelling ueber Faraday’s
Entdeckung, p. 27.
13 Ampère, p. 69.
Besides the confirmation of Oersted’s observations by many
experimenters, great additions were made to his facts: of these, one
of the most important was due to Ampère. Since the earth is in fact
magnetic, the voltaic wire ought to be affected by terrestrial
magnetism alone, and ought to tend to assume a position depending on
the position of the compass-needle. At first, the attempts to produce
this effect failed, but soon, with a more delicate apparatus, the
result was found to agree with the anticipation.
It is impossible here to dwell on any of the subsequent researches,
except so far as they are essential to our great object, the progress
towards a general theory of the subject. I proceed, therefore,
immediately to the attempts made towards this object. 245</div></body></text></TEI>