<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Cosmos: A Sketch of the Physical Description of the Universe, Vol. 1</title><author>Humboldt, Alexander von (1769-1859)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1845</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="2">
Introduction. — Reflections on the different Degrees of Enjoyment presented
to us by the Aspect of Nature and the scientific Exposition of the Laws of
the Universe . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .  . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
. .  .Page 23-78
Insight into the connection of phenomena as the aim of all natural
investigation.  Nature presents itself to meditative contemplation as a
unity in diversity.  Differences in the grades of enjoyment yielded by
nature.  Effect of contact with free nature; enjoyment derived from nature
independently of a knowledge of the action of natural forces, or of the
physiognomy and configuration of the surface, or of the character of
vegetation.  Reminiscences of the woody valleys of the Cordilleras and of
the Peak of Teneriffe.  Advantages of the mountainous region near the
equator, where the multiplicity of natural impressions attains its maximum
within the most circumscribed limits, and where it is permitted to man
simultaneously to behold all the stars of the firmament and all the forms of
vegetation — p. 23-33.
Tendency toward the investigation of the causes of physical phenomena.
Erroneous views of the character of natural forces arising from an imperfect
mode of observation or of induction.  The crude accumulation of physical
dogmas transmitted from one country to another.  Their diffusion among the
higher classes.
Scientific physics are associated with another and a deep-rooted system of
untried and misunderstood experimental positions.  Investigation of natural
laws.  Apprehension that nature may lose a portion of its secret charm by an
inquiry into the internal character of its forces, and that the enjoyment of
nature must necessarily be weakened by a study of its domain.  Advantages of
general views which impart an exalted and solemn character to natural
science.  The possibility of separating generalities from specialties.
Examples drawn from astronomy, recent optical discoveries, physical
geognosy, and the geography of plants.  Practicability of the study of
physical cosmography — p. 33-54.  Misunderstood popular knowledge,
confounding cosmography with a mere encyclopedic enumeration of natural
sciences.  Necessity for a simultaneous regard for all branches of natural
science.  Influence of this study on national prosperity and the welfare of
nations; its more earnest and characteristic aim is an inner one, arising
from exalted mental activity.  Mode of treatment with regard to the object
and presentation; reciprocal connection existing between thought and speech
— p. 54-56.
The notes to p. 28-33.  Comparative hypsometrical data of the elevations of
the Dhawalagiri, Jawahir, Chimborazo, Aetna (according to the measurement of
Sir John Herschel), the Swiss Alps, etc. — p. 28.  Rarity
p 16
of palms and ferns in the Himalaya Mountains — p. 29.  European vegetable
forms in the Indian Mountains — p. 30.  Northern and southern limits of
perpetual snow on the Himalaya; influence of the elevated plateau of Thibet
— p. 30-33.  Fishes of an earlier world — p. 46.
Limits and Method of Exposition of the Physical Description of the Universe
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .. . . . .
Page 56-78
Subjects embraced by the study of the Cosmos or of physical cosmography.
Separation of other kindred studies — p. 56-62.  The uranological portion
of the Cosmos is more simple than the telluric; the impossibility of
ascertaining the diversity of matter simplifies the study of the mechanism
of the heavens.  Origin of the word 'Cosmos', its signification of adornment
and order of the universe.  The 'existing' can not be absolutely separated
in our contemplation of nature from the 'future'.  History of the world and
description of the world — p. 26-73.
Attempts to embrace the multiplicity of the phenomena of the Cosmos in the
unity of thought and under the form of a purely rational combination.
Natural philosophy, which preceded all exact observation in antiquity, is a
natural, but not unfrequently ill-directed, effort of reason.  Two forms of
abstraction rule in the whole mass of knowledge, viz.:  the 'quantitative',
relative determinations according to number and magnitude, and
'qualitative', material characters.  Means of submitting phenomena to
calculation.  Atoms, mechanical methods of construction.  Figurative
representations; mythical conception of imponderable matters, and the
peculiar vital forces in every organism.  That which is attained by
observation and experiment (calling forth phenomena) leads, by analogy and
induction, to a knowledge of 'empirical laws'; their gradual simplification
and generalization.  Arrangement of the facts discovered in accordance with
leading ideas.  The treasure of empirical contemplation, collected through
ages, is in no danger of experiencing any hostile agency from philosophy —
p. 73-78.
[In the notes appended to p. 66-70 are considerations of the general and
comparative geography of Varenius.  Philological investigation into the
meaning of the words [Greek word] and 'mundus'.]
Delineation of Nature.  General Review of Natural Phenomena. . . . . p.
79-359
Introduction — p. 79-83.  A descriptive delineation of the world embraces
the whole universe ([Greek words]) in the celestial and terrestrial spheres.
 Form and course of the representation.  It begins with the laws of
gravitation, and with the region of the remotest nebulous spots and double
stars, and then, gradually descending through the starry stratum to which
our solar system belongs, it contemplates this terrestrial spheroid,
surrounded by air and water, and finally, proceeds to the consideration of
the form of our planet, its temperature and magnetic tension, and the
fullness of organic vitality which is unfolded on its surface under the
action of light.  Partial insight into the relative dependence existing
among all phenomena.  Amid all the mobile and unstable elements in space,
'mean numerical values' are the ultimate aim of investigation, being the
expression of the physical laws, or forces of the Cosmos.  The delineation
of the universe does not begin with the earth, from which a merely
subjective point of view might have led us to start, but rather with the
objects comprised in the regions of space.  Distribution of matter, which is
partially conglomerated into rotating
p 17
and circling heavenly bodies of very different density and magnitude, and
partly scattered as self-luminous vapor.  Review of the separate portions of
the picture of nature, for the purpose of explaining the reciprocal
connection of all phenomena.
I.  Celestial Portion of the Cosmos . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .Page
83-154
II.  Terrestrial Portion of the Cosmos . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .p.
154-359
a.  Form of the earth, its mean density, quantity of heat, electro-magnetic
activity, process of light — p. 154-202.
b.  Vital activity of the earth toward its external surface.  Reaction of
the interior of a planet on its crust and surface.  Subterranean noise
without waves of concussion.  Earthquakes dynamic phenomena — p. 202-217.
c.  Material products which frequently accompany earthquakes.  Gaseous and
aqueous springs.  Salses and mud volcanoes.  Upheavals of the soil by
elastic forces — p. 217-228.
d.  Fire-emitting mountains.  Craters of elevation.  Distribution of
volcanoes on the earth — p. 228-247.
e.  Volcanic forces form new kinds of rock, and metamorphose those already
existing.  Geognostical classification of rocks into four groups.  Phenomena
of contact.  Fossiliferous strata; their vertical arrangement.  The faunas
and floras of an earlier world.  Distribution of masses of rock — p.
247-384.
f.  Geognostical epochs, which are indicated by the mineralogical difference
of rocks, have determined the distribution of solids and fluids into
continents and seas.  Individual configuration of solids into horizontal
expansion and vertical elevation.  Relations of area.  Articulation.
Probability of the continued elevation of the earth's crust in ridges — p.
284-301.
g.  Liquid and aeriform envelopes of the solid surface of our planet.
Distribution of heat in both.  The sea.  The tides.  Currents and their
effects — p. 301-311.
h.  The atmosphere.  Its chemical composition.  Fluctuations in its density.
 Law of the direction of the winds.  Mean temperature.  Enumeration of the
causes which tend to raise and lower the temperature.  Continental and
insular climates.  East and west coasts.  Cause of the curvature of the
isothermal lines.  Limits of perpetual snow.  Quantity of vapor.
Electricity in the atmosphere.  Forms of the clouds — p. 311-339.
i.  Separation of inorganic terrestrial life from the geography of vital
organisms; the geography of vegetables and animals.  Physical gradations of
the human race — p. 339-359.
Special Analysis of the Delineation of Nature, including References to the

Subjects treated of in the Notes.
I.  Celestial Portion of the Cosmos . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . p.
83-154
The universe and all that it comprises — multiform nebulous spots,
planetary vapor, and nebulous stars.  The picturesque charm of a southern
sky — note, p. 85.  Conjectures on the position in space of the world.  Our
stellar masses.  A cosmical island.  Gauging stars.  Double stars revolving
round a common center.  Distance of the star 61 Cygni — p. 88 and note.
Our solar system more complicated than was conjectured at the close of the
last century.  Primary planets with Neptune, Astrea, Hebe, Iris, and Flora,
now constitute 16; secondary planets 18; myriad of comets of which many of
the inner ones are inclosed
p 18
in the orbits of the planets; a rotating ring (the zodiacal light) and
meteoric stones, probably to be regarded as small cosmical bodies.  The
telescopic planets, Vesta, Juno, Ceres, Pallas, Astrea, Hebe, Iris and
Flora, with their frequently intersecting, strongly inclined, and more
eccentric orbits, constitute a central group of separation between the inner
planetary group (Mercury, Venus, the Earth, and Mars) and the outer group
(Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, and Neptune).  Contrasts of these planetary
groups.  Relations of distance from one central body.  Differences of
absolute magnitude, density, period of revolution, eccentricity, and
inclination of the orbits.  The so-called law of the distances of the
planets from their central sun.  The planets which have the largest number
of moons — p. 96 and note.  Relations in space, both absolute and relative,
of the secondary planets.  Largest and smallest of the moons.  Greatest
approximation to a primary planet.  Retrogressive movement of the moons of
Uranus.  Libration of the Earth's satellite — p. 98 and note.  Comets; the
nucleus and tail; various forms and directions of the emanations in conoidal
envelopes, with more or less dense walls.  Several tails inclined toward the
sun; change of form of fixed stars by the nuclei of comets.  Eccentricity of
their orbits and periods of revolution.  Greatest distance and greatest
approximation of comets.  Passage through the system of Jupiter's
satellites.  Comets of short periods of revolution, more correctly termed
inner comets (Encke, Biela, Faye) — p. 107 and note.  Revolving aerolites
(meteoric stones, fire-balls, falling stars).  Their planetary velocity,
magnitude, form, observed height.  Periodic return in streams; the November
stream and the stream of St. Lawrence.  Chemical composition of meteoric
asteroids — p. 130 and notes.  Ring of zodiacal light.  Limitation of the
present solar atmosphere — p. 141 and note.  Translatory motion of the
whole solar system — p. 145-149 and note.  The existence of the law of
gravitation beyond our solar system.  The milky way of stars and its
conjectured breaking up.  Milky way of nebulous spots, at right angles with
that of the stars.  Periods of revolutions of bi-colored double stars.
Canopy of stars; openings in the stellar stratum.  Events in the universe;
the apparition of new stars.  Propagation of light, the aspect of the starry
vault of the heavens conveys to the mind an idea of inequality of time — p.
149-154 and notes.
II.  Terrestrial Portion of the Cosmos . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Page
154-359
a.  Figure of the earth.  Density, quantity of heat, electro-magnetic
tension, and terrestrial light — p. 154-202 and note.  Knowledge of the
compression and curvature of the earth's surface acquired by measurements of
degrees, pendulum oscillations, and certain inequalities in the moon's
orbit.  Mean density of the earth.  The earth's crust, and the depth to
which we are able to penetrate — p. 159, 160, note.  Threefold movement of
the heat of the earth; its thermic condition.  Law of the increase of heat
with the increase of depth — p. 160, 161 and note.  Magnetism electricity
in motion.  Periodical variation of terrestrial magnetism.  Disturbance of
the regular course of the magnetic needle.  Magnetic storms; extension of
their action.  Manifestations of magnetic force on the earth's surface
presented under three classes of phenomena, namely, lines of equal force
(isodynamic), equal inclination (isoclinic), and equal deviation (isogonic).
 Position of the magnetic pole.  Its probable connection with the poles of
cold.  Change of all the magnetic phenomena of the earth.  Erection of
magnetic observatories
p 19
since 1828; a far-extending net-work of magnetic stations — p. 190 and
note.  Development of light at the magnetic poles; terrestrial light as a
consequence of the electro-magnetic activity of our planet.  Elevation of
polar light.  Whether magnetic storms are accompanied by noise.  Connection
of polar light (an electro-magnetic development of light) with the formation
of cirrus clouds.  Other examples of the generation of terrestrial light —
p. 202 and note.
b.  The vital activity of a planet manifested from within outward, the
principal source of geognostic phenomena.  Connection between merely dynamic
concussions or the upheaval of whole portions of the earth's crust,
accompanied by the effusion of matter, and the generation of gaseous and
liquid fluids, of hot mud and fused earths, which solidify into rocks.
Volcanic action, in the most general conception of the idea, is the reaction
of the interior of a planet on its outer surface.  Earthquakes.  Extent of
the circles of commotion and their gradual increase.  Whether there exists
any connection between the changes in terrestrial magnetism and the
processes of the atmosphere.  Noises, subterranean thunder without any
perceptible concussion.  The rocks which modify the propagation of the waves
of concussion.  Upheavals; eruption of water, hot steam, mud mofettes,
smoke, and flame during an earthquake — p. 202-218 and notes.
c.  Closer consideration of material products as a consequence of internal
planetary activity.  There rise from the depths of the earth, through
fissures and cones of eruption, various gases, liquid fluids (pure or
acidulated), mud, and molten earths.  Volcanoes are a species of
intermittent spring.  Temperature of thermal springs; their constancy and
change.  Depth of the foci — p. 219-224 and notes.  Salses, mud volcanoes.
While fire-emitting mountains, being sources of molten earths, produce
volcanic rocks, spring water forms, by precipitation, strata of limestone.
Continued generation of sedimentary rocks — p. 228 and note.
d.  Diversity of volcanic elevations.  Dome-like closed trachytic mountains.
 Actual volcanoes which are formed from craters of elevations or among the
detritus of their original structure.  Permanent connection of the interior
of our earth with the atmosphere.  Relation to certain rocks.  Influence of
the relations of height on the frequency of the eruptions.  Heights of the
cone of cinders.  Characteristics of those volcanoes which rise above the
snow-line.  Columns of ashes and fire.  Volcanic storm during the eruption.
Mineral composition of lavas — p. 236 and notes.  Distribution of volcanoes
on the earth's surface; central and linear volcanoes; insular and littoral
volcanoes.  Distance of volcanoes from the sea-coast.  Extinction of
volcanic forces — p. 246 and notes.
e.  Relation of volcanoes to the character of rocks.  Volcanic forces form
new rocks, and metamorphose the more ancient ones.  The study of these
relations leads, by a double course, to the mineral portion of geognosy (the
study of the textures and of the position of the earth's strata), and to the
configuration of continents and insular groups elevated above the level of
the sea (the study of the geographical form and outlines of the different
parts of the earth.  Classification of rocks according to the scale of the
phenomena of structure and metamorphosis, which are still passing before our
eyes.  Rocks of eruption, sedimentary rocks, changed (metamorphosed) rocks,
conglomerates — compound rocks are definite associations of
cryctognostically simple fossils.  There are four phases in the formative
condition; rocks of eruption,
p 20
endogenous (granite, sienite, porphyry, greenstone, hyperathene, rock,
euphotide, melaphyre, basalt, and phonolithe); sedimentary rocks (silurian
schist, coal measures, limestone, travertino, infusorial deposit);
metamorphosed rock, which contains also, together with the detritus mica
schist, and more ancient metamorphic masses.  Aggregate and sandstone
formations.  The phenomenon of contact explained by the artificial imitation
of minerals.  Effects of pressure and the various rapidity of cooling.
Origin of granular or saccharoidal marble, silicification of schist into
ribbon jasper.  Metamorphosis of calcareous marl into micaceous schist
through granite.  Conversion of dolomite and granite into argillaceous
schist, by contact with basaltic and doleritic rocks.  Filling up of the
veins from below.  Processes of cementation in agglomerate structures.
Friction conglomerates — p. 269 and note.  Relative age of rocks,
chronometry of the earth's crust.  Fossiliferous strata.  Relative age of
organisms.  Simplicity of the first vital forms.  Dependence of
physiological gradations on the age of the formations.  Geognostic horizon,
whose careful investigation may yield certain data regarding the identity or
the relative age of formations, the periodic recurrence of certain strata,
their parallelism, or their total suppression.  Types of the sedimentary
structures considered in their most simple and general characters; silurian
and devonian formations (formerly known as rocks of transition); the lower
trias (mountain limestone, coal measures, together with 'todilegende' and
zechstein); the upper trias (butter sandstone, muschelkalk, and keuper);
Jura limestone (lias and oolite); freestone, lower and upper chalk, as the
last of the flotz strata, which begin with mountain limestone; tertiary
formations in three divisions, which are designated by granular limestone,
lignite, and south Apennine gravel — p. 269-278.
The faunas and floras of an earlier world, and their relations to existing
organisms.  Colossal bones of antediluvian mammalia in the upper alluvium.
Vegetation of an earlier world; monuments of the history of its vegetation.
The points at which certain vegetable groups attain their maximum; cycadeae
in the keuper and lias, and coniferae in the butter sandstone.  Lignite and
coal measures (amber-tree).  Deposition of large masses of rock; doubts
regarding their origin — p. 285 and note.
f.  The knowledge of geognostic epochs — of the upheaval of mountain chains
and elevated plateaux, by which lands are both formed and destroyed, leads,
by an internal causal connection, to the distribution into solids and
fluids, and to the peculiarities in the natural configuration of the earth's
surface.  Existing areal relations of the solid to the fluid differ
considerably from those presented by the maps of the physical portion of a
more ancient geography.  Importance of the eruption of quartzose, porphyry
with reference to the then existing configuration of continental masses.
Individual conformation in horizontal extension (relations of articulation)
and in vertical elevation (hypsometrical views).  Influence of the relations
of the area of land and sea on the temperature, direction of the winds,
abundance or scarcity of organic products, and on all meteorological
processes collectively.  Direction of the major axes of continental masses.
Articulation and pyramidal termination toward the south.  Series of
peninsulas.  Valley-like formation of the Atlantic Ocean.  Forms which
frequently recur — p. 285-293 and notes.  Ramifications and systems of
mountain chains, and the means of determining their relative ages.  Attempts
to determine the centre of gravity of the volume of the lands upheaved above
the level
p 21
of the sea.  The elevation of continents is still progressing slowly, and is
being compensated for at some definite points by a perceptible sinking.  All
geognostic phenomena indicate a periodical alteration of activity in the
interior of our planet.  Probability of new elevations of ridges — p.
293-301 and notes.
g.  The solid surface of the earth has two envelopes, one liquid, and the
other aeriform.  Contrasts and analogies which these envelopes — the sea
and the atmosphere — present in their conditions of aggregation and
electricity, and in their relations of currents and temperature.  Depths of
the ocean and of the atmosphere, the shoals of which constitute our
highlands and mountain chains.  The degree of heat at the surface of the sea
in different latitudes and in the lower strata.  Tendency of the sea to
maintain the temperature of the surface in the strata nearest to the
atmosphere, in consequence of the mobility of its particles and the
alteration in its density.  Maximum of  the density of salt water.  Position
of the zones of the hottest water, and of those having the greatest saline
contents.  Thermic influence of the lower polar current and the counter
currents in the straits of the sea — p. 302-304 and notes.  General level
of the sea, and permanent local disturbances of equilibrium; the periodic
disturbances manifested as tides.  Oceanic currents; the equatorial or
rotation current, the Atlantic warm Gulf Stream, and the further impulse
which it receives; the cold Peruvian stream in the eastern portion of the
Pacific Ocean of the southern zone.  Temperature of shoals.  The universal
diffusion of life in the ocean.  Influence of the small submarine sylvan
region at the bottom of beds of rooted algae, or on far-extending floating
layers of fucus — p. 302-311 and notes.
h.  The gaseous envelope of our planet, the atmosphere.  Chemical
composition of the atmosphere, its transparency, its polarization, pressure,
temperature, humidity, and electric tension.  Relation of oxygen to
nitrogen; amount of carbonic acid; carbureted hydrogen; ammoniacal vapors.
Miamata.  Regular (horary) changes in the pressure of the atmosphere.  Mean
barometrical height at the level of the sea in different zones of the earth.
 Isobarometrical curves.  Barometrical windroses.  Law of rotation of the
winds, and its importance with reference to the knowledge of many
meteorological processes.  Land and sea winds, trade winds and monsoons —
p. 311-317.  Climatic distribution of heat in the atmosphere, as the effect
of the relative position of transparent and opaque masses (fluid and solid
superficial area), and of the hypsometrical configuration of continents.
Curvature of the isothermal lines in a horizontal and vertical direction, on
the earth's surface and in the superimposed strata of air.  Convexity and
concavity of the isothermal lines.  Mean heat of the year, seasons, months,
and days.  Enumeration of the causes which produce disturbances in the form
of isothermal lines, i.e., their deviation from the position of the
geographical parallels.  Isochimenal and isotheral lines are the lines of
equal winter and summer heat.  Causes which raise or lower the temperature.
Radiation of the earth's surface, according to its inclination, color,
density, dryness, and chemical composition.  The form of the cloud which
announces what is passing in the upper strata of the atmosphere is the image
of the strongly radiating ground projected on a hot summer sky.  Contrast
between an insular or littoral climate, such as is experienced by all
deeply-articulated continents, and the climate of the interior of large
tracts of land.  East and west coasts.  Difference between the southern and
northern hemispheres.  Thermal scales of
p 22
cultivated plants, going down from the vanilla, cacoa, and musaceae, by
citrous and olives, and to vines yielding potable wines.  The influence
which these scales exercise on the geographical distribution of cultivated
plants.  The favorable ripening and the immaturity of fruits are essentially
influenced by the difference in the action of direct or scattered light in a
clear sky or in one overcast with mist.  General summary of the causes which
yield a more genial climate to the greater portion of Europe considered as
the western peninsula of Asia — p. 326.  Determination of the changes in
the mean annual and summer temperature, which correspond to one degree of
geographical latitude.  Equality of the mean temperature of a mountain
station, and of the polar distance of any point lying at the level of the
sea.  Decrease of temperature with the decrease in elevation.  Limits of
perpetual snow, and the fluctuations in these limits.  Causes of disturbance
in the regularity of the phenomenon.  Northern and southern chains of the
Himalaya; habitability of the elevated plateaux of Thibet — p. 331.
Quantity of moisture in the atmosphere, according to the hours of the day,
the seasons of the year, degrees of latitude, and elevation.  Greatest
dryness of the atmosphere observed in Northern Asia, between the river
districts of the Irtysch and the Obi.  Dew, a consequence of radiation.
Quantity of rain — p. 335.  Electricity of the atmosphere, and disturbance
of the electric tension.  Geographical distribution of storms.
Predettermination of atmospheric changes.  The most important climatic
disturbances can not be traced, at the place of observation, to any local
cause, but are rather the consequence of some occurrence by which the
equilibrium in the atmospheric currents has been destroyed at some
considerable distance — p. 335-339.
i.  Physical geography is not limited to elementary inorganic terrestrial
life, but, elevated to a higher point of view, it embraces the sphere of
organic life, and the numerous gradations of its typical development.
Animal and vegetable life.  General diffusion of life in the sea and on the
land; microscopic vital forms discovered in the polar ice no less than in
the depths of the ocean within the tropics.  Extension imparted to the
horizon of life by Ehrenberg's discoveries.  Estimation of the mass (volume)
of animal and vegetable organisms — p. 339-346.  Geography of plants and
animals.  Migrations of organisms in the ovum, or by means of organs capable
of spontaneous motion.  Spheres of distribution depending on climatic
relations.  Regions of vegetation, and classification of the genera of
animals.  Isolated and social living plants and animals.  The character of
flora and fauna is not determined so much by the predominance of separate
families, in certain parallels of latitude, as by the highly complicated
relations of the association of many families, and the relative numerical
value of their species.  The forms of natural families which increase or
decrease from the equator to the poles.  Investigations into the numerical
relation existing in different districts of the earth between each one of
the large families to the whole mass of phanerogamia — p. 346-351.  The
human race considered according to its physical gradations, and the
geographical distribution of its simultaneously occurring types.  Races and
varieties.  All races of men are forms of one single species.  Unity of the
human race.  Languages considered as the intellectual creations of mankind,
or as portions of the history of mental activity, manifest a character of
nationality, although certain historical occurrences have been the means of
diffusing idioms of the same family of languages among nations of wholly
different descent — p. 351-359.
In This material taken from pages 23 to 56
COSMOS: A Sketch of the Physical Description of the Universe, Vol. 1
by Alexander von Humboldt
Translated by E C Otte
from the 1858 Harper & Brothers edition of Cosmos, volume 1
—————————————————————————
p 23
INTRODUCTION.
————————
</div></body></text></TEI>