<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="55">

CHAPTER III.
Speculations founded upon the Symmetry of Crystals.



1. WHEN
a crystal, as, for instance, a crystal of
Galena, (sulphuret of lead,) is readily divisible into smaller cubes, and these into smaller ones,
and so on without limit, it is very natural to represent
to ourselves the original cube as really consisting of
small cubical elements; and to imagine that it is a philosophical account of the physical structure of such a
substance to say that it is made up of cubical molecules. And when the Galena crystal has externally
the form of a cube, there is no difficulty in such a conception; for the surface of the crystal is also conceived
as made up of the surfaces of its cubical molecules.
We conceive the crystal so constituted, as we conceive
a wall built of bricks.
But if, as often happens, the Galena crystal be an
octahedron, a further consideration is requisite in order
to understand its structure, pursuing still the same
hypothesis. The mineral is still, as in the other case,
readily cleavable into small cubes, having their corners
turned to the faces of the octahedron. Therefore these
faces can no longer be conceived as made up of the
faces of cubical elements of which the whole is constituted. If we suppose a pile of such small cubes to be
closely built together, but with decreasing width above,
so as to form a pyramid, the face of such a pyramid
will no longer be plane; it will consist of a great number of the corners or edges of the small elementary
cubes. It would appear at first sight, therefore, that
such a face cannot represent the smooth polished surface of a crystal. 81
But when we come to look more closely, this difficulty disappears. For how large are these elementary
cubes? We cannot tell, even supposing they really
have any size. But we know that they must be, at
any rate, very small; so small as to be inappreciable by
our senses, for our senses find no limit to the divisibility of minerals by cleavage. Hence the surface of
the pyramid above described would not consist of
visible corners or edges, but would be roughened by
specks of imperceptible size; or rather, by supposing
these specks to become still smaller, the roughness
becomes smoothness. And thus we may have a crystal
with a smooth surface, made up of small cubes in such
a manner that their surfaces are all oblique to the surface of the crystal.
Haüy, struck by some instances in which the supposition of such a structure of crystals appeared to account happily for several of their relations and properties, adopted and propounded it as a general theory.
The small elements, of which he supposed crystals to
be thus built up, he termed integrant molecules. The
form of these molecules might or might not be the
same as the primitive form with which his construction was supposed to begin; but there was, at any rate,
a close connexion between these forms, since both of
them were founded on the cleavage of the mineral.
The tenet that crystals are constituted in the manner
which I have been describing, I shall call the Theory
of Integrant Molecules, and I have now to make some
remarks on the grounds of this theory.
2. In the case of which I have spoken, the mineral
used as the example, Galena, readily splits into cubes,
and cubes are easily placed together so as to fit each
other, and fill the space which they occupy. The same
is the case in the mineral which suggested to Haüy his
theory, namely, Calc Spar. The crystals of this substance are readily divisible into rhombohedrons, a
form like a brick with oblique angles; and such bricks
can be built together so as to produce crystals of all the
immense varieties of form which Calc Spar presents.
This kind of masonry is equally possible in many other 82 minerals; but as we go through the mineral kingdom
in our survey, we soon find cases which offer difficulties. Some minerals cleave only in two directions,
some in one only; in such cases we cannot by cleavage
obtain an integrant molecule of definite form; one of
its dimensions, at least, must remain indeterminate
and arbitrary. Again, in some instances, we have
more than three different planes of cleavage, as in
Fluor Spar, where we have four. The solid, bounded
by four planes, is a tetrahedron; or if we take four
pairs of parallel faces, an octahedron. But if we
attempt to take either of these forms for our integrant
molecule, we are met by this difficulty: that a collection of such forms will not fill space. Perhaps this
difficulty will be more readily conceived by the general
reader if it be contemplated with reference to plane
figures. It will readily be seen that a number of
equal squares may be put together so as to fill the
space which they occupy; but if we take a number of
equal regular octagons, we may easily convince ourselves that no possible arrangement can make them
cover a flat space without leaving blank spots between.
In like manner octahedrons or tetrahedrons cannot be
arranged in solid space so as to fill it. They necessarily leave vacancies. Hence the structure of Fluor
Spar, and similar crystals, was a serious obstacle in the
way of the theory of integrant molecules. That theory
had been adopted in the first instance because portions of the crystal, obtained by cleavage, could be
built up into a solid mass; but this ground of the
theory failed altogether in such instances as I have
described, and hence the theory, even upon the representations of its adherents, had no longer any claim to
assent.
The doctrine of Integral Molecules, however, was
by no means given up at once, even in such instances.
In this and in other subjects, we may observe that a
theory, once constructed and carried into detail, has
such a hold upon the minds of those who have been in
the habit of applying it, that they will attempt to uphold it by introducing suppositions inconsistent with 83 the original foundations of the theory. Thus those who
assert the Atomic Theory, reconcile it with facts by
taking the halves of atoms; and thus the Theory of Integrant Molecules was maintained for Fluor Spar, by
representing the elementary octahedrons of which crystals are built up, as touching each other only by the
edges. The contact of surface with surface amongst
integrant molecules had been the first basis of the
theory; but this supposition being here inapplicable,
was replaced by one which made the theory no longer
a representation of the facts (the cleavages), but a
mere geometrical construction. Although, however,
the inapplicability of the theory to such cases was thus,
in some degree, disguised to the disciples of Haüy, it
was plain that, in the face of such difficulties, the
Theory of Integrant Molecules could not hold its place
as a philosophical truth. But it still answered the
purpose (a very valuable one, and one to which crystallography is much indebted,) of an instrument for calculating the geometrical relations of the parts of crystals
to each other: for the integrant molecules were supposed to be placed layer above layer, each layer as we
ascend, decreasing by a certain number of molecules
and rows of molecules; and the calculation of these
laws of decrement was, in fact, the best mode then
known of determining the positions of the faces. The
Theory of Decrements served to express and to determine, in a great number of the most obvious cases, the
laws of phenomena in crystalline forms, though the
Theory of Integrant Molecules could not be maintained
as a just view of the structure of crystals.
3. The Theory of Integrant Molecules, however, involved this just and important principle: that a true
view of the intimate structure of crystals must include
and explain the facts of crystallization, that is, crystalline form and cleavage; and that it must take these
into account, according to their degree of Symmetry.
So far all theories concerning the elements of crystals
must agree. And it was soon seen that this was, in
reality, all that had been established by the investigations of Haüy and his school. I have already, in the 84 History, quoted Weiss’s reflections on making this
step. ‘When in 1809,’ he says5, ‘I published my
Dissertation, I shared the common opinion as to the
necessity of the assumption, and the reality of the existence of a primitive form, at least in a sense not very
different from the usual sense of the expression.’ He
then proceeds to relate that he sought a ground for
such an opinion, independent of the doctrine of Atoms,
which he, in common with a great number of philosophers of that time in his own country, was disposed to
reject, inclining to believe that the properties of bodies
were determined by Forces which acted in them, and
not by Molecules of which they were composed. He
adds, that in pursuing this train of thought, he found,
‘that out of his Primitive Forms there was gradually
unfolded to his hands that which really governs them,
and is not affected by their casual fluctuations; namely,
the Fundamental Relations of their Dimensions,’ or as
we now may call them, Axes of Symmetry. With
reference to these Axes, he found, as he goes on to say,
that ‘a multiplicity of internal Oppositions, necessarily
and mutually interdependent, are developed in the
crystalline mass, each Relation having its own Polarity;
so that the Crystalline Character is co-extensive with
these Polarities.’ The character of these polarities,
whether manifested in crystalline faces, cleavage, or
any other incidents of crystallization, is necessarily displayed in the degree and kind of Symmetry which the
crystal possesses: and thus this Symmetry, in all our
speculations concerning the structure of crystals, necessarily takes the place of that enumeration of Primitive
Forms which were rejected as inconsistent with observed
facts, and destitute of sound scientific principle.</div></body></text></TEI>