<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="69">

BOOK X.


THE PHILOSOPHY OF PALÆTIOLOGY.

CHAPTER I.
Of Palætiological Sciences in General.


1. I HAVE
already stated in the History of the
Sciences1, that the class of Sciences which I
designate as Palætiological are those in which the object is to ascend from the present state of things to a
more ancient condition, from which the present is derived by intelligible causes. As conspicuous examples
of this class we may take Geology, Glossology or
Comparative Philology, and Comparative Archæology.
These provinces of knowledge might perhaps be intelligibly described as Histories; the History of the
Earth,—the History of Languages,—the History of
Arts. But these phrases would not fully describe
the sciences we have in view; for the object to which
we now suppose their investigations to be directed is,
not merely to ascertain what the series of events has
been, as in the common forms of History, but also how
it has been brought about. These sciences are to treat
of causes as well as of effects. Such researches might
be termed Philosophical History; or, in order to mark
more distinctly that the causes of events are the leading object of attention, Ætiological History. But since 258 it will be more convenient to describe this class of
sciences by a single appellation, I have taken the liberty
of proposing to call them2 the Palætiological Sciences.</div></body></text></TEI>