<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="15"> 

CHAPTER V.
Analysis of the Process of Induction.


Aphorism XXXIV.
The Process of Induction may be resolved into three steps;
the Selection of the Idea, the Construction of the Conception,
and the Determination of the Magnitudes.
Aphorism XXXV.
These three steps correspond to the determination of the
Independent Variable, the Formula, and the Coefficients,
in mathematical investigations; or to the Argument, the
Law, and the Numerical Data, in a Table of an astronomical
or other Inequality.
Aphorism XXXVI.
The Selection of the Idea depends mainly upon inventive
sagacity: which operates by suggesting and trying various
hypotheses. Some inquirers try erroneous hypotheses; and
thus, exhausting the forms of errour, form the Prelude to
Discovery.
Aphorism XXXVII.
The following Rules may be given, in order to the selection
of the Idea for purposes of Induction:—the Idea and the
Facts must be homogeneous; and the Rule must be tested
by the Facts.
Sect. I.—The Three Steps of Induction.

1. WHEN
facts have been decomposed and phenomena measured,
the philosopher endeavours to combine them into general laws,
by the aid of 187 Ideas and Conceptions; these being
illustrated and regulated by such means as we have spoken of in the last
two chapters. In this task, of gathering laws of nature
from observed facts, as we have already
said24, the natural
sagacity of gifted minds is the power by which
the greater part of the successful results have been
obtained; and this power will probably always be more
efficacious than any Method can be. Still there are
certain methods of procedure which may, in such investigations,
give us no inconsiderable aid, and these I
shall endeavour to expound.</div></body></text></TEI>