<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="26">

BOOK III.

THE PHILOSOPHY OF THE MECHANICAL SCIENCES.

CHAPTER I.
Of the Mechanical Sciences.


In
the History of the Sciences, that class of which we here
speak occupies a conspicuous and important place; coming
into notice immediately after those parts of Astronomy which
require for their cultivation merely the ideas of space,
time, motion, and number. It appears from our History, that
certain truths concerning the equilibrium of bodies
were established by Archimedes;—that, after a long interval
of inactivity, his principles were extended and pursued
further in modern times:—and that to these doctrines
concerning equilibrium and the forces which produce it,
(which constitute the science Statics,) were added
many other doctrines concerning the motions of
bodies, considered also as produced by forces, and thus the
science of Dynamics was produced. The assemblage of
these sciences composes the province of Mechanics.
Moreover, philosophers have laboured to make out the laws of
the equilibrium of fluid as well as solid bodies; and
hence has arisen the science of Hydrostatics. And the
doctrines of Mechanics have been found to have a most
remarkable bearing upon the motions of the heavenly bodies;
with reference to which, indeed, they were at first
principally studied. The explanation of those cosmical facts
by means of mechanical 172 principles and their
consequences, forms the science of Physical
Astronomy. These are the principal examples of
mechanical science; although some other portions of Physics,
as Magnetism and Electrodynamics, introduce mechanical
doctrines very largely into their speculations.
Now in all these sciences we have to consider Forces.
In all mechanical reasonings forces enter, either as
producing motion, or as prevented from doing so by other
forces. Thus force, in its most general sense, is the
cause of motion, or of tendency to motion; and in
order to discover the principles on which the mechanical
sciences truly rest, we must examine the nature and origin
of our knowledge of Causes.
In these sciences, however, we have not to deal with Cause
in its more general acceptation, in which it applies to all
kinds of agency, material or immaterial;—to the influence
of thought and will, as well as of bodily pressure and
attractive force. Our business at present is only with such
causes as immediately operate upon matter. We shall
nevertheless, in the first place, consider the nature of
Cause in its most general form; and afterwards narrow our
speculations so as to direct them specially to the
mechanical sciences.</div></body></text></TEI>