<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="19">CHAPTER XIX.
DESTROYING AND TRANSPORTING EFFECTS OF TIDES AND CURRENTS.
Difference in the rise of tides—Lagullas and Gulf
currents—Velocity of currents—Causes
of currents—Action of the sea on the British coast—Shetland Islands—Large
blocks removed—Isles reduced to clusters of rocks—Orkney
isles—Waste
of East coast of Scotland—and East coast of England—Waste of the
cliffs of Holderness, Norfolk, and Suffolk—Sand-dunes, how far chronometers—Silting
up of estuaries—Yarmouth estuary—Suffolk coast—Dunwich—Essex
coast—Estuary of the Thames—Goodwin Sands—Coast of
Kent—Formation of
the Straits of Dover—South coast of
England—Sussex—Hants—Dorset—Portland—Origin
of the Chesil Bank—Cornwall—Coast of Brittany.
Although the movements of great bodies of water, termed tides and
currents, are in general due to very distinct causes, their effects cannot
be studied separately; for they produce, by their joint action, aided by
that of the waves, those changes which are objects of geological interest.
These forces may be viewed in the same manner as we before
considered rivers, first, as employed in destroying portions of the solid
crust of the earth and removing them to other places; secondly, as reproductive
of new strata.
Tides.—It would be superfluous at the present day to offer any remarks
on the cause of the tides. They are not perceptible in lakes or
in most inland seas; in the Mediterranean even, deep and extensive as
is that sea, they are scarcely sensible to ordinary observation, their
effects being quite subordinate to those of the winds and currents. In
some places, however, as in the Straits of Messina, there is an ebb and
flow to the amount of two feet and upwards; at Naples and at the
291
Euripus, of twelve or thirteen inches; and at Venice, according to Rennell,
of five feet.378 In the Syrtes, also, of the ancients, two wide shallow
gulfs, which penetrate very far within the northern coast of Africa,
between Carthage and Cyrene, the rise is said to exceed five feet.379
In islands remote from any continent, the ebb and flow of the ocean
is very slight, as at St. Helena, for example, where it is rarely above
three feet.380 In any given line of coast, the tides are greatest in narrow
channels, bays, and estuaries, and least in the intervening tracts where
the land is prominent. Thus, at the entrance of the estuary of the
Thames and Medway, the rise of the spring tides is eighteen feet; but
when we follow our eastern coast from thence northward, towards
Lowestoff and Yarmouth, we find a gradual diminution, until at the
places last mentioned, the highest rise is only seven or eight feet.
From this point there begins again to be an increase, so that at Comer,
where the coast again retires towards the west, the rise is sixteen feet;
and towards the extremity of the gulf called "the Wash," as at Lynn
and in Boston Deeps, it is from twenty-two to twenty-four feet, and in
some extraordinary cases twenty-six feet. From thence again there is
a decrease towards, the north, the elevation at the Spurn Point being
from nineteen to twenty feet, and at Flamborough Head and the Yorkshire
coast from fourteen to sixteen feet.381
At Milford Haven in Pembrokeshire, at the mouth of the Bristol
Channel, the tides rise thirty-six feet; and at King-Road near Bristol,
forty-two feet. At Chepstow on the Wye, a small river which opens
into the estuary of the Severn, they reach fifty feet, and sometimes
sixty-nine, and even seventy-two feet. A current which sets in on
the French coast, to the west of Cape La Hague, becomes pent up by
Guernsey, Jersey, and other islands, till the rise of the tide is from
twenty to forty-five feet, which last height it attains at Jersey, and at
St. Malo, a seaport of Brittany. The tides in the Basin of Mines, at the
head of the Bay of Fundy in Nova Scotia, rise to the height of seventy
feet.
There are, however, some coasts where the tides seem to offer an
exception to the rule above mentioned; for while there is scarcely any
rise in the estuary of the Plata in S. America, there is an extremely high
tide on the open coast of Patagonia, farther to the south. Yet even in
this region the tides reach their greatest elevation (about fifty feet) in
the Straits of Magellan, and so far at least they conform to the general
rule.382
Currents.—The most extensive and best determined system of currents,
is that which has its source in the Indian Ocean under the influence
of the trade winds; and which, after doubling the Cape of Good
292
Hope, inclines to the northward, along the western coast of Africa, then
across the Atlantic, near the equator, where it is called the equatorial
current, and is lost in the Caribbean Sea, yet seems to be again revived
in the current which issues from the Gulf of Mexico. From thence it
flows rapidly through the Straits of Bahama, taking the name of the
Gulf Stream, and passing in a northeasterly direction, by the Banks
of Newfoundland, towards the Azores.
We learn from the posthumous work of Rennell on this subject, that
the Lagullas current, so called from the cape and bank of that name, is
formed by the junction of two streams, flowing from the Indian Ocean;
the one from the channel of Mozambique, down the southeast coast of
Africa; the other from the ocean at large. The collective stream is
from ninety to one hundred miles in breadth, and runs at the rate of
from two and a half to more than four miles per hour. It is at length
turned westward by the Lagullas bank, which rises from a sea of great
depth to within one hundred fathoms of the surface. It must therefore
be inferred, says Rennell, that the current here is more than one hundred
fathoms deep, otherwise the main body of it would pass across the
bank, instead of being deflected westward, so as to flow round the Cape
of Good Hope. From this cape it flows northward, as before stated,
along the western coast of Africa, taking the name of the South Atlantic
current. It then enters the Bight, or Bay of Benin, and is turned westward,
partly by the form of the coast there, and partly, perhaps, by the
Guinea current, which runs from the north into the same great bay.
From the centre of this bay proceeds the equatorial current already
mentioned, holding a westerly direction across the Atlantic, which it
traverses, from the coast of Guinea to that of Brazil, flowing afterwards
by the shores of Guiana to the West Indies. The breadth of this current
varies from 160 to 450 geographical miles, and its velocity is from
twenty-five to seventy-nine miles per day, the mean rate being about
thirty miles. The length of its whole course is about 4000 miles. As
it skirts the coast of Guiana, it is increased by the influx of the waters
of the Amazon and Orinoco, and by their junction acquires accelerated
velocity. After passing the island of Trinidad it expands, and is almost
lost in the Caribbean Sea; but there appears to be a general movement
of that sea towards the Mexican Gulf, which discharges the most powerful
of all currents through the Straits of Florida, where the waters run
in the northern part with a velocity of four or five miles an hour, having
a breadth of from thirty-five to fifty miles.383
The temperature of the Gulf of Mexico is 86° F. in summer, or 6°
higher than that of the ocean, in the same parallel (25° N. lat.), and
a large proportion of this warmth is retained, even where the stream
reaches the 43° N. lat. After issuing from the Straits of Florida, the
current runs in a northerly direction to Cape Hatteras, in North Carolina,
about 35° N. lat., where it is more than seventy miles broad, and
293
still moves at the rate of seventy-five miles per day. In about the 40°
N. lat., it is turned more towards the Atlantic by the extensive banks
of Nantucket and St. George, which are from 200 to 300 feet beneath
the surface of the sea; a clear proof that the current exceeds that depth.
On arriving near the Azores, the stream widens, and overflows, as it
were, forming a large expanse of warm water in the centre of the North
Atlantic, over a space of 200 or 300 miles from north to south, and
having a temperature of from 8° to 10° Fahr. above the surrounding
ocean. The whole area, covered by the Gulf water, is estimated by
Rennell at 2000 miles in length, and, at a mean, 350 miles in breadth;
an area more extensive than that of the Mediterranean. The warm
water has been sometimes known to reach the Bay of Biscay, still retaining
five degrees of temperature above that of the adjoining ocean;
and a branch of the Gulf current occasionally drifts fruits, plants, and
wood, the produce of America and the West Indies, to the shores of
Ireland and the Hebrides.
From the above statements we may understand why Rennell has
characterized some of the principal currents as oceanic rivers, which he
describes as being from 50 to 250 miles in breadth, and having a
rapidity exceeding that of the largest navigable rivers of the continents,
and so deep as to be sometimes obstructed, and occasionally turned
aside, by banks, the tops of which do not rise within forty, fifty, or
even one hundred fathoms of the surface of the sea.384
Greatest velocity of currents.—The ordinary velocity of the principal
currents of the ocean is from one to three miles per hour; but when
the boundary lands converge, large bodies of water are driven gradually
into a narrow space, and then wanting lateral room, are compelled to
raise their level. Whenever this occurs their velocity is much increased.
The current which runs through the Race of Alderney, between
the island of that name and the main land, has a velocity of
about eight English miles an hour. Captain Hewett found that in the
Pentland Firth, the stream, in ordinary spring tides, runs ten miles and
a half an hour, and about thirteen miles during violent storms. The
greatest velocity of the tidal current through the "Shoots" or New
Passage, in the Bristol Channel, is fourteen English miles an hour;
and Captain King observed, in his survey of the Straits of Magellan,
that the tide ran at the same rate through the "First Narrows," and
about eight geographical miles an hour, in other parts of those straits.
Causes of currents.—That movements of no inconsiderable magnitude
should be impressed on an expansive ocean, by winds blowing
for many months in one direction, may easily be conceived, when we
observe the effects produced in our own seas by the temporary action
of the same cause. It is well known that a strong southwest or northwest
wind invariably raises the tides to an unusual height along the
west coast of England and in the Channel; and that a northwest wind
294
of any continuance causes the Baltic to rise two feet and upwards
above its ordinary level. Smeaton ascertained by experiment, that in
a canal four miles in length, the water was kept up four inches higher
at one end than at the other, merely by the action of the wind along
the canal; and Rennell informs us that a large piece of water, ten
miles broad, and generally only three feet deep, has, by a strong wind,
had its waters driven to one side, and sustained so as to become six
feet deep, while the windward side was laid dry.385
As water, therefore, he observes, when pent up so that it cannot
escape, acquires a higher level, so, in a place where it can escape, the
same operation produces a current; and this current will extend to a
greater or less distance, according to the force by which it is produced.
By the side of the principal oceanic currents, such as the Lagullas and
the Gulf Stream, are parallel "counter-currents" running steadily in an
opposite direction.
Currents flowing alternately in opposite directions are occasioned by
the rise and fall of the tides. The effect of this cause is, as before
observed, most striking in estuaries and channels between islands.
A third cause of oceanic currents is evaporation by solar heat, of
which the great current setting through the Straits of Gibraltar into the
Mediterranean is a remarkable example, and will be fully considered
in the next chapter. A stream of colder water also flows from the
Black Sea into the Mediterranean. It must happen in many other
parts of the world that large quantities of water raised from one tract
of the ocean by solar heat, are carried to some other where the vapor
is condensed and falls in the shape of rain, and this, in flowing back
again to restore equilibrium, will cause sensible currents.
These considerations naturally lead to the inquiry whether the level
of those seas out of which currents flow, is higher than that of seas into
which they flow. If not, the effect must be immediately equalized by
under-currents or counter-currents. Arago is of opinion that, so far as
observations have gone, there are no exact proofs of any such difference
of level. It was inferred from the measurements of M. Lepére, that
the level of the Mediterranean, near Alexandria, was lower by 26 feet 6
inches, than the Red Sea near Suez at low water, and about 30 feet
lower than the Red Sea at the same place at high water,386 but Mr.
Robert Stevenson affirms, as the result of a more recent survey, that
there is no difference of level between the two seas.387
It was formerly imagined that there was an equal, if not greater,
diversity in the relative levels of the Atlantic and Pacific, on the opposite
sides of the Isthmus of Panama. But the levellings carried across
that isthmus by Capt. Lloyd, in 1828, to ascertain the relative height
of the Pacific Ocean at Panama, and of the Atlantic at the mouth of
the river Chagres, have shown, that the difference of mean level between
295
those oceans is not considerable, and, contrary to expectation, the
difference which does exist is in favor of the greater height of the Pacific.
According to this survey, the mean height of the Pacific is three feet
and a half, or 3·52 above the Atlantic, if we assume the mean level of a
sea to coincide with the mean between the extremes of the elevation
and depression of the tides; for between the extreme levels of the
greatest tides in the Pacific, at Panama, there is a difference of 27·44
feet; and at the usual spring tides 21·22 feet; whereas at Chagres
this difference is only 1·16 feet, and is the same at all seasons of the
year.
The tides, in short, in the Caribbean Sea are scarcely perceptible, not
equalling those in some parts of the Mediterranean, whereas the rise is
very high in the Bay of Panama; so that the Pacific is at high tide
lifted up several feet above the surface of the Gulf of Mexico, and then
at low water let down as far below it.388 But astronomers are agreed
that, on mathematical principles, the rise of the tidal wave above the
mean level of a particular sea must be greater than the fall below it;
and although the difference has been hitherto supposed insufficient to
cause an appreciable error, it is, nevertheless, worthy of observation,
that the error, such as it may be, would tend to reduce the small difference,
now inferred, from the observations of Mr. Lloyd, to exist between
the levels of the two oceans.
There is still another way in which heat and cold must occasion great
movements in the ocean, a cause to which, perhaps, currents are principally
due. Whenever the temperature of the surface of the sea is
lowered, condensation takes place, and the superficial water, having its
specific gravity increased, falls to the bottom, upon which lighter water
rises immediately and occupies its place. When this circulation of
ascending and descending currents has gone on for a certain time in
high latitudes, the inferior parts of the sea are made to consist of colder
or heavier fluid than the corresponding depths of the ocean between the
tropics. If there be a free communication, if no chain of submarine
mountains divide the polar from the equatorial basins, a horizontal movement
will arise by the flowing of colder water from the poles to the
equator, and there will then be a reflux of warmer superficial water
from the equator to the poles. A well-known experiment has been adduced
to elucidate this mode of action in explanation of the "trade
winds."389 If a long trough, divided in the middle by a sluice or partition,
have one end filled with water and the other with quicksilver, both
fluids will remain quiet so long as they are divided; but when the sluice
is drawn up, the heavier fluid will rush along the bottom of the trough,
while the lighter, being displaced, will rise, and, flowing in an opposite
direction, spread itself at the top. In like manner the expansion and
contraction of sea-water by heat and cold, have a tendency to set under-currents
296
in motion from the poles to the equator, and to cause
counter-currents at the surface, which are impelled in a direction contrary
to that of the prevailing trade winds. The geographical and
other circumstances being very complicated, we cannot expect to trace
separately the movements due to each cause, but must be prepared for
many anomalies, especially as the configuration of the bed of the ocean
must often modify and interfere with the course of the inferior currents,
as much as the position and form of continents and islands alter the direction
of those on the surface. Thus on sounding at great depths in
the Mediterranean, Captains Berard and D'Urville have found that the
cold does not increase in a high ratio as in the tropical regions of the
ocean, the thermometer remaining fixed at about 55° F. between the
depths of 1000 and 6000 feet. This might have been anticipated, as
Captain Smyth in his survey had shown that the deepest part of the
Straits of Gibraltar is only 1320 feet, so that a submarine barrier exists
there which must prevent the influx of any under-current of the ocean
cooled by polar ice.
Each of the four causes above mentioned, the wind, the tides, evaporation,
and the expansion and contraction of water by heat and cold,
may be conceived to operate independently of the others, and although
the influence of all the rest were annihilated. But there is another
cause, the rotation of the earth on its axis, which can only come into
play when the waters have already been set in motion by some one or
all of the forces above described, and when the direction of the current
so raised happens to be from south to north, or from north to
south.
The principle on which this cause operates is probably familiar to the
reader, as it has long been recognized in the case of the trade winds.
Without enlarging, therefore, on the theory, it will be sufficient to offer
an example of the mode of action alluded to. When a current flows
from the Cape of Good Hope towards the Gulf of Guinea, it consists of
a mass of water, which, on doubling the Cape, in lat. 35°, has a rotatory
velocity of about 800 miles an hour; but when it reaches the line,
where it turns westward, it has arrived at a parallel where the surface
of the earth is whirled round at the rate of 1000 miles an hour, or
about 200 miles faster. If this great mass of water was transferred
suddenly from the higher to the lower latitude, the deficiency of its rotatory
motion, relatively to the land and water with which it would
come into juxtaposition, would be such as to cause an apparent motion
of the most rapid kind (of no less than 200 miles an hour) from east
to west.
In the case of such a sudden transfer, the eastern coast of America,
being carried round in an opposite direction, might strike against a large
body of water with tremendous violence, and a considerable part of the
continent might be submerged. This disturbance does not occur, because
the water of the stream, as it advances gradually into new zones
of the sea which are moving more rapidly, acquires by friction an accelerated
297
velocity. Yet as this motion is not imparted instantaneously,
the fluid is unable to keep up with the full speed of the new surface
over which it is successively brought. Hence, to borrow the language
of Herschel, when he speaks of the trade winds, "it lags or hangs back,
in a direction opposite to the earth's rotation, that is, from east to
west,"390 and thus a current, which would have run simply towards
the north but for the rotation, may acquire a relative direction towards
the west.
We may next consider a case where the circumstances are the converse
of the above. The Gulf Stream flowing from about lat. 20° is at
first impressed with a velocity of rotation of about 940 miles an hour,
and runs to the lat. 40°, where the earth revolves only at the rate of
766 miles, or 174 miles slower. In this case a relative motion of an
opposite kind may result; and the current may retain an excess of rotatory
velocity, tending continually to deflect it eastward. Polar currents,
therefore, or those flowing from high to low latitudes, are driven towards
the eastern shores of continents, while tropical currents flowing towards
the poles are directed against their western shores.
Thus it will be seen that currents depend, like the tides, on no temporary
or accidental circumstances, but on the laws which preside over
the motions of the heavenly bodies. But although the sum of their
influence in altering the surface of the earth may be very constant
throughout successive epochs, yet the points where these operations are
displayed in fullest energy shift perpetually. The height to which the
tides rise, and the violence and velocity of currents, depend in a great
measure on the actual configuration of the land, the contour of a long
line of continental or insular coast, the depth and breadth of channels,
the peculiar form of the bottom of seas—in a word, on a combination of
circumstances which are made to vary continually by many igneous and
aqueous causes, and, amongst the rest, by the tides and currents themselves.
Although these agents, therefore, of decay and reproduction are
local in reference to periods of short duration, such as those which history
embraces, they are nevertheless universal, if we extend our views to a
sufficient lapse of ages.
Destroying and transporting power of currents.—After these preliminary
remarks on the nature and causes of currents, their velocity and
direction, we may next consider their action on the solid materials of the
earth. We shall find that their efforts are, in many respects, strictly
analogous to those of rivers. I have already treated in the third chapter,
of the manner in which currents sometimes combine with ice, in
carrying mud, pebbles, and large fragments of rock to great distances.
Their operations are more concealed from our view than those of rivers,
but extend over wider areas, and are therefore of more geological
importance.
Waste of the British coasts.—Shetland Islands.—If we follow the
298
eastern and southern shores of the British islands, from our Ultima
Thule in Shetland to the Land's End in Cornwall, we shall find evidence
of a series of changes since the historical era, very illustrative of the
kind and degree of force exerted by tides and currents co-operating with
the waves of the sea. In this survey we shall have an opportunity of
tracing their joint power on islands, promontories, bays, and estuaries;
on bold, lofty cliffs, as well as on low shores; and on every description
of rock and soil, from granite to blown sand.
The northernmost group of the British islands, the Shetland, are composed
of a great variety of rocks, including granite, gneiss, mica-slate,
serpentine, greenstone, and many others, with some secondary rocks,
chiefly sandstone and conglomerate. These islands are exposed continually
to the uncontrolled violence of the Atlantic, for no land intervenes
between their western shores and America. The prevalence, therefore,
of strong westerly gales, causes the waves to be sometimes driven with
irresistible force upon the coast, while there is also a current setting from
the north. The spray of the sea aids the decomposition of the rocks,
and prepares them to be breached by the mechanical force of the waves.
Steep cliffs are hollowed out into deep caves and lofty arches; and almost
every promontory ends in a cluster of rocks, imitating the forms of
columns, pinnacles, and obelisks.
Drifting of large masses of rock.—Modern observations show that the
reduction of continuous tracts to such insular masses is a process in
which nature is still actively engaged. "The isle of Stenness," says Dr.
Hibbert, "presents a scene of unequalled desolation. In stormy winters,
huge blocks of stones are overturned, or are removed from their native
beds, and hurried up a slight acclivity to a distance almost incredible.
In the winter of 1802, a tabular-shaped mass, eight feet two inches by
seven feet, and five feet one inch thick, was dislodged from its bed, and
removed to a distance of from eighty to ninety feet. I measured the
recent bed from which a block had been carried away the preceding
winter (A. D. 1818), and found it to be seventeen feet and a half by
seven feet, and the depth two feet eight inches. The removed mass had
been borne to a distance of thirty feet, when it was shivered into thirteen
or more lesser fragments, some of which, were carried still farther,
from 30 to 120 feet. A block, nine feet two inches by six feet and a
half, and four feet thick, was hurried up the acclivity to a distance of
150 feet."391
At Northmavine, also, angular blocks of stone have been removed in
a similar manner to considerable distances by the waves of the sea, some
of which are represented in the annexed figure.
Effects of lightning.—In addition to numerous examples of masses
detached and driven by the waves, tides, and currents from their
place, some remarkable effects of lightning are recorded in these
299
isles. At Funzie, in Fetlar, about the middle of the last century, a
rock of mica-schist, 105 feet long, ten feet broad, and in some places
four feet thick, was in an instant torn by a flash of lightning from its
bed, and broken into three large and several smaller fragments. One
of these, twenty-six feet long, ten feet broad, and four feet thick, was
simply turned over. The second, which was twenty-eight feet long,
seventeen broad, and five feet in thickness, was hurled across a high
point to the distance of fifty yards. Another broken mass, about forty
feet long, was thrown still farther, but in the same direction, quite into
the sea. There were also many smaller fragments scattered up and
down.392
Fig. 27.
Stony fragments drifted by the sea. Northmavine, Shetland.
When we thus see electricity co-operating with the violent movements
of the ocean in heaping up piles of shattered rocks on dry land
and beneath the waters, we cannot but admit that a region which shall
be the theatre, for myriads of ages, of the action of such disturbing
causes, might present, at some future period, if upraised far above the
bosom of the deep, a scene of havoc and ruin that may compare with
any now found by the geologist on the surface of our continents.
In some of the Shetland Isles, as on the west of Meikle Roe, dikes, or
veins of soft granite, have mouldered away; while the matrix in which
they were inclosed, being of the same substance, but of a firmer texture,
has remained unaltered. Thus, long narrow ravines, sometimes
twenty feet wide, are laid open, and often give access to the waves.
After describing some huge cavernous apertures into which the sea
flows for 250 feet in Roeness, Dr. Hibbert, writing in 1822, enumerates
other ravages of the ocean. "A mass of rock, the average dimensions
of which may perhaps be rated at twelve or thirteen feet square, and
four and a half or five in thickness, was first moved from its bed, about
fifty years ago, to a distance of thirty feet, and has since been twice
turned over."
Passage forced by the sea through porphyritic rocks.—"But the most
sublime scene is where a mural pile of porphyry, escaping the process
300
of disintegration that is devastating the coast, appears to have been left
as a sort of rampart against the inroads of the ocean;—the Atlantic,
when provoked by wintry gales, batters against it with all the force of
real artillery—the waves having, in their repeated assaults, forced themselves
an entrance. This breach, named the Grind of the Navir (fig.
28), is widened every winter by the overwhelming surge that, finding a
passage through it, separates large stones from its sides, and forces
them to a distance of no less than 180 feet. In two or three spots,
the fragments which have been detached are brought together in immense
heaps, that appear as an accumulation of cubical masses, the
product of some quarry."393
Fig. 28.
Grind of the Navir—passage forced by the sea through rocks of hard porphyry.
It is evident from this example, that although the greater indestructibility
of some rocks may enable them to withstand, for a longer time,
the action of the elements, yet they cannot permanently resist. There
are localities in Shetland, in which rocks of almost every variety of
mineral composition are suffering disintegration; thus the sea makes
great inroads on the clay slate of Fitfel Head, on the serpentine of the
Vord Hill in Fetlar, and on the mica-schist of the Bay of Triesta, on
the east coast of the same island, which decomposes into angular blocks.
The quartz rock on the east of Walls, and the gneiss and mica-schist of
Garthness, suffer the same fate.
Destruction of islands.—Such devastation cannot be incessantly committed
for thousands of years without dividing islands, until they become
at last mere clusters of rocks, the last shreds of masses once continuous.
To this state many appear to have been reduced, and innumerable
fantastic forms are assumed by rocks adjoining these islands to which
the name of Drongs is applied, as it is to those of similar shape in Feroe.
Fig. 29.
Granitic rocks named the Drongs, between Papa Stour and Hillswick Ness.

Fig. 30.
Granitic rocks to the south of Hillswick Ness, Shetland.
301
The granite rocks (fig. 29), between Papa Stour and Hillswick Ness
afford an example. A still more singular cluster of rocks is seen to
the south of Hillswick Ness (fig. 30), which presents a variety of forms
as viewed from different points, and has often been likened to a small
fleet of vessels with spread sails.394 We may imagine that in the course
of time Hillswick Ness itself may present a similar wreck, from the
unequal decomposition of the rocks whereof it is composed, consisting of
gneiss and mica-schist traversed in all directions by veins of felspar-porphyry.
Midway between the groups of Shetland and Orkney is Fair Island,
said to be composed of sandstone with high perpendicular cliffs. The
current runs with such velocity, that during a calm, and when there is
no swell, the rocks on its shores are white with the foam of the sea
driven against them. The Orkneys, if carefully examined, would probably
302
illustrate our present topic as much as the Shetland group. The
northeast promontory of Sanda, one of these islands, has been cut off in
modern times by the sea, so that it became what is now called Start
Island, where a lighthouse was erected in 1807, since which time the
new strait has grown broader.
East coast of Scotland.—To pass over to the main land of Scotland,
we find that in Inverness-shire there have been inroads of the sea at
Fort George, and others in Morayshire, which have swept away the old
town of Findhorn. On the coast of Kincardineshire, an illustration was
afforded at the close of the last century, of the effect of promontories
in protecting a line of low shore. The village of Mathers, two miles
south of Johnshaven, was built on an ancient shingle beach, protected
by a projecting ledge of limestone rock. This was quarried for lime to
such an extent that the sea broke through, and in 1795 carried away
the whole village in one night, and penetrated 150 yards inland, where
it has maintained its ground ever since, the new village having been
built farther inland on the new shore. In the bay of Montrose, we find
the North Esk and the South Esk rivers pouring annually into the sea
large quantities of sand and pebbles; yet they have formed no deltas,
for the waves, aided by the current, setting across their mouths, sweep
away all the materials. Considerable beds of shingle, brought down by
the North Esk, are seen along the beach.
Proceeding southwards, we learn that at Arbroath, in Forfarshire,
which stands on a rock of red sandstone, gardens and houses have been
carried away since the commencement of the present century by encroachments
of the sea. It had become necessary before 1828, to
remove the lighthouses at the mouth of the estuary of the Tay, in the
same county, at Button Ness, which were built on a tract of blown
sand, the sea having encroached for three-quarters of a mile.
Force of waves and currents in estuaries.—The combined power
which waves and currents can exert in estuaries (a term which I
confine to bays entered both by rivers and the tides of the sea),
was remarkably exhibited during the building of the Bell Rock Lighthouse,
off the mouth of the Tay. The Bell Rock is a sunken reef,
consisting of red sandstone, being from twelve to sixteen feet under
the surface at high water, and about twelve miles from the mainland.
At the distance of 100 yards, there is a depth, in all directions
of two or three fathoms at low water. In 1807, during the erection
of the lighthouse, six large blocks of granite, which had been landed
on the reef, were removed by the force of the sea, and thrown over
a rising ledge to the distance of twelve or fifteen paces; and an anchor,
weighing about 22 cwt., was thrown up upon the rock.395 Mr. Stevenson
informs us moreover, that drift stones, measuring upwards of
thirty cubic feet, or more than two tons' weight, have, during storms,
been often thrown upon the rock from the deep water.396
303Submarine forests.—Among the proofs that the sea has encroached
on the land bordering the estuary of the Tay, Dr. Fleming has mentioned
a submarine forest which has been traced for several miles along
the northern shore of the county of Fife.397 But subsequent surveys
seem to have shown that the bed of peat containing tree-roots, leaves,
and branches, now occurring at a lower level than the Tay, must have
come into its present position by a general sinking of the ground on
which the forest grew. The peat-bed alluded to is not confined, says
Mr. Buist, to the present channel of the Tay, but extends far beyond it,
and is covered by stratified clay from fifteen to twenty-five feet in thickness,
in the midst of which, in some places, is a bed full of
sea-shells.398
Recent discoveries having established the fact that upward and downward
movements have affected our island since the general coast-line
had nearly acquired its present shape, we must hesitate before we attribute
any given change to a single cause, such as the local encroachment
of the sea upon low land.
On the coast of Fife, at St. Andrew's, a tract of land, said to have
intervened between the castle of Cardinal Beaton and the sea, has been
entirely swept away, as were the last remains of the Priory of Crail, in
the same county, in 1803. On both sides of the Frith of Forth, land
has been consumed; at North Berwick in particular, and at Newhaven,
where an arsenal and dock, built in the reign of James IV., in the fifteenth
century, has been overflowed.
East coast of England.—If we now proceed to the English coast, we
find records of numerous lands having been destroyed in Northumberland,
as those near Bamborough and Holy Island, and at Tynemouth
Castle, which now overhangs the sea, although formerly separated from
it by a strip of land. At Hartlepool, and several other parts of the
coast of Durham composed of magnesian limestone, the sea has made
considerable inroads.
Coast of Yorkshire.—Almost the whole coast of Yorkshire, from the
mouth of the Tees to that of the Humber, is in a state of gradual dilapidation.
That part of the cliffs which consist of lias, the oolite series,
and chalk, decays slowly. They present abrupt and naked precipices,
often 300 feet in height; and it is only at a few points that the grassy
covering of the sloping talus marks a temporary relaxation of the erosive
action of the sea. The chalk cliffs are worn into caves and needles in
the projecting headland of Flamborough, where they are decomposed
by the salt spray, and slowly crumble away. But the waste is most
rapid between that promontory and Spurn Point, or the coast of Holderness,
as it is called, a tract consisting of beds of clay, gravel, sand,
and chalk rubble. The irregular intermixture of the argillaceous beds
causes many springs to be thrown out, and this facilitates the undermining
process, the waves beating against them, and a strong current
304
setting chiefly from the north. The wasteful action is very conspicuous
at Dimlington Height, the loftiest point in Holderness, where the beacon
stands on a cliff 146 feet above high water, the whole being composed
of clay, with pebbles scattered through it.399 "For many years," says
Professor Phillips, "the rate at which the cliffs recede from Bridlington
to Spurn, a distance of thirty-six miles, has been found by measurement
to equal on an average two and a quarter yards annually, which, upon
thirty-six miles of coast, would amount to about thirty acres a year.
At this rate, the coast, the mean height of which above the sea is about
forty feet, has lost one mile in breadth since the Norman Conquest, and
more than two miles since the occupation of York (Eboracum) by the
Romans."400 The extent of this denudation, as estimated by the number
of cubic feet of matter removed annually, will be again spoken of in
chapter 22.
In the old maps of Yorkshire, we find spots, now sand-banks in the sea,
marked as the ancient sites of the towns and villages of Auburn, Hartburn,
and Hyde. "Of Hyde," says Pennant, "only the tradition is
left; and near the village of Hornsea, a street called Hornsea Beck has
long since been swallowed."401 Owthorne and its church have also been
in great part destroyed, and the village of Kilnsea; but these places
are now removed farther inland. The annual rate of encroachment at
Owthorne for several years preceding 1830, is stated to have averaged
about four yards. Not unreasonable fears are entertained that at some
future time the Spurn Point will become an island, and that the ocean,
entering into the estuary of the Humber, will cause great devastation.402
Pennant, after speaking of the silting up of some ancient ports in that
estuary, observes, "But, in return, the sea has made most ample reprisals;
the site, and even the very names of several places, once towns
of note upon the Humber, are now only recorded in history; and
Ravensper was at one time a rival to Hull (Madox, Ant. Exch. i. 422),
and a port so very considerable in 1332, that Edward Baliol and the
confederated English barons sailed from hence to invade Scotland; and
Henry IV., in 1399, made choice of this port to land at, to effect the
deposal of Richard II.; yet the whole of this has long since been devoured
by the merciless ocean; extensive sands, dry at low water, are
to be seen in their stead."403
Pennant describes Spurn Head as a promontory in the form of a
sickle, and says the land, for some miles to the north, was "perpetually
preyed on by the fury of the German Sea, which devours whole acres
at a time, and exposes on the shores considerable quantities of beautiful
amber."
Lincolnshire.—The maritime district of Lincolnshire consists chiefly
of lands that lie below the level of the sea, being protected by embankments.
305
Some of the fens were embanked and drained by the Romans;
but after their departure the sea returned, and large tracts were covered
with beds of silt, containing marine shells, now again converted into
productive lands. Many dreadful catastrophes are recorded by incursions
of the sea, whereby several parishes have been at different times
overwhelmed.
Norfolk.—The decay of the cliffs of Norfolk and Suffolk is incessant.
At Hunstanton, on the north, the undermining of the lower arenaceous
beds at the foot of the cliff, causes masses of red and white chalk to be
precipitated from above. Between Hunstanton and Weybourne, low
hills, or dunes, of blown sand, are formed along the shore, from fifty to
sixty feet high. They are composed of dry sand, bound in a compact
mass by the long creeping roots of the plant called Marram (Arundo
arenaria). Such is the present set of the tides, that the harbors of
Clay, Wells, and other places are securely defended by these barriers;
affording a clear proof that it is not the strength of the material at particular
points that determines whether the sea shall be progressive or
stationary, but the general contour of the coast.
The waves constantly undermine the low chalk cliffs, covered with
sand and clay, between Weybourne and Sherringham, a certain portion
of them being annually removed. At the latter town I ascertained, in
1829, some facts which throw light on the rate at which the sea gains
upon the land. It was computed, when the present inn was built, in
1805, that it would require seventy years for the sea to reach the spot:
the mean loss of land being calculated, from previous observations, to
be somewhat less than one yard, annually. The distance between the
house and the sea was fifty yards; but no allowance was made for the
slope of the ground being from the sea, in consequence of which the
waste was naturally accelerated every year, as the cliff grew lower,
there being at each succeeding period less matter to remove when portions
of equal area fell down. Between the years 1824 and 1829, no
less than seventeen yards were swept away, and only a small garden
was then left between the building and the sea. There was, in 1829,
a depth of twenty feet (sufficient to float a frigate) at one point in the
harbor of that port, where, only forty-eight years before, there stood a
cliff fifty feet high, with houses upon it! If once in half a century an
equal amount of change were produced suddenly by the momentary
shock of an earthquake, history would be filled with records of such wonderful
revolutions of the earth's surface; but, if the conversion of high
land into deep sea be gradual, it excites only local attention. The flagstaff
of the Preventive Service station, on the south side of this harbor,
was thrice removed inland between the years 1814 and 1829, in consequence
of the advance of the sea.
Farther to the south we find cliffs, composed, like those of Holderness
before mentioned, of alternating strata of blue clay, gravel, loam,
and fine sand. Although they sometimes exceed 300 feet in height, the
havoc made on the coast is most formidable. The whole site of ancient
306
Cromer now forms part of the German Ocean, the inhabitants having
gradually retreated inland to their present situation, from whence the
sea still threatens to dislodge them. In the winter of 1825, a fallen
mass was precipitated from near the lighthouse, which covered twelve
acres, extending far into the sea, the cliffs being 250 feet in height.404
The undermining by springs has sometimes caused large portions of the
upper part of the cliffs, with houses still standing upon them, to give
way, so that it is impossible, by erecting breakwaters at the base of the
cliffs, permanently to ward off the danger.
Fig. 31.
Tower of the buried Church of Eccles, Norfolk, A. D. 1839.
The inland slope of the hills of blown sand is shown in this view, with the lighthouse of
Hasborough in the distance.
On the same coast, says Mr. R. C. Taylor, the ancient villages of
Shipden, Wimpwell, and Eccles have disappeared; several manors and
large portions of neighboring parishes having, piece after piece, been
swallowed up; nor has there been any intermission, from time immemorial,
in the ravages of the sea along a line of coast twenty miles in
length, in which these places stood.405 Of Eccles, however, a monument
still remains in the rained tower of the old church, which is half
buried in the dunes of sand within a few paces (60?) of the sea-beach
(fig. 31). So early as 1605 the inhabitants petitioned James I. for a
reduction of taxes, as 300 acres of land, and all their houses, save fourteen,
had then been destroyed by the sea. Not one half that number
of acres now remains in the parish, and hills of blown sand now occupy
the site of the houses which were still extant in 1605. When I visited
the spot in 1839, the sea was fast encroaching on the sand-hills, and
had laid open on the beach the foundations of a house fourteen yards
square, the upper part of which had evidently been pulled down before
it had been buried under sand. The body of the church has also been
long buried, but the tower still remains visible.
307
M. E. de Beaumont has suggested that sand-dunes in Holland and
other countries may serve as natural chronometers, by which the date
of the existing continents may be ascertained. The sands, he says, are
continually blown inland by the force of the winds, and by observing
the rate of their march we may calculate the period when the movement
commenced.406 But the example just given will satisfy every geologist
that we cannot ascertain the starting-point of dunes, all coasts
being liable to waste, and the shores of the Low Countries in particular,
being not only exposed to inroads of the sea, but, as M. de Beaumont
himself has well shown, having even in historical times undergone a
change of level. The dunes may indeed, in some cases, be made use
of as chronometers, to enable us to assign a minimum of antiquity to
existing coast-lines; but this test must be applied with great caution, so
variable is the rate at which the sands may advance into the interior.
Hills of blown sand, between Eccles and Winterton, have barred up
and excluded the tide for many hundred years from the mouths of
several small estuaries; but there are records of nine breaches, from 20
to 120 yards wide, having been made through these, by which immense
damage was done to the low grounds in the interior. A few miles
south of Happisburgh, also, are hills of blown sand, which extend to
Yarmouth. These dunes afford a temporary protection to the coast,
and an inland cliff, about a mile long, at Winterton, shows clearly that
at that point the sea must have penetrated formerly farther than at
present.
Silting up of estuaries/—At Yarmouth, the sea has not advanced
upon the sands in the slightest degree since the reign of Elizabeth. In
the time of the Saxons, a great estuary extended as far as Norwich,
which city, is represented; even in the thirteenth and fourteenth centuries,
as "situated on the banks of an arm of the sea." The sands
whereon Yarmouth is built, first became firm and habitable ground
about the year 1008, from which time a line of dunes has gradually increased
in height and breadth, stretching across the whole entrance of
the ancient estuary, and obstructing the ingress of the tides so completely,
that they are only admitted by the narrow passage which the
river keeps open, and which has gradually shifted several miles to the
south. The ordinary tides at the river's mouth rise, at present, only to
the height, of three or four feet, the spring tides to about eight or nine.
By the exclusion of the sea, thousands of acres in the interior have
become cultivated lands; and, exclusive of smaller pools, upwards of
sixty freshwater lakes have been formed, varying in depth from fifteen
to thirty feet, and in extent from one acre to twelve hundred.407 The
Yare, and other rivers, frequently communicate with these sheets of
water; and thus they are liable to be filled up gradually with lacustrine
and fluviatile deposits, and to be converted into land covered with
308
forests. Yet it must not be imagined, that the acquisition of new land
fit for cultivation in Norfolk and Suffolk indicates any permanent growth
of the eastern limits of our island to compensate its reiterated losses.
No delta can form on such a shore.
Immediately off Yarmouth, and parallel to the shore, is a great range
of sand-banks, the shape of which varies slowly from year to year, and
often suddenly after great storms. Captain Hewitt, R. N., found in
these banks, in 1836, a broad channel sixty-five feet deep, where there
was only a depth of four feet during a prior survey in 1822. The sea
had excavated to the depth of sixty feet in the course of fourteen years,
or perhaps a shorter period. The new channel thus formed serves at
present (1838), for the entrance of ships into Yarmouth Roads; and
the magnitude of this change shows how easily a new set of the waves
and currents might endanger the submergence of the land gained within
the ancient estuary of the Yare.
That great banks should be thrown across the mouths of estuaries on
our eastern coast, where there is not a large body of river-water to
maintain an open channel, is perfectly intelligible, when we bear in mind
that the marine current, sweeping along the coast, is charged with the
materials of wasting cliffs, and ready to form a bar anywhere the instant
its course is interrupted or checked by any opposing stream. The mouth
of the Yare has been, within the last five centuries, diverted about four
miles to the south. In like manner it is evident that, at some remote
period, the river Alde entered the sea at Aldborough, until its ancient
outlet was barred up and at length transferred to a point no less than
ten miles distant to the southwest. In this case, ridges of sand and
shingle, like those of Lowestoff Ness, which will be described by and
by, have been thrown up between the river and the sea; and an ancient
sea-cliff is to be seen now inland.
It may be asked why the rivers on our east coast are always deflected
southwards, although the tidal current flows alternately from the south
and north? The cause is to be found in the superior force of what is
commonly called "the flood tide from the north," a tidal wave derived
from the Atlantic, a small part of which passes eastward up the English
Channel, and through the Straits of Dover and then northwards, while
the principal body of water, moving much more rapidly in a more open
sea, on the western side of Britain, first passes the Orkneys, and then
turning, flows down between Norway and Scotland, and sweeps with
great velocity along our eastern coast. It is well known that the highest
tides on this coast are occasioned by a powerful northwest wind,
which raises the eastern part of the Atlantic, and causes it to pour a
greater volume of water into the German Ocean. This circumstance of
a violent off-shore wind being attended with a rise of the waters, instead
of a general retreat of the sea, naturally excites the wonder of the inhabitants
of our coast. In many districts they look with confidence for
a rich harvest of that valuable manure, the sea-weed, when the north-westerly
gales prevail, and are rarely disappointed.
Fig. 32.
Map of Lowestoff Ness, Suffolk.408
a, a. The dotted lines express a series of sand and shingle, forming the extremity of the triangular
space called the Ness.
b, b, b. The dark line represents the inland cliff on which the town of Lowestoff stands, between
which and the sea is the Ness.
309Coast of Suffolk.—The cliffs of Suffolk, to which we next proceed,
are somewhat less elevated than those of Norfolk, but composed of
similar alternations of clay, sand, and gravel. From Gorleston in Suffolk,
to within a few miles north of Lowestoff, the cliffs are slowly
undermined. Near the last-mentioned town, there is an inland cliff
about sixty feet high, the sloping talus of which is covered with turf
and heath. Between the cliff and the sea is a low flat tract of sand
called the Ness, nearly three miles long, and for the most part out of
reach of the highest tides. The point of the Ness projects from the
base of the original cliff to the distance of 660 yards. This accession
of land, says Mr. Taylor, has been effected at distinct and distant intervals,
by the influence of currents running between the land and a shoal
about a mile off Lowestoff, called the Holm Sand. The lines of growth
in the Ness are indicated by a series of concentric ridges or embankments
inclosing limited areas, and several of these ridges have been
formed within the observation of persons now living. A rampart of
heavy materials is first thrown up to an unusual altitude by some
extraordinary tide, attended with a violent gale. Subsequent tides
extend the base of this high bank of shingle, and the interstices are
then filled with sand blown from the beach. The Arundo and other
marine plants by degrees obtain a footing; and creeping along the
ridge, give solidity to the mass, and form in some cases a matted covering
of turf. Meanwhile another mound is forming externally, which
by the like process rises and gives protection to the first. If the sea
forces its way through one of the external and incomplete mounds, the
breach is soon repaired. After a while the marine plants within the
areas inclosed by these embankments are succeeded by a better species
of herbage affording good pasturage, and the sands become sufficiently
firm to support buildings.
Destruction of Dunwich by the sea.—Of the gradual destruction of
Dunwich, once the most considerable seaport on this coast, we have
many authentic records. Gardner, in his history of that borough,
310
published in 1754, shows, by reference to documents, beginning with
Doomsday Book, that the cliffs at Dunwich, Southwold, Eastern, and
Pakefield, have been always subject to wear away. At Dunwich, in
particular, two tracts of land which had been taxed in the eleventh century,
in the time of King Edward the Confessor, are mentioned in the
Conqueror's survey, made but a few years afterwards, as having been
devoured by the sea. The losses, at a subsequent period, of a monastery,—at
another of several churches,—afterwards of the old port,—then
of four hundred houses at once,—of the church of St. Leonard,
the high-road, town-hall, jail, and many other buildings, are mentioned,
with the dates when they perished. It is stated that, in the
sixteenth century, not one-quarter of the town was left standing; yet
the inhabitants retreating inland, the name was preserved, as has been
the case with many other ports when their ancient site has been blotted
out. There is, however, a church of considerable antiquity still
standing, the last of twelve mentioned in some records. In 1740, the
laying open of the churchyard of St. Nicholas and St. Francis, in the
sea-cliffs, is well described by Gardner, with the coffins and skeletons
exposed to view—some lying on the beach, and rocked

"In cradle of the rude imperious surge."

Of these cemeteries no remains can now be seen. Ray also says, "that
ancient writings make mention of a wood a mile and a half to the east
of Dunwich, the site of which must at present be so far within the
sea."409 This city, once so flourishing and populous, is now a small
village, with about twenty houses, and one hundred inhabitants.
There is an old tradition, "that the tailors sat in their shops at
Dunwich, and saw the ships in Yarmouth Bay;" but when we consider
how far the coast at Lowestoff Ness projects between these places,
we cannot give credit to the tale, which, nevertheless, proves how much
the inroads of the sea in times of old had prompted men of lively imagination
to indulge their taste for the marvellous.
Gardner's description of the cemeteries laid open by the waves reminds
us of the scene which has been so well depicted by Bewick,410
and of which numerous points on the same coast might have suggested
the idea. On the verge of a cliff, which the sea has undermined, are
represented the unshaken tower and western end of an abbey. The
eastern aisle is gone, and the pillars of the cloister are soon to follow.
The waves have almost isolated the promontory, and invaded the cemetery,
where they have made sport with the mortal relics, and thrown
up a skull upon the beach. In the foreground is seen a broken tombstone,
erected, as its legend tells, "to perpetuate the memory"—of
one whose name is obliterated, as is that of the county for which he
was "Custos Rotulorum." A cormorant is perched on the monument,
311
defiling it, as if to remind some moralizer like Hamlet, of "the base
uses" to which things sacred may be turned. Had this excellent artist
desired to satirize certain popular theories of geology, he might have
inscribed the stone to the memory of some philosopher who taught
"the permanency of existing continents"—"the era of repose"—"the
impotence of modern causes."
The incursions of the sea at Aldborough, were formerly very destructive,
and this borough is known to have been once situated a quarter of
a mile east of the present shore. The inhabitants continued to build
farther inland, till they arrived at the extremity of their property, and
then the town decayed greatly; but two sand-banks, thrown up at a
short distance, now afford a temporary safeguard to the coast. Between
these banks and the present shore, where the current now flows, the
sea is twenty-four feet deep on the spot where the town formerly stood.
Essex.—Harwich is said to have owed its rise to the destruction of
Orwell, a town which stood on the spot now called "the west rocks,"
and was overwhelmed by an inroad of the sea since the Conquest. Apprehensions
have been entertained that the isthmus on which Harwich
stands may at no remote period become an island, for the sea may be
expected to make a breach near Lower Dover Court, where Beacon
Cliff is composed of horizontal beds of London clay containing septaria.
It had wasted away considerably between the years 1829 and 1838, at
both which periods I examined this coast. In that short interval several
gardens and many houses had been swept into the sea, and in April,
1838, a whole street was threatened with destruction. The advance of
the sea is much accelerated by the traffic carried on in septaria, which
are shipped off for cement as fast as they fall down upon the beach.
These stones, if allowed to remain in heaps on the shore, would break
the force of the waves and retard the conversion of the peninsula into an
island, an event which might be followed by the destruction of the town
of Harwich. Captain Washington, R. N., ascertained in 1847, that
Beacon Cliff, above mentioned, which is about fifty feet high, had given
way at the rate of forty feet in forty-seven years, between 1709 and
1756; eighty feet between 1756 and 1804; and three hundred and
fifty feet between the latter period and 1841; showing a rapidly accelerated
rate of destruction.411
Among other losses it is recorded that, since the year 1807, a field
called the Vicar's Field, which belonged to the living of Harwich, has
been overwhelmed;412 and in the year 1820 there was a considerable
space between the battery at Harwich, built in the beginning of the
present century, and the sea; part of the fortification had been swept
away in 1829, and the rest then overhung the water.
At Walton Naze, in the same county, the cliffs, composed of London
clay, capped by the shelly sands of the crag, reach the height of about
312
100 feet, and are annually undermined by the waves. The old churchyard
of Walton has been washed away, and the cliffs to the south are
constantly disappearing.
Kent.—Isle of Sheppey.—On the coast bounding the estuary of the
Thames, there are numerous examples both of the gain and loss of land.
The Isle of Sheppey, which is now about six miles long by four in
breadth, is composed of London clay. The cliffs on the north, which
are from sixty to eighty feet high, decay rapidly, fifty acres having been
lost in twenty years, between 1810 and 1830. The church at Minster,
now near the coast, is said to have been in the middle of the island in
1780; and if the present rate of destruction should continue, we might
calculate the period, and that not a very remote one, when the whole
island will be annihilated. On the coast of the mainland, to the east of
Sheppey, is Herne Bay: a place still retaining the name of a bay, although
it is no longer appropriate, as the waves and currents have
swept away the ancient headlands. There was formerly a small promontory
in the line of the shoals where the present pier is built, by which
the larger bay was divided into two, called the Upper and Lower.413
Fig. 33.
View of Reculver Church, taken in the year 1781.
1. Isle of Sheppey. 2. Ancient chapel now destroyed. The cottage between this chapel and the
cliff was demolished by the sea, in 1782.
Still farther east stands the church of Reculver, upon a cliff composed
of clay and sand, about twenty-five feet high. Reculver (Regulvium)
was an important military station in the time of the Romans, and appears,
from Leland's account, to have been, so late as Henry VIII.'s
reign, nearly one mile distant from the sea. In the "Gentleman's Magazine,"
there is a view of it, taken in 1781, which still represents a considerable
space as intervening between the north wall of the churchyard
and the cliff.414 Sometime before the year 1780, the waves had reached
the site of the ancient Roman camp or fortification, the walls of which
313
had continued for several years after they were undermined to overhang
the sea, being firmly cemented into one mass. They were eighty yards
nearer the sea than the church, and they are spoken of in the "Topographica
Britannica," in the year 1780, as having recently fallen down.
In 1804, part of the churchyard with some adjoining houses was washed
away, and the ancient church, with its two spires, was dismantled and
abandoned as a place of worship, but kept in repair as a landmark well
known to mariners. I visited the spot in June, 1851, and saw human
bones and part of a wooden coffin projecting from the cliff, near the
top. The whole building would probably have been swept away long
ere this, had not the force of the waves been checked by an artificial
causeway of stones and large wooden piles driven into the sands on the
beach to break the force of the waves.
Fig. 34.
Reculver Church, in 1834.
Isle of Thanet.—The isle of Thanet was, in the time of the Romans,
separated from the rest of Kent by a navigable channel, through which
the Roman fleets sailed on their way to and from London. Bede describes
this small estuary as being, in the beginning of the eighth
century, three furlongs in breadth; and it is supposed that it began to
grow shallow about the period of the Norman conquest. It was so far
silted up in the year 1485, that an act was then obtained to build a
bridge across it; and it has since become marsh land with small streams
running through it. On the coast, Bedlam Farm, belonging to the
hospital of that name, lost eight acres in the twenty years preceding
314
1830, the land being composed of chalk from forty to fifty feet above
the level of the sea. It has been computed that the average waste of
the cliff between the North Foreland and the Reculvers, a distance of
about eleven miles, is not less than two feet per annum. The chalk
cliffs on the south of Thanet, between Ramsgate and Pegwell Bay, have
on an average lost three feet per annum for the last ten years (preceding
1830).
Goodwin Sands.—The Goodwin Sands lie opposite this part of the
Kentish coast. They are about ten miles in length, and are in some
parts three, and in others seven, miles distant from the shore; and, for
a certain space, are laid bare at low water. That they are a remnant of
land, and not "a mere accumulation of sea sand," as Rennell imagined,415
may be presumed from the fact that, when the erection of a lighthouse
on this shoal was in contemplation by the Trinity Board in the year
1817, it was found, by borings, that the bank consisted of fifteen feet
of sand, resting on blue clay; and, by subsequent borings, the subjacent
chalk has been reached. An obscure tradition has come down to us,
that the estates of Earl Goodwin, the father of Harold, who died in the
year 1053, were situated here, and some have conjectured that they
were overwhelmed by the flood mentioned in the Saxon chronicle, sub
anno 1099. The last remains of an island, consisting, like Sheppey, of
clay, may perhaps have been carried away about that time.
Fig. 35.
Shakspeare's Cliff in 1836, seen from the northeast.
There are other records of waste in the county of Kent, as at Deal;
and at Dover, where Shakspeare's Cliff, composed entirely of chalk, has
suffered greatly, and continually diminishes in height, the slope of the
hill being towards the land. (See fig. 35.) There was an immense
landslip from this cliff in 1810, by which Dover was shaken as if by an
315
earthquake, and a still greater one in 1772.416 We may suppose, therefore,
that the view from the top of the precipice in the year 1600, when
the tragedy of King Lear was written, was more "fearful and dizzy"
than it is now. The best antiquarian authorities are agreed, that Dover
Harbor was formerly an estuary, the sea flowing up a valley between
the chalk hills. The remains found in different excavations confirm the
description of the spot given by Cæsar and Antoninus, and there is
clear historical evidence to prove that at an early period there was no
shingle at all at Dover.417
Straits of Dover.—In proceeding from the northern parts of the
German Ocean towards the Straits of Dover, the water becomes gradually
more shallow, so that, in the distance of about two hundred
leagues, we pass from a depth of 120 to that of 58, 38, 18, and even
less than 2 fathoms. The shallowest part follows a line drawn between
Romney Marsh and Boulogne. From this point the English Channel
again deepens progressively as we proceed westward, so that the Straits
of Dover may be said to part two seas.418
Whether England was formerly united with France has often been
a favorite subject of speculation. So early as 1605 our countryman
Verstegan, in his "Antiquities of the English Nation," observed that
many preceding writers had maintained this opinion, but without supporting
it by any weighty reasons. He accordingly endeavors himself
to confirm it by various arguments, the principal of which are, first, the
proximity and identity of the composition of the opposite cliffs and
shores of Albion and Gallia, which, whether flat and sandy, or steep
and chalky, correspond exactly with each other; secondly the occurrence
of a submarine ridge, called "our Lady's Sand," extending from
shore to shore at no great depth, and which, from its composition,
appears to be the original basis of the isthmus; thirdly, the identity of
the noxious animals in France and England, which could neither have
swum across, nor have been introduced by man. Thus no one, he says,
would have imported wolves, therefore "these wicked beasts did of
themselves pass over." He supposes the ancient isthmus to have been
about six English miles in breadth, composed entirely of chalk and flint,
and in some places of no great height above the sea-level. The operation
of the waves and tides, he says, would have been more powerful
when the straits were narrower, and even now they are destroying cliffs
composed of similar materials. He suggests the possible co-operation
of earthquakes; and when we consider how many submarine forests
skirt the southern and eastern shores of England, and that there are
raised beaches at many points above the sea-level, containing fossil
shells of recent species, it seems reasonable to suppose that such upward
316
now in progress in Sweden and Greenland, may have greatly assisted the
denuding force of "the ocean stream," Ποταμοιο μεγα σθενος Ωχεανοτο.
Folkstone.—At Folkstone, the sea undermines the chalk and subjacent
strata. About the year 1716 there was a remarkable sinking of a
tract of land near the sea, so that houses became visible from certain
points at sea, and from particular spots on the sea cliffs, from whence
they could not be seen previously. In the description of this subsidence
in the Phil. Trans. 1716, it is said, "that the land consisted of a
solid stony mass (chalk), resting on wet clay (gault), so that it slid
forwards towards the sea, just as a ship is launched on tallowed planks."
It is also stated that, within the memory of persons then living, the
cliff there had been washed away to the extent of ten rods.
Encroachments of the sea at Hythe are also on record; but between
this point and Rye there has been a gain of land within the times of
history; the rich level tract called Romney Marsh, or Dungeness, about
ten miles in width and five in breadth, and formed of silt, having received
great accession. It has been necessary, however, to protect it
from the sea, from the earliest periods, by embankments, the towns of
Lydd and Romney being the only parts of the marsh above the level of
the highest tides.419 Mr. Redman has cited numerous old charts and
trustworthy authorities to prove that the average annual increase of the
promontory of shingle called Dungeness amounted for two centuries,
previous to 1844, to nearly six yards. Its progress, however, has
fluctuated during that period; for between 1689 and 1794, a term of
105 years, the rate was as much as 8-1/4 yards per annum.420 It is ascertained
that the shingle is derived from the westward. Whether the
pebbles are stopped by the meeting of the tide from the north flowing
through the Straits of Dover, with that which comes up the Channel
from the west, as was formerly held, or by the check given to the tidal
current by the waters of the Rother, as some maintain, is still a disputed
question.
Rye, situated to the south of Romney Marsh, was once destroyed by
the sea, but it is now two miles distant from it. The neighboring town
of Winchelsea was destroyed in the reign of Edward I., the mouth of
the Rother stopped up, and the river diverted into another channel.
In its old bed, an ancient vessel, apparently a Dutch merchantman,
was found about the year 1824. It was built entirely of oak, and much
blackened.421 Large quantities of hazel-nuts, peat, and wood are found
in digging in Romney Marsh.
South coast of England.—Westward of Hastings, or of St. Leonard's,
the shore line has been giving way as far as Pevensey Bay, where formerly
there existed a haven now entirely blocked up by shingle. The
317
degradation has equalled for a series of years seven feet per annum in
some places, and several martello towers had in consequence, before
1851, been removed by the Ordnance.422 At the promontory of Beachy
Head a mass of chalk, three hundred feet in length, and from seventy
to eighty in breadth, fell in the year 1813 with a tremendous crash;
and similar slips have since been frequent.423
About a mile to the west of the town of Newhaven, the remains of an
ancient intrenchment are seen on the brow of Castle Hill. This earthwork,
supposed to be Roman, was evidently once of considerable extent
and of an oval form, but the greater part has been cut away by the sea.
The cliffs, which are undermined here, are high; more than one hundred
feet of chalk being covered by tertiary clay and sand, from sixty to
seventy feet in thickness. In a few centuries the last vestiges of the
plastic clay formation on the southern borders of the chalk of the South
Downs on this coast will probably be annihilated, and future geologists
will learn, from historical documents, the ancient geographical boundaries
of this group of strata in that direction. On the opposite side of the
estuary of the Ouse, on the east of Newhaven harbor, a bed of shingle,
composed of chalk flints derived from the waste of the adjoining cliffs,
had accumulated at Seaford for several centuries. In the great storm
of November, 1824, this bank was entirely swept away, and the town
of Seaford inundated. Another great beach of shingle is now forming
from fresh materials.
The whole coast of Sussex has been incessantly encroached upon by
the sea from time immemorial; and, although sudden inundations only,
which overwhelmed fertile or inhabited tracts, are noticed in history, the
records attest an extraordinary amount of loss. During a period of no
more than eighty years, there are notices of about twenty inroads, in
which tracts of land of from twenty to four hundred acres in extent were
overwhelmed at once, the value of the tithes being mentioned in the
Taxatio Ecclesiastica.424 In the reign of Elizabeth, the town of Brighton
was situated on that tract where the chain pier now extends into the sea.
In the year 1665, twenty-two tenements had been destroyed under the
cliff. At that period there still remained under the cliff 113 tenements,
the whole of which were overwhelmed in 1703 and 1705. No traces of
the ancient town are now perceptible, yet there is evidence that the sea
has merely resumed its ancient position at the base of the cliffs, the site
of the whole town having been merely a beach abandoned by the ocean
for ages.
Hampshire.—Isle of Wight.—It would be endless to allude to all
the localities on the Sussex and Hampshire coasts where the land has
given way; but I may point out the relation which the geological structure
of the Isle of Wight bears to its present shape, as attesting that the
318
coast owes its outline to the continued action of the sea. Through the
middle of the island runs a high ridge of chalk strata, in a vertical position,
and in a direction east and west. This chalk forms the projecting
promontory of Culver Cliff on the east, and of the Needles on the west;
while Sandown Bay on the one side, and Compton Bay on the other,
have been hollowed out of the softer sands and argillaceous strata, which
are inferior, in geological position, to the chalk.
The same phenomena are repeated in the Isle of Purbeck, where the
line of vertical chalk forms the projecting promontory of Handfast
Point; and Swanage Bay marks the deep excavation made by the waves
in the softer strata, corresponding to those of Sandown Bay.
Hurst Castle bank—progressive motion of sea beaches.—Although the
loose pebbles and grains of sand composing any given line of sea-beach
are carried sometimes one way, sometimes another, they have, nevertheless,
an ultimate motion in one particular direction.425 Their progress,
for example, on the south coast of England, is from west to east, which
is owing partly to the action of the waves driven eastwards by the prevailing
wind, and partly to the current, or the motion of the general
body of water caused by the tides and winds. The force of the waves
gives motion to pebbles which the velocity of the currents alone would
be unable to carry forwards; but as the pebbles are finally reduced to
sand or mud, by continual attrition, they are brought within the influence
of a current; and this cause must determine the course which the main
body of matter derived from wasting cliffs will eventually take.
It appears, from the observations of Mr. Palmer and others, that if
a pier or groin be erected anywhere on our southern or southeastern
coast to stop the progress of the beach, a heap of shingle soon collects
on the western side of such artificial barriers. The pebbles continue to
accumulate till they rise as high as the pier or groin, after which they
pour over in great numbers during heavy gales.426
The western entrance of the Channel, called the Solent, is crossed for
more than two-thirds of its width by the shingle-bank of Hurst Castle,
which is about two miles long, seventy yards broad, and twelve feet
high, presenting an inclined plane to the west. This singular bar consists
of a bed of rounded chalk flints, resting on a submarine argillaceous
base. The flints and a few other pebbles, intermixed, are derived from
the waste of Hordwell, and other cliffs to the westward, where tertiary
strata, capped with a covering of broken chalk flints, from five to fifty
feet thick, are rapidly undermined. In the great storm of November,
1824, this bank of shingle was moved bodily forwards for forty yards
towards the northeast; and certain piles, which served to mark the
boundaries of two manors, were found after the storm on the opposite
side of the bar. At the same time many acres of pasture land were
319
covered by shingle, on the farm of Westover, near Lymington. But the
bar was soon restored in its old position by pebbles drifted from the
west; and it appears from ancient maps that it has preserved the same
general outline and position for centuries.427
Mr. Austen remarks that, as a general rule, it is only when high
tides concur with a gale of wind, that the sea reaches the base of cliffs
so as to undermine them and throw down earth and stone. But the
waves are perpetually employed in abrading and fashioning the materials
already strewed over the beach. Much of the gravel and shingle
is always travelling up and down, between high-water mark and a slight
depth below the level of the lowest tides, and occasionally the materials
are swept away and carried into deeper water. Owing to these movements
every portion of our southern coast may be seen at one time or
other in the condition of bare rock. Yet other beds of sand and shingle
soon collect, and, although composed of new materials, invariably exhibit
on the same spots precisely similar characters.428
The cliffs between Hurst Shingle Bar and Christchurch are undermined
continually, the sea having often encroached for a series of years
at the rate of a yard annually. Within the memory of persons now
living, it has been necessary thrice to remove the coast-road farther inland.
The tradition, therefore, is probably true, that the church of
Hordwell was once in the middle of that parish, although now (1830)
very near the sea. The promontory of Christchurch Head gives
way slowly. It is the only point between Lymington and Poole Harbor,
in Dorsetshire, where any hard stony masses occur in the cliffs.
Five layers of large ferruginous concretions, somewhat like the septaria
of the London clay, have occasioned a resistance at this point, to which
we may ascribe this headland. In the mean time, the waves have cut
deeply into the soft sands and loam of Poole Bay; and, after severe
frosts, great landslips take place, which by degrees become enlarged
into narrow ravines, or chines, as they are called, with vertical sides.
One of these chines, near Boscomb, has been deepened twenty feet
within a few years. At the head of each there is a spring, the waters
of which have been chiefly instrumental in producing these narrow excavations,
which are sometimes from 100 to 150 feet deep.
Isle of Portland.—The peninsulas of Purbeck and Portland are continually
wasting away. In the latter, the soft argillaceous substratum
(Kimmeridge clay) hastens the dilapidation of the superincumbent mass
of limestone.
In 1655 the cliffs adjoining the principal quarries in Portland gave
way to the extent of one hundred yards, and fell into the sea; and in
December, 1734, a slide to the extent of 150 yards occurred on the
east side of the isle, by which several skeletons buried between slabs of
stone, were discovered. But a much more memorable occurrence of
320
this nature, in 1792, occasioned probably by the undermining of the cliffs,
is thus described in Hutchin's History of Dorsetshire:—"Early in the
morning the road was observed to crack: this continued increasing, and
before two o'clock the ground had sunk several feet, and was in one
continued motion, but attended with no other noise than what was occasioned
by the separation of the roots and brambles, and now and then a
falling rock. At night it seemed to stop a little, but soon moved again;
and, before morning, the ground from the top of the cliff to the waterside
had sunk in some places fifty feet perpendicular. The extent of
ground that moved was about a mile and a quarter from north to south,
and 600 yards from east to west."
Formation of the Chesil Bank.—Portland is connected with the mainland
by the Chesil Bank, a ridge of shingle about seventeen miles in
length, and, in most places, nearly a quarter of a mile in breadth. The
pebbles forming this immense barrier are chiefly siliceous, all loosely
thrown together, and rising to the height of from twenty to thirty feet
above the ordinary high-water mark; and at the southeastern end,
which is nearest the Isle of Portland, where the pebbles are largest,
forty feet. The fundamental rocks whereon the shingle rests are found
at the depth of a few yards only below the level of the sea. The formation
of that part of the bar which attaches Portland to the mainland
may have been due to an original shoal or reef, or to the set of the
tides in the narrow channel, by which the course of the pebbles, which
are always coming from the west, has been arrested. It is a singular
fact that, throughout the Chesil Bank, the pebbles increase gradually in
size as we proceed southeastward, or as we go farther from the quarter
which supplied them. Had the case been reversed, we should naturally
have attributed the circumstance to the constant wearing down of the
pebbles by friction, as they are rolled along a beach seventeen miles in
length. But the true explanation of the phenomenon is doubtless this:
the tidal current runs strongest from west to east, and its power is
greater in the more open channel or farther from the land. In other
words its force increases southwards, and as the direction of the bank
is from northwest to southeast, the size of the masses coming from
the westward and thrown ashore must always be largest where the
motion of the water is most violent. Colonel Reid states that all calcareous
stones rolled along from the west are soon ground into sand,
and in this form they pass round Portland Island.429
The storm of 1824 burst over the Chesil Bank with great fury, and
the village of Chesilton, built upon its southern extremity, was overwhelmed,
with many of the inhabitants. The same storm carried away
part of the Breakwater at Plymouth, and huge masses of rock, from
two to five tons in weight, were lifted from the bottom of the weather
side, and rolled fairly to the top of the pile. One block of limestone,
321
weighing seven tons, was washed round the western extremity of the
Breakwater, and carried 150 feet.430 The propelling power is derived in
these cases from the breaking of the waves, which run fastest in shallow
water, and for a short space far exceed the most rapid currents in swiftness.
It was in the same month, and also during a spring-tide, that a
great flood is mentioned on the coasts of England, in the year 1099.
Florence of Worcester says, "On the third day of the nones of Nov.
1099, the sea came out upon the shore and buried towns and men very
many, and oxen and sheep innumerable." We also read in the Saxon
Chronicle, for the year 1099, "This year eke on St. Martin's mass day,
the 11th of Novembre, sprung up so much of the sea flood, and so
myckle harm did, as no man minded that it ever afore did, and there
was the ylk day a new moon."
South of the Bill, or southern point of Portland, is a remarkable
shoal in the channel at the depth of seven fathoms, called "the Shambles,"
consisting entirely of rolled and broken shells of Purpura lapillus,
Mytilus edulis, and other species now living. This mass of light materials
is always in motion, varying in height from day to day, and yet
the shoal remains constant.
Dorsetshire.—Devonshire.—At Lyme Regis, in Dorsetshire, the
"Church Cliffs," as they are called, consisting of lias about one hundred
feet in height, gradually fell away at the rate of one yard a year,
from 1800 to 1829.431
Fig. 36.
Landslip, near Axmouth, Dec. 1839. (Rev. W. D. Conybeare.)
A. Tract of Downs still remaining at their original level.
B. New ravine.
C, D. Sunk and fractured strip united to A, before the convulsion.
D, E. Bendon undercliff as before, but more fissured, and thrust forward about fifty feet, towards
the sea.
F. Pyramidal crag, sunk from seventy to twenty feet in height.
G. New reef upheaved from the sea.
An extraordinary landslip occurred on the 24th of December, 1839,
on the coast between Lyme Regis and Axmouth, which has been described
by the Rev. W. D. Conybeare, to whose kindness I am indebted
for the accompanying section, fig. 36. The tract of downs ranging
322
there along the coast is capped by chalk (h), which rests on sandstone,
alternating with chert (i), beneath which is more than 100 feet of loose
sand (k), with concretions at the bottom, and belonging like i to the
green-sand formation; the whole of the above masses, h, i, k, reposing
on retentive beds of clay (l), belonging to the lias, which shelves towards
the sea. Numerous springs issuing from the loose sand (k), have
gradually removed portions of it, and thus undermined the superstratum,
so as to have caused subsidences at former times, and to have produced
a line of undercliff between D and E. In 1839 an excessively
wet season had saturated all the rocks with moisture, so as to increase
the weight of the incumbent mass, from which the support had already
been withdrawn by the action of springs. Thus the superstrata were
precipitated into hollows prepared for them, and the adjacent masses of
partially undermined rock, to which the movement was communicated,
were made to slide down on a slippery basis of watery sand towards the
sea. These causes gave rise to a convulsion, which began on the morning
of the 24th of December, with a crashing noise; and, on the evening
of the same day, fissures were seen opening in the ground, and
the walls of tenements rending and sinking, until a deep chasm or
ravine, B, was formed, extending nearly three-quarters of a mile in
length, with a depth of from 100 to 150 feet, and a breadth exceeding
240 feet. At the bottom of this deep gulf lie fragments of the original
surface thrown together in the wildest confusion. In consequence
of lateral movements, the tract intervening between the new fissure and
the sea, including the ancient undercliff, was fractured, and the whole
line of sea-cliff carried bodily forwards for many yards. "A remarkable
pyramidal crag, F, off Culverhole Point, which lately formed a distinguishing
landmark, has sunk from a height of about seventy to twenty
feet, and the main cliff, E, before more than fifty feet distant from
this insulated crag, is now brought almost close to it. This motion of
the sea-cliff has produced a farther effect, which may rank among the
most striking phenomena of this catastrophe. The lateral pressure of
the descending rocks has urged the neighboring strata, extending beneath
the shingle of the shore, by their state of unnatural condensation,
to burst upwards in a line parallel to the coast—thus an elevated
ridge, G, more than a mile in length, and rising more than forty feet,
covered by a confused assemblage of broken strata, and immense blocks
of rock, invested with sea-weed and corallines, and scattered over with
shells and star-fish, and other productions of the deep, forms an extended
reef in front of the present range of cliffs."432
A full account of this remarkable landslip, with a plan, sections, and
many fine illustrative drawings, was published by Messrs. Conybeare
and Buckland,433 from one of which the annexed cut has been reduced,
fig. 37.
323
Fig. 37.
View of the Axmouth landslip from Great Bindon, looking westward to the Sidmouth hills,
and estuary of the Exe. From an original drawing by Mrs. Buckland.
Cornwall.—Near Penzance, in Cornwall, there is a projecting tongue
of land, called the "Green," formed of granitic sand, from which more
than thirty acres of pasture land have been gradually swept away, in
the course of the last two or three centuries.434 It is also said that St.
Michael's Mount, now an insular rock, was formerly situated in a wood,
several miles from the sea; and its old Cornish name (Caraclowse in
Cowse) signifies, according to Carew, the Hoar Rock in the wood.435
Between the Mount and Newlyn there is seen under the sand, black
vegetable mould, full of hazel-nuts, and the branches, leaves, roots, and
trunks of forest-trees, all of indigenous species. This stratum has been
traced seaward as far as the ebb permits, and many proofs of a submerged
vegetable accumulation, with stumps of trees in the position in
which they grew, have been traced, says Sir Henry De la Beche, round
the shores of Devon, Cornwall, and Western Somerset. The facts not
only indicate a change in the relative level of the sea and land, since
the species of animals and plants were the same as those now living in
this district; but, what is very remarkable, there seems evidence of the
submergence having been effected, in part at least, since the country
was inhabited by man.436
A submarine forest occurring at the mouth of the Parret in Somersetshire,
on the south side of the Bristol Channel, was described by
Mr. L. Horner, in 1815, and its position attributed to subsidence. A
bed of peat is there seen below the level of the sea, and the trunks of
324
large trees, such as the oak and yew, having their roots still diverging
as they grew, and fixed in blue clay.437
Tradition of loss of land in Cornwall.—The oldest historians mention
a tradition in Cornwall, of the submersion of the Lionnesse, a country
said to have stretched from the Land's End to the Scilly Islands.
The tract, if it existed, must have been thirty miles in length, and perhaps
ten in breadth. The land now remaining on either side is from
two hundred to three hundred feet high; the intervening sea about
three hundred feet deep. Although there is no authentic evidence for
this romantic tale, it probably originated in some former inroads of the
Atlantic, accompanying, perhaps, a subsidence of land on this coast.438
West coast of England.—Having now brought together an ample
body of proofs of the destructive operations of the waves, tides, and
currents, on our eastern and southern shores, it will be unnecessary to
enter into details of changes on the western coast, for they present
merely a repetition of the same phenomena, and in general on an inferior
scale. On the borders of the estuary of the Severn the flats of
Somersetshire and Gloucestershire have received enormous accessions,
while, on the other hand, the coast of Cheshire, between the rivers
Mersey and Dee, has lost, since the year 1764, many hundred yards,
and some affirm more than half a mile, by the advance of the sea upon
the abrupt cliffs of red clay and marls. Within the period above mentioned
several lighthouses have been successively abandoned.439 There
are traditions in Pembrokeshire440 and Cardiganshire441 of far greater losses
of territory than that which the Lionnesse tale of Cornwall pretends to
commemorate. They are all important, as demonstrating that the
earliest inhabitants were familiar with the phenomenon of incursions of
the sea.
Loss of land on the coast of France.—The French coast, particularly
that part of Brittany, where the tides rise to an extraordinary height, is
the constant prey of the waves. In the ninth century many villages
and woods are reported to have been carried away, the coast undergoing
great change, whereby the hill of St. Michael was detached from
the mainland. The parish of Bourgneuf, and several others in that
neighborhood, were overflowed in the year 1500. In 1735, during a
great storm, the ruins of Palnel were seen uncovered in the sea.442

325</div></body></text></TEI>