<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="41">CHAPTER XLI.
EXTINCTION OF SPECIES.—CHANGES IN THE STATIONS OF ANIMALS.
Extension of the range of one species alters the condition of many others—The
first appearance of a new species causes the chief disturbance—Changes
known to have resulted from the advance of human population—Whether
man increases the productive powers of the earth—Indigenous quadrupeds
and birds extirpated in Great Britain—Extinction of the dodo—Rapid propagation
of domestic quadrupeds in America—Power of exterminating species
no prerogative of man—Concluding remarks.
We have seen that the stations of animals and plants depend not
merely on the influence of external agents in the inanimate world, and
the relations of that influence to the structure and habits of each species,
but also on the state of the contemporary living beings which
inhabit the same part of the globe. In other words, the possibility of
the existence of a certain species in a given place, or of its thriving
more or less therein, is determined not merely by temperature, humidity,
soil, elevation, and other circumstances of the like kind; but also
by the existence or non-existence, the abundance or scarcity, of a particular
assemblage of other plants and animals in the same region.
If it be shown that both these classes of circumstances, whether
relating to the animate or inanimate creation, are perpetually changing,
it will follow that species are subject to incessant vicissitudes; and if
678
the result of these mutations, in the course of ages, be so great as
materially to affect the general condition of stations, it will follow that
the successive destruction of species must now be part of the regular
and constant order of nature.
Extension of the range of one species alters the condition of the others.—It
will be desirable, first, to consider the effects which every extension
of the numbers or geographical range of one species must produce on
the condition of others inhabiting the same regions. When the necessary
consequences of such extensions have been fully explained, the
reader will be prepared to appreciate the important influence which
slight modifications in the physical geography of the globe may exert
on the condition of organic beings.
In the first place, it is clear that when any region is stocked with as
great a variety of animals and plants as the productive powers of that
region will enable it to support, the addition of any new species, or the
permanent numerical increase of one previously established, must always
be attended either by the local extermination or the numerical decrease
of some other species.
There may undoubtedly be considerable fluctuations from year to
year, and the equilibrium may be again restored without any permanent
alteration; for, in particular seasons, a greater supply of heat, humidity,
or other causes, may augment the total quantity of vegetable produce,
in which case all the animals subsisting on vegetable food, and others
which prey on them, may multiply without any one species giving way:
but whilst the aggregate quantity of vegetable produce remains unaltered,
the progressive increase of one animal or plant implies the decline of
another.
All agriculturists and gardeners are familiar with the fact that when
weeds intrude themselves into the space appropriated to cultivated species,
the latter are starved in their growth, or stifled. If we abandon
for a short time a field or garden, a host of indigenous plants,

The darnel, hemlock, and rank fumitory,

pour in and obtain the mastery, extirpating the exotics, or putting an
end to the monopoly of some native plants.
If we inclose a park, and stock it with as many deer as the herbage
will support, we cannot add sheep without lessening the number of the
deer; nor can other herbivorous species be subsequently introduced, unless
the individuals of each species in the park become fewer in proportion.
So, if there be an island where leopards are the only beasts of prey,
and the lion, tiger, and hyæna afterwards enter, the leopards, if they
stand their ground, will be reduced in number. If the locusts then
arrive and swarm greatly, they may deprive a large number of plant-eating
animals of their food, and thereby cause a famine, not only
among them, but among the beasts of prey: certain species perhaps,
which had the weakest footing in the island, may thus be annihilated.
679
We have seen how many distinct geographical provinces there are of
aquatic and terrestrial species, and how great are the powers of migration
conferred on different classes, whereby the inhabitants of one region
may be enabled from time to time to invade another, and do actually so
migrate and diffuse themselves over new countries. Now, although our
knowledge of the history of the animate creation dates from so recent a
period, that we can scarcely trace the advance or decline of any animal
or plant, except in those cases where the influence of man has intervened;
yet we can easily conceive what must happen when some new colony of
wild animals or plants enters a region for the first time, and succeeds in
establishing itself.
Supposed effects of the first entrance of the polar bear into Iceland.—Let
us consider how great are the devastations committed at certain
periods by the Greenland bears, when they are drifted to the shores of
Iceland in considerable numbers on the ice. These periodical invasions
are formidable even to man; so that when the bears arrive, the inhabitants
collect together, and go in pursuit of them with fire-arms—each
native who slays one being rewarded by the King of Denmark. The
Danes of old, when they landed in their marauding expeditions upon our
coast, hardly excited more alarm, nor did our islanders muster more
promptly for the defence of their lives and property against the common
enemy, than the modern Icelanders against these formidable brutes. It
often happens, says Henderson, that the natives are pursued by the bear
when he has been long at sea, and when his natural ferocity has been
heightened by the keenness of hunger; if unarmed, it is frequently by
stratagem only that they make their escape.965
Let us cast our thoughts back to the period when the first polar bears
reached Iceland, before it was colonized by the Norwegians in 874: we
may imagine the breaking up of an immense barrier of ice like that
which, in 1816 and the following year, disappeared from the east coast
of Greenland, which it had surrounded for four centuries. By the aid of
such means of transportation a great number of these quadrupeds might
effect a landing at the same time, and the havoc which they would make
among the species previously settled in the island would be terrific. The
deer, foxes, seals, and even birds, on which these animals sometimes prey,
would be soon thinned down.
But this would be a part only, and probably an insignificant portion,
of the aggregate amount of change brought about by the new invader.
The plants on which the deer fed, being less consumed in consequence of
the lessened numbers of that herbivorous species, would soon supply more
food to several insects, and probably to some terrestrial testacea, so that
the latter would gain ground. The increase of these would furnish other
insects and birds with food, so that the numbers of these last would be
augmented. The diminution of the seals would afford a respite to some
fish which they had persecuted; and these fish, in their turn, would then
680
multiply and press upon their peculiar prey. Many water-fowls, the eggs
and young of which are devoured by foxes, would increase when the foxes
were thinned down by the bears; and the fish on which the water-fowls
subsisted would then, in their turn, be less numerous. Thus the numerical
proportions of a great number of the inhabitants, both of the land and
sea, might be permanently altered by the settling of one new species in
the region; and the changes caused indirectly would ramify through all
classes of the living creation, and be almost endless.
An actual illustration of what we have here only proposed hypothetically,
is in some degree afforded by the selection of small islands by the
eider duck for its residence during the season of incubation, its nest being
seldom if ever found on the shores of the main land, or even of a large
island. The Icelanders are so well aware of this, that they have expended
a great deal of labor in forming artificial islands, by separating from the
main land certain promontories, joined to it by narrow isthmuses. This
insular position is necessary to guard against the destruction of the eggs
and young birds, by foxes, dogs, and other animals. One year, says
Hooker, it happened that, in the small island of Vidoe, adjoining the coast
of Iceland, a fox got over upon the ice, and caused great alarm, as an immense
number of ducks were then sitting on their eggs or young ones.
It was long before he was taken, which was at last, however, effected by
bringing another fox to the island, and fastening it by a string near the
haunt of the former, by which he was allured within shot of the hunter.966
The first appearance of a new species causes the chief disturbance.—It
is usually the first appearance of an animal or plant, in a region to which
it was previously a stranger, that gives rise to the chief alteration; since,
after a time, an equilibrium is again established. But it must require
ages before such a new adjustment of the relative forces of so many conflicting
agents can be definitely settled. The causes in simultaneous
action are so numerous, that they admit of an almost infinite number of
combinations; and it is necessary that all these should have occurred once
before the total amount of change, capable of flowing from any new disturbing
force, can be estimated.
Thus, for example, suppose that once in two centuries a frost of unusual
intensity, or a volcanic eruption of great violence accompanied by
floods from the melting of glaciers, should occur in Iceland; or an epidemic
disease, fatal to the larger number of individuals of some one species,
and not affecting others,—these, and a variety of other contingencies, all
of which may occur at once, or at periods separated by different intervals
of time, ought to happen before it would be possible for us to declare what
ultimate alteration the presence of any new comer, such as the bear before
mentioned, might occasion in the animal population of the isle.
Every new condition in the state of the organic or inorganic creation,
a new animal or plant, an additional snow-clad mountain, any permanent
change, however slight in comparison to the whole, gives rise to a
681
new order of things, and may make a material change in regard to some
one or more species. Yet a swarm of locusts, or a frost of extreme
intensity, or an epidemic disease, may pass away without any great
apparent derangement; no species may be lost, and all may soon
recover their former relative numbers, because the same scourges may
have visited the region again and again, at preceding periods. Every
plant that was incapable of resisting such a degree of cold, every animal
which was exposed to be entirely cut off by an epidemic or by famine
caused by the consumption of vegetation by the locusts, may have
perished already, so that the subsequent recurrence of similar catastrophes
is attended only by a temporary change.
Changes caused by Man
We are best acquainted with the mutations brought about by the
progress of human population, and the growth of plants and animals
favored by man. To these, therefore, we should in the first instance
turn our attention. If we conclude, from the concurrent testimony of
history and of the evidence yielded by geological data, that man is,
comparatively speaking, of very modern origin, we must at once perceive
how great a revolution in the state of the animate world the increase
of the human race, considered merely as consumers of a certain quantity
of organic matter, must necessarily cause.
Whether man increases the productive powers of the earth.—It may
perhaps, be said, that man has, in some degree, compensated for the
appropriation to himself of so much food, by artificially improving the
natural productiveness of soils, by irrigation, manure, and a judicious
intermixture of mineral ingredients conveyed from different localities.
But it admits of reasonable doubt whether, upon the whole, we fertilize
or impoverish the lands which we occupy. This assertion may seem
startling to many; because they are so much in the habit of regarding
the sterility or productiveness of land in relation to the wants of man,
and not as regards the organic world generally. It is difficult, at first,
to conceive, if a morass is converted into arable land, and made to yield
a crop of grain, even of moderate abundance, that we have not improved
the capabilities of the habitable surface—that we have not empowered
it to support a larger quantity of organic life. In such cases, however,
a tract, before of no utility to man, may be reclaimed, and become of
high agricultural importance, though it may, nevertheless, yield a
scantier vegetation. If a lake be drained, and turned into a meadow,
the space will provide sustenance to man, and many terrestrial animals
serviceable to him, but not, perhaps, so much food as it previously yielded
to the aquatic races.
If the pestiferous Pontine marshes were drained, and covered with
corn, like the plains of the Po, they might, perhaps, feed a smaller
number of animals than they do now; for these morasses are filled with
herds of buffaloes and swine, and they swarm with birds, reptiles, and
insects.
682
The felling of dense and lofty forests, which covered, even within the
records of history, a considerable space on the globe, now tenanted by
civilized man, must generally have lessened the amount of vegetable
food throughout the space where these woods grew. We must also
take into our account the area covered by towns, and a still larger surface
occupied by roads.
If we force the soil to bear extraordinary crops one year, we are,
perhaps, compelled to let it lie fallow the next. But nothing so much
counterbalances the fertilizing effects of human art as the extensive
cultivation of foreign herbs and shrubs, which, although they are often
more nutritious to man, seldom thrive with the same rank luxuriance as
the native plants of a district. Man is, in truth, continually striving to
diminish the natural diversity of the stations of animals and plants in
every country, and to reduce them all to a small number fitted for
species of economical use. He may succeed perfectly in attaining his
object, even though the vegetation be comparatively meagre, and the
total amount of animal life be greatly lessened.
Spix and Martius have given a lively description of the incredible
number of insects which lay waste the crops in Brazil, besides swarms
of monkeys, flocks of parrots, and other birds, as well as the paca,
agouti, and wild swine. They describe the torment which the planter
and the naturalist suffer from the musquitoes, and the devastation of
the ants and blattæ; they speak of the dangers to which they were
exposed from the jaguar, the poisonous serpents, crocodiles, scorpions,
centipedes, and spiders. But with the increasing population and cultivation
of the country, say these naturalists, these evils will gradually
diminish; when the inhabitants have cut down the woods, drained the
marshes, made roads in all directions, and founded villages and towns,
man will, by degrees, triumph over the rank vegetation and the noxious
animals, and all the elements will second and amply recompense his
activity.967
The number of human beings now peopling the earth is supposed to
amount to eight hundred millions, so that we may easily understand
how great a number of beasts of prey, birds, and animals of every class,
this prodigious population must have displaced, independently of the
still more important consequences which have followed from the
derangement brought about by man in the relative numerical strength
of particular species.
Indigenous quadrupeds and birds extirpated in Great Britain.—Let
us make some inquiries into the extent of the influence which the progress
of society has exerted during the last seven or eight centuries, in
altering the distribution of indigenous British animals. Dr. Fleming
has prosecuted this inquiry with his usual zeal and ability; and in a
memoir on the subject has enumerated the best-authenticated examples
of the decrease or extirpation of certain species during a period when
683
our population has made the most rapid advances. I shall offer a brief
outline of his results.968
The stag, as well as the fallow deer and the roe, were formerly so
abundant in our island, that, according to Lesley, from five hundred to
a thousand were sometimes slain at a hunting match; but the native
races would already have been extinguished, had they not been carefully
preserved in certain forests. The otter, the marten, and the
polecat, were also in sufficient numbers to be pursued for the sake of
their fur; but they have now been reduced within very narrow bounds.
The wild cat and fox have also been sacrificed throughout the greater
part of the country, for the security of the poultry-yard or the fold.
Badgers have been expelled from nearly every district, which at former
periods they inhabited.
Besides these, which have been driven out from their favorite haunts,
and everywhere reduced in number, there are some which have been
wholly extirpated; such as the ancient breed of indigenous horses, and
the wild boar; of the wild oxen a few remains are still preserved in
some of the old English parks. The beaver, which is eagerly sought
after for its fur, had become scarce at the close of the ninth century;
and, by the twelfth century, was only to be met with, according to
Giraldus de Barri, in one river in Wales, and another in Scotland. The
wolf, once so much dreaded by our ancestors, is said to have maintained
its ground in Ireland so late as the beginning of the eighteenth century
(1710), though it had been extirpated in Scotland thirty years before,
and in England at a much earlier period. The bear, which, in Wales,
was regarded as a beast of the chase equal to the hare or the boar969,
only perished, as a native of Scotland, in the year 1057.970
Many native birds of prey have also been the subjects of unremitting
persecution. The eagles, larger hawks, and ravens, have disappeared
from the more cultivated districts. The haunts of the mallard, the snipe,
the redshank, and the bittern, have been drained equally with the
summer dwellings of the lapwing and the curlew. But these species still
linger in some portion of the British isles; whereas the larger capercailzies
or wood grouse, formerly natives of the pine-forests of Ireland and Scotland,
have been destroyed within the last sixty years. The egret and
the crane, which appear to have been formerly very common in Scotland,
are now only occasional visitants.971
The bustard (Otis tarda), observes Graves, in his British Ornithology972,
"was formerly seen in the downs and heaths of various parts of
our island, in flocks of forty or fifty birds; whereas it is now a circumstance
of rare occurrence to meet with a single individual." Bewick
also remarks, "that they were formerly more common in this island
than at present; they are now found only in the open counties of the
684
south and east—in the plains of Wiltshire, Dorsetshire, and some parts
of Yorkshire."973 In the few years that have elapsed since Bewick
wrote, this bird has entirely disappeared from Wiltshire and Dorsetshire.
These changes, it may be observed, are derived from very imperfect
memorials, and relate only to the larger and more conspicuous animals
inhabiting a small spot on the globe; but they cannot fail to exalt our
conception of the enormous revolutions which, in the course of several
thousand years, the whole human species must have effected.
Extinction of the dodo.—The kangaroo and the emu are retreating
rapidly before the progress of colonization in Australia; and it scarcely
admits of doubt, that the general cultivation of that country must lead
to the extirpation of both. The most striking example of the loss,
even within the last two centuries, of a remarkable species, is that of
the dodo—a bird first seen by the Dutch, when they landed on the Isle
of France, at that time uninhabited, immediately after the discovery of
the passage to the East Indies by the Cape of Good Hope. It was of
a large size, and singular form; its wings short, like those of an ostrich,
and wholly incapable of sustaining its heavy body, even for a short
flight. In its general appearance it differed from the ostrich, cassowary,
or any known bird.974
Many naturalists gave figures of the dodo after the commencement
of the seventeenth century; and there is a painting of it in the British
Museum, which is said to have been taken from a living individual.
Beneath the painting is a leg, in a fine state of preservation, which ornithologists
are agreed cannot belong to any other known bird. In the
museum at Oxford, also, there is a foot and a head in an imperfect state.
In spite of the most active search, during the last century, no information
respecting the dodo was obtained, and some authors have gone
so far as to pretend that it never existed; but a great mass of satisfactory
evidence in favor of its recent existence has now been collected
by Mr. Broderip,975 and by Mr. Strickland and Dr. Melville. Mr. Strickland,
agreeing with Professor Reinhardt, of Copenhagen, in referring
the dodo to the Columbidæ, calls it a "vulture-like frugivorous pigeon."
It appears, also, that another short-winged bird of the same order, called
"The Solitaire," inhabited the small island of Rodrigues, 300 miles east
of the Mauritius, and has been exterminated by man, as have one or
two different but allied birds of the Isle of Bourbon.976
685
Rapid propagation of domestic quadrupeds over the American continent.—Next
to the direct agency of man, his indirect influence in
multiplying the numbers of large herbivorous quadrupeds of domesticated
races may be regarded as one of the most obvious causes of the
extermination of species. On this, and on several other grounds, the
introduction of the horse, ox, and other mammalia, into America, and
their rapid propagation over that continent within the last three centuries,
is a fact of great importance in natural history. The extraordinary
herds of wild cattle and horses which overran the plains of South
America sprung from a very few pairs first carried over by the Spaniards;
and they prove that the wide geographical range of large species in
great continents does not necessarily imply that they have existed there
from remote periods.
Humboldt observes, in his Travels, on the authority of Azzara, that
it is believed there exist, in the Pampas of Buenos Ayres, twelve million
cows and three million horses, without comprising, in this enumeration,
the cattle that have no acknowledged proprietor. In the Llanos of Caraccas,
the rich hateros, or proprietors of pastoral farms, are entirely ignorant
of the number of cattle they possess. The young are branded
with a mark peculiar to each herd, and some of the most wealthy
owners mark as many as fourteen thousand a year.977 In the northern
plains, from the Orinoco to the lake of Maraycabo, M. Depons reckoned
that 1,200,000 oxen, 180,000 horses, and 90,000 mules, wandered at
large.978 In some parts of the valley of the Mississippi, especially in the
country of the Osage Indians, wild horses are immensely numerous.
The establishment of black cattle in America dates from Columbus's
second voyage to St. Domingo. They there multiplied rapidly; and
that island presently became a kind of nursery from which these animals
were successively transported to various parts of the continental
coast, and from thence into the interior. Notwithstanding these
numerous exportations, in twenty-seven years after the discovery of the
island, herds of four thousand head, as we learn from Oviedo, were not
uncommon, and there were even some that amounted to eight thousand.
In 1587, the number of hides exported from St. Domingo alone, according
to Acosta's report, was 35,444; and in the same year there were
exported 64,350 from the ports of New Spain. This was in the sixty-fifth
year after the taking of Mexico, previous to which event the
Spaniards, who came into that country, had not been able to engage in
anything else than war.979 Every one is aware that these animals are
now established throughout the American continent from Canada to
the Straits of Magellan.
The ass has thriven very generally in the New World; and we learn
from Ulloa, that in Quito they ran wild, and multiplied in amazing
numbers, so as to become a nuisance. They grazed together in herds,
686
and when attacked defended themselves with their mouths. If a horse
happened to stray into the places where they fed, they all fell upon him,
and did not cease biting and kicking till they left him dead.980
The first hogs were carried to America by Columbus, and established
in the Island of St. Domingo the year following its discovery, in
November, 1493. In succeeding years they were introduced into other
places where the Spaniards settled; and, in the space of half a century,
they were found established in the New World, from the latitude of
25° north, to the 40th degree of south latitude. Sheep, also, and
goats have multiplied enormously in the New World, as have also the
cat and the rat; which last, as before stated, has been imported unintentionally
in ships. The dogs introduced by man which have at
different periods become wild in America, hunted in packs, like the
wolf and the jackall, destroying not only hogs, but the calves and
foals of the wild cattle and horses.
Ulloa in his voyage, and Buffon on the authority of old writers, relate
a fact which illustrates very clearly the principle before explained, of
the check which the increase of one animal necessarily offers to that of
another. The Spaniards had introduced goats into the Island of Juan
Fernandez, where they became so prolific as to furnish the pirates who
infested those seas with provisions. In order to cut off this resource
from the buccaneers, a number of dogs were turned loose into the island;
and so numerous did they become in their turn, that they destroyed the
goats in every accessible part, after which the number of the wild dogs
again decreased.981
Increase of rein-deer imported into Iceland.—As an example of the
rapidity with which a large tract may become peopled by the offspring
of a single pair of quadrupeds, it may be mentioned that in the year
1773 thirteen rein-deer were exported from Norway, only three of which
reached Iceland. These were turned loose into the mountains of Guldbringè
Syssel, where they multiplied so greatly, in the course of forty
years, that it was not uncommon to meet with herds, consisting of from
forty to one hundred, in various districts.
The rein-deer, observes a modern writer, is in Lapland a loser by his
connexion with man, but Iceland will be this creature's paradise.
There is, in the interior, a tract which Sir. G. Mackenzie computes at
not less than forty thousand square miles, without a single human habitation,
and almost entirely unknown to the natives themselves. There
are no wolves: the Icelanders will keep out the bears; and the reindeer,
being almost unmolested by man, will have no enemy whatever,
unless it has brought with it its own tormenting gad-fly.982
Besides the quadrupeds before enumerated, our domestic fowls have
also succeeded in the West Indies and America, where they have the
687
common fowl, the goose, the duck, the peacock, the pigeon, and the
guinea-fowl. As these were often taken suddenly from the temperate
to very hot regions, they were not reared at first without much difficulty:
but after a few generations, they became familiarized to the climate,
which, in many cases, approached much nearer than that of Europe to
the temperature of their original native countries.
The fact of so many millions of wild and tame individuals of our domestic
species, almost all of them the largest quadrupeds and birds,
having been propagated throughout the new continent within the short
period that has elapsed since the discovery of America, while no appreciable
improvement can have been made in the productive powers of
that vast continent, affords abundant evidence of the extraordinary
changes which accompany the diffusion and progressive advancement of
the human race over the globe. That it should have remained for us to
witness such mighty revolutions is a proof, even if there was no other
evidence, that the entrance of man into the planet is, comparatively
speaking, of extremely modern date, and that the effects of his agency
are only beginning to be felt.
Population which the globe is capable of supporting.—A modern
writer has estimated, that there are in America upwards of four million
square miles of useful soil, each capable of supporting 200 persons; and
nearly six million, each mile capable of supporting 490 persons.983 If this
conjecture be true, it will follow, as that author observes, that if the
natural resources of America were fully developed, it would afford sustenance
to five times as great a number of inhabitants as the entire mass
of human beings existing at present upon the globe. The new continent,
he thinks, though less than half the size of the old, contains an equal
quantity of useful soil, and much more than an equal amount of productive
power. Be this as it may, we may safely conclude that the amount
of human population now existing constitutes but a small proportion of
that which the globe is capable of supporting, or which it is destined to
sustain at no distant period, by the rapid progress of society, especially
in America, Australia, and certain parts of the old continent.
Power of exterminating species no prerogative of man.—But if we reflect
that many millions of square miles of the most fertile land, occupied
originally by a boundless variety of animal and vegetable forms, have
been already brought under the dominion of man, and compelled, in a
great measure, to yield nourishment to him, and to a limited number of
plants and animals which he has caused to increase, we must at once be
convinced, that the annihilation of a multitude of species has already been
effected, and will continue to go on hereafter, in certain regions, in a still
more rapid ratio, as the colonies of highly civilized nations spread themselves
over unoccupied lands.
Yet, if we wield the sword of extermination as we advance, we have no
reason to repine at the havoc committed, nor to fancy, with the Scottish
688
poet, that "we violate the social union of nature;" or complain, with the
melancholy Jacques, that we


Are mere usurpers, tyrants, and what's worse,
To fright the animals and to kill them up
In their assign'd and native dwelling-place.


We have only to reflect, that in thus obtaining possession of the earth
by conquest, and defending our acquisitions by force, we exercise no exclusive
prerogative. Every species which has spread itself from a small
point over a wide area must, in like manner, have marked its progress
by the diminution or the entire extirpation of some other, and must
maintain its ground by a successful struggle against the encroachments of
other plants and animals. That minute parasitic plant, called "the rust" in
wheat, has, like the Hessian fly, the locust, and the aphis, caused famines
ere now amongst the "lords of the creation." The most insignificant and
diminutive species, whether in the animal or vegetable kingdom, have
each slaughtered their thousands, as they disseminated themselves over
the globe, as well as the lion, when first it spread itself over the tropical
regions of Africa.
Concluding remarks.—Although we have as yet considered one class
only of the causes (the organic) by which species may become exterminated,
yet it cannot but appear evident that the continued action of these
alone, throughout myriads of future ages, must work an entire change
in the state of the organic creation, not merely on the continents and
islands, where the power of man is chiefly exerted, but in the great
ocean, where his control is almost unknown. The mind is prepared by
the contemplation of such future revolutions to look for the signs of
others, of an analogous nature, in the monuments of the past. Instead
of being astonished at the proofs there manifested of endless mutations
in the animate world, they will appear to one who has thought profoundly
on the fluctuations now in progress, to afford evidence in favor of the
uniformity of the system, unless, indeed, we are precluded from speaking
of uniformity when we characterize a principle of endless variation.

689</div></body></text></TEI>