<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="45">CHAPTER XLIII.
It may seem extraordinary that I should instantly have
known him. He was sitting at a table, covered with[431]
papers, and with one or two aides-de-camp waiting to receive
his orders. He was clothed in complete armour,
and his casque was resting on the ground by his side.
When I entered, his eye was fixed on a despatch that day
received from the great palatine of Hungary; but, in little
more than a minute, he raised his head, and his countenance
was completely presented to my view. It was
fifteen years since I had beheld it; he was then scarcely
above half his present age, a mere stripling, in whom the
first blush of manhood had awakened the sentiment of independence
and an honour impatient of a shade; he was
now a leader of warlike bands, his complexion olived over
with service, and his eye rendered steady with observation
and thought. But I knew him; I knew him in a moment.
My soul, with the rapidity of lightning, told me who he
was. Not all the arts in the world could have hid him
from me; not all the tales that delusion ever framed could
have baffled me; I could have challenged him against the
earth!
I have already had occasion to explain the complexity of
my feelings, when, after a long absence, I visited the
heiresses of the house of St. Leon. The sweets of recognition,
that transporting effervescence of the mind, where
the heart bounds to meet a kindred heart, where emotions
and tears mingle in speechless encounter, where all is
gazing love and strict embrace,—these pleasures were
denied me. I stood stiff and motionless in the presence of
my child. My heart might burst; but it must not, and it
could not communicate its feelings.
After an instant’s pause of overwhelming sensation, I
sunk back on myself, and considered my own figure. It
happened that, exactly opposite to me, in the tent of my son,
hung his armour, and over the rest his polished shield, in
which I saw my own person clearly reflected. The youth
of my figure indeed was still visible; but the hardships of
my dungeon had imprinted themselves in glaring characters
on my face. My beard was neglected, my hair was matted
and shaggy, my complexion was of a strong and deadly
yellow. My appearance to a considerable degree told my
story without the need of words. Charles enquired of[432]
those who brought me, where they had found this wretched
and unhappy figure; and was told that I had been seen a
few minutes before coming out from the ruins of Bethlem
Gabor’s castle. He humanely and naturally concluded,
that I was a victim on whom the tyrant had exercised his
ferocity, and that I had been shut up in some dungeon of
the fortress: it was impossible that any person above ground
in the castle should have come out alive from the operation
of the flames. He commanded that I should be led to a
neighbouring tent and taken care of. After having been
refreshed with food and rest, and attired with other apparel,
he directed that I should be brought to him again,
that he might hear my story.
Under these circumstances there was nothing for which
I was more anxious, than that I might recruit myself, and
shake off as quickly as possible the effects of my confinement.
Cordials were brought me, and I tasted of them:
I bathed in a neighbouring stream: one of my son’s attendants
removed my beard, and arranged my hair. I now
desired to be left alone, that I might take some needful
repose. I could not sleep; but I reclined my limbs upon
a couch, and began to collect my thoughts.
I saw myself in one hour the sport of the most complete
reverse of fortune that could happen to a mortal. I had
been the prisoner of a cavern so wild and pathless, as almost
to defy the utmost extent of human sagacity to explore
its recesses. From this cavern, but for the sudden
and extraordinary event which had just occurred, I could
never have come forth alive. All sober calculation would
have taught me to expect that I should have remained
there, chained up like a savage tiger in his cage, as long as
Bethlem Gabor existed; and that, when he died, I should
perish, unheard, unknown; no creature that lived suspecting
my situation, no lapse of ages ever bringing to light my
dismal catastrophe. The remorse and relenting of Bethlem
Gabor towards me seemed so little to accord with any thing
that I had personally witnessed of his habits and his mind,
that even now I feel myself totally unable to account for it.
As it was however, I was once again free. From the state
of an outlaw imprisoned for life, I suddenly saw myself at[433]
large, inspirited by the light of the sun, and refreshed by
his genial rays, in the full possession of youth and all its
faculties, enabled to return amidst my clients of Buda, or
to seek some new adventure, in any corner of the earth to
which my inclination led me. There is no man, however
overwhelmed with calamities, however persecuted with endless
disappointment, however disgusted with life and all its
specious allurements, to whom so sudden and admirable a
change would not convey some portion of elasticity and
joy.
But there was one thought that entirely occupied me. I
cannot describe how my soul yearned towards this my only
son: the sentiment, even now as I write, is an oppression
I am scarcely able to sustain. Willingly, most willingly,
would I have traversed every region of the globe, if so I
might have discovered his unknown retreat: and now suddenly,
without the smallest effort on my part, he was placed
before me. His last solemn parting, his abjuration of my society
and intercourse for ever, rose to my memory, and gave
a zest inexpressible to our present encounter. At the thought
that my son was in the neighbouring tent, all earthly objects
beside faded from my mind, and appeared uninteresting
and contemptible. I instantly resolved to devote myself
to his service, and to place all my enjoyment in the
contemplation of his happiness, and the secret consciousness
of promoting it. He had, if I may so express myself, in
my own person forbidden me his presence: in my now
altered figure I might disobey his injunction without fearing
his rebuke. Let not the reader condemn me, that, endowed
as I was with unlimited powers of action, I preferred
a single individual, my own son, to all the world
beside. Philanthropy is a godlike virtue, and can never be
too loudly commended, or too ardently enjoined; but natural
affection winds itself in so many folds about the
heart, and is the parent of so complicated, so various and
exquisite emotions, that he who should attempt to divest
himself of it, will find that he is divesting himself of all
that is most to be coveted in existence. It is not a selfish
propensity; on the contrary, I will venture to affirm that
the generosity it breathes is its greatest charm. Beside, in[434]
my case I considered my own existence as blasted; and I
could therefore find nothing better than to forget myself in
my son. I had made a sufficient experiment of the philosopher’s
stone, and all my experiments had miscarried. My
latest trials in attempting to be the benefactor of nations
and mankind, not only had been themselves abortive, but
contained in them shrewd indications that no similar plan
could ever succeed. I therefore discarded, for the present
at least, all ambitious and comprehensive views, and believed
that I ought to be well content, if I could prove the
unknown benefactor of the son of Marguerite de Damville.
I entered into a solemn engagement with myself that I
would forget and trample upon every personal concern, and
be the victim and the sacrifice, if need were, of the happiness
of my child. Dismissing my project of becoming a
factor for the Hungarian people, I determined to lay aside
the name of Chatillon, and cut off every indication that
might connect my present existence with that of the rich
stranger of Buda. One of the advantages I possessed for
that purpose was, that no creature in Hungary had the
slightest suspicion that the sieur de Chatillon had ever been
the prisoner of Bethlem Gabor.
Having thus arranged my thoughts, I now called for the
garments that had been assigned me. They were supplied
me from the stock of my son; and, when I had put them
on, I overheard the attendants whispering to each other their
astonishment, at the striking resemblance between their
master and myself. When I came once more into the
tent of their captain, and stood as in the former instance
before his shield, I did not wonder at their remark.
The coincidence of our features was so great, that, had we
passed through a strange place in each other’s company, I
should infallibly have been regarded as his younger brother.
Yet there was something of Marguerite in the countenance
of Charles that I wanted. When I recovered, as in a short
time afterwards I did, my vigour and health, I was more
blooming than he; but there was something graceful, ingenuous
and prepossessing in his aspect, which I could by no
means boast in an equal degree, and which might have
carried him unhurt and honoured through the world. We[435]
shall see some of the effects of this in what I shall presently
have occasion to relate.
When my son required of me to declare who I was, I
told him, as I had already determined to do, that I was a
cadet of the house of Aubigny in France; that, after having
passed through several other countries, I had come into
Poland with the floating and half formed purpose of entering
as a volunteer against the Turk; but that, before my
plan was completely arranged, having been led, by my
juvenile ardour in a hunting party, far within the frontier
of Hungary, I had been so unfortunate as to become a
prisoner to the troopers of Bethlem Gabor. I added that,
when introduced to their chief, I had given him so much
offence, by the firmness of my manner, and my refusing to
comply with certain propositions he made me, that he had
thrust me into a dungeon, from which, but for the gallant
exertions of the present detachment, I should never have
come out alive.
Charles heard my story with attention and interest. He
called on me to resume my courage and my hopes, and to
be confident that my sufferings were now at an end. He
told me, that he was a Frenchman as well as myself, and
like myself, had been a soldier of fortune. He felt, he
said, a powerful sympathy in my tale; there was something
in my countenance that irresistibly won his kindness; and,
if I would put myself under his protection, he did not
doubt to be the means of my future success. He spoke
with great asperity of Bethlem Gabor, who, as an
intrepid, indefatigable and sanguinary partisan, had been
the author of greater mischiefs to the Christian cause, than
any of the immediate servants of the sultan of Constantinople.
He congratulated himself that the same action that
had delivered the world from so murderous a renegado, had
rendered him the preserver of a youth of so much enterprise
and worth, as he doubted not I should prove. He
said, there was but one other man in Hungary, who
had been so effectual an enemy to the cause of truth
and Christianity as Bethlem Gabor. The name of this
man he understood was Chatillon, and he grieved to say[436]
that he bore the appellation of a Frenchman. To the
eternal disgrace of the nation that gave him birth, he had
joined the Turkish standard, and, by exertions difficult to
be comprehended, had rescued the infidels from famine at
a time when, but for his inauspicious interference, Buda,
and perhaps every strong town in Hungary, were on the
point of falling into the hands of the Christians. It was
this same man who had revived the resources of Bethlem
Gabor, after they had once before, by his own fortunate
exertions, been routed out; and whom I might therefore
in some sense consider as the author of my calamities, as
well as the inveterate foe of Christendom. Such a wretch
as this was scarcely entitled to the common benefit of the
laws of war: and he would not answer for himself if Chatillon
had fallen into his power, to what extremity his holy
resentment against this degenerate fellow-countryman might
have hurried him. Providence however had overtaken him
in his impious career; and he had fallen obscurely, as he
had lived basely, in a night skirmish with a party of
marauders from the Austrian camp.—The reader may
believe that I did not a little rejoice that, in announcing
myself a few moments before, I had taken the name, not
of Chatillon, but D’Aubigny. What I heard however
occasioned in me a profound reflection on the capriciousness
of honour and fame, and the strange contrarieties with
which opposite prejudices cause the same action to be
viewed. I could not repress the vehemence of my emotions,
while I was thus calumniated and vilified for actions,
which I had firmly believed no malice could misrepresent,
and fondly supposed that all sects and ages, as far as their
record extended, would agree to admire.
In another point of view, the invective which my son
thus unconsciously poured in my ears, had the effect of
making me regard with a more complacent satisfaction the
plan I had formed of devoting myself to his service. Here
I pursued no delusive meteor of fame; the very essence of
my project lay in its obscurity. Kings and prelates, armies
and churches, would no longer find an interest in disputing
about my measures; I should indulge the secret promptings
of my soul, undisturbed alike by the censure of the[437]
world, and its applause. It was thus that, under every
change of fortune, I continued to soothe my soul with delusive
dreams.
Meanwhile my project went on with the happiest auspices.
The friendship between me and Charles continued
hourly to increase. As a Frenchman, whom chance had
introduced to his acquaintance in a distant country, it was
natural that he should feel a strong bias of affection towards
me. But that sort of fraternal resemblance which the most
inattentive spectator remarked in us, operated forcibly to the
increase of Charles’s attachment. He would often, in the
ingenuous opening of his soul towards me, call me his
brother, and swear that I should for ever experience from
him a brother’s love. Charles had by this time completed
the thirty-second year of his age; I was, in appearance, at
least ten years younger than he. There is something in
this degree of disparity, that greatly contributes to the cultivation
of kindness, and is adapted to the engendering a
thousand interesting sentiments. Frequently would he exclaim,
“Our fortunes, my dear Henry,” that was the name I
assumed, “have been in a considerable degree similar: we
were both of us early cast on the world; I indeed at the
immature age of seventeen. I entered the world without
an adviser or a friend; but my destiny was favourable, and
I escaped its quicksands and its rocks. I have now by a
concurrence of happy circumstances obtained a place among
honourable men and soldiers, and for what is to come may
reasonably regard myself with some degree of confidence.
You are yet in one of the most dangerous periods of human
life; your work is all to do; your battles are yet to fight.
Suffer me, my dear friend, to represent your better genius,
and act an elder brother’s part. You shall find me no
ignorant Mentor, and no ungentle one.”
Nothing could be more gratifying to me than to see the
shoots of affection thus springing up spontaneously in
Charles’s bosom. I willingly humoured the generous deception
that he was putting on himself, and heard with
transports inconceivable his assurances of kindness and protection.
We rode, and we walked together; we were in a
manner inseparable. When he went out to reconnoitre, I[438]
was his chosen companion; when he inspected the discipline
and condition of his soldiers, he applied that opportunity
to initiate me in the science of war; when he expected to
encounter the enemy, he placed me immediately by his side.
Sometimes he would open his heart to me, and dwell
with a melancholy delight upon his secret sorrows. “It is
no wonder, my Henry,” he would say, “that I feel this uncommon
attachment to you. I am alone in the world. I
have no father, no mother, and no brethren. I am an
exile from my country, and cut off for ever from those of
my own lineage and blood. It is with inexpressible delight
that I thus cheat the malice of my fate, and hold you to
my bosom as if you were indeed my brother. I would not
part with the fiction for the mines of Peru; and I know
not whether I do not cultivate it more assiduously, and regard
it with a sentiment of more anxiety and zeal, because
it is a fiction, than I should do if it were a reality. I had
indeed,” added Charles, “a mother!”—And, when he had
started this theme, he would dwell for ever on her praises.
I easily saw that never son loved a mother more cordially,
than Charles loved the all-accomplished Marguerite. With
what sentiments did I hear her eulogium? I could not join
in her praises; I could not be supposed to know her. I
stood there, as the statue of Prometheus might have done,
if, after being informed with a living soul, the Gods had
seen fit to chain its limbs in everlasting marble. The passion
within me panted and laboured for a vent; but I was
invincibly silent. With what sentiments did I hear her
eulogium? Every word of it was a dagger to my heart;
every word said, “And thou, villain, wert not thou her
murderer?” more painfully, than the fiercest reproaches
could have done.
When Charles had celebrated with an eloquence truly
divine this incomparable mother, a sudden pang of memory
would make him start into rage.——“And this mother I
left! Of this mother I cannot tell whether she is alive or
dead! What shall I say? the crime, or the not less fatal
error of my father, separated me from this mother! I
loved my father: I loved him because he was my father;
I had great obligations to him; he once had virtues. But[439]
my mother,—if I could have found her in the wildest
desert of Africa, and have known her virtues, a stranger
to my blood, descended from the remotest tribe of the human
race, I should have chosen her for my friend, my
preceptress and my guide, beyond all that youth and beauty,
with their most radiant charms, could tender to my acceptance!”
Thus unconsciously, yet ingeniously, did my dear son
from time to time torture his father’s heart. I could not
even deliver him from the gloomy and wretched uncertainty,
whether this mother were alive or dead. With one
word I could have composed his soul into a sober grief; I
could have said, Your adorable mother at length rests from
her sorrows; she is no longer the victim of a misguided
and a cruel father; you have no longer occasion to brood
over that most disconsolate of reflections, “I know not what
anguish may be at this moment suffered by her who is entitled
to all my duty and all my affection.” With one
word I might have told this; and that word I dared not
utter.
</div></body></text></TEI>