<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="28">CHAPTER II.
Inductive Epoch of Galileo.—Discovery of the
Laws of Motion in Simple Cases.

Sect. 1.—Establishment of the First
Law of Motion.
AFTER mathematicians had begun
to doubt or reject the authority of Aristotle, they were still some
time in coming to the conclusion, that the distinction of Natural and
Violent Motions was altogether untenable;—that the velocity of a
body in motion increased or diminished in consequence of the action of
extrinsic causes, not of any property of the motion itself;—and
that the apparently universal fact, of bodies growing slower and
slower, as if by their own disposition, till they finally stopped,
from which Motions had been called Violent, arose from the action of
external obstacles not immediately obvious, as the friction and the
resistance of the air when a ball runs on the ground, and the action
of gravity, when it is thrown upwards. But the truth to which they
were at last led, was, that such causes would account for all
the diminution of velocity which bodies experience when apparently
left to themselves  and that without such causes, the motion of all
bodies would go on forever, in a straight line and with a uniform
velocity.
Who first announced this Law in a general form, it may be difficult
to point out; its exact or approximate truth was necessarily taken for
granted in all complete investigations on the subject of the laws of
motion of falling bodies, and of bodies projected so as to describe
curves. In Galileo’s first attempt to solve the problem of falling
bodies, he did not carry his analysis back to the notion of force, and
therefore this law does not appear. In 1604 he had an erroneous
opinion on this subject  and we do not know when he was led to the
true doctrine which he published in his Discorso, in 1638. In
his third Dialogue he gives the instance of water in a vessel, for the
purpose of showing that circular motion has a tendency to continue.
And in his first Dialogue on the Copernican System7 (published in
1630), he asserts 323 Circular Motion alone to be naturally
uniform, and retains the distinction between Natural and Violent
Motion. In the Dialogues on Mechanics, however, published in
1638, but written apparently at an earlier period, in treating of
Projectiles,8 he asserts the true Law. “Mobile super
planum horizontale projectum mente concipio omni secluso impedimento;
jam constat ex his quæ fusius alibi dicta sunt, illius motum equabilem
et perpetuum super ipso plano futurum esse, si planum in infinitum
extendatur.” “Conceive a movable body upon a horizontal plane, and
suppose all obstacles to motion to be removed; it is then manifest,
from what has been said more at large in another place, that the
body’s motion will be uniform and perpetual upon the plane, if the
plane be indefinitely extended.” His pupil Borelli, in 1667 (in the
treatise De Vi Percussionis), states the proposition generally,
that “Velocity is, by its nature, uniform, and perpetual;” and this
opinion appears to have been, at that time, generally diffused, as we
find evidence in Wallis and others. It is commonly said that Descartes
was the first to state this generally. His Principia were
published in 1644; but his proofs of this First Law of Motion are
rather of a theological than of a mechanical kind. His reason for this
Law is,9 “the immutability and simplicity of the
operation by which God preserves motion in matter. For he only
preserves it precisely as it is in that moment in which he preserves
it, taking no account of that which may have been previously.”
Reasoning of this abstract and à priori kind, though it may be
urged in favor of true opinions after they have been inductively
established, is almost equally capable of being called in on the side
of error, as we have seen in the case of Aristotle’s philosophy. We
ought not, however, to forget that the reference to these abstract and
à priori principles is an indication of the absolute
universality and necessity which we look for in complete Sciences, and
a result of those faculties by which such Science is rendered
possible, and suitable to man’s intellectual nature.
7 Dial. i. p. 40.
8 p. 141.
9 Princip. p. 34.
The induction by which the First Law of Motion is established,
consists, as induction consists in all cases, in conceiving clearly
the Law, and in perceiving the subordination of Facts to it. But the
Law speaks of bodies not acted upon by any external force,—a
case which never occurs in fact; and the difficulty of the step
consisted in bringing all the common cases in which motion is
gradually extinguished, under the notion of the action of a retarding
force. In order to do this, 324 Hooke and others showed that, by
diminishing the obvious resistances, the retardation also became less;
and men were gradually led to a distinct appreciation of the
Resistance, Friction, &c., which, in all terrestrial motions,
prevent the Law from being evident; and thus they at last established
by experiment a Law which cannot be experimentally exemplified. The
natural uniformity of motion was proved by examining all kinds of
cases in which motion was not uniform. Men culled the abstract Rule
out of the concrete Experiment; although the Rule was, in every case,
mixed with other Rules, and each Rule could be collected from the
Experiment only by supposing the others known. The perfect simplicity
which we necessarily seek for in a law of nature, enables us to
disentangle the complexity which this combination appears at first
sight to occasion.
The First Law of Motion asserts that the motion of a body, when
left to itself will not only be uniform, but rectilinear also. This
latter part of the law is indeed obvious of itself as soon as we
conceive a body detached from all special reference to external points
and objects. Yet, as we have seen, Galileo asserted that the naturally
uniform motion of bodies was that which takes place in a circle.
Benedetti, however, in 1585, had entertained sound notions on this
subject. In commenting on Aristotle’s question, why we obtain an
advantage in throwing by using a sling, he says,10 that the body,
when whirled round, tends to go on in a straight line. In Galileo’s
second Dialogue, he makes one of his interlocutors (Simplicio), when
appealed to on this subject, after thinking intently for a little
while, give the same opinion; and the principle is, from this time,
taken for granted by the authors who treat of the motion of
projectiles. Descartes, as might be supposed, gives the same reason
for this as for the other part of the law, namely, the immutability of
the Deity.
10 “Corpus vellet recta iter
peragere.” Speculationum Liber, p. 160.
Sect. 2.—Formation and Application of the Notion
of Accelerating Force.—Laws of Falling Bodies.
We have seen how rude and vague were the
attempts of Aristotle and his followers to obtain a philosophy of
bodies falling downwards or thrown in any direction. If the First Law
of Motion had been clearly known, it would then, perhaps, have been
seen that the way to understand and analyze the motion of any body, is
to consider the 325
Causes of change of motion which at each instant operate upon
it; and thus men would have been led to the notion of Accelerating
Forces, that is, Forces which act upon bodies already in motion, and
accelerate, retard, or deflect their motions. It was, however, only
after many attempts that they reached this point. They began by
considering the whole motion with reference to certain
ill-defined abstract Notions, instead of considering, with a clear
apprehension of the conditions of Causation, the successive
parts of which the motion consists. Thus, they spoke of the
tendency of bodies to the Centre, or to their Own Place;—of
Projecting Force, of Impetus, of Retraction;—with little or no
profit to knowledge. The indistinctness of their notions may, perhaps,
be judged of from their speculations concerning projectiles.
Santbach,11 in 1561, imagined that a body thrown
with great velocity, as, for instance, a ball from a cannon, went in a
straight line till all its velocity was exhausted, and then fell
directly downwards. He has written a treatise on gunnery, founded on
this absurd assumption. To this succeeded another doctrine, which,
though not much more philosophical than the former, agreed much better
with the phenomena. Nicolo Tartalea (Nuova Scienza, Venice,
1550; Quesiti et Inventioni Diversi, 1554) and Gualter Rivius
(Architectura, &c., Basil, 1582) represented the path of a
cannon-ball as consisting, first of a straight line in the direction
of the original projection, then of an arc of a circle in which it
went on till its motion became vertical downwards, and then of a
vertical line in which it continued to fall. The latter of these
writers, however, was aware that the path must, from the first, be a
curve; and treated it as a straight line, only because the curvature
is very slight. Even Santbach’s figure represents the path of the ball
as partially descending before its final fall, but then it descends by
steps, not in a curve. Santbach, therefore, did not conceive
the Composition of the effect of gravity with the existing
motion, but supposed them to act alternately; Rivius, however,
understood this Composition, and saw that gravity must act as a
deflecting force at every point of the path. Galileo, in his second
Dialogue,12 makes Simplicius come to the same
conclusion. “Since,” he says, “there is nothing to support the body,
when it quits that which projects it, it cannot be but that its proper
gravity must operate,” and it must immediately begin to decline
downwards.
11 Problematum Astronomicorum et
Geometricorum Sectiones vii. &c. &c. Auctore Daniele
Santbach, Noviomago. Basileæ, 1561.
12 P. 147.
326 The Force of
Gravity which thus produces deflection and curvature in the path of a
body thrown obliquely, constantly increases the velocity of a
body when it falls vertically downwards. The universality of
this increase was obvious, both from reasoning and in fact; the law of
it could only be discovered by closer consideration; and the full
analysis of the problem required a distinct measure of the quantity of
Accelerating Force. Galileo, who first solved this problem, began by
viewing it as a question of fact, but conjectured the solution by
taking for granted that the rule must be the simplest possible.
“Bodies,” he says,13 “will fall in the most simple way,
because Natural Motions are always the most simple. When a stone
falls, if we consider the matter attentively, we shall find that there
is no addition, no increase, of the velocity more simple than that
which is always added in the same manner,” that is, when equal
additions take place in equal times; “which we shall easily understand
if we attend to the close connection of motion and time.” From this
Law, thus assumed, he deduced that the spaces described from the
beginning of the motion must be as the squares of the times; and,
again, assuming that the laws of descent for balls rolling down
inclined planes, must be the same as for bodies falling freely, he
verified this conclusion by experiment.
13 Dial. Sc. iv. p. 91.
It will, perhaps, occur to the reader that this argument, from the
simplicity of the assumed law, is somewhat insecure. It is not always
easy for us to discern what that greatest simplicity is, which nature
adopts in her laws. Accordingly, Galileo was led wrong by this way of
viewing the subject before he was led right. He at first supposed,
that the Velocity which the body had acquired at any point must be
proportional to the Space described from the point where the
motion began. This false law is as simple in its enunciation as the
true law, that the Velocity is proportional to the Time: it
had been asserted as the true law by M. Varro (De Motu
Tractatus, Genevæ, 1584), and by Baliani, a gentleman of Genoa,
who published it in 1638. It was, however, soon rejected by Galileo,
though it was afterwards taken up and defended by Casræus, one of
Galileo’s opponents. It so happens, indeed, that the false law is not
only at variance with fact, but with itself: it involves a
mathematical self-contradiction. This circumstance, however, was
accidental: it would be easy to state laws of the increase of velocity
which should be simple, and yet false in fact, though quite possible
in their own nature. 327
The Law of Velocity was hitherto, as we have seen, treated as a law
of phenomena, without reference to the Causes of the law. “The cause
of the acceleration of the motions of falling bodies is not,” Galileo
observes, “a necessary part of the investigation. Opinions are
different. Some refer it to the approach to the centre; others say
that there is a certain extension of the centrical medium, which,
closing behind the body, pushes it forwards. For the present, it is
enough for us to demonstrate certain properties of Accelerated Motion,
the acceleration being according to the very simple Law, that the
Velocity is proportional to the Time. And if we find that the
properties of such motion are verified by the motions of bodies
descending freely, we may suppose that the assumption agrees with the
laws of bodies falling freely by the action of gravity.”14
14 Gal. Op. iii. 91, 92.
It was, however, an easy step to conceive this acceleration as
caused by the continual action of Gravity. This account had already
been given by Benedetti, as we have seen. When it was once adopted,
Gravity was considered as a constant or uniform force;
on this point, indeed, the adherents of the law of Galileo and of that
of Casræus were agreed; but the question was, what is a
Uniform Force? The answer which Galileo was led to give was obviously
this;—that is a Uniform Force which generates equal
velocities in equal successive times; and this principle leads at once
to the doctrine, that Forces are to be compared by comparing the
Velocities generated by them in equal times.
Though, however, this was a consequence of the rule by which
Gravity is represented as a Uniform Force, the subject presents some
difficulty at first sight. It is not immediately obvious that we may
thus measure forces by the Velocity added in a given time,
without taking into account the velocity they have already. If we
communicate velocity to a body by the hand or by a spring, the effect
we produce in a second of time is lessened, when the body has already
a velocity which withdraws it from the pressure of the agent. But it
appears that this is not so in the case of gravity; the velocity added
in one second is the same, whatever downward motion the body already
possesses. A body falling from rest acquires a velocity, in one
second, of thirty-two feet; and if a cannon-ball were shot downwards
with a velocity of 1000 feet a second, it would equally, at the end of
one second, have received an accession of 32 feet to its velocity.
This conception of Gravity as a Uniform Force,—as constantly
and 328 equally
increasing the velocity of a descending body,—will
become clear by a little attention; but it undoubtedly presents
difficulty at first. Accordingly, we find that Descartes did not
accept it. “It is certain,” he says, “that a stone is not equally
disposed to receive a new motion or increase of velocity when it is
already moving very quickly, and when it is moving slowly.”
Descartes showed, by other expressions, that he had not caught hold
of the true notion of accelerating force. Thus, he says in a letter to
Mersenne, “I am astonished at what you tell me, of having found, by
experiment, that bodies thrown up in the air take neither more nor
less time to rise than to fall again; and you will excuse me if I say
that I look upon the experiment as a very difficult one to make
accurately.” Yet it is clear from the Notion of a Constant Force that
(omitting the resistance of the air) this equality must take place;
for the Force which will gradually destroy the whole velocity in a
certain time in ascending, will, in the same time, generate again the
same velocity by the same gradations inverted; and therefore the same
space will be passed over in the same time in the descent and in the
ascent.
Another difficulty arose from a necessary consequence of the Laws
of Falling Bodies thus established;—the proposition, namely,
that in acquiring its motion, a body passes through every intermediate
degree of velocity, from the smallest conceivable, up to that which it
at last acquires. When a body falls from rest, it begins to fall with
no velocity; the velocity increases with the time; and in
one-thousandth part of a second, the body has only acquired
one-thousandth part of the velocity which it has at the end of one
second.
This is certain, and manifest on consideration; yet there was at
first much difficulty raised on the subject of this assertion; and
disputes took place concerning the velocity with which a body
begins to fall. On this subject also Descartes did not form
clear notions. He writes to a correspondent, “I have been revising my
notes on Galileo, in which I have not said expressly that falling
bodies do not pass through every degree of slowness, but I said that
this cannot be known without knowing what Weight is, which comes to
the same thing; as to your example, I grant that it proves that every
degree of velocity is infinitely divisible, but not that a falling
body actually passes through all these divisions.”
The Principles of the Motion of Falling Bodies being thus
established by Galileo, the Deduction of the principal mathematical
consequences was, as is usual, effected with great rapidity, and is to
be found 329 in his
works, and in those of his scholars and successors. The motion of
bodies falling freely was, however, in such treatises, generally
combined with the motion of bodies Falling along Inclined Planes; a
part of the theory of which we have still to speak.
The Notion of Accelerating Force and of its operation, once formed,
was naturally applied in other cases than that of bodies falling
freely. The different velocities with which heavy and light bodies
fall were explained by the different resistance of the air, which
diminishes the accelerating force;15 and it was
boldly asserted, that in a vacuum a lock of wool and a piece of lead
would fall equally quickly. It was also maintained16 that any falling
body, however large and heavy, would always have its velocity in some
degree diminished by the air in which it falls, and would at last be
reduced to a state of uniform motion, as soon as the resistance
upwards became equal to the accelerating force downwards. Though the
law of progress of a body to this limiting velocity was not made out
till the Principia of Newton appeared, the views on which
Galileo made this assertion are perfectly sound, and show that he had
clearly conceived the nature and operation of accelerating and
retarding force.
15 Galileo, iii. 43.
16 iii. 54.
When Uniform Accelerating Forces had once been mastered, there
remained only mathematical difficulties in the treatment of Variable
Forces. A Variable Force was measured by the Limit of the
increment of the Velocity, compared with the increment of the Time;
just as a Variable Velocity was measured by the Limit of the increment
of the Space compared with that of the Time.
With this introduction of the Notion of Limits, we are, of course,
led to the Higher Geometry, either in its geometrical or its
analytical form. The general laws of bodies falling by the action of
any Variable Forces were given by Newton in the Seventh Section of the
Principia. The subject is there, according to Newton’s
preference of geometrical methods, treated by means of the Quadrature
of Curves; the Doctrine of Limits being exhibited in a peculiar manner
in the First Section of the work, in order to prepare the way for such
applications of it. Leibnitz, the Bernouillis, Euler, and since their
time, many other mathematicians, have treated such questions by means
of the analytical method of limits, the Differential Calculus. The
Rectilinear Motion of bodies acted upon by variable forces is, of
course, a simpler problem than their Curvilinear Motion, to which we
have now to proceed. But it 330 may be remarked that Newton, having
established the laws of Curvilinear Motion independently, has, in a
great part of his Seventh Section, deduced the simpler case of the
Rectilinear Motion from the move complex problem, by reasonings of
great ingenuity and beauty.
Sect. 3.—Establishment of the Second Law of
Motion.—Curvilinear Motions.
A slight degree of distinctness in men’s
mechanical notions enabled them to perceive, as we have already
explained, that a body which traces a curved line must be urged by
some force, by which it is constantly made to deviate from that
rectilinear path, which it would pursue if acted upon by no force.
Thus, when a body is made to describe a circle, as when a stone is
whirled round in a sling, we find that the string does exert such a
force on the stone; for the string is stretched by the effort, and if
it be too slender, it may thus be broken. This centrifugal
force of bodies moving in circles was noticed even by the
ancients. The effect of force to produce curvilinear motion also
appears in the paths described by projectiles. We have already seen
that though Tartalea did not perceive this correctly, Rivius, about
the same time, did.
To see that a transverse force would produce a curve, was one step;
to determine what the curve is, was another step, which involved the
discovery of the Second Law of Motion. This step was made by Galileo.
In his Dialogues on Motion, he asserts that a body projected
horizontally will retain a uniform motion in the horizontal direction,
and will have, compounded with this, a uniformly accelerated motion
downwards, that is, the motion of a body falling vertically from rest;
and will thus describe the curve called a parabola.
The Second Law of Motion consists of this assertion in a general
form;—namely, that in all cases the motion which the force will
produce is compounded with the motion which the body previously has.
This was not obvious; for Cardan had maintained,17 that “if a body
is moved by two motions at once, it will come to the place resulting
from their composition slower than by either of them.” The proof of
the truth of the law to Galileo’s mind was, so far as we collect from
the Dialogue itself, the simplicity of the supposition, and his clear
perception of the causes which, in some cases, produced an obvious
deviation in practice 331 from this theoretical result. For it may
be observed, that the curvilinear paths ascribed to military
projectiles by Rivius and Tartalea, and by other writers who followed
them, as Digges and Norton in our own country, though utterly
different from the theoretical form, the parabola, do, in fact,
approach nearer the true paths of a cannon or musket ball than a
parabola would do; and this approximation more especially exists in
that which at first sight appears most absurd in the old theory;
namely, the assertion that the ball, which ascends in a sloping
direction, finally descends vertically. In consequence of the
resistance of the air, this is really the path of a projectile; and
when the velocity is very great, as in military projectiles, the
deviation from the parabolic form is very manifest. This cause of
discrepancy between the theory, which does not take resistance into
the account, and the fact, Galileo perceived; and accordingly he
says,18 that the velocities of the projectiles,
in such cases, may be considered as excessive and supernatural. With
the due allowance to such causes, he maintained that his theory was
verified, and might be applied in practice. Such practical
applications of the doctrine of projectiles no doubt had a share in
establishing the truth of Galileo’s views. We must not forget,
however, that the full establishment of this second law of motion was
the result of the theoretical and experimental discussions concerning
the motion of the earth: its fortunes were involved in those of the
Copernican system; and it shared the triumph of that doctrine. This
triumph was already decisive, indeed, in the time of Galileo, but not
complete till the time of Newton.
17 Op. vol. iv. p. 490.
18 Op. vol. iii. p. 147.
Sect. 4.—Generalization of the Laws of
Equilibrium.—Principle of Virtual Velocities.
It was known, even as early as Aristotle,
that the two weights which balance each other on the lever, if they
move at all, move with velocities which are in the inverse proportions
of the weights. The peculiar resources of the Greek language, which
could state this relation of inverse proportionality in a single word
(ἀντιπέπονθεν), fixed it in men’s minds, and prompted them to
generalize from this property. Such attempts were at first made with
indistinct ideas, and on conjecture only, and had, therefore, no
scientific value. This is the judgment which we must pass on the book
of Jordanus Nemorarius, which 332 we have already
mentioned. Its reasonings are professedly on Aristotelian principles,
and exhibit the common Aristotelian absence of all distinct mechanical
ideas. But in Varro, whose Tractatus de Motu appeared in 1584,
we find the principle, in a general form, not satisfactorily proved,
indeed, but much more distinctly conceived. This is his first theorem:
“Duarum virium connexarum quarum (si moveantur) motus erunt ipsis
ἀντιπεπονθῶς proportionales, neutra alteram movebit, sed equilibrium
facient.” The proof offered of this is, that the resistance to a force
is as the motion produced; and, as we have seen, the theorem is
rightly applied in the example of the wedge. From this time it appears
to have been usual to prove the properties of machines by means of
this principle. This is done, for instance, in Les Raisons des
Forces Mouvantes, the production of Solomon de Caus, engineer to
the Elector Palatine, published at Antwerp in 1616; in which the
effect of Toothed-Wheels and of the Screw is determined in this
manner, but the Inclined Plane is not treated of. The same is the case
in Bishop Wilkins’s Mathematical Magic, in 1648.
When the true doctrine of the Inclined Plane had been established,
the laws of equilibrium for all the simple machines or Mechanical
Powers, as they had usually been enumerated in books on Mechanics,
were brought into view; for it was easy to see that the Wedge
and the Screw involved the same principle as the Inclined
Plane, and the Pulley could obviously be reduced to the
Lever. It was, also, not difficult for a person with clear
mechanical ideas to perceive how any other combination of bodies, on
which pressure and traction are exerted, may be reduced to these
simple machines, so as to disclose the relation of the forces. Hence
by the discovery of Stevinus, all problems of equilibrium were
essentially solved.
The conjectural generalization of the property of the lever, which
we have just mentioned, enabled mathematicians to express the solution
of all these problems by means of one proposition. This was done by
saying, that in raising a weight by any machine, we lose in
Time what we gain in Force; the weight raised moves as much
slower than the power, as it is larger than the
power. This was explained with great clearness by Galileo, in the
preface to his Treatise on Mechanical Science, published in
1592.
The motions, however, which we here suppose the parts of the
machine to have, are not motions which the forces produce; for at
present we are dealing with the case in which the forces balance each
other, and therefore produce no motion. But we ascribe to the 333 Weights and Powers
hypothetical motions, arising from some other cause; and then, by the
construction of the machine, the velocities of the Weights and Powers
must have certain definite ratios. These velocities, being thus
hypothetically supposed and not actually produced, are called
Virtual Velocities. And the general law of equilibrium is, that
in any machine, the Weights which balance each other, are reciprocally
to each other as their Virtual Velocities. This is called the
Principle of Virtual Velocities.
This Principle (which was afterwards still further generalized) is,
by some of the admirers of Galileo, dwelt upon as one of his great
services to Mechanics. But if we examine it more nearly, we shall see
that it has not much importance in our history. It is a
generalization, but a generalization established rather by enumeration
of cases, than by any induction proceeding upon one distinct Idea,
like those generalizations of Facts by which Laws are primarily
established. It rather serves verbally to conjoin Laws previously
known, than to exhibit a connection in them: it is rather a help for
the memory than a proof for the reason.
The Principle of Virtual Velocities is so far from implying any
clear possession of mechanical ideas, that any one who knows the
property of the Lever, whether he is capable of seeing the reason for
it or not, can see that the greater weight moves slower in the exact
proportion of its greater magnitude. Accordingly, Aristotle, whose
entire want of sound mechanical views we have shown, has yet noticed
this truth. When Galileo treats of it, instead of offering any reasons
which could independently establish this principle, he gives his
readers a number of analogies and illustrations, many of them very
loose ones. Thus the raising a great weight by a small force, he
illustrates by supposing the weight broken into many small parts, and
conceiving those parts raised one by one. By other persons, the
analogy, already intimated, of gain and loss is referred to as an
argument for the principle in question. Such images may please the
fancy, but they cannot be accepted as mechanical reasons.
Since Galileo neither first enunciated this rule, nor ever proved
it as an independent principle of Mechanics, we cannot consider the
discovery of it as one of his mechanical achievements. Still less can
we compare his reference to this principle with Stevinus’s proof of
the Inclined Plane; which, as we have seen, was rigorously inferred
from the sound axiom, that a body cannot put itself in motion. If we
were to assent to the really self-evident axioms of Stevinus, only in
virtue 334 of the
unproved verbal generalization of Galileo, we should be in great
danger of allowing ourselves to be referred successively from one
truth to another, without any reasonable hope of ever arriving at any
thing ultimate and fundamental.
But though this Principle of Virtual Velocity cannot be looked upon
as a great discovery of Galileo, it is a highly useful rule; and the
various forms under which he and his successors urged it, tended much
to dissipate the vague wonder with which the effects of machines had
been looked upon; and thus to diffuse sounder and clearer notions on
such subjects.
The Principle of Virtual Velocities also affected the progress of
mechanical science in another way: it suggested some of the analogies
by the aid of which the Third Law of Motion was made out; leading to
the adoption of the notion of Momentum as the arithmetical
product of weight and velocity. Since on a machine on which a weight
of two pounds at one part balances three pounds at another part, the
former weight would move through three inches while the latter would
move through two inches; we see (since three multiplied into two is
equal to two multiplied into three) that the Product of the
weight and the velocity is the same for the two balancing weights; and
if we call this Product Momentum, the Law of Equilibrium is,
that when two weights balance on a machine, the Momentum of the two
would be the same, if they were put in motion.
The Notion of Momentum was here employed in connection with Virtual
Velocities; but it also came under consideration in treating of Actual
Velocities, as we shall soon see.
Sect. 5.—Attempts at the Third Law of
Motion.—Notion of Momentum.
In the questions we have hitherto had to
consider respecting Motion, no regard is had to the Size of the body
moved, but only to the Velocity and Direction of the motion. We must
now trace the progress of knowledge respecting the mode in which the
Mass of the body influences the effect of Force. This is a more
difficult and complex branch of the subject; but it is one which
requires to be noticed, as obviously as the former. Questions
belonging to this department of Mechanics, as well as to the others,
occur in Aristotle’s Mechanical Problems. “Why,” says he, “is it, that
neither very small nor very large bodies go far when we throw them;
but, in order that this may 335 happen, the thing thrown must have a
certain proportion to the agent which throws it? Is it that what is
thrown or pushed must react19 against that which pushes it; and that
a body so large as not to yield at all, or so small as to yield
entirely, and not to react, produces no throw or push?” The same
confusion of ideas prevailed after his time; and mechanical questions
were in vain discussed by means of general and abstract terms,
employed with no distinct and steady meaning; such as impetus,
power, momentum, virtue, energy, and the
like. From some of these speculations we may judge how thorough the
confusion in men’s heads had become. Cardan perplexes himself with the
difficulty, already mentioned, of the comparison of the forces of
bodies at rest and in motion. If the Force of a body depends on its
velocity, as it appears to do, how is it that a body at rest has any
Force at all, and how can it resist the slightest effort, or exert any
pressure? He flatters himself that he solves the question, by
asserting that bodies at rest have an occult motion. “Corpus movetur
occulto motu quiescendo.”—Another puzzle, with which he appears
to distress himself rather more wantonly, is this: “If one man can
draw half of a certain weight, and another man also one half; when the
two act together, these proportions should be compounded; so that they
ought to be able to draw one half of one half, or one quarter only.”
The talent which ingenious men had for getting into such perplexities,
was certainly at one time very great. Arriaga,20 who wrote in
1639, is troubled to discover how several flat weights, lying one upon
another on a board, should produce a greater pressure than the lowest
one alone produces, since that alone touches the board. Among other
solutions, he suggests that the board affects the upper weight, which
it does not touch, by determining its ubication, or
whereness.
19 ἀντερείδειν.
20 Rod. de Arriaga, Cursus
Philosophicus. Paris, 1639.
Aristotle’s doctrine, that a body ten times as heavy as another,
will fall ten times as fast, is another instance of the confusion of
Statical and Dynamical Forces: the Force of the greater body, while
at rest, is ten times as great as that of the other; but the
Force as measured by the velocity produced, is equal in the
two cases. The two bodies would fall downwards with the same rapidity,
except so far as they are affected by accidental causes. The merit of
proving this by experiment, and thus refuting the Aristotelian dogma,
is usually ascribed to Galileo, who made his experiment from the
famous leaning tower of Pisa, about 1590. But others about the same
time had not 336
overlooked so obvious a fact—F. Piccolomini, in his Liber
Scientiæ de Natura, published at Padua, in 1597, says, “On the
subject of the motion of heavy and light bodies, Aristotle has put
forth various opinions, which are contrary to sense and experience,
and has delivered rules concerning the proportion of quickness and
slowness, which are palpably false. For a stone twice as great does
not move twice as fast.” And Stevinus, in the Appendix to his
Statics, describes his having made the experiment, and speaks with
great correctness of the apparent deviations from the rule, arising
from the resistance of the air. Indeed, the result followed by very
obvious reasoning; for ten bricks, in contact with each other, side by
side, would obviously fall in the same time as one; and these might be
conceived to form a body ten times as large as one of them.
Accordingly, Benedetti, in 1585, reasons in this manner with regard to
bodies of different size, though he retains Aristotle’s error as to
the different velocity of bodies of different density.
The next step in this subject is more clearly due to Galileo; he
discovered the true proportion which the Accelerating Force of a body
falling down an inclined plane bears to the Accelerating Force of the
same body falling freely. This was at first a happy conjecture; it was
then confirmed by experiments, and, finally, after some hesitation, it
was referred to its true principle, the Third Law of Motion, with
proper elementary simplicity. The Principle here spoken of is
this:—that for the same body, the Dynamical effect of force is
as the Statical effect; that is, the Velocity which any force
generates in a given time when it puts the body in motion, is
proportional to the Pressure which the same force produces in a body
at rest. The Principle, so stated, appears very simple and obvious;
yet this was not the form in which it suggested itself either to
Galileo or to other persons who sought to prove it. Galileo, in his
Dialogues on Motion, assumes, as his fundamental proposition on
this subject, one much less evident than that we have quoted, but one
in which that is involved. His Postulate is,21 that when the
same body falls down different planes of the same height, the
velocities acquired are equal. He confirms and illustrates this by a
very ingenious experiment on a pendulum, showing that the weight
swings to the same height whatever path it be compelled to follow.
Torricelli, in his treatise published 1644, says that he had heard
that Galileo had, towards the end of his life, proved his 337 assumption, but that,
not having seen the proof, he will give his own. In this he refers us
to the right principle, but appears not distinctly to conceive the
proof, since he estimates momentum indiscriminately by the
statical Pressure of a body, and by its Velocity when in motion; as if
these two quantities were self-evidently equal. Huyghens, in 1673,
expresses himself dissatisfied with the proof by which Galileo’s
assumption was supported in the later editions of his works. His own
proof rests on this principle;—that if a body fall down one
inclined plane, and proceed up another with the velocity thus
acquired, it cannot, under any circumstances, ascend to a higher
position than that from which it fell. This principle coincides very
nearly with Galileo’s experimental illustration. In truth, however,
Galileo’s principle, which Huyghens thus slights, may be looked upon
as a satisfactory statement of the true law  namely, that, in the same
body, the velocity produced is as the pressure which produces it. “We
are agreed,” he says,22 “that, in a movable body, the
impetus, energy, momentum, or propension to
motion, is as great as is the force or least
resistance which suffices to support it.” The various terms
here used, both for dynamical and statical Force, show that Galileo’s
ideas were not confused by the ambiguity of any one term, as appears
to have happened to some mathematicians. The principle thus announced,
is, as we shall see, one of great extent and value; and we read with
interest the circumstances of its discovery, which are thus
narrated.23 When Viviani was studying with Galileo,
he expressed his dissatisfaction at the want of any clear reason for
Galileo’s postulate respecting the equality of velocities acquired
down inclined planes of the same heights; the consequence of which
was, that Galileo, as he lay, the same night, sleepless through
indisposition, discovered the proof which he had long sought in vain,
and introduced it in the subsequent editions. It is easy to see, by
looking at the proof, that the discoverer had had to struggle, not for
intermediate steps of reasoning between remote notions, as in a
problem of geometry, but for a clear possession of ideas which were
near each other, and which he had not yet been able to bring into
contact, because he had not yet a sufficiently firm grasp of them.
Such terms as Momentum and Force had been sources of confusion from
the time of Aristotle; and it required considerable steadiness of
thought to compare the forces of bodies at rest and in motion under
the obscurity and vacillation thus produced.
21 Opere, iii. 96.
22 Galileo, Op. iii. 104.
23 Drinkwater, Life of Galileo,
p. 59.
338 The term
Momentum had been introduced to express the force of bodies in
motion, before it was known what that effect was. Galileo, in his
Discorso intorno alle Cose che stanno in su l’ Acqua, says,
that “Momentum is the force, efficacy, or virtue, with which the
motion moves and the body moved resists, depending not upon weight
only, but upon the velocity, inclination, and any other cause of such
virtue.” When he arrived at more precision in his views, he
determined, as we have seen, that, in the same body, the Momentum is
proportional to the Velocity; and, hence it was easily seen
that in different bodies it was proportional to the Velocity and Mass
jointly. The principle thus enunciated is capable of very extensive
application, and, among other consequences, leads to a determination
of the results of the mutual Percussion of Bodies. But though Galileo,
like others of his predecessors and contemporaries, had speculated
concerning the problem of Percussion, he did not arrive at any
satisfactory conclusion; and the problem remained for the
mathematicians of the next generation to solve.
We may here notice Descartes and his Laws of Motion, the
publication of which is sometimes spoken of as an important event in
the history of Mechanics. This is saying far too much. The
Principia of Descartes did little for physical science. His
assertion of the Laws of Motion, in their most general shape, was
perhaps an improvement in form; but his Third Law is false in
substance. Descartes claimed several of the discoveries of Galileo and
others of his contemporaries; but we cannot assent to such claims,
when we find that, as we shall see, he did not understand, or would
not apply, the Laws of Motion when he had them before him. If we were
to compare Descartes with Galileo, we might say, that of the
mechanical truths which were easily attainable in the beginning of the
seventeenth century, Galileo took hold of as many, and Descartes of as
few, as was well possible for a man of genius.
[2d Ed.] [The following remarks of M. Libri appear to be just.
After giving an account of the doctrines put forth on the subject of
Astronomy, Mechanics, and other branches of science, by Leonardo da
Vinci, Fracastoro, Maurolycus, Commandinus, Benedetti, he adds
(Hist. des Sciences Mathématiques en Italie, t. iii. p. 131):
“This short analysis is sufficient to show that, at the period at
which we are arrived, Aristotle no longer reigned unquestioned in the
Italian Schools. If we had to write the history of philosophy, we
should prove by a multitude of facts that it was the Italians who
overthrew the ancient idol of philosophers. Men go on incessantly
repeating that the 339 struggle was begun by Descartes, and
they proclaim him the legislator of modern philosophers. But when we
examine the philosophical writings of Fracastoro, of Benedetti, of
Cardan, and above all, those of Galileo; when we see on all sides
energetic protests raised against the peripatetic doctrines; we ask,
what there remained for the inventor of vortices to do, in overturning
the natural philosophy of Aristotle? In addition to this, the
memorable labors of the School of Cosenza, of Telesius, of Giordano
Bruno, of Campanella; the writings of Patricius, who was, besides, a
good geometer; of Nizolius, whom Leibnitz esteemed so highly, and of
the other metaphysicians of the same epoch,—prove that the
ancient philosophy had already lost its empire on that side the Alps,
when Descartes threw himself upon the enemy now put to the rout. The
yoke was cast off in Italy, and all Europe had only to follow the
example, without its being necessary to give a new impulse to real
science.”
In England, we are accustomed to hear Francis Bacon, rather than
Descartes, spoken of as the first great antagonist of the Aristotelian
schools, and the legislator of modern philosophy. But it is true, both
of one and the other, that the overthrow of the ancient system had
been effectively begun before their time by the practical discoverers
here mentioned, and others who, by experiment and reasoning,
established truths inconsistent with the received Aristotelian
doctrines. Gilbert in England, Kepler in Germany, as well as Benedetti
and Galileo in Italy, gave a powerful impulse to the cause of real
knowledge, before the influence of Bacon and Descartes had produced
any general effect. What Bacon really did was this;—that by the
august image which he presented of a future Philosophy, the rival of
the Aristotelian, and far more powerful and extensive, he drew to it
the affections and hopes of all men of comprehensive and vigorous
minds, as well as of those who attended to special trains of
discovery. He announced a New Method, not merely a correction of
special current errors; he thus converted the Insurrection into a
Revolution, and established a new philosophical Dynasty. Descartes
had, in some degree, the same purpose; and, in addition to this, he
not only proclaimed himself the author of a New Method, but professed
to give a complete system of the results of the Method. His physical
philosophy was put forth as complete and demonstrative, and thus
involved the vices of the ancient dogmatism. Telesius and Campanella
had also grand notions of an entire reform in the method of
philosophizing, as I have noticed in the Philosophy of the
Inductive Sciences, Book xii.] 340</div></body></text></TEI>