<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="46">CHAPTER I.
Prelude to Copernicus.

Nicolas of Cus.
I WILL quote the passage, in
the writings of this author, which bears upon the subject in question.
I translate it from the edition of his book De Docta
Ignorantia, from his works published at Basil in 1565. He praises
Learned Ignorance—that is, Acknowledged
Ignorance—as the source of knowledge. His ground for asserting
the motions of the earth is, that there is no such thing as perfect
rest, or an exact centre, or a perfect circle, nor perfect uniformity
of motion. “Neque verus circulus dabilis est, quinetiam verior dari
possit, neque unquam uno tempore sicut alio æqualiter præcisè, aut
movetur, aut circulum veri similem, æqualem describit, etiamsi nobis
hoc non appareat. Et ubicumque quis fuerit, se in centro esse credit.”
(Lib. i. cap. xi. p. 39.) He adds, “The Ancients did not attain to
this knowledge, because they were wanting in Learned Ignorance. Now it
is manifest to us that the Earth is truly in motion, although this do
not appear to us; since we do not apprehend motion except by
comparison with something fixed. For if any one were in a boat in the
middle of a river, ignorant that the water was flowing, and not seeing
the banks, how could he apprehend that the boat was moving? And thus
since every one, whether he be in the Earth, or in the Sun, or in any
other star, thinks that he is in an immovable centre, and that
everything else is moving; he would assign different poles for
himself, others as being in the Sun, others in the Earth, and others
in the Moon, and so of the rest. Whence the machine of the world is as
if it had its centre everywhere and its circumference nowhere.” This
train of thought 524 might be a preparation for the reception
of the Copernican system; but it is very different from the doctrine
that the Sun is the centre of the Planetary Motions.
</div></body></text></TEI>