<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="34">

CHAPTER XXV.
OF RELATION.

1. Relation, what.


BESIDES the ideas, whether simple or complex, that the mind has of things as
they are in themselves, there are others it gets from their comparison one with
another. The understanding, in the consideration of anything, is not confined
to that precise object: it can carry any idea as it were beyond itself, or at
least look beyond it, to see how it stands in conformity to any other. When the
mind so considers one thing, that it does as it were bring it to, and set it by
another, and carries its view from one to the other—this is, as the words
import, RELATION and RESPECT; and the denominations given to positive things,
intimating that respect, and serving as marks to lead the thoughts beyond the
subject itself denominated, to something distinct from it, are what we call
RELATIVES; and the things so brought together, RELATED. Thus, when the mind
considers Caius as such a positive being, it takes nothing into that idea but
what really exists in Caius; v.g. when I consider him as a man, I have nothing
in my mind but the complex idea of the species, man. So likewise, when I say
Caius is a white man, I have nothing but the bare consideration of a man who
hath that white colour. But when I give Caius the name HUSBAND, I intimate some
other person; and when I give him the name WHITER, I intimate some other thing:
in both cases my thought is led to something beyond Caius, and there are two
things brought into consideration. And since any idea, whether simple or
complex, may be the occasion why the mind thus brings two things together, and
as it were takes a view of them at once, though still considered as distinct:
therefore any of our ideas may be the foundation of relation. As in the
above-mentioned instance, the contract and ceremony of marriage with Sempronia
is the occasion of the denomination and relation of husband; and the colour
white the occasion why he is said to be whiter than free-stone.


2. Ideas of relations without correlative Terms, not easily apprehended.


These and the like relations, expressed by relative terms that have others
answering them, with a reciprocal intimation, as father and son, bigger and
less, cause and effect, are very obvious to every one, and everybody at first
sight perceives the relation. For father and son, husband and wife, and such
other correlative terms, seem so nearly to belong one to another, and, through
custom, do so readily chime and answer one another in people’s memories, that,
upon the naming of either of them, the thoughts are presently carried beyond
the thing so named; and nobody overlooks or doubts of a relation, where it is
so plainly intimated. But where languages have failed to give correlative
names, there the relation is not always so easily taken notice of. CONCUBINE
is, no doubt, a relative name, as well as wife: but in languages where this and
the like words have not a correlative term, there people are not so apt to take
them to be so, as wanting that evident mark of relation which is between
correlatives, which seem to explain one another, and not to be able to exist,
but together. Hence it is, that many of those names, which, duly considered, do
include evident relations, have been called EXTERNAL DENOMINATIONS. But all
names that are more than empty sounds must signify some idea, which is either
in the thing to which the name is applied, and then it is positive, and is
looked on as united to and existing in the thing to which the denomination is
given; or else it arises from the respect the mind finds in it to something
distinct from it, with which it considers it, and then it includes a relation.


3. Some seemingly absolute Terms contain Relations.


Another sort of relative terms there is, which are not looked on to be either
relative, or so much as external denominations: which yet, under the form and
appearance of signifying something absolute in the subject, do conceal a tacit,
though less observable, relation. Such are the seemingly positive terms of OLD,
GREAT, IMPERFECT, &c., whereof I shall have occasion to speak more at large
in the following chapters.


4. Relation different from the Things related.


This further may be observed, That the ideas of relations may be the same in
men who have far different ideas of the things that are related, or that are
thus compared: v. g. those who have far different ideas of a man, may yet agree
in the notion of a father; which is a notion superinduced to the substance, or
man, and refers only to an act of that thing called man whereby he contributed
to the generation of one of his own kind, let man be what it will.


5. Change of Relation may be without any Change in the things related.


The nature therefore of relation consists in the referring or comparing two
things one to another; from which comparison one or both comes to be
denominated. And if either of those things be removed, or cease to be, the
relation ceases, and the denomination consequent to it, though the other
receive in itself no alteration at all; v.g. Caius, whom I consider to-day as a
father, ceases to be so to-morrow, only by the death of his son, without any
alteration made in himself. Nay, barely by the mind’s changing the object to
which it compares anything, the same thing is capable of having contrary
denominations at the same time: v.g. Caius, compared to several persons, may
truly be said to be older and younger, stronger and weaker, &c.


6. Relation only betwixt two things.


Whatsoever doth or can exist, or be considered as one thing is positive: and so
not only simple ideas and substances, but modes also, are positive beings:
though the parts of which they consist are very often relative one to another:
but the whole together considered as one thing, and producing in us the complex
idea of one thing, which idea is in our minds, as one picture, though an
aggregate of divers parts, and under one name, it is a positive or absolute
thing, or idea. Thus a triangle, though the parts thereof compared one to
another be relative, yet the idea of the whole is a positive absolute idea. The
same may be said of a family, a tune, &c.; for there can be no relation but
betwixt two things considered as two things. There must always be in relation
two ideas or things, either in themselves really separate, or considered as
distinct, and then a ground or occasion for their comparison.


7. All Things capable of Relation.


Concerning relation in general, these things may be considered:


First, That there is no one thing, whether simple idea, substance, mode, or
relation, or name of either of them, which is not capable of almost an infinite
number of considerations in reference to other things: and therefore this makes
no small part of men’s thoughts and words: v.g. one single man may at once be
concerned in, and sustain all these following relations, and many more, viz.
father, brother, son, grandfather, grandson, father-in-law, son-in-law,
husband, friend, enemy, subject, general, judge, patron, client, professor,
European, Englishman, islander, servant, master, possessor, captain, superior,
inferior, bigger, less, older, younger, contemporary, like, unlike, &c., to
an almost infinite number: he being capable of as many relations as there can
be occasions of comparing him to other things, in any manner of agreement,
disagreement, or respect whatsoever. For, as I said, relation is a way of
comparing or considering two things [*dropped line] from that comparison; and
sometimes giving even the relation itself a name.


8. Our Ideas of Relations often clearer than of the Subjects related.


Secondly, This further may be considered concerning relation, that though it be
not contained in the real existence of things, but something extraneous and
superinduced, yet the ideas which relative words stand for are often clearer
and more distinct than of those substances to which they do belong. The notion
we have of a father or brother is a great deal clearer and more distinct than
that we have of a man; or, if you will, PATERNITY is a thing whereof it is
easier to have a clear idea, than of HUMANITY; and I can much easier conceive
what a friend is, than what God; because the knowledge of one action, or one
simple idea, is oftentimes sufficient to give me the notion of a relation; but
to the knowing of any substantial being, an accurate collection of sundry ideas
is necessary. A man, if he compares two things together, can hardly be supposed
not to know what it is wherein he compares them: so that when he compares any
things together, he cannot but have a very clear idea of that relation. THE
IDEAS, THEN, OF RELATIONS, ARE CAPABLE AT LEAST OF BEING MORE PERFECT AND
DISTINCT IN OUR MINDS THAN THOSE OF SUBSTANCES. Because it is commonly hard to
know all the simple ideas which are really in any substance, but for the most
part easy enough to know the simple ideas that make up any relation I think on,
or have a name for: v.g. comparing two men in reference to one common parent,
it is very easy to frame the ideas of brothers, without having yet the perfect
idea of a man. For significant relative words, as well as others, standing only
for ideas; and those being all either simple, or made up of simple ones, it
suffices for the knowing the precise idea the relative term stands for, to have
a clear conception of that which is the foundation of the relation; which may
be done without having a perfect and clear idea of the thing it is attributed
to. Thus, having the notion that one laid the egg out of which the other was
hatched, I have a clear idea of the relation of DAM and CHICK between the two
cassiowaries in St. James’s Park; though perhaps I have but a very obscure and
imperfect idea of those birds themselves.


9. Relations all terminate in simple Ideas.


Thirdly, Though there be a great number of considerations wherein things may be
compared one with another, and so a multitude of relations, yet they all
terminate in, and are concerned about those simple ideas, either of sensation
or reflection, which I think to be the whole materials of all our knowledge. To
clear this, I shall show it in the most considerable relations that we have any
notion of; and in some that seem to be the most remote from sense or
reflection: which yet will appear to have their ideas from thence, and leave it
past doubt that the notions we have of them are but certain simple ideas, and
so originally derived from sense or reflection.


10. Terms leading the Mind beyond the Subject denominated, are relative.


Fourthly, That relation being the considering of one thing with another which
is extrinsical to it, it is evident that all words that necessarily lead the
mind to any other ideas than are supposed really to exist in that thing to
which the words are applied are relative words: v.g.a MAN, BLACK, MERRY,
THOUGHTFUL, THIRSTY, ANGRY, EXTENDED; these and the like are all absolute,
because they neither signify nor intimate anything but what does or is supposed
really to exist in the man thus denominated; but FATHER, BROTHER, KING,
HUSBAND, BLACKER, MERRIER, &c., are words which, together with the thing
they denominate, imply also something else separate and exterior to the
existence of that thing.


11. All relatives made up of simple ideas.


Having laid down these premises concerning relation in general, I shall now
proceed to show, in some instances, how all the ideas we have of relation are
made up, as the others are, only of simple ideas; and that they all, how
refined or remote from sense soever they seem, terminate at last in simple
ideas. I shall begin with the most comprehensive relation, wherein all things
that do, or can exist, are concerned, and that is the relation of CAUSE and
EFFECT: the idea whereof, how derived from the two fountains of all our
knowledge, sensation and reflection, I shall in the next place consider.


</div></body></text></TEI>