<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="28">
FURTHER ILLUSTRATIONS OF THE APHORISMS
ON SCIENTIFIC LANGUAGE, FROM THE
RECENT COURSE OF SCIENCES.
1. Botany.
The nomenclature of Botany as rescued from confusion
by Linnæus, has in modern times been in some
danger of relapsing into disorder or becoming intolerably
extensive, in consequence of the multiplication of
genera by the separation of one old genus into several
new ones, and the like subdivisions of the higher groups,
as subclasses and classes. This inconvenience, and the
origin of it, have been so well pointed out by Mr. G.
Bentham65,
that I shall venture to adopt his judgment
as an Aphorism, and give his reasons for it.
65 Linnæan Society’s Proceedings, vol. ii. p. 30 (June, 1857).
Aphorism XXIII.
It is of the greatest importance that the Groups which
give their substantive names to every included species should
remain large.
It will be recollected that according to the Linnæan
nomenclature, the genus is marked by a substantive, (as
Rosa), and the species designated by an adjective added
to this substantive, (as Rosa Alpina); while the natural
orders are described by adjectives taken substantively,
(as Rosaceæ), But this rule, though it has been
universally assented to in theory, has often been deviated
from in practice. The number of known species
having much increased, and the language of Linnæus
and the principles of Jussieu having much augmented
the facilities for the study of affinities, botanists have
become aware that the species of a genus and the genera
of an order can be collected into intermediate groups 347
as natural and as well defined as the genera and orders
themselves, and names are required for these subordinate
groups as much as for the genera and orders.
Now two courses have been followed in providing
names for these subordinate groups.
1. The original genera (considering the case of genera
in the first place) have been preserved, (if well founded);
and the lower groups have been called subgenera, sections,
subsections, divisions, &c.: and the original names
of the genera have been maintained for the purpose of
nomenclature, in order to retain a convenient and stable
language. But when these subordinate groups are so
well defined and so natural, that except for the convenience
of language, they might be made good genera,
there are given also to these subordinate groups,
substantive or substantively-taken adjective names. When
these subordinate groups are less defined or less natural,
either no names at all are given, and they are distinguished
by figures or signs such as *, **, or § 1, § 2,
&c. or there are given them mere adjective names.
Or, 2, To regard these intermediate groups between
species and the original genera, as so many independent
genera; and to give them substantive names, to be used
in ordinary botanical nomenclature.
Now the second course is that which has produced
the intolerable multiplication of genera in modern
times; and the first course is the only one which can
save botanical nomenclature from replunging into the
chaos in which Linnæus found it. It was strongly
advocated by the elder De Candolle; although in the
latter years of his life, seeing how general was the
disposition to convert his subgenera and sections into
genera, he himself more or less gave in to the general
practice. The same principle was adopted by Endlichen,
but he again was disposed to go far in giving
substantive names to purely technical or ill-defined
subsections of genera.
The multiplication of genera has been much too
common. Botanists have a natural pride in establishing
new genera (or orders); and besides this, it is felt
how useful it is, in the study of affinities, to define and 348
name all natural groups in every grade, however numerous
they may be: and in the immense variety of language
it is found easy to coin names indefinitely.
But the arguments on the other side much preponderate.
In attempting to introduce all these new
names into ordinary botanical language, the memory is
taxed beyond the capabilities of any mind, and the original
and legitimate object of the Linnæan nomenclature is
wholly lost sight of. In a purely scientific view
it matters little if the Orders are converted into Classes
or Alliances, the Genera into Orders, and the Sections
or Subsections into Genera: their relative importance
does not depend on the names given to them, but on
their height in the scale of comprehensiveness. But
for language, the great implement without which science
cannot work, it is of the greatest importance, as our
Aphorism declares, That the groups which give their
substantive names to every species which they include,
should remain large. If, independently of the inevitable
increase of Genera by new discoveries, such old
ones as Ficus, Begonia, Arum, Erica, &c. are divided
into 10, 20, 30, or 40 independent Genera, with names
and characters which are to be recollected before any
one species can be spoken of;—if Genera are to be
reckoned by tens of thousands instead of by thousands;—the
range of any individual botanist will be limited
to a small portion of the whole field of the sciences.
And in like manner with regard to Orders, so long
as the number of Orders can be kept within, or not
much beyond a couple of hundred, it may reasonably
be expected that a botanist of ordinary capacity shall
obtain a sufficient general idea of their nature and
characters to call them at any time individually to his mind
for the purpose of comparison: but if we double the
number of Orders, all is confusion.
The inevitable confusion and the necessity of maintaining
in some way the larger groups, have been perceived
by those even who have gone the furthest in
lowering the scale of Orders and Genera. As a remedy
for this confusion, they propose to erect the old genera
into independent orders, and the old orders into classes 349
or divisions. But this is but an incomplete resumption
of the old principles, without the advantage of the old
nomenclature.
And it will not be asserted, with regard to these new
genera, formed by cutting up the old ones, that the new
group is better defined than the group above it: on the
contrary, it is frequently less so. It is not pretended
that Urostigma or Phannacosyce, new genera formed
out of the old genus Ficus, are better defined than the
genus Ficus: or that the new genera which have lately
been cut out of the old genus Begonia, form more natural
groups than Begonia itself does. The principle
which seems to be adopted in such subdivisions of old
genera is this: that the lowest definable group above a
species is a genus. If we were to go a step further,
every species becomes a genus with a substantive name.
It ought always to be recollected that though the
analytical process carried to the uttermost, and
separating groups by observation of differences, is necessary for
the purpose of ascertaining the facts upon which botany
or any other classificatory science is based, it is
a judicious synthesis alone, associating individuals by the ties
of language, which can enable the human mind to take
a comprehensive view of these facts, to deduce from
them the principles of the science, or to communicate
to others either facts or principles.
2. Comparative Anatomy.
The Language of Botany, as framed by Linnæus, and
regulated by his Canons, is still the most notable and
successful example of scientific terminology which has
obtained general reception among naturalists. But the
Language of Anatomy, and especially of the Comparative
Anatomy of the skeleton, has of late been an object
of great attention to physiologists; and especially to
Mr. Owen; and the collection of terms which he has
proposed are selected with so much thought and care,
that they may minister valuable lessons to us in this
part of our subject.
There is, at first sight, this broad difference between
the descriptive language of Botany and of Comparative 350
Anatomy; that in the former science, we have comparatively
few parts to describe, (calyx, corolla, stamen,
pistil, pericarp, seed, &c.): while each of these parts is
susceptible of many forms, for describing which with
precision many terms must be provided: in Comparative
Anatomy, on the other hand, the skeletons of many animals
are to be regarded as modifications of a common
type, and the terms by which their parts are described
are to mark this community of type. The terminology
of Botany has for its object description; the language
of Comparative Anatomy must have for its basis morphology.
Accordingly, Mr. Owen’s terms are selected
so as to express the analogies, or, as he calls them, the
homologies of the skeleton; those parts of the skeleton
being termed homologues, which have the same place in
the general type, and therefore ought to have the same
name.
Yet this distinction of the basis of botanical and
anatomical terminology is not to be pushed too far.
The primary definitions in botany, as given by Linnæus,
are founded on morphological views; and imply
a general type of the structure of plants. These are his
definitions (Phil. Bot. Art. 86).
 Calyx, Cortex plantæ in Fructificatione præsens.
 Corolla, Liber plantæ in Flora præsens.
 Stamen, Viscus pro Pollinis præparatione.
 Pistillum, Viscus fructui adherens pro Pollinis receptione.
 Pericarpium, Viscus gravidum seminibus, quæ matura dimittit.
But in what follows these leading definitions, the
terms are descriptive merely. Now in Comparative
Anatomy, an important object of terms is, to express
what part of the type each bone represents—to answer
the question, what is it? before we proceed, assuming
that we know what it is, to describe its shape. The
difficulty of this previous question is very great when
we come to the bones of the head; and when we assume,
as morphology leads us to do, that the heads of all
vertebrated animals, including even fishes, are
composed of homologous bones. And, as I have already 351
said in the History (b. xvii. c. 7), speaking of Animal
Morphology, the best physiologists are now agreed that
the heads of vertebrates may be resolved into a series
of vertebræ, homologically repeated and modified in
different animals. This doctrine has been gradually
making its way among anatomists, through a great
variety of views respecting details; and hence, with
great discrepancies in the language by which it has
been expressed. Mr. Owen has proposed a complete
series of terms for the bones of the head of all vertebrates;
and these names are supported by reasons which
are full of interest and instruction to the physiologist,
on account of the comprehensive and precise knowledge
of comparative osteology which they involve; but they
are also, as I have said, interesting and instructive to
us, as exemplifying the reasons which may be given for
the adoption of words in scientific language. The reasons
thus given agree with several of the aphorisms
which I have laid down, and may perhaps suggest a
few others. Mr. Owen has done me the great honour
to quote with approval some of these aphorisms. The
terms which he has proposed belong, as I have already
said, to the Terminology, not to the Nomenclature of
Zoology. In the latter subject, the Nomenclature (the
names of species) the binary nomenclature established
by Linnæus remains, in its principle, unshaken, simple
and sufficient.
I shall best derive from Mr. Owen’s labours and reflexions
some of the instruction which they supply with
reference to the Language of Science, by making
remarks on his terminology with reference to such
aphorisms as I have propounded on the subject, and others
of a like kind.
Mr. Owen, in his Homologies of the Vertebrate
Skeleton, has given in a Tabular Form his views of
the homology of the bones of the head of vertebrates,
and the names which he consequently proposes for each
bone, with the synonyms as they occur in the writings
of some of the most celebrated anatomical philosophers,
Cuvier, Geoffroy, Hallmann, Meckel and Wagner,
Agassiz and Soemmering. And he has added to this
Table his reasons for dissenting from his predecessors 352
to the extent to which he has done so. He has done
this, he says, only where nature seemed clearly to refuse
her sanction to them; acting upon the maxim (our
Aphorism X.) that new terms and changes of terms
which are not needed in order to express truth, are to
be avoided. The illustrations which I have there given,
however, of this maxim, apply rather to the changes in
nomenclature than in terminology; and though many
considerations apply equally to these two subjects, there
are some points in which the reasons differ in the two
cases: especially in this point:—the names, both of
genera and of species, in a system of nomenclature, may
be derived from casual or arbitrary circumstances, as I
have said in Aphorism XIII. But the terms of a scientific
terminology ought to cohere as a system, and therefore
should not commonly be derived from anything
casual or arbitrary, but from some analogy or connexion.
Hence it seems unadvisable to apply to bones
terms derived from the names of persons, as ossa
wormiana; or even from an accident in anatomical
history, as os innominatum.
It is further desirable that in establishing such a
terminology, each bone should be designated by a single
word, and not by a descriptive phrase, consisting of
substantive and adjective. On this ground Mr. Owen
proposes presphenoid for sphenöide anterieur. So also
prefrontal is preferred to anterior frontal,
and postfrontal to posterior frontal.
And the reason which he
gives for this is worthy of being stated as an Aphorism,
among those which should regulate this subject.
I shall therefore state it thus:
Aphorism XXIV.
It is advisable to substitute definite single names
for descriptive phrases as better instruments of thought.
It will be recollected by the reader that in the case of
the Linnæan reform of the botanical nomenclature of
species, this was one of the great improvements which
was introduced.
Again: some of the first of the terms which Mr. Owen
proposes illustrate, and confirm by their manifest claim 353
to acceptance, a maxim which we stated as Aphorism
XXII.: namely,
When alterations in technical terms become necessary,
it is desirable that the new term should contain
in its form some memorial of the old one.
Thus for ‘basilaire,’ which Cuvier exclusively applies
to the ‘pars basilaris’ of the occiput, and which
Geoffroy as exclusively applies (in birds) to the
‘pars basilaris’ of the sphenoid, Mr. Owen substitutes the term
basioccipital.
Again: for the term ‘suroccipital’ of Geoffroy, Mr.
Owen proposes paroccipital, to avoid confusion and false
suggestion: and with reference to this word, he makes
a remark in agreement with what we have said in the
discussion of Aphorism XXI.: namely, that the combination
of different languages in the derivation of words,
though to be avoided in general, is in some cases admissible.
He says, ‘If the purists who are distressed by
such harmless hybrids as “mineralogy,” “terminology,”
and “mammalogy,” should protest against the combination
of the Greek prefix to the Latin noun, I can
only plead that servility to a particular source of the
fluctuating sounds of vocal language is a matter of taste:
and that it seems no unreasonable privilege to use such
elements as the servants of thought; and in the interests
of science to combine them, even though they come
from different countries, when the required duty is best
and most expeditiously performed by their combination.’
So again we have illustrations of our Aphorism XII.,
that if terms are systematically good they are not to be
rejected because they are etymologically inaccurate. In
reference to that bone of the skull which has commonly
been called vomer, the ploughshare: a term which
Geoffroy rejected, but which Mr. Owen retains, he says,
‘When Geoffrey was induced to reject the term vomer
as being applicable only to the peculiar form of the bone
in a small portion of the vertebrata, he appears not to
have considered that the old term, in its wider application,
would be used without reference to its primary
allusion to the ploughshare, and that becoming, as it 354
has, a purely arbitrary term, it is superior and preferable
to any partially descriptive one.’
Another condition which I have mentioned in Aphorism XX.,
as valuable in technical terms is, that they
should be susceptible of such grammatical relations as
their scientific use requires.
This is, in fact, one of the grounds of the Aphorism
which we have already borrowed from Mr. Owen, that
we are to prefer single substantives to descriptive
phrases. For from such substantives we can derive
adjectives, and other forms; and thus the term becomes,
as Mr. Owen says, a better instrument of thought.
Hence, he most consistently mentions it as a recommendation
of his system of names, that by them the
results of a long series of investigations into the special
homologies of the bones of the head are expressed
in simple and definite terms, capable of every requisite
inflection to express the proportion of the parts.
I may also, in reference to this same passage in Mr.
Owen’s appeal in behalf of his terminology, repeat what
I have said under Aphorism X.: that the persons who
may most properly propose new scientific terms, are those
who have much new knowledge to communicate: so
that the vehicle is commended to general reception by
the value of what it contains. It is only to eminent
discoverers and profound philosophers that the authority
is conceded of introducing a new system of terms; just
as it is only the highest authority in the state which has
the power of putting a new coinage into circulation.
The long series of investigations of which the results are
contained in Mr. Owen’s table of synonyms, and the
philosophical spirit of his generalizations, entitles him to a
most respectful hearing when he appeals to the Professors
and Demonstrators of Human Anatomy for an unbiassed
consideration of the advantages of the terms
proposed by him, as likely to remedy the conflicting
and unsettled synonymy which has hitherto pervaded
the subject.
There is another remark which is suggested by the
works on Comparative Anatomy, which I am now considering.
I have said in various places that Technical 355
Terms are a necessary condition of the progress of a science.
But we may say much more than this: and the
remark is so important, that it deserves to be stated as
one of our Aphorisms, as follows:
Aphorism XXV.
In an advanced Science, the history of the Language of
the Science is the history of the Science itself.
I have already stated in previous Aphorisms (VIII.
and XI.) that Terms must be constructed so as to
be fitted to enunciate general propositions, and that
Terms which imply theoretical views are admissible for
this purpose. And hence it happens that the history of
Terms in any science which has gone through several
speculative stages, is really the history of the
generalizations and theories which have had currency
among the cultivators of the science.
This appears in Comparative Anatomy from what we
have been saying. The recent progress of that science
is involved in the rise and currency of the Terms which
have been used by the anatomists whose synonyms Mr.
Owen has to discuss; and the reasons for selecting among
these, or inventing others, include those truths and
generalizations which are the important recent steps of the
science. The terms which are given by Mr. Owen in his
table to denote the bones of the head are good terms, if
they are good terms, because their adoption and use is
the only complete way of expressing the truths of homology:
namely, of that Special Homology, according to
which all vertebrate skeletons are referred to the human
skeleton as their type, and have their parts designated
accordingly.
But further: there is another kind of homology which
Mr. Owen calls General Homology, according to which
the primary type of a vertebrate animal is merely a series
of vertebræ; and all limbs and other appendages are
only developements of the parts of one or another of the
vertebræ. And in order to express this view, and in
proportion as the doctrine has become current amongst 356
anatomists, the parts of vertebræ have been described by
terms of a degree of generality which admit of such an
interpretation. And here, also, Mr. Owen has proposed
a terminology for the parts of the vertebræ, which
seems to convey more systematically and comprehensively
than those of preceding writers the truths to
which they have been tending. Each vertebra is composed
of a centrum, neurapophysis, parapophysis,
pleurapophysis, hæmaphysis, neural spine and
hæmal spine, with certain exogenous parts.
The opinion that the head, as well as the other parts
of the frame of vertebrates, is composed of vertebræ, is
now generally accepted among philosophical anatomists.
In the History (Hist. I. S. b. xvii. c. 7, sect. 1), I have
mentioned this opinion as proposed by some writers;
and I have stated that Oken, in 1807 published a ‘Program’
On the signification of the bones of the Skull, in
which he maintained, that these bones are equivalent to
four vertebræ: while Meckel, Spix, and Geoffroy took
views somewhat different. Cuvier and Agassiz opposed
this doctrine, but Mr. Owen has in his Archetype and
Homologies of the Vertebrate Skeleton (1848), accepted
the views of Oken, and argued at length against the
objections of Cuvier, and also those of Mr. Agassiz.
As I have noted in the last edition of the History of
the Inductive Sciences (b. xvii. c. 7), he gives a Table in
which the Bones of the Head are resolved into four vertebræ,
which he terms the Occipital, Parietal, Frontal
and Nasal Vertebræ respectively: the neural arches of
which agree with what Oken called the Ear-vertebra, the
Jaw-vertebra, the Eye-vertebra, and the Nose-vertebra.
Besides these doctrines of Special Homology by which
the bones of all vertebrates are referred to their
corresponding bones in the human skeleton, and of General
Homology, by which the bones are referred to the parts
of vertebræ which they represent, Mr. Owen treats of
Serial Homology, the recognition of the same elements
throughout the series of segments of the same skeleton;
as when we shew in what manner the arms correspond
to the legs. And thus, he says, in the head also, the
basioccipital, basisphenoid,
presphenoid and vomer are 357
homotypes with the centrums of all succeeding vertebræ.
The excoccipitals, alisphenoids, orbitosphenoids,
and prefrontals, are homotypes with the neurapophyses
of all the succeeding vertebræ. The paroccipitals,
mactoids and postfrontals, with the transverse processes
of all the succeeding vertebræ: and so on. Perhaps
these examples may exemplify sufficiently for the general
reader both Mr. Owen’s terminology, and the intimate
manner in which it is connected with the widest
generalizations to which anatomical philosophy has yet been
led.
The same doctrine, that the history of the Language
of a Science is the history of the Science, appears also
in the recent progress of Chemistry; but we shall be
better able to illustrate our Aphorism in this case by
putting forward previously one or two other Aphorisms
bearing upon the history of that Science.
Aphorism XXVI.
In the Terminology of Science it may be necessary to
employ letters, numbers, and algebraical symbols.
1. Mineralogy.
I have already said, in Aphorism XV., that
symbols have been found requisite as a part of the
terminology of Mineralogy. The names proposed by
Haüy, borrowed from the crystalline laws, were so
inadequate and unsystematic that they could not be
retained. He himself proposed a notation for crystalline forms,
founded upon his principle of the derivation of such forms
from a primitive form, by decrements, on its edges
or its angles. To denote this derivation he took
the first letters of the three syllables to
mark the faces of the PriMiTive form, P, M, T; the
vowels A, E, I, O to mark the angles; the consonants
B, C, D, &c. to mark the edges; and numerical
exponents, annexed in various positions to these letters,
represented the law and manner of derivation. Thus
when the primitive form was a cube, 1B
represented the result of a derivation by a
decrement of one row 358
on an edge; that is, a rhombic octahedron;
and 1BP represented
the combination of this octahedron with
the primitive cube. In this way the pentagonal
dodecahedron, produced by decrements of 2 to 1
on half the edges of the cube, was represented by
B² ½C G² ²G
Not only, however, was the hypothesis of primitive
forms and decrements untenable, but this notation
was too unsystematic to stand long. And when Weiss
and Mohs established the distinction of Systems of
Crystallography66,
they naturally founded upon that
distinction a notation for crystalline forms. Mohs had
several followers; but his algebraical notation so
barbarously violated all algebraical meaning, that it was
not likely to last. Thus, from a primitive rhombohedron
which he designated by R, he derived, by a
certain process, a series of other rhombohedrons, which
he denoted by R + 1,
R + 2,
R − 1, &c.; and then, by
another mode of derivation from them, he obtained
forms which he marked as (R + 2)²,
(R + 2)³, &c. In
doing this he used the algebraical marks of addition
and involution without the smallest ground; besides
many other proposals no less transgressing mathematical
analogy and simplicity.
66
Hist. Ind. Sc. b. xv. c. 4.
But this notation might easily suggest a better. If
we take a primitive form, we can generally, by two
steps of derivation, each capable of numerical measure,
obtain any possible face; and therefore any crystalline
form bounded by such faces. Hence all that we need
indicate in our crystalline laws is the primitive form,
and two numerical exponents; and rejecting all
superfluity in our symbols, instead of (R + 2)³
we might write 2 R 3. Nearly of this kind is the notation of
Naumann. The systems of crystallization, the octahedral
or tessular, the rhombic, and the prismatic, are
marked by the letters O, R, P; and from these are
derived, by certain laws, such symbols as
3 O ½, ∞ R 2, ½ P 2,  359
which have their definite signification flowing from
the rules of the notation.
But Professor Miller, who has treated the subject
of Crystallography in the most general and symmetrical
manner, adopts the plan of marking each crystalline
plane by three numerical indices. Thus in the
Octahedral System, the cube is {100}; the octahedron
is {111}; the rhombic dodecahedron is {011}; the
pentagonal dodecahedron is π {012}; where π indicates
that the form is not holohedral but hemihedral,
only half the number of faces being taken which the
law of derivation would give. This system is the
most mathematically consistent, and affords the best
means of calculation, as Professor Miller has shown;
but there appears to be in it this defect, that though
an essential part of the scheme is the division of
crystalline forms into Systems,—the Octahedral,
Pyramidal, Rhombohedral and Prismatic,—this division
does not at all appear in the notation.
But whatever be the notation which the crystallographer
adopts, it is evident that he must employ
some notation; and that, without it, he will be unable
to express the forms and relations of forms with which
he has to deal.
2. Chemistry.
The same has long been the case in Chemistry.
As I have stated elsewhere67,
the chemical nomenclature
of the oxygen theory was for a time very useful
and effective. But yet it had defects which could not
be overlooked, as I have already stated under Aphorism II.
The relations of elements were too numerous, and their
numerical properties too important, to
be expressed by terminations and other modifications
of words. Thus the compounds of Nitrogen and
Oxygen are the Protoxide, the Deutoxide, Nitrous
Acid, Peroxide of Nitrogen, Nitric Acid. The systematic
nomenclature here, even thus loosely extended,
does not express our knowledge. And the Atomic
Theory, when established, brought to view numerical 360
relations which it was very important to keep in
sight. If N represents Nitrogen and O Oxygen, the
compounds of the two elements just mentioned might
be denoted by N + O, N + 2O,
N + 3O, N + 4O, N + 5O.
And by adopting a letter for each of the elementary
substances, all the combinations of them might be expressed in this manner.
67
Hist. Ind. Sc. b. xiv. c. 6.
But in chemistry there are different orders of combination.
A salt, for instance, is a compound of a
base and an acid, each of which is already compound.
If Fe be iron and C be carbon, Fe + O
will be the protoxide of iron, and C + 2O will be carbonic acid; and
the carbonate of iron (more properly carbonate of
protoxide of iron), may be represented by
(Fe + O) + (C + 2O)
where the brackets indicate the first stage of composition.
But these brackets and signs of addition, in complex
cases, would cumber the page in an inconvenient degree;
and oxygen is of such very wide occurrence, that
it seems desirable to abridge the notation so far as it
is concerned. Hence Berzelius
proposed68
that in the first stage of composition the oxygen should be expressed
by dots over the letter; and thus the carbonate of iron
would be Ḟe + C̈. But Berzelius
further introduced into his notation indexes such as
in algebra denote involution to the square, cube, &c.
Thus Cu being copper, the sulphate of copper is represented
by S⃛²C̈u. This notation, when first proposed,
was strongly condemned by English chemists, and
Berzelius’s reply to them may be taken as stating the
reasons in favour of such notation. He
says69, ‘We
answer to the opponents, that undoubtedly the matter
may be looked at in various lights. The use
of Formulæ has always, for a person who has not
accustomed himself to them, something repulsive; but
this is easy to overcome. I agree with my opponent, 361
who says that nothing can be understood in a Formula
which cannot be expressed in words; and that if the
words express it as easily as the Formula, the use of
the latter would be a folly. But there are cases in
which this is not so; in which the Formula says in a
glance what it would take many lines to express in
words; and in which the expression of the Formula is
clearer and more easily apprehended by the reader
than the longer description in words. Let us examine
such a Formula, and compare it with the equivalent
description in words. Take, for example, crystallized
sulphate of copper, of which the Formula is
C̈uS⃛² + 10H² O.
Now this Formula expresses the following propositions:
 ‘That the salt consists of one atom of copper-oxide
combined with 2 atoms of sulphuric acid and with 10
atoms of water; that the copper-oxide contains two
atoms of oxygen; and that the sulphuric acid contains
3 atoms of oxygen for one atom of sulphur; that its
oxygen is three times as much as that of the oxide;
and that the number of atoms of oxygen in the acid is
6; and that the number of atoms of oxygen in the
water is 10; that is, 5 times the number in the oxide;
and that finally the salt contains, of simple atoms, 1
copper, 2 sulphur, 20 hydrogen, and 18 oxygen.
68
System of Mineralogy, 1816.
69
Jahresbericht, 1824, p. 119.
‘Since so much is expressed in this brief Formula,
how very long would the explanation be for a more
composite body, for example, Alum; for which the
Formula is
K̈ S⃛² + 2A⃛l S⃛³
+ 48H² O.
It would take half a page to express all which this
Formula contains.
‘Perhaps it may be objected that it is seldom that
any one wants to know all this at once. But it might
reasonably be said in reply, that the peculiar value of
the Formula consists in this, that it contains answers
to all the questions which can be asked with regard
to the composition of the body. 362
‘But these Formulæ have also another application,
of which I have sometimes had occasion to make use.
Experiments sometimes bring before us combinations
which cannot be foreseen from the nomenclature, and
for which it is not always easy to find a consistent
and appropriate name. In writing, the Formula may
be applied instead of a Name: and the reader understands
it better than if one made a new name. In
my treatise upon the sulphuretted alkalies I found
Degrees of Sulphur-combination, for which Nomenclature
has no name. I expressed them, for example,
by KS6, KS8, KS10 and I believed
that every one understood what was thereby meant. Moreover, I found
another class of bodies in which an electro-negative
sulphuretted metal played the part of an Acid with
respect to an electro-positive sulphuretted metal, for
which a whole new nomenclature was needed; while
yet it were not prudent to construct such a nomenclature,
till more is known on the subject. Instead of
new names I used formulas; for example,
KS² + 2As S³,
instead of saying the combination of 2 atoms of Sulphuret
of Arsenic containing 3 atoms of Sulphur,
with one atom of Sulphuret of Potassium (Kali) with
the least dose of sulphur.’
Berzelius goes on to say that the English chemists
had found themselves unable to find any substitutes
for his formulæ when they translated his papers.
Our English chemists have not generally adopted
the notation of oxygen by dots; but have employed
commas or full stops and symbols (, or . and +), to
denote various degrees of union, and numerical indices.
Thus the double sulphate of copper and potash
is Cu O, SO3 + KO, SO3.
What has been said is applicable mainly to inorganic
bodies (as salts and
minerals)70.
In these bodies there
is (at least according to the views of many intelligent
chemists) a binary plan of combination, union taking 363
place between pairs of elements, and the compounds
so produced again uniting themselves to other compound
bodies in the same manner. Thus, in the above
example, copper and oxygen combine into oxide of
copper, potassium and oxygen into potash, sulphur
and oxygen into sulphuric acid; sulphuric acid in its
turn combines both with oxide of copper and oxide
of potassium, generating a pair of salts which are
capable of uniting to form the double compound
Cu O, SO3 + KO, SO3.
70
Fownes’s Chemistry. Part iii.
The most complicated products of inorganic chemistry
may be thus shown to be built up by this
repeated pairing on the part of their constituents.
But with organic bodies the case is remarkably different;
no such arrangement can here be traced. In
sugar, which is C12 H11 O11,
or morphia71, which is
C35 H20 NO6, the elements are
as it were bound together into a single whole, which can enter
into combination with other substances, and be thence discharged
with properties unaltered; the elements not being
obviously arranged in any subordinate groups. Hence
the symbols for those substances are such as I have
given above, no marks of combination being used.
71
Fownes’s Chemistry, p. 354.
It is perhaps a consequence of this peculiarity that
organic compounds are unstable in comparison with
inorganic. In unorganic substances generally the elements
are combined in such a way that the most
powerful affinities are
satisfied72,
and hence arises a
state of very considerable permanence and durability.
But in an organic substance containing three
or four elements, there are often opposing affinities
nearly balanced, and when one of these tendencies by
some accident obtains a preponderance and the equilibrium
is destroyed, then the organic body breaks up
into two or more new bodies of simpler and more permanent constitution.
72
See Hist. Ind. Sc. b. xiv. c. 3.
There is another property of many organic substances which
is called the Law of Substitution. The 364
Hydrogen of the organic substance may often be replaced
by Chlorine, Bromine, Iodine, or some other
elements, without the destruction of the primitive
type or constitution of the compound so modified.
And this substitution may take place by several successive
steps, giving rise to a series of substitution-compounds,
which depart more and more in properties
from the original substance. This Law also gives rise
to a special notation. Thus a certain compound called
Dutch liquid has the elements
C4 H4 Cl2:
but this substance is affected by chlorine (Cl) in obedience to the
law of substitution; one and two equivalents of hydrogen being
successively removed by the prolonged
action of chlorine gas aided by sunshine. The successive
products may be thus written
C4 H4 Cl2;
C4 { H3Cl }  Cl2;
C4 { H2Cl2 } Cl2.
Perhaps at a future period, chemical symbols, and
especially those of organic bodies, may be made more
systematic and more significant than they at present
are.
Aphorism XXVII.
In using algebraical symbols as a part of scientific
language, violations of algebraical analogy are to be avoided,
but may be admitted when necessary.
As we must in scientific language conform to etymology,
so must we to algebra; and as we are not to
make ourselves the slaves of the former, so also, not to
the latter. Hence we reject such crystallographical
notation as that of Mohs; and in chemistry we use
C2, O3 rather
than C2, O3, which
signify the square
of C and the cube of O. But we may use, as we have
said, both the comma and the sign of addition, for
chemical combination, for the sake of brevity, though
both steps of combination are really addition. 365
Aphorism XXVIII.
In a complex science, which is in a state of transition,
capricious and detached derivations of terms are common;
but are not satisfactory.
In this remark I have especial reference to Chemistry;
in which the discoveries made, especially in organic
chemistry, and the difficulty of reducing them to a
system, have broken up in several instances the old
nomenclature, without its being possible at present to
construct a new set of terms systematically connected.
Hence it has come to pass that chemists have constructed
words in a capricious and detached way: as
by taking fragments of words, and the like. I shall
give some examples of such derivations, and also of
some attempts which have more of a systematic character.
I have mentioned (Aph. XX.
sect. 7) the word Ellagic
(acid), made by inverting the word Galle. Several
words have recently been formed by chemists by
taking syllables from two or more different words.
Thus Chevreul discovered a substance to which he gave
the name Ethal, from the first syllables of the words
ether and alcohol, because of its analogy to those liquids
in point of composition73.
So Liebig has the word
chloral74.
73
Turner’s Chemistry, 1834, p. 955
74
Berzelius’ Jahresbericht, xv. p. 372.
Liebig, examining the product of distillation of alcohol,
sulphuric acid and amber, found a substance which
he termed Aldehyd, from the words Alcohol
dehydrogenated75.
This mode of making Words has been
strongly objected to by Mr.
Dumas76.
Still more has
he objected to the word Mercaptan (of Zeise), which 366
he says rests upon a mere play of words; for it means
both mercurium captans and mercurio aptum.
75
Ibid. xvi. p. 308.
76
Leçons de Chimie, p. 354.
Dumas and Peligot, working on pyroligneous acids,
found reason to believe the existence of a
substance77
which they called methylene, deriving the name from
methy, a spirituous fluid, and hyle, wood. Berzelius
remarks that the name should rather be methyl, and
that ὕλη may be taken in its signification of matter, to
imply the Radical of Wine: and he proposes that the
older Æther-Radical,
C4 H10
shall be called Æthyl,
the newer,  C2 H6, Methyl.
77
Berzelius’ Jahresbericht, xv. (1836).
This notion of marking by the termination yl the
hypothetical compound radical of a series of chemical
compounds has been generally adopted; and, as we see
from the above reference, it must be regarded as representing
the Greek word ὕλη: and such hypothetical
radicals of bases have been termed in general basyls.
Bunsen obtained from Cadet’s fuming liquid a substance
which he called Alkarsin (alkali-arsenic?): and
the substance produced from this by oxidation he
called Alkargen78.
Berzelius was of opinion, that the
true view of its composition was that it contained a
compound ternary radical =
C6 H12
As2, after the manner
of organic bodies; and he proposed for this the
name79 Kakodyl.
Alkarsin is Kakodyl-oxyd, K̇d,
Alkargen is Kakodyl-acid, K̈̇d.
78
Ibid. xviii. p. 497.
79
Ibid. xx. p. 527.
The discovery of Kakodyl was the first instance of
the insulation of an organic metallic
basyl80.
80
Miller’s Chemistry, iii. 220.
The first of the Hydrocarbon Radicals of the Alcohols was
the radical of Tetrylic alcohol obtained by
Kolbe from Valerate of Potash, and hence called Valyl
C16 H18.
Chloroform is perchloride of formyl,
the hypothetical radical of formic
acid81.
81
Dumas, Leçons sur la Phil. Chim. p. 356.
367
The discovery of such bases goes back to 1815.
The substance formerly called Prussiate of Mercury,
being treated in a particular manner, was resolved into
metallic mercury and Cyanogen. This substance, Cyanogen,
is, according to the older nomenclature, Bicarburet
of Nitrogen; but chemists are agreed that its
most convenient name is Cyanogen, proposed by its
discoverer, Gay-Lussac, in
181582.
The importance
of the discovery consists in this; that this substance
was the first compound body which was distinctly
proved to enter into combination with elementary substances
in a manner similar to that in which they
combine with each other.
82
Turner’s Chemistry (1834), p. 420. Miller’s Chemistry, ii. 66.
The truth of our Aphorism (XXV.) that in such a
science as chemistry, the history of the scientific nomenclature
is the history of the science, appears from this;
that the controversies with respect to chemical theories
and their application take the form of objections to the
common systematic names and proposals of new names
instead. Thus a certain compound of potassa, sulphur,
hydrogen, and oxygen, may be regarded either as Hydrosulphate
of Potassa, or as Sulphide of Potassium in
solution, according to different
views83. In some cases
indeed, changes are made merely for the sake of clearness.
Instead of Hydrochloric and Hydrocyanic acid,
many French writers, following Thenard, transpose the
elements of these terms; they speak of Chlorhydric and
Cyanhydric acid; by this means they avoid any ambiguity
which might arise from the use of the prefix
Hydro, which has sometimes been applied to compounds
which contain water84.
83
Miller’s Chemistry, vol. ii. p. 583.
84
Ibid. ii. 433.
An incompleteness in chemical nomenclature was
further felt, when it appeared, from the properties of
various substances, that mere identity in chemical
composition is not sufficient to produce identity of
chemical character or
properties85.
The doctrine of 368
the existence of compounds identical in ultimate composition,
but different in chemical properties, was
termed Isomerism. Thus chemists enumerate the following
compounds, all of which contain carbon and
hydrogen in the proportion of single equivalents of
each86;—Methylene,
Olefiant gas, Propylene, Oil gas,
Amylene, Caproylene, Naphthene, Eleene, Peramylene,
Cetylene, Cerotylene, Melissine.
85
Ibid. ii. 653.
86
Miller’s Chemistry, ii. p. 654.
I will, in the last place, propound an Aphorism
which has already offered itself in considering the
history of Chemistry87
as having a special bearing upon
that Science, but which may be regarded as the supreme
and ultimate rule with regard to the language
of Science.
87
Hist. Ind. Sc. b. xiv. c. 1.
Aphorism XXIX.
In learning the meaning of Scientific Terms, the history of
science is our Dictionary: the steps of scientific induction are
our Definitions.
It is usual for unscientific readers to complain that
the technical terms which they meet with in books of
science are not accompanied by plain definitions such as
they can understand. But such definitions cannot be
given. For definitions must consist of words; and, in
the case of scientific terms, must consist of words which
require again to be defined: and so on, without limit.
Elementary substances in chemistry, for instance, what
are they? The substances into which bodies can be
analysed, and by the junction of which they are composed.
But what is analysis? what is composition? We
have seen that it required long and laborious courses of
experiment to answer these questions; and that finally
the balance decided among rival answers. And so it
is in other cases. In entering upon each science, we
come upon a new set of words. And how are we to learn 369
the meaning of this collection of words? In what other
language shall it be explained? In what terms shall we
define these new expressions? To this we are compelled
to reply, that we cannot translate these terms into any
ordinary or familiar language. Here, as in all other
branches of knowledge, the meaning of words is to be
sought in the progress of thought. It is only by going
back through the successful researches of men respecting
the composition and elements of bodies, that we can
learn in what sense such terms can be understood, so as
to convey real knowledge. In order that they may have
a meaning for us, we must inquire what meaning they
had in the minds of the authors of our discoveries. And
the same is the case in other subjects. To take the instance
of Morphology. When the beginner is told that
every group of animals may be reduced to an Archetype,
he will seek for a definition of Archetype. Such a definition
has been offered, to this effect: the Archetype of
a group of animals is a diagram embodying all the organs
and parts which are found in the group in such a relative
position as they would have had if none had attained
an excessive development. But, then, we are led
further to ask, How are we in each case to become
acquainted with the diagram; to know of what parts it
consists, and how they are related; and further;
What is the standard of excess? It is by a wide
examination of particular species, and by several successive
generalizations of observed facts, that we are led
to a diagram of an animal form of a certain kind, (for
example, a vertebrate;) and of the various ways,
excessive and defective, in which the parts may be developed.
This craving for definitions, as we have already said,
arises in a great degree from the acquaintance with geometry
which most persons acquire at an early age.
The definitions of geometry are easily intelligible by a
beginner, because the idea of space, of which they are
modifications, is clearly possessed without any special
culture. But this is not and cannot be the case in other
sciences founded upon a wide and exact observation of
facts. 370
It was formerly said that there was no Royal Road
to Geometry: in modern times we have occasion often
to repeat that there is no Popular Road—no road easy,
pleasant, offering no difficulty and demanding no toil,—to
Comparative Anatomy, Chemistry or any other of
the Inductive Sciences.
THE END.
CAMBRIDGE: PRINTED BY C. J. CLAY, M.A. AT THE UNIVERSITY PRESS.
Transcriber’s Notes
Whewell published the
first edition of the Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences in
1840 in two volumes, as a companion to the 1837 History of the
Inductive Sciences. Revised second editions of both works
appeared in 1847. The third editions saw a major reshaping of the
Philosophy: a two volume History of Scientific Ideas
(1858 – in Project Gutenberg as #69093), Novum Organon
Renovatum (1858 – the present text, relying upon resources
kindly provided by the Internet Archive), and On the Philosophy
of Discovery: chapters historical and critical (1860 –
long since in Project Gutenberg’s collection: #5155). (The third
edition of the History of the Inductive Sciences is available in PG as #68693.)
Adaptations in this text
In the present text footnotes are numbered by Book and are placed
after the paragraph to which they attach; in the original, notes
were numbered by chapter. Page numbers appear in colour; where a
word was hyphenated across pages the number has been placed before
the word. Fractions have been transcribed as numerator ⁄  denominator;
the original usually has numerator over a line with denominator
below.
Some unusual symbols occur. On pages 357 and 358, there are
italic letters with a number written above them. On two occasions
B  has a 1 above it, and once C has ½ above it. On page 364
a formula is written with two entries containing H on a line above
Cl. These superpositions have all been transcribed by superscripting the first
and subscripting the second item (with the result that the letters are printed
smaller than in the original). The other oddities have been captured in Unicode.
On pages 152 and 197  Whewell uses
a raised dot as a decimal point and in
footnote 26 of Book III. a comma. These have been replaced by a mid
dot.
Inductive Charts
At the end of Book II. (p. 140), Whewell included two very large inserts,
described in some detail in the Book itself. They were not captured by the scans
available in the Internet Archive. I was kindly provided with photographs of them.
Those charts were four times as wide as the normal page and a quarter as long.
In the html version they have been fairly accurately represented via tables;
but with up to 25 columns these tables will be very difficult to decipher on
small screens. In the text version, coded structure diagrams have been used,
which again utilise the full 70 spaces Project Gutenberg allows.
Corrections
Corrections are comparatively few. Apart from the silent ones,
they have been marked by dotted red underline, on mouse-over
revealing the nature of the change. Given the various editions, some
of the internal cross-references turn out to be obsolete or
erroneous:  note 11 in Book III.
The text reads B. viii. c. iii. but it refers actually to Book viii.
c. ii. article 3 in earlier editions and in the History of Scientific Ideas, cf. Aphorism
88 in Book I. of the present volume. Compare also Aphorism 19 in this volume’s Book IV.  notes 58 and 59 in Book III. refer to Book v.
c. i. For the present third edition they should have been aimed at
that chapter of the History of Scientific Ideas.
 On page 252 we are told that the Work is about to conclude, as
the first edition did in a way (all the aphorisms were gathered
after Book XIII. [= our Book III.], followed by various appendices).
But we have Book IV. yet to come, plus some extra illustrations
regarding language and symbols in science.
(I might add that I have not checked the many references to Whewell’s
other related works. The errors here suggest one might need to take
them with a pinch of salt, and help from the browser’s search function.)
 There
are some inconsistencies, notably in spelling, which have in
general not been adjusted; nor have Whewell’s unbalanced quotation
marks and positioning of footnote anchors been modernized.
</div></body></text></TEI>