<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="29">
CHAPTER X.

The Law of Gravitation.

We shall proceed to make a few observations on
the Law of Gravity, in virtue of which the motions
of planets about the sun, and of satellites about their
planets take place; and by which also are produced[167]
the fall downwards of all bodies within our reach,
and the pressure which they exert upon their supports
when at rest. The identification of the latter
forces with the former, and the discovery of the single
law by which these forces are every where regulated,
was the great discovery of Newton: and we
wish to make it appear that this law is established by
an intelligent and comprehensive selection.
The law of the sun’s attraction upon the planets
is, that this attraction varies inversely as the square
of the distance; that is, it decreases as that square
increases. If we take three points or planets of the
solar system, the distances of which from the sun are
in proper proportion one, two, three; the attractive
force which the sun at these distances exercises, is
as one, one-fourth, and one-ninth respectively. In
the smaller variations of distance which occur in the
elliptical motion of one planet, the variations of the
force follow the same law. Moreover, not only does
the sun attract the planets, but they attract each
other according to the same law; the tendency to
the earth which makes bodies heavy, is one of the
effects of this law: and all these effects of the attractions
of large masses may be traced to the attractions
of the particles of which they are composed; so that
the final generalization, including all the derivative
laws, is, that every particle of matter in the universe
attracts every other, according to the law of the inverse
square of the distance.
Such is the law of universal gravitation. Now,
the question is, why do either the attractions of
masses, or those of their component particles, follow
this law of the inverse square of the distance rather
than any other? When the distance becomes one,
two, and three, why should not the force also become
one, two, and three?—or if it must be weaker at
points more remote from the attracting body, why
should it not be one, a half, a third? or one, an eighth,
a twenty-seventh? Such law’s could easily be expressed
mathematically, and their consequences calculated.[168]
Can any reason be assigned why the law
which we find in operation must obtain? Can any
be assigned why it should obtain?
The answer to this is, that no reason, at all satisfactory,
can be given why such a law must, of necessity,
be what it is; but that very strong reasons
can be pointed out why, for the beauty and advantage
of the system, the present one is better than
others. We will point out some of these reasons.
1. In the first place, the system could not have
subsisted, if the force had followed a direct instead
of an inverse law, with respect to the distance; that
is, if it had increased when the distance increased.
It has been sometimes said, that “all direct laws of
force are excluded on account of the danger from
perturbing forces;”[23] that if the planets had pulled at
this earth, the harder the further off they were, they
would have dragged it entirely out of its course.
This is not an exact statement of what would happen:
if the force were to be simply in the direct
ratio of the distance, any number of planets might
revolve in the most regular and orderly manner.
Their mutual effects, which we may call perturbations
if we please, would be considerable; but these
perturbations would be so combined with the unperturbed
motion, as to produce a new motion not less
regular than the other. This curious result would
follow, that every body in the system would describe,
or seem to describe, about every other, an exact
elliptical orbit; and that the times of the revolution
of every body in its orbit would be all equal. This
is proved by Newton, in the sixty-fourth proposition
of the Principia. There would be nothing to prevent
all the planets, on this supposition, from moving
round the sun in orbits exactly circular, or nearly
circular, according to the mode in which they were
set in motion.
But though the perturbations of the system would[169]
not make this law inadmissible, there are other circumstances
which would do so. Under this law, the
gravity of bodies at the earth’s surface would cease
to exist. Nothing would fall or weigh downwards.
The greater action of the distant sun and planets
would exactly neutralize the gravity of the earth: a
ball thrown from the hand, however gently, would
immediately become a satellite of the earth, and
would for the future accompany it in its course, revolving
about it in the space of one year. All terrestrial
things would float about with no principle of
coherence or stability: they would obey the general
law of the system, but would acknowledge no particular
relation to the earth. We can hardly pretend
to judge of the abstract possibility of such a system
of things; but it is clear that it could not exist without
an utter subversion of all that we can conceive
of the economy and structure of the world which we
inhabit.
With any other direct law of force, we should in
like manner lose gravity, without gaining the theoretical
regularity of the planetary motions which we
have described in the case just considered.
2. Among inverse laws of the distance, (that is,
those according to which the force diminishes as the
distance from the origin of force increases,) all which
diminish the central force faster than the cube of the
distance increases are inadmissible, because they are
incompatible with the permanent revolution of a
planet. Under such laws it would follow, that a
planet would describe a spiral line about the sun,
and would either approach nearer and nearer to
him perpetually, or perpetually go further and further
off: nearly as a stone at the end of a string,
when the string is whirled round, and is allowed to
wrap round the hand, or to unwrap from it, approaches
to or recedes from the hand.
If we endeavour to compare the law of the inverse
square of the distance, which really regulates the
central force, with other laws, not obviously inadmissible,[170]
as for instance, the inverse simple ratio of
the distance, a considerable quantity of calculation
is found to be necessary in order to trace the results,
and especially the perturbations in the two cases.
The perturbations in the supposed case have not
been calculated; such a calculation being a process
so long and laborious that it is never gone through,
except for the purpose of comparing the results of
theory with those of observation, as we can do with
regard to the law of inverse square. We can only
say, therefore, that the stability of the system, and
the moderate limits of the perturbations, which we
know to be secured by the existing law, would not,
so far as we know, be obtained by any different law.
Without going into further examination of the
subject, we may observe that there are some circumstances
in which the present system has a manifest
superiority in its simplicity over the condition which
would have belonged to it if the force had followed
any other law. Thus, with the present law of gravitation
the planets revolve, returning perpetually on
the same track, very nearly. The earth describes
an oval, in consequence of which motion she is
nearer to the sun in our winter than in our summer
by about one-thirtieth part of the whole distance.
And, as the matter now is, the nearest approach to
the sun, and the farthest recess from him, occur always
at the same points of the orbit. There is indeed
a slight alteration in these points arising from
disturbing forces, but this is hardly sensible in the
course of several ages. Now if the force had followed
any other law, we should have had the earth running
perpetually on a new track. The greatest and
least distances would have occurred at different
parts in every successive revolution. The orbit
would have perpetually intersected and been interlaced
with the path described in former revolutions;
and the simplicity and regularity which characterizes
the present motion would have been quite
wanting.
[171]
3. Another peculiar point of simplicity in the present
law of mutual attraction is this: that it makes
the law of attraction for spherical masses the same
as for single particles. If particles attract with
forces which are inversely as the square of the distance,
spheres composed of such particles, will exert
a force which follows the same law. In this character
the present law is singular, among all possible
laws, excepting that of the direct distance which we
have already discussed. If the law of the gravitation
of particles had been that of the inverse simple
distance, the attraction of a sphere would have been
expressed by a complex series of mathematical expressions,
each representing a simple law. It is truly
remarkable that the law of the inverse square of the
distance, which appears to be selected as that of the
masses of the system, and of which the mechanism
is, that it arises from the action of the particles of
the system, should lead us to the same law for the
action of these particles: there is a striking prerogative
of simplicity in the law thus adopted.
The law of gravitation actually prevailing in the
solar system has thus great and clear advantages
over any law widely different from it; and has moreover,
in many of its consequences, a simplicity which
belongs to this precise law alone. It is in many such
respects a unique law; and when we consider that it
possesses several properties which are peculiar to it,
and several advantages which may be peculiar to it,
and which are certainly nearly so; we have some
ground, it would appear, to look upon its peculiarities
and its advantages as connected. For the reasons
mentioned in the last chapter, we can hardly
expect to see fully the way in which the system is
benefited by the simplicity of this law, and by the
mathematical elegance of its consequences: but when
we see that it has some such beauties, and some manifest
benefits, we may easily suppose that our ignorance
and limited capacity alone prevent our seeing
that there are, for the selection of this law of force,[172]
reasons of a far more refined and comprehensive
kind than we can distinctly apprehend.
4. But before quitting this subject we may offer a
few further observations on the question, whether
gravitation and the law of gravitation be necessary
attributes of matter. We have spoken of the selection
of this law, but is it selected? Could it have
been otherwise? Is not the force of attraction a
necessary consequence of the fundamental properties
of matter?
This is a question which has been much agitated
among the followers of Newton. Some have maintained,
as Cotes, that gravity is an inherent property
of all matter; others, with Newton himself, have
considered it as an appendage to the essential qualities
of matter, and have proposed hypotheses to
account for the mode in which its effects are produced.
The result of all that can be said on the subject
appears to be this: that no one can demonstrate the
possibility of deducing gravity from the acknowledged
fundamental properties of matter: and that
no philosopher asserts, that matter has been found
to exist, which was destitute of gravity. It is a property
which we have no right to call necessary to
matter, but every reason to suppose universal.
If we could show gravity to be a necessary consequence
of those properties which we adopt as essential
to our notion of matter, (extension, solidity,
mobility, inertia) we might then call it also one of the
essential properties. But no one probably will assert
that this is the case. Its universality is a fact of
observation merely. How then can a property,—in
its existence so needful for the support of the universe,
in its laws so well adapted to the purposes of
creation,—how came it to be thus universal? Its
being found every where is necessary for its uses;
but this is so far from being a sufficient explanation
of its existence, that it is an additional fact to be
explained. We have here, then, an agency most[173]
simple in its rule, most comprehensive in its influence,
most effectual and admirable in its operation.
What evidence could be afforded of design,
by laws of mechanical action, which this law thus
existing and thus operating does not afford us?
5. It is not necessary for our purpose to consider
the theories which have been proposed to account
for the action of gravity. They have proceeded on
the plan of reducing this action to the result of pressure
or impulse. Even if such theories could be
established, they could not much, or at all, affect
our argument; for the arrangements by which pressure
or impact could produce the effects which gravity
produces, must be at least as clearly results of
contrivance, as gravity itself can be.
In fact, however, none of these attempts can be
considered as at all successful. That of Newton is
very remarkable: it is found among the Queries in
the second edition of his Optics. “To show,” he
says, “that I do not take gravity for an essential
property of bodies, I have added one question concerning
its cause, choosing to propose it by way of
question, because I am not yet satisfied about it for
want of experiments.” The hypothesis which he
thus suggests is, that there is an elastic medium pervading
all space, and increasing in elasticity as we
proceed from dense bodies outwards: that this
“causes the gravity of such dense bodies to each
other: every body endeavouring to go from the
denser parts of the medium towards the rarer.” Of
this hypothesis we may venture to say, that it is in
the first place quite gratuitous; we cannot trace in
any other phenomena a medium possessing these
properties: and in the next place, that the hypothesis
contains several suppositions which are more
complex than the fact to be explained, and none
which are less so. Can we, on Newton’s principles,
conceive an elastic medium otherwise than as a collection
of particles, repelling each other? and is the
repulsion of such particles a simpler fact than the[174]
attraction of those which gravitate? And when we
suppose that the medium becomes more elastic as we
proceed from each attracting body, what cause can
we conceive capable of keeping it in such a condition,
except a repulsive force emanating from the
body itself: a supposition at least as much requiring
to be accounted for, as the attraction of the body.
It does not appear, then, that this hypothesis will
bear examination; although, for our purpose, the argument
would be rather strengthened than weakened,
if it could be established.
6. Another theory of the cause of gravity, which
at one time excited considerable notice, was that originally
proposed by M. Le Sage, in 
a memoir entitled “Lucrece Newtonien,” and further illustrated by
M. Prevost; according to which all space is occupied
by currents of matter, moving perpetually in
straight lines, in all directions, with a vast velocity,
and penetrating all bodies. When two bodies are
near each other, they intercept the current which
would flow in the intermediate space if they were
not there, and thus receive a tendency towards each
other from the pressure of the currents on their
farther sides. Without examining further this curious
and ingenious hypothesis, we may make upon
it the same kind of observations as before;—that it
is perfectly gratuitous, except as a means of explaining
the phenomena; and that, if it were proved, it
would still remain to be shown what necessity has
caused the existence of these two kinds of matter;
the first kind being that which is commonly called
matter, and which alone affects our senses, while it
is inert as to any tendency to motion; the second
kind being something imperceptible to our senses,
except by the effects it produces on matter of the
former kind; yet exerting an impulse on every material
body, permeating every portion of common
matter, flowing with inconceivable 
velocity, in inexhaustible abundance, from every part of the abyss of
infinity on one side, to the opposite part of the same[175]
abyss; and so constituted that through all eternity it
can never bend its path, or return, or tarry in its
course.
If we were to accept this theory, it would little or
nothing diminish our wonder at the structure of the
universe. We might well continue to admire the evidence
of contrivance, if such a machinery should be
found to produce all the effects which flow from the
law of gravitation.
7. The arguments for and against the necessity of
the law of the inverse square of the distance in the
force of gravity, were discussed with great animation
about the middle of the last century. Clairault,
an eminent mathematician, who did more than almost
any other person for the establishment and development
of the Newtonian doctrines, maintained,
at one period of his researches, not only that the inverse
square was not the necessary law, but also that
it was not the true law. The occasion of this controversy
was somewhat curious.
Newton and other astronomers had found that the
line of the moon’s apsides (that is of her greatest and
least distances from the earth) moves round to different
parts of the heavens with a velocity twice as
great as that which the calculation from the law of
gravitation seems at first to give. According to the
theory, it appeared that this line ought to move round
once in eighteen years; according to observation, it
moves round once in nine years. This difference,
the only obvious failure of the theory of gravitation,
embarrassed mathematicians exceedingly. It is true,
it was afterwards discovered that the apparent discrepancy
arose from a mistake; the calculation,
which is long and laborious, was supposed to have
been carried far enough to get close to the truth;
but it appeared afterwards that the residue which
had been left out as insignificant, produced, by an
unexpected turn in the reckoning, an effect as large
as that which had been taken for the whole. But
this discovery was not made till afterwards; and in[176]
the mean time the law of the inverse square appeared
to be at fault. Clairault tried to remedy the defect
by supposing that the force of the earth’s gravity consisted
of a large force varying as the square of the
distance, and a very small force varying as the fourth
power (the square of the square.) By such a supposition,
observation and theory could be reconciled;
but on the suggestion of it, Buffon came forward
with the assertion that the force could not vary according
to any other law than the inverse square.
His arguments are rather metaphysical than physical
or mathematical. Gravity, he urges, is a quality,
an emanation; and all emanations are inversely as
the square of the distance, as light, odours. To this
Clairault replies by asking, how we know that light
and odours have their intensity inversely as the
square of the distance from their origin: not, he observes,
by measuring the intensity, but by supposing
these effects to be material emanations. But who,
he asks, supposes gravity to be a material emanation
from the attracting body.
Buffon again pleads that so many facts prove the
law of the inverse square, that a single one, which
occurs to interfere with this agreement, must be in
some manner capable of being explained away.
Clairault replies, that the facts do not prove this law
to obtain exactly; that small effects, of the same order
as the one under discussion, have been neglected;
and that therefore the law is only known to be true,
as far as such an approximation goes, and no farther.
Buffon then argues, that there can be no such additional
fraction of the force, following a different
law, as Clairault supposes: for what, he asks, is there
to determine the magnitude of the fraction to one
amount rather than another? why should nature select
for it any particular magnitude? To this it is replied,
that, whether we can explain the fact or not,
nature does select certain magnitudes in preference
to others: that where we ascertain she does this, we
are not to deny the fact because we cannot assign the[177]
grounds of her preference. What is there, it is asked,
to determine the magnitude of the whole force at
any fixed distance? We cannot tell; yet the force is
of a certain definite intensity and no other.
Finally, Clairault observes, that we have, in cohesion,
capillary attraction, and various other cases,
examples of forces varying according to other laws
than the inverse square; and that therefore this cannot
be the only possible law.
The discrepancy between observation and theory
which gave rise to this controversy was removed, as
has been already stated, by a more exact calculation:
and thus, as Laplace observes, in this case the
metaphysician turned out to be right and the mathematician
to be wrong. But most persons, probably,
who are familiar with such trains of speculation, will
allow, that Clairault had the best of the argument,
and that the attempts to show the law of gravitation
to be necessarily what it is, are fallacious and unsound.
8. We may observe, however, that the law of gravitation
according to the inverse square of the distance,
which thus regulates the motions of the solar
system, is not confined to that province of the universe,
as has been shown by recent researches. It
appears by the observations and calculations of Sir
John Herschel, that several of the stars, called double
stars, consist of a pair of luminous bodies which revolve
above each other in ellipses, in such a manner
as to show that the force, by which they are attracted
to each other, varies according to the law of the
inverse square. We thus learn a remarkable fact
concerning bodies which seemed so far removed that
no effort of our science could reach them; and we
find that the same law of mutual attraction which we
have before traced to the farthest bounds of the solar
system, prevails also in spaces at a distance compared
with which the orbit of Saturn shrinks into a point.
The establishment of such a truth certainly suggests,
as highly probable, the prevalence of this law among[178]
all the bodies of the universe. And we may therefore
suppose, that the same ordinance which gave to
the parts of our system that rule by which they fulfil
the purposes of their creation, impressed the same
rule on the other portions of matter which are scattered
in the most remote parts of the universe; and
thus gave to their movements the same grounds of
simplicity and harmony which we find reason to admire,
as far as we can acquire any knowledge of our
own more immediate neighbourhood.
</div></body></text></TEI>