<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="37">

BOOK IV.

THE PHILOSOPHY OF THE SECONDARY MECHANICAL SCIENCES.

CHAPTER I.
Of the Idea of a Medium as commonly employed.


1. Of Primary and Secondary Qualities.—In the same
way in which the mechanical sciences depend upon the Idea of
Cause, and have their principles regulated by the
development of that Idea, it will be found that the sciences
which have for their subject Sound, Light, and Heat, depend
for their principles upon the Fundamental Idea of
Media by means of which we perceive those qualities. Like
the idea of cause, this idea of a medium is unavoidably
employed, more or less distinctly, in the common,
unscientific operations of the understanding; and is
recognized as an express principle in the earliest
speculative essays of man. But here also, as in the case of
the mechanical sciences, the development of the idea, and
the establishment of the scientific truths which depend upon
it, was the business of a succeeding period, and was only
executed by means of long and laborious researches,
conducted with a constant reference to experiment and
observation.
Among the most prominent manifestations of the influence of
the idea of a medium of which we have now to speak, is the
distinction of the qualities of bodies into
primary, and secondary qualities. This
distinction has 294 been constantly spoken of in modern
times: yet it has often been a subject of discussion among
metaphysicians whether there be really such a distinction,
and what the true difference is. Locke states it thus1:
Original or Primary qualities of bodies are ‘such as are
utterly inseparable from the body in what estate soever it
may be,—such as sense constantly finds in every particle of
matter which has bulk enough to be perceived, and the mind
finds inseparable from every particle of matter, though less
than to make itself singly perceived by our senses:’ and he
enumerates them as solidity, extension, figure, motion or
rest, and number. Secondary qualities, on the other hand,
are such ‘which in truth are nothing in the objects
themselves, but powers to produce various sensations in us
by their primary qualities, i.e. by the bulk, figure,
texture, and motion of their insensible parts, as colours,
sounds, tastes, &c.’</div></body></text></TEI>