<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="32">

CHAPTER VII.
Of the Establishment of the Principles of Dynamics.



1. IN
the History of Mechanics, I have traced the steps by
which the three Laws of Motion and the other principles of
mechanics were discovered, established, and extended to the
widest generality of form and application. We have, in these
laws, examples of principles which were, historically
speaking, obtained by reference to experience. Bearing in
mind the object and the result of the preceding discussions,
we cannot but turn with much interest to examine these
portions of science; to inquire whether there be any real
difference in the grounds and nature between the knowledge
thus obtained, and those truths which we have already
contemplated; and which, as we have seen, contain their own
evidence, and do not require proof from experiment.
2. The First Law of Motion.—The first law of motion
is, that When a body moves not acted upon by any force,
it will go on perpetually in a straight line, and with a
uniform velocity. Now what is the real ground of our
assent to this proposition? That it is not at first sight a
self-evident truth, appears to be clear; since from the time
of Aristotle to that of Galileo the opposite assertion was
held to be true; and it was believed that all bodies in
motion had, by their own nature, a constant tendency to move
more and more slowly, so as to stop at last. This belief,
indeed, is probably even now entertained by most persons,
till their attention is fixed upon the arguments by which
the first law of motion is established. It is, however, not
difficult to lead any person of a speculative habit 236 of
thought to see that the retardation which constantly takes
place in the motion of all bodies when left to themselves,
is, in reality, the effect of extraneous forces which
destroy the velocity. A top ceases to spin because the
friction against the ground and the resistance of the air
gradually diminish its motion, and not because its motion
has any internal principle of decay or fatigue. This may be
shown, and was, in fact, shown by Hooke before the Royal
Society, at the time when the laws of motion were still
under discussion, by means of experiments in which the
weight of the top is increased, and the resistance to motion
offered by its support, is diminished; for by such
contrivances its motion is made to continue much longer than
it would otherwise do. And by experiments of this nature,
although we can never remove the whole of the external
impediments to continued motion, and although, consequently,
there will always be some retardation; and an end of the
motion of a body left to itself, however long it may be
delayed, must at last come; yet we can establish a
conviction that if all resistance could be removed, there
would be no diminution of velocity, and thus the motion
would go on for ever.
If we call to mind the axioms which we formerly stated, as
containing the most important conditions involved in the
idea of Cause, it will be seen that our conviction in this
case depends upon the first axiom of Causation, that nothing
can happen without a cause. Every change in the velocity of
the moving body must have a cause; and if the change can, in
any manner, be referred to the presence of other bodies,
these are said to exert force upon the moving body:
and the conception of force is thus evolved from the general
idea of cause. Force is any cause which has motion, or
change of motion, for its effect; and thus, all the
change of velocity of a body which can be referred to
extraneous bodies,—as the air which surrounds it, or the
support on which it rests,—is considered as the effect of
forces; and this consideration is looked upon as explaining
the difference between the motion which really takes places
in the experiment, and that motion 237 which, as the law
asserts, would take place if the body were not acted on by
any forces.
Thus the truth of the first law of motion depends upon the
axiom that no change can take place without a cause; and
follows from the definition of force, if we suppose that
there can be none but an external cause of change. But in
order to establish the law, it was necessary further to be
assured that there is no internal cause of change of
velocity belonging to all matter whatever, and operating in
such a manner that the mere progress of time is sufficient
to produce a diminution of velocity in all moving bodies. It
appears from the history of mechanical science, that this
latter step required a reference to observation and
experiment; and that the first law of motion is so far,
historically at least, dependent upon our experience.
But notwithstanding this historical evidence of the need
which we have of a reference to observed facts, in order to
place this first law of motion out of doubt, it has been
maintained by very eminent mathematicians and philosophers,
that the law is, in truth, evident of itself, and does not
really rest upon experimental proof. Such, for example, is
the opinion of d’Alembert20, who offers what is called
an à priori proof of this law; that is, a
demonstration derived from our ideas alone. When a body is
put in motion, either, he says, the cause which puts it in
motion at first, suffices to make it move one foot, or the
continued action of the cause during this foot is requisite
for the motion. In the first case, the same reason which
made the body proceed to the end of the first foot will hold
for its going on through a second, a third, a fourth foot,
and so on for any number. In the second case, the same
reason which made the force continue to act during the first
foot, will hold for its acting, and therefore for the body
moving during each succeeding foot. And thus the body, once
beginning to move, must go on moving for ever.</div></body></text></TEI>