<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="12">

BOOK IV.

PHYSICAL SCIENCE IN THE MIDDLE
AGES.

GENERAL REMARKS.
IN the twelfth Book of the
Philosophy, in which I have given a Review of Opinions on the
Nature of Knowledge and the method of seeking it, I have given some
account of several of the most important persons belonging to the ages
now under consideration. I have there (vol. ii. b. xii. p. 146) spoken
of the manner in which remarks made by Aristotle came to be accepted
as fundamental maxims in the schools of the middle ages, and of the
manner in which they were discussed by the greatest of the schoolmen,
as Thomas Aquinas, Albertus Magnus, and the like. I have spoken also
(p. 149) of a certain kind of recognition of the derivation of our
knowledge from experience; as shown in Richard of St. Victor, in the
twelfth century. I have considered (p. 152) the plea of the admirers
of those ages, that religious authority was not claimed for physical
science.
I have noticed that the rise of Experimental Philosophy exhibited
two features (chap. vii. p. 155), the Insurrection against Authority,
and the Appeal to Experience: and as exemplifying these features, I
have spoken of Raymond Lully and of Roger Bacon. I have further
noticed the opposition to the prevailing Aristotelian dogmatism
manifested (chap. viii.) by Nicolas of Cus, Marsilius Ficinus, Francis
Patricius, Picus of Mirandula, Cornelius Agrippa, Theophrastus
Paracelsus, Robert Fludd. I have gone on to notice the Theoretical
Reformers of Science (chap. ix.), Bernardinus Telesius, Thomas
Campanella, Andreas Cæsalpinus, Peter Ramus; and the Protestant
Reformers, as Melancthon. After these come the Practical Reformers of
Science, who have their place in the subsequent history of Inductive
Philosophy; Leonardo da Vinci, and the Heralds of the dawning light of
real science, whom Francis Bacon welcomes, as Heralds are accosted in
Homer:</div></body></text></TEI>