<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol I</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1794</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="17">SECT. XVII.
THE CATENATION OF MOTIONS.

I. 1.
  Catenations of animal motion. 2.
  Are produced by irritations, by sensations, by volitions. 3. They continue some time after they have
  been excited. Cause of catenation. 4.
  We can then exert our attention on other objects. 5. Many catenations of motions go on
  together. 6. Some links of the
  catenations of motions may be left out without disuniting the chain.
7. Interrupted circles of motion continue
  confusedly till they come to the part of the circle, where they were
  disturbed. 8. Weaker catenations are
  dissevered by stronger. 9. Then new
  catenations take place. 10. Much
  effort prevents their reuniting. Impediment of speech. 11. Trains more easily dissevered than
  circles. 12. Sleep destroys volition
  and external stimulus. II. Instances of
  various catenations in a young lady playing on the harpsichord. III. 1. What
  catenations are the strongest. 2.
  Irritations joined with associations from strongest connexions. Vital
  motions. 3. New links with increased
  force, cold fits of fever produced. 4.
  New links with decreased force. Cold bath. 5. Irritation joined with sensation.
  Inflammatory fever. Why children cannot tickle themselves. 6. Volition joined with sensation. Irritative
  ideas of sound become sensible. 7.
  Ideas of imagination, dissevered by irritations, by volition,
  production of surprise.

I. 1. To
  investigate with precision the catenations of animal motions, it would be
  well to attend to the manner of their production; but we cannot begin
  this disquisition early enough for this purpose, as the catenations of
  motion seem to begin with life, and are only extinguishable with it; We
  have spoken of the power of irritation, of sensation, of volition, and of
  association, as preceding the fibrous motions; we now step forwards, and
  consider, that conversely they are in their turn preceded by those
  motions; and that all the successive trains or circles of our actions are
  composed of this twofold concatenation. Those we shall call trains of
  action, which continue to proceed without any stated repetitions; and
  those circles of action, when the parts of them return at certain
  periods, though the trains, of which they consist, are not exactly
  similar. The reading an epic poem is a train of actions; the reading a
  song with a chorus at equal distances in the measure constitutes so many
  circles of action.
2. Some catenations of animal motion are
  produced by reiterated successive irritations, as when we learn to repeat
  the alphabet in its order by frequently reading the letters of it. Thus
  the vermicular motions of the bowels were originally produced by the
  successive irritations of the passing aliment; and the succession of
  actions of the auricles and ventricles of the heart was originally formed
  by successive stimulus of the blood, these afterwards become part of the
  diurnal circles of animal actions, as appears by the periodical returns
  of hunger, and the quickened pulse of weak people in the evening.
Other catenations of animal motion are gradually acquired by
  successive agreeable sensations, as in learning a favourite song or
  dance; others by disagreeable sensations, as in coughing or nictitation;
  these become associated by frequent repetition, and afterwards compose
  parts of greater circles of action like those above mentioned.
Other catenations of motions are gradually acquired by frequent
  voluntary repetitions; as when we deliberately learn to march, read,
  fence, or any mechanic art, the motions of many of our muscles become
  gradually linked together in trains, tribes, or circles of action. Thus
  when any one at first begins to use the tools in turning wood or metals
  in a lathe, he wills the motions of his hand or fingers, till at length
  these actions become so connected with the effect, that he seems only to
  will the point of the chisel. These are caused by volition, connected by
  association like those above described, and afterwards become parts of
  our diurnal trains or circles of action.
3. All these catenations of animal
  motions, are liable to proceed some time after they are excited, unless
  they are disturbed or impeded by other irritations, sensations, or
  volitions; and in many instances in spite of our endeavours to stop them;
  and this property of animal motions is probably the cause of their
  catenation. Thus when a child revolves some minute on one foot, the
  spectra of the ambient objects appear to circulate round him some time
  after he falls upon the ground. Thus the palpitation of the heart
  continues some time after the object of fear, which occasioned it, is
  removed. The blush of shame, which is an excess of sensation, and the
  glow of anger, which is an excess of volition, continue some time, though
  the affected person finds, that those emotions were caused by mistaken
  facts, and endeavours to extinguish their appearance. See Sect. XII. 1. 5.
4. When a circle of motions becomes
  connected, by frequent repetitions as above, we can exert our attention
  strongly on other objects, and the concatenated circle of motions will
  nevertheless proceed in due order; as whilst you are thinking on this
  subject, you use variety of muscles in walking about your parlour, or in
  sitting at your writing-table.
5. Innumerable catenations of motions may
  proceed at the same time, without incommoding each other. Of these are
  the motions of the heart and arteries; those of digestion and glandular
  secretion; of the ideas, or sensual motions; those of progression, and of
  speaking; the great annual circle of actions so apparent in birds in
  their times of breeding and moulting; the monthly circles of many female
  animals; and the diurnal circles of sleeping and waking, of fulness and
  inanition.
6. Some links of successive trains or of
  synchronous tribes of action may be left out without disjoining the
  whole. Such are our usual trains of recollection; after having travelled
  through an entertaining country, and viewed many delightful lawns,
  rolling rivers, and echoing rocks; in the recollection of our journey we
  leave out the many districts, that we crossed, which were marked with no
  peculiar pleasure. Such also are our complex ideas, they are catenated
  tribes of ideas, which do not perfectly resemble their correspondent
  perceptions, because some of the parts are omitted.
7. If an interrupted circle of actions is
  not entirely dissevered, it will continue to proceed confusedly, till it
  comes to the part of the circle, where it was interrupted.
The vital motions in a fever from drunkenness, and in other periodical
  diseases, are instances of this circumstance. The accidental inebriate
  does not recover himself perfectly till about the same hour on the
  succeeding day. The accustomed drunkard is disordered, if he has not his
  usual potation of fermented liquor. So if a considerable part of a
  connected tribe of action be disturbed, that whole tribe goes on with
  confusion, till the part of the tribe affected regains its accustomed
  catenations. So vertigo produces vomiting, and a great secretion of bile,
  as in sea-sickness, all these being parts of the tribe of irritative
  catenations.
8. Weaker catenated trains may be
  dissevered by the sudden exertion of the stronger. When a child first
  attempts to walk across a room, call to him, and he instantly falls upon
  the ground. So while I am thinking over the virtues of my friends, if the
  tea-kettle spurt out some hot water on my stocking; the sudden pain
  breaks the weaker chain of ideas, and introduces a new group of figures
  of its own. This circumstance is extended to some unnatural trains of
  action, which have not been confirmed by long habit; as the hiccough, or
  an ague-fit, which are frequently curable by surprise. A young lady about
  eleven years old had for five days had a contraction of one muscle in her
  fore arm, and another in her arm, which occurred four or five times every
  minute; the muscles were seen to leap, but without bending the arm. To
  counteract this new morbid habit, an issue was placed over the convulsed
  muscle of her arm, and an adhesive plaster wrapped tight like a bandage
  over the whole fore arm, by which the new motions were immediately
  destroyed, but the means were continued some weeks to prevent a
  return.
9. If any circle of actions is dissevered,
  either by omission of some of the links, as in sleep, or by insertion of
  other links, as in surprise, new catenations take place in a greater or
  less degree. The last link of the broken chain of actions becomes
  connected with the new motion which has broken it, or with that which was
  nearest the link omitted; and these new catenations proceed instead of
  the old ones. Hence the periodic returns of ague-fits, and the chimeras
  of our dreams.
10. If a train of actions is dissevered,
  much effort of volition or sensation will prevent its being restored.
  Thus in the common impediment of speech, when the association of the
  motions of the muscles of enunciation with the idea of the word to be
  spoken is disordered, the great voluntary efforts, which distort the
  countenance, prevent the rejoining of the broken associations. See No. II. 10. of this Section. It is thus likewise
  observable in some inflammations of the bowels, the too strong efforts
  made by the muscles to carry forwards the offending material fixes it
  more firmly in its place, and prevents the cure. So in endeavouring to
  recal to our memory some particular word of a sentence, if we exert
  ourselves too strongly about it, we are less likely to regain it.
11. Catenated trains or tribes of action
  are easier dissevered than catenated circles of action. Hence in
  epileptic fits the synchronous connected tribes of action, which keep the
  body erect, are dissevered, but the circle of vital motions continues
  undisturbed.
12. Sleep destroys the power of volition,
  and precludes the stimuli of external objects, and thence dissevers the
  trains, of which these are a part; which confirms the other catenations,
  as those of the vital motions, secretions, and absorptions; and produces
  the new trains of ideas, which constitute our dreams.
II. 1. All the
  preceding circumstances of the catenations of animal motions will be more
  clearly understood by the following example of a person learning music;
  and when we recollect the variety of mechanic arts, which are performed
  by associated trains of muscular actions catenated with the effects they
  produce, as in knitting, netting, weaving; and the greater variety of
  associated trains of ideas caused or catenated by volitions or
  sensations, as in our hourly modes of reasoning, or imagining, or
  recollecting, we shall gain some idea of the innumerable catenated trains
  and circles of action, which form the tenor of our lives, and which
  began, and will only cease entirely with them.
2. When a young lady begins to learn
  music, she voluntarily applies herself to the characters of her
  music-book, and by many repetitions endeavours to catenate them with the
  proportions of sound, of which they are symbols. The ideas excited by the
  musical characters are slowly connected with the keys of the harpsichord,
  and much effort is necessary to produce every note with the proper
  finger, and in its due place and time; till at length a train of
  voluntary exertions becomes catenated with certain irritations. As the
  various notes by frequent repetitions become connected in the order, in
  which they are produced, a new catenation of sensitive exertions becomes
  mixed with the voluntary ones above described; and not only the musical
  symbols of crotchets and quavers, but the auditory notes and tones at the
  same time, become so many successive or synchronous links in this circle
  of catenated actions.
At length the motions of her fingers become catenated with the musical
  characters; and these no sooner strike the eye, than the finger presses
  down the key without any voluntary attention between them; the activity
  of the hand being connected with the irritation of the figure or place of
  the musical symbol on the retina; till at length by frequent repetitions
  of the same tune the movements of her fingers in playing, and the muscles
  of the larynx in singing, become associated with each other, and form
  part of those intricate trains and circles of catenated motions,
  according with the second article of the preceding propositions in No. 1. of this Section.
3. Besides the facility, which by habit
  attends the execution of this musical performance, a curious circumstance
  occurs, which is, that when our young musician has began a tune, she
  finds herself inclined to continue it; and that even when she is
  carelessly singing alone without attending to her own song; according
  with the third preceding article.
4. At the same time that our young
  performer continues to play with great exactness this accustomed tune,
  she can bend her mind, and that intensely, on some other object,
  according with the fourth article of the preceding proportions.
The manuscript copy of this work was lent to many of my friends at
  different times for the purpose of gaining their opinions and criticisms
  on many parts of it, and I found the following anecdote written with a
  pencil opposite to this page, but am not certain by whom. "I remember
  seeing the pretty young actress, who succeeded Mrs. Arne in the
  performance of the celebrated Padlock, rehearse the musical parts at her
  harpsichord under the eye of her master with great taste and accuracy;
  though I observed her countenance full of emotion, which I could not
  account for; at last she suddenly burst into tears; for she had all this
  time been eyeing a beloved canary bird, suffering great agonies, which at
  that instant fell dead from its perch."
5. At the same time many other catenated
  circles of action are going on in the person of our fair musician, as
  well as the motions of her fingers, such as the vital motions,
  respiration, the movements of her eyes and eyelids, and of the intricate
  muscles of vocality, according with the fifth preceding article.
6. If by any strong impression on the mind
  of our fair musician she should be interrupted for a very inconsiderable
  time, she can still continue her performance, according to the sixth
  article.
7. If however this interruption be
  greater, though the chain of actions be not dissevered, it proceeds
  confusedly, and our young performer continues indeed to play, but in a
  hurry without accuracy and elegance, till she begins the tune again,
  according to the seventh of the preceding articles.
8. But if this interruption be still
  greater, the circle of actions becomes entirely dissevered, and she finds
  herself immediately under the necessity to begin over again to recover
  the lost catenation, according to the eighth preceding article.
9. Or in trying to recover it she will
  sing some dissonant notes, or strike some improper keys, according to the
  ninth preceding article.
10. A very remarkable thing attends this
  breach of catenation, if the performer has forgotten some word of her
  song, the more energy of mind she uses about it, the more distant is she
  from regaining it; and artfully employs her mind in part on some other
  object, or endeavours to dull its perceptions, continuing to repeat, as
  it were inconsciously, the former part of the song, that she remembers,
  in hopes to regain the lost connexion.
For if the activity of the mind itself be more energetic, or takes its
  attention more, than the connecting word, which is wanted; it will not
  perceive the slighter link of this lost word; as who listens to a feeble
  sound, must be very silent and motionless; so that in this case the very
  vigour of the mind itself seems to prevent it from regaining the lost
  catenation, as well as the too great exertion in endeavouring to regain
  it, according to the tenth preceding article.
We frequently experience, when we are doubtful about the spelling of a
  word, that the greater voluntary exertion we use, that is the more
  intensely we think about it, the further are we from regaining the lost
  association between the letters of it, but which readily recurs when we
  have become careless about it. In the same manner, after having for an
  hour laboured to recollect the name of some absent person, it shall seem,
  particularly after sleep, to come into the mind as it were spontaneously;
  that is the word we are in search of, was joined to the preceding one by
  association; this association being dissevered, we endeavour to recover
  it by volition; this very action of the mind strikes our attention more,
  than the faint link of association, and we find it impossible by this
  means to retrieve the lost word. After sleep, when volition is entirely
  suspended, the mind becomes capable of perceiving the fainter link of
  association, and the word is regained.
On this circumstance depends the impediment of speech before
  mentioned; the first syllable of a word is causable by volition, but the
  remainder of it is in common conversation introduced by its associations
  with this first syllable acquired by long habit. Hence when the mind of
  the stammerer is vehemently employed on some idea of ambition of shining,
  or fear of not succeeding, the associations of the motions of the muscles
  of articulation with each other become dissevered by this greater
  exertion, and he endeavours in vain by voluntary efforts to rejoin the
  broken association. For this purpose he continues to repeat the first
  syllable, which is causable by volition, and strives in vain, by various
  distortions of countenance, to produce the next links, which are subject
  to association. See Class IV. 3. 1. 1.
11. After our accomplished musician has
  acquired great variety of tunes and songs, so that some of them begin to
  cease to be easily recollected, she finds progressive trains of musical
  notes more frequently forgotten, than those which are composed of
  reiterated circles, according with the eleventh preceding article.
12. To finish our example with the
  preceding articles we must at length suppose, that our fair performer
  falls asleep over her harpsichord; and thus by the suspension of
  volition, and the exclusion of external stimuli, she dissevers the trains
  and circles of her musical exertions.
III. 1. Many of
  these circumstances of catenations of motions receive an easy explanation
  from the four following consequences to the seventh law of animal
  causation in Sect. IV. These are, first, that
  those successions or combinations of animal motions, whether they were
  united by causation, association, or catenation, which have been most
  frequently repeated, acquire the strongest connection. Secondly, that of
  these, those, which have been less frequently mixed with other trains or
  tribes of motion, have the strongest connection. Thirdly, that of these,
  those, which were first formed, have the strongest connection. Fourthly,
  that if an animal motion be excited by more than one causation,
  association, or catenation, at the same time, it will be performed with
  greater energy.
2. Hence also we understand, why the
  catenations of irritative motions are more strongly connected than those
  of the other classes, where the quantity of unmixed repetition has been
  equal; because they were first formed. Such are those of the secerning
  and absorbent systems of vessels, where the action of the gland produces
  a fluid, which stimulates the mouths of its correspondent absorbents. The
  associated motions seem to be the next most strongly united, from their
  frequent repetition; and where both these circumstances unite, as in the
  vital motions, their catenations are indissoluble but by the destruction
  of the animal.
3. Where a new link has been introduced
  into a circle of actions by some accidental defect of stimulus; if that
  defect of stimulus be repeated at the same part of the circle a second or
  a third time, the defective motions thus produced, both by the repeated
  defect of stimulus and by their catenation with the parts of the circle
  of actions, will be performed with less and less energy. Thus if any
  person is exposed to cold at a certain hour to-day, so long as to render
  some part of the system for a time torpid; and is again exposed to it at
  the same hour to-morrow, and the next day; he will be more and more
  affected by it, till at length a cold fit of fever is completely formed,
  as happens at the beginning of many of those fevers, which are called
  nervous or low fevers. Where the patient has slight periodical shiverings
  and paleness for many days before the febrile paroxysm is completely
  formed.
4. On the contrary, if the exposure to
  cold be for so short a time, as not to induce any considerable degree of
  torpor or quiescence, and is repeated daily as above mentioned, it loses
  its effect more and more at every repetition, till the constitution can
  bear it without inconvenience, or indeed without being conscious of it.
  As in walking into the cold air in frosty weather. The same rule is
  applicable to increased stimulus, as of heat, or of vinous spirit, within
  certain limits, as is applied in the two last paragraphs to Deficient
  Stimulus; as is further explained in Sect. XXXVI. on the Periods of Diseases.
5. Where irritation coincides with
  sensation to produce the same catenations of motion, as in inflammatory
  fevers, they are excited with still greater energy than by the irritation
  alone. So when children expect to be tickled in play, by a feather
  lightly passed over the lips, or by gently vellicating the soles of their
  feet, laughter is most vehemently excited; though they can stimulate
  these parts with their own fingers unmoved. Here the pleasureable idea of
  playfulness coincides with the vellication; and there is no voluntary
  exertion used to diminish the sensation, as there would be, if a child
  should endeavour to tickle himself. See Sect. XXXIV. 1. 4.
6. And lastly, the motions excited by the
  junction of voluntary exertion with irritation are performed with more
  energy, than those by irritation singly; as when we listen to small
  noises, as to the ticking of a watch in the night, we perceive the most
  weak sounds, that are at other times unheeded. So when we attend to the
  irritative ideas of sound in our ears, which are generally not attended
  to, we can hear them; and can see the spectra of objects, which remain in
  the eye, whenever we please to exert our voluntary power in aid of those
  weak actions of the retina, or of the auditory nerve.
7. The temporary catenations of ideas,
  which are caused by the sensations of pleasure or pain, are easily
  dissevered either by irritations, as when a sudden noise disturbs a
  day-dream; or by the power of volition, as when we awake from sleep.
  Hence in our waking hours, whenever an idea occurs, which is incongruous
  to our former experience, we instantly dissever the train of imagination
  by the power of volition, and compare the incongruous idea with our
  previous knowledge of nature, and reject it. This operation of the mind
  has not yet acquired a specific name, though it is exerted every minute
  of our waking hours; unless it may be termed INTUITIVE
  ANALOGY. It is an act of reasoning of which we are unconscious
  except from its effects in preserving the congruity of our ideas, and
  bears the same relation to the sensorial power of volition, that
  irritative ideas, of which we are inconscious except by their effects, do
  to the sensorial power of irritation; as the former is produced by
  volition without our attention to it, and the latter by irritation
  without our attention to them.
If on the other hand a train of imagination or of voluntary ideas are
  excited with great energy, and passing on with great vivacity, and become
  dissevered by some violent stimulus, as the discharge of a pistol near
  one's ear, another circumstance takes place, which is termed SURPRISE; which by exciting violent irritation, and
  violent sensation, employs for a time the whole sensorial energy, and
  thus dissevers the passing trains of ideas, before the power of volition
  has time to compare them with the usual phenomena of nature. In this case
  fear is generally the companion of surprise, and adds to our
  embarrassment, as every one experiences in some degree when he hears a
  noise in the dark, which he cannot instantly account for. This catenation
  of fear with surprise is owing to our perpetual experience of injuries
  from external bodies in motion, unless we are upon our guard against
  them. See Sect. XVIII. 17. XIX. 2.
Many other examples of the catenations of animal motions are explained
  in Sect. XXXVI. on the Periods of Diseases.

</div></body></text></TEI>