<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol I</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1794</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="19">SECT. XIX.
OF REVERIE.

1. Various degrees of reverie. 2. Sleep-walkers. Case of a young lady. Great
  surprise at awaking. And total forgetfulness of what passed in
  reverie. 3. No suspension of volition in
  reverie. 4. Sensitive motions continue,
  and are consistent. 5. Irritative
  motions continue, but are not succeeded by sensation. 6. Volition necessary for the perception of
  feeble impressions. 7. Associated
  motions continue. 8. Nerves of sense are
  irritable in sleep, but not in reverie. 9.
  Somnambuli are not asleep. Contagion received but once. 10. Definition of reverie.

1. When we are employed with great sensation
  of pleasure, or with great efforts of volition, in the pursuit of some
  interesting train of ideas, we cease to be conscious of our existence,
  are inattentive to time and place, and do not distinguish this train of
  sensitive and voluntary ideas from the irritative ones excited by the
  presence of external objects, though our organs of sense are furnished
  with their accustomed stimuli, till at length this interesting train of
  ideas becomes exhausted, or the appulses of external objects are applied
  with unusual violence, and we return with surprise, or with regret, into
  the common track of life. This is termed reverie or studium.
In some constitutions these reveries continue a considerable time, and
  are not to be removed without greater difficulty, but are experienced in
  a less degree by us all; when we attend earnestly to the ideas excited by
  volition or sensation, with their associated connexions, but are at the
  same time conscious at intervals of the stimuli of surrounding bodies.
  Thus in being present at a play, or in reading a romance, some persons
  are so totally absorbed as to forget their usual time of sleep, and to
  neglect their meals; while others are said to have been so involved in
  voluntary study as not to have heard the discharge of artillery; and
  there is a story of an Italian politician, who could think so intensely
  on other subjects, as to be insensible to the torture of the rack.
From hence it appears, that these catenations of ideas and muscular
  motions, which form the trains of reverie, are composed both of voluntary
  and sensitive associations of them; and that these ideas differ from
  those of delirium or of sleep, as they are kept consistent by the power
  of volition; and they differ also from the trains of ideas belonging to
  insanity, as they are as frequently excited by sensation as by volition.
  But lastly, that the whole sensorial power is so employed on these trains
  of complete reverie, that like the violent efforts of volition, as in
  convulsions or insanity; or like the great activity of the irritative
  motions in drunkenness; or of the sensitive motions in delirium; they
  preclude all sensation consequent to external stimulus.
2. Those persons, who are said to walk in
  their sleep, are affected with reverie to so great a degree, that it
  becomes a formidable disease; the essence of which consists in the
  inaptitude of the mind to attend to external stimuli. Many histories of
  this disease have been published by medical writers; of which there is a
  very curious one in the Lausanne Transactions. I shall here subjoin an
  account of such a case, with its cure, for the better illustration of
  this subject.
A very ingenious and elegant young lady, with light eyes and hair,
  about the age of seventeen, in other respects well, was suddenly seized
  soon after her usual menstruation with this very wonderful malady. The
  disease began with vehement convulsions of almost every muscle of her
  body, with great but vain efforts to vomit, and the most violent
  hiccoughs, that can be conceived: these were succeeded in about an hour
  with a fixed spasm; in which one hand was applied to her head, and the
  other to support it: in about half an hour these ceased, and the reverie
  began suddenly, and was at first manifest by the look of her eyes and
  countenance, which seemed to express attention. Then she conversed aloud
  with imaginary persons with her eyes open, and could not for about an
  hour be brought to attend to the stimulus of external objects by any kind
  of violence, which it was proper to use; these symptoms returned in this
  order every day for five or six weeks.
These conversations were quite consistent, and we could understand,
  what she supposed her imaginary companions to answer, by the continuation
  of her part of the discourse. Sometimes she was angry, at other times
  shewed much wit and vivacity, but was most frequently inclined to
  melancholy. In these reveries she sometimes sung over some music with
  accuracy, and repeated whole pages from the English poets. In repeating
  some lines from Mr. Pope's works she had forgot one word, and began
  again, endeavouring to recollect it; when she came to the forgotten word,
  it was shouted aloud in her ear, and this repeatedly, to no purpose; but
  by many trials she at length regained it herself.
These paroxysms were terminated with the appearance of inexpressible
  surprise, and great fear, from which she was some minutes in recovering
  herself, calling on her sister with great agitation, and very frequently
  underwent a repetition of convulsions, apparently from the pain of fear.
  See Sect. XVII. 3. 7.
After having thus returned for about an hour every day for two or
  three weeks, the reveries seemed to become less complete, and some of
  their circumstances varied; so that she could walk about the room in them
  without running against any of the furniture; though these motions were
  at first very unsteady and tottering. And afterwards she once drank a
  dish of tea, when the whole apparatus of the tea-table was set before
  her; and expressed some suspicion, that a medicine was put into it, and
  once seemed to smell of a tuberose, which was in flower in her chamber,
  and deliberated aloud about breaking it from the stem, saying, "it would
  make her sister so charmingly angry." At another time in her melancholy
  moments she heard the sound of a passing bell, "I wish I was dead," she
  cried, listening to the bell, and then taking off one of her shoes, as
  she sat upon the bed, "I love the colour black," says she, "a little
  wider, and a little longer, even this might make me a coffin!"—Yet
  it is evident, she was not sensible at this time, any more than formerly,
  of seeing or hearing any person about her; indeed when great light was
  thrown upon her by opening the shutters of the window, her trains of
  ideas seemed less melancholy; and when I have forcibly held her hands, or
  covered her eyes, she appeared to grow impatient, and would say, she
  could not tell what to do, for she could neither see nor move. In all
  these circumstances her pulse continued unaffected as in health. And when
  the paroxysm was over, she could never recollect a single idea of what
  had passed in it.
This astonishing disease, after the use of many other medicines and
  applications in vain, was cured by very large doses of opium given about
  an hour before the expected returns of the paroxysms; and after a few
  relapses, at the intervals of three or four months, entirely disappeared.
  But she continued at times to have other symptoms of epilepsy.
3. We shall only here consider, what happened
  during the time of her reveries, as that is our present subject; the fits
  of convulsion belong to another part of this treatise. Sect. XXXIV. 1. 4.
There seems to have been no suspension of volition during the fits of
  reverie, because she endeavoured to regain the lost idea in repeating the
  lines of poetry, and deliberated about breaking the tuberose, and
  suspected the tea to have been medicated.
4. The ideas and muscular movements depending
  on sensation were exerted with their usual vivacity, and were kept from
  being inconsistent by the power of volition, as appeared from her whole
  conversation, and was explained in Sect. XVII.
  3. 7. and XVIII. 16.
5. The ideas and motions dependant on
  irritation during the first weeks of her disease, whilst the reverie was
  complete, were never succeeded by the sensation of pleasure or pain; as
  she neither saw, heard, nor felt any of the surrounding objects. Nor was
  it certain that any irritative motions succeeded the stimulus of external
  objects, till the reverie became less complete, and then she could walk
  about the room without running against the furniture of it. Afterwards,
  when the reverie became still less complete from the use of opium, some
  few irritations were at times succeeded by her attention to them. As when
  she smelt at a tuberose, and drank a dish of tea, but this only when she
  seemed voluntarily to attend to them.
6. In common life when we listen to distant
  sounds, or wish to distinguish objects in the night, we are obliged
  strongly to exert our volition to dispose the organs of sense to perceive
  them, and to suppress the other trains of ideas, which might interrupt
  these feeble sensations. Hence in the present history the strongest
  stimuli were not perceived, except when the faculty of volition was
  exerted on the organ of sense; and then even common stimuli were
  sometimes perceived: for her mind was so strenuously employed in pursuing
  its own trains of voluntary or sensitive ideas, that no common stimuli
  could so far excite her attention as to disunite them; that is, the
  quantity of volition or of sensation already existing was greater than
  any, which could be produced in consequence of common degrees of
  stimulation. But the few stimuli of the tuberose, and of the tea, which
  she did perceive, were such, as accidentally coincided with the trains of
  thought, which were passing in her mind; and hence did not disunite those
  trains, and create surprise. And their being perceived at all was owing
  to the power of volition preceding or coinciding with that of
  irritation.
This explication is countenanced by a fact mentioned concerning a
  somnambulist in the Lausanne Transactions, who sometimes opened his eyes
  for a short time to examine, where he was, or where his ink-pot stood,
  and then shut them again, dipping his pen into the pot every now and
  then, and writing on, but never opening his eyes afterwards, although he
  wrote on from line to line regularly, and corrected some errors of the
  pen, or in spelling: so much easier was it to him to refer to his ideas
  of the positions of things, than to his perceptions of them.
7. The associated motions persisted in their
  usual channel, as appeared by the combinations of her ideas, and the use
  of her muscles, and the equality of her pulse; for the natural motions of
  the arterial system, though originally excited like other motions by
  stimulus, seem in part to continue by their association with each other.
  As the heart of a viper pulsates long after it is cut out of the body,
  and removed from the stimulus of the blood.
8. In the section on sleep, it was observed
  that the nerves of sense are equally alive and susceptible to irritation
  in that state, as when we are awake; but that they are secluded from
  stimulating objects, or rendered unfit to receive them: but in complete
  reverie the reverse happens, the immediate organs of sense are exposed to
  their usual stimuli; but are either not excited into action at all, or
  not into so great action, as to produce attention or sensation.
The total forgetfulness of what passes in reveries; and the surprise
  on recovering from them, are explained in Section XVIII. 19. and in Section XVII. 3. 7.
9. It appears from hence, that reverie is a
  disease of the epileptic or cataleptic kind, since the paroxysms of this
  young lady always began and frequently terminated with convulsions; and
  though in its greatest degree it has been called somnambulation, or
  sleep-walking, it is totally different from sleep; because the essential
  character of sleep consists in the total suspension of volition, which in
  reverie is not affected; and the essential character of reverie consists
  not in the absence of those irritative motions of our senses, which are
  occasioned by the stimulus of external objects, but in their never being
  productive of sensation. So that during a fit of reverie that strange
  event happens to the whole system of nerves, which occurs only to some
  particular branches of them in those, who are a second time exposed to
  the action of contagious matter. If the matter of the small-pox be
  inserted into the arm of one, who has previously had that disease, it
  will stimulate the wound, but the general sensation or inflammation of
  the system does not follow, which constitutes the disease. See Sect. XII. 3. 6. XXXIII. 2.
  8.
10. The following is the definition or
  character of complete reverie. 1. The irritative motions occasioned by
  internal stimuli continue, those from the stimuli of external objects are
  either not produced at all, or are never succeeded by sensation or
  attention, unless they are at the same time excited by volition. 2. The
  sensitive motions continue, and are kept consistent by the power of
  volition. 3. The voluntary motions continue undisturbed. 4. The associate
  motions continue undisturbed.
Two other cases of reverie are related in Section XXXIV. 3. which further evince, that reverie is
  an effort of the mind to relieve some painful sensation, and is hence
  allied to convulsion, and to insanity. Another case is related in Class
  III. 1. 2. 2.

</div></body></text></TEI>