<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="33">
CHAPTER I.

The Creator of the Physical World is the Governor of
the Moral World.

With our views of the moral government of the
world and the religious interests of man, the study of
material nature is not and cannot be directly and
closely connected. But it may be of some service to
trace in these two lines of reasoning, seemingly so
remote, a manifest convergence to the same point, a
demonstrable unity of result. It may be useful to
show that we are thus led, not to two rulers of the
universe, but to one God;—to make it appear that
the Creator and Preserver of the world is also the
Governor and Judge of men;—that the Author of the
Laws of Nature is also the Author of the Law of
Duty;—that He who regulates corporeal things by[196]
properties of attraction and affinity and assimilating
power, is the same Being who regulates the actions
and conditions of men, by the influence of the feeling
of responsibility, the perception of right and wrong,
the hope of happiness, the love of good.
The conviction that the Divine attributes which
we are taught by the study of the material world,
and those which we learn from the contemplation of
man as a responsible agent, belong to the same Divine
Being, will be forced upon us, if we consider
the manner in which all the parts of the universe,
the corporeal and intellectual, the animal and moral,
are connected with each other. In each of these
provinces of creation we trace refined adaptations
and arrangements which lead us to the Creator 
and Director of so skilful a system; but these provinces
are so intermixed, these different trains of
contrivance so interwoven, that we cannot, in our
thoughts, separate the author of one part from the
author of another. The Creator of the Heavens and
of the Earth, of the inorganic and of the organic
world, of animals and of man, of the affections and
the conscience, appears inevitably to be one and the
same God.
We will pursue this reflection a little more into
detail.
1. The Atmosphere is a mere mass of fluid floating
on the surface of the ball of the earth; it is one of
the inert and inorganic portions of the universe, and
must be conceived to have been formed by the same
Power which formed the solid mass of the earth and
all other parts of the solar system. But how far is
the atmosphere from being inert in its effects on organic
beings, and unconnected with the world of
life! By what wonderful adaptations of its mechanical
and chemical properties, and of the vital powers
of plants, to each other, are the developement and
well-being of plants and animals secured! The creator
of the atmosphere must have been also the creator
of plants and animals: we cannot for an instant[197]
believe the contrary. But the atmosphere is not only
subservient to the life of animals, and of man among
the rest; it is also the vehicle of voice; it answers
the purpose of intercourse; and, in the case of man,
of rational intercourse. We have seen how remarkably
the air is fitted for this office; the construction
of the organs of articulation, by which they are enabled
to perform their part of the work, is, as is well
known, a most exquisite system of contrivances. But
though living in an atmosphere capable of transmitting
articulate sound, and though provided with organs
fitted to articulate, man would never attain to
the use of language, if he were not also endowed
with another set of faculties. The powers of abstraction
and generalization, memory and reason, the tendencies
which occasion the inflexions and combinations
of words, are all necessary to the formation
and use of language. Are not these parts of the
same scheme of which the bodily faculties by which
we are able to speak are another part? Has man
his mental powers independently of the creator of
his bodily frame? To what purpose then, or by
what cause was the curious and complex machinery
of the tongue, the glottis, the larynx produced?
These are useful for speech, and full of contrivances
which suggest such a use as the end for which those
organs were constructed. But speech appears to
have been no less contemplated in the intellectual
structure of man. The processes of which we have
spoken, generalization, abstraction, reasoning, have
a close dependence on the use of speech. These faculties
are presupposed in the formation of language,
but they are developed and perfected by the use of
language. The mind of man then, with all its intellectual
endowments, is the work of the same artist
by whose hands his bodily frame was fashioned; as
his bodily faculties again are evidently constructed
by the maker of those elements on which their action
depends. The creator of the atmosphere and
of the material universe is the creator of the human[198]
mind, and the author of those wonderful powers of
thinking, judging, inferring, discovering, by
we are able to reason concerning the world in which
we are placed; and which aid us in lifting our thoughts
to the source of our being himself.
2. Light, or the means by which light is propagated,
is another of the inorganic elements which forms
a portion of the mere material world. The luminiferous
ether, if we adopt that theory, or the fluid
light of the theory of emission, must indubitably pervade
the remotest regions of the universe, and must
be supposed to exist, as soon as we suppose the material
parts of the universe to be in existence. The
origin of light then must be at least as far removed
from us as the origin of the solar system. Yet how
closely connected are the properties of light with the
structure of our own bodies! The mechanism of the
organs of vision and the mechanism of light are, as
we have seen, most curiously adapted to each other.
We must suppose, then, that the same power and
skill produced one and the other of these two sets of
contrivances, which so remarkably fit into each other.
The creator of light is the author of our visual powers.
But how small a portion does mere visual perception
constitute of the advantages which we derive from
vision! We possess ulterior faculties and capacities
by which sight becomes a source of happiness and
good to man. The sense of beauty, the love of art,
the pleasure arising from the contemplation of nature,
are all dependent on the eye; and we can hardly
doubt that these faculties were bestowed on man
to further the best interests of his being. The sense
of beauty both animates and refines his domestic
tendencies; the love of art is a powerful instrument
for raising him above the mere cravings and satisfactions
of his animal nature; the expansion of mind
which rises in us at the sight of the starry sky, the
cloud-capt mountain, the boundless ocean, seems intended
to direct our thoughts by an impressive though
indefinite feeling, to the Infinite Author of All. But[199]
if these faculties be thus part of the scheme of man’s
inner being, given him by a good and wise creator,
can we suppose that this creator was any other than
the creator also of those visual organs, without which
the faculties could have no operation and no existence?
As clearly as light and the eye are the work
of the same author, so clearly also do our capacities
for the most exalted visual pleasures, and the feelings
flowing from them, proceed from the same Divine
Hand.
3. The creator of the earth must be conceived to
be the author also of all those qualities in the soil,
chemical and whatever else, by which it supports
vegetable life, under all the modifications of natural
and artificial condition. Among the attributes which
the earth thus possesses, there are some which seem
to have an especial reference to man in a state of
society. Such are—the power of the earth to increase
its produce under the influence of cultivation, and
the necessary existence of property in land, in order
that this cultivation may be advantageously applied;
the rise, under such circumstances, of a surplus produce,
of a quantity of subsistence exceeding the
wants of the cultivators alone; and the consequent
possibility of inequalities of rank, and of all the arrangements
of civil society. These are all parts of
the constitution of the earth. But these would all
remain mere idle possibilities, if the nature of man
had not a corresponding direction. If man had not
a social and economical tendency, a disposition to
congregate and co-operate, to distribute possessions
and offices among the members of the community,
to make and obey and enforce laws, the earth would
in vain be ready to respond to the care of the husbandman.
Must we not then suppose that this attribute
of the earth was bestowed upon it by Him who
gave to man those corresponding attributes, through
which the apparent niggardliness of the soil is the
source of general comfort and security, of polity and
law? Must we not suppose that He who created the[200]
soil also inspired man with those social desires and
feelings which produce cities and states, laws and
institutions, arts and civilization; and that thus the
apparently inert mass of earth is a part of the same
scheme as those faculties and powers with which
man’s moral and intellectual progress is most connected?
4. Again:—It will hardly be questioned that the
author of the material elements is also the author
of the structure of animals, which is adapted to and
provided for by the constitution of the elements in
such innumerable ways. But the author of the
bodily structure of animals must also be the author
of their instincts, for without these the structure
would not answer its purpose. And these
instincts frequently assume the character of affections
in a most remarkable manner. The love of
offspring, of home, of companions, are often displayed
by animals, in a way that strikes the most indifferent
observer; and yet these affections will hardly
be denied to be a part of the same scheme as the instincts
by which the same animals seek food and the
gratifications of sense. Who can doubt that the
anxious and devoted affection of the mother-bird 
for her young after they are hatched, is a part of the
same system of Providence as the instinct by which
she is impelled to sit upon her eggs? and this, of the
same by which her eggs are so organized that incubation
leads to the birth of the young animal? Nor,
again, can we imagine that while the structure and
affections of animals belong to one system of things,
the affections of man, in many respects so similar to
those of animals, and connected with the bodily
frame in a manner so closely analogous, can belong
to a different scheme. Who, that reads the touching
instances of maternal affection, related so often of
the women of all nations, and of the females of all
animals, can doubt that the principle of action is the
same in the two cases, though enlightened in one of
them by the rational faculty: And who can place in[201]
separate provinces the supporting and protecting
love of the father and the mother? or consider as
entirely distinct from these, and belonging to another
part of our nature, the other kinds of family affection?
or disjoin man’s love of his home, his clan, his
tribe, his country, from the affection which he bears
to his family? The love of offspring, home, friends,
in man, is then part of the same system of contrivances
of which bodily organization is another part.
And thus the author of our corporeal frame is also the
author of our capacity of kindness and resentment,
of our love and of our wish to be loved, of all the
emotions which bind us to individuals, to our families,
and to our kind.
It is not necessary here to follow out and classify
these emotions and affections; or to examine how
they are combined and connected with our other
motives of action, mutually giving and receiving
strength and direction. The desire of esteem, of
power, of knowledge, of society, the love of kindred,
of friends, of our country, are manifestly among the
main forces by which man is urged to act and to abstain.
And as these parts of the constitution of man
are clearly intended, as we conceive, to impel him
in his appointed path; so we conceive that they are
no less clearly the work of the same great Artificer
who created the heart, the eye, the hand, the tongue,
and that elemental world in which, by means of these
instruments, man pursues the objects of his appetites,
desires, and affections.
5. But if the Creator of the world be also the author
of our intellectual powers, of our feeling for
the beautiful and the sublime, of our social tendencies,
and of our natural desires and affections, we
shall find it impossible not to ascribe also to Him the
higher directive attributes of our nature, the conscience
and the religious feeling, the reference of our
actions to the rule of duty and to the will of God.
It would not suit the plan of the present treatise
to enter into any detailed analysis of the connexion[202]
of these various portions of our moral constitution.
But we may observe that the existence and universality
of the conception of duty and right cannot be
doubted, however men may differ as to its original
or derivative nature. All men are perpetually led
to form judgments concerning actions, and emotions
which lead to action, as right or wrong; as what
they ought or ought not to do or feel. There is a faculty
which approves and disapproves, acquits or
condemns the workings of our other faculties. Now,
what shall we say of such a judiciary principle, thus
introduced among our motives to action? Shall we
conceive that while the other springs of action are
balanced against each other by our Creator, this, the
most pervading and universal regulator, was no part
of the original scheme? That—while the love of
animal pleasures, of power, of fame, the regard for
friends, the pleasure of bestowing pleasure, were infused
into man as influences by which his course of
life was to be carried on, and his capacities and
powers developed and exercised;—this reverence
for a moral law, this acknowledgment of the obligation
of duty,—a feeling which is every where found,
and which may become a powerful, a predominating
motive of action,—was given for no purpose, and
belongs not to the design? Such an opinion would
be much as if we should acknowledge the skill and
contrivance manifested in the other parts of a ship,
but should refuse to recognize the rudder as exhibiting
any evidence of a purpose. Without the reverence
which the opinion of right inspires, and the
scourge of general disapprobation inflicted on that
which is accounted wicked, society could scarcely
go on; and certainly the feelings and thoughts and
characters of men could not be what they are.
Those impulses of nature which involve no acknowledgment
of responsibility, and the play and struggle
of interfering wishes, might preserve the species
in some shape of existence, as we see in the case of
brutes. But a person must be strangely constituted,[203]
who, living amid the respect for law, the admiration
for what is good, the order and virtues and graces
of civilized nations, (all which have their origin in
some degree in the feeling of responsibility) can
maintain that all these are casual and extraneous
circumstances, no way contemplated in the formation
of man; and that a condition in which there
should be obligation in law, no merit in self-restraint,
no beauty in virtue, is equally suited to the powers
and the nature of man, and was equally contemplated
when those powers were given him.
If this supposition be too extravagant to be admitted,
as it appears to be, it remains then that man,
intended, as we have already seen from his structure
and properties, to be a discoursing, social being,
acting under the influence of affections, desires, and
purposes, was also intended to act under the influence
of a sense of duty; and that the acknowledgment
of the obligation of a moral law is as much
part of his nature, as hunger or thirst, maternal love
or the desire of power; that, therefore, in conceiving
man as the work of a Creator, we must imagine
his powers and character given him with an intention
on the Creator’s part that this sense of duty
should occupy its place in his constitution as an active
and thinking being: and that this directive and
judiciary principle is a part of the work of the same
Author who made the elements to minister to the
material functions, and the arrangements of the
world to occupy the individual and social affections
of his living creatures.
This principle of conscience, it may further be
observed, does not stand upon the same level as the
other impulses of our constitution by which we are
prompted or restrained. By its very nature and essence,
it possesses a supremacy over all others.
“Your obligation to obey this law is its being the
law of your nature. That your conscience approves
of and attests such a course of action is itself alone
an obligation. Conscience does not only offer itself[204]
to show us the way we should walk in, but it likewise
carries its own authority with it, that it is our
natural guide: the guide assigned us by the author
of our nature.”[26] That we ought to do an action, is
of itself a sufficient and ultimate answer to the questions,
why we should do it?—how we are obliged to
do it? The conviction of duty implies the soundest
reason, the strongest obligation, of which our nature
is susceptible.
We appear then to be using only language which
is well capable of being justified, when we speak of
this irresistible esteem for what is right, this conviction
of a rule of action extending beyond the gratification
of our irreflective impulses, as an impress
stamped upon the human mind by the Deity himself;
a trace of His nature; an indication of His will; an
announcement of His purpose; a promise of His
favour: and though this faculty may need to be confirmed
and unfolded, instructed and assisted by other
aids, it still seems to contain in itself a sufficient intimation
that the highest objects of man’s existence
are to be attained, by means of a direct and intimate
reference of his thoughts and actions to the
Divine Author of his being.
Such then is the Deity to which the researches of
Natural Theology point; and so far is the train of
reflections in which we have engaged, from being
merely speculative and barren. With the material
world we cannot stop. If a superior Intelligence
have ordered and adjusted the succession of seasons
and the structure of the plants of the field, we must
allow far more than this at first sight would seem to
imply. We must admit still greater powers, still
higher wisdom for the creation of the beasts of the
forest with their faculties; and higher wisdom still
and more transcendent attributes, for the creation of
man. And when we reach this point, we find that it
is not knowledge only, not power only, not foresight[205]
and beneficence alone, which we must attribute to
the Maker of the World; but that we must consider
him as the Author, in us, of a reverence for moral
purity and rectitude; and, if the author of such emotions
in us, how can we conceive of Him otherwise,
than that these qualities are parts of his nature; and
that he is not only wise and great, and good, incomparably
beyond our highest conceptions, but also
conformed 
in his purposes to the rule which he thus
impresses upon us, that is, Holy in the highest degree
which we can imagine to ourselves as possible.
</div></body></text></TEI>