<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="10">
CHAPTER X.

The Laws of Heat with respect to Air.

We have seen in the preceding chapter how many
and how important are the offices discharged by the
aqueous part of the atmosphere. The aqueous part
is, however, a very small part only; it may vary,
perhaps, from less 
than 1-100th to nearly as much
as 1-20th in weight, of the whole aerial ocean. We
have to offer some considerations with regard to the
remainder of the mass.
1. In the first place we may observe that the aerial
atmosphere is necessary as a vehicle for the aqueous
vapour. Salutary as is the operation of this last element
to the whole organized creation, it is a substance
which would not have answered its purposes
if it had been administered pure. It requires to be
diluted and associated with dry air, to make it serviceable.
A little consideration will show this.
We can suppose the earth with no atmosphere except
the vapour which arises from its watery parts:
and if we suppose also the equatorial parts of the
globe to be hot, and the polar parts cold, we may
easily see what would be the consequence. The
waters at the equator, and near the equator, would
produce steam of greater elasticity, rarity, and temperature,[82]
than that which occupies the regions further
polewards; and such steam, as it came in contact
with the colder vapour of a higher latitude,
would be precipitated into the form of water. Hence
there would be a perpetual current of steam from
the equatorial parts towards each pole, which would
be condensed, would fall to the surface, and flow
back to the equator in the form of fluid. We should
have a circulation which might be regarded as a
species of regulated distillation.[11] On a globe so
constituted, the sky of the equatorial zone would be
perpetually cloudless; but in all other latitudes we
should have an uninterrupted shroud of clouds, fogs,
rains, and, near the poles, a continual fall of snow.
This would be balanced by a constant flow of the
currents of the ocean from each pole towards the
equator. We should have an excessive circulation
of moisture, but no sunshine, and probably only minute
changes in the intensity and appearances of
one eternal drizzle or shower.
It is plain that this state of things would but ill answer
the ends of vegetable and animal life: so that
even if the lungs of animals and the leaves of plants
were so constructed as to breathe steam instead of
air, an atmosphere of unmixed steam would deprive
those creatures of most of the other external conditions
of their well being.
The real state of things which we enjoy, the steam
being mixed in our breath and in our sky in a moderate
quantity, gives rise to results very different from
those which have been described. The machinery by
which these results are produced is not a little curious.
It is in fact the machinery of the weather, and therefore
the reader will not be surprised to find it both
complex and apparently uncertain in its working.
At the same time some of the general principles
which govern it seem now to be pretty well made
out, and they offer no small evidence of beneficent
arrangement.
[83]
Besides our atmosphere of aqueous vapour, we
have another and far larger atmosphere of common
air; a permanently elastic fluid, that is, one which is
not condensed into a liquid form by pressure or cold,
such as it is exposed to in the order of natural events.
The pressure of the dry air is about twenty-nine and
a half inches of mercury; that of the watery vapour,
perhaps, half an inch. Now if we had the earth
quite dry, and covered with an atmosphere of dry
air, we can trace in a great measure what would be
the results, supposing still the equatorial zone to be
hot, and the temperature of the surface to decrease
perpetually as we advance into higher latitudes.
The air at the equator would be rarefied by the heat,
and would be perpetually displaced below by the
denser portions which belonged to cooler latitudes.
We should have a current of air from the equator to
the poles in the higher regions of the atmosphere,
and at the surface a returning current setting towards
the equator to fill up the void so created.
Such aerial currents, combined with the rotatory
motion of the earth, would produce oblique winds;
and we have in fact instances of winds so produced,
in the trade winds, which between the tropics blow
constantly from the quarters between east and north,
and are, we know, balanced by opposite currents in
higher regions. The effect of a heated surface of
land would be the same as that of the heated zone of
the equator, and would attract to it a sea breeze
during the day time, a phenomenon, as we also
know, of perpetual occurrence.
Now a mass of dry air of such a character as this,
is by far the dominant part of our atmosphere; and
hence carries with it in its motions the thinner and
smaller eddies of aqueous vapour. The latter fluid
may be considered as permeating and moving in the
interstices of the former, as a spring of water flows
through a sand rock.[12] The lower current of air is,[84]
as has been said, directed towards the equator, and
hence it resists the motion of the steam, the tendency
of which is in the opposite direction; and prevents
or much retards that continual flow of hot vapour
into colder regions, by which a constant precipitation
would take place in the latter situations.
If, in this state of things, the flow of the current
of air, which blows from any colder place into a
warmer region, be retarded or stopped, the aqueous
vapours will now be able to make their way to the
colder point, where they will be precipitated in clouds
or showers.
Thus, in the lower part of the atmosphere, there
are tendencies to a current of air in one direction,
and a current of vapour in the opposite; and these
tendencies exist in the average weather of places
situated at a moderate distance from the equator.
The air tends from the colder to the warmer parts,
the vapour from the warmer to the colder.
The various distribution of land and sea, and many
other causes make these currents far from simple.
But in general the air current predominates, and
keeps the skies clear and the moisture dissolved.
Occasional and irregular occurrences disturb this
predominance; the moisture is then precipitated, the
skies are clouded, and the clouds may descend in copious
rains.
These alternations of fair weather and showers,
appear to be much more favourable to vegetable and
animal life than any uniform course of weather could
have been. To produce this variety, we have two
antagonist forces, by the struggle of which such
changes occur. Steam and air, two transparent and
elastic fluids, expansible by heat, are in many respects
and properties very like each other. Yet, the
same heat similarly applied to the globe, produces
at the surface currents of these fluids, tending in opposite
directions. And these currents mix and balance,
conspire and interfere, so that our trees and
fields have alternately water and sunshine; our fruits[85]
and grain are successively developed and matured.
Why should such laws of heat and elastic fluids so
obtain, and be so combined? Is it not in order that
they may be fit for such offices? There is here an
arrangement, which no chance could have produced.
The details of this apparatus may be beyond our
power of tracing; its springs may be out of our sight.
Such circumstances do not make it the less a curious
and beautiful contrivance: they need not prevent our
recognizing the skill and benevolence which we can
discover.
2. But we have not yet done with the machinery
of the weather. In ascending from the earth’s surface
through the atmosphere, we find a remarkable
difference in the heat and in the pressure of the air.
It becomes much colder, and much lighter; men’s
feelings tell them this; and the thermometer and barometer
confirm these indications. And here again
we find something to remark.
In both the simple atmospheres of which we have
spoken, the one of air and the one of steam, the property
which we have mentioned must exist. In each
of them, both the temperature and the tension would
diminish in ascending. But they would diminish at
very different rates. The temperature, for instance,
would decrease much more rapidly for the same
height in dry air than in steam. If we begin with a
temperature of 80 degrees at the surface, on ascending
five thousand feet the steam is still 76½ degrees,
the air is only 64½ degrees; at ten thousand feet,
the steam is 73 degrees, the air 48½ degrees; at
fifteen thousand feet, steam is at 70 degrees, air has
fallen below the freezing point to 31½ degrees.
Hence these two atmospheres cannot exist together
without modifying one another: one must heat or cool
the other, so that the coincident parts may be of the
same temperature. This accordingly does take
place, and this effect influences very greatly the constitution
of the atmosphere. For the most part, the
steam is compelled to accommodate itself to the temperature[86]
of the air, the latter being of much the
greater bulk. But if the upper parts of the aqueous
vapour be cooled down to the temperature of the air,
they will not by any means exert on the lower parts
of the same vapour so great a pressure as the gaseous
form of these could bear. Hence, there will be a deficiency
of moisture in the lower part of the atmosphere,
and if water exist there, it will rise by evaporation,
the surface feeling an insufficient tension;
and there will thus be a fresh supply of vapour upwards.
As, however, the upper regions already contain
as much as their temperature will support in
the state of gas, a precipitation will now take place,
and the fluid thus formed will descend till it arrives
in a lower region, where the tension and temperature
are again adapted to its evaporation.
Thus, we can have no equilibrium in such an atmosphere,
but a perpetual circulation of vapour between
its upper and lower parts. The currents of
air which move about in different directions, at different
altitudes, will be differently charged with
moisture, and as they touch and mingle, lines of
cloud are formed, which grow and join, and are
spread out in floors, or rolled together in piles. These,
again, by an additional accession of humidity, are
formed into drops, and descend in showers into the
lower regions, and if not evaporated in their fall,
reach the surface of the earth.
The varying occurrences thus produced, tend to
multiply and extend their own variety. The ascending
streams of vapour carry with them that latent
heat belonging to their gaseous state, which, when
they are condensed, they give out as sensible heat.
They thus raise the temperature of the upper regions
of air, and occasion changes in the pressure and
motion of its currents. The clouds, again, by shading
the surface of the earth from the sun, diminish
the evaporation by which their own substance is
supplied, and the heating effects by which currents
are caused. Even the mere mechanical effects of[87]
the currents of fluid on the distribution of its own
pressure, and the dynamical conditions of its motion,
are in a high degree abstruse in their principles and
complex in their results. It need not be wondered,
therefore, if the study of this subject is very difficult
and entangled, and our knowledge, after all, very
imperfect.
In the middle of all this apparent confusion, however,
we can see much that we can understand.
And, among other things, we may notice some of
the consequences of the difference of the laws of
temperature followed by steam and by air in going
upwards. One important result is that the atmosphere
is much drier, near the surface, than it would
have been if the laws of density and temperature
had been the same for both gases. If this had been
so, the air would always have been saturated with
vapour. It would have contained as much as the
existing temperature could support, and the slightest
cooling of any object would have covered it with a
watery film like dew. As it is, the air contains
much less than its full quantity of vapour: we may
often cool an object ten, twenty, or thirty degrees
without obtaining a deposition of water upon it, or
reaching the dew-point, as it is called. To have had
such a dripping state of the atmosphere as the former
arrangement would have produced, would have
been inconvenient, and so far as we can judge, unsuited
to vegetables as well as animals. No evaporation
from the surface of either could have taken
place under such conditions.
The sizes and forms of clouds appear to depend
on the same circumstance, of the air not being saturated
with moisture. And it is seemingly much
better that clouds should be comparatively small and
well defined, as they are, than that they should fill
vast depths of the atmosphere with a thin mist, which
would have been the consequence of the imaginary
condition of things just mentioned.
Here then we have another remarkable exhibition[88]
of two laws, in two nearly similar gaseous fluids,
producing effects alike in kind, but different in degree,
and by the play of their difference giving rise
to a new set of results, peculiar in their nature and
beneficial in their tendency. The form of the laws
of air and of steam with regard to heat might, so far
as we can see, have been more similar, or more dissimilar,
than it now is: the rate of each law might
have had a different amount from its present one, so
as quite to alter the relation of the two. By the laws
having such forms and such rates as they have, effects
are produced, some of which we can distinctly
perceive to be beneficial. Perhaps most persons will
feel a strong persuasion, that if we understood the
operation of these laws more distinctly, we should
see still more clearly the beneficial tendency of these
effects, and should probably discover others, at present
concealed in the apparent perplexity of the subject.
3. From what has been said, we may see, in a
general way, both the causes and the effects of winds.
They arise from any disturbance by temperature,
motion, pressure, &c. of the equilibrium of the atmosphere,
and are the efforts of nature to restore the
balance. Their office in the economy of nature is to
carry heat and moisture from one tract to another,
and they are the great agents in the distribution of
temperature and the changes of weather. Other
purposes might easily be ascribed to them in the
business of the vegetable and animal kingdoms, and
in the arts of human life, of which we shall not here
treat. That character in which we now consider
them, that of the machinery of atmospheric changes,
and thus, immediately or remotely, the instruments
of atmospheric influences, cannot well be refused
them by any person.
4. There is still one reflexion which ought not to
be omitted. All the changes of the weather, even
the most violent tempests and torrents of rain, may
be considered as oscillations about the mean or[89]
average condition belonging to each place. All
these oscillations are limited and transient; the storm
spends its fury, the inundation passes off, the sky
clears, the calmer course of nature succeeds. In
the forces which produce this derangement, there is
a provision for making it short and moderate. The
oscillation stops of itself, like the rolling of a ship,
when no longer impelled by the wind. Now, why
should this be so? Why should the oscillations, produced
by the conflict of so many laws, seemingly
quite unconnected with each other, be of this converging
and subsiding character? Would it be so
under all arrangements? Is it a matter of mechanical
necessity that disturbance must end in the restoration
of the medium condition? By no means.
There may be an utter subversion of the equilibrium.
The ship may roll too far, and may capsize. The
oscillations may go on, becoming larger and larger,
till all trace of the original condition is lost; till new
forces of inequality and disturbance are brought into
play; and disorder and irregularity may succeed,
without apparent limit or check in its own nature,
like the spread of a conflagration in a city. This is
a possibility in any combination of mechanical
forces; why does it not happen in the one now before
us? By what good fortune are the powers of
heat, of water, of steam, of air, the effects of the
earth’s annual and diurnal motions, and probably
other causes, so adjusted, that through all their
struggles the elemental world goes on, upon the
whole, so quietly and steadily? Why is the whole
fabric of the weather never utterly deranged, its
balance lost irrecoverably? Why is there not an
eternal conflict, such as the poets imagine to take
place in their chaos?</div></body></text></TEI>