<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="65">

CHAPTER IV.
Attempts to form Ideas of separate Vital Forces, and first of Assimilation and Secretion.


Sect. I.—Course of Biological Research.

1. IT
is to be observed that at present I do not
speak of the progress of our knowledge with
regard to the detail of the processes which take place
in the human body, but of the approach made to some
distinct Idea of the specially vital part of each process.
In the History of Physiology, it has been seen72 that
all the great discoveries made respecting the organs
and motions of the animal frame have been followed
by speculations and hypotheses connected with such
discoveries. The discovery of the circulation of the
blood led to theories of animal heat; the discovery of
the motion of the chyle led to theories of digestion;
the close examination of the process of reproduction in
plants and animals led to theories of generation. In
all these cases, the discovery brought to light some
portion of the process which was mechanical or chemical, but it also, in each instance, served to show that
the process was something more than mechanical or
chemical. The theory attempted to explain the process by the application of known causes; but there
always remained some part of it which must unavoidably be referred to an unknown cause. But though
unknown, such a cause was not a hopeless object of
study. As the vital functions became better and better
understood, it was seen more and more clearly at what
precise points of the process it was necessary to assume
a peculiar vital energy, and what sort of properties 204 this energy must be conceived to possess. It was perceived where, in what manner, in what degree, mechanical and chemical agencies were modified, over-ruled,
or counteracted, by agencies which must be hypermechanical and hyperchemical. And thus the discoveries made in anatomy by a laborious examination of
facts, pointed out the necessity of introducing new
ideas, in order that the facts might be intelligible.
Observation taught much; and among other things,
she taught that there was something which could not
be observed, but which must, if possible, be conceived. I shall notice a few instances of this.</div></body></text></TEI>