<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="7">

CHAPTER III.
NO INNATE PRACTICAL PRINCIPLES

1. No moral Principles so clear and so generally received as the forementioned
speculative Maxims.


If those speculative Maxims, whereof we discoursed in the foregoing chapter,
have not an actual universal assent from all mankind, as we there proved, it is
much more visible concerning PRACTICAL Principles, that they come short of an
universal reception: and I think it will be hard to instance any one moral rule
which can pretend to so general and ready an assent as, “What is, is”; or to be
so manifest a truth as this, that “It is impossible for the same thing to be
and not to be.” Whereby it is evident that they are further removed from a
title to be innate; and the doubt of their being native impressions on the mind
is stronger against those moral principles than the other. Not that it brings
their truth at all in question. They are equally true, though not equally
evident. Those speculative maxims carry their own evidence with them: but moral
principles require reasoning and discourse, and some exercise of the mind, to
discover the certainty of their truth. They lie not open as natural characters
engraved on the mind; which, if any such were, they must needs be visible by
themselves, and by their own light be certain and known to everybody. But this
is no derogation to their truth and certainty; no more than it is to the truth
or certainty of the three angles of a triangle being equal to two right ones
because it is not so evident as “the whole is bigger than a part,” nor so apt
to be assented to at first hearing. It may suffice that these moral rules are
capable of demonstration: and therefore it is our own faults if we come not to
a certain knowledge of them. But the ignorance wherein many men are of them,
and the slowness of assent wherewith others receive them, are manifest proofs
that they are not innate, and such as offer themselves to their view without
searching.


2. Faith and Justice not owned as Principles by all Men.


Whether there be any such moral principles, wherein all men do agree, I appeal
to any who have been but moderately conversant in the history of mankind, and
looked abroad beyond the smoke of their own chimneys. Where is that practical
truth that is universally received, without doubt or question, as it must be if
innate? JUSTICE, and keeping of contracts, is that which most men seem to agree
in. This is a principle which is thought to extend itself to the dens of
thieves, and the confederacies of the greatest villains; and they who have gone
furthest towards the putting off of humanity itself, keep faith and rules of
justice one with another. I grant that outlaws themselves do this one amongst
another: but it is without receiving these as the innate laws of nature. They
practise them as rules of convenience within their own communities: but it is
impossible to conceive that he embraces justice as a practical principle who
acts fairly with his fellow-highwayman, and at the same time plunders or kills
the next honest man he meets with. Justice and truth are the common ties of
society; and therefore even outlaws and robbers, who break with all the world
besides, must keep faith and rules of equity amongst themselves; or else they
cannot hold together. But will any one say, that those that live by fraud or
rapine have innate principles of truth and justice which they allow and assent
to?


3. Objection: though Men deny them in their Practice, yet they admit them in
their Thoughts answered.


Perhaps it will be urged, that the tacit assent of their minds agrees to what
their practice contradicts. I answer, first, I have always thought the actions
of men the best interpreters of their thoughts. But, since it is certain that
most men’s practices, and some men’s open professions, have either questioned
or denied these principles, it is impossible to establish an universal consent,
(though we should look for it only amongst grown men,) without which it is
impossible to conclude them innate. Secondly, it is very strange and
unreasonable to suppose innate practical principles, that terminate only in
contemplation. Practical principles, derived from nature, are there for
operation, and must produce conformity of action, not barely speculative assent
to their truth, or else they are in vain distinguished from speculative maxims.
Nature, I confess, has put into man a desire of happiness and an aversion to
misery: these indeed are innate practical principles which (as practical
principles ought) DO continue constantly to operate and influence all our
actions without ceasing: these may be observed in all persons and all ages,
steady and universal; but these are INCLINATIONS OF THE APPETITE to good, not
impressions of truth on the understanding. I deny not that there are natural
tendencies imprinted on the minds of men; and that from the very first
instances of sense and perception, there are some things that are grateful and
others unwelcome to them; some things that they incline to and others that they
fly: but this makes nothing for innate characters on the mind, which are to be
the principles of knowledge regulating our practice. Such natural impressions
on the understanding are so far from being confirmed hereby, that this is an
argument against them; since, if there were certain characters imprinted by
nature on the understanding, as the principles of knowledge, we could not but
perceive them constantly operate in us and influence our knowledge, as we do
those others on the will and appetite; which never cease to be the constant
springs and motives of all our actions, to which we perpetually feel them
strongly impelling us.


4. Moral Rules need a Proof, ergo not innate.


Another reason that makes me doubt of any innate practical principles is, that
I think there cannot any one moral Rule be propos’d whereof a Man may not
justly demand a Reason: which would be perfectly ridiculous and absurd if
they were innate; or so much as self-evident, which every innate principle must
needs be, and not need any proof to ascertain its truth, nor want any reason to
gain it approbation. He would be thought void of common sense who asked on the
one side, or on the other side went to give a reason WHY “it is impossible for
the same thing to be and not to be.” It carries its own light and evidence with
it, and needs no other proof: he that understands the terms assents to it for
its own sake or else nothing will ever be able to prevail with him to do it.
But should that most unshaken rule of morality and foundation of all social
virtue, “That one should do as he would be done unto,” be proposed to one who
never heard of it before, but yet is of capacity to understand its meaning;
might he not without any absurdity ask a reason why? And were not he that
proposed it bound to make out the truth and reasonableness of it to him? Which
plainly shows it not to be innate; for if it were it could neither want nor
receive any proof; but must needs (at least as soon as heard and understood) be
received and assented to as an unquestionable truth, which a man can by no
means doubt of. So that the truth of all these moral rules plainly depends upon
some other antecedent to them, and from which they must be deduced; which could
not be if either they were innate or so much as self-evident.


5. Instance in keeping Compacts


That men should keep their compacts is certainly a great and undeniable rule in
morality. But yet, if a Christian, who has the view of happiness and misery in
another life, be asked why a man must keep his word, he will give this as a
reason:—Because God, who has the power of eternal life and death,
requires it of us. But if a Hobbist be asked why? he will answer:—Because
the public requires it, and the Leviathan will punish you if you do not. And if
one of the old philosophers had been asked, he would have
answered:—Because it was dishonest, below the dignity of a man, and
opposite to virtue, the highest perfection of human nature, to do otherwise.


6. Virtue generally approved not because innate, but because profitable.


Hence naturally flows the great variety of opinions concerning moral rules
which are to be found among men, according to the different sorts of happiness
they have a prospect of, or propose to themselves; which could not be if
practical principles were innate, and imprinted in our minds immediately by the
hand of God. I grant the existence of God is so many ways manifest, and the
obedience we owe him so congruous to the light of reason, that a great part of
mankind give testimony to the law of nature: but yet I think it must be allowed
that several moral rules may receive from mankind a very general approbation,
without either knowing or admitting the true ground of morality; which can only
be the will and law of a God, who sees men in the dark, has in his hand rewards
and punishments, and power enough to call to account the proudest offender.
For, God having, by an inseparable connexion, joined virtue and public
happiness together, and made the practice thereof necessary to the preservation
of society, and visibly beneficial to all with whom the virtuous man has to do;
it is no wonder that every one should not only allow, but recommend and magnify
those rules to others, from whose observance of them he is sure to reap
advantage to himself. He may, out of interest as well as conviction, cry up
that for sacred, which, if once trampled on and profaned, he himself cannot be
safe nor secure. This, though it takes nothing from the moral and eternal
obligation which these rules evidently have, yet it shows that the outward
acknowledgment men pay to them in their words proves not that they are innate
principles: nay, it proves not so much as that men assent to them inwardly in
their own minds, as the inviolable rules of their own practice; since we find
that self-interest, and the conveniences of this life, make many men own an
outward profession and approbation of them, whose actions sufficiently prove
that they very little consider the Lawgiver that prescribed these rules; nor
the hell that he has ordained for the punishment of those that transgress them.


7. Men’s actions convince us, that the Rule of Virtue is not their internal
Principle.


For, if we will not in civility allow too much sincerity to the professions of
most men, but think their actions to be the interpreters of their thoughts, we
shall find that they have no such internal veneration for these rules, nor so
full a persuasion of their certainty and obligation. The great principle of
morality, ‘To do as one would be done to,’ is more commended than practised.
But the breach of this rule cannot be a greater vice, than to teach others,
that it is no moral rule, nor obligatory, would be thought madness, and
contrary to that interest men sacrifice to, when they break it themselves.
Perhaps CONSCIENCE will be urged as checking us for such breaches, and so the
internal obligation and establishment of the rule be preserved.


8. Conscience no Proof of any innate Moral Rule.


To which I answer, that I doubt not but, without being written on their hearts,
many men may, by the same way that they come to the knowledge of other things,
come to assent to several moral rules, and be convinced of their obligation.
Others also may come to be of the same mind, from their education, company, and
customs of their country; which persuasion, however got, will serve to set
conscience on work; which is nothing else but our own opinion or judgment of
the moral rectitude or gravity of our own actions; and if conscience be a proof
of innate principles, contraries may be innate principles; since some men with
the same bent of conscience prosecute what others avoid.


9. Instances of Enormities practised without Remorse.


But I cannot see how any men should ever transgress those moral rules, with
confidence and serenity, were they innate, and stamped upon their minds. View
but an army at the sacking of a town, and see what observation or sense of
moral principles, or what touch of conscience for all the outrages they do.
Robberies, murders, rapes, are the sports of men set at liberty from punishment
and censure. Have there not been whole nations, and those of the most civilized
people, amongst whom the exposing their children, and leaving them in the
fields to perish by want or wild beasts has been the practice; as little
condemned or scrupled as the begetting them? Do they not still, in some
countries, put them into the same graves with their mothers, if they die in
childbirth; or despatch them, if a pretended astrologer declares them to have
unhappy stars? And are there not places where, at a certain age, they kill or
expose their parents, without any remorse at all? In a part of Asia, the sick,
when their case comes to be thought desperate, are carried out and laid on the
earth before they are dead; and left there, exposed to wind and weather, to
perish without assistance or pity. It is familiar among the Mingrelians, a
people professing Christianity, to bury their children alive without scruple.
There are places where they eat their own children. The Caribbees were wont to
geld their children, on purpose to fat and eat them. And Garcilasso de la Vega
tells us of a people in Peru which were wont to fat and eat the children they
got on their female captives, whom they kept as concubines for that purpose,
and when they were past breeding, the mothers themselves were killed too and
eaten. The virtues whereby the Tououpinambos believed they merited paradise,
were revenge, and eating abundance of their enemies. They have not so much as a
name for God, and have no religion, no worship. The saints who are canonized
amongst the Turks, lead lives which one cannot with modesty relate. A
remarkable passage to this purpose, out of the voyage of Baumgarten, which is a
book not every day to be met with, I shall set down at large, in the language
it is published in.


Ibi (sc. prope Belbes in Aegypto) vidimus sanctum unum Saracenicum inter
arenarum cumulos, ita ut ex utero matris prodiit nudum sedentem. Mos est, ut
didicimus, Mahometistis, ut eos, qui amentes et sine ratione sunt, pro sanctis
colant et venerentur. Insuper et eos, qui cum diu vitam egerint
inquinatissimam, voluntariam demum poenitentiam et paupertatem, sanctitate
venerandos deputant. Ejusmodi vero genus hominum libertatem quandam effrenem
habent, domos quos volunt intrandi, edendi, bibendi, et quod majus est,
concumbendi; ex quo concubitu, si proles secuta fuerit, sancta similiter
habetur. His ergo hominibus dum vivunt, magnos exhibent honores; mortuis vero
vel templa vel monumenta extruunt amplissima, eosque contingere ac sepelire
maximae fortunae ducunt loco. Audivimus haec dicta et dicenda per interpretem a
Mucrelo nostro. Insuper sanctum ilium, quern eo loco vidimus, publicitus
apprime commendari, eum esse hominem sanctum, divinum ac integritate
praecipuum; eo quod, nec faminarum unquam esset, nec puerorum, sed tantummodo
asellarum concubitor atque mularum. (Peregr. Baumgarten, 1. ii. c. i. p. 73.)


Where then are those innate principles of justice, piety, gratitude, equity,
chastity? Or where is that universal consent that assures us there are such
inbred rules? Murders in duels, when fashion has made them honourable, are
committed without remorse of conscience: nay, in many places innocence in this
case is the greatest ignominy. And if we look abroad to take a view of men as
they are, we shall find that they have remorse, in one place, for doing or
omitting that which others, in another place, think they merit by.


10. Men have contrary practical Principles.


He that will carefully peruse the history of mankind, and look abroad into the
several tribes of men, and with indifferency survey their actions, will be able
to satisfy himself, that there is scarce that principle of morality to be
named, or, rule of virtue to be thought on, (those only excepted that are
absolutely necessary to hold society together, which commonly too are neglected
betwixt distinct societies,) which is not, somewhere or other, slighted and
condemned by the general fashion of whole societies of men, governed by
practical opinions and rules of living quite opposite to others.


11. Whole Nations reject several Moral Rules.


Here perhaps it will be objected, that it is no argument that the rule is not
known, because it is broken. I grant the objection good where men, though they
transgress, yet disown not the law; where fear of shame, censure, or
punishment, carries the mark of some awe it has upon them. But it is impossible
to conceive that a whole nation of men should all publicly reject and renounce
what every one of them certainly and infallibly knew to be a law; for so they
must who have it naturally imprinted on their minds. It is possible men may
sometimes own rules of morality which in their private thoughts they do not
believe to be true, only to keep themselves in reputation and esteem amongst
those who are persuaded of their obligation. But it is not to be imagined that
a whole society of men should publicly and professedly disown and cast off a
rule which they could not in their own minds but be infallibly certain was a
law; nor be ignorant that all men they should have to do with knew it to be
such: and therefore must every one of them apprehend from others all the
contempt and abhorrence due to one who professes himself void of humanity: and
one who, confounding the known and natural measures of right and wrong, cannot
but be looked on as the professed enemy of their peace and happiness. Whatever
practical principle is innate, cannot but be known to every one to be just and
good. It is therefore little less than a contradiction to suppose, that whole
nations of men should, both in their professions and practice, unanimously and
universally give the lie to what, by the most invincible evidence, every one of
them knew to be true, right, and good. This is enough to satisfy us that no
practical rule which is anywhere universally, and with public approbation or
allowance, transgressed, can be supposed innate.—But I have something
further to add in answer to this objection.


12. The generally allowed breach of a rule proof that it is not innate.


The breaking of a rule, say you, is no argument that it is unknown. I grant it:
but the GENERALLY ALLOWED breach of it anywhere, I say, is a proof that it is
not innate. For example: let us take any of these rules, which, being the most
obvious deductions of human reason, and conformable to the natural inclination
of the greatest part of men, fewest people have had the impudence to deny or
inconsideration to doubt of. If any can be thought to be naturally imprinted,
none, I think, can have a fairer pretence to be innate than this: “Parents,
preserve and cherish your children.” When, therefore, you say that this is an
innate rule, what do you mean? Either that it is an innate principle which upon
all occasions excites and directs the actions of all men; or else, that it is a
truth which all men have imprinted on their minds, and which therefore they
know and assent to. But in neither of these senses is it innate. FIRST, that it
is not a principle which influences all men’s actions, is what I have proved by
the examples before cited: nor need we seek so far as the Mingrelia or Peru to
find instances of such as neglect, abuse, nay, and destroy their children; or
look on it only as the more than brutality of some savage and barbarous
nations, when we remember that it was a familiar and uncondemned practice
amongst the Greeks and Romans to expose, without pity or remorse, their
innocent infants. SECONDLY, that it is an innate truth, known to all men, is
also false. For, “Parents preserve your children,” is so far from an innate
truth, that it is no truth at all: it being a command, and not a proposition,
and so not capable of truth or falsehood. To make it capable of being assented
to as true, it must be reduced to some such proposition as this: “It is the
duty of parents to preserve their children.” But what duty is, cannot be
understood without a law; nor a law be known or supposed without a lawmaker, or
without reward and punishment; so that it is impossible that this, or any
other, practical principle should be innate, i.e. be imprinted on the mind as a
duty, without supposing the ideas of God, of law, of obligation, of punishment,
of a life after this, innate: for that punishment follows not in this life the
breach of this rule, and consequently that it has not the force of a law in
countries where the generally allowed practice runs counter to it, is in itself
evident. But these ideas (which must be all of them innate, if anything as a
duty be so) are so far from being innate, that it is not every studious or
thinking man, much less every one that is born, in whom they are to be found
clear and distinct; and that one of them, which of all others seems most likely
to be innate, is not so, (I mean the idea of God,) I think, in the next
chapter, will appear very evident to any considering man.


13. If men can be ignorant of what is innate, certainty is not described by
innate principles.


From what has been said, I think we may safely conclude that whatever practical
rule is in any place generally and with allowance broken, cannot be supposed
innate; it being impossible that men should, without shame or fear, confidently
and serenely, break a rule which they could not but evidently know that God had
set up, and would certainly punish the breach of, (which they must, if it were
innate,) to a degree to make it a very ill bargain to the transgressor. Without
such a knowledge as this, a man can never be certain that anything is his duty.
Ignorance or doubt of the law, hopes to escape the knowledge or power of the
law-maker, or the like, may make men give way to a present appetite; but let
any one see the fault, and the rod by it, and with the transgression, a fire
ready to punish it; a pleasure tempting, and the hand of the Almighty visibly
held up and prepared to take vengeance, (for this must be the case where any
duty is imprinted on the mind,) and then tell me whether it be possible for
people with such a prospect, such a certain knowledge as this, wantonly, and
without scruple, to offend against a law which they carry about them in
indelible characters, and that stares them in the face whilst they are breaking
it? Whether men, at the same time that they feel in themselves the imprinted
edicts of an Omnipotent Law-maker, can, with assurance and gaiety, slight and
trample underfoot his most sacred injunctions? And lastly, whether it be
possible that whilst a man thus openly bids defiance to this innate law and
supreme Lawgiver, all the bystanders, yea, even the governors and rulers of the
people, full of the same sense both of the law and Law-maker, should silently
connive, without testifying their dislike or laying the least blame on it?
Principles of actions indeed there are lodged in men’s appetites; but these are
so far from being innate moral principles, that if they were left to their full
swing they would carry men to the overturning of all morality. Moral laws are
set as a curb and restraint to these exorbitant desires, which they cannot be
but by rewards and punishments that will overbalance the satisfaction any one
shall propose to himself in the breach of the law. If, therefore, anything be
imprinted on the minds of all men as a law, all men must have a certain and
unavoidable knowledge that certain and unavoidable punishment will attend the
breach of it. For if men can be ignorant or doubtful of what is innate, innate
principles are insisted on, and urged to no purpose; truth and certainty (the
things pretended) are not at all secured by them; but men are in the same
uncertain floating estate with as without them. An evident indubitable
knowledge of unavoidable punishment, great enough to make the transgression
very uneligible, must accompany an innate law; unless with an innate law they
can suppose an innate Gospel too. I would not here be mistaken, as if, because
I deny an innate law I thought there were none but positive laws. There is a
great deal of difference between an innate law, and a law of nature between
something imprinted on our minds in their very original, and something that we,
being ignorant of, may attain to the knowledge of, by the use and due
application of our natural faculties. And I think they equally forsake the
truth who, running into contrary extremes, either affirm an innate law, or deny
that there is a law knowable by the light of nature, i.e. without the help of
positive revelation.


14. Those who maintain innate practical Principles tell us not what they are.


The difference there is amongst men in their practical principles is so evident
that I think I need say no more to evince, that it will be impossible to find
any innate moral rules by this mark of general assent; and it is enough to make
one suspect that the supposition of such innate principles is but an opinion
taken up at pleasure; since those who talk so confidently of them are so
sparing to tell us WHICH THEY ARE. This might with justice be expected from
those men who lay stress upon this opinion; and it gives occasion to distrust
either their knowledge or charity, who, declaring that God has imprinted on the
minds of men the foundations of knowledge and the rules of living, are yet so
little favourable to the information of their neighbours, or the quiet of
mankind, as not to point out to them which they are, in the variety men are
distracted with. But, in truth, were there any such innate principles there
would be no need to teach them. Did men find such innate propositions stamped
on their minds, they would easily be able to distinguish them from other truths
that they afterwards learned and deduced from them; and there would be nothing
more easy than to know what, and how many, they were. There could be no more
doubt about their number than there is about the number of our fingers; and it
is like then every system would be ready to give them us by tale. But since
nobody, that I know, has ventured yet to give a catalogue of them, they cannot
blame those who doubt of these innate principles; since even they who require
men to believe that there are such innate propositions, do not tell us what
they are. It is easy to foresee, that if different men of different sects
should go about to give us a list of those innate practical principles, they
would set down only such as suited their distinct hypotheses, and were fit to
support the doctrines of their particular schools or churches; a plain evidence
that there are no such innate truths. Nay, a great part of men are so far from
finding any such innate moral principles in themselves, that, by denying
freedom to mankind, and thereby making men no other than bare machines, they
take away not only innate, but all moral rules whatsoever, and leave not a
possibility to believe any such, to those who cannot conceive how anything can
be capable of a law that is not a free agent. And upon that ground they must
necessarily reject all principles of virtue, who cannot put MORALITY and
MECHANISM together, which are not very easy to be reconciled or made
consistent.


15. Lord Herbert’s innate Principles examined.


When I had written this, being informed that my Lord Herbert had, in his book
De Veritate, assigned these innate principles, I presently consulted him,
hoping to find in a man of so great parts, something that might satisfy me in
this point, and put an end to my inquiry. In his chapter De Instinctu Naturali,
I met with these six marks of his Notitice Communes:—1. Prioritas. 2.
Independentia. 3. Universalitas. 4. Certitudo. 5. Necessitas, i. e. as he
explains it, faciunt ad hominis conservationem. 6. Modus conformationis, i.e.
Assensus nulla interposita mora. And at the latter end of his little treatise
De Religione Laici, he says this of these innate principles: Adeo ut non
uniuscujusvis religionis confinio arctentur quae ubique vigent veritates. Sunt
enim in ipsa mente caelitus descriptae, nullisque traditionibus, sive scriptis,
sive non scriptis, obnoxiae, p.3 And Veritates nostrae catholicae, quae tanquam
indubia Dei emata in foro interiori descriptae.


Thus, having given the marks of the innate principles or common notions, and
asserted their being imprinted on the minds of men by the hand of God, he
proceeds to set them down, and they are these:—1. Esse aliquod supremum
numen. 2. Numen illud coli debere. 3. Virtutem cum pietate conjunctam optimum
esse rationem cultus divini. 4. Resipiscendum esse a peccatis. 5. Dari praemium
vel paenam post hanc vitam transactam. Though I allow these to be clear truths,
and such as, if rightly explained, a rational creature can hardly avoid giving
his assent to, yet I think he is far from proving them innate impressions in
foro interiori descriptae. For I must take leave to observe:—


16. These five either not all, or more than all, if there are any.


First, that these five propositions are either not all, or more than all, those
common notions written on our minds by the finger of God; if it were reasonable
to believe any at all to be so written. Since there are other propositions
which, even by his own rules, have as just a pretence to such an original, and
may be as well admitted for innate principles, as at least some of these five
he enumerates, viz. ‘Do as thou wouldst be done unto.’ And perhaps some
hundreds of others, when well considered.


17. The supposed marks wanting.


Secondly, that all his marks are not to be found in each of his five
propositions, viz. his first, second, and third marks agree perfectly to
neither of them; and the first, second, third, fourth, and sixth marks agree
but ill to his third, fourth, and fifth propositions. For, besides that we are
assured from history of many men, nay whole nations, who doubt or disbelieve
some or all of them, I cannot see how the third, viz. “That virtue joined with
piety is the best worship of God,” can be an innate principle, when the name or
sound virtue, is so hard to be understood; liable to so much uncertainty in its
signification; and the thing it stands for so much contended about and
difficult to be known. And therefore this cannot be but a very uncertain rule
of human practice, and serve but very little to the conduct of our lives, and
is therefore very unfit to be assigned as an innate practical principle.


18. Of little use if they were innate.


For let us consider this proposition as to its meaning, (for it is the sense,
and not sound, that is and must be the principle or common notion,) viz.
“Virtue is the best worship of God,” i.e. is most acceptable to him; which, if
virtue be taken, as most commonly it is, for those actions which, according to
the different opinions of several countries, are accounted laudable, will be a
proposition so far from being certain, that it will not be true. If virtue be
taken for actions conformable to God’s will, or to the rule prescribed by
God—which is the true and only measure of virtue when virtue is used to
signify what is in its own nature right and good—then this proposition,
“That virtue is the best worship of God,” will be most true and certain, but of
very little use in human life: since it will amount to no more but this, viz.
“That God is pleased with the doing of what he commands”;—which a man may
certainly know to be true, without knowing what it is that God doth command;
and so be as far from any rule or principle of his actions as he was before.
And I think very few will take a proposition which amounts to no more than
this, viz. “That God is pleased with the doing of what he himself commands,”
for an innate moral principle written on the minds of all men, (however true
and certain it may be,) since it teaches so little. Whosoever does so will have
reason to think hundreds of propositions innate principles; since there are
many which have as good a title as this to be received for such, which nobody
yet ever put into that rank of innate principles.


19. Scarce possible that God should engrave principles in words of uncertain
meaning.


Nor is the fourth proposition (viz. “Men must repent of their sins”) much more
instructive, till what those actions are that are meant by sins be set down.
For the word peccata, or sins, being put, as it usually is, to signify in
general ill actions that will draw punishment upon the doers, what great
principle of morality can that be to tell us we should be sorry, and cease to
do that which will bring mischief upon us; without knowing what those
particular actions are that will do so? Indeed this is a very true proposition,
and fit to be inculcated on and received by those who are supposed to have been
taught WHAT actions in all kinds ARE sins: but neither this nor the former can
be imagined to be innate principles; nor to be of any use if they were innate,
unless the particular measures and bounds of all virtues and vices were
engraven in men’s minds, and were innate principles also, which I think is very
much to be doubted. And therefore, I imagine, it will scarcely seem possible
that God should engrave principles in men’s minds, in words of uncertain
signification, such as VIRTUES and SINS, which amongst different men stand for
different things: nay, it cannot be supposed to be in words at all, which,
being in most of these principles very general names, cannot be understood but
by knowing the particulars comprehended under them. And in the practical
instances, the measures must be taken from the knowledge of the actions
themselves, and the rules of them,—abstracted from words, and antecedent
to the knowledge of names; which rules a man must know, what language soever he
chance to learn, whether English or Japan, or if he should learn no language at
all, or never should understand the use of words, as happens in the case of
dumb and deaf men. When it shall be made out that men ignorant of words, or
untaught by the laws and customs of their country, know that it is part of the
worship of God not to kill another man; not to know more women than one; not to
procure abortion; not to expose their children; not to take from another what
is his, though we want it ourselves, but on the contrary, relieve and supply
his wants; and whenever we have done the contrary we ought to repent, be sorry,
and resolve to do so no more;—when I say, all men shall be proved
actually to know and allow all these and a thousand other such rules, all of
which come under these two general words made use of above, viz. virtutes et
peccata virtues and sins, there will be more reason for admitting these and the
like, for common notions and practical principles. Yet, after all, universal
consent (were there any in moral principles) to truths, the knowledge whereof
may be attained otherwise, would scarce prove them to be innate; which is all I
contend for.


20. Objection, Innate Principles may be corrupted, answered.


Nor will it be of much moment here to offer that very ready but not very
material answer, viz. that the innate principles of morality may, by education,
and custom, and the general opinion of those amongst whom we converse, be
darkened, and at last quite worn out of the minds of men. Which assertion of
theirs, if true, quite takes away the argument of universal consent, by which
this opinion of innate principles is endeavoured to be proved; unless those men
will think it reasonable that their private persuasions, or that of their
party, should pass for universal consent;—a thing not unfrequently done,
when men, presuming themselves to be the only masters of right reason, cast by
the votes and opinions of the rest of mankind as not worthy the reckoning. And
then their argument stands thus:—“The principles which all mankind allow
for true, are innate; those that men of right reason admit, are the principles
allowed by all mankind; we, and those of our mind, are men of reason;
therefore, we agreeing, our principles are innate”;—which is a very
pretty way of arguing, and a short cut to infallibility. For otherwise it will
be very hard to understand how there be some principles which all men do
acknowledge and agree in; and yet there are none of those principles which are
not, by depraved custom and ill education, blotted out of the minds of many
men: which is to say, that all men admit, but yet many men do deny and dissent
from them. And indeed the supposition of SUCH first principles will serve us to
very little purpose; and we shall be as much at a loss with as without them, if
they may, by any human power—such as the will of our teachers, or
opinions of our companions—be altered or lost in us: and notwithstanding
all this boast of first principles and innate light, we shall be as much in the
dark and uncertainty as if there were no such thing at all: it being all one to
have no rule, and one that will warp any way; or amongst various and contrary
rules, not to know which is the right. But concerning innate principles, I
desire these men to say, whether they can or cannot, by education and custom,
be blurred and blotted out; if they cannot, we must find them in all mankind
alike, and they must be clear in everybody; and if they may suffer variation
from adventitious notions, we must then find them clearest and most perspicuous
nearest the fountain, in children and illiterate people, who have received
least impression from foreign opinions. Let them take which side they please,
they will certainly find it inconsistent with visible matter of fact and daily
observation.


21. Contrary Principles in the World.


I easily grant that there are great numbers of opinions which, by men of
different countries, educations, and tempers, are received and embraced as
first and unquestionable principles; many whereof, both for their absurdity as
well as oppositions to one another, it is impossible should be true. But yet
all those propositions, how remote soever from reason are so sacred somewhere
or other, that men even of good understanding in other matters, will sooner
part with their lives, and whatever is dearest to them, than suffer themselves
to doubt, or others to question, the truth of them.


22. How men commonly come by their Principles.


This, however strange it may seem, is that which every day’s experience
confirms; and will not, perhaps, appear so wonderful, if we consider the ways
and steps by which it is brought about; and how really it may come to pass,
that doctrines that have been derived from no better original than the
superstition of a nurse, or the authority of an old woman, may, by length of
time and consent of neighbours, grow up to the dignity of PRINCIPLES in
religion or morality. For such, who are careful (as they call it) to principle
children well, (and few there be who have not a set of those principles for
them, which they believe in,) instil into the unwary, and as yet unprejudiced,
understanding, (for white paper receives any characters,) those doctrines they
would have them retain and profess. These being taught them as soon as they
have any apprehension; and still as they grow up confirmed to them, either by
the open profession or tacit consent of all they have to do with; or at least
by those of whose wisdom, knowledge, and piety they have an opinion, who never
suffer those propositions to be otherwise mentioned but as the basis and
foundation on which they build their religion and manners, come, by these
means, to have the reputation of unquestionable, self-evident, and innate
truths.


23. Principles supposed innate because we do not remember when we began to hold
them.


To which we may add, that when men so instructed are grown up, and reflect on
their own minds, they cannot find anything more ancient there than those
opinions, which were taught them before their memory began to keep a register
of their actions, or date the time when any new thing appeared to them; and
therefore make no scruple to conclude, that those propositions of whose
knowledge they can find in themselves no original, were certainly the impress
of God and nature upon their minds, and not taught them by any one else. These
they entertain and submit to, as many do to their parents with veneration; not
because it is natural: nor do children do it where they are not so taught; but
because, having been always so educated, and having no remembrance of the
beginning of this respect, they think it is natural.


24. How such principles come to be held.


This will appear very likely, and almost unavoidable to come to pass, if we
consider the nature of mankind and the constitution of human affairs; wherein
most men cannot live without employing their time in the daily labours of their
callings; nor be at quiet in their minds without SOME foundation or principle
to rest their thoughts on. There is scarcely any one so floating and
superficial in his understanding, who hath not some reverenced propositions,
which are to him the principles on which he bottoms his reasonings, and by
which he judgeth of truth and falsehood, right and wrong; which some, wanting
skill and leisure, and others the inclination, and some being taught that they
ought not to examine, there are few to be found who are not exposed by their
ignorance, laziness, education, or precipitancy, to TAKE THEM UPON TRUST.


25. Further explained.


This is evidently the case of all children and young folk; and custom, a
greater power than nature, seldom failing to make them worship for divine what
she hath inured them to bow their minds and submit their understandings to, it
is no wonder that grown men, either perplexed in the necessary affairs of life,
or hot in the pursuit of pleasures, should not seriously sit down to examine
their own tenets; especially when one of their principles is, that principles
ought not to be questioned. And had men leisure, parts, and will, who is there
almost that dare shake the foundations of all his past thoughts and actions,
and endure to bring upon himself the shame of having been a long time wholly in
mistake and error? Who is there hardy enough to contend with the reproach which
is everywhere prepared for those who dare venture to dissent from the received
opinions of their country or party? And where is the man to be found that can
patiently prepare himself to bear the name of whimsical, sceptical, or atheist;
which he is sure to meet with, who does in the least scruple any of the common
opinions? And he will be much more afraid to question those principles, when he
shall think them, as most men do, the standards set up by God in his mind, to
be the rule and touchstone of all other opinions. And what can hinder him from
thinking them sacred, when he finds them the earliest of all his own thoughts,
and the most reverenced by others?


26. A worship of idols.


It is easy to imagine how, by these means, it comes to pass that men worship
the idols that have been set up in their minds; grow fond of the notions they
have been long acquainted with there; and stamp the characters of divinity upon
absurdities and errors; become zealous votaries to bulls and monkeys, and
contend too, fight, and die in defence of their opinions. Dum solos credit
habendos esse deos, quos ipse colit. For, since the reasoning faculties of
the soul, which are almost constantly, though not always warily nor wisely
employed, would not know how to move, for want of a foundation and footing, in
most men, who through laziness or avocation do not, or for want of time, or
true helps, or for other causes, cannot penetrate into the principles of
knowledge, and trace truth to its fountain and original, it is natural for
them, and almost unavoidable, to take up with some borrowed principles; which
being reputed and presumed to be the evident proofs of other things, are
thought not to need any other proof themselves. Whoever shall receive any of
these into his mind, and entertain them there with the reverence usually paid
to principles, never venturing to examine them, but accustoming himself to
believe them, because they are to be believed, may take up, from his education
and the fashions of his country, any absurdity for innate principles; and by
long poring on the same objects, so dim his sight as to take monsters lodged in
his own brain for the images of the Deity, and the workmanship of his hands.


27. Principles must be examined.


By this progress, how many there are who arrive at principles which they
believe innate may be easily observed, in the variety of opposite principles
held and contended for by all sorts and degrees of men. And he that shall deny
this to be the method wherein most men proceed to the assurance they have of
the truth and evidence of their principles, will perhaps find it a hard matter
any other way to account for the contrary tenets, which are firmly believed,
confidently asserted, and which great numbers are ready at any time to seal
with their blood. And, indeed, if it be the privilege of innate principles to
be received upon their own authority, without examination, I know not what may
not be believed, or how any one’s principles can be questioned. If they may and
ought to be examined and tried, I desire to know how first and innate
principles can be tried; or at least it is reasonable to demand the MARKS and
CHARACTERS whereby the genuine innate principles may be distinguished from
others: that so, amidst the great variety of pretenders, I may be kept from
mistakes in so material a point as this. When this is done, I shall be ready to
embrace such welcome and useful propositions; and till then I may with modesty
doubt; since I fear universal consent, which is the only one produced, will
scarcely prove a sufficient mark to direct my choice, and assure me of any
innate principles.


From what has been said, I think it past doubt, that there are no practical
principles wherein all men agree; and therefore none innate.


</div></body></text></TEI>