<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 165, folios 165-169</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 165, folios 165-169.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1840">undated (estimated from box 165 date range)</date>
          <note type="place">[no place]</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 165, folios 165-169</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_165_folios_165-169.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Thursday Night</p>
      <p>Dearest William. I have had much satisfaction in my consultation with Dr L-- as to my case. Altho' he takes a somewhat different view from what he did; &amp; I think anticipates that a period of some duration will be requisite. He is now trying an experiment upon me, which we hope will answer.-- Something or other</p>
      <p>further is most clearly requisite; for I am far from improving, in several respects.-- Dr L-- says that I want watching for a time; &amp; is very glad that I am to be now within reach.--</p>
      <p>I am terribly tormented by smoke here;-- in fact it is quite filthy &amp; odious. I have no peace with it; having only the choice of suffocation or starvation.</p>
      <p>I have just returned from seeing the Merchant of Venice at Drury</p>
      <p>Lane. And I cannot say how gratified I have been.-- Macready's Shylock is so excellent, that really you must see it. I am highly pleased with all I see &amp; hear of his undertaking in that Theatre. He seems likely to raise the tone &amp; style of our stage most laudably;-- &amp; Shakespeare's plays have a chance of being worthily performed.--</p>
      <p>Pray pity me, as I am at this moment; covered with showers of blacks, &amp; unable to see distinctly even across my little sitting-room,</p>
      <p>altho' I am shivering with the door open.--</p>
      <p>Friday. 4 o'clock. My Dear! Do rejoice with the happy excited joyful little Avis.--</p>
      <p>I am distracted with delight on 2 subjects. 1stly: the Artificial Ice, which I saw this morning. I am astonished and delighted beyond all measure. It seems decidedly preferable even to real Ice; &amp; these are the testimonies of first-rate Skaters on the subject.--</p>
      <p>It is proposed to lay down the floors of drawing-</p>
      <p>-rooms, &amp; other private dwelling apartments, in this material; a carpet being thrown over &amp; taken up at pleasure. It want no repair at all scarcely.</p>
      <p>It is expected to be a great resource in Country-Houses in the evenings .-- Mr Kirk is desirous to speak to you on business respecting their plans, with Lord Portman.</p>
      <p>And I have ventured to promise for you that you will go to see the specimen on Thursday or Friday next.</p>
      <p>But you must fix an hour for it, &amp; let me know by return of post please.</p>
      <p>Any hour either morning or night will suit them, that you choose to name.</p>
      <p>It is in the New Road, [W? or nr? (abbreviation for near?)] Dorset Sqre, at Jenkins's Nursery Grounds. It is a subject of real importance; &amp; when you see &amp; hear all that I have, you will be as wild as I am about it;-- &amp; as anxious, I am sure, to promote the</p>
      <p>success of so delightful &amp; beneficial a discovery.-- The 2 Mr Kirks &amp; Mr Bradwell, all had much conversation with me; &amp; are agreeable &amp; highly gentlemanlike persons; seeming likewise to possess much taste &amp; love of the Arts.</p>
      <p>Then subject No 2, is my Singing. I have just had my first lesson; from a Signor Faia, a highly reputable &amp; suitable person in all respects.-- He seems not a little pleased with me; &amp; to anticipate</p>
      <p>that I may even attain any degree of perfection; having a wonderful facility.</p>
      <p>He is to come to Ockham twice, for 6 days each time.-- Mr Knoff &amp; I could not hit it off together. But I think I have found exactly what I want.--</p>
      <p>I am very glad that I have discovered an excellent restauranteur's; a very nice respectable Shop in Oxford St, where I can get either hot or cold breakfasts, dinners, or suppers, at a moment's notice.</p>
      <p>It is the greatest possible convenience to me sometimes.</p>
      <p>I am just starting for Esher. So Good Bye.</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
