<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="41">CHAPTER XXXIX.
While Bethlem Gabor became every day more confirmed
in his antipathy against me, I reposed in him an unsuspecting
confidence—a confidence more extensive than
I had, since the singular and fatal acquisition I had made,
reposed in any other man. Frequently for a considerable
time together he resided under my roof; frequently we
went forth together in those excursions which either my
projects or his views rendered it necessary for us to make.
In his character of a nobleman of great consideration in
his native country, he was now rising like a phœnix from
its ashes. His castles were repairing; his property was
restored; the list of his retainers daily became more numerous;
he revived and carefully recruited the martial
band, which, in the first exacerbations of his despair, he
had dismissed from his service. My purse and all that I
had were his; he never made a demand upon me that I
did not instantly supply; I reaped a particular pleasure
from the largeness and frequency of his requisitions; there
was nothing for which I was more anxious, than to bind
him to me in indissoluble ties of gratitude and affection.
Little, alas! did I understand the compound of tenderness
and ferocity, of decisiveness and inscrutability, with
which I was now concerned. My friend, such I esteemed
him, had been absent some time; I expected his return
to my residence at Buda; and anxious to pay him every
mark of attention and respect, I set out to meet him. It
was scarcely safe, during the existing hostilities between
the Austrians and the Turks, to travel any where without
a guard; I had the precaution in the present instance to
take with me an attendance of twenty men.
[403]
It was after having partaken of a slight and early dinner
that I set out on my excursion. The season was remarkably
fine, and the air genial and balsamic. I scarcely ever
commenced any tour with more agreeable sensations. The
harvest was already ripe; and, as I passed along, I saw
reapers from time to time entering upon the first essay of
their interesting occupation. I felt that I had at length
surmounted one of those difficulties, with which I had been
so strongly assailed, and to which I had refused to yield.
If I were not free from apprehensions from the arbitrary
nature of the government under which I lived, I believed
however that I had nothing further to dread from the
misconstruction and animosity of the nation I preserved.
My anxiety as to whether I should be able to substantiate
the benefit I had sought to confer, was at an end; and I
had little doubt that, with the plenteous crops which were
on the point of being gathered, my popularity would return,
and the gratitude of my clients become more ardent
than ever. It was a delicious enjoyment that I now experienced;
the pleasures that the eye unavoidably takes in
from the spectacle of a luxuriant autumn, became blended
in my mind with the ideas of famine put to flight, my own
rectitude vindicated, and the benevolent purposes realised,
the prosecution of which had cost me so profound a heartache.
We at length passed the lines of the soldiers planted for
the defence of the soil against the depredations of the
enemy. I had calculated that I should meet my guest a
few leagues from Buda; I was deceived in my estimate.
The day however of his arrival was fixed; I could not be
mistaken in his route; I resolved not to turn back without
meeting him. The road I took led upon the borders of
that part of Hungary which owned the Austrian yoke;
the shades of night were fast gathering round us, and we
heard at a distance the alarm-guns and the drums of the
enemy. I was not however a novice in the appearances of
a country, the seat of military excursions and war; and, if
my mind were not wholly free from perturbation and
uncertainty, I at least resolved not to be turned aside from
my purpose. We travelled two hours longer; still no[404]
notice of the approach of Bethlem Gabor. At length a
question was started whether we were still in the right
road, and I thought it advisable to hold a sort of council
of war to deliberate respecting our further proceedings.
Having assembled my attendants for that purpose, I was
now first struck with the apprehensions and timidity which
they unanimously betrayed. They had been drawn out
rather for show, and to keep accidental stragglers in awe,
than with the expectation of actual service. I became sensible
that nothing was to be hoped from their resistance in
the event of an action; and the utmost I could aim at was
in the mean time to hold them together by the sentiment
of a common danger.
It was resolved to return; I began to be apprehensive
that Bethlem Gabor had been prevented by some unexpected
occurrence from observing his appointment. Scarcely had
we faced about, before we heard a body of cavalry approaching
us. I called to my party to halt. I soon discerned,
from symptoms not difficult to be remarked by a
careful observer, that the party at hand was composed of
Austro-Hungarians. We had every thing to fear from
them. I held myself bound under these circumstances first
to make experiment of the fleetness of our horses. I
however charged my people to keep together, and not to
suffer the enemy, by means of our inadvertence and folly,
to make an easy prize of us one after another. In a short
time I found that our pursuers sensibly gained ground upon
us. I was mounted upon an excellent beast, and could
easily have rode away from my troop, while they would
have been placed as a sort of intercepting object between
me and the enemy. But I had too much of a military
spirit not instantly to reject so inglorious an expedient. I
called a second time to my attendants to halt. I judged
that the party of our antagonists was less numerous than
ours. I was convinced that our common safety depended
upon our concerted resistance. Filled with the gallantry
that my situation inspired, I did not perceive, till it was too
late, that my present call to halt was attended to by few;
even those few rather hung back, divided between apprehension
and shame. I was the foremost, and, before I was[405]
aware, I found myself, through the means of the darkness,
enveloped by the enemy. From my appearance they
judged that I was the master, and the rest my attendants;
they contented themselves therefore with the prize they had
made, and did not give themselves the trouble to pursue
the fugitives. They eagerly enquired of me who I was;
and, comparing my answers with various circumstances
which rumour had brought to their ear, they easily concluded
that I was the rich stranger of Buda. The character
they had heard of me did not produce in these freebooters
any sentiments of forbearance, or demonstrations of respect;
the only point about which persons of their habits were
concerned, was how they should make the greatest advantage
of what the fortune of war had thrown in their
way.
While they were consulting, and various expedients were
started by one and another for this purpose, a second alarm
was given, and one of the party being despatched to reconnoitre,
presently returned with intelligence, that the persons
approaching were horsemen of the enemy, and that they
amounted, as he guessed, to forty in number. Upon this
information the party whose prisoner I was, agreed to return
with all expedition by the way they had come, and
commanded me upon pain of death to proceed in their
company. This menace had not the effect to deprive me of
courage or presence of mind; and I easily conceived that
the readiest way to deliver myself from my embarrassment
would be to join at the first opportunity the band of Turco-Hungarians,
whose approach had occasioned our sudden
retreat. The darkness of the night was favourable to my
purpose; and, taking advantage of a sudden winding in
the road, I slackened all at once the pace of my horse without
being observed by my companions, who, as the enemy
approached, had now their thoughts almost wholly intent
upon the safety of their retreat. They passed me; and I
no sooner perceived that to be the case, than, covered from
their observation by the intervening inclosure, I turned my
horse, and gradually, as my distance from my keepers increased,
urged him to a fuller speed. It was not long
before I came up with the band which had produced our[406]
alarm; and hailing them with the acclamation, “Long live
the mighty sultan!” was without difficulty admitted into
their troop. I instantly understood to my great joy that
this was the party of Bethlem Gabor that I had come out
to meet.
He received me with much cordiality, and seemed greatly
rejoiced that fortune had made him the instrument of my
rescue. He proposed however that, having met on the
road, I should now, instead of proceeding to Buda, return
with him to his northern castle, from which our distance
was scarcely greater than from the metropolis. The proposal
was such as I had not expected, nor could I well
comprehend the purpose with which it was made. But the
habitual demeanour of Bethlem Gabor neither accorded
with his minutely assigning a reason for what he did, nor
was calculated to encourage enquiry in another. I saw no
material objection, and therefore felt little scruple in yielding
to his desires. Our brief consultation on this point
passed at some little distance from the rest of the troop.
When the morning broke, the first thing that excited
my attention was the appearance of his followers. They
were full forty in number, well mounted, of a large and
athletic figure, with sun-burnt faces, immense whiskers and
a ferocious countenance. I thought I had never seen so
tremendous a band. To me they were every one of them
strangers; of all the persons that surrounded me, the only
one of whom I had the slightest knowledge was Bethlem
Gabor himself. I know not why it was, but I no sooner
beheld my situation than I was struck with alarm. I saw
myself completely in the power of a man who three months
before was ignorant even of my existence. I had not a
single attendant of my own, not an individual with me over
whom I had personal authority or command. I had no
reason to distrust my host; towards me his demeanour had
ever been frank, confidential, and manly; I had every
imaginable claim upon his generosity and his gratitude.
But our senses are often the masters of our mind, and reason
vainly opposes itself to the liveliness of their impressions.
Every time that I lifted my eyes, and saw myself
hemmed in by these barbarians, my heart seemed involuntarily[407]
to fail me. Bethlem Gabor too appeared to neglect
me; he had never shown himself so little obliging and attentive
as at this moment; and, aided by the rest of the
scene, I thought I had never beheld him so deformed or so
tremendous. I was more than half inclined to wish myself
again a prisoner with the Austrians.
When we arrived at the castle, we were all of us fatigued
and hungry; we had roamed during the whole night. A
repast was prepared; we sat down to partake of it. “Excuse
me,” said Bethlem Gabor, in a low voice as he passed
me, “that I this night offer you the fare of a soldier; to-morrow
you shall be accommodated in a different manner.”
The words were innocent; the proceeding natural; but
there was a mysterious gloom, at least as I thought, in the
tone in which he spoke, that electrified me. The hall in
which we supped was spacious and lofty; the naked walls
and rafters were imbrowned with age. Though it was
daybreak as we entered, the windows were still darkened,
and the apartment was illuminated only by the partial
glare of lamps depending from the roof. As I sat at table
with the troop of my host, I appeared to myself as if inclosed
in a cavern of banditti. Though excellent partisans,
skilful in execution, and perfect in their discipline, they were
unpolished in their manners and brutal in their conversation.
I had been inured from infancy to all the refinement
that the age in which I lived had any where to boast; and,
amidst the various evils I had suffered, that of being associated
with the vulgar and the base had never presented
itself. While they uttered, now a loathsome jest, and now
a sanguinary ejaculation, I became ashamed of my species,
and the pride of manhood perished within me. They however
paid little attention either to my feelings or my person;
and, accustomed as I had been, whether with friends or
enemies, to be regarded as of some importance, I found
myself unaccountably and suddenly dwindled into a cipher.
I felt it like a release from the state of a galley-slave, when
Bethlem Gabor proposed that we should break up our meeting
and retire to rest.

[408]</div></body></text></TEI>