<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="112">CHAPTER VIII.
Attempts at the Classification of
Minerals.

Sect. 1.—Proper object of
Classification.
THE fixity of the crystalline
and other physical properties of minerals is turned to account by
being made the means of classifying such objects. To use the language
of Aristotle,39 Classification is the
architectonic science, to which Crystallography and the
Doctrine of External Characters are subordinate and ministerial, as
the art of the bricklayer and carpenter are to that of the architect.
But classification itself is useful only as subservient to an ulterior
science, which shall furnish us with knowledge concerning things so
classified. To classify is to divide and to name; and the value of the
Divisions which we thus make, and of the names which we give them, is
this;—that they render exact knowledge and general propositions
possible. Now the knowledge which we principally seek concerning
minerals is a knowledge of their chemical composition; the general
propositions to which we hope to be led are such as assert relations
between their intimate constitution and their external attributes.
Thus our Mineralogical Classification must always have an eye turned
towards Chemistry. We cannot get rid of the fundamental conviction,
that the elementary composition of bodies, since it fixes their
essence, must determine their properties. Hence all mineralogical
arrangements, whether they profess it or not, must be, in effect,
chemical; they must have it for their object to bring into view a set
of relations, which, whatever else they may be, are at least chemical
relations. We may begin with the outside, but it is only in order to
reach the inner 340
structure. We may classify without reference to chemistry; but if we
do so, it is only that we may assert chemical propositions with
reference to our classification.
39 Eth. Nicom. i. 2.
But, as we have already attempted to show,
we not only may, but we must classify, by other than chemical
characters, in order to be able to make our classification the basis
of chemical knowledge. In order to assert chemical truths concerning
bodies, we must have the bodies known by some tests not chemical. The
chemist cannot assert that Arragonite does or does not contain
Strontia, except the mineralogist can tell him whether any given
specimen is or is not Arragonite. If chemistry be called upon
to supply the definitions as well as the doctrines
of mineralogy, the science can only consist of identical
propositions.
Yet chemistry has been much employed in mineralogical
classifications, and, it is generally believed, with advantage to the
science: How is this consistent with what has been said?
To this the answer is, that when this has been done with
advantage, the authority of external characters, as well as of
chemical constitution, has really been brought into play. We have two
sets of properties to compare, chemical and physical; to exhibit the
connexion of these is the object of scientific mineralogy. And though
this connexion would be most distinctly asserted, if we could keep the
two sets of properties distinct, yet it may be brought into view in a
great degree, by classifications in which both are referred to as
guides. Since the governing principle of the attempts at
classification is the conviction that the chemical constitution and
the physical properties have a definite relation to each other, we
appear entitled to use both kinds of evidence, in proportion as we can
best obtain each; and then the general consistency and convenience of
our system will be the security for its containing substantial
knowledge, though this be not presented in a rigorously logical or
systematic form.
Such mixed systems of classification, resting partly on
chemical and partly on physical characters, naturally appeared as the
earliest attempts in this way, before the two members of the subject
had been clearly separated in men’s minds; and these systems,
therefore, we must first give an account of.
Sect. 2.—Mixed Systems of Classification.
Early Systems.—The first attempts at classifying
minerals went upon the ground of those differences of general aspect
which had been 341
recognized in the formation of common language; as earths,
stones, metals. But such arrangements were manifestly
vague and confused; and when chemistry had advanced to power and
honor, her aid was naturally called in to introduce a better order.
“Hiarne and Bromell were, as far as I know,” says40 Cronstedt, “the
first who founded any mineral system upon chemical principles; to them
we owe the three known divisions of the most simple mineral bodies;
viz., the calcarei, vitrescentes, and apyri.” But
Cronstedt’s own Essay towards a System of Mineralogy, published
in Swedish in 1758, had perhaps more influence than any other, upon
succeeding systems. In this, the distinction of earths and stones, and
also of vitrescent and non-vitrescent earths (apyri), is
rejected. The earths are classed as calcareous,
siliceous, argillaceous, and the like. Again, calcareous
earth is pure (calc spar), or united with acid of vitriol
(gypsum), or united with the muriatic add (sal
ammoniac), and the like. It is easy to see that this is the
method, which, in its general principle, has been continued to our own
time. In such methods, it is supposed that we can recognize the
substance by its general appearance, and on this assumption, its place
in the system conveys to us chemical knowledge concerning it.
40 Mineralogy, Pref. p.
viii.
But as the other branches of Natural History, and especially
Botany, assumed a systematic form, many mineralogists became
dissatisfied with this casual and superficial mode of taking account
of external characters; they became convinced, that in Mineralogy as
in other sciences, classification must have its system and its rules.
The views which Werner ascribes to his teacher, Pabst van Ohain,41 show the rise of those opinions which
led through Werner to Mohs: “He was of opinion that a natural mineral
system must be constructed by chemical determinations, and external
characters at the same time (methodus mixta); but that along
with this, mineralogists ought also to construct and employ what he
called an artificial system, which might serve us as a guide
(loco indicis) how to introduce newly-discovered fossils into
the system, and how to find easily and quickly those already known and
introduced.” Such an artificial system, containing not the grounds of
classification, but marks for recognition, was afterwards attempted by
Mohs, and termed by him the Characteristic of his system.
41 Frisch. Werner’s Leben, p.
15.
Werner’s System.—But, in the mean time, Werner’s
classification had an extensive reign, and this was still a mixed
system. Werner himself, indeed, never published a system of
mineralogy. “We might 342 almost imagine,” Cuvier says,42 “that when he had produced his
nomenclature of external characters, he was affrighted with his own
creation; and that the reason of his writing so little after his first
essay, was to avoid the shackles which he had imposed upon others.”
His system was, indeed, made known both in and out of Germany, by his
pupils; but in consequence of Werner’s unwillingness to give it on his
own authority, it assumed, in its published forms, the appearance of
an extorted secret imperfectly told. A Notice of the Mineralogical
Cabinet of Mine-Director Pabst von Ohain, was, in 1792, published
by Karsten and Hoffman, under Werner’s direction; and conveyed by
example, his views of mineralogical arrangement; and43 in 1816 his Doctrine of
Classification was surreptitiously copied from his manuscript, and
published in a German Journal, termed The Hesperus. But it was
only in 1817, after his death, that there appeared Werner’s Last
Mineral System, edited from his papers by Breithaupt and Köhler:
and by this time, as we shall soon see, other systems were coming
forwards on the stage.
42 Cuv. El. ii. 314.
43 Frisch. p. 52.
A very slight notice of Werner’s arrangement will suffice to show
that it was, as we have termed it, a Mixed System. He makes four great
Classes of fossils, Earthy, Saline, Combustible,
Metallic: the earthy fossils are in eight Genera—Diamond,
Zircon, Silica, Alumina, Talc, Lime, Baryta, Hallites. It is clear
that these genera are in the main chemical, for chemistry alone can
definitely distinguish the different Earths which characterize them.
Yet the Wernerian arrangement supposed the distinctions to be
practically made by reference to those external characters which the
teacher himself could employ with such surpassing skill. And though it
cannot be doubted, that the chemical views which prevailed around him
had a latent influence on his classification in some cases, he
resolutely refused to bend his system to the authority of chemistry.
Thus,44 when he was blamed for having, in
opposition to the chemists, placed diamond among the earthy fossils,
he persisted in declaring that, mineralogically considered, it was a
stone, and could not be treated as anything else.
44 Frisch. p. 62.
This was an indication to that tendency, which, under his
successor, led to a complete separation of the two grounds of
classification. But before we proceed to this, we must notice what was
doing at this period in other parts of Europe.
Haüy’s System.—Though Werner, on his own principles,
ought to 343 have
been the first person to see the immense value of the most marked of
external characters, crystalline form, he did not, in fact, attach
much importance to it. Perhaps he was in some measure fascinated by a
fondness for those characters which he had himself systematized, and
the study of which did not direct him to look for geometrical
relations. However this may be, the glory of giving to Crystallography
its just importance in Mineralogy is due to France: and the Treatise
of Haüy, published in 1801, is the basis of the best succeeding works
of mineralogy. In this work, the arrangement is professedly chemical;
and the classification thus established is employed as the means of
enunciating crystallographic and other properties. “The principal
object of this Treatise,” says the author,45 “is the
exposition and development of a method founded on certain principles,
which may serve as a frame-work for all the knowledge which Mineralogy
can supply, aided by the different sciences which can join hands with
her and march on the same line.” It is worthy of notice, as characteristic of this
period of Mixed Systems, that the classification of Haüy, though
founded on principles so different from the Wernerian ones, deviates
little from it in the general character of the divisions. Thus, the
first Order of the first Class of Haüy is Acidiferous Earthy
Substances; the first genus is Lime; the species are,
Carbonate of Lime, Phosphate of Lime, Fluate of
Lime, Sulphate of Lime, and so on.
45 Disc. Prél. p. xvii.
Other Systems.—Such mixed methods were introduced also
into this country, and have prevailed, we may say, up to the present
time. The Mineralogy of William Phillips, which was published
in 1824, and which was an extraordinary treasure of crystallographic
facts, was arranged by such a mixed system; that is, by a system
professedly chemical; but, inasmuch as a rigid chemical system is
impossible, and the assumption of such a one leads into glaring
absurdities, the system was, in this and other attempts of the same
kind, corrected by the most arbitrary and lax application of other
considerations.
It is a curious example of the difference of national intellectual
character, that the manifest inconsistencies of the prevalent systems,
which led in Germany, as we shall see, to bold and sweeping attempts
at reform, produced in England a sort of contemptuous despair with
regard to systems in general;—a belief that no system could be
consistent or useful;—and a persuasion that the only valuable
knowledge is the accumulation of particular facts. This is not the
place to 344
explain how erroneous and unphilosophical such an opinion is. But we
may notice that while such a temper prevails among us, our place in
this science can never be found in advance of that position which we
are now considering as exemplified in the period of Werner and Haüy.
So long as we entertain such views respecting the objects of
Mineralogy, we can have no share in the fortunes of the succeeding
period of its history, to which I now proceed.
</div></body></text></TEI>