<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="19">

PHYSICAL OPTICS.

CHAPTER X.
Prelude to the Epoch of Young and
Fresnel.
BY Physical Optics we
mean, as has already been stated, the theories which explain optical
phenomena on mechanical principles. No such explanation could be given
till true mechanical principles had been obtained; and, accordingly,
we must date the commencement of the essays towards physical optics
from Descartes, the founder of the modern mechanical philosophy. His
hypothesis concerning light is, that it consists of small particles
emitted by the luminous body. He compares these particles to balls,
and endeavors to explain, by means of this comparison, the laws of
reflection and refraction.62 In order to account for the production
of colors by refraction, he ascribes to these balls an alternating
rotatory motion.63 This form of the emission
theory, was, like most of the physical speculations of its author,
hasty and gratuitous; but was extensively accepted, like the rest of
the Cartesian doctrines, in consequence of the love which men have for
sweeping and simple dogmas, and deductive reasonings from them. In a
short time, however, the rival optical theory of undulations
made its appearance. Hooke in his Micrographia (1664) propounds
it, upon occasion of his observations, already noticed, (chap. vii.,) on the colors of thin plates. He there
asserts64 light to consist in a “quick, short,
vibrating motion,” and that it is propagated in a homogeneous medium,
in such a way that “every pulse or vibration of the luminous body will
generate a sphere, which will continually increase and grow bigger,
just after the same manner (though indefinitely swifter) as the waves
or rings on the surface of water do swell into bigger and bigger
circles about a point in it.”65 He applies this
to the explanation of refraction, 86 by supposing that the rays in a denser
medium move more easily, and hence that the pulses become oblique; a
far less satisfactory and consistent hypothesis than that of Huyghens,
of which we shall next have to speak. But Hooke has the merit of
having also combined with his theory, though somewhat obscurely, the
Principle of Interferences, in the application which he makes
of it to the colors of thin plates. Thus66 he supposes the
light to be reflected at the first surface of such plates; and he
adds, “after two refractions and one reflection (from the second
surface) there is propagated a kind of fainter ray,” which comes
behind the other reflected pulse; “so that hereby (the surfaces ab and ef being so near
together that the eye cannot discriminate them from one), this
compound or duplicated pulse does produce on the retina the sensation
of a yellow.” The reason for the production of this particular color,
in the case of which he here speaks, depends on his views concerning
the kind of pulses appropriate to each color; and, for the same
reason, when the thickness is different, he finds that the result will
be a red or a green. This is a very remarkable anticipation of the
explanation ultimately given of these colors; and we may observe that
if Hooke could have measured the thickness of his thin plates, he
could hardly have avoided making considerable progress in the doctrine
of interferences.</div></body></text></TEI>