<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Humboldt Alexander</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1814</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="12">CHAPTER 1.13.
ABODE AT CARACAS.
MOUNTAINS IN THE VICINITY OF THE TOWN.
EXCURSION TO THE SUMMIT OF THE SILLA.
INDICATIONS OF MINES.
I remained two months at Caracas, where M. Bonpland and I lived in
a large house in the most elevated part of the town. From a gallery
we could survey at once the summit of the Silla, the serrated ridge
of the Galipano, and the charming valley of the Guayra, the rich
culture of which was pleasingly contrasted with the gloomy curtain
of the surrounding mountains. It was in the dry season, and to
improve the pasturage, the savannahs and the turf covering the
steepest rocks were set on fire. These vast conflagrations, viewed
from a distance, produce the most singular effects of light.
Wherever the savannahs, following the undulating slope of the
rocks, have filled up the furrows hollowed out by the waters, the
flame appears in a dark night like currents of lava suspended over
the valley. The vivid but steady light assumes a reddish tint, when
the wind, descending from the Silla, accumulates streams of vapour
in the low regions. At other times (and this effect is still more
curious) these luminous bands, enveloped in thick clouds, appear
only at intervals where it is clear; and as the clouds ascend,
their edges reflect a splendid light. These various phenomena, so
common in the tropics, acquire additional interest from the form of
the mountains, the direction of the slopes, and the height of the
savannahs covered with alpine grasses. During the day, the wind of
Petare, blowing from the east, drives the smoke towards the town,
and diminishes the transparency of the air.
If we had reason to be satisfied with the situation of our house,
we had still greater cause for satisfaction in the reception we met
with from all classes of the inhabitants. Though I have had the
advantage, which few Spaniards have shared with me, of having
successively visited Caracas, the Havannah, Santa Fe de Bogota,
Quito, Lima, and Mexico, and of having been connected in these six
capitals of Spanish America with men of all ranks, I will not
venture to decide on the various degrees of civilization, which
society has attained in the several colonies. It is easier to
indicate the different shades of national improvement, and the
point towards which intellectual development tends, than to compare
and class things which cannot all be considered under one point of
view. It appeared to me, that a strong tendency to the study of
science prevailed at Mexico and Santa Fe de Bogota; more taste for
literature, and whatever can charm an ardent and lively
imagination, at Quito and Lima; more accurate notions of the
political relations of countries, and more enlarged views on the
state of colonies and their mother-countries, at the Havannah and
Caracas. The numerous communications with commercial Europe, with
the Caribbean Sea (which we have described as a Mediterranean with
many outlets), have exercised a powerful influence on the progress
of society in the five provinces of Venezuela and in the island of
Cuba. In no other part of Spanish America has civilization assumed
a more European character. The great number of Indian cultivators
who inhabit Mexico and the interior of New Grenada, impart a
peculiar, I may almost say, an exotic aspect, on those vast
countries. Notwithstanding the increase of the black population, we
seem to be nearer to Cadiz and the United States, at Caracas and
the Havannah, than in any other part of the New World.
When, in the reign of Charles V, social distinctions and their
consequent rivalries were introduced from the mother-country to the
colonies, there arose in Cumana and in other commercial towns of
Terra Firma, exaggerated pretensions to nobility on the part of
some of the most illustrious families of Caracas, distinguished by
the designation of los Mantuanos. The progress of knowledge, and
the consequent change in manners, have, however, gradually and
pretty generally neutralized whatever is offensive in those
distinctions among the whites. In all the Spanish colonies there
exist two kinds of nobility. One is composed of creoles, whose
ancestors only from a very recent period filled great stations in
America. Their prerogatives are partly founded on the distinction
they enjoy in the mother-country; and they imagine they can retain
those distinctions beyond the sea, whatever may be the date of
their settlement in the colonies. The other class of nobility has
more of an American character. It is composed of the descendants of
the Conquistadores, that is to say, of the Spaniards who served in
the army at the time of the first conquest. Among the warriors who
fought with Cortez, Losada, and Pizarro, several belonged to the
most distinguished families of the Peninsula; others, sprung from
the inferior classes of the people, have shed lustre on their
names, by that chivalrous spirit which prevailed at the beginning
of the sixteenth century. In the records of those times of
religious and military enthusiasm, we find, among the followers of
the great captains, many simple, virtuous, and generous characters,
who reprobated the cruelties which then stained the glory of the
Spanish name, but who, being confounded in the mass, have not
escaped the general proscription. The name of Conquistadares
remains the more odious, as the greater number of them, after
having outraged peaceful nations, and lived in opulence, did not
end their career by suffering those misfortunes which appease the
indignation of mankind, and sometimes soothe the severity of the
historian.
But it is not only the progress of ideas, and the conflict between
two classes of different origin, which have induced the privileged
castes to abandon their pretensions, or at least cautiously to
conceal them. Aristocracy in the Spanish colonies has a
counterpoise of another kind, the action of which becomes every day
more powerful. A sentiment of equality, among the whites, has
penetrated every bosom. Wherever men of colour are either
considered as slaves or as having been enfranchised, that which
constitutes nobility is hereditary liberty—the proud boast of
having never reckoned among ancestors any but freemen. In the
colonies, the colour of the skin is the real badge of nobility. In
Mexico, as well as Peru, at Caracas as in the island of Cuba, a
bare-footed fellow with a white skin, is often heard to exclaim:
"Does that rich man think himself whiter than I am?" The population
which Europe pours into America being very considerable, it may
easily be supposed, that the axiom, 'every white man is noble'
(todo blanco es caballero), must singularly wound the pretensions
of many ancient and illustrious European families. But it may be
further observed, that the truth of this axiom has long since been
acknowledged in Spain, among a people justly celebrated for
probity, industry, and national spirit. Every Biscayan calls
himself noble; and there being a greater number of Biscayans in
America and the Philippine Islands, than in the Peninsula, the
whites of that race have contributed, in no small degree, to
propagate in the colonies the system of equality among all men
whose blood has not been mixed with that of the African race.
Moreover, the countries of which the inhabitants, even without a
representative government, or any institution of peerage, annex so
much importance to genealogy and the advantages of birth, are not
always those in which family aristocracy is most offensive. We do
not find among the natives of Spanish origin, that cold and
assuming air which the character of modern civilization seems to
have rendered less common in Spain than in the rest of Europe.
Conviviality, candour, and great simplicity of manner, unite the
different classes of society in the colonies, as well as in the
mother-country. It may even be said, that the expression of vanity
and self-love becomes less offensive, when it retains something of
simplicity and frankness.
I found in several families at Caracas a love of information, an
acquaintance with the masterpieces of French and Italian
literature, and a marked predilection for music, which is greatly
cultivated, and which (as always results from a taste for the fine
arts) brings the different classes of society nearer to each other.
The mathematical sciences, drawing, and painting, cannot here boast
of any of those establishments with which royal munificence and the
patriotic zeal of the inhabitants have enriched Mexico. In the
midst of the marvels of nature, so rich in interesting productions,
it is strange that we found no person on this coast devoted to the
study of plants and minerals. In a Franciscan convent I met, it is
true, with an old monk who drew up the almanac for all the
provinces of Venezuela, and who possessed some accurate knowledge
of astronomy. Our instruments interested him deeply, and one day
our house was filled with all the monks of San Francisco, begging
to see a dipping-needle. The curiosity excited by physical
phenomena is naturally great in countries undermined by volcanic
fires, and in a climate where nature is at once so majestic and so
mysteriously convulsed.
When we remember, that in the United States of North America,
newspapers are published in small towns not containing more than
three thousand inhabitants, it seems surprising that Caracas, with
a population of forty or fifty thousand souls, should have
possessed no printing office before 1806; for we cannot give the
name of a printing establishment to a few presses which served only
from year to year to promulgate an almanac of a few pages, or the
pastoral letter of a bishop. Though the number of those who feel
reading to be a necessity is not very considerable, even in the
Spanish colonies most advanced in civilization, yet it would be
unjust to reproach the colonists for a state of intellectual
lassitude which has been the result of a jealous policy. A
Frenchman, named Delpeche, has the merit of having established the
first printing office in Caracas. It appears somewhat extraordinary
that an establishment of this kind should have followed, and not
preceded, a political revolution.
In a country abounding in such magnificent scenery, and at a period
when, notwithstanding some symptoms of popular commotion, most of
the inhabitants seem only to direct attention to physical objects,
such as the fertility of the year, the long drought, or the
conflicting winds of Petare and Catia, I expected to find many
individuals well acquainted with the lofty surrounding mountains.
But I was disappointed; and we could not find in Caracas a single
person who had visited the summit of the Silla. Hunters do not
ascend so high on the ridges of mountains; and in these countries
journeys are not undertaken for such purposes as gathering alpine
plants, carrying a barometer to an elevated point, or examining the
nature of rocks. Accustomed to a uniform and domestic life, the
people dread fatigue and sudden changes of climate. They seem to
live not to enjoy life, but only to prolong it.
Our walks led us often in the direction of two coffee plantations,
the proprietors of which, Don Andres de Ibarra and M. Blandin, were
men of agreeable manners. These plantations were situated opposite
the Silla de Caracas. Surveying, by a telescope, the steep
declivity of the mountains, and the form of the two peaks by which
it is terminated, we could form an idea of the difficulties we
should have to encounter in reaching its summit. Angles of
elevation, taken with the sextant at our house, had led me to
believe that the summit was not so high above sea-level as the
great square of Quito. This estimate was far from corresponding
with the notions entertained by the inhabitants of the city.
Mountains which command great towns, have acquired, from that very
circumstance, an extraordinary celebrity in both continents. Long
before they have been accurately measured, a conventional height is
assigned to them; and to entertain the least doubt respecting that
height is to wound a national prejudice.
The captain-general, Senor de Guevara, directed the teniente of
Chacao to furnish us with guides to conduct us on our ascent of the
Silla. These guides were negroes, and they knew something of the
path leading over the ridge of the mountain, near the western peak
of the Silla. This path is frequented by smugglers, but neither the
guides, nor the most experienced of the militia, accustomed to
pursue the smugglers in these wild spots, had been on the eastern
peak, forming the most elevated summit of the Silla. During the
whole month of December, the mountain (of which the angles of
elevation made me acquainted with the effects of the terrestrial
refractions) had appeared only five times free of clouds. In this
season two serene days seldom succeed each other, and we were
therefore advised not to choose a clear day for our excursion, but
rather a time when, the clouds not being elevated, we might hope,
after having crossed the first layer of vapours uniformly spread,
to enter into a dry and transparent air. We passed the night of the
2nd of January in the Estancia de Gallegos, a plantation of
coffee-trees, near which the little river of Chacaito, flowing in a
luxuriantly shaded ravine, forms some fine cascades in descending
the mountains. The night was pretty clear; and though on the day
preceding a fatiguing journey it might have been well to have
enjoyed some repose, M. Bonpland and I passed the whole night in
watching three occultations of the satellites of Jupiter. I had
previously determined the instant of the observation, but we missed
them all, owing to some error of calculation in the Connaissance
des Temps. The apparent time had been mistaken for mean time.
I was much disappointed by this accident; and after having observed
at the foot of the mountain the intensity of the magnetic forces,
before sunrise, we set out at five in the morning, accompanied by
slaves carrying our instruments. Our party consisted of eighteen
persons, and we all walked one behind another, in a narrow path,
traced on a steep acclivity, covered with turf. We endeavoured
first to reach a hill, which towards the south-east seems to form a
promontory of the Silla. It is connected with the body of the
mountain by a narrow dyke, called by the shepherds the Gate, or
Puerta de la Silla. We reached this dyke about seven. The morning
was fine and cool, and the sky till then seemed to favour our
excursion. I saw that the thermometer kept a little below 14
degrees (11.2 degrees Reaum.). The barometer showed that we were
already six hundred and eighty-five toises above the level of the
sea, that is, nearly eighty toises higher than at the Venta, where
we enjoyed so magnificent a view of the coast. Our guides thought
that it would require six hours more to reach the summit of the
Silla.
We crossed a narrow dyke of rocks covered with turf; which led us
from the promontory of the Puerta to the ridge of the great
mountain. Here the eye looks down on two valleys, or rather narrow
defiles, filled with thick vegetation. On the right is perceived
the ravine which descends between the two peaks to the farm of
Munoz; on the left we see the defile of Chacaito, with its waters
flowing out near the farm of Gallegos. The roaring of the cascades
is heard, while the water is unseen, being concealed by thick
groves of erythrina, clusia, and the Indian fig-tree.* (* Ficus
nymphaeifolia, Erythrina mitis. Two fine species of mimosa are
found in the same valley; Inga fastuosa, and I. cinerea.) Nothing
can be more picturesque, in a climate where so many plants have
broad, large, shining, and coriaceous leaves, than the aspect of
trees when the spectator looks down from a great height above them,
and when they are illumined by the almost perpendicular rays of the
sun.
From the Puerta de la Silla the steepness of the ascent increases,
and we were obliged to incline our bodies considerably forwards as
we advanced. The slope is often from 30 to 32 degrees.* (* Since my
experiments on slopes, mentioned above in Chapter 1.2, I have
discovered in the Figure de la Terre of Bouguer, a passage, which
shows that this astronomer, whose opinions are of such weight,
considered also 36 degrees as the inclination of a slope quite
inaccessible, if the nature of the ground did not admit of forming
steps with the foot.) We felt the want of cramp-irons, or sticks
shod with iron. Short grass covered the rocks of gneiss, and it was
equally impossible to hold by the grass, or to form steps as we
might have done in softer ground. This ascent, which was attended
with more fatigue than danger, discouraged those who accompanied us
from the town, and who were unaccustomed to climb mountains. We
lost a great deal of time in waiting for them, and we did not
resolve to proceed alone till we saw them descending the mountain
instead of climbing up it. The weather was becoming cloudy; the
mist already issued in the form of smoke, and in slender and
perpendicular streaks, from a small humid wood which bordered the
region of alpine savannahs above us. It seemed as if a fire had
burst forth at once on several points of the forest. These streaks
of vapour gradually accumulated together, and rising above the
ground, were carried along by the morning breeze, and glided like a
light cloud over the rounded summit of the mountain.
M. Bonpland and I foresaw from these infallible signs, that we
should soon be covered by a thick fog; and lest our guides should
take advantage of this circumstance and leave us, we obliged those
who carried the most necessary instruments to precede us. We
continued climbing the slopes which lead towards the ravine of
Chacaito. The familiar loquacity of the Creole blacks formed a
striking contrast with the taciturn gravity of the Indians, who had
constantly accompanied us in the missions of Caripe. The negroes
amused themselves by laughing at the persons who had been in such
haste to abandon an expedition so long in preparation; above all,
they did not spare a young Capuchin monk, a professor of
mathematics, who never ceased to boast of the superior physical
strength and courage possessed by all classes of European Spaniards
over those born in Spanish America. He had provided himself with
long slips of white paper, which were to be cut, and flung on the
savannah, to indicate to those who might stray behind, the
direction they ought to follow. The professor had even promised the
friars of his order to fire off some rockets, to announce to the
whole town of Caracas that we had succeeded in an enterprise which
to him appeared of the utmost importance. He had forgotten that his
long and heavy garments would embarrass him in the ascent. Having
lost courage long before the creoles, he passed the rest of the day
in a neighbouring plantation, gazing at us through a glass directed
to the Silla, as we climbed the mountain. Unfortunately for us, he
had taken charge of the water and the provision so necessary in an
excursion to the mountains. The slaves, who were to rejoin us, were
so long detained by him, that they arrived very late, and we were
ten hours without either bread or water.
The eastern peak is the most elevated of the two which form the
summit of the mountain, and to this we directed our course with our
instruments. The hollow between these two peaks has suggested the
Spanish name of Silla (saddle), which is given to the whole
mountain. The narrow defile which we have already mentioned,
descends from this hollow toward the valley of Caracas, commencing
near the western dome. The eastern summit is accessible only by
going first to the west of the ravine over the promontory of the
Puerta, proceeding straight forward to the lower summit; and not
turning to the east till the ridge, or the hollow of the Silla
between the two peaks, is nearly reached. The general aspect of the
mountain points out this path; the rocks being so steep on the east
of the ravine that it would be extremely difficult to reach the
summit of the Silla by ascending straight to the eastern dome,
instead of going by the way of the Puerta.
From the foot of the cascade of Chacaito to one thousand toises of
elevation, we found only savannahs. Two small liliaceous plants,
with yellow flowers,* alone lift up their heads, among the grasses
which cover the rocks. (* Cypura martinicensis, and Sisyrinchium
iridifolium. This last is found also near the Venta of La Guayra,
at 600 toises of elevation.) A few brambles* (* Rubus jamaicensis.)
remind us of the form of our European vegetation. We in vain hoped
to find on the mountains of Caracas, and subsequently on the back
of the Andes, an eglantine near these brambles. We did not find one
indigenous rose-tree in all South America, notwithstanding the
analogy existing between the climates of the high mountains of the
torrid zone and the climate of our temperate zone. It appears that
this charming shrub is wanting in all the southern hemisphere,
within and beyond the tropics. It was only on the Mexican mountains
that we were fortunate enough to discover, in the nineteenth degree
of latitude, American eglantines.* (* M. Redoute, in his superb
work on rose-trees, has given our Mexican eglantine, under the name
of Rosier de Montezuma, Montezuma rose.)
We were sometimes so enveloped in mist, that we could not, without
difficulty, find our way. At this height there is no path, and we
were obliged to climb with our hands, when our feet failed us, on
the steep and slippery acclivity. A vein filled with porcelain-clay
attracted our attention.* (* The breadth of the vein is three feet.
This porcelain-clay, when moistened, readily absorbs oxygen from
the atmosphere. I found, at Caracas, the residual nitrogen very
slightly mingled with carbonic acid, though the experiment was made
in phials with ground-glass stoppers, not filled with water.) It is
of snowy whiteness, and is no doubt the remains of a decomposed
feldspar. I forwarded a considerable portion of it to the intendant
of the province. In a country where fuel is not scarce, a mixture
of refractory earths may be useful, to improve the earthenware, and
even the bricks. Every time that the clouds surrounded us, the
thermometer sunk as low as 12 degrees (to 9.6 degrees R.); with a
serene sky it rose to 21 degrees. These observations were made in
the shade. But it is difficult, on such rapid declivities, covered
with a dry, shining, yellow turf, to avoid the effects of radiant
heat. We were at nine hundred and forty toises of elevation; and
yet at the same height, towards the east, we perceived in a ravine,
not merely a few solitary palm-trees, but a whole grove. It was the
palma real; probably a species of the genus Oreodoxa. This group of
palms, at so considerable an elevation, formed a striking contrast
with the willows* scattered on the depth of the more temperate
valley of Caracas. (* Salix Humboldtiana of Willdenouw. On the
alpine palm-trees, see my Prolegomena de Dist. Plant. page 235.) We
here discovered plants of European forms, situated below those of
the torrid zone.
After proceeding for the space of four hours across the savannahs,
we entered into a little wood composed of shrubs and small trees,
called el Pejual; doubtless from the great abundance here of the
pejoa (Gaultheria odorata), a plant with very odoriferous leaves.*
(* It is a great advantage of the Spanish language, and a
peculiarity which it shares in common with the Latin, that, from
the name of a tree, may be derived a word designating an
association or group of trees of the same species. Thus are formed
the words olivar, robledar, and pinal, from olivo, roble, and pino.
The Hispano-Americans have added tunal, pejual, guayaval, etc.,
places where a great many Cactuses, Gualtheria odoratas, and
Psidiums, grow together.) The steepness of the mountain became less
considerable, and we felt an indescribable pleasure in examining
the plants of this region. Nowhere, perhaps, can be found collected
together, in so small a space, productions so beautiful, and so
remarkable in regard to the geography of plants. At the height of a
thousand toises, the lofty savannahs of the hills terminate in a
zone of shrubs which, by their appearance, their tortuous branches,
their stiff leaves, and the magnitude and beauty of their purple
flowers, remind us of what is called, in the Cordilleras of the
Andes, the vegetation of the paramos and the punas.* (* For the
explanation of these words, see above Chapter 1.5.) We there find
the family of the alpine rhododendrons, the thibaudias, the
andromedas, the vacciniums, and those befarias with resinous
leaves, which we have several times compared to the rhododendron of
our European Alps.
Even when nature does not produce the same species in analogous
climates, either in the plains of isothermal parallels,* (We may
compare together either latitudes which in the same hemisphere
present the same mean temperature (as, for instance, Pennsylvania
and the central part of France, Chile and the southern part of New
Holland); or we may consider the relations that may exist between
the vegetation of the two hemispheres under isothermal parallels.)
or on table-lands, the temperature of which resembles that of
places nearer the poles,* we still remark a striking resemblance of
appearance and physiognomy in the vegetation of the most distant
countries. (* The geography of plants comprises not merely an
examination of the analogies observed in the same hemisphere; as
between the vegetation of the Pyrenees and that of the Scandinavian
plains; or between that of the Cordilleras of Peru and of the
coasts of Chile. It also investigates the relations between the
alpine plants of both hemispheres. It compares the vegetation of
the Alleghanies and the Cordilleras of Mexico, with that of the
mountains of Chile and Brazil. Bearing in mind that every
isothermal line has an alpine branch (as, for instance, that which
connects Upsala with a point in the Swiss Alps), the great problem
of the analogy of vegetable forms may be defined as follows: 1st,
examining in each hemisphere, and at the level of the coasts, the
vegetation on the same isothermal line, especially near convex or
concave summits; 2nd, comparing, with respect to the form of
plants, on the same isothermal line north and south of the equator,
the alpine branch with that traced in the plains; 3rd, comparing
the vegetation on homonymous isothermal lines in the two
hemispheres, either in the low regions, or in the alpine regions.)
This phenomenon is one of the most curious in the history of
organic forms. I say the history; for in vain would reason forbid
man to form hypotheses on the origin of things; he still goes on
puzzling himself with insoluble problems relating to the
distribution of beings.
A gramen of Switzerland grows on the granitic rocks of the straits
of Magellan.* (* Phleum alpinum, examined by Mr. Brown. The
investigations of this great botanist prove that a certain number
of plants are at once common to both hemispheres. Potentilla
anserina, Prunella vulgaris, Scirpus mucronatus, and Panicum
crus-galli, grow in Germany, in Australia, and in Pennsylvania.)
New Holland contains above forty European phanerogamous plants: and
the greater number of those plants, which are found equally in the
temperate zones of both hemispheres, are entirely wanting in the
intermediary or equinoctial region, as well in the plains as on the
mountains. A downy-leaved violet, which terminates in some sort the
zone of the phanerogamous plants at Teneriffe, and which was long
thought peculiar to that island,* is seen three hundred leagues
farther north, near the snowy summit of the Pyrenees. (* The Viola
cheiranthifolia has been found by MM. Kunth and Von Buch among the
alpine plants which Jussieu brought from the Pyrenees.) Gramina and
cyperaceous plants of Germany, Arabia, and Senegal, have been
recognized among those that were gathered by M. Bonpland and myself
on the cold table-lands of Mexico, along the burning shores of the
Orinoco, and in the southern hemisphere on the Andes and Quito.* (*
Cyperus mucronatus, Poa eragrostis, Festuca myurus, Andropogos
avenaceus, Lapago racemosa. (See the Nova Genera et Species
Plantarum volume 1 page 25.)) How can we conceive the migration of
plants through regions now covered by the ocean? How have the germs
of organic life, which resemble each other in their appearance, and
even in their internal structure, unfolded themselves at unequal
distances from the poles and from the surface of the seas, wherever
places so distant present any analogy of temperature?
Notwithstanding the influence exercised on the vital functions of
plants by the pressure of the air, and the greater or less
extinction of light, heat, unequally distributed in different
seasons of the year, must doubtless be considered as the most
powerful stimulus of vegetation.
The number of identical species in the two continents and in the
two hemispheres is far less than the statements of early travellers
would lead us to believe. The lofty mountains of equinoctial
America have certainly plantains, valerians, arenarias,
ranunculuses, medlars, oaks, and pines, which from their
physiognomy we might confound with those of Europe; but they are
all specifically different. When nature does not present the same
species, she loves to repeat the same genera. Neighbouring species
are often placed at enormous distances from each other, in the low
regions of the temperate zone, and on the alpine heights of the
equator. At other times (and the Silla of Caracas affords a
striking example of this phenomenon), they are not the European
genera, which have sent species to people like colonists the
mountains of the torrid zone, but genera of the same tribe,
difficult to be distinguished by their appearance, which take the
place of each other in different latitudes.
The mountains of New Grenada surrounding the table-lands of Bogota
are more than two hundred leagues distant from those of Caracas,
and yet the Silla, the only elevated peak in the chain of low
mountains, presents those singular groupings of befarias with
purple flowers, of andromedas, of gualtherias, of myrtilli, of uvas
camaronas,* (* The names vine-tree, and uvas camaronas, are given
in the Andes to plants of the genus Thibaudia, on account of their
large succulent fruits. Thus the ancient botanists gave the name of
bear's vine, uva ursi, and vine of Mount Ida (Vitis idaea), to an
arbutus and a myrtillus, which belong, like the thibaudia, to the
family of the Ericineae.) of nerteras, and of aralias with hoary
leaves,* (* Nertera depressa, Aralia reticulata, Hedyotis
blaerioides.) which characterize the vegetation of the paramos on
the high Cordilleras of Santa Fe. We found the same Thibaudia
glandulosa at the entrance of the table-land of Bogota, and in the
Pejual of the Silla. The coast-chain of Caracas is unquestionably
connected (by the Torito, the Palomera, Tocuyo, and the paramos of
Rosas, of Bocono, and of Niquitao) with the high Cordilleras of
Merida, Pamplona, and Santa Fe; but from the Silla to Tocuyo, along
a distance of seventy leagues, the mountains of Caracas are so low,
that the shrubs of the family of the ericineous plants, just cited,
do not find the cold climate which is necessary for their
development. Supposing, as is probable, that the thibaudias and the
rhododendron of the Andes, or befaria, exist in the paramo of
Niquitao and in the Sierra de Merida, covered with eternal snow,
these plants would nevertheless want a ridge sufficiently lofty and
long for their migration towards the Silla of Caracas.
The more we study the distribution of organized beings on the
globe, the more we are inclined, if not to abandon the ideas of
migration, at least to consider them as hypotheses not entirely
satisfactory. The chain of the Andes divides the whole of South
America into two unequal longitudinal parts. At the foot of this
chain, on the east and west, we found a great number of plants
specifically the same. The various passages of the Cordilleras
nowhere permit the vegetable productions of the warm regions to
proceed from the coasts of the Pacific to the banks of the Amazon.
When a peak attains a great elevation, either in the middle of very
low mountains and plains, or in the centre of an archipelago heaved
up by volcanic fires, its summit is covered with alpine plants,
many of which are again found, at immense distances, on other
mountains having an analogous climate. Such are the general
phenomena of the distribution of plants.
It is now said that a mountain is high enough to enter into the
limits of the rhododendrons and the befarias, as it has long been
said that such a mountain reached the limit of perpetual snow. In
using this expression, it is tacitly admitted, that under the
influence of certain temperatures, certain vegetable forms must
necessarily be developed. Such a supposition, however, taken in all
its generality, is not strictly accurate. The pines of Mexico are
wanting on the Cordilleras of Peru. The Silla of Caracas is not
covered with the oaks which flourish in New Grenada at the same
height. Identity of forms indicates an analogy of climate; but in
similar climates the species may be singularly diversified.
The charming rhododendron of the Andes (the befaria) was first
described by M. Mutis, who observed it near Pamplona and Santa Fe
de Bogota, in the fourth and seventh degree of north latitude. It
was so little known before our expedition to the Silla, that it was
scarcely to be found in any herbal in Europe. The learned editors
of the Flora of Peru had even described it under another name, that
of acunna. In the same manner as the rhododendrons of Lapland,
Caucasus, and the Alps* (* Rhododendron lapponicum, R. caucasicum,
R. ferrugineum, and R. hirsutum.) differ from each other, the two
species of befaria we brought from the Silla* (* Befaria glauca, B.
ledifolia.) are also specifically different from that of Santa Fe
and Bogota.* (* Befaria aestuans, and B. resinosa.) Near the
equator the rhododendrons of the Andes (Particularly B. aestuans of
Mutis, and two new species of the southern hemisphere, which we
have described under the name of B. coarctata, and B. grandiflora.)
cover the mountains as far as the highest paramos, at sixteen and
seventeen hundred toises of elevation. Advancing northward, on the
Silla de Caracas, we find them much lower, a little below one
thousand toises. The befaria recently discovered in Florida, in
latitude 30 degrees, grows even on hills of small elevation. Thus
in a space of six hundred leagues in latitude, these shrubs descend
towards the plains in proportion as their distance from the equator
augments. The rhododendron of Lapland grows also at eight or nine
hundred toises lower than the rhododendron of the Alps and the
Pyrenees. We were surprised at not meeting with any species of
befaria in the mountains of Mexico, between the rhododendrons of
Santa Fe and Caracas, and those of Florida.
In the small grove which crowns the Silla, the Befaria ledifolia is
only three or four feet high. The trunk is divided from its root
into a great many slender and even verticillate branches. The
leaves are oval, lanceolate, glaucous on their inferior part, and
curled at the edges. The whole plant is covered with long and
viscous hairs, and emits a very agreeable resinous smell. The bees
visit its fine purple flowers, which are very abundant, as in all
the alpine plants, and, when in full blossom, they are often nearly
an inch wide.
The rhododendron of Switzerland, in those places where it grows, at
the elevation of between eight hundred and a thousand toises,
belongs to a climate, the mean temperature of which is +2 and-1
degrees, like that of the plains of Lapland. In this zone the
coldest months are-4, and-10 degrees: the hottest, 12 and 7
degrees. Thermometrical observations, made at the same heights and
in the same latitudes, render it probable that, at the Pejual of
the Silla, one thousand toises above the Caribbean Sea, the mean
temperature of the air is still 17 or 18 degrees; and that the
thermometer keeps, in the coolest season, between 15 and 20 degrees
in the day, and in the night between 10 and 12 degrees. At the
hospital of St. Gothard, situated nearly on the highest limit of
the rhododendron of the Alps, the maximum of heat, in the month of
August at noon, in the shade, is usually 12 or 13 degrees; in the
night, at the same season, the air is cooled by the radiation of
the soil down to +1 or-1.5 degrees. Under the same barometric
pressure, consequently at the same height, but thirty degrees of
latitude nearer the equator, the befaria of the Silla is often, at
noon, in the sun, exposed to a heat of 23 or 24 degrees. The
greatest nocturnal refrigeration probably never exceeds 7 degrees.
We have carefully compared the climate, under the influence of
which, at different latitudes, two groups of plants of the same
family vegetate at equal heights above the level of the sea. The
results would have been far different, had we compared zones
equally distant, either from the perpetual snow, or from the
isothermal line of 0 degrees.* (* The stratum of air, the mean
temperature of which is 0 degrees, and which scarcely coincides
with the superior limit of perpetual snow, is found in the parallel
of the rhododendrons of Switzerland at nine hundred toises; in the
parallel of the befarias of Caracas, at two thousand seven hundred
toises of elevation.)
In the little thicket of the Pejual, near the purple-flowered
befaria, grows a heath-leaved hedyotis, eight feet high; the
caparosa,* which is a large arborescent hypericum (* Vismia
caparosa (a loranthus clings to this plant, and appropriates to
itself the yellow juice of the vismia); Davallia meifolia, Heracium
avilae, Aralia arborea, Jacq., and Lepidium virginicum. Two new
species of lycopodium, the thyoides, and the aristatum, are seen
lower down, near the Puerto de la Silla.); a lepidium, which
appears identical with that of Virginia; and lastly, lycopodiaceous
plants and mosses, which cover the rocks and roots of the trees.
That which gives most celebrity in the country to the little
thicket, is a shrub ten or fifteen feet high, of the corymbiferous
family. The Creoles call it incense (incienso).* (* Trixis
nereifolia of M. Bonpland.) Its tough and crenate leaves, as well
as the extremities of the branches, are covered with a white wool.
It is a new species of Trixis, extremely resinous, the flowers of
which have the agreeable odour of storax. This smell is very
different from that emitted by the leaves of the Trixis
terebinthinacea of the mountains of Jamaica, opposite to those of
Caracas. The people sometimes mix the incienso of the Silla with
the flowers of the pevetera, another composite plant, the smell of
which resembles that of the heliotropium of Peru. The pevetera does
not, however, grow on the mountains so high as the zone of the
befarias; it vegetates in the valley of Chacao, and the ladies of
Caracas prepare from it an extremely pleasant odoriferous water.
We spent a long time in examining the fine resinous and fragrant
plants of the Pejual. The sky became more and more cloudy, and the
thermometer sank below 11 degrees, a temperature at which, in this
zone, people begin to suffer from the cold. Quitting the little
thicket of alpine plants, we found ourselves again in a savannah.
We climbed over a part of the western dome, in order to descend
into the hollow of the Silla, a valley which separates the two
summits of the mountain. We there had great difficulties to
overcome, occasioned by the force of the vegetation. A botanist
would not readily guess that the thick wood covering this valley is
formed by the assemblage of a plant of the musaceous family.*
(*Scitamineous plants, or family of the plantains.) It is probably
a maranta, or a heliconia; its leaves are large and shining; it
reaches the height of fourteen or fifteen feet, and its succulent
stalks grow near one another like the stems of the reeds found in
the humid regions of the south of Europe.* (* Arundo donax.) We
were obliged to cut our way through this forest. The negroes walked
before with their cutlasses or machetes. The people confound this
alpine scitamineous plant with the arborescent gramina, under the
name of carice. We saw neither its fruit nor flowers. We are
surprised to meet with a monocotyledonous family, believed to be
exclusively found in the hot and low regions of the tropics, at
eleven hundred toises of elevation; much higher than the
andromedas, the thibaudias, and the rhododendron of the
Cordilleras.* (* Befaria.) In a chain of mountains no less
elevated, and more northern (the Blue Mountains of Jamaica), the
Heliconia of the parrots and the bihai, rather grow in the alpine
shaded situations.* (* Heliconia psittacorum, and H. bihai. These
two heliconias are very common in the plains of Terra Firma.)
Wandering in this thick wood of musaceae or arborescent plants, we
constantly directed our course towards the eastern peak, which we
perceived from time to time through an opening. On a sudden we
found ourselves enveloped in a thick mist; the compass alone could
guide us; but in advancing northward we were in danger at every
step of finding ourselves on the brink of that enormous wall of
rocks, which descends almost perpendicularly to the depth of six
thousand feet towards the sea. We were obliged to halt. Surrounded
by clouds sweeping the ground, we began to doubt whether we should
reach the eastern peak before night. Happily, the negroes who
carried our water and provisions, rejoined us, and we resolved to
take some refreshment. Our repast did not last long. Possibly the
Capuchin father had not thought of the great number of persons who
accompanied us, or perhaps the slaves had made free with our
provisions on the way; be that as it may, we found nothing but
olives, and scarcely any bread. Horace, in his retreat at Tibur,
never boasted of a repast more light and frugal; but olives, which
might have afforded a satisfactory meal to a poet, devoted to
study, and leading a sedentary life, appeared an aliment by no
means sufficiently substantial for travellers climbing mountains.
We had watched the greater part of the night, and we walked for
nine hours without finding a single spring. Our guides were
discouraged; they wished to go back, and we had great difficulty in
preventing them.
In the midst of the mist I made trial of the electrometer of Volta,
armed with a smoking match. Though very near a thick wood of
heliconias, I obtained very sensible signs of atmospheric
electricity. It often varied from positive to negative, its
intensity changing every instant. These variations, and the
conflict of several small currents of air, which divided the mist,
and transformed it into clouds, the borders of which were visible,
appeared to me infallible prognostics of a change in the weather.
It was only two o'clock in the afternoon; we entertained some hope
of reaching the eastern summit of the Silla before sunset, and of
re-descending into the valley separating the two peaks, intending
there to pass the night, to light a great fire, and to make our
negroes construct a hut with the leaves of the heliconia. We sent
off half of our servants with orders to hasten the next morning to
meet us, not with olives, but with a supply of salt beef.
We had scarcely made these arrangements when the east wind began to
blow violently from the sea. The thermometer rose to 12.5 degrees.
It was no doubt an ascending wind, which, by heightening the
temperature, dissolved the vapours. In less than two minutes the
clouds dispersed, and the two domes of the Silla appeared to us
singularly near. We opened the barometer in the lowest part of the
hollow that separates the two summits, near a little pool of very
muddy water. Here, as in the West India Islands, marshy plains are
found at great elevations; not because the woody mountains attract
the clouds, but because they condense the vapours by the effect of
nocturnal refrigeration, occasioned by the radiation of heat from
the ground, and from the parenchyma of the leaves. The mercury was
at 21 inches 5.7 lines. We shaped our course direct to the eastern
summit. The obstruction caused by the vegetation gradually
diminished; it was, however, necessary to cut down some heliconias;
but these arborescent plants were not now very thick or high. The
peaks of the Silla themselves, as we have several times mentioned,
are covered only with gramina and small shrubs of befaria. Their
barrenness, however, is not owing to their height: the limit of
trees in this region is four hundred toises higher; since, judging
according to the analogy of other mountains, this limit would be
found here only at a height of eighteen hundred toises. The absence
of large trees on the two rocky summits of the Silla may be
attributed to the aridity of the soil, the violence of the winds
blowing from the sea, and the conflagrations so frequent in all the
mountains of the equinoctial region.
To reach the eastern peak, which is the highest, it is necessary to
approach as near as possible the great precipice which descends
towards Caravalleda and the coast. The gneiss as far as this spot
preserves its lamellar texture and its primitive direction; but
where we climbed the summit of the Silla, we found it had passed
into granite. Its texture becomes granular; the mica, less
frequent, is more unequally spread through the rock. Instead of
garnets we met with a few solitary crystals of hornblende. It is,
however, not a syenite, but rather a granite of new formation. We
were three quarters of an hour in reaching the summit of the
pyramid. This part of the way is not dangerous, provided the
traveller carefully examines the stability of each fragment of rock
on which he places his foot. The granite superposed on the gneiss
does not present a regular separation into beds: it is divided by
clefts, which often cross one another at right angles. Prismatic
blocks, one foot wide and twelve long, stand out from the ground
obliquely, and appear on the edges of the precipice like enormous
beams suspended over the abyss.
Having arrived at the summit, we enjoyed, for a few minutes only,
the serenity of the sky. The eye ranged over a vast extent of
country: looking down to the north was the sea, and to the south,
the fertile valley of Caracas. The barometer was at 20 inches 7.6
lines; the thermometer at 13.7 degrees. We were at thirteen hundred
and fifty toises of elevation. We gazed on an extent of sea, the
radius of which was thirty-six leagues. Persons who are affected by
looking downward from a considerable height should remain at the
centre of the small flat which crowns the eastern summit of the
Silla. The mountain is not very remarkable for height: it is nearly
eighty toises lower than the Canigou; but it is distinguished among
all the mountains I have visited by an enormous precipice on the
side next the sea. The coast forms only a narrow border; and
looking from the summit of the pyramid on the houses of
Caravalleda, this wall of rocks seems, by an optical illusion, to
be nearly perpendicular. The real slope of the declivity appeared
to me, according to an exact calculation, 53 degrees 28 minutes.*
(* Observations of the latitude give for the horizontal distance
between the foot of the mountain near Caravalleda, and the vertical
line passing through its summit, scarcely 1000 toises.) The mean
slope of the peak of Teneriffe is scarcely 12 degrees 30 minutes. A
precipice of six or seven thousand feet, like that of the Silla of
Caracas, is a phenomenon far more rare than is generally believed
by those who cross mountains without measuring their height, their
bulk, and their slope. Since the experiments on the fall of bodies,
and on their deviation to the south-east, have been resumed in
several parts of Europe, a rock of two hundred and fifty toises of
perpendicular elevation has been in vain sought for among all the
Alps of Switzerland. The declivity of Mont Blanc towards the Allee
Blanche does not even reach an angle of 45 degrees; though in the
greater number of geological works, Mont Blanc is described as
perpendicular on the south side.
At the Silla of Caracas, the enormous northern cliff is partly
covered with vegetation, notwithstanding the extreme steepness of
its slope. Tufts of befaria and andromedas appear as if suspended
from the rock. The little valley which separates the domes towards
the south, stretches in the direction of the sea. Alpine plants
fill this hollow; and, not confined to the ridge of the mountain,
they follow the sinuosities of the ravine. It would seem as if
torrents were concealed under that fresh foliage; and the
disposition of the plants, the grouping of so many inanimate
objects, give the landscape all the charm of motion and of life.
Seven months had now elapsed since we had been on the summit of the
peak of Teneriffe, whence we surveyed a space of the globe equal to
a fourth part of France. The apparent horizon of the sea is there
six leagues farther distant than at the top of the Silla, and yet
we saw that horizon, at least for some time, very distinctly. It
was strongly marked, and not confounded with the adjacent strata of
air. At the Silla, which is five hundred and fifty toises lower
than the peak of Teneriffe, the horizon, though nearer, continued
invisible towards the north and north-north-east. Following with
the eye the surface of the sea, which was smooth as glass, we were
struck with the progressive diminution of the reflected light.
Where the visual ray touched the last limit of that surface, the
water was lost among the superposed strata of air. This appearance
has something in it very extraordinary. We expect to see the
horizon level with the eye; but, instead of distinguishing at this
height a marked limit between the two elements, the more distant
strata of water seem to be transformed into vapour, and mingled
with the aerial ocean. I observed the same appearance, not in one
spot of the horizon alone, but on an extent of more than a hundred
and sixty degrees, along the Pacific, when I found myself for the
first time on the pointed rock that commands the crater of
Pichincha; a volcano, the elevation of which exceeds that of Mont
Blanc.* (* See Views of Nature, Bohn's edition, page 358.) The
visibility of a very distant horizon depends, when there is no
mirage, upon two distinct things: the quantity of light received on
that part of the sea where the visual ray terminates; and the
extinction of the reflected light during its passage through the
intermediate strata of air. It may happen, notwithstanding the
serenity of the sky and the transparency of the atmosphere, that
the ocean is feebly illuminated at thirty or forty leagues'
distance; or that the strata of air nearest the earth may
extinguish a great deal of the light, by absorbing the rays that
traverse them.
The rounded peak, or western dome of the Silla, concealed from us
the view of the town of Caracas; but we distinguished the nearest
houses, the villages of Chacao and Petare, the coffee plantations,
and the course of the Rio Guayra, a slender streak of water
reflecting a silvery light. The narrow band of cultivated ground
was pleasingly contrasted with the wild and gloomy aspect of the
neighbouring mountains. Whilst contemplating these grand scenes, we
feel little regret that the solitudes of the New World are not
embellished with the monuments of antiquity.
But we could not long avail ourselves of the advantage arising from
the position of the Silla, in commanding all the neighbouring
summits. While we were examining with our glasses that part of the
sea, the horizon of which was clearly defined, and the chain of the
mountains of Ocumare, behind which begins the unknown world of the
Orinoco and the Amazon, a thick fog from the plains rose to the
elevated regions, first filling the bottom of the valley of
Caracas. The vapours, illumined from above, presented a uniform
tint of a milky white. The valley seemed overspread with water, and
looked like an arm of the sea, of which the adjacent mountains
formed the steep shore. In vain we waited for the slave who carried
Ramsden's great sextant. Eager to avail myself of the favourable
state of the sky, I resolved to take a few solar altitudes with a
sextant by Troughton of two inches radius. The disk of the sun was
half-concealed by the mist. The difference of longitude between the
quarter of the Trinidad and the eastern peak of the Silla appears
scarcely to exceed 0 degrees 3 minutes 22 seconds.* (* The difference
of longitude between the Silla and La Guayra, according to Fidalgo,
is 0 degrees 6 minutes 40 seconds.)
Whilst, seated on the rock, I was determining the dip of the
needle, I found my hands covered with a species of hairy bee, a
little smaller than the honey-bee of the north of Europe. These
insects make their nests in the ground. They seldom fly; and, from
the slowness of their movements, I should have supposed they were
benumbed by the cold of the mountains. The people, in these
regions, call them angelitos (little angels), because they very
seldom sting. They are no doubt of the genus Apis, of the division
melipones. It has been erroneously affirmed that these bees, which
are peculiar to the New World, are destitute of all offensive
weapons. Their sting is indeed comparatively feeble, and they use
it seldom; but a person, not fully convinced of the harmlessness of
these angelitos, can scarcely divest himself of a sensation of
fear. I must confess, that, whilst engaged in my astronomical
observations, I was often on the point of letting my instruments
fall, when I felt my hands and face covered with these hairy bees.
Our guides assured us that they attempt to defend themselves only
when irritated by being seized by their legs. I was not tempted to
try the experiment on myself.
The dip of the needle at the Silla was one centesimal degree less
than in the town of Caracas. In collecting the observations which I
made during calm weather and in very favourable circumstances, on
the mountains as well as along the coast, it would at first seem,
that we discover, in that part of the globe, a certain influence of
the heights on the dip of the needle, and the intensity of the
magnetical forces; but we must remark, that the dip at Caracas is
much greater than could be supposed, from the situation of the
town, and that the magnetical phenomena are modified by the
proximity of certain rocks, which constitute so many particular
centres or little systems of attraction.* (* I have seen fragments
of quartz traversed by parallel bands of magnetic iron, carried
into the valley of Caracas by the waters descending from the
Galipano and the Cerro de Avila. This banded magnetic iron-ore is
found also in the Sierra Nevada of Merida. Between the two peaks of
the Silla, angular fragments of cellular quartz are found, covered
with red oxide of iron. They do not act on the needle. This oxide
is of a cinnabar-red colour.)
The temperature of the atmosphere varied on the summit of the Silla
from eleven to fourteen degrees, according as the weather was calm
or windy. Every one knows how difficult it is to verify, on the
summit of a mountain, the temperature, which is to serve for the
barometric calculation. The wind was east, which would seem to
prove that the trade-winds extend in this latitude much higher than
fifteen hundred toises. Von Buch had observed that, at the peak of
Teneriffe, near the northern limit of the trade-winds, there exists
generally at the elevation of one thousand nine hundred toises, a
contrary current from the west. The Academy of Sciences recommended
the men of science who accompanied the unfortunate La Perouse, to
employ small air-balloons for the purpose of ascertaining at sea
the extent of the trade-winds within the tropics. Such experiments
are very difficult. Small balloons do not in general reach the
height of the Silla; and the light clouds which are sometimes
perceived at an elevation of three or four thousand toises, for
instance, the fleecy clouds, called by the French moutons, remain
almost fixed, or have such a slow motion, that it is impossible to
judge of the direction of the wind.
During the short space of time that the sky was serene at the
zenith, I found the blue of the atmosphere sensibly deeper than on
the coasts. It is probable that, in the months of July and August,
the difference between the colour of the sky on the coasts and on
the summit of the Silla is still more considerable, but the
meteorological phenomenon with which M. Bonpland and myself were
most struck during the hour we passed on the mountain, was the
apparent dryness of the air, which seemed to increase as the fog
augmented.
This fog soon became so dense that it would have been imprudent to
remain longer on the edge of a precipice of seven or eight thousand
feet deep.* (* In the direction of north-west the slopes appear
more accessible; and I have been told of a path frequented by
smugglers, which leads to Caravalleda, between the two peaks of the
Silla. From the eastern peak I took the bearings of the western
peak, 64 degrees 40 minutes south-west; and of the houses, which I
was told belonged to Caravalleda, 55 degrees 20 minutes north-west.
) We descended the eastern dome of the Silla, and gathered in our
descent a gramen, which not only forms a new and very remarkable
genus, but which, to our great astonishment, we found again some
time after on the summit of the volcano of Pichincha, at the
distance of four hundred leagues from the Silla, in the southern
hemisphere.* (* Aegopogon cenchroides.) The Lichen floridus, so
common in the north of Europe, covered the branches of the befaria
and the Gualtheria odorata, descending even to the roots of these
shrubs. Examining the mosses which cover the rocks of gneiss in the
valley between the two peaks, I was surprised at finding real
pebbles,—rounded fragments of quartz.* (* Fragments of brown
copper-ore were found mixed with these pebbles, at an elevation of
1170 toises.) It may be conceived that the valley of Caracas was
once an inland lake, before the Rio Guayra found an issue to the
east near Caurimare, at the foot of the hill of Auyamas, and before
the ravine of Tipe opened on the west, in the direction of Gatia
and Cabo Blanco. But how can we imagine that these waters could
ascend as high as the Silla, when the mountains opposite this peak,
those of Ocumare, were too low to prevent their overflow into the
llanos? The pebbles could not have been brought by torrents from
more elevated points, since there is no height that commands the
Silla. Must we admit that they have been heaved up, like all the
mountains which border the coast.
It was half after four in the afternoon when we finished our
observations. Satisfied with the success of our journey, we forgot
that there might be danger in descending in the dark, steep
declivities covered by a smooth and slippery turf. The mist
concealed the valley from us; but we distinguished the double hill
of La Puerta, which, like all objects lying almost perpendicularly
beneath the eye, appeared extremely near. We relinquished our
design of passing the night between the two summits of the Silla,
and having again found the path we had cut through the thick wood
of heliconia, we soon arrived at the Pejual, the region of
odoriferous and resinous plants. The beauty of the befarias, and
their branches covered with large purple flowers, again rivetted
our attention. When, in these climates, a botanist gathers plants
to form his herbal, he becomes difficult in his choice in
proportion to the luxuriance of vegetation. He casts away those
which have been first cut, because they appear less beautiful than
those which were out of reach. Though loaded with plants before
quitting the Pejual, we still regretted not having made a more
ample harvest. We tarried so long in this spot, that night
surprised us as we entered the savannah, at the elevation of
upwards of nine hundred toises.
As there is scarcely any twilight in the tropics, we pass suddenly
from bright daylight to darkness. The moon was on the horizon; but
her disk was veiled from time to time by thick clouds, drifted by a
cold and rough wind. Rapid slopes, covered with yellow and dry
grass, now seen in shade, and now suddenly illumined, seemed like
precipices, the depth of which the eye sought in vain to measure.
We proceeded onwards, in single file, and endeavoured to support
ourselves by our hands, lest we should roll down. The guides, who
carried our instruments, abandoned us successively, to sleep on the
mountain. Among those who remained with us was a Congo black, who
evinced great address, bearing on his head a large dipping-needle:
he held it constantly steady, notwithstanding the extreme declivity
of the rocks. The fog had dispersed by degrees in the bottom of the
valley; and the scattered lights we perceived below us caused a
double illusion. The steeps appeared still more dangerous than they
really were; and, during six hours of continual descent, we seemed
to be always equally near the farms at the foot of the Silla. We
heard very distinctly the voices of men and the notes of guitars.
Sound is generally so well propagated upwards, that in a balloon at
the elevation of three thousand toises, the barking of dogs is
sometimes heard.* (* Gay-Lussac's account of his ascent on the 15th
of September, 1805.)
We did not arrive till ten at night at the bottom of the valley. We
were overcome with fatigue and thirst, having walked for fifteen
hours, nearly without stopping. The soles of our feet were cut and
torn by the asperities of a rocky soil and the hard and dry stalks
of the gramina, for we had been obliged to pull off our boots, the
soles having become too slippery. On declivities devoid of shrubs
or ligneous herbs, which may be grasped by the hand, the danger of
the descent is diminished by walking barefoot. In order to shorten
the way, our guides conducted us from the Puerta de la Silla to the
farm of Gallegos by a path leading to a reservoir of water, called
el Tanque. They missed their way, however; and this last descent,
the steepest of all, brought us near the ravine of Chacaito. The
noise of the cascades gave this nocturnal scene a grand and wild
character.
We passed the night at the foot of the Silla. Our friends at
Caracas had been able to distinguish us with glasses on the summit
of the eastern peak. They felt interested in hearing the account of
our expedition, but they were not satisfied with the result of our
measurement, which did not assign to the Silla even the elevation
of the highest summit of the Pyrenees.* (* It was formerly believed
that the height of the Silla of Caracas scarcely differed from that
of the peak of Teneriffe.) One cannot blame the national feeling
which suggests exaggerated ideas of the monuments of nature, in a
country in which the monuments of art are nothing; nor can we
wonder that the inhabitants of Quito and Riobamba, who have prided
themselves for ages on the height of Chimborazo, mistrust those
measurements which elevate the mountains of Himalaya above all the
colossal Cordilleras?
During our journey to the Silla, and in all our excursions in the
valley of Caracas, we were very attentive to the lodes and
indications of ore which we found in the strata of gneiss. No
regular diggings having been made, we could only examine the
fissures, the ravines, and the land-slips occasioned by torrents in
the rainy season. The rock of gneiss, passing sometimes into a
granite of new formation, sometimes into mica-slate,* (* Especially
at great elevations.) belongs in Germany to the most metalliferous
rocks; but in the New Continent, the gneiss has not hitherto been
remarked as very rich in ores worth working. The most celebrated
mines of Mexico and Peru are found in the primitive and transition
schists, in the trap-porphyries, the grauwakke, and the alpine
limestones. In several spots of the valley of Caracas, the gneiss
contains a small quantity of gold, disseminated in small veins of
quartz, sulphuretted silver, azure copper-ore, and galena; but it
is doubtful whether these different metalliferous substances are
not too poor to encourage any attempt at working them. Such
attempts were, however, made at the conquest of the province, about
the middle of the sixteenth century.
From the promontory of Paria to beyond cape Vela, the early
navigators had seen gold ornaments and gold dust, in the possession
of the inhabitants of the coast. They penetrated into the interior
of the country, to discover whence the precious metal came; and
though the information obtained in the province of Coro, and the
markets of Curiana and Cauchieto,* (* The Spaniards found, in 1500,
in the country of Curiana (now Coro), little birds, frogs, and
other ornaments made of gold. Those who had cast these figures
lived at Cauchieto, a place nearer the Rio de la Hacha. I have seen
ornaments resembling those described by Peter Martyr of Anghiera
(which indicate tolerable skill in goldsmiths' work), among the
remains of the ancient inhabitants of Cundinamarca. The same art
appears to have been practised in places along the coasts, and also
farther to the south, among the mountains of New Grenada.) clearly
proved that real mineral wealth was to be found only to the west
and south-west of Coro (that is to say, in the mountains near those
of New Grenada), the whole province of Caracas was nevertheless
eagerly explored. A governor, newly arrived on that coast, could
recommend himself to the Spanish court only by boasting of the
mines of his province; and in order to take from cupidity what was
most ignoble and repulsive, the thirst of gold was justified by the
purpose to which it was pretended the riches acquired by fraud and
violence might be employed. "Gold," says Christopher Columbus, in
his last letter* (Lettera rarissima data nelle Indie nella isola di
Jamaica a 7 Julio dei 1503.—"Le oro e metallo sopra gli altri
excellentissimo; e dell' oro si fanno li tesori e chi lo tiene fa e
opera quanto vuole nel mondo[?], e finel[?]mente aggionge a mandare
le anime al Paradiso.") to King Ferdinand, "gold is a thing so much
the more necessary to your majesty, because, in order to fulfil the
ancient prophecy, Jerusalem is to be rebuilt by a prince of the
Spanish monarchy. Gold is the most excellent of metals. What
becomes of those precious stones, which are sought for at the
extremities of the globe? They are sold, and are finally converted
into gold. With gold we not only do whatever we please in this
world, but we can even employ it to snatch souls from Purgatory,
and to people Paradise." These words bear the stamp of the age in
which Columbus lived; but we are surprised to see this pompous
eulogium of riches written by a man whose whole life was marked by
the most noble disinterestedness.
The conquest of the province of Venezuela having been begun at its
western extremity, the neighbouring mountains of Coro, Tocuyo, and
Barquisimeto, first attracted the attention of the Conquistadores.
These mountains join the Cordilleras of New Grenada (those of Santa
Fe, Pamplona, la Grita, and Merida) to the littoral chain of
Caracas. It is a land the more interesting in a geognostical point
of view, as no map has yet made known the mountainous ramifications
which the paramos of Niquitao and Las Rosas send out towards the
north-east. Between Tocuyo, Araure, and Barquisimeto, rises the
group of the Altar Mountains, connected on the south-east with the
paramo of Las Rosas. A branch of the Altar stretches north-east by
San Felipe el Fuerte, joining the granitic mountains of the coast
near Porto Cabello. The other branch takes an eastward direction
towards Nirgua and Tinaco, and joins the chain of the interior,
that of Yusma, Villa de Cura, and Sabana de Ocumare.
The region we have been here describing separates the waters which
flow to the Orinoco from those which run into the immense lake of
Maracaybo and the Caribbean Sea. It includes climates which may be
termed temperate rather than hot; and it is looked upon in the
country, notwithstanding the distance of more than a hundred
leagues, as a prolongation of the metalliferous soil of Pamplona.
It was in the group of the western mountains of Venezuela, that the
Spaniards, in the year 1551, worked the gold mine of Buria,* (*
Real de Minas de San Felipe de Buria.) which was the origin of the
foundation of the town of Barquisimeto.* (* Nueva Segovia.) But
these works, like many other mines successively opened, were soon
abandoned. Here, as in all the mountains of Venezuela, the produce
of the ore has been found to be very variable. The lodes are very
often divided, or they altogether cease; and the metals appear only
in kidney-ores, and present the most delusive appearances. It is,
however, only in this group of mountains of San Felipe and
Barquisimeto, that the working of mines has been continued till the
present time. Those of Aroa, near San Felipe el Fuerte, situated in
the centre of a very insalubrious country, are the only mines which
are wrought in the whole capitania-general of Caracas. They yield a
small quantity of copper.
Next to the works at Buria, near Barquisimeto, those of the valley
of Caracas, and of the mountains near the capital, are the most
ancient. Francisco Faxardo and his wife Isabella, of the nation of
the Guaiquerias,* often visited the table-land where the capital of
Venezuela is now situated. (* Faxardo and his wife were the
founders of the town of the Collado, now called Caravalleda.) They
had given this table-land the name of Valle de San Francisco; and
having seen some bits of gold in the hands of the natives, Faxardo
succeeded, in the year 1560, in discovering the mines of Los
Teques,* to the south-west of Caracas, near the group of the
mountains of Cocuiza, which separate the valleys of Caracas and
Aragua. (* Thirteen years later, in 1573, Gabriel de Avila, one of
the alcaldes of the new town of Caracas, renewed the working of
these mines, which were from that time called the "Real de Minas de
Nuestra Senora." Probably this same Avila, on account of a few
farms which he possessed in the mountains adjacent to La Guayra and
Caracas, has occasioned the Cumbre to receive the name of Montana
de Avila. This name has subsequently been applied erroneously to
the Silla, and to all the chain which extends towards cape Codera.)
It is thought that in the first of these valleys, near Baruta,
south of the village of Valle, the natives had made some
excavations in veins of auriferous quartz; and that, when the
Spaniards first settled there, and founded the town of Caracas,
they filled the shafts, which had been dry, with water. It is now
impossible to ascertain this fact; but it is certain that, long
before the Conquest, grains of gold were a medium of exchange, I do
not say generally, but among certain nations of the New Continent.
They gave gold for the purchase of pearls; and it does not appear
extraordinary, that, after having for a long time picked up grains
of gold in the rivulets, people who had fixed habitations, and were
devoted to agriculture, should have tried to trace the auriferous
veins in the superior surface of the soil. The mines of Los Teques
could not be peaceably wrought, till the defeat of the Cacique
Guaycaypuro, a celebrated chief of the Teques, who long contested
with the Spaniards the possession of the province of Venezuela.
We have yet to mention a third point to which the attention of the
Conquistadores was called by indications of mines, so early as the
end of the sixteenth century. In following the valley of Caracas
eastward beyond Caurimare, on the road to Caucagua, we reach a
mountainous and woody country, where a great quantity of charcoal
is now made, and which anciently bore the name of the Province of
Los Mariches. In these eastern mountains of Venezuela, the gneiss
passes into the state of talc. It contains, as at Salzburg, lodes
of auriferous quartz. The works anciently begun in those mines have
often been abandoned and resumed.
The mines of Caracas were forgotten during more than a hundred
years. But at a period comparatively recent, about the end of the
last century, an Intendant of Venezuela, Don Jose Avalo, again fell
into the illusions which had flattered the cupidity of the
Conquistadores. He fancied that all the mountains near the capital
contained great metallic riches. Some Mexican miners were engaged,
and their operations were directed to the ravine of Tipe, and the
ancient mines of Baruta to the south of Caracas, where the Indians
gather even now some little gold-washings. But the zeal which had
prompted the enterprise soon diminished, and after much useless
expense, the working of the mines of Caracas was totally abandoned.
A small quantity of auriferous pyrites, sulphuretted silver, and a
little native gold, were found; but these were only feeble
indications; and in a country where labour is extremely dear, there
was no inducement to pursue works so little productive.
We visited the ravine of Tipe, situated in that part of the valley
which opens in the direction of Cabo Blanco. Proceeding from
Caracas, we traverse, in the direction of the great barracks of San
Carlos, a barren and rocky soil. Only a very few plants of Argemone
mexicana are to be found. The gneiss appears everywhere above
ground. We might have fancied ourselves on the table-land of
Freiberg. We crossed first the little rivulet of Agua Salud, a
limpid stream, which has no mineral taste, and then the Rio
Garaguata. The road is commanded on the right by the Cerro de Avila
and the Cumbre; and on the left, by the mountains of Aguas Negras.
This defile is very interesting in a geological point of view. At
this spot the valley of Caracas communicates, by the valleys of
Tacagua and of Tipe, with the coast near Catia. A ridge of rock,
the summit of which is forty toises above the bottom of the valley
of Caracas, and more than three hundred toises above the valley of
Tacagua, divides the waters which flow into the Rio Guayra and
towards Cabo Blanco. On this point of division, at the entrance of
the branch, the view is highly pleasing. The climate changes as we
descend westward. In the valley of Tacagua we found some new
habitations, and also conucos of maize and plantains. A very
extensive plantation of tuna, or cactus, stamps this barren country
with a peculiar character. The cactuses reach the height of fifteen
feet, and grow in the form of candelabra, like the euphorbia of
Africa. They are cultivated for the purpose of selling their
refreshing fruits in the market of Caracas. The variety which has
no thorns is called, strangely enough, in the colonies, tuna de
Espana (Spanish cactus). We measured, at the same place, magueys or
agaves, the long stems of which, laden with flowers, were
forty-four feet high. However common this plant is become in the
south of Europe, the native of a northern climate is never weary of
admiring the rapid development of a liliaceous plant, which
contains at once a sweet juice and astringent and caustic liquids,
employed to cauterize wounds.
We found several veins of quartz in the valley of Tipe visible
above the soil. They contained pyrites, carbonated iron-ore, traces
of sulphuretted silver (glasserz), and grey copper-ore (fahlerz).
The works which had been undertaken, either for extracting the ore,
or exploring the nature of its bed, appeared to be very
superficial. The earth falling in had filled up those excavations,
and we could not judge of the richness of the lode. Notwithstanding
the expense incurred under the intendancy of Don Jose Avalo, the
great question whether the province of Venezuela contains mines
rich enough to be worked, is yet problematical. Though in countries
where hands are wanting, the culture of the soil demands
unquestionably the first care of the government, yet the example of
New Spain sufficiently proves that mining is not always
unfavourable to the progress of agriculture. The best-cultivated
Mexican lands, those which remind the traveller of the most
beautiful districts of France and the south of Germany, extend from
Silao towards the Villa of Leon: they are in the neighbourhood of
the mines of Guanaxuato, which alone furnish a sixth part of all
the silver of the New World.</div></body></text></TEI>