<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="3">
CHAPTER III.

The Mass of the Earth.

We shall now consider the adaptation which may,
as we conceive, be traced in the amount of some of
the quantities which determine the course of events
in the organic world; and especially in the amount
of the forces which are in action. The life of vegetables
and animals implies a constant motion of their
fluid parts, and this motion must be produced by
forces which urge or draw the particles of the fluids.
The positions of the parts of vegetables are also the
result of the flexibility and elasticity of their substance;
the voluntary motions of animals are produced
by the tension of the muscles. But in all those
cases, the effect really produced depends upon the
force of gravity also; and in order that the motions
and positions may be such as answer their purpose,
the forces which produce them must have a due proportion
to the force of gravity. In human works, if,
for instance, we have a fluid to raise, or a weight to
move, some calculation is requisite, in order to determine
the power which we must use, relatively to
the work which is to be done: we have a mechanical
problem to solve, in order that we may adjust the
one to the other. And the same adjustment, the
same result of a comparison of quantities, manifests
itself in the relation which the forces of the organic
world bear to the force of gravity.
[44]
The force of gravity might, so far as we can judge,
have been different from what it now is. It depends
upon the mass of the earth; and this mass is one of
the elements of the solar system, which is not determined
by any cosmical necessity of which we are
aware. The masses of the several planets are very
different, and do not appear to follow any determinate
rule, except that upon the whole those nearer
to the sun appear to be smaller, and those nearer the
outskirts of the system to be larger. We cannot see
any thing which would have prevented either the
size or the density of the earth from being different,
to a very great extent, from what they are.
Now, it will be very obvious that if the intensity
of gravity were to be much increased, or much diminished,
if every object were to become twice as
heavy or only half as heavy as it now is, all the
forces, both of involuntary and voluntary motion
which produce the present orderly and suitable results
by being properly proportioned to the resistance
which they experience, would be thrown off their
balance; they would produce motions too quick or
too slow, wrong positions, jerks and stops, instead of
steady, well conducted movements. The universe
would be like a machine ill regulated; every thing
would go wrong; repeated collisions and a rapid
disorganization must be the consequence. We will,
however, attempt to illustrate one or two of the cases
in which this would take place, by pointing out
forces which act in the organic world, and which
are adjusted to the force of gravity.
1. The first instance we shall take, is the force
manifested by the ascent of the sap in vegetables. It
appears by a multitude of indisputable experiments,
(among the rest, those of Hales, Mirbel, and Dutrochet,)
that all plants imbibe moisture by their roots,
and pump it up, by some internal force, into every
part of their frame, distributing it into every leaf. It
will be easily conceived that this operation must require
a very considerable mechanical force; for the[45]
fluid must be sustained as if it were a single column
reaching to the top of the tree. The division into
minute parts and distribution through small vessels
does not at all diminish the total force requisite to
raise it. If, for instance, the tree be thirty-three feet
high, the pressure must be fifteen pounds upon every
square inch in the section of the vessels of the bottom
in order merely to support the sap. And it is
not only supported, but propelled upwards with great
force, so as to supply the constant evaporation of the
leaves. The pumping power of the tree must, therefore,
be very considerable.
That this power is great, has been confirmed by
various curious experiments, especially by those of
Hales. He measured the force with which the stems
and branches of trees draw the fluid from below, and
push it upwards. He found, for instance, that a vine
in the bleeding season could push up its sap in a glass
tube to the height of twenty-one feet above the stump
of an amputated branch.
The force which produces this effect is part of the
economy of the vegetable world; and it is clear that
the due operation of the force depends upon its being
rightly proportioned to the force of gravity. The
weight of the fluid must be counterbalanced, and an
excess of force must exist to produce the motion upwards.
In the common course of vegetable life, the
rate of ascent of the sap is regulated, on the one
hand, by the upward pressure of the vegetable
power, and on the other, by the amount of the gravity
of the fluid, along with the other resistances,
which are to be overcome. If, therefore, we suppose
gravity to increase, the rapidity of this vegetable
circulation will diminish, and the rate at which
this function proceeds, will not correspond either to
the course of the seasons, or the other physiological
processes with which this has to co-operate. We
might easily conceive such an increase of gravity as
would stop the vital movements of the plant in a
very short time. In like manner, a diminution of the[46]
gravity of the vegetable juices would accelerate the
rising of the sap, and would, probably, hurry and
overload the leaves and other organs, so as to interfere
with their due operation. Some injurious change,
at least, would take place.
Here, then, we have the forces of the minutest
parts of vegetables adjusted to the magnitude of the
whole mass of the earth on which they exist. There
is no apparent connexion between the quantity of
matter of the earth, and the force of imbibition of
the roots of a vine, or the force of propulsion of the
vessels of its branches. Yet, these things have such
a proportion as the well being of the vine requires.
How is this to be accounted for, but by supposing
that the circumstances under which the vine was to
grow, were attended to in devising its structure?
We have not here pretended to decide whether
this force of propulsion of vegetables is mechanical
or not, because the argument is the same for our
purpose on either supposition. Some very curious
experiments have recently been made, (by M. Dutrochet,)
which are supposed to show that the force
is mechanical; that when two different fluids are separated
by a thin membrane, a force which M. Dutrochet
calls endosmose urges one fluid through the
membrane: and that the roots of plants are provided
with small vesicles which act the part of such a
membrane. M. Poisson has further attempted to
show that this force of endosmose may be considered
as a particular modification of capillary action. If
these views be true, we have here two mechanical
forces, capillary action and gravity, which are adjusted
to each other in the manner precisely suited
to the welfare of vegetables.
2. As another instance of adaptation between the
force of gravity and forces which exist in the vegetable
world, we may take the positions of flowers.
Some flowers grow with the hollow of their cup upwards:
others “hang the pensive head,” and turn
the opening downwards. Now of these “nodding[47]
flowers,” as Linnæus calls them, he observes that
they are such as have their pistil longer than the
stamens; and, in consequence of this position, the
dust from the anthers which are at the ends of the
stamens can fall upon the stigma or extremity of the
pistil; which process is requisite for making the
flower fertile. He gives as instances the flowers
campanula, leucoium, galanthus, fritillaria. Other
botanists have remarked that the position changes at
different periods of the flower’s progress. The pistil
of the Euphorbia (which is a little globe or germen
on 
a slender stalk) grows upright at first, and is taller
than the stamens: at the period suited to its fecundation,
the stalk bends under the weight of the ball
at its extremity, so as to depress the germen below
the stamens; after this it again becomes erect, the
globe being now a fruit filled with fertile seeds.
The positions in all these cases depend upon the
length and flexibility of the stalk which supports the
flower, or in the case of the Euphorbia, the germen.
It is clear that a very slight alteration in the force of
gravity, or in the stiffness of the stalk, would entirely
alter the position of the flower cup, and thus make
the continuation of the species impossible. We have
therefore here a little mechanical contrivance, which
would have been frustrated if the proper intensity of
gravity had not been assumed in the reckoning. An
earth greater or smaller, denser or rarer than the
one on which we live, would require a change in the
structure and strength of the footstalks of all the little
flowers that hang their heads under our hedges.
There is something curious in thus considering the
whole mass of the earth from pole to pole, and from
circumference to centre, as employed in keeping a
snowdrop in the position most suited to the promotion
of its vegetable health.
It would be easy to mention many other parts of
the economy of vegetable life, which depend for
their use on their adaptation to the force of gravity.
Such are the forces and conditions which determine[48]
the positions of leaves and of branches. Such again
those parts of the vegetable constitution which have
reference to the pressure of the atmosphere; for differences
in this pressure appear to exercise a powerful
influence on the functions of plants, and to require
differences of structure. But we pass over these considerations.
The slightest attention to the relations
of natural objects will show that the subject is inexhaustible;
and all that we can or need do is to
give a few examples, such as may show the nature
of the impression which the examination of the universe
produces.
3. Another instance of the adjustment of organic
structure to the force of gravity may be pointed out
in the muscular powers of animals. If the force of
gravity were increased in any considerable proportion
at the surface of the earth, it is manifest that all
the swiftness, and strength, and grace of 
animal motions must disappear. If, for instance, the earth were
as large as Jupiter, gravity would be eleven times
what it is, the lightness of the fawn, the speed of the
hare, the spring of the tiger, could no longer exist
with the existing muscular powers of those animals;
for man to lift himself upright, or to crawl from
place to place, would be a labour slower and more
painful than the motions of the sloth. The density
and pressure of the air too would be increased to an
intolerable extent, and the operation of respiration,
and others, which depend upon these mechanical properties,
would be rendered laborious, ineffectual, and
probably impossible.
If, on the other hand, the force of gravity were
much lessened, inconveniences of an opposite kind
would occur. The air would be too thin to breathe;
the weight of our bodies, and of all the substances
surrounding us, would become too slight to resist
the perpetually occurring causes of derangement and
unsteadiness: we should feel a want of ballast in our
movements.
It has sometimes been maintained by fanciful theorists[49]
that the earth is merely a shell, and that the
central parts are hollow. All the reasons we can
collect appear to be in favour of its being a solid
mass, considerably denser than any known rock. If
this be so, and if we suppose the interior to be at any
time scooped out, so as to leave only such a shell as
the above mentioned speculators have asserted, we
should not be left in ignorance of the change, though
the appearance of the surface might remain the
same. We should discover the want of the usual
force of gravity, by the instability of all about us.
Things would not lie where we placed them, but
would slide away with the slightest push. We should
have a difficulty in standing or walking, something
like what we have on ship-board when the deck is
inclined; and we should stagger helplessly through
an atmosphere thinner than that which oppresses the
respiration of the traveller on the tops of the highest
mountains.
We see therefore that those dark and unknown
central portions of the earth, which are placed far
beyond the reach of the miner and the geologist, and
of which man will probably never know anything
directly, are not to be considered as quite disconnected
with us, as deposits of useless lumber without
effect or purpose. We feel their influence on every
step we take and on every breath we draw; and the
powers we possess, and the comforts we enjoy would
be unprofitable to us, if they had not been prepared
with a reference to those as well as to the near and
visible portions of the earth’s mass.
The arbitrary quantity, therefore, of which we
have been treating, the intensity of the force of gravity,
appears to have been taken account of, in establishing
the laws of those forces by which the processes
of vegetable and animal life are carried on.
And this leads us inevitably, we conceive, to the belief
of a supreme contriving mind, by which these
laws were thus devised and thus established.
</div></body></text></TEI>