<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="127">CHAPTER V.
Examination of the Nervous System, and Consequent
Speculations.

Sect. 1.—The Examination of the
Nervous System.
IT is hardly necessary to
illustrate by further examples the manner in which anatomical
observation has produced conjectural and hypothetical attempts to
connect structure and action with some 462 higher principle, of a more peculiarly
physiological kind. But it may still be instructive to notice a case
in which the principle, which is thus brought into view, is far more
completely elevated above the domain of matter and mechanism than in
those we have yet considered;—a case where we have not only
Irritation, but Sensation;—not only Life, but Consciousness and
Will. A part of science in which suggestions present themselves,
brings us, in a very striking manner, to the passage from the physical
to the hyperphysical sciences.
We have seen already (chap. i.) that Galen
and his predecessors had satisfied themselves that the nerves are the
channels of perception; a doctrine which had been distinctly taught by
Herophilus61 in the Alexandrian school. Herophilus,
however, still combined, under the common name of Nerves, the Tendons;
though he distinguished such Nerves from those which arise from the
brain and the spinal marrow, and which are subservient to the will. In
Galen’s time this subject had been prosecuted more into detail. That
anatomist has left a Treatise expressly upon The Anatomy of the
Nerves; in which he describes the successive Pairs of
Nerves: thus, the First Pair are the visual nerves: and we see, in the
language which Galen uses, the evidence of the care and interest with
which he had himself examined them. “These nerves,” he says, “are not
resolved into many fibres, like all the other nerves, when they reach
the organs to which they belong; but spread out in a different and
very remarkable manner, which it is not easy to describe or to
believe, without actually seeing it.” He then gives a description of
the retina. In like manner he describes the Second Pair, which is
distributed to the muscles of the eyes; the Third and Fourth Pairs,
which go to the tongue and palate; and so on to the Seventh Pair. This
division into Seven Pairs was established by Marinus,62 but Vesalius found it to be incomplete.
The examination which is the basis of the anatomical enumeration of
the Nerves at present recognized was that of Willis. His book,
entitled Cerebri Anatome, cui accessit Nervorum descriptio et
usus, appeared at London in 1664. He made important additions to
the knowledge of this subject.63 Thus he is the
first who describes in a distinct manner what has been called the
Nervous Centre,64 the pyramidal eminences which,
according to more recent anatomists, are the communication of the
brain with the spinal marrow: and of which the Decussation,
described by Santorini, affords the explanation of the action of a
part 463 of the
brain upon the nerves of the opposite side. Willis proved also that
the Rete Mirabile, the remarkable net-work of arteries at the
base of the brain, observed by the ancients in ruminating animals,
does not exist in man. He described the different Pairs of Nerves with
more care than his predecessors; and his mode of numbering them is
employed up to the present time. He calls the Olfactory Nerves the
First Pair; previously to him, these were not reckoned a Pair: and
thus the optic nerves were, as we have seen, called the first. He
added the Sixth and the Ninth Pairs, which the anatomists who preceded
him did not reckon. Willis also examined carefully the different
Ganglions, or knots which occur upon the nerves. He traced them
wherever they were to be found, and he gave a general figure of what
Cuvier calls the nervous skeleton, very superior to that of
Vesalius, which was coarse and inexact. Willis also made various
efforts to show the connexion of the parts of the brain. In the
earlier periods of anatomy, the brain had been examined by slicing it,
so as to obtain a section. Varolius endeavored to unravel it, and was
followed by Willis. Vicq d’Azyr, in modern times, has carried the
method of section to greater perfection than had before been given
it;65 as Vieussens and Gall have done with
respect to the method of Varolius and Willis. Recently Professor
Chaussier66 makes three kinds of Nerves:—the
Encephalic, which proceed from the head, and are twelve on each
side;—the Rachidian, which proceed from the spinal
marrow, and are thirty on each side;—and Compound Nerves,
among which is the Great Sympathetic Nerve.
61 Spr. i. 534.
62 Dic. Sc. Med. xxxv.
467.
63 Cuv. Sc. Nat. p. 385.
64 Ibid.
65 Cuv. p. 40.
66 Dict. Sc. Nat. xxxv.
467.
One of the most important steps ever made in our knowledge of the
nerves is, the distinction which Bichat is supposed to have
established, of a ganglionic system, and a cerebral
system. And we may add, to the discoveries in nervous anatomy, the
remarkable one, made in our own time, that the two offices—of
conducting the motive impressions from the central seat of the will to
the muscles, and of propagating sensations from the surface of the
body and the external organs of sense to the sentient
mind—reside in two distinct portions of the nervous
substance:—a discovery which has been declared67 to be “doubtless the most important
accession to physiological (anatomical) knowledge since the time of
Harvey.” This doctrine was first published and taught by Sir Charles
Bell: after an interval of some 464 years, it was more distinctly delivered
in the publications of Mr. John Shaw, Sir C. Bell’s pupil. Soon
afterwards it was further confirmed, and some part of the evidence
corrected, by Mr. Mayo, another pupil of Sir C. Bell, and by M.
Majendie.68
67 Dr. Charles Henry’s Report of
Brit. Assoc. iii. p. 62.
68 As authority for the expressions
which I have now used in the text, I will mention Müller’s Manual
of Physiology (4th edition, 1844). In Book iii. Section 2, Chap.
i., “On the Nerves of Sensation and Motion,” Müller says, “Charles
Bell was the first who had the ingenious thought that the posterior
roots of the nerves of the spine—those which are furnished with
a ganglion—govern sensation only; that the anterior roots are
appointed for motion; and that the primitive fibres of these roots,
after being united in a single nervous cord, are mingled together in
order to supply the wants of the skin and muscles. He developed this
idea in a little work (An Idea of a new Anatomy of the Brain,
London, 1811), which was not intended to travel beyond the circle of
his friends.” Müller goes on to say, that eleven years later, Majendie
prosecuted the same theory. But Mr. Alexander Shaw, in 1839, published
A Narrative of the Discoveries of Sir Charles Bell in the Nervous
System, in which it appears that Sir Charles Bell had further
expounded his views in his lectures to his pupils (p. 89), and that
one of these, Mr. John Shaw, had in various publications, in 1821 and
1822, further insisted upon the same views; especially in a Memoir
On Partial Paralysis (p. 75). MM. Mayo and Majendie both
published Memoirs in August, 1822; and these and subsequent works
confirmed the doctrine of Bell. Mr. Alexander Shaw states (p. 97),
that a mistake of Sir Charles Bell’s, in an experiment which he had
made to prove his doctrine, was discovered through the joint labors of
M. Majendie and Mr. Mayo.
Sect. 2.—The Consequent Speculations. Hypotheses
respecting Life, Sensation, and Volition.
I shall not attempt to
explain the details of these anatomical investigations; and I shall
speak very briefly of the speculations which have been suggested by
the obvious subservience of the nerves to life, sensation, and
volition. Some general inferences from their distribution were
sufficiently obvious; as, that the seat of sensation and volition is
in the brain. Galen begins his work, On the Anatomy of the
Nerves, thus: “That none of the members of the animal either
exercises voluntary motion, or receives sensation, and that if the
nerve be cut, the part immediately becomes inert and insensible, is
acknowledged by all physicians. But that the origin of the nerves is
partly from the brain, and partly from the spinal marrow, I proceed to
explain.” And in his work On the Doctrines of Plato and
Hippocrates, he proves at 465 great length69 that the brain
is the origin of sensation and motion, refuting the opinions of
earlier days, as that of Chrysippus,70 who placed the
hegemonic or master-principle of the soul, in the heart. But
though Galen thought that the rational soul resides in the brain, he
was disposed to agree with the poets and philosophers, according to
whom the heart is the seat of courage and anger, and the liver the
seat of love.71 The faculties of the soul were by
succeeding physiologists confined to the brain; but the disposition
still showed itself, to attribute to them distinct localities. Thus
Willis72 places the imagination in the corpus
callosum, the memory in the folds of the hemispheres, the
perception in the corpus striatum. In more recent times, a
system founded upon a similar view has been further developed by Gall
and his followers. The germ of Gall’s system may be considered as
contained in that of Willis; for Gall represents the hemispheres as
the folds of a great membrane which is capable of being unwrapped and
spread out, and places the different faculties of man in the different
regions of this membrane. The chasm which intervenes between matter
and motion on the one side, and thought and feeling on the other, is
brought into view by all such systems; but none of the hypotheses
which they involve can effectually bridge it over.
69 Lib. vii.
70 Lib. iii. c. 1.
71 Lib. vi. c. 8.
72 Cuv. Sc. Nat. p. 384.
The same observation may be made respecting the attempts to explain
the manner in which the nerves operate as the instruments of sensation
and volition. Perhaps a real step was made by Glisson,73 professor of medicine in the University
of Cambridge, who distinguished in the fibres of the muscles of motion
a peculiar property, different from any merely mechanical or physical
action. His work On the Nature of the Energetic Substance, or on
the Life of Nature and of its Three First Faculties, The Perceptive,
Appetitive, and Motive, which was published in 1672, is rather
metaphysical than physiological. But the principles which he
establishes in this treatise he applies more specially to physiology
in a treatise On the Stomach and Intestines (Amsterdam, 1677).
In this he ascribes to the fibres of the animal body a peculiar power
which he calls Irritability. He divides irritation into
natural, vital, and animal; and he points out, though briefly, the
gradual differences of irritability in different organs. “It is hardly
comprehensible,” says Sprengel,74 “how this 466 lucid and excellent
notion of the Cambridge teacher was not accepted with greater
alacrity, and further unfolded by his contemporaries.” It has,
however, since been universally adopted.
73 Cuv. Sc. Nat. p. 434.
74 Spr. iv. 47.
But though the discrimination of muscular irritability as a
peculiar power might be a useful step in physiological research, the
explanations hitherto offered, of the way in which the nerves operate
on this irritability, and discharge their other offices, present only
a series of hypotheses. Glisson75 assumed the
existence of certain vital spirits, which, according to him, are a
mild, sweet fluid, resembling the spirituous part of white of egg, and
residing in the nerves.—This hypothesis, of a very subtle humor
or spirit existing in the nerves, was indeed very early taken up.76 This nervous spirit had been compared
to air by Erasistratus, Asclepiades, Galen, and others. The chemical
tendencies of the seventeenth century led to its being described as
acid, sulphureous or nitrous. At the end of that century, the
hypothesis of an ether attracted much notice as a means of
accounting for many phenomena; and this ether was identified with the
nervous fluid. Newton himself inclines to this view, in the remarkable
Queries which are annexed to his Opticks. After ascribing many
physical effects to his ether, he adds (Query 23), “Is not vision
performed chiefly by the vibrations of this medium, excited in the
bottom of the eye by the rays of light, and propagated through the
solid, pellucid, and uniform capillamenta of the nerves into the place
of sensation?” And (Query 24), “Is not animal motion performed by the
vibrations of this medium, excited in the brain by the power of the
will, and propagated from thence through the capillamenta of the
nerves into the muscles for contracting and dilating them?” And an
opinion approaching this has been adopted by some of the greatest of
modern physiologists; as Haller, who says,77 that, though it
is more easy to find what this nervous spirit is not than what it is,
he conceives that, while it must be far too fine to be perceived by
the sense, it must yet be more gross than fire, magnetism, or
electricity; so that it may be contained in vessels, and confined by
boundaries. And Cuvier speaks to the same effect:78 “There is a
great probability that it is by an imponderable fluid that the nerve
acts on the fibre, and that this nervous fluid is drawn from the
blood, and secreted by the medullary matter.”
75 Spr. iv. 38.
76 Haller, Physiol. iv.
365.
77 Physiol. iv. 381, lib. x.
sect. viii. § 15.
78 Règne Animal, Introd. p.
30.
Without presuming to dissent from such authorities on a point of
467 anatomical
probability, we may venture to observe, that these hypotheses do not
tend at all to elucidate the physiological principle which is here
involved; for this principle cannot be mechanical, chemical, or
physical, and therefore cannot be better understood by embodying it in
a fluid; the difficulty we have in conceiving what the moving force
is, is not got rid of by explaining the machinery by which it is
merely transferred. In tracing the phenomena of sensation and
volition to their cause, it is clear that we must call in some
peculiar and hyperphysical principle. The hypothesis of a fluid is not
made more satisfactory by attenuating the fluid; it becomes subtle,
spirituous, ethereal, imponderable, to no purpose; it must cease to be
a fluid, before its motions can become sensation and volition. This,
indeed, is acknowledged by most physiologists; and strongly stated by
Cuvier.79 “The impression of external objects
upon the me, the production of a sensation, of
an image, is a mystery impenetrable for our thoughts.” And in several
places, by the use of this peculiar phrase, “the me,” (le
moi) for the sentient and volent faculty, he marks, with peculiar
appropriateness and force, that phraseology borrowed from the world of
matter will, in this subject, no longer answer our purpose. We have
here to go from Nouns to Pronouns, from Things to Persons. We pass
from the Body to the Soul, from Physics to Metaphysics. We are come to
the borders of material philosophy; the next step is into the domain
of Thought and Mind. Here, therefore, we begin to feel that we have
reached the boundaries of our present subject. The examination of that
which lies beyond them must be reserved for a philosophy of another
kind, and for the labors of the future; if we are ever enabled to make
the attempt to extend into that loftier and wider scene, the
principles which we gather on the ground we are now laboriously
treading.
79 Règne Animal, Introd. p.
47.
Such speculations as I have quoted respecting the nervous fluid,
proceeding from some of the greatest philosophers who ever lived,
prove only that hitherto the endeavor to comprehend the mystery of
perception and will, of life and thought, have been fruitless and
vain. Many anatomical truths have been discovered, but, so far as our
survey has yet gone, no genuine physiological principle. All the
trains of physiological research which we have followed have begun in
exact examination of organization and function, and have ended in wide
conjectures and arbitrary hypotheses. The stream of knowledge in all
such cases is 468
clear and lively at its outset; but, instead of reaching the great
ocean of the general truths of science, it is gradually spread abroad
among sands and deserts till its course can be traced no longer.
Hitherto, therefore, we must consider that we have had to tell the
story of the failures of physiological speculation. But of
late there have come into view and use among physiologists certain
principles which may be considered as peculiar to organized subjects;
and of which the introduction forms a real advance in organical
science. Though these have hitherto been very imperfectly developed,
we must endeavor to exhibit, in some measure, their history and
bearing.
[2nd Ed.] [In order to show that I am not unaware how imperfect the
sketch given in this work is, as a History of Physiology, I may refer
to the further discussions on these subjects contained in the
Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences, Book ix. I have there
(Chap. ii.) noticed the successive Biological Hypotheses of the
Mystical, the Iatrochemical, and Iatromathematical Schools, the
Vital-Fluid School, and the Psychical School. I have (Chaps. iii.,
iv., v.) examined several of the attempts which have been made to
analyze the Idea of Life, to classify Vital Functions, and to form
Ideas of Separate Vital Forces. I have considered in particular, the
attempts to form a distinct conception of Assimilation and Secretion,
of Generation, and of Voluntary Motion; and I have (Chap. vi.) further
discussed the Idea of Final Causes as employed in Biology.]
</div></body></text></TEI>