<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="18"> 

CHAPTER VIII.
Methods of Induction depending on Resemblance.


Aphorism XLIX.
The Law of Continuity is this:—that a quantity cannot
pass from one amount to another by any change of conditions,
without passing through all intermediate magnitudes
according to the intermediate conditions. This Law may
often be employed to disprove distinctions which have no real
foundation.
Aphorism L.
The Method of Gradation consists in taking a number of
stages of a property in question, intermediate between two
extreme cases which appear to be different. This Method is
employed to determine whether the extreme cases are really
distinct or not.
Aphorism LI.
The Method of Gradation, applied to decide the question,
whether the existing geological phenomena arise from existing
causes, leads to this result:—That the phenomena do appear
to arise from Existing Causes, but that the action of existing
causes may, in past times, have transgressed, to any extent,
their recorded limits of intensity.
Aphorism LII.
The Method of Natural Classification consists in classing
cases, not according to any assumed Definition, but according
to the connexion of the facts themselves, so as to make them
the means of asserting general truths. 221
Sect. I.—The Law of Continuity.

1. THE
Law of Continuity is applicable to quantity
primarily, and therefore might be associated
with the methods treated of in the last chapter: but
inasmuch as its inferences are made by a transition from
one degree to another among contiguous cases, it will
be found to belong more properly to the Methods of
Induction of which we have now to speak.
The Law of Continuity consists in this proposition,—That
a quantity cannot pass from one amount to
another by any change of conditions, without passing
through all intermediate degrees of magnitude according
to the intermediate conditions. And this law may
often be employed to correct inaccurate inductions,
and to reject distinctions which have no real foundation
in nature. For example, the Aristotelians made
a distinction between motions according to nature, (as
that of a body falling vertically downwards,) and motions
contrary to nature, (as that of a body moving
along a horizontal plane:) the former, they held, became
naturally quicker and quicker, the latter naturally
slower and slower. But to this it might be replied,
that a horizontal line may pass, by gradual motion,
through various inclined positions, to a vertical
position: and thus the retarded motion may pass into the
accelerated; and hence there must be some inclined
plane on which the motion downwards is naturally
uniform: which is false, and therefore the distinction
of such kinds of motion is unfounded. Again, the
proof of the First Law of Motion depends upon the
Law of Continuity: for since, by diminishing the
resistance to a body moving on a horizontal plane, we
diminish the retardation, and this without limit, the
law of continuity will bring us at the same time to
the case of no resistance and to the case of no retardation.
2. The Law of Continuity is asserted by Galileo
in a particular application; and the assertion which it 222
suggests is by him referred to
Plato;—namely36 that a
moveable body cannot pass from rest to a determinate
degree of velocity without passing through all smaller
degrees of velocity. This law, however, was first asserted
in a more general and abstract form by
Leibnitz37:
and was employed by him to show that the laws
of motion propounded by Descartes must be false. The
Third Cartesian Law of Motion was
this38: that when
one moving body meets another, if the first body have
a less momentum than the second, it will be reflected
with its whole motion: but if the first have a greater
momentum than the second, it will lose a part of its
motion, which it will transfer to the second. Now
each of these cases leads, by the Law of Continuity, to
the case in which the two bodies have equal momentums:
but in this case, by the first part of the law the
body would retain all its motion; and by the second
part of the law it would lose a portion of it: hence the
Cartesian Law is false.</div></body></text></TEI>