<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="35">CHAPTER III.
Sequel to the Epoch of Newton.—Reception of the
Newtonian Theory.

Sect. 1.—General Remarks.
THE doctrine of universal
gravitation, like other great steps in science, required a certain
time to make its way into men’s minds; and had to be confirmed,
illustrated, and completed, by the labors of succeeding philosophers.
As the discovery itself was great beyond former example, the features
of the natural sequel to the discovery were also on a gigantic scale;
and many vast and laborious trains of research, each of which might,
in itself, be considered as forming a wide science, and several of
which have occupied many profound and zealous inquirers from that time
to our own day, come before us as parts only of the verification of
Newton’s Theory. Almost every thing that has been done, and is doing,
in astronomy, falls inevitably under this description; and it is only
when the astronomer travels to the very limits of his vast field of
labor, that he falls in with phenomena which do not acknowledge the
jurisdiction of the Newtonian legislation. We must give some account
of the events of this part of the history of astronomy; but our
narrative must necessarily be extremely brief and imperfect; for the
subject is most large and copious, and our limits are fixed and
narrow. We have here to do with the history of discoveries, only so
far as it illustrates their philosophy. And though the 421 astronomical
discoveries of the last century are by no means poor, even in interest
of this kind, the generalizations which they involve are far less
important for our object, in consequence of being included in a
previous generalization. Newton shines out so brightly, that all who
follow seem faint and dim. It is not precisely the case which the poet
describes—


As in a theatre the eyes of men,
After some well-graced actor leaves the
stage,
Are idly bent on him that enters next,
Thinking his prattle to be tedious:
but our eyes are at least less intently bent on the
astronomers who succeeded, and we attend to their communications with
less curiosity, because we know the end, if not the course of their
story; we know that their speeches have all closed with Newton’s
sublime declaration, asserted in some new form.
Still, however, the account of the verification and extension of
any great discovery is a highly important part of its history. In this
instance it is most important; both from the weight and dignity of the
theory concerned, and the ingenuity and extent of the methods
employed: and, of course, so long as the Newtonian theory still
required verification, the question of the truth or falsehood of such
a grand system of doctrines could not but excite the most intense
curiosity. In what I have said, I am very far from wishing to
depreciate the value of the achievements of modern astronomers, but it
is essential to my purpose to mark the subordination of narrower to
wider truths—the different character and import of the labors of
those who come before and after the promulgation of a master-truth.
With this warning I now proceed to my narrative.
Sect. 2.—Reception of the Newtonian Theory in
England.
There appears to be a popular persuasion
that great discoveries are usually received with a prejudiced and
contentious opposition, and the authors of them neglected or
persecuted. The reverse of this was certainly the case in England with
regard to the discoveries of Newton. As we have already seen, even
before they were published, they were proclaimed by Halley to be
something of transcendent value; and from the moment of their
appearance, they rapidly made their way from one class of thinkers to
another, nearly as fast as the nature of men’s intellectual capacity
allows. Halley, Wren, and all the leading 422 members of the Royal Society, appear to
have embraced the system immediately and zealously. Men whose pursuits
had lain rather in literature than in science, and who had not the
knowledge and habits of mind which the strict study of the system
required, adopted, on the credit of their mathematical friends, the
highest estimation of the Principia, and a strong regard for
its author, as Evelyn, Locke, and Pepys. Only five years after the
publication, the principles of the work were referred to from the
pulpit, as so incontestably proved that they might be made the basis
of a theological argument. This was done by Dr. Bentley, when he
preached the Boyle’s Lectures in London, in 1692. Newton himself, from
the time when his work appeared, is never mentioned except in terms of
profound admiration; as, for instance, when he is called by Dr.
Bentley, in his sermon,53 “That very excellent and divine
theorist, Mr. Isaac Newton.” It appears to have been soon suggested,
that the Government ought to provide in some way for a person who was
so great an honor to the nation. Some delay took place with regard to
this; but, in 1695, his friend Mr. Montague, afterwards Earl of
Halifax, at that time Chancellor of the Exchequer, made him Warden of
the Mint; and in 1699, he succeeded to the higher office of Master of
the Mint, a situation worth £1200 or £1500 a year, which he filled to
the end of his life. In 1703, he became President of the Royal
Society, and was annually re-elected to this office during the
remaining twenty-five years of his life. In 1705, he was knighted in
the Master’s Lodge, at Trinity College, by Queen Anne, then on a visit
to the University of Cambridge. After the accession of George the
First, Newton’s conversation was frequently sought by the Princess,
afterwards Queen Caroline, who had a taste for speculative studies,
and was often heard to declare in public, that she thought herself
fortunate in living at a time which enabled her to enjoy the society
of so great a genius. His fame, and the respect paid him, went on
increasing to the end of his life; and when, in 1727, full of years
and glory, his earthly career was ended, his death was mourned as a
national calamity, with the forms usually confined to royalty. His
body lay in state in the Jerusalem chamber; his pall was borne by the
first nobles of the land  and his earthly remains were deposited in
the centre of Westminster Abbey, in the midst of the memorials of the
greatest and wisest men whom England has produced.
53 Serm. vii. 221.
It cannot be superfluous to say a word or two on the reception of
423 his philosophy
in the universities of England. These are often represented as places
where bigotry and ignorance resist, as long as it is possible to
resist, the invasion of new truths. We cannot doubt that such opinions
have prevailed extensively, when we find an intelligent and generally
temperate writer, like the late Professor Playfair of Edinburgh, so
far possessed by them, as to be incapable of seeing, or interpreting,
in any other way, any facts respecting Oxford and Cambridge. Yet,
notwithstanding these opinions, it will be found that, in the English
universities, new views, whether in science or in other subjects, have
been introduced as soon as they were clearly established;—that
they have been diffused from the few to the many more rapidly there
than elsewhere occurs;—and that from these points, the light of
newly-discovered truths has most usually spread over the land. In most
instances undoubtedly there has been something of a struggle, on such
occasions, between the old and the new opinions. Few men’s minds can
at once shake off a familiar and consistent system of doctrines, and
adopt a novel and strange set of principles as soon as presented; but
all can see that one change produces many, and that change, in itself,
is a source of inconvenience and danger. In the case of the admission
of the Newtonian opinions into Cambridge and Oxford, however, there
are no traces even of a struggle. Cartesianism had never struck its
roots deep in this country; that is, the peculiar hypotheses of
Descartes. The Cartesian books, such, for instance, as that of
Rohault, were indeed in use; and with good reason, for they contained
by far the best treatises on most of the physical sciences, such as
Mechanics, Hydrostatics, Optics, and Formal Astronomy, which could
then be found. But I do not conceive that the Vortices were ever dwelt
upon as a matter of importance in our academic teaching. At any rate,
if they were brought among us, they were soon dissipated. Newton’s
College, and his University, exulted in his fame, and did their utmost
to honor and aid him. He was exempted by the king from the obligation
of taking orders, under which the fellows of Trinity College in
general are; by his college he was relieved from all offices which
might interfere, however slightly, with his studious employments,
though he resided within the walls of the society thirty-five years,
almost without the interruption of a month.54 By the
University he was elected their representative in parliament in 1688,
424 and again in
1701; and though he was rejected in the dissolution of 1705, those who
opposed him acknowledged him55 to be “the glory
of the University and nation,” but considered the question as a
political one, and Newton as sent “to tempt them from their duty, by
the great and just veneration they had for him.” Instruments and other
memorials, valued because they belonged to him, are still preserved in
his college, along with the tradition of the chambers which he
occupied.
54 His name is nowhere found on the
college-books, as appointed to any of the offices which usually pass
down the list of resident fellows in rotation. This might be owing in
part, however, to his being Lucasian Professor. The constancy of his
residence in college appears from the exit and redit
book of that time, which is still preserved.
55 A pamphlet by Styan Thurlby.
The most active and powerful minds at Cambridge became at once
disciples and followers of Newton. Samuel Clarke, afterwards his
friend, defended in the public schools a thesis taken from his
philosophy, as early as 1694; and in 1697 published an edition of
Rohault’s Physics, with notes, in which Newton is frequently
referred to with expressions of profound respect, though the leading
doctrines of the Principia are not introduced till a later
edition, in 1703. In 1699, Bentley, whom we have already mentioned as
a Newtonian, became Master of Trinity College; and in the same year,
Whiston, another of Newton’s disciples, was appointed his deputy as
professor of mathematics. Whiston delivered the Newtonian doctrines,
both from the professor’s chair, and in works written for the use of
the University; yet it is remarkable that a taunt respecting the late
introduction of the Newtonian system into the Cambridge course of
education, has been founded on some peevish expressions which he uses
in his Memoirs, written at a period when, having incurred expulsion
from his professorship and the University, he was naturally querulous
and jaundiced in his views. In 1709–10, Dr. Laughton, who was
tutor in Clare Hall, procured himself to be appointed moderator of the
University disputations, in order to promote the diffusion of the new
mathematical doctrines. By this time the first edition of the
Principia was become rare, and fetched a great price. Bentley
urged Newton to publish a new one; and Cotes, by far the first, at
that time, of the mathematicians of Cambridge, undertook to
superintend the printing, and the edition was accordingly published in
1713.
[2d Ed.] [I perceive that my accomplished German translator,
Littrow, has incautiously copied the insinuations of some modern
writers to the effect that Clarke’s reference to Newton, in his
Edition of Rohault’s Physics, was a mode of introducing
Newtonian doctrines covertly, when it was not allowed him to introduce
such novelties 425
openly. I am quite sure that any one who looks into this matter will
see that this supposition of any unwillingness at Cambridge to receive
Newton’s doctrine is quite absurd, and can prove nothing but the
intense prejudices of those who maintain such an opinion. Newton
received and held his professorship amid the unexampled admiration of
all contemporary members of the University. Whiston, who is sometimes
brought as an evidence against Cambridge on this point, says, “I with
immense pains set myself with the utmost zeal to the study of Sir
Isaac Newton’s wonderful discoveries in his Philosophiæ Naturalis
Principia Mathematica, one or two of which lectures I had
heard him read in the public schools, though I understood them
not at the time.” As to Rohault’s Physics, it really did
contain the best mechanical philosophy of the time;—the
doctrines which were held by Descartes in common with Galileo, and
with all the sound mathematicians who succeeded them. Nor does it look
like any great antipathy to novelty in the University of Cambridge,
that this book, which was quite as novel in its doctrines as Newton’s
Principia, and which had only been published at Paris in 1671,
had obtained a firm hold on the University in less than twenty years.
Nor is there any attempt made in Clarke’s notes to conceal the novelty
of Newton’s discoveries, but on the contrary, admiration is claimed
for them as new.
The promptitude with which the Mathematicians of the University of
Cambridge adopted the best parts of the mechanical philosophy of
Descartes, and the greater philosophy of Newton, in the seventeenth
century, has been paralleled in our own times, in the promptitude with
which they have adopted and followed into their consequences the
Mathematical Theory of Heat of Fourier and Laplace, and the Undulatory
Theory of Light of Young and Fresnel.
In Newton’s College, we possess, besides the memorials of him
mentioned above (which include two locks of his silver-white hair), a
paper in his own handwriting, describing the preparatory reading which
was necessary in order that our College students might be able to read
the Principia. I have printed this paper in the Preface to my
Edition of the First Three Sections of the Principia in the
original Latin (1846).
Bentley, who had expressed his admiration for Newton in his Boyle’s
Lectures in 1692, was made Master of the College in 1699, as I have
stated; and partly, no doubt, in consequence of the Newtonian sermons
which he had preached. In his administration of the College, he
zealously stimulated and assisted the exertions of Cotes, Whiston, and
other disciples of Newton. Smith, Bentley’s successor as Master of
426 the College,
erected a statue of Newton in the College Chapel (a noble work of
Roubiliac), with the inscription, Qui genus humanum ingenio
superavit.]
At Oxford, David Gregory and Halley, both zealous and distinguished
disciples of Newton, obtained the Savilian professorships of astronomy
and geometry in 1691 and 1703.
David Gregory’s Astronomiæ Physicæ et Geometricæ Elementa
issued from the Oxford Press in 1702. The author, in the first
sentence of the Preface, states his object to be to explain the
mechanics of the universe (Physica Cœlestis), which Isaac Newton, the
Prince of Geometers, has carried to a point of elevation which all
look up to with admiration. And this design is executed by a full
exposition of the Newtonian doctrines and their results. Keill, a
pupil of Gregory, followed his tutor to Oxford, and taught the
Newtonian philosophy there in 1700, being then Deputy Sedleian
Professor. He illustrated his lectures by experiments, and published
an Introduction to the Principia which is not out of use even
yet.
In Scotland, the Newtonian philosophy was accepted with great
alacrity, as appears by the instances of David Gregory and Keill.
David Gregory was professor at Edinburgh before he removed to Oxford,
and was succeeded there by his brother James. The latter had, as early
as 1690, printed a thesis, containing in twenty-two propositions, a
compend of Newton’s Principia.56 Probably these
were intended as theses for academical disputations; as Laughton at
Cambridge introduced the Newtonian philosophy into these exercises.
The formula at Cambridge, in use till very recently in these
disputations, was “Rectè statuit Newtonus de Motu Lunæ;” or the
like.
56 See Hutton’s Math. Dict.,
art. James Gregory. If it fell in with my plan to notice
derivative works, I might speak of Maclaurin’s admirable Account of
Sir Isaac Newton’s Discoveries, published in 1748. This is still
one of the best books on the subject. The late Professor Rigaud’s
Historical Essay on the First Publication of Sir Isaac Newton’s
“Principia” (Oxf. 1838) contains a careful and candid view of the
circumstances of that event.
The general diffusion of these opinions in England took place, not
only by means of books, but through the labors of various experimental
lecturers, like Desaguliers, who removed from Oxford to London in
1713; when he informs us,57 that “he found the Newtonian philosophy
generally received among persons of all ranks and professions, and
even among the ladies by the help of experiments.”
57 Desag. Pref.
427 We might
easily trace in our literature indications of the gradual progress of
the Newtonian doctrines. For instance, in the earlier editions of
Pope’s Dunciad, this couplet occurred, in the description of
the effects of the reign of Dulness:


Philosophy, that reached the heavens
before,
Shrinks to her hidden cause, and is no
more.
“And this,” says his editor, Warburton, “was intended
as a censure on the Newtonian philosophy. For the poet had been misled
by the prejudices of foreigners, as if that philosophy had recurred to
the occult qualities of Aristotle. This was the idea he received of it
from a man educated much abroad, who had read every thing, but every
thing superficially.58 When I hinted to him how he had been
imposed upon, he changed the lines with great pleasure into a
compliment (as they now stand) on that divine genius, and a satire on
that very folly by which he himself had been misled.” In 1743 it was
printed,


Philosophy, that leaned on heaven
before,
Shrinks to her second cause, and is no
more.
The Newtonians repelled the charge of dealing in
occult causes;59 and, referring gravity to the will of
the Deity, as the First Cause, assumed a superiority over those whose
philosophy rested in second causes.
58 I presume Bolingbroke is here
meant.
59 See Cotes’s Pref. to the
Principia.
To the cordial reception of the Newtonian theory by the English
astronomers, there is only one conspicuous exception; which is,
however, one of some note, being no other than Flamsteed, the
Astronomer Royal, a most laborious and exact observer. Flamsteed at
first listened with complacency to the promises of improvements in the
Lunar Tables, which the new doctrines held forth, and was willing to
assist Newton, and to receive assistance from him. But after a time,
he lost his respect for Newton’s theory, and ceased to take any
interest in it. He then declared to one of his correspondents,60 “I have determined to lay these
crotchets of Sir Isaac Newton’s wholly aside.” We need not, however,
find any difficulty in this, if we recollect that Flamsteed, though a
good observer, was no philosopher;—never understood by a Theory
any thing more than a Formula which should predict results;—and
was incapable of comprehending the object of Newton’s theory, which
was to assign causes as well as rules, and to satisfy the conditions
of Mechanics as well as of Geometry.
60 Baily’s Account of Flamsteed,
&c., p. 309.
428 [2d Ed.] [I
do not see any reason to retract what was thus said; but it ought
perhaps to be distinctly said that on these very accounts Flamsteed’s
rejection of Newton’s rules did not imply a denial of the doctrine of
gravitation. In the letter above quoted, Flamsteed says that he has
been employed upon the Moon, and that “the heavens reject that
equation of Sir I. Newton which Gregory and Newton called his sixth: I
had then [when he wrote before] compared but 72 of my observations
with the tables, now I have examined above 100 more. I find them all
firm in the same, and the seventh [equation] too.” And thereupon he
comes to the determination above stated.
At an earlier period Flamsteed, as I have said, had received
Newton’s suggestions with great deference, and had regulated his own
observations and theories with reference to them. The calculation of
the lunar inequalities upon the theory of gravitation was found by
Newton and his successors to be a more difficult and laborious task
than he had anticipated, and was not performed without several trials
and errors. One of the equations was at first published (in Gregory’s
Astronomiæ Elementa) with a wrong sign. And when Newton had
done all, Flamsteed found that the rules were far from coming up to
the degree of accuracy which had been claimed for them, that they
could give the moon’s place true to 2 or 3 minutes. It was not till
considerably later that this amount of exactness was attained.
The late Mr. Baily, to whom astronomy and astronomical literature
are so deeply indebted, in his Supplement to the Account of
Flamsteed, has examined with great care and great candor the
assertion that Flamsteed did not understand Newton’s Theory. He
remarks, very justly, that what Newton himself at first presented as
his Theory, might more properly be called Rules for computing lunar
tables, than a physical Theory in the modern acceptation of the term.
He shows, too, that Flamsteed had read the Principia with
attention.61 Nor do I doubt that many considerable
mathematicians gave the same imperfect assent to Newton’s doctrine
which Flamsteed did. But when we find that others, as Halley, David
Gregory, and Cotes, at once not only saw in the doctrine a source of
true formulæ, but also a magnificent physical discovery, we are
obliged, I think, to make Flamsteed, in this respect, an exception to
the first class of astronomers of his own time.
61 Supp. p. 691.
Mr. Baily’s suggestion that the annual equations for the
corrections of the lunar apogee and node were collected from
Flamsteed’s tables 429 and observations independently of their
suggestion by Newton as the results of Theory (Supp. p. 692,
Note, and p. 698), appears to me not to be adequately supported by the
evidence given.]  ~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~
Sect. 3.—Reception of the Newtonian Theory
abroad.
The reception of the Newtonian theory on
the Continent, was much more tardy and unwilling than in its native
island. Even those whose mathematical attainments most fitted them to
appreciate its proofs, were prevented by some peculiarity of view from
adopting it as a system; as Leibnitz, Bernoulli, Huyghens; who all
clung to one modification or other of the system of vortices. In
France, the Cartesian system had obtained a wide and popular
reception, having been recommended by Fontenelle with the graces of
his style; and its empire was so firm and well established in that
country, that it resisted for a long time the pressure of Newtonian
arguments. Indeed, the Newtonian opinions had scarcely any disciples
in France, till Voltaire asserted their claims, on his return from
England in 1728: until then, as he himself says, there were not twenty
Newtonians out of England.
The hold which the Philosophy of Descartes had upon the minds of
his countrymen is, perhaps, not surprising. He really had the merit, a
great one in the history of science, of having completely overturned
the Aristotelian system, and introduced the philosophy of matter and
motion. In all branches of mixed mathematics, as we have already said,
his followers were the best guides who had yet appeared. His
hypothesis of vortices, as an explanation of the celestial motions,
had an apparent advantage over the Newtonian doctrine, in this
respect;—that it referred effects to the most intelligible, or
at least most familiar kinds of mechanical causation, namely, pressure
and impulse. And above all, the system was acceptable to most minds,
in consequence of being, as was pretended, deduced from a few simple
principles by necessary consequences; and of being also directly
connected with metaphysical and theological speculations. We may add,
that it was modified by its mathematical adherents in such a way as to
remove most of the objections to it. A vortex revolving about a centre
could be constructed, or at least it was supposed that it could be
constructed, so as to produce a tendency of bodies to the centre. In
all cases, therefore, where a central force acted, a vortex was
supposed; but in reasoning to the results of this hypothesis, it was
430 easy to leave
out of sight all other effects of the vortex, and to consider only the
central force; and when this was done, the Cartesian mathematician
could apply to his problems a mechanical principle of some degree of
consistency. This reflection will, in some degree, account for what at
first seems so strange;—the fact that the language of the French
mathematicians is Cartesian, for almost half a century after the
publication of the Principia of Newton.
There was, however, a controversy between the two opinions going on
all this time, and every day showed the insurmountable difficulties
under which the Cartesians labored. Newton, in the Principia,
had inserted a series of propositions, the object of which was to
prove, that the machinery of vortices could not be accommodated to one
part of the celestial phenomena, without contradicting another part. A
more obvious difficulty was the case of gravity of the earth; if this
force arose, as Descartes asserted, from the rotation of the earth’s
vortex about its axis, it ought to tend directly to the axis, and not
to the centre. The asserters of vortices often tried their skill in
remedying this vice in the hypothesis, but never with much success.
Huyghens supposed the ethereal matter of the vortices to revolve about
the centre in all directions; Perrault made the strata of the vortex
increase in velocity of rotation as they recede from the centre;
Saurin maintained that the circumambient resistance which comprises
the vortex will produce a pressure passing through the centre. The
elliptic form of the orbits of the planets was another difficulty.
Descartes had supposed the vortices themselves to be oval  but others,
as John Bernoulli, contrived ways of having elliptical motion in a
circular vortex.
The mathematical prize-questions proposed by the French Academy,
naturally brought the two sets of opinions into conflict. The
Cartesian memoir of John Bernoulli, to which we have just referred,
was the one which gained the prize in 1730. It not unfrequently
happened that the Academy, as if desirous to show its impartiality,
divided the prize between the Cartesians and Newtonians. Thus in 1734,
the question being, the cause of the inclination of the orbits of the
planets, the prize was shared between John Bernoulli, whose Memoir was
founded on the system of vortices, and his son Daniel, who was a
Newtonian. The last act of homage of this kind to the Cartesian system
was performed in 1740, when the prize on the question of the Tides was
distributed between Daniel Bernoulli, Euler, Maclaurin, and
Cavallieri; the last of whom had tried to patch up and amend the
Cartesian hypothesis on this subject. 431
Thus the Newtonian system was not adopted in France till the
Cartesian generation had died off; Fontenelle, who was secretary to
the Academy of Sciences, and who lived till 1756, died a Cartesian.
There were exceptions; for instance, Delisle, an astronomer who was
selected by Peter the Great of Russia, to found the Academy of St
Petersburg; who visited England in 1724, and to whom Newton then gave
his picture, and Halley his Tables. But in general, during the
interval, that country and this had a national difference of creed on
physical subjects. Voltaire, who visited England in 1727, notices this
difference in his lively manner. “A Frenchman who arrives in London,
finds a great alteration in philosophy, as in other things. He left
the world full [a plenum], he finds it empty. At Paris you see the
universe composed of vortices of subtle matter, in London we see
nothing of the kind. With you it is the pressure of the moon which
causes the tides of the sea, in England it is the sea which gravitates
towards the moon; so that when you think the moon ought to give us
high water, these gentlemen believe that you ought to have low water;
which unfortunately we cannot test by experience; for in order to do
that, we should have examined the Moon and the Tides at the moment of
the creation. You will observe also that the sun, which in France has
nothing to do with the business, here comes in for a quarter of it.
Among you Cartesians, all is done by an impulsion which one does not
well understand; with the Newtonians, it is done by an attraction of
which we know the cause no better. At Paris you fancy the earth shaped
like a melon, at London it is flattened on the two sides.”
It was Voltaire himself as we have said, who was mainly
instrumental in giving the Newtonian doctrines currency in France. He
was at first refused permission to print his Elements of the
Newtonian Philosophy, by the Chancellor, D’Aguesseaux, who was a
Cartesian; but after the appearance of this work in 1738, and of other
writings by him on the same subject, the Cartesian edifice, already
without real support or consistency, crumbled to pieces and
disappeared. The first Memoir in the Transactions of the French
Academy in which the doctrine of central force is applied to the
solar system, is one by the Chevalier de Louville in 1720, On the
Construction and Theory of Tables of the Sun. In this, however,
the mode of explaining the motions of the planets by means of an
original impulse and an attractive force is attributed to Kepler, not
to Newton. The first Memoir which refers to the universal gravitation
of matter is by Maupertuis, in 432 1736. But Newton was not unknown or
despised in France till this time. In 1699 he was admitted one of the
very small number of foreign associates of the French Academy of
Sciences. Even Fontenelle, who, as we have said, never adopted his
opinions, spoke of him in a worthy manner, in the Eloge which
he composed on the occasion of his death. At a much earlier period
too, Fontenelle did homage to his fame. The following passage refers,
I presume, to Newton. In the History of the Academy for 1708,
which is written by the secretary, he says,62 in referring to
the difficulty which the comets occasion in the Cartesian hypothesis:
“We might relieve ourselves at once from all the embarrassment which
arises from the directions of these motions, by suppressing, as has
been done by one of the greatest geniuses of the age, all
this immense fluid matter, which we commonly suppose between the
planets, and conceiving them suspended in a perfect void.”
62 Hist. Ac. Sc. 1708. p.
103.
Comets, as the above passage implies, were a kind of artillery
which the Cartesian plenum could not resist. When it appeared
that the paths of such wanderers traversed the vortices in all
directions, it was impossible to maintain that these imaginary
currents governed the movements of bodies immersed in them  and the
mechanism ceased to have any real efficacy. Both these phenomena of
comets, and many others, became objects of a stronger and more general
interest, in consequence of the controversy between the rival parties;
and thus the prevalence of the Cartesian system did not seriously
impede the progress of sound knowledge. In some cases, no doubt, it
made men unwilling to receive the truth, as in the instance of the
deviation of the comets from the zodiacal motion; and again, when
Römer discovered that light was not instantaneously propagated. But it
encouraged observation and calculation, and thus forwarded the
verification and extension of the Newtonian system; of which process
we must now consider some of the incidents. 433</div></body></text></TEI>