<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="1">

TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE THOMAS, EARL OF PEMBROKE AND MONTGOMERY, BARON HERBERT
OF CARDIFF LORD ROSS, OF KENDAL, PAR, FITZHUGH, MARMION, ST. QUINTIN, AND
SHURLAND;


LORD PRESIDENT OF HIS MAJESTY’S MOST HONOURABLE PRIVY COUNCIL; AND LORD
LIEUTENANT OF THE COUNTY OF WILTS, AND OF SOUTH WALES.

MY LORD,

This Treatise, which is grown up under your lordship’s eye, and has ventured
into the world by your order, does now, by a natural kind of right, come to
your lordship for that protection which you several years since promised it. It
is not that I think any name, how great soever, set at the beginning of a book,
will be able to cover the faults that are to be found in it. Things in print
must stand and fall by their own worth, or the reader’s fancy. But there being
nothing more to be desired for truth than a fair unprejudiced hearing, nobody
is more likely to procure me that than your lordship, who are allowed to have
got so intimate an acquaintance with her, in her more retired recesses. Your
lordship is known to have so far advanced your speculations in the most
abstract and general knowledge of things, beyond the ordinary reach or common
methods, that your allowance and approbation of the design of this Treatise
will at least preserve it from being condemned without reading, and will
prevail to have those parts a little weighed, which might otherwise perhaps be
thought to deserve no consideration, for being somewhat out of the common road.
The imputation of Novelty is a terrible charge amongst those who judge of men’s
heads, as they do of their perukes, by the fashion, and can allow none to be
right but the received doctrines. Truth scarce ever yet carried it by vote
anywhere at its first appearance: new opinions are always suspected, and
usually opposed, without any other reason but because they are not already
common. But truth, like gold, is not the less so for being newly brought out of
the mine. It is trial and examination must give it price, and not any antique
fashion; and though it be not yet current by the public stamp, yet it may, for
all that, be as old as nature, and is certainly not the less genuine. Your
lordship can give great and convincing instances of this, whenever you please
to oblige the public with some of those large and comprehensive discoveries you
have made of truths hitherto unknown, unless to some few, from whom your
lordship has been pleased not wholly to conceal them. This alone were a
sufficient reason, were there no other, why I should dedicate this Essay to
your lordship; and its having some little correspondence with some parts of
that nobler and vast system of the sciences your lordship has made so new,
exact, and instructive a draught of, I think it glory enough, if your lordship
permit me to boast, that here and there I have fallen into some thoughts not
wholly different from yours. If your lordship think fit that, by your
encouragement, this should appear in the world, I hope it may be a reason, some
time or other, to lead your lordship further; and you will allow me to say,
that you here give the world an earnest of something that, if they can bear
with this, will be truly worth their expectation. This, my lord, shows what a
present I here make to your lordship; just such as the poor man does to his
rich and great neighbour, by whom the basket of flowers or fruit is not ill
taken, though he has more plenty of his own growth, and in much greater
perfection. Worthless things receive a value when they are made the offerings
of respect, esteem, and gratitude: these you have given me so mighty and
peculiar reasons to have, in the highest degree, for your lordship, that if
they can add a price to what they go along with, proportionable to their own
greatness, I can with confidence brag, I here make your lordship the richest
present you ever received. This I am sure, I am under the greatest obligations
to seek all occasions to acknowledge a long train of favours I have received
from your lordship; favours, though great and important in themselves, yet made
much more so by the forwardness, concern, and kindness, and other obliging
circumstances, that never failed to accompany them. To all this you are pleased
to add that which gives yet more weight and relish to all the rest: you
vouchsafe to continue me in some degrees of your esteem, and allow me a place
in your good thoughts, I had almost said friendship. This, my lord, your words
and actions so constantly show on all occasions, even to others when I am
absent, that it is not vanity in me to mention what everybody knows: but it
would be want of good manners not to acknowledge what so many are witnesses of,
and every day tell me I am indebted to your lordship for. I wish they could as
easily assist my gratitude, as they convince me of the great and growing
engagements it has to your lordship. This I am sure, I should write of the
UNDERSTANDING without having any, if I were not extremely sensible of them, and
did not lay hold on this opportunity to testify to the world how much I am
obliged to be, and how much I am,

MY LORD,

Your Lordship’s most humble and most obedient servant,

JOHN LOCKE

2 Dorset Court, 24th of May, 1689


</div></body></text></TEI>