<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="31">

CHAPTER XXII.
OF MIXED MODES.

1. Mixed Modes, what.


Having treated of SIMPLE MODES in the foregoing chapters, and given several
instances of some of the most considerable of them, to show what they are, and
how we come by them; we are now in the next place to consider those we call
MIXED MODES; such are the complex ideas we mark by the names OBLIGATION,
DRUNKENNESS, a LIE, &c.; which consisting of several combinations of simple
ideas of DIFFERENT kinds, I have called mixed modes, to distinguish them from
the more simple modes, which consist only of simple ideas of the SAME kind.
These mixed modes, being also such combinations of simple ideas as are not
looked upon to be characteristical marks of any real beings that have a steady
existence, but scattered and independent ideas put together by the mind, are
thereby distinguished from the complex ideas of substances.


2. Made by the Mind.


That the mind, in respect of its simple ideas, is wholly passive, and receives
them all from the existence and operations of things, such as sensation or
reflection offers them, without being able to MAKE any one idea, experience
shows us. But if we attentively consider these ideas I call mixed modes, we are
now speaking of, we shall find their origin quite different. The mind often
exercises an ACTIVE power in making these several combinations. For, it being
once furnished with simple ideas, it can put them together in several
compositions, and so make variety of complex ideas, without examining whether
they exist so together in nature. And hence I think it is that these ideas are
called NOTIONS: as they had their original, and constant existence, more in the
thoughts of men, than in the reality of things; and to form such ideas, it
sufficed that the mind put the parts of them together, and that they were
consistent in the understanding without considering whether they had any real
being: though I do not deny but several of them might be taken from
observation, and the existence of several simple ideas so combined, as they are
put together in the understanding. For the man who first framed the idea of
HYPOCRISY, might have either taken it at first from the observation of one who
made show of good qualities which he had not; or else have framed that idea in
his mind without having any such pattern to fashion it by. For it is evident
that, in the beginning of languages and societies of men, several of those
complex ideas, which were consequent to the constitutions established amongst
them, must needs have been in the minds of men before they existed anywhere
else; and that many names that stood for such complex ideas were in use, and so
those ideas framed, before the combinations they stood for ever existed.


3. Sometimes got by the Explication of their Names.


Indeed, now that languages are made, and abound with words standing for such
combinations, an usual way of GETTING these complex ideas is, by the
explication of those terms that stand for them. For, consisting of a company of
simple ideas combined, they may, by words standing for those simple ideas, be
represented to the mind of one who understands those words, though that complex
combination of simple ideas were never offered to his mind by the real
existence of things. Thus a man may come to have the idea of SACRILEGE or
MURDER, by enumerating to him the simple ideas which these words stand for;
without ever seeing either of them committed.


4. The Name ties the Parts of mixed Modes into one Idea.


Every mixed mode consisting of many distinct simple ideas, it seems reasonable
to inquire, Whence it has its unity; and how such a precise multitude comes to
make but one idea; since that combination does not always exist together in
nature? To which I answer, it is plain it has its unity from an act of the
mind, combining those several simple ideas together, and considering them as
one complex one, consisting of those parts; and the mark of this union, or that
which is looked on generally to complete it, is one NAME given to that
combination. For it is by their names that men commonly regulate their account
of their distinct species of mixed modes, seldom allowing or considering any
number of simple ideas to make one complex one, but such collections as there
be names for. Thus, though the killing of an old man be as fit in nature to be
united into one complex idea, as the killing a man’s father; yet, there being
no name standing precisely for the one, as there is the name of PARRICIDE to
mark the other, it is not taken for a particular complex idea, nor a distinct
species of actions from that of killing a young man, or any other man.


5. The Cause of making mixed Modes.


If we should inquire a little further, to see what it is that occasions men to
make several combinations of simple ideas into distinct, and, as it were,
settled modes, and neglect others, which in the nature of things themselves,
have as much an aptness to be combined and make distinct ideas, we shall find
the reason of it to be the end of language; which being to mark, or communicate
men’s thoughts to one another with all the dispatch that may be, they usually
make SUCH collections of ideas into complex modes, and affix names to them, as
they have frequent use of in their way of living and conversation, leaving
others which they have but seldom an occasion to mention, loose and without
names that tie them together: they rather choosing to enumerate (when they have
need) such ideas as make them up, by the particular names that stand for them,
than to trouble their memories by multiplying of complex ideas with names to
them, which they seldom or never have any occasion to make use of.


6. Why Words in one Language have none answering in another.


This shows us how it comes to pass that there are in every language many
particular words which cannot be rendered by any one single word of another.
For the several fashions, customs, and manners of one nation, making several
combinations of ideas familiar and necessary in one, which another people have
had never an occasion to make, or perhaps so much as take notice of, names come
of course to be annexed to them, to avoid long periphrases in things of daily
conversation; and so they become so many distinct complex ideas in their minds.
Thus ostrakismos amongst the Greeks, and proscriptio amongst the Romans, were
words which other languages had no names that exactly answered; because they
stood for complex ideas which were not in the minds of the men of other
nations. Where there was no such custom, there was no notion of any such
actions; no use of such combinations of ideas as were united, and, as it were,
tied together, by those terms: and therefore in other countries there were no
names for them.


7. And Languages change.


Hence also we may see the reason, why languages constantly change, take up new
and lay by old terms. Because change of customs and opinions bringing with it
new combinations of ideas, which it is necessary frequently to think on and
talk about, new names, to avoid long descriptions, are annexed to them; and so
they become new species of complex modes. What a number of different ideas are
by this means wrapped up in one short sound, and how much of our time and
breath is thereby saved, any one will see, who will but take the pains to
enumerate all the ideas that either REPRIEVE or APPEAL stand for; and instead
of either of those names, use a periphrasis, to make any one understand their
meaning.


8. Mixed Modes


Though I shall have occasion to consider this more at-large when I come to
treat of Words and their use, yet I could not avoid to take thus much notice
here of the NAMES OF MIXED MODES; which being fleeting and transient
combinations of simple ideas, which have but a short existence anywhere but in
the minds of men, and there too have no longer any existence than whilst they
are thought on, have not so much anywhere the appearance of a constant and
lasting existence as in their names: which are therefore, in this sort of
ideas, very apt to be taken for the ideas themselves. For, if we should inquire
where the idea of a TRIUMPH or APOTHEOSIS exists, it is evident they could
neither of them exist altogether anywhere in the things themselves, being
actions that required time to their performance, and so could never all exist
together; and as to the minds of men, where the ideas of these actions are
supposed to be lodged, they have there too a very uncertain existence: and
therefore we are apt to annex them to the names that excite them in us.


9. How we get the Ideas of mixed Modes.


There are therefore three ways whereby we get these complex ideas of mixed
modes:—(1) By experience and OBSERVATION of things themselves: thus, by
seeing two men mixed wrestle or fence, we get the idea of wrestling or fencing.
(2) By INVENTION, or voluntary putting together of several simple ideas in our
own minds: so he that first invented printing or etching, had an idea of it in
his mind before it ever existed. (3) Which is the most usual way, by EXPLAINING
THE NAMES of actions we never saw, or motions we cannot see; and by
enumerating, and thereby, as it were, setting before our imaginations all those
ideas which go to the making them up, and are the constituent parts of them.
For, having by sensation and reflection stored our minds with simple ideas, and
by use got the names that stand for them, we can by those means represent to
another any complex idea we would have him conceive; so that it has in it no
simple ideas but what he knows, and has with us the same name for. For all our
complex ideas are ultimately resolvable into simple ideas, of which they are
compounded and originally made up, though perhaps their immediate ingredients,
as I may so say, are also complex ideas. Thus, the mixed mode which the word
LIE stands for is made of these simple ideas:—(1) Articulate sounds. (2)
Certain ideas in the mind of the speaker. (3) Those words the signs of those
ideas. (4) Those signs put together, by affirmation or negation, otherwise than
the ideas they stand for are in the mind of the speaker. I think I need not go
any further in the analysis of that complex idea we call a lie: what I have
said is enough to show that it is made up of simple ideas. And it could not be
but an offensive tediousness to my reader, to trouble him with a more minute
enumeration of every particular simple idea that goes to this complex one;
which, from what has been said, he cannot but be able to make out to himself.
The same may be done in all our complex ideas whatsoever; which, however
compounded and decompounded, may at last be resolved into simple ideas, which
are all the materials of knowledge or thought we have, or can have. Nor shall
we have reason to fear that the mind is hereby stinted to too scanty a number
of ideas, if we consider what an inexhaustible stock of simple modes number and
figure alone afford us. How far then mixed modes, which admit of the various
combinations of different simple ideas, and their infinite modes, are from
being few and scanty, we may easily imagine. So that, before we have done, we
shall see that nobody need be afraid he shall not have scope and compass enough
for his thoughts to range in, though they be, as I pretend, confined only to
simple ideas, received from sensation or reflection, and their several
combinations.


10. Motion, Thinking, and Power have been most modified.


It is worth our observing, which of all our simple ideas have been MOST
modified, and had most mixed ideas made out of them, with names given to them.
And those have been these three:—THINKING and MOTION (which are the two
ideas which comprehend in them all action,) and POWER, from whence these
actions are conceived to flow. These simple ideas, I say, of thinking, motion,
and power, have been those which have been most modified; and out of whose
modifications have been made most complex modes, with names to them. For ACTION
being the great business of mankind, and the whole matter about which all laws
are conversant, it is no wonder that the several modes of thinking and motion
should be taken notice of, the ideas of them observed, and laid up in the
memory, and have names assigned to them; without which laws could be but ill
made, or vice and disorders repressed. Nor could any communication be well had
amongst men without such complex ideas, with names to them: and therefore men
have settled names, and supposed settled ideas in their minds, of modes of
actions, distinguished by their causes, means, objects, ends, instruments,
time, place, and other circumstances; and also of their powers fitted for those
actions: v.g. BOLDNESS is the power to speak or do what we intend, before
others, without fear or disorder; and the Greeks call the confidence of
speaking by a peculiar name, [word in Greek]: which power or ability in man of
doing anything, when it has been acquired by frequent doing the same thing, is
that idea we name HABIT; when it is forward, and ready upon every occasion to
break into action, we call it DISPOSITION. Thus, TESTINESS is a disposition or
aptness to be angry.


To conclude: Let us examine any modes of action, v.g. CONSIDERATION and ASSENT,
which are actions of the mind; RUNNING and SPEAKING, which are actions of the
body; REVENGE and MURDER, which are actions of both together, and we shall find
them but so many collections of simple ideas, which, together, make up the
complex ones signified by those names.


11. Several Words seeming to signify Action, signify but the effect.


POWER being the source from whence all action proceeds, the substances wherein
these powers are, when they *[lost line??] exert this power into act, are
called CAUSES, and the substances which thereupon are produced, or the simple
ideas which are introduced into any subject by the exerting of that power, are
called EFFECTS. The EFFICACY whereby the new substance or idea is produced is
called, in the subject exerting that power, ACTION; but in the subject wherein
any simple idea is changed or produced, it is called PASSION: which efficacy,
however various, and the effects almost infinite, yet we can, I think, conceive
it, in intellectual agents, to be nothing else but modes of thinking and
willing; in corporeal agents, nothing else but modifications of motion. I say I
think we cannot conceive it to be any other but these two. For whatever sort of
action besides these produces any effects, I confess myself to have no notion
nor idea of; and so it is quite remote from my thoughts, apprehensions, and
knowledge; and as much in the dark to me as five other senses, or as the ideas
of colours to a blind man. And therefore many words which seem to express some
action, signify nothing of the action or MODUS OPERANDI at all, but barely the
effect, with some circumstances of the subject wrought on, or cause operating:
v.g. CREATION, ANNIHILATION, contain in them no idea of the action or manner
whereby they are produced, but barely of the cause, and the thing done. And
when a countryman says the cold freezes water, though the word freezing seems
to import some action, yet truly it signifies nothing but the effect, viz. that
water that was before fluid is become hard and consistent, without containing
any idea of the action whereby it is done.


12. Mixed Modes made also of other Ideas than those of Power and Action.


I think I shall not need to remark here that, though power and action make the
greatest part of mixed modes, marked by names, and familiar in the minds and
mouths of men, yet other simple ideas, and their several combinations, are not
excluded: much less, I think, will it be necessary for me to enumerate all the
mixed modes which have been settled, with names to them. That would be to make
a dictionary of the greatest part of the words made use of in divinity, ethics,
law, and politics, and several other sciences. All that is requisite to my
present design, is to show what sort of ideas those are which I call mixed
modes; how the mind comes by them; and that they are compositions made up of
simple ideas got from sensation and reflection; which I suppose I have done.


</div></body></text></TEI>