<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="25">
CHAPTER VI.

The Stability of the Ocean.

What is meant by the stability of the ocean may
perhaps be explained by means of the following illustration.
If we suppose the whole globe of the
Earth to be composed of water, a sphere of cork,
immersed in any part of it, would come to the surface
of the water, except it were placed exactly at
the centre of the earth; and even if it were the
slightest displacement of the cork sphere would end
in its rising and floating. This would be the case
whatever were the size of the cork sphere, and even
if it were so large as to leave comparatively little
room for the water; and the result would be nearly
the same, if the cork sphere, when in its central
position, had on its surface prominences which projected
above the surface of the water. Now this
brings us to the case in which we have a globe resembling
our present earth, composed like it of water
and of a solid centre, with islands and continents,
but having these solid parts all made of cork. And
it appears by the preceding reasoning, that in this
case, if there were any disturbance either of the
solid or fluid parts, the solid parts would rise from
the centre of the watery sphere as far as they could:
that is, all the water would run to one side and leave
the land on the other. Such an ocean would be in
unstable equilibrium.
Now a question naturally occurs, is the equilibrium
of our present ocean of this unstable kind, or is it
stable? The sea, after its most violent agitations,[141]
appears to return to its former state of repose; but
may not some extraordinary cause produce in it
some derangement which may go on increasing till
the waters all rush one way, and thus drown the
highest mountains? And if we are safe from this
danger, what are the conditions by which we are so
secured?
The illustration which we have employed obviously
suggests the answer to this question; namely,
that the equilibrium is unstable, so long as the solid
parts are of such a kind as to float in the fluid parts;
and of course we should expect that the equilibrium
will be stable whenever the contrary is the case, that
is, when the solid parts of the earth are of greater
specific gravity than the sea. A more systematic
mathematical calculation has conducted Laplace to
a demonstration of this result.
The mean specific gravity of the earth appears to
be about five times that of water, so that the condition
of the stability of the ocean is abundantly fulfilled.
And the provision by which this stability is
secured was put in force through the action of those
causes, whatever they were, which made the density
of the solid materials and central parts of the
earth greater than the density of the incumbent fluid.
When we consider, however, the manner in which
the wisdom of the Creator, even in those cases in
which his care is most apparent, as in the structure
of animals, works by means of intermediate causes
and general laws, we shall not be ready to reject all
belief of an end in such a case as this, merely because
the means are mechanical agencies. Laplace
says, “in virtue of gravity, the most dense of the
strata of the earth are those nearest to the centre;
and thus the mean density exceeds that of the waters
which cover it; which suffices to secure the stability
of the equilibrium of the seas, and to put a bridle
upon the fury of the waves.” This statement, if
exact, would not prove that He who subjected the
materials of the earth to the action of gravity did[142]
not intend to restrain the rage of the waters: but the
statement is not true in fact. The lower strata, so
far as man has yet examined, are very far from being
constantly, or even generally, heavier than the
superincumbent ones. And certainly solidification
by no means implies a greater density than fluidity:
the density of Jupiter is one fourth, that of Saturn
less than one seventh, of that of the earth. If an
ocean of water were poured into the cavities upon
the surface of Saturn, its equilibrium would not be
stable. It would leave its bed on one side of the
globe; and the planet would finally be composed of
one hemisphere of water and one of land. If the
Earth had an ocean of a fluid six times as heavy as
water, (quicksilver is thirteen times as heavy,) we
should have, in like manner, a dry and a fluid hemisphere.
Our inland rivers would probably never be
able to reach the shores, but would be dried up on
their way, like those which run in torrid desarts;
perhaps the evaporation from the ocean would
never reach the inland mountains, and we should
have no rivers at all. Without attempting to
imagine the details of such a condition, it is easy to
see, that to secure the existence of a different one is
an end which is in harmony with all that we see of
the preserving care displayed in the rest of creation.[20]
</div></body></text></TEI>