<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="68">CHAPTER VII.
Discovery of the Laws of the Colours of Thin
Plates.
THE facts which we have now to
consider are remarkable, inasmuch as the colours are produced merely
by the smallness of dimensions of the bodies employed. The light is
not analysed by any peculiar 77 property of the substances, but dissected
by the minuteness of their parts. On this account, these phenomena
give very important indications of the real structure of light; and at
an early period, suggested views which are, in a great measure,
just.
Hooke appears to be the first person who made any progress in
discovering the laws of the colors of thin plates. In his
Micrographia, printed by the Royal Society in 1664, he
describes, in a detailed and systematic manner, several phenomena of
this kind, which he calls “fantastical colors.” He examined them in
Muscovy glass or mica, a transparent mineral which is capable
of being split into the exceedingly thin films which are requisite for
such colors; he noticed them also in the fissures of the same
substance, in bubbles blown of water, rosin, gum, glass; in the films
on the surface of tempered steel; between two plane pieces of glass;
and in other cases. He perceived also,48 that the
production of each color required a plate of determinate thickness,
and he employed this circumstance as one of the grounds of his theory
of light.
48 Micrographia, p. 53.
Newton took up the subject where Hooke had left it; and followed it
out with his accustomed skill and clearness, in his Discourse on
Light and Colors, communicated to the Royal Society in 1675. He
determined, what Hooke had not ascertained, the thickness of the film
which was requisite for the production of each color; and in this way
explained, in a complete and admirable manner, the colored rings which
occur when two lenses are pressed together, and the scale of
color which the rings follow; a step of the more consequence, as
the same scale occurs in many other optical phenomena.
It is not our business here to state the hypothesis with regard to
the properties of light which Newton founded on these facts;—the
“fits of easy transmission and reflection.” We shall see hereafter
that his attempted induction was imperfect; and his endeavor to
account, by means of the laws of thin plates, for the colors of
natural bodies, is altogether unsatisfactory. But notwithstanding
these failures in the speculations on this subject, he did make in it
some very important steps; for he clearly ascertained that when the
thickness of the plate was about 1⁄178000th of an inch, or
three times, five times, seven times that magnitude, there was a
bright color produced; but blackness, when the thickness was exactly
intermediate between those magnitudes. He found, also, that the
thicknesses which gave red and 78 violet49 were as fourteen
to nine; and the intermediate colors of course corresponded to
intermediate thicknesses, and therefore, in his apparatus, consisting
of two lenses pressed together, appeared as rings of intermediate
sizes. His mode of confirming the rule, by throwing upon this
apparatus differently colored homogeneous light, is striking and
elegant. “It was very pleasant,” he says, “to see the rings gradually
swell and contract as the color of the light was changed.”
49 Opticks, p. 184.
It is not necessary to enter further into the detail of these
phenomena, or to notice the rings seen by transmission, and other
circumstances. The important step made by Newton in this matter was,
the showing that the rays of light, in these experiments, as they pass
onwards go periodically through certain cycles of modification, each
period occupying nearly the small fraction of an inch mentioned above;
and this interval being different for different colors. Although
Newton did not correctly disentangle the conditions under which this
periodical character is manifestly disclosed, the discovery that,
under some circumstances, such a periodical character does exist, was
likely to influence, and did influence, materially and beneficially,
the subsequent progress of Optics towards a connected theory.
We must now trace this progress; but before we proceed to this
task, we will briefly notice a number of optical phenomena which had
been collected, and which waited for the touch of sound theory to
introduce among them that rule and order which mere observation had
sought for in vain.
</div></body></text></TEI>