<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="22">
      SECTION 2. ON THE ART OF OBSERVING.
    

      The remarks in this section are not proposed for the assistance of those
      who are already observers, but are intended to show to persons not
      familiar with the subject, that in observations demanding no unrivalled
      accuracy, the principles of common sense may be safely trusted, and that
      any gentleman of liberal education may, by perseverance and attention,
      ascertain the limits within which he may trust both his instrument and
      himself.
    

      If the instrument is a divided one, the first thing is to learn to read
      the verniers. If the divisions are so fine that the coincidence is
      frequently doubtful, the best plan will be for the learner to get some
      acquaintance who is skilled in the use of instruments, and having set the
      instrument at hazard, to write down the readings of the verniers, and then
      request his friend to do the same; whenever there is any difference, he
      should carefully examine the doubtful one, and ask his friend to point out
      the minute peculiarities on which he founds his decision. This should be
      repeated frequently; and after some practice, he should note how many
      times in a hundred his reading differs from his friend's, and also how
      many divisions they usually differ.
    

      The next point is, to ascertain the precision with which the learner can
      bisect an object with the wires of the telescope. This can be done without
      assistance. It is not necessary even to adjust the instrument, but merely
      to point it to a distant object. When it bisects any remarkable point,
      read off the verniers, and write down the result; then displace the
      telescope a little, and adjust it again. A series of such observations
      will show the confidence which is due to the observer's eye in bisecting
      an object, and also in reading the verniers; and as the first direction
      gave him some measure of the latter, he may, in a great measure,
      appreciate his skill in the former. He should also, when he finds a
      deviation in the reading, return to the telescope, and satisfy himself if
      he has made the bisection as complete as he can. In general, the student
      should practise each adjustment separately, and write down the results
      wherever he can measure its deviations.
    

      Having thus practised the adjustments, the next step is to make an
      observation; but in order to try both himself and the instrument, let him
      take the altitude of some fixed object, a terrestrial one, and having
      registered the result, let him derange the adjustment, and repeat the
      process fifty or a hundred times. This will not merely afford him
      excellent practice, but enable him to judge of his own skill.
    

      The first step in the use of every instrument, is to find the limits
      within which its employer can measure the SAME OBJECT UNDER THE SAME
      CIRCUMSTANCES. It is only from a knowledge of this, that he can have
      confidence in his measures of the SAME OBJECT UNDER DIFFERENT
      CIRCUMSTANCES, and after that, of DIFFERENT OBJECTS UNDER DIFFERENT
      CIRCUMSTANCES.
    

      These principles are applicable to almost all instruments. If a person is
      desirous of ascertaining heights by a mountain barometer, let him begin by
      adjusting the instrument in his own study; and having made the upper
      contact, let him write down the reading of the vernier, and then let him
      derange the UPPER adjustment ONLY, re-adjust, and repeat the reading. When
      he is satisfied about the limits within which he can make that adjustment,
      let him do the same repeatedly with the lower; but let him not, until he
      knows his own errors in reading and adjusting, pronounce upon those of the
      instrument. In the case of a barometer, he must also be assured, that the
      temperature of the mercury does not change during the interval.
    

      A friend once brought to me a beautifully constructed piece of mechanism,
      for marking minute portions of time; the three-hundredth parts of a second
      were indicated by it. It was a kind of watch, with a pin for stopping one
      of the hands. I proposed that we should each endeavour to stop it twenty
      times in succession, at the same point. We were both equally unpractised,
      and our first endeavours showed that we could not be confident of the
      twentieth part of a second. In fact, both the time occupied in causing the
      extremities of the fingers to obey the volition, as well as the time
      employed in compressing the flesh before the fingers acted on the stop,
      appeared to influence the accuracy of our observations. From some few
      experiments I made, I thought I perceived that the rapidity of the
      transmission of the effects of the will, depended on the state of fatigue
      or health of the body. If any one were to make experiments on this
      subject, it might be interesting, to compare the rapidity of the
      transmission of volition in different persons, with the time occupied in
      obliterating an impression made on one of the senses of the same persons.
      For example, by having a mechanism to make a piece of ignited charcoal
      revolve with different degrees of velocity, some persons will perceive a
      continuous circle of light before others, whose retina does not retain so
      long impressions that are made upon it.
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>