<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="145">CHAPTER VII.
Magneto-electric Induction.
FARADAY’S discovery that, in
combinations like those in which a voltaic current was known to
produce motion, motion would produce a voltaic current, naturally
excited great attention among the scientific men of Europe. The
general nature of his discovery was communicated by letter26 to M. Hachette at Paris, in December,
1831; and experiments having the like results were forthwith made by
MM. Becquerel and Ampère at Paris, and MM. Nobili and Antinori at
Florence.
26 Ann. de Chimie, vol. xlviii.
(1831), p. 402.
It was natural also that in a case in which the relations of space
which determine the results are so complicated, different philosophers
should look at them in different ways. There had been, from the first
discovery by Oersted of the effect of a voltaic current upon a magnet,
two rival methods of regarding the facts. Electric and magnetic lines
exert an effort to place themselves transverse to each other (see chapter iv. of this Book), and (as I have already
said) two ways offered themselves of simplifying this general
truth:—to suppose an electric current made up of transverse
magnetic lines; or to suppose magnetic lines made up of transverse
electric currents. On either of these assumptions, the result was
expressed by saying that like currents or lines (electric or
magnetic) tend to place themselves parallel; which is a law more
generally intelligible than the law of transverse position. Faraday
had adopted the former view; had taken the lines of magnetic force for
the fundamental lines of his system, and defined the direction of the
magneto-electric current of induction by the relation 619 of the motion to
these lines. Ampère, on the other hand, supposed the magnet to be made
up of transverse electric currents (chap.
vi.); and had deduced all the facts of electro-dynamical action,
with great felicity, from this conception. The question naturally
arose, in what manner, on this view, were the new facts of
magneto-electric induction by motion to be explained, or even
expressed?
Various philosophers attempted to answer this question. Perhaps the
form in which the answer has obtained most general acceptance is that
in which it was put by Lenz, who discoursed on the subject to the
Academy of St. Petersburg in 1833.27 His general rule
is to this effect: when a wire moves in the neighborhood of an
electric current or a magnet, a current takes place in it, such as,
existing independently, would have produced a motion opposite to the
actual motion. Thus two parallel forward currents move towards
each other:—hence if a current move towards a parallel wire, it
produces in it a backward current. A moveable wire conducting a
current downwards will move round the north pole of a magnet in
the direction N., W., S., E.:—hence if, when the wire have in it
no current, we move it in the direction N., W., S., E., we produce in
the wire an upward current. And thus, as M. de la Rive
remarks,28 in cases in which the mutual action of
two currents produces a limited motion, as attraction or repulsion, or
a deviation right or left, the corresponding magneto-electric
induction produces an instantaneous current only; but when the
electrodynamic action produces a continued motion, the corresponding
motion produces, by induction, a continued current.
27 Acad. Petrop. Nov. 29, 1833.
Pogg. Ann. vol. xxxi. p. 483.
28 Traité de l’Electricité,
vol. i. p. 441 (1854).
Looking at this mode of stating the law, it is impossible not to
regard this effect as a sort of reaction; and accordingly, this view
was at once taken of it. Professor Ritchie said, in 1833, “The law is
founded on the universal principle that action and reaction are
equal.” Thus, if voltaic electricity induce magnetism under certain
arrangements, magnetism will, by similar arrangements, react on a
conductor and induce voltaic electricity.29
29 On the Reduction of Mr. Faraday’s
discoveries in Magneto-electric Induction to a General Law.
Trans. of R. S. in Phil. Mag. N.S. vol. iii. 37, and
vol. iv. p. 11. In the second edition of this history I used the like
expressions.
There are still other ways of looking at this matter. I have
elsewhere pointed out that where polar properties co-exist, they are
620 generally found
to be connected,30 and have illustrated this law in the
case of electrical, magnetical, and chemical polarities. If we regard
motion backwards and forwards, to the right and the left, and the
like, as polar relations, we see that magneto-electric
induction gives us a new manifestation of connected polarities.
30 Phil. Ind. Sc. B. v. c.
ii.
Diamagnetic Polarity.
But the manifestation of co-existent polarities which are brought
into view in this most curious department of nature is not yet
exhausted by those which we have described. I have already spoken (chap. vii.) of Dr. Faraday’s discovery that there are
diamagnetic as well as magnetic bodies; bodies which are repelled by
the pole of a magnet, as well as bodies which are attracted. Here is a
new opposition of properties. What is the exact definition of this
opposition in connexion with other polarities? To this, at present,
different philosophers give different answers. Some say that
diamagnetism is completely the opposite of ordinary magnetism, or, as
Dr. Faraday has termed it for the sake of distinction, of
paramagnetism. They say that as a north pole of a magnet gives
to the neighboring extremity of a piece of soft iron a south pole, so
it gives to the neighboring extremity of a piece of bismuth a north
pole, and that the bismuth becomes for a time an inverted magnet; and
hence, arranges itself across the line of magnetised force, instead of
along it. Dr. Faraday himself at first adopted this view;31 but he now conceives that the bismuth
is not made polar, but is simply repelled by the magnet; and that the
transverse position which it assumes, arises merely from its elongated
form, each end trying to recede as far as possible from the repulsive
pole of the magnet.
31 Faraday’s Researches, Art.
2429, 2430.
Several philosophers of great eminence, however, who have examined
the subject with great care, adhere to Dr. Faraday’s first view of the
nature of Diamagnetism—as W. Weber,32 Plücker, and Mr.
Tyndall among ourselves. If we translate this view into the language
of Ampère’s theory, it comes to this:—that as currents are
induced in iron and magnetics parallel to those existing in the
inducing magnet or battery wire; so in bismuth, heavy glass, and other
diamagnetic bodies, the currents induced are in the contrary 621
directions:—these hypothetical currents being in non-conducting
diamagnetic, as in magnetic bodies, not in the mass, but round the
particles of the matter.
32 Poggendorf’s Ann. Jou.
1848.
Magneto-optic Effects and Magnecrystallic Polarity.
Not even yet have we terminated the enumeration of the co-existent
polarities which in this province of nature have been brought into
view. Light has polar properties; the very term polarization is
the record of the discovery of these. The forces which determine the
crystalline forms of bodies are of a polar nature: crystalline forms,
when complete, may be defined as those forms which have a certain
degree of symmetry in reference to opposite poles. Now has this
optical and crystalline polarity any relation to the electrical
polarity of which we have been speaking?
However much we might be disposed beforehand to conjecture that
there is some relation between these two groups of polar properties,
yet in this as in the other parts of this history of discoveries
respecting polarities, no conjecture hits the nature of the relation,
such as experiment showed it to be. In November, 1846, Faraday
announced the discovery of what he then called “the action of magnets
on light.” But this action was manifested, not on light directly, but
on light passing through certain kinds of glass.33 When this glass,
subjected to the action of the powerful magnets which he used,
transmitted a ray of light parallel to the line of magnetic force, an
effect was produced upon the light. But of what nature was this
effect? When light was ordinary light, no change in its condition was
discoverable. But if the light were light polarized in any plane, the
plane of polarization was turned round through a certain angle while
the ray passed through the glass:—a greater angle, in proportion
as the magnetic force was greater, and the thickness of the glass
greater.
33 Silicated borate of lead. See
Researches, § 2151, &c. Also flint glass, rock salt, water
(2215).
A power in some respects of this kind, namely, a power to rotate
the plane of polarization of a ray passing through them, is possessed
by some bodies in their natural state; for instance, quartz crystals,
and oil of turpentine. But yet, as Dr. Faraday remarks,34 there is a great difference in the two
cases. When polarized rays pass through oil of turpentine, in whatever
direction they pass, they all of them have their 622 plane of polarization
rotated in the same direction; that is, all to the right or all to the
left; but when a ray passes through the heavy glass, the power of
rotation exists only in a plane perpendicular to the magnetic line,
and its direction as right or left-handed is reversed by reversing the
magnetic polarity.
34 Researches, Art. 2231.
In this case, we have optical properties, which do not depend on
crystalline form, affected by the magnetic force. But it has also been
found that crystalline form, which is so fertile a source of optical
properties, affords indications of magnetic forces. In 1847, M.
Plücker,35 of the University of Bonn, using a
powerful magnetic apparatus, similar to Faraday’s, found that crystals
in general are magnetic, in this sense, that the axes of crystalline
form tend to assume a certain position with reference to the magnetic
lines of force. The possession of one optic axis or of two is one of
the broad distinctions of the different crystalline forms: and using
this distinction, M. Plücker found that a crystal having a single
optic axis tends to place itself with this axis transverse to the
magnetic line of force, as if its optic axis were repelled by each
magnetic pole; and crystals with two axes act as if each of these axes
were repelled by the magnetic poles. This force is independent of the
magnetic or diamagnetic character of the crystal; and is a directive,
more properly than an attractive or repulsive force.
35 Taylor’s Scientific Memoirs,
vol. v.
Soon afterwards (in 1848) Faraday also discovered36 an effect of magnetism depending on
crystalline form, which at first sight appeared to be different from
the effects observed by M. Plücker. He found that a crystal of
bismuth, of which the form is nearly a cube, but more truly a
rhombohedron with one diagonal a little longer than the others, tends
to place itself with this diagonal in the direction of the lines of
magnetic force. At first he conceived37 the properties
thus detected to be different from those observed by M. Plücker; since
in this case the force of a crystalline axis is axial, whereas in
those, it was equatorial. But a further consideration of the subject,
led him38 to a conviction that these forces must
be fundamentally identical: for it was easy to conceive a combination
of bismuth crystals which would behave in the magnetic field as a
crystal of calcspar does; or a combination of calcspar crystals which
would behave as a crystal of bismuth does.
36 Researches, Art. 2454,
&c.
37 Art. 2469.
38 Art. 2593, 2601.
And thus we have fresh examples to show that the Connexion of
coexistent Polarities is a thought deeply seated in the minds of the
623 profoundest and
most sagacious philosophers, and perpetually verified and illustrated,
by unforeseen discoveries in unguessed forms, through the labors of
the most skilful experimenters.
Magneto-electric Machines.
The discovery that a voltaic wire moved in presence of a magnet,
has a current generated in it, was employed as the ground of the
construction of machines to produce electrical effects. In Saxton’s
machine two coils of wire including a core of soft iron revolved
opposite to the ends of a horseshoe magnet, and thus, as the two coils
came opposite to the N. and S. and to the S. and N. poles of the
magnet, currents were generated alternately in the wires in opposite
directions. But by arranging the connexions of the ends of the wires,
the successive currents might be made to pass in corresponding
directions. The alternations or successions of currents in such
machines are governed by a contrivance which alternately interrupts
and permits the action; this contrivance has been called a
rheotome. Clarke gave a new form to a machine of the same
nature as Saxton’s. But the like effect may be produced by using an
electro-magnet instead of a common magnet. When this is done, a
current is produced which by induction produces a current in another
wire, and the action is alternately excited and interrupted. When the
inducing current is interrupted, a momentary current in an
opposite direction is produced in the induced wire; and when this
current stops, it produces in the inducing wire a current in the
original direction, which may be adjusted so as to reinforce the
resumed action of the original current. This was pointed out by M. De
la Rive in 1843.39 Machines have been constructed on such
principles by him and others. Of such machines the most powerful
hitherto known is that constructed by M. Ruhmkorff. The effects of
this instrument are exceedingly energetic.
39 Traité de l’Elect. i.
391.
Applications of Electrodynamic Discoveries.
The great series of discoveries of which I have had to speak have
been applied in many important ways to the uses of life. The
Electric Telegraph is one of the most remarkable of these. By
wires extended to the most distant places, the electric current is
transmitted 624
thither in an imperceptible time; and by means of well-devised systems
of operation, is made to convey from man to man words, which are now
most emphatically “winged words.” In the most civilised states such
wires now form a net-work across the land, which is familiar to our
thoughts as the highway is to our feet; and wide seas have such
pathways of human thought buried deep in their waves from shore to
shore. Again, by using the chemical effects of electrodynamic action,
of which we shall have to speak in the next Book,
a new means has been obtained of copying, with an exactness
unattainable before, any forms which art or nature has produced, and
of covering them with a surface of metal. The Electrotype
Process is now one of the great powers which manufacturing art
employs.
But these discoveries have also been employed in explaining natural
phenomena, the causes of which had before been altogether inscrutable.
This is the case with regard to the diurnal variation of the magnetic
needle; a fact  which as to its existence is universal in all places,
and which yet is so curiously diverse in its course at different
places. Dr. Faraday has shown that some of the most remarkable of
these diversities, and probably all, seem to be accounted for by the
different magnetic effects of air at different temperatures: although,
as I have already said, (Book xii.) the discovery of a
decennial period in the diurnal changes of magnetic declination shows
that any explanation of those changes which refers them to causes
existing in the atmosphere must be very incomplete.40
40 Researches, Art. 2892.


BOOK XIV.

CHEMISTRY.
</div></body></text></TEI>