<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="31">
CHAPTER XII.

Friction.[25]

We shall not pursue this argument of the last
chapter, by considering the other laws of motion in
the same manner as we have there considered the[184]
first, which might be done. But the facts which
form exceptions and apparent contradictions to the
first law of which we have been treating, and which
are very numerous, offer, we conceive, an additional
exemplification of the same argument; and this we
shall endeavour to illustrate.
The rule that a body naturally moves for ever
with an undiminished speed, is so far from being obviously
true, that it appears on a first examination to
be manifestly false. The hoop of the school boy, left
to itself, runs on a short distance, and then stops;
his top spins a little while, but finally flags and falls;
all motion on the earth appears to decay by its own
nature; all matter which we move appears to have
a perpetual tendency to divest itself of the velocity
which we communicate to it. How is this reconcileable
with the first law of motion on which we
have been insisting?
It is reconciled principally by considering the effect
of Friction. Among terrestrial objects friction
exerts an agency almost as universal and constant
as the laws of motion themselves; an agency which
completely changes and disguises the results of those
laws. We shall consider some of these effects.
It is probably not necessary to explain at any
length the nature and operation of friction. When
a body cannot move without causing two surfaces to
rub together, this rubbing has a tendency to diminish
the body’s motion or to prevent it entirely. If the
body of a carriage be placed on the earth without
the wheels, a considerable force will be requisite in
order to move it at all: it is here the friction against
the ground which obstructs the motion. If the carriage
be placed on its wheels, a much less force will
move it, but if moved it will soon stop: it is the friction
at the ground and at the axles which stops it:
placed on a level rail road, with well made and well
oiled wheels, and once put in motion, it might run a
considerable distance alone, for the friction is here[185]
much less; but there is friction, and therefore the
motion would after a time cease.
1. The friction which we shall principally consider
is the friction which prevents motion. So employed,
friction is one of the most universal and important
agents in the mechanism of our daily comforts and
occupations. It is a force which is called into play
to an extent incomparably greater than all the other
forces with which we are concerned in the course of
our daily life. We are dependent upon it at every
instant and in every action; and it is not possible to
enumerate the ways in which it serves us; scarcely
even to suggest a sufficient number of them to give
us a true notion of its functions.
What can appear a more simple operation than
standing and walking? yet it is easy to see that
without the aid of friction these simple actions would
scarcely be possible. Every one knows how difficult
and dangerous they are when performed on smooth
ice. In such a situation we cannot always succeed
in standing: if the ice be very smooth, it is by no
means easy to walk, even when the surface is perfectly
level; and if it were ever so little inclined, no
one would make the attempt. Yet walking on the
ice and on the ground differ only in our experiencing
more friction in the latter case. We say more, for
there is a considerable friction even in the case of
ice, as we see by the small distance which a stone
slides when thrown along the surface. It is this friction
of the earth which, at every step we take, prevents
the foot from sliding back; and thus allows us
to push the body and the other foot forwards. And
when we come to violent bodily motions, to running,
leaping, pulling or pushing objects, it is easily seen
how entirely we depend upon the friction of the
ground for our strength and force. Every one
knows how completely powerless we become in any
of these actions by the foot slipping.
In the same manner it is the friction of objects to
which the hand is applied, which enables us to hold[186]
them with any degree of firmness. In some contests
it was formerly the custom for the combatants to rub
their bodies with oil, that the adversary might not
be able to keep his grasp. If the pole of the boatman,
the rope of the sailor, were thus smooth and
lubricated, how weak would be the thrust and the
pull! Yet this would only be the removal of friction.
Our buildings are no less dependent on this force
for their stability. Some edifices are erected without
the aid of cement; and if the stones be large
and well squared, such structures may be highly
substantial and durable; even when rude and slight,
houses so built answer the purposes of life. These
are entirely upheld by friction, and without that agent
they would be thrown down by the Zephyr, far more
easily than if all the stones were lumps of ice with a
thawing surface. But even in cases where cement
binds the masonry, it does not take the duty of holding
it together. In consequence of the existence of
friction, there is no constant tendency of the stones
to separate; they are in a state of repose. If this
were not so, if every shock and every breeze required
to be counteracted by the cement, no composition
exists which would long sustain such a wear
and tear. The cement excludes the corroding elements,
and helps to resist extraordinary violence;
but it is friction which gives the habitual state of rest.
We are not to consider friction as a small force,
slightly modifying the effects of other agencies. On
the contrary its amount is in most cases very great.
When a body lies loose on the ground, the friction is
equal to one-third or one-half, or in some cases the
whole of its weight. But in cases of bodies supported
by oblique pressure, the amount is far more enormous.
In the arch of a bridge, the friction which is
called into play between two of the vaulting stones,
may be equal to the whole weight of the bridge. In
such cases this conservative force is so great, that
the common theory, which neglects it, does not help[187]
us even to guess what will take place. According
to the theory, certain forms of arches only will stand,
but in practice almost any form will stand, and it is
not easy to construct a model of a bridge which will
fall.
We may see the great force of friction in the
brake, by which a large weight running down a long
inclined plane has its motion moderated and stopt;
in the windlass, where a few coils of the rope round
a cylinder sustain the stress and weight of a large
iron anchor; in the nail or screw which holds together
large beams; in the mode of raising large blocks
of granite by an iron rod driven into a hole in the
stone. Probably no greater forces are exercised in
any processes in the arts than the force of friction;
and it is always employed to produce rest, stability,
moderate motion. Being always ready and never
wearied, always at hand and augmenting with the
exigency, it regulates, controls, subdues all motions;—counteracts
all other agents;—and finally gains
the mastery over all other terrestrial agencies, however
violent, frequent, or long continued. The perpetual
action of all other terrestrial forces appears,
on a large scale, only as so many interruptions of
the constant and stationary rule of friction.
The objects which every where surround us, the
books or dishes which stand on our tables, our tables
and chairs themselves, the loose clods and stones in
the field, the heaviest masses produced by nature or
art, would be in a perpetual motion, quick or slow
according to the forces which acted on them, and to
their size, if it were not for the tranquillizing and
steadying effects of the agent we are considering.
Without this, our apartments, if they kept their
shape, would exhibit to us articles of furniture, and
of all other kinds, sliding and creeping from side to
side with every push and every wind, like loose objects
in a ship’s cabin, when she is changing her
course in a gale.
Here, then, we have a force, most extensive and[188]
incessant in its operation, which is absolutely essential
to the business of this terrestrial world, according
to any notion which we can form. The more
any one considers its effects, and the more he will
find how universally dependent he is upon it, in
every action of his life; resting or moving, dealing
with objects of art or of nature, with instruments of
enjoyment or of action.
2. Now we have to observe concerning this agent,
Friction, that we have no ground for asserting it to
be a necessary result of other properties of matter,
for instance, of their solidity and coherency. Philosophers
have not been able to deduce the laws of
friction from the other known properties of matter,
nor even to explain what we know experimentally of
such laws, (which is not much,) without introducing
new hypotheses concerning the surfaces of bodies,
&c.—hypotheses which are not supplied us by any
other set of phenomena. So far as our knowledge
goes, friction is a separate property, and may be
conceived to have been bestowed upon matter for
particular purposes. How well it answers the purpose
of fitting matter for the uses of the daily life of
man, we have already seen.
We may make suppositions as to the mode in
which friction is connected with the texture of bodies;
but little can be gained for philosophy, or for speculation
of any kind, by such conjectures respecting
unknown connexions. If, on the other hand, we
consider this property of friction, and find that it
prevails there, and there only, where the general
functions, analogies, and relations of the universe
require it, we shall probably receive a strong impression
that it was introduced into the system of the
world for a purpose.
3. It is very remarkable that this force, which is
thus so efficacious and discharges such important
offices in all earthly mechanism, disappears altogether
when we turn to the mechanism of the heavens.
All motions on the earth soon stop;—a machine[189]
which imitates the movements of the stars cannot
go long without winding up: but the stars themselves
have gone on in their courses for ages, with no diminution
of their motions, and offer no obvious prospect
of any change. This is so palpable a fact, that
the first attempts of men to systematize their mechanical
notions were founded upon it. The ancients
held that motions were to be distinguished into natural
motions and violent,—the former go on without
diminution—the latter are soon extinguished;—the
motions of the stars are of the former kind;—those
of a stone thrown, and in short all terrestrial motions,
of the latter. Modern philosophers maintain
that the laws of motion are the same for celestial
and terrestrial bodies;—that all motions are natural
according to the above description;—but that in terrestrial
motions, friction comes in and alters their character,—destroys
them so speedily that they appear to
have existed only during an effort. And that this is
the case will not now be contested. Is it not then
somewhat remarkable that the same laws which produce
a state of permanent motion in the heavens,
should, on the earth, give rise to a condition in which
rest is the rule and motion the exception? The air,
the waters, and the lighter portions of matter are,
no doubt, in a state of perpetual motion; over these
friction has no empire: yet even their motions are
interrupted, alternate, variable, and on the whole
slight deviations from the condition of equilibrium.
But in the solid parts of the globe, rest predominates
incomparably over motion: and this, not only with
regard to the portions which cohere as parts of the
same solid; for the whole surface of the earth is
covered with loose masses, which, if the power of
friction were abolished, would rush from their places
and begin one universal and interminable dance,
which would make the earth absolutely uninhabitable.
If, on the other hand, the dominion of friction were
extended in any considerable degree into the planetary[190]
spaces, there would soon be an end of the system.
If the planet had moved in a fluid, as the Cartesians
supposed, and if this fluid had been subject to
the rules of friction which prevail in terrestrial fluids,
their motions could not have been of long duration.
The solar system must soon have ceased to be a system
of revolving bodies.
But friction is neither abolished on the earth, nor
active in the heavens. It operates where it is wanted,
it is absent where it would be prejudicial. And both
these circumstances occasion, in a remarkable manner,
the steadiness of the course of nature. The
stable condition of the objects in man’s immediate
neighbourhood, and the unvarying motions of the
luminaries of heaven, are alike conducive to his well-being.
This requires that he should be able to depend
upon a fixed order of place, a fixed course of
time. It requires, therefore, that terrestrial objects
should be affected by friction, and that celestial
should not; as is the case, in fact. What further
evidence of benevolent design could this part of the
constitution of the universe supply?
4. There is another view which may be taken of
the forces which operate on the earth to produce
permanency or change. Some parts of the terrestrial
system are under the dominion of powers which
act energetically to prevent all motion, as the crystalline
forces by which the parts of rocks are bound
together; other parts are influenced by powers which
produce a perpetual movement and change in the
matter of which they consist; thus plants and animals
are in a constant state of internal movement,
by the agency of the vital forces. In the former case
rigid immutability, in the latter perpetual developement,
are the tendencies of the agencies employed.
Now in the case of objects affected by friction, we
have a kind of intermediate condition, between the
constantly fixed and the constantly moveable. Such
objects can and do move; but they move but for a
short time if left to the laws of nature. When at[191]
rest, they can easily be put in motion, but still not
with unlimited ease; a certain finite effort, different
in different cases, is requisite for their purpose. Now
this immediate condition, this capacity of receiving
readily and alternately the states of rest and motion,
is absolutely requisite for the nature of man, for the
exertion of will, of contrivance, of foresight, as well
as for the comfort of life and the conditions of our
material existence. If all objects were fixed and
immoveable, as if frozen into one mass; or if they
were susceptible of such motions only as are found
in the parts of vegetables, we attempt in vain to conceive
what would come of the business of the world.
But besides the state of a particle which cannot be
moved, and of a particle which cannot be stopped,
we have the state of a particle moveable but not
moved; or moved, but moved only while we choose:
and this state is that about which the powers, the
thoughts, and the wants of man are mainly conversant.
Thus the forces by which solidity and by which
organic action are produced, the laws of permanence
and of developement, do not bring about all that happens.
Besides these, there is a mechanical condition,
that of a body exposed to friction, which is neither
one of absolute permanency nor one naturally progressive;
but is yet one absolutely necessary to make
material objects capable of being instruments and
aids to man; and this is the condition of by far the
greater part of terrestrial things. The habitual
course of events with regard to motion and rest is
not the same for familiar moveable articles, as it is
for the parts of the mineral, or of the vegetable world,
when left to themselves; such articles are in a condition
far better adapted than any of those other conditions
would be, to their place and purpose. Surely
this shows us an adaptation, an adjustment, of the
constitution of the material world to the nature of
man. And as the organization of plants cannot be
conceived otherwise than as having their life and[192]
growth for its object, so we cannot conceive that
friction should be one of the leading agencies in the
world in which man is placed, without supposing
that it was intended to be of use when man should
walk and run, and build houses and ships, and bridges,
and execute innumerable other processes, all of which
would be impossible, admirably constituted as man is
in other respects, if friction did not exist. And believing,
as we conceive we cannot but believe, that
the laws of motion and rest were thus given with reference
to their ends, we perceive in this instance, as
in others, how wide and profound this reference is,
how simple in its means, how fertile in its consequences,
how effective in its details.
</div></body></text></TEI>