<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="5">

CHAPTER V.
Of the Grounds of Necessary Truths.



1. TO
the question just stated, I reply, that the necessity
and universality of the truths which form a part of our
knowledge, are derived from the Fundamental Ideas
which those truths involve. These ideas entirely shape and
circumscribe our knowledge; they regulate the active
operations of our minds, without which our passive
sensations do not become knowledge. They govern these
operations, according to rules which are not only fixed and
permanent, but which may be expressed in plain and definite
terms; and these rules, when thus expressed, may be made the
basis of demonstrations by which the necessary relations
imparted to our knowledge by our Ideas may be traced to
their consequences in the most remote ramifications of
scientific truth.
These enunciations of the necessary and evident conditions
imposed upon our knowledge by the Fundamental Ideas which it
involves, are termed Axioms. Thus the Axioms of
Geometry express the necessary conditions which result from
the Idea of Space; the Axioms of Mechanics express the
necessary conditions which flow from the Ideas of Force and
Motion; and so on.
2. It will be the office of several of the succeeding Books
of this work to establish and illustrate in detail what I
have thus stated in general terms. I shall there pass in
review many of the most important fundamental ideas on which
the existing body of our science depends; and I shall
endeavour to show, for each such idea in succession, that
knowledge involves an active as well as a passive element;
that it is not possible without an act of the mind,
regulated by certain 70 laws. I shall further attempt to
enumerate some of the principal fundamental relations which
each idea thus introduces into our thoughts, and to express
them by means of definitions and axioms, and other suitable
forms.
I will only add a remark or two to illustrate further this
view of the ideal grounds of our knowledge.
3. To persons familiar with any of the demonstrative
sciences, it will be apparent that if we state all the
Definitions and Axioms which are employed in the
demonstrations, we state the whole basis on which those
reasonings rest. For the whole process of demonstrative or
deductive reasoning in any science, (as in geometry, for
instance,) consists entirely in combining some of these
first principles so as to obtain the simplest propositions
of the science; then combining these so as to obtain other
propositions of greater complexity; and so on, till we
advance to the most recondite demonstrable truths; these
last, however intricate and unexpected, still involving no
principles except the original definitions and axioms. Thus,
by combining the Definition of a triangle, and the
Definitions of equal lines and equal angles, namely, that
they are such as when applied to each other, coincide, with
the Axiom respecting straight lines (that two such lines
cannot inclose a space,) we demonstrate the equality of
triangles, under certain assumed conditions. Again, by
combining this result with the Definition of parallelograms,
and with the Axiom that if equals be taken from equals the
wholes are equal, we prove the equality of parallelograms
between the same parallels and upon the same base. From this
proposition, again, we prove the equality of the square on
the hypotenuse of a triangle to the squares on the two sides
containing the right angle. But in all this there is nothing
contained which is not rigorously the result of our
geometrical Definitions and Axioms. All the rest of our
treatises of geometry consists only of terms and phrases of
reasoning, the object of which is to connect those first
principles, and to exhibit the effects of their combination
in the shape of demonstration. 71
4. This combination of first principles takes place
according to the forms and rules of Logic. All the
steps of the demonstration may be stated in the shape in
which logicians are accustomed to exhibit processes of
reasoning in order to show their conclusiveness, that is, in
Syllogisms. Thus our geometrical reasonings might be
resolved into such steps as the following:—
 All straight lines drawn from the centre of a circle to its
circumference are equal:
 But the straight lines ab, ac, are drawn from the centre of
a circle to its circumference:
 Therefore the straight lines ab, ac, are equal.
Each step of geometrical, and all other demonstrative
reasoning, may be resolved into three such clauses as these;
and these three clauses are termed respectively, the
major premiss, the minor premiss, and the
conclusion; or, more briefly, the major, the
minor, and the conclusion.
The principle which justifies the reasoning when exhibited
in this syllogistic form, is this:—that a truth which can
be asserted as generally, or rather as universally true, can
be asserted as true also in each particular case. The
minor only asserts a certain particular case to be an
example of such conditions as are spoken of in the
major; and hence the conclusion, which is true of the
major by supposition, is true of the minor by consequence;
and thus we proceed from syllogism to syllogism, in each one
employing some general truth in some particular instance.
Any proof which occurs in geometry, or any other science of
demonstration, may thus be reduced to a series of processes,
in each of which we pass from some general proposition to
the narrower and more special propositions which it
includes. And this process of deriving truths by the mere
combination of general principles, applied in particular
hypothetical cases, is called deduction; being
opposed to induction, in which, as we have seen
(chap. i. sect. 3), a new general principle is introduced at
every step.
5. Now we have to remark that, this being so, however far we
follow such deductive reasoning, we can 72 never have, in
our conclusion any truth which is not virtually included in
the original principles from which the reasoning started.
For since at any step we merely take out of a general
proposition something included in it, while at the preceding
step we have taken this general proposition out of one more
general, and so on perpetually, it is manifest that our last
result was really included in the principle or principles
with which we began. I say principles, because,
although our logical conclusion can only exhibit the
legitimate issue of our first principles, it may,
nevertheless, contain the result of the combination of
several such principles, and may thus assume a great degree
of complexity, and may appear so far removed from the parent
truths, as to betray at first sight hardly any relationship
with them. Thus the proposition which has already been
quoted respecting the squares on the sides of a right-angled
triangle, contains the results of many elementary
principles; as, the definitions of parallels, triangle, and
square; the axioms respecting straight lines, and respecting
parallels; and, perhaps, others. The conclusion is
complicated by containing the effects of the combination of
all these elements; but it contains nothing, and can contain
nothing, but such elements and their combinations.
This doctrine, that logical reasoning produces no new
truths, but only unfolds and brings into view those truths
which were, in effect, contained in the first principles of
the reasoning, is assented to by almost all who, in modern
times, have attended to the science of logic. Such a view is
admitted both by those who defend, and by those who
depreciate the value of logic. ‘Whatever is established by
reasoning, must have been contained and virtually asserted
in the premises6.’ ‘The only truth which such
propositions can possess consists in conformity to the
original principles.’</div></body></text></TEI>