<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="79">CHAPTER IV.
Physical Theories of Heat.
WHEN we look at the condition
of that branch of knowledge which, according to the phraseology
already employed, we must call Physical Thermotics, in
opposition to Formal Thermotics, which gives us detached laws of
phenomena, we find the prospect very different from that which was
presented to us by physical astronomy, optics, and acoustics. In these
sciences, the maintainers of a distinct and comprehensive theory have
professed at least to show that it explains and includes the principal
laws of phenomena of various kinds; in Thermotics, we have only
attempts to explain a part of the facts. We have here no example of an
hypothesis which, assumed in order to explain one class of phenomena,
has been found also to account exactly for another; as when central
forces led to the precession of the equinoxes, or when the explanation
of polarization explained also double refraction; or when the pressure
of the atmosphere, as measured by the barometer, gave the true
velocity of sound. Such coincidences, or consiliences, as I
have elsewhere called them, are the test of truth; and thermotical
theories cannot yet exhibit credentials of this kind. 181
On looking back at our view of this science, it will be seen that
it may be distinguished into two parts; the Doctrines of Conduction
and Radiation, which we call Thermotics proper; and the Doctrines
respecting the relation of Heat, Airs, and Moisture, which we have
termed Atmology. These two subjects differ in their bearing on our
hypothetical views.
Thermotical Theories.—The phenomena of radiant heat,
like those of radiant light, obviously admit of general explanation in
two different ways;—by the emission of material particles, or by
the propagation of undulations. Both these opinions have found
supporters. Probably most persons, in adopting Prevost’s theory of
exchanges, conceive the radiation of heat to be the radiation of
matter. The undulation hypothesis, on the other hand, appears to be
suggested by the production of heat by friction, and was accordingly
maintained by Rumford and others. Leslie68 appears, in a
great part of his Inquiry, to be a supporter of some undulatory
doctrine, but it is extremely difficult to make out what his
undulating medium is; or rather, his opinions wavered during his
progress. In page 31, he asks, “What is this calorific and frigorific
fluid? and after keeping the reader in suspense for a moment, he
replies,
“Quod petis hic est.
It is merely the ambient AIR.” But at page 150, he
again asks the question, and, at page 188, he answers, “It is the same
subtile matter that, according to its different modes of existence,
constitutes either heat or light.” A person thus vacillating between
two opinions, one of which is palpably false, and the other laden with
exceeding difficulties which he does not even attempt to remove, had
little right to protest against69 “the sportive
freaks of some intangible aura;” to rank all other hypotheses
than his own with the “occult qualities of the schools;” and to class
the “prejudices” of his opponents with the tenets of those who
maintained the fuga vacui in opposition to Torricelli. It is
worth while noticing this kind of rhetoric, in order to observe, that
it may be used just as easily on the wrong side as on the right.
68 An Experimental Inquiry into
the Nature and Propagation of Heat, 1804.
69 Ib. p. 47.
Till recently, the theory of material heat, and of its propagation
by emission, was probably the one most in favor with those who had
studied mathematical thermotics. As we have said, the laws of 182 conduction, in their ultimate analytical
form, were almost identical with the laws of motion of fluids.
Fourier’s principle also, that the radiation of heat takes place from
points below the surface, and is intercepted by the superficial
particles, appears to favor the notion of material emission.
Accordingly, some of the most eminent modern French mathematicians
have accepted and extended the hypothesis of a material caloric. In
addition to Fourier’s doctrine of molecular extra-radiation, Laplace
and Poisson have maintained the hypothesis of molecular
intra-radiation, as the mode in which conduction takes place; that
is, they say that the particles of bodies are to be considered as
discrete, or as points separated from each other, and acting on
each other at a distance; and the conduction of heat from one part to
another, is performed by radiation between all neighboring particles.
They hold that, without this hypothesis, the differential equations
expressing the conditions of conduction cannot be made homogeneous:
but this assertion rests, I conceive, on an error, as Fourier has
shown, by dispensing with the hypothesis. The necessity of the
hypothesis of discrete molecular action in bodies, is maintained in
all cases by M. Poisson; and he has asserted Laplace’s theory of
capillary attraction to be defective on this ground, as Laplace
asserted Fourier’s reasoning respecting heat to be so. In reality,
however, this hypothesis of discrete molecules cannot be maintained as
a physical truth; for the law of molecular action, which is assumed in
the reasoning, after answering its purpose in the progress of
calculation, vanishes in the result; the conclusion is the same,
whatever law of the intervals of the molecules be assumed. The
definite integral, which expresses the whole action, no more proves
that this action is actually made of the differential parts by means
of which it was found, than the processes of finding the weight of a
body by integration, prove it to be made up of differential weights.
And therefore, even if we were to adopt the emission theory of heat,
we are by no means bound to take along with it the hypothesis of
discrete molecules.
But the recent discovery of the refraction, polarization, and
depolarization of heat, has quite altered the theoretical aspect of
the subject, and, almost at a single blow, ruined the emission theory.
Since heat is reflected and refracted like light, analogy would lead
us to conclude that the mechanism of the processes is the same in the
two cases. And when we add to these properties the property of
polarization, it is scarcely possible to believe otherwise than that
heat consists in 183 transverse vibrations; for no wise
philosopher would attempt an explanation by ascribing poles to the
emitted particles, after the experience which Optics affords, of the
utter failure of such machinery.
But here the question occurs, If heat consists in vibrations,
whence arises the extraordinary identity of the laws of its
propagation with the laws of the flow of matter? How is it that, in
conducted heat, this vibration creeps slowly from one part of the body
to another, the part first heated remaining hottest; instead of
leaving its first place and travelling rapidly to another, as the
vibrations of sound and light do? The answer to these questions has
been put in a very distinct and plausible form by that distinguished
philosopher, M. Ampère, who published a Note on Heat and Light
considered as the results of Vibratory Motion,70 in 1834 and 1835; and though this
answer is an hypothesis, it at least shows that there is no fatal
force in the difficulty.
70 Bibliothèque Universelle de
Genève, vol. xlix. p. 225. Ann. Chim. tom. lvii. p.
434.
M. Ampère’s hypothesis is this; that bodies consist of solid
molecules, which may be considered as arranged at intervals in a very
rare ether; and that the vibrations of the molecules, causing
vibrations of the ether and caused by them, constitute heat. On these
suppositions, we should have the phenomena of conduction explained;
for if the molecules at one end of a bar be hot, and therefore in a
state of vibration, while the others are at rest, the vibrating
molecules propagate vibrations in the ether, but these vibrations do
not produce heat, except in proportion as they put the quiescent
molecules of the bar in vibration; and the ether being very rare
compared with the molecules, it is only by the repeated impulses of
many successive vibrations that the nearest quiescent molecules are
made to vibrate; after which they combine in communicating the
vibration to the more remote molecules. “We then find necessarily,” M.
Ampère adds, “the same equations as those found by Fourier for the
distribution of heat, setting out from the same hypothesis, that the
temperature or heat transmitted is proportional to the difference of
the temperatures.”
Since the undulatory hypothesis of heat can thus answer all obvious
objections, we may consider it as upon its trial, to be confirmed or
modified by future discoveries; and especially by an enlarged
knowledge of the laws of the polarization of heat.
[2nd Ed.] [Since the first edition was written, the analogies
between light and heat have been further extended, as I have already
stated. It 184 has
been discovered by MM. Biot and Melloni that quartz impresses a
circular polarization upon heat; and by Prof. Forbes that mica, of a
certain thickness, produces phenomena such as would be produced by the
impression of circular polarization of the supposed transversal
vibrations of radiant heat; and further, a rhomb of rock-salt, of the
shape of the glass rhomb which verified Fresnel’s extraordinary
anticipation of the circular polarization of light, verified the
expectation, founded upon other analogies, of the polarization of
heat. By passing polarized heat through various thicknesses of mica,
Prof. Forbes has attempted to calculate the length of an undulation
for heat.
These analogies cannot fail to produce a strong disposition to
believe that light and heat, essences so closely connected that they
can hardly be separated, and thus shown to have so many curious
properties in common, are propagated by the same machinery; and thus
we are led to an Undulatory Theory of Heat.
Yet such a Theory has not yet by any means received full
confirmation. It depends upon the analogy and the connexion of the
Theory of Light, and would have little weight if those were removed.
For the separation of the rays in double refraction, and the phenomena
of periodical intensity, the two classes of facts out of which the
Undulatory Theory of Optics principally grew, have neither of them
been detected in thermotical experiments. Prof. Forbes has assumed
alternations of heat for increasing thicknesses of mica, but in his
experiments we find only one maximum. The occurrence of
alternate maxima and minima under the like circumstances would exhibit
visible waves of heat, as the fringes of shadows do of light, and
would thus add much to the evidence of the theory.
Even if I conceived the Undulatory Theory of Heat to be now
established, I should not venture, as yet, to describe its
establishment as an event in the history of the Inductive Sciences. It
is only at an interval of time after such events have taken place that
their history and character can be fully understood, so as to suggest
lessons in the Philosophy of Science.]
Atmological Theories.—Hypotheses of the relations of
heat and air almost necessarily involve a reference to the forces by
which the composition of bodies is produced, and thus cannot properly
be treated of, till we have surveyed the condition of chemical
knowledge. But we may say a few words on one such hypothesis; I mean
the hypothesis on the subject of the atmological laws of heat,
proposed by Laplace, in the twelfth Book of the Mécanique
Céléste, and published in 1823. 185 It will be recollected that the main
laws of phenomena for which we have to account, by means of such an
hypothesis, are the following:—
(1.) The law of Boyle and Mariotte, that the elasticity of an air
varies as its density. See Chap. iii., Sect.
1 of this Book.
(2.) The Law of Gay-Lussac and Dalton, that all airs expand equally
by heat. See Chap. ii. Sect. 1.
(3.) The production of heat by sudden compression. See Chap. ii. Sect. 2.
(4.) Dalton’s principle of the mechanical mixture of airs. See
Chap. iii. Sect. 3.
(5.) The Law of expansion of solids and fluids by heat. See Chap.
ii. Sect. 1.
(6.) Changes of consistence by heat, and the doctrine of latent
heat. See Chap. ii. Sect. 3.
(7.) The Law of the expansive force of steam. See Chap. iii. Sect. 4.
Besides these, there are laws of which it is doubtful whether they
are or are not included in the preceding, as the low temperature of
the air in the higher parts of the atmosphere. (See Chap. iii. Sect. 5.)
Laplace’s hypothesis71 is this:—that bodies consist of
particles, each of which gathers round it, by its attraction, a
quantity of caloric: that the particles of the bodies attract each
other, besides attracting the caloric, and that the particles of the
caloric repel each other.
71 Méc. Cél. t. v. p.
89.
In gases, the particles of the bodies are so far removed, that
their mutual attraction is insensible, and the matter tends to expand
by the mutual repulsion of the caloric. He conceives this caloric to
be constantly radiating among the particles; the density of this
internal radiation is the temperature, and he proves that, on
this supposition, the elasticity of the air will be as the density,
and as this temperature. Hence follow the three first rules above
stated. The same suppositions lead to Dalton’s principle of mixtures
(4), though without involving his mode of conception; for Laplace says
that whatever the mutual action of two gases be, the whole pressure
will be equal to the sum of the separate pressures.72 Expansion (5), and the changes of
consistence (6), are explained by supposing73 that in solids,
the mutual attraction of the particles of the body is the greatest
force; in liquids, the attraction of the particles for the caloric; in
airs, the repulsion of 186 the caloric. But the doctrine of latent
heat again modifies74 the hypothesis, and makes it necessary
to include latent heat in the calculation; yet there is not, as we
might suppose there would be if the theory were the true one, any
confirmation of the hypothesis resulting from the new class of laws
thus referred to. Nor does it appear that the hypothesis accounts for
the relation between the elasticity and the temperature of steam.
72 Ib. p. 110.
73 Ib. p. 92.
74 Méc. Cél. t. v. p.
93.
It will be observed that Laplace’s hypothesis goes entirely upon
the materiality of heat, and is inconsistent with any vibratory
theory; for, as Ampère remarks, “It is clear that if we admit heat to
consist in vibrations, it is a contradiction to attribute to heat (or
caloric) a repulsive force of the particles which would be a cause of
vibration.”
An unfavorable judgment of Laplace’s Theory of Gases is suggested
by looking for that which, in speaking of Optics, was mentioned as the
great characteristic of a true theory; namely, that the hypotheses,
which were assumed in order to account for one class of facts, are
found to explain another class of a different nature:—the
consilience of inductions. Thus, in thermotics, the law of an
intensity of radiation proportional to the sine of the angle of the
ray with the surface, which is founded on direct experiments of
radiation, is found to be necessary in order to explain the tendency
of neighboring bodies to equality of temperature; and this leads to
the higher generalization, that heat is radiant from points below the
surface. But in the doctrine of the relation of heat to gases, as
delivered by Laplace, there is none of this unexpected confirmation;
and though he explains some of the leading laws, his assumptions bear
a large proportion to the laws explained. Thus, from the assumption
that the repulsion of gases arises from the mutual repulsion of the
particles of caloric, he finds that the pressure in any gas is as the
square of the density and of the quantity of caloric;75 and from the assumption that the
temperature is the internal radiation, he finds that this temperature
is as the density and the square of the caloric.76 Hence he
obtains the law of Boyle and Mariotte, and that of Dalton and
Gay-Lussac. But this view of the subject requires other assumptions
when we come to latent heat; and accordingly, he introduces, to
express the latent heat, a new quantity.77 Yet this
quantity produces no effect on his calculations, nor does he apply his
reasoning to any problem in which latent heat is concerned.
75 P = 2 π h
k ρ2c2 (1) p. 107.
76 q′ Π (a) =
ρc2 (2) p. 108.
77 The quantity i, p.
113.
187 Without,
then, deciding upon this theory, we may venture to say that it is
wanting in all the prominent and striking characteristics which we
have found in those great theories which we look upon as clearly and
indisputably established.
Conclusion.—We may observe, moreover, that heat has
other bearings and effects, which, as soon as they have been analysed
into numerical laws of phenomena, must be attended to in the formation
of thermotical theories. Chemistry will probably supply many such;
those which occur to us, we must examine hereafter. But we may mention
as examples of such, MM. De la Rive and Marcet’s law, that the
specific heat of all gases is the same;78 and MM. Dulong
and Petit’s law, that single atoms of all simple bodies have the same
capacity for heat.79 Though we have not yet said anything of
the relation of different gases, or explained the meaning of
atoms in the chemical sense, it will easily be conceived that
these are very general and important propositions.
78 Ann. Chim. xxxv.
(1827.)
79 Ib. x. 397.
Thus the science of Thermotics, imperfect as it is, forms a
highly-instructive part of our survey; and is one of the cardinal
points on which the doors of those chambers of physical knowledge must
turn which hitherto have remained closed. For, on the one hand, this
science is related by strong analogies and dependencies to the most
complete portions of our knowledge, our mechanical doctrines and
optical theories; and on the other, it is connected with properties
and laws of a nature altogether different,—those of chemistry;
properties and laws depending upon a new system of notions and
relations, among which clear and substantial general principles are
far more difficult to lay hold of and with which the future progress
of human knowledge appears to be far more concerned. To these notions
and relations we must now proceed; but we shall find an intermediate
stage, in certain subjects which I shall call the
Mechanico-chemical Sciences; viz., those which have to do with
Magnetism, Electricity, and Galvanism.
~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~


BOOK XI.

THE MECHANICO-CHEMICAL
SCIENCES.

HISTORY OF ELECTRICITY.

Parva metu primo: mox sese
extollit in auras,
Ingrediturque solo, et caput inter nubila
condit.
Æn. iv.
176.    


A timid breath at first, a transient touch,
How soon it swells from little into much!
Runs o’er the ground, and springs into the
air,
And fills the tempest’s gloom, the lightning’s
glare;
While denser darkness than the central
storm
Conceals the secrets of its inward form.

</div></body></text></TEI>