<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="20">
[121]
CHAPTER I.

The Structure of the Solar System.

In the cosmical considerations which we have to
offer, we shall suppose the general truths concerning
the structure of the solar system and of the universe,
which have been established by astronomers
and mathematicians, to be known to the reader. It
is not necessary to go into much detail on this subject.
The five planets known to the ancients, Mercury,
Venus, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn, revolve round
the sun, at different distances, in orbits nearly circular,
and nearly in one plane. Between Venus and
Mars, our Earth, herself one of the planets, revolves
in like manner. Beyond Saturn, Uranus has
been discovered describing an orbit of the same
kind; and between Mars and Jupiter, four smaller
bodies perform their revolutions in orbits somewhat
less regular than the rest. These planets are all
nearly globular, and all revolve upon their axis.
Some of them are accompanied by satellites, or attendant
bodies which revolve about them; and these
bodies also have their orbits nearly circular, and
nearly in the same plane as the others. Saturn’s
ring is a solitary example, so far as we know, of
such an appendage to a planet.
These circular motions of the planets round the
sun, and of the satellites round their primary planets,
are all kept going by the attraction of the respective
central bodies, which restrains the corresponding
revolving bodies from flying off. It is perhaps not
very easy to make this operation clear to common
apprehension. We cannot illustrate it by a comparison
with any machine of human contrivance and
fabrication: in such machines every thing goes on[122]
by contact and impulse: pressure, and force of all
kinds, is exercised and transferred from one part to
another, by means of a material connexion; by rods,
ropes, fluids, gases. In the machinery of the universe
there is, so far as we know, no material connexion
between the parts which act on each other.
In the solar system no part touches or drives another:
all the bodies affect each other at a distance,
as the magnet affects the needle. The production
and regulation of such effects, if attempted by our
mechanicians, would require great skill and nicety
of adjustment; but our artists have not executed any
examples of this sort of machinery, by reference to
which we can illustrate the arrangements of the
solar system.
Perhaps the following comparison may serve to
explain the kind of adjustments of which we shall
have to speak. If there be a wide shallow round
basin of smooth marble, and if we take a smooth
ball, as a billiard ball or a marble pellet, and throw
it along the surface of the inside of the basin, the
ball will generally make many revolutions round the
inside of the bowl, gradually tending to the bottom
in its motion. The gradual diminution of the motion,
and consequent tendency of the ball to the bottom
of the bowl, arises from the friction; and in order
to make the motion correspond to that which takes
place through the action of a central force, we must
suppose this friction to be got rid of. In this case,
the ball, once set a going, would run round the basin
for ever, describing either a circle, or various kinds
of ovals, according to the way in which it was originally
thrown; whether quick or slow, and whether
more or less obliquely along the surface.
Such a motion would be capable of the same kind
of variety, and the same sort of adjustments, as the
motion of a body revolving about a larger one by
means of a central force. Perhaps the reader may
understand what kind of adjustments these are, by
supposing such a bowl and ball to be used for a game[123]
of skill. If the object of the players be to throw the
pellet along the surface of the basin, so that after describing
its curved path it shall pass through a small
hole in a barrier at some distance from the starting
point, it will easily be understood that some nicety in
the regulation of the force and direction with which
the ball is thrown will be necessary for success. In
order to obtain a better image of the solar system,
we must suppose the basin to be very large and the
pellet very small. And it will easily be understood
that as many pellets as there are planets might run
round the bowl at the same time with different velocities.
Such a contrivance might form a planetarium
in which the mimic planets would be regulated by
the laws of motion as the real planets are; instead of
being carried by wires and wheels, as is done in
such machines of the common construction: and in
this planetarium the tendency of the planets to the
sun is replaced by the tendency of the representative
pellets to run down the slope of the bowl. We shall
refer again to this basin, thus representing the solar
system with its loose planetary balls.
</div></body></text></TEI>