<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="86">CHAPTER II.
Reception and Confirmation of the Discovery of
Voltaic Electricity.
GALVANI’S experiments excited
a great interest all over Europe, in consequence partly of a
circumstance which, as we have seen, was unessential, the muscular
contractions and various sensations which they occasioned. Galvani
himself had not only considered the animal element of the circuit as
the origin of the electricity, but had framed a theory,5
in which he compared the muscles to charged jars, and the nerves to
the discharging wires; and a controversy was, for some time, carried
on, in Italy, between the adherents of Galvani and those of Volta.6
5 Ib. viii. 613.
6 Ib. viii. 619.
The galvanic experiments, and especially those which appeared to
have a physiological bearing, were verified and extended by a number
of the most active philosophers of Europe, and especially William von
Humboldt. A commission of the Institute of France, appointed in 1797,
repeated many of the known experiments, but does not seem to have
decided any disputed points. The researches of this 241 commission referred
rather to the discoveries of Galvani than to those of Volta: the
latter were, indeed, hardly known in France till the conquest of Italy
by Bonaparte, in 1801. France was, at the period of these discoveries,
separated from all other countries by war, and especially from
England,7 where Volta’s Memoirs were
published.
7 Biog. Univ., art.
Volta, (by Biot.)
The political revolutions of Italy affected, in very different
manners, the two discoverers of whom we speak. Galvani refused to take
an oath of allegiance to the Cisalpine republic, which the French
conqueror established; he was consequently stripped of all his
offices; and deprived, by the calamities of the times, of most of his
relations, he sank into poverty, melancholy, and debility. At last his
scientific reputation induced the republican rulers to decree his
restoration to his professorial chair; but his claims were recognised
too late, and he died without profiting by this intended favor, in
1798.
Volta, on the other hand, was called to Paris by Bonaparte as a man
of science, and invested with honors, emoluments, and titles. The
conqueror himself, indeed, was strongly interested by this train of
research.8 He himself founded valuable prizes,
expressly with a view to promote its prosecution. At this period,
there was something in this subject peculiarly attractive to his
Italian mind; for the first glimpses of discoveries of great promise
have always excited an enthusiastic activity of speculation in the
philosophers of Italy, though generally accompanied with a want of
precise thought. It is narrated9 of Bonaparte,
that after seeing the decomposition of the salts by means of the
voltaic pile, he turned to Corvisart, his physician, and said, “Here,
doctor, is the image of life; the vertebral column is the pile, the
liver is the negative, the bladder the positive, pole.” The importance
of voltaic researches is not less than it was estimated by Bonaparte;
but the results to which it was to lead were of a kind altogether
different from those which thus suggested themselves to his mind. The
connexion of mechanical and chemical action was the first great point
to be dealt with; and for this purpose the laws of the mechanical
action of voltaic electricity were to be studied.
8 Becquerel, Traité d’Electr.
t. i. p. 107.
9 Ib. t. i. p. 108.
It will readily be supposed that the voltaic researches, thus
begun, opened a number of interesting topics of examination and
discussion. These, however, it does not belong to our place to dwell
upon at present; since they formed parts of the theory of the subject,
which 242 was not
completed till light had been thrown upon it from other quarters. The
identity of galvanism with electricity, for instance, was at first, as
we have intimated, rather conjectured than proved. It was denied by
Dr. Fowler, in 1793; was supposed to be confirmed by Dr. Wells two
years later; but was, still later, questioned by Davy. The nature of
the operation of the pile was variously conceived. Volta himself had
obtained a view of it which succeeding researches confirmed, when he
asserted,10 in 1800, that it resembled an electric
battery feebly charged and constantly renewing its charge. In
pursuance of this view, the common electrical action was, at a later
period (for instance by Ampère, in 1820), called electrical
tension, while the voltaic action was called the electrical
current, or electromotive action. The different effects
produced, by increasing the size and the number of the plates in the
voltaic trough, were also very remarkable. The power of producing heat
was found to depend on the size of the plates; the power of producing
chemical changes, on the other hand, was augmented by the number of
plates of which the battery consisted. The former effect was referred
to the increased quantity, the latter to the
intensity, of the electric fluid. We mention these
distinctions at present, rather for the purpose of explaining the
language in which the results of the succeeding investigations are
narrated, than with the intention of representing the hypotheses and
measures which they imply, as clearly established, at the period of
which we speak. For that purpose new discoveries were requisite, which
we have soon to relate.
10 Phil. Trans. p. 403.
</div></body></text></TEI>