<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="10">CHAPTER X.
SUPPOSED INTENSITY OF AQUEOUS FORCES AT REMOTE PERIODS.
Intensity of aqueous causes—Slow accumulation of strata proved by fossils—Rate
of denudation can only keep pace with deposition—Erratics, and effects of ice—Deluges,
and the causes to which they are referred—Supposed universality of
ancient deposits.
Intensity of aqueous causes.—The great problem considered in the
preceding chapters, namely, whether the former changes of the earth
made known to us by geology, resemble in kind and degree those now
in daily progress, may still be contemplated from several other points of
view. We may inquire, for example, whether there are any grounds
for the belief entertained by many, that the intensity both of aqueous
and of igneous forces, in remote ages, far exceeded that which we witness
in our own times.
First, then, as to aqueous causes: it has been shown, in our history
of the science, that Woodward did not hesitate, in 1695, to teach that
the entire mass of fossiliferous strata contained in the earth's crust had
been deposited in a few months; and, consequently, as their mechanical
and derivative origin was already admitted, the reduction of rocky
masses into mud, sand, and pebbles, the transportation of the same to
a distance, and their accumulation elsewhere in regular strata, were all
assumed to have taken place with a rapidity unparalleled in modern
times. This doctrine was modified by degrees, in proportion as different
classes of organic remains, such as shells, corals, and fossil plants, had
been studied with attention. Analogy led every naturalist to assume,
that each full-grown individual of the animal or vegetable kingdom, had
required a certain number of months or years for the attainment of maturity,
and the perpetuation of its species by generation; and thus the
154
first approach was made to the conception of a common standard of
time, without which there are no means whatever of measuring the
comparative rate at which any succession of events has taken place at
two distinct periods. This standard consisted of the average duration
of the lives of individuals of the same genera or families in the animal
and vegetable kingdoms; and the multitude of fossils dispersed through
successive strata implied the continuance of the same species for many
generations. At length the idea that species themselves had had a
limited duration, arose out of the observed fact that sets of strata of different
ages contained fossils of distinct species. Finally, the opinion
became general, that in the course of ages, one assemblage of animals
and plants had disappeared after another again and again, and new
tribes had started into life to replace them.
Denudation.—In addition to the proofs derived from organic remains,
the forms of stratification led also, on a fuller investigation, to the belief
that sedimentary rocks had been slowly deposited; but it was still supposed
that denudation, or the power of running water, and the waves
and currents of the ocean, to strip off superior strata, and lay bare the
rocks below, had formerly operated with an energy wholly unequalled
in our times. These opinions were both illogical and inconsistent, because
deposition and denudation are parts of the same process, and
what is true of the one must be true of the other. Their speed must
be always limited by the same causes, and the conveyance of solid matter
to a particular region can only keep pace with its removal from another,
so that the aggregate of sedimentary strata in the earth's crust
can never exceed in volume the amount of solid matter which has been
ground down and washed away by running water. How vast, then,
must be the spaces which this abstraction of matter has left vacant!
how far exceeding in dimensions all the valleys, however numerous, and
the hollows, however vast, which we can prove to have been cleared out
by aqueous erosion! The evidences of the work of denudation are defective,
because it is the nature of every destroying cause to obliterate
the signs of its own agency; but the amount of reproduction in the form
of sedimentary strata must always afford a true measure of the minimum
of denudation which the earth's surface has undergone.
Erratics.—The next phenomenon to which the advocates of the
excessive power of running water in times past have appealed, is the
enormous size of the blocks called erratic, which lie scattered over the
northern parts of Europe and North America. Unquestionably a large
proportion of these blocks have been transported far from their original
position, for between them and the parent rocks we now find, not unfrequently,
deep seas and valleys intervening, or hills more than a thousand
feet high. To explain the present situation of such travelled fragments,
a deluge of mud has been imagined by some to have come from the
north, bearing along with it sand, gravel, and stony fragments, some of
them hundreds of tons in weight. This flood, in its transient passage
over the continents, dispersed the boulders irregularly over hill, valley,
155
and plain; or forced them along over a surface of hard rock, so as to
polish it and leave it indented with parallel scratches and grooves—such
markings as are still visible in the rocks of Scandinavia, Scotland, Canada,
and many other countries.
There can be no doubt that the myriads of angular and rounded blocks
above alluded to, cannot have been borne along by ordinary rivers or
marine currents, so great is their volume and weight, and so clear are
the signs, in many places, of time having been occupied in their successive
deposition; for they are often distributed at various depths through
heaps of regularly stratified sand and gravel. No waves of the sea
raised by earthquakes, nor the bursting of lakes dammed up for a time
by landslips or by avalanches of snow, can account for the observed
facts; but I shall endeavor to show, in the next book, chap. 15,236 that
a combination of existing causes may have conveyed erratics into their
present situations.
The causes which will be referred to are, first, the carrying power of
ice, combined with that of running water; and second, the upward
movement of the bed of the sea, converting it gradually into land.
Without entering at present into any details respecting these causes,
I may mention that the transportation of blocks by ice is now simultaneously
in progress in the cold and temperate latitudes, both of the
northern and southern hemisphere, as, for example, on the coasts of Canada
and Gulf of St. Lawrence, and also in Chili, Patagonia, and the
island of South Georgia. In those regions the uneven bed of the ocean
is becoming strewed over with ice-drifted fragments, which have either
stranded on shoals, or been dropped in deep water by melting bergs. The
entanglement of boulders in drift-ice will also be shown to occur annually
in North America, and these stones, when firmly frozen into ice, wander
year after year from Labrador to the St. Lawrence, and reach points of
the western hemisphere farther south than any part of Great Britain.
The general absence of erratics in the warmer parts of the equatorial
regions of Asia, Africa, and America, confirms the same views. As to
the polishing and grooving of hard rocks, it has lately been ascertained
that glaciers give rise to these effects when pushing forward sand, pebbles,
and rocky fragments, and causing them to grate along the bottom.
Nor can there be any reasonable doubt that icebergs, when they run
aground on the floor of the ocean, must imprint similar marks upon it.
It is unnecessary, therefore, to refer to deluges, or even to speculate
on the former existence of a climate more severe than that now prevailing
in the western hemisphere, to explain the geographical distribution
of most of the European erratics.
Deluges.—As deluges have been often alluded to, I shall say something
of the causes which may be supposed to give rise to these grand
movements of water in addition to those already alluded to (p. 9).
Geologists who believe that mountain-chains have been thrown up suddenly
156
at many successive epochs, imagine that the waters of the ocean
may be raised by these convulsions, and then break in terrific waves upon
the land, sweeping over whole continents, hollowing out valleys, and
transporting sand, gravel, and erratics, to great distances. The sudden
rise of the Alps or Andes, it is said, may have produced a flood even
subsequently to the time when the earth became the residence of man.
But it seems strange that none of the writers who have indulged their
imaginations in conjectures of this kind, should have ascribed a deluge
to the sudden conversion of part of the unfathomable ocean into a shoal
rather than to the rise of mountain-chains. In the latter case, the
mountains themselves could do no more than displace a certain quantity
of atmospheric air, whereas, the instantaneous formation of the shoal
would displace a vast body of water, which being heaved up to a great
height might roll over and permanently submerge a large portion of a
continent.
If we restrict ourselves to combinations of causes at present known,
it would seem that the two principal sources of extraordinary inundations
are, first, the escape of the waters of a large lake raised far above
the sea; and, secondly, the pouring down of a marine current into lands
depressed below the mean level of the ocean.
As an example of the first of these cases, we may take Lake Superior,
which is more than 400 geographical miles in length and about 150 in
breadth, having an average depth of from 500 to 900 feet. The surface
of this vast body of fresh water is no less than 600 feet above the
level of the ocean; the lowest part of the barrier which separates the
lake on its southwest side from those streams which flow into the head
waters of the Mississippi being about 600 feet high. If, therefore, a
series of subsidences should lower any part of this barrier 600 feet, any
subsequent rending or depression, even of a few yards at a time, would
allow the sudden escape of vast floods of water into a hydrographical
basin of enormous extent. If the event happened in the dry season,
when the ordinary channels of the Mississippi and its tributaries are in a
great degree empty, the inundation might not be considerable; but if in
the flood-season, a region capable of supporting a population of many
millions might be suddenly submerged. But even this event would be
insufficient to cause a violent rush of water, and to produce those effects
usually called diluvial; for the difference of level of 600 feet between
Lake Superior and the Gulf of Mexico, when distributed over a distance
of 1800 miles, would give an average fall of only four inches per mile.
The second case before adverted to is where there are large tracts of
dry land beneath the mean level of the ocean. It seems, after much
controversy, to be at length a settled point, that the Caspian is really
83 feet 6 inches lower than the Black Sea. As the Caspian covers an
area about equal to that of Spain, and as its shores are in general low
and flat, there must be many thousand square miles of country less than
83 feet above the level of that inland sea, and consequently depressed
below the Black Sea and Mediterranean. This area includes the site of
157
the populous city of Astrakhan and other towns. Into this region the
ocean would pour its waters, if the land now intervening between the
Sea of Azof and the Caspian should subside. Yet even if this event
should occur, it is most probable that the submergence of the whole
region would not be accomplished simultaneously, but by a series of
minor floods, the sinking of the barrier being gradual.237
Supposed universality of ancient deposits.—The next fallacy which
has helped to perpetuate the doctrine that the operations of water were
on a different and grander scale in ancient times, is founded on the indefinite
areas over which homogeneous deposits were supposed to extend.
No modern sedimentary strata, it is said, equally identical in mineral
character and fossil contents, can be traced continuously from one quarter
of the globe to another. But the first propagators of these opinions
were very slightly acquainted with the inconstancy in mineral composition
of the ancient formations, and equally so of the wide spaces over
which the same kind of sediment is now actually distributed by rivers
and currents in the course of centuries. The persistency of character
in the older series was exaggerated, its extreme variability in the newer
was assumed without proof. In the chapter which treats of river-deltas
and the dispersion of sediment by currents, and in the description of
reefs of coral now growing over areas many hundred miles in length, I
shall have opportunities of convincing the reader of the danger of hasty
generalizations on this head.
In regard to the imagined universality of particular rocks of ancient
date, it was almost unavoidable that this notion, when once embraced,
should be perpetuated; for the same kinds of rock have occasionally
been reproduced at successive epochs; and when once the
agreement or disagreement in mineral character alone was relied on as
the test of age, it followed that similar rocks, if found even at the
antipodes, were referred to the same era, until the contrary could be
shown.
158
Now it is usually impossible to combat such an assumption on geological
grounds, so long as we are imperfectly acquainted with the order
of superposition and the organic remains of these same formations.
Thus, for example, a group of red marl and red sandstone, containing
salt and gypsum, being interposed in England between the Lias and the
Coal, all other red marls and sandstones, associated some of them with
salt, and others with gypsum, and occurring not only in different parts of
Europe, but in North America, Peru, India, the salt deserts of Asia,
those of Africa—in a word, in every quarter of the globe, were referred
to one and the same period. The burden of proof was not supposed to
rest with those who insisted on the identity in age of all these groups—their
identity in mineral composition was thought sufficient. It was in
vain to urge as an objection the improbability of the hypothesis which
implies that all the moving waters on the globe were once simultaneously
charged with sediment of a red color.
But the rashness of pretending to identify, in age, all the red sandstones
and marls in question, has at length been sufficiently exposed, by
the discovery that, even in Europe, they belong decidedly to many different
epochs. It is already ascertained, that the red sandstone and red
marl containing the rock-salt of Cardona in Catalonia is newer than the
Oolitic, if not more modern than the Cretaceous period. It is also
known that certain red marls and variegated sandstones in Auvergne
which are undistinguishable in mineral composition from the New Red
Sandstone of English geologists, belong, nevertheless, to the Eocene
period; and, lastly, the gypseous red marl of Aix, in Provence, formerly
supposed to be a marine secondary group, is now acknowledged
to be a tertiary freshwater formation. In Nova Scotia one great deposit
of red marl, sandstone, and gypsum, precisely resembling in mineral
character the "New Red" of England, occurs as a member of the
Carboniferous group, and in the United States near the Falls of Niagara,
a similar formation constitutes a subdivision of the Silurian
series.238
Nor was the nomenclature commonly adopted in geology without its
influence in perpetuating the erroneous doctrine of universal formations.
Such names, for example, as Chalk, Green Sand, Oolite, Red Marl, Coal,
and others, were given to some of the principal fossiliferous groups in
consequence of mineral peculiarities which happened to characterize
them in the countries where they were first studied. When geologists
had at length shown, by means of fossils and the order of superposition,
that other strata, entirely dissimilar in color, texture, and composition,
were of contemporaneous date, it was thought convenient still to retain
the old names. That these were often inappropriate was admitted;
but the student was taught to understand them in no other than a
chronological sense; so that the Chalk might not be a white cretaceous
rock, but a hard dolomitic limestone, as in the Alps, or a brown sandstone
or green marl, as in New Jersey, U. S. In like manner, the
159
Green Sand, it was said, might in some places be represented by red
sandstone, red marl, salt, and gypsum, as in the north of Spain. So
the oolitic texture was declared to be rather an exception than otherwise
to the general rule in rocks of the Oolitic period; and it often
became necessary to affirm that no particle of carbonaceous matter
could be detected in districts where the true Coal series abounded. In
spite of every precaution the habitual use of this language could scarcely
fail to instil into the mind of the pupil an idea that chalk, coal, salt, red
marl, or the Oolitic structure were far more widely characteristic of
the rocks of a given age than was really the case.
There is still another cause of deception, disposing us to ascribe a
more limited range to the newer sedimentary formations as compared
to the older, namely, the very general concealment of the newer strata
beneath the waters of lakes and seas, and the wide exposure above
waters of the more ancient. The Chalk, for example, now seen stretching
for thousands of miles over different parts of Europe, has become
visible to us by the effect, not of one, but of many distinct series of subterranean
movements. Time has been required, and a succession of
geological periods, to raise it above the waves in so many regions; and
if calcareous rocks of the middle and upper tertiary periods have been
formed, as homogeneous in mineral composition throughout equally extensive
regions, it may require convulsions as numerous as all those
which have occurred since the origin of the Chalk to bring them up
within the sphere of human observation. Hence the rocks of more
modern periods may appear partial, as compared to those of remoter
eras, not because of any original inferiority in their extent, but because
there has not been sufficient time since their origin for the development
of a great series of elevatory movements.
In regard, however, to one of the most important characteristics of
sedimentary rocks, their organic remains, many naturalists of high authority
have maintained that the same species of fossils are more uniformly
distributed through formations of high antiquity than in those of
more modern date, and that distinct zoological and botanical provinces,
as they are called, which form so striking a feature in the living creation,
were not established at remote eras. Thus the plants of the Coal,
the shells, the trilobites of the Silurian rocks, and the ammonites of the
Oolite, have been supposed to have a wider geographical range than
any living species of plants, crustaceans, or mollusks. This opinion
seems in certain cases to be well founded, especially in relation to the
plants of the Carboniferous epoch, owing probably to the more uniform
temperature of the globe, at a time when the position of sea and land
was less favorable to variations in climate, according to principles
already explained in the seventh and eighth chapters. But a recent
comparison of the fossils of North American rocks with those of corresponding
ages in the European series, has proved that the terrestrial
vegetation of the Carboniferous epoch is an exception to the general
rule, and that the fauna and flora of the earth at successive periods,
160
from the oldest Silurian to the newest Tertiary was as diversified as
now. The shells, corals, and other classes of organic remains demonstrate
the fact that the earth might then have been divided into separate
zoological provinces, in a manner analogous to that observed in the geographical
distribution of species now living.
</div></body></text></TEI>