<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="34">CHAPTER II.
The Inductive Epoch of Newton.—Discovery of the
Universal Gravitation of Matter, according to the Law of the Inverse
Square of the Distance.
IN order that we may the more
clearly consider the bearing of this, the greatest scientific
discovery ever made, we shall resolve it into the partial propositions
of which it consists. Of these we may enumerate five. The doctrine of
universal gravitation asserts,
1. That the force by which the different planets are
attracted to the sun is in the inverse proportion of the squares of
their distances;
2. That the force by which the same planet is attracted to
the sun, in different parts of its orbit, is also in the inverse
proportion of the squares of the distances;
3. That the earth also exerts such a force on the
moon, and that this force is identical with the force of
gravity;
4. That bodies thus act on other bodies, besides those
which revolve round them; thus, that the sun exerts such a force on
the moon and satellites, and that the planets exert such forces on
one another;
5. That this force, thus exerted by the general masses of the sun,
earth, and planets, arises from the attraction of each
particle of these masses; which attraction follows the above law,
and belongs to all matter alike.
The history of the establishment of these five truths will be given
in order.
1. Sun’s Force on Different Planets.—With regard to
the first of the above five propositions, that the different planets
are attracted to the sun by a force which is inversely as the square
of the distance, Newton had so far been anticipated, that several
persons had discovered it to be true, or nearly true; that is, they
had discovered that if the orbits of the planets were circles, the
proportions of the central force to the inverse square of the distance
would follow from Kepler’s third law, of the sesquiplicate proportion
of the periodic times. As we have seen, Huyghens’ theorems would have
proved this, if they had been so applied; Wren knew it; Hooke not only
knew it, but claimed a prior knowledge to Newton; and Halley had
satisfied himself that it was at 400 least nearly true, before he visited
Newton. Hooke was reported to Newton at Cambridge, as having applied
to the Royal Society to do him justice with regard to his claims; but
when Halley wrote and informed Newton (in a letter dated June 29,
1686), that Hooke’s conduct “had been represented in worse colors than
it ought,” Newton inserted in his book a notice of these his
predecessors, in order, as he said, “to compose the dispute.”25 This notice appears in a Scholium to
the fourth Proposition of the Principia, which states the
general law of revolutions in circles. “The case of the sixth
corollary,” Newton there says, “obtains in the celestial bodies, as
has been separately inferred by our countrymen, Wren, Hooke, and
Halley;” he soon after names Huyghens, “who, in his excellent treatise
De Horologio Oscillatorio, compares the force of gravity with
the centrifugal forces of revolving bodies.”
25 Biog. Brit. folio, art.
Hooke.
The two steps requisite for this discovery were, to propose the
motions of the planets as simply a mechanical problem, and to apply
mathematical reasoning so as to solve this problem, with reference to
Kepler’s third law considered as a fact. The former step was a
consequence of the mechanical discoveries of Galileo and his school;
the result of the firm and clear place which these gradually obtained
in men’s mind, and of the utter abolition of all the notions of solid
spheres by Kepler. The mathematical step required no small
mathematical powers; as appears, when we consider that this was the
first example of such a problem, and that the method of limits, under
all its forms, was at this time in its infancy, or rather, at its
birth. Accordingly, even this step, though much the easiest in the
path of deduction, no one before Newton completely executed.
2. Force in different Points of an Orbit.—The
inference of the law of the force from Kepler’s two laws concerning
the elliptical motion, was a problem quite different from the
preceding, and much more difficult; but the dispute with respect to
priority in the two propositions was intermingled. Borelli, in 1666,
had, as we have seen, endeavored to reconcile
the general form of the orbit with the notion of a central attractive
force, by taking centrifugal force into the account; and Hooke, in
1679, had asserted that the result of the law of the inverse square in
the force of the earth would be an ellipse,26 or a curve like
an ellipse.27 But it does not appear that this was
any thing more than 401 a conjecture. Halley says28 that “Hooke, in 1683, told him he had
demonstrated all the laws of the celestial motions by the reciprocally
duplicate proportion of the force of gravity; but that, being offered
forty shillings by Sir Christopher Wren to produce such a
demonstration, his answer was, that he had it, but would conceal it
for some time, that others, trying and failing, might know how to
value it when he should make it public.” Halley, however, truly
observes, that after the publication of the demonstration in the
Principia, this reason no longer held; and adds, “I have
plainly told him, that unless he produce another differing
demonstration, and let the world judge of it, neither I nor any one
else can believe it.”
26 Newton’s Letter, Biog.
Brit., Hooke, p. 2660.
27 Birch’s Hist. R. S.,
Wallis’s Life.
28 Enc. Brit., Hooke, p.
2660.
Newton allows that Hooke’s assertions in 1679 gave occasion to his
investigation on this point of the theory. His demonstration is
contained in the second and third Sections of the Principia. He
first treats of the general law of central forces in any curve; and
then, on account, as he states, of the application to the motion of
the heavenly bodies, he treats of the case of force varying inversely
as the square of the distance, in a more diffuse manner.
In this, as in the former portion of his discovery, the two steps
were, the proposing the heavenly motions as a mechanical problem, and
the solving this problem. Borelli and Hooke had certainly made the
former step, with considerable distinctness; but the mathematical
solution required no common inventive power.
Newton seems to have been much ruffled by Hooke’s speaking slightly
of the value of this second step; and is moved in return to deny
Hooke’s pretensions with some asperity, and to assert his own. He
says, in a letter to Halley, “Borelli did something in it, and wrote
modestly; he (Hooke) has done nothing; and yet written in such a way
as if he knew, and had sufficiently hinted all but what remained to be
determined by the drudgery of calculations and observations; excusing
himself from that labor by reason of his other business; whereas he
should rather have excused himself by reason of his inability; for it
is very plain, by his words, he knew not how to go about it. Now is
not this very fine? Mathematicians that find out, settle, and do all
the business, must content themselves with being nothing but dry
calculators and drudges; and another that does nothing but pretend and
grasp at all things, must carry away all the inventions, as well of
those that were to follow him as of those that 402 went before.” This
was written, however, under the influence of some degree of mistake;
and in a subsequent letter, Newton says, “Now I understand he was in
some respects misrepresented to me, I wish I had spared the postscript
to my last,” in which is the passage just quoted. We see, by the
melting away of rival claims, the undivided honor which belongs to
Newton, as the real discoverer of the proposition now under notice. We
may add, that in the sequel of the third Section of the
Principia, he has traced its consequences, and solved various
problems flowing from it with his usual fertility and beauty of
mathematical resource; and has there shown the necessary connection of
Kepler’s third law with his first and second.
3. Moon’s Gravity to the Earth.—Though others had
considered cosmical forces as governed by the general laws of motion,
it does not appear that they had identified such forces with the force
of terrestrial gravity. This step in Newton’s discoveries has
generally been the most spoken of by superficial thinkers; and a false
kind of interest has been attached to it, from the story of its being
suggested by the fall of an apple. The popular mind is caught by the
character of an eventful narrative which the anecdote gives to this
occurrence; and by the antithesis which makes a profound theory appear
the result of a trivial accident. How inappropriate is such a view of
the matter we shall soon see. The narrative of the progress of
Newton’s thoughts, is given by Pemberton (who had it from Newton
himself) in his preface to his View of Newton’s Philosophy, and
by Voltaire, who had it from Mrs. Conduit, Newton’s niece.29 “The first thoughts,” we are told,
“which gave rise to his Principia, he had when he retired from
Cambridge, in 1666, on account of the plague (he was then twenty-four
years of age). As he sat alone in a garden, he fell into a speculation
on the power of gravity; that as this power is not found sensibly
diminished at the remotest distance from the centre of the earth to
which we can rise, neither at the tops of the loftiest buildings, nor
even on the summits of the highest mountains, it appeared to him
reasonable to conclude that this power must extend much further than
was usually thought: Why not as high as the moon? said he to himself;
and if so, her motion must be influenced by it; perhaps she is
retained in her orbit thereby.”
29 Elémens de Phil. de Newton,
3me partie, chap. iii.
The thought of cosmical gravitation was thus distinctly brought
into being; and Newton’s superiority here was, that he conceived the
403 celestial
motions as distinctly as the motions which took place close to
him;—considered them as of the same kind, and applied the same
rules to each, without hesitation or obscurity. But so far, this
thought was merely a guess: its occurrence showed the activity of the
thinker; but to give it any value, it required much more than a “why
not?”—a “perhaps.” Accordingly, Newton’s “why not?” was
immediately succeeded by his “if so, what then?” His reasoning was,
that if gravity reach to the moon, it is probably of the same kind as
the central force of the sun, and follows the same rule with respect
to the distance. What is this rule? We have already seen that, by
calculating from Kepler’s laws, and supposing the orbits to be
circles, the rule of the force appears to be the inverse duplicate
proportion of the distance; and this, which had been current as a
conjecture among the previous generation of mathematicians, Newton had
already proved by indisputable reasonings, and was thus prepared to
proceed in his train of inquiry. If, then, he went on, pursuing his
train of thought, the earth’s gravity extend to the moon, diminishing
according to the inverse square of the distance, will it, at the
moon’s orbit, be of the proper magnitude for retaining her in her
path? Here again came in calculation, and a calculation of extreme
interest; for how important and how critical was the decision which
depended on the resulting numbers? According to Newton’s calculations,
made at this time, the moon by her motion in her orbit, was deflected
from the tangent every minute through a space of thirteen feet. But by
noticing the space through which bodies would fall in one minute at
the earth’s surface, and supposing this to be diminished in the ratio
of the inverse square, it appeared that gravity would, at the moon’s
orbit, draw a body through more than fifteen feet. The difference
seems small, the approximation encouraging, the theory plausible; a
man in love with his own fancies would readily have discovered or
invented some probable cause of this difference. But Newton acquiesced
in it as a disproof of his conjecture, and “laid aside at that time
any further thoughts of this matter;” thus resigning a favorite hypothesis,
with a candor and openness to conviction not inferior to Kepler,
though his notion had been taken up on far stronger and sounder
grounds than Kepler dealt in; and without even, so far as we know,
Kepler’s regrets and struggles. Nor was this levity or indifference;
the idea, though thus laid aside, was not finally condemned and
abandoned. When Hooke, in 1679, contradicted Newton on the subject of
the curve described by a falling body, and asserted it to be an
ellipse, Newton 404
was led to investigate the subject, and was then again conducted, by
another road, to the same law of the inverse square of the distance.
This naturally turned his thoughts to his former speculations. Was
there really no way of explaining the discrepancy which this law gave,
when he attempted to reduce the moon’s motion to the action of
gravity? A scientific operation then recently completed, gave the
explanation at once. He had been mistaken in the magnitude of the
earth, and consequently in the distance of the moon, which is
determined by measurements of which the earth’s radius is the base. He
had taken the common estimate, current among geographers and seamen,
that sixty English miles are contained in one degree of latitude. But
Picard, in 1670, had measured the length of a certain portion of the
meridian in France, with far greater accuracy than had yet been
attained  and this measure enabled Newton to repeat his calculations
with these amended data. We may imagine the strong curiosity which he
must have felt as to the result of these calculations. His former
conjecture was now found to agree with the phenomena to a remarkable
degree of precision. This conclusion, thus coming after long doubts
and delays, and falling in with the other results of mechanical
calculation for the solar system, gave a stamp from that moment to his
opinions, and through him to those of the whole philosophical
world.
[2d Ed.] [Dr. Robison (Mechanical Philosophy, p. 288) says
that Newton having become a member of the Royal Society, there learned
the accurate measurement of the earth by Picard, differing very much
from the estimation by which he had made his calculations in 1666. And
M. Biot, in his Life of Newton, published in the Biographie
Universelle, says, “According to conjecture, about the month of
June, 1682, Newton being in London at a meeting of the Royal Society,
mention was made of the new measure of a degree of the earth’s
surface, recently executed in France by Picard; and great praise was
given to the care which had been employed in making this measure
exact.”
I had adopted this conjecture as a fact in my first edition; but it
has been pointed out by Prof. Rigaud (Historical Essay on the First
Publication of the Principia, 1838), that Picard’s measurement was
probably well known to the Fellows of the Royal Society as early as
1675, there being an account of the results of it given in the
Philosophical Transactions for that year. Newton appears to
have discovered the method of determining that a body might describe
an ellipse when acted upon by a force residing in the focus, and
varying 405
inversely as the square of the distance, in 1679, upon occasion of his
correspondence with Hooke. In 1684, at Halley’s request, he returned
to the subject, and in February, 1685, there was inserted in the
Register of the Royal Society a paper of Newton’s (Isaaci Newtoni
Propositiones de Motu) which contained some of the principal
Propositions of the first two Books of the Principia. This
paper, however, does not contain the Proposition “Lunam gravitare in
terram,” nor any of the other propositions of the third Book. The
Principia was printed in 1686 and 7, apparently at the expense
of Halley. On the 6th of April, 1687, the third Book was presented to
the Royal Society.]
It does not appear, I think, that before Newton, philosophers in
general had supposed that terrestrial gravity was the very force by
which the moon’s motions are produced. Men had, as we have seen, taken
up the conception of such forces, and had probably called them
gravity: but this was done only to explain, by analogy, what
kind of forces they were, just as at other times they
compared them with magnetism; and it did not imply that terrestrial
gravity was a force which acted in the celestial spaces. After Newton
had discovered that this was so, the application of the term “gravity”
did undoubtedly convey such a suggestion; but we should err if we
inferred from this coincidence of expression that the notion was
commonly entertained before him. Thus Huyghens appears to use language
which may be mistaken, when he says,30 that Borelli was
of opinion that the primary planets were urged by “gravity” towards
the sun, and the satellites towards the primaries. The notion of
terrestrial gravity, as being actually a cosmical force, is foreign to
all Borelli’s speculations.31 But Horrox, as early as 1635, appears
to have entertained the true view on this subject, although vitiated
by Keplerian errors concerning the connection between the rotation of
the central body and its effect on the body which revolves about it.
Thus he says,32 that the emanation of the earth carries
a projected stone along with the motion of the earth, just in the same
way as it carries the moon in her orbit; and that this force is
greater on the stone than on the moon, because the distance is
less.
30 Cosmotheoros, l. 2. p.
720.
31 I have found no instance in which
the word is so used by him.
32 Astronomia Kepleriana defensa et
promota, cap. 2. See further on this subject in the Additions to this volume.
The Proposition in which Newton has stated the discovery of which
we are now speaking, is the fourth of his third Book: “That the moon
gravitates to the earth, and by the force of gravity is perpetually
406 deflected from
a rectilinear motion, and retained in her orbit.” The proof consists
in the numerical calculation, of which he only gives the elements, and
points out the method; but we may observe, that no small degree of
knowledge of the way in which astronomers had obtained these elements,
and judgment in selecting among them, were necessary: thus, the mean
distance of the moon had been made as little as fifty-six and a half
semidiameters of the earth by Tycho, and as much as sixty-two and a
half by Kircher: Newton gives good reasons for adopting sixty-one.
The term “gravity,” and the expression “to gravitate,” which, as we
have just seen, Newton uses of the moon, were to receive a still wider
application in consequence of his discoveries; but in order to make
this extension clearer, we consider it as a separate step.
~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~
4. Mutual Attraction of all the Celestial Bodies.—If
the preceding parts of the discovery of gravitation were comparatively
easy to conjecture, and difficult to prove, this was much more the
case with the part of which we have now to speak, the attraction of
other bodies, besides the central ones, upon the planets and
satellites. If the mathematical calculation of the unmixed effect of a
central force required transcendent talents, how much must the
difficulty be increased, when other influences prevented those first
results from being accurately verified, while the deviations from
accuracy were far more complex than the original action! If it had not
been that these deviations, though surprisingly numerous and
complicated in their nature, were very small in their quantity, it
would have been impossible for the intellect of man to deal with the
subject; as it was, the struggle with its difficulties is even now a
matter of wonder.
The conjecture that there is some mutual action of the planets, had
been put forth by Hooke in his Attempt to prove the Motion of the
Earth (1674). It followed, he said, from his doctrine, that not
only the sun and moon act upon the course and motion of the earth, but
that Mercury, Venus, Mars, Jupiter, and Saturn, have also, by their
attractive power, a considerable influence upon the motion of the
earth, and the earth in like manner powerfully affects the motions of
those bodies. And Borelli, in attempting to form “theories” of the
satellites of Jupiter, had seen, though dimly and confusedly, the
probability that the sun would disturb the motions of these bodies.
Thus he says (cap. 14), “How can we believe that the Medicean globes
are not, like other planets, impelled with a greater velocity when
they approach the sun: and thus they are acted upon by two moving
forces, one of 407
which produces their proper revolution about Jupiter, the other
regulates their motion round the sun.” And in another place (cap. 20),
he attempts to show an effect of this principle upon the inclination
of the orbit; though, as might be expected, without any real
result.
The case which most obviously suggests the notion that the sun
exerts a power to disturb the motions of secondary planets about
primary ones, might seem to be our own moon; for the great
inequalities which had hitherto been discovered, had all, except the
first, or elliptical anomaly, a reference to the position of the sun.
Nevertheless, I do not know that any one had attempted thus to explain
the curiously irregular course of the earth’s attendant. To calculate,
from the disturbing agency, the amount of the irregularities, was a
problem which could not, at any former period, have been dreamt of as
likely to be at any time within the verge of human power.
Newton both made the step of inferring that there were such forces,
and, to a very great extent, calculated the effects of them. The
inference is made on mechanical principles, in the sixth Theorem of
the third Book of the Principia;—that the moon is
attracted by the sun, as the earth is;—that the satellites of
Jupiter and Saturn are attracted as the primaries are; in the same
manner, and with the same forces. If this were not so, it is shown
that these attendant bodies could not accompany the principal ones in
the regular manner in which they do. All those bodies at equal
distances from the sun would be equally attracted.
But the complexity which must occur in tracing the results of this
principle will easily be seen. The satellite and the primary, though
nearly at the same distance, and in the same direction, from the sun,
are not exactly so. Moreover the difference of the distances and of
the directions is perpetually changing; and if the motion of the
satellite be elliptical, the cycle of change is long and intricate: on
this account alone the effects of the sun’s action will inevitably
follow cycles as long and as perplexed as those of the positions. But
on another account they will be still more complicated; for in the
continued action of a force, the effect which takes place at first,
modifies and alters the effect afterwards. The result at any moment is
the sum of the results in preceding instants: and since the terms, in
this series of instantaneous effects, follow very complex rules, the
sums of such series will be, it might be expected, utterly incapable
of being reduced to any manageable degree of simplicity.
It certainly does not appear that any one but Newton could make
408 any impression
on this problem, or course of problems. No one for sixty years after
the publication of the Principia, and, with Newton’s methods,
no one up to the present day, had added any thing of any value to his
deductions. We know that he calculated all the principal lunar
inequalities; in many of the cases, he has given us his processes; in
others, only his results. But who has presented, in his beautiful
geometry, or deduced from his simple principles, any of the
inequalities which he left untouched? The ponderous instrument of
synthesis, so effective in his hands, has never since been grasped by
one who could use it for such purposes; and we gaze at it with
admiring curiosity, as on some gigantic implement of war, which stands
idle among the memorials of ancient days, and makes us wonder what
manner of man he was who could wield as a weapon what we can hardly
lift as a burden.
It is not necessary to point out in detail the sagacity and skill
which mark this part of the Principia. The mode in which the
author obtains the effect of a disturbing force in producing a motion
of the apse of an elliptical orbit (the ninth Section of the first
Book), has always been admired for its ingenuity and elegance. The
general statement of the nature of the principal inequalities produced
by the sun in the motion of a satellite, given in the sixty-sixth
Proposition, is, even yet, one of the best explanations of such
action; and the calculations of the quantity of the effects in the
third Book, for instance, the variation of the moon, the
motion of the nodes and its inequalities, the change of
inclination of the orbit,—are full of beautiful and
efficacious artifices. But Newton’s inventive faculty was exercised to
an extent greater than these published investigations show. In several
cases he has suppressed the demonstration of his method, and given us
the result only; either from haste or from mere weariness, which might
well overtake one who, while he was struggling with facts and numbers,
with difficulties of conception and practice, was aiming also at that
geometrical elegance of exposition, which he considered as alone fit
for the public eye. Thus, in stating the effect of the eccentricity of
the moon’s orbit upon the motion of the apogee, he says,33 “The computations, as too intricate and
embarrassed with approximations, I do not choose to introduce.”
33 Schol. to Prop. 35, first
edit.
The computations of the theoretical motion of the moon being thus
difficult, and its irregularities numerous and complex, we may ask
409 whether
Newton’s reasoning was sufficient to establish this part of his
theory; namely, that her actual motions arise from her gravitation to
the sun. And to this we may reply, that it was sufficient for that
purpose,—since it showed that, from Newton’s hypothesis,
inequalities must result, following the laws which the moon’s
inequalities were known to follow;—since the amount of the
inequalities given by the theory agreed nearly with the rules which
astronomers had collected from observation;—and since, by the
very intricacy of the calculation, it was rendered probable, that the
first results might be somewhat inaccurate, and thus might give rise
to the still remaining differences between the calculations and the
facts. A Progression of the Apogee; a Regression of the
Nodes; and, besides the Elliptical, or first Inequality, an
inequality, following the law of the Evection, or second
inequality discovered by Ptolemy; another, following the law of the
Variation discovered by Tycho;—were pointed out in the
first edition of the Principia, as the consequences of the
theory. Moreover, the quantities of these inequalities were calculated
and compared with observation with the utmost confidence, and the
agreement in most instances was striking. The Variation agreed with
Halley’s recent observations within a minute of a degree.34 The Mean Motion of the Nodes in a year
agreed within less than one-hundredth of the whole.35 The Equation of the Motion of the Nodes
also agreed well.36 The Inclination of the Plane of the
Orbit to the ecliptic, and its changes, according to the different
situations of the nodes, likewise agreed.37 The Evection has
been already noticed as encumbered with peculiar difficulties: here
the accordance was less close. The Difference of the daily progress of
the Apogee in syzygy, and its daily Regress in Quadratures, is, Newton
says, “4¼ minutes by the Tables, 6⅔ by our calculation.” He boldly
adds, “I suspect this difference to be due to the fault of the
Tables.” In the second edition (1711) he added the calculation of
several other inequalities, as the Annual Equation, also
discovered by Tycho; and he compared them with more recent
observations made by Flamsteed at Greenwich; but even in what has
already been stated, it must be allowed that there is a wonderful
accordance of theory with phenomena, both being very complex in the
rules which they educe.
34 B. iii. Prop. 29.
35 Prop. 32.
36 Prop. 33.
37 Prop. 35.
The same theory which gave these Inequalities in the motion of the
Moon produced by the disturbing force of the sun, gave also 410 corresponding
Inequalities in the motions of the Satellites of other planets,
arising from the same cause; and likewise pointed out the necessary
existence of irregularities in the motions of the Planets arising from
their mutual attraction. Newton gave propositions by which the
Irregularities of the motion of Jupiter’s moons might be deduced from
those of our own;38 and it was shown that the motions of
their nodes would be slow by theory, as Flamsteed had found it to be
by observation.39 But Newton did not attempt to calculate
the effect of the mutual action of the planets, though he observes,
that in the case of Jupiter and Saturn this effect is too considerable
to be neglected;40 and he notices in the second edition,41 that it follows from the theory of
gravity, that the aphelia of Mercury, Venus, the Earth, and Mars,
slightly progress.
38 B. i. Prop. 66.
39 B. iii. Prop. 23.
40 B. iii. Prop. 13.
41 Scholium to Prop. 14. B. iii.
In one celebrated instance, indeed, the deviation of the theory of
the Principia from observation was wider, and more difficult to
explain; and as this deviation for a time resisted the analysis of
Euler and Clairaut, as it had resisted the synthesis of Newton, it at
one period staggered the faith of mathematicians in the exactness of
the law of the inverse square of the distance. I speak of the Motion
of the Moon’s Apogee, a problem which has already been referred to; and in which Newton’s
method, and all the methods which could be devised for some time
afterwards, gave only half the observed motion; a circumstance which
arose, as was discovered by Clairaut in 1750, from the insufficiency
of the method of approximation. Newton does not attempt to conceal
this discrepancy. After calculating what the motion of apse would be,
upon the assumption of a disturbing force of the same amount as that
which the sun exerts on the moon, he simply says,42 “the apse of the
moon moves about twice as fast.”
42 B. i. Prop. 44, second edit. There
is reason to believe, however, that Newton had, in his unpublished
calculations, rectified this discrepancy.
The difficulty of doing what Newton did in this branch of the
subject, and the powers it must have required, may be judged of from
what has already been stated;—that no one, with his methods, has
yet been able to add any thing to his labors: few have undertaken to
illustrate what he has written, and no great number have understood it
throughout. The extreme complication of the forces, and of the
conditions under which they act, makes the subject by far the most
thorny walk of mathematics. It is necessary to resolve the action
411 into many
elements, such as can be separated; to invent artifices for dealing
with each of these; and then to recompound the laws thus obtained into
one common conception. The moon’s motion cannot be conceived without
comprehending a scheme more complex than the Ptolemaic epicycles and
eccentrics in their worst form; and the component parts of the system
are not, in this instance, mere geometrical ideas, requiring only a
distinct apprehension of relations of space in order to hold them
securely; they are the foundations of mechanical notions, and require
to be grasped so that we can apply to them sound mechanical
reasonings. Newton’s successors, in the next generation, abandoned the
hope of imitating him in this intense mental effort; they gave the
subject over to the operation of algebraical reasoning, in which
symbols think for us, without our dwelling constantly upon their
meaning, and obtain for us the consequences which result from the
relations of space and the laws of force, however complicated be the
conditions under which they are combined. Even Newton’s countrymen,
though they were long before they applied themselves to the method
thus opposed to his, did not produce any thing which showed that they
had mastered, or could retrace, the Newtonian investigations.
Thus the Problem of Three Bodies,43 treated
geometrically, belongs exclusively to Newton; and the proofs of the
mutual action of the sun, planets, and satellites, which depend upon
such reasoning, could not be discovered by any one but him.
43 See the history of the Problem
of Three Bodies, ante, in Book vi. Chap. vi. Sect. 7.
But we have not yet done with his achievements on this subject; for
some of the most remarkable and beautiful of the reasonings which he
connected with this problem, belong to the next step of his
generalization.
5. Mutual Attraction of all Particles of Matter.—That
all the parts of the universe are drawn and held together by love, or
harmony, or some affection to which, among other names, that of
attraction may have been given, is an assertion which may very
possibly have been made at various times, by speculators writing at
random, and taking their chance of meaning and truth. The authors of
such casual dogmas have generally nothing accurate or substantial,
either in their conception of the general proposition, or in their
reference to examples of it; and, therefore, their doctrines are no
concern of ours at present. But among those who were really the first
to think of the mutual 412 attraction of matter, we cannot help
noticing Francis Bacon; for his notions were so far from being
chargeable with the looseness and indistinctness to which we have
alluded, that he proposed an experiment44 which was to
decide whether the facts were so or not;—whether the gravity of
bodies to the earth arose from an attraction of the parts of matter
towards each other, or was a tendency towards the centre of the earth.
And this experiment is, even to this day, one of the best which can be
devised, in order to exhibit the universal gravitation of matter: it
consists in the comparison of the rate of going of a clock in a deep
mine, and on a high place. Huyghens, in his book De Causâ
Gravitatis, published in 1690, showed that the earth would have an
oblate form, in consequence of the action of the centrifugal force;
but his reasoning does not suppose gravity to arise from the mutual
attraction of the parts of the earth. The apparent influence of the
moon upon the tides had long been remarked; but no one had made any
progress in truly explaining the mechanism of this influence; and all
the analogies to which reference had been made, on this and similar
subjects, as magnetic and other attractions, were rather delusive than
illustrative, since they represented the attraction as something
peculiar in particular bodies, depending upon the nature of each
body.
44 Nov. Org. Lib. ii. Aph.
36.
That all such forces, cosmical and terrestrial, were the same
single force, and that this was nothing more than the insensible
attraction which subsists between one stone and another, was a
conception equally bold and grand; and would have been an
incomprehensible thought, if the views which we have already explained
had not prepared the mind for it. But the preceding steps having
disclosed, between all the bodies of the universe, forces of the same
kind as those which produce the weight of bodies at the earth, and,
therefore, such as exist in every particle of terrestrial matter; it
became an obvious question, whether such forces did not also belong to
all particles of planetary matter, and whether this was not, in fact,
the whole account of the forces of the solar system. But, supposing
this conjecture to be thus suggested, how formidable, on first
appearance at least, was the undertaking of verifying it! For if this
be so, every finite mass of matter exerts forces which are the result
of the infinitely numerous forces of its particles, these forces
acting in different directions. It does not appear, at first sight,
that the law by which the force is related to the distance, will be
the same for the particles as it is for the masses; and, in reality,
it 413 is not so,
except in special cases. And, again, in the instance of any effect
produced by the force of a body, how are we to know whether the force
resides in the whole mass as a unit, or in the separate particles? We
may reason, as Newton does,45 that the rule which proves gravity to
belong universally to the planets, proves it also to belong to their
parts; but the mind will not be satisfied with this extension of the
rule, except we can find decisive instances, and calculate the effects
of both suppositions, under the appropriate conditions. Accordingly,
Newton had to solve a new series of problems suggested by this
inquiry; and this he did.
45 Princip. B. iii. Prop.
7.
These solutions are no less remarkable for the mathematical power
which they exhibit, than the other parts of the Principia. The
propositions in which it is shown that the law of the inverse square
for the particles gives the same law for spherical masses, have that
kind of beauty which might well have justified their being published
for their mathematical elegance alone, even if they had not applied to
any real case. Great ingenuity is also employed in other instances, as
in the case of spheroids of small eccentricity. And when the amount of
the mechanical action of masses of various forms has thus been
assigned, the sagacity shown in tracing the results of such action in
the solar system is truly admirable; not only the general nature of
the effect being pointed out, but its quantity calculated. I speak in
particular of the reasonings concerning the Figure of the Earth, the
Tides, the Precession of the Equinoxes, the Regression of the Nodes of
a ring such as Saturn’s; and of some effects which, at that time, had
not been ascertained even as facts of observation; for instance, the
difference of gravity in different latitudes, and the Nutation of the
earth’s axis. It is true, that in most of these cases, Newton’s
process could be considered only as a rude approximation. In one (the
Precession) he committed an error, and in all, his means of
calculation were insufficient. Indeed these are much more difficult
investigations than the Problem of Three Bodies, in which three points
act on each other by explicit laws. Up to this day, the resources of
modern analysis have been employed upon some of them with very partial
success; and the facts, in all of them, required to be accurately
ascertained and measured, a process which is not completed even now.
Nevertheless the form and nature of the conclusions which Newton did
obtain, were such as to inspire a strong confidence in the competency
of his theory to explain 414 all such phenomena as have been spoken
of. We shall afterwards have to speak of the
labors, undertaken in order to examine the phenomena more exactly, to
which the theory gave occasion.
Thus, then, the theory of the universal mutual gravitation of all
the particles of matter, according to the law of the inverse square of
the distances, was conceived, its consequences calculated, and its
results shown to agree with phenomena. It was found that this theory
took up all the facts of astronomy as far as they had hitherto been
ascertained; while it pointed out an interminable vista of new facts,
too minute or too complex for observation alone to disentangle, but
capable of being detected when theory had pointed out their laws, and
of being used as criteria or confirmations of the truth of the
doctrine. For the same reasoning which explained the evection,
variation, and annual equation of the moon, showed that there must be
many other inequalities besides these; since these resulted from
approximate methods of calculation, in which small quantities were
neglected. And it was known that, in fact, the inequalities hitherto
detected by astronomers did not give the place of the moon with
satisfactory accuracy; so that there was room, among these hitherto
untractable irregularities, for the additional results of the theory.
To work out this comparison was the employment of the succeeding
century; but Newton began it. Thus, at the end of the proposition in
which he asserts,46 that “all the lunar motions and their
irregularities follow from the principles here stated,” he makes the
observation which we have just made; and gives, as examples, the
different motions of the apogee and nodes, the difference of the
change of the eccentricity, and the difference of the moon’s
variation, according to the different distances of the sun. “But this
inequality,” he says, “in astronomical calculations, is usually
referred to the prosthaphæresis of the moon, and confounded with
it.”
46 B. iii. Prop. 22.
Reflections on the Discovery.—Such, then, is the great
Newtonian Induction of Universal Gravitation, and such its history. It
is indisputably and incomparably the greatest scientific discovery
ever made, whether we look at the advance which it involved, the
extent of the truth disclosed, or the fundamental and satisfactory
nature of this truth. As to the first point, we may observe that any
one of the five steps into which we have separated the doctrine,
would, of itself, have been considered as an important
advance;—would have conferred distinction on the persons who
made it, and the time to which it belonged. All 415 the five steps made
at once, formed not a leap, but a flight,—not an improvement
merely, but a metamorphosis,—not an epoch, but a termination.
Astronomy passed at once from its boyhood to mature manhood. Again,
with regard to the extent of the truth, we obtain as wide a
generalization as our physical knowledge admits, when we learn that
every particle of matter, in all times, places, and circumstances,
attracts every other particle in the universe by one common law of
action. And by saying that the truth was of a fundamental and
satisfactory nature, I mean that it assigned, not a rule merely, but a
cause, for the heavenly motions; and that kind of cause which most
eminently and peculiarly we distinctly and thoroughly conceive,
namely, mechanical force. Kepler’s laws were merely formal
rules, governing the celestial motions according to the relations of
space, time, and number; Newton’s was a causal law, referring
these motions to mechanical reasons. It is no doubt conceivable that
future discoveries may both extend and further explain Newton’s
doctrines;—may make gravitation a case of some wider law, and
may disclose something of the mode in which it operates; questions
with which Newton himself struggled. But, in the mean time, few
persons will dispute, that both in generality and profundity, both in
width and depth, Newton’s theory is altogether without a rival or
neighbor.47
47 The value and nature of this step
have long been generally acknowledged wherever science is cultivated.
Yet it would appear that there is, in one part of Europe, a school of
philosophers who contest the merit of this part of Newton’s
discoveries. “Kepler,” says a celebrated German metaphysician,*
“discovered the laws of free motion; a discovery of immortal glory. It
has since been the fashion to say that Newton first found out the
proof of these rules. It has seldom happened that the glory of the
first discoverer has been more unjustly transferred to another
person.” It may appear strange that any one in the present day should
hold such language; but if we examine the reasons which this author
gives, they will be found, I think, to amount to this: that his mind
is in the condition in which Kepler’s was; and that the whole range of
mechanical ideas and modes of conception which made the transition
from Kepler and Newton possible, are extraneous to the domain of his
philosophy. Even this author, however, if I understand him rightly,
recognizes Newton as the author of the doctrine of Perturbations.
 I have given a further account of these views, in a Memoir On
Hegel’s Criticism of Newton’s Principia. Cambridge Transactions,
1849.
* Hegel, Encyclopædia, § 270.
The requisite conditions of such a discovery in the mind of its
author were, in this as in other cases, the idea, and its comparison
with facts;—the conception of the law, and the moulding this
conception in such a form as to correspond with known realities. The
idea of mechanical 416 force as the cause of the celestial
motions, had, as we have seen, been for some time growing up in men’s
minds; had gone on becoming more distinct and more general; and had,
in some persons, approached the form in which it was entertained by
Newton. Still, in the mere conception of universal gravitation, Newton
must have gone far beyond his predecessors and contemporaries, both in
generality and distinctness; and in the inventiveness and sagacity
with which he traced the consequences of this conception, he was, as
we have shown, without a rival, and almost without a second. As to the
facts which he had to include in his law, they had been accumulating
from the very birth of astronomy; but those which he had more
peculiarly to take hold of were the facts of the planetary motions as
given by Kepler, and those of the moon’s motions as given by Tycho
Brahe and Jeremy Horrox.
We find here occasion to make a remark which is important in its
bearing on the nature of progressive science. What Newton thus used
and referred to as facts, were the laws which his
predecessors had established. What Kepler and Horrox had put forth as
“theories,” were now established truths, fit to be used in the
construction of other theories. It is in this manner that one theory
is built upon another;—that we rise from particulars to
generals, and from one generalization to another;—that we have,
in short, successive steps of induction. As Newton’s laws assumed
Kepler’s, Kepler’s laws assumed as facts the results of the planetary
theory of Ptolemy; and thus the theories of each generation in the
scientific world are (when thoroughly verified and established,) the facts of the
next generation. Newton’s theory is the circle of generalization which
includes all the others;—the highest point of the inductive
ascent;—the catastrophe of the philosophic drama to which Plato
had prologized;—the point to which men’s minds had been
journeying for two thousand years.
Character of Newton.—It is not easy to anatomize the
constitution and the operations of the mind which makes such an
advance in knowledge. Yet we may observe that there must exist in it,
in an eminent degree, the elements which compose the mathematical
talent. It must possess distinctness of intuition, tenacity and
facility in tracing logical connection, fertility of invention, and a
strong tendency to generalization. It is easy to discover indications
of these characteristics in Newton. The distinctness of his intuitions
of space, and we may add of force also, was seen in the amusements of
his youth; in his constructing clocks and mills, carts and dials, as
well as the facility with which he 417 mastered geometry. This fondness for
handicraft employments, and for making models and machines, appears to
be a common prelude of excellence in physical science;48 probably on this very account, that it
arises from the distinctness of intuitive power with which the child
conceives the shapes and the working of such material combinations.
Newton’s inventive power appears in the number and variety of the
mathematical artifices and combinations which he devised, and of which
his books are full. If we conceive the operation of the inventive
faculty in the only way in which it appears possible to conceive
it;—that while some hidden source supplies a rapid stream of
possible suggestions, the mind is on the watch to seize and detain any
one of these which will suit the case in hand, allowing the rest to
pass by and be forgotten;—we shall see what extraordinary
fertility of mind is implied by so many successful efforts; what an
innumerable host of thoughts must have been produced, to supply so
many that deserved to be selected. And since the selection is
performed by tracing the consequences of each suggestion, so as to
compare them with the requisite conditions, we see also what rapidity
and certainty in drawing conclusions the mind must possess as a
talent, and what watchfulness and patience as a habit.
48 As in Galileo, Hooke, Huyghens, and
others.
The hidden fountain of our unbidden thoughts is for us a mystery;
and we have, in our consciousness, no standard by which we can measure
our own talents; but our acts and habits are something of which we are
conscious; and we can understand, therefore, how it was that Newton
could not admit that there was any difference between himself and
other men, except in his possession of such habits as we have
mentioned, perseverance and vigilance. When he was asked how he made
his discoveries, he answered, “by always thinking about them;” and at
another time he declared that if he had done any thing, it was due to
nothing but industry and patient thought: “I keep the subject of my
inquiry constantly before me, and wait till the first dawning opens
gradually, by little and little, into a full and clear light.” No
better account can be given of the nature of the mental
effort which gives to the philosopher the full benefit of his
powers; but the natural powers of men’s minds are not on that
account the less different. There are many who might wait through ages
of darkness without being visited by any dawn.
The habit to which Newton thus, in some sense, owed his 418 discoveries, this
constant attention to the rising thought, and development of its
results in every direction, necessarily engaged and absorbed his
spirit, and made him inattentive and almost insensible to external
impressions and common impulses. The stories which are told of his
extreme absence of mind, probably refer to the two years during which
he was composing his Principia, and thus following out a train
of reasoning the most fertile, the most complex, and the most
important, which any philosopher had ever had to deal with. The
magnificent and striking questions which, during this period, he must
have had daily rising before him; the perpetual succession of
difficult problems of which the solution was necessary to his great
object; may well have entirely occupied and possessed him. “He existed
only to calculate and to think.”49 Often, lost in
meditation, he knew not what he did, and his mind appeared to have
quite forgotten its connection with the body. His servant reported
that, on rising in a morning, he frequently sat a large portion of the
day, half-dressed, on the side of his bed  and that his meals waited
on the table for hours before he came to take them. Even with his
transcendent powers, to do what he did was almost irreconcilable with
the common conditions of human life; and required the utmost devotion
of thought, energy of effort, and steadiness of will—the
strongest character, as well as the highest endowments, which belong
to man.
49  Biot.
Newton has been so universally considered as the greatest example
of a natural philosopher, that his moral qualities, as well as his
intellect, have been referred to as models of the philosophical
character; and those who love to think that great talents are
naturally associated with virtue, have always dwelt with pleasure upon
the views given of Newton by his contemporaries; for they have
uniformly represented him as candid and humble, mild and good. We may
take as an example of the impressions prevalent about him in his own
time, the expressions of Thomson, in the Poem on his Death.50 419


Say ye who best can tell, ye happy few,
Who saw him in the softest lights of life,
All unwithheld, indulging to his friends
The vast unborrowed treasures of his mind,
Oh, speak the wondrous man! how mild, how
calm
How greatly humble, how divinely good,
How firm established on eternal truth!
Fervent in doing well, with every nerve
Still pressing on, forgetful of the past,
And panting for perfection; far above
Those little cares and visionary joys
That so perplex the fond impassioned heart
Of ever-cheated, ever-trusting man.
50 In the same strain we find the
general voice of the time. For instance, one of Loggan’s “Views of
Cambridge” is dedicated “Isaaco Newtono . . Mathematico, Physico,
Chymico consummatissimo; nec minus suavitate morum  et candore animi .
. . spectabili.”
 In opposition to the general current of such testimony, we have
the complaints of Flamsteed, who ascribes to Newton angry language and
harsh conduct in the matter of the publication of the Greenwich
Observations, and of Whiston. Yet even Flamsteed speaks well of his
general disposition. Whiston was himself so weak and prejudiced that
his testimony is worth very little.
[2d Ed.] [In the first edition of the Principia, published
in 1687, Newton showed that the nature of all the then known
inequalities of the moon, and in some cases, their quantities, might
be deduced from the principles which he laid down  but the
determination of the amount and law of most of the inequalities was
deferred to a more favorable opportunity, when he might be furnished
with better astronomical observations. Such observations as he needed
for this purpose had been made by Flamsteed, and for these he applied,
representing how much value their use would add to the observations.
“If,” he says, in 1694, “you publish them without such a theory to
recommend them, they will only be thrown into the heap of the
observations of former astronomers, till somebody shall arise that by
perfecting the theory of the moon shall discover your observations to
be exacter than the rest; but when that shall be, God knows: I fear,
not in your lifetime, if I should die before it is done. For I find
this theory so very intricate, and the theory of gravity so necessary
to it, that I am satisfied it will never be perfected but by somebody
who understands the theory of gravity as well, or better than I do.”
He obtained from Flamsteed the lunar observations for which he
applied, and by using these he framed the Theory of the Moon which is
given as his in David Gregory’s Astronomiæ Elementa.51 He also obtained from Flamsteed the
diameters of the planets as observed at various times, and the
greatest elongation of Jupiter’s Satellites, both of which, Flamsteed
says, he made use of in his Principia.
51 In the Preface to a Treatise on
Dynamics, Part i., published in 1836, I have endeavored to show
that Newton’s modes of determining several of the lunar inequalities
admitted of an accuracy not very inferior to the modern analytical
methods.
Newton, in his letters to Flamsteed in 1694 and 5, acknowledges
this service.52]
52 The quarrel on the subject of the
publication of Flamsteed’s Observations took place at a later period.
Flamsteed wished to have his Observations printed complete and entire.
Halley, who, under the authority of Newton and others, had the
management of the printing, made many alterations and omissions, which
Flamsteed considered as deforming and spoiling the work. The
advantages of publishing a complete series of observations,
now generally understood, were not then known to astronomers in
general, though well known to Flamsteed, and earnestly insisted upon
in his remonstrances. The result was that Flamsteed published his
Observations at his own expense, and finally obtained permission to
destroy the copies printed by Halley, which he did. In 1726, after
Flamsteed’s death, his widow applied to the Vice-Chancellor of Oxford,
requesting that the volume printed by Halley might be removed out of
the Bodleian Library, where it exists, as being “nothing more than an
erroneous abridgment of Mr. Flamsteed’s works,” and unfit to see the
light. 420</div></body></text></TEI>