<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="10">
      SECTION 3. OF THE SECRETARISHIPS.
    

      Whether the present Secretaries are the best qualified to aid in reforming
      the Society, is a question I shall not discuss. With regard to the senior
      Secretary, the time of his holding office is perhaps more unfortunate than
      the circumstance. If I might be permitted to allude for a moment to his
      personal character, I should say that the mild excellencies of his heart
      have prevented the Royal Society from deriving the whole of that advantage
      from his varied knowledge and liberal sentiments which some might perhaps
      have anticipated; and many will agree with me in regretting that his
      judgment has not directed a larger portion of the past deeds of the
      Councils of the Royal Society. Of the junior Secretary I shall only
      observe, that whilst I admit his industry, his perseverance, and his
      talents, I regret to see such valuable qualities exerted at a
      disadvantage, and that I sincerely wish them all the success they merit in
      situations more adapted for their developement.
    

      There are, however, some general principles which it may be important to
      investigate, which relate to the future as well as to the past state of
      the office of Secretary of the Royal Society. Inconvenience has already
      arisen from having had at a former period one of our Secretaries the
      conductor of a scientific journal; and this is one of the points in which
      I can agree with those who now manage the affairs of the Society. [These
      observations were written previous to the late appointment, to which I now
      devote Section 6. Experience seems to be lost on the Council of the Royal
      Society.] Perhaps it might be advantageous to extend the same
      understanding to the other officers of the Society at least, if not to the
      members of its Council.
    

      Another circumstance worthy of the attention of the Society is, to
      consider whether it is desirable, except in special cases, to have
      military persons appointed to any of its offices. There are several
      peculiarities in the military character, which, though they do not
      absolutely unfit their possessors for the individual prosecution of
      science, may in some degree disqualify such persons from holding offices
      in scientific institutions. The habits both of obedience and command,
      which are essential in military life, are little fitted for that perfect
      freedom which should reign in the councils of science. If a military chief
      commit an oversight or an error, it is necessary, in order to retain the
      confidence of those he commands, to conceal or mask it as much as
      possible. If an experimentalist make a mistake, his only course to win the
      confidence of his fellow-labourers in science, and to render his future
      observations of any use, is to acknowledge it in the most full and
      explicit manner. The very qualifications which contribute to the
      professional excellence of the soldier, constitute his defects when he
      enters the paths of science; and it is only in those rare cases where the
      force of genius is able to control and surmount these habits, that his
      admission to the offices of science can be attended with any advantage to
      it.
    

      Another objection deserving notice, although not applying exclusively to
      the military profession, is, that persons not imbued with the feelings of
      men of science, when they have published their observations, are too apt
      to view every criticism upon them as a personal question, and to consider
      that it is as offensive to doubt the accuracy of their observations as it
      is to doubt their word. Nothing can be more injurious to science than that
      such an opinion should be tolerated. The most unreserved criticism is
      necessary for truth; and those suspicions respecting his own accuracy,
      which every philosophical experimenter will entertain concerning his own
      researches, ought never to be considered as a reproach, when they are kept
      in view in examining the experiments of others. The minute circumstances
      and apparently trivial causes which lend their influence towards error,
      even in persons of the most candid judgment, are amongst the most curious
      phenomena of the human mind.
    

      The importance of affording every aid to enable others to try the merits
      of observations, has been so well expressed by Mayer, that I shall
      conclude these remarks with an extract from the Preface to his
      Observations:
    

      "Officii enim cujusque observatoris ease reor, de habitu instrumenti sui,
      de cura ac precautione, qua usus est, ad illud recte tractandum, deque
      mediis in errores ejus inquirendi rationem reddere publice, ut aliis
      quoque copia sit judicandi, quanta fides habenda conclusionibus ex nostris
      observationibus deductis aut deducendis. Hoc cum minus fecissent
      precedentis saeculi astronomi, praxin nimis secure, nimisque theoretice
      tractantes, factum inde potissimum est, ut illorum observationes tot
      vigiliis tantoque labore comparatae tam cito obsoleverint." P. viii.
    

      There are certain duties which the Royal Society owes to its own character
      as well as to the public, which, having been on some occasions apparently
      neglected, it may be here the proper place to mention, since it is
      reasonable to suppose that attention to them is within the province of its
      Secretaries.
    

      The first to which I shall allude is the singular circumstances attending
      the fact of the Royal Society having printed a volume of Astronomical
      Observations which were made at the Observatory of Paramatta (New South
      Wales), bearing the title of "The Third Part of the Philosophical
      Transactions for the Year 1829."
    

      Now this Observatory was founded at the private expense of a British
      officer; the instruments were paid for out of his purse; two observers
      were brought from Europe, to be employed in making use of those
      instruments, at salaries defrayed by him. A considerable portion of the
      observations so printed were made by these astronomers during their
      employment in his service, and some of them are personally his own. Yet
      has the Royal Society, in adopting them as part of its Transactions,
      omitted all mention, either in their title-page, preface, or in any part
      of the volume, of the FACT that the world owed these valuable observations
      to the enlightened munificence of Lieutenant-General Sir Thomas Brisbane;
      whose ardent zeal in the pursuit of science induced him to found, at his
      own private expense, an establishment which it has been creditable to the
      British Government to continue as a national institution. Had any kindred
      feelings existed in the Council, instead of endeavouring to shift the
      responsibility, they would have hastened to rectify an omission, less
      unjust to the individual than it was injurious to English science.
    

      Another topic, which concerns most vitally the character and integrity of
      the Royal Society, I hardly know how to approach. It has been publicly
      stated that confidence cannot be placed in the written minutes of the
      Society; and an instance has been adduced, in which an entry has been
      asserted to have been made, which could not have been the true statement
      of what actually passed at the Council.
    

      The facts on which the specific instance rests are not difficult to verify
      by members of the Royal Society. I have examined them, and shall state
      them before I enter on the reasoning which may be founded upon them. In
      the minutes of the Council, 26th November, 1829, we find—
    

      "Resolved, that the following gentlemen be recommended to be put upon the
      Council for the ensuing year." [Here follows a list of persons, amongst
      whom the name of Sir John Franklin occurs [Sir John Franklin was absent
      from London, and altogether unacquainted with this transaction, until he
      saw it stated in the newspapers some months after it had taken place. That
      his name was the one substituted for that of Captain Beaufort I know, from
      other evidence which need not be produced here, as the omission of the
      latter name is the charge that has been made.], and that of Captain
      Beaufort is not found. [Any gentleman may satisfy himself that this is not
      a mistake of the Assistant Secretary's, in copying, by consulting the
      rough minutes of that meeting of the Council, which it might perhaps be as
      well to write in a rough minute-book, instead of upon loose sheets of
      paper; nor can it be attributed to any error arising from accidentally
      mislaying the real minutes, for in that case the error would have been
      rectified immediately it was detected; and this has remained uncorrected,
      although publicly spoken of for months. As there is no erasure in the
      list, one is reluctantly compelled to conjecture that the real minutes of
      that meeting have been destroyed.]]
    

      Now this could not be the list actually recommended by the Council on the
      morning of the 26th of November, because the President himself, on the
      evening of that day, informed Capt. Beaufort that he was placed on the
      house list; and that officer, with the characteristic openness of his
      profession, wrote on the next or the following day to the President,
      declining that situation, and stating his reasons for the step.
    

      Upon the fact, therefore, of the suppression of part of a resolution of
      the Council, on the 26th of November, there can be no doubt; but in order
      to understand the whole nature of the transaction, other information is
      necessary. It has been the wish of many members of the Society, that the
      President should not absolutely name his own Council, but that the subject
      should be discussed fairly at the meeting previous to the Anniversary—this
      has always been opposed by Mr. Gilbert, and those who support him. Now, it
      has been stated, that, at the meeting of the Council on the 26th of
      November, the President took out of his pocket a bit of paper, from which
      he read the names of several persons as fit to be on the Council for the
      ensuing year;—that it was not understood that any motion was made,
      and it is certain that none was seconded, nor was any ballot taken on such
      an important question; and it was a matter of considerable surprise to
      some of those present, to discover afterwards that it was entered on the
      minutes as a resolution. This statement I have endeavoured to verify, and
      I believe it to be substantially correct; if it was a resolution, it was
      dictated, not discussed. It is also important to observe, that no similar
      resolution stands on the council-books for any previous year.
    

      On examining the minutes of the succeeding Council, no notice of the
      letter of Captain Beaufort to the President is found. Why was it omitted?
      If the first entry had been truly made, there would have been no necessity
      for the omission; and after the insertion of that letter, a resolution
      would naturally have followed, recommending another name instead of the
      one withdrawn. Such was the natural and open course; but this would have
      exposed to the Society the weakness of those who manage it. If the rough
      minutes of each meeting of the Council were read over before it separated,
      and were copied previously to the next meeting, such a substitution could
      hardly have occurred; but, unfortunately, this is not the case, and the
      delay is in some cases considerable. Thus, the minutes of the three
      Councils, held on February 4, on February 11, and on March 11, were not
      entered on the minute-books of the Council on Tuesday, the 16th March; nor
      was this the fault of the Assistant-secretary, for up to that day the
      rough minutes of no one of those Councils had been transmitted to him.
    

      Deeply as every friend to the Royal Society must regret such an
      occurrence, one slight advantage may accrue. Should that resolution be
      ever quoted hereafter to prove that the Council of 1829 really discussed
      the persons to be recommended as their successors, the detection of this
      suppression of one portion of it, will furnish better means of estimating
      the confidence due to the whole.
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>