<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="8">
      SECTION 1. MODE OF BECOMING A FELLOW OF THE ROYAL SOCIETY.
    

      I have no intention of stating what ought to be the qualifications of a
      Fellow of the Royal Society; but, for years, the practical mode of
      arriving at that honour, has been as follows:—
    

      A. B. gets any three Fellows to sign a certificate, stating that he (A.
      B.) is desirous of becoming a member, and likely to be a useful and
      valuable one. This is handed in to the Secretary, and suspended in the
      meeting-room. At the end of ten weeks, if A. B. has the good fortune to be
      perfectly unknown by any literary or scientific achievement, however
      small, he is quite sure of being elected as a matter of course. If, on the
      other hand, he has unfortunately written on any subject connected with
      science, or is supposed to be acquainted with any branch of it, the
      members begin to inquire what he has done to deserve the honour; and,
      unless he has powerful friends, he has a fair chance of being
      black-balled. [I understand that certificates are now read at the Council,
      previously to their being hung up in the meeting-room; but I am not aware
      that this has in the slightest degree diminished their number, which was,
      at the time of writing this note, TWENTY-FOUR.]
    

      In fourteen years' experience, the few whom I have seen rejected, have all
      been known persons; but even in such cases a hope remains;—perseverance
      will do much, and a gentleman who values so highly the distinction of
      admission to the Royal Society, may try again; and even after being twice
      black-balled, if he will a third time condescend to express his desire to
      become a member, he may perhaps succeed, by the aid of a hard canvass. In
      such circumstances, the odds are much in favour of the candidate
      possessing great scientific claims; and the only objection that could then
      reasonably be suggested, would arise from his estimating rather too highly
      a distinction which had become insignificant from its unlimited extension.
    

      It should be observed, that all members contribute equally, and that the
      sum now required is fifty pounds. It used, until lately, to be ten pounds
      on entrance, and four pounds annually. The amount of this subscription is
      so large, that it is calculated to prevent many men of real science from
      entering the Society, and is a very severe tax on those who do so; for
      very few indeed of the cultivators of science rank amongst the wealthy
      classes. Several times, whilst I have been consulting books or papers at
      Somerset House, persons have called to ask the Assistant-secretary the
      mode of becoming a member of the Royal Society. I should conjecture, from
      some of these applications, that it is not very unusual for gentlemen in
      the country to order their agents in London to take measures for putting
      them up at the Royal Society.
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>