<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="62">

BOOK IX.

THE
PHILOSOPHY
OF
BIOLOGY.
La vie est donc un Tourbillon plus ou moins rapide, plus
ou moins compliqué, dont la direction est constante, et qui
entraine toujours des molecules de mêmes sorts, mais où les
molecules individuelles entrent et d’où elles sortent continuellement, de manière que la Forme du corps vivant lui est plus
essentielle que sa Matière.
Tant que ce mouvement subsiste, le corps où il s’exerce est
vivant; il vit. Lorsque le mouvement s’arrête sans retour, le
corps meurt.
Cuvier, Règne Animal, s. 12.
I remember, upon asking our famous Harvey, what induced
him to think of a circulation of the blood, he said, that observing
the valves in the veins of many parts of the body, so placed as to
give a free passage to the blood towards the heart, but to oppose
the passage of the venal blood the contrary way, he imagined
that so provident a cause as nature had not thus placed so many
valves without design; and as no design seemed more probable
than that the blood could not well, because of the interposing
valves, be sent by the veins to the limbs, it should be sent through
the arteries and return through the veins when valves did not
oppose its course that way.
Boyle
 On the Final Causes of Natural Things. On the
Proposition: ’Tis often allowable for a naturalist, from the
manifest and apposite uses of the parts of animal bodies, to collect
some of the particular ends for which the Creator designed them:
and in some cases we may, from the known nature and structure of
the parts, draw particular conjectures about the particular offices of
them.
</div></body></text></TEI>