<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="133">CHAPTER II.
Formation of Systematic Descriptive
Geology.

Sect. 1.—Discovery of the Order and
Stratification of the Materials of the Earth.
THAT the substances of which
the earth is framed are not scattered and mixed at random, but possess
identity and continuity to a considerable extent, Lister was aware,
when he proposed his map. But there is, in his suggestions, nothing
relating to stratification; nor any order of position, still less of
time, assigned to these materials. Woodward, however, appears to have
been fully aware of the general law of stratification. On collecting
information from all parts, “the result was,” he says, “that in time I
was abundantly assured that the circumstances of these things in
remoter countries were much the same with those of ours here: that the
stone, and other terrestrial matter in France, Flanders, Holland,
Spain, Italy, Germany, Denmark, and Sweden, was distinguished into
strata or layers, as it is in England; that these strata were
divided by parallel fissures; that there were enclosed in the stone
and all the other denser kinds of terrestrial matter, great numbers of
the shells, and other productions of the sea, in the same manner as in
that of this island.”13 So remarkable a truth, thus collected
from a copious collection of particulars by a patient induction, was
an important step in the science.
13 Natural History of the
Earth, 1723.
These general facts now began to be commonly recognized, and
followed into detail. Stukeley the antiquary14 (1724),
remarked an important feature in the strata of England, that their
escarpments, or steepest sides, are turned towards the west and
north-west; and Strachey15 (1719), gave a stratigraphical
description of certain coal-mines near Bath.16 Michell,
appointed Woodwardian Professor at Cambridge 512 in 1762, described this stratified
structure of the earth far more distinctly than his predecessors, and
pointed out, as the consequence of it, that “the same kinds of earths,
stones, and minerals, will appear at the surface of the earth in long
parallel slips, parallel to the long ridges of mountains; and so, in
fact, we find them.”17
14 Itinerarium Curiosum,
1724.
15 Phil. Trans. 1719, and
Observations on Strata, &c. 1729.
16 Fitton, Annals of
Philosophy, N. S. vol. i. and ii. (1832, ’3), p.  157.
17 Phil. Trans. 1760.
Michell (as appeared by papers of his which were examined after his
death) had made himself acquainted with the series of English strata
which thus occur from Cambridge to York;—that is, from the chalk
to the coal. These relations of position required that geological
maps, to complete the information they conveyed, should be accompanied
by geological Sections, or imaginary representations of the
order and mode of superpositions, as well as of the superficial extent
of the strata, as in more recent times has usually been done. The
strata, as we travel from the higher to the lower, come from under
each other into view; and this out-cropping, basseting,
or by whatever other term it is described, is an important feature in
their description.
It was further noticed that these relations of position were
combined with other important facts, which irresistibly suggested the
notion of a relation in time. This, indeed, was implied in all
theories of the earth; but observations of the facts most require our
notice. Steno is asserted by Humboldt18 to be the first
who (in 1669) distinguished between rocks anterior to the existence of
plants and animals upon the globe, containing therefore no organic
remains; and rocks super-imposed on these, and full of such remains;
“turbidi maris sedimenta sibi invicem imposita”.
18 Essai Géognostique.
Rouelle is stated, by his pupil Desmarest, to have made some
additional and important observations. “He saw,” it is said, “that the
shells which occur in rocks were not the same in all countries; that
certain species occur together, while others do not occur in the same
beds; that there is a constant order in the arrangement of these
shells, certain species lying in distinct bands.”19
19 Encycl. Méthod. Geogr.
Phys. tom. i. p. 416, as quoted by Fitton as above, p. 159.
Such divisions as these required to be marked by technical names. A
distinction was made of l’ancienne terre and la nouvelle
terre, to which Rouelle added a travaille intermédiaire.
Rouelle died in 1770, having been known by lectures, not by books.
Lehman, in 1756, claims for himself the credit of being the first to
observe and describe correctly the structure of stratified countries;
being ignorant, 513
probably, of the labors of Strachey in England. He divided mountains
into three classes;20 primitive, which were formed
with the world;—those which resulted from a partial destruction
of the primitive rocks;—and a third class resulting from local
or universal deluges. In 1759, also, Arduine,21 in his Memoirs
on the mountains of Padua, Vicenza, and Verona, deduced, from original
observations, the distinction of rocks into primary,
secondary, and tertiary.
20 Lyell, i. 70.
21 Ib. 72.
The relations of position and fossils were, from this period,
inseparably connected with opinions concerning succession in time.
Odoardi remarked,22 that the strata of the Sub-Apennine hills are unconformable to
those of the Apennine, (as Strachey had observed, that the strata
above the coal were unconformable to the coal;23) and his work
contained a clear argument respecting the different ages of these two
classes of hills. Fuchsel was, in 1762, aware of the distinctness of
strata of different ages in Germany. Pallas and Saussure were guided
by general views of the same kind in observing the countries which
they visited: but, perhaps, the general circulation of such notions
was most due to Werner.
22 Ib. 74.
23 Fitton, p. 157.
Sect. 2.—Systematic form given to Descriptive
Geology.—Werner.
Werner expressed the general
relations of the strata of the earth by means of classifications
which, so far as general applicability is concerned, are extremely
imperfect and arbitrary; he promulgated a theory which almost entirely
neglected all the facts previously discovered respecting the grouping
of fossils,—which was founded upon observations made in a very
limited district of Germany,—and which was contradicted even by
the facts of this district. Yet the acuteness of his discrimination in
the subjects which he studied, the generality of the tenets he
asserted, and the charm which he threw about his speculations, gave to
Geology, or, as he termed it, Geognosy, a popularity and
reputation which it had never before possessed. His system had
asserted certain universal formations, which followed each other in a
constant order;—granite the lowest,—then mica-slate and
clay-slate;—upon these primitive rocks, generally highly
inclined, rest other transition strata;—upon these, lie
secondary ones, which being more nearly horizontal, are called
flötz or flat. The term formation, 514 which we have thus
introduced, indicating groups which, by evidence of all
kinds,—of their materials, their position, and their organic
contents,—are judged to belong to the same period, implies no
small amount of theory: yet this term, from this time forth, is to be
looked upon as a term of classification solely, so far as
classification can be separately attended to.
Werner’s distinctions of strata were for the most part drawn from
mineralogical constitution. Doubtless, he could not fail to perceive
the great importance of organic fossils. “I was witness,” says M. de
Humboldt, one of his most philosophical followers, “of the lively
satisfaction which he felt when, in 1792, M. de Schlottheim,
one of the most distinguished geologists of the school of Freiberg,
began to make the relations of fossils to strata the principal object
of his studies.” But Werner and the disciples of his school, even the
most enlightened of them, never employed the characters derived from
organic remains with the same boldness and perseverance as those who
had from the first considered them as the leading phenomena: thus M.
de Humboldt expresses doubts which perhaps many other geologists do
not feel when, in 1823, he says, “Are we justified in concluding that
all formations are characterized by particular species? that the
fossil-shells of the chalk, the muschelkalk, the Jura limestone, and
the Alpine limestone, are all different? I think this would be pushing
the induction much too far.”24 In Prof.
Jamieson’s Geognosy, which may be taken as a representation of
the Wernerian doctrines, organic fossils are in no instance referred
to as characters of formations or strata. After the curious and
important evidence, contained in organic fossils, which had been
brought into view by the labors of Italian, English, and German
writers, the promulgation of a system of Descriptive Geology, in which
all this evidence was neglected, cannot be considered otherwise than
as a retrograde step in science.
24 Gissement des Roches, p.
41.
Werner maintained the aqueous deposition of all strata above the
primitive rocks; even of those trap rocks, to which, from their
resemblance to lava and other phenomena, Raspe, Arduino, and others,
had already assigned a volcanic origin. The fierce and long
controversy between the Vulcanists and Neptunists, which
this dogma excited, does not belong to this part of our history; but
the discovery of veins of granite penetrating the superincumbent
slate, to which the controversy led, was an important event in
descriptive geology. Hutton, the 515 author of the theory of igneous
causation which was in this country opposed to that of Werner, sought
and found this phenomenon in the Grampian hills, in 1785. This
supposed verification of his system “filled him with delight, and
called forth such marks of joy and exultation, that the guides who
accompanied him were persuaded, says his biographer,25 that he must have discovered a vein of
silver or gold.”26
25 Playfair’s Works, vol. iv.
p. 75.
26 Lyell, i. 90.
Desmarest’s examination of Auvergne (1768) showed that there was
there an instance of a country which could not even be described
without terms implying that the basalt, which covered so large a
portion of it, had flowed from the craters of extinct volcanoes. His
map of Auvergne was an excellent example of a survey of such a
country, thus exhibiting features quite different from those of common
stratified countries.27
27 Lyell, i. 86.
The facts connected with metalliferous veins were also objects of
Werner’s attention. A knowledge of such facts is valuable to the
geologist as well as to the miner, although even yet much difficulty
attends all attempts to theorize concerning them. The facts of this
nature have been collected in great abundance in all mining districts;
and form a prominent part of the descriptive geology of such
districts; as, for example, the Hartz, and Cornwall.
Without further pursuing the history of the knowledge of the
inorganic phenomena of the earth, I turn to a still richer department
of geology, which is concerned with organic fossils.
Sect. 3.—Application of Organic Remains as a
Geological Character.—Smith.
Rouelle and Odoardi had
perceived, as we have seen, that fossils were grouped in bands: but
from this general observation to the execution of a survey of a large
kingdom, founded upon this principle, would have been a vast stride,
even if the author of it had been aware of the doctrines thus asserted
by these writers. In fact, however, William Smith executed such a
survey of England, with no other guide or help than his own sagacity
and perseverance. In his employments as a civil engineer, he noticed
the remarkable continuity and constant order of the strata in the
neighborhood of Bath, as discriminated by their fossils; and about the
year 1793, he28 drew up a Tabular View of the 516 strata of that
district, which contained the germ of his subsequent discoveries.
Finding in the north of England the same strata and associations of
strata with which he had become acquainted in the west, he was led to
name them and to represent them by means of maps, according to their
occurrence over the whole face of England. These maps appeared29 in 1815; and a work by the same author,
entitled The English Strata identified by Organic Remains, came
forth later. But the views on which this identification of strata
rests, belong to a considerably earlier date; and had not only been
acted upon, but freely imparted in conversation many years before.
28 Fitton, p. 148.
29 Brit. Assoc. 1832. Conybeare, p.
373.
In the meantime the study of fossils was pursued with zeal in
various countries. Lamarck and Defrance employed themselves in
determining the fossil shells of the neighborhood of Paris;30 and the interest inspired by this
subject was strongly nourished and stimulated by the memorable work of
Cuvier and Brongniart, On the Environs of Paris, published in
1811, and by Cuvier’s subsequent researches on the subjects thus
brought under notice. For now, not only the distinction, succession,
and arrangement, but many other relations among fossil strata,
irresistibly arrested the attention of the philosopher. Brongniart31 showed that very striking resemblances
occurred in their fossil remains, between certain strata of Europe and
of North America; and proved that a rock may be so much disguised,
that the identity of the stratum can only be recognized by geological
characters.32
30 Humboldt, Giss. d. R. p.
35.
31 Hist. Nat. des Crustacés
Fossiles, pp. 57, 62.
32 Humboldt, Giss. d. R. p.
45.
The Italian geologists had found in their hills, for the most part,
the same species of shells which existed in their seas; but the German
and English writers, as Gesner,33 Raspe,34 and Brander,35 had perceived
that the fossil-shells were either of unknown species, or of such as
lived in distant latitudes. To decide that the animals and plants, of
which we find the remains in a fossil state, were of species now
extinct, obviously required an exact and extensive knowledge of
natural history. And if this were so, to assign the relations of the
past to the existing tribes of beings, and the peculiarities of their
vital processes and habits, were tasks which could not be performed
without the most consummate physiological skill and talent. Such
tasks, however, have been the familiar employments of geologists, and
naturalists incited and 517 appealed to by geologists, ever since
Cuvier published his examination of the fossil inhabitants of the
Paris basin. Without attempting a history of such labors, I may notice
a few circumstances connected with them.
33 Lyell, i. 70.
34 Ib. 74.
35 Ib. 76.
Sect. 4.—Advances in
Palæontology.—Cuvier.
So long as the organic
fossils which were found in the strata of the earth were the remains
of marine animals, it was very difficult for geologists to be assured
that the animals were such as did not exist in any part or clime of
the existing ocean. But when large land and river animals were
discovered, different from any known species, the persuasion that they
were of extinct races was forced upon the naturalist. Yet this opinion
was not taken up slightly, nor acquiesced in without many
struggles.
Bones supposed to belong to fossil elephants, were some of the
first with regard to which this conclusion was established. Such
remains occur in vast numbers in the soil and gravel of almost every
part of the world; especially in Siberia, where they are called the
bones of the mammoth. They had been noticed by the ancients, as
we learn from Pliny;36 and had been ascribed to human giants,
to elephants imported by the Romans, and to many other origins. But in
1796, Cuvier had examined these opinions with a more profound
knowledge than his predecessors; and he thus stated the result of his
researches.37 “With regard to what have been called
the fossil remains of elephants, from Tentzelius to Pallas, I believe
that I am in the condition to prove, that they belong to animals which
were very clearly different in species from our existing elephants,
although they resembled them sufficiently to be considered as
belonging to the same genera.” He had founded this conclusion
principally on the structure of the teeth, which he found to differ in
the Asiatic and African elephant; while, in the fossil animal, it was
different from both. But he also reasoned in part on the form of the
skull, of which the best-known example had been described in the
Philosophical Transactions as early as 1737.38 “As soon,” says Cuvier, at a later
period, “as I became acquainted with Messerschmidt’s drawing, and
joined to the differences which it presented, those which I had myself
observed in the inferior jaw and the 518 molar teeth, I no longer doubted that
the fossil elephants were of a species different from the Indian
elephant. This idea, which I announced to the Institute in the month
of January, 1796, opened to me views entirely new respecting the
theory of the earth; and determined me to devote myself to the long
researches and to the assiduous labors which have now occupied me for
twenty-five years.”39
36 Hist. Nat. lib. xxxvi.
18.
37 Mém. Inst. Math. et Phys.
tom. ii. p. 4.
38 Described by Breyne from a
specimen found in Siberia by Messerschmidt in 1722. Phil.
Trans. xl. 446.
39 Ossemens Fossiles, second
edit. i. 178.
We have here, then, the starting-point of those researches
concerning extinct animals, which, ever since that time, have
attracted so large a share of notice from geologists and from the
world. Cuvier could hardly have anticipated the vast storehouse of
materials which lay under his feet, ready to supply him occupation of
the most intense interest in the career on which he had thus entered.
The examination of the strata on which Paris stands, and of which its
buildings consist, supplied him with animals, not only different from
existing ones, but some of them of great size and curious
peculiarities. A careful examination of the remains which these strata
contain was undertaken soon after the period we have referred to. In
1802, Defrance had collected several hundreds of undescribed species
of shells; and Lamarck40 began a series of Memoirs upon them;
remodelling the whole of Conchology, in order that they might be
included in its classifications. And two years afterwards (1804)
appears the first of Cuvier’s grand series of Memoirs containing the
restoration of the vertebrate animals of these strata. In this vast
natural museum, and in contributions from other parts of the globe, he
discovered the most extraordinary creatures:—the Palæotherium,41 which is intermediate between the horse
and the pig; the Anoplotherium, which stands nearest to the rhinoceros
and the tapir; the Megalonix and Megatherium, animals of the sloth
tribe, but of the size of the ox and the rhinoceros. The Memoirs which
contained these and many other discoveries, set the naturalists to
work in every part of Europe.
40 Annales du Muséum d’Hist.
Nat. tom. i. p. 308, and the following volumes.
41 Daubuisson, ii. 411.
Another very curious class of animals was brought to light
principally by the geologists of England; animals of which the bones,
found in the lias stratum, were at first supposed to be those
of crocodiles. But in 1816,42 Sir Everard
Home says, “In truth, on a consideration of this skeleton, we cannot
but be inclined to believe, that among the animals destroyed by the
catastrophes of remote antiquity, there had 519 been some at least that differ so
entirely in their structure from any which now exist as to make it
impossible to arrange their fossil remains with any known class of
animals.” The animal thus referred to, being clearly intermediate
between fishes and lizards, was named by Mr. König,
Ichthyosaurus; and its structure and constitution were more
precisely determined by Mr. Conybeare in 1821, when he had occasion to
compare with it another extinct animal of which he and Mr. de la Beche
had collected the remains. This animal, still more nearly approaching
the lizard tribe, was by Mr. Conybeare called Plesiosaurus.43 Of each of these two genera several
species were afterwards found.
42 Phil. Trans. 1816, p.
20.
43 Geol. Trans. vol. v.
Before this time, the differences of the races of animals and
plants belonging to the past and the present periods of the earth’s
history, had become a leading subject of speculation among geological
naturalists. The science produced by this study of the natural history
of former states of the earth has been termed Palæontology; and
there is no branch of human knowledge more fitted to stir men’s
wonder, or to excite them to the widest physiological speculations.
But in the present part of our history this science requires our
notice, only so far as it aims at the restoration of the types of
ancient animals, on clear and undoubted principles of comparative
anatomy. To show how extensive and how conclusive is the science when
thus directed, we need only refer to Cuvier’s Ossemens
Fossiles;44 a work of vast labor and profound
knowledge, which has opened wide the doors of this part of geology. I
do not here attempt even to mention the labors of the many other
eminent contributors to Palæontology; as Brocchi, Des Hayes, Sowerby,
Goldfuss, Agassiz, who have employed themselves on animals, and
Schlottheim, Brongniart, Hutton, Lindley, on plants.
44 The first edition appeared in
1812, consisting principally of the Memoirs to which reference has
already been made.
[2nd Ed.] [Among the many valuable contributions to Palæontology in
more recent times, I may especially mention Mr. Owen’s Reports on
British Fossil Reptiles, on British Fossil Mammalia, and
on the Extinct Animals of Australia, with descriptions of
certain Fossils indicative of large Marsupial Pachydermata: and M.
Agassiz’s Report on the Fossil Fishes of the Devonian System,
his Synoptical Table of British Fossil Fishes, and his
Report on the Fishes of the London Clay. All these are
contained in the volumes produced by the British Association from 1839
to 1845. 520
A new and most important instrument of palæontological
investigation has been put in the geologist’s hand by Prof. Owen’s
discovery, that the internal structure of teeth, as disclosed by the
microscope, is a means of determining the kind of the animal. He has
carried into every part of the animal kingdom an examination founded
upon this discovery, and has published the results of this in his
Odontography. As an example of the application of this
character of animals, I may mention that a tooth brought from Riga by
Sir R. Murchison was in this way ascertained by Mr. Owen to belong to
a fish of the genus Dendrodus. (Geology of Russia, i.
67.)]
When it had thus been established, that the strata of the earth are
characterized by innumerable remains of the organized beings which
formerly inhabited it, and that anatomical and physiological
considerations must be carefully and skilfully applied in order
rightly to interpret these characters, the geologist and the
palæontologist obviously had, brought before them, many very wide and
striking questions. Of these we may give some instances; but, in the
first place, we may add a few words concerning those eminent
philosophers to whom the science owed the basis on which succeeding
speculations were to be built.
Sect. 5.—Intellectual Characters of the Founders
of Systematic Descriptive Geology.
It would be in accordance
with the course we have pursued in treating of other subjects, that we
should attempt to point out in the founders of the science now under
consideration, those intellectual qualities and habits to which we
ascribe their success. The very recent date of the generalizations of
geology, which has hardly allowed us time to distinguish the calm
expression of the opinion of the wisest judges, might, in this
instance, relieve us from such a duty; but since our plan appears to
suggest it, we will, at least, endeavor to mark the characters of the
founders of geology, by a few of their prominent lines.
The three persons who must be looked upon as the main authors of
geological classification are, Werner, Smith, and Cuvier. These three
men were of very different mental constitution; and it will, perhaps,
not be difficult to compare them, in reference to those qualities
which we have all along represented as the main features of the
discoverer’s genius, clearness of ideas, the possession of numerous
facts, and the power of bringing these two elements into contact.
521
In the German, considering him as a geologist, the ideal element
predominated. That Werner’s powers of external discrimination were
extremely acute, we have seen in speaking of him as a mineralogist;
and his talent and tendency for classifying were, in his mineralogical
studies, fully fed by an abundant store of observation; but when he
came to apply this methodizing power to geology, the love of system,
so fostered, appears to have been too strong for the collection of
facts he had to deal with. As we have already said, he promulgated, as
representing the world, a scheme collected from a province, and even
too hastily gathered from that narrow field. Yet his intense spirit of
method in some measure compensated for other deficiencies, and enabled
him to give the character of a science to what had been before a
collection of miscellaneous phenomena. The ardor of system-making
produced a sort of fusion, which, however superficial, served to bind
together the mass of incoherent and mixed materials, and thus to form,
though by strange and anomalous means, a structure of no small
strength and durability, like the ancient vitrified structures which
we find in some of our mountain regions.
Of a very different temper and character was William Smith. No
literary cultivation of his youth awoke in him the speculative love of
symmetry and system; but a singular clearness and precision of the
classifying power, which he possessed as a native talent, was
exercised and developed by exactly those geological facts among which
his philosophical task lay. Some of the advances which he made, had,
as we have seen, been at least entered upon by others who preceded
him: but of all this he was ignorant; and, perhaps, went on more
steadily and eagerly to work out his own ideas, from the persuasion
that they were entirely his own. At a later period of his life, he
himself published an account of the views which had animated him in
his earlier progress. In this account45 he dates his
attempts to discriminate and connect strata from the year 1790, at
which time he was twenty years old. In 1792, he “had considered how he
could best represent the order of superposition—continuity of
course—and general eastern declination of the strata.” Soon
after, doubts which had arisen were removed by the “discovery of a
mode of identifying the strata by the organized fossils respectively
imbedded therein.” And “thus stored with ideas,” as he expresses
himself, he began to communicate them to his friends. In all this, we
see great vividness 522 of thought and activity of mind,
unfolding itself exactly in proportion to the facts with which it had
to deal. We are reminded of that cyclopean architecture in which each
stone, as it occurs, is, with wonderful ingenuity, and with the least
possible alteration of its form, shaped so as to fit its place in a
solid and lasting edifice.
45 Phil. Mag. 1833, vol. i. p.
38.
Different yet again was the character (as a geological discoverer)
of the great naturalist of the beginning of the nineteenth century. In
that part of his labors of which we have now to speak, Cuvier’s
dominant ideas were rather physiological than geological. In his views
of past physical changes, he did not seek to include any ranges of
facts which lay much beyond the narrow field of the Paris basin. But
his sagacity in applying his own great principle of the Conditions of
Existence, gave him a peculiar and unparalleled power in interpreting
the most imperfect fossil records of extinct anatomy. In the
constitution of his mind, all philosophical endowments were so
admirably developed and disciplined, that it was difficult to say,
whether more of his power was due to genius or to culture. The talent
of classifying which he exercised in geology, was the result of the
most complete knowledge and skill in zoology; while his views
concerning the revolutions which had taken place in the organic and
inorganic world, were in no small degree aided by an extraordinary
command of historical and other literature. His guiding ideas had been
formed, his facts had been studied, by the assistance of all the
sciences which could be made to bear upon them. In his geological
labors we seem to see some beautiful temple, not only firm and fair in
itself, but decorated with sculpture and painting, and rich in all
that art and labor, memory and imagination, can contribute to its
beauty.
[2nd Ed.] [Sir Charles Lyell (B. i. c. iv.) has quoted with
approval what I have elsewhere said, that the advancement of three of
the main divisions of geology in the beginning of the present century
was promoted principally by the three great nations of
Europe,—the German, the English, and the
French:—Mineralogical Geology by the German school of
Werner:—Secondary Geology by Smith and his English
successors;—Tertiary Geology by Cuvier and his fellow-laborers
in France.] 523</div></body></text></TEI>