<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Temple of Nature</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1803</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="22">(p. 046) ADDITIONAL NOTES. XII.

CHEMICAL THEORY OF ELECTRICITY AND MAGNETISM.

  Then mark how two electric streams conspire
  To form the resinous and vitreous fire.
Canto III. l. 21.
I. Of Attraction and Repulsion.
The motions, which accomplish the combinations and decompositions of
bodies, depend on the peculiar attractions and repulsions of the
particles of those bodies, or of the sides and angles of them; while
the motions of the sun and planets, of the air and ocean, and of all
bodies approaching to a general centre or retreating from it, depend
on the general attraction or repulsion of those masses of matter. The
peculiar attractions above mentioned are termed chemical affinities,
and the general attraction is termed gravitation; but the peculiar
repulsions of the particles of bodies, or the general repulsion of the
masses of matter, have obtained no specific names, nor have been
sufficiently considered; though they appear to be as powerful agents
as the attractions.
The motions of ethereal fluids, as of magnetism and electricity, are
yet imperfectly understood, and seem to depend both on chemical
affinity, and on gravitation; and also on the peculiar repulsions of
the particles of bodies, and on the general repulsion of the masses of
matter.
In what manner attraction and repulsion are produced has not yet been
attempted to be explained by modern philosophers; but as nothing can
act, where it does not exist, all distant attraction of the particles
of bodies, as well as general gravitation, must be ascribed to some
still finer ethereal fluid; which fills up all space between the suns
and their planets, as well as the interstices of coherent matter.
Repulsion in the same manner must consist of some finer ethereal
fluid; (p. 047) which at first projected the planets from the sun,
and I suppose prevents their return to it; and which occasionally
volatilizes or decomposes solid bodies into fluid or aerial ones, and
perhaps into ethereal ones.
May not the ethereal matter which constitutes repulsion, be the same
as the matter of heat in its diffused state; which in its quiescent
state is combined with various bodies, as appears from many chemical
explosions, in which so much heat is set at liberty? The ethereal
matter, which constitutes attraction, we are less acquainted with; but
it may also exist combined with bodies, as well as in its diffused
state; since the specific gravities of some metallic mixtures are said
not to accord with what ought to result from the combination of their
specific gravities, which existed before their mixture; but their
absolute gravities have not been attended to sufficiently; as these
have always been supposed to depend on their quantity of matter, and
situation in respect to the centre of the earth.
The ethereal fluids, which constitute peculiar repulsions and
attractions, appear to gravitate round the particles of bodies mixed
together; as those, which constitute the general repulsion or
attraction, appear to gravitate round the greater masses of matter
mixed together; but that which constitutes attraction seems to exist
in a denser state next to the particles or masses of matter; and that
which constitutes repulsion to exist more powerfully in a sphere
further from them; whence many bodies attract at one distance, and
repel at another. This may be observed by approaching to each other
two electric atmospheres round insulated cork-balls; or by pressing
globules of mercury, which roll on the surface, till they unite with
it; or by pressing the drops of water,' which stand on a cabbage leaf,
till they unite with it, and hence light is reflected from the surface
of a mirror without touching it.
Thus the peculiar attractions and repulsions of the particles of
bodies, and the general ones of the masses of matter, perpetually
oppose and counteract each other; whence if the power of attraction
should cease to act, all matter would be dissipated by the power of
repulsion into boundless space; and if heat, or the power of
repulsion, should cease to act, the whole world would become one solid
mass, condensed into a point.
(p. 048) II. Preliminary Propositions.
The following propositions concerning Electricity and Galvanism will
either be proved by direct experiments, or will be rendered probable
by their tending to explain or connect the variety of electric facts,
to which they will be applied.
1. There are two kinds of electric ether, which exist either
separately or in combination. That which is accumulated on the surface
of smooth glass, when it is rubbed with a cushion, is here termed
vitreous ether; and that which is accumulated on the surface of resin
or sealing-wax, when it is rubbed with a cushion, is here termed
resinous ether; and a combination of them, as in their usual state,
may be termed neutral electric ethers.
2. Atmospheres of vitreous or of resinous or of neutral electricity
surround all separate bodies, are attracted by them, and permeate
those, which are called conductors, as metallic and aqueous and
carbonic ones; but will not permeate those, which are termed
nonconductors, as air, glass, silk, resin, sulphur.
3. The particles of vitreous electric ether strongly repel each other
as they surround other bodies; but strongly attract the particles of
resinous electric ether: in similar manner the particles of the
resinous ether powerfully repel each other, and as powerfully attract
those of the vitreous ether. Hence in their separate state they appear
to occupy much greater space, as they, gravitate round insulated
bodies, and are then only cognizable by our senses or experiments.
They rush violently together through conducting substances, and then
probably possess much less space in this their combined state. They
thus resemble oxygen gas and nitrous gas; which rush violently
together when in contact; and occupy less space when united, than
either of them possessed separately before their union. When the two
electric ethers thus unite, a chemical explosion occurs, like an
ignited train of gunpowder; as they give out light and heat; and rend
or fuse the bodies they occupy; which cannot be accounted for on the
mechanical theory of Dr. Franklin.
(p. 049) 4. Glass holds within it in combination much resinous
electric ether, which constitutes a part of it, and which more
forcibly attracts vitreous electric ether from surrounding bodies,
which stands on it mixed with a less proportion of resinous ether like
an atmosphere, but cannot unite with the resinous ether, which is
combined with the glass; and resin, on the contrary, holds within it
in combination much vitreous electric ether, which constitutes a part
of it, and which more forcibly attracts resinous electric ether from
surrounding bodies, which stands on it mixed with a less proportion of
vitreous ether like an atmosphere, but cannot unite with the vitreous
ether, which is combined with the resin.
As in the production of vitrification, those materials are necessary
which contain much oxygen, as minium, and manganese; there is probably
much oxygen combined with glass, which may thence be esteemed a solid
acid, as water may be esteemed a fluid one. It is hence not
improbable, that one kind of electric ether may also be combined with
it, as it seems to affect the oxygen of water in the Galvanic
experiments. The combination of the other kind of electric ether with
wax or sulphur, is countenanced from those bodies, when heated or
melted, being said to part with much electricity as they cool, and as
it appears to affect the hydrogen in the decomposition of water by
Galvanism.
5. Hence the nonconductors of electricity are of two kinds; such as
are combined with vitreous ether, as resin, and sulphur; and such as
are combined with resinous ether, as glass, air, silk. But both these
kinds of nonconductors are impervious to either of the electric
ethers; as those ethers being already combined with other bodies will
not unite with each other, or be removed from their situations by each
other. Whereas the perfect conducting bodies, as metals, water,
charcoal, though surrounded with electric atmospheres, as they have
neither of the electric ethers combined with them, suffer them to
permeate and pass through them, whether separately or in their neutral
state of reciprocal combination.
But it is probable, that imperfect conductors may possess more or less
of either the vitreous or resinous ether combined with them, (p. 050)
since their natural atmospheres are dissimilar as mentioned below; and
that this makes them more or less imperfect conductors.
6. Those bodies which are perfect conductors, have probably neutral
electric atmospheres gravitating round them consisting of an equal or
saturated mixture of the two electric ethers, whereas the atmospheres
round the nonconducting bodies probably consist of an unequal mixture
of the electric ethers, as more of the vitreous one round glass, and
more of the resinous one round resin; and, it is probable, that these
mixed atmospheres, which surround imperfect conducting bodies, consist
also of different proportions of the vitreous and resinous ethers,
according to their being more or less perfect conductors. These minute
degrees of the difference of these electric atmospheres are evinced by
Mr. Bennet's Doubler of Electricity, as shown in his work, and are
termed by him Adhesive Electric Atmospheres, to distinguish them from
those accumulated by art; thus the natural adhesive electricity of
silver is more of the vitreous kind compared with that of zinc, which
consists of a greater proportion of the resinous; that is, in his
language, silver is positive and zinc negative. This experiment I have
successfully repeated with Mr. Bennet's Doubler along with Mr.
Swanwick.
7. Great accumulation or condensation of the separate electric ethers
attract each other so strongly, that they will break a passage through
nonconducting bodies, as through a plate of glass, or of air, and will
rend bodies which are less perfect conductors, and give out light and
heat like the explosion of a train of gunpowder; whence, when a strong
electric shock is passed through a quire of paper, a bur, or elevation
of the sheets, is seen on both sides of it occasioned by the
explosion. Whence trees and stone walls are burst by lightning, and
wires are fused, and inflammable bodies burnt, by the heat given out
along with the flash of light, which cannot be explained by the
mechanic theory.
8. When artificial or natural accumulations of these separate ethers
are very minute in quantity or intensity, they pass slowly and with
difficulty from one body to another, and require the best conductors
for this purpose; whence many of the phenomena of the torpedo or
gymnotus, and of Galvanism. Thus after having discharged a coated
(p. 051) jar, if the communicating wire has been quickly withdrawn, a
second small shock may be taken after the principal discharge, and
this repeatedly two or three times.
Hence the charge of the Galvanic pile being very minute in quantity or
intensity, will not readily pass through the dry cuticle of the hands,
though it so easily passes through animal flesh or nerves, as this
combination of charcoal with water seems to constitute the most
perfect conductor yet known.
9. As light is reflected from the surface of a mirror before it
actually touches it, and as drops of water are repelled from cabbage
leaves without touching them, and as oil lies on water without
touching it, and also as a fine needle may be made to lie on water
without touching it, as shown by Mr. Melville in the Literary Essays
of Edinburgh; there is reason to believe, that the vitreous and
resinous electric ethers are repelled by, or will not pass through,
the surfaces of glass or resin, to which they are applied. But though
neither of these electric ethers passes through the surfaces of glass
or resin, yet their attractive or repulsive powers pass through them:
as the attractive or repulsive power of the magnet to iron passes
through the atmosphere, and all other bodies which exist between them.
So an insulated cork-ball, when electrised either with vitreous or
resinous ether, repels another insulated cork-ball electrised with the
same kind of ether, through half an inch of common air, though these
electric atmospheres do not unite.
Whence it may be concluded, that the general attractive and repulsive
ethers accompany the electric ethers as well as they accompany all
other bodies; and that the electric ethers do not themselves attract
or repel through glass or resin, as they cannot pass through them, but
strongly attract each other when they come into contact, rush
together, and produce an explosion of the sudden liberation of heat
and light.
III. Effect of Metallic Points.
1. When a pointed wire is presented by a person standing on the ground
to an insulated conductor, on which either vitreous or resinous
(p. 052) electricity is accumulated, the accumulated electricity will
pass off at a much greater distance than if a metallic knob be fixed
on the wire and presented in its stead.
2. The same occurs if the metallic point be fixed on the electrised
conductor, and the finger of a person standing on the ground be
presented to it, the accumulated electricity will pass off at a much
greater distance, and indeed will soon discharge itself by
communicating the accumulated electricity to the atmosphere.
3. If a metallic point be fixed on the prime conductor, and the flame
of a candle be presented to it, on electrising the conductor either
with vitreous or resinous ether, the flame of the candle is blown from
the point, which must be owing to the electric fluid in its passage
from the point carrying along with it a stream of atmospheric air.
The manner in which the accumulated electricity so readily passes off
by a metallic point may be thus understood; when a metallic point
stands erect from an electrised metallic plane, the accumulated
electricity which exists on the extremity of the point, is attracted
less than that on the other parts of the electrised surface. For the
particle of electric matter immediately over the point is attracted by
that point only, whereas the particles of electric matter over every
other part of the electrised plane, is not only attracted by the parts
of the plane immediately under them, but also laterally by the
circumjacent parts of it; whence the accumulated electric fluid is
pushed off at this point by that over the other parts being more
strongly attracted to the plane.
Thus if a light insulated horizontal fly be constructed of wire with
points fixed as tangents to the circle, it will revolve the way
contrary to the direction of the points as long as it continues to be
electrised. For the same reason as when a circle of cork, with a point
of the cork standing from it like a tangent, is smeared with oil, and
thrown upon a lake, it will continue to revolve backwards in respect
to the direction of the point till all the oil is dispersed upon the
lake, as first observed by Dr. Franklin; for the oil being attracted
to all the other parts of the cork-circle more than towards the
pointed tangent, that part over the point is pushed off and diffuses
itself on the water, over which it passes without touching, and
consequently without friction; and thus the cork revolves in the
contrary direction.
(p. 053) As the flame of a candle is blown from a point fixed on an
electrised conductor, whether vitreous or resinous electricity is
accumulated on it, it shows that in both cases electricity passes from
the point, which is a forcible argument against the mechanical theory
of positive and negative electricity; because then the flame should be
blown towards the point in one case, and from it in the other.
So the electric fly, as it turns horizontally, recedes from the
direction of the points of the tangents, whether it be electrised with
vitreous or resinous electricity; whereas if it was supposed to
receive electricity, when electrised by resin, and to part with it
when electrised by glass, it ought to revolve different ways; which
also forcibly opposes the theory of positive and negative electricity.
As an electrised point with either kind of electricity causes a stream
of air to pass from it in the direction of the point, it seems to
affect the air much in the same manner as the fluid matter of heat
affects it; that is, it will not readily pass through it, but will
adhere to the particles of air, and is thus carried away with them.
From this it will also appear, that points do not attract electricity,
properly speaking, but suffer it to depart from them; as it is there
less attracted to the body which it surrounds, than by any other part
of the surface.
And as a point presented to an electrised conductor facilitates the
discharge of it, and blows the flame of a candle towards the
conductor, whether vitreous or resinous electricity be accumulated
upon it; it follows, that in both cases some electric matter passes
from the point to the conductor, and that hence there are two electric
ethers; and that they combine or explode when they meet together, and
give out light and heat, and occupy less space in this their combined
state, like the union of nitrous gas with oxygen gas.
</div></body></text></TEI>