<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="35">

CHAPTER X.
Of the general Diffusion of clear Mechanical Ideas.



1. WE
have seen how the progress of knowledge upon the
subject of motion and force has produced, in the course of
the world’s history, a great change in the minds of acute
and speculative men; so that such persons can now reason
with perfect steadiness and precision upon subjects on
which, at first, their thoughts were vague and confused; and
can apprehend, as truths of complete certainty and evidence,
laws which it required great labour and time to discover.
This complete development and clear manifestation
of mechanical ideas has taken place only among
mathematicians and philosophers. But yet a progress of
thought upon such subjects,—an advance from the obscure to
the clear, and from errour to truth,—may be traced in the
world at large, and among those who have not directly
cultivated the exact sciences. This diffused and collateral
influence of science manifests itself, although in a
wavering and fluctuating manner, by various indications, at
various periods of literary history. The opinions and
reasonings which are put forth upon mechanical subjects, and
above all, the adoption, into common language, of terms and
phrases belonging to the prevalent mechanical systems,
exhibit to us the most profound discoveries and speculations
of philosophers in their effect upon more common and
familiar trains of thought. This effect is by no means
unimportant, and we shall point out some examples of such
indications as we have mentioned.
2. The discoveries of the ancients in speculative mechanics
were, as we have seen, very scanty; and 280 hardly
extended their influence to the unmathematical world. Yet
the familiar use of the term ‘center of gravity’ preserved
and suggested the most important part of what the Greeks had
to teach. The other phrases which they employed, as
momentum, energy, virtue, force,
and the like, never had any exact meaning, even among
mathematicians; and therefore never, in the ancient world,
became the means of suggesting just habits of thought. I
have pointed out, in the History of Science, several
circumstances which appear to denote the general confusion
of ideas which prevailed upon mechanical subjects during the
times of the Roman empire. I have there taken as one of the
examples of this confusion, the fable narrated by Pliny and
others concerning the echineïs, a small fish, which was said
to stop a ship merely by sticking to it45. This story
was adduced as betraying the absence of any steady
apprehension of the equality of action and reaction; since
the fish, except it had some immoveable obstacle to hold by,
must be pulled forward by the ship, as much as it pulled the
ship backward. If the writers who speak of this wonder had
shown any perception of the necessity of a reaction, either
produced by the rapid motion of the fish’s fins in the
water, or in any other way, they would not be chargeable
with this confusion of thought; but from their expressions
it is, I think, evident that they saw no such
necessity46. Their idea of mechanical action was not
sufficiently distinct to enable them to see the absurdity of
281 supposing an intense pressure with no obstacle for it
to exert itself against.</div></body></text></TEI>