<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="47">CHAPTER XLV.
Among the various confidences reposed in me by my son,
one was his love. The object of his attachment was a
young lady of quality, named Pandora, niece to Nadasti,
great palatine of Hungary. In consequence of the earnest
recommendation of Castaldo in 1553, Nadasti had taken my
son under his particular protection, and Charles’s principal
home at the periods when the army was dispersed in winter-quarters
was at the palatine’s house in the city of Presburg.
Here his manners had become more polished, and his taste
more refined. Till then, bred in tents, and living amidst
the clangour of arms, he had been a mere soldier, rough,
generous, manly, and brave. But Nadasti was an elegant
scholar, smitten with that ardent love of classical and
ancient lore which has so eminently distinguished the sixteenth
century. He assembled round him men of letters
from various parts of Europe; and, under his auspices, the
days of Matthias Corvinus, king of Hungary, seemed to be
revived, whose love of literature was such, that he kept three
hundred transcribers in his house, constantly employed in
multiplying copies of the precious relics of Roman and
Athenian learning. The consort of Nadasti was one of the
most accomplished matrons of the age in which she lived,
and her three daughters were patterns of every polite and
amiable accomplishment. Such was the school into which
the chevalier de Damville entered at the age of twenty-five,
immediately after the retreat of Castaldo. This may seem
an age somewhat late for new-modelling the character, but
Charles had an enterprising and aspiring temper; and he
soon became a distinguished ornament of courts and the
society of ladies. Castaldo had taught him all he knew,[450]
the temper, the manners, and the science of a military
chieftain: the palace of Nadasti finished and completed the
education of my son.
Pandora was only fourteen years of age when Charles de
Damville first became a sort of inmate of the house of her
uncle. She at that time lived with her father; but he
being afterwards killed in the battle which Nadasti fought
for the relief of Ziget, Pandora occupied an apartment in
the palatine palace. From the first hour he saw her, a
mere child as it were, accompanied by her governess, Charles
confessed to me that he had beheld her with eyes of distinction.
He had said to himself, This little girl will hereafter
be a jewel worthy of the crown of an emperor. He
had found something inexpressibly attractive in the starry
brightness of her complexion; her air he regarded as both
lighter and more graceful than any thing he had ever before
seen; and her speaking and humid eye seemed to him the
very emblem of sensibility and sweetness. If, at the girlish
and immature season of fourteen, he had ascribed to her all
these perfections, it will easily be supposed that, as she increased
in stature as the beauties of form unfolded themselves
in her, and she advanced in sentiment and a lovely
consciousness of her worth, the partiality of Charles became
more deep and unalterable. But the orphan niece of Nadasti
was altogether without a portion; and the great
palatine would have seen with more complacency the chevalier
de Damville addressing his pretensions to one of his
daughters.
Charles confessed to me that the passion he nourished
had been fruitful of pleasures and griefs, of hope and perplexity.
It was now almost a year since Pandora and
himself had confessed a mutual affection. The confession
had not been the result of design on either side: both had
wished to suppress it; Pandora from virgin dignity and
reserve; and Charles, because he saw not how their affection
could be crowned with success, and he dreaded, more than
any misery to himself, to be the author of degradation and
misery to her he loved. But what is ever uppermost in
the heart will at some time or other betray itself. Their
sympathetic and accordant feelings upon a point so deeply[451]
interesting to both, rendered them eagle-eyed to discern
the smallest indications. They had had a thousand opportunities,
and a thousand opportunities had been resisted.
They became more than usually silent and reserved towards
each other; they shunned to meet, and, when they met,
avoided each other’s eyes. One day a casual encounter in
a solitary retreat, which each had sought principally with
intention to escape the presence of the other, had taken
them off their guard. They were mutually hesitating and
perplexed; each discerned more unequivocal indications
than had ever occurred before of the state of the other’s
sentiments; the entire accord snapped as it were at once
the chains of reserve; and each, after a short interval of
hesitation, spoke with an eloquence, hitherto untried, the
language of love. The difference of years between them
gave a zest to the communication. Pandora seemed to be
throwing herself upon the protection of an elder brother,
of a guardian, one in whose prudence she confided as the
antidote of her inexperience; Charles felt his maturer years
as imposing on him more severely that sacred integrity, the
obligation of which, at least as society is at present constituted,
seems in the majority of cases to grow out of the
relative situation of the sexes, of the protectorship of the
one, and the dependence of the other.
“And now,” exclaimed Charles, “what am I to do?
what am I to desire? It would be affectation in me to
conceal from myself on an occasion like this, that the reputation
I have acquired both in the arts of peace and war
is such, as to have caused Nadasti to set his heart upon
my becoming his son-in-law. The great palatine, though
in many respects generous and liberal, has that inflexibleness
of opinion, which is perhaps more apt to grow up in
the hearts of scholars, than in other departments of society.
He is grave and solemn; all his habits are of a majestic
and lordly nature; and I have small reason to hope that I
shall find him accessible to my representations. He is little
subject to sallies of passion; his own propensities are wholly
under the control of his judgment; and it is not likely
that he will make allowance for the ardent affections of
other minds. Pandora is entirely dependent on him; in[452]
any case the portion she would receive from him would be
very inadequate to her worth; but, discarded and discountenanced
by him who has the absolute rule of Christian
Hungary, what can she expect? I am myself destitute of
fortune; my provision as a soldier will be very inadequate
to the wants of the first and softest of her sex. But even
of that provision Nadasti will deprive me, if I marry in
opposition to his pleasure. Shall I make Pandora the inhabitant
of tents and encampments; shall I expose her to
all the changes and hazards of a military life; shall I drag
her as the attendant of a soldier of fortune through every
climate of Europe? No, by heavens! I should regard
myself as the most selfish and the basest of mankind, if I
could deliberate on such a question. Never shall the charmer
of my soul owe a single privation to her Charles. I love
her with so pure and entire a passion, that I prefer her
prosperity to every earthly good. Nor is it merely necessary
to my attachment that she should live in plenty and ease;
I require that my Pandora should be seen in her native
lustre, that she should be surrounded with every appendage
due to her merit, that she should command applause from
the mercenary, and homage from the superficial. Her
praise is the only music I enjoy. I could not bear to hear
her name coupled with levity and scorn. I could not bear
that, where she appeared, every eye should not be turned
to her with reverence and honour. My passion, I confess
it, is that of a disciple of liberal arts and a nobleman, not
that of an Arcadian.”
The period of the campaign now drew to an end, and
Charles, having requested me to accompany him, set out
for his usual winter retreat in the city of Presburg. I saw
Pandora. Never in my life had I beheld any thing so
sweetly simple. I had always been an admirer of the sex;
but the perfections of Pandora were of a nature that I had
not observed in any other woman. Her symmetry was so
perfect, the pearly lustre of her skin so admirable, and her
form and carriage so light and ethereal, that at first view it
was difficult to persuade one’s self that she was framed of
the same gross materials as the rest of the species. She
seemed not constructed to endure the shocks of the world,
and the rude assaults of ill humour or neglect, of censure or[453]
adversity. Her voice was of the sweetest, the clearest and
softest tone I ever heard. There was a peculiar naïveté in
her accents, that riveted your soul in irresistible fetters.
Her conversation, for in the sequel I enjoyed much of her
conversation, had a very uncommon zest. She seemed to
have no art, and what she uttered appeared as if wholly unchecked
by consideration or reserve. You were persuaded
that she always delivered without restraint the first thing
that occurred to her mind; yet in what she said there was
so much good sense, so much true feeling, and, as the occasion
allowed, so much whim and imagination, that you could
not discover how any of her words could be changed but
for a worse. This circumstance strikingly contrasted with
the childish simplicity, or rather the feminine softness and
sylph-like delicacy, of her manner and her tone. The opposition
of appearance between her and my son made a
strong impression upon me. He was a perfect soldier, with
an ample chest, broad shoulders, and a figure, though graceful
and well proportioned, yet so strong, that it seemed
framed to contend with and to conquer the wrestlers in the
Grecian games. His complexion, shaded with luxuriant
curls of manly hair, was itself made brown with the rigours
of climate. Pandora was so heavenly fair, so sweetly delicate
and slender, that you would have thought she would be
withered and destroyed in his embrace, like the frailest ornament
of the garden before the northern breeze. But
courage to choose what is rugged and manlike is often characteristic
of the softest of her sex.
I speedily contracted an intimate commerce with the
beautiful Pandora. I was naturally desirous to be as consummate
a judge as possible of those perfections, which I
believed fated to determine the future happiness of my son.
When sufficiently satisfied in that respect, I still continued
the indulgence, and found a pure and exquisite pleasure in
the daily contemplation of accomplishments that were to
prove the materials of his gratification and delight, whose
gratification I preferred to my own. I had a still further
view in this commerce. I was anxious to be perfectly informed
of the connections and family of Pandora, that upon
them I might build a project I had deeply at heart, of bestowing[454]
on her, in the least questionable and exceptionable
manner, a dowry, that should place her upon an equality
with her cousins, the daughters of Nadasti, and deliver my
son from all apprehension of the unpleasing consequences
to result from the resentment of the great palatine. Nadasti
was opulent, and the portions of his daughters very
considerable; and, however inclined, I could not exceed
this limit without risking the entire miscarriage of my project.
Charles thought nothing too rich either in situation
or income to do honour to the mistress of his soul; but,
separately from this enthusiastic sentiment, both he and
Pandora had too just a taste, not to prefer the simple majesty
of ancient nobility, to the expensive ostentations of
modern refinement.
Having digested my plan I was obliged to travel as far
as Venice for the execution of it. The mother of Pandora
had been a Venetian, and the uncle of her mother was one
of the adventurers who had sailed with Pizarro for the conquest
of Peru. He had died before the completion of that
business, and had left behind him no relative so near to
him in blood as the lovely Pandora. By a singular piece
of good fortune, I encountered at Venice an individual who
had sailed in the same ship with the young lady’s uncle.
The uncle having died prematurely, the share he might
otherwise have obtained of the spoils of Peru was sunk in
the shares of the rest, and nothing was allowed to remain
that might have descended to his heirs. His friend and
countryman I found, though once rich with the booty he
made, had by a series of calamities, before he reached his
native home, been reduced to a state of poverty. The vicissitudes
he experienced, had produced in him the effect
of a very uncommon eagerness for acquisition. This man
I fixed on for my instrument; I opened to him my plan,
and offered him a very ample gratification, provided he
acted successfully the part I assigned him. In concert with
each other we digested and forged the various documents
that were best calculated to give credibility to the tale.
Having completed our arrangement, I set out for Presburg
without a moment’s delay, and directed my Venetian not to
follow till after a stipulated interval. He was not to enter[455]
into full possession of his reward till he had completed the
task he had undertaken. It was fixed that no person in
Hungary should be acquainted with my visit to Venice,
but only be allowed to understand generally, that I had been
engaged for a certain time in an excursion of amusement.
So hard is the fate of the possessor of the philosopher’s
stone, and so limited his power, as to have rendered all
these precautions on my part indispensably necessary. Had
not the various circumstances concurred, the detail of which
is here stated, the birth of Pandora’s mother in a maritime
state, the expedition of Pizarro to Peru, her uncle’s engaging
in this expedition and dying before it was completed,
and my own casual rencounter with his compagnon
du voyage, my project would too probably have been baffled.
A direct gift of the fortune I designed would never have
been admitted of; and, had not the coincidence been eminently
favourable, even though I should have succeeded in
misleading every other party, I could not hope to have
eluded the perspicacity and jealous honour of my son.
When I returned to Presburg, I again renewed my intercourse
with Pandora. The passion entertained by Damville
for the beautiful orphan was a secret to every person
at court; they had managed so discreetly as to have avoided
every hint of suspicion; and, as it was universally known
that the great palatine had an eye on this gallant soldier for
one of his daughters, few persons entertained a doubt that
my son would speedily declare his election among the co-heiresses
of Nadasti. On the other hand, in the friendly
intercourse between me and Pandora, neither she nor myself
felt that there was any thing to conceal, and it was
therefore a matter of complete notoriety. My blooming
youth of appearance was remarked; by the majority of
bystanders we were judged formed for each other; and,
before I was aware, the beautiful Hungarian was awarded
to me by the general voice as my destined bride. When
however I became acquainted with the rumour, I was contented
to smile at it; the consciousness in my own breast
how far the public sagacity had wandered in its guess, gave
to that guess, in my apprehension, a certain air of whimsical
and amusing.

[456]</div></body></text></TEI>