<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="139">CHAPTER VIII.
The Two Antagonist Doctrines of Geology.

Sect. 1.—Of the Doctrine of
Geological Catastrophes.
THAT great changes, of a kind
and intensity quite different from the common course of events, and
which may therefore properly be called catastrophes, have taken place
upon the earth’s surface, was an opinion which appeared to be forced
upon men by obvious facts. Rejecting, as a mere play of fancy, the
notions of the destruction of the earth by cataclysms or
conflagrations, of which we have already spoken, we find that the
first really scientific examination of the materials of the earth,
that of the Sub-Apennine hills, led men to draw this inference.
Leonardo da Vinci, whom we have already noticed for his early and
strenuous assertion of the real marine origin of fossil impressions of
shells, also maintained that the bottom of the sea had become the top
of the mountain; yet his mode of explaining this may perhaps be
claimed by the modern advocates of uniform causes as more allied to
their 587 opinion,
than to the doctrine of catastrophes.101 But Steno, in
1669, approached nearer to this doctrine; for he asserted that Tuscany
must have changed its face at intervals, so as to acquire six
different configurations, by the successive breaking down of the older
strata into inclined positions, and the horizontal deposit of new ones
upon them. Strabo, indeed, at an earlier period had recourse to
earthquakes, to explain the occurrence of shells in mountains; and
Hooke published the same opinion later. But the Italian geologists
prosecuted their researches under the advantage of having, close at
hand, large collections of conspicuous and consistent phenomena.
Lazzaro Moro, in 1740, attempted to apply the theory of earthquakes to
the Italian strata; but both he and his expositor, Cirillo Generelli,
inclined rather to reduce the violence of these operations within the
ordinary course of nature,102 and thus
leant to the doctrine of uniformity, of which we have afterwards to
speak. Moro was encouraged in this line of speculation by the
extraordinary occurrence, as it was deemed by most persons, of the
rise of a new volcanic island from a deep part of the Mediterranean,
near Santorino, in 1707.103 But in other
countries, as the geological facts were studied, the doctrine of
catastrophes appeared to gain ground. Thus in England, where, through
a large part of the country, the coal-measures are extremely inclined
and contorted, and covered over by more horizontal fragmentary beds,
the opinion that some violent catastrophe had occurred to dislocate
them, before the superincumbent strata were deposited, was strongly
held. It was conceived that a period of violent and destructive action
must have succeeded to one of repose; and that, for a time, some
unusual and paroxysmal forces must have been employed in elevating and
breaking the pre-existing strata, and wearing their fragments into
smooth pebbles, before nature subsided into a new age of tranquillity
and vitality. In like manner Cuvier, from the alternations of
fresh-water and salt-water species in the strata of Paris, collected
the opinion of a series of great revolutions, in which “the thread of
induction was broken.” Deluc and others, to whom we owe the first
steps in geological dynamics, attempted carefully to distinguish
between causes now in action, and those which have ceased to act; in
which latter class they reckoned the causes which have 588 elevated the existing
continents. This distinction was assented to by many succeeding
geologists. The forces which have raised into the clouds the vast
chains of the Pyrenees, the Alps, the Andes, must have been, it was
deemed, something very different from any agencies now operating.
101 “Here is a part of the earth
which has become more light, and which rises, while the opposite part
approaches nearer to the centre, and what was the bottom of the sea is
become the top of the mountain.”—Venturi’s Léonardo da
Vinci.
102 Lyell, i. 3. p. 64. (4th
ed.)
103 Ib. p. 60.
This opinion was further confirmed by the appearance of a complete
change in the forms of animal and vegetable life, in passing from one
formation to another. The species of which the remains occurred, were
entirely different, it was said, in two successive epochs: a new
creation appears to have intervened; and it was readily believed that
a transition, so entirely out of the common course of the world, might
be accompanied by paroxysms of mechanical energy. Such views prevail
extensively among geologists up to the present time: for instance, in
the comprehensive theoretical generalizations of Elie de Beaumont and
others, respecting mountain-chains, it is supposed that, at certain
vast intervals, systems of mountains, which may be recognized by the
parallelism of course of their inclined beds, have been disturbed and
elevated, lifting up with them the aqueous strata which had been
deposited among them in the intervening periods of tranquillity, and
which are recognized and identified by means of their organic remains:
and according to the adherents of this hypothesis, these sudden
elevations of mountain-chains have been followed, again and again, by
mighty waves, desolating whole regions of the earth.
The peculiar bearing of such opinions upon the progress of physical
geology will be better understood by attending to the doctrine of
uniformity, which is opposed to them, and with the consideration
of which we shall close our survey of this science, the last branch of
our present task.
Sect. 2.—Of the Doctrine of Geological
Uniformity.
The opinion that the history
of the earth had involved a serious of catastrophes, confirmed by the
two great classes of facts, the symptoms of mechanical violence on a
very large scale, and of complete changes in the living things by
which the earth had been tenanted, took strong hold of the geologists
of England, France, and Germany. Hutton, though he denied that there
was evidence of a beginning of the present state of things, and
referred many processes in the formation of strata to existing causes,
did not assert that the elevatory forces which raise continents from
the bottom of the ocean, were of the same order, 589 as well as of the
same kind, with the volcanoes and earthquakes which now shake the
surface. His doctrine of uniformity was founded rather on the supposed
analogy of other lines of speculation, than on the examination of the
amount of changes now going on. “The Author of nature,” it was said,
“has not permitted in His works any symptom of infancy or of old age,
or any sign by which we may estimate either their future or their past
duration:” and the example of the planetary system was referred to in
illustration of this.104 And a general persuasion that the
champions of this theory were not disposed to accept the usual
opinions on the subject of creation, was allowed, perhaps very
unjustly, to weigh strongly against them in the public opinion.
104 Lyell, i. 4, p. 94.
While the rest of Europe had a decided bias towards the doctrine of
geological catastrophes, the phenomena of Italy, which, as we have
seen, had already tended to soften the rigor of that doctrine, in the
progress of speculation from Steno to Generelli, were destined to
mitigate it still more, by converting to the belief of uniformity
transalpine geologists who had been bred up in the catastrophist
creed. This effect was, indeed, gradual. For a time the distinction of
the recent and the tertiary period was held to be marked
and strong. Brocchi asserted that a large portion of the Sub-Apennine
fossil shells belonged to a living species of the Mediterranean Sea:
but the geologists of the rest of Europe turned an incredulous ear to
this Italian tenet; and the persuasion of the distinction of the
tertiary and the recent period was deeply impressed on most geologists
by the memorable labors of Cuvier and Brongniart on the Paris basin.
Still, as other tertiary deposits were examined, it was found that
they could by no means be considered as contemporaneous, but that they
formed a chain of posts, advancing nearer and nearer to the recent
period. Above the strata of the basins of London and Paris,105 lie the newer strata of Touraine, of
Bourdeaux, of the valley of the Bormida and the Superga near Turin,
and of the basin of Vienna, explored by M. Constant Prevost. Newer and
higher still than these, are found the Sub-Apennine formations of
Northern Italy, and probably of the same period, the English “crag” of
Norfolk and Suffolk. And most of these marine formations are
associated with volcanic products and fresh-water deposits, so as to
imply apparently a long train of alternations of corresponding
processes. It may easily be supposed that, when the subject had
assumed this form, the boundary of the present and past condition of
the earth 590 was
in some measure obscured. But it was not long before a very able
attempt was made to obliterate it altogether. In 1828, Mr. Lyell set
out on a geological tour through France and Italy.106 He had already conceived the idea of
classing the tertiary groups by reference to the number of recent
species which were found in a fossil state. But as he passed from the
north to the south of Italy, he found, by communication with the best
fossil conchologists, Borelli at Turin, Guidotti at Parma, Costa at
Naples, that the number of extinct species decreased; so that the
last-mentioned naturalist, from an examination of the fossil shells of
Otranto and Calabria, and of the neighboring seas, was of opinion that
few of the tertiary shells were of extinct species. To complete the
series of proof, Mr. Lyell himself explored the strata of Ischia, and
found, 2000 feet above the level of the sea, shells, which were all
pronounced to be of species now inhabiting the Mediterranean; and soon
after, he made collections of a similar description on the flanks of
Etna, in the Val di Noto, and in other places.
105 Lyell, 1st ed. vol. iii. p.
61.
106 1st ed. vol. iii. Pref.
The impression produced by these researches is described by
himself.107 “In the course of my tour I had been
frequently led to reflect on the precept of Descartes, that a
philosopher should once in his life doubt everything he had been
taught; but I still retained so much faith in my early geological
creed as to feel the most lively surprize on visiting Sortino,
Pentalica, Syracuse, and other parts of the Val di Noto, at beholding
a limestone of enormous thickness, filled with recent shells, or
sometimes with mere casts of shells, resting on marl in which shells
of Mediterranean species were imbedded in a high state of
preservation. All idea of [necessarily] attaching a high antiquity to
a regularly-stratified limestone, in which the casts and impressions
of shells alone were visible, vanished at once from my mind. At the
same time, I was struck with the identity of the associated igneous
rocks of the Val di Noto with well-known varieties of ‘trap’ in
Scotland and other parts of Europe; varieties which I had also seen
entering largely into the structure of Etna.
107 Lyell, 1st ed. Pref. x.
“I occasionally amused myself,” Mr. Lyell adds, “with speculating
on the different rate of progress which geology might have made, had
it been first cultivated with success at Catania, where the phenomena
above alluded to, and the great elevation of the modern tertiary beds
in the Val di Noto, and the changes produced in the historical era by
the Calabrian earthquakes, would have been familiarly known.” 591
Before Mr. Lyell entered upon his journey, he had put into the
hands of the printer the first volume of his “Principles of Geology,
being an attempt to explain the former Changes of the Earth’s Surface
by reference to the Causes now in Operation.” And after viewing
such phenomena as we have spoken of, he, no doubt, judged that the
doctrine of catastrophes of a kind entirely different from the
existing course of events, would never have been generally received,
if geologists had at first formed their opinions upon the Sicilian
strata. The boundary separating the present from the anterior state of
things crumbled away; the difference of fossil and recent species had
disappeared, and, at the same time, the changes of position which
marine strata had undergone, although not inferior to those of earlier
geological periods, might be ascribed, it was thought, to the same
kind of earthquakes as those which still agitate that region. Both the
supposed proofs of catastrophic transition, the organical and the
mechanical changes, failed at the same time; the one by the removal of
the fact, the other by the exhibition of the cause. The powers of
earthquakes, even such as they now exist, were, it was supposed, if
allowed to operate for an illimitable time, adequate to produce all
the mechanical effects which the strata of all ages display. And it
was declared that all evidence of a beginning of the present state of
the earth, or of any material alteration in the energy of the forces
by which it has been modified at various epochs, was entirely
wanting.
Other circumstances in the progress of geology tended the same way.
Thus, in cases where there had appeared in one country a sudden and
violent transition from one stratum to the next, it was found, that by
tracing the formations into other countries, the chasm between them
was filled up by intermediate strata; so that the passage became as
gradual and gentle as any other step in the series. For example,
though the conglomerates, which in some parts of England overlie the
coal-measures, appear to have been produced by a complete
discontinuity in the series of changes; yet in the coal-fields of
Yorkshire, Durham, and Cumberland, the transition is smoothed down in
such a way that the two formations pass into each other. A similar
passage is observed in Central-Germany, and in Thuringia is so
complete, that the coal-measures have sometimes been considered as
subordinate to the todtliegendes.108
108 De la Beche, p. 414,
Manual.
Upon such evidence and such arguments, the doctrine of 592 catastrophes was
rejected with some contempt and ridicule; and it was maintained, that
the operation of the causes of geological change may properly and
philosophically be held to have been uniform through all ages and
periods. On this opinion, and the grounds on which it he been urged,
we shall make a few concluding remarks.
It must be granted at once, to the advocates of this geological
uniformity, that we are not arbitrarily to assume the existence of
catastrophes. The degree of uniformity and continuity with which
terremotive forces have acted, must be collected, not from any
gratuitous hypothesis, but from the facts of the case. We must suppose
the causes which have produced geological phenomena, to have been as
similar to existing causes, and as dissimilar, as the effects teach
us. We are to avoid all bias in favor of powers deviating in kind and
degree from those which act at present; a bias which, Mr. Lyell
asserts, has extensively prevailed among geologists.
But when Mr. Lyell goes further, and considers it a merit in a
course of geological speculation that it rejects any
difference between the intensity of existing and of past causes, we
conceive that he errs no less than those whom he censures. “An
earnest and patient endeavor to reconcile the former
indication of change,”109 with any restricted class of
causes,—a habit which he enjoins,—is not, we may suggest,
the temper in which science ought to be pursued. The effects must
themselves teach us the nature and intensity of the causes which have
operated; and we are in danger of error, if we seek for slow and shun
violent agencies further than the facts naturally direct us, no less
than if we were parsimonious of time and prodigal of violence.
Time, inexhaustible and ever accumulating his efficacy, can
undoubtedly do much for the theorist in geology; but Force,
whose limits we cannot measure, and whose nature we cannot fathom, is
also a power never to be slighted: and to call in the one to protect
us from the other, is equally presumptuous, to whichever of the two
our superstition leans. To invoke Time, with ten thousand earthquakes,
to overturn and set on edge a mountain-chain, should the phenomena
indicate the change to have been sudden and not successive, would be
ill excused by pleading the obligation of first appealing to known
causes.110
109 Lyell, B. iv. c. i. p. 328, 4th
ed.
110 [2nd Ed.] [I have, in the text,
quoted the fourth edition of Mr. Lyell’s Principles, in which
he recommends “an earnest and patient endeavor to reconcile the former
indications of change with the evidence of gradual mutation now in
progress.” In the sixth edition, in that which is, I presume, the
corresponding passage, although it is transferred from the fourth to
the first Book (B. i. c. xiii. p. 325) he recommends, instead, “an
earnest and patient inquiry how far geological appearances are
reconcileable with the effect of changes now in progress.” But while
Mr. Lyell has thus softened the advocate’s character in his language
in this passage, the transposition which I have noticed appears to me
to have an opposite tendency. For in the former edition, the causes
now in action were first described in the second and third Books, and
the great problem of Geology, stated in the first Book, was attempted
to be solved in the fourth. But by incorporating this fourth Book with
the first, and thus prefixing to the study of existing causes
arguments against the belief of their geological insufficiency, there
is an appearance as if the author wished his reader to be prepared by
a previous pleading against the doctrine of catastrophes, before he
went to the study of existing causes. The Doctrines of Catastrophes
and of Uniformity, and the other leading questions of the
Palætiological Sciences, are further discussed in the Philosophy of
the Inductive Sciences, Book x.]
593 In truth, we
know causes only by their effects; and in order to learn the nature of
the causes which modify the earth, we must study them through all ages
of their action, and not select arbitrarily the period in which we
live as the standard for all other epochs. The forces which have
produced the Alps and Andes are known to us by experience, no less
than the forces which have raised Etna to its present height; for we
learn their amount in both cases by their results. Why, then, do we
make a merit of using the latter case as a measure for the former? Or
how can we know the true scale of such force, except by comprehending
in our view all the facts which we can bring together?
In reality when we speak of the uniformity of nature, are
we not obliged to use the term in a very large sense, in order to make
the doctrine at all tenable? It includes catastrophes and convulsions
of a very extensive and intense kind; what is the limit to the
violence which we must allow to these changes? In order to enable
ourselves to represent geological causes as operating with uniform
energy through all time, we must measure our time by long cycles, in
which repose and violence alternate; how long may we extend this cycle
of change, the repetition of which we express by the word
uniformity?
And why must we suppose that all our experience, geological as well
as historical, includes more than one such cycle? Why must we
insist upon it, that man has been long enough an observer to obtain
the average of forces which are changing through immeasurable
time? 594
The analogy of other sciences has been referred to, as sanctioning
this attempt to refer the whole train of facts to known causes. To
have done this, it has been said, is the glory of Astronomy: she seeks
no hidden virtues, but explains all by the force of gravitation, which
we witness operating at every moment. But let us ask, whether it would
really have been a merit in the founders of Physical Astronomy, to
assume that the celestial revolutions resulted from any selected class
of known causes? When Newton first attempted to explain the motions of
the moon by the force of gravity, and failed because the measures to
which he referred were erroneous, would it have been philosophical in
him, to insist that the difference which he found ought to be
overlooked, since otherwise we should be compelled to go to causes
other than those which we usually witness in action? Or was there any
praise due to those who assumed the celestial forces to be the same
with gravity, rather than to those who assimilated them with any other
known force, as magnetism, till the calculation of the laws and amount
of these forces, from the celestial phenomena, had clearly sanctioned
such an identification? We are not to select a conclusion now well
proved, to persuade ourselves that it would have been wise to assume
it anterior to proof, and to attempt to philosophize in the method
thus recommended.
Again, the analogy of Astronomy has been referred to, as confirming
the assumption of perpetual uniformity. The analysis of the heavenly
motions, it has been said, supplies no trace of a beginning, no
promise of an end. But here, also, this analogy is erroneously
applied. Astronomy, as the science of cyclical motions, has nothing in
common with Geology. But look at Astronomy where she has an analogy
with Geology; consider our knowledge of the heavens as a
palætiological science;—as the study of a past condition, from
which the present is derived by causes acting in time. Is there then
no evidence of a beginning, or of a progress? What is the import of
the Nebular Hypothesis? A luminous matter is condensing, solid bodies
are forming, are arranging themselves into systems of cyclical motion;
in short, we have exactly what we are told, on this analogy, we ought
not to have;—the beginning of a world. I will not, to justify
this argument, maintain the truth of the nebular hypothesis; but if
geologists wish to borrow maxims of philosophizing from astronomy,
such speculations as have led to that hypothesis must be their
model.
Or, let them look at any of the other provinces of palætiological
speculation; at the history of states, of civilization, of languages.
We 595 may assume
some resemblance or connexion between the principles which
determined the progress of government, or of society, or of
literature, in the earliest ages, and those which now operate; but who
has speculated successfully, assuming an identity of such
causes? Where do we now find a language in the process of formation,
unfolding itself in inflexions, terminations, changes of vowels by
grammatical relations, such as characterize the oldest known
languages? Where do we see a nation, by its natural faculties,
inventing writing, or the arts of life, as we find them in the most
ancient civilized nations? We may assume hypothetically, that man’s
faculties develop themselves in these ways; but we see no such effects
produced by these faculties, in our own time, and now in progress,
without the influence of foreigners.
Is it not clear, in all these cases, that history does not exhibit
a series of cycles, the aggregate of which may be represented as a
uniform state, without indication of origin or termination? Does it
not rather seem evident that, in reality, the whole course of the
world, from the earliest to the present times, is but one cycle, yet
unfinished;—offering, indeed, no clear evidence of the mode of
its beginning; but still less entitling us to consider it as a
repetition or series of repetitions of what had gone before?
Thus we find, in the analogy of the sciences, no confirmation of
the doctrine of uniformity, as it has been maintained in Geology. Yet
we discern, in this analogy, no ground for resigning our hope, that
future researches, both in Geology and in other palætiological
sciences, may throw much additional light on the question of the
uniform or catastrophic progress of things, and on the earliest
history of the earth and of man. But when we see how wide and complex
is the range of speculation to which our analogy has referred us, we
may well be disposed to pause in our review of science;—to
survey from our present position the ground that we have passed
over;—and thus to collect, so far as we may, guidance and
encouragement to enable us to advance in the track which lies before
us.
Before we quit the subject now under consideration, we may,
however, observe, that what the analogy of science really teaches us,
as the most promising means of promoting this science, is the
strenuous cultivation of the two subordinate sciences, Geological
Knowledge of Facts, and Geological Dynamics. These are the two
provinces of knowledge—corresponding to Phenomenal Astronomy,
and Mathematical Mechanics—which may lead on to the epoch of the
Newton of 596
geology. We may, indeed, readily believe that we have much to do in
both these departments. While so large a portion of the globe is
geologically unexplored;—while all the general views which are
to extend our classifications satisfactorily from one hemisphere to
another, from one zone to another, are still unformed; while the
organic fossils of the tropics are almost unknown, and their general
relation to the existing state of things has not even been
conjectured;—how can we expect to speculate rightly and
securely, respecting the history of the whole of our globe? And if
Geological Classification and Description are thus imperfect, the
knowledge of Geological Causes is still more so. As we have seen, the
necessity and the method of constructing a science of such causes, are
only just beginning to be perceived. Here, then, is the point where
the labors of geologists may be usefully applied; and not in premature
attempts to decide the widest and abstrusest questions which the human
mind can propose to itself.
It has been stated,111 that when the Geological Society of
London was formed, their professed object was to multiply and record
observations, and patiently to await the result at some future time;
and their favorite maxim was, it is added, that the time was not yet
come for a General System of Geology. This was a wise and
philosophical temper, and a due appreciation of their position. And
even now, their task is not yet finished; their mission is not yet
accomplished. They have still much to do, in the way of collecting
Facts; and in entering upon the exact estimation of Causes, they have
only just thrown open the door of a vast Labyrinth, which it may
employ many generations to traverse, but which they must needs
explore, before they can penetrate to the Oracular Chamber of
Truth.
111 Lyell, B. i. c. iv. p.
103.
~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~

I rejoice, on many accounts,
to find myself arriving at the termination of the task which I have
attempted. One reason why I am glad to close my history is, that in it
I have been compelled, especially in the latter part of my labors, to
speak as a judge respecting eminent philosophers whom I reverence as
my Teachers in those very sciences on which I have had to pronounce a
judgment;—if, indeed, even the appellation of Pupil be not too
presumptuous. But I doubt not that such men are as full of candor and
tolerance, as they are of knowledge and thought. And if they deem, as
I did, that such a history of 597 science ought to be attempted, they will
know that it was not only the historian’s privilege, but his duty, to
estimate the import and amount of the advances which he had to
narrate; and if they judge, as I trust they will, that the attempt has
been made with full integrity of intention and no want of labor, they
will look upon the inevitable imperfections of the execution of my
work with indulgence and hope.
There is another source of satisfaction in arriving at this point
of my labors. If, after our long wandering through the region of
physical science, we were left with minds unsatisfied and unraised, to
ask, “Whether this be all?”—our employment might well be deemed
weary and idle. If it appeared that all the vast labor and intense
thought which has passed under our review had produced nothing but a
barren Knowledge of the external world, or a few Arts ministering
merely to our gratification; or if it seemed that the methods of
arriving at truth, so successfully applied in these cases, aid us not
when we come to the higher aims and prospects of our being;—this
History might well be estimated as no less melancholy and unprofitable
than those which narrate the wars of states and the wiles of
statesmen. But such, I trust, is not the impression which our survey
has tended to produce. At various points, the researches which we have
followed out, have offered to lead us from matter to mind, from the
external to the internal world; and it was not because the thread of
investigation snapped in our hands, but rather because we were
resolved to confine ourselves, for the present, to the material
sciences, that we did not proceed onwards to subjects of a closer
interest. It will appear, also, I trust, that the most perfect method
of obtaining speculative truth,—that of which I have had to
relate the result,—is by no means confined to the least worthy
subjects; but that the Methods of learning what is really true, though
they must assume different aspects in cases where a mere contemplation
of external objects is concerned, and where our own internal world of
thought, feeling, and will, supplies the matter of our speculations,
have yet a unity and harmony throughout all the possible employments
of our minds. To be able to trace such connexions as this, is the
proper sequel, and would be the high reward, of the labor which has
been bestowed on the present work. And if a persuasion of the reality
of such connexions, and a preparation for studying them, have been
conveyed to the reader’s mind while he has been accompanying me
through our long survey, his time may not have been employed on 598 these pages in vain.
However vague and hesitating and obscure may be such a persuasion, it
belongs, I doubt not, to the dawning of a better Philosophy, which it
may be my lot, perhaps, to develop more fully hereafter, if permitted
by that Superior Power to whom all sound philosophy directs our
thoughts.


ADDITIONS TO THE THIRD EDITION.

BOOK VIII.
ACOUSTICS.
</div></body></text></TEI>