<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="2">
[37]
CHAPTER II.

The Length of the Day.

We shall now consider another astronomical element,
the time of the revolution of the earth on its
axis; and we shall find here also that the structure of
organized bodies are suited to this element;—that
the cosmical and physiological arrangements are
adapted to each other.
We can very easily conceive the earth to revolve
on her axis faster or slower than she does, and thus
the days to be longer or shorter than they are, without
supposing any other change to take place. There
is no apparent reason why this globe should turn on
its axis just three hundred and sixty-six times while
it describes its orbit round the sun. The revolutions
of the other planets, so far as we know them, do not
appear to follow any rule by which they are connected
with the distance from the sun. Mercury,
Venus, and Mars have days nearly the length of
ours. Jupiter and Saturn revolve in about ten hours
each. For any thing we can discover, the earth
might have revolved in this or any other smaller
period; or we might have had, without mechanical
inconvenience, much longer days than we have.
But the terrestrial day, and consequently the length
of the cycle of light and darkness, being what it is,
we find various parts of the constitution both of animals
and vegetables, which have a periodical character
in their functions, corresponding to the diurnal
succession of external conditions; and we find that
the length of the period, as it exists in their constitution,
coincides with the length of the natural day.
The alternation of processes which takes place in
plants by day and by night is less obvious, and less[38]
obviously essential to their well-being, than the annual
series of changes. But there are abundance of
facts which serve to show that such an alternation is
part of the vegetable economy.
In the same manner in which Linnæus proposed a
Calendar of Flora, he also proposed a Dial of Flora,
or Flower-Clock; and this was to consist, as will
readily be supposed, of plants, which mark certain
hours of the day, by opening and shutting their flowers.
Thus the day-lily (hemerocallis fulva) opens at
five in the morning; the leontodon taraxacum, or
common dandelion, at five or six; the hieracium latifolium
(hawkweed), at seven; the hieracium pilosella,
at eight; the calendula arvensis, or marigold, at nine;
the mesembryanthemum neapolitanum, at ten or
eleven; and the closing of these and other flowers
in the latter part of the day offers a similar system
of hour marks.
Some of these plants are thus expanded in consequence
of the stimulating action of the light and
heat of the day, as appears by their changing their
time, when these influences are changed; but others
appear to be constant to the same hours, and independent
of the impulse of such external circumstances.
Other flowers by their opening and shutting
prognosticate the weather. Plants of the latter kind
are called by Linnæus meteoric flowers, as being regulated
by atmospheric causes: those which change
their hour of opening and shutting with the length of
the day, he terms tropical; and the hours which they
measure are, he observes, like Turkish hours, of varying
length at different seasons. But there are other
plants which he terms equinoctial; their vegetable
days, like the days of the equator, being always of
equal length; and these open, and generally close,
at a fixed and positive hour of the day. Such plants
clearly prove that the periodical character, and the
period of the motions above described, do not depend
altogether on external circumstances.
Some curious experiments on this subject were[39]
made by Decandolle. He kept certain plants in two
cellars, one warmed by a stove and dark, the other
lighted by lamps. On some of the plants the artificial
light appeared to have no influence, (convolvulus
arvensis, convolvulus cneorum, silene fruticosa) and
they still followed the clock hours in their opening
and closing. The night-blowing plants appeared
somewhat disturbed, both by perpetual light and perpetual
darkness. In either condition they accelerated
their going so much, that in three days they had
gained half a day, and thus exchanged night for day
as their time of opening. Other flowers went slower
in the artificial light (convolvulus purpureus.) In like
manner those plants which fold and unfold their
leaves were variously affected by this mode of treatment.
The oxalis stricta and oxalis incarnata kept
their habits, without regarding either artificial light
or heat. The mimosa leucocephala folded and unfolded
at the usual times, whether in light or in darkness,
but the folding up was not so complete as in
the open air. The mimosa pudica (sensitive plant,)
kept in darkness during the day time, and illuminated
during the night, had in three days accommodated
herself to the artificial state, opening in the
evening, and closing in the morning; restored to the
open air, she recovered her usual habits.
Tropical plants in general, as is remarked by our
gardeners, suffer from the length of our summer
daylight; and it has been found necessary to shade
them during a certain part of the day.
It is clear from these facts, that there is a diurnal
period belonging to the constitution of vegetables;
though the succession of functions depends in part
on external stimulants, as light and heat, their periodical
character is a result of the structure of the
plant; and this structure is such, that the length of
the period, under the common influences to which
plants are exposed, coincides with the astronomical
day. The power of accommodation which vegetables
possess in this respect, is far from being such as[40]
either to leave the existence of this periodical constitution
doubtful, or to entitle us to suppose that the
day might be considerably lengthened or shortened
without injury to the vegetable kingdom.
Here then we have an adaptation between the
structure of plants, and the periodical order of light
and darkness which arises from the earth’s rotation;
and the arbitrary quantity, the length of the cycle
of the physiological and of the astronomical fact, is
the same. Can this have occurred any otherwise
than by an intentional adjustment?
Any supposition that the astronomical cycle has
occasioned the physiological one, that the structure
of plants has been brought to be what it is by the
action of external causes, or that such plants as
could not accommodate themselves to the existing
day have perished, would be not only an arbitrary
and baseless assumption, but moreover useless for
the purposes of explanation which it professes, as we
have noticed of a similar supposition with respect to
the annual cycle. How came plants to have periodicity
at all in those functions which have a relation
to light and darkness? This part of their
constitution was suited to organized things which
were to flourish on the earth, and it is accordingly
bestowed on them; it was necessary for this end that
the period should be of a certain length; it is of that
length and no other. Surely this looks like intentional
provision.
Animals also have a period in their functions and
habits; as in the habits of waking, sleeping, eating,
&c. and their well-being appears to depend on the
coincidence of this period with the length of the
natural day. We see that in the day, as it now is,
all animals find seasons for taking food and repose,
which agree perfectly with their health and comfort.
Some animals feed during the day, as nearly all the
ruminating animals and land birds; others feed only
in the twilight, as bats and owls, and are called
crepuscular; while many beasts of prey, aquatic[41]
birds, and others, take their food during the night.
Those animals which are nocturnal feeders are diurnal
sleepers, while those which are crepuscular,
sleep partly in the night and partly in the day; but
in all, the complete period of these functions is
twenty-four hours. Man, in like manner, in all nations
and ages, takes his principal rest once in
twenty-four hours; and the regularity of this practice
seems most suitable to his health, though the
duration of the time allotted to repose is extremely
different in different cases. So far as we can judge,
this period is of a length beneficial to the human
frame, independently of the effect of external agents.
In the voyages recently made into high northern latitudes,
where the sun did not rise for three months,
the crews of the ships were made to adhere, with
the utmost punctuality, to the habit of retiring to
rest at nine, and rising a quarter before six; and
they enjoyed, under circumstances apparently the
most trying, a state of salubrity quite remarkable.
This shows, that according to the common constitution
of such men, the cycle of twenty-four hours is
very commodious, though not imposed on them by
external circumstances.
The hours of food and repose are capable of such
wide modifications in animals, and above all in man,
by the influence of external stimulants and internal
emotions, that it is not easy to distinguish what portion
of the tendency to such alternations depends on
original constitution. Yet no one can doubt that the
inclination to food and sleep is periodical, or can
maintain, with any plausibility, that the period may
be lengthened or shortened without limit. We may
be tolerably certain that a constantly recurring period
of forty-eight hours would be too long for one
day of employment and one period of sleep, with
our present faculties; and all, whose bodies and
minds are tolerably active, will probably agree that,
independently of habit, a perpetual alternation of
eight hours up and four in bed would employ the[42]
human powers less advantageously and agreeably
than an alternation of sixteen and eight. A creature
which could employ the full energies of his body
and mind uninterruptedly for nine months, and then
take a single sleep of three months, would not be a
man.
When, therefore, we have subtracted from the
daily cycle of the employments of men and animals,
that which is to be set down to the account of habits
acquired, and that which is occasioned by extraneous
causes, there still remains a periodical character;
and a period of a certain length, which coincides
with, or at any rate easily accommodates itself to,
the duration of the earth’s revolution. The physiological
analysis of this part of our constitution is not
necessary for our purpose. The succession of exertion
and repose in the muscular system, of excited
and dormant sensibility in the nervous, appear to be
fundamentally connected with the muscular and nervous
powers, whatever the nature of these may be.
The necessity of these alternations is one of the
measures of the intensity of those vital energies;
and it would seem that we cannot, without assuming
the human powers to be altered, suppose the intervals
of tranquillity which they require to be much
changed. This view agrees with the opinion of some
of the most eminent physiologists. Thus Cabanis[4]
notices the periodical and isochronous character of
the desire of sleep, as well as of other appetites.
He states also that sleep is more easy and more salutary,
in proportion as we go to rest and rise every
day at the same hours; and observes that this periodicity
seems to have a reference to the motions of
the solar system.
Now how should such a reference be at first
established in the constitution of man, animals, and
plants, and transmitted from one generation of them
to another? If we suppose a wise and benevolent[43]
Creator, by whom all the parts of nature were fitted
to their uses and to each other, this is what we might
expect and can understand. On any other supposition
such a fact appears altogether incredible and
inconceivable.
</div></body></text></TEI>