<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Temple of Nature</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1803</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="17">(p. 023) ADDITIONAL NOTE. VII.
OLD AGE AND DEATH.

  The age-worn fibres goaded to contract
  By repetition palsied, cease to act.
Canto II. l. 4
I. Effects of Age.
The immediate cause of the infirmities of age, or of the progress of
life to death, has not yet been well ascertained. The answer to the
question, why animals become feeble and diseased after a time, though
nourished with the same food which increased their growth from
infancy, and afterwards supported them for many years in unimpaired
health and strength, must be sought for from the laws of animal
excitability, which, though at first increased, is afterwards
diminished by frequent repetitions of its adapted stimulus, and at
length ceases to obey it.
1. There are four kinds of stimulus which induce the fibres to
contract, which constitute the muscles or the organs of sense; as,
first, The application of external bodies, which excites into action
the sensorial power of irritation; 2dly, Pleasure and pain, which
excite into action the sensorial power of sensation; 3dly, Desire and
aversion, which excite into action the power of volition; and lastly,
The fibrous contractions, which precede association, which is another
sensorial power; see Zoonomia, Vol. I. Sect. II. 13.
Many of the motions of the organic system, which are necessary to
life, are excited by more than one of these stimuli at the same time,
and some of them occasionally by them all. Thus respiration is
generally caused by the stimulus of blood in the lungs, or by the
sensation of the want of oxygen; but is also occasionally voluntary.
The actions of the heart also, though generally owing to the stimulus
of the blood, are also inflamed by the association of its motions with
those of the stomach, whence sometimes arises an inequality of the
pulse, and with other parts of the system, as with the capillaries,
whence heat of the skin in fevers with a feeble pulse, see Zoonomia.
(p. 024) They are also occasionally influenced by sensation, as is
seen in the paleness occasioned by fear, or the blush of shame and
anger; and lastly the motions of the heart are sometimes assisted by
volition; thus in those who are much weakened by fevers, the pulse is
liable to stop during their sleep, and to induce great distress; which
is owing at that time to the total suspension of voluntary power; the
same occurs during sleep in some asthmatic patients.
2. The debility of approaching age appears to be induced by the
inactivity of many parts of the system, or their disobedience to their
usual kinds and quantities of stimulus: thus the pallid appearance of
the skin of old age is owing to the inactivity of the heart, which
ceases to obey the irritation caused by the stimulus of the blood, or
its association with other moving organs with its former energy;
whence the capillary arteries are not sufficiently distended in their
diastole, and consequently contract by their elasticity, so as to
close the canal, and their sides gradually coalesce. Of these, those
which are most distant from the heart, and of the smallest diameters,
will soonest close, and become impervious; hence the hard pulse of
aged patients is occasioned by the coalescence of the sides of the
vasa vasorum, or capillary arteries of the coats of the other
arteries.
The veins of elderly people become turgid or distended with blood, and
stand prominent on the skin; for as these do not possess the
elasticity of the arteries, they become distended with accumulation of
blood; when the heart by its lessened excitability does not contract
sufficiently forcibly, or frequently, to receive, as fast as usual,
the returning blood; and their apparent prominence on the skin is
occasioned by the deficient secretion of fat or mucus in the cellular
membrane; and also to the contraction and coalescence and consequent
less bulk of many capillary arteries.
3. Not only the muscular fibres lose their degree of excitability from
age, as in the above examples; and as may be observed in the tremulous
hands and feeble step of elderly persons; but the organs of sense
become less excitable by the stimulus of external objects; whence the
sight and hearing become defective; the stimulus of the sensorial
power of sensation also less affects the aged, who grieve less for the
loss of friends or for other disappointments; it should nevertheless
be observed, that (p. 025) when the sensorial power of irritation is
much exhausted, or its production much diminished; the sensorial power
of sensation appears for a time to be increased; as in intoxication
there exists a kind of delirium and quick flow of ideas, and yet the
person becomes so weak as to totter as he walks; but this delirium is
owing to the defect of voluntary power to correct the streams of ideas
by intuitive analogy, as in dreams: see Zoonomia: and thus also those
who are enfeebled by habits of much vinous potation, or even by age
alone, are liable to weep at shaking hands with a friend, whom they
have not lately seen; which is owing to defect of voluntary power to
correct their trains of ideas caused by sensation, and not to the
increased quantity of sensation, as I formerly supposed.
The same want of voluntary power to keep the trains of sensitive ideas
consistent, and to compare them by intuitive analogy with the order of
nature, is the occasion of the starting at the clapping to of a door,
or the fall of a key, which occasions violent surprise with fear and
sometimes convulsions, in very feeble hysterical patients, and is not
owing I believe (as I formerly supposed) to increased sensation; as
they are less sensible to small stimuli than when in health.
Old people are less able also to perform the voluntary exertions of
exercise or of reasoning, and lastly the association of their ideas
becomes more imperfect, as they are forgetful of the names of persons
and places; the associations of which are less permanent, than those
of the other words of a language, which are more frequently repeated.
4. This disobedience of the fibres of age to their usual stimuli, has
generally been ascribed to repetition or habit, as those who live near
a large clock, or a mill, or a waterfall, soon cease to attend to the
perpetual noise of it in the day, and sleep dining the night
undisturbed. Thus all medicines, if repeated too frequently, gradually
lose their effect; as wine and opium cease to intoxicate: some
disagreeable tastes as tobacco, by frequent repetition cease to be
disagreeable; grief and pain gradually diminish and at length cease
altogether; and hence life itself becomes tolerable.
This diminished power of contraction of the fibres of the muscles or
organs of sense, which constitutes permanent debility or old age, may
arise from a deficient secretion of sensorial power in the brain, as
(p. 026) well as from the disobedience of the muscles and organs of
sense to their usual stimuli; but this less production of sensorial
power must depend on the inactivity of the glands, which compose the
brain, and are believed to separate it perpetually from the blood; and
is thence owing to a similar cause with the inaction of the fibres of
the other parts of the system.
It is finally easy to understand how the fibres may cease to act by
the usual quantity of stimulus after having been previously exposed to
a greater quantity of stimulus, or to one too long continued; because
the expenditure of sensorial power has then been greater than its
production; but it is not easy to explain why the repetition of
fibrous contractions, which during the meridian of life did not expend
the sensorial power faster than it was produced; or only in such a
degree as was daily restored by rest and sleep, should at length in
the advance of life expend too much of it; or otherwise, that less of
it should be produced in the brain; or reside in the nerves; lastly
that the fibres should become less excitable by the usual quantity of
it.
5. But these facts would seem to show, that all parts of the system
are not changed as we advance in life, as some have supposed; as in
that case it might have preserved for ever its excitability; and it
might then perhaps have been easier for nature to have continued her
animals and vegetables for ever in their mature state, than
perpetually by a complicate apparatus to have produced new ones, and
suffer the old ones to perish; for a further account of stimulus and
the consequent animal exertion, see Zoonomia, Vol. I. Sect. 12.
II. Means of preventing old age.
The means of preventing the approach of age must therefore consist in
preventing the inexcitability of the fibres, or the diminution of the
production of sensorial power.
1. As animal motion cannot be performed without the fluid matter of
heat, in which all things are immersed, and without a sufficient
quantity of moisture to prevent rigidity: nothing seems so well
adapted to both these purposes as the use of the warm bath; and
especially in (p. 027) those, who become thin or emaciated with age,
and who have a hard and dry skin, with hardness of the coat of the
arteries; which feels under the finger like a cord; the patient should
sit in warm water for half an hour every day, or alternate days, or
twice a week; the heat should be about ninety-eight degrees on
Fahrenheit's scale, or of such a warmth, as may be most agreeable to
his sensation; but on leaving the bath he should always be kept so
cool, whether he goes into bed, or continues up, as not sensibly to
perspire.
There is a popular prejudice, that the warm bath relaxes people, and
that the cold bath braces them; which are mechanical terms belonging
to drums and fiddle-strings, but not applicable except metaphorically
to animal bodies, and then commonly mean weakness and strength: during
the continuance in the bath the patient does not lose weight, unless
he goes in after a full meal, but generally weighs heavier as the
absorption is greater than the perspiration; but if he suffers himself
to sweat on his leaving the bath, he will undoubtedly be weakened by
the increased action of the system, and its exhaustion: the same
occurs to those who are heated by exercise, or by wine, or spice, but
not during their continuance in the warm bath: whence we may conclude,
that the warm bath is the most harmless of all those stimuli, which
are greater than our natural habits have accustomed us to; and that it
particularly counteracts the approach of old age in emaciated people
with dry skins.
It may be here observed in favour of bathing, that some fish are
believed to continue to a great age, and continually to enlarge in
size, as they advance in life; and that long after their state of
puberty. I have seen perch full of spawn, which were less than two
inches long; and it is known, that they will grow to six or eight
times that size; it is said, that the whales, which have been caught
of late years, are much less in size than those, which were caught,
when first the whale-fishery was established; as the large ones, which
were supposed to have been some hundred years old, are believed to be
already destroyed.
All cold-blooded amphibious animals more slowly waste their sensorial
power; as they are accustomed to less stimulus from their respiring
less oxygen; and their movements in water are slower than those of
aerial animals from the greater resistance of the element. There
besides (p. 028) seems to be no obstacle to the growth of aquatic
animals; as by means of the air-bladder, they can make their specific
gravity the same as that of the water in which they swim. And the
moisture of the element seems well adapted to counteract the rigidity
of their fibres; and as their exertions in locomotion, and the
pressure of some parts on others, are so much less than in the bodies
of land animals.
2. But as all excessive stimuli exhaust the sensorial power, and
render the system less excitable for a time till the quantity of
sensorial power is restored by sleep, or by the diminution or absence
of stimulus; which is seen by the weakness of inebriates for a day at
least after intoxication. And as the frequent repetition of this great
and unnatural stimulus of fermented liquors produces a permanent
debility, or disobedience of the system to the usual and natural kinds
and quantities of stimulus, as occurs in those who have long been
addicted to the ingurgitation of fermented liquors.
And as, secondly, the too great deficiency of the quantity of natural
stimuli, as of food, and warmth, or of fresh air, produces also
diseases; as is often seen in the children of the poor in large towns,
who become scrofulous from want of due nourishment, and from cold,
damp, unairy lodgings.
The great and principal means to prevent the approach of old age and
death, must consist in the due management of the quantity of every
kind of stimulus, but particularly of that from objects external to
the moving organ; which may excite into action too great or too small
a quantity of the sensorial power of irritation, which principally
actuates the vital organs. Whence the use of much wine, or opium, or
spice, or of much salt, by their unnatural stimulus induces consequent
debility, and shortens life, on the one hand, by the exhaustion of
sensorial power; so on the other hand, the want of heat, food, and
fresh air, induces debility from defect of stimulus, and a consequent
accumulation of sensorial power, and a general debility of the system.
Whence arise the pains of cold and hunger, and those which are called
nervous; and which are the cause of hysteric, epileptic, and perhaps
of asthmatic paroxysms, and of the cold fits of fever.
3. Though all excesses of increase and decrease of stimulus should be
avoided, yet a certain variation of stimulus seems to prolong the
(p. 029) excitability of the system; as during any diminution of the
usual quantity of stimulus, an accumulation of sensorial power is
produced; and in consequence the excitability, which was lessened by
the action of habitual stimulus, becomes restored. Thus those, who are
uniformly habituated to much artificial heat, as in warm parlours in
the winter months, lose their irritability in some degree, and become
feeble like hot-house plants; but by frequently going for a time into
the cold air, the sensorial power of irritability is accumulated and
they become stronger.
Whence it may be deduced, that the variations of the cold and heat of
this climate contribute to strengthen its inhabitants, who are more
active and vigorous, and live longer, than those of either much warmer
or much colder latitudes.
This accumulation of sensorial power from diminution of stimulus any
one may observe, who in severe weather may sit by the fire-side till
he is chill and uneasy with the sensation of cold; but if he walks
into the frosty air for a few minutes, an accumulation of sensorial
power is produced by diminution of the stimulus of heat, and on his
returning into the room where he was chill before, his whole skin will
now glow with warmth.
Hence it may be concluded, that the variations of the quantity of
stimuli within certain limits contribute to our health; and that those
houses which are kept too uniformly warm, are less wholesome than
where the inhabitants are occasionally exposed to cold air in passing
from one room to another.
Nevertheless to those weak habits with pale skins and large pupils of
the eyes, whose degree of irritability is less than health requires,
as in scrofulous, hysterical, and some consumptive constitutions, a
climate warmer than our own may be of service, as a greater stimulus
of heat may be wanted to excite their less irritability. And also a
more uniform quantity of heat may be serviceable to consumptive
patients than is met with in this country, as the lungs cannot be
clothed like the external skin, and are therefore subject to greater
extremes of heat and cold in passing in winter from a warm room into
the frosty air.
4. It should nevertheless be observed, that there is one kind of
(p. 030) stimulus, which though it be employed in quantity beyond its
usual state, seems to increase the production of sensorial power
beyond the expenditure of it (unless its excess is great indeed) and
thence to give permanent strength and energy to the system; I mean
that of volition. This appears not only from the temporary strength of
angry or insane people, but because insanity even cures some diseases
of debility, as I have seen in dropsy, and in some fevers; but it is
also observable, that many who have exerted much voluntary effort
during their whole lives, have continued active to great age. This
however may be conceived to arise from these great exertions being
performed principally by the organs of sense, that is by exciting and
comparing ideas; as in those who have invented sciences, or have
governed nations, and which did not therefore exhaust the sensorial
power of those organs which are necessary to life, but perhaps rather
prevented them from being sooner impaired, their sensorial power not
having been so frequently exhausted by great activity, for very
violent exercise of the body, long continued, forwards old age; as is
seen in post-horses that are cruelly treated, and in many of the poor,
who with difficulty support their families by incessant labour.

III. Theory of the Approach of Age.
The critical reader is perhaps by this time become so far interested
in this subject as to excuse a more prolix elucidation of it.
In early life the repetition of animal actions occasions them to be
performed with greater facility, whether those repetitions are
produced by volition, sensation, or irritation; because they soon
become associated together, if as much sensorial power is produced
between every reiteration of action, as is expended by it.
But if a stimulus be repeated at uniform intervals of time, the
action, whether of our muscles or organs of sense, is performed with
still greater facility and energy; because the sensorial power of
association mentioned above, is combined with the sensorial power of
irritation, and forms part of the diurnal chain of animal motions;
that (p. 031) is, in common language, the acquired habit assists the
power of the stimulus; see Zoonomia, Vol. I. Sect. XXII. 2. and Sect.
XII. 3. 3.
On this circumstance depends the easy motions of the fingers in
performing music, and of the feet and arms in dancing and fencing, and
of the hands in the use of tools in mechanic arts, as well as all the
vital motions which animate and nourish organic bodies.
On the contrary, many animal motions by perpetual repetition are
performed with less energy; as those who live near a waterfall, or a
smith's forge, after a time, cease to hear them. And in those
infectious diseases which are attended with fever, as the small-pox
and measles, violent motions of the system are excited, which at
length cease, and cannot again be produced by application of the same
stimulating material; as when those are inoculated for the small-pox,
who have before undergone that malady. Hence the repetition, which
occasions animal actions for a time to be performed with greater
energy, occasions them at length to become feeble, or to cease
entirely.
To explain this difficult problem we must more minutely consider the
catenations of animal motions, as described in Zoonomia, Vol. I. Sect.
XVII. The vital motions, as suppose of the heart and arterial system,
commence from the irritation occasioned by the stimulus of the blood,
and then have this irritation assisted by the power of association; at
the same time an agreeable sensation is produced by the due actions of
the fibres, as in the secretions of the glands, which constitutes the
pleasure of existence; this agreeable sensation is intermixed between
every link of this diurnal chain of actions, and contributes to
produce it by what is termed animal causation. But there is also a
degree of the power of volition excited in consequence of this vital
pleasure, which is also intermixed between the links of the chain of
fibrous actions; and thus also contributes to its uniform easy and
perpetual production.
The effects of surprise and novelty must now be considered by the
patient reader, as they affect the catenations of action; and, I hope,
the curiosity of the subject will excuse the prolixity of this account
of it. When any violent stimulus breaks the passing current or
catenation of our ideas, surprise is produced, which is accompanied
with (p. 032) pain or pleasure, and consequent volition to examine
the object of it, as explained in Zoonomia, Vol. I. Sect. XVIII. 17,
and which never affects us in sleep. In our waking hours whenever an
idea of imagination occurs, which is incongruous to our former
experience, we feel another kind of surprise, and instantly dissever
the train of imagination by the power of volition, and compare the
incongruous idea with our previous knowledge of nature, and reject it
by an act of reasoning, of which we are unconscious, termed in
Zoonomia, "Intuitive Analogy," Vol. I Sect. XVII. 7.
The novelty of any idea may be considered as affecting us with another
kind of surprise, or incongruity, as it differs from the usual train
of our ideas, and forms a new link in this perpetual chain; which, as
it thus differs from the ordinary course of nature, we instantly
examine by the voluntary efforts of intuitive analogy; or by
reasoning, which we attend to; and compare it with the usual
appearances of nature.
These ideas which affect us with surprise, or incongruity, or novelty,
are attended with painful or pleasurable sensation; which we mentioned
before as intermixing with all catenations of animal actions, and
contributing to strengthen their perpetual and energetic production;
and also exciting in some degree the power of volition, which also
intermixes with the links of the chain of animal actions, and
contributes to produce it.
Now by frequent repetition the surprise, incongruity, or novelty
ceases; and, in consequence, the pleasure or pain which accompanied
it, and also the degree of volition which was excited by that
sensation of pain or pleasure; and thus the sensorial power of
sensation and of volition are subducted from the catenation of vital
actions, and they are in consequence produced much weaker, and at
length cease entirely. Whence we learn why contagious matters induce
their effects on the circulation but once; and why, in process of
time, the vital movements are performed with less energy, and at
length cease; whence the debilities of age, and consequent death.
</div></body></text></TEI>