<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="102">CHAPTER IX.
Epoch of Davy and Faraday.

Sect. 1.—Promulgation of the
Electro-chemical Theory by Davy.
THE reader will recollect that
the History of Chemistry, though highly important and instructive in
itself, has been an interruption of the History of Electro-dynamic
Research:—a necessary interruption, however; for till we became
acquainted with Chemistry in general, we could not follow the course
of Electro-chemistry: we could not estimate its vast yet philosophical
theories, nor even express its simplest facts. We have now to endeavor
to show what has thus been done, and by what steps;—to give a
fitting view of the Epoch of Davy and Faraday.
This is, doubtless, a task of difficulty and delicacy. We cannot
execute it at all, except we suppose that the great truths, of which
the discovery marks this epoch, have already assumed their definite
and permanent form. For we do not learn the just value and right place
of imperfect attempts and partial advances in science, except by
seeing to what they lead. We judge properly of our trials and guesses
only when we have gained our point and guessed rightly. We might
personify philosophical theories, and might represent them to
ourselves as figures, all pressing eagerly onwards in the same 292 direction, whom we
have to pursue: and it is only in proportion as we ourselves overtake
those figures in the race, and pass beyond them, that we are enabled
to look back upon their faces; to discern their real aspects, and to
catch the true character of their countenances. Except, therefore, I
were of opinion that the great truths which Davy brought into sight
have been firmly established and clearly developed by Faraday, I could
not pretend to give the history of this striking portion of science.
But I trust, by the view I have to offer of these beautiful trains of
research and their result, to justify the assumption on which I thus
proceed.
I must, however, state, as a further appeal to the reader’s
indulgence, that, even if the great principles of electro-chemistry
have now been brought out in their due form and extent, the discovery
is but a very few years, I might rather say a few months, old, and
that this novelty adds materially to the difficulty of estimating
previous attempts from the point of view to which we are thus led. It
is only slowly and by degrees that the mind becomes sufficiently
imbued with those new truths, of which the office is, to change the
face of a science. We have to consider familiar appearances under a
new aspect; to refer old facts to new principles; and it is not till
after some time, that the struggle and hesitation which this
employment occasions, subsides into a tranquil equilibrium. In the
newly acquired provinces of man’s intellectual empire, the din and
confusion of conquest pass only gradually into quiet and security. We
have seen, in the history of all capital discoveries, how hardly they
have made their way, even among the most intelligent and candid
philosophers of the antecedent schools: we must, therefore, not expect
that the metamorphosis of the theoretical views of chemistry which is
now going on, will be effected without some trouble and delay.
I shall endeavor to diminish the difficulties of my undertaking, by
presenting the earlier investigations in the department of which I
have now to speak, as much as possible according to the most
deliberate view taken of them by the great discoverers themselves,
Davy and Faraday; since these philosophers are they who have taught us
the true import of such investigations.
There is a further difficulty in my task, to which I might
refer;—the difficulty of speaking, without error and without
offence, of men now alive, or who were lately members of social
circles which exist still around us. But the scientific history in
which such persons play a part, is so important to my purpose, that I
do not hesitate to incur 293 the responsibility which the narration
involves; and I have endeavored earnestly, and I hope not in vain, to
speak as if I were removed by centuries from the personages of my
story.
The phenomena observed in the Voltaic apparatus were naturally the
subject of many speculations as to their cause, and thus gave rise to
“Theories of the Pile.” Among these phenomena there was one class
which led to most important results: it was discovered by Nicholson
and Carlisle, in 1800, that water was decomposed by the pile
of Volta; that is, it was found that when the wires of the pile were
placed with their ends near each other in the fluid, a stream of
bubbles of air arose from each wire, and these airs were found on
examination to be oxygen and hydrogen: which, as we have had to
narrate, had already been found to be the constituents of water. This
was, as Davy says,53 the true origin of all that has been
done in electro-chemical science. It was found that other substances
also suffered a like decomposition under the same circumstances.
Certain metallic solutions were decomposed, and an alkali was
separated on the negative plates of the apparatus. Cruickshank, in
pursuing these experiments, added to them many important new results;
such as the decomposition of muriates of magnesia, soda, and ammonia
by the pile; and the general observation that the alkaline matter
always appeared at the negative, and the acid at the
positive, pole.
53 Phil. Trans. 1826, p.
386.
Such was the state of the subject when one who was destined to do
so much for its advance, first contributed his labors to it. Humphry
Davy was a young man who had been apprenticed to a surgeon at
Penzance, and having shown an ardent love and a strong aptitude for
chemical research, was, in 1798, made the superintendent of a
“Pneumatic Institution,” established at Bristol by Dr. Beddoes, for
the purpose of discovering medical powers of factitious airs.54 But his main attention was soon drawn
to galvanism; and when, in consequence of the reputation he had
acquired, he was, in 1801, appointed lecturer at the Royal Institution
in London (then recently established), he was soon put in possession
of a galvanic apparatus of great power; and with this he was not long
in obtaining the most striking results.
54 Paris, Life of Davy, i.
58.
His first paper on the subject55 is sent from
Bristol, in September, 1800; and describes experiments, in which he
had found that the decompositions observed by Nicholson and Carlisle
go on, although the 294 water, or other substance in which the
two wires are plunged, be separated into two portions, provided these
portions are connected by muscular or other fibres. This use of
muscular fibres was, probably, a remnant of the original disposition,
or accident, by which galvanism had been connected with physiology, as
much as with chemistry. Davy, however, soon went on towards the
conclusion, that the phenomena were altogether chemical in their
nature. He had already conjectured,56 in 1802, that
all decompositions might be polar; that is, that in all cases
of chemical decomposition, the elements might be related to each other
as electrically positive and negative; a thought which
it was the peculiar glory of his school to confirm and place in a
distinct light. At this period such a view was far from obvious; and
it was contended by many, on the contrary, that the elements which the
voltaic apparatus brought to view, were not liberated from
combinations, but generated. In 1806, Davy attempted the solution of
this question; he showed that the ingredients which had been supposed
to be produced by electricity, were due to impurities in the water, or
to the decomposition of the vessel; and thus removed all preliminary
difficulties. And then he says,57 “referring to
my experiments of 1800, 1801, and 1802, and to a number of new facts,
which showed that inflammable substances and oxygen, alkalies and
acids, and oxidable and noble metals, were in electrical relations of
positive and negative, I drew the conclusion, that the
combinations and decompositions by electricity were referrible to the
law of electrical attractions and repulsions,” and advanced the
hypothesis, “that chemical and electrical attractions were
produced by the same cause, acting in the one case on particles, in
the other on masses; . . . and that the same property, under different
modifications, was the cause of all the phenomena exhibited by
different voltaic combinations.”
55 Nicholson’s Journal, 4to.
iv. 275.
56 Phil. Trans. 1826.
57 Ib. 1826, p. 389.
Although this is the enunciation, in tolerably precise terms, of
the great discovery of his epoch, it was, at the period of which we
speak, conjectured rather than proved; and we shall find that neither
Davy nor his followers, for a considerable period, apprehended it with
that distinctness which makes a discovery complete. But in a very
short time afterwards, Davy drew great additional notice to his
researches by effecting, in pursuance, as it appeared, of his
theoretical views, the decomposition of potassa into a metallic base
and oxygen. This was, as he truly said, in the memorandum written in
his journal at the 295 instant, “a capital experiment.” This
discovery was soon followed by that of the decomposition of soda; and
shortly after, of other bodies of the same kind; and the interest and
activity of the whole chemical world were turned to the subject in an
intense degree.
At this period, there might be noticed three great branches of
speculation on this subject; the theory of the pile, the
theory of electrical decomposition, and the theory of the
identity of chemical and electrical forces; which last doctrine,
however, was found to include the other two, as might have been
anticipated from the time of its first suggestion.
It will not be necessary to say much on the theories of the voltaic
pile, as separate from other parts of the subject. The
contact-theory, which ascribed the action to the contact of
different metals, was maintained by Volta himself; but gradually
disappeared, as it was proved (by Wollaston58 especially,)
that the effect of the pile was inseparably connected with oxidation
or other chemical changes. The theories of electro-chemical
decomposition were numerous, and especially after the promulgation of
Davy’s Memoir in 1806; and, whatever might be the defects under
which these speculations for a long time labored, the subject was
powerfully urged on in the direction in which truth lay, by Davy’s
discoveries and views. That there remained something still to be done,
in order to give full evidence and consistency to the theory, appears
from this;—that some of the most important parts of Davy’s
results struck his followers as extraordinary paradoxes;—for
instance, the fact that the decomposed elements are transferred from
one part of the circuit to another, in a form which escapes the
cognizance of our senses, through intervening substances for which
they have a strong affinity. It was found afterwards that the
circumstance which appeared to make the process so wonderful, was, in
fact, the condition of its going on at all. Davy’s expressions often
seem to indicate the most exact notions: for instance, he says, “It is
very natural to suppose that the repellent and attractive energies are
communicated from one particle to another of the same kind, so as to
establish a conducting chain in the fluid; and that the
locomotion takes place in consequence;”59 and yet at
other times he speaks of the element as attracted and
repelled by the metallic surfaces which form the
poles;—a different, and, as it appeared afterwards, an
untenable view. Mr. Faraday, who supplied what was wanting, justly
notices this vagueness. 296 He says,60 that though, in
Davy’s celebrated Memoir of 1806, the points established are of the
utmost value, the mode of action by which the effects take place is
stated very generally; so generally, indeed, that probably a dozen
precise schemes of electro-chemical action might be drawn up,
differing essentially from each other, yet all agreeing with the
statement there given.” And at a period a little later, being
reproached by Davy’s brother with injustice in this expression, he
substantiated his assertion by an enumeration of twelve such schemes
which had been published.
58 Phil. Trans. 1801, p.
427.
59 Paris, i. 154.
60 Researches, 482.
But yet we cannot look upon this Memoir of 1806, otherwise than as
a great event, perhaps the most important event of the epoch now under
review. And as such it was recognized at once all over Europe. In
particular, it received the distinguished honor of being crowned by
the Institute of France, although that country and England were then
engaged in fierce hostility. Buonaparte had proposed a prize of sixty
thousand francs “to the person who by his experiments and discoveries
should advance the knowledge of electricity and galvanism, as much as
Franklin and Volta did;” and “of three thousand francs for the best
experiment which should be made in the course of each year on the
galvanic fluid;” the latter prize was, by the First Class of the
Institute, awarded to Davy.
From this period he rose rapidly to honors and distinctions, and
reached a height of scientific fame as great as has ever fallen to the
lot of a discoverer in so short a time. I shall not, however, dwell on
such circumstances, but confine myself to the progress of my
subject.
Sect. 2.—Establishment of the Electro-chemical
Theory by Faraday.
The defects of Davy’s
theoretical views will be seen most clearly by explaining what Faraday
added to them. Michael Faraday was in every way fitted and led to
become Davy’s successor in his great career of discovery. In 1812,
being then a bookseller’s apprentice, he attended the lectures of
Davy, which at that period excited the highest admiration.61 “My desire to escape from trade,” Mr.
Faraday says, “which I thought vicious and selfish, and to enter into
the service of science, which I imagined made its pursuers amiable and
liberal, induced me at last to take the bold and simple step of
writing to Sir H. Davy.” He was favorably received, and, in the next
year, became 297
Davy’s assistant at the Institution; and afterwards his successor. The
Institution which produced such researches as those of these two men,
may well be considered as a great school of exact and philosophical
chemistry. Mr. Faraday, from the beginning of his course of inquiry,
appears to have had the consciousness that he was engaged on a great
connected work. His Experimental Researches, which appeared in
a series of Memoirs in the Philosophical Transactions, are
divided into short paragraphs, numbered into a continued order from 1
up to 1160, at the time at which I write;62 and destined,
probably, to extend much further. These paragraphs are connected by a
very rigorous method of investigation and reasoning which runs through
the whole body of them. Yet this unity of purpose was not at first
obvious. His first two Memoirs were upon subjects which we have
already treated of (B. xiii. c. 5 and c. 8), Voltaic Induction, and the evolution of
Electricity from Magnetism. His “Third Series” has also been already referred to. Its object was, as a
preparatory step towards further investigation, to show the identity
of voltaic and animal electricity with that of the electrical machine;
and as machine electricity differs from other kinds in being
successively in a state of tension and explosion, instead of a
continued current, Mr. Faraday succeeded in identifying it with them,
by causing the electrical discharge to pass through a bad conductor
into a discharging-train of vast extent; nothing less, indeed, than
the whole fabric of the metallic gas-pipes and water-pipes of London.
In this Memoir63 it is easy to see already traces of the
general theoretical views at which he had arrived; but these are not
expressly stated till his “Fifth Series;” his intermediate Fourth
Series being occupied by another subsidiary labor on the conditions of
conduction. At length, however, in the Fifth Series, which was read to
the Royal Society in June, 1833, he approaches the theory of
electro-chemical decomposition. Most preceding theorists, and Davy
amongst the number, had referred this result to attractive
powers residing in the poles of the apparatus; and had
even pretended to compare the intensity of this attraction at
different distances from the poles. By a number of singularly
beautiful and skilful experiments, Mr. Faraday shows that the
phenomena can with no propriety be 298 ascribed to the attraction of the
poles.64 “As the substances evolved in cases of
electro-chemical decomposition may be made to appear against air,65 which, according to common language, is
not a conductor, nor is decomposed; or against water,66 which is a conductor, and can be
decomposed; as well as against the metal poles, which are excellent
conductors, but undecomposable; there appears but little reason to
consider this phenomenon generally as due to the attraction or
attractive powers of the latter, when used in the ordinary way, since
similar attractions can hardly be imagined in the former
instances.”
61 Paris, ii. 3.
62 December, 1835. (At present, when
I am revising the second edition, September, 1846, Dr. Faraday has
recently published the “Twenty-first Series” of his Researches
ending with paragraph 2453.)
63 Phil. Trans. 1833.
64 Researches, Art. 497
65 Researches, Arts. 465,
469.
66 495.
Faraday’s opinion, and, indeed, the only way of expressing the
results of his experiments, was, that the chemical elements, in
obedience to the direction of the voltaic currents established in the
decomposing substance, were evolved, or, as he prefers to say,
ejected at its extremities.67 He afterwards
states that the influence which is present in the electric current may
be described68 as an axis of power, having
[at each point] contrary forces exactly equal in amount in
contrary directions.
67 493.
68 517.
Having arrived at this point, Faraday rightly wished to reject the
term poles, and other words which could hardly be used without
suggesting doctrines now proved to be erroneous. He considered, in the
case of bodies electrically decomposed, or, as he termed them,
electrolytes, the elements as travelling in two opposite
directions; which, with reference to the direction of terrestrial
magnetism, might be considered as naturally east and west; and he
conceived elements as, in this way, arriving at the doors or outlets
at which they finally made their separate appearance. The doors he
called electrodes, and, separately, the anode and the
cathode;69 and the elements which thus travel he
termed the anïon and the catïon (or cathïon).70 By means of this nomenclature he was
able to express his general results with much more distinctness and
facility.
69 663.
70 The analogy of the Greek
derivation requires catïon; but to make the relation to
cathode obvious to the English reader, and to avoid a violation
of the habits of English pronunciation, I should prefer
cathïon.
But this general view of the electrolytical process required to be
pursued further, in order to explain the nature of the action. The
identity of electrical and chemical forces, which had been hazarded as
299 a conjecture by
Davy, and adopted as the basis of chemistry by Berzelius, could only
be established by exact measures and rigorous proofs. Faraday had, in
his proof of the identity of voltaic and electric agency, attempted
also to devise such a measure as should give him a comparison of their
quantity; and in this way he proved that71 a voltaic group
of two small wires of platinum and zinc, placed near each other, and
immersed in dilute acid for three seconds, yields as much electricity
as the electrical battery, charged by ten turns of a large machine;
and this was established both by its momentary electro-magnetic
effect, and by the amount of its chemical action.72
71 Researches, Art. 371.
72 537.
It was in his “Seventh Series,” that he finally established a
principle of definite measurement of the amount of electrolytical
action, and described an instrument which he termed73 a volta-electrometer. In this
instrument the amount of action was measured by the quantity of water
decomposed: and it was necessary, in order to give validity to the
mensuration, to show (as Faraday did show) that neither the size of
the electrodes, nor the intensity of the current, nor the strength of
the acid solution which acted on the plates of the pile, disturbed the
accuracy of this measure. He proved, by experiments upon a great
variety of substances, of the most different kinds, that the
electro-chemical action is definite in amount according to the
measurement of the new instrument.74 He had already,
at an earlier period,75 asserted, that the chemical power
of a current of electricity is in direct proportion to the absolute
quantity of electricity which passes; but the volta-electrometer
enabled him to fix with more precision the meaning of this general
proposition, as well as to place it beyond doubt.
73 739.
74 Arts. 758, 814.
75 377.
The vast importance of this step in chemistry soon came into view.
By the use of the volta-electrometer, Faraday obtained, for each
elementary substance, a number which represented the relative amount
of its decomposition, and which might properly76 be called its
“electro-chemical equivalent.” And the question naturally occurs,
whether these numbers bore any relation to any previously established
chemical measures. The answer is remarkable. They were no other
than the atomic weights of the Daltonian theory, which formed the
climax of the previous ascent of chemistry; and thus here, as
everywhere in 300
the progress of science, the generalizations of one generation are
absorbed in the wider generalizations of the next.
76 792.
But in order to reach securely this wider generalization, Faraday
combined the two branches of the subject which we have already
noticed;—the theory of electrical decomposition with the
theory of the pile. For his researches on the origin of
activity of the voltaic circuit (his Eighth Series), led him to see
more clearly than any one before him, what, as we have said, the most
sagacious of preceding philosophers had maintained, that the current
in the pile was due to the mutual chemical action of its elements. He
was led to consider the processes which go on in the
exciting-cell and in the decomposing place as of the same kind,
but opposite in direction. The chemical composition of the
fluid with the zinc, in the common apparatus, produces, when the
circuit is completed, a current of electric influence in the wire; and
this current, if it pass through an electrolyte, manifests itself by
decomposition, overcoming the chemical affinity which there
resists it. An electrolyte cannot conduct without being decomposed.
The forces at the point of composition and the point of decomposition
are of the same kind, and are opposed to each other by means of the
conducting-wire; the wire may properly be spoken of77 as conducting chemical affinity:
it allows two forces of the same kind to oppose one another;78 electricity is only another mode of the
exertion of chemical forces;79 and we might
express all the circumstances of the voltaic pile without using any
other term than chemical affinity, though that of electricity may be
very convenient.80 Bodies are held together by a definite
power, which, when it ceases to discharge that office, may be thrown
into the condition of an electric current.81
77 Researches Art. 918.
78 910.
79 915.
80 917.
81 855.
Thus the great principle of the identity of electrical and chemical
action was completely established. It was, as Faraday with great
candor says,82 a confirmation of the general views put
forth by Davy, in 1806, and might be expressed in his terms, that
“chemical and electrical attractions are produced by the same cause;”
but it is easy to see that neither was the full import of these
expressions understood nor were the quantities to which they refer
conceived as measurable quantities, nor was the assertion anything but
a sagacious conjecture, till Faraday gave the interpretation, measure,
and proof, of which we have spoken. The evidence of the incompleteness
of the views of his predecessor we have already adduced, in speaking of his vague and
301 inconsistent
theoretical account of decomposition. The confirmation of Davy’s
discoveries by Faraday is of the nature of Newton’s confirmation of
the views of Borelli and Hooke respecting gravity, or like Young’s
confirmation of the undulatory theory of Huyghens.
82 965.
We must not omit to repeat here the moral which we wish to draw
from all great discoveries, that they depend upon the combination of
exact facts with clear ideas. The former of these
conditions is easily illustrated in the case of Davy and Faraday, both
admirable and delicate experimenters. Davy’s rapidity and resource in
experimenting were extraordinary,83 and extreme
elegance and ingenuity distinguish almost every process of Faraday. He
had published, in 1829, a work on Chemical Manipulation, in
which directions are given for performing in the neatest manner all
chemical processes. Manipulation, as he there truly says, is to the
chemist like the external senses to the mind;84 and without the
supply of fit materials which such senses only can give, the mind can
acquire no real knowledge.
83 Paris, i. 145.
84 Pref. p. ii.
But still the operations of the mind as well as the information of
the senses, ideas as well as facts, are requisite for the attainment
of any knowledge; and all great steps in science require a peculiar
distinctness and vividness of thought in the discoverer. This it is
difficult to exemplify in any better way than by the discoveries
themselves. Both Davy and Faraday possessed this vividness of mind;
and it was a consequence of this endowment, that Davy’s lectures upon
chemistry, and Faraday’s upon almost any subject of physical
philosophy, were of the most brilliant and captivating character. In
discovering the nature of voltaic action, the essential intellectual
requisite was to have a distinct conception of that which Faraday
expressed by the remarkable phrase,85 “an axis of
power having equal and opposite forces;” and the distinctness of
this idea in Faraday’s mind shines forth in every part of his
writings. Thus he says, the force which determines the decomposition
of a body is in the body, not in the poles.86 But for the most part he can of course
only convey this fundamental idea by illustrations. Thus87 he represents the voltaic circuit by a
double circle, studded with the elements of the circuit, and shows how
the anïons travel round it in one direction, and the
cathïons in the opposite. He considers88 the powers at
the two places of action as balancing against each other through the
medium of the conductors, in a manner 302 analogous to that in which mechanical
forces are balanced against each other by the intervention of the
lever. It is impossible to him89 to resist the
idea, that the voltaic current must be preceded by a state of tension
in its interrupted condition, which is relieved when the circuit is
completed. He appears to possess the idea of this kind of force with
the same eminent distinctness with which Archimedes in the ancient,
and Stevinus in the modern history of science, possessed the idea of
pressure, and were thus able to found the science of mechanics.90 And when he cannot obtain these
distinct modes of conception, he is dissatisfied, and conscious of
defect. Thus in the relation between magnetism and electricity,91 “there appears to be a link in the
chain of effects, a wheel in the physical mechanism of the action, as
yet unrecognized.” All this variety of expression shows how deeply
seated is the thought. This conception of Chemical Affinity as a
peculiar influence of force, which, acting in opposite directions,
combines and resolves bodies;—which may be liberated and thrown
into the form of a voltaic current, and thus be transferred to remote
points, and applied in various ways; is essential to the
understanding, as it was to the making, of these discoveries.
85 Art. 517.
86 Art. 661.
87 963.
88 917.
89 Art. 950.
90 990.
91 1114.
By those to whom this conception has been conveyed, I venture to
trust that I shall be held to have given a faithful account of this
important event in the history of science. We may, before we quit the
subject, notice one or two of the remarkable subordinate features of
Faraday’s discoveries.
Sect. 3.—Consequences of Faraday’s
Discoveries.
Faraday’s volta-electrometer,
in conjunction with the method he had already employed, as we have
seen, for the comparison of voltaic and common electricity, enabled
him to measure the actual quantity of electricity which is exhibited,
in given cases, in the form of chemical affinity. His results appeared
in numbers of that enormous amount which so often comes before us in
the expression of natural laws. One grain of water92 will require for its decomposition as
much electricity as would make a powerful flash of lightning. By
further calculation, he finds this quantity to be not less than
800,000 charges of his Leyden battery;93 and this is, by
his theory of the identity of the combining with the decomposing
force, the quantity of electricity 303 which is naturally associated with the
elements of the grain of water, endowing them with their mutual
affinity.
92 853.
93 861.
Many of the subordinate facts and laws which were brought to light
by these researches, clearly point to generalizations, not included in
that which we have had to consider, and not yet discovered: such laws
do not properly belong to our main plan, which is to make our way
up to the generalizations. But there is one which so
evidently promises to have an important bearing on future chemical
theories, that I will briefly mention it. The class of bodies which
are capable of electrical decomposition is limited by a very
remarkable law: they are such binary compounds only as consist of
single proportionals of their elementary principles. It does
not belong to us here to speculate on the possible import of this
curious law; which, if not fully established, Faraday has rendered, at
least, highly probable:94 but it is impossible not to see how
closely it connects the Atomic with the Electro-chemical Theory; and
in the connexion of these two great members of Chemistry, is involved
the prospect of its reaching wider generalizations, and principles
more profound than we have yet caught sight of.
94 Art. 697.
As another example of this connexion, I will, finally, notice that
Faraday has employed his discoveries in order to decide, in some
doubtful cases, what is the true chemical equivalent;95 “I have such conviction,” he says,
“that the power which governs electro-decomposition and ordinary
chemical attractions is the same; and such confidence in the
overruling influence of those natural laws which render the former
definite, as to feel no hesitation in believing that the latter must
submit to them too. Such being the case, I can have no doubt that,
assuming hydrogen as 1, and dismissing small fractions for the
simplicity of expression, the equivalent number or atomic weight of
oxygen is 8, of chlorine 36, of bromine 78·4, of lead 103·5, of tin
59, &c.; notwithstanding that a very high authority doubles
several of these numbers.”
95 851.
Sect. 4.—Reception of the Electro-chemical
Theory.
The epoch of establishment of
the electro-chemical theory, like other great scientific epochs, must
have its sequel, the period of its reception and confirmation,
application and extension. In that period we 304 are living, and it must be the task of
future historians to trace its course.
We may, however, say a word on the reception which the theory met
with, in the forms which it assumed, anterior to the labors of
Faraday. Even before the great discovery of Davy, Grotthuss, in 1805,
had written upon the theory of electro-chemical decomposition; but he
and, as we have seen, Davy, and afterwards other writers, as Riffault
and Chompré, in 1807, referred the effects to the poles.96 But the most important attempt to
appropriate and employ the generalization which these discoveries
suggested, was that of Berzelius; who adopted at once the view of the
identity, or at least the universal connexion, of electrical relations
with chemical affinity. He considered,97 that in all
chemical combinations the elements may be considered as
electro-positive and electro-negative; and made this opposition the
basis of his chemical doctrines; in which he was followed by a large
body of the chemists of Germany. He held too that the heat and light,
evolved during cases of powerful combination, are the consequence of
the electric discharge which is at that moment taking place: a
conjecture which Faraday at first spoke of with praise.98 But at a later period he more sagely
says,99 that the flame which is produced in
such cases exhibits but a small portion of the electric power which
really acts. “These therefore may not, cannot, be taken as evidences
of the nature of the action; but are merely incidental results,
incomparably small in relation to the forces concerned, and supplying
no information of the way in which the particles are active on each
other, or in which their forces are finally arranged.” And comparing
the evidence which he himself had given of the principle on which
Berzelius’s speculations rested, with the speculations themselves,
Faraday justly conceived, that he had transferred the doctrine from
the domain of what he calls doubtful knowledge, to that of
inductive certainty.
96 Faraday (Researches, Art.
481, 492).
97 Ann. Chim. lxxxvi. 146, for
1813.
98 Researches, Art. 870
99 960.
Now that we are arrived at the starting-place, from which this
well-proved truth, the identity of electric and chemical forces, must
make its future advances, it would be trifling to dwell longer on the
details of the diffusion of that doubtful knowledge which preceded
this more certain science. Our history of chemistry is, therefore,
here at an end. I have, as far as I could, executed my task; which
was, to mark all the 305 great steps of its advance, from the
most unconnected facts and the most imperfect speculations, to the
highest generalization at which chemical philosophers have yet
arrived.
Yet it will appear to our purpose to say a few words on the
connexion of this science with those of which we are next to treat;
and that I now proceed to do.
</div></body></text></TEI>