<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="3">CHAPTER II.
The Greek School Philosophy.

Sect. 1.—The general Foundation of
the Greek School Philosophy.
THE physical philosophy of the
Greek Schools was formed by looking at the material world through the
medium of that common language which men employ to answer the common
occasions of life; and by adopting, arbitrarily, as the grounds of
comparison of facts, and of inference from them, notions more abstract
and large than those with which men are practically familiar, but not
less vague and obscure. Such a philosophy, however much it might be
systematized, by classifying and analyzing the conceptions which it
involves, could not overcome the vices of its fundamental principle.
But before speaking of these defects, we must give some indications of
its character.
The propensity to seek for principles in the common usages of
language may be discerned at a very early period. Thus we have an
example of it in a saying which is reported of Thales, the founder of
Greek philosophy.13 When he was asked, “What is the
greatest thing?” he replied, “Place; for all other
things are in the world, but the world is in it.” In
Aristotle we have the consummation of this mode of speculation. The
usual point from which he starts in his inquiries is, that we say thus
or thus in common language. Thus, when he has to discuss the question,
whether there be, in any part of the universe, a Void, or space in
which there is nothing, he inquires first in how many senses we say
that one thing is in another. He enumerates many of these;14 we say the part is in the whole, as the
finger is in the hand; again we say, the species is in the
genus, as man is included in animal; again, the government of
Greece is in the king; and various other senses are described
or exemplified, but of all these the most proper is when we
say a thing is in a vessel, and generally, in place.
He next examines what place is, and comes to this conclusion,
that “if about a body there be another body including it, it is in
place, and if not, not.” A body moves when it changes its
place; but 64 he
adds, that if water be in a vessel, the vessel being at rest, the
parts of the water may still move, for they are included by each
other; so that while the whole does not change its place, the parts
may change their places in a circular order. Proceeding then to the
question of a void, he, as usual, examines the different
senses in which the term is used, and adopts, as the most proper,
place without matter; with no useful result, as we shall soon see.
13 Plut. Conv. Sept. Sap. Diog.
Laert. i. 35.
14 Physic. Ausc. iv. 3.
Again,15 in a question concerning mechanical
action, he says, “When a man moves a stone by pushing it with a stick,
we say both that the man moves the stone, and that the stick
moves the stone, but the latter more properly.”
15 Physic. Ausc. viii. 5.
Again, we find the Greek philosophers applying themselves to
extract their dogmas from the most general and abstract notions which
they could detect; for example,—from the conception of the
Universe as One or as Many things. They tried to determine how far we
may, or must, combine with these conceptions that of a whole, of
parts, of number, of limits, of place, of beginning or end, of full or
void, of rest or motion, of cause and effect, and the like. The
analysis of such conceptions with such a view, occupies, for instance,
almost the whole of Aristotle’s Treatise on the Heavens.
The Dialogue of Plato, which is entitled Parmenides, appears
at first as if its object were to show the futility of this method of
philosophizing; for the philosopher whose name it bears, is
represented as arguing with an Athenian named Aristotle,16 and, by a process of metaphysical
analysis, reducing him at least to this conclusion, “that whether
One exist, or do not exist, it follows that both it and other
things, with reference to themselves and to each other, all and in all
respects, both are and are not, both appear and appear not.” Yet the
method of Plato, so far as concerns truths of that kind with which we
are here concerned, was little more efficacious than that of his
rival. It consists mainly, as may be seen in several of the dialogues,
and especially in the Timæus, in the application of notions as
loose as those of the Peripatetics; for example, the conceptions of
the Good, the Beautiful, the Perfect; and these are rendered still
more arbitrary, by assuming an acquaintance with the views of the
Creator of the universe. The philosopher is thus led to maxims which
agree with those 65
of the Aristotelians, that there can be no void, that things seek
their own place, and the like.17
16 This Aristotle is not the
Stagirite, who was forty-five years younger than Plato, but one of the
“thirty tyrants,” as they were called.
17 Timæus, p. 80.
Another mode of reasoning, very widely applied in these attempts,
was the doctrine of contrarieties, in which it was assumed, that
adjectives or substantives which are in common language, or in some
abstract mode of conception, opposed to each other, must point at some
fundamental antithesis in nature, which it is important to study. Thus
Aristotle18 says, that the Pythagoreans, from the
contrasts which number suggests, collected ten
principles,—Limited and Unlimited, Odd and Even, One and Many,
Right and Left, Male and Female, Rest and Motion, Straight and Curved,
Light and Darkness, Good and Evil, Square and Oblong. We shall see
hereafter, that Aristotle himself deduced the doctrine of Four
Elements, and other dogmas, by oppositions of the same kind.
18 Metaph. 1. 5.
The physical speculator of the present day will learn without
surprise, that such a mode of discussion as this, led to no truths of
real or permanent value. The whole mass of the Greek philosophy,
therefore, shrinks into an almost imperceptible compass, when viewed
with reference to the progress of physical knowledge. Still the
general character of this system, and its fortunes from the time of
its founders to the overthrow of their authority, are not without
their instruction, and, it may be hoped, not without their interest. I
proceed, therefore, to give some account of these doctrines in their
most fully developed and permanently received form, that in which they
were presented by Aristotle.
Sect. 2.—The Aristotelian Physical
Philosophy.
The principal physical treatises of
Aristotle are, the eight Books of “Physical Lectures,” the four Books
“Of the Heavens,” the two Books “Of Production and Destruction:” for
the Book “Of the World” is now universally acknowledged to be
spurious; and the “Meteorologies,” though full of physical
explanations of natural phenomena, does not exhibit the doctrines and
reasonings of the school in so general a form; the same may be said of
the “Mechanical Problems.” The treatises on the various subjects of
Natural History, “On Animals,” “On the Parts of Animals,” “On Plants,”
“On Physiognomonics,” “On Colors,” “On Sound,” contain an
extraordinary 66
accumulation of facts, and manifest a wonderful power of
systematizing; but are not works which expound principles, and
therefore do not require to be here considered.
The Physical Lectures are possibly the work concerning which a
well-known anecdote is related by Simplicius, a Greek commentator of
the sixth century, as well as by Plutarch. It is said, that Alexander
the Great wrote to his former tutor to this effect; “You have not done
well in publishing these lectures; for how shall we, your pupils,
excel other men, if you make that public to all, which we learnt from
you?” To this Aristotle is said to have replied: “My Lectures are
published and not published; they will be intelligible to those who
heard them, and to none besides.” This may very easily be a story
invented and circulated among those who found the work beyond their
comprehension; and it cannot be denied, that to make out the meaning
and reasoning of every part, would be a task very laborious and
difficult, if not impossible. But we may follow the import of a large
portion of the Physical Lectures with sufficient clearness to
apprehend the character and principles of the reasoning; and this is
what I shall endeavor to do.
The author’s introductory statement of his view of the nature of
philosophy falls in very closely with what has been said, that he
takes his facts and generalizations as they are implied in the
structure of language. “We must in all cases proceed,” he says, “from
what is known to what is unknown.” This will not be denied; but we can
hardly follow him in his inference. He adds, “We must proceed,
therefore, from universal to particular. And something of this,” he
pursues, “may be seen in language; for names signify things in a
general and indefinite manner, as circle, and by defining we
unfold them into particulars.” He illustrates this by saying, “thus
children at first call all men father, and all women
mother, but afterwards distinguish.”
In accordance with this view, he endeavors to settle
several of the great questions concerning the universe, which had been
started among subtle and speculative men, by unfolding the meaning of
the words and phrases which are applied to the most general notions of
things and relations. We have already noticed this method. A few
examples will illustrate it further:—Whether there was or was
not a void, or place without matter, had already been debated
among rival sects of philosophers. The antagonist arguments were
briefly these:—There must be a void, because a body cannot move
into a space except it is 67 empty, and therefore without a void there
could be no motion:—and, on the other hand, there is no void,
for the intervals between bodies are filled with air, and air is
something. These opinions had even been supported by reference to
experiment. On the one hand, Anaxagoras and his school had shown, that
air, when confined, resisted compression, by squeezing a blown
bladder, and pressing down an inverted vessel in the water; on the
other hand, it was alleged that a vessel full of fine ashes held as
much water as if the ashes were not there, which could only be
explained by supposing void spaces among the ashes. Aristotle decides
that there is no void, on such arguments as this:19—In a void
there could be no difference of up and down; for as in nothing there
are no differences, so there are none in a privation or negation; but
a void is merely a privation or negation of matter; therefore, in a
void, bodies could not move up and down, which it is in their nature
to do. It is easily seen that such a mode of reasoning, elevates the
familiar forms of language and the intellectual connections of terms,
to a supremacy over facts; making truth depend upon whether terms are
or are not privative, and whether we say that bodies fall
naturally. In such a philosophy every new result of observation
would be compelled to conform to the usual combinations of phrases, as
these had become associated by the modes of apprehension previously
familiar.
19 Physic. Ausc. iv. 7, p. 215.
It is not intended here to intimate that the common modes of
apprehension, which are the basis of common language, are limited and
casual. They imply, on the contrary, universal and necessary
conditions of our perceptions and conceptions; thus all things are
necessarily apprehended as existing in Time and Space, and as
connected by relations of Cause and Effect; and so far as the
Aristotelian philosophy reasons from these assumptions, it has a real
foundation, though even in this case the conclusions are often
insecure. We have an example of this reasoning in the eighth Book,20 where he proves that there never was a
time in which change and motion did not exist; “For if all things were
at rest, the first motion must have been produced by some change in
some of these things; that is, there must have been a change before
the first change;” and again, “How can before and after
apply when time is not? or how can time be when motion is not? If,” he
adds, “time is a numeration of motion, and if time be eternal, motion
must be eternal.” But he sometimes 68 introduces principles of a more arbitrary
character; and besides the general relations of thought, takes for
granted the inventions of previous speculators; such, for instance, as
the then commonly received opinions concerning the frame of the world.
From the assertion that motion is eternal, proved in the manner just
stated, Aristotle proceeds by a curious train of reasoning, to
identify this eternal motion with the diurnal motion of the heavens.
“There must,” he says, “be something which is the First Mover:”21 this follows from the relation of
causes and effects. Again, “Motion must go on constantly, and,
therefore, must be either continuous or successive. Now what is
continuous is more properly said to take place constantly, than
what is successive. Also the continuous is better; but we always
suppose that which is better to take place in nature, if it be
possible. The motion of the First Mover will, therefore, be
continuous, if such an eternal motion be possible.” We here see the
vague judgment of better and worse introduced, as that
of natural and unnatural was before, into physical
reasonings.
20 Ib. viii. 1, p. 258.
21 Physic. Ausc. viii. 6. p.
258.
I proceed with Aristotle’s argument.22 “We have now,
therefore, to show that there may be an infinite single, continuous
motion, and that this is circular.” This is, in fact, proved, as may
readily be conceived, from the consideration that a body may go on
perpetually revolving uniformly in a circle. And thus we have a
demonstration, on the principles of this philosophy, that there is and
must be a First Mover, revolving eternally with a uniform circular
motion.
22 Ib. viii. 8.
Though this kind of philosophy may appear too trifling to deserve
being dwelt upon, it is important for our purpose so far as to
exemplify it, that we may afterwards advance, confident that we have
done it no injustice.
I will now pass from the doctrines relating to the motions of the
heavens, to those which concern the material elements of the universe.
And here it may be remarked that the tendency (of which we are here
tracing the development) to extract speculative opinions from the
relations of words, must be very natural to man; for the very widely
accepted doctrine of the Four Elements which appears to be founded on
the opposition of the adjectives hot and cold,
wet and dry, is much older than Aristotle, and was
probably one of the earliest of philosophical dogmas. The great master
of this philosophy, however, puts the opinion in a more systematic
manner than his predecessors. 69
“We seek,” he says,23 “the principles of sensible things,
that is, of tangible bodies. We must take, therefore, not all the
contrarieties of quality, but those only which have reference to the
touch. Thus black and white, sweet and bitter, do not differ as
tangible qualities, and therefore must be rejected from our
consideration.
23 De Gen. et Corrupt. ii. 2.
“Now the contrarieties of quality which refer to the touch are
these: hot, cold; dry, wet; heavy, light; hard, soft; unctuous,
meagre; rough, smooth; dense, rare.” He then proceeds to reject all
but the four first of these, for various reasons; heavy and light,
because they are not active and passive qualities; the others, because
they are combinations of the four first, which therefore he infers to
be the four elementary qualities.
“24Now in four things there are six
combinations of two; but the combinations of two opposites, as hot and
cold, must be rejected; we have, therefore, four elementary
combinations, which agree with the four apparently elementary bodies.
Fire is hot and dry; air is hot and wet (for steam is air); water is
cold and wet, earth is cold and dry.”
24 Ib. iii. 8.
It may be remarked that this disposition to assume that some common
elementary quality must exist in the cases in which we habitually
apply a common adjective, as it began before the reign of the
Aristotelian philosophy, so also survived its influence. Not to
mention other cases, it would be difficult to free Bacon’s
Inquisitio in naturam calidi, “Examination of the nature of
heat,” from the charge of confounding together very different classes
of phenomena under the cover of the word hot.
The correction of these opinions concerning the elementary
composition of bodies belongs to an advanced period in the history of
physical knowledge, even after the revival of its progress. But there
are some of the Aristotelian doctrines which particularly deserve our
attention, from the prominent share they had in the very first
beginnings of that revival; I mean the doctrines concerning
motion.
These are still founded upon the same mode of reasoning from
adjectives; but in this case, the result follows, not only from the
opposition of the words, but also from the distinction of their being
absolutely or relatively true. “Former writers,” says
Aristotle, “have considered heavy and light relatively only,
taking cases, where both things have weight, but one is lighter than
the other; and they imagined that, in 70 this way, they defined what was
absolutely (ἁπλῶς) heavy and light.” We now know that things
which rise by their lightness do so only because they are pressed
upwards by heavier surrounding bodies; and this assumption of absolute
levity, which is evidently gratuitous, or rather merely nominal,
entirely vitiated the whole of the succeeding reasoning. The inference
was, that fire must be absolutely light, since it tends to take its
place above the other three elements; earth absolutely heavy, since it
tends to take its place below fire, air, and water. The philosopher
argued also, with great acuteness, that air, which tends to take its
place below fire and above water, must do so by its nature,
and not in virtue of any combination of heavy and light elements. “For
if air were composed of the parts which give fire its levity, joined
with other parts which produce gravity, we might assume a quantity of
air so large, that it should be lighter than a small quantity of fire,
having more of the light parts.” It thus follows that each of the four
elements tends to its own place, fire being the highest, air the next,
water the next, and earth the lowest.
The whole of this train of errors arises from fallacies which have
a verbal origin;—from considering light as opposite to heavy;
and from considering levity as a quality of a body, instead of
regarding it as the effect of surrounding bodies.
It is worth while to notice that a difficulty which often
embarrasses persons on their entrance upon physical
speculations,—the difficulty of conceiving that up and down are
different directions in different places,—had been completely
got over by Aristotle and the Greek philosophers. They were steadily
convinced of the roundness of the earth, and saw that this truth led
to the conclusion that all heavy bodies tend in converging directions
to the centre. And, they added, as the heavy tends to the centre, the
light tends to the exterior, “for Exterior is opposite to Centre as
heavy is to light.”25
25 De Cœlo, iv. 4.
The tendencies of bodies downwards and upwards, their weight, their
fall, their floating or sinking, were thus accounted for in a manner
which, however unsound, satisfied the greater part of the speculative
world till the time of Galileo and Stevinus, though Archimedes in the
mean time published the true theory of floating bodies, which is very
different from that above stated. Other parts of the doctrines of
motion were delivered by the Stagirite in the same spirit and with the
same success. The motion of a body which is thrown along the 71 ground diminishes and
finally ceases; the motion of a body which falls from a height goes on
becoming quicker and quicker; this was accounted for on the usual
principle of opposition, by saying that the former is a
violent, the latter a natural motion. And the later
writers of this school expressed the characters of such motions in
verse. The rule of natural motion was26


Principium tepeat, medium cum fine
calebit.
Cool at the first, it warm and warmer
glows.

And of violent motion, the law was—


Principium fervet, medium calet, ultima
friget.
Hot at the first, then barely warm, then
cold.

26 Alsted. Encyc. tom. i. p.
687.
It appears to have been considered by Aristotle a difficult problem
to explain why a stone thrown from the hand continues to move for some
time, and then stops. If the hand was the cause of the motion, how
could the stone move at all when left to itself? if not, why does it
ever stop? And he answers this difficulty by saying,27 “that there is a motion communicated to
the air, the successive parts of which urge the stone onwards; and
that each part of this medium continues to act for some while after it
has been acted on, and the motion ceases when it comes to a particle
which cannot act after it has ceased to be acted on.” It will be
readily seen that the whole of this difficulty, concerning a body
which moves forward and is retarded till it stops, arises from
ascribing the retardation, not to the real cause, the surrounding
resistances, but to the body itself.
27 Phys. Ausc. viii. 10.
One of the doctrines which was the subject of the warmest
discussion between the defenders and opposers of Aristotle, at the
revival of physical knowledge, was that in which he asserts,28 “That body is heavier than another
which in an equal bulk moves downward quicker.” The opinion maintained
by the Aristotelians at the time of Galileo was, that
bodies fall quicker exactly in proportion to their weight. The master
himself asserts this in express terms, and reasons upon it.29 Yet in another passage he appears to
distinguish between weight and actual motion downwards.30 “In physics, we call bodies heavy and
light from their power of motion; but these names are not
applied to their actual operations (ἐνέργειαις) except any one thinks
72 momentum
(ῥοπὴ) to be a word of both applications. But heavy and light are, as
it were, the embers or sparks of motion, and therefore
proper to be treated of here.”
28 De Cœlo, iv. 1, p. 308.
29 Ib. iii. 2.
30 Ib. iv. 1, p. 307.
The distinction just alluded to, between Power or Faculty of
Action, and actual Operation or Energy, is one very frequently
referred to by Aristotle; and though not by any means useless, may
easily be so used as to lead to mere verbal refinements instead of
substantial knowledge.
The Aristotelian distinction of Causes has not any very immediate
bearing upon the parts of physics of which we have here mainly spoken;
but it was so extensively accepted, and so long retained, that it may
be proper to notice it.31 “One kind of Cause is the matter of
which any thing is made, as bronze of a statue, and silver of a vial;
another is the form and pattern, as the Cause of an octave is the
ratio of two to one; again, there is the Cause which is the origin of
the production, as the father of the child; and again, there is the
End, or that for the sake of which any thing is done, as health is the
cause of walking.” These four kinds of Cause, the material, the
formal, the efficient, and the final, were long
leading points in all speculative inquiries; and our familiar forms of
speech still retain traces of the influence of this division.
31 Phys. ii. 3.
It is my object here to present to the reader in an intelligible
shape, the principles and mode of reasoning of the Aristotelian
philosophy, not its results. If this were not the case, it would be
easy to excite a smile by insulating some of the passages which are
most remote from modern notions. I will only mention, as specimens,
two such passages, both very remarkable.
In the beginning of the book “On the Heavens,” he proves32 the world to be perfect, by
reasoning of the following kind: “The bodies of which the world is
composed are solids, and therefore have three dimensions: now three is
the most perfect number; it is the first of numbers, for of one
we do not speak as a number; of two we say both; but
three is the first number of which we say all; moreover,
it has a beginning, a middle, and an end.”
32 De Cœlo, i. 1.
The reader will still perceive the verbal foundations of opinions
thus supported.
“The simple elements must have simple motions, and thus fire and
air have their natural motions upwards, and water and earth have 73 their natural motions
downwards; but besides these motions, there is motion in a circle,
which is unnatural to these elements, but which is a more perfect
motion than the other, because a circle is a perfect line, and a
straight line is not; and there must be something to which this motion
is natural. From this it is evident,” he adds, with obvious animation,
“that there is some essence of body different from those of the four
elements, more divine than those, and superior to them. If things
which move in a circle move contrary to nature, it is marvellous, or
rather absurd, that this, the unnatural motion, should alone be
continuous and eternal; for unnatural motions decay speedily. And so,
from all this, we must collect, that besides the four elements which
we have here and about us, there is another removed far off, and the
more excellent in proportion as it is more distant from us.” This
fifth element was the “quinta essentia,” of after writers, of
which we have a trace in our modern literature, in the word
quintessence.
Sect. 3.—Technical Forms of the Greek
Schools.
We have hitherto considered only the
principle of the Greek Physics; which was, as we have seen, to deduce
its doctrines by an analysis of the notions which common language
involves. But though the Grecian philosopher began by studying words
in their common meanings, he soon found himself led to fix upon some
special shades or applications of these meanings as the permanent and
standard notion, which they were to express; that is, he made his
language technical. The invention and establishment of
technical terms is an important step in any philosophy, true or false;
we must, therefore, say a few words on this process, as exemplified in
the ancient systems.
1. Technical Forms of the Aristotelian Philosophy.—We
have already had occasion to cite some of the distinctions introduced
by Aristotle, which may be considered as technical; for instance, the
classification of Causes as material, formal,
efficient, and final; and the opposition of Qualities as
absolute and relative. A few more of the most important
examples may suffice. An analysis of objects into Matter and
Form, when metaphorically extended from visible objects to
things conceived in the most general manner, became an habitual
hypothesis of the Aristotelian school. Indeed this metaphor is even
yet one of the most significant of those which we can employ, to
suggest one of the most comprehensive and fundamental antitheses with
which philosophy has to do;—the opposition of sense and reason,
of 74 impressions
and laws. In this application, the German philosophers have, up to the
present time, rested upon this distinction a great part of the weight
of their systems; as when Kant says, that Space and Time are the
Forms of Sensation. Even in our own language, we retain a trace
of the influence of this Aristotelian notion, in the word
Information, when used for that knowledge which may be
conceived as moulding the mind into a definite shape, instead of
leaving it a mere mass of unimpressed susceptibility.
Another favorite Aristotelian antithesis is that of Power
and Act (δύναμις, ἐνέργεια). This distinction is made the basis
of most of the physical philosophy of the school; being, however,
generally introduced with a peculiar limitation. Thus, Light is
defined to be “the Act of what is lucid, as being lucid. And if,” it
is added, “the lucid be so in power but not in act, we have darkness.”
The reason of the limitation, “as being lucid,” is, that a lucid body
may act in other ways; thus a torch may move as well as shine, but its
moving is not its act as being a lucid body.
Aristotle appears to be well satisfied with this explanation, for
he goes on to say, “Thus light is not Fire, nor any body whatever, or
the emanation of any body (for that would be a kind of body), but it
is the presence of something like Fire in the body; it is, however,
impossible that two bodies should exist in the same place, so that it
is not a body;” and this reasoning appears to leave him more satisfied
with his doctrine, that Light is an Energy or Act.
But we have a more distinctly technical form given to this notion.
Aristotle introduced a word formed by himself to express the act which
is thus opposed to inactive power: this is the celebrated word
ἐντελέχεια. Thus the noted definition of Motion in the third book of
the Physics,33 is that it is “the Entelechy, or
Act, of a movable body in respect of being movable;” and the
definition of the Soul is34 that it is “the Entelechy of a
natural body which has life by reason of its power.” This word has
been variously translated by the followers of Aristotle, and some of
them have declared it untranslatable. Act and Action are
held to be inadequate substitutes; the very act, ipse cursus
actionis, is employed by some; primus actus is employed by
many, but another school use primus actus of a non-operating
form. Budæus uses efficacia. Cicero35 translates it
“quasi quandam continuatam motionem, et perennem;” but this
paraphrase, though it may 75 fall in with the description of the soul,
which is the subject with which Cicero is concerned, does not appear
to agree with the general applications of the term. Hermolaus Barbarus
is said to have been so much oppressed with this difficulty of
translation, that he consulted the evil spirit by night, entreating to
be supplied with a more common and familiar substitute for this word:
the mocking fiend, however, suggested only a word equally obscure, and
the translator, discontented with this, invented for himself the word
perfectihabia.
33 Phys. iii. 1.
34 De Animâ, ii. 1.
35 Tusc. i. 10.
We need not here notice the endless apparatus of technicalities
which was, in later days, introduced into the Aristotelian philosophy;
but we may remark, that their long continuance and extensive use show
us how powerful technical phraseology is, for the perpetuation either
of truth or error. The Aristotelian terms, and the metaphysical views
which they tend to preserve, are not yet extinct among us. In a very
recent age of our literature it was thought a worthy employment by
some of the greatest writers of the day, to attempt to expel this
system of technicalities by ridicule.
“Crambe regretted extremely that substantial forms, a race
of harmless beings, which had lasted for many years, and afforded a
comfortable subsistence to many poor philosophers, should now be
hunted down like so many wolves, without a possibility of retreat. He
considered that it had gone much harder with them than with
essences, which had retired from the schools into the
apothecaries’ shops, where some of them had been advanced to the
degree of quintessences.”36
36 Martinus Scriblerus, cap.
vii.
We must now say a few words on the technical terms which others of
the Greek philosophical sects introduced.
2. Technical Forms of the Platonists.—The other sects
of the Greek philosophy, as well as the Aristotelians, invented and
adopted technical terms, and thus gave fixity to their tenets and
consistency to their traditionary systems; of these I will mention a
few.
A technical expression of a contemporary school has acquired
perhaps greater celebrity than any of the terms of Aristotle. I mean
the Ideas of Plato. The account which Aristotle gives of the
origin of these will serve to explain their nature.37 “Plato,” says he, “who, in his youth,
was in habits of communication first with Cratylus and the Heraclitean
opinions, which represent all the objects of sense as being in a
perpetual flux, so that concerning these no science nor certain 76 knowledge can exist,
entertained the same opinions at a later period also. When,
afterwards, Socrates treated of moral subjects, and gave no attention
to physics, but, in the subjects which he did discuss, arrived at
universal truths, and before any man, turned his thoughts to
definitions, Plato adopted similar doctrines on this subject also; and
construed them in this way, that these truths and definitions must be
applicable to something else, and not to sensible things: for it was
impossible, he conceived, that there should be a general common
definition of any sensible object, since such were always in a state
of change. The things, then, which were the subjects of universal
truths he called Ideas; and held that objects of sense had
their names according to Ideas and after them; so that things
participated in that Idea which had the same name as was applied to
them.”
37 Arist. Metaph. i. 6. The same
account is repeated, and the subject discussed, Metaph. xii. 4.
In agreement with this, we find the opinions suggested in the
Parmenides of Plato, the dialogue which is considered by many
to contain the most decided exposition of the doctrine of Ideas. In
this dialogue, Parmenides is made to say to Socrates, then a young
man,38 “O Socrates, philosophy has not yet
claimed you for her own, as, in my judgment, she will claim you, and
you will not dishonor her. As yet, like a young man as you are, you
look to the opinions of men. But tell me this: it appears to you, as
you say, that there are certain Kinds or Ideas (εἰδὴ) of
which things partake and receive applications according to that of
which they partake: thus those things which partake of Likeness
are called like; those things which partake of Greatness
are called great; those things which partake of Beauty
and Justice are called beautiful and just.” To
this Socrates assents. And in another part of the dialogue he shows
that these Ideas are not included in our common knowledge, from whence
he infers that they are objects of the Divine mind.
38 Parmenid. p. 131.
In the Phædo the same opinion is maintained, and is summed up in
this way, by a reporter of the last conversation of Socrates,39 εἶναι τι ἕκαστον τῶν εἰδῶν, καὶ τούτων
τ’ ἄλλα μεταλαμβάνοντα αὐτῶν τούτων τὴν ἐπωνυμίαν ἴσχειν; “that each
Kind has an existence, and that other things partake of these
Kinds, and are called according to the Kind of which they
partake.”
39 Phædo, p. 102.
The inference drawn from this view was, that in order to obtain
true and certain knowledge, men must elevate themselves, as much as
possible, to these Ideas of the qualities which they have to consider:
77 and as things
were thus called after the Ideas, the Ideas had a priority and
pre-eminence assigned them. The Idea of Good, Beautiful, and
Wise was the “First Good,” the “First Beautiful,” the “First Wise.”
This dignity and distinction were ultimately carried to a large
extent. Those Ideas were described as eternal and self-subsisting,
forming an “Intelligible World,” full of the models or archetypes of
created things. But it is not to our purpose here to consider the
Platonic Ideas in their theological bearings. In physics they were
applied in the same form as in morals. The primum calidum,
primum frigidum were those Ideas of fundamental Principles by
participation of which, all things were hot or cold.
This school did not much employ itself in the development of its
principles as applied to physical inquiries: but we are not without
examples of such speculations. Plutarch’s Treatise Περὶ τοῦ Πρώτου
Ψυχροῦ, “On the First Cold,” may be cited as one. It is in reality a
discussion of a question which has been agitated in modern times
also;—whether cold be a positive quality or a mere privation.
“Is there, O Favorinus,” he begins, “a First Power and Essence of the
Cold, as Fire is of the Hot; by a certain presence and participation
of which all other things are cold: or is rather coldness a privation
of heat, as darkness is of light, and rest of motion?” ~Additional
material in the 3rd edition.~
3. Technical Forms of the Pythagoreans.—The
Numbers of the Pythagoreans, when propounded as the explanation
of physical phenomena, as they were, are still more obscure than the
Ideas of the Platonists. There were, indeed, considerable resemblances
in the way in which these two kinds of notions were spoken of. Plato
called his Ideas unities, monads; and as, according to
him, Ideas, so, according to the Pythagoreans, Numbers, were the
causes of things being what they are.40 But there was
this difference, that things shared the nature of the Platonic Ideas
“by participation,” while they shared the nature of Pythagorean
Numbers “by imitation.” Moreover, the Pythagoreans followed their
notion out into much greater development than any other school,
investing particular numbers with extraordinary attributes, and
applying them by very strange and forced analogies. Thus the number
Four, to which they gave the name of Tetractys, was held to be
the most perfect number, and was conceived to correspond to the human
soul, in some way which appears to be very imperfectly understood by
the commentators of this philosophy.
40 Arist. Metaph. i. 6.
78 It has been
observed by a distinguished modern scholar,41 that the place
which Pythagoras ascribed to his numbers is intelligible only by
supposing that he confounded, first a numerical unit with a
geometrical point, and then this with a material atom. But this
criticism appears to place systems of physical philosophy under
requisitions too severe. If all the essential properties and
attributes of things were fully represented by the relations of
number, the philosophy which supplied such an explanation of the
universe, might well be excused from explaining also that existence of
objects which is distinct from the existence of all their qualities
and properties. The Pythagorean love of numerical speculations might
have been combined with the doctrine of atoms, and the combination
might have led to results well worth notice. But so far as we are
aware, no such combination was attempted in the ancient schools of
philosophy; and perhaps we of the present day are only just beginning
to perceive, through the disclosures of chemistry and crystallography,
the importance of such a line of inquiry.
41 Thirlwall’s Hist. Gr. ii.
142.
4. Technical Forms of the Atomists and Others.—The
atomic doctrine, of which we have just spoken, was one of the most
definite of the physical doctrines of the ancients, and was applied
with most perseverance and knowledge to the explanation of phenomena.
Though, therefore, it led to no success of any consequence in ancient
times, it served to transmit, through a long series of ages, a habit
of really physical inquiry; and, on this account, has been thought
worthy of an historical disquisition by Bacon.42
42 Parmenidis et Telesii et præcipue
Democriti Philosophia, &c., Works, vol. ix. 317.
The technical term, Atom, marks sufficiently the nature of
the opinion. According to this theory, the world consists of a
collection of simple particles, of one kind of matter, and of
indivisible smallness (as the name indicates), and by the various
configurations and motions of these particles, all kinds of matter and
all material phenomena are produced.
To this, the Atomic Doctrine of Leucippus and Democritus, was
opposed the Homoiomeria of Anaxagoras; that is, the opinion
that material things consist of particles which are homogeneous in
each kind of body, but various in different kinds: thus for example,
since by food the flesh and blood and bones of man increase, the
author of this doctrine held that there are in food particles of
flesh, and blood, 79
and bone. As the former tenet points to the corpuscular theories of
modern times, so the latter may be considered as a dim glimpse of the
idea of chemical analysis. The Stoics also, who were, especially at a
later period, inclined to materialist views, had their technical modes
of speaking on such subjects. They asserted that matter contained in
itself tendencies or dispositions to certain forms, which dispositions
they called λόγοι σπερματικοὶ, seminal proportions, or
seminal reasons.
Whatever of sound view, or right direction, there might be in the
notions which suggested these and other technical expressions, was, in
all the schools of philosophy (so far as physics was concerned)
quenched and overlaid by the predominance of trifling and barren
speculations; and by the love of subtilizing and commenting upon the
works of earlier writers, instead of attempting to interpret the book
of nature. Hence these technical terms served to give fixity and
permanence to the traditional dogmas of the sect, but led to no
progress of knowledge.
The advances which were made in physical science proceeded, not
from these schools of philosophy (if we except, perhaps, the
obligations of the science of Harmonics to the Pythagoreans), but from
reasoners who followed an independent path. The sequel of the
ambitious hopes, the vast schemes, the confident undertakings of the
philosophers of ancient Greece, was an entire failure in the physical
knowledge of which it is our business to trace the history. Yet we are
not, on that account, to think slightingly of these early speculators.
They were men of extraordinary acuteness, invention, and range of
thought; and, above all, they had the merit of first completely
unfolding the speculative faculty—of starting in that keen and
vigorous chase of knowledge out of which all the subsequent culture
and improvement of man’s intellectual stores have arisen. The sages of
early Greece form the heroic age of science. Like the first navigators
in their own mythology, they boldly ventured their untried bark in a
distant and arduous voyage, urged on by the hopes of a supernatural
success; and though they missed the imaginary golden prize which they
sought, they unlocked the gates of distant regions, and opened the
seas to the keels of the thousands of adventurers who, in succeeding
times, sailed to and fro, to the indefinite increase of the mental
treasures of mankind.
But inasmuch as their attempts, in one sense, and at first, failed,
we must proceed to offer some account of this failure, and of its
nature and causes. 80</div></body></text></TEI>