<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="111">CHAPTER VII.
Attempts to Establish the Fixity of other Physical
Properties.—Werner.
THE reflections from which it
appeared, (at the end of the last Book,) that
in order to obtain general knowledge respecting bodies, we must give
scientific fixity to our appreciation of their properties, applies to
their other properties as well as to their crystalline 337 form. And though none
of the other properties have yet been referred to standards so
definite as that which geometry supplies for crystals, a system has
been introduced which makes their measures far more constant and
precise than they are to a common undisciplined sense.
The author of this system was Abraham Gottlob Werner, who had been
educated in the institutions which the Elector of Saxony had
established at the mines of Freiberg. Of an exact and methodical
intellect, and of great acuteness of the senses, Werner was well
fitted for the task of giving fixity to the appreciation of outward
impressions; and this he attempted in his Dissertation on the
external Characters of Fossils, which was published at Leipzig in
1774. Of the precision of his estimation of such characters, we may
judge from the following story, told by his biographer Frisch.38 One of his companions had received a
quantity of pieces of amber, and was relating to Werner, then very
young, that he had found in the lot one piece from which he could
extract no signs of electricity. Werner requested to be allowed to put
his hand in the bag which contained these pieces, and immediately drew
out the unelectrical piece. It was yellow chalcedony, which is
distinguishable from amber by its weight and coldness.
38 Werner’s Leben, p.
26.
The principal external characters which were subjected by Werner to
a systematic examination were color, lustre, hardness, and specific
gravity. His subdivisions of the first character (Color), were
very numerous; yet it cannot be doubted that if we recollect them by
the eye, and not by their names, they are definite and valuable
characters, and especially the metallic colors. Breithaupt, merely by
the aid of this character, distinguished two new compounds among the
small grains found along with the grains of platinum, and usually
confounded with them. The kinds of Lustre, namely,
glassy, fatty, adamantine, metallic, are,
when used in the same manner, equally valuable. Specific
Gravity obviously admits of a numerical measure; and the
Hardness of a mineral was pretty exactly defined by the
substances which it would scratch, and by which it was capable of
being scratched.
Werner soon acquired a reputation as a mineralogist, which drew
persons from every part of Europe to Freiberg in order to hear his
lectures; and thus diffused very widely his mode of employing external
characters. It was, indeed, impossible to attend so closely to 338 these characters as
the Wernerian method required, without finding that they were more
distinctive than might at first sight be imagined; and the analogy
which this mode of studying Mineralogy established between that and
other branches of Natural History, recommended the method to those in
whom a general inclination to such studies was excited. Thus Professor
Jameson of Edinburgh, who had been one of the pupils of Werner at
Freiberg, not only published works in which he promulgated the
mineralogical doctrines of his master, but established in Edinburgh a
“Wernerian Society,” having for its object the general cultivation of
Natural History.
Werner’s standards and nomenclature of external characters were
somewhat modified by Mohs, who, with the same kinds of talents and
views, succeeded him at Freiberg. Mohs reduced hardness to numerical
measure by selecting ten known minerals, each harder than the other in
order, from talc to corundum and diamond, and by
making the place which these minerals occupy in the list, the
numerical measure of the hardness of those which are compared with
them. The result of the application of this fixed measurement and
nomenclature of external characters will appear in the History of
Classification, to which we now proceed.


SYSTEMATIC MINERALOGY.
</div></body></text></TEI>