<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="31">CHAPTER V.
Generalization of the Principles of
Mechanics.

Sect. 1.—Generalization of the Second
Law of Motion.—Central Forces.
THE Second Law of Motion being
proved for constant Forces which act in parallel lines, and the Third
Law for the Direct Action of bodies, it still required great
mathematical talent, and some inductive power, to see clearly the laws
which govern the motion of any number of bodies, acted upon by each
other, and by any forces, anyhow varying in magnitude and direction.
This was the task of the generalization of the laws of motion.
Galileo had convinced himself that the velocity of projection, and
that which gravity alone would produce, are “both maintained, without
being altered, perturbed, or impeded in their mixture.” It is to be
observed, however, that the truth of this result depends upon a
particular circumstance, namely, that gravity, at all points, acts in
lines, which, as to sense, are parallel. When we have to consider
cases in which this is not true, as when the force tends to the centre
of a circle, the law of composition cannot be applied in the same way;
and, in this case, mathematicians were met by some peculiar
difficulties.
One of these difficulties arises from the apparent inconsistency of
the statical and dynamical measures of force. When a body moves in a
circle, the force which urges the body to the centre is only a
tendency to motion; for the body does not, in fact, approach
to the centre; and this mere tendency to motion is combined with an
actual motion, which takes place in the circumference. We appear to
have to compare two things which are heterogeneous. Descartes had
noticed this difficulty, but without giving any satisfactory solution
of it.33 If we combine the actual motion to or
from the centre with the traverse motion about the centre, we obtain a
result which is false on mechanical principles. Galileo endeavored in
this way to find the curve described by a body which falls towards the
earth’s centre, and is, at the same time, carried 353 round by the motion
of the earth; and obtained an erroneous result. Kepler and Fermat
attempted the same problem, and obtained solutions different from that
of Galileo, but not more correct.
33 Princip. P. iii. 59.
Even Newton, at an early period of his speculations, had an
erroneous opinion respecting this curve, which he imagined to be a
kind of spiral. Hooke animadverted upon this opinion when it was laid
before the Royal Society of London in 1679, and stated, more truly,
that, supposing no resistance, it would be “an eccentric ellipsoid,”
that is, a figure resembling an ellipse. But though he had made out
the approximate form of the curve, in some unexplained way, we have no
reason to believe that he possessed any means of determining the
mathematical properties of the curve described in such a case. The
perpetual composition of a central force with the previous motion of
the body, could not be successfully treated without the consideration
of the Doctrine of Limits, or something equivalent to that doctrine.
The first example which we have of the right solution of such a
problem occurs, so far as I know, in the Theorems of Huyghens
concerning Circular Motion, which were published, without
demonstration, at the end of his Horologium Oscillatorium, in
1673. It was there asserted that when equal bodies describe circles,
if the times are equal, the centrifugal forces will be as the
diameters of the circles; if the velocities are equal, the forces will
be reciprocally as the diameters, and so on. In order to arrive at
these propositions, Huyghens must, virtually at least, have applied
the Second Law of Motion to the limiting elements of the curve,
according to the way in which Newton, a few years later, gave the
demonstration of the theorems of Huyghens in the Principia.
The growing persuasion that the motions of the heavenly bodies
about the sun might be explained by the action of central forces, gave
a peculiar interest to these mechanical speculations, at the period
now under review. Indeed, it is not easy to state separately, as our
present object requires us to do, the progress of Mechanics, and the
progress of Astronomy. Yet the distinction which we have to make is,
in its nature, sufficiently marked. It is, in fact, no less marked
than the distinction between speaking logically and speaking truly.
The framers of the science of motion were employed in establishing
those notions, names, and rules, in conformity to which all
mechanical truth must be expressed; but what was the
truth with regard to the mechanism of the universe remained to be
determined by other means. Physical Astronomy, at the period of which
we speak, eclipsed and overlaid 354 theoretical Mechanics, as, a little
previously, Dynamics had eclipsed and superseded Statics.
The laws of variable force and of curvilinear motion were not much
pursued, till the invention of Fluxions and of the Differential
Calculus again turned men’s minds to these subjects, as easy and
interesting exercises of the powers of these new methods. Newton’s
Principia, of which the first two Books are purely dynamical,
is the great exception to this assertion; inasmuch as it contains
correct solutions of a great variety of the most general problems of
the science; and indeed is, even yet, one of the most complete
treatises which we possess upon the subject.
We have seen that Kepler, in his attempts to explain the
curvilinear motions of the planets by means of a central force,
failed, in consequence of his belief that a continued transverse
action of the central body was requisite to keep up a continual
motion. Galileo had founded his theory of projectiles on the principle
that such an action was not necessary; yet Borelli, a pupil of
Galileo, when, in 1666, he published his theory of the Medicean Stars
(the satellites of Jupiter), did not keep quite clear of the same
errors which had vitiated Kepler’s reasonings. In the same way, though
Descartes is sometimes spoken of as the first promulgator of the First
Law of Motion, yet his theory of Vortices must have been mainly
suggested by a want of an entire confidence in that law. When he
represented the planets and satellites as owing their motions to
oceans of fluid diffused through the celestial spaces, and constantly
whirling round the central bodies, he must have felt afraid of
trusting the planets to the operation of the laws of motion in free
space. Sounder physical philosophers, however, began to perceive the
real nature of the question. As early as 1666, we read, in the
Journals of the Royal Society, that “there was read a paper of Mr.
Hooke’s explicating the inflexion of a direct motion into a curve by a
supervening attractive principle;” and before the publication of the
Principia in 1687, Huyghens, as we have seen, in Holland, and,
in our own country, Wren, Halley, and Hooke, had made some progress in
the true mechanics of circular motion,34 and had
distinctly contemplated the problem of the motion of a body in an
ellipse by a central force, though they could not solve it. Halley
went to Cambridge in 1684,35 for the express purpose of consulting
Newton upon the subject of the production of the elliptical motion of
the planets by means of a central 355 force, and, on the 10th of December,36 announced to the Royal Society that he
had seen Mr. Newton’s book, De Motu Corporum. The feeling that
mathematicians were on the brink of discoveries such as are contained
in this work was so strong, that Dr. Halley was requested to remind
Mr. Newton of his promise of entering them in the Register of the
Society, “for securing the invention to himself till such time as he
can be at leisure to publish it.” The manuscript, with the title
Philosophiæ Naturalis Principia Mathematica, was presented to
the society (to which it was dedicated) on the 28th of April, 1686.
Dr. Vincent, who presented it, spoke of the novelty and dignity of the
subject; and the president (Sir J. Hoskins) added, with great truth,
“that the method was so much the more to be prized as it was both
invented and perfected at the same time.”
34 Newt. Princip. Schol. to
Prop. iv.
35 Sir D. Brewster’s Life of
Newton, p. 154.
36 Id. p. 184.
The reader will recollect that we are here speaking of the
Principia as a Mechanical Treatise only; we shall afterwards
have to consider it as containing the greatest discoveries of Physical
Astronomy. As a work on Dynamics, its merit is, that it exhibits a
wonderful store of refined and beautiful mathematical artifices,
applied to solve all the most general problems which the subject
offered. The Principia can hardly be said to contain any new
inductive discovery respecting the principles of mechanics; for though
Newton’s Axioms or Laws of Motion which stand at the beginning
of the book, are a much clearer and more general statement of the
grounds of Mechanics than had yet appeared, they do not involve any
doctrines which had not been previously stated or taken for granted by
other mathematicians.
The work, however, besides its unrivalled mathematical skill,
employed in tracing out, deductively, the consequences of the laws of
motion, and its great cosmical discoveries, which we shall hereafter
treat of, had great philosophical value in the history of Dynamics, as
exhibiting a clear conception of the new character and functions of
that science. In his Preface, Newton says, “Rational Mechanics must be
the science of the Motions which result from any Forces, and of the
Forces which are required for any Motions, accurately propounded and
demonstrated. For many things induce me to suspect, that all natural
phenomena may depend upon some Forces by which the particles of bodies
are either drawn towards each other, and cohere, or repel and recede
from each other: and these Forces being hitherto unknown, philosophers
have pursued their researches in vain. And I hope 356 that the principles
expounded in this work will afford some light, either to this mode of
philosophizing, or to some mode which is more true.”
Before we pursue this subject further, we must trace the remainder
of the history of the Third Law.
Sect. 2.—Generalization of the Third Law of
Motion.—Centre of Oscillation.—Huyghens.
The Third Law of Motion, whether expressed
according to Newton’s formula (by the equality of Action and
Reaction), or in any other of the ways employed about the same time,
easily gave the solution of mechanical problems in all cases of
direct action; that is, when each body acted directly on
others. But there still remained the problems in which the action is
indirect;—when bodies, in motion, act on each other by
the intervention of levers, or in any other way. If a rigid rod,
passing through two weights, be made to swing about its upper point,
so as to form a pendulum, each weight will act and react on the other
by means of the rod, considered as a lever turning about the point of
suspension. What, in this case, will be the effect of this action and
reaction? In what time will the pendulum oscillate by the force of
gravity? Where is the point at which a single weight must be placed to
oscillate in the same time? in other words, where is the Centre of
Oscillation?
Such was the problem—an example only of the general problem
of indirect action—which mathematicians had to solve. That it
was by no means easy to see in what manner the law of the
communication of motion was to be extended from simpler cases to those
where rotatory motion was produced, is shown by this;—that
Newton, in attempting to solve the mechanical problem of the
Precession of the Equinoxes, fell into a serious error on this very
subject. He assumed that, when a part has to communicate rotatory
movement to the whole (as the protuberant portion of the terrestrial
spheroid, attracted by the sun and moon, communicates a small movement
to the whole mass of the earth), the quantity of the motion,
“motus,” will not be altered by being communicated. This principle is
true, if, by motion, we understand what is called moment of
inertia, a quantity in which both the velocity of each particle
and its distance from the axis of rotation are taken into account: but
Newton, in his calculations of its amount, considered the velocity
only; thus making motion, in this case, identical with the
momentum which he introduces in treating of the simpler case
357 of the third
law of motion, when the action is direct. This error was retained even
in the later editions of the Principia.37
37 B. iii. Lemma iii. to Prop,
xxxix.
The question of the centre of oscillation had been proposed by
Mersenne somewhat earlier,38 in 1646. And though the problem was out
of the reach of any principles at that time known and understood, some
of the mathematicians of the day had rightly solved some cases of it,
by proceeding as if the question had been to find the Centre of
Percussion. The Centre of Percussion is the point about which the
momenta of all the parts of a body balance each other, when it is in
motion about any axis, and is stopped by striking against an obstacle
placed at that centre. Roberval found this point in some easy cases;
Descartes also attempted the problem; their rival labors led to an
angry controversy: and Descartes was, as in his physical speculations
he often was, very presumptuous, though not more than half right.
38 Mont. ii. 423.
Huyghens was hardly advanced beyond boyhood when Mersenne first
proposed this problem; and, as he says,39 could see no
principle which even offered an opening to the solution, and had thus
been repelled at the threshold. When, however, he published his
Horologium Oscillatorium in 1673, the fourth part of that work
was on the Centre of Oscillation or Agitation; and the principle which
he then assumed, though not so simple and self-evident as those to
which such problems were afterwards referred, was perfectly correct
and general, and led to exact solutions in all cases. The reader has
already seen repeatedly in the course of this history, complex and
derivative principles presenting themselves to men’s minds, before
simple and elementary ones. The “hypothesis” assumed by Huyghens was
this; “that if any weights are put in motion by the force of gravity,
they cannot move so that the centre of gravity of them all
shall rise higher than the place from which it descended.”
This being assumed, it is easy to show that the centre of gravity
will, under all circumstances, rise as high as its original
position; and this consideration leads to a determination of the
oscillation of a compound pendulum. We may observe, in the principle
thus selected, a conviction that, in all mechanical action, the centre
of gravity may be taken as the representative of the whole system.
This conviction, as we have seen, may be traced in the axioms of
Archimedes and Stevinus; and Huyghens, when he proceeds upon it,
undertakes to show,40 that he assumes only this, that a heavy
body cannot, of itself, move upwards.
39 Hor. Osc. Pref.
40 Hor. Osc. p. 121.
358 Clear as
Huyghen’s principle appeared to himself, it was, after some time,
attacked by the Abbé Catelan, a zealous Cartesian. Catelan also put
forth principles which he conceived were evident, and deduced from
them conclusions contradictory to those of Huyghens. His principles,
now that we know them to be false, appear to us very gratuitous. They
are these; “that in a compound pendulum, the sum of the velocities of
the component weights is equal to the sum of the velocities which they
would have acquired if they had been detached pendulums;” and “that
the time of the vibration of a compound pendulum is an arithmetic mean
between the times of the vibrations of the weights, moving as detached
pendulums.” Huyghens easily showed that these suppositions would make
the centre of gravity ascend to a greater height than that from which
it fell; and after some time, James Bernoulli stept into the arena,
and ranged himself on the side of Huyghens. As the discussion thus
proceeded, it began to be seen that the question really was, in what
manner the Third Law of Motion was to be extended to cases of indirect
action; whether by distributing the action and reaction according to
statical principles, or in some other way. “I propose it to the
consideration of mathematicians,” says Bernoulli in 1686, “what law of
the communication of velocity is observed by bodies in motion, which
are sustained at one extremity by a fixed fulcrum, and at the other by
a body also moving, but more slowly. Is the excess of velocity which
must be communicated from the one body to the other to be distributed
in the same proportion in which a load supported on the lever would be
distributed?” He adds, that if this question be answered in the
affirmative, Huyghens will be found to be in error; but this is a
mistake. The principle, that the action and reaction of bodies thus
moving are to be distributed according to the rules of the lever, is
true; but Bernoulli mistook, in estimating this action and reaction by
the velocity acquired at any moment; instead of taking, as he
should have done, the increment of velocity which gravity
tended to impress in the next instant. This was shown by the Marquis
de l’Hôpital; who adds, with justice, “I conceive that I have thus
fully answered the call of Bernoulli, when he says, I propose it to
the consideration of mathematicians, &c.”
We may, from this time, consider as known, but not as fully
established, the principle that “When bodies in motion affect each
other, the action and reaction are distributed according to the laws
of Statics;” although there were still found occasional difficulties
in the 359
generalization and application of the role. James Bernoulli, in 1703,
gave “a General Demonstration of the Centre of Oscillation, drawn from
the nature of the Lever.” In this demonstration41 he takes as a
fundamental principle, that bodies in motion, connected by levers,
balance, when the products of their momenta and the lengths of the
levers are equal in opposite directions. For the proof of this
proposition, he refers to Marriotte, who had asserted it of weights
acting by percussion,42 and in order to prove it, had balanced
the effect of a weight on a lever by the effect of a jet of water, and
had confirmed it by other experiments.43 Moreover, says
Bernoulli, there is no one who denies it. Still, this kind of proof
was hardly satisfactory or elementary enough. John Bernoulli took up
the subject after the death of his brother James, which happened in
1705. The former published in 1714 his Meditatio de Naturâ Centri
Oscillationis. In this memoir, he assumes, as his brother had
done, that the effects of forces on a lever in motion are distributed
according to the common rules of the lever.44 The principal
generalization which he introduced was, that he considered gravity as
a force soliciting to motion, which might have different intensities
in different bodies. At the same time, Brook Taylor in England solved
the problem, upon the same principles as Bernoulli; and the question
of priority on this subject was one point in the angry intercourse
which, about this time, became common between the English
mathematicians and those of the Continent. Hermann also, in his
Phoronomia, published in 1716, gave a proof which, as he
informs us, he had devised before he saw John Bernoulli’s. This proof
is founded on the statical equivalence of the “solicitations of
gravity” and the “vicarious solicitations” which correspond
to the actual motion of each part; or, as it has been expressed by
more modern writers, the equilibrium of the impressed and
effective forces.
41 Op. ii. 930.
42 Choq. des Corps, p.
296.
43 Ib. Prop. xi.
44 P. 172.
It was shown by John Bernoulli and Hermann, and was indeed easily
proved, that the proposition assumed by Huyghens as the foundation of
his solution, was, in fact, a consequence of the elementary principles
which belong to this branch of mechanics. But this assumption of
Huyghens was an example of a more general proposition, which by some
mathematicians at this time had been put forward as an original and
elementary law; and as a principle which ought to supersede the usual
measure of the forces of bodies in motion; this principle they called
“the Conservation of Vis Viva.” The attempt to 360 make this change was
the commencement of one of the most obstinate and curious of the
controversies which form part of the history of mechanical science.
The celebrated Leibnitz was the author of the new opinion. In 1686, he
published, in the Leipsic Acts, “A short Demonstration of a memorable
Error of Descartes and others, concerning the natural law by which
they think that God always preserves the same quantity of motion; in
which they pervert mechanics.” The principle that the same quantity of
motion, and therefore of moving force, is always preserved in the
world, follows from the equality of action and reaction; though
Descartes had, after his fashion, given a theological reason for it;
Leibnitz allowed that the quantity of moving force remains always the
same, but denied that this force is measured by the quantity of motion
or momentum. He maintained that the same force is requisite to raise a
weight of one pound through four feet, and a weight of four pounds
through one foot, though the momenta in this case are as one to two.
This was answered by the Abbé de Conti; who truly observed, that
allowing the effects in the two cases to be equal, this did not prove
the forces to be equal; since the effect, in the first case, was
produced in a double time, and therefore it was quite consistent to
suppose the force only half as great. Leibnitz, however, persisted in
his innovation; and in 1695 laid down the distinction between vires
mortuæ, or pressures, and vires vivæ, the name he gave to
his own measure of force. He kept up a correspondence with John
Bernoulli, whom he converted to his peculiar opinions on this subject;
or rather, as Bernoulli says,45 made him think
for himself, which ended in his proving directly that which Leibnitz
had defended by indirect reasons. Among other arguments, he had
pretended to show (what is certainly not true), that if the common
measure of forces be adhered to, a perpetual motion would be possible.
It is easy to collect many cases which admit of being very simply and
conveniently reasoned upon by means of the vis viva, that is,
by taking the force to be proportional to the square of the
velocity, and not to the velocity itself. Thus, in order to give the
arrow twice the velocity, the bow must be four times
as strong; and in all cases in which no account is taken of the time
of producing the effect, we may conveniently use similar methods.
45 Op. iii. 40.
But it was not till a later period that the question excited any
general notice. The Academy of Sciences of Paris in 1724 proposed
361 as a subject
for their prize dissertation the laws of the impact of bodies.
Bernoulli, as a competitor, wrote a treatise, upon Leibnitzian
principles, which, though not honored with the prize, was printed by
the Academy with commendation.46 The opinions
which he here defended and illustrated were adopted by several
mathematicians; the controversy extended from the mathematical to the
literary world, at that time more attentive than usual to mathematical
disputes, in consequence of the great struggle then going on between
the Cartesian and the Newtonian system. It was, however, obvious that
by this time the interest of the question, so far as the progress of
Dynamics was concerned, was at an end; for the combatants all agreed
as to the results in each particular case. The Laws of Motion were now
established; and the question was, by means of what definitions and
abstractions could they be best expressed;—a metaphysical, not a
physical discussion, and therefore one in which “the paper
philosophers,” as Galileo called them, could bear a part. In the first
volume of the Transactions of the Academy of St. Petersburg,
published in 1728, there are three Leibnitzian memoirs by Hermann,
Bullfinger, and Wolff. In England, Clarke was an angry assailant of
the German opinion, which S’Gravesande maintained. In France, Mairan
attacked the vis viva in 1728; “with strong and victorious
reasons,” as the Marquise du Chatelet declared, in the first edition
of her Treatise on Fire.47 But shortly
after this praise was published, the Chateau de Cirey, where the
Marquise usually lived, became a school of Leibnitzian opinions, and
the resort of the principal partisans of the vis viva. “Soon,”
observes Mairan, “their language was changed; the vis viva was
enthroned by the side of the monads.” The Marquise tried to
retract or explain away her praises; she urged arguments on the other
side. Still the question was not decided; even her friend Voltaire was
not converted. In 1741 he read a memoir On the Measure and Nature
of Moving Forces, in which he maintained the old opinion. Finally,
D’Alembert in 1743 declared it to be, as it truly was, a mere question
of words; and by the turn which Dynamics then took, it ceased to be of
any possible interest or importance to mathematicians.
46 Discours sur les Loix de la
Communication du Mouvement.
47 Mont. iii. 640.
The representation of the laws of motion and of the reasonings
depending on them, in the most general form, by means of analytical
language, cannot be said to have been fully achieved till the time of
D’Alembert; but as we have already seen, the discovery of these laws
362 had taken place
somewhat earlier; and that law which is more particularly expressed in
D’Alembert’s Principle (the equality of the action gained and
lost) was, it has been seen, rather led to by the general current
of the reasoning of mathematicians about the end of the seventeenth
century than discovered by any one. Huyghens, Marriotte, the two
Bernoulli’s, L’Hôpital, Taylor, and Hermann, have each of them their
name in the history of this advance; but we cannot ascribe to any of
them any great real inductive sagacity shown in what they thus
contributed, except to Huyghens, who first seized the principle in
such a form as to find the centre of oscillation by means of it.
Indeed, in the steps taken by the others, language itself had almost
made the generalization for them at the time when they wrote; and it
required no small degree of acuteness and care to distinguish the old
cases, in which the law had already been applied, from the new cases,
in which they had to apply it.
</div></body></text></TEI>