<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="2">

THE EPISTLE TO THE READER
READER,

I have put into thy hands what has been the diversion of some of my idle and
heavy hours. If it has the good luck to prove so of any of thine, and thou hast
but half so much pleasure in reading as I had in writing it, thou wilt as
little think thy money, as I do my pains, ill bestowed. Mistake not this for a
commendation of my work; nor conclude, because I was pleased with the doing of
it, that therefore I am fondly taken with it now it is done. He that hawks at
larks and sparrows has no less sport, though a much less considerable quarry,
than he that flies at nobler game: and he is little acquainted with the subject
of this treatise—the UNDERSTANDING—who does not know that, as it is
the most elevated faculty of the soul, so it is employed with a greater and
more constant delight than any of the other. Its searches after truth are a
sort of hawking and hunting, wherein the very pursuit makes a great part of the
pleasure. Every step the mind takes in its progress towards Knowledge makes
some discovery, which is not only new, but the best too, for the time at least.


For the understanding, like the eye, judging of objects only by its own sight,
cannot but be pleased with what it discovers, having less regret for what has
escaped it, because it is unknown. Thus he who has raised himself above the
alms-basket, and, not content to live lazily on scraps of begged opinions, sets
his own thoughts on work, to find and follow truth, will (whatever he lights
on) not miss the hunter’s satisfaction; every moment of his pursuit will reward
his pains with some delight; and he will have reason to think his time not ill
spent, even when he cannot much boast of any great acquisition.


This, Reader, is the entertainment of those who let loose their own thoughts,
and follow them in writing; which thou oughtest not to envy them, since they
afford thee an opportunity of the like diversion, if thou wilt make use of thy
own thoughts in reading. It is to them, if they are thy own, that I refer
myself: but if they are taken upon trust from others, it is no great matter
what they are; they are not following truth, but some meaner consideration; and
it is not worth while to be concerned what he says or thinks, who says or
thinks only as he is directed by another. If thou judgest for thyself I know
thou wilt judge candidly, and then I shall not be harmed or offended, whatever
be thy censure. For though it be certain that there is nothing in this Treatise
of the truth whereof I am not fully persuaded, yet I consider myself as liable
to mistakes as I can think thee, and know that this book must stand or fall
with thee, not by any opinion I have of it, but thy own. If thou findest little
in it new or instructive to thee, thou art not to blame me for it. It was not
meant for those that had already mastered this subject, and made a thorough
acquaintance with their own understandings; but for my own information, and the
satisfaction of a few friends, who acknowledged themselves not to have
sufficiently considered it.


Were it fit to trouble thee with the history of this Essay, I should tell thee,
that five or six friends meeting at my chamber, and discoursing on a subject
very remote from this, found themselves quickly at a stand, by the difficulties
that rose on every side. After we had awhile puzzled ourselves, without coming
any nearer a resolution of those doubts which perplexed us, it came into my
thoughts that we took a wrong course; and that before we set ourselves upon
inquiries of that nature, it was necessary to examine our own abilities, and
see what OBJECTS our understandings were, or were not, fitted to deal with.
This I proposed to the company, who all readily assented; and thereupon it was
agreed that this should be our first inquiry. Some hasty and undigested
thoughts, on a subject I had never before considered, which I set down against
our next meeting, gave the first entrance into this Discourse; which having
been thus begun by chance, was continued by intreaty; written by incoherent
parcels; and after long intervals of neglect, resumed again, as my humour or
occasions permitted; and at last, in a retirement where an attendance on my
health gave me leisure, it was brought into that order thou now seest it.


This discontinued way of writing may have occasioned, besides others, two
contrary faults, viz., that too little and too much may be said in it. If thou
findest anything wanting, I shall be glad that what I have written gives thee
any desire that I should have gone further. If it seems too much to thee, thou
must blame the subject; for when I put pen to paper, I thought all I should
have to say on this matter would have been contained in one sheet of paper; but
the further I went the larger prospect I had; new discoveries led me still on,
and so it grew insensibly to the bulk it now appears in. I will not deny, but
possibly it might be reduced to a narrower compass than it is, and that some
parts of it might be contracted, the way it has been writ in, by catches, and
many long intervals of interruption, being apt to cause some repetitions. But
to confess the truth, I am now too lazy, or too busy, to make it shorter. I am
not ignorant how little I herein consult my own reputation, when I knowingly
let it go with a fault, so apt to disgust the most judicious, who are always
the nicest readers. But they who know sloth is apt to content itself with any
excuse, will pardon me if mine has prevailed on me, where I think I have a very
good one. I will not therefore allege in my defence, that the same notion,
having different respects, may be convenient or necessary to prove or
illustrate several parts of the same discourse, and that so it has happened in
many parts of this: but waiving that, I shall frankly avow that I have
sometimes dwelt long upon the same argument, and expressed it different ways,
with a quite different design. I pretend not to publish this Essay for the
information of men of large thoughts and quick apprehensions; to such masters
of knowledge I profess myself a scholar, and therefore warn them beforehand not
to expect anything here, but what, being spun out of my own coarse thoughts, is
fitted to men of my own size, to whom, perhaps, it will not be unacceptable
that I have taken some pains to make plain and familiar to their thoughts some
truths which established prejudice, or the abstractedness of the ideas
themselves, might render difficult. Some objects had need be turned on every
side; and when the notion is new, as I confess some of these are to me; or out
of the ordinary road, as I suspect they will appear to others, it is not one
simple view of it that will gain it admittance into every understanding, or fix
it there with a clear and lasting impression. There are few, I believe, who
have not observed in themselves or others, that what in one way of proposing
was very obscure, another way of expressing it has made very clear and
intelligible; though afterwards the mind found little difference in the
phrases, and wondered why one failed to be understood more than the other. But
everything does not hit alike upon every man’s imagination. We have our
understandings no less different than our palates; and he that thinks the same
truth shall be equally relished by every one in the same dress, may as well
hope to feast every one with the same sort of cookery: the meat may be the
same, and the nourishment good, yet every one not be able to receive it with
that seasoning; and it must be dressed another way, if you will have it go down
with some, even of strong constitutions. The truth is, those who advised me to
publish it, advised me, for this reason, to publish it as it is: and since I
have been brought to let it go abroad, I desire it should be understood by
whoever gives himself the pains to read it. I have so little affection to be in
print, that if I were not flattered this Essay might be of some use to others,
as I think it has been to me, I should have confined it to the view of some
friends, who gave the first occasion to it. My appearing therefore in print
being on purpose to be as useful as I may, I think it necessary to make what I
have to say as easy and intelligible to all sorts of readers as I can. And I
had much rather the speculative and quick-sighted should complain of my being
in some parts tedious, than that any one, not accustomed to abstract
speculations, or prepossessed with different notions, should mistake or not
comprehend my meaning.


It will possibly be censured as a great piece of vanity or insolence in me, to
pretend to instruct this our knowing age; it amounting to little less, when I
own, that I publish this Essay with hopes it may be useful to others. But, if
it may be permitted to speak freely of those who with a feigned modesty condemn
as useless what they themselves write, methinks it savours much more of vanity
or insolence to publish a book for any other end; and he fails very much of
that respect he owes the public, who prints, and consequently expects men
should read, that wherein he intends not they should meet with anything of use
to themselves or others: and should nothing else be found allowable in this
Treatise, yet my design will not cease to be so; and the goodness of my
intention ought to be some excuse for the worthlessness of my present. It is
that chiefly which secures me from the fear of censure, which I expect not to
escape more than better writers. Men’s principles, notions, and relishes are so
different, that it is hard to find a book which pleases or displeases all men.
I acknowledge the age we live in is not the least knowing, and therefore not
the most easy to be satisfied. If I have not the good luck to please, yet
nobody ought to be offended with me. I plainly tell all my readers, except half
a dozen, this Treatise was not at first intended for them; and therefore they
need not be at the trouble to be of that number. But yet if any one thinks fit
to be angry and rail at it, he may do it securely, for I shall find some better
way of spending my time than in such kind of conversation. I shall always have
the satisfaction to have aimed sincerely at truth and usefulness, though in one
of the meanest ways. The commonwealth of learning is not at this time without
master-builders, whose mighty designs, in advancing the sciences, will leave
lasting monuments to the admiration of posterity: but every one must not hope
to be a Boyle or a Sydenham; and in an age that produces such masters as the
great Huygenius and the incomparable Mr. Newton, with some others of that
strain, it is ambition enough to be employed as an under-labourer in clearing
the ground a little, and removing some of the rubbish that lies in the way to
knowledge;—which certainly had been very much more advanced in the world,
if the endeavours of ingenious and industrious men had not been much cumbered
with the learned but frivolous use of uncouth, affected, or unintelligible
terms, introduced into the sciences, and there made an art of, to that degree
that Philosophy, which is nothing but the true knowledge of things, was thought
unfit or incapable to be brought into well-bred company and polite
conversation. Vague and insignificant forms of speech, and abuse of language,
have so long passed for mysteries of science; and hard and misapplied words,
with little or no meaning, have, by prescription, such a right to be mistaken
for deep learning and height of speculation, that it will not be easy to
persuade either those who speak or those who hear them, that they are but the
covers of ignorance, and hindrance of true knowledge. To break in upon the
sanctuary of vanity and ignorance will be, I suppose, some service to human
understanding; though so few are apt to think they deceive or are deceived in
the use of words; or that the language of the sect they are of has any faults
in it which ought to be examined or corrected, that I hope I shall be pardoned
if I have in the Third Book dwelt long on this subject, and endeavoured to make
it so plain, that neither the inveterateness of the mischief, nor the
prevalency of the fashion, shall be any excuse for those who will not take care
about the meaning of their own words, and will not suffer the significancy of
their expressions to be inquired into.


I have been told that a short Epitome of this Treatise, which was printed in
1688, was by some condemned without reading, because INNATE IDEAS were denied
in it; they too hastily concluding, that if innate ideas were not supposed,
there would be little left either of the notion or proof of spirits. If any one
take the like offence at the entrance of this Treatise, I shall desire him to
read it through; and then I hope he will be convinced, that the taking away
false foundations is not to the prejudice but advantage of truth, which is
never injured or endangered so much as when mixed with, or built on, falsehood.
In the Second Edition I added as followeth:—


The bookseller will not forgive me if I say nothing of this New Edition, which
he has promised, by the correctness of it, shall make amends for the many
faults committed in the former. He desires too, that it should be known that it
has one whole new chapter concerning Identity, and many additions and
amendments in other places. These I must inform my reader are not all new
matter, but most of them either further confirmation of what I had said, or
explications, to prevent others being mistaken in the sense of what was
formerly printed, and not any variation in me from it.


I must only except the alterations I have made in Book II. chap. xxi.


What I had there written concerning Liberty and the Will, I thought deserved as
accurate a view as I am capable of; those subjects having in all ages exercised
the learned part of the world with questions and difficulties, that have not a
little perplexed morality and divinity, those parts of knowledge that men are
most concerned to be clear in. Upon a closer inspection into the working of
men’s minds, and a stricter examination of those motives and views they are
turned by, I have found reason somewhat to alter the thoughts I formerly had
concerning that which gives the last determination to the Will in all voluntary
actions. This I cannot forbear to acknowledge to the world with as much freedom
and readiness; as I at first published what then seemed to me to be right;
thinking myself more concerned to quit and renounce any opinion of my own, than
oppose that of another, when truth appears against it. For it is truth alone I
seek, and that will always be welcome to me, when or from whencesoever it
comes. But what forwardness soever I have to resign any opinion I have, or to
recede from anything I have writ, upon the first evidence of any error in it;
yet this I must own, that I have not had the good luck to receive any light
from those exceptions I have met with in print against any part of my book, nor
have, from anything that has been urged against it, found reason to alter my
sense in any of the points that have been questioned. Whether the subject I
have in hand requires often more thought and attention than cursory readers, at
least such as are prepossessed, are willing to allow; or whether any obscurity
in my expressions casts a cloud over it, and these notions are made difficult
to others’ apprehensions in my way of treating them; so it is, that my meaning,
I find, is often mistaken, and I have not the good luck to be everywhere
rightly understood.


Of this the ingenious author of the Discourse Concerning the Nature of Man has
given me a late instance, to mention no other. For the civility of his
expressions, and the candour that belongs to his order, forbid me to think that
he would have closed his Preface with an insinuation, as if in what I had said,
Book II. ch. xxvii, concerning the third rule which men refer their actions to,
I went about to make virtue vice and vice virtue, unless he had mistaken my
meaning; which he could not have done if he had given himself the trouble to
consider what the argument was I was then upon, and what was the chief design
of that chapter, plainly enough set down in the fourth section and those
following. For I was there not laying down moral rules, but showing the
original and nature of moral ideas, and enumerating the rules men make use of
in moral relations, whether these rules were true or false: and pursuant
thereto I tell what is everywhere called virtue and vice; which “alters not the
nature of things,” though men generally do judge of and denominate their
actions according to the esteem and fashion of the place and sect they are of.


If he had been at the pains to reflect on what I had said, Bk. I. ch. ii. sect.
18, and Bk. II. ch. xxviii. sect. 13, 14, 15 and 20, he would have known what I
think of the eternal and unalterable nature of right and wrong, and what I call
virtue and vice. And if he had observed that in the place he quotes I only
report as a matter of fact what OTHERS call virtue and vice, he would not have
found it liable to any great exception. For I think I am not much out in saying
that one of the rules made use of in the world for a ground or measure of a
moral relation is—that esteem and reputation which several sorts of
actions find variously in the several societies of men, according to which they
are there called virtues or vices. And whatever authority the learned Mr. Lowde
places in his Old English Dictionary, I daresay it nowhere tells him (if I
should appeal to it) that the same action is not in credit, called and counted
a virtue, in one place, which, being in disrepute, passes for and under the
name of vice in another. The taking notice that men bestow the names of
‘virtue’ and ‘vice’ according to this rule of Reputation is all I have done, or
can be laid to my charge to have done, towards the making vice virtue or virtue
vice. But the good man does well, and as becomes his calling, to be watchful in
such points, and to take the alarm even at expressions, which, standing alone
by themselves, might sound ill and be suspected.


‘Tis to this zeal, allowable in his function, that I forgive his citing as he
does these words of mine (ch. xxviii. sect. II): “Even the exhortations of
inspired teachers have not feared to appeal to common repute, Philip, iv. 8;”
without taking notice of those immediately preceding, which introduce them, and
run thus: “Whereby even in the corruption of manners, the true boundaries of
the law of nature, which ought to be the rule of virtue and vice, were pretty
well preserved. So that even the exhortations of inspired teachers,” &c. By
which words, and the rest of that section, it is plain that I brought that
passage of St. Paul, not to prove that the general measure of what men called
virtue and vice throughout the world was the reputation and fashion of each
particular society within itself; but to show that, though it were so, yet, for
reasons I there give, men, in that way of denominating their actions, did not
for the most part much stray from the Law of Nature; which is that standing and
unalterable rule by which they ought to judge of the moral rectitude and
gravity of their actions, and accordingly denominate them virtues or vices. Had
Mr. Lowde considered this, he would have found it little to his purpose to have
quoted this passage in a sense I used it not; and would I imagine have spared
the application he subjoins to it, as not very necessary. But I hope this
Second Edition will give him satisfaction on the point, and that this matter is
now so expressed as to show him there was no cause for scruple.


Though I am forced to differ from him in these apprehensions he has expressed,
in the latter end of his preface, concerning what I had said about virtue and
vice, yet we are better agreed than he thinks in what he says in his third
chapter (p. 78) concerning “natural inscription and innate notions.” I shall
not deny him the privilege he claims (p. 52), to state the question as he
pleases, especially when he states it so as to leave nothing in it contrary to
what I have said. For, according to him, “innate notions, being conditional
things, depending upon the concurrence of several other circumstances in order
to the soul’s exerting them,” all that he says for “innate, imprinted,
impressed notions” (for of innate IDEAS he says nothing at all), amounts at
last only to this—that there are certain propositions which, though the
soul from the beginning, or when a man is born, does not know, yet “by
assistance from the outward senses, and the help of some previous cultivation,”
it may AFTERWARDS come certainly to know the truth of; which is no more than
what I have affirmed in my First Book. For I suppose by the “soul’s exerting
them,” he means its beginning to know them; or else the soul’s ‘exerting of
notions’ will be to me a very unintelligible expression; and I think at best is
a very unfit one in this, it misleading men’s thoughts by an insinuation, as if
these notions were in the mind before the ‘soul exerts them,’ i. e. before they
are known;—whereas truly before they are known, there is nothing of them
in the mind but a capacity to know them, when the ‘concurrence of those
circumstances,’ which this ingenious author thinks necessary ‘in order to the
soul’s exerting them,’ brings them into our knowledge.


P. 52 I find him express it thus: ‘These natural notions are not so imprinted
upon the soul as that they naturally and necessarily exert themselves (even in
children and idiots) without any assistance from the outward senses, or without
the help of some previous cultivation.’ Here, he says, they ‘exert themselves,’
as p. 78, that the ‘soul exerts them.’ When he has explained to himself or
others what he means by ‘the soul’s exerting innate notions,’ or their
‘exerting themselves;’ and what that ‘previous cultivation and circumstances’
in order to their being exerted are—he will I suppose find there is so
little of controversy between him and me on the point, bating that he calls
that ‘exerting of notions’ which I in a more vulgar style call ‘knowing,’ that
I have reason to think he brought in my name on this occasion only out of the
pleasure he has to speak civilly of me; which I must gratefully acknowledge he
has done everywhere he mentions me, not without conferring on me, as some
others have done, a title I have no right to.


There are so many instances of this, that I think it justice to my reader and
myself to conclude, that either my book is plainly enough written to be rightly
understood by those who peruse it with that attention and indifferency, which
every one who will give himself the pains to read ought to employ in reading;
or else that I have written mine so obscurely that it is in vain to go about to
mend it. Whichever of these be the truth, it is myself only am affected
thereby; and therefore I shall be far from troubling my reader with what I
think might be said in answer to those several objections I have met with, to
passages here and there of my book; since I persuade myself that he who thinks
them of moment enough to be concerned whether they are true or false, will be
able to see that what is said is either not well founded, or else not contrary
to my doctrine, when I and my opposer come both to be well understood.


If any other authors, careful that none of their good thoughts should be lost,
have published their censures of my Essay, with this honour done to it, that
they will not suffer it to be an essay, I leave it to the public to value the
obligation they have to their critical pens, and shall not waste my reader’s
time in so idle or ill-natured an employment of mine, as to lessen the
satisfaction any one has in himself, or gives to others, in so hasty a
confutation of what I have written.


The booksellers preparing for the Fourth Edition of my Essay, gave me notice of
it, that I might, if I had leisure, make any additions or alterations I should
think fit. Whereupon I thought it convenient to advertise the reader, that
besides several corrections I had made here and there, there was one alteration
which it was necessary to mention, because it ran through the whole book, and
is of consequence to be rightly understood. What I thereupon said was
this:—


CLEAR and DISTINCT ideas are terms which, though familiar and frequent in men’s
mouths, I have reason to think every one who uses does not perfectly
understand. And possibly ‘tis but here and there one who gives himself the
trouble to consider them so far as to know what he himself or others precisely
mean by them. I have therefore in most places chose to put DETERMINATE or
DETERMINED, instead of CLEAR and DISTINCT, as more likely to direct men’s
thoughts to my meaning in this matter. By those denominations, I mean some
object in the mind, and consequently determined, i. e. such as it is there seen
and perceived to be. This, I think, may fitly be called a determinate or
determined idea, when such as it is at any time objectively in the mind, and so
determined there, it is annexed, and without variation determined, to a name or
articulate sound, which is to be steadily the sign of that very same object of
the mind, or determinate idea.


To explain this a little more particularly. By DETERMINATE, when applied to a
simple idea, I mean that simple appearance which the mind has in its view, or
perceives in itself, when that idea is said to be in it: by DETERMINED, when
applied to a complex idea, I mean such an one as consists of a determinate
number of certain simple or less complex ideas, joined in such a proportion and
situation as the mind has before its view, and sees in itself, when that idea
is present in it, or should be present in it, when a man gives a name to it. I
say SHOULD be, because it is not every one, nor perhaps any one, who is so
careful of his language as to use no word till he views in his mind the precise
determined idea which he resolves to make it the sign of. The want of this is
the cause of no small obscurity and confusion in men’s thoughts and discourses.


I know there are not words enough in any language to answer all the variety of
ideas that enter into men’s discourses and reasonings. But this hinders not but
that when any one uses any term, he may have in his mind a determined idea,
which he makes it the sign of, and to which he should keep it steadily annexed
during that present discourse. Where he does not, or cannot do this, he in vain
pretends to clear or distinct ideas: it is plain his are not so; and therefore
there can be expected nothing but obscurity and confusion, where such terms are
made use of which have not such a precise determination.


Upon this ground I have thought determined ideas a way of speaking less liable
to mistakes, than clear and distinct: and where men have got such determined
ideas of all that they reason, inquire, or argue about, they will find a great
part of their doubts and disputes at an end; the greatest part of the questions
and controversies that perplex mankind depending on the doubtful and uncertain
use of words, or (which is the same) indetermined ideas, which they are made to
stand for. I have made choice of these terms to signify, (1) Some immediate
object of the mind, which it perceives and has before it, distinct from the
sound it uses as a sign of it. (2) That this idea, thus determined, i.e. which
the mind has in itself, and knows, and sees there, be determined without any
change to that name, and that name determined to that precise idea. If men had
such determined ideas in their inquiries and discourses, they would both
discern how far their own inquiries and discourses went, and avoid the greatest
part of the disputes and wranglings they have with others.


Besides this, the bookseller will think it necessary I should advertise the
reader that there is an addition of two chapters wholly new; the one of the
Association of Ideas, the other of Enthusiasm. These, with some other larger
additions never before printed, he has engaged to print by themselves, after
the same manner, and for the same purpose, as was done when this Essay had the
second impression.


In the Sixth Edition there is very little added or altered. The greatest part
of what is new is contained in the twenty-first chapter of the second book,
which any one, if he thinks it worth while, may, with a very little labour,
transcribe into the margin of the former edition.


</div></body></text></TEI>