<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol I</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1794</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="11">SECT. XI.
ADDITIONAL OBSERVATIONS ON THE SENSORIAL POWERS.

I. Stimulation is of various kinds adapted
  to the organs of sense, to the muscles, to hollow membranes, and glands.
  Some objects irritate our senses by repeated impulses. II. 1. Sensation and
  volition frequently affect the whole sensorium. 2. Emotions, passions, appetites. 3. Origin of desire and aversion. Criterion of
  voluntary actions, difference of brutes and men. 4. Sensibility and voluntarity. III. Associations formed before nativity,
  irritative motions mistaken for officiated ones.

Irritation.
I. The various organs of sense require various
  kinds of stimulation to excite them into action; the particles of light
  penetrate the cornea and humours of the eye, and then irritate the naked
  retina; rapid particles, dissolved or diffused in water or saliva, and
  odorous ones, mixed or combined with the air, irritate the extremities of
  the nerves of taste and smell; which either penetrate, or are expanded on
  the membranes of the tongue and nostrils; the auditory nerves are
  stimulated by the vibrations of the atmosphere communicated by means of
  the tympanum and of the fluid, whether of air or of water, behind it; and
  the nerves of touch by the hardness of surrounding bodies, though the
  cuticle is interposed between these bodies and the medulla of the
  nerve.
As the nerves of the senses have each their appropriated objects,
  which stimulate them into activity; so the muscular fibres, which are the
  terminations of other sets of nerves, have their peculiar objects, which
  excite them into action; the longitudinal muscles are stimulated into
  contraction by extension, whence the stretching or pandiculation after a
  long continued posture, during which they have been kept in a state of
  extension; and the hollow muscles are excited into action by distention,
  as those of the rectum and bladder are induced to protrude their contents
  from their sense of the distention rather than of the acrimony of those
  contents.
There are other objects adapted to stimulate the nerves, which
  terminate in variety of membranes, and those especially which form the
  terminations of canals; thus the preparations of mercury particularly
  affect the salivary glands, ipecacuanha the stomach, aloe the sphincter
  of the anus, cantharides that of the bladder, and lastly every gland of
  the body appears to be indued with a kind of taste, by which it selects
  or forms each its peculiar fluid from the blood; and by which it is
  irritated into activity.
Many of these external properties of bodies, which stimulate our
  organs of sense, do not seem to effect this by a single impulse, but by
  repeated impulses; as the nerve of the ear is probably not excitable by a
  single vibration of air, nor the optic nerve by a single particle of
  light; which circumstance produces some analogy between those two senses,
  at the same time the solidity of bodies is perceived by a single
  application of a solid body to the nerves of touch, and that even through
  the cuticle; and we are probably possessed of a peculiar sense to
  distinguish the nice degrees of heat and cold.
The senses of touch and of hearing acquaint us with the mechanical
  impact and vibration of bodies, those of smell and taste seem to acquaint
  us with some of their chemical properties, while the sense of vision and
  of heat acquaint us with the existence of their peculiar fluids.
Sensation and Volition.
II. Many motions are produced by pleasure or
  pain, and that even in contradiction to the power of volition, as in
  laughing, or in the strangury; but as no name has been given to pleasure
  or pain, at the time it is exerted so as to cause fibrous motions, we
  have used the term sensation for this purpose; and mean it to bear the
  same analogy to pleasure and pain, that the word volition does to desire
  and aversion.
1. It was mentioned in the fifth Section,
  that, what we have termed sensation is a motion of the central parts, or
  of the whole sensorium, beginning at some of the extremities of
  it. This appears first, because our pains and pleasures are always caused
  by our ideas or muscular motions, which are the motions of the
  extremities of the sensorium. And, secondly, because the sensation of
  pleasure or pain frequently continues some time after the ideas or
  muscular motions which excited it have ceased: for we often feel a glow
  of pleasure from an agreeable reverie, for many minutes after the ideas,
  that were the subject of it, have escaped our memory; and frequently
  experience a dejection of spirits without being able to assign the cause
  of it but by much recollection.
When the sensorial faculty of desire or aversion is exerted so as to
  cause fibrous motions, it is termed volition; which is said in Sect. V. to be a motion of the central parts, or of the
  whole sensorium, terminating in some of the extremities of it.
  This appears, first, because our desires and aversions always terminate
  in recollecting and comparing our ideas, or in exerting our muscles;
  which are the motions of the extremities of the sensorium. And, secondly,
  because desire or aversion begins, and frequently continues for a time in
  the central parts of the sensorium, before it is peculiarly exerted at
  the extremities of it; for we sometimes feel desire or aversion without
  immediately knowing their objects, and in consequence without immediately
  exerting any of our muscular or sensual motions to attain them: as in the
  beginning of the passion of love, and perhaps of hunger, or in the ennui
  of indolent people.
Though sensation and volition begin or terminate at the extremities or
  central parts of the sensorium, yet the whole of it is frequently
  influenced by the exertion of these faculties, as appears from their
  effects on the external habit: for the whole skin is reddened by shame,
  and an universal trembling is produced by fear: and every muscle of the
  body is agitated in angry people by the desire of revenge.
There is another very curious circumstance, which shews that sensation
  and volition are movements of the sensorium in contrary directions; that
  is, that volition begins at the central parts of it, and proceeds to the
  extremities; and that sensation begins at the extremities, and proceeds
  to the central parts: I mean that these two sensorial faculties cannot be
  strongly exerted at the same time; for when we exert our volition
  strongly, we do not attend to pleasure or pain; and conversely, when we
  are strongly affected with the sensation of pleasure or pain, we use no
  volition. As will be further explained in Section XVIII. on sleep, and Section XXXIV. on volition.
2. All our emotions and passions seem to
  arise out of the exertions of these two faculties of the animal
  sensorium. Pride, hope, joy, are the names of particular pleasures:
  shame, despair, sorrow, are the names of peculiar pains: and love,
  ambition, avarice, of particular desires: hatred, disgust, fear, anxiety,
  of particular aversions. Whilst the passion of anger includes the pain
  from a recent injury, and the aversion to the adversary that occasioned
  it. And compassion is the pain we experience at the sight of misery, and
  the desire of relieving it.
There is another tribe of desires, which are commonly termed
  appetites, and are the immediate consequences of the absence of some
  irritative motions. Those, which arise from defect of internal
  irritations, have proper names conferred upon them, as hunger, thirst,
  lust, and the desire of air, when our respiration is impaired by noxious
  vapours; and of warmth, when we are exposed to too great a degree of
  cold. But those, whose stimuli are external to the body, are named from
  the objects, which are by nature constituted to excite them; these
  desires originate from our past experience of the pleasurable sensations
  they occasion, as the smell of an hyacinth, or the taste of a
  pine-apple.
Whence it appears, that our pleasures and pains are at least as
  various and as numerous as our irritations; and that our desires and
  aversions must be as numerous as our pleasures and pains. And that as
  sensation is here used as a general term for our numerous pleasures and
  pains, when they produce the contractions of our fibres; so volition is
  the general name for our desires and aversions, when they produce fibrous
  contractions. Thus when a motion of the central parts, or of the whole
  sensorium, terminates in the exertion of our muscles, it is generally
  called voluntary action; when it terminates in the exertion of our ideas,
  it is termed recollection, reasoning, determining.
3. As the sensations of pleasure and pain
  are originally introduced by the irritations of external objects: so our
  desires and aversions are originally introduced by those sensations; for
  when the objects of our pleasures or pains are at a distance, and we
  cannot instantaneously possess the one, or avoid the other, then desire
  or aversion is produced, and a voluntary exertion of our ideas or muscles
  succeeds.
The pain of hunger excites you to look out for food, the tree, that
  shades you, presents its odoriferous fruit before your eyes, you
  approach, pluck, and eat.
The various movements of walking to the tree, gathering the fruit, and
  masticating it, are associated motions introduced by their connection
  with sensation; but if from the uncommon height of the tree, the fruit be
  inaccessible, and you are prevented from quickly possessing the intended
  pleasure, desire is produced. The consequence of this desire is, first, a
  deliberation about the means to gain the object of pleasure in process of
  time, as it cannot be procured immediately; and, secondly, the muscular
  action necessary for this purpose.
You voluntarily call up all your ideas of causation, that are related
  to the effect you desire, and voluntarily examine and compare them, and
  at length determine whether to ascend the tree, or to gather stones from
  the neighbouring brook, is easier to practise, or more promising of
  success; and, finally, you gather the stones, and repeatedly fling them
  to dislodge the fruit.
Hence then we gain a criterion to distinguish voluntary acts or
  thoughts from those caused by sensation. As the former are always
  employed about the means to acquire pleasurable objects, or the
  means to avoid painful ones; while the latter are employed in the
  possession of those, which are already in our power.
Hence the activity of this power of volition produces the great
  difference between the human and the brute creation. The ideas and the
  actions of brutes are almost perpetually employed about their present
  pleasures, or their present pains; and, except in the few instances which
  are mentioned in Section XVI, on instinct, they
  seldom busy themselves about the means of procuring future bliss, or of
  avoiding future misery; so that the acquiring of languages, the making of
  tools, and labouring for money, which are all only the means to procure
  pleasures; and the praying to the Deity, as another means to procure
  happiness, are characteristic of human nature.
4. As there are many diseases produced by
  the quantity of the sensation of pain or pleasure being too great or too
  little; so are there diseases produced by the susceptibility of the
  constitution to motions causable by these sensations being too dull or
  too vivid. This susceptibility of the system to sensitive motions is
  termed sensibility, to distinguish it from sensation, which is the actual
  existence or exertion of pain or pleasure.
Other classes of diseases are owing to the excessive promptitude, or
  sluggishness of the constitution to voluntary exertions, as well as to
  the quantity of desire or of aversion. This susceptibility of the system
  to voluntary motions is termed voluntarity, to distinguish it from
  volition, which is the exertion of desire or aversion; these diseases
  will be treated of at length in the progress of the work.
Association.
III. 1. It is not
  easy to assign a cause, why those animal movements, that have once
  occurred in succession, or in combination, should afterwards have a
  tendency to succeed or accompany each other. It is a property of
  animation, and distinguishes this order of being from the other
  productions of nature.
When a child first wrote the word man, it was distinguished in his
  mind into three letters, and those letters into many parts of letters;
  but by repeated use the word man becomes to his hand in writing it, as to
  his organs of speech in pronouncing it, but one movement without any
  deliberation, or sensation, or irritation, interposed between the parts
  of it. And as many separate motions of our muscles thus become united,
  and form, as it were, one motion; so each separate motion before such
  union may be conceived to consist of many parts or spaces moved through;
  and perhaps even the individual fibres of our muscles have thus gradually
  been brought to act in concert, which habits began to be acquired as
  early as the very formation of the moving organs, long before the
  nativity of the animal; as explained in the Section XVI. 2. on instinct.
2. There are many motions of the body,
  belonging to the irritative class, which might by a hasty observer be
  mistaken for associated ones; as the peristaltic motion of the stomach
  and intestines, and the contractions of the heart and arteries, might be
  supposed to be associated with the irritative motions of their nerves of
  sense, rather than to be excited by the irritation of their muscular
  fibres by the distention, acrimony, or momentum of the blood. So the
  distention or elongation of muscles by objects external to them irritates
  them into contraction, though the cuticle or other parts may intervene
  between the stimulating body and the contracting muscle. Thus a horse
  voids his excrement when its weight or bulk irritates the rectum or
  sphincter ani. These muscles act from the irritation of distention, when
  he excludes his excrement, but the muscles of the abdomen and diaphragm
  are brought into motion by association with those of the sphincter and
  rectum.

</div></body></text></TEI>