<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="19">
[119]
BOOK II.
COSMICAL ARRANGEMENTS.

When we turn our attention to the larger portions
of the universe, the sun, the planets, and the earth
as one of them, the moon and other satellites, the
fixed stars and other heavenly bodies;—the views
which we obtain concerning their mutual relations,
arrangement and movements, are called, as we have
already stated, cosmical views. These views will, we
conceive, afford us indications of the wisdom and
care of the Power by which the objects which we
thus consider, were created and are preserved: and
we shall now proceed to point out some circumstances
in which these attributes may be traced.
It has been observed by writers on Natural Theology,
that the arguments for the being and perfections
of the Creator, drawn from cosmical considerations,
labour under some disadvantages when compared
with the arguments founded on those provisions
and adaptations which more immediately affect the
well-being of organized creatures. The structure of
the solar system has far less analogy with such machinery
as we can construct and comprehend, than we
find in the structure of the bodies of animals, or even
in the causes of the weather. Moreover, we do not
see the immediate bearing of cosmical arrangements
on that end which we most readily acknowledge to
be useful and desirable, the support and comfort of
sentient natures. So that, from both causes, the impression
of benevolent design in this case is less[120]
striking and pointed than that which results from the
examination of some other parts of nature.
But in considering the universe, according to the
view we have taken, as a collection of laws, astronomy,
the science which teaches us the laws of the
motions of the heavenly bodies, possesses some advantages,
among the subjects from which we may
seek to learn the character of the government of the
world. For our knowledge of the laws of the motions
of the planets and satellites is far more complete
and exact, far more thorough and satisfactory,
than the knowledge which we possess in any other
department of Natural Philosophy. Our acquaintance
with the laws of the solar system is such, that
we can calculate the precise place and motion of
most of its parts at any period, past or future, however
remote; and we can refer the changes which
take place in these circumstances to their proximate
cause, the attraction of one mass of matter to another,
acting between all the parts of the universe.
If, therefore, we trace indications of the Divine
care, either in the form of the laws which prevail
among the heavenly bodies, or in the arbitrary
quantities which such laws involve; (according to
the distinction explained in the former part of this
work;) we may expect that our examples of such
care, though they may be less numerous and obvious,
will be more precise than they can be in
other subjects, where the laws of facts are imperfectly
known, and their causes entirely hid. We
trust that this will be found to be the case with regard
to some of the examples which we shall adduce.
</div></body></text></TEI>