<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="137">CHAPTER VI.
Progress of the Geological Dynamics of Organized
Beings.

Sect. 1.—Objects of this
Science.
PERHAPS in extending the term
Geological Dynamics to the causes of changes in organized
beings, I shall be thought to be employing a forced and inconvenient
phraseology. But it will be found that, in order to treat geology in a
truly scientific manner, we must bring together all the classes of
speculations concerning known causes of change; and the Organic
Dynamics of Geology, or of Geography, if the reader prefers the word,
appears not an inappropriate phrase for one part of this body of
researches.
As has already been said, the species of plants and animals which
are found embedded in the strata of the earth, are not only different
from those which now live in the same regions, but, for the most part,
different from any now existing on the face of the earth. The remains
which we discover imply a past state of things different from that
which now prevails; they imply also that the whole organic creation
has been renewed, and that this renewal has taken place several times.
Such extraordinary general facts have naturally put in activity very
bold speculations.
But it has already been said, we cannot speculate upon such facts
in the past history of the globe, without taking a large survey of its
present condition. Does the present animal and vegetable population
differ from the past, in the same way in which the products of one
region of the existing earth differ from those of another? Can the
creation and diffusion of the fossil species be explained in the same
manner as the creation and diffusion of the creatures among which we
live? And these questions lead us onwards another step, to
ask,—What are the laws by which the plants and animals
of different parts of the earth differ? What was the manner in which
they were originally diffused?—Thus we have to include, as
portions of our subject, 562 the Geography of Plants, and
of Animals, and the History of their change and
diffusion; intending by the latter subject, of course,
palætiological history,—the examination of the causes of
what has occurred, and the inference of past events, from what we know
of causes.
It is unnecessary for me to give at any length a statement of the
problems which are included in these branches of science, or of the
progress which has been made in them; since Mr. Lyell, in his
Principles of Geology, has treated these subjects in a very
able manner, and in the same point of view in which I am thus led to
consider them. I will only briefly refer to some points, availing
myself of his labors and his ideas.
Sect. 2.—Geography of Plants and Animals.
With regard both to plants
and animals, it appears,78 that besides such differences in the
products of different regions as we may naturally suppose to be
occasioned by climate and other external causes; an examination of the
whole organic population of the globe leads us to consider the earth
as divided into provinces, each province being occupied by its
own group of species, and these groups not being mixed or interfused
among each other to any great extent. And thus, as the earth is
occupied by various nations of men, each appearing at first sight to
be of a different stock, so each other tribe of living things is
scattered over the ground in a similar manner, and distributed into
its separate nations in distant countries. The places where
species are thus peculiarly found, are, in the case of plants, called
their stations. Yet each species in its own region loves and
selects some peculiar conditions of shade or exposure, soil or
moisture: its place, defined by the general description of such
conditions, is called its habitation.
78 Lyell, Principles, B. iii.
c. v.
Not only each species thus placed in its own province, has its
position further fixed by its own habits, but more general groups and
assemblages are found to be determined in their situation by more
general conditions. Thus it is the character of the flora of a
collection of islands, scattered through a wide ocean in a tropical
and humid climate, to contain an immense preponderance of tree-ferns.
In the same way, the situation and depth at which certain genera of
shells are found have been tabulated79 by Mr.
Broderip. Such general inferences, if 563 they can be securely made, are of
extreme interest in their bearing on geological speculations.
79 Greenough, Add. 1835, p.
20.
The means by which plants and animals are now diffused from one
place to another, have been well described by Mr. Lyell.80 And he has considered also, with due
attention, the manner in which they become imbedded in mineral
deposits of various kinds.81 He has thus
followed the history of organized bodies, from the germ to the tomb,
and thence to the cabinet of the geologist.
80 Lyell, B. iii. c. v. vi.
vii.
81 B. iii. c. xiii. xiv. xv.
xvi.
But, besides the fortunes of individual plants and animals, there
is another class of questions, of great interest, but of great
difficulty;—the fortunes of each species. In what manner do
species which were not, begin to be? as geology teaches us that they
many times have done; and, as even our own reasonings convince us they
must have done, at least in the case of the species among which we
live.
We here obviously place before us, as a subject of research, the
Creation of Living Things;—a subject shrouded in mystery, and
not to be approached without reverence. But though we may conceive,
that, on this subject, we are not to seek our belief from science
alone, we shall find, it is asserted, within the limits of allowable
and unavoidable speculation, many curious and important problems which
may well employ our physiological skill. For example, we may
ask:—how we are to recognize the species which were originally
created distinct?—whether the population of the earth at one
geological epoch could pass to the form which it has at a succeeding
period, by the agency of natural causes alone?—and if not, what
other account we can give of the succession which we find to have
taken place?
The most remarkable point in the attempts to answer these and the
like questions, is the controversy between the advocates and the
opponents of the doctrine of the transmutation of species. This
question is, even from its mere physiological import, one of great
interest; and the interest is much enhanced by our geological
researches, which again bring the question before us in a striking
form, and on a gigantic scale. We shall, therefore, briefly state the
point at issue.
Sect. 3.—Question of the Transmutation of
Species.
We see that animals and
plants may, by the influence of breeding, and of external agents
operating upon their constitution, be greatly 564 modified, so as to give rise to
varieties and races different from what before existed. How different,
for instance, is one kind and breed of dog from another! The question,
then, is, whether organized beings can, by the mere working of natural
causes, pass from the type of one species to that of another? whether
the wolf may, by domestication, become the dog? whether the
ourang-outang may, by the power of external circumstances, be brought
within the circle of the human species? And the dilemma in which we
are placed is this;—that if species are not thus
interchangeable, we must suppose the fluctuations of which each
species is capable, and which are apparently indefinite, to be bounded
by rigorous limits; whereas, if we allow such a transmutation of
species, we abandon that belief in the adaptation of the structure
of every creature to its destined mode of being, which not only most
persons would give up with repugnance, but which, as we have seen, has
constantly and irresistibly impressed itself on the minds of the best
naturalists, as the true view of the order of the world.
But the study of Geology opens to us the spectacle of many groups
of species which have, in the course of the earth’s history, succeeded
each other at vast intervals of time; one set of animals and plants
disappearing, as it would seem, from the face of our planet, and
others, which did not before exist, becoming the only occupants of the
globe. And the dilemma then presents itself to us anew:—either
we must accept the doctrine of the transmutation of species, and must
suppose that the organized species of one geological epoch were
transmuted into those of another by some long-continued agency of
natural causes; or else, we must believe in many successive acts of
creation and extinction of species, out of the common course of
nature; acts which, therefore, we may properly call miraculous.
This latter dilemma, however, is a question concerning the facts
which have happened in the history of the world; the deliberation
respecting it belongs to physical geology itself, and not to that
subsidiary science which we are now describing, and which is concerned
only with such causes as we know to be in constant and orderly
action.
The former question, of the limited or unlimited extent of the
modifications of animals and plants, has received full and careful
consideration from eminent physiologists; and in their opinions we
find, I think, an indisputable preponderance to that decision which
rejects the transmutation of species, and which accepts the former
side of the dilemma; namely, that the changes of which each species is
565 susceptible,
though difficult to define in words, are limited in fact. It is
extremely interesting and satisfactory thus to receive an answer in
which we can confide, to inquiries seemingly so wide and bold as those
which this subject involves. I refer to Mr. Lyell, Dr. Prichard, Mr.
Lawrence, and others, for the history of the discussion, and for the
grounds of the decision; and I shall quote very briefly the main
points and conclusions to which the inquiry has led.82
82 Lyell, B. iii. c. iv.
It may be considered, then, as determined by the over-balance of
physiological authority, that there is a capacity in all species to
accommodate themselves, to a certain extent, to a change of external
circumstances; this extent varying greatly according to the species.
There may thus arise changes of appearance or structure, and some of
these changes are transmissible to the offspring: but the mutations
thus superinduced are governed by constant laws, and confined within
certain limits. Indefinite divergence from the original type is not
possible; and the extreme limit of possible variation may usually be
reached in a brief period of time: in short, species have a real
existence in nature, and a transmutation from one to another does
not exist.
Thus, for example, Cuvier remarks, that notwithstanding all the
differences of size, appearance, and habits, which we find in the dogs
of various races and countries, and though we have (in the Egyptian
mummies) skeletons of this animal as it existed three thousand years
ago, the relation of the bones to each other remains essentially the
same; and, with all the varieties of their shape83 and size, there
are characters which resist all the influences both of external
nature, of human intercourse, and of time.
83 Ossem. Foss. Disc. Prél.
p. 61.
Sect. 4.—Hypothesis of Progressive
Tendencies.
Within certain limits,
however, as we have said, external circumstances produce changes in
the forms of organized beings. The causes of change, and the laws and
limits of their effects, as they obtain in the existing state of the
organic creation, are in the highest degree interesting. And, as has
been already intimated, the knowledge thus obtained, has been applied
with a view to explain the origin of the existing population of the
world, and the succession of its past conditions. But those who have
attempted such an explanation, have found it necessary to assume
certain additional laws, in order to enable themselves to 566 deduce, from the
tenet of the transmutability of the species of organized beings, such
a state of things as we see about us, and such a succession of states
as is evidenced by geological researches. And here, again, we are
brought to questions of which we must seek the answers from the most
profound physiologists. Now referring, as before, to those which
appear to be the best authorities, it is found that these additional
positive laws are still more inadmissible than the primary assumption
of indefinite capacity of change. For example, in order to account, on
this hypothesis, for the seeming adaptation of the endowments of
animals to their wants, it is held that the endowments are the result
of the wants; that the swiftness of the antelope, the claws and teeth
of the lion, the trunk of the elephant, the long neck of the giraffe
have been produced by a certain plastic character in the constitution
of animals, operated upon, for a long course of ages, by the attempts
which these animals made to attain objects which their previous
organization did not place within their reach. In this way, it is
maintained that the most striking attributes of animals, those which
apparently imply most clearly the providing skill of their Creator,
have been brought forth by the long-repeated efforts of the creatures
to attain the object of their desire; thus animals with the highest
endowments have been gradually developed from ancestral forms of the
most limited organization; thus fish, bird, and beast, have grown from
small gelatinous bodies, “petits corps gelatineux,”
possessing some obscure principle of life, and the capacity of
development; and thus man himself with all his intellectual and moral,
as well as physical privileges, has been derived from some creature of
the ape or baboon tribe, urged by a constant tendency to improve, or
at least to alter his condition.
As we have said, in order to arrive even hypothetically at this
result, it is necessary to assume besides a mere capacity for change,
other positive and active principles, some of which we may notice.
Thus, we must have as the direct productions of nature on this
hypothesis, certain monads or rough draughts, the primary
rudiments of plants and animals. We must have, in these, a
constant tendency to progressive improvement, to the attainment
of higher powers and faculties than they possess; which tendency is
again perpetually modified and controlled by the force of external
circumstances. And in order to account for the simultaneous
existence of animals in every stage of this imaginary progress, we
must suppose that nature is compelled to be constantly
producing those elementary beings, from which all animals are
successively developed. 567
I need not stay to point out how extremely arbitrary every part of
this scheme is; and how complex its machinery would be, even if it did
account for the facts. It may be sufficient to observe, as others have
done,84 that the capacity of change, and of
being influenced by external circumstances, such as we really find it
in nature, and therefore such as in science we must represent it, is a
tendency, not to improve, but to deteriorate. When species are
modified by external causes, they usually degenerate, and do not
advance. And there is no instance of a species acquiring an entirely
new sense, faculty, or organ, in addition to, or in the place of, what
it had before.
84 Lyell, B. iii. c. iv.
Not only, then, is the doctrine of the transmutation of species in
itself disproved by the best physiological reasonings, but the
additional assumptions which are requisite, to enable its advocates to
apply it to the explanation of the geological and other phenomena of
the earth, are altogether gratuitous and fantastical.
Such is the judgment to which we are led by the examination of the
discussions which have taken place on this subject. Yet in certain
speculations, occasioned by the discovery of the Sivatherium, a
new fossil animal from the Sub-Himalaya mountains of India, M.
Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire speaks of the belief in the immutability of
species as a conviction which is fading away from men’s minds. He
speaks too of the termination of the age of Cuvier, “la clôture du
siècle de Cuvier,” and of the commencement of a better zoological
philosophy.85 But though he expresses himself with
great animation, I do not perceive that he adduces, in support of his
peculiar opinions, any arguments in addition to those which he urged
during the lifetime of Cuvier. And the reader86 may recollect
that the consideration of that controversy led us to very different
anticipations from his, respecting the probable future progress of
physiology. The discovery of the Sivatherium supplies no particle of
proof to the hypothesis, that the existing species of animals are
descended from extinct creatures which are specifically distinct: and
we cannot act more wisely than in listening to the advice of that
eminent naturalist, M. de Blainville.87 “Against this
hypothesis, which, up to the present time, I regard as purely
gratuitous, and likely to turn geologists out of the sound and
excellent road in which they now are, I willingly raise my voice, with
the most absolute conviction of being in the right.”
85 Compte Rendu de l’Acad. des
Sc. 1837, No. 3, p. 81.
86 See B. xvii. c. vii.
87 Compte Rendu, 1837, No. 5,
p. 168.
568 [2nd Ed.]
[The hypothesis of the progressive developement of species has been
urged recently, in connexion with the physiological tenet of Tiedemann
and De Serres, noticed in B. xvii. c. vii. sect. 3;—namely, that the embryo of the
higher forms of animals passes by gradations through those forms which
are permanent in inferior animals. Assuming this tenet as exact, it
has been maintained that the higher animals which are found in the
more recent strata may have been produced by an ulterior development
of the lower forms in the embryo state; the circumstances being such
as to favor such a developement. But all the best physiologists agree
in declaring that such an extraordinary developement of the embryo is
inconsistent with physiological possibility. Even if the progression
of the embryo in time have a general correspondence with the order of
animal forms as more or less perfectly organized (which is true in an
extremely incomplete and inexact degree), this correspondence must be
considered, not as any indication of causality, but as one of those
marks of universal analogy and symmetry which are stamped upon every
part of the creation.
Mr. Lyell88 notices this doctrine of Tiedemann and
De Serres; and observes, that though nature presents us with cases of
animal forms degraded by incomplete developement, she offers none of
forms exalted by extraordinary developement. Mr. Lyell’s own
hypothesis of the introduction of new species upon the earth, not
having any physiological basis, hardly belongs to this chapter.]
88 Principles, B. iii. c. iv.
Sect. 5.—Question of Creation as related to
Science.
But since we reject the
production of new species by means of external influence, do we then,
it may be asked, accept the other side of the dilemma which we have
stated; and admit a series of creations of species, by some power
beyond that which we trace in the ordinary course of nature?
To this question, the history and analogy of science, I conceive,
teach us to reply as follows:—All palætiological sciences, all
speculations which attempt to ascend from the present to the remote
past, by the chain of causation, do also, by an inevitable
consequence, urge us to look for the beginning of the state of things
which we thus contemplate; but in none of these cases have men been
able, by the aid of science, to arrive at a beginning which is
homogeneous with the 569 known course of events. The first origin
of language, of civilization, of law and government, cannot be clearly
made out by reasoning and research; just as little, we may expect,
will a knowledge of the origin of the existing and extinct species of
plants and animals, be the result of physiological and geological
investigation.
But, though philosophers have never yet demonstrated, and perhaps
never will be able to demonstrate, what was that primitive state of
things in the social and material worlds, from which the progressive
state took its first departure; they can still, in all the lines of
research to which we have referred, go very far back;—determine
many of the remote circumstances of the past sequence of
events;—ascend to a point which, from our position at least,
seems to be near the origin;—and exclude many suppositions
respecting the origin itself. Whether, by the light of reason alone,
men will ever be able to do more than this, it is difficult to say. It
is, I think, no irrational opinion, even on grounds of philosophical
analogy alone, that in all those sciences which look back and seek a
beginning of things, we may be unable to arrive at a consistent and
definite belief, without having recourse to other grounds of truth, as
well as to historical research and scientific reasoning. When our
thoughts would apprehend steadily the creation of things, we find that
we are obliged to summon up other ideas than those which regulate the
pursuit of scientific truths;—to call in other powers than those
to which we refer natural events: it cannot, then, be considered as
very surprizing, if, in this part of our inquiry, we are compelled to
look for other than the ordinary evidence of science.
Geology, forming one of the palætiological class of sciences, which
trace back the history of the earth and its inhabitants on
philosophical grounds, is thus associated with a number of other kinds
of research, which are concerned about language, law, art, and
consequently about the internal faculties of man, his thoughts, his
social habits, his conception of right, his love of beauty. Geology
being thus brought into the atmosphere of moral and mental
speculations, it may be expected that her investigations of the
probable past will share an influence common to them; and that she
will not be allowed to point to an origin of her own, a merely
physical beginning of things; but that, as she approaches towards such
a goal, she will be led to see that it is the origin of many trains of
events, the point of convergence of many lines. It may be, that
instead of being allowed to travel up to this focus of being, we are
only able to estimate its place and nature, and 570 to form of it such a
judgment as this;—that it is not only the source of mere
vegetable and animal life, but also of rational and social life,
language and arts, law and order; in short, of all the progressive
tendencies by which the highest principles of the intellectual and
moral world have been and are developed, as well as of the succession
of organic forms, which we find scattered, dead or living, over the
earth.
This reflection concerning the natural scientific view of creation,
it will be observed, has not been sought for, from a wish to arrive at
such conclusions; but it has flowed spontaneously from the manner in
which we have had to introduce geology into our classification of the
sciences; and this classification was framed from an unbiassed
consideration of the general analogies and guiding ideas of the
various portions of our knowledge. Such remarks as we have made may on
this account be considered more worthy of attention.
But such a train of thought must be pursued with caution. Although
it may not be possible to arrive at a right conviction respecting the
origin of the world, without having recourse to other than physical
considerations, and to other than geological evidence: yet extraneous
considerations, and extraneous evidence, respecting the nature of the
beginning of things, must never be allowed to influence our physics or
our geology. Our geological dynamics, like our astronomical dynamics,
may be inadequate to carry us back to an origin of that state of
things, of which it explains the progress: but this deficiency must be
supplied, not by adding supernatural to natural geological dynamics,
but by accepting, in their proper place, the views supplied by a
portion of knowledge of a different character and order. If we include
in our Theology the speculations to which we have recourse for this
purpose, we must exclude from them our Geology. The two sciences may
conspire, not by having any part in common: but because, though widely
diverse in their lines, both point to a mysterious and invisible
origin of the world.
All that which claims our assent on those higher grounds of which
theology takes cognizance, must claim such assent as is consistent
with those grounds; that is, it must require belief in respect of all
that bears upon the highest relations of our being, those on which
depend our duties and our hopes. Doctrines of this kind may and must
be conveyed and maintained, by means of information concerning the
past history of man, and his social and material, as well as moral and
spiritual fortunes. He who believes that a Providence has 571 ruled the affairs of
mankind, will also believe that a Providence has governed the material
world. But any language in which the narrative of this government of
the material world can be conveyed, must necessarily be very imperfect
and inappropriate; being expressed in terms of those ideas which have
been selected by men, in order to describe appearances and relations
of created things as they affect one another. In all cases, therefore,
where we have to attempt to interpret such a narrative, we must feel
that we are extremely liable to err; and most of all, when our
interpretation refers to those material objects and operations which
are most foreign to the main purpose of a history of providence. If we
have to consider a communication containing a view of such a
government of the world, imparted to us, as we may suppose, in order
to point out the right direction for our feelings of trust, and
reverence, and hope, towards the Governor of the world, we may expect
that we shall be in no danger of collecting from our authority
erroneous notions with regard to the power, and wisdom, and goodness
of His government; or with respect to our own place, duties, and
prospects, and the history of our race so far as our duties and
prospects are concerned. But that we shall rightly understand the
detail of all events in the history of man, or of the skies, or of the
earth, which are narrated for the purpose of thus giving a right
direction to our minds, is by no means equally certain; and I do not
think it would be too much to say, that an immunity from perplexity
and error, in such matters, is, on general grounds, very improbable.
It cannot then surprise us to find, that parts of such narrations
which seem to refer to occurrences like those of which astronomers and
geologists have attempted to determine the laws, have given rise to
many interpretations, all inconsistent with one another, and most of
them at variance with the best established principles of astronomy and
geology.
It may be urged, that all truths must be consistent with all other
truths, and that therefore the results of true geology or astronomy
cannot be irreconcileable with the statements of true theology. And
this universal consistency of truth with itself must be assented to;
but it by no means follows that we must be able to obtain a full
insight into the nature and manner of such a consistency. Such an
insight would only be possible if we could obtain a clear view of that
central body of truth, the source of the principles which appear in
the separate lines of speculation. To expect that we should see
clearly how the providential government of the world is consistent
with the unvarying laws 572 by which its motions and developements
are regulated, is to expect to understand thoroughly the laws of
motion, of developement, and of providence; it is to expect that we
may ascend from geology and astronomy to the creative and legislative
centre, from which proceeded earth and stars; and then descend again
into the moral and spiritual world, because its source and centre are
the same as those of the material creation. It is to say that reason,
whether finite or infinite, must be consistent with itself; and that,
therefore, the finite must be able to comprehend the infinite, to
travel from any one province of the moral and material universe to any
other, to trace their bearing, and to connect their boundaries.
One of the advantages of the study of the history and nature of
science in which we are now engaged is, that it warns us of the
hopeless and presumptuous character of such attempts to understand the
government of the world by the aid of science, without throwing any
discredit upon the reality of our knowledge;—that while it shows
how solid and certain each science is, so long as it refers its own
facts to its own ideas, it confines each science within its own
limits, and condemns it as empty and helpless, when it pronounces upon
those subjects which are extraneous to it. The error of persons who
should seek a geological narrative in theological records, would be
rather in the search itself than in their interpretation of what they
might find; and in like manner the error of those who would conclude
against a supernatural beginning, or a providential direction of the
world, upon geological or physiological reasonings, would be, that
they had expected those sciences alone to place the origin or the
government of the world in its proper light.
Though these observations apply generally to all the palætiological
sciences, they may be permitted here, because they have an especial
bearing upon some of the difficulties which have embarrassed the
progress of geological speculation; and though such difficulties are,
I trust, nearly gone by, it is important for us to see them in their
true bearing.
From what has been said, it follows that geology and astronomy are,
of themselves, incapable of giving us any distinct and satisfactory
account of the origin of the universe, or of its parts. We need not
wonder, then, at any particular instance of this incapacity; as, for
example, that of which we have been speaking, the impossibility of
accounting by any natural means for the production of all the
successive tribes of plants and animals which have peopled the world
in the 573 various
stages of its progress, as geology teaches us. That they were, like
our own animal and vegetable contemporaries, profoundly adapted to the
condition in which they were placed, we have ample reason to believe;
but when we inquire whence they came into this our world, geology is
silent. The mystery of creation is not within the range of her
legitimate territory; she says nothing, but she points upwards.
Sect. 6.—The Hypothesis of the
regular Creation and Extinction of Species.
1. Creation of Species.—We have already seen, how
untenable, as a physiological doctrine, is the principle of the
transmutability and progressive tendency of species; and therefore,
when we come to apply to theoretical geology the principles of the
present chapter, this portion of the subject will easily be disposed
of. I hardly know whether I can state that there is any other
principle which has been applied to the solution of the geological
problem, and which, therefore, as a general truth, ought to be
considered here. Mr. Lyell, indeed, has spoken89 of an
hypothesis that “the successive creation of species may constitute a
regular part of the economy of nature:” but he has nowhere, I think,
so described this process as to make it appear in what department of
science we are to place the hypothesis. Are these new species created
by the production, at long intervals, of an offspring different in
species from the parents? Or are the species so created produced
without parents? Are they gradually evolved from some embryo
substance? or do they suddenly start from the ground, as in the
creation of the poet?

. . . . . . . Perfect
forms
Limbed and full-grown: out of the ground up
rose
As from his lair, the wild beast where he
wons
In forest wild, in thicket, brake, or
den; . . .
The grassy clods now calved; now half
appeared
The tawny lion, pawing to get free
His hinder parts; then springs as broke from
bounds,
And rampant shakes his brinded mane; &c.
&c.
Paradise Lost, B. vii.

89 B. iii. c.
xi. p. 234.
Some selection of one of these forms of the hypothesis, rather than
the others, with evidence for the selection, is requisite to entitle
us to 574 place it
among the known causes of change which in this chapter we are
considering. The bare conviction that a creation of species has taken
place, whether once or many times, so long as it is unconnected with
our organical sciences, is a tenet of Natural Theology rather than of
Physical Philosophy.
[2nd Ed.] [Mr. Lyell has explained his theory90 by supposing
man to people a great desert, introducing into it living plants and
animals: and he has traced, in a very interesting manner, the results
of such a hypothesis on the distribution of vegetable and animal
species. But he supposes the agents who do this, before they import
species into particular localities, to study attentively the climate
and other physical conditions of each spot, and to use various
precautions. It is on account of the notion of design thus introduced
that I have, above, described this opinion as rather a tenet of
Natural Theology than of Physical Philosophy.
90 B.  iii.
c. viii. p. 166.
Mr. Edward Forbes has published some highly interesting
speculations on the distribution of existing species of animals and
plants. It appears that the manner in which animal and vegetable forms
are now diffused requires us to assume centres from which the
diffusion took place by no means limited by the present divisions of
continents and islands. The changes of land and water which have thus
occurred since the existing species were placed on the earth must have
been very extensive, and perhaps reach into the glacial period of
which I have spoken above.91
91 See, in Memoirs of the
Geological Survey of Great Britain, vol. i. p. 336, Professor
Forbes’s Memoir “On the Connection between the Distribution of the
existing Fauna and Flora of the British Isles, and the Geological
Changes which have affected their area, especially during the epoch of
the Northern Drift.”
According to Mr. Forbes’s views, for which he has offered a great
body of very striking and converging reasons, the present vegetable
and animal population of the British Isles is to be accounted for by
the following series of events. The marine deposits of the
meiocine formation were elevated into a great Atlantic
continent, yet separate from what is now America, and having its
western shore where now the great semi-circular belt of gulf-weed
ranges from the 15th to the 45th parallel of latitude. This continent
then became stocked with life, and of its vegetable population, the
flora of the west of Ireland, which has many points in common with the
flora of Spain and the 575 Atlantic islands (the Asturian
flora), is the record. The region between Spain and Ireland, and the
rest of this meiocene continent, was destroyed by some geological
movement, but there were left traces of the connexion which still
remain. Eastwards of the flora just mentioned, there is a flora common
to Devon and Cornwall, to the south-east part of Ireland, the Channel
Isles, and the adjacent provinces of France;—a flora passing to
a southern character; and having its course marked by the remains of a
great rocky barrier, the destruction of which probably took place
anterior to the formation of the narrower part of the channel.
Eastward from this Devon or Norman flora, again, we have
the Kentish flora, which is an extension of the flora of
North-western France, insulated by the breach which formed the straits
of Dover. Then came the Glacial period, when the east of
England and the north of Europe were submerged, the northern drift was
distributed, and England was reduced to a chain of islands or ridges,
formed by the mountains of Wales, Cumberland, and Scotland, which were
connected with the land of Scandinavia. This was the period of
glaciers, of the dispersion of boulders, of the grooving and
scratching of rocks as they are now found. The climate being then much
colder than it now is, the flora, even down to the water’s edge,
consisted of what are now Alpine plants; and this Alpine flora
is common to Scandinavia and to our mountain-summits. And these plants
kept their places, when, by the elevation of the land, the whole of
the present German Ocean became a continent connecting Britain with
central Europe. For the increased elevation of their stations
counterbalanced the diminished cold of the succeeding period. Along
the dry bed of the German Sea, thus elevated, the principal part of
the existing flora of England, the Germanic flora, migrated. A
large portion of our existing animal population also came over through
the same region; and along with those, came hyenas, tigers,
rhinoceros, aurochs, elk, wolves, beavers, which are extinct in
Britain, and other animals which are extinct altogether, as the
primigenian elephant or mammoth. But then, again, the German Ocean and
the Irish Channel were scooped out; and the climate again changed. In
our islands, so detached, many of the larger beasts perished, and
their bones were covered up in peat-mosses and caves, where we find
them. This distinguished naturalist has further shown that the
population of the sea lends itself to the same view. Mr. Forbes says
that the writings of Mr. Smith, of Jordan-hill, “On the last Changes
in the relative Levels of the Land and Sea in the British Islands,”
published in the Memoirs of the 576 Wernerian Society for
1837–8, must be esteemed the foundation of a critical
investigation of this subject in Britain.]
2. Extinction of Species.—With regard to the
extinction of species Mr. Lyell has propounded a doctrine which is
deserving of great attention here. Brocchi, when he had satisfied
himself, by examination of the Sub-Apennines, that about half the
species which had lived at the period of their deposition, had since
become extinct, suggested as a possible cause for this occurrence,
that the vital energies of a species, like that of an individual,
might gradually decay in the progress of time and of generations, till
at last the prolific power might fail, and the species wither away.
Such a property would be conceivable as a physiological fact; for we
see something of the kind in fruit-trees propagated by cuttings: after
some time, the stock appears to wear out, and loses its peculiar
qualities. But we have no sufficient evidence that this is the case in
generations of creatures continued by the reproductive powers. Mr.
Lyell conceives, that, without admitting any inherent constitutional
tendency to deteriorate, the misfortunes to which plants and animals
are exposed by the change of the physical circumstances of the earth,
by the alteration of land and water, and by the changes of climate,
must very frequently occasion the loss of several species. We have
historical evidence of the extinction of one conspicuous species, the
Dodo, a bird of large size and singular form, which inhabited the Isle
of France when that island was first discovered, and which now no
longer exists. Several other species of animals and plants seem to be
in the course of vanishing from the face of the earth, even under our
own observation. And taking into account the greater changes of the
surface of the globe which geology compels us to assume, we may
imagine many or all the existing species of living things to be
extirpated. If, for instance, that reduction of the climate of the
earth which appears, from geological evidence, to have taken place
already, be supposed to go on much further, the advancing snow and
cold of the polar regions may destroy the greater part of our plants
and animals, and drive the remainder, or those of them which possess
the requisite faculties of migration and accommodation, to seek an
asylum near the equator. And if we suppose the temperature of the
earth to be still further reduced, this zone of now-existing life,
having no further place of refuge, will perish, and the whole earth
will be tenanted, if at all, by a new creation. Other causes might
produce the same effect as a change of climate; and, without supposing
such causes to affect the whole globe, it is easy to 577 imagine circumstances
such as might entirely disturb the equilibrium which the powers of
diffusion of different species have produced;—might give to some
the opportunity of invading and conquering the domain of others; and
in the end, the means of entirely suppressing them, and establishing
themselves in their place.
That this extirpation of certain species, which, as we have seen,
happens in a few cases under common circumstances, might happen upon a
greater scale, if the range of external changes were to be much
enlarged, cannot be doubted. The extent, therefore, to which natural
causes may account for the extinction of species, will depend upon the
amount of change which we suppose in the physical conditions of the
earth. It must be a task of extreme difficulty to estimate the effect
upon the organic world, even if the physical circumstances were given.
To determine the physical condition to which a given state of the
earth would give rise, I have already noted as another very difficult
problem. Yet these two problems must be solved, in order to enable us
to judge of the sufficiency of any hypothesis of the extinction of
species; and in the mean time, for the mode in which new species come
into the places of those which are extinguished, we have (as we have
seen) no hypothesis which physiology can, for a moment, sanction.
Sect. 7.—The Imbedding of Organic
Remains.
There is still one portion of
the Dynamics of Geology, a branch of great and manifest importance,
which I have to notice, but upon which I need only speak very briefly.
The mode in which the spoils of existing plants and animals are
imbedded in the deposits now forming, is a subject which has naturally
attracted the attention of geologists. During the controversy which
took place in Italy respecting the fossils of the Sub-Apennine hills,
Vitaliano Donati,92 in 1750, undertook an examination of
the Adriatic, and found that deposits containing shells and corals,
extremely resembling the strata of the hills, were there in the act of
formation. But without dwelling on other observations of like kind, I
may state that Mr. Lyell has treated this subject, and all the topics
connected with it, in a very full and satisfactory manner. He has
explained,93 by an excellent collection of
illustrative facts, how deposits of various substance and contents are
formed; how plants and animals become fossil in peat, in blown sand,
in volcanic matter, in 578 alluvial soil, in caves, and in the beds
of lakes and seas. This exposition is of the most instructive
character, as a means of obtaining right conclusions concerning the
causes of geological phenomena. Indeed, in many cases, the similarity
of past effects with operations now going on, is so complete, that
they may be considered as identical; and the discussion of such cases
belongs, at the same time, to Geological Dynamics and to Physical
Geology; just as the problem of the fall of meteorolites may be
considered as belonging alike to mechanics and to physical astronomy.
The growth of modern peat-mosses, for example, fully explains the
formation of the most ancient: objects are buried in the same manner
in the ejections of active and of extinct volcanoes; within the limits
of history, many estuaries have been filled up; and in the deposits
which have occupied these places, are strata containing shells,94 as in the older formations.
92 Lyell, B.  i. c. iii. p. 67. (4th ed.)
93 B.  iii.
c. xiii. xiv. xv. xvi. xvii.
94 Lyell, B.  iii. c. xvii. p. 286. See also his Address to the
Geological Society in 1837, for an account of the Researches of Mr.
Stokes and of Professor Göppert, on the lapidification of
vegetables.


PHYSICAL GEOLOGY.
</div></body></text></TEI>