<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="8">CHAPTER VI.
In the evening of the same day, my beloved Marguerite
arrived unexpectedly at Paris. In the beginning of our
separation, I had been to the last degree punctual in my
letters. I had no pleasure so great, as retiring to my
closet, and pouring out my soul to the most adorable of
women. By degrees I relaxed in punctuality. Ordinary
occupations, however closely pursued, have a method in
them, that easily combines with regularity in points of an
incidental nature. But gaming, when pursued with avidity,[60]
subverts all order, and forces every avocation from the
place assigned it. When my insane project of supplying
the inadequateness of my fortune by this expedient began
to produce an effect exactly opposite, I could not, but with
the extremest difficulty, string my mind to write to the
mistress of my soul. I endeavoured not to think, with
distinctness and attention, of the persons whose happiness
was most nearly involved with mine. I said to myself,
Yet another venture must be tried; fortune shall change
the animosity with which she has lately pursued me; I
will repair the breaches that have been sustained; and I
shall then return with tenfold avidity to subjects that at
present I dare not fix my mind upon. My letters were
accordingly short, unfrequent, and unsatisfactory; and
those of Marguerite discovered increasing anguish, perturbation,
and anxiety. What a change in the minds of
both had the lapse of a few months produced! Not that
my attachment had suffered the diminution of a single
particle; but that attachment, which had lately been the
source of our mutual felicity, was now fraught only with
distress. My mind was filled with horrors; and Marguerite
expected from me an encouragement and consolation in
absence, which, alas, I had it not in my power to give!
I had now continued in Paris for a time vastly greater
than I had originally proposed. After having remained
more than ten days without receiving one word of intelligence,
a letter of mine was delivered to Marguerite, more
short, mysterious, and distressing to her feelings, than any
that had preceded. The ten days’ silence, from me who
at first had never missed an opportunity of pouring out
my soul to her, and contributing to her pleasure, was exquisitely
painful. There is scarcely any thing that produces
such a sickness of the heart as the repeated prorogation
of hope. But, when the letter arrived that had
been so anxiously looked for, when the hand-writing of
the superscription was recognised, when the letter was
treasured up for the impatiently desired moment of solitude,
that the sacred emotions of the heart might suffer no
interruption, and when it at last appeared so cold, so
ominous, so withering to the buds of affection, the determination[61]
of Marguerite was speedily formed. The relations
that bound us together were of too mighty a value
to be dispensed or to be trifled with. She felt them as
the very cords of existence. For ten years she had known
no solace that was disconnected from my idea, no care but
of our own happiness and that of our offspring. Benevolent
she was almost beyond human example, and interested
for the welfare of all she knew; but these were
brief and mutable concerns; they were not incorporated
with the stamina of her existence. I was the whole world
to her; she had no idea of satisfaction without me. Her
firmness had been sufficiently tried by the interposal of
separation and absence. How was she to interpret the
obscurity that had now arisen? Had I forgotten my
family and my wife? Had I been corrupted and debauched
by that Paris, the effects of which upon my
character her father had so deeply apprehended? Had I,
in contempt of every thing sacred, entered into some new
attachment? Had the attractions of some new beauty in
the metropolis made me indifferent to the virtue of my
children, and the life of their mother? Perhaps the length
of our attachment had infected me with satiety, and the
inconstancy of my temper had been roused by the charms
of novelty. Perhaps the certainty of her kindness and
regard had no longer allurements for me; and I might be
excited to the pursuit of another by the pleasures of hope
combined with uncertainty, and of a coyness, that seemed
to promise compliance hereafter, even while it pronounced
a present denial. These were the images that haunted her
mind; they engendered all the wildness, and all the torments,
of a delirious paroxysm; she resolved that no time
should be sacrificed to needless uncertainty, and that no
effort of hers should be unexerted to prevent the mischief
she feared.
It was evening when she arrived. I was upon the
point of repairing to that scene of nightly resort, the source
of all my guilt and all my miseries. I enquired of my
son’s valet where he was, and how he had been in the
course of the day. He was gone to bed: he had appeared
unusually sad, sometimes in tears; and, while he was[62]
undressing, had sighed deeply two or three times. While
I was collecting this account in my own apartment, the
gates of the hotel opened, and a number of horsemen
entered the court-yard. I was somewhat surprised; because,
though I was accustomed to see much company,
few of my acquaintance visited me at so late an hour,
except on the evenings appropriated to receive them. I
crossed the saloon to enquire. One of the servants exclaimed,
“It is Bernardin’s voice: it must be my mistress
that is come!”
Nothing could be further from my mind than the
thought of her arrival. I flew through the passage; I
was on the spot the moment that the servant prepared to
conduct his mistress from the litter; I received Marguerite
in my arms, and led her into the house. If I had expected
her arrival, I should infallibly have met her at this
moment with anxiety and confusion; I should have gone
round the circle of my thoughts, and should not have had
confidence to encounter the beam of her eye. But the
event was so unexpected as to drive all other ideas from
my mind; and, in consequence, I enjoyed several minutes,—ages,
rather let me say,—of the sincerest transport.
I kissed the mistress of my soul with ecstasy; I gazed
upon her well known lineaments and features; I listened
to the pleasing melody of her voice; I was intoxicated
with delight. Upon occasions like this, it seems as if
every former joy that had marked the various periods of
intercourse distilled its very spirit and essence, to compose
a draught, ten times more delicious and refined than
had ever before been tasted. Our meeting was like awaking
from the dead; it was the emancipation of the weary
captive, who exchanges the dungeon’s gloom for the lustre
of the morning, and who feels a celestial exhilaration of
heart, the very memory of which had been insensibly wearing
away from his treacherous brain. All my senses partook
of the rapture. Marguerite seemed to shed ambrosial
odours round her; her touch was thrilling; her lips were
nectar; her figure was that of a descended deity!
Her pleasure was not less than mine. It is indeed absurd,
it may be termed profanation, to talk of solitary[63]
pleasure. No sensation ordinarily distinguished by that
epithet can endure the test of a moment’s inspection, when
compared with a social enjoyment. It is then only that a
man is truly pleased, when pulse replies to pulse, when the
eyes discourse eloquently to each other, when in responsive
tones and words the soul is communicated. Altogether, we
are conscious of a sober, a chaste, and dignified intoxication,
an elevation of spirit, that does not bereave the mind of itself,
and that endures long enough for us to analyse and savour
the causes of our joy.
For some time we rested on a sofa, each filled and
occupied with the observation of the other. My eyes assured
Marguerite of the constancy of my affection; my
kisses were those of chaste, undivided, entire attachment.
Our words were insignificant and idle, the broken and
incoherent phrases of a happiness that could not be silent.
At length Marguerite exclaimed, “It is enough; my fears
are vanished; I have no questions to ask, no doubts to remove.
Yet why, my Reginald, did you suffer those doubts
to gather, those fears to accumulate? Surely you knew
the singleness of my affection! How many painful days
and hours might you have saved me, almost by a word!”
“Forgive me, my love,” replied I. “Waste not the golden
hour of meeting in recrimination! Feeling, as your angelic
goodness now makes me feel, I wonder at myself, that I
could for one moment have consented to separation; that I
could have thought any thing but this existence; or that,
having experienced the joys that you have bestowed, I
could lose all image of the past, and, dwelling in a desert,
imagine it paradise!”
“Recrimination!” rejoined Marguerite. “No, my love;
you make me too happy to leave room for any thing but
gratitude and affection! Forgive me, Reginald, if I pretend
that, in meeting you thus, I find myself your superior
in happiness and love. You only awake from lethargy,
forgetfulness of yourself and—of me; but I awake from
anguish, a separation, that I desired not at first, and of
which I hourly wished to see an end, from doubts that
would intrude, and refused to be expelled, from the incessant
contemplation and regret of a felicity, once possessed,[64]
but possessed no longer! Melancholy ideas, gloomy prognostics
overspread my sleepless nights, and bedewed my
pillow with tears! This it is, that, at last, has driven me
from my family and daughters, resolved to obtain the certainty
of despair, or the dispersion of my fears! Have I
known all this, and think you that I do not enjoy with rapture
this blissful moment?”
While we were thus conversing, Charles entered the
room. He was not yet asleep when his mother arrived:
he heard her voice; and hastened to put on his clothes,
that he might rush into her arms. The pleasure Marguerite
had conceived from our meeting, and the affectionate
serenity that had taken possession of her soul, infused
double ardour into the embraces she bestowed on her son.
He gazed earnestly in her face; he kissed her with fervency;
but was silent.
“Why, Charles!” said she, “what is the matter with you?
Are not you glad to see me?”
“That I am, mamma! So glad, that I do not know what
to do with myself! I was afraid I never should have been
glad again!”
“Pooh, boy! what do you mean? You were not mother-sick,
were you?”
“Yes, indeed, I was sick, sick at heart! Not that I am
a coward! I think that I could have been satisfied to have
been without either my father or you for a little while.
But papa is so altered, you cannot think! He never smiles
and looks happy; and, when I see him, instead of making
me joyful, as it used to do, it makes me sad!”
“Dear Reginald!” replied the mother, looking at me, “is
it possible that, while my heart was haunted with fear and
suspicions, separation alone should have had such an effect
on you?”
“I dare say it was that,” interposed the boy. “I could
not make papa smile, all I could do: but, now you are come,
he will soon be well! How much he must love you,
mamma!”
The artless prattle of my son struck anguish to my soul;
and awakened a whole train of tormenting thoughts. Alas!
thought I, can it indeed be love, that thus contrives against[65]
the peace of its object? Would to God, my child! that
my thoughts were as simple and pure as thy innocent
bosom!
“And yet,” added the boy, as if recollecting himself, “if
he could not see you, sure that was no reason for him to avoid
me? He seemed as much afraid of me, as I have seen
some of my play-fellows of a snake! Indeed, mamma, it
was a sad thing that, when I wanted him to kiss me and
press me to his bosom, he shrunk away from me! There
now! it was just so, as he looks now, that papa used to
frown upon me, I cannot tell how often! Now is not that
ugly, mamma?”
I could no longer govern the tumult of my thoughts.
“Peace, urchin!” cried I. “Why did you come to mar
the transport of our meeting? Just now, Marguerite, I
forgot myself, and was happy! Now all the villain rises
in my soul!”
My wife was so astonished at the perturbation of my
manner, and at the words I uttered, that she was scarcely
able to articulate. “Reginald!” in broken accents she exclaimed—“my
love!—my husband!”
“No matter,” said I. “It shall yet be well! My heart
assures me it shall!—Be not disturbed, my love! I will
never cause you a moment’s anguish! I would sooner die a
thousand deaths!—Forget the odious thoughts that poor
Charles has excited in me so unseasonably! They were
mere idle words! Depend upon it they were!”
While I was speaking, Marguerite hid her face upon the
sofa. I took her hand, and by my caresses endeavoured to
soothe and compose her. At length, turning to me,—“Reginald!”
said she, in a voice of anguish, “do you then
endeavour to hide from me the real state of your thoughts?
Was the joy that attended our meeting perishable and deceitful?
After ten years of unbounded affection and confidence,
am I denied to be the partner of your bosom?”
“No, Marguerite, no! this was but the thought of a moment!
By to-morrow’s dawn it shall have no existence in
my bosom. Why should I torment you with what so soon
shall have no existence to myself? Meanwhile, be assured,
my love (instead of suffering diminution) is more full, more
fervent and entire, than it ever was!”
[66]
At this instant my mind experienced an extraordinary impression.
Instead of being weaned, by the presence of this
admirable woman, from my passion for gaming, it became
stronger than ever. If Charles had not entered at the critical
moment he did, I should have remained with Marguerite,
and, amidst the so long untasted solace of love, have,
at least for this night, forgotten my cares. But that occurrence
had overturned every thing, had uncovered the wounds
of my bosom, and awakened conceptions that refused to be
laid to sleep again. The arms of my wife, that were about
to embrace me, suddenly became to me a nest of scorpions.
I could as soon have rested and enjoyed myself upon the
top of Vesuvius, when it flamed. New as I was to this
species of anguish, tranquilly and full of virtuous contentment
as I had hitherto passed the years of my married state,
the pangs of a guilty conscience I was wholly unable to bear.
I rose from my seat, and was upon the point of quitting
the room.
Marguerite perceived by my manner that there was something
extraordinary passing in my mind. “Where are you
going, Reginald?” said she.
I answered with a slight nod. “Not far,” I replied,
attempting an air of apathy and unconcern.
She was not satisfied. “You are not going out?” she
enquired.
I returned to where I had been sitting. “My love, I
was going out at the moment of your arrival. It is necessary,
I assure you. I hope I shall soon be back. I am
sorry I am obliged to leave you. Compose yourself. You
are in want of rest, and had better go to bed.”
“Stop, Reginald! Afford me a minute’s leisure before
you depart! Leave us, Charles! Good night, my dear
boy! Kiss me; remember that your mother is now in the
same house with you; and sleep in peace.”
The boy quitted the room.
“Reginald!” said the mother, “I have no wish to control
your desires, or be a spy upon your actions; but your
conduct seems so extraordinary in this instance, as to dispense
me from the observation of common rules. I have
always been a complying wife; I have never set myself in
contradiction to your will; I appeal to yourself for the[67]
truth of this. I despise, however, those delicacies, an adherence
to which would entail upon us the sacrifice of all
that is most valuable in human life. Can I shut my ears
upon the mysterious expressions which Charles’s complaints
have extorted from you? Can I be insensible to the extraordinary
purpose you declare of leaving me, when I have
yet been scarcely half an hour under the roof with you?
Before Charles came in, you seem to have entertained no
such design.”
“My love,” replied I, “how seriously you comment upon
the most insignificant incident! Is it extraordinary that your
unexpected arrival should at first have made me forget an
engagement that I now recollect?”
“St. Leon,” answered my wife, “before you indulge in
surprise at my earnestness, recollect the circumstances that
immediately preceded it. Through successive weeks I have
waited for some satisfactory and agreeable intelligence from
you. I had a right before this to have expected your return.
Uncertainty and a thousand fearful apprehensions have at
length driven me from my home, and brought me to Paris.
I am come here for satisfaction to my doubts, and peace to
my anxious heart. Wonder not, therefore, if you find
something more earnest and determined in my proceedings
now, than upon ordinary occasions. Give me, I conjure
you, give me ease and relief, if you are able! If not, at least
allow me this consolation, to know the worst!”
“Be pacified, Marguerite!” I rejoined. “I am grieved,
Heaven knows how deeply grieved, to have occasioned you
a moment’s pain. But, since you lay so much stress upon
this circumstance, depend upon it, I will postpone the
business I was going about, and stay with you.”
This concession, voluntary and sincere, produced an
effect that I had not foreseen. Marguerite gazed for a
moment in my face, and then threw herself upon my
neck.
“Forgive me, my beloved husband!” she cried. “You
indeed make me ashamed of myself. I feel myself inexcusable.
I feel that I have been brooding over imaginary
evils, and creating the misery that corroded my heart.
How inexpressibly you rise my superior! But I will conquer[68]
my weakness. I insist upon your going to the engagement
you have made, and will henceforth place the
most entire confidence in your prudence and honour.”
Every word of this speech was a dagger to my heart.
What were my feelings, while this admirable woman was
taking shame to herself for her suspicions, and pouring out
her soul in commendation of my integrity! I looked inward,
and found every thing there the reverse of her
apprehension, a scene of desolation and remorse. I embraced
her in silence. My heart panted upon her bosom,
and seemed bursting with a secret that it was death to reveal.
I ought, in return for her generosity, to have given
up my feigned engagement, and devoted this night at least
to console and pacify her. But I could not, and I dared
not. The wound of my bosom was opened, and would
not be closed. The more I loved her for her confidence,
the less I could endure myself in her presence. To play
the hypocrite for so many hours, to assume a face of tranquillity
and joy while all within was tumult and horror,
was a task too mighty for human powers to execute. I
accepted of Marguerite’s permission, and left her. Even
in the short interval before I quitted the house, my carriage
was near to betraying me. I could perceive her watchful
of my countenance, as if again suspicious that some fatal
secret lurked in my mind. She said nothing further upon
the subject however, and I presently escaped the inquisition
of her eye.
It is scarcely necessary to describe the state of my mind
as I passed along the streets. It is sufficient to say that
every thing I had felt before from the passion of gaming
was trivial to the sensations that now occupied me. Now
first it stood confessed before me, a demon that poisoned all
my joys, that changed the transport of a meeting with the
adored of my soul into anguish, that drove me forth from
her yet untasted charms a solitary wanderer on the face of
the earth. My busy soul drew forth at length the picture
of what this encounter would have been, if it had been
sanctified with the stamp of conscious innocence. At one
moment I felt myself the most accursed of mankind; I
believed that he who could find, as I did, barrenness and[69]
blasting in the choicest of Heaven’s blessings, must be
miserable beyond precedent or hope. Shortly after, however,
I reviewed again the image of my poison, and found
in it the promise of a cure. The more desperate my case
appeared to me, with the greater insanity of expectation
did I assure myself that this one night should retrieve all
my misfortunes. In giving to it this destination indeed, I
should afflict the gentle bosom of my wife but too probably
with some hours of uneasiness. But the event would
richly repay her for so transitory a suffering; I would
then open my whole mind to her. I would practise no
more reserves; I should no longer be driven to the refuge
of a vile hypocrisy. I would bid farewell to the frowns
and the caresses of fortune. I would require of her no
further kindnesses. If I were incapable myself of a rigid
economy, I would commit implicitly to Marguerite the
disposal of my income, whom I knew to be every way
qualified for the office. With these reflections I nerved
my mind to the most decisive adventures.
Why should I enter into a long detail of the incidents
of this crisis? Soon, though not immediately, I began to
lose considerable sums. I brought with me in the first instance
a penetrating eye, a collected mind, an intellect
prepared for unintermitted exertion. Misfortune subverted
all this. My eye grew wild, my soul tempestuous,
my thoughts incoherent and distracted. I was incapable of
any thing judicious; but I was determined to persevere.
I played till morning, nor could the light of morning induce
me to desist. The setting sun of that day beheld me
a beggar!
There is a degree of misery, which, as it admits of no
description, so does it leave no distinct traces in the memory.
It seems as if the weakness of the human mind
alike incapacitated it to support the delirium of joy, and
the extremity of sorrow. Of what immediately succeeded
the period to which I have conducted my narrative I have
no recollection, but a horror beyond all names of horror,
wild, inexplicable, unintelligible. Let no one, however,
imagine, that the temporary desertion of the soul is any
alleviation of its misery. The mind that sinks under its[70]
suffering does not by that conduct shake off its burden.
Rather, ten thousand times rather, would I endure all the
calamities that have ever yet received a name, the sensations
and history of which are capable of being delineated, than
sustain that which has no words by which to express itself,
and the conception of which must be trusted solely to the
faculties and sympathy of the reader. Where is the cold
and inapprehensive spirit that talks of madness as a refuge
from sorrow? Oh, dull and unconceiving beyond all
belief! I cannot speak of every species of madness; but
I also have been mad! This I know, that there is a
vacancy of soul, where all appears buried in stupidity, and
scarcely deserves the name of thought, that is more intolerable
than the bitterest reflections. This I know, that
there is an incoherence, in which the mind seems to wander
without rudder and pilot, that laughs to scorn the superstitious
fictions of designing priests. Oh, how many
sleepless days and weeks did I endure! the thoughts frantic,
the tongue raving! While we can still adhere, if I
may so express myself, to the method of misery, there is a
sort of nameless complacency that lurks under all that we
can endure. We are still conscious that we are men; we
wonder at and admire our powers of being miserable; but,
when the masts and tackle of the intellectual vessel are all
swept away, then is the true sadness. We have no consciousness
to sustain us, no sentiment of dignity, no secret
admiration of what we are, still clinging to our hearts.
All this I venture to affirm, with the full recollection
of what I suffered, when restored to my senses, present to
my mind.
When the account was closed, and the loss of my last
stake had finished the scene, I rose, and, quitting the fatal
spot where these transactions had passed, entered the street,
with a heart oppressed, and a bursting head. My eyes
glared, but I saw nothing, and could think of nothing. It
was already nearly dark; and the day which had been
tempestuous, was succeeded by a heavy and settled rain. I
wandered for some time, not knowing whither I went. My
pace, which had at first been slow, gradually increased, and
I traversed the whole city with a hurried and impatient[71]
step. The streets which had contained few persons at
first, gradually lost those few. I was almost alone. I saw
occasionally ragged and houseless misery shrinking under
the cover of a miserable shed; I saw the midnight robber,
watching for his prey, and ready to start upon the unwary
passenger. From me he fled; there was something in my
air that impelled even desperate violation to shrink from
the encounter. I continued this incessant, unmeaning exertion
for hours. At length, by an accidental glance of the
eye, I found myself at the gate of my own hotel. Heedless
of what I did, I entered; and, as nature was now completely
exhausted within me, sunk down in a sort of insensibility
at the foot of the grand staircase.
This stupor, after a considerable interval, gradually subsided.
I opened my eyes, and saw various figures flitting
about me; but I seemed to myself equally incapable of
collecting my thoughts, and of speech. My understanding
indeed shortly became clearer, but an insuperable reluctance
to voluntary exertion hung upon me. I explained myself
only in monosyllables; a sort of instinctive terror of disclosing
what had passed to the admirable woman I had
sacrificed maintained in me this perpetual reserve. For
several days together I sat from morning till night in one
immovable posture, nor was any thing of force enough to
awaken me to exertion.
</div></body></text></TEI>