<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="18">

CHAPTER IX.
OF PERCEPTION.

1. Perception the first simple Idea of Reflection.


PERCEPTION, as it is the first faculty of the mind exercised about our ideas;
so it is the first and simplest idea we have from reflection, and is by some
called thinking in general. Though thinking, in the propriety of the English
tongue, signifies that sort of operation in the mind about its ideas, wherein
the mind is active; where it, with some degree of voluntary attention,
considers anything. For in bare naked perception, the mind is, for the most
part, only passive; and what it perceives, it cannot avoid perceiving.


2. Reflection alone can give us the idea of what perception is.


What perception is, every one will know better by reflecting on what he does
himself, when he sees, hears, feels, &c., or thinks, than by any discourse
of mine. Whoever reflects on what passes in his own mind cannot miss it. And if
he does not reflect, all the words in the world cannot make him have any notion
of it.


3. Arises in sensation only when the mind notices the organic impression.


This is certain, that whatever alterations are made in the body, if they reach
not the mind; whatever impressions are made on the outward parts, if they are
not taken notice of within, there is no perception. Fire may burn our bodies
with no other effect than it does a billet, unless the motion be continued to
the brain, and there the sense of heat, or idea of pain, be produced in the
mind; wherein consists actual perception.


4. Impulse on the organ insufficient.


How often may a man observe in himself, that whilst his mind is intently
employed in the contemplation of some objects, and curiously surveying some
ideas that are there, it takes no notice of impressions of sounding bodies made
upon the organ of hearing, with the same alteration that uses to be for the
producing the idea of sound? A sufficient impulse there may be on the organ;
but it not reaching the observation of the mind, there follows no perception:
and though the motion that uses to produce the idea of sound be made in the
ear, yet no sound is heard. Want of sensation, in this case, is not through any
defect in the organ, or that the man’s ears are less affected than at other
times when he does hear but that which uses to produce the idea, though
conveyed in by the usual organ, not being taken notice of in the understanding,
and so imprinting no idea in the mind, there follows no sensation. So that
wherever there is sense of perception, there some idea is actually produced,
and present in the understanding.


5. Children, though they may have Ideas in the Womb, have none innate.


Therefore I doubt not but children, by the exercise of their senses about
objects that affect them in the womb receive some few ideas before they are
born, as the unavoidable effects, either of the bodies that environ them, or
else of those wants or diseases they suffer; amongst which (if one may
conjecture concerning things not very capable of examination) I think the ideas
of hunger and warmth are two: which probably are some of the first that
children have, and which they scarce ever part with again.


6. The effects of Sensation in the womb.


But though it be reasonable to imagine that children receive some ideas before
they come into the world, yet these simple ideas are far from those INNATE
PRINCIPLES which some contend for, and we, above, have rejected. These here
mentioned, being the effects of sensation, are only from some affections of the
body, which happen to them there, and so depend on something exterior to the
mind; no otherwise differing in their manner of production from other ideas
derived from sense, but only in the precedency of time. Whereas those innate
principles are supposed to be quite of another nature; not coming into the mind
by any accidental alterations in, or operations on the body; but, as it were,
original characters impressed upon it, in the very first moment of its being
and constitution.


7. Which Ideas appear first is not evident, nor important.


As there are some ideas which we may reasonably suppose may be introduced into
the minds of children in the womb, subservient to the necessities of their life
and being there: so, after they are born, those ideas are the earliest
imprinted which happen to be the sensible qualities which first occur to them;
amongst which light is not the least considerable, nor of the weakest efficacy.
And how covetous the mind is to be furnished with all such ideas as have no
pain accompanying them, may be a little guessed by what is observable in
children new-born; who always turn their eyes to that part from whence the
light comes, lay them how you please. But the ideas that are most familiar at
first, being various according to the divers circumstances of children’s first
entertainment in the world, the order wherein the several ideas come at first
into the mind is very various, and uncertain also; neither is it much material
to know it.


8. Sensations often changed by the Judgment.


We are further to consider concerning perception, that the ideas we receive by
sensation are often, in grown people, altered by the judgment, without our
taking notice of it. When we set before our eyes a round globe of any uniform
colour, v.g. gold, alabaster, or jet, it is certain that the idea thereby
imprinted on our mind is of a flat circle, variously shadowed, with several
degrees of light and brightness coming to our eyes. But we having, by use, been
accustomed to perceive what kind of appearance convex bodies are wont to make
in us; what alterations are made in the reflections of light by the difference
of the sensible figures of bodies;—the judgment presently, by an habitual
custom, alters the appearances into their causes. So that from that which is
truly variety of shadow or colour, collecting the figure, it makes it pass for
a mark of figure, and frames to itself the perception of a convex figure and an
uniform colour; when the idea we receive from thence is only a plane variously
coloured, as is evident in painting. To which purpose I shall here insert a
problem of that very ingenious and studious promoter of real knowledge, the
learned and worthy Mr. Molineux, which he was pleased to send me in a letter
some months since; and it is this:—“Suppose a man BORN blind, and now
adult, and taught by his TOUCH to distinguish between a cube and a sphere of
the same metal, and nighly of the same bigness, so as to tell, when he felt one
and the other, which is the cube, which the sphere. Suppose then the cube and
sphere placed on a table, and the blind man be made to see: quaere, whether BY
HIS SIGHT, BEFORE HE TOUCHED THEM, he could now distinguish and tell which is
the globe, which the cube?” To which the acute and judicious proposer answers,
“Not. For, though he has obtained the experience of how a globe, how a cube
affects his touch, yet he has not yet obtained the experience, that what
affects his touch so or so, must affect his sight so or so; or that a
protuberant angle in the cube, that pressed his hand unequally, shall appear to
his eye as it does in the cube.”—I agree with this thinking gentleman,
whom I am proud to call my friend, in his answer to this problem; and am of
opinion that the blind man, at first sight, would not be able with certainty to
say which was the globe, which the cube, whilst he only saw them; though he
could unerringly name them by his touch, and certainly distinguish them by the
difference of their figures felt. This I have set down, and leave with my
reader, as an occasion for him to consider how much he may be beholden to
experience, improvement, and acquired notions, where he thinks he had not the
least use of, or help from them. And the rather, because this observing
gentleman further adds, that “having, upon the occasion of my book, proposed
this to divers very ingenious men, he hardly ever met with one that at first
gave the answer to it which he thinks true, till by hearing his reasons they
were convinced.”


9. This judgement apt to be mistaken for direct perception.


But this is not, I think, usual in any of our ideas, but those received by
sight. Because sight, the most comprehensive of all our senses, conveying to
our minds the ideas of light and colours, which are peculiar only to that
sense; and also the far different ideas of space, figure, and motion, the
several varieties whereof change the appearances of its proper object, viz.
light and colours; we bring ourselves by use to judge of the one by the other.
This, in many cases by a settled habit,—in things whereof we have
frequent experience is performed so constantly and so quick, that we take that
for the perception of our sensation which is an idea formed by our judgment; so
that one, viz. that of sensation, serves only to excite the other, and is
scarce taken notice of itself;—as a man who reads or hears with attention
and understanding, takes little notice of the characters or sounds, but of the
ideas that are excited in him by them.


10. How, by Habit, ideas of Sensation are unconsciously changed into ideas of
Judgment.


Nor need we wonder that this is done with so little notice, if we consider how
quick the actions of the mind are performed. For, as itself is thought to take
up no space to have no extension; so its actions seem to require no time but
many of them seem to be crowded into an instant. I speak this in comparison to
the actions of the body. Any one may easily observe this in his own thoughts,
who will take the pains to reflect on them. How, as it were in an instant, do
our minds, with one glance, see all the parts of a demonstration, which may
very well be called a long one, if we consider the time it will require to put
it into words, and step by step show it another? Secondly, we shall not be so
much surprised that this is done in us with so little notice, if we consider
how the facility which we get of doing things, by a custom of doing, makes them
often pass in us without our notice. Habits, especially such as are begun very
early, come at last to produce actions in us, which often escape our
observation. How frequently do we, in a day, cover our eyes with our eyelids,
without perceiving that we are at all in the dark! Men that, by custom, have
got the use of a by-word, do almost in every sentence pronounce sounds which,
though taken notice of by others, they themselves neither hear nor observe. And
therefore it is not so strange, that our mind should often change the idea of
its sensation into that of its judgment, and make one serve only to excite the
other, without our taking notice of it.


11. Perception puts the difference between Animals and Vegetables.


This faculty of perception seems to me to be, that which puts the distinction
betwixt the animal kingdom and the inferior parts of nature. For, however
vegetables have, many of them, some degrees of motion, and upon the different
application of other bodies to them, do very briskly alter their figures and
motions, and so have obtained the name of sensitive plants, from a motion which
has some resemblance to that which in animals follows upon sensation: yet I
suppose it is all bare MECHANISM; and no otherwise produced than the turning of
a wild oat-beard, by the insinuation of the particles of moisture, or the
shortening of a rope, by the affusion of water. All which is done without any
sensation in the subject, or the having or receiving any ideas.


12. Perception in all animals.


Perception, I believe, is, in some degree, in all sorts of animals; though in
some possibly the avenues provided by nature for the reception of sensations
are so few, and the perception they are received with so obscure and dull, that
it comes extremely short of the quickness and variety of sensation which is in
other animals; but yet it is sufficient for, and wisely adapted to, the state
and condition of that sort of animals who are thus made. So that the wisdom and
goodness of the Maker plainly appear in all the parts of this stupendous
fabric, and all the several degrees and ranks of creatures in it.


13. According to their condition.


We may, I think, from the make of an oyster or cockle, reasonably conclude that
it has not so many, nor so quick senses as a man, or several other animals; nor
if it had, would it, in that state and incapacity of transferring itself from
one place to another, be bettered by them. What good would sight and hearing do
to a creature that cannot move itself to or from the objects wherein at a
distance it perceives good or evil? And would not quickness of sensation be an
inconvenience to an animal that must lie still where chance has once placed it,
and there receive the afflux of colder or warmer, clean or foul water, as it
happens to come to it?


14. Decay of perception in old age.


But yet I cannot but think there is some small dull perception, whereby they
are distinguished from perfect insensibility. And that this may be so, we have
plain instances, even in mankind itself. Take one in whom decrepit old age has
blotted out the memory of his past knowledge, and clearly wiped out the ideas
his mind was formerly stored with, and has, by destroying his sight, hearing,
and smell quite, and his taste to a great degree, stopped up almost all the
passages for new ones to enter; or if there be some of the inlets yet half
open, the impressions made are scarcely perceived, or not at all retained. How
far such an one (notwithstanding all that is boasted of innate principles) is
in his knowledge and intellectual faculties above the condition of a cockle or
an oyster, I leave to be considered. And if a man had passed sixty years in
such a state, as it is possible he might, as well as three days, I wonder what
difference there would be, in any intellectual perfections, between him and the
lowest degree of animals.


15. Perception the Inlet of all materials of Knowledge.


Perception then being the FIRST step and degree towards knowledge, and the
inlet of all the materials of it; the fewer senses any man, as well as any
other creature, hath; and the fewer and duller the impressions are that are
made by them; and the duller the faculties are that are employed about
them,—the more remote are they from that knowledge which is to be found
in some men. But this being in great variety of degrees (as may be perceived
amongst men) cannot certainly be discovered in the several species of animals,
much less in their particular individuals. It suffices me only to have remarked
here,—that perception is the first operation of all our intellectual
faculties, and the inlet of all knowledge in our minds. And I am apt too to
imagine, that it is perception, in the lowest degree of it, which puts the
boundaries between animals and the inferior ranks of creatures. But this I
mention only as my conjecture by the by; it being indifferent to the matter in
hand which way the learned shall determine of it.


</div></body></text></TEI>