<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Reflections on the Decline of Science in England</title><author>Babbage, Charles (1791-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>B. Fellowes</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="25">
      SECTION 1. OF THE NECESSITY THAT MEMBERS OF THE ROYAL SOCIETY SHOULD EXPRESS THEIR OPINIONS.
    

      One of the causes which has contributed to the success of the PARTY, is to
      be found in the great reluctance with which many of those whose names
      added lustre to the Society expressed their opinions, and the little
      firmness with which they maintained their objections. How many times have
      those whose activity was additionally stimulated by their interest,
      proposed measures which a few words might have checked; whilst the names
      of those whose culpable silence thus permitted the project to be matured,
      were immediately afterwards cited by their grateful coadjutors, as having
      sanctioned that which in their hearts they knew to be a job.
    

      Even in the few cases which have passed the limits of such forbearance,
      when the subject has been debated in the Council, more than one, more than
      two instances are known, where subsequent circumstances have occurred,
      which proved, with the most irresistible moral evidence, that members have
      spoken on one side of the question, and have voted on the contrary.
    

      This reluctance to oppose that which is disapproved, has been too
      extensively and too fatally prevalent for the interests of the Royal
      Society. It may partly be attributed to that reserved and retiring
      disposition, which frequently marks the man of real knowledge, as strongly
      as an officious interference and flippant manner do the charlatan, or the
      trader in science. Some portion of it is due to that improper deference
      which was long paid to every dictum of the President, and much of it to
      that natural indisposition to take trouble on any point in which a man's
      own interest is not immediately concerned. It is to be hoped, for the
      credit of that learned body, that no anticipation of the next feast of St.
      Andrew ever influenced the taciturnity of their disposition. [It may be
      necessary to inform those who are not members of the Royal Society, that
      this is the day on which those Fellows who choose, meet at Somerset House,
      to register the names of the Council and Officers the President has been
      pleased to appoint for the ensuing year; and who afterwards dine together,
      for the purpose of praising each other over wine, which, until within
      these few years, was PAID for out of the FUNDS of the Society. This abuse
      was attacked by an enterprising reformer, and of course defended by the
      coterie. It was, however, given up as too bad. The public may form some
      idea of the feeling which prevails in the Council, when they are informed
      that this practice was defended by one of the officers of the Society, on
      the ground that, if abolished, THE ASSISTANT SECRETARY WOULD LOSE HIS
      PERCENTAGE ON THE TAVERN BILLS.]
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>