<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="36">CHAPTER XXXVI.
WHETHER SPECIES HAVE A REAL EXISTENCE IN NATURE—continued.
Phenomena of hybrids—Hunter's opinions—Mules not strictly intermediate
between parent species—Hybrid plants—Experiments of Kölreuter and Wiegmann—Vegetable
hybrids prolific throughout several generations—Why rare
in a wild state—Decundolle on hybrid plants—The phenomena of hybrids
confirm the distinctness of species—Theory of the gradation in the intelligence
of animals as indicated by the facial angle—Doctrine that certain
organs of the fœtus in mammalia assume successively the forms of fish, reptile,
and bird—Recapitulation.
Phenomena of hybrids.—We have yet to consider another class of phenomena,
those relating to the production of hybrids, which have been
regarded in a very different light with reference to their bearing on the
question of the permanent distinctness of species; some naturalists considering
them as affording the strongest of all proofs in favor of the
reality of species; others, on the contrary, appealing to them as countenancing
the opposite doctrine, that all the varieties of organization and
instinct now exhibited in the animal and vegetable kingdoms may have
been propagated from a small number of original types.
In regard to the mammifers and birds it is found that no sexual
union will take place between races which are remote from each other
in their habits and organization; and it is only in species that are very
nearly allied that such unions produce offspring. It may be laid down
601
as a general rule, admitting of very few exceptions among quadrupeds,
that the hybrid progeny is sterile; and there seem to be no well
authenticated examples of the continuance of the mule race beyond
one generation. The principal number of observations and experiments
relate to the mixed offspring of the horse and the ass; and
in this case it is well established that the he-mule can generate, and
the she-mule produce. Such cases occur in Spain and Italy, and much
more frequently in the West Indies and New Holland; but these mules
have never bred in cold climates, seldom in warm regions, and still
more rarely in temperate countries.
The hybrid offspring of the she-ass and the stallion, the γιννος of
Aristotle, and the hinnus of Pliny, differs from the mule, or the offspring
of the ass and mare. In both cases, says Buffon, these animals
retain more of the dam than of the sire, not only in the magnitude, but
in the figure of the body: whereas, in the form of the head, limbs, and
tail, they bear a greater resemblance to the sire. The same naturalist
infers, from various experiments respecting cross-breeds between the
he-goat and ewe, the dog and she-wolf, the goldfinch and canary-bird,
that the male transmits his sex to the greatest number, and that the
preponderance of males over females exceeds that which prevails where
the parents are of the same species.
Hunter's opinion.—The celebrated John Hunter has observed, that
the true distinction of species must ultimately be gathered from their
incapacity of propagating with each other, and producing offspring
capable of again continuing itself. He was unwilling, however, to admit
that the horse and the ass were of the same species, because some
rare instances had been adduced of the breeding of mules, although he
maintained that the wolf, the dog, and the jackal were all of one species;
because he had found, by two experiments, that the dog would breed
both with the wolf and the jackal; and that the mule, in each case,
would breed again with the dog. In these cases, however, it may be
observed, that there was always one parent at least of pure breed, and
no proof was obtained that a true hybrid race could be perpetuated; a
fact of which I believe no examples are yet recorded, either in regard to
mixtures of the horse and ass, or any other of the mammalia.
Should the fact be hereafter ascertained, that two mules can propagate
their kind, we must still inquire whether the offspring may not be
regarded in the light of a monstrous birth, proceeding from some accidental
cause, or, rather, to speak more philosophically, from some general
law not yet understood, but which may not be permitted permanently
to interfere with those laws of generation by which species may, in
general, be prevented from becoming blended. If, for example, we
discovered that the progeny of a mule race degenerated greatly, in the
first generation, in force, sagacity, or any attribute necessary for its
preservation in a state of nature, we might infer that, like a monster, it
is a mere temporary and fortuitous variety. Nor does it seem probable
that the greater number of such monsters could ever occur unless obtained
602
by art; for, in Hunter's experiments, stratagem or force was, in
most instances, employed to bring about the irregular connexion.827
Mules not strictly intermediate between the parent
species.—It seems
rarely to happen that the mule offspring is truly intermediate in character
between the two parents. Thus Hunter mentions that, in his
experiments, one of the hybrid pups resembled the wolf much more
than the rest of the litter; and we are informed by Wiegmann, that, in
a litter lately obtained in the Royal Menagerie at Berlin, from a white
pointer and a she-wolf, two of the cubs resembled the common
wolf-dog,
but the third was like a pointer with hanging ears.
There is undoubtedly a very close analogy between these phenomena
and those presented by the intermixture of distinct races of the same
species, both in the inferior animals and in man. Dr. Prichard, in his
"Physical History of Mankind," cites examples where the peculiarities
of the parents have been transmitted very unequally to the offspring;
as where children, entirely white, or perfectly black, have sprung from
the union of the European and the negro. Sometimes the colour or
other peculiarities of one parent, after having failed to show themselves
in the immediate progeny, reappear in a subsequent generation; as
where a white child is born of two black parents, the grandfather having
been a white.828
The same author judiciously observes that, if different species mixed
their breed, and hybrid races were often propagated, the animal world
would soon present a scene of confusion; its tribes would be every where
blended together, and we should perhaps find more hybrid creatures
than genuine and uncorrupted races.829
Hybrid plants.—Kölreuter's experiments.—The history of the vegetable
kingdom has been thought to afford more decisive evidence in
favour of the theory of the formation of new and permanent species
from hybrid stocks. The first accurate experiments in illustration of
this curious subject appear to have been made by Kölreuter, who obtained
a hybrid from two species of tobacco, Nicotiana rustica and N.
paniculata, which differ greatly in the shape of their leaves, the colour
of the corolla, and the height of the stem. The stigma of a plant of N.
rustica was impregnated with the pollen of a plant of N. paniculata.
The seed ripened, and produced a hybrid which was intermediate
between the two parents, and which, like all the hybrids which this
botanist brought up, had imperfect stamens. He afterwards impregnated
this hybrid with the pollen of N. paniculata, and obtained plants
which much more resembled the last. This he continued through
several generations, until, by due perseverance, he actually changed the
Nicotiana rustica into the Nicotiana paniculata.
The plan of impregnation adopted, was the cutting off of the anthers
603
of the plant intended for fructification before they had shed pollen, and
then laying on foreign pollen upon the stigma.
Wiegmann's experiments.—The same experiment has since been
repeated with success by Wiegmann, who found that he could bring
back the hybrids to the exact likeness of either parent, by crossing them
a sufficient number of times.
The blending of the characters of the parent stocks, in many other
of Wiegmann's experiments, was complete; the colour and shape of the
leaves and flowers, and even the scent, being intermediate, as in the
offspring of the two species of verbascum. An intermarriage, also, between
the common onion and the leek (Allium cepa and A. porrum)
gave a mule plant, which, in the character of its leaves and flowers,
approached most nearly to the garden onion, but had the elongated
bulbous root and smell of the leek.
The same botanist remarks, that vegetable hybrids, when not strictly
intermediate, more frequently approach the female than the male parent
species; but they never exhibit characters foreign to both. A re-cross
with one of the original stocks generally causes the mule plant to revert
towards that stock; but this is not always the case, the offspring sometimes
continuing to exhibit the character of a full hybrid.
In general, the success attending the production and perpetuity of
hybrids among plants depends, as in the animal kingdom, on the degree
of proximity between the species intermarried. If their organization be
very remote, impregnation never takes place; if somewhat less distant,
seeds are formed, but always imperfect and sterile. The next degree of
relationship yields hybrid seedlings, but these are barren; and it is only
when the parent species are very nearly allied that the hybrid race may
be perpetuated for several generations. Even in this case the best authenticated
examples seem confined to the crossing of hybrids with
individuals of pure breed. In none of the experiments most accurately
detailed does it appear that both the parents were mules.
Wiegmann diversified as much as possible his mode of bringing
about these irregular unions among plants. He often sowed parallel
rows, near to each other, of the species from which he desired to breed;
and, instead of mutilating, after Kölreuter's fashion, the plants of one
of the parent stocks, he merely washed the pollen off their anthers.
The branches of the plants in each row were then gently bent towards
each other and intertwined; so that the wind, and numerous insects, as
they passed from the flowers of one to those of the other species, carried
the pollen and produced fecundation.
Vegetable hybrids why rare in a wild slate.—The same observer saw
a good exemplification of the manner in which hybrids may be formed in
a state of nature. Some wallflowers and pinks had been growing in a
garden, in a dry sunny situation, and their stigmas had been ripened so
as to be moist, and to absorb pollen with avidity, although their anthers
were not yet developed. These stigmas became impregnated by pollen
blown from some other adjacent plants of the same species; but had
604
they been of different species, and not too remote in their organization,
mule races must have resulted.
When, indeed, we consider how busily some insects have been shown
to be engaged in conveying anther-dust from flower to flower, especially
bees, flower-eating beetles, and the like, it seems a most enigmatical
problem how it can happen that promiscuous alliances between distinct
species are not perpetually occurring.
How continually do we observe the bees diligently employed in collecting
the red and yellow powder by which the stamens of flowers are
covered, loading it on their hind legs, and carrying it to their hive for
the purpose of feeding their young! In thus providing for their own
progeny, these insects assist materially the process of fructification.830
Few persons need be reminded that the stamens in certain plants grow
on different blossoms from the pistils; and unless the summit of the pistil
be touched with the fertilizing dust, the fruit does not swell, nor the
seed arrive at maturity. It is by the help of bees chiefly, that the development
of the fruit of many such species is secured, the powder which
they have collected from the stamens being unconsciously left by them
in visiting the pistils.
How often, during the heat of a summer's day, do we see the males of
diœcious plants, such as the yew-tree, standing separate from the females,
and sending off into the air, upon the slightest breath of wind, clouds of
buoyant pollen! That the zephyr should so rarely intervene to fecundate
the plants of one species with the anther-dust of others, seems almost to
realize the converse of the miracle believed by the credulous herdsmen
of the Lusitanian mares—


Ore omnes versæ in Zephyrum, stant rupibus altis
Exceptantque leves auras: et sæpe sine ullis
Conjugiis, vento gravidæ, mirabile dictu.831


But, in the first place, it appears that there is a natural aversion in
plants, as well as in animals, to irregular sexual unions; and in most of the
successful experiments in the animal and vegetable world, some violence
has been used in order to procure impregnation. The stigma imbibes,
slowly and reluctantly, the granules of the pollen of another species,
even when it is abundantly covered with it; and if it happen that, during
this period, ever so slight a quantity of the anther-dust of its own
species alight upon it, this is instantly absorbed, and the effect of the
foreign pollen destroyed. Besides, it does not often happen that the
male and female organs of fructification, in different species, arrive at a
state of maturity at precisely the same time. Even where such synchronism
does prevail, so that a cross impregnation is effected, the
chances are very numerous against the establishment of a hybrid race.
If we consider the vegetable kingdom generally, it must be recollected
that even of the seeds which are well ripened, a great part are either
605
eaten by insects, birds, and other animals, or decay for want of room
and opportunity to germinate. Unhealthy plants are the first which are
cut off by causes prejudicial to the species, being usually stifled by more
vigorous individuals of their own kind. If, therefore, the relative
fecundity or hardiness of hybrids be in the least degree inferior, they
cannot maintain their footing for many generations, even if they were
ever produced beyond one generation in a wild state. In the universal
struggle for existence, the right of the strongest eventually prevails;
and the strength and durability of a race depend mainly on its prolificness,
in which hybrids are acknowledged to be deficient.
Centaurea hybrida, a plant which never bears seed, and is supposed
to be produced by the frequent intermixture of two well-known species
of Centaurea, grows wild upon a hill near Turin. Ranunculus lacerus,
also sterile, has been produced accidentally at Grenoble, and near Paris,
by the union of two Ranunculi; but this occurred in gardens.832
Mr. Herbert's experiments.—Mr. Herbert, in one of his ingenious
papers on mule plants, endeavors to account for their non-occurrence
in a state of nature, from the circumstance that all the combinations
that were likely to occur have already been made many centuries ago,
and have formed the various species of botanists; but in our gardens,
he says, whenever species, having a certain degree of affinity to each
other, are transported from different countries, and brought for the first
time into contact, they give rise to hybrid species.833 But we have no
data, as yet, to warrant the conclusion, that a single permanent hybrid
race has ever been formed, even in gardens, by the intermarriage of two
allied species brought from distant habitations. Until some fact of this
kind is fairly established, and a new species, capable of perpetuating
itself in a state of perfect independence of man, can be pointed out, it
seems reasonable to call in question entirely this hypothetical source
of new species. That varieties do sometimes spring up from cross-breeds,
in a natural way, can hardly be doubted; but they probably die
out even more rapidly than races propagated by grafts or layers.
Opinion of De Candolle.—De Candolle, whose opinion on a philosophical
question of this kind deserves the greatest attention, has observed,
in his Essay on Botanical Geography, that the varieties of plants
range themselves under two general heads: those produced by external
circumstances, and those formed by hybridity. After adducing various
arguments to show that neither of these causes can explain the permanent
diversity of plants indigenous in different regions, he says, in regard
to the crossing of races, "I can perfectly comprehend without altogether
sharing the opinion, that, where many species of the same genera occur
near together, hybrid species may be formed, and I am aware that the
great number of species of certain genera which are found in particular
regions may be explained in this manner; but I am unable to conceive
how any one can regard the same explanation as applicable to species
606
which live naturally at great distances. If the three larches, for example,
now known in the world, lived in the same localities, I might then
believe that one of them was the produce of the crossing of the two
others; but I never could admit that the Siberian species has been produced
by the crossing of those of Europe and America. I see, then,
that there exist in organized beings, permanent differences which cannot
be referred to any one of the actual causes of variation, and these differences
are what constitute species."834
Reality of species confirmed by the phenomena of
hybrids.—The most
decisive arguments perhaps, amongst many others, against the probability
of the derivation of permanent species from cross-breeds, are to be
drawn from the fact alluded to by De Candolle, of species having a
close affinity to each other occurring in distinct botanical provinces, or
countries inhabited by groups of distinct species of indigenous plants;
for in this case naturalists, who are not prepared to go the whole length
of the transmutationists, are under the necessity of admitting that, in
some cases, species which approach very near to each other in their
characters, were so created from their origin; an admission fatal to the
idea of its being a general law of nature that a few original types only
should be formed, and that all intermediate races should spring from
the intermixture of those stocks.
This notion, indeed, is wholly at variance with all that we know of
hybrid generation; for the phenomena entitle us to affirm, that had the
types been at first somewhat distinct, no cross-breeds would ever have
been produced, much less those prolific races which we now recognize as
distinct species.
In regard, moreover, to the permanent propagation of hybrid races
among animals, insuperable difficulties present themselves, when we
endeavor to conceive the blending together of the different instincts and
propensities of two species, so as to insure the preservation of the intermediate
race. The common mule, when obtained by human art, may
be protected by the power of man; but, in a wild state, it would not
have precisely the same wants either as the horse or the ass; and if
in consequence of some difference of this kind, it strayed from the herd,
it would soon be hunted down by beasts of prey, and destroyed.
If we take some genus of insects, such as the bee, we find that each
of the numerous species has some difference in its habits, its mode of
collecting honey, or constructing its dwelling, or providing for its young,
and other particulars. In the case of the common hive bee, the workers
are described, by Kirby and Spence, as being endowed with no less
than thirty distinct instincts.835 So also we find that, amongst a most
numerous class of spiders, there are nearly as many different modes of
spinning their webs as there are species. When we recollect how complicated
are the relations of these instincts with co-existing species, both
607
of the animal and vegetable kingdoms, it is scarcely possible to imagine
that a bastard race could spring from the union of two of these species,
and retain just so much of the qualities of each parent stock as to preserve
its ground in spite of the dangers which surround it.
We might also ask, if a few generic types alone have been created
among insects, and the intermediate species have proceeded from
hybridity, where are those original types, combining, as they ought to
do, the elements of all the instincts which have made their appearance
in the numerous derivative races? So also in regard to animals of all
classes, and of plants; if species are in general of hybrid origin, where
are the stocks which combine in themselves the habits, properties, and
organs, of which all the intervening species ought to afford us mere
modifications?
Recapitulation of the arguments from hybrids.—I shall now conclude
this subject by summing up, in a few words, the results to which I have
been led by the consideration of the phenomena of hybrids. It appears
that the aversion of individuals of distinct species to the sexual union is
common to animals and plants; and that it is only when the species
approach near to each other in their organization and habits, that any
offspring are produced from their connexion. Mules are of extremely
rare occurrence in a state of nature, and no examples are yet known of
their having procreated in a wild state. But it has been proved, that
hybrids are not universally sterile, provided the parent stocks have a
near affinity to each other, although the continuation of the mixed
race, for several generations, appears hitherto to have been obtained
only by crossing the hybrids with individuals of pure species; an
experiment which by no means bears out the hypothesis that a true
hybrid race could ever be permanently established.
Hence we may infer, that aversion to sexual intercourse is, in general,
a good test of the distinctness of original stocks, or of species; and
the procreation of hybrids is a proof of the near affinity of species. Perhaps,
hereafter, the number of generations for which hybrids may be
continued, before the race dies out (for it seems usually to degenerate
rapidly), may afford the zoologist and botanist an experimental test of
the difference in the degree of affinity of allied species.
I may also remark, that if it could have been shown that a single
permanent species had ever been produced by hybridity (of which there
is no satisfactory proof), it might certainly have lent some countenance
to the notions of the ancients respecting the gradual deterioration of
created things, but none whatever to Lamarck's theory of their progressive
perfectibility, for observations have hitherto shown that there is a
tendency in mule animals and plants to degenerate in organization.
It was before remarked, that the theory of progressive development
arose partly from an attempt to ingraft the doctrines of the transmutationists
upon one of the most popular generalizations in geology. But we
have seen in the ninth chapter, that the modern researches of geologists
have broken at many points the chain of evidence once supposed to exist
608
in favor of the doctrine, that, at each successive period in the earth's
history, animals and plants of a higher grade, or more complex organization,
have been created. The recent origin of man, and the absence
of all signs of any rational being holding an analogous relation to former
states of the animate world, affords one, and perhaps in the present
state of science the only argument of much weight in support of the
hypothesis of a progressive scheme; but none whatever in favor of the
fancied evolution of one species out of another.
Theory of the gradation of intellect as shown by the facial angle.—When
the celebrated anatomist, Camper, first attempted to estimate the
degrees of sagacity of different animals, and of the races of man, by the
measurement of the facial angle, some speculators were bold enough to
affirm that certain Simiæ, or apes, differed as little from the more
savage races of men, as those do from the human race in general; and
that a scale might be traced from "apes with foreheads villanous low"
to the African variety of the human species, and from that to the European.
The facial angle was measured by drawing a line from the prominent
centre of the forehead to the most advanced part of the lower
jaw-bone, and observing the angle which it made with the horizontal
line; and it was affirmed, that there was a regular series of such angles
from birds to the mammalia.
The gradation from the dog to the monkey was said to be perfect,
and from that again to man. One of the ape tribe has a facial angle of
42°; and another, which approximated nearest to man in figure, an
angle of 50°. To this succeeds (longo sed proximus intervallo) the
head of the African negro, which, as well as that of the Calmuck,
forms an angle of 70°; while that of the European contains 80°. The
Roman painters preferred the angle of 95°; and the character of beauty
and sublimity so striking in some works of Grecian sculpture, as in the
head of the Apollo, and in the Medusa of Sisocles, is given by an angle
which amounts to 100°.836
A great number of valuable facts and curious analogies in comparative
anatomy were brought to light during the investigations which
were made by Camper, John Hunter, and others, to illustrate this scale
of organization; and their facts and generalizations must not be confounded
with the fanciful systems which White and others deduced
from them.837
That there is some connexion between an elevated and capacious
forehead, in certain races of men, and a large developement of the intellectual
faculties, seems highly probable; and that a low facial angle is
frequently accompanied with inferiority of mental powers, is certain;
but the attempt to trace a gradual scale of intelligence through the different
species of animals accompanying the modifications of the form of the
scull, is a mere visionary speculation. It has been found necessary to
609
exaggerate the sagacity of the ape tribe at the expense of the dog; and
strange contradictions have arisen in the conclusions deduced from the
structure of the elephant; some anatomists being disposed to deny the
quadruped the intelligence which he really possesses, because they
found that the volume of his brain was small in comparison to that of
the other mammalia; while others were inclined to magnify extravagantly
the superiority of his intellect, because the vertical height of his
skull is so great when compared to its horizontal length.
Different races of men are all of one species.—It would be irrelevant
to our subject if we were to enter into a farther discussion on these
topics; because, even if a graduated scale of organization and intelligence
could have been established, it would prove nothing in favor of a tendency,
in each species, to attain a higher state of perfection. I may
refer the reader to the writings of Blumenbach, Prichard, Lawrence, and
more recently Latham838, for convincing proofs that the varieties of form,
color, and organization of different races of men, are perfectly consistent
with the generally received opinion, that all the individuals of the species
have originated from a single pair; and, while they exhibit in man as
many diversities of a physiological nature as appear in any other species,
they confirm also the opinion of the slight deviation from a common
standard of which species are capable.
The power of existing and multiplying in every latitude, and in every
variety of situation and climate, which has enabled the great human
family to extend itself over the habitable globe, is partly, says Lawrence,
the result of physical constitution, and partly of the mental prerogative
of man. If he did not possess the most enduring and flexible corporeal
frame, his arts would not enable him to be the inhabitant of all climates,
and to brave the extremes of heat and cold, and the other destructive
influences of local situation.839 Yet, notwithstanding this flexibility of
bodily frame, we find no signs of indefinite departure from a common
standard, and the intermarriages of individuals of the most remote
varieties are not less fruitful than between those of the same tribe.
Tiedemann on the brain of the fœtus in vertebrated animals.—There
is yet another department of anatomical discovery to which I must
allude, because it has appeared to some persons to afford a distant analogy,
at least, to that progressive development by which some of the
inferior species may have been gradually perfected into those of more
complex organization. Tiedemann found, and his discoveries have been
most fully confirmed and elucidated by M. Serres, that the brain of the
fœtus, in the highest class of vertebrated animals, assumes, in succession,
forms, bearing a certain degree of resemblance to those which belong to
fishes, reptiles, and birds, before it acquires the additions and modifications
which are peculiar to the mammiferous tribe; so that, in the passage
from the embryo to the perfect mammifer, there is a typical representation,
610
it is said, of all those transformations which the primitive species
are supposed to have undergone, during a long series of generations,
between the present period and the remotest geological era.
"If you examine the brain of the mammalia," says M. Serres, "at an
early stage of uterine life, you perceive the cerebral hemispheres consolidated,
as in fish, in two vesicles, isolated one from the other; at a later
period, you see them affect the configuration of the cerebral hemispheres
of reptiles; still later again, they present you with the forms of those of
birds; finally they acquire, at the era of birth, and sometimes later, the
permanent forms which the adult mammalia present.
"The cerebral hemispheres, then, arrive at the state which we observe
in the higher animals only by a series of successive metamorphoses. If
we reduce the whole of these evolutions to four periods, we shall see,
that in the first are born the cerebral lobes of fishes; and this takes place
homogeneously in all classes. The second period will give us the organization
of reptiles; the third, the brain of birds; and the fourth, the
complex hemispheres of mammalia.
"If we could develop the different parts of the brain of the inferior
classes, we should make, in succession, a reptile out of a fish, a bird out
of a reptile, and a mammiferous quadruped out of a bird. If, on the
contrary, we could starve this organ in the mammalia, we might reduce
it successively to the condition of the brain of the three inferior classes.
"Nature often presents us with this last phenomenon in monsters, but
never exhibits the first. Among the various deformities which organized
beings may experience, they never pass the limits of their own classes to
put on the forms of the class above them. Never does a fish elevate
itself so as to assume the form of the brain of a reptile; nor does the
latter ever attain that of birds; nor the bird that of the mammifer. It
may happen that a monster may have two heads; but the conformation
of the brain always remains circumscribed narrowly within the limits of
its class."840
Dr. Clark of Cambridge, in a memoir on "Fœtal Development" (1845),
has shown that the concurrent labours of Valentin, Ratké, and Bischoff
disprove the reality of the supposed anatomical analogy between the
embryo condition of certain organs in the higher orders, and the perfect
structure of the same organs in animals of an inferior class. The hearts
and brains, for example, of birds and mammals do not pass through
forms which are permanent in fishes and reptiles; there is only just so
much resemblance as may point to a unity of plan running through the
organization of the whole series of vertebrated animals; but which lends
no support whatever to the notion of a gradual transmutation of one
species into another; least of all of the passage, in the course of many
generations, from an animal of a more simple to one of a more complex
structure.
611
Recapitulation.—For the reasons, therefore, detailed in this and
the two preceding chapters, we may draw the following inferences in
regard to the reality of species in nature:—
1st. That there is a capacity in all species to accommodate themselves,
to a certain extent, to a change of external circumstances, this extent
varying greatly, according to the species.
2ndly. When the change of situation which they can endure is great,
it is usually attended by some modifications of the form, colour, size,
structure, or other particulars; but the mutations thus superinduced are
governed by constant laws, and the capability of so varying, forms part
of the permanent specific character.
3dly. Some acquired peculiarities, of form, structure, and instinct, are
transmissible to the offspring; but these consist of such qualities and
attributes only as are intimately related to the natural wants and propensities
of the species.
4thly. The entire variation from the original type, which any given
kind of change can produce, may usually be effected in a brief period of
time, after which no farther deviation can be obtained by continuing to
alter the circumstances, though ever so gradually; indefinite divergence,
either in the way of improvement or deterioration, being prevented, and
the least possible excess beyond the defined limits being fatal to the existence
of the individual.
5thly. The intermixture of distinct species is guarded against by the
aversion of the individuals composing them to sexual union, or by the
sterility of the mule offspring. It does not appear that true hybrid races
have ever been perpetuated for several generations, even by the assistance
of man; for the cases usually cited relate to the crossing of mules with
individuals of pure species, and not to the intermixture of hybrid with
hybrid.
6thly. From the above considerations, it appears that species have a
real existence in nature; and that each was endowed, at the time of its
creation, with the attributes and organization by which it is now distinguished.

612</div></body></text></TEI>