<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="42">

BOOK V.

THE PHILOSOPHY OF THE MECHANICO-CHEMICAL SCIENCES.

CHAPTER I.
Attempts at the Scientific Application of the Idea of Polarity.



1. IN
some of the mechanical sciences, as Magnetism and
Optics, the phenomena are found to depend upon position (the
position of the magnet, or of the ray of light,) in a
peculiar alternate manner. This dependence, as it was first
apprehended, was represented by means of certain conceptions
of space and force, as for instance by considering the two
Poles of a magnet. But in all such modes of
representing these alternations by the conceptions borrowed
from other ideas, a closer examination detected something
superfluous and something defective; and in proportion as
the view which philosophers took of this relation was
gradually purified from these incongruous elements, and was
rendered more general and abstract by the discovery of
analogous properties in new cases, it was perceived that the
relation could not be adequately apprehended without
considering it as involving a peculiar and independent Idea,
which we may designate by the term Polarity.
We shall trace some of the forms in which this Idea has
manifested itself in the history of science. In doing so we
shall not begin, as in other Books of this work we have
done, by speaking of the notion as it is 360 employed in
common use: for the relation of Polarity is of so abstract
and technical a nature, that it is not employed, at least in
any distinct and obvious manner, on any ordinary or
practical occasions. The idea belongs peculiarly to the
region of speculation: in persons of common habits of
thought it is probably almost or quite undeveloped; and even
most of those whose minds have been long occupied by
science, find a difficulty in apprehending it in its full
generality and abstraction, and stript of all irrelevant
hypothesis.
2. Magnetism.—The name and the notion of
Poles were first adopted in the case of a magnet. If
we have two magnets, their extremities attract and repel
each other alternatively. If the first end of the one
attract the first end of the other, it repels the second
end, and conversely. In order to express this rule
conveniently, the two ends of each magnet are called the
north pole and the south pole respectively,
the denominations being borrowed from the poles of the earth
and heavens. ‘These poles,’ as Gilbert says1, ‘regulate
the motions of the celestial spheres and of the earth. In
like manner the magnet has its poles, a northern and a
southern one; certain and determined points constituted by
nature in the stone, the primary terms of its motions and
effects, the limits and governors of many actions and
virtues.’</div></body></text></TEI>