<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="21">CHAPTER I.
Prelude to the Inductive Epoch of
Copernicus.
THE Doctrine of Copernicus,
that the Sun is the true centre of the celestial motions, depends
primarily upon the consideration that such a supposition explains very
simply and completely all the obvious appearances of the heavens. In
order to see that it does this, nothing more is requisite than a
distinct conception of the nature of Relative Motion, and a knowledge
of the principal Astronomical Phenomena. There was, therefore, no
reason why such a doctrine might not be discovered, that is,
suggested as a theory plausible at first sight, long before the time
of Copernicus; or rather, it was impossible that this guess, among
others, should not be propounded as a solution of the appearances of
the heavens. We are not, therefore, to be surprised if we find, in the
earliest times of Astronomy, and at various succeeding periods, such a
system spoken of by astronomers, and maintained by some as true,
though rejected by the majority, and by the principal writers.
When we look back at such a difference of opinion, having in our
minds, as we unavoidably have, the clear and irresistible
considerations by which the Copernican Doctrine is established for
us, it is difficult for us not to attribute superior sagacity and
candor to those who held that side of the question, and to imagine
those who clung to the Ptolemaic Hypothesis to have been blind and
prejudiced; incapable of seeing the beauty of simplicity and symmetry,
or indisposed to resign established errors, and to accept novel and
comprehensive truths. Yet in judging thus, we are probably ourselves
influenced by prejudices arising from the knowledge and received
opinions of our own times. For is it, in reality, clear that, before
the time of Copernicus, the 258 Heliocentric Theory (that which
places the centre of the celestial motions in the Sun) had a claim to
assent so decidedly superior to the Geocentric Theory, which places
the Earth in the centre? What is the basis of the heliocentric
theory?—That the relative motions are the
same, on that and on the other supposition. So far, therefore,
the two hypotheses are exactly on the same footing. But, it is urged,
on the heliocentric side we have the advantage of
simplicity:—true; but we have, on the other side, the testimony
of our senses; that is, the geocentric doctrine (which asserts that
the Earth rests and the heavenly bodies move) is the obvious and
spontaneous interpretation of the appearances. Both these arguments,
simplicity on the one side, and obviousness on the
other, are vague, and we may venture to say, both indecisive. We
cannot establish any strong preponderance of probability in favor of
the former doctrine, without going much further into the arguments of
the question.
Nor, when we speak of the superior simplicity of the
Copernican theory, must we forget, that though this theory has
undoubtedly, in this respect, a great advantage over the Ptolemaic,
yet that the Copernican system itself is very complex, when it
undertakes to account, as the Ptolemaic did, for the
Inequalities of the Motions of the sun, moon, and planets;
and, that in the hands of Copernicus, it retained a large share of the
eccentrics and epicycles of its predecessor, and, in some parts, with
increased machinery. The heliocentric theory, without these
appendages, would not approach the Ptolemaic, in the accurate
explanation of facts; and as those who had placed the sun in the
centre had never, till the time of Copernicus, shown how the
inequalities were to be explained on that supposition, we may assert
that after the promulgation of the theory of eccentrics and epicycles
on the geocentric hypothesis, there was no published
heliocentric theory which could bear a comparison with that
hypothesis.
It is true, that all the contrivances of epicycles, and the like,
by which the geocentric hypothesis was made to represent the
phenomena, were susceptible of an easy adaptation to a heliocentric
method, when a good mathematician had once proposed to himself the
problem: and this was precisely what Copernicus undertook and
executed. But, till the appearance of his work, the heliocentric
system had never come before the world except as a hasty and imperfect
hypothesis; which bore a favorable comparison with the phenomena, so
long as their general features only were known; but which had been
completely thrown into the shade by the labor and intelligence
bestowed upon 259
the Hipparchian or Ptolemaic theories by a long series of great
astronomers of all civilized countries.
But, though the astronomers who, before Copernicus, held the
heliocentric opinion, cannot, on any good grounds, be considered as
much more enlightened than their opponents, it is curious to trace the
early and repeated manifestations of this view of the universe. The
distinct assertion of the heliocentric theory among the Greeks is an
evidence of the clearness of their thoughts, and the vigour of their
minds; and it is a proof of the feebleness and servility of intellect
in the stationary period, that, till the period of Copernicus, no one
was found to try the fortune of this hypothesis, modified according to
the improved astronomical knowledge of the time.
The most ancient of the Greek philosophers to whom the ancients
ascribe the heliocentric doctrine, is Pythagoras; but Diogenes
Laertius makes Philolaus, one of the followers of Pythagoras, the
first author of this doctrine. We learn from Archimedes, that it was
held by his contemporary, Aristarchus. “Aristarchus of Samos,” says
he,1 “makes this supposition,—that the
fixed stars and the sun remain at rest, and that the earth revolves
round the sun in a circle.” Plutarch2 asserts that this,
which was only a hypothesis in the hands of Aristarchus, was
proved by Seleucus; but we may venture to say that, at that
time, no such proof was possible. Aristotle had recognized the
existence of this doctrine by arguing against it. “All things,” says
he,3 “tend to the centre of the earth, and
rest there, and therefore the whole mass of the earth cannot rest
except there.” Ptolemy had in like manner argued against the diurnal
motion of the earth: such a revolution would, he urged, disperse into
surrounding space all the loose parts of the earth. Yet he allowed
that such a supposition would facilitate the explanation of some
phenomena. Cicero appears to make Mercury and Venus revolve about the
sun, as does Martianus Capella at a later period; and Seneca says4
it is a worthy subject of contemplation, whether the earth be at rest
or in motion: but at this period, as we may see from Seneca himself,
that habit of intellect which was requisite for the solution of such a
question, had been succeeded by indistinct views, and rhetorical forms
of speech. If there were any good mathematicians and good observers at
this period, they were employed in cultivating and verifying the
Hipparchian theory.
1 Archim. Arenarius.
2 Quest. Plat. Delamb. A.
A. vi.
3 Quoted by Copernic. i. 7.
4 Quest. Nat. vii. 2.
Next to the Greeks, the Indians appear to have possessed that 260 original vigor and
clearness of thought, from which true science springs. It is
remarkable that the Indians, also, had their heliocentric theorists.
Aryabatta5 (a. d. 1322),
and other astronomers of that country, are said to have advocated the
doctrine of the earth’s revolution on its axis; which opinion,
however, was rejected by subsequent philosophers among the
Hindoos.
5 Lib. U. K. Hist. Ast. p.
11.
Some writers have thought that the heliocentric doctrine was
derived by Pythagoras and other European philosophers, from
some of the oriental nations. This opinion, however, will appear to
have little weight, if we consider that the heliocentric hypothesis,
in the only shape in which the ancients knew it, was too obvious to
require much teaching; that it did not and could not, so far as we
know, receive any additional strength from any thing which the
oriental nations could teach; and that each astronomer was induced to
adopt or reject it, not by any information which a master could give
him, but by his love of geometrical simplicity on the one hand, or the
prejudices of sense on the other. Real science, depending on a clear
view of the relation of phenomena to general theoretical ideas, cannot
be communicated in the way of secret and exclusive traditions, like
the mysteries of certain arts and crafts. If the philosopher do not
see that the theory is true, he is little the better for
having heard or read the words which assert its truth.
It is impossible, therefore, for us to assent to those views which
would discover in the heliocentric doctrines of the ancients, traces
of a more profound astronomy than any which they have transmitted to
us. Those doctrines were merely the plausible conjectures of men with
sound geometrical notions; but they were never extended so as to
embrace the details of the existing astronomical knowledge; and
perhaps we may say, that the analysis of the phenomena into the
arrangements of the Ptolemaic system, was so much more obvious than
any other, that it must necessarily come first, in order to form an
introduction to the Copernican.
The true foundation of the heliocentric theory for the ancients
was, as we have intimated, its perfect geometrical consistency with
the general features of the phenomena, and its simplicity. But it was
unlikely that the human mind would be content to consider the subject
under this strict and limited aspect alone. In its eagerness for wide
speculative views, it naturally looked out for other and vaguer
principles of connection and relation. Thus, as it had been urged in
261 favor of the
geocentric doctrine, that the heaviest body must be in the centre, it
was maintained, as a leading recommendation of the opposite opinion,
that it placed the Fire, the noblest element, in the Centre of the
Universe. The authority of mythological ideas was called in on both
sides to support these views. Numa, as Plutarch6 informs us, built
a circular temple over the ever-burning Fire of Vesta; typifying, not
the earth, but the Universe, which, according to the Pythagoreans, has
the Fire seated at its Centre. The same writer, in another of his
works, makes one of his interlocutors say, “Only, my friend, do not
bring me before a court of law on a charge of impiety; as Cleanthes
said, that Aristarchus the Samian ought to be tried for impiety,
because he removed the Hearth of the Universe.” This, however, seems
to have been intended as a pleasantry.
6 De Facie in Orbe Lunæ,
6.
The prevalent physical views, and the opinions concerning the
causes of the motions of the parts of the universe, were scarcely more
definite than the ancient opinions concerning the relations of the
four elements, till Galileo had founded the true Doctrine of Motion.
Though, therefore, arguments on this part of the subject were the most
important part of the controversy after Copernicus, the force of such
arguments was at his time almost balanced. Even if more had been known
on such subjects, the arguments would not have been conclusive: for
instance, the vast mass of the heavens, which is commonly urged as a
reason why the heavens do not move round the earth, would not make
such a motion impossible; and, on the other hand, the motions of
bodies at the earth’s surface, which were alleged as inconsistent with
its motion, did not really disprove such an opinion. But according to
the state of the science of motion before Copernicus, all reasonings
from such principles were utterly vague and obscure.
We must not omit to mention a modern who preceded Copernicus, in
the assertion at least of the heliocentric doctrine. This was Nicholas
of Cusa (a village near Treves), a cardinal and bishop, who, in the
first half of the fifteenth century, was very eminent as a divine and
mathematician; and who in a work, De Doctâ Ignorantiâ,
propounded the doctrine of the motion of the earth; more, however, as
a paradox than as a reality. We cannot consider this as any distinct
anticipation of a profound and consistent view of the truth.
We shall now examine further the promulgation of the Heliocentric
System by Copernicus, and its consequences.  ~Additional material in
the 3rd edition.~ 262</div></body></text></TEI>