<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="31">
      SECTION 7. OF THE UNION OF SCIENTIFIC SOCIETIES.
    

      This idea has occurred to several persons, as likely to lead to
      considerable advantages to science. If the various scientific societies
      could unite in the occupation of one large building, considerable economy
      would result from the union. By properly arranging their evenings of
      meeting, one meeting-room only need be required. The libraries might
      either be united, or arranged in adjoining rooms; and such a system would
      greatly facilitate the inquiries of scientific persons.
    

      Whether it would be possible to reunite in any way the different societies
      to the Royal Society, might be a delicate question; but although, on some
      accounts, desirable, that event is not necessary for the purpose of their
      having a common residence.
    

      The Medico-Botanical Society might, perhaps, from sympathy, be the first
      to which the Royal Society would apply; and by a proper interchange of
      diplomas, [A thing well understood by the INITIATED, both at HOME and
      ABROAD.] the two societies might be inoculated with each other. But even
      here some tact would be required; the Medico-Botanical is a little
      particular about the purity of its written documents, and lately
      attributed blame to one of its officers for some slight tampering with
      them, a degree of illiberality which the Council of the Royal Society are
      far from imitating.
    

      The Geological and the Astronomical Societies nourish no feelings of
      resentment to the parent institution for their early persecution; and
      though they have no inducement to seek, would scarcely refuse any union
      which might be generally advantageous to science.
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>