<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="1">
CHAPTER I.

The Length of the Year.

A year is the most important and obvious of the
periods which occur in the organic, and especially
in the vegetable world. In this interval of time the
cycle of most of the external influences which operate
upon plants is completed. There is also in
plants a cycle of internal functions, corresponding to
this succession of external causes. The length of
either of these periods might have been different
from what it is, according to any grounds of necessity
which we can perceive. But a certain length is
selected in both instances, and in both instances the
same. The length of the year is so determined as
to be adapted to the constitution of most vegetables;
or the construction of vegetables is so adjusted as to
be suited to the length which the year really has,
and unsuited to a duration longer or shorter by any[29]
considerable portion. The vegetable clock-work is
so set as to go for a year.
The length of the year or interval of recurrence
of the seasons is determined by the time which the
earth employs in performing its revolution round the
sun: and we can very easily conceive the solar system
so adjusted that the year should be longer or
shorter than it actually is. We can imagine the
earth to revolve round the sun at a distance greater
or less than that which it at present has, all the
forces of the system remaining unaltered. If the
earth were removed towards the centre by about
one-eighth of its distance, the year would be diminished
by about a month; and in the same manner
it would be increased by a month on increasing
the distance by one-eighth. We can suppose the
earth at a distance of eighty-four or a hundred and
eight millions of miles, just as easily as at its present
distance of ninety-six millions: we can suppose the
earth with its present stock of animals and vegetables
placed where Mars or where Venus is, and revolving
in an orbit like one of theirs: on the former supposition
our year would become twenty-three, on the
latter seven of our present months. Or we can conceive
the present distances of the parts of the system
to continue what they are, and the size, or the density
of the central mass, the sun, to be increased or
diminished in any proportion; and in this way the
time of the earth’s revolution might have been increased
or diminished in any degree; a greater velocity,
and consequently a diminished period, being
requisite in order to balance an augmented central
attraction. In any of these ways the length of the
earth’s natural year might have been different from
what it now is: in the last way without any necessary
alteration, so far as we can see, of temperature.
Now, if any change of this kind were to take
place, the working of the botanical world would be
thrown into utter disorder, the functions of plants[30]
would be entirely deranged, and the whole vegetable
kingdom involved in instant decay and rapid extinction.
That this would be the case, may be collected
from innumerable indications. Most of our fruit
trees, for example, require the year to be of its present
length. If the summer and the autumn were
much shorter, the fruit could not ripen; if these seasons
were much longer, the tree would put forth a
fresh suit of blossoms, to be cut down by the winter.
Or if the year were twice its present length, a second
crop of fruit would probably not be matured,
for want, among other things, of an intermediate
season of rest and consolidation, such as the winter
is. Our forest trees in like manner appear to need
all the seasons of our present year for their perfection;
the spring, summer, and autumn, for the developement
of their leaves and consequent formation
of their proper juice, and of wood from this; and the
winter for the hardening and solidifying the substance
thus formed.
Most plants, indeed, have some peculiar function
adapted to each period of the year, that is of the
now existing year. The sap ascends with extraordinary
copiousness at two seasons, in the spring and
in the autumn, especially the former. The opening
of the leaves and the opening of the flowers of the
same plants are so constant to their times, (their
appointed times, as we are naturally led to call
them,) that such occurrences might be taken as indications
of the times of the year. It has been proposed
in this way to select a series of botanical facts
which should form a calendar; and this has been
termed a calendar of Flora. Thus, if we consider
the time of putting forth leaves,[1] the honeysuckle
protrudes them in the month of January; the gooseberry,
currant, and elder in the end of February, or
beginning of March; the willow, elm, and lime-tree[31]
in April; the oak and ash, which are always the
latest among trees, in the beginning or towards the
middle of May. In the same manner the flowering
has its regular time: the mezereon and snowdrop
push forth their flowers in February; the primrose
in the month of March; the cowslip in April; the
great mass of plants in May and June; many in
July, August, and September; some, not till the
month of October, as the meadow saffron; and some
not till the approach and arrival of winter, as the
laurustinus and arbutus.
The fact which we have here to notice, is the recurrence
of these stages in the developement of
plants, at intervals precisely or very nearly of twelve
months. Undoubtedly, this result is in part occasioned
by the action of external stimulants upon the
plant, especially heat, and by the recurrence of the
intensity of such agents. Accordingly, there are
slight differences in the times of such occurrences,
according to the backwardness or forwardness of
the season, and according as the climate is genial or
otherwise. Gardeners use artifices which will, to a
certain extent, accelerate or retard the time of developement
of a plant. But there are various circumstances
which show that this recurrence of the
same events and equal intervals is not entirely owing
to external causes, and that it depends also upon
something in the internal structure of vegetables.
Alpine plants do not wait for the stimulus of the
sun’s heat, but exert such a struggle to blossom, that
their flowers are seen among the yet unmelted snow.
And this is still more remarkable in the naturalization
of plants from one hemisphere to the other.
When we transplant our fruit trees to the temperate
regions south of the equator, they continue for some
years to flourish at the period which corresponds to
our spring. The reverse of this obtains, with certain
trees of the southern hemisphere. Plants from
the Cape of Good Hope, and from Australia, countries
whose summer is simultaneous with our winter,[32]
exhibit their flowers in the coldest part of the year,
as the heaths.
This view of the subject agrees with that maintained
by the best botanical writers. Thus Decandolle
observes that after making allowance for all
meteorological causes, which determine the epoch
of flowering, we must reckon as another cause the
peculiar nature of each species. The flowering once
determined, appears to be subject to a law of
periodicity and habit.[2]
It appears then that the functions of plants have
by their nature a periodical character; and the
length of the period thus belonging to vegetables is
a result of their organization. Warmth and light,
soil and moisture, may in some degree modify, and
hasten or retard the stages of this period; but when
the constraint is removed the natural period is again
resumed. Such stimulants as we have mentioned
are not the causes of this periodicity. They do not
produce the varied functions of the plant, and could
not occasion their performance at regular intervals,
except the plant possessed a suitable construction.
They could not alter the length of the cycle of vegetable
functions, except within certain very narrow
limits. The processes of the rising of the sap, of the
formation of proper juices, of the unfolding of leaves,
the opening of flowers, the fecundation of the fruit,
the ripening of the seed, its proper deposition in order
for the reproduction of a new plant;—all these operations
require a certain portion of time, and could
not be compressed into a space less than a year, or
at least could not be abbreviated in any very great
degree. And on the other hand, if the winter were
greatly longer than it now is, many seeds would not
germinate at the return of spring. Seeds which
have been kept too long require stimulants to make
them fertile.
If therefore the duration of the seasons were much[33]
to change, the processes of vegetable life would be
interrupted, deranged, distempered. What, for instance,
would become of our calendar of Flora, if
the year were lengthened or shortened by six months?
Some of the dates would never arrive in the one
case, and the vegetable processes which mark them
would be superseded; some seasons would be without
dates in the other case, and these periods would
be employed in a way harmful to the plants, and no
doubt speedily destructive. We should have not
only a year of confusion, but, if it were repeated and
continued, a year of death.
But in the existing state of things, the duration of
the earth’s revolution round the sun, and the duration
of the revolution of the vegetable functions of
most plants are equal. These two periods are adjusted
to each other. The stimulants which the elements
apply come at such intervals and continue for
such times, that the plant is supported in health and
vigour, and enabled to reproduce its kind. Just such
a portion of time is measured out for the vegetable
powers to execute their task, as enables them to do
so in the best manner.
Now such an adjustment must surely be accepted
as a proof of design, exercised in the formation of
the world. Why should the solar year be so long
and no longer? or, this being of such a length, why
should the vegetable cycle be exactly of the same
length? Can this be chance? And this occurs, it
is to be observed, not in one, or in a few species of
plants, but in thousands. Take a small portion only
of known species, as the most obviously endowed
with this adjustment, and say ten thousand. How
should all these organized bodies be constructed for
the same period of a year? How should all these
machines be wound up so as to go for the same time?
Even allowing that they could bear a year of a month
longer or shorter, how do they all come within such
limits? No chance could produce such a result.
And if not by chance, how otherwise could such a[34]
coincidence occur, than by an intentional adjustment
of these two things to one another? by a selection
of such an organization in plants, as would fit them
to the earth on which they were to grow; by an
adaptation of construction to conditions; of the scale
of the construction to the scale of the conditions.
It cannot be accepted as an explanation of this
fact in the economy of plants, that it is necessary to
their existence; that no plants could possibly have
subsisted, and come down to us, except those which
were thus suited to their place on earth. This is true;
but this does not at all remove the necessity of recurring
to design as the origin of the construction by
which the existence and continuance of plants is
made possible. A watch could not go, except there
were the most exact adjustment in the forms and
positions of its wheels; yet no one would accept it
as an explanation of the origin of such forms and
positions, that the watch would not go if these were
other than they are. If the objector were to suppose
that plants were originally fitted to years of various
lengths, and that such only have survived to the present
time, as had a cycle of a length equal to our
present year, or one which could be accommodated
to it; we should reply, that the assumption is too gratuitous
and extravagant to require much consideration;
but that, moreover, it does not remove the difficulty.
How came the functions of plants to be
periodical at all? Here is, in the first instance, an
agreement in the form of the laws that prevail in
the organic and in the inorganic world, which appears
to us a clear evidence of design in their Author.
And the same kind of reply might be made to
any similar objection to our argument. Any supposition
that the universe has gradually approximated
to that state of harmony among the operations of its
different parts, of which we have one instance in the
coincidence now under consideration, would make it
necessary for the objector to assume a previous state
of things preparatory to this perfect correspondence.[35]
And in this preparatory condition we should still be
able to trace the rudiments of that harmony, for
which it was proposed to account: so that even the
most unbounded license of hypothesis would not enable
the opponent to obliterate the traces of an intentional
adaptation of one part of nature to another.
Nor would it at all affect the argument, if these
periodical occurrences could be traced to some
proximate cause: if for instance it could be shown,
that the budding or flowering of plants is brought
about at particular intervals, by the nutriment accumulated
in their vessels during the preceding months.
For the question would still remain, how their functions
were so adjusted, that the accumulation of the
nutriment necessary for budding and flowering, together
with the operation itself, comes to occupy exactly
a year, instead of a month only, or ten years.
There must be in their structure some reference to
time: how did such a reference occur? how was it
i determined to the particular time of the earth’s revolution
round the sun? This could be no otherwise,
as we conceive, than by design and appointment.
We are left therefore with this manifest adjustment
before us, of two parts of the universe, at first
sight so remote; the dimensions of the solar system
and the powers of vegetable life. These two things
are so related, that one has been made to fit the
other. The relation is as clear as that of a watch to
a sundial. If a person were to compare the watch
with the dial, hour after hour, and day after day, it
would be impossible for him not to believe that the
watch had been contrived to accommodate itself to
the solar day. We have at least ten thousand kinds
of vegetable watches of the most various forms,
which are all accommodated to the solar year; and
the evidence of contrivance seems to be no more
capable of being eluded in this case than in the other.
The same kind of argument might be applied to
the animal creation. The pairing, nesting, hatching,
fledging, and flight of birds, for instance, occupy[36]
each its peculiar time of the year; and, together
with a proper period of rest, fill up the twelve months.
The transformations of most insects have a similar
reference to the seasons, their progress and duration.
“In every species,” (except man,) says a writer[3] on
animals, “there is a peculiar period of the year in
which the reproductive system exercises its energies.
And the season of love and the period of gestation
are so arranged that the young ones are produced
at the time wherein the conditions of temperature
are most suited to the commencement of life.”
It is not our business here to consider the details of
such provisions, beautiful and striking as they are.
But the prevalence of the great law of periodicity
in the vital functions of organized beings will be allowed
to have a claim to be considered in its reference
to astronomy, when it is seen that their periodical
constitution derives its use from the periodical
nature of the motions of the planets round the sun;
and that the duration of such cycles in the existence
of plants and animals has a reference to the arbitrary
elements of the solar system: a reference
which, we maintain, is inexplicable and unintelligible,
except by admitting into our conceptions; an Intelligent
Author, alike of the organic and inorganic
universe.
</div></body></text></TEI>