<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="122">INTRODUCTION.
Of the Organical Sciences
THOUGH the general notion of
life is acknowledged by the most profound philosophers to be
dim and mysterious, even up to the present time; and must, in the
early stages of human speculation, have been still more obscure and
confused; it was sufficient, even then, to give interest and connexion
to men’s observations upon their own bodies and those of other
animals. It was seen, that in living things, certain peculiar
processes were constantly repeated, as those of breathing and of
taking food, for example; and that a certain conformation of the parts
of the animal was subservient to these processes; and thus were
gradually formed the notions of Function and of
Organization. And the sciences of which these notions formed
the basis are clearly distinguishable from all those which we have
hitherto considered. We conceive an organized body to be one
in which the parts are there for the sake of the whole, in a manner
different from any mechanical or chemical connexion; we conceive a
function to be not merely a process of change, but of change
connected with the general vital process. When mechanical or chemical
processes occur in the living body, they are instrumental to, and
directed by, the peculiar powers of life. The sciences which thus
consider organization and vital functions may be termed
organical sciences.
When men began to speculate concerning such subjects, the general
mode of apprehending the process in the cases of some functions,
appeared to be almost obvious; thus it was conceived that the growth
of animals arose from their frame appropriating to itself a part of
the substance of the food through the various passages of the body.
Under the influence of such general conceptions, speculative men were
naturally led to endeavor to obtain more clear and definite views of
the course of each of such processes, and of the mode in which the
separate parts contributed to it. Along with the observation of the
living person, the more searching examination which could be carried
on in the dead body, and the comparison of various kinds of animals,
soon showed that this pursuit was rich in knowledge and in interest.
436 Moreover,
besides the interest which the mere speculative faculty gave to this
study, the Art of Healing added to it a great practical value; and the
effects of diseases and of medicines supplied new materials and new
motives for the reasonings of the philosopher.
In this manner anatomy or physiology may be considered as a science
which began to be cultivated in the earliest periods of civilization.
Like most other ancient sciences, its career has been one of perpetual
though variable progress; and as in others, so in this, each step has
implied those which had been previously made, and cannot be understood
aright except we understand them. Moreover, the steps of this advance
have been very many and diverse; the cultivators of anatomy have in
all ages been numerous and laborious; the subject is one of vast
extent and complexity; almost every generation had added something to
the current knowledge of its details; and the general speculations of
physiologists have been subtle, bold, and learned. It must, therefore,
be difficult or impossible for a person who has not studied the
science with professional diligence and professional advantages, to
form just judgments of the value of the discoveries of various ages
and persons, and to arrange them in their due relation to each other.
To this we may add, that though all the discoveries which have been
made with respect to particular functions or organizations are
understood to be subordinate to one general science, the Philosophy of
Life, yet the principles and doctrines of this science nowhere exist
in a shape generally received and assented to among physiologists; and
thus we have not, in this science, the advantage which in some others
we have possessed;—of discerning the true direction of its first
movements, by knowing the point to which they ultimately
tend;—of running on beyond the earlier discoveries, and thus
looking them in the face, and reading their true features. With these
disadvantages, all that we can have to say respecting the history of
Physiology must need great indulgence on the part of the reader.
Yet here, as in other cases, we may, by guiding our views by those
of the greatest and most philosophical men who have made the subject
their study, hope to avoid material errors. Nor can we well evade
making the attempt. To obtain some simple and consistent view of the
progress of physiological science, is in the highest degree important
to the completion of our views of the progress of physical science.
For the physiological or organical sciences form a class to which the
classes already treated of, the mechanical, chemical, and
classificatory sciences, are subordinate and auxiliary. Again, another
437 circumstance
which makes physiology an important part of our survey of human
knowledge is, that we have here a science which is concerned, indeed,
about material combinations, but in which we are led almost beyond the
borders of the material world, into the region of sensation and
perception, thought and will. Such a contemplation may offer some
suggestions which may prepare us for the transition from physical to
metaphysical speculations.
In the survey which we must, for such purposes, take of the
progress of physiology, it is by no means necessary that we should
exhaust the subject, and attempt to give the history of every branch
of the knowledge of the phenomena and laws of living creatures. It
will be sufficient, if we follow a few of the lines of such
researches, which may be considered as examples of the whole. We see
that life is accompanied and sustained by many processes, which at
first offer themselves to our notice as separate functions, however
they may afterwards be found to be connected and identified; such are
feeling, digestion, respiration, the action of the heart and pulse,
generation, perception, voluntary motion. The analysis of any one of
these functions may be pursued separately. And since in this, as in
all genuine sciences, our knowledge becomes real and scientific, only
in so far as it is verified in particular facts, and thus established
in general propositions, such an original separation of the subjects
of research is requisite to a true representation of the growth of
real knowledge. The loose hypotheses and systems, concerning the
connexion of different vital faculties and the general nature of
living things, which have often been promulgated, must be excluded
from this part of our plan. We do not deny all value and merit to such
speculations; but they cannot be admitted in the earlier stages of the
history of physiology, treated of as an inductive science. If the
doctrine so propounded have a solid and permanent truth, they will
again come before us when we have travelled through the range of more
limited truths, and are prepared to ascend with security and certainty
into the higher region of general physiological principles. If they
cannot be arrived at by such a road, they are then, however plausible
and pleasing, no portion of that real and progressive science with
which alone our history is concerned.
We proceed, therefore, to trace the establishment of some of the
more limited but certain doctrines of physiology. 438</div></body></text></TEI>