<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="30">CHAPTER XXVIII.
Before the dawn of the succeeding morning I turned my
face towards Lucca. I beheld the last cloud of mingling
smoke and flame ascend from the ashes of my villa. The
blaze sunk, its materials were nearly consumed, and it
yielded an uncertain and fitful light only, when I withdrew
from being any longer the melancholy and heart-wounded
spectator of the ruin. I took an everlasting leave of the
marchese. I had been introduced to him under a friendly
aspect, as the man who had had courage to perform the
last offices of humanity to his unfortunate brother; and
he had conceived a warm affection for me. The painful
nature of the catastrophe he had witnessed melted his heart,
and he earnestly pressed me to draw upon him for any
supplies I wanted, or rather to receive from him a sum
equivalent to the damage the superstition of his countrymen
had inflicted on me. This I positively refused; but
I found it impossible to silence his importunity, till I
submitted to the duplicity of promising that, if I found
myself reduced to any necessity, I would not fail to apply
to him. It was in the very moment of our separation
that intelligence was brought me of the fate of Hector.
The reader may imagine with how heavy a heart I set out
on my journey.
[292]
Lucca is about seventeen miles from the city of Pisa;
from the place where I had spent the greater part of this
memorable night it was twenty. The marchese made me
promise to take a serpentine and circuitous route, the more
completely to elude the possibility of future danger. An
adventure occurred to me in this passage, with the relation
of which I will not interrupt my narrative, which prevented
me from arriving at Lucca till the noon of the
following day. Suffice it to say, that it was of such a
nature, that, impatient as I was under my present extraordinary
circumstances to rejoin my family, I should have
held myself destitute of every atom of humanity, if I had
not submitted to this short delay.
Short as it was, I found, when I reached Lucca, that
my evil genius had been busy to accumulate for me new
misfortunes. Marguerite and her daughters were wholly
unknown in this place; and the intelligence of the Pisan
riot having reached Lucca in the course of the day, it was
related to my wife, as to a hearer unconcerned, with all its
horrid circumstances and the calamitous fate of our generous
Hector, by the hostess of the inn. The rapidity of events,
during the last part of our residence in the Pisan territory,
was such as to have obliged me to say little of the effect
they produced upon Marguerite. But the reader can
scarcely be so inadvertent and unreflecting, as not easily to
imagine to himself that she felt them in the highest degree
painful and overwhelming. This last blow was too much.
Marguerite had been some months pregnant. She was
immediately seized with the pains of labour, and delivered
of a dead child. The first intelligence communicated to
me upon my arrival was that my wife was dying.
Lucca however did not witness the period of her existence.
After having continued for several days upon the
very extremity, as it were, between life and death, she
grew perceptibly better; and in a week more, though in a
very feeble state, it became apparent that her case was not
a rapid one. We agreed to proceed upon our Spanish
voyage. It appeared not improbable that the sea-air might
be found beneficial, and the experiment was warmly recommended
by her physicians. They were not however[293]
aware of the whole extent of her disorder. During the
voyage her crisis returned with such malignant symptoms,
as scarcely to permit us the hope she would reach the land
alive. We debarked at Barcelona on the 14th of April 1546.
We had no sooner taken up our abode in this city than,
fully aware of the state of her disease, she assembled her
daughters, and poured forth to them without restraint that
flood of affection, that ardent spirit of love, by which she
was distinguished and elevated above every creature that
lived. Her mind was clear, her intellectual powers were
complete and entire. The enthusiasm with which she
now expressed herself was not of that inconsiderate nature
which should tend to make them feel with greater acuteness
the loss they were about to sustain. It was bright,
unclouded and serene. It was the eloquence as of a disembodied
spirit, freed from the perturbation and alloy of
human passions. She reminded them that they were sisters,
and exhorted each to fulfil the duties of a sister and
a mother to the other two. If wise and good, they would
be happy in each other, and their little association would be
a school, preparing them for the more genuine and venerable
duties for which nature had destined them. Her views
of all human things were altered by her present situation on
the brink of the grave. Our reserves and misunderstandings
had wrung her heart; but she forgave me. Things
which had lately appeared of the highest magnitude and
moment, faded in the distance, and mingled with the vulgar
crowd of human concerns which was now retiring from
her view: she must again return, she said, to life, before she
could again feel the passions and the interests of this petty
scene. For the sake of her daughters she had lately desired
to live. She was now reconciled and content to die.
She had formed the chain and link of connection between
me and my girls; perhaps it was better that we should
burst our fetters and be free. On the fourth day after
our arrival at Barcelona Marguerite expired.
There is nothing in the vast variety of objects which
this wretched world presents to our view so dreadful and
distressing as the sight of one we have loved, but who is
now no more. I saw, these eyes beheld, the lifeless corse[294]
of Marguerite. Great God of heaven! what is man?
and of what are we made? Within that petty frame resided
for years all that we worship, for there resided all
that we know and can conceive of excellence. That heart
is now still. Within the whole extent of that frame there
exists no thought, no feeling, no virtue. It remains no
longer, but to mock my sense and scoff at my sorrow, to
rend my bosom with a woe, complicated, matchless and
inexpressible. The cheek is pale and livid; the eyes are
sunk and circled with blackness. Corruption and ruin
have already seized their prey and turned it into horror.
Draw, for heaven’s sake, draw the pall over those lifeless
features! Bury, bury them deep in the bowels of the
earth! Let not my imagination follow them into the
chambers of the grave, and dwell amidst pestilential damps
and all the series of destruction! Let me recollect all that
Marguerite was as she lived, her numerous accomplishments,
her unparalleled virtues,—ay, in all the magnitude
and wealth of their detail,—for that is a divine and
celestial madness: but let me not recollect her as I saw her
on the bier, lest I become raving and blaspheme!
I have no power to talk of the situation in which I was
now placed, and the reader must therefore explain it for
himself,—if he can. I never loved but once; I never
loved but Marguerite. All other affection is stillness and
ice compared with this. This is the great crisis of my
history, the gap between life and death, the gulf that cut
me off for ever from every thing that deserves the name of
human. Such was the legacy of the stranger! my son an
exile, myself publicly arraigned as a murderer, the unmerited
and tragical death of Hector, the premature and
self-deriving loss of the better half of my soul! Who
would have believed that this envenomed gift would, in less
than two years, have thus dreadfully changed the face of
my affairs, and destroyed every thing that composed the
happiness of my life?
After some delay in this wretched and ill-omened town of
Barcelona (such it has ever since appeared to my thoughts),
we proceeded to Madrid. The reader will give me credit,
when I tell him that, however eager I had lately felt to[295]
exhibit my magnificence and my wealth, I had no such
eagerness now. I speak no more of the character of Marguerite;
I attempt not to compose her panegyric. The
story of her life is the best record of her virtues. Her defects,
if defects she had, drew their pedigree from rectitude
of sentiment and perception, from the most generous sensibility,
from a heart pervaded and leavened with tenderness.
A simple stone in the western aisle of the great
church at Barcelona records her personal and her family
name, with this single addition, THE PRESERVER OF HER
FAMILY IN POVERTY AND RUIN, THE VICTIM OF HER DISCONSOLATE
AND REPENTANT HUSBAND’S UNHALLOWED
WEALTH.
But, dismissing for ever, and henceforth consigning to
unviolated silence her excellencies, could I avoid feeling
that I could never again form a similar, or indeed any
real union, so long as I existed? Being now indeed more
than forty years of age, having spent near twenty of that
forty in a most enviable wedlock, and being blessed with a
sufficiently numerous offspring, it may be thought perhaps
I might be contented. But, without discussing the propriety
of such a maxim as it relates to the species in
general, it must be recollected in my case that my youth
was to be recommenced by a perpetual series of renewals.
I never gave credit to that axiom of a sickly sensibility,
that it is a sacrilege, in him who has been engaged in one
cordial and happy union, ever to turn his thoughts to
another. Much more reasonable than this is the Indian
doctrine, that the survivor ought to leap into the flames,
and perish upon the funeral pyre of the deceased. While
we live, it is one of our most imperious duties to seek
our happiness. He that dedicates his days to an endless
sorrow is the worst and most degraded of suicides. It is
an important question in the economy of human life, up to
what age we should allow ourselves to contract engagements
to a wife and a probable offspring: but, separately
from this consideration, I should hold that in many cases
he who entered into a second marriage, by that action
yielded a pure and honourable homage to the manes of the
first. But from genuine marriage I was henceforth for[296]
ever debarred. An immortal can form no true and real
attachment to the insect of an hour.
Mourning, a depressing and speechless regret, was yet
the inmate of our house. Grief does not commonly lay a
strong and invincible hold of us in the morning of our
days; and, though the temper of Julia was perhaps at her
age the most tender and susceptible I ever knew, even she,
who was now in her seventeenth year, reaped the benefit
of that elasticity which in early life is the portion of
humanity. Nothing material occurred to us in the first
three months of our residence in Madrid. It was impossible
for any one to be surrounded with a more lovely
and blooming family than I was.
Yet from happiness I was immeasurably distant. Exclusively
of my recent and in every sense irreparable loss,
my mind was full of dark and gloomy forebodings. I
feared not for myself, but I had an unconquerable alarm
and apprehension for my children. My youngest was but
ten years of age; the eldest was not seventeen. Sweet,
tender blossoms, that the cruelty and hardness of mankind
might so easily blight, and that required a concurrence of
favourable circumstances to ripen into all they were capable
of becoming! When I recollected what had happened in
the course of the last two years, I could not flatter myself
that our misfortunes were at an end, or that I had not, to
speak moderately, many fierce trials yet to encounter. I
seemed, like the far-famed tree of Java, to be destined to
shelter only to destroy, and to prove a deadly poison to
whatever sought its refuge under my protecting branches.
In this melancholy frame of mind the last words of my
adored Marguerite passed and repassed ten thousand times
through my recollection. “She had formed the chain and
link of connection between me and my girls; perhaps it
was better that we should burst our fetters and be free.”
Whatever she had said was sacred to the present temper
of my imagination: her last behest I would have died to
execute. The idea contained in the sentence I have just
repeated was ambiguous and obscure, rather hinted, than
expressed. But was it worthy of the less attention, because
its author, with her usual gentleness and sweetness,[297]
had modestly suggested an advice, instead, which she was
well entitled to have done, of prescribing a will? I determined
to part with my children, that I might no longer
be to them a source of corroding misery and affliction. I
believed that the cloud that now oppressed me was transitory.
I seemed pursued for the present by a malignant
genius; but a man, endowed as I was with unbounded
wealth and immortal vigour, cannot easily be reduced to
despair. When the tide of my prosperity should unfold
its rich and ample current, I might easily communicate of
its bounty to my daughters. If I parted with them now,
I did not lose them as I had perhaps lost their brother for
ever. I could turn to a particular point, and say, “There
lies my soul!” I could cast my eye upon a projection
of the globe, and put my finger upon their residence.
Wherever I wandered, whether I were plunged in a dungeon
or mounted a throne, my heart, like the mariner’s
needle, would tremble towards that point as its cynosure.
I had still something to love, something to pant for, something
to dream about, and be happy.
Having ruminated insatiably upon the last expressions
of Marguerite, having formed my commentary, and fixed
my predilection, I recollected a person, then a young
woman upon my paternal estate, for whom my wife had
conceived a remarkable friendship. She was the daughter
of a peasant, her birth had been low, and her education
confined. But she had taste, she had discretion, she had
integrity, I think I may add, she had genius. As Marguerite
had discovered her merits, and distinguished her
from her equals, she had been of great use to this extraordinary
rustic in unfolding her mind, and guiding her
propensities. This was not so much a matter of deliberate
and meditated purpose in la dame du seigneur; it rose
out of the circumstances of their situation. They were
almost of an age; and Marguerite frequently invited her
to be the associate of her studies and amusements. Mariana,
that was her name, did not perhaps resemble my wife
considerably in her features, but her stature was the same,
her complexion and the colour of her hair. The similarity
in carriage and gesture, Mariana having never had an[298]
opportunity of contemplating the accomplishments she
admired in any one but madame de St. Leon, was still
more striking. There were points indeed in which no
human creature could compare with Marguerite, the expressive
and flexible tone of her voice, and those cadences,
which sprung from, and communicated to every susceptible
hearer, the divinest sensibility. One of the unhappy consequences
of our exile from the Bordelois was the misfortunes
of Mariana. Her father had fallen to decay. To
relieve his distress she had contracted a marriage, not of
sentiment and predilection, but with a man who had promised
her that her father should never come to want. This
marriage had been unhappy. The husband was a prodigal
and a profligate. A period of seven years however delivered
her from her Egyptian bondage. She had but
lately become a widow; and the prudence and integrity of
her conduct had rendered this alliance, which to many
women would have proved a rock of destruction, an additional
source of honour and respect. Mariana, at the
death of her husband, had no children; she had buried her
father; she was consequently entirely alone.
It was this woman I fixed upon as the protector of my
daughters. I was better pleased with the meanness of her
extraction, than I should have been with one of the high-born
descendants of the houses of St. Leon or Damville,
had it been my fortune to have had in the female line any
near relations on either side. My daughters were no longer
children; they were singularly prudent, considerate, and
unimpeachable in their conduct and propensities. They
wanted a protector in the eye of the world; it was desirable
for them that they should have an adviser; but I should
have been grieved and mortified to give them a dictator.
I wrote to Mariana Chabot, communicating my project,
and requesting her to give us the meeting at St. Lizier on
the frontiers of France. She was delighted with the office
I tendered to her acceptance, and readily consented to every
thing I required. I conducted my daughters to the place
of rendezvous without imparting to them the design by
which I was actuated; I believed that they would of their
own motion conceive a partiality for the friend of their[299]
mother. I was not deceived in my prognostic; the meeting
was an interesting one. The eyes of Mariana overflowed
at meeting, after so long an interval, the husband and progeny
of the dearest and most revered friend she had ever
known; the mourning we wore reminded her how lately
her incomparable patroness had been committed to the
grave. My girls were struck with the resemblance of
Mariana to their mother. Accident had prevented us from
cultivating almost any intimate connections out of our own
family from the period of our exile; my girls had therefore
never met with a person who approached in any degree so
near their mother in accomplishments, in skill, in turn of
thinking and opinion. Mariana came up to my warmest
hopes as a protector and companion for my children; her
unhappy marriage, by concentrating her thoughts and expectations
in herself, had perhaps rendered her more exemplary
in carriage, and more elevated in sentiment, than she
would ever have been without it.
At St. Lizier I passed myself for monsieur Valmier, the
guardian of the orphan heiresses of St. Leon. It fortunately
happened that my paternal estate was at this time
upon sale. I determined to become the purchaser, and to
settle my girls in the scene of their nativity. I procured
an agent, and despatched him with an ample commission
for that purpose. Having adjusted this point, I resolved to
make a tour with my daughters, through Languedoc, Dauphiné,
and the provinces usually known by the denomination
of the south of France. I wished to familiarise them to
the society of madame Chabot, and to assist them in discerning
her merits under a variety of points of view. I
asked them whether they would not be delighted to obtain
her as a companion, who might assist and conduct them in
such points as only a woman of understanding and experience
is competent to. They, every one of them, listened
to the idea with pleasure.
At length I received the information that the purchase of
St. Leon was completed, and I proceeded to the critical disclosure
that my daughters were on the point of being
separated from their father. They listened to the communication
with astonishment and terror. They had entered[300]
successively into the feelings of their deceased mother, and
I am well persuaded felt a less ardent attachment to my
person than they had done at the cottage of the lake of
Constance. But, culpable and criminal as I had been, I
was not destitute of every virtue, and they could not extinguish
in themselves the respect they had so long entertained
for me. Habit has a resistless empire over the
human mind; and, when we reflect with how much reluctance
we consent to the removal of a tree or a hedge, to
the sight of which we have been accustomed, it will not be
wondered at that my daughters could not calmly think of so
complete a separation from their father. The impression
of their mother’s death was yet green, and to lose me, was
to become orphans a second time. But I had fully meditated
my plan, and was peremptory. That I might
withhold from them no advantage it was in my power to
confer, I gave them Bernardin for their superintending
bailiff and steward of their property. Our parting was not
less painful and melancholy, than its occasion was extraordinary
and its mode uncommon. It took place at the
town of Montauban.
I saw my dear children set forward on their journey, and
I knew not that I should ever behold them more. I was
determined never again to see them to their injury; and I
could not take to myself the consolation,—on such a day,
in such a month, or even after such a lapse of years, I will
again have the joy to embrace them. In a little while
they were out of sight, and I was alone. The reader will
perhaps agree with me, that no man had more exquisitely
enjoyed the dearest ties of society than I had, and that
perhaps few men were ever better formed to enjoy them.
This complete and dreadful separation, this stroke that
seemed to cut me off abruptly from every thing most
valuable that the earth contains, was not the result of any
of the ordinary necessities of human life. Still less was it
the dictate of alienation or indifference. No; it was the
pure effect of love, of a love so strong, complete, and uncontrollable,
as inflexibly to refuse every thing that could be
injurious to its objects. I own I could not thus have
parted with Marguerite. Her idea was mingled with the[301]
vital springs of my existence; and scarcely any power less
resistless than death could have made me consent to pass
an entire day without her society. But then it is to be
considered, that my daughters were in the morning of life;
their hopes were untarnished, their prospects not obscured
by a single cloud; and that the crime would probably have
been greater, obstinately to have made them the partners of
my misfortunes and disgrace. There are persons who will
regard this passage in my history as culpable, and the testimony
of a cold and unsusceptible heart. I contemplate
it, even at this distance of time, as the noblest and most
virtuous effort of my life; and a thousand circumstances
have occurred since, to induce me to congratulate myself
that I had the courage to achieve my purpose.
</div></body></text></TEI>