<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Reflections on the Decline of Science in England</title><author>Babbage, Charles (1791-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>B. Fellowes</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="3">
      SECTION 1. PROFESSIONAL IMPULSES.
    

      A large portion of those who are impelled by ambition or necessity to
      advance themselves in the world, make choice of some profession in which
      they imagine their talents likely to be rewarded with success; and there
      are peculiar advantages resulting to each from this classification of
      society into professions. The ESPRIT DE CORPS frequently overpowers the
      jealousy which exists between individuals, and pushes on to advantageous
      situations some of the more fortunate of the profession; whilst, on the
      other hand, any injury or insult offered to the weakest, is redressed or
      resented by the whole body. There are other advantages which are perhaps
      of more importance to the public. The numbers which compose the learned
      professions in England are so considerable, that a kind of public opinion
      is generated amongst them, which powerfully tends to repress conduct that
      is injurious either to the profession or to the public. Again, the mutual
      jealousy and rivalry excited amongst the whole body is so considerable,
      that although the rank and estimation which an individual holds in the
      profession may be most unfairly appreciated, by taking the opinion of his
      rival; yet few estimations will be found generally more correct than the
      opinion of a whole profession on the merits of any one of its body. This
      test is of great value to the public, and becomes the more so, in
      proportion to the difficulty of the study to which the profession is
      devoted. It is by availing themselves of it that men of sense and
      judgment, who have occasion for the services of professional persons, are,
      in a great measure, guided in their choice.
    

      The pursuit of science does not, in England, constitute a distinct
      profession, as it does in many other countries. It is therefore, on that
      ground alone, deprived of many of the advantages which attach to
      professions. One of its greatest misfortunes arises from this
      circumstance; for the subjects on which it is conversant are so difficult,
      and require such unremitted devotion of time, that few who have not spent
      years in their study can judge of the relative knowledge of those who
      pursue them. It follows, therefore, that the public, and even that men of
      sound sense and discernment, can scarcely find means to distinguish
      between the possessors of knowledge, in the present day, merely
      elementary, and those whose acquirements are of the highest order. This
      remark applies with peculiar force to all the more difficult applications
      of mathematics; and the fact is calculated to check the energies of those
      who only look to reputation in England.
    

      As there exists with us no peculiar class professedly devoted to science,
      it frequently happens that when a situation, requiring for the proper
      fulfilment of its duties considerable scientific attainments, is vacant,
      it becomes necessary to select from among amateurs, or rather from among
      persons whose chief attention has been bestowed on other subjects, and to
      whom science has been only an occasional pursuit. A certain quantity of
      scientific knowledge is of course possessed by individuals in many
      professions; and when added to the professional acquirements of the army,
      the navy, or to the knowledge of the merchant, is highly meritorious: but
      it is obvious that this may become, when separated from the profession,
      quite insignificant as the basis of a scientific reputation.
    

      To those who have chosen the profession of medicine, a knowledge of
      chemistry, and of some branches of natural history, and, indeed, of
      several other departments of science, affords useful assistance. Some of
      the most valuable names which adorn the history of English science have
      been connected with this profession.
    

      The causes which induce the selection of the clerical profession are not
      often connected with science; and it is, perhaps, a question of
      considerable doubt whether it is desirable to hold out to its members
      hopes of advancement from such acquirements. As a source of recreation,
      nothing can be more fit to occupy the attention of a divine; and our
      church may boast, in the present as in past times, that the domain of
      science has been extended by some of its brightest ornaments.
    

      In England, the profession of the law is that which seems to hold out the
      strongest attraction to talent, from the circumstance, that in it ability,
      coupled with exertion, even though unaided by patronage, cannot fail of
      obtaining reward. It is frequently chosen as an introduction to public
      life. It also presents great advantages, from its being a qualification
      for many situations more or less remotely connected with it, as well as
      from the circumstance that several of the highest officers of the state
      must necessarily have sprung from its ranks.
    

      A powerful attraction exists, therefore, to the promotion of a study and
      of duties of all others engrossing the time most completely, and which is
      less benefited than most others by any acquaintance with science. This is
      one amongst the causes why it so very rarely happens that men in public
      situations are at all conversant even with the commonest branches of
      scientific knowledge, and why scarcely an instance can be cited of such
      persons acquiring a reputation by any discoveries of their own.
    

      But, however consistent other sciences may be with professional
      avocations, there is one which, from its extreme difficulty, and the
      overwhelming attention which it demands, can only be pursued with success
      by those whose leisure is undisturbed by other claims. To be well
      acquainted with the present state of mathematics, is no easy task; but to
      add to the powers which that science possesses, is likely to be the lot of
      but few English philosophers.
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>