<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol II</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1796</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="6">ZOONOMIA;
OR,
THE LAWS OF ORGANIC LIFE.
PART III.
CONTAINING
THE ARTICLES OF THE MATERIA MEDICA,
WITH AN ACCOUNT OF THE
OPERATION OF MEDICINES.




IN VIVUM CORPUS
AGUNT MEDICAMENTA.




PREFACE.
The Materia Medica includes all those
  substances, which may contribute to the restoration of health. These may
  be conveniently distributed under seven articles according to the
  diversity of their operations.
1. Nutrientia, or those
  things which preserve in their natural state the due exertions of all the
  irritative motions.
2. Incitantia, or those
  things which increase the exertions of all the irritative motions.
3. Secernentia, or
  those things which increase the irritative motions, which constitute
  secretion.
4. Sorbentia, or those
  things which increase the irritative motions, which constitute
  absorption.
5. Invertentia, or those
  things which invert the natural order of the successive irritative
  motions.
6. Revertentia, or those
  things which restore the natural order of the inverted irritative
  motions.
7. Torpentia, those
  things which diminish the exertions of all the irritative motions.
It is necessary to apprize the reader, that in the following account
  of the virtues of Medicines their usual doses are always supposed to be
  exhibited; and the patient to be exposed to the degree of exterior heat,
  which he has been accustomed to, (where the contrary is not mentioned),
  as any variation of either of these circumstances varies their
  effects.


ARTICLES
OF THE</div></body></text></TEI>