<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="7">
CHAPTER VII.

The Variety of Organization corresponding to the Variety
of Climate.

The organization of plants and animals is in different
tribes formed upon schemes more or less different,
but in all cases adjusted in a general way to
the course and action of the elements. The differences
are connected with the different habits and
manners of living which belong to different species;
and at any one place the various species, both of
animals and plants, have a number of relations and
mutual dependences arising out of these differences.
But besides the differences of this kind, we find in
the forms of organic life another set of differences,
by which the animal and vegetable kingdom are fitted
for that variety in the climates of the earth,
which we have been endeavouring to explain.
The existence of such differences is too obvious to
require to be dwelt upon. The plants and animals
which flourish and thrive in countries remote from
each other, offer to the eye of the traveller a series
of pictures, which, even to an ignorant and unreflective
spectator, is full of a peculiar and fascinating interest
in consequence of the novelty and strangeness
of the successive scenes.
Those who describe the countries between the
tropics, speak with admiration of the luxuriant profusion
and rich variety of the vegetable productions[58]
of those regions. Vegetable life seems there far more
vigorous and active, the circumstances under which
it goes on, far more favourable than in our latitudes.
Now if we conceive an inhabitant of those regions,
knowing, from the circumstances of the earth’s form
and motion, the difference of climates which must
prevail upon it, to guess, from what he saw about
him, the condition of other parts of the globe as to
vegetable wealth, is not likely that he would suppose
that the extra-tropical climates must be almost devoid
of plants? We know that the ancients, living in the
temperate zone, came to the conclusion that both the
torrid and the frigid zones must be uninhabitable. In
like manner the equatorial reasoner would probably
conceive that vegetation must cease, or gradually
die away, as he should proceed to places further and
further removed from the genial influence of the sun.
The mean temperature of his year being about 80
degrees, he would hardly suppose that any plants
could subsist through a year, where the mean temperature
was only 50, where the temperature of the
summer quarter was only 64, and where the mean
temperature of a whole quarter of the year was a
very few degrees removed from that at which water
becomes solid. He would suppose that scarcely any
tree, shrub, or flower could exist in such a state of
things, and so far as the plants of his own country
are concerned, he would judge rightly.
But the countries further removed from the equator
are not left thus unprovided. Instead of being
scantily occupied by such of the tropical plants as
could support a stunted and precarious life in ungenial
climes, they are abundantly stocked with a multitude
of vegetables which appear to be constructed
expressly for them, inasmuch as these species can no
more flourish at the equator than the equatorial species
can in these temperate regions. And such new
supplies thus adapted to new conditions, recur perpetually
as we advance towards the apparently frozen
and untenantable regions in the neighbourhood of the[59]
pole. Every zone has its peculiar vegetables; and as
we miss some, we find others make their appearance,
as if to replace those which are absent.
If we look at the indigenous plants of Asia and
Europe, we find such a succession as we have here
spoken of. At the equator we find the natives of the
Spice Islands, the clove and nutmeg trees, pepper
and mace. Cinnamon bushes clothe the surface of
Ceylon; the odoriferous sandal wood, the ebony tree,
the teak tree, the banyan, grow in the East Indies.
In the same latitudes in Arabia the Happy we find
balm, frankincense and myrrh, the coffee tree, and
the tamarind. But in these countries, at least in the
plains, the trees and shrubs which decorate our more
northerly climes are wanting. And as we go northwards,
at every step we change the vegetable group,
both by addition and by subtraction. In the thickets
to the west of the Caspian Sea we have the apricot,
citron, peach, walnut. In the same latitude in Spain,
Sicily, and Italy, we find the dwarf palm, the cypress,
the chestnut, the cork tree: the orange and
lemon tree perfume the air with their blossoms; the
myrtle and pomegranate grow wild among the rocks.
We cross the Alps, and we find the vegetation which
belongs to northern Europe, of which England is an
instance. The oak, the beech, and the elm are natives
of Great Britain: the elm tree seen in Scotland,
and in the north of England, is the wych elm. As
we travel still further to the north the forests again
change their character. In the northern provinces
of the Russian empire are found forests of the various
species of firs: the Scotch and spruce fir, and
the larch. In the Orkney Islands no tree is found
but the hazel, which occurs again on the northern
shores of the Baltic. As we proceed into colder regions
we still find species which appear to have been
made for these situations. The hoary or cold elder
makes its appearance north of Stockholm: the sycamore
and mountain ash accompany us to the head
of the gulf of Bothnia: and as we leave this and traverse[60]
the Dophrian range, we pass in succession the
boundary lines of the spruce fir, the Scotch fir, and
those minute shrubs which botanists distinguish as
the dwarf birch and dwarf willow. Here, near to
or within the arctic circle, we yet find wild flowers
of great beauty; the mezereum, the yellow and white
water lily, and the European globe flower. And
when these fail us, the reindeer moss still makes the
country habitable for animals and man.
We have thus a variety in the laws of vegetable
organization remarkably adapted to the variety of
climates; and by this adaptation the globe is clothed
with vegetation and peopled with animals from pole
to pole, while without such an adaptation vegetable
and animal life must have been confined almost, or
entirely, to some narrow zone on the earth’s surface.
We conceive that we see here the evidence of a wise
and benevolent intention, overcoming the varying
difficulties, or employing the varying resources of
the elements, with an inexhaustible fertility of contrivance,
a constant tendency to diffuse life and well
being.
2. One of the great uses to which the vegetable
wealth of the earth is applied, is the support of man,
whom it provides with food and clothing; and the
adaptation of tribes of indigenous vegetables to every
climate has, we cannot but believe, a reference to the
intention that the human race should be diffused over
the whole globe. But this end is not answered by
indigenous vegetables alone; and in the variety of
vegetables capable of being cultivated with advantage
in various countries, we conceive that we find
evidence of an additional adaptation of the scheme
of organic life to the system of the elements.
The cultivated vegetables, which form the necessaries
or luxuries of human life, are each confined
within limits, narrow, when compared with the whole
surface of the earth; yet almost every part of the
earth’s surface is capable of being abundantly covered
with one kind or other of these. When one[61]
class fails, another appears in its place. Thus corn,
wine, and oil, have each its boundaries. Wheat extends
through the old Continent, from England to
Thibet: but it stops soon in going northwards, and
is not found to succeed in the west of Scotland. Nor
does it thrive better in the torrid zone than in the
polar regions: within the tropics, wheat, barley and
oats are not cultivated, excepting in situations considerably
above the level of the sea: the inhabitants
of those countries have other species of grain, or
other food. The cultivation of the vine succeeds
only in countries where the annual temperature is
between 50 and 63 degrees. In both hemispheres,
the profitable culture of this plant ceases within 30
degrees of the equator, unless in elevated situations,
or in islands, as Teneriffe. The limits of the cultivation
of maize and of olives in France are parallel
to those which bound the vine and corn in succession
to the north. In the north of Italy, west of
Milan, we first meet with the cultivation of rice;
which extends over all the southern part of Asia,
wherever the land can be at pleasure covered with
water. In great part of Africa millet is one of the
principal kinds of grain.
Cotton is cultivated to latitude 40 in the new world,
but extends to Astrachan in latitude 46 in the old.
The sugar cane, the plantain, the mulberry, the betel
nut, the indigo tree, the tea tree, repay the labours
of the cultivator in India and China; and several of
these plants have been transferred, with success, to
America and the West Indies. In equinoctial America
a great number of inhabitants find abundant
nourishment on a narrow space cultivated with plantain,
cassava yams, and maize. The bread fruit tree
begins to be cultivated in the Manillas, and extends
through the Pacific; the sago palm in the Moluccas,
the cabbage tree in the Pelew islands.
In this manner the various tribes of men are provided
with vegetable food. Some however live on[62]
their cattle, and thus make the produce of the earth
only mediately subservient to their wants. Thus the
Tartar tribes depend on their flocks and herds for
food: the taste for the flesh of the horse seems to
belong to the Mongols, Fins, and other descendants
of the ancient Scythians: the locust eaters are found
now, as formerly, in Africa.
Many of these differences depend upon custom,
soil, and other causes with which we do not here
meddle; but many are connected with climate: and
the variety of the resources which man thus possesses,
arises from the variety of constitution belonging to
cultivable vegetables, through which one is fitted to
one range of climate, and another to another. We
conceive that this variety and succession of fitness
for cultivation, shows undoubted marks of a most
foreseeing and benevolent design in the Creator of
man and of the world.
3. By differences in vegetables of the kind we
have above described, the sustentation and gratification
of man’s physical nature is copiously provided
for. But there is another circumstance, a result of
the difference of the native products of different regions,
and therefore a consequence of that difference
of climate on which the difference of native products
depends,[5] which appears to be worthy our
notice. The difference of the productions of different
countries has a bearing not only upon the physical,
but upon the social and moral condition of
man.
The intercourse of nations in the way of discovery,
colonization, commerce; the study of the
natural history, manners, institutions of foreign
countries; lead to most numerous and important results.
Without dwelling upon this subject, it will[63]
probably be allowed that such intercourse has a
great influence upon the comforts, the prosperity,
the arts, the literature, the power, of the nations
which thus communicate. Now the variety of the
productions of different lands supplies both the stimulus
to this intercourse, and the instruments by
which it produces its effects. The desire to possess
the objects or the knowledge which foreign countries
alone can supply, urges the trader, the traveller, the
discoverer to compass land and sea; and the progress
of the arts and advantages of civilization consists
almost entirely in the cultivation, the use, the
improvement of that which has been received from
other countries.
This is the case to a much greater extent than
might at first sight be supposed. Where man is
active as a cultivator, he scarcely ever bestows
much of his care on those vegetables which the
land would produce in a state of nature. He does
not select some of the plants of the soil and improve
them by careful culture, but, for the most part, he
expels the native possessors of the land, and introduces
colonies of strangers.
Thus, to take the condition of our own part of the
globe as an example; scarcely one of the plants
which occupy our fields and gardens is indigenous
to the country. The walnut and the peach come to
us from Persia; the apricot from Armenia: from
Asia Minor, and Syria, we have the cherry tree,
the fig, the pear, the pomegranate, the olive, the
plum, and the mulberry. The vine which is now
cultivated is not a native of Europe; it is found wild
on the shores of the Caspian, in Armenia and Caramania.
The most useful species of plants, the cereal
vegetables, are certainly strangers, though their
birth place seems to be an impenetrable secret.
Some have fancied that barley is found wild on the
banks of the Semara, in Tartary, rye in Crete, wheat
at Baschkiros, in Asia; but this is held by the best
botanists to be very doubtful. The potatoe, which[64]
has been so widely diffused over the world in modern
times, and has added so much to the resources of
life in many countries, has been found equally difficult
to trace back to its wild condition.
Thus widely are spread the traces of the connexion
of the progress of civilization with national intercourse.
In our own country a higher state of the
arts of life is marked by a more ready and extensive
adoption of foreign productions. Our fields are
covered with herbs from Holland, and roots from
Germany; with Flemish farming and Swedish turnips;
our hills with forests of the firs of Norway.
The chestnut and poplar of the south of Europe
adorn our lawns, and below them flourish shrubs
and flowers from every clime in profusion. In the
mean time Arabia improves our horses, China our
pigs, North America our poultry, Spain our sheep,
and almost every country sends its dog. The products
which are ingredients in our luxuries, and
which we cannot naturalize at home, we raise in our
colonies; the cotton, coffee, sugar of the east are
thus transplanted to the farthest west; and man lives
in the middle of a rich and varied abundance which
depends on the facility with which plants and animals
and modes of culture can be transferred into lands
far removed from those in which nature had placed
them. And this plenty and variety of material comforts
is the companion and the mark of advantages
and improvements in social life, of progress in art
and science, of activity of thought, of energy of
purpose, and of ascendancy of character.
The differences in the productions of different
countries which lead to the habitual intercourse of
nations, and through this to the benefits which we
have thus briefly noticed, do not all depend upon the
differences of temperature and climate alone. But
these differences are among the causes, and are some
of the most important causes, or conditions, of the
variety of products; and thus that arrangement of[65]
the earth’s form and motion from which the different
climates of different places arises, is connected with
the social and moral welfare and advancement of
man.
We conceive that this connexion, though there
must be to our apprehension much that is indefinite
and uncertain in tracing its details, is yet a point
where we may perceive the profound and comprehensive
relations established by the counsel and foresight
of a wise and good Creator of the world and of
man, by whom the progress and elevation of the human
species was neither uncontemplated nor uncared
for.
4. We have traced, in the variety of organized
beings, an adaptation to the variety of climates, a
provision for the sustentation of man all over the
globe, and an instrument for the promotion of civilization
and many attendant benefits. We have not
considered this variety as itself a purpose which we
can perceive or understand without reference to
some ulterior end. Many persons, however, and
especially those who are already in the habit of referring
the world to its Creator, will probably see
something admirable in itself in this vast variety of
created things. There is indeed something well
fitted to produce and confirm a reverential wonder,
in these apparently inexhaustible stores of new forms
of being and modes of existence; the fixity of the
laws of each class, its distinctness from all others, its
relations to many. Structures and habits and characters
are exhibited, which are connected and distinguished
according to every conceivable degree of
subordination and analogy, in their resemblances
and in their differences. Every new country we explore
presents us with new combinations, where the
possible cases seem to be exhausted; and with new
resemblances and differences, constructed as if to
elude what conjecture might have hit upon, by proceeding
from the old ones. Most of those who have[66]
any large portion of nature brought under their notice
in this point of view, are led to feel that there is,
in such a creation, a harmony, a beauty, and a dignity,
of which the impression is irresistible; which
would have been wanting in any more uniform and
limited system such as we might try to imagine; and
which of itself gives to the arrangements by which
such a variety on the earth’s surface is produced, the
character of well devised means to a worthy end.
</div></body></text></TEI>