<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Chambers Robert</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="18">p.
361PURPOSE AND GENERAL CONDITION OF THE ANIMATED
CREATION.
We have now to inquire how this
view of the constitution and origin of nature bears upon the
condition of man upon the earth, and his relation to
supra-mundane things.
That enjoyment is the proper attendant of animal existence is
pressed upon us by all that we see and all we experience. 
Everywhere we perceive in the lower creatures, in their ordinary
condition, symptoms of enjoyment.  Their whole being is a
system of needs, the supplying of which is gratification, and of
faculties, the exercise of which is pleasurable.  When we
consult our own sensations, we find that, even in a sense of a
healthy performance of all the functions of the animal economy,
God has furnished us with an innocent and very high
enjoyment.  The mere quiet consciousness of a healthy play
of the mental functions—a mind at ease with itself and all
around it—is in like manner extremely agreeable.  This
negative class of enjoyments, it may be remarked, is likely to be
even more extensively experienced by the lower animals than by
man, at least in the proportion of their absolute endowments, as
their mental and bodily functions are much less liable to
derangement than ours.  To find the world constituted on
this principle is only what in reason we would expect.  We
cannot conceive that so vast a system could have been created for
a contrary purpose.  No averagely constituted human being
would, in his own limited sphere of action, think of producing a
similar system upon an opposite principle.  But to form so
vast a range of being, and to make being everywhere a source of
gratification, is conformable to our ideas of a Creator in whom
we are constantly discovering traits of a nature, of which our
own is but a faint and far-cast shadow at the best.
It appears at first difficult to reconcile with this idea the
many miseries which we see all sentient beings, ourselves
included, occasionally enduring.  How, the sage has asked in
every age, should a Being so transcendently kind, have allowed of
so large an admixture of evil in the condition of his
creatures?  Do we not at length find an answer to a certain
extent satisfactory, in the view which has now been given of the
constitution of nature?  We there see the Deity operating in
the most august of his works by fixed laws, an arrangement which,
it is clear, only admits of the main and primary results being
good, but disregards exceptions.  Now the mechanical laws
are so definite in their purposes, that no exceptions ever take
place in that department; if there is a certain quantity of
nebulous matter to be agglomerated and divided and set in motion
as a planetary system, it will be so with hair’s-breadth
accuracy, and cannot be otherwise.  But the laws presiding
over meteorology, life, and mind, are necessarily less definite,
as they have to produce a great variety of mutually related
results.  Left to act independently of each other, each
according to its separate commission, and each with a wide range
of potentiality to be modified by associated conditions, they can
only have effects generally beneficial: often there must be an
interference of one law with another, often a law will chance to
operate in excess, or upon a wrong object, and thus evil will be
produced.  Thus, winds are generally useful in many ways,
and the sea is useful as a means of communication between one
country and another; but the natural laws which produce winds are
of indefinite range of action, and sometimes are unusually
concentrated in space or in time, so as to produce storms and
hurricanes, by which much damage is done; the sea may be by these
causes violently agitated, so that many barks and many lives
perish.  Here, it is evident, the evil is only
exceptive.  Suppose, again, that a boy, in the course of the
lively sports proper to his age, suffers a fall which injures his
spine, and renders him a cripple for life.  Two things have
been concerned in the case: first, the love of violent exercise,
and second, the law of gravitation.  Both of these things
are good in the main.  In the rash enterprises and rough
sports in which boys engage, they prepare their bodies and minds
for the hard tasks of life.  By gravitation, all moveable
things, our own bodies included, are kept stable on the surface
of the earth.  But when it chances that the playful boy
loses his hold (we shall say) of the branch of a tree, and has no
solid support immediately below, the law of gravitation
unrelentingly pulls him to the ground, and thus he is hurt. 
Now it was not a primary object of gravitation to injure boys;
but gravitation could not but operate in the circumstances, its
nature being to be universal and invariable.  The evil is,
therefore, only a casual exception from something in the main
good.
The same explanation applies to even the most conspicuous of
the evils which afflict society.  War, it may be said, and
said truly, is a tremendous example of evil, in the misery,
hardship, waste of human life, and mis-spending of human
energies, which it occasions.  But what is it that produces
war?  Certain tendencies of human nature, as keen assertion
of a supposed right, resentment of supposed injury,
acquisitiveness, desire of admiration, combativeness, or mere
love of excitement.  All of these are tendencies which are
every day, in a legitimate extent of action, producing great and
indispensable benefits to us.  Man would be a tame,
indolent, unserviceable being without them, and his fate would be
starvation.  War, then, huge evil though it be, is, after
all, but the exceptive case, a casual misdirection of properties
and powers essentially good.  God has given us the
tendencies for a benevolent purpose.  He has only not laid
down any absolute obstruction to our misuse of them.  That
were an arrangement of a kind which he has nowhere made. 
But he has established many laws in our nature which tend to
lessen the frequency and destructiveness of these abuses. 
Our reason comes to see that war is purely an evil, even to the
conqueror.  Benevolence interposes to make its ravages less
mischievous to human comfort, and less destructive to human
life.  Men begin to find that their more active powers can
be exercised with equal gratification on legitimate objects; for
example, in overcoming the natural difficulties of their path
through life, or in a generous spirit of emulation in a line of
duty beneficial to themselves and their fellow-creatures. 
Thus, war at length shrinks into a comparatively narrow compass,
though there certainly is no reason to suppose that it will be at
any early period, if ever, altogether dispensed with, while
man’s constitution remains as it is.  In considering
an evil of this kind, we must not limit our view to our own or
any past time.  Placed upon the earth with faculties
prepared to act, but inexperienced, and with the more active
propensities necessarily in great force to suit the condition of
the globe, man was apt to misuse his powers much in this way at
first, compared with what he is likely to do when he advances
into a condition of civilization.  In the scheme of
providence, thousands of years of frequent warfare, all the
so-called glories which fill history, may be only an exception to
the general rule.
The sex passion in like manner leads to great evils; but the
evils are only an exception from the vast mass of good connected
with this affection.  Providence has seen it necessary to
make very ample provision for the preservation and utmost
possible extension of all species.  The aim seems to be to
diffuse existence as widely as possible, to fill up every vacant
piece of space with some sentient being to be a vehicle of
enjoyment.  Hence this passion is conferred in great
force.  But the relation between the number of beings, and
the means of supporting them, is only on the footing of general
law.  There may be occasional discrepancies between the laws
operating for the multiplication of individuals, and the laws
operating to supply them with the means of subsistence, and evils
will be endured in consequence, even in our own highly favoured
species.  But against all these evils, and against those
numberless vexations which have arisen in all ages from the
attachment of the sexes, place the vast amount of happiness which
is derived from this source—the basis of the whole circle
of the domestic affections, the sweetening principle of life, the
prompter of all our most generous feelings, and even of our most
virtuous resolves—and every ill that can be traced to it is
but as dust in the balance.  And here, also, we must be on
our guard against judging from what we see in the world at a
particular era.  As reason and the higher sentiments of
man’s nature increase in force, this passion is put under
better regulation, so as to lessen many of the evils connected
with it.  The civilized man is more able to give it due
control; his attachments are less the result of impulse; he
studies more the weal of his partner and offspring.  There
are even some of the resentful feelings connected in early
society with love, such as hatred of successful rivalry, and
jealousy, which almost disappear in an advanced stage of
civilization.  The evils springing, in our own species at
least, from this passion, may therefore be an exception mainly
peculiar to a particular term of the world’s progress, and
which may be expected to decrease greatly in amount.
With respect, again, to disease, so prolific a cause of
suffering to man, the human constitution is merely a complicated
but regular process in electro-chemistry, which goes on well, and
is a source of continual gratification, so long as nothing occurs
to interfere with it injuriously, but which is liable every
moment to be deranged by various external agencies, when it
becomes a source of pain, and, if the injury be severe, ceases to
be capable of retaining life.  It may be readily admitted
that the evils experienced in this way are very great; but, after
all, such experiences are no more than occasional, and not
necessarily frequent—exceptions from a general rule of
which the direct action is to confer happiness.  The human
constitution might have been made of a more hardy character; but
we always see hardiness and insensibility go together, and it may
be of course presumed that we only could have purchased this
immunity from suffering at the expense of a large portion of that
delicacy in which lie some of our most agreeable
sensations.  Or man’s faculties might have been
restricted to definiteness of action, as is greatly the case with
those of the lower animals, and thus we should have been equally
safe from the aberrations which lead to disease; but in that
event we should have been incapable of acting to so many
different purposes as we are, and of the many high enjoyments
which the varied action of our faculties places in our power: we
should not, in short, have been human beings, but merely on a
level with the inferior animals.  Thus, it appears, that the
very fineness of man’s constitution, that which places him
in such a high relation to the mundane economy, and makes him the
vehicle of so many exquisitely delightful sensations—it is
this which makes him liable to the sufferings of disease. 
It might be said, on the other hand, that the noxiousness of the
agencies producing disease might have been diminished or
extinguished; but the probability is, that this could not have
been done without such a derangement of the whole economy of
nature as would have been attended with more serious evils. 
For example—a large class of diseases are the result of
effluvia from decaying organic matter.  This kind of matter
is known to be extremely useful, when mixed with earth, in
favouring the process of vegetation.  Supposing the
noxiousness to the human constitution done away with, might we
not also lose that important quality which tends so largely to
increase the food raised from the ground?  Perhaps (as has
been suggested) the noxiousness is even a matter of special
design, to induce us to put away decaying organic substances into
the earth, where they are calculated to be so useful.  Now
man has reason to enable him to see that such substances are
beneficial under one arrangement, and noxious in the other. 
He is, as it were, commanded to take the right method in dealing
with it.  In point of fact, men do not always take this
method, but allow accumulations of noxious matter to gather close
about their dwellings, where they generate fevers and
agues.  But their doing so may be regarded as only a
temporary exception from the operation of mental laws, the
general tendency of which is to make men adopt the proper
measures.  And these measures will probably be in time
universally adopted, so that one extensive class of diseases will
be altogether or nearly abolished.
Another large class of diseases spring from mismanagement of
our personal economy.  Eating to excess, eating and drinking
what is noxious, disregard to that cleanliness which is necessary
for the right action of the functions of the skin, want of fresh
air for the supply of the lungs, undue, excessive, and irregular
indulgence of the mental affections, are all of them recognised
modes of creating that derangement of the system in which disease
consists.  Here also it may be said that a limitation of the
mental faculties to definite manifestations (vulgo,
instincts) might have enabled us to avoid many of these errors;
but here again we are met by the consideration that, if we had
been so endowed, we should have been only as the lower animals
are, wanting that transcendently higher character of sensation
and power, by which our enjoyments are made so much
greater.  In making the desire of food, for example, with us
an indefinite mental manifestation, instead of the definite one,
which it is amongst the lower animals, the Creator has given us a
means of deriving far greater gratifications from food
(consistently with health) than the lower animals appear to be
capable of.  He has also given us reason to act as a guiding
and controlling power over this and other propensities, so that
they may be prevented from becoming causes of malady.  We
can see that excess is injurious, and are thus prompted to
moderation.  We can see that all the things which we feel
inclined to take are not healthful, and are thus exhorted to
avoid what are pernicious.  We can also see that a cleanly
skin and a constant supply of pure air are necessary to the
proper performance of some of the most important of the organic
functions, and thus are stimulated to frequent ablution, and to a
right ventilation of our parlours and sleeping apartments. 
And so on with the other causes of disease.  Reason may not
operate very powerfully to these purposes in an early state of
society, and prodigious evils may therefore have been endured
from disease in past ages; but these are not necessarily to be
endured always.  As civilization advances, reason acquires a
greater ascendancy; the causes of the evils are seen and avoided;
and disease shrinks into a comparatively narrow compass. 
The experience of our own country places this in a striking
light.  In the middle ages, when large towns had no police
regulations, society was every now and then scourged by
pestilence.  The third of the people of Europe are said to
have been carried off by one epidemic.  Even in London the
annual mortality has greatly sunk within a century.  The
improvement in human life, which has taken place since the
construction of the Northampton tables by Dr. Price, is equally
remarkable.  Modern tables still shew a prodigious mortality
among the young in all civilized countries—evidently a
result of some prevalent error in the usual modes of rearing
them.  But to remedy this evil there is the sagacity of the
human mind, and the sense to adopt any reformed plans which may
be shewn to be necessary.  By a change in the management of
an orphan institution in London, during the last fifty years, an
immense reduction in the mortality took place.  We may of
course hope to see measures devised and adopted for producing a
similar improvement of infant life throughout the world at
large.
In this part of our subject, the most difficult point
certainly lies in those occurrences of disease where the
afflicted individual has been in no degree concerned in bringing
the visitation upon himself.  Daily experience shews us
infectious disease arising in a place where the natural laws in
respect of cleanliness are neglected, and then spreading into
regions where there is no blame of this kind.  We then see
the innocent suffering equally with those who may be called the
guilty.  Nay, the benevolent physician who comes to succour
the miserable beings whose error may have caused the mischief, is
sometimes seen to fall a victim to it, while many of his patients
recover.  We are also only too familiar with the
transmission of diseases from erring parents to innocent
children, who, accordingly suffer, and perhaps die prematurely,
as it were for the sins of others.  After all, however
painful such cases may be in contemplation, they cannot be
regarded in any other light than as exceptions from arrangements,
the general working of which is beneficial.
With regard to the innocence of the suffering parties, there
is one important consideration which is pressed upon us from many
quarters, namely—that moral conditions have not the least
concern in the working of these simply physical laws.  These
laws proceed with an entire independence of all such conditions,
and desirably so, for otherwise there could be no certain
dependence placed upon them.  Thus it may happen that two
persons ascending a piece of scaffolding, the one a virtuous, the
other a vicious man, the former, being the less cautious of the
two, ventures upon an insecure place, falls, and is killed, while
the other, choosing a better footing, remains uninjured.  It
is not in what we can conceive of the nature of things, that
there should be a special exemption from the ordinary laws of
matter, to save this virtuous man.  So it might be that, of
two physicians, attending fever cases, in a mean part of a large
city, the one, an excellent citizen, may stand in such a position
with respect to the beds of the patients as to catch the
infection, of which he dies in a few days, while the other, a bad
husband and father, and who, unlike the other, only attends such
cases with selfish ends, takes care to be as much as possible out
of the stream of infection, and accordingly escapes.  In
both of these cases man’s sense of good and evil—his
faculty of conscientiousness—would incline him to destine
the vicious man to destruction and save the virtuous.  But
the Great Ruler of Nature does not act on such principles. 
He has established laws for the operation of inanimate matter,
which are quite unswerving, so that when we know them, we have
only to act in a certain way with respect to them, in order to
obtain all the benefits and avoid all the evils connected with
them.  He has likewise established moral laws in our nature,
which are equally unswerving, (allowing for their wider range of
action,) and from obedience to which unfailing good is to be
derived.  But the two sets of laws are independent of each
other.  Obedience to each gives only its own proper
advantage, not the advantage proper to the other.  Hence it
is that virtue forms no protection against the evils connected
with the physical laws, while, on the other hand, a man skilled
in and attentive to these, but unrighteous and disregardful of
his neighbour, is in like manner not protected by his attention
to physical circumstances from the proper consequences of neglect
or breach of the moral laws.
Thus it is that the innocence of the party suffering for the
faults of a parent, or of any other person or set of persons, is
evidently a consideration quite apart from that suffering.
It is clear, moreover, from the whole scope of the natural
laws, that the individual, as far as the present sphere of being
is concerned, is to the Author of Nature a consideration of
inferior moment.  Everywhere we see the arrangements for the
species perfect; the individual is left, as it were, to take his
chance amidst the mêlée of the various laws
affecting him.  If he be found inferiorly endowed, or ill
befalls him, there was at least no partiality against him. 
The system has the fairness of a lottery, in which every one has
the like chance of drawing the prize.
Yet it is also to be observed that few evils are altogether
unmixed.  God, contemplating apparently the unbending action
of his great laws, has established others which appear to be
designed to have a compensating, a repairing, and a consoling
effect.  Suppose, for instance, that, from a defect in the
power of development in a mother, her offspring is ushered into
the world destitute of some of the most useful members, or blind,
or deaf, or of imperfect intellect, there is ever to be found in
the parents and other relatives, and in the surrounding public, a
sympathy with the sufferer, which tends to make up for the
deficiency, so that he is in the long run not much a loser. 
Indeed, the benevolence implanted in our nature seems to be an
arrangement having for one of its principal objects to cause us,
by sympathy and active aid, to remedy the evils unavoidably
suffered by our fellow-creatures in the course of the operation
of the other natural laws.  And even in the sufferer
himself, it is often found that a defect in one point is made up
for by an extra power in another.  The blind come to have a
sense of touch much more acute than those who see.  Persons
born without hands have been known to acquire a power of using
their feet for a number of the principal offices usually served
by that member.  I need hardly say how remarkably fatuity is
compensated by the more than usual regard paid to the children
born with it by their parents, and the zeal which others usually
feel to protect and succour such persons.  In short, we
never see evil of any kind take place where there is not some
remedy or compensating principle ready to interfere for its
alleviation.  And there can be no doubt that in this manner
suffering of all kinds is very much relieved.
We may, then, regard the globes of space as theatres designed
for the residence of animated sentient beings, placed there with
this as their first and most obvious purpose—namely, to be
sensible of enjoyments from the exercise of their faculties in
relation to external things.  The faculties of the various
species are very different, but the happiness of each depends on
the harmony there may be between its particular faculties and its
particular circumstances.  For instance, place the
small-brained sheep or ox in a good pasture, and it fully enjoys
this harmony of relation; but man, having many more faculties,
cannot be thus contented.  Besides having a sufficiency of
food and bodily comfort, he must have entertainment for his
intellect, whatever be its grade, objects for the domestic and
social affections, objects for the sentiments.  He is also a
progressive being, and what pleases him to-day may not please him
to-morrow; but, in each case he demands a sphere of appropriate
conditions in order to be happy.  By virtue of his superior
organization, his enjoyments are much higher and more varied than
those of any of the lower animals; but the very complexity of
circumstances affecting him renders it at the same time
unavoidable, that his nature should be often inharmoniously
placed and disagreeably affected, and that he should therefore be
unhappy.  Still unhappiness amongst mankind is the exception
from the rule of their condition, and an exception which is
capable of almost infinite diminution, by virtue of the improving
reason of man, and the experience which he acquires in working
out the problems of society.
To secure the immediate means of happiness it would seem to be
necessary for men first to study with all care the constitution
of nature, and, secondly, to accommodate themselves to that
constitution, so as to obtain all the realizable advantages from
acting conformably to it, and to avoid all likely evils from
disregarding it.  It will be of no use to sit down and
expect that things are to operate of their own accord, or through
the direction of a partial deity, for our benefit; equally so
were it to expose ourselves to palpable dangers, under the notion
that we shall, for some reason, have a dispensation or exemption
from them: we must endeavour so to place ourselves, and so to
act, that the arrangements which Providence has made impartially
for all may be in our favour, and not against us; such are the
only means by which we can obtain good and avoid evil here
below.  And, in doing this, it is especially necessary that
care be taken to avoid interfering with the like efforts of other
men, beyond what may have been agreed upon by the mass as
necessary for the general good.  Such interferences, tending
in any way to injure the body, property, or peace of a neighbour,
or to the injury of society in general, tend very much to reflect
evil upon ourselves, through the re-action which they produce in
the feelings of our neighbour and of society, and also the
offence which they give to our own conscientiousness and
benevolence.  On the other hand, when we endeavour to
promote the efforts of our fellow-creatures to attain happiness,
we produce a re-action of the contrary kind, the tendency of
which is towards our own benefit.  The one course of action
tends to the injury, the other to the benefit of ourselves and
others.  By the one course the general design of the Creator
towards his creatures is thwarted; by the other it is
favoured.  And thus we can readily see the most substantial
grounds for regarding all moral emotions and doings as divine in
their nature, and as a means of rising to and communing with
God.  Obedience is not selfishness, which it would otherwise
be—it is worship.  The merest barbarians have a
glimmering sense of this philosophy, and it continually shines
out more and more clearly in the public mind, as a nation
advances in intelligence.  Nor are individuals alone
concerned here.  The same rule applies as between one great
body or class of men and another, and also between nations. 
Thus if one set of men keep others in the condition of
slaves—this being a gross injustice to the subjected party,
the mental manifestations of that party to the masters will be
such as to mar the comfort of their lives; the minds of the
masters themselves will be degraded by the association with
beings so degraded; and thus, with some immediate or apparent
benefit from keeping slaves, there will be in a far greater
degree an experience of evil.  So also, if one portion of a
nation, engaged in a particular department of industry, grasp at
some advantages injurious to the other sections of the people,
the first effect will be an injury to those other portions of the
nation, and the second a re-active injury to the injurers, making
their guilt their punishment.  And so when one nation
commits an aggression upon the property or rights of another, or
even pursues towards it a sordid or ungracious policy, the
effects are sure to be redoubled evil from the offended
party.  All of these things are under laws which make the
effects, on a large range, absolutely certain; and an individual,
a party, a people, can no more act unjustly with safety, than I
could with safety place my leg in the track of a coming wain, or
attempt to fast thirty days.  We have been constituted on
the principle of only being able to realize happiness for
ourselves when our fellow-creatures are also happy; we must
therefore both do to others only as we would have others to do to
us, and endeavour to promote their happiness as well as our own,
in order to find ourselves truly comfortable in this field of
existence.  These are words which God speaks to us as truly
through his works, as if we heard them uttered in his own voice
from heaven.
It will occur to every one, that the system here unfolded does
not imply the most perfect conceivable love or regard on the part
of the Deity towards his creatures.  Constituted as we are,
feeling how vain our efforts often are to attain happiness or
avoid calamity, and knowing that much evil does unavoidably
befall us from no fault of ours, we are apt to feel that this is
a dreary view of the Divine economy; and before we have looked
farther, we might be tempted to say, Far rather let us cling to
the idea, so long received, that the Deity acts continually for
special occasions, and gives such directions to the fate of each
individual as he thinks meet; so that, when sorrow comes to us,
we shall have at least the consolation of believing that it is
imposed by a Father who loves us, and who seeks by these means to
accomplish our ultimate good.  Now, in the first place, if
this be an untrue notion of the Deity and his ways, it can be of
no real benefit to us; and, in the second, it is proper to
inquire if there be necessarily in the doctrine of natural law
any peculiarity calculated materially to affect our hitherto
supposed relation to the Deity.  It may be that while we are
committed to take our chance in a natural system of undeviating
operation, and are left with apparent ruthlessness to endure the
consequences of every collision into which we knowingly or
unknowingly come with each law of the system, there is a system
of Mercy and Grace behind the screen of nature, which is to make
up for all casualties endured here, and the very largeness of
which is what makes these casualties a matter of indifference to
God.  For the existence of such a system, the actual
constitution of nature is itself an argument.  The reasoning
may proceed thus: The system of nature assures us that
benevolence is a leading principle in the divine mind.  But
that system is at the same time deficient in a means of making
this benevolence of invariable operation.  To reconcile this
to the recognised character of the Deity, it is necessary to
suppose that the present system is but a part of a whole, a stage
in a Great Progress, and that the Redress is in reserve. 
Another argument here occurs—the economy of nature,
beautifully arranged and vast in its extent as it is, does not
satisfy even man’s idea of what might be; he feels that, if
this multiplicity of theatres for the exemplification of such
phenomena as we see on earth were to go on for ever unchanged, it
would not be worthy of the Being capable of creating it.  An
endless monotony of human generations, with their humble
thinkings and doings, seems an object beneath that august
Being.  But the mundane economy might be very well as a
portion of some greater phenomenon, the rest of which was yet to
be evolved.  It therefore appears that our system, though it
may at first appear at issue with other doctrines in esteem
amongst mankind, tends to come into harmony with them, and even
to give them support.  I would say, in conclusion, that,
even where the two above arguments may fail of effect, there may
yet be a faith derived from this view of nature sufficient to
sustain us under all sense of the imperfect happiness, the
calamities, the woes, and pains of this sphere of being. 
For let us but fully and truly consider what a system is here
laid open to view, and we cannot well doubt that we are in the
hands of One who is both able and willing to do us the most
entire justice.  And in this faith we may well rest at ease,
even though life should have been to us but a protracted disease,
or though every hope we had built on the secular materials within
our reach were felt to be melting from our grasp.  Thinking
of all the contingencies of this world as to be in time melted
into or lost in the greater system, to which the present is only
subsidiary, let us wait the end with patience, and be of good
cheer.</div></body></text></TEI>