<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="35">CHAPTER XXXV.
WHETHER SPECIES HAVE A REAL EXISTENCE IN NATURE—continued.
Limits of the variability of species—Species susceptible of modification may be
altered greatly in a short time, and in a few generations; after which they remain
stationary—The animals now subject to man had originally an aptitude to
domesticity—Acquired peculiarities which become hereditary have a close connexion
with the habits or instincts of the species in a wild state—Some qualities
in certain animals have been conferred with a view of their relation to man—Wild
elephant domesticated in a few years, but its faculties incapable of further
development.]
Variability of a species compared to that of an individual.—I
endeavored, in the last chapter, to show, that a belief in the reality
of species is not inconsistent with the idea of a considerable degree
of variability in the specific character. This opinion, indeed, is little
more than an extension of the idea which we must entertain of
the identity of an individual, throughout the changes which it is capable
of undergoing.
If a quadruped, inhabiting a cold northern latitude, and covered
with a warm coat of hair or wool, be transported to a southern climate,
it will often, in the course of a few years, shed a considerable portion
of its coat, which it gradually recovers on being again restored to its
native country. Even there the same changes are, perhaps, superinduced
to a certain extent by the return of winter and summer.
We know that the Alpine hare (Lepus variabilis, Pal.) and the
ermine, or stoat, (Mustela erminea, Linn.) become white during winter,
and again obtain their full color during the warmer season; that the
plumage of the ptarmigan undergoes a like metamorphosis in color
and quantity, and that the change is equally temporary. We
are aware that, if we reclaim some wild animal, and modify its habits
and instincts by domestication, it may, if it escapes, become in a few
years nearly as wild and untractable as ever; and if the same individual
be again retaken, it may be reduced to its former tame state. A plant
is sown in a prepared soil, in order that the petals of its flowers may
multiply, and their color be heightened or changed: if we then withhold
our care, the flowers of this same species become again single. In
these, and innumerable other instances, we must suppose that the
species was produced with a certain number of qualities; and, in the
case of animals, with a variety of instincts, some of which may or may
not be developed according to circumstances, or which, after having
been called forth, may again become latent when the exciting causes are
removed.
592
Now, the formation of races seems the necessary consequence
of such a capability in species to vary, if it be a general law that the
offspring should very closely resemble the parent. But, before
we can infer that there are no limits to the deviation from an original
type which may be brought about in the course of an indefinite
number of generations, we ought to have some proof that, in each
successive generation, individuals may go on acquiring an equal
amount of new peculiarities, under the influence of equal changes
of circumstances. The balance of evidence, however, inclines most
decidedly on the opposite side; for in all cases we find that the quantity
of divergence diminishes after a few generations in a very rapid
ratio.
Species susceptible of modification may be greatly altered in a few
generations.—It cannot be objected, that it is out of our power to go
on varying the circumstances in the same manner as might happen
in the natural course of events during some great geological cycle.
For in the first place, where a capacity is given to individuals to adapt
themselves to new circumstances, it does not generally require a very
long period for its development: if, indeed, such were the case, it is
not easy to see how the modification would answer the ends proposed,
for all the individuals would die before new qualities, habits, or instincts
were conferred.
When we have succeeded in naturalizing some tropical plant in
a temperate climate, nothing prevents us from attempting gradually to
extend its distribution to higher latitudes, or to greater elevations
above the level of the sea, allowing equal quantities of time, or an
equal number of generations, for habituating the species to successive
increments of cold. But every husbandman and gardener is aware
that such experiments will fail; and we are more likely to succeed in
making some plants, in the course of the first two generations, support
a considerable degree of difference of temperature, than a very small
difference afterwards, though we persevere for many centuries.
It is the same if we take any other cause instead of temperature;
such as the quality of the food, or the kind of dangers to which an
animal is exposed, or the soil in which a plant lives. The alteration
in habits, form, or organization, is often rapid during a short period;
but when the circumstances are made to vary farther, though in ever
so slight a degree, all modification ceases, and the individual perishes.
Thus some herbivorous quadrupeds may be made to feed partially on
fish or flesh; but even these can never be taught to live on some herbs
which they reject, and which would even poison them, although the
same may be very nutritious to other species of the same natural order.
So when man uses force or stratagem against wild animals, the persecuted
race soon becomes more cautious, watchful, and cunning; new
instincts seem often to be developed, and to become hereditary in the
first two or three generations: but let the skill and address of man
increase, however gradually, no farther variation can take place, no new
593
qualities are elicited by the increasing dangers. The alteration of the
habits of the species has reached a point beyond which no ulterior
modification is possible, however indefinite the lapse of ages during
which the new circumstances operate. Extirpation then follows, rather
than such a transformation as could alone enable the species to perpetuate
itself under the new state of things.
Animals now subject to man had originally an aptitude to domesticity.—It
has been well observed by M. F. Cuvier and M. Dureau de
la Malle, that unless some animals had manifested in a wild state an
aptitude to second the efforts of man, their domestication would never
have been attempted. If they had all resembled the wolf, the fox, and
the hyæna, the patience of the experimentalist would have been
exhausted by innumerable failures before he at last succeeded in obtaining
some imperfect results; so if the first advantages derived from the
cultivation of plants had been elicited by as tedious and costly a process
as that by which we now make some slight additional improvements
in certain races, we should have remained to this day in ignorance
of the greater number of their useful qualities.
Acquired instincts of some animals become hereditary.—It is undoubtedly
true, that many new habits and qualities have not only been
acquired in recent times by certain races of dogs, but have been transmitted
to their offspring. But in these cases it will be observed, that
the new peculiarities have an intimate relation to the habits of the
animal in a wild state, and therefore do not attest any tendency to
a departure to an indefinite extent from the original type of the
species. A race of dogs employed for hunting deer in the platform of
Sante Fé, in Mexico, affords a beautiful illustration of a new hereditary
instinct. The mode of attack, observes M. Roulin, which they employ
consists in seizing the animal by the belly and overturning it by a
sudden effort, taking advantage of the moment when the body of the
deer rests only upon the fore-legs. The weight of the animal thus thrown
over is often six times that of its antagonist. The dog of pure breed
inherits a disposition to this kind of chase, and never attacks a deer
from before while running. Even should the deer, not perceiving him,
come directly upon him, the dog steps aside and makes his assault on
the flank; whereas other hunting dogs, though of superior strength,
and general sagacity, which are brought from Europe, are destitute of
this instinct. For want of similar precautions, they are often killed by
the deer on the spot, the vertebræ of their neck being dislocated by the
violence of the shock.817
A new instinct has also become hereditary in a mongrel race of dogs
employed by the inhabitants of the banks of the Magdalena almost
exclusively in hunting the white-lipped pecari. The address of these
dogs consists in restraining their ardor, and attaching themselves to no
animal in particular, but keeping the whole herd in check. Now,
594
among these dogs some are found, which the very first time they are
taken to the woods, are acquainted with this mode of attack; whereas,
a dog of another breed starts forward at once, is surrounded by the
pecari, and, whatever may be his strength, is destroyed in a moment.
Some of our countrymen, engaged of late in conducting one of the
principal mining associations in Mexico, that of Real del Monte, carried
out with them some English greyhounds of the best breed, to hunt the
hares which abound in that country. The great platform which is the
scene of sport is at an elevation of about nine thousand feet above the
level of the sea, and the mercury in the barometer stands habitually at
the height of about nineteen inches. It was found that the greyhounds
could not support the fatigues of a long chase in this attenuated atmosphere,
and before they could come up with their prey, they lay down
gasping for breath; but these same animals have produced whelps
which have grown up, and are not in the least degree incommoded by
the want of density in the air, but run down the hares with as much
ease as the fleetest of their race in this country.
The fixed and deliberate stand of the pointer has with propriety been
regarded as a mere modification of a habit, which may have been useful
to a wild race accustomed to wind game, and steal upon it by surprise,
first pausing for an instant, in order to spring with unerring aim.
The faculty of the retriever, however, may justly be regarded as more
inexplicable and less easily referable to the instinctive passions of the
species. M. Majendie, says a French writer in a recently published
memoir, having learnt that there was a race of dogs in England which
stopped and brought back game of their own accord, procured a
pair, and having obtained a whelp from them, kept it constantly under
his eyes, until he had an opportunity of assuring himself that, without
having received any instruction, and on the very first day that it was
carried to the chase, it brought back game with as much steadiness as
dogs which had been schooled into the same manœuvre by means of the
whip and collar.
Attributes of animals in their relation to man.—Such attainments, as
well as the habits and dispositions which the shepherd's dog and many
others inherit, seem to be of a nature and extent which we can hardly
explain by supposing them to be modifications of instincts necessary
for the preservation of the species in a wild state. When such remarkable
habits appear in races of this species we may reasonably
conjecture that they were given with no other view than for the use of
man and the preservation of the dog, which thus obtains protection.
As a general rule, I fully agree with M. F. Cuvier, that, in studying
the habits of animals, we must attempt, as far as possible, to refer their
domestic qualities to modifications of instincts which are implanted in
them in a state of nature; and that writer has successfully pointed out,
in an admirable essay on the domestication of the mammalia818, the true
595
origin of many dispositions which are vulgarly attributed to the influence
of education alone. But we should go too far if we did not admit
that some of the qualities of particular animals and plants may have
been given solely with a view to the connection which it was foreseen
would exist between them and man—especially when we see that connexion
to be in many cases so intimate, that the greater number, and
sometimes, as in the case of the camel, all the individuals of the species
which exist on the earth are in subjection to the human race.
We can perceive in a multitude of animals, especially in some of the
parasitic tribes, that certain instincts and organs are conferred for the
purpose of defence or attack against some other species. Now if we
are reluctant to suppose the existence of similar relations between
man and the instincts of many of the inferior animals, we adopt an
hypothesis no less violent, though in the opposite extreme to that which
has led some to imagine the whole animate and inanimate creation to
have been made solely for the support, gratification, and instruction of
mankind.
Many species, most hostile to our persons or property, multiply, in
spite of our efforts to repress them; others, on the contrary, are
intentionally augmented many hundred fold in number by our exertions.
In such instances, we must imagine the relative resources of man, and
of species friendly or inimical to him, to have been prospectively calculated
and adjusted. To withhold assent to this supposition, would be
to refuse what we must grant in respect to the economy of nature in
every other part of the organic creation; for the various species of
contemporary plants and animals have obviously their relative forces,
nicely balanced, and their respective tastes, passions, and instincts so
contrived, that they are all in perfect harmony with each other. In no
other manner could it happen that each species, surrounded, as it is, by
countless dangers, should be enabled to maintain its ground for periods
of considerable duration.
The docility of the individuals of some of our domestic species,
extending, as it does, to attainments foreign to their natural habits and
faculties, may, perhaps, have been conferred with a view to their association
with man. But, lest species should be thereby made to vary
indefinitely, we find that such habits are never transmissible by
generation.
A pig has been trained to hunt and point game with great activity
and steadiness819; and other learned individuals, of the same species,
have been taught to spell; but such fortuitous acquirements never
become hereditary, for they have no relation whatever to the exigencies
of the animal in a wild state, and cannot, therefore, be developments of
any instinctive propensities.
Influence of domestication.—An animal in domesticity, says M. F.
596
Cuvier, is not essentially in a different situation, in regard to the
feeling of restraint, from one left to itself. It lives in society without
constraint, because, without doubt, it was a social animal; and it conforms
itself to the will of man, because it had a chief, to which, in a
wild state, it would have yielded obedience. There is nothing in its
new situation that is not conformable to its propensities; it is satisfying
its wants by submission to a master, and makes no sacrifice of its
natural inclinations. All the social animals, when left to themselves,
form herds more or less numerous; and all the individuals of the
same herd know each other, are mutually attached, and will not allow
a strange individual to join them. In a wild state, moreover, they
obey some individual, which, by its superiority, has become the chief
of the herd. Our domestic species had, originally, this sociability of
disposition; and no solitary species, however easy it may be to tame
it, has yet afforded true domestic races. We merely, therefore, develope,
to our own advantage, propensities which propel the individuals of
certain species to draw near to their fellows.
The sheep which we have reared is induced to follow us, as it
would be led to follow the flock among which it was brought up; and,
when individuals of gregarious species have been accustomed to one
master, it is he alone whom they acknowledge as their chief—he only
whom they obey. "The elephant allows himself to be directed only
by the carnac whom he has adopted; the dog itself, reared in solitude
with its master, manifests a hostile disposition towards all others;
and every body knows how dangerous it is to be in the midst of a herd
of cows, in pasturages that are little frequented, when they have not at
their head the keeper who takes care of them.
"Every thing, therefore, tends to convince us, that formerly men
were only with regard to the domestic animals, what those who are
particularly charged with the care of them still are—namely, members
of the society which these animals form among themselves; and, that
they are only distinguished, in the general mass, by the authority
which they have been enabled to assume from their superiority of intellect.
Thus, every social animal which recognizes man as a member,
and as the chief of its herd, is a domestic animal. It might even be
said, that, from the moment when such an animal admits man as a
member of its society, it is domesticated, as man could not enter into
such society without becoming the chief of it."820
But the ingenious author whose observations I have here cited,
admits that the obedience which the individuals of many domestic
species yield indifferently to every person, is without analogy in any
state of things which could exist previously to their subjugation by
man. Each troop of wild horses, it is true, has some stallion for its
chief, who draws after him all the individuals of which the herd is composed;
but when a domesticated horse has passed from hand to hand,
597
and has served several masters, he becomes equally docile towards any
person, and is subjected to the whole human race. It seems fair to presume
that the capability in the instinct of the horse to be thus modified,
was given to enable the species to render greater services to
man; and, perhaps, the facility with which many other acquired
characters become hereditary in various races of the horse, may be
explicable only on a like supposition. The amble, for example, a
pace to which the domestic races in some parts of Spanish America
are exclusively trained, has, in the course of several generations, become
hereditary, and is assumed by all the young colts before they are
broken in.821
It seems, also, reasonable to conclude, that the power bestowed on
the horse, the dog, the ox, the sheep, the cat, and many species of
domestic fowls, of supporting almost every climate, was given expressly
to enable them to follow man throughout all parts of the
globe, in order that we might obtain their services, and they our protection.
If it be objected that the elephant which, by the union of
strength, intelligence, and docility, can render the greatest services to
mankind, is incapable of living in any but the warmest latitudes, we may
observe that the quantity of vegetable food required by this quadruped
would render its maintenance in the temperate zones too costly, and in
the arctic impossible.
Among the changes superinduced by man, none appear, at first sight,
more remarkable than the perfect tameness of certain domestic races.
It is well known that, at however early an age we obtain possession of
the young of many unreclaimed races, they will retain, throughout life,
a considerable timidity and apprehensiveness of danger; whereas, after
one or two generations, the descendants of the same stock will habitually
place the most implicit confidence in man. There is good reason,
however, to suspect that such changes are not without analogy in a
state of nature; or, to speak more correctly, in situations where man
has not interfered.
We learn from Mr. Darwin, that in the Galapagos archipelago, placed
directly under the equator, and nearly 600 miles west of the American
continent, all the terrestrial birds, as the finches, doves, hawks, and
others, are so tame, that they may be killed with a switch. One day,
says this author, "a mocking bird alighted on the edge of a pitcher
which I held in my hand, and began quietly to sip the water, and
allowed me to lift it with the vessel from the ground." Yet formerly,
when the first Europeans landed, and found no inhabitants in these
islands, the birds were even tamer than now: already they are beginning
to acquire that salutary dread of man which in countries long
settled is natural even to young birds which have never received any
injury. So in the Falkland Islands, both the birds and foxes are entirely
without fear of man; whereas, in the adjoining mainland of South
598
America, many of the same species of birds are extremely wild; for there
they have for ages been persecuted by the natives.822
Dr. Richardson informs us, in his able history of the habits of the
North American animals, that, "in the retired parts of the mountains
where the hunters had seldom penetrated, there is no difficulty in
approaching the Rocky Mountain sheep, which there exhibit the simplicity
of character so remarkable in the domestic species; but where they
have been often fired at, they are exceedingly wild, alarm their companions,
on the approach of danger, by a hissing noise, and scale the rocks
with a speed and agility that baffle pursuit."823
It is probable, therefore, that as man, in diffusing himself over the
globe, has tamed many wild races, so, also, he has made many tame
races wild. Had some of the larger carnivorous beasts, capable of scaling
the rocks, made their way into the North American mountains
before our hunters, a similar alteration in the instincts of the sheep
would doubtless have been brought about.
Wild elephants domesticated in a few years.—No animal affords a
more striking illustration of the principal points which I have been endeavouring
to establish than the elephant; for, in the first place, the
wonderful sagacity with which he accommodates himself to the society of
man, and the new habits which he contracts, are not the result of time,
nor of modifications produced in the course of many generations.
These animals will breed in captivity, as is now ascertained, in opposition
to the vulgar opinion of many modern naturalists, and in conformity
to that of the ancients Ælian and Columella824: yet it has always been the
custom, as the least expensive mode of obtaining them, to capture wild
individuals in the forests, usually when full grown; and, in a few years
after they are taken—sometimes, it is said, in the space of a few months—their
education is completed.
Had the whole species been domesticated from an early period in the
history of man, like the camel, their superior intelligence would, doubtless,
have been attributed to their long and familiar intercourse with the
lord of the creation; but we know that a few years is sufficient to bring
about this wonderful change of habits; and although the same individual
may continue to receive tuition for a century afterwards, yet it
makes no farther progress in the general development of its faculties.
Were it otherwise, indeed, the animal would soon deserve more than the
poet's epithet of "half-reasoning."
From the authority of our countrymen employed in the late Burmese
war, it appears, in corroboration of older accounts, that when elephants
are required to execute extraordinary tasks, they may be made to understand
that they will receive unusual rewards. Some favourite dainty is
shown to them, in the hope of acquiring which the work is done; and
so perfectly does the nature of the contract appear to be understood,
599
that the breach of it, on the part of the master, is often attended with
danger. In this case, a power has been given to the species to adapt
their social instincts to new circumstances with surprising rapidity; but
the extent of this change is defined by strict and arbitrary limits.
There is no indication of a tendency to continued divergence from
certain attributes with which the elephant was originally endued—no
ground whatever for anticipating that, in thousands of centuries, any
material alteration could ever be effected. All that we can infer from
analogy is, that some more useful and peculiar races might probably
be formed, if the experiment were fairly tried; and that some individual
characteristic, now only casual and temporary, might be perpetuated
by generation.
In all cases, therefore, where the domestic qualities exist in animals,
they seem to require no lengthened process for their developement;
and they appear to have been wholly denied to some classes, which,
from their strength and social disposition, might have rendered great
services to man; as, for example, the greater part of the quadrumana.
The orang-outang, indeed, which, for its resemblance in form to man,
and apparently for no other good reason, has been assumed by Lamarck
to be the most perfect of the inferior animals, has been tamed by the
savages of Borneo, and made to climb lofty trees, and to bring down
the fruit. But he is said to yield to his masters an unwilling obedience,
and to be held in subjection only by severe discipline. We know
nothing of the faculties of this animal which can suggest the idea that
it rivals the elephant in intelligence; much less anything which can
countenance the dreams of those who have fancied that it might have
been transmuted into the "dominant race." One of the baboons of
Sumatra (Simia carpolegus) appears to be more docile, and is frequently
trained by the inhabitants to ascend trees, for the purpose of gathering
cocoa-nuts; a service in which the animal is very expert. He selects,
says Sir Stamford Raffles, the ripe nuts, with great judgment, and pulls
no more than he is ordered.825 The capuchin and cacajao monkeys are,
according to Humboldt, taught to ascend trees in the same manner,
and to throw down fruit on the banks of the lower Orinoco.826
It is for the Lamarckians to explain how it happens that those same
savages of Borneo have not themselves acquired, by dint of longing, for
many generations, for the power of climbing trees, the elongated arms
of the ourang, or even the prehensile tails of some American monkeys:
Instead of being reduced to the necessity of subjugating stubborn and
untractable brutes, we should naturally have anticipated "that their
wants would have excited them to efforts, and that continued efforts
would have given rise to new organs;" or rather to the re-acquisition
of organs which, in a manner irreconcileable with the principle of the
600
progressive system, have grown obsolete in tribes of men which have
such constant need of them.
Recapitulation.—It follows, then, from the different facts which have
been considered in this chapter, that a short period of time is generally
sufficient to effect nearly the whole change which an alteration of external
circumstances can bring about in the habits of a species, and that
such capacity of accommodation to new circumstances is enjoyed in
very different degrees, by different species.
Certain qualities appear to be bestowed exclusively with a view to
the relations which are destined to exist between different species, and,
among others, between certain species and man; but these latter are
always so nearly connected with the original habits and propensities of
each species in a wild state, that they imply no indefinite capacity of
varying from the original type. The acquired habits derived from human
tuition are rarely transmitted to the offspring; and when this happens,
it is almost universally the case with those merely which have
some obvious connexion with the attributes of the species when in a
state of independence.
</div></body></text></TEI>