<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="12">
CHAPTER VII.
Of Laws of Phenomena and of Causes.
Aphorism XXIV.
Inductive truths are of two kinds, Laws of Phenomena,
and Theories of Causes. It is necessary to begin in every
science with the Laws of Phenomena; but it is impossible that
we should be satisfied to stop short of a Theory of Causes. In
Physical Astronomy, Physical Optics, Geology, and other
sciences, we have instances showing that we can make a great
advance in inquiries after true Theories of Causes.
1. IN
the first attempts at acquiring an exact and
connected knowledge of the appearances and operations
which nature presents, men went no further
than to learn what takes place, not why it occurs.
They discovered an Order which the phenomena follow,
Rules which they obey; but they did not come in
sight of the Powers by which these rules are determined,
the Causes of which this order is the effect.
Thus, for example, they found that many of the celestial
motions took place as if the sun and stars were
carried round by the revolutions of certain celestial
spheres; but what causes kept these spheres in constant
motion, they were never able to explain. In
like manner in modern times, Kepler discovered that
the planets describe ellipses, before Newton explained
why they select this particular curve, and describe it
in a particular manner. The laws of reflection, refraction,
dispersion, and other properties of light have
long been known; the causes of these laws are at
present under discussion. And the same might be 119
said of many other sciences. The discovery of the
Laws of Phenomena is, in all cases, the first step in
exact knowledge; these Laws may often for a long
period constitute the whole of our science; and it is
always a matter requiring great talents and great efforts,
to advance to a knowledge of the Causes of the
phenomena.
Hence the larger part of our knowledge of nature,
at least of the certain portion of it, consists of the
knowledge of the Laws of Phenomena. In Astronomy
indeed, besides knowing the rules which guide the appearances,
and resolving them into the real motions
from which they arise, we can refer these motions to
the forces which produce them. In Optics, we have
become acquainted with a vast number of laws by
which varied and beautiful phenomena are governed;
and perhaps we may assume, since the evidence of the
Undulatory Theory has been so fully developed, that
we know also the Causes of the Phenomena. But in
a large class of sciences, while we have learnt many
Laws of Phenomena, the causes by which these are
produced are still unknown or disputed. Are we to
ascribe to the operation of a fluid or fluids, and if so,
in what manner, the facts of heat, magnetism, electricity,
galvanism? What are the forces by which the
elements of chemical compounds are held together?
What are the forces, of a higher order, as we cannot
help believing, by which the course of vital action in
organized bodies is kept up? In these and other cases,
we have extensive departments of science; but we are
as yet unable to trace the effects to their causes; and
our science, so far as it is positive and certain, consists
entirely of the laws of phenomena.
2. In those cases in which we have a division of
the science which teaches us the doctrine of the causes,
as well as one which states the rules which the effects
follow, I have, in the History, distinguished the two
portions of the science by certain terms. I have thus
spoken of Formal Astronomy and Physical Astronomy.
The latter phrase has long been commonly employed to
describe that department of Astronomy which deals with 120
those forces by which the heavenly bodies are guided in
their motions; the former adjective appears well suited
to describe a collection of rules depending on those ideas
of space, time, position, number, which are, as we have
already said, the forms of our apprehension of phenomena.
The laws of phenomena may be considered as
formulæ, expressing results in terms of those ideas.
In like manner, I have spoken of Formal Optics and
Physical Optics; the latter division including all
speculations concerning the machinery by which the
effects are produced. Formal Acoustics and Physical
Acoustics may be distinguished in like manner, although
these two portions of science have been a good
deal mixed together by most of those who have treated
of them. Formal Thermotics, the knowledge of the
laws of the phenomena of heat, ought in like manner
to lead to Physical Thermotics, or the Theory of Heat
with reference to the cause by which its effects are
produced;—a branch of science which as yet can hardly
be said to exist.
3. What kinds of cause are we to admit in science?
This is an important, and by no means an easy question.
In order to answer it, we must consider in what
manner our progress in the knowledge of causes has
hitherto been made. By far the most conspicuous instance
of success in such researches, is the discovery
of the causes of the motions of the heavenly bodies.
In this case, after the formal laws of the motions,—their
conditions as to space and time,—had become
known, men were enabled to go a step further; to reduce
them to the familiar and general cause of motion—mechanical
force; and to determine the laws which
this force follows. That this was a step in addition to
the knowledge previously possessed, and that it was a
real and peculiar truth, will not be contested. And a
step in any other subject which should be analogous to
this in astronomy;—a discovery of causes and forces
as certain and clear as the discovery of universal
gravitation;—would undoubtedly be a vast advance upon
a body of science consisting only of the laws of phenomena. 121
4. But although physical astronomy may well be
taken as a standard in estimating the value and magnitude
of the advance from the knowledge of phenomena to the
knowledge of causes; the peculiar features
of the transition from formal to physical science in
that subject must not be allowed to limit too narrowly
our views of the nature of this transition in other
cases. We are not, for example, to consider that the
step which leads us to the knowledge of causes in any
province of nature must necessarily consist in the
discovery of centers of forces, and collections of
such centers, by which the effects are produced. The discovery
of the causes of phenomena may imply the detection
of a fluid by whose undulations, or other operations,
the results are occasioned. The phenomena of acoustics
are, we know, produced in this manner by the air;
and in the cases of light, heat, magnetism, and others,
even if we reject all the theories of such fluids which
have hitherto been proposed, we still cannot deny that
such theories are intelligible and possible, as the
discussions concerning them have shown. Nor can it be
doubted that if the assumption of such a fluid, in any
case, were as well evidenced as the doctrine of universal
gravitation is, it must be considered as a highly
valuable theory.
5. But again; not only must we, in aiming at the
formation of a Causal Section in each Science of Phenomena,
consider Fluids and their various modes of
operation admissible, as well as centers of mechanical
force; but we must be prepared, if it be necessary, to
consider the forces, or powers to which we refer the
phenomena, under still more general aspects, and invested
with characters different from mere mechanical
force. For example; the forces by which the chemical
elements of bodies are bound together, and from which
arise, both their sensible texture, their crystalline form,
and their chemical composition, are certainly forces of
a very different nature from the mere attraction of
matter according to its mass. The powers of assimilation
and reproduction in plants and animals are obviously
still more removed from mere mechanism; yet 122
these powers are not on that account less real, nor a
less fit and worthy subject of scientific inquiry.
6. In fact, these forces—mechanical, chemical and
vital,—as we advance from one to the other, each bring
into our consideration new characters; and what these
characters are, has appeared in the historical survey
which we made of the Fundamental Ideas of the various
sciences. It was then shown that the forces by which
chemical effects are produced necessarily involve the
Idea of Polarity,—they are polar forces; the particles
tend together in virtue of opposite properties which in
the combination neutralize each other. Hence, in attempting
to advance to a theory of Causes in chemistry,
our task is by no means to invent laws of mechanical
force, and collections of forces, by which the effects
may be produced. We know beforehand that no such
attempt can succeed. Our aim must be to conceive
such new kinds of force, including Polarity among
their characters, as may best render the results intelligible.
7. Thus in advancing to a Science of Cause in any
subject, the labour and the struggle is, not to analyse
the phenomena according to any preconceived and
already familiar ideas, but to form distinctly new
conceptions, such as do really carry us to a more intimate
view of the processes of nature. Thus in the case of
astronomy, the obstacle which deferred the discovery
of the true causes from the time of Kepler to that of
Newton, was the difficulty of taking hold of mechanical
conceptions and axioms with sufficient clearness and
steadiness; which, during the whole of that interval,
mathematicians were learning to do. In the question
of causation which now lies most immediately in the
path of science, that of the causes of electrical and
chemical phenomena, the business of rightly fixing and
limiting the conception of polarity, is the proper object
of the efforts of discoverers. Accordingly a large portion
of Mr Faraday’s recent
labours23
is directed, not to 123
the attempt at discovering new laws of phenomena, but
to the task of throwing light upon the conception of
polarity, and of showing how it must be understood, so
that it shall include electrical induction and other phenomena,
which have commonly been ascribed to forces
acting mechanically at a distance. He is by no means
content, nor would it answer the ends of science that
he should be, with stating the results of his experiments;
he is constantly, in every page, pointing out
the interpretation of his experiments, and showing how
the conception of Polar Forces enters into this interpretation.
‘I shall,’ he says24,
‘use every opportunity
which presents itself of returning to that strong test of
truth, experiment; but,’ he adds, ‘I shall necessarily
have occasion to speak theoretically, and even hypothetically.’
His hypothesis that electrical inductive
action always takes place by means of a continuous line
of polarized particles, and not by attraction and repulsion
at a distance, if established, cannot fail to be a
great step on our way towards a knowledge of causes,
as well as phenomena, in the subjects under his consideration.
23 Eleventh, Twelfth,
and Thirteenth Series of Researches, Phil. Trans. 1837 and 8.
24 Art. 1318.
8. The process of obtaining new conceptions is, to
most minds, far more unwelcome than any labour in
employing old ideas. The effort is indeed painful and
oppressive; it is feeling in the dark for an object which
we cannot find. Hence it is not surprising that we
should far more willingly proceed to seek for new causes
by applying conceptions borrowed from old ones. Men
were familiar with solid frames, and with whirlpools of
fluid, when they had not learnt to form any clear conception
of attraction at a distance. Hence they at
first imagined the heavenly motions to be caused by
Crystalline Spheres, and by Vortices. At length they
were taught to conceive Central Forces, and then they
reduced the solar system to these. But having done
this, they fancied that all the rest of the machinery of
nature must be central forces. We find Newton 124
expressing this conviction25,
and the mathematicians of
the last century acted upon it very extensively. We
may especially remark Laplace’s labours in this field.
Having explained, by such forces, the phenomena of
capillary attraction, he attempted to apply the same
kind of explanation to the reflection, refraction, and
double refraction of light;—to the constitution of
gases;—to the operation of heat. It was soon seen that
the explanation of refraction was arbitrary, and that
of double refraction illusory; while polarization entirely
eluded the grasp of this machinery. Centers of force
would no longer represent the modes of causation
which belonged to the phenomena. Polarization required
some other contrivance, such as the undulatory
theory supplied. No theory of light can be of any
avail in which the fundamental idea of Polarity is not
clearly exhibited.
25
Multa me movent, &c.,—Pref. to the Principia, already quoted in the
History.
9. The sciences of magnetism and electricity have
given rise to theories in which this relation of polarity
is exhibited by means of two opposite
fluids26;—a
positive and a negative fluid, or a vitreous and a resinous,
for electricity, and a boreal and an austral fluid
for magnetism. The hypothesis of such fluids gives
results agreeing in a remarkable manner with the
facts and their measures, as Coulomb and others have
shown. It may be asked how far we may, in such a
case, suppose that we have discovered the true cause of
the phenomena, and whether it is sufficiently proved
that these fluids really exist. The right answer seems
to be, that the hypothesis certainly represents the
truth so far as regards the polar relation of the two
energies, and the laws of the attractive and repulsive
forces of the particles in which these energies reside;
but that we are not entitled to assume that the vehicles
of these energies possess other attributes of material
fluids, or that the forces thus ascribed to the
particles are the primary elementary forces from which 125
the action originates. We are the more bound to
place this cautious limit to our acceptance of the Coulombian
theory, since in electricity Faraday has in
vain endeavoured to bring into view one of the polar
fluids without the other: whereas such a result ought
to be possible if there were two separable fluids. The
impossibility of this separate exhibition of one fluid
appears to show that the fluids are real only so far as
they are polar. And Faraday’s view above mentioned,
according to which the attractions at a distance are
resolved into the action of lines of polarized particles
of air, appears still further to show that the conceptions
hitherto entertained of electrical forces, according
to the Coulombian theory, do not penetrate to the real
and intimate nature of the causation belonging to this
case.
26
Hist. Ind. Sc. b. xi. c. ii.
10. Since it is thus difficult to know when we have
seized the true cause of the phenomena in any department
of science, it may appear to some persons that
physical inquirers are imprudent and unphilosophical
in undertaking this Research of Causes; and that it
would be safer and wiser to confine ourselves to the
investigation of the laws of phenomena, in which field
the knowledge which we obtain is definite and certain.
Hence there have not been wanting those who have
laid it down as a maxim that ‘science must study only
the laws of phenomena, and never the mode of
production27.’
But it is easy to see that such a maxim would
confine the breadth and depth of scientific inquiries to
a most scanty and miserable limit. Indeed, such a
rule would defeat its own object; for the laws of phenomena,
in many cases, cannot be even expressed or
understood without some hypothesis respecting their
mode of production. How could the phenomena of
polarization have been conceived or reasoned upon,
except by imagining a polar arrangement of particles,
or transverse vibrations, or some equivalent hypothesis?
The doctrines of fits of easy transmission, the doctrine
of moveable polarization, and the like, even when 126
erroneous as representing the whole of the phenomena,
were still useful in combining some of them into laws;
and without some such hypotheses the facts could not
have been followed out. The doctrine of a fluid caloric
may be false; but without imagining such a fluid, how
could the movement of heat from one part of a body to
another be conceived? It may be replied that Fourier,
Laplace, Poisson, who have principally cultivated the
Theory of Heat, have not conceived it as a fluid, but
have referred conduction to the radiation of the molecules
of bodies, which they suppose to be separate points.
But this molecular constitution of bodies is itself an
assumption of the mode in which the phenomena are
produced; and the radiation of heat suggests inquiries
concerning a fluid emanation, no less than its conduction
does. In like manner, the attempts to connect
the laws of phenomena of heat and of gases, have led
to hypotheses respecting the constitution of gases, and
the combination of their particles with those of caloric,
which hypotheses may be false, but are probably the
best means of discovering the truth.
27
 Comte, Philosophie Positive.
To debar science from inquiries like these, on the
ground that it is her business to inquire into facts,
and not to speculate about causes, is a curious example
of that barren caution which hopes for truth without
daring to venture upon the quest of it. This temper
would have stopped with Kepler’s discoveries, and
would have refused to go on with Newton to inquire
into the mode in which the phenomena are produced.
It would have stopped with Newton’s optical facts,
and would have refused to go on with him and his
successors to inquire into the mode in which these
phenomena are produced. And, as we have abundantly
shown, it would, on that very account, have failed in
seeing what the phenomena really are.
In many subjects the attempt to study the laws of
phenomena, independently of any speculations respecting
the causes which have produced them, is neither
possible for human intelligence nor for human temper.
Men cannot contemplate the phenomena without
clothing them in terms of some hypothesis, and will 127
not be schooled to suppress the questionings which at
every moment rise up within them concerning the
causes of the phenomena. Who can attend to the
appearances which come under the notice of the geologist;—strata
regularly bedded, full of the remains of
animals such as now live in the depths of the ocean,
raised to the tops of mountains, broken, contorted,
mixed with rocks such as still flow from the mouths of
volcanos,—who can see phenomena like these, and
imagine that he best promotes the progress of our
knowledge of the earth’s history, by noting down the
facts, and abstaining from all inquiry whether these
are really proof of past states of the earth and of
subterraneous forces, or merely an accidental imitation of
the effects of such causes? In this and similar cases,
to proscribe the inquiry into causes would be to annihilate the science.
Finally, this caution does not even gain its own
single end, the escape from hypotheses. For, as we
have said, those who will not seek for new and appropriate
causes of newly-studied phenomena, are almost
inevitably led to ascribe the facts to modifications of
causes already familiar. They may declare that they
will not hear of such causes as vital powers, elective
affinities, electric, or calorific, or luminiferous ethers or
fluids; but they will not the less on that account
assume hypotheses equally unauthorized;—for instance—universal
mechanical forces; a molecular constitution of bodies;
solid, hard, inert matter;—and will
apply these hypotheses in a manner which is arbitrary
in itself as well as quite insufficient for its purpose.
11. It appears, then, to be required, both by the
analogy of the most successful efforts of science in past
times and by the irrepressible speculative powers of
the human mind, that we should attempt to discover
both the laws of phenomena, and their causes. In every
department of science, when prosecuted far enough,
these two great steps of investigation must succeed
each other. The laws of phenomena must be known
before we can speculate concerning causes; the causes
must be inquired into when the phenomena have been 128
reduced to rule. In both these speculations the suppositions
and conceptions which occur must be constantly tested by
reference to observation and experiment. In both we must,
as far as possible, devise
hypotheses which, when we thus test them, display
those characters of truth of which we have already
spoken;—an agreement with facts such as will stand
the most patient and rigid inquiry; a provision for
predicting truly the results of untried cases; a consilience
of inductions from various classes of facts; and
a progressive tendency of the scheme to simplicity and
unity.
We shall attempt hereafter to give several rules of a
more precise and detailed kind for the discovery of the
causes, and still more, of the laws of phenomena. But
it will be useful in the first place to point out the
Classification of the Sciences which results from the
principles already established in this
work. And for
this purpose we must previously decide the question,
whether the practical Arts, as Medicine and Engineering,
must be included in our list of Sciences.
</div></body></text></TEI>