<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="20">INTRODUCTION.
Of Formal and Physical Astronomy.
WE have thus rapidly traced
the causes of the almost complete blank which the history of physical
science offers, from the decline of the Roman empire, for a thousand
years. Along with the breaking up of the ancient forms of society,
were broken up the ancient energy of thinking, the clearness of idea,
and steadiness of intellectual action. This mental declension produced
a servile admiration for the genius of the better periods, and thus,
the spirit of Commentation: Christianity established the claim of
truth to govern the world; and this principle, misinterpreted and
combined with the ignorance and servility of the times, gave rise to
the Dogmatic System: and the love of speculation, finding no secure
and permitted path on solid ground, went off into the regions of
Mysticism.
The causes which produced the inertness and blindness of the
stationary period of human knowledge, began at last to yield to the
influence of the principles which tended to progression. The
indistinctness of thought, which was the original feature in the
decline of sound knowledge, was in a measure remedied by the steady
cultivation of Pure Mathematics and Astronomy, and by the progress of
inventions in the Arts, which call out and fix the distinctness of our
conceptions of the relations of natural phenomena. As men’s minds
became clear, they became less servile: the perception of the nature
of truth drew men away from controversies about mere opinion; when
they saw distinctly the relations of things, they ceased to
give their whole attention to what had been said concerning
them; and thus, as science rose into view, the spirit of commentation
lost its way. And when men came to feel what it was to think for
themselves on subjects of science, they soon rebelled against the
right of others to impose opinions upon them. When they threw off
their blind admiration for the ancients, they were disposed to cast
away also their passive obedience to the ancient system of doctrines.
When they were no longer inspired by the spirit of commentation, they
were no longer submissive to the dogmatism of the schools. When they
began to feel that they could 256 discover truths, they felt also a
persuasion of a right and a growing will so to do.
Thus the revived clearness of ideas, which made its appearance at
the revival of letters, brought on a struggle with the authority,
intellectual and civil, of the established schools of philosophy. This
clearness of idea showed itself, in the first instance, in Astronomy,
and was embodied in the system of Copernicus; but the contest did not
come to a crisis till a century later, in the time of Galileo and
other disciples of the new doctrine. It is our present business to
trace the principles of this series of events in the history of
philosophy.
I do not profess to write a history of Astronomy, any further than
is necessary in order to exhibit the principles on which the
progression of science proceeds; and, therefore, I neglect subordinate
persons and occurrences, in order to bring into view the leading
features of great changes. Now in the introduction of the Copernican
system into general acceptation, two leading views operated upon men’s
minds; the consideration of the system as exhibiting the apparent
motions of the universe, and the consideration of this system with
reference to its causes;—the formal and the
physical aspect of the Theory;—the relations of Space and
Time, and the relations of Force and Matter. These two divisions of
the subject were at first not clearly separated; the second was long
mixed, in a manner very dim and obscure, with the first, without
appearing as a distinct subject of attention; but at last it was
extricated and treated in a manner suitable to its nature. The views
of Copernicus rested mainly on the formal condition of the universe,
the relations of space and time; but Kepler, Galileo, and others, were
led, by controversies and other causes, to give a gradually increasing
attention to the physical relations of the heavenly bodies; an impulse
was given to the study of Mechanics (the Doctrine of Motion), which
became very soon an important and extensive science; and in no long
period, the discoveries of Kepler, suggested by a vague but intense
belief in the physical connection of the parts of the universe, led to
the decisive and sublime generalizations of Newton.
The distinction of formal and physical Astronomy thus
becomes necessary, in order to treat clearly of the discussions which
the propounding of the Copernican theory occasioned. But it may be
observed that, besides this great change, Astronomy made very great
advances in the same path which we have already been tracing, namely,
the determination of the quantities and laws of the celestial motions,
in so far as they were exhibited by the ancient theories, or 257 might be represented
by obvious modifications of those theories. I speak of new
Inequalities, new Phenomena, such as Copernicus, Galileo, and Tycho
Brahe discovered. As, however, these were very soon referred to the
Copernican rather than the Ptolemaic hypothesis, they may be
considered as developments rather of the new than of the old Theory;
and I shall, therefore, treat of them, agreeably to the plan of the
former part, as the sequel of the Copernican Induction.
</div></body></text></TEI>