<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="20">
CHAPTER IV.
Of Methods of acquiring clear Scientific Ideas,
continued.—Of the Discussion of Ideas.
Aphorism XXXIII.
The conception involved in scientific truths have attained
the requisite degree of clearness by means of the Discussions
respecting ideas which have taken place among discoverers
and their followers. Such discussions are very far from
being unprofitable to science. They are metaphysical, and
must be so: the difference between discoverers and barren
reasoners is, that the former employ good, and the latter bad
metaphysics.
1. IT
is easily seen that in every part of science, the
establishment of a new set of ideas has been accompanied
with much of doubt and dissent. And by
means of discussions so occasioned, the new conceptions,
and the opinions which involve them, have gradually become
definite and clear. The authors and
asserters of the new opinions, in order to make them
defensible, have been compelled to make them consistent:
in order to recommend them to others, they have
been obliged to make them more entirely intelligible
to themselves. And thus the Terms which formed the
main points of the controversy, although applied in a
loose and vacillating manner at first, have in the end
become perfectly definite and exact. The opinions discussed
have been, in their main features, the same
throughout the debate; but they have at first been
dimly, and at last clearly apprehended: like the objects
of a landscape, at which we look through a telescope
ill adjusted, till, by sliding the tube backwards and 181
forwards, we at last bring it into focus, and perceive
every feature of the prospect sharp and bright.
2. We have in the last
Book21 fully exemplified
this gradual progress of conceptions from obscurity
to clearness by means of Discussion. We have
seen, too, that this mode of treating the subject has
never been successful, except when it has been associated
with an appeal to facts as well as to reasonings.
A combination of experiment with argument, of observation
with demonstration, has always been found
requisite in order that men should arrive at those
distinct conceptions which give them substantial truths.
The arguments used led to the rejection of undefined,
ambiguous, self-contradictory notions; but the reference
to facts led to the selection, or at least to the
retention, of the conceptions which were both true and
useful. The two correlative processes, definition and
true assertion, the formation of clear ideas and the
induction of laws, went on together.
21 
B. ii. c. ii.
Of the Explication of Conceptions.
Thus those discussions by which scientific conceptions
are rendered ultimately quite distinct and fixed,
include both reasonings from Principles and illustrations
from Facts. At present we turn our attention
more peculiarly to the former part of the process;
according to the distinction already drawn, between the
Explication of Conceptions and the Colligation of Facts.
The Discussions of which we here speak, are the Method
(if they may be called a method) by which the
Explication of Conceptions is carried to the requisite
point among philosophers.
3. In the History of the Fundamental Ideas of the
Sciences which forms the Prelude to this work, and
in the History of the Inductive Sciences, I have, in
several instances, traced the steps by which, historically
speaking, these Ideas have obtained their ultimate and
permanent place in the minds of speculative
men. I have thus exemplified the reasonings and controversies
which constitute such Discussion as we now
speak of. I have stated, at considerable length, the 182
various attempts, failures, and advances, by which the
ideas which enter into the science of Mechanics were
evolved into their present evidence. In like manner
we have seen the conception of refracted rays of light,
obscure and confused in Seneca, growing clearer in
Roger Bacon, more definite in Descartes, perfectly
distinct in Newton. The polarity of light, at first
contemplated with some perplexity, became very distinct
to Malus, Young, and Fresnel; yet the phenomena of
circular polarization, and still more, the circular
polarization of fluids, leave us, even at present, some
difficulty in fully mastering this conception. The related
polarities of electricity and magnetism are not yet
fully comprehended, even by our greatest philosophers.
One of Mr. Faraday’s late papers (the Fourteenth Series of his
Researches) is employed in an experimental
discussion of this subject, which leads to no satisfactory
result. The controversy between MM. Biot and
Ampère22,
on the nature of the Elementary Forces in electro-dynamic
action, is another evidence that the discussion of this
subject has not yet reached its termination.
With regard to chemical polarity, I have already stated
that this idea is as yet very far from being brought to
an ultimate condition of definiteness; and the subject
of Chemical Forces, (for that whole subject must be included
in this idea of polarity,) which has already occasioned much
perplexity and controversy, may easily
occasion much more, before it is settled to the satisfaction
of the philosophical world. The ideas of the
classificatory sciences also have of late been undergoing
much, and very instructive discussion, in the controversies
respecting the relations and offices of the natural
and artificial methods. And with regard to physiological
ideas, it would hardly be too much to say,
that the whole history of physiology up to the present
time has consisted of the discussion of the fundamental
ideas of the science, such as Vital Forces, Nutrition,
Reproduction, and the like. We had before us at
some length, in the History of Scientific Ideas, a review
183 of
the opposite opinions which have been advanced
on this subject; and we attempted in some degree to
estimate the direction in which these ideas are permanently
settling. But without attaching any importance
to this attempt, the account there given may at least
serve to show, how important a share in the past progress
of this subject the discussion of its Fundamental
Ideas has hitherto had.
22
 Hist. Ind. Sc. b. xiii. c. 6.
4. There is one reflexion which is very pointedly
suggested by what has been said. The manner in
which our scientific ideas acquire their distinct and
ultimate form being such as has been described,—always
involving much abstract reasoning and analysis
of our conceptions, often much opposite argumentation
and debate;—how unphilosophical is it to speak of
abstraction and analysis, of dispute and controversy, as
frivolous and unprofitable processes, by which true
science can never be benefitted; and how erroneous
to put such employments in antithesis with the study
of facts!
Yet some writers are accustomed to talk with contempt
of all past controversies, and to wonder at the
blindness of those who did not at first take the view
which was established at last. Such persons forget
that it was precisely the controversy, which established
among speculative men that final doctrine which they
themselves have quietly accepted. It is true, they
have had no difficulty in thoroughly adopting the
truth; but that has occurred because all dissentient
doctrines have been suppressed and forgotten; and because
systems, and books, and language itself, have
been accommodated peculiarly to the expression of
the accepted truth. To despise those who have, by
their mental struggles and conflicts, brought the subject
into a condition in which errour is almost out of
our reach, is to be ungrateful exactly in proportion to
the amount of the benefit received. It is as if a child,
when its teacher had with many trials and much
trouble prepared a telescope so that the vision through
it was distinct, should wonder at his stupidity in
pushing the tube of the eye-glass out and in so often. 184
5. Again, some persons condemn all that we have
here spoken of as the discussion of ideas, terming it
metaphysical: and in this spirit, one
writer23 has
spoken of the ‘metaphysical period’ of each science,
as preceding the period of ‘positive knowledge.’ But
as we have seen, that process which is here termed
‘metaphysical,’—the analysis of our conceptions and
the exposure of their inconsistencies,—(accompanied
with the study of facts,)—has always gone on most
actively in the most prosperous periods of each science.
There is, in Galileo, Kepler, Gassendi, and the other
fathers of mechanical philosophy, as much of metaphysics
as in their adversaries. The main difference
is, that the metaphysics is of a better kind; it is more
conformable to metaphysical truth. And the same is
the case in other sciences. Nor can it be otherwise.
For all truth, before it can be consistent with facts,
must be consistent with itself: and although this rule
is of undeniable authority, its application is often far
from easy. The perplexities and ambiguities which
arise from our having the same idea presented to us
under different aspects, are often difficult to
disentangle: and no common acuteness and steadiness of
thought must be expended on the task. It would be
easy to adduce, from the works of all great discoverers,
passages more profoundly metaphysical than any which
are to be found in the pages of barren à priori reasoners.
23
 M. Auguste Comte, Cours de Philosophie Positive.
6. As we have said, these metaphysical discussions
are not to be put in opposition to the study of facts;
but are to be stimulated, nourished and directed by a
constant recourse to experiment and observation. The
cultivation of ideas is to be conducted as having for
its object the connexion of facts; never to be pursued
as a mere exercise of the subtilty of the mind, striving
to build up a world of its own, and neglecting that
which exists about us. For although man may in this
way please himself, and admire the creations of his
own brain, he can never, by this course, hit upon the 185
real scheme of nature. With his ideas unfolded by
education, sharpened by controversy, rectified by metaphysics,
he may understand the natural world, but he
cannot invent it. At every step, he must try the value
of the advances he has made in thought, by applying
his thoughts to things. The Explication of Conceptions
must be carried on with a perpetual reference to
the Colligation of Facts.
Having here treated of Education and Discussion as
the methods by which the former of these two processes
is to be promoted, we have now to explain the
methods which science employs in order most successfully
to execute the latter. But the Colligation of
Facts, as already stated, may offer to us two steps of
a very different kind,—the laws of Phenomena, and
their Causes. We shall first describe some of the
methods employed in obtaining truths of the former of
these two kinds.
</div></body></text></TEI>