<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="9">

BOOK I.

THE GREEK SCHOOL PHILOSOPHY.

CHAPTER II.
The Greek Schools.

The Platonic Doctrine of
Ideas.
IN speaking of the Foundation
of the Greek School Philosophy, I have referred to the dialogue
entitled Parmenides, commonly ascribed to Plato. And the
doctrines ascribed to Parmenides, in that and in other works of
ancient authors, are certainly remarkable examples of the tendency
which prevailed among the Greeks to rush at once to the highest
generalizations of which the human mind is capable. The distinctive
dogma of the Eleatic School, of which Parmenides was one of the most
illustrious teachers, was that All Things are One. This indeed
was rather a doctrine of metaphysical theology than of physical
science. It tended to, or agreed with, the doctrine that All things
are God:—the doctrine commonly called Pantheism. But the
tenet of the Platonists which was commonly put in opposition to this,
that we must seek The One in the Many, had a bearing upon
physical science; at least, if we interpret it, as it is generally
interpreted, that we must seek the one Law which pervades a
multiplicity of Phenomena. We may however take the liberty of
remarking, that to speak of a Rule which is exemplified in many cases,
as being “the One in the Many” (a way of speaking by which we put out
of sight the consideration what very different kinds of things the
One and the Many are), is a mode of expression which makes
a very simple matter look very mysterious; and is another example of
the tendency which urges speculative men to aim at metaphysical
generality rather than scientific truth.
The Dialogue Parmenides is, as I have said, commonly
referred to Plato. Yet it is entirely different in substance, manner,
and tendency 492
from the most characteristic of the Platonic Dialogues. In these,
Socrates is represented as finally successful in refuting or routing
his adversaries, however confident their tone and however popular
their assertions. They are angered or humbled; he retains his good
temper and his air of superiority, and when they are exhausted, he
sums up in his own way.
In the Parmenides, on the contrary, everything is the
reverse of this. Parmenides and Zeno exchange good-humoured smiles at
Socrates’s criticism, when the bystanders expect them to grow angry.
They listen to Socrates while he propounds Plato’s doctrine of Ideas;
and reply to him with solid arguments which he does not answer, and
which have never yet been answered. Parmenides, in a patronising way,
lets him off; and having done this, being much entreated, he
pronounces a discourse concerning the One and the Many; which, obscure
as it may seem to us, was obviously intended to be irrefutable: and
during the whole of this part of the Dialogue, the friend of Socrates
appears only as a passive respondent, saying Yes or No
as the assertions of Parmenides require him to do; just in the same
way in which the opponents of Socrates are represented in other
Dialogues.
These circumstances, to which other historical difficulties might
be added, seem to show plainly that the Parmenides must be
regarded as an Eleatic, not as a Platonic Dialogue;—as composed
to confute, not to assert, the Platonic doctrine of Ideas.
The Platonic doctrine of Ideas has an important bearing upon the
philosophy of Science, and was suggested in a great measure by the
progress which the Greeks had really made in Geometry, Astronomy, and
other Sciences, as I shall elsewhere endeavor to show. This doctrine
has been recommended in our own time,1 as containing “a
mighty substance of imperishable truth.” It cannot fail to be
interesting to see in what manner the doctrine is presented by those
who thus judge of it. The following is the statement of its leading
features which they give us.</div></body></text></TEI>