<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol I</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1794</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="8">SECT. VIII.
OF SENSITIVE MOTIONS.

I. 1.
  Sensitive muscular motions were originally excited into action by
  irritation. 2. And sensitive sensual
  motions, ideas of imagination, dreams. II.
  1. Sensitive muscular motions are
  occasionally obedient to volition. 2.
  And sensitive sensual motions. III. 1. Other muscular motions are associated
  with the sensitive ones. 2. And other
  sensual motions.

I. 1. Many of
  the motions of our muscles, that are excited into action by irritation,
  are at the same time accompanied with painful or pleasurable sensations;
  and at length become by habit causable by the sensations. Thus the
  motions of the sphincters of the bladder and anus were originally excited
  into action by irritation; for young children give no attention to these
  evacuations; but as soon as they become sensible of the inconvenience of
  obeying these irritations, they suffer the water or excrement to
  accumulate, till it disagreeably affects them; and the action of those
  sphincters is then in consequence of this disagreeable sensation. So the
  secretion of saliva, which in young children is copiously produced by
  irritation, and drops from their mouths, is frequently attended with the
  agreeable sensation produced by the mastication of tasteful food;, till
  at length the sight of such food to a hungry person excites into action
  these salival glands; as is seen in the slavering of hungry dogs.
The motions of those muscles, which are affected by lascivious ideas,
  and those which are exerted in smiling, weeping, starting from fear, and
  winking at the approach of danger to the eye, and at times the actions of
  every large muscle of the body become causable by our sensations. And all
  these motions are performed with strength and velocity in proportion to
  the energy of the sensation that excites them, and the quantity of
  sensorial power.
2. Many of the motions of our organs of
  sense, or ideas, that were originally excited into action by irritation,
  become in like manner more frequently causable by our sensations of
  pleasure or pain. These motions are then termed the ideas of imagination,
  and make up all the scenery and transactions of our dreams. Thus when any
  painful or pleasurable sensations possess us, as of love, anger, fear;
  whether in our sleep or waking hours, the ideas, that have been formerly
  excited by the objects of these sensations, now vividly recur before us
  by their connection with these sensations themselves. So the fair smiling
  virgin, that excited your love by her presence, whenever that sensation
  recurs, rises before you in imagination; and that with all the pleasing
  circumstances, that had before engaged your attention. And in sleep, when
  you dream under the influence of fear, all the robbers, fires, and
  precipices, that you formerly have seen or heard of, arise before you
  with terrible vivacity. All these sensual motions, like the muscular ones
  above mentioned, are performed with strength and velocity in proportion
  to the energy of the sensation of pleasure or pain, which excites them,
  and the quantity of sensorial power.
II. 1. Many of
  these muscular motions above described, that are most frequently excited
  by our sensations, are nevertheless occasionally causable by volition;
  for we can smile or frown spontaneously, can make water before the
  quantity or acrimony of the urine produces a disagreeable sensation, and
  can voluntarily masticate a nauseous drug, or swallow a bitter draught,
  though our sensation would strongly dissuade us.
2. In like manner the sensual motions, or
  ideas, that are most frequently excited by our sensations, are
  nevertheless occasionally causeable by volition, as we can spontaneously
  call up our last night's dream before us, tracing it industriously step
  by step through all its variety of scenery and transaction; or can
  voluntarily examine or repeat the ideas, that have been excited by out
  disgust or admiration.
III. 1.
  Innumerable trains or tribes of motions are associated with these
  sensitive muscular motions above mentioned; as when a drop of water
  falling into the wind-pipe disagreeably affects the air-vessels of the
  lungs, they are excited into violent action; and with these sensitive
  motions are associated the actions of the pectoral and intercostal
  muscles, and the diaphragm; till by their united and repeated succussions
  the drop is returned through the larinx. The same occurs when any thing
  disagreeably affects the nostrils, or the stomach, or the uterus; variety
  of muscles are excited by association into forcible action, not to be
  suppressed by the utmost efforts of the will; as in sneezing, vomiting,
  and parturition.
2. In like manner with these sensitive
  sensual motions, or ideas of imagination, are associated many other
  trains or tribes of ideas, which by some writers of metaphysics have been
  classed under the terms of resemblance, causation, and contiguity; and
  will be more fully treated of hereafter.

</div></body></text></TEI>