<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="33">CHAPTER I.
Prelude to the Inductive Epoch of Newton.
WE have now to contemplate the
last and most splendid period of the progress of Astronomy;—the
grand completion of the history of the most ancient and prosperous
province of human knowledge;—the steps which elevated this
science to an unrivalled eminence above other sciences;—the
first great example of a wide and complex assemblage of phenomena
indubitably traced to their single simple cause;—in short, the
first example of the formation of a perfect Inductive Science.
In this, as in other considerable advances in real science, the
complete disclosure of the new truths by the principal discoverer, was
preceded by movements and glimpses, by trials, seekings, and guesses
on the part of others; by indications, in short, that men’s minds were
already carried by their intellectual impulses in the direction in
which the truth lay, and were beginning to detect its nature. In a
case so important and interesting as this, it is more peculiarly
proper to give some view of this Prelude to the Epoch of the full
discovery.
(Francis Bacon.) That Astronomy should become Physical
Astronomy,—that the motions of the heavenly bodies should be
traced to their causes, as well as reduced to rule,—was felt by
all persons of active and philosophical minds as a pressing and
irresistible need, at the time of which we speak. We have already seen
how much this feeling had to do in impelling Kepler to the train of
laborious research by which he made his discoveries. Perhaps it may be
interesting to point out how strongly this persuasion of the necessity
of giving a physical character to astronomy, had taken possession of
the mind of Bacon, who, looking at the progress of knowledge with a
more comprehensive spirit, and from a higher point of view than
Kepler, could have none of his astronomical prejudices, since on that
subject he was of a different school, and of far inferior knowledge.
In his “Description of the Intellectual Globe,” Bacon says that while
Astronomy had, up to that time, had it for her business to inquire
into the rules of the heavenly motions, and Philosophy into their
causes, they had both so far worked without due appreciation of their
respective tasks; Philosophy neglecting facts, and Astronomy claiming
assent to her 386
mathematical hypotheses, which ought to be considered as mere steps of
calculation. “Since, therefore,” he continues,1 “each science has
hitherto been a slight and ill-constructed thing, we must assuredly
take a firmer stand; our ground being, that these two subjects, which
on account of the narrowness of men’s views and the traditions of
professors have been so long dissevered, are, in fact, one and the
same thing, and compose one body of science.” It must be allowed that,
however erroneous might be the points of Bacon’s positive astronomical
creed, these general views of the nature and position of the science
are most sound and philosophical.
1 Vol. ix. 221.
(Kepler) In his attempts to suggest a right
physical view of the starry heavens and their relation to the earth,
Bacon failed, along with all the writers of his time. It has already
been stated that the main cause of this failure was the want of a
knowledge of the true theory of motion;—the non-existence of the
science of Dynamics. At the time of Bacon and Kepler, it was only just
beginning to be possible to reduce the heavenly motions to the laws of
earthly motion, because the latter were only just then divulged.
Accordingly, we have seen that the whole of Kepler’s physical
speculations proceed upon an ignorance of the first law of motion, and
assume it to be the main problem of the physical astronomer to assign
the cause which keeps up the motions of the planets. Kepler’s
doctrine is, that a certain Force or Virtue resides in the sun, by
which all bodies within his influence are carried round him. He
illustrates2 the nature of this Virtue in various
ways, comparing it to Light, and to the Magnetic Power, which it
resembles in the circumstances of operating at a distance, and also in
exercising a feebler influence as the distance becomes greater. But it
was obvious that these comparisons were very imperfect; for they do
not explain how the sun produces in a body at a distance a motion
athwart the line of emanation; and though Kepler introduced
an assumed rotation of the sun on his axis as the cause of this
effect, that such a cause could produce the result could not be
established by any analogy of terrestrial motions. But another image
to which he referred, suggested a much more substantial and
conceivable kind of mechanical action by which the celestial motions
might be produced, namely, a current of fluid matter circulating round
the sun, and carrying the planet with it, like a boat in a stream. In
the Table of Contents of the work on the planet Mars, the purport of
the chapter to which I have alluded is 387 stated as follows: “A physical
speculation, in which it is demonstrated that the vehicle of that
Virtue which urges the planets, circulates through the spaces of the
universe after the manner of a river or whirlpool (vortex),
moving quicker than the planets.” I think it will be found, by any one
who reads Kepler’s phrases concerning the moving force,—the
magnetic nature,—the immaterial virtue of the sun, that they
convey no distinct conception, except so far as they are interpreted
by the expressions just quoted. A vortex of fluid constantly whirling
round the sun, kept in this whirling motion by the rotation of the sun
himself, and carrying the planets round the sun by its revolution, as
a whirlpool carries straws, could be readily understood; and though it
appears to have been held by Kepler that this current and vortex was
immaterial, he ascribes to it the power of overcoming the inertia of
bodies, and of putting them and keeping them in motion, the only
material properties with which he had any thing to do. Kepler’s
physical reasonings, therefore, amount, in fact, to the doctrine of
Vortices round the central bodies, and are occasionally so stated by
himself; though by asserting these vortices to be “an immaterial
species,” and by the fickleness and variety of his phraseology on the
subject, he leaves this theory in some confusion;—a proceeding,
indeed, which both his want of sound mechanical conceptions, and his
busy and inventive fancy, might have led us to expect. Nor, we may
venture to say, was it easy for any one at Kepler’s time to devise a
more plausible theory than the theory of vortices might have been
made. It was only with the formation and progress of the science of
Mechanics that this theory became untenable.
2 De Stellâ Martis, P. 3. c.
xxxiv.
(Descartes) But if Kepler might be excused, or indeed
admired, for propounding the theory of Vortices at his time, the case
was different when the laws of motion had been fully developed, and
when those who knew the state of mechanical science ought to have
learned to consider the motions of the stars as a mechanical problem,
subject to the same conditions as other mechanical problems, and
capable of the same exactness of solution. And there was an especial
inconsistency in the circumstance of the Theory of Vortices being put
forwards by Descartes, who pretended, or was asserted by his admirers,
to have been one of the discoverers of the true Laws of Motion. It
certainly shows both great conceit and great shallowness, that he
should have proclaimed with much pomp this crude invention of the
ante-mechanical period, at the time when the best mathematicians of
Europe, as Borelli in Italy, Hooke and Wallis in England, Huyghens in
Holland, 388 were
patiently laboring to bring the mechanical problem of the universe
into its most distinct form, in order that it might be solved at last
and forever.
I do not mean to assert that Descartes borrowed his doctrines from
Kepler, or from any of his predecessors, for the theory was
sufficiently obvious; and especially if we suppose the inventor to
seek his suggestions rather in the casual examples offered to the
sense than in the exact laws of motion. Nor would it be reasonable to
rob this philosopher of that credit, of the plausible deduction of a
vast system from apparently simple principles, which, at the time, was
so much admired; and which undoubtedly was the great cause of the many
converts to his views. At the same time we may venture to say that a
system of doctrine thus deduced from assumed principles by a long
chain of reasoning, and not verified and confirmed at every step by
detailed and exact facts, has hardly a chance of containing any truth.
Descartes said that he should think it little to show how the world
is constructed, if he could not also show that it
must of necessity have been so constructed. The more modest
philosophy which has survived the boastings of his school is content
to receive all its knowledge of facts from experience, and never
dreams of interposing its peremptory must be when nature is
ready to tell us what is. The à priori philosopher
has, however, always a strong feeling in his favor among men. The
deductive form of his speculations gives them something of the charm
and the apparent certainty of pure mathematics; and while he avoids
that laborious recurrence to experiments, and measures, and multiplied
observations, which is irksome and distasteful to those who are
impatient to grow wise at once, every fact of which the theory appears
to give an explanation, seems to be an unasked and almost an
infallible witness in its favor.
My business with Descartes here is only with his physical Theory of
Vortices; which, great as was its glory at one time, is now utterly
extinguished. It was propounded in his Principia Philosophiæ,
in 1644. In order to arrive at this theory, he begins, as might be
expected of him, from reasonings sufficiently general. He lays it down
as a maxim, in the first sentence of his book, that a person who seeks
for truth must, once in his life, doubt of all that he most believes.
Conceiving himself thus to have stripped himself of all his belief on
all subjects, in order to resume that part of it which merits to be
retained, he begins with his celebrated assertion, “I think, therefore
I am;” which appears to him a certain and immovable principle, by
means of 389 which
he may proceed to something more. Accordingly, to this he soon adds
the idea, and hence the certain existence, of God and his perfections.
He then asserts it to be also manifest, that a vacuum in any part of
the universe is impossible; the whole must be filled with matter, and
the matter must be divided into equal angular parts, this being the
most simple, and therefore the most natural supposition.3
This matter being in motion, the parts are necessarily ground into a
spherical form; and the corners thus rubbed off (like filings or
sawdust) form a second and more subtle matter.4 There is, besides,
a third kind of matter, of parts more coarse and less fitted for
motion. The first matter makes luminous bodies, as the sun, and the
fixed stars; the second is the transparent substance of the skies; the
third is the material of opake bodies, as the earth, planets, and
comets. We may suppose, also,5 that the motions of these parts take the
form of revolving circular currents,6 or
vortices. By this means, the first matter will be collected to
the centre of each vortex, while the second, or subtle matter,
surrounds it, and, by its centrifugal effort, constitutes light. The
planets are carried round the sun by the motion of his vortex,7
each planet being at such a distance from the sun as to be in a part
of the vortex suitable to its solidity and mobility. The motions are
prevented from being exactly circular and regular by various causes;
for instance, a vortex may be pressed into an oval shape by contiguous
vortices. The satellites are, in like manner, carried round their
primary planets by subordinate vortices; while the comets have
sometimes the liberty of gliding out of one vortex into the one next
contiguous, and thus travelling in a sinuous course, from system to
system, through the universe. It is not necessary for us to speak here
of the entire deficiency of this system in mechanical consistency, and
in a correspondency to observation in details and measures. Its
general reception and temporary sway, in some instances even among
intelligent men and good mathematicians, are the most remarkable facts
connected with it. These may be ascribed, in part, to the circumstance
that philosophers were now ready and eager for a physical astronomy
commensurate with the existing state of knowledge; they may have been
owing also, in some measure, to the character and position of
Descartes. He was a man of high claims in every department of
speculation, and, in pure mathematics, a genuine inventor of great
eminence;—a man of family and a soldier;—an inoffensive
philosopher, attacked and persecuted 390 for his opinions with great bigotry and
fury by a Dutch divine, Voet;—the favorite and teacher of two
distinguished princesses, and, it is said, the lover of one of them.
This was Elizabeth, the daughter of the Elector Frederick, and
consequently grand-daughter of our James the First. His other royal
disciple, the celebrated Christiana of Sweden, showed her zeal for his
instructions by appointing the hour of five in the morning for their
interviews. This, in the climate of Sweden, and in the winter, was too
severe a trial for the constitution of the philosopher, born in the
sunny valley of the Loire; and, after a short residence at Stockholm,
he died of an inflammation of the chest in 1650. He always kept up an
active correspondence with his friend Mersenne, who was called, by
some of the Parisians, “the Resident of Descartes at Paris;” and who
informed him of all that was done in the world of science. It is said
that he at first sent to Mersenne an account of a system of the
universe which he had devised, which went on the assumption of a
vacuum; Mersenne informed him that the vacuum was no longer
the fashion at Paris; upon which he proceeded to remodel his system,
and to re-establish it on the principle of a plenum.
Undoubtedly he tried to avoid promulgating opinions which might bring
him into trouble. He, on all occasions, endeavored to explain away the
doctrine of the motion of the earth, so as to evade the scruples to
which the decrees of the pope had given rise; and, in stating the
theory of vortices, he says,8 “There is no doubt that the world was
created at first with all its perfection; nevertheless, it is well to
consider how it might have arisen from certain principles, although we
know that it did not.” Indeed, in the whole of his philosophy, he
appears to deserve the character of being both rash and cowardly,
“pusillanimus simul et audax,” far more than Aristotle, to
whose physical speculations Bacon applies this description.9
3 Prin. p. 58.
4 Ib. p. 59.
5 Ib. p. 56.
6 Ib. p. 61.
7 Ib. c. 140, p. 114.
8 Prin. p. 56.
9 Bacon, Descriptio Globi
Intellectualis.
Whatever the causes might be, his system was well received and
rapidly adopted. Gassendi, indeed, says that he found nobody who had
the courage to read the Principia through;10 but the system
was soon embraced by the younger professors, who were eager to dispute
in its favor. It is said11 that the University of Paris was on the
point of publishing an edict against these new doctrines, and was only
prevented from doing so by a pasquinade which is worth mentioning. It
was composed by the poet Boileau (about 1684), and professed to be a
Request in favor of Aristotle, and an Edict issued from Mount 391 Parnassus in
consequence. It is obvious that, at this time, the cause of
Cartesianism was looked upon as the cause of free inquiry and modern
discovery, in opposition to that of bigotry, prejudice, and ignorance.
Probably the poet was far from being a very severe or profound critic
of the truth of such claims. “This petition of the Masters of Arts,
Professors and Regents of the University of Paris, humbly showeth,
that it is of public notoriety that the sublime and incomparable
Aristotle was, without contest, the first founder of the four
elements, fire, air, earth, and water; that he did, by special grace,
accord unto them a simplicity which belongeth not to them of natural
right;” and so on. “Nevertheless, since, a certain time past, two
individuals, named Reason and Experience, have leagued themselves
together to dispute his claim to the rank which of justice pertains to
him, and have tried to erect themselves a throne on the ruins of his
authority; and, in order the better to gain their ends, have excited
certain factious spirits, who, under the names of Cartesians and
Gassendists, have begun to shake off the yoke of their master,
Aristotle; and, contemning his authority, with unexampled temerity,
would dispute the right which he had acquired of making true pass for
false and false for true;”—In fact, this production does not
exhibit any of the peculiar tenets of Descartes, although, probably,
the positive points of his doctrines obtained a footing in the
University of Paris, under the cover of this assault on his
adversaries. The Physics of Rohault, a zealous disciple of Descartes,
was published at Paris about 1670,12 and was, for a
time, the standard book for students of this subject, both in France
and in England. I do not here speak of the later defenders of the
Cartesian system, for, in their hands, it was much modified by the
struggle which it had to maintain against the Newtonian system.
10 Del. A. M. ii. 193.
11 Enc. Brit. art.
Cartesianism.
12 And a second edition in 1672.
We are concerned with Descartes and his school only as they form
part of the picture of the intellectual condition of Europe just
before the publication of Newton’s discoveries. Beyond this, the
Cartesian speculations are without value. When, indeed, Descartes’
countrymen could no longer refuse their assent and admiration to the
Newtonian theory, it came to be the fashion among them to say that
Descartes had been the necessary precursor of Newton; and to adopt a
favorite saying of Leibnitz, that the Cartesian philosophy was the
antechamber of Truth. Yet this comparison is far from being happy: it
appeared rather as if these suitors had mistaken the door; for those
392 who first came
into the presence of Truth herself, were those who never entered this
imagined antechamber, and those who were in the antechamber first,
were the last in penetrating further. In partly the same spirit,
Playfair has noted it as a service which Newton perhaps owed to
Descartes, that “he had exhausted one of the most tempting forms of
error.” We shall see soon that this temptation had no attraction for
those who looked at the problem in its true light, as the Italian and
English philosophers already did. Voltaire has observed, far more
truly, that Newton’s edifice rested on no stone of Descartes’
foundations. He illustrates this by relating that Newton only once
read the work of Descartes, and, in doing so, wrote the word
“error,” repeatedly, on the first seven or eight pages; after
which he read no more. This volume, Voltaire adds, was for some time
in the possession of Newton’s nephew.13
13 Cartesianism, Enc.
Phil.
(Gassendi.) Even in his own country, the system of Descartes
was by no means universally adopted. We have seen that though Gassendi
was coupled with Descartes as one of the leaders of the new
philosophy, he was far from admiring his work. Gassendi’s own views of
the causes of the motions of the heavenly bodies are not very clear,
nor even very clearly referrible to the laws of mechanics; although he
was one of those who had most share in showing that those laws apply
to astronomical motions. In a chapter, headed14 “Quæ sit motrix
siderum causa,” he reviews several opinions; but the one which he
seems to adopt, is that which ascribes the motion of the celestial
globes to certain fibres, of which the action is similar to that of
the muscles of animals. It does not appear, therefore, that he had
distinctly apprehended, either the continuation of the movements of
the planets by the First Law of Motion, or their deflection by the
Second Law;—the two main steps on the road to the discovery of
the true forces by which they are made to describe their orbits.
14 Gassendi, Opera, vol. i. p.
639.
(Leibnitz, &c.) Nor does it appear that in Germany
mathematicians had attained this point of view. Leibnitz, as we have
seen, did not assent to the opinions of Descartes, as containing the
complete truth; and yet his own views of the physics of the universe
do not seem to have any great advantage over these. In 1671 he
published A new physical hypothesis, by which the causes of most
phenomena are deduced from a certain single universal motion supposed
in our globe;—not to be despised either by the Tychonians or the
Copernicans. He supposes 393 the particles of the earth to have
separate motions, which produce collisions, and thus propagate15 an “agitation of the ether,” radiating
in all directions; and,16 “by the rotation of the sun on its
axis, concurring with its rectilinear action on the earth, arises the
motion of the earth about the sun.” The other motions of the solar
system are, as we might expect, accounted for in a similar manner; but
it appears difficult to invest such an hypothesis with any mechanical
consistency.
15 Art. 5.
16 Ib. 8.
John Bernoulli maintained to the last the Cartesian hypothesis,
though with several modifications of his own, and even pretended to
apply mathematical calculation to his principles. This, however,
belongs to a later period of our history; to the reception, not to the
prelude, of the Newtonian theory.
(Borelli.) In Italy, Holland, and England,
mathematicians appear to have looked much more steadily at the problem
of the celestial motions, by the light which the discovery of the real
laws of motion threw upon it. In Borelli’s Theories of the Medicean
Planets, printed at Florence in 1666, we have already a conception
of the nature of central action, in which true notions begin to
appear. The attraction of a body upon another which revolves about it
is spoken of and likened to magnetic action; not converting the
attracting force into a transverse force, according to the erroneous
views of Kepler, but taking it as a tendency of the bodies to meet.
“It is manifest,” says he,17 “that every planet and satellite
revolves round some principal globe of the universe as a fountain of
virtue, which so draws and holds them that they cannot by any means be
separated from it, but are compelled to follow it wherever it goes, in
constant and continuous revolutions.” And, further on, he describes18 the nature of the action, as a matter
of conjecture indeed, but with remarkable correctness.19 “We shall account for these motions by
supposing, that which can hardly be denied, that the planets have a
certain natural appetite for uniting themselves with the globe round
which they revolve, and that they really tend, with all their efforts,
to approach to such globe; the planets, for instance, to the sun, the
Medicean Stars to Jupiter. It is certain, also, that circular motion
gives a body a tendency to recede from the centre of such revolution,
as we find in a wheel, or a stone whirled in a sling. Let us suppose,
then, the planet to endeavor to approach the sun; since, in the mean
time, it requires, by the circular motion, a force to recede from the
same central body, it comes to pass, that when 394 those two opposite
forces are equal, each compensates the other, and the planet cannot go
nearer to the sun nor further from him than a certain determinate
space, and thus appears balanced and floating about him.”
17 Cap. 2.
18 Ib. 11.
19 P. 47.
This is a very remarkable passage; but it will be observed, at the
same time, that the author has no distinct conception of the manner in
which the change of direction of the planet’s motion is regulated from
one instant to another; still less do his views lead to any mode of
calculating the distance from the central body at which the planet
would be thus balanced, or the space through which it might approach
to the centre and recede from it. There is a great interval from
Borelli’s guesses, even to Huyghens’ theorems  and a much greater to
the beginning of Newton’s discoveries.
(England.) It is peculiarly interesting to us to trace the
gradual approach towards these discoveries which took place in the
minds of English mathematicians  and this we can do with tolerable
distinctness. Gilbert, in his work, De Magnete, printed in
1600, has only some vague notions that the magnetic virtue of the
earth in some way determines the direction of the earth’s axis, the
rate of its diurnal rotation, and that of the revolution of the moon
about it.20 He died in 1603, and, in his posthumous
work, already mentioned (De Mundo nostro
Sublunari Philosophia nova, 1651), we have already a more distinct
statement of the attraction of one body by another.21 “The force which emanates from the moon
reaches to the earth, and, in like manner, the magnetic virtue of the
earth pervades the region of the moon: both correspond and conspire by
the joint action of both, according to a proportion and conformity of
motions; but the earth has more effect, in consequence of its superior
mass; the earth attracts and repels the moon, and the moon, within
certain limits, the earth; not so as to make the bodies come together,
as magnetic bodies do, but so that they may go on in a continuous
course.” Though this phraseology is capable of representing a good
deal of the truth, it does not appear to have been connected, in the
author’s mind, with any very definite notions of mechanical action in
detail. We may probably say the same of Milton’s language:


  What if the sun
Be centre to the world; and other stars,
By his attractive virtue and their own
Incited, dance about him various rounds?
Par. Lost, B. viii.  

20 Lib. vi. cap. 6, 7.
21 Ib. ii. c. 19.
395 Boyle, about
the same period, seems to have inclined to the Cartesian hypothesis.
Thus, in order to show the advantage of the natural theology which
contemplates organic contrivances, over that which refers to
astronomy, he remarks: “It may be said, that in bodies inanimate,22 the contrivance is very rarely so
exquisite but that the various motions and occurrences of their parts
may, without much improbability, be suspected capable, after many
essays, to cast one another into several of those circumvolutions
called by Epicurus συστροφὰς and by Descartes, vortices; which
being once made, may continue a long time after the manner explained
by the latter.” Neither Milton nor Boyle, however, can be supposed to
have had an exact knowledge of the laws of mechanics; and therefore
they do not fully represent the views of their mathematical
contemporaries. But there arose about this time a group of
philosophers, who began to knock at the door where Truth was to be
found, although it was left for Newton to force it open. These were
the founders of the Royal Society, Wilkins, Wallis, Seth Ward, Wren,
Hooke, and others. The time of the beginning of the speculations and
association of these men corresponds to the time of the civil wars
between the king and parliament in England  and it does not appear a
fanciful account of their scientific zeal and activity, to say, that
while they shared the common mental ferment of the times, they sought
in the calm and peaceful pursuit of knowledge a contrast to the
vexatious and angry struggles which at that time disturbed the repose
of society. It was well if these dissensions produced any good to
science to balance the obvious evils which flowed from them.
Gascoigne, the inventor of the micrometer, a friend of Horrox, was
killed in the battle of Marston Moor. Milburne, another friend of
Horrox, who like him detected the errors of Lansberg’s astronomical
tables, left papers on this subject, which were lost by the coming of
the Scotch army into England in 1639; in the civil war which ensued,
the anatomical collections of Harvey were plundered and destroyed.
Most of these persons of whom I have lately had to speak, were
involved in the changes of fortune of the Commonwealth, some on one
side, and some on the other. Wilkins was made Warden of Wadham by the
committee of parliament appointed for reforming the University of
Oxford; and was, in 1659, made Master of Trinity College, Cambridge,
by Richard Cromwell, but ejected thence the year following, upon the
restoration of the 396 royal sway. Seth Ward, who was a Fellow
of Sidney College, Cambridge, was deprived of his Fellowship by the
parliamentary committee; but at a later period (1649) he took the
engagement to be faithful to the Commonwealth, and became Savilian
Professor of Astronomy at Oxford. Wallis held a Fellowship of Queen’s
College, Cambridge, but vacated it by marriage. He was afterwards much
employed by the royal party in deciphering secret writings, in which
art he had peculiar skill. Yet he was appointed by the parliamentary
commissioners Savilian Professor of Geometry at Oxford, in which
situation he was continued by Charles II. after his restoration.
Christopher Wren was somewhat later, and escaped these changes. He was
chosen Fellow of All-Souls in 1652, and succeeded Ward as Savilian
Professor of Astronomy. These men, along with Boyle and several
others, formed themselves into a club, which they called the
Philosophical, or the Invisible College; and met, from about the year
1645, sometimes in London, and sometimes in Oxford, according to the
changes of fortune and residence of the members. Hooke went to Christ
Church, Oxford, in 1663, where he was patronized by Boyle, Ward, and
Wallis; and when the Philosophical College resumed its meetings in
London, after the Restoration, as the Royal Society, Hooke was made
“curator of experiments.” Halley was of the next generation, and comes
after Newton; he studied at Queen’s College, Oxford, in 1673; but was
at first a man of some fortune, and not engaged in any official
situation. His talents and zeal, however, made him an active and
effective ally in the promotion of science.
22 Shaw’s Boyle’s Works, ii.
160.
The connection of the persons of whom we have been speaking has a
bearing on our subject, for it led, historically speaking, to the
publication of Newton’s discoveries in physical astronomy. Rightly to
propose a problem is no inconsiderable step to its solution; and it
was undoubtedly a great advance towards the true theory of the
universe to consider the motion of the planets round the sun as a
mechanical question, to be solved by a reference to the laws of
motion, and by the use of mathematics. So far the English philosophers
appear to have gone, before the time of Newton. Hooke, indeed, when
the doctrine of gravitation was published, asserted that he had
discovered it previously to Newton; and though this pretension could
not be maintained, he certainly had perceived that the thing to be
done was, to determine the effect of a central force in producing
curvilinear motion; which effect, as we have already seen, he illustrated by experiment as
early as 1666. Hooke had also spoken more clearly on this subject
397 in An
Attempt to prove the Motion of the Earth from Observations,
published in 1674. In this, he distinctly states that the planets
would move in straight lines, if they were not deflected by central
forces; and that the central attractive power increases in approaching
the centre in certain degrees, dependent on the distance. “Now what
these degrees are,” he adds, “I have not yet experimentally verified;”
but he ventures to promise to any one who succeeds in this
undertaking, a discovery of the cause of the heavenly motions. He
asserted, in conversation, to Halley and Wren, that he had solved this
problem, but his solution was never produced. The proposition that the
attractive force of the sun varies inversely as the square of the
distance from the centre, had already been divined, if not fully
established. If the orbits of the planets were circles, this
proportion of the forces might be deduced in the same manner as the
propositions concerning circular motion, which Huyghens published in
1673; yet it does not appear that Huyghens made this application of
his principles. Newton, however, had already made this step some years
before this time. Accordingly, he says in a letter to Halley, on
Hooke’s claim to this discovery,23 “When Huygenius
put out his Horologium Oscillatorium, a copy being presented to
me, in my letter of thanks I gave those rules in the end thereof a
particular commendation for their usefulness in computing the forces
of the moon from the earth, and the earth from the sun.” He says,
moreover, “I am almost confident by circumstances, that Sir
Christopher Wren knew the duplicate proportion when I gave him a
visit; and then Mr. Hooke, by his book Cometa, will prove the
last of us three that knew it.” Hooke’s Cometa was published in
1678. These inferences were all connected with Kepler’s law, that the
times are in the sesquiplicate ratio of the major axes of the orbits.
But Halley had also been led to the duplicate proportion by another
train of reasoning, namely, by considering the force of the sun as an
emanation, which must become more feeble in proportion to the
increased spherical surface over which it is diffused, and therefore
in the inverse proportion of the square of the distances.24 In this view of the matter, however,
the difficulty was to determine what would be the motion of a body
acted on by such a force, when the orbit is not circular but oblong.
The investigation of this case was a problem which, we can 398 easily conceive, must
have appeared of very formidable complexity while it was unsolved, and
the first of its kind. Accordingly Halley, as his biographer says,
“finding himself unable to make it out in any geometrical way, first
applied to Mr. Hooke and Sir Christopher Wren, and meeting with no
assistance from either of them, he went to Cambridge in August (1684),
to Mr. Newton, who supplied him fully with what he had so ardently
sought.”
23 Biog. Brit., art.
Hooke.
24 Bullialdus, in 1645, had asserted
that the force by which the sun “prehendit et harpagat,” takes hold of
and grapples the planets, must be as the inverse square of the
distance.
A paper of Halley’s in the Philosophical Transactions for
January, 1686, professedly inserted as a preparation for Newton’s
work, contains some arguments against the Cartesian hypothesis of
gravity, which seem to imply that Cartesian opinions had some footing
among English philosophers; and we are told by Whiston, Newton’s
successor in his professorship at Cambridge, that Cartesianism formed
a part of the studies of that place. Indeed, Rohault’s Physics
was used as a classbook at that University long after the time of
which we are speaking; but the peculiar Cartesian doctrines which it
contained were soon superseded by others.
With regard, then, to this part of the discovery, that the force of
the sun follows the inverse duplicate proportion of the distances, we
see that several other persons were on the verge of it at the same
time with Newton; though he alone possessed that combination of
distinctness of thought and power of mathematical invention, which
enabled him to force his way across the barrier. But another, and so
far as we know, an earlier train of thought, led by a different path
to the same result; and it was the convergence of these two lines of
reasoning that brought the conclusion to men’s minds with irresistible
force. I speak now of the identification of the force which retains
the moon in her orbit with the force of gravity by which bodies fall
at the earth’s surface. In this comparison Newton had, so far as I am
aware, no forerunner. We are now, therefore, arrived at the point at
which the history of Newton’s great discovery properly begins. ~Additional
material in the 3rd edition.~ 399</div></body></text></TEI>