<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="53">CHAPTER  VI.

Sect. 1.
Instruments.—2. Clocks.
IN page
473, I have described the manner in which astronomers are able to
observe the transit of a star, and other astronomical phenomena, to
the exactness of a tenth of a second of time. The mode of observation
there described implies that the observer at the moment of observation
compares the impressions of the eye and of the ear. Now it is found
that the habit which the observer must form of doing this operates
differently in different observers, so that one observer notes the
same fact as happening a fraction of a second earlier or later than
another observer does; and this in every case. Thus, using the term
equation, as we use it in Astronomy, to express a correction by
which we get regularity from irregularity, there is a personal
equation belonging to this mode of observation, showing that it is
liable to error. Can this error be got rid of?
It is at any rate much diminished by a method of observation
recently introduced into observatories, and first practised in
America. The essential feature of this mode of observation consists in
combining the impression of sight with that of touch, instead of with
that of hearing. The observer at the moment of observation presses
with his finger so as to make a mark on a machine which by its motion
measures time with great accuracy and on a large scale; and thus small
intervals of time are made visible.
A universal, though not a necessary, part of this machinery, as
hitherto adopted, is, that a galvanic circuit has been employed in
conveying the impression from the finger to the part where time is
measured and marked. The facility with which galvanic wires can 566 thus lead the
impression by any path to any distance, and increase its force in any
degree, has led to this combination, and almost identification, of
observation by touch with its record by galvanism.
The method having been first used by Mr. Bond at Cambridge, in
North America, has been adopted elsewhere, and especially at
Greenwich, where it is used for all the instruments; and consequently
a collection of galvanic batteries is thus as necessary a part of the
apparatus of the establishment as its graduated circles and arcs.
END OF VOL. I.

HISTORY
OF THE
INDUCTIVE SCIENCES.

VOLUME II.

BOOK VIII.

THE SECONDARY MECHANICAL
SCIENCES.

HISTORY OF ACOUSTICS.

. . . . . . Go,
demand
Of mighty Nature, if ’twas ever meant
That we should pry far off and be unraised,
That we should pore, and dwindle as we
pore,
Viewing all objects unremittingly
In disconnexion dead and spiritless;
And still dividing, and dividing still,
Break down all grandeur, still unsatisfied
With the perverse attempt, while littleness
May yet become more little; waging thus
An impious warfare ’gainst the very life
Of our own souls. Worsdworth,
Excursion.    



 . . . . . . 
Ἐσσυμένη δὲ
Ἠερίην ἀψῖδα διεῤῥοίζησε πεδίλῳ
Εἰς δόμον ἉΡΜΟΝIΗΣ παμμητόρος, ὁππόθι νύμφη
Ἴκελον οἶκον ἐναίε τύπῳ τετράζυγι κόσμου
Αὐτοπαγῆ  Nonnus. Dionysiac. xli.
275.    

Along the skiey arch the goddess trode,
And sought Harmonia’s august abode;
The universal plan, the mystic Four,
Defines the figure of the palace-floor.
Solid and square the ancient fabric stands,
Raised by the labors of unnumbered hands.



BOOK VIII.
</div></body></text></TEI>