<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="109">CHAPTER V.
Reception and Confirmation of the Distinction of
Systems of Crystallization.
DIFFUSION of the Distinction of
Systems.—The distinction of systems of crystallization
was so far founded on obviously true views, that it was speedily
adopted by most mineralogists. I need not dwell on the steps by which
this took place. Mr. Haidinger’s translation of Mohs was a principal
occasion of its introduction in England. As an indication of dates,
bearing on this subject, perhaps I may be allowed to notice, that
there appeared in the Philosophical Transactions for 1825, A
General Method of Calculating the Angles of Crystals, which I had
written, and in which I referred only to Haüy’s views; but that in
1826,34 I published a Memoir On the
Classification of Crystalline Combinations, founded on the methods
of Weiss and Mohs, especially the latter; with which I had in the mean
time become acquainted, and which appeared to me to contain their own
evidence and recommendation. General methods, such as was attempted in
the Memoir just quoted, are part of that process in the history of
sciences, by which, when the principles are once established, the
mathematical operation of deducing their consequences is made more and
more general and symmetrical: which we have seen already exemplified
in the history of celestial mechanics after the time of Newton. It
does not enter into our plan, to dwell upon the various steps in this
way 331 made by
Levy, Naumann, Grassmann, Kupffer, Hessel, and by Professor Miller
among ourselves. I may notice that one great improvement was, the
method introduced by Monteiro and Levy, of determining the laws of
derivation of forces by means of the parallelisms of edges;
which was afterwards extended so that faces were considered as
belonging to zones. Nor need I attempt to enumerate (what
indeed it would be difficult to describe in words) the various methods
of notation by which it has been proposed to represent the
faces of crystals, and to facilitate the calculations which have
reference to them.
34 Camb. Trans. vol. ii. p.
391.
[2nd Ed.] [My Memoir of 1825 depended on the views of Haüy in so
far as that I started from his “primitive forms;” but being a general
method of expressing all forms by co-ordinates, it was very little
governed by these views. The mode of representing crystalline forms
which I proposed seemed to contain its own evidence of being more true
to nature than Haüy’s theory of decrements, inasmuch as my method
expressed the faces at much lower numbers. I determine a face by means
of the dimensions of the primary form divided by certain
numbers; Haüy had expressed the face virtually by the same dimensions
multiplied by numbers. In cases where my notation gives such
numbers as (3, 4, 1), (1, 3, 7), (5, 1, 19), his method involves the
higher numbers (4, 3, 12), (21, 7, 3), (19, 95, 5). My method however
has, I believe, little value as a method of “calculating the
angles of crystals.”
M. Neumann, of Königsberg, introduced a very convenient and elegant
mode of representing the position of faces of crystals by
corresponding points on the surface of a circumscribing sphere. He
gave (in 1823) the laws of the derivation of crystalline faces,
expressed geometrically by the intersection of zones, (Beiträge zur
Krystallonomie.) The same method of indicating the position of
faces of crystals was afterwards, together with the notation,
re-invented by M. Grassmann, (Zur Krystallonomie und Geometrischen
Combinationslehre, 1829.) Aiding himself by the suggestions of
these writers, and partly adopting my method, Prof. Miller has
produced a work on Crystallography remarkable for mathematical
elegance and symmetry; and has given expressions really useful for
calculating the angles of crystalline faces, (A Treatise on
Crystallography. Cambridge, 1839.)]
Confirmation of the Distinction of Systems by the Optical
Properties of Minerals.—Brewster.—I must not omit to
notice the striking confirmation which the distinction of systems of
crystallization received from optical discoveries, especially those of
Sir D. Brewster. Of the 332 history of this very rich and beautiful
department of science, we have already given some account, in speaking
of Optics. The first facts which were noticed, those relating to
double refraction, belonged exclusively to crystals of the
rhombohedral system. The splendid phenomena of the rings and
lemniscates produced by dipolarizing crystals, were afterwards
discovered; and these were, in 1817, classified by Sir David Brewster,
according to the crystalline forms to which they belong. This
classification, on comparison with the distinction of Systems of
Crystallization, resolved itself into a necessary relation of
mathematical symmetry: all crystals of the pyramidal and rhombohedral
systems, which from their geometrical character have a single axis of
symmetry, are also optically uniaxal, and produce by dipolarization
circular rings; while the prismatic system, which has no such single
axis, but three unequal axes of symmetry, is optically biaxal, gives
lemniscates by dipolarized light, and according to Fresnel’s theory,
has three rectangular axes of unequal elasticity.
[2nd Ed.] [I have placed Sir David Brewster’s arrangement of
crystalline forms in this chapter, as an event belonging to the
confirmation of the distinctions of forms introduced by Weiss
and Mohs; because that arrangement was established, not on
crystallographical, but on optical grounds. But Sir David Brewster’s
optical discovery was a much greater step in science than the systems
of the two German crystallographers; and even in respect to the
crystallographical principle, Sir D. Brewster had an independent share
in the discovery. He divided crystalline forms into three classes,
enumerating the Hauïan “primitive forms” which belonged to each; and
as he found some exceptions to this classification, (such as idocrase,
&c.,) he ventured to pronounce that in those substances the
received primitive forms were probably erroneous; a judgment which was
soon confirmed by a closer crystallographical scrutiny. He also showed
his perception of the mineralogical importance of his discovery by
publishing it, not only in the Phil. Trans. (1818), but also in
the Transactions of the Wernerian Society of Natural History.
In a second paper inserted in this later series, read in 1820, he
further notices Mohs’s System of Crystallography, which had then
recently appeared, and points out its agreement with his own.
Another reason why I do not make his great optical discovery a
cardinal point in the history of crystallography is, that as a
crystallographical system it is incomplete. Although we are thus led
to distinguish the tessular and the prismatic systems
(using Mohs’s terms) 333 from the rhombohedral and the
square prismatic, we are not led to distinguish the latter two
from each other; inasmuch as they have no optical difference of
character. But this distinction is quite essential in crystallography;
for these two systems have faces formed by laws as different as those
of the other two systems.
Moreover, Weiss and Mohs not only divided crystalline forms into
certain classes, but showed that by doing this, the derivation of all
the existing forms from the fundamental ones assumed a new aspect of
simplicity and generality; and this was the essential part of what
they did.
On the other hand, I do not think it is too much to say as I have
elsewhere said35 that “Sir D. Brewster’s optical
experiments must have led to a classification of crystals into the
above systems, or something nearly equivalent, even if crystals had
not been so arranged by attention to their forms.”]
35 Philosophy of the Inductive
Sciences, B. viii. C. iii. Art. 3.
Many other most curious trains of research have confirmed the
general truth, that the degree and kind of geometrical symmetry
corresponds exactly with the symmetry of the optical properties. As an
instance of this, eminently striking for its singularity, we may
notice the discovery of Sir John Herschel, that the plagihedral
crystallization of quartz, by which it exhibits faces twisted
to the right or the left, is accompanied by right-handed or
left-handed circular polarization respectively. No one acquainted with
the subject can now doubt, that the correspondence of geometrical and
optical symmetry is of the most complete and fundamental kind.
[2nd Ed.] [Our knowledge with respect to the positions of the
optical axes of the oblique prismatic crystals is still imperfect. It
appears to be ascertained that, in singly oblique crystals, one of the
axes of optical elasticity coincides with the rectangular
crystallographic axis. In doubly oblique crystals, one of the axes of
optical elasticity is, in many cases, coincident with the axis of a
principal zone. I believe no more determinate laws have been
discovered.]
Thus the highest generalization at which mathematical
crystallographers have yet arrived, may be considered as fully
established; and the science of Crystallography, in the condition in
which these place it, is fit to be employed as one of the members of
Mineralogy, and thus to fill its appropriate place and office.
~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~
334</div></body></text></TEI>