<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ninth Bridgewater Treatise</title><author>Babbage, Charles (1791-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="15">ON TIME.
 Time and change are great, only with reference to the faculties of the beings
 which note them. The insect of an hour, fluttering, during its transient existence,
 in an atmosphere of perfume, would attribute unchanging duration to the beautiful
 flowers of the cistus, whose petals cover the dewy
[page] 88
 grass but a few hours after it has received the lifeless body of the gnat.
 These flowers, could they reflect, might contrast their transitory lives with
 the prolonged existence. of their greener neighbours. The leaves themselves,
 counting their brief span by the lapse of a few moons, might regard as almost
 indefinitely extended the duration of the common parent of both leaf and flower.
 The lives of individual trees are lost in the continued destruction and renovation
 which take place in forest masses. Forests themselves, starved by the exhaustion
 of the soil, or consumed by fire, succeed each other in slow gradation. A forest
 of oaks waves its luxuriant branches over a spot which has been fertilized by
 the ashes of a forest of pines. These periods again merge into other and still
 longer cycles, during which the latest of a thousand forests sinks beneath the
 waves, from the gradual subsidence of its parent earth; or in which extensive
 inundations, by accumulating the silt of centuries, gradually convert the
[page] 89
 living trunks into their stony resemblances. Stratum upon stratum subsides
 in comminuted particles, and is accumulated in the depths of ocean, whence they
 again arise, consolidated by pressure and by heat, to form the continents and
 mountains of a new creation. Such, in endless succession, is the history of
 the changes of the globe we dwell upon; and human observation, aided by human
 reason, has as yet discovered few signs of a beginning—no symptom of an end.
 Yet, in that more extended view which recognises our planet as one amongst the
 attendants of a central luminary; that sun itself,—the soul, as it were, of
 vegetable and animal existence, but an insignificant individual among its congeners
 of the milky way:—when we remember that that cloud of light, gleaming with
 its myriad systems, is but an isolated nebula amongst a countless host of rivals,
 which the starry firmament surrounding us
[page] 90
 on all sides, presents in every varied form;—some as uncondensed masses
 of attenuated light;—some as having, in obedience to attractive forces, assumed
 a spherical figure; others, as if farther advanced in the history of their fate,
 enclosing a denser central nucleus surrounded by a more diluted light, spreading
 into such vast space, that the whole of our own nebula would be lost in it:—others
 there are, in hich the apparently unformed and irregular mass of nebulous light
 is just curdling, as it were, into separate systems; whilst many present a
 congeries of distinct points of light, each, perhaps, the splendid luminary
 of a creation more glorious than our own;—when the birth, the progress, and
 the history of sidereal systems are considered, we require some other unit of
 time than even that comprehensive one which astronomy has unfolded to our view.
 Minute and almost infinitesimal as is the time which comprises the history of
 our race compared with that which records the history of our system, the space
 even of
[page] 91
 this latter period forms too limited a standard wherewith to measure the footmarks
 of eternity.
[page] 92</div></body></text></TEI>