<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Vestiges of the Natural History of Creation</title><author>Chambers, Robert (1802-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="13">p.
165PARTICULAR CONSIDERATIONS
RESPECTING
THE ORIGIN OF THE ANIMATED TRIBES.
The general likelihood of an
organic creation by law having been shewn, we are next to inquire
if science has any facts tending to bring the assumption more
nearly home to nature.  Such facts there certainly are; but
it cannot be surprising that they are comparatively few and
scattered, when we consider that the inquiry is into one of
nature’s profoundest mysteries, and one which has hitherto
engaged no direct attention in almost any quarter.
Crystallization is confessedly a phenomenon of inorganic
matter; yet the simplest rustic observer is struck by the
resemblance which the examples of it left upon a window by frost
bear to vegetable forms.  In some crystallizations the
mimicry is beautiful and complete; for example, in the well-known
one called the Arbor Dianæ.  An amalgam of four
parts of silver and two of mercury being dissolved in nitric
acid, and water equal to thirty weights of the metals being
added, a small piece of soft amalgam of silver suspended in the
solution, quickly gathers to itself the particles of the silver
of the amalgam, which form upon it a crystallization precisely
resembling a shrub.  The experiment may be varied in a
way which serves better to detect the influence of electricity in
such operations, as noted below. [166]  Vegetable
figures are also presented in some of the most ordinary
appearances of the electric fluid.  In the marks caused by
positive electricity, or which it leaves in its passage, we see
the ramifications of a tree, as well as of its individual leaves;
those of the negative, recal the bulbous or the spreading root,
according as they are clumped or divergent.  These phenomena
seem to say that the electric energies have had something to do
in determining the forms of plants.  That they are
intimately connected with vegetable life is indubitable, for
germination will not proceed in water charged with negative
electricity, while water charged positively greatly favours it;
and a garden sensibly increases in luxuriance, when a number of
conducting rods are made to terminate in branches over its
beds.  With regard to the resemblance of the ramifications
of the branches and leaves of plants to the traces of the
positive electricity, and that of the roots to the negative, it
is a circumstance calling for especial remark, that the
atmosphere, particularly its lower strata, is generally charged
positively, while the earth is always charged negatively. 
The correspondence here is curious.  A plant thus appears as
a thing formed on the basis of a natural electrical
operation—the brush realized.  We can thus
suppose the various forms of plants as, immediately, the result
of a law in electricity variously affecting them according to
their organic character, or respective germinal
constituents.  In the poplar, the brush is unusually
vertical, and little divergent; the reverse in the beech: in the
palm, a pencil has proceeded straight up for a certain distance,
radiates there, and turns outwards and downwards; and so
on.  We can here see at least traces of secondary means by
which the Almighty Deviser might establish all the vegetable
forms with which the earth is overspread.
Vegetable and animal bodies are mainly composed of the same
four simple substances or elements—carbon, oxygen,
hydrogen, and nitrogen.  The first combinations of these in
animals are into what are called proximate principles, as
albumen, fibrin, urea, alantoin, &c., out of which the
structure of the animal body is composed.  Now the chemist,
by the association of two parts oxygen, four hydrogen, two
carbon, and two nitrogen, can make urea.  Alantoin
has also been produced artificially.  Two of the proximate
principles being realizable by human care, the possibility of
realizing or forming all is established.  Thus the chemist
may be said to have it in his power to realize the first step in
organization. [169a]  Indeed, it is fully
acknowledged by Dr. Daubeny, that in the combinations forming the
proximate principles there is no chemical peculiarity. 
“It is now certain,” he says, “that the same
simple laws of composition pervade the whole creation; and that,
if the organic chemist only takes the requisite precautions to
avoid resolving into their ultimate elements the proximate
principles upon which he operates, the results of his analysis
will shew that they are combined precisely according to the same
plan as the elements of mineral bodies are known to be.” [169b]  A particular fact is here
worthy of attention.  “The conversion of fecula into
sugar, as one of the ordinary processes of vegetable economy, is
effected by the production of a secretion termed diastose,
which occasions both the rupture of the starch vesicles, and the
change of their contained gum into sugar.  This diastose may
be separately obtained by the chemist, and it acts as effectually
in his laboratory as in the vegetable organization.  He can
also imitate its effects by other chemical agents.” [170]  The writer quoted below adds,
“No reasonable ground has yet been adduced for supposing
that, if we had the power of bringing together the elements of
any organic compound, in their requisite states and proportions,
the result would be any other than that which is found in the
living body.”
It is much to know the elements out of which organic bodies
are composed.  It is something more to know their first
combinations, and that these are simply chemical.  How these
combinations are associated in the structure of living bodies is
the next inquiry, but it is one to which as yet no satisfactory
answer can be given.  The investigation of the minutiæ
of organic structure by the microscope is of such recent origin,
that its results cannot be expected to be very clear.  Some
facts, however, are worthy of attention with regard to the
present inquiry.  It is ascertained that the basis of all
vegetable and animal substances consists of nucleated cells; that
is, cells having granules within them.  Nutriment is
converted into these before being assimilated by the
system.  The tissues are formed from them.  The ovum
destined to become a new creature, is originally only a cell with
a contained granule.  We see it acting this reproductive
part in the simplest manner in the cryptogamic plants. 
“The parent cell, arrived at maturity by the exercise of
its organic functions, bursts, and liberates its contained
granules.  These, at once thrown upon their own resources,
and entirely dependent for their nutrition on the surrounding
elements, develop themselves into new cells, which repeat the
life of their original.  Amongst the higher tribes of the
cryptogamia, the reproductive cell does not burst, but the first
cells of the new structure are developed within it, and these
gradually extend, by a similar process of multiplication, into
that primary leaf-like expansion which is the first formed
structure in all plants.”  [171]  Here the little cell becomes
directly a plant, the full formed living being. 
It is also worthy of remark that, in the sponges, (an animal
form,) a gemmule detached from the body of the parent, and
trusting for sustentation only to the fluid into which it has
been cast, becomes, without further process, the new
creature.  Further, it has been recently discovered by means
of the microscope, that there is, as far as can be judged, a
perfect resemblance between the ovum of the mammal tribes, during
that early stage when it is passing through the oviduct, and the
young of the infusory animalcules.  One of the most
remarkable of these, the volvox globator, has exactly the
form of the germ which, after passing through a long fœtal
progress, becomes a complete mammifer, an animal of the highest
class.  It has even been found that both are alike provided
with those cilia, which, producing a revolving motion, or
its appearance, is partly the cause of the name given to this
animalcule.  These resemblances are the more entitled to
notice, that they were made by various observers, distant from
each other at the time. [172]  It has
likewise been noted that the globules of the blood are reproduced
by the expansion of contained granules; they are, in short,
distinct organisms multiplied by the same fissiparous
generation.  So that all animated nature may be said to
be based on this mode of origin; the fundamental form of
organic being is a globule, having a new globule forming
within itself, by which it is in time discharged, and which
is again followed by another and another, in endless
succession.  It is of course obvious that, if these globules
could be produced by any process from inorganic elements, we
should be entitled to say that the fact of a transit from the
inorganic into the organic had been witnessed in that instance;
the possibility of the commencement of animated creation by the
ordinary laws of nature might be considered as established. 
Now it was given out some years ago by a French physiologist,
that globules could be produced in albumen by
electricity.  If, therefore, these globules be identical
with the cells which are now held to be reproductive, it might be
said that the production of albumen by artificial means is the
only step in the process wanting.  This has not yet been
effected; but it is known to be only a chemical process, the mode
of which may be any day discovered in the laboratory, and two
compounds perfectly co-ordinate, urea and alantoin, have actually
been produced.
In such an investigation as the present, it is not unworthy of
notice that the production of shell is a natural operation which
can be precisely imitated artificially.  Such an
incrustation takes place on both the outside and inside of the
wheel in a bleaching establishment, in which cotton cloth is
rinsed free of the lime employed in its purification.  From
the dressing employed by the weaver, the cloth obtains the
animal matter, gelatin; this and the lime form the
constituents of the incrustation, exactly as in natural
shell.  In the wheel employed at Catrine, in Ayrshire, where
the phenomenon was first observed by the eye of science, it had
required ten years to produce a coating the tenth of an inch in
thickness.  This incrustation has all the characters of
shell, displaying a highly polished surface, beautifully
iridescent, and, when broken, a foliated texture.  The
examination of it has even thrown some light on the character and
mode of formation of natural shell.  “The plates into
which the substance is divisible have been formed in succession,
and certain intervals of time have elapsed between their
formation; in general, every two contiguous laminæ are
separated by a thin iridescent film, varying from the three to
the fifty millionth part of an inch in thickness, and producing
all the various colours of thin plates which correspond to
intermediate thicknesses: between some of the laminæ no
such film exists, probably in consequence of the interval of time
between their formation being too short; and between others the
film has been formed of unequal thickness.  There can be no
doubt that these iridescent films are formed when the dash-wheel
is at rest during the night, and that when no film exists between
two laminæ, an interval too short for its formation,
(arising, perhaps, from the stopping of the work during the day,)
has elapsed during the drying or induration of one lamina and the
deposition of another.” [175]  From this it
has been deduced, by a patient investigation, that those colours
of mother-of-pearl, which are incommunicable to wax, arise from
iridescent films deposited between the laminæ of its
structure, and it is hence inferred that the animal, like
the wheel, rests periodically from its labours in forming the
natural substance.
These, it will be owned, are curious and not irrelevant facts;
but it will be asked what actual experience says respecting the
origination of life.  Are there, it will be said, any
authentic instances of either plants or animals, of however
humble and simple a kind, having come into existence otherwise
than in the ordinary way of generation, since the time of which
geology forms the record?  It may be answered, that the
negative of this question could not be by any means formidable to
the doctrine of law-creation, seeing that the conditions
necessary for the operation of the supposed life-creating laws
may not have existed within record to any great extent.  On
the other hand, as we see the physical laws of early times still
acting with more or less force, it might not be unreasonable to
expect that we should still see some remnants, or partial and
occasional workings of the life-creating energy amidst a system
of things generally stable and at rest.  Are there, then,
any such remnants to be traced in our own day, or during
man’s existence upon earth?  If there be, it clearly
would form a strong evidence in favour of the doctrine, as what
now takes place upon a confined scale and in a comparatively
casual manner may have formerly taken place on a great scale, and
as the proper and eternity-destined means of supplying a vacant
globe with suitable tenants.  It will at the same time be
observed that, the earth being now supplied with both kinds of
tenants in great abundance, we only could expect to find the
life-originating power at work in some very special and
extraordinary circumstances, and probably only in the inferior
and obscurer departments of the vegetable and animal
kingdoms.
Perhaps, if the question were asked of ten men of approved
reputation in science, nine out of the number would answer in the
negative.  This is because, in a great number of instances
where the superficial observers of former times assumed a
non-generative origin for life, (as in the celebrated case in
Virgil’s fourth Georgic,) either the direct contrary has
been ascertained, or exhaustive experiments have left no
alternative from the conclusion that ordinary generation did take
place, albeit in a manner which escapes observation. 
Finding that an erroneous assumption has been formed in many
cases, modern inquirers have not hesitated to assume that there
can be no case in which generation is not concerned; an
assumption not only unwarranted by, but directly opposed to, the
principles of philosophical investigation.  Yet this is
truly the point at which the question now rests in the scientific
world.
I have no wish here to enter largely into a subject so wide
and so full of difficulties; but I may remark, that the
explanations usually suggested where life takes its rise without
apparent generative means, always appear to me to partake much of
the fallacy of the petitio principii.  When, for
instance, lime is laid down upon a piece of waste moss ground,
and a crop of white clover for which no seeds were sown is the
consequence, the explanation that the seeds have been dormant
there for an unknown time, and were stimulated into germination
when the lime produced the appropriate circumstances, appears
extremely unsatisfactory, especially when we know that (as in an
authentic case under my notice) the spot is many miles from where
clover is cultivated, and that there is nothing for six feet
below but pure peat moss, clover seeds being, moreover, known to
be too heavy to be transported, as many other seeds are, by the
winds.  Mushrooms, we know, can be propagated by their seed;
but another mode of raising them, well known to the gardener, is
to mix cow and horse dung together, and thus form a bed in which
they are expected to grow without any seed being planted. 
It is assumed that the seeds are carried by the atmosphere,
unperceived by us, and, finding here an appropriate field for
germination, germinate accordingly; but this is only assumption,
and though designed to be on the side of a severe philosophy, in
reality makes a pretty large demand on credulity.  There are
several persons eminent in science who profess at least to find
great difficulties in accepting the doctrine of invariable
generation.  One of these, in the work noted below, [179a] has stated several considerations
arising from analogical reasoning, which appear to him to throw
the balance of evidence in favour of the aboriginal production of
infusoria, [179b] the vegetation called mould, and the
like.  One seems to be of great force; namely, that the
animalcules, which are supposed (altogether hypothetically) to be
produced by ova, are afterwards found increasing their numbers,
not by that mode at all, but by division of their bodies. 
If it be the nature of these creatures to propagate in this
splitting or fissiparous manner, how could they be communicated
to a vegetable infusion?  Another fact of very high
importance is presented in the following terms:—“The
nature of the animalcule, or vegetable production, bears a
constant relation to the state of the infusion, so that, in
similar circumstances, the same are always produced without this
being influenced by the atmosphere.  There seems to be a
certain progressive advance in the productive powers of the
infusion, for at the first the animalcules are only of the
smaller kinds, or monades, and afterwards they become
gradually larger and more complicated in their structure;
after a time, the production ceases, although
the materials are by no means exhausted.  When the
quantity of water is very small, and the organic matter abundant,
the production is usually of a vegetable nature; when there is
much water, animalcules are more frequently
produced.”  It has been shewn by the opponents of this
theory, that when a vegetable infusion is debarred from the
contact of the atmosphere, by being closely sealed up or covered
with a layer of oil, no animalcules are produced; but it has been
said, on the other hand, that the exclusion of the air may
prevent some simple condition necessary for the aboriginal
development of life—and nothing is more likely. 
Perhaps the prevailing doctrine is in nothing placed in greater
difficulties than it is with regard to the entozoa, or creatures
which live within the bodies of others.  These creatures do,
and apparently can, live nowhere else than in the interior of
other living bodies, where they generally take up their abode in
the viscera, but also sometimes in the chambers of the eye, the
interior of the brain, the serous sacs, and other places having
no communication from without.  Some are viviparous, others
oviparous.  Of the latter it cannot reasonably be supposed
that the ova ever pass through the medium of the air, or through
the blood-vessels, for they are too heavy for the one transit,
and too large for the other.  Of the former, it cannot be
conceived how they pass into young animals—certainly not by
communication from the parent, for it has often been found that
entozoa do not appear in certain generations, and some of
peculiar and noted character have only appeared at rare
intervals, and in very extraordinary circumstances.  A
candid view of the less popular doctrine, as to the origin of
this humble form of life, is taken by a distinguished living
naturalist.  “To explain the beginning of these worms
within the human body, on the common doctrine that all created
beings proceed from their likes, or a primordial egg, is so
difficult, that the moderns have been driven to speculate, as our
fathers did, on their spontaneous birth; but they have received
the hypothesis with some modification.  Thus it is not from
putrefaction or fermentation that the entozoa are born, for both
of these processes are rather fatal to their existence, but from
the aggregation and fit apposition of matter which is already
organized, or has been thrown from organized surfaces. 
Their origin in this manner is not more wonderful or more
inexplicable than that of many of the inferior animals from
sections of themselves. * * Particles of matter fitted by
digestion, and their transmission through a living body, for
immediate assimilation with it, or flakes of lymph detached from
surfaces already organized, seem neither to exceed nor fall below
that simplicity of structure which favours this wonderful
development; and the supposition that, like morsels of a
planaria, they may also, when retained in contact with living
parts, and in other favourable circumstances, continue to live
and be gradually changed into creatures of analogous
conformation, is surely not so absurd as to be brought into
comparison with the Metamorphoses of Ovid. * * We think the
hypothesis is also supported in some degree by the fact, that the
origin of the entozoa is favoured by all causes which tend to
disturb the equality between the secerning and absorbent
systems.” [182]  Here particles of organized
matter are suggested as the germinal origin of distinct and fully
organized animals, many of which have a highly developed
reproductive system.  How near such particles must be to the
inorganic form of matter may be judged from what has been said
within the last few pages.  If, then, this view of the
production of entozoa be received, it must be held as in no small
degree favourable to the general doctrine of an organic creation
by law.
There is another series of facts, akin to the above, and which
deserve not less attention.  The pig, in its domestic state,
is subject to the attacks of a hydatid, from which the wild
animal is free; hence the disease called measles in pork. 
The domestication of the pig is of course an event subsequent to
the origin of man; indeed, comparatively speaking, a recent
event.  Whence, then, the first progenitor of this
hydatid?  So also there is a tinea which attacks dressed
wool, but never touches it in its unwashed state.  A
particular insect disdains all food but chocolate, and the larva
of the oinopota cellaris lives nowhere but in wine and
beer, all of these being articles manufactured by man. 
There is likewise a creature called the pimelodes
cyclopum, which is only found in subterranean cavities
connected with certain specimens of the volcanic formation in
South America, dating from a time posterior to the arrangements
of the earth for our species.  Whence the first pymelodes
cyclopum?  Will it, to a geologist, appear irrational to
suppose that, just as the pterodactyle was added in the era of
the new red sandstone, when the earth had become suited for such
a creature, so may these creatures have been added when media
suitable for their existence arose, and that such phenomena may
take place any day, the only cause for their taking place seldom
being the rarity of the rise of new physical conditions on a
globe which seems to have already undergone the principal part of
its destined mutations?
Between such isolated facts and the greater changes which
attended various geological eras, it is not easy to see any
difference, besides simply that of the scale on which the
respective phenomena took place, as the throwing off of one copy
from an engraved plate is exactly the same process as that by
which a thousand are thrown off.  Nothing is more easy to
conceive than that to Creative Providence, the numbers of such
phenomena, the time when, and the circumstances under which they
take place, are indifferent matters.  The Eternal One has
arranged for everything beforehand, and trusted all to the
operation of the laws of his appointment, himself being ever
present in all things.  We can even conceive that man, in
his many doings upon the surface of the earth, may occasionally,
without his being aware of it, or otherwise, act as an instrument
in preparing the association of conditions under which the
creative laws work; and perhaps some instances of his having
acted as such an instrument have actually occurred in our own
time.
I allude, of course, to the experiments conducted a few years
ago by Mr. Crosse, which seemed to result in the production of a
heretofore unknown species of insect in considerable
numbers.  Various causes have prevented these experiments
and their results from receiving candid treatment, but they may
perhaps be yet found to have opened up a new and most interesting
chapter of nature’s mysteries.  Mr. Crosse was
pursuing some experiments in crystallization, causing a powerful
voltaic battery to operate upon a saturated solution of silicate
of potash, when the insects unexpectedly made their
appearance.  He afterwards tried nitrate of copper, which is
a deadly poison, and from that fluid also did live insects
emerge.  Discouraged by the reception of his experiments,
Mr. Crosse soon discontinued them; but they were some years after
pursued by Mr. Weekes, of Sandwich, with precisely the same
results.  This gentleman, besides trying the first of the
above substances, employed ferro-cyanet of potash, on account of
its containing a larger proportion of carbon, the principal
element of organic bodies; and from this substance the insects
were produced in increased numbers.  A few weeks
sufficed for this experiment, with the powerful battery of Mr.
Crosse; but the first attempts of Mr. Weekes required about
eleven months, a ground of presumption in itself that the
electricity was chiefly concerned in the phenomenon.  The
changes undergone by the fluid operated upon, were in both cases
remarkable, and nearly alike.  In Mr. Weekes’
apparatus, the silicate of potash became first turbid, then of a
milky appearance; round the negative wire of the battery, dipped
into the fluid, there gathered a quantity of gelatinous
matter, a part of the process of considerable importance,
considering that gelatin is one of the proximate
principles, or first compounds, of which animal bodies are
formed.  From this matter Mr. Weekes observed one of the
insects in the very act of emerging, immediately after which, it
ascended to the surface of the fluid, and sought concealment in
an obscure corner of the apparatus.  The insects produced by
both experimentalists seem to have been the same, a species of
acarus, minute and semi-transparent, and furnished with long
bristles, which can only be seen by the aid of the
microscope.  It is worthy of remark, that some of these
insects, soon after their existence had commenced, were found to
be likely to extend their species.  They were sometimes
observed to go back to the fluid to feed, and occasionally they
devoured each other. [187]
The reception of novelties in science must ever be regulated
very much by the amount of kindred or relative phenomena which
the public mind already possesses and acknowledges, to which the
new can be assimilated.  A novelty, however true, if there
be no received truths with which it can be shewn in harmonious
relation, has little chance of a favourable hearing.  In
fact, as has been often observed, there is a measure of
incredulity from our ignorance as well as from our knowledge, and
if the most distinguished philosopher three hundred years ago had
ventured to develop any striking new fact which only could
harmonize with the as yet unknown Copernican solar system, we
cannot doubt that it would have been universally scoffed at in
the scientific world, such as it then was, or at the best
interpreted in a thousand wrong ways in conformity with ideas
already familiar.  The experiments above described, finding
a public mind which had never discovered a fact or conceived an
idea at all analogous, were of course ungraciously
received.  It was held to be impious, even to surmise that
animals could have been formed through any instrumentality of an
apparatus devised by human skill.  The more likely account
of the phenomena was said to be, that the insects were only
developed from ova, resting either in the fluid, or in the wooden
frame on which the experiments took place.  On these
objections the following remarks may be made.  The
supposition of impiety arises from an entire misconception of
what is implied by an aboriginal creation of insects.  The
experimentalist could never be considered as the author of the
existence of these creatures, except by the most unreasoning
ignorance.  The utmost that can be claimed for, or imputed
to him is that he arranged the natural conditions under which the
true creative energy—that of the Divine Author of all
things—was pleased to work in that instance.  On the
hypothesis here brought forward, the acarus Crossii was a
type of being ordained from the beginning, and destined to be
realized under certain physical conditions.  When a human
hand brought these conditions into the proper arrangement, it did
an act akin to hundreds of familiar ones which we execute every
day, and which are followed by natural results; but it did
nothing more.  The production of the insect, if it did take
place as assumed, was as clearly an act of the Almighty himself,
as if he had fashioned it with hands.  For the presumption
that an act of aboriginal creation did take place, there is this
to be said, that, in Mr. Weekes’s experiment, every care
that ingenuity could devise was taken to exclude the possibility
of a development of the insects from ova.  The wood of the
frame was baked in a powerful heat; a bell-shaped glass covered
the apparatus, and from this the atmosphere was excluded by the
constantly rising fumes from the liquid, for the emission of
which there was an aperture so arranged at the top of the glass,
that only these fumes could pass.  The water was distilled,
and the substance of the silicate had been subjected to white
heat.  Thus every source of fallacy seemed to be shut
up.  In such circumstances, a candid mind, which sees
nothing either impious or unphilosophical in the idea of a new
creation, will be disposed to think that there is less difficulty
in believing in such a creation having actually taken place, than
in believing that, in two instances, separated in place and time,
exactly the same insects should have chanced to arise from
concealed ova, and these a species heretofore unknown.</div></body></text></TEI>