<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="78">CHAPTER III.
The Relation of Vapor and Air.

Sect. 1.—The Boylean Law of the Air’s
Elasticity.
IN the Sixth Book (Chap. iv.
Sect. 1.) we have already seen how the
conception on the laws of fluid equilibrium was, by Pascal and others,
extended to air, as well as water. But though air presses and is
pressed as water presses and is pressed, pressure produces upon air an
effect which it does not, in any obvious degree, produce upon water.
Air which is pressed is also compressed, or made to occupy a
smaller space; and is consequently also made more dense, or
condensed; and on the other hand, when the pressure upon a
portion of air is diminished, the air expands or is rarefied. These
broad facts are evident. They are expressed in a general way by saying
that air is an elastic fluid, yielding in a certain degree to
pressure, and recovering its previous dimensions when the pressure is
removed.
But when men had reached this point, the questions obviously
offered themselves, in what degree and according to what law air
yields to pressure; when it is compressed, what relation does the
density bear to the pressure? The use which had been made of tubes
containing columns of mercury, by which the pressure of portions of
air was varied and measured, suggested obvious modes of devising
experiments by which this question might be answered. Such experiments
accordingly were made by Boyle about 1650; and the result at which he
arrived was, that when air is thus compressed, the density is as the
pressure. Thus if the pressure of the atmosphere in its common state
be equivalent to 30 inches of mercury, as shown by the barometer; if
air included in a tube be pressed by 30 additional inches of 164 mercury, its density
will be doubled, the air being compressed into one half the space. If
the pressure be increased threefold, the density is also trebled; and
so on. The same law was soon afterwards (in 1676) proved
experimentally by Mariotte. And this law of the air’s elasticity, that
the density is as the pressure, is sometimes called the Boylean
Law, and sometimes the Law of Boyle and Mariotte.
Air retains its aerial character permanently; but there are other
aerial substances which appear as such, and then disappear or change
into some other condition. Such are termed vapors. And the
discovery of their true relation to air was the result of a long
course of researches and speculations.
[2nd Ed.] [It was found by M. Cagniard de la Tour (in 1823), that
at a certain temperature, a liquid, under sufficient pressure, becomes
clear transparent vapor or gas, having the same bulk as the liquid.
This condition Dr. Faraday calls the Cagniard de la Tour state,
(the Tourian state?) It was also discovered by Dr. Faraday that
carbonic-acid gas, and many other gases, which were long conceived to
be permanently elastic, are really reducible to a liquid state by
pressure.39 And in 1835, M. Thilorier found the
means of reducing liquid carbonic acid to a solid form, by means of
the cold produced in evaporation. More recently Dr. Faraday has added
several substances usually gaseous to the list of those which could
previously be shown in the liquid state, and has reduced others,
including ammonia, nitrous oxide, and sulphuretted hydrogen, to a
solid consistency.40 After these discoveries, we may, I
think, reasonably doubt whether all bodies are not capable of existing
in the three consistencies of solid, liquid, and air.
39 Phil. Trans. 1823.
40 Ib. Pt. 1. 1845.
We may note that the law of Boyle and Mariotte is not exactly true
near the limit at which the air passes to the liquid state in such
cases as that just spoken of. The diminution of bulk is then more
rapid than the increase of pressure.
The transition of fluids from a liquid to an airy consistence
appears to be accompanied by other curious phenomena. See Prof.
Forbes’s papers on the Color of Steam under certain
circumstances, and on the Colors of the Atmosphere, in the
Edin. Trans. vol. xiv.] 165
Sect. 2.—Prelude to Dalton’s Doctrine of
Evaporation.
Visible clouds, smoke,
distillation, gave the notion of Vapor; vapor was at first conceived
to be identical with air, as by Bacon.41 It was easily
collected, that by heat, water might be converted into vapor. It was
thought that air was thus produced, in the instrument called the
æolipile, in which a powerful blast is caused by a boiling
fluid; but Wolfe showed that the fluid was not converted into air, by
using camphorated spirit of wine, and condensing the vapor after it
had been formed. We need not enumerate the doctrines (if very vague
hypotheses may be so termed) of Descartes, Dechales, Borelli.42 The latter accounted for the rising of
vapor by supposing it a mixture of fire and water; and thus, fire
being much lighter than air, the mixture also was light. Boyle
endeavored to show that vapors do not permanently float in
vacuo. He compared the mixture of vapor with air to that of salt
with water. He found that the pressure of the atmosphere affected the
heat of boiling water; a very important fact. Boyle proved this by
means of the air-pump; and he and his friends were much surprised to
find that when air was removed, water only just warm boiled violently.
Huyghens mentions an experiment of the same kind made by Papin about
1673.
41 Bacon’s Hist. Nat. Cent. i.
p. 27.
42 They may be seen in Fischer,
Geschichte der Physik, vol. ii. p. 175.
The ascent of vapor was explained in various ways in succession,
according to the changes which physical science underwent. It was a
problem distinctly treated of, at a period when hydrostatics had
accounted for many phenomena; and attempts were naturally made to
reduce this fact to hydrostatical principles. An obvious hypothesis,
which brought it under the dominion of these principles, was, to
suppose that the water, when converted into vapor, was divided into
small hollow globules;—thin pellicles including air or heat.
Halley gave such an explanation of evaporation; Leibnitz calculated
the dimensions of these little bubbles; Derham managed (as he
supposed) to examine them with a magnifying glass: Wolfe also examined
and calculated on the same subject. It is curious to see so much
confidence in so lame a theory; for if water became hollow globules in
order to rise as vapor, we require, in order to explain the formation
of these globules, new laws of nature, which are not even hinted at by
166 the supporters
of the doctrine, though they must be far more complex than the
hydrostatical law by which a hollow sphere floats.
Newton’s opinion was hardly more satisfactory; he43 explained evaporation by the repulsive
power of heat; the parts of vapors, according to him, being small, are
easily affected by this force, and thus become lighter than the
atmosphere.
43 Opticks, Qu. 31.
Muschenbroek still adhered to the theory of globules, as the
explanation of evaporation; but he was manifestly discontented with
it; and reasonably apprehended that the pressure of the air would
destroy the frail texture of these bubbles. He called to his aid a
rotation of the globules (which Descartes also had assumed); and, not
satisfied with this, threw himself on electrical action as a reserve.
Electricity, indeed, was now in favor, as hydrostatics had been
before; and was naturally called in, in all cases of difficulty.
Desaguliers, also, uses this agent to account for the ascent of vapor,
introducing it into a kind of sexual system of clouds; according to
him, the male fire (heat) does a part, and the female fire
(electricity) performs the rest. These are speculations of small merit
and no value.
In the mean time, Chemistry made great progress in the estimation
of philosophers, and had its turn in the explanation of the important
facts of evaporation. Bouillet, who, in 1742, placed the particles of
water in the interstices of those of air, may be considered as
approaching to the chemical theory. In 1748, the Academy of Sciences
of Bourdeaux proposed the ascent of vapors as the subject of a prize;
which was adjudged in a manner very impartial as to the choice of a
theory; for it was divided between Kratzenstein, who advocated the
bubbles, (the coat of which he determined to be 1⁄50,000th
of an inch thick,) and Hamberger, who maintained the truth to be the
adhesion of particles of water to those of air and fire. The latter
doctrine had become much more distinct in the author’s mind when seven
years afterwards (1750) he published his Elementa Physices. He
then gave the explanation of evaporation in a phrase which has since
been adopted,—the solution of water in air; which he
conceived to be of the same kind as other chemical solutions.
This theory of solution was further advocated and developed by Le
Roi;44 and in his hands assumed a form which
has been extensively adopted up to our times, and has, in many
instances, tinged the language commonly used. He conceived that air,
like other solvents, 167 might be saturated; and that when
the water was beyond the amount required for saturation, it appeared
in a visible form. The saturating quantity was held to depend mainly
on warmth and wind.
44 Ac. R. Sc. Paris,
1750.
This theory was by no means devoid of merit; for it brought
together many of the phenomena, and explained a number of the
experiments which Le Roi made. It explained the facts of the
transparency of vapor, (for perfect solutions are transparent,) the
precipitation of water by cooling, the disappearance of the visible
moisture by warming it again, the increased evaporation by rain and
wind; and other observed phenomena. So far, therefore, the
introduction of the notion of the chemical solution of water in air
was apparently very successful. But its defects are of a very fatal
kind; for it does not at all apply to the facts which take place when
air is excluded.
In Sweden, in the mean time,45 the subject had
been pursued in a different, and in a more correct manner. Wallerius
Ericsen had, by various experiments, established the important fact,
that water evaporates in a vacuum. His experiments are clear
and satisfactory; and he inferred from them the falsity of the common
explanation of evaporation by the solution of water in air.
His conclusions are drawn in a very intelligent manner. He considers
the question whether water can be changed into air, and whether the
atmosphere is, in consequence, a mere collection of vapors; and on
good reasons, decides in the negative, and concludes the existence of
permanently-elastic air different from vapor. He judges, also, that
there are two causes concerned, one acting to produce the first ascent
of vapors, the other to support them afterwards. The first, which acts
in a vacuum, he conceives to be the mutual repulsion of the particles;
and since this force is independent of the presence of other
substances, this seems to be a sound induction. When the vapors have
once ascended into the air, it may readily be granted that they are
carried higher, and driven from side to side by the currents of the
atmosphere. Wallerius conceives that the vapor will rise till it gets
into air of the same density as itself, and being then in equilibrium,
will drift to and fro.
45 Fischer, Gesch. Phys. vol.
v. p. 63.
The two rival theories of evaporation, that of chemical
solution and that of independent vapor, were, in various
forms, advocated by the next generation of philosophers. De Saussure
may be considered as the leader on one side, and De Luc on the other.
The former maintained the solution theory, with some modifications of
his own. De 168 Luc
denied all solution, and held vapor to be a combination of the
particles of water with fire, by which they became lighter than air.
According to him, there is always fire enough present to produce this
combination, so that evaporation goes on at all temperatures.
This mode of considering independent vapor as a combination of fire
with water, led the attention of those who adopted that opinion to the
thermometrical changes which take place when vapor is formed and
condensed. These changes are important, and their laws curious. The
laws belong to the induction of latent heat, of which we have just spoken; but a knowledge of them is not
absolutely necessary in order to enable us to understand the manner in
which steam exists in air.
De Luc’s views led him46 also to the consideration of the effect
of pressure on vapor. He explains the fact that pressure will condense
vapor, by supposing that it brings the particles within the distance
at which the repulsion arising from fire ceases. In this way, he also
explains the fact, that though external pressure does thus condense
steam, the mixture of a body of air, by which the pressure is equally
increased, will not produce the same effect; and therefore, vapors can
exist in the atmosphere. They make no fixed proportion of it; but at
the same temperature we have the same pressure arising from
them, whether they are in air or not. As the heat increases,
vapor becomes capable of supporting a greater and greater pressure,
and at the boiling heat, it can support the pressure of the
atmosphere.
46 Fischer, vol. vii. p. 453.
Nouvelles Idées sur la Météorologie, 1787.
De Luc also marked very precisely (as Wallerius had done) the
difference between vapor and air; the former being capable of change
of consistence by cold or pressure, the latter not so. Pictet,
in 1786, made a hygrometrical experiment, which appeared to him to
confirm De Luc’s views; and De Luc, in 1792, published a concluding
essay on the subject in the Philosophical Transactions.
Pictet’s Essay on Fire, in 1791, also demonstrated that “all
the train of hygrometrical phenomena takes place just as well, indeed
rather quicker, in a vacuum than in air, provided the same quantity of
moisture is present.” This essay, and De Luc’s paper, gave the
death-blow to the theory of the solution of water in air.
Yet this theory did not fall without an obstinate struggle. It was
taken up by the new school of French chemists, and connected with
their views of heat. Indeed, it long appears as the prevalent opinion.
169 Girtanner,47 in his Grounds of the Antiphlogistic
Theory, may be considered as one of the principal expounders of
this view of the matter. Hube, of Warsaw, was, however, the strongest
of the defenders of the theory of solution, and published upon it
repeatedly about 1790. Yet he appears to have been somewhat
embarrassed with the increase of the air’s elasticity by vapor.
Parrot, in 1801, proposed another theory, maintaining that De Luc had
by no means successfully attacked that of solution, but only De
Saussure’s superfluous additions to it.
47 Fischer, vol. vii. 473.
It is difficult to see what prevented the general reception of the
doctrine of independent vapor; since it explained all the facts very
simply, and the agency of air was shown over and over again to be
unnecessary. Yet, even now, the solution of water in air is hardly
exploded. M. Gay Lussac,48 in 1800, talks of the quantity of water
“held in solution” by the air; which, he says, varies according to its
temperature and density by a law which has not yet been discovered.
And Professor Robison, in the article “Steam,” in the Encyclopædia
Britannica (published about 1800), says,49 “Many
philosophers imagine that spontaneous evaporation, at low
temperatures, is produced in this way (by elasticity alone). But we
cannot be of this opinion; and must still think that this kind of
evaporation is produced by the dissolving power of the air.” He then
gives some reasons for his opinion. “When moist air is suddenly
rarefied, there is always a precipitation of water. But by this new
doctrine the very contrary should happen, because the tendency of
water to appear in the elastic form is promoted by removing the
external pressure.” Another main difficulty in the way of the doctrine
of the mere mixture of vapor and air was supposed to be this; that if
they were so mixed, the heavier fluid would take the lower part, and
the lighter the higher part, of the space which they occupied.
48 Ann. Chim. tom.
xliii.
49 Robison’s Works, ii.
37.
The former of these arguments was repelled by the consideration
that in the rarefaction of air, its specific heat is changed, and thus
its temperature reduced below the constituent temperature of the vapor
which it contains. The latter argument is answered by a reference to
Dalton’s law of the mixture of gases. We must consider the
establishment of this doctrine in a new section, as the most material
step to the true notion of evaporation. 170
Sect. 3.—Dalton’s Doctrine of
Evaporation.
A portion of that which
appears to be the true notion of evaporation was known, with greater
or less distinctness, to several of the physical philosophers of whom
we have spoken. They were aware that the vapor which exists in air, in
an invisible state, may be condensed into water by cold: and they had
noticed that, in any state of the atmosphere, there is a certain
temperature lower than that of the atmosphere, to which, if we depress
bodies, water forms upon them in fine drops like dew; this temperature
is thence called the dew-point. The vapor of water which exists
anywhere may be reduced below the degree of heat which is necessary to
constitute it vapor, and thus it ceases to be vapor. Hence this
temperature is also called the constituent temperature. This
was generally known to the meteorological speculators of the last
century, although, in England, attention was principally called to it
by Dr. Wells’s Essay on Dew, in 1814. This doctrine readily
explains how the cold produced by rarefaction of air, descending below
the constituent temperature of the contained vapor, may precipitate a
dew; and thus, as we have said, refutes one obvious objection to the
theory of independent vapor.
The other difficulty was first fully removed by Mr. Dalton. When
his attention was drawn to the subject of vapor, he saw insurmountable
objections to the doctrine of a chemical union of water and air. In
fact, this doctrine was a mere nominal explanation; for, on closer
examination, no chemical analogies supported it. After some
reflection, and in the sequel of other generalizations concerning
gases, he was led to the persuasion, that when air and steam are mixed
together, each follows its separate laws of equilibrium, the particles
of each being elastic with regard to those of their own kind only: so
that steam may be conceived as flowing among the particles of air50 “like a stream of water among pebbles;”
and the resistance which air offers to evaporation arises, not from
its weight, but from the inertia of its particles.
50 Manchester Memoirs, vol. v.
p. 581.
It will be found that the theory of independent vapor, understood
with these conditions, will include all the facts of the
case;—gradual evaporation in air; sudden evaporation in a
vacuum; the increase of 171 the air’s elasticity by vapor;
condensation by its various causes; and other phenomena.
But Mr. Dalton also made experiments to prove his fundamental
principle, that if two different gases communicate, they will diffuse
themselves through each other;51—slowly,
if the opening of communication be small. He observes also, that all
the gases had equal solvent powers for vapor, which could hardly have
happened, had chemical affinity been concerned. Nor does the density
of the air make any difference.
51 New System of Chemical
Philosophy, vol. i. p. 151.
Taking all these circumstances into the account, Mr. Dalton
abandoned the idea of solution. “In the autumn of 1801,” he says, “I
hit upon an idea which seemed to be exactly calculated to explain the
phenomena of vapor: it gave rise to a great variety of experiments,”
which ended in fixing it in his mind as a true idea. “But,” he adds,
“the theory was almost universally misunderstood, and consequently
reprobated.”
Mr. Dalton answers various objections. Berthollet had urged that we
can hardly conceive the particles of an elastic substance added to
those of another, without increasing its elasticity. To this Mr.
Dalton replies by adducing the instance of magnets, which repel each
other, but do not repel other bodies. One of the most curious and
ingenious objections is that of M. Gough, who argues, that if each gas
is elastic with regard to itself alone, we should hear, produced by
one stroke, four sounds; namely, first, the sound through
aqueous vapor; second, the sound through azotic gas;
third, the sound through oxygen gas; fourth, the sound
through carbonic acid. Mr. Dalton’s answer is, that the difference of
time at which these sounds would come is very small; and that, in
fact, we do hear, sounds double and treble.
In his New System of Chemical Philosophy, Mr. Dalton
considers the objections of his opponents with singular candor and
impartiality. He there appears disposed to abandon that part of the
theory which negatives the mutual repulsion of the particles of the
two gases, and to attribute their diffusion through one another to the
different size of the particles, which would, he thinks,52 produce the same effect.
52 New System, vol. i. p.
188.
In selecting, as of permanent importance, the really valuable part
of this theory, we must endeavor to leave out all that is doubtful or
unproved. I believe it will be found that in all theories hitherto
172 promulgated,
all assertions respecting the properties of the particles of bodies,
their sizes, distances, attractions, and the like, are insecure and
superfluous. Passing over, then, such hypotheses, the inductions which
remain are these;—that two gases which are in communication
will, by the elasticity of each, diffuse themselves in one another,
quickly or slowly; and—that the quantity of steam contained in a
certain space of air is the same, whatever be the air, whatever be its
density, and even if there be a vacuum. These propositions may be
included together by saying, that one gas is mechanically mixed
with another; and we cannot but assent to what Mr. Dalton says of the
latter fact,—“this is certainly the touchstone of the mechanical
and chemical theories.” This doctrine of the mechanical mixture of
gases appears to supply answers to all the difficulties opposed to
it by Berthollet and others, as Mr. Dalton has shown;53 and we may, therefore, accept it as
well established.
53 New System, vol. i. p. 160,
&c.
This doctrine, along with the principle of the constituent
temperature of steam, is applicable to a large series of
meteorological and other consequences. But before considering the
applications of theory to natural phenomena, which have been made, it
will be proper to speak of researches which were carried on, in a
great measure, in consequence of the use of steam in the arts: I mean
the laws which connect its elastic force with its constituent
temperature.
Sect. 4.—Determination of the Laws of the Elastic
Force of Steam.
The expansion of aqueous
vapor at different temperatures is governed, like that of all other
vapors, by the law of Dalton and Gay-Lussac, already mentioned; and
from this, its elasticity, when its expansion is resisted, will be
known by the law of Boyle and Mariotte; namely, by the rule that the
pressure of airy fluids is as the condensation. But it is to be
observed, that this process of calculation goes on the supposition
that the steam is cut off from contact with water, so that no more
steam can be generated; a case quite different from the common one, in
which the steam is more abundant as the heat is greater. The
examination of the force of vapor, when it is in contact with water,
must be briefly noticed.
During the period of which we have been speaking, the progress of
the investigation of the laws of aqueous vapor was much accelerated
173 by the growing
importance of the steam-engine, in which those laws operated in a
practical form. James Watts, the main improver of that machine, was
thus a great contributor to speculative knowledge, as well as to
practical power. Many of his improvements depended on the laws which
regulate the quantity of heat which goes to the formation or
condensation of steam; and the observations which led to these
improvements enter into the induction of latent heat. Measurements of
the force of steam, at all temperatures, were made with the same view.
Watts’s attention had been drawn to the steam-engine in 1759, by
Robison, the former being then an instrument-maker, and the latter a
student at the University of Glasgow.54 In 1761 or
1762, he tried some experiments on the force of steam in a Papin’s
Digester;55 and formed a sort of working model of a
steam-engine, feeling already his vocation to develope the powers of
that invention. His knowledge was at that time principally derived
from Desaguliers and Belidor, but his own experiments added to it
rapidly. In 1764 and 1765, he made a more systematical course of
experiments, directed to ascertain the force of steam. He tried this
force, however, only at temperatures above the boiling-point; and
inferred it at lower degrees from the supposed continuity of the law
thus obtained. His friend Robison, also, was soon after led, by
reading the account of some experiments of Lord Charles Cavendish, and
some others of Mr. Nairne, to examine the same subject. He made out a
table of the correspondence of the elasticity and the temperature of
vapor, from thirty-two to two hundred and eighty degrees of
Fahrenheit’s thermometer.56 The thing here to be remarked, is the
establishment of a law of the pressure of steam, down to the
freezing-point of water. Ziegler of Basle, in 1769, and Achard of
Berlin, in 1782, made similar experiments. The latter examined also
the elasticity of the vapor of alcohol. Betancourt, in 1792, published
his Memoir on the expansive force of vapors; and his tables were for
some time considered the most exact. 174 Prony, in his Architecture
Hydraulique (1796), established a mathematical formula,57 on the experiments of Betancourt, who
began his researches in the belief that he was first in the field,
although he afterwards found that he had been anticipated by Ziegler.
Gren compared the experiments of Betancourt and De Luc with his own.
He ascertained an important fact, that when water boils, the
elasticity of the steam is equal to that of the atmosphere. Schmidt at
Giessen endeavored to improve the apparatus used by Betancourt; and
Biker, of Rotterdam, in 1800, made new trials for the same
purpose.
54 Robison’s Works, vol. ii.
p. 113.
55 Denis Papin, who made many of
Boyle’s experiments for him, had discovered that if the vapor be
prevented from rising, the water becomes hotter than the usual
boiling-point; and had hence invented the instrument called Papin’s
Digester. It is described in his book, La manière d’amolir les
os et de faire cuire toutes sorts de viandes en fort peu de temps et à
peu de frais. Paris, 1682.
56 These were afterwards published in
the Encyclopædia Britannica; in the article “Steam,” written by
Robison.
57 Architecture Hydraulique,
Seconde Partie, p. 163.
In 1801, Mr. Dalton communicated to the Philosophical Society of
Manchester his investigations on this subject; observing truly, that
though the forces at high temperatures are most important when steam
is considered as a mechanical agent, the progress of philosophy is
more immediately interested in accurate observations on the force at
low temperatures. He also found that his elasticities for equidistant
temperatures resembled a geometrical progression, but with a
ratio constantly diminishing. Dr. Ure, in 1818, published in the
Philosophical Transactions of London, experiments of the same
kind, valuable from the high temperatures at which they were made, and
for the simplicity of his apparatus. The law which he thus obtained
approached, like Dalton’s, to a geometrical progression. Dr.
Ure says, that a formula proposed by M. Biot gives an error of near
nine inches out of seventy-five, at a temperature of 266 degrees. This
is very conceivable, for if the formula be wrong at all, the
geometrical progress rapidly inflames the error in the higher portions
of the scale. The elasticity of steam, at high temperatures, has also
been experimentally examined by Mr. Southern, of Soho, and Mr. Sharpe,
of Manchester. Mr. Dalton has attempted to deduce certain general laws
from Mr. Sharpe’s experiments; and other persons have offered other
rules, as those which govern the force of steam with reference to the
temperature: but no rule appears yet to have assumed the character of
an established scientific truth. Yet the law of the expansive force of
steam is not only required in order that the steam-engine may be
employed with safety and to the best advantage; but must also be an
important point in every consistent thermotical theory.
[2nd Ed.] [To the experiments on steam made by private physicists,
are to be added the experiments made on a grand scale by order of the
governments of France and of America, with a view to 175 legislation on the
subject of steam-engines. The French experiments were made in 1823,
under the direction of a commission consisting of some of the most
distinguished members of the Academy of Sciences; namely, MM. de
Prony, Arago, Girard, and Dulong. The American experiments were placed
in the hands of a committee of the Franklin Institute of the State of
Pennsylvania, consisting of Prof. Bache and others, in 1830. The
French experiments went as high as 435° of Fahrenheit’s thermometer,
corresponding to a pressure of 60 feet of mercury, or 24 atmospheres.
The American experiments were made up to a temperature of 346°, which
corresponded to 274 inches of mercury, more than 9 atmospheres. The
extensive range of these experiments affords great advantages for
determining the law of the expansive force. The French Academy found
that their experiments indicated an increase of the elastic force
according to the fifth power of a binominal 1 + mt, where t is
the temperature. The American Institute were led to a sixth
power of a like binominal. Other experimenters have expressed their
results, not by powers of the temperature, but by geometrical ratios.
Dr. Dalton had supposed that the expansion of mercury being as the
square of the true temperature above its freezing-point, the expansive
force of steam increases in geometrical ratio for equal increments of
temperature. And the author of the article Steam in the Seventh
Edition of the Encyclopædia Britannica (Mr. J. S. Russell), has
found that the experiments are best satisfied by supposing mercury, as
well as steam, to expand in a geometrical ratio for equal increments
of the true temperature.
It appears by such calculation, that while dry gas increases in the
ratio of 8 to 11, by an increase of temperature from freezing to
boiling water; steam in contact with water, by the same increase of
temperature above boiling water, has its expansive force increased in
the proportion of 1 to 12. By an equal increase of temperature,
mercury expands in about the ratio of 8 to 9.
Recently, MM. Magnus of Berlin, Holzmann and Regnault, have made
series of observations on the relation between temperature and
elasticity of steam.58
58 See Taylor’s Scientific
Memoirs, Aug. 1845, vol. iv. part xiv., and Ann. de Chimie.
Prof. Magnus measured his temperatures by an air-thermometer; a
process which, I stated in the first edition, seemed to afford the
best promise of simplifying the law of expansion. His result is, that
the 176 elasticity
proceeds in a geometric series when the temperature proceeds in an
arithmetical series nearly; the differences of temperature for equal
augmentations of the ratio of elasticity being somewhat greater for
the higher temperatures.
The forces of the vapors of other liquids in contact with their
liquids, determined by Dr. Faraday, as mentioned in Chap. ii. Sect. 1, are analogous to the elasticity of
steam here spoken of.]
~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~
Sect. 5.—Consequences of the Doctrine of
Evaporation.—Explanation of Rain, Dew, and Clouds.
The discoveries concerning
the relations of heat and moisture which were made during the last
century, were principally suggested by meteorological inquiries, and
were applied to meteorology as fast as they rose. Still there remains,
on many points of this subject, so much doubt and obscurity, that we
cannot suppose the doctrines to have assumed their final form; and
therefore we are not here called upon to trace their progress and
connexion. The principles of atmology are pretty well understood; but
the difficulty of observing the conditions under which they produce
their effects in the atmosphere is so great, that the precise theory
of most meteorological phenomena is still to be determined.
We have already considered the answers given to the question:
According to what rules does transparent aqueous vapor resume its form
of visible water? This question includes, not only the problems of
Rain and Dew, but also of Clouds; for clouds are not vapor, but water,
vapor being always invisible. An opinion which attracted much notice
in its time, was that of Hutton, who, in 1784, endeavored to prove
that if two masses of air saturated with transparent vapor at
different temperatures are mixed together, the precipitation of water
in the form either of cloud or of drops will take place. The reason he
assigned for the opinion was this: that the temperature of the mixture
is a mean between the two temperatures, but that the force of the
vapor in the mixture, which is the mean of the forces of the two
component vapors, will be greater than that which corresponds to the
mean temperature, since the force increases faster than the
temperature;59 and hence some part of the vapor will
be precipitated. This doctrine, it will be seen, speaks of vapor as
“saturating” air, and is 177 therefore, in this form, inconsistent
with Dalton’s principle; but it is not difficult to modify the
expression so as to retain the essential part of the explanation.
59 Edin. Trans. vol. 1. p.
42.
Dew.—The principle of a “constituent temperature” of
steam, and the explanation of the “dew-point,” were known, as we have
said (chap. iii. sect. 3,) to the
meteorologists of the last century; but we perceive how incomplete
their knowledge was, by the very gradual manner in which the
consequences of this principle were traced out. We have already
noticed, as one of the books which most drew attention to the true
doctrine, in this country at least, Dr. Wells’s Essay on Dew,
published in 1814. In this work the author gives an account of the
progress of his opinions;60 “I was led,” he says, “in the autumn of
1784, by the event of a rude experiment, to think it probable that the
formation of dew is attended with the production of cold.” This was
confirmed by the experiments of others. But some years after, “upon
considering the subject more closely, I began to suspect that Mr.
Wilson, Mr. Six, and myself, had all committed an error in regarding
the cold which accompanies the dew, as an effect of the
formation of the dew.” He now considered it rather as the
cause: and soon found that he was able to account for the
circumstances of this formation, many of them curious and paradoxical,
by supposing the bodies on which dew is deposited, to be cooled down,
by radiation into the clear night-sky, to the proper temperature. The
same principle will obviously explain the formation of mists over
streams and lakes when the air is cooler than the water; which was put
forward by Davy, even in 1810, as a new doctrine, or at least not
familiar.
60 Essay on Dew, p. 1.
Hygrometers.—According as air has more or less of
vapor in comparison with that which its temperature and pressure
enable it to contain, it is more or less humid; and an instrument
which measures the degrees of such a gradation is a hygrometer.
The hygrometers which were at first invented, were those which
measured the moisture by its effect in producing expansion or
contraction in certain organic substances; thus De Saussure devised a
hair-hygrometer, De Luc a whalebone-hygrometer, and Dalton used a
piece of whipcord. All these contrivances were variable in the amount
of their indications under the same circumstances; and, moreover, it
was not easy to know the physical meaning of the degree indicated. The
dew-point, or constituent temperature of the vapor which exists in the
air, is, on 178 the
other hand, both constant and definite. The determination of this
point, as a datum for the moisture of the atmosphere, was employed by
Le Roi, and by Dalton (1802), the condensation being obtained by cold
water:61 and finally, Mr. Daniell (1812)
constructed an instrument, where the condensing temperature was
produced by evaporation of ether, in a very convenient manner. This
invention (Daniell’s Hygrometer) enables us to determine the
quantity of vapor which exists in a given mass of the atmosphere at
any time of observation.
61 Daniell, Met. Ess. p. 142.
Manch. Mem. vol. v. p. 581.
[2nd Ed.] [As a happy application of the Atmological Laws which
have been discovered, I may mention the completion of the theory and
use of the Wet-bulb Hygrometer; an instrument in which, from
the depression of temperature produced by wetting the bulb of a
thermometer, we infer the further depression which would produce dew.
Of this instrument the history is thus summed up by Prof.
Forbes:—“Hutton invented the method; Leslie revived and extended
it, giving probably the earliest, though an imperfect theory;
Gay-Lussac, by his excellent experiments and reasoning from them,
completed the theory, so far as perfectly dry air is concerned; Ivory
extended the theory; which was reduced to practice by Auguste and
Bohnenberger, who determined the constant with accuracy. English
observers have done little more than confirm the conclusions of our
industrious Germanic neighbors; nevertheless the experiments of Apjohn
and Prinsep must ever be considered as conclusively settling the value
of the coefficient near the one extremity of the scale, as those of
Kæmtz have done for the other.”62
62 Second Report on
Meteorology, p. 101.
Prof. Forbes’s two Reports On the Recent Progress and Present
State of Meteorology given among the Reports of the British
Association for 1832 and 1840, contain a complete and luminous
account of recent researches on this subject. It may perhaps be asked
why I have not given Meteorology a place among the Inductive Sciences;
but if the reader refers to these accounts, or any other adequate view
of the subject, he will see that Meteorology is not a single Inductive
Science, but the application of several sciences to the explanation of
terrestrial and atmospheric phenomena. Of the sciences so applied,
Thermotics and Atmology are the principal ones. But others also come
into play; as Optics, in the explanation of Rainbows, Halos, 179 Parhelia, Coronæ,
Glories, and the like; Electricity, in the explanation of Thunder and
Lightning, Hail, Aurora Borealis; to which others might be added.]
Clouds.—When vapor becomes visible by being cooled
below its constituent temperature, it forms itself into a very fine
watery powder, the diameter of the particles of which this powder
consists being very small: they are estimated by various writers, from
1⁄100,000th to 1⁄20,000th
of an inch.63 Such particles, even if solid, would
descend very slowly; and very slight causes would suffice for their
suspension, without recurring to the hypothesis of vesicles, of which
we have already spoken. Indeed that
hypothesis will not explain the fact, except we suppose these vesicles
filled with a rarer air than that of the atmosphere; and, accordingly,
though this hypothesis is still maintained by some,64 it is asserted as a fact of
observation, proved by optical or other phenomena, and not deduced
from the suspension of clouds. Yet the latter result is still
variously explained by different philosophers: thus, M. Gay-Lussac65 accounts for it by upward currents of
air, and Fresnel explains it by the heat and rarefaction of air in the
interior of the cloud.
63 Kæmtz, Met. i. 393.
64 Ib. i. 393. Robison, ii. 13.
65 Ann. Chim. xxv. 1822.
Classification of Clouds.—A classification of clouds
can then only be consistent and intelligible when it rests upon their
atmological conditions. Such a system was proposed by Mr. Luke Howard,
in 1802–3. His primary modifications are, Cirrus,
Cumulus, and Stratus, which the Germans have translated
by terms equivalent in English to feather-cloud,
heap-cloud, and layer-cloud. The cumulus increases by
accumulations on its top, and floats in the air with a horizontal
base; the stratus grows from below, and spreads along the earth; the
cirrus consists of fibres in the higher regions of the atmosphere,
which grow every way. Between the simple modifications are
intermediate ones, cirro-cumulus and cirro-stratus; and,
again, compound ones, the cumulo-stratus and the nimbus,
or rain-cloud. These distinctions have been generally accepted
all over Europe: and have rendered a description of all the processes
which go on in the atmosphere far more definite and clear than it
could be made before their use.
I omit a mass of facts and opinions, supposed laws of phenomena and
assigned causes, which abound in meteorology more than in any other
science. The slightest consideration will show us what a great 180 amount of labor, of
persevering and combined observation, the progress of this branch of
knowledge requires. I do not even speak of the condition of the more
elevated parts of the atmosphere. The diminution of temperature as we
ascend, one of the most marked of atmospheric facts, has been
variously explained by different writers. Thus Dalton66 (1808) refers it to a principle “that
each atom of air, in the same perpendicular column, is possessed of
the same degree of heat,” which principle he conceives to be entirely
empirical in this case. Fourier says67 (1817), “This
phenomenon results from several causes: one of the principal is the
progressive extinction of the rays of heat in the successive strata of
the atmosphere.”
66 New Syst. of Chem. vol. i.
p. 125.
67 Ann. Chim. vi. 285.
Leaving, therefore, the application of thermotical and atmological
principles in particular cases, let us consider for a moment the
general views to which they have led philosophers. ~Additional
material in the 3rd edition.~
</div></body></text></TEI>