<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="37">

BOOK IX.

PHYSICAL OPTICS.

Photography.
I HAVE, at the end of Chapter xi., stated that the theory of which I
have endeavored to sketch the history professes to explain only the
phenomena of radiant visible light; and that though we know that light
has other properties—for instance, that it produces chemical
effects—these are not contemplated as included within the domain
of the theory. The chemical effects of light cannot as yet be included
in exact and general truths, such as those which constitute the
undulatory theory of radiant visible light. But though the present age
has not yet attained to a Science of the chemistry of Light,
it has been enriched with a most exquisite Art, which
involves the principles of such a science, and may hereafter be made
the instrument of bringing them into the view of the philosopher. I
speak of the Art of Photography, in which chemistry has
discovered the means of producing surfaces almost as sensitive to the
modifications of light as the most sensitive of organic textures, the
retina of the eye: and has given permanence to images which in the eye
are only momentary impressions. Hereafter, when the laws shall have
been theoretically established, which connect the chemical
constitution of bodies with the action of light upon them, the
prominent names in the Prelude to such an Epoch must be those who by
their insight, invention, and perseverance, discovered and carried to
their present marvellous perfection the processes of photographic
Art:—Niepce and Daguerre in France, and our own accomplished
countryman, Mr. Fox Talbot.
Fluorescence.
As already remarked, it is not within the province of the
undulatory theory to explain the phenomena of the absorption of light
which take place in various ways when the light is transmitted through
various 602
mediums. I have, at the end of Chapter iii.,
given the reasons which prevent my assenting to the assertion of a
special analysis of light by absorption. In the same manner, with
regard to other effects produced by media upon light, it is sufficient
for the defence of the theory that it should be consistent with the
possibility of the laws of phenomena which are observed, not that it
should explain those laws; for they belong, apparently, to another
province of philosophy.
Some of the optical properties of bodies which have recently
attracted notice appear to be of this kind. It was noticed by Sir John
Herschel,4 that a certain liquid, sulphate of
quinine, which is under common circumstances colorless, exhibits in
certain aspects and under certain incidences of light, a beautiful
celestial blue color. It appeared that this color proceeded from the
surface on which the light first fell; and color thus produced Sir J.
Herschel called epipolic colors, and spoke of the light as
epipolized. Sir David Brewster had previously noted effects of
color in transparent bodies which he ascribed to internal
dispersion:5 and he conceived that the colors
observed by Sir J. Herschel were of the same class. Professor Stokes6
of Cambridge applied himself to the examination of these phenomena,
and was led to the conviction that they arise from a power which
certain bodies possess, of changing the color, and with it, the
refrangibility of the rays of light which fall upon them: and he
traced this property in various substances, into various remarkable
consequences. As this change of refrangibility always makes the rays
less refrangible, it was proposed to call it a
degradation of the light; or again, dependent emission,
because the light is emitted in the manner of self-luminous bodies,
but only in dependence upon the active rays, and so long as the body
is under their influence. In this respect it differs from
phosphorescence, in which light is emitted without such
dependence. The phenomenon occurs in a conspicuous and beautiful
manner in certain kinds of fluor spar: and the term
fluorescence, suggested by Professor Stokes, has the advantage
of inserting no hypothesis, and will probably be found the most
generally acceptable.7</div></body></text></TEI>