<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="21">

CHAPTER XII.
OF COMPLEX IDEAS.

1. Made by the Mind out of simple Ones.


We have hitherto considered those ideas, in the reception whereof the mind is
only passive, which are those simple ones received from sensation and
reflection before mentioned, whereof the mind cannot make one to itself, nor
have any idea which does not wholly consist of them. As simple ideas are
observed to exist in several combinations united together, so the mind has a
power to consider several of them united together as one idea; and that not
only as they are united in external objects, but as itself has joined them
together. Ideas thus made up of several simple ones put together, I call
COMPLEX;—such as are beauty, gratitude, a man, an army, the universe;
which, though complicated of various simple ideas, or complex ideas made up of
simple ones, yet are, when the mind pleases, considered each by itself, as one
entire thing, signified by one name.


2. Made voluntarily.


In this faculty of repeating and joining together its ideas, the mind has great
power in varying and multiplying the objects of its thoughts, infinitely beyond
what sensation or reflection furnished it with: but all this still confined to
those simple ideas which it received from those two sources, and which are the
ultimate materials of all its compositions. For simple ideas are all from
things themselves, and of these the mind CAN have no more, nor other than what
are suggested to it. It can have no other ideas of sensible qualities than what
come from without [*dropped word] the senses; nor any ideas of other kind of
operations of a thinking substance, than what it finds in itself. But when it
has once got these simple ideas, it is not confined barely to observation, and
what offers itself from without; it can, by its own power, put together those
ideas it has, and make new complex ones, which it never received so united.


3. Complex ideas are either of Modes, Substances, or Relations.


COMPLEX IDEAS, however compounded and decompounded, though their number be
infinite, and the variety endless, wherewith they fill and entertain the
thoughts of men; yet I think they may be all reduced under these three
heads:—1. MODES. 2. SUBSTANCES. 3. RELATIONS.


4. Ideas of Modes.


First, MODES I call such complex ideas which, however compounded, contain not
in them the supposition of subsisting by themselves, but are considered as
dependences on, or affections of substances;—such as are the ideas
signified by the words triangle, gratitude, murder, &c. And if in this I
use the word mode in somewhat a different sense from its ordinary
signification, I beg pardon; it being unavoidable in discourses, differing from
the ordinary received notions, either to make new words, or to use old words in
somewhat a new signification; the later whereof, in our present case, is
perhaps the more tolerable of the two.


5. Simple and mixed Modes of Ideas.


Of these MODES, there are two sorts which deserve distinct
consideration:—


First, there are some which are only variations, or different combinations of
the same simple idea, without the mixture of any other;—as a dozen, or
score; which are nothing but the ideas of so many distinct units added
together, and these I call SIMPLE MODES as being contained within the bounds of
one simple idea.


Secondly, there are others compounded of simple ideas of several kinds, put
together to make one complex one;—v.g. beauty, consisting of a certain
composition of colour and figure, causing delight to the beholder; theft, which
being the concealed change of the possession of anything, without the consent
of the proprietor, contains, as is visible, a combination of several ideas of
several kinds: and these I call MIXED MODES.


6. Ideas of Substances, single or collective.


Secondly, the ideas of SUBSTANCES are such combinations of simple ideas as are
taken to represent distinct PARTICULAR things subsisting by themselves; in
which the supposed or confused idea of substance, such as it is, is always the
first and chief. Thus if to substance be joined the simple idea of a certain
dull whitish colour, with certain degrees of weight, hardness, ductility, and
fusibility, we have the idea of lead; and a combination of the ideas of a
certain sort of figure, with the powers of motion, thought and reasoning,
joined to substance, make the ordinary idea of a man. Now of substances also,
there are two sorts of ideas:—one of SINGLE substances, as they exist
separately, as of a man or a sheep; the other of several of those put together,
as an army of men, or flock of sheep—which COLLECTIVE ideas of several
substances thus put together are as much each of them one single idea as that
of a man or an unit.


7. Ideas of Relation.


Thirdly, the last sort of complex ideas is that we call RELATION, which
consists in the consideration and comparing one idea with another.


Of these several kinds we shall treat in their order.


8. The abstrusest Ideas we can have are all from two Sources.


If we trace the progress of our minds, and with attention observe how it
repeats, adds together, and unites its simple ideas received from sensation or
reflection, it will lead us further than at first perhaps we should have
imagined. And, I believe, we shall find, if we warily observe the originals of
our notions, that EVEN THE MOST ABSTRUSE IDEAS, how remote soever they may seem
from sense, or from any operations of our own minds, are yet only such as the
understanding frames to itself, by repeating and joining together ideas that it
had either from objects of sense, or from its own operations about them: so
that those even large and abstract ideas are derived from sensation or
reflection, being no other than what the mind, by the ordinary use of its own
faculties, employed about ideas received from objects of sense, or from the
operations it observes in itself about them, may, and does, attain unto.


This I shall endeavour to show in the ideas we have of space, time, and
infinity, and some few others that seem the most remote, from those originals.


</div></body></text></TEI>