<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="51">

CHAPTER V.
The Atomic Theory.


1. The Atomic Theory considered on Chemical
Grounds.—We have already seen that the combinations which result from chemical affinity are definite, a
certain quantity of one ingredient uniting, not with
an uncertain, but with a certain quantity of another
ingredient. But it was found, in addition to this principle, that one ingredient would often unite with
another in different proportions, and that, in such
cases, these proportions are multiples one of another.
In the three salts formed by potassa with oxalic acid,
the quantities of acid which combine with the same
quantity of alkali are exactly in the proportion of the
numbers 1, 2, 4. And the same rule of the existence of multiple proportions is found to obtain in other
cases.
It is obvious that such results will be accounted for,
if we suppose that the base and the acid consist each of
numerous definite equal particles, and that the formation of the salts above mentioned consists in the combination of one particle of the base with one particle of
acid, with two particles of acid, and with four particles
of acid, respectively. But further; as we have already
stated, chemical affinity is not only definite, but reciprocal. The proportions of potassa and soda which form
neutral salts being 590 and 391 in one case, they are so
in all cases. These numbers represent proportions of
weight in which the two bases, potassa and soda, enter
into analogous combinations; 590 of potassa is equivalent to 391 of soda. These facts with regard to combination are still expressed by the above supposition
of equal particles, assuming that the weights of a 49 particle of potassa and of soda are in the proportion
of 590 to 391.
But we pursue our analysis further. We find that
potassa is a compound of a metallic base, potassium,
and of oxygen, in the proportion of 490 to 100; we
suppose, then, that the particle of potassa consists of
a particle of potassium and a particle of oxygen; and
these latter particles, since we see no present need to
suppose them divided, potassium and oxygen being
simple bodies, we may call atoms, and assume to be
indivisible. And by supposing all simple bodies to
consist of such atoms, and compounds to be formed by
the union of two, or three, or more of such atoms, we
explain the occurrence of definite and multiple proportions, and we construct the Atomic Theory.
2. Hypothesis of Atoms.—So far as the assumption
of such atoms as we have spoken of serves to express
those laws of chemical composition which we have
referred to, it is a clear and useful generalization. But
if the Atomic Theory be put forwards (and its author,
Dr. Dalton, appears to have put it forwards with such
an intention,) as asserting that chemical elements are
really composed of atoms, that is, of such particles not
further divisible, we cannot avoid remarking, that for
such a conclusion, chemical research has not afforded,
nor can afford, any satisfactory evidence whatever.
The smallest observable quantities of ingredients, as
well as the largest, combine according to the laws of
proportions and equivalence which have been cited
above. How are we to deduce from such facts any
inference with regard to the existence of certain smallest possible particles? The Theory, when dogmatically taught as a physical truth, asserts that all observable quantities of elements are composed of proportional numbers of particles which can no further
be subdivided; but all which observation teaches us is,
that if there be such particles, they are smaller than
the smallest observable quantities. In chemical experiment, at least, there is not the slightest positive
evidence for the existence of such atoms. The assumption of indivisible particles, smaller than the smallest 50 observable, which combine, particle with particle, will
explain the phenomena; but the assumption of particles bearing this proportion, but not possessing the
property of indivisibility, will explain the phenomena
at least equally well. The decision of the question,
therefore, whether the Atomic Hypothesis be the proper way of conceiving the chemical combinations of
substances, must depend, not upon chemical facts, but
upon our conception of Substance. In this sense the
question is an ancient and curious controversy, and
we shall hereafter have to make some remarks upon it.
3. Chemical Difficulties of the Hypothesis.—But
before doing this, we may observe that there is no
small difficulty in reconciling this hypothesis with the
facts of chemistry. According to the theory, all salts,
compounded of an acid and a base, are analogous in
their atomic constitution; and the number of atoms in
one such compound being known or assumed, the
number of atoms in other salts may be determined.
But when we proceed in this course of reasoning to
other bodies, as metals, we find ourselves involved in
difficulties. The protoxide of iron is a base which,
according to all analogy, must consist of one atom of
iron and one of oxygen: but the peroxide of iron is
also a base, and it appears by the analysis of this substance that it must consist of two-thirds of an atom of
iron and one atom of oxygen. Here, then, our indivisible atoms must be divisible, even upon chemical
grounds. And if we attempt to evade this difficulty
by making the peroxide of iron consist of two atoms of
iron and three of oxygen, we have to make a corresponding alteration in the theoretical constitution of
all bodies analogous to the protoxide; and thus we
overturn the very foundation of the theory. Chemical
facts, therefore, not only do not prove the Atomic
Theory as a physical truth, but they are not, according
to any modification yet devised of the theory, reconcileable with its scheme.
Nearly the same conclusions result from the attempts to employ the Atomic Hypothesis in expressing another important chemical law;—the law of the 51 combinations of gases according to definite proportions
of their volumes, experimentally established by Gay
Lussac40. In order to account for this law, it has been
very plausibly suggested that all gases, under the same
pressure, contain an equal number of atoms in the
same space; and that when they combine, they unite
atom to atom. Thus one volume of chlorine unites
with one volume of hydrogen, and forms hydrochloric
acid41. But then this hydrochloric acid occupies the
space of the two volumes; and therefore the proper
number of particles cannot be supplied, and the uniform distribution of atoms in all gases maintained,
without dividing into two each of the compound particles, constituted of an atom of chlorine and an atom of
hydrogen. And thus in this case, also, the Atomic
Theory becomes untenable if it be understood to imply
the indivisibility of the atoms.</div></body></text></TEI>