<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="1">INTRODUCTION.

IT is my purpose to write the
History of some of the most important of the Physical Sciences, from
the earliest to the most recent periods. I shall thus have to trace
some of the most remarkable branches of human knowledge, from their
first germ to their growth into a vast and varied assemblage of
undisputed truths; from the acute, but fruitless, essays of the early
Greek Philosophy, to the comprehensive systems, and demonstrated
generalizations, which compose such sciences as the Mechanics,
Astronomy, and Chemistry, of modern times.
The completeness of historical view which belongs to such a design,
consists, not in accumulating all the details of the cultivation of
each science, but in marking the larger features of its formation. The
historian must endeavor to point out how each of the important
advances was made, by which the sciences have reached their present
position; and when and by whom each of the valuable truths was
obtained, of which the aggregate now constitutes a costly
treasure.
Such a task, if fitly executed, must have a well-founded interest
for all those who look at the existing condition of human knowledge
with complacency and admiration. The present generation finds itself
the heir of a vast patrimony of science; and it must needs concern us
to know the steps by which these possessions were acquired, and the
documents by which they are secured to us and our heirs forever. Our
species, from the time of its creation, has been travelling onwards in
pursuit of truth; and now that we have reached a lofty and commanding
position, with the broad light of day around us, it must be grateful
to look back on the line of our vast progress;—to review the
journey, begun in early twilight amid primeval wilds; for a long time
continued with slow advance and obscure prospects; and gradually and
in later days followed along more open and lightsome paths, in a wide
and fertile region. The historian of science, from early periods to
the present times, may hope for favor on the score of the mere subject
of his narrative, and in virtue of the curiosity which the men 42 of the present day may
naturally feel respecting the events and persons of his story.
But such a survey may possess also an interest of another kind; it
may be instructive as well as agreeable; it may bring before the
reader the present form and extent, the future hopes and prospects of
science, as well as its past progress. The eminence on which we stand
may enable us to see the land of promise, as well as the wilderness
through which we have passed. The examination of the steps by which
our ancestors acquired our intellectual estate, may make us acquainted
with our expectations as well as our possessions;—may not only
remind us of what we have, but may teach us how to improve and
increase our store. It will be universally expected that a History of
Inductive Science should point out to us a philosophical distribution
of the existing body of knowledge, and afford us some indication of
the most promising mode of directing our future efforts to add to its
extent and completeness.
To deduce such lessons from the past history of human knowledge,
was the intention which originally gave rise to the present work. Nor
is this portion of the design in any measure abandoned; but its
execution, if it take place, must be attempted in a separate and
future treatise, On the Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences.
An essay of this kind may, I trust, from the progress already made in
it, be laid before the public at no long interval after the present
history.1
1 The Philosophy of the Inductive
Sciences was published shortly after the present work.
Though, therefore, many of the principles and maxims of such a work
will disclose themselves with more or less of distinctness in the
course of the history on which we are about to enter, the systematic
and complete exposition of such principles must be reserved for this
other treatise. My attempts and reflections have led me to the
opinion, that justice cannot be done to the subject without such a
division of it.
To this future work, then, I must refer the reader who is disposed
to require, at the outset, a precise explanation of the terms which
occur in my title. It is not possible, without entering into this
philosophy, to explain adequately how science which is Inductive differs from that which is not so; or why
some portions of knowledge may properly be selected from the
general mass and termed Science. It will be
sufficient at present to say, that the sciences of which we have 43 here to treat, are
those which are commonly known as the Physical Sciences; and
that by Induction is to be understood that process of
collecting general truths from the examination of particular facts, by
which such sciences have been formed.
There are, however, two or three remarks, of which the application
will occur so frequently, and will tend so much to give us a clearer
view of some of the subjects which occur in our history, that I will
state them now in a brief and general manner.
Facts and Ideas.2—In the first place then, I remark,
that, to the formation of science, two things are
requisite;—Facts and Ideas; observation of Things without, and
an inward effort of Thought; or, in other words, Sense and Reason.
Neither of these elements, by itself can constitute substantial
general knowledge. The impressions of sense, unconnected by some
rational and speculative principle, can only end in a practical
acquaintance with individual objects; the operations of the rational
faculties, on the other hand, if allowed to go on without a constant
reference to external things, can lead only to empty abstraction and
barren ingenuity. Real speculative knowledge demands the combination
of the two ingredients;—right reason, and facts to reason upon.
It has been well said, that true knowledge is the interpretation of
nature; and therefore it requires both the interpreting mind, and
nature for its subject; both the document, and the ingenuity to read
it aright. Thus invention, acuteness, and connection of thought, are
necessary on the one hand, for the progress of philosophical
knowledge; and on the other hand, the precise and steady application
of these faculties to facts well known and clearly conceived. It is
easy to point out instances in which science has failed to advance, in
consequence of the absence of one or other of these requisites;
indeed, by far the greater part of the course of the world, the
history of most times and most countries, exhibits a condition thus
stationary with respect to knowledge. The facts, the impressions on
the senses, on which the first successful attempts at physical
knowledge proceeded, were as well known long before the time when they
were thus turned to account, as at that period. The motions of the
stars, and the effects of weight, were familiar to man before the rise
of the Greek Astronomy and Mechanics: but the “diviner mind” was still
absent; the act of thought had not been exerted, by which these facts
were bound together under the form of laws and principles. And even at
44 this day, the
tribes of uncivilized and half-civilized man, over the whole face of
the earth, have before their eyes a vast body of facts, of exactly the
same nature as those with which Europe has built the stately fabric of
her physical philosophy; but, in almost every other part of the earth,
the process of the intellect by which these facts become science, is
unknown. The scientific faculty does not work. The scattered stones
are there, but the builder’s hand is wanting. And again, we have no
lack of proof that mere activity of thought is equally inefficient in
producing real knowledge. Almost the whole of the career of the Greek
schools of philosophy; of the schoolmen of Europe in the middle ages;
of the Arabian and Indian philosophers; shows us that we may have
extreme ingenuity and subtlety, invention and connection,
demonstration and method; and yet that out of these germs, no physical
science may be developed. We may obtain, by such means, Logic and
Metaphysics, and even Geometry and Algebra; but out of such materials
we shall never form Mechanics and Optics, Chemistry and Physiology.
How impossible the formation of these sciences is without a constant
and careful reference to observation and experiment;—how rapid
and prosperous their progress may be when they draw from such sources
the materials on which the mind of the philosopher employs
itself;—the history of those branches of knowledge for the last
three hundred years abundantly teaches us.
2 For the Antithesis of Facts and
Ideas, see the Philosophy, book i. ch. 1, 2, 4, 5.
Accordingly, the existence of clear Ideas applied to distinct Facts
will be discernible in the History of Science, whenever any marked
advance takes place. And, in tracing the progress of the various
provinces of knowledge which come under our survey, it will be
important for us to see that, at all such epochs, such a combination
has occurred; that whenever any material step in general knowledge has
been made,—whenever any philosophical discovery arrests our
attention,—some man or men come before us, who have possessed,
in an eminent degree, a clearness of the ideas which belong to the
subject in question, and who have applied such ideas in a vigorous and
distinct manner to ascertained facts and exact observations. We shall
never proceed through any considerable range of our narrative, without
having occasion to remind the reader of this reflection.
Successive Steps in Science.3—But there is
another remark which we must also make. Such sciences as we have here
to do with are, 45
commonly, not formed by a single act;—they are not completed by
the discovery of one great principle. On the contrary, they consist in
a long-continued advance; a series of changes; a repeated progress
from one principle to another, different and often apparently
contradictory. Now, it is important to remember that this
contradiction is apparent only. The principles which constituted the
triumph of the preceding stages of the science, may appear to be
subverted and ejected by the later discoveries, but in fact they are
(so far as they were true) taken up in the subsequent doctrines and
included in them. They continue to be an essential part of the
science. The earlier truths are not expelled but absorbed, not
contradicted but extended; and the history of each science, which may
thus appear like a succession of revolutions, is, in reality, a series
of developments. In the intellectual, as in the material world,


Omnia mutantur nil
interit . . . . .
Nec manet ut fuerat nec formas servat
easdem,
Sed tamen ipsa eadem est.
All changes, naught is lost; the forms are
changed,
And that which has been is not what it
was,
Yet that which has been is.

Nothing which was done was useless or unessential,
though it ceases to be conspicuous and primary.
3 Concerning Successive
Generalizations in Science see the Philosophy, book i. ch.
2, sect. 11.
Thus the final form of each science contains the substance of each
of its preceding modifications; and all that was at any antecedent
period discovered and established, ministers to the ultimate
development of its proper branch of knowledge. Such previous doctrines
may require to be made precise and definite, to have their superfluous
and arbitrary portions expunged, to be expressed in new language, to
be taken up into the body of science by various processes;—but
they do not on such accounts cease to be true doctrines, or to form a
portion of the essential constituents of our knowledge.
Terms record Discoveries.4—The modes in
which the earlier truths of science are preserved in its later forms,
are indeed various. From being asserted at first as strange
discoveries, such truths come at last to be implied as almost
self-evident axioms. They are recorded by some familiar maxim, or
perhaps by some new word or phrase, which becomes part of the current
language of the philosophical world; and thus asserts a principle,
while it appears merely to indicate a transient 46 notion;—preserves
as well as expresses a truth;—and, like a medal of gold, is a
treasure as well as a token. We shall frequently have to notice the
manner in which great discoveries thus stamp their impress upon the
terms of a science; and, like great political revolutions, are
recorded by the change of the current coin which has accompanied
them.
4 Concerning Technical Terms,
see Philosophy, book i. ch. 3.
Generalization.—The great changes which thus take
place in the history of science, the revolutions of the intellectual
world, have, as a usual and leading character, this, that they are
steps of generalization; transitions from particular truths
to others of a wider extent, in which the former are included. This
progress of knowledge, from individual facts to universal
laws,—from particular propositions to general ones,—and
from these to others still more general, with reference to which the
former generalizations are particular,—is so far familiar to
men’s minds, that, without here entering into further explanation, its
nature will be understood sufficiently to prepare the reader to
recognize the exemplifications of such a process, which he will find
at every step of our advance.
Inductive Epochs; Preludes; Sequels.—In our history,
it is the progress of knowledge only which we have to attend
to. This is the main action of our drama; and all the events which do
not bear upon this, though they may relate to the cultivation and the
cultivators of philosophy, are not a necessary part of our theme. Our
narrative will therefore consist mainly of successive steps of
generalization, such as have just been mentioned. But among these, we
shall find some of eminent and decisive importance, which have more
peculiarly influenced the fortunes of physical philosophy, and to
which we may consider the rest as subordinate and auxiliary. These
primary movements, when the Inductive process, by which science is
formed, has been exercised in a more energetic and powerful manner,
may be distinguished as the Inductive Epochs of scientific
history; and they deserve our more express and pointed notice. They
are, for the most part, marked by the great discoveries and the great
philosophical names which all civilized nations have agreed in
admiring. But, when we examine more clearly the history of such
discoveries, we find that these epochs have not occurred suddenly and
without preparation. They have been preceded by a period, which we may
call their Prelude during which the ideas and facts on which
they turned were called into action;—were gradually evolved into
clearness and connection, permanency and certainty; till at last the
discovery which marks the epoch, seized and fixed forever the truth
which had till then been obscurely and 47 doubtfully discerned. And again, when this
step has been made by the principal discoverers, there may generally
be observed another period, which we may call the Sequel of the
Epoch, during which the discovery has acquired a more perfect
certainty and a more complete development among the leaders of the
advance; has been diffused to the wider throng of the secondary
cultivators of such knowledge, and traced into its distant
consequences. This is a work, always of time and labor, often of
difficulty and conflict. To distribute the History of science into
such Epochs, with their Preludes and Sequels, if successfully
attempted, must needs make the series and connections of its
occurrences more distinct and intelligible. Such periods form
resting-places, where we pause till the dust of the confused march is
laid, and the prospect of the path is clear.
Inductive Charts.5—Since the advance of science
consists in collecting by induction true general laws from particular
facts, and in combining several such laws into one higher
generalization, in which they still retain their truth; we might form
a Chart, or Table, of the progress of each science, by setting down
the particular facts which have thus been combined, so as to form
general truths, and by marking the further union of these general
truths into others more comprehensive. The Table of the progress of
any science would thus resemble the Map of a River, in which the
waters from separate sources unite and make rivulets, which again meet
with rivulets from other fountains, and thus go on forming by their
junction trunks of a higher and higher order. The representation of
the state of a science in this form, would necessarily exhibit all the
principal doctrines of the science; for each general truth contains
the particular truths from which it was derived, and may be followed
backwards till we have these before us in their separate state. And
the last and most advanced generalization would have, in such a
scheme, its proper place and the evidence of its validity. Hence such
an Inductive Table of each science would afford a criterion of
the correctness of our distribution of the inductive Epochs, by its
coincidence with the views of the best judges, as to the substantial
contents of the science in question. By forming, therefore, such
Inductive Tables of the principal sciences of which I have here to
speak, and by regulating by these tables, my views of the history of
the sciences, I conceive that I have secured the distribution of my
48 history from
material error; for no merely arbitrary division of the events could
satisfy such conditions. But though I have constructed such charts to
direct the course of the present history, I shall not insert them in
the work, reserving them for the illustration of the philosophy of the
subject; for to this they more properly belong, being a part of the
Logic of Induction.
5 Inductive charts of the History of
Astronomy and of Optics, such as are here referred to, are given in
the Philosophy, book xi. ch. 6.
Stationary Periods.—By the lines of such maps the real
advance of science is depicted, and nothing else. But there are
several occurrences of other kinds, too interesting and too
instructive to be altogether omitted. In order to understand the
conditions of the progress of knowledge, we must attend, in some
measure, to the failures as well as the successes by which such
attempts have been attended. When we reflect during how small a
portion of the whole history of human speculations, science has really
been, in any marked degree, progressive, we must needs feel some
curiosity to know what was doing in these stationary periods;
what field could be found which admitted of so wide a deviation, or at
least so protracted a wandering. It is highly necessary to our
purpose, to describe the baffled enterprises as well as the
achievements of human speculation.
Deduction.—During a great part of such stationary
periods, we shall find that the process which we have spoken of as
essential to the formation of real science, the conjunction of clear
Ideas with distinct Facts, was interrupted; and, in such cases, men
dealt with ideas alone. They employed themselves in reasoning from
principles, and they arranged, and classified, and analyzed their
ideas, so as to make their reasonings satisfy the requisitions of our
rational faculties. This process of drawing conclusions from our
principles, by rigorous and unimpeachable trains of demonstration, is
termed Deduction. In its due place, it is a highly important
part of every science; but it has no value when the fundamental
principles, on which the whole of the demonstration rests, have not
first been obtained by the induction of facts, so as to supply the
materials of substantial truth. Without such materials, a series of
demonstrations resembles physical science only as a shadow resembles a
real object. To give a real significance to our propositions,
Induction must provide what Deduction cannot supply. From a pictured
hook we can hang only a pictured chain.
Distinction of common Notions and Scientific Ideas.6—When the 49 notions with which men are conversant in
the common course of practical life, which give meaning to their
familiar language, and employment to their hourly thoughts, are
compared with the Ideas on which exact science is founded, we find
that the two classes of intellectual operations have much that is
common and much that is different. Without here attempting fully to
explain this relation (which, indeed, is one of the hardest problems
of our philosophy), we may observe that they have this in common, that
both are acquired by acts of the mind exercised in connecting external
impressions, and may be employed in conducting a train of reasoning;
or, speaking loosely (for we cannot here pursue the subject so as to
arrive at philosophical exactness), we may say, that all notions and
ideas are obtained by an inductive, and may be used in a
deductive process. But scientific Ideas and common Notions
differ in this, that the former are precise and stable, the latter
vague and variable; the former are possessed with clear insight, and
employed in a sense rigorously limited, and always identically the
same; the latter have grown up in the mind from a thousand dim and
diverse suggestions, and the obscurity and incongruity which belong to
their origin hang about all their applications. Scientific Ideas can
often be adequately exhibited for all the purposes of reasoning, by
means of Definitions and Axioms; all attempts to reason by means of
Definitions from common Notions, lead to empty forms or entire
confusion.
6 Scientific Ideas depend upon certain
Fundamental Ideas, which are enumerated in the
Philosophy, book i. ch. 8.
Such common Notions are sufficient for the common practical conduct
of human life: but man is not a practical creature merely; he has
within him a speculative tendency, a pleasure in the
contemplation of ideal relations, a love of knowledge as knowledge. It
is this speculative tendency which brings to light the difference of
common Notions and scientific Ideas, of which we have spoken. The mind
analyzes such Notions, reasons upon them, combines and connects them;
for it feels assured that intellectual things ought to be able to bear
such handling. Even practical knowledge, we see clearly, is not
possible without the use of the reason; and the speculative reason is
only the reason satisfying itself of its own consistency. The
speculative faculty cannot be controlled from acting. The mind cannot
but claim a right to speculate concerning all its own acts and
creations; yet, when it exercises this right upon its common practical
notions, we find that it runs into barren abstractions and
ever-recurring cycles of subtlety. Such Notions are like waters
naturally stagnant; however much we urge and agitate them, they only
revolve in stationary 50 whirlpools. But the mind is capable of
acquiring scientific Ideas, which are better fitted to undergo
discussion and impulsion. When our speculations are duly fed from the
springheads of Observation, and frequently drawn off into the region
of Applied Science, we may have a living stream of consistent and
progressive knowledge. That science may be both real as to its import,
and logical as to its form, the examples of many existing sciences
sufficiently prove.
School Philosophy.—So long, however, as attempts are
made to form sciences, without such a verification and realization of
their fundamental ideas, there is, in the natural series of
speculation, no self-correcting principle. A philosophy constructed on
notions obscure, vague, and unsubstantial, and held in spite of the
want of correspondence between its doctrines and the actual train of
physical events, may long subsist, and occupy men’s minds. Such a
philosophy must depend for its permanence upon the pleasure which men
feel in tracing the operations of their own and other men’s minds, and
in reducing them to logical consistency and systematical
arrangement.
In these cases the main subjects of attention are not external
objects, but speculations previously delivered; the object is not to
interpret nature, but man’s mind. The opinions of the Masters are the
facts which the Disciples endeavor to reduce to unity, or to follow
into consequences. A series of speculators who pursue such a course,
may properly be termed a School, and their philosophy a
School Philosophy; whether their agreement in such a mode of
seeking knowledge arise from personal communication and tradition, or
be merely the result of a community of intellectual character and
propensity. The two great periods of School Philosophy (it will be
recollected that we are here directing our attention mainly to
physical science) were that of the Greeks and that of the Middle
Ages;—the period of the first waking of science, and that of its
midday slumber.
What has been said thus briefly and imperfectly, would require
great detail and much explanation, to give it its full significance
and authority. But it seemed proper to state so much in this place, in
order to render more intelligible and more instructive, at the first
aspect, the view of the attempted or effected progress of science.
It is, perhaps, a disadvantage inevitably attending an undertaking
like the present, that it must set out with statements so abstract;
and must present them without their adequate development and proof.
Such an Introduction, both in its character and its scale of
execution, may be compared to the geographical sketch of a country,
with which 51 the
historian of its fortunes often begins his narration. So much of
Metaphysics is as necessary to us as such a portion of Geography is to
the Historian of an Empire; and what has hitherto been said, is
intended as a slight outline of the Geography of that Intellectual
World, of which we have here to study the History.
The name which we have given to this History—A History of the Inductive Sciences—has the
fault of seeming to exclude from the rank of Inductive Sciences those
which are not included in the History; as Ethnology and Glossology,
Political Economy, Psychology. This exclusion I by no means wish to
imply; but I could find no other way of compendiously describing my
subject, which was intended to comprehend those Sciences in which, by
the observation of facts and the use of reason, systems of doctrine
have been established which are universally received as truths among
thoughtful men; and which may therefore be studied as examples of the
manner in which truth is to be discovered. Perhaps a more exact
description of the work would have been, A History of the principal
Sciences hitherto established by Induction. I may add that I do
not include in the phrase “Inductive Sciences,” the branches of Pure
Mathematics (Geometry, Arithmetic, Algebra, and the like), because, as
I have elsewhere stated (Phil. Ind. Sc., book ii. c. 1), these
are not Inductive but Deductive Sciences. They do
not infer true theories from observed facts, and more general from
more limited laws: but they trace the conditions of all theory, the
properties of space and number; and deduce results from ideas without
the aid of experience. The History of these Sciences is briefly given
in Chapters 13 and 14 of the Second Book of the Philosophy just
referred to.

I may further add that the other work to which I refer, the
Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences, is in a great measure
historical, no less than the present History. That work
contains the history of the Sciences so far as it depends on
Ideas; the present work contains the history so far as it
depends upon Observation. The two works resulted simultaneously
from the same examination of the principal writers on science in all
ages, and may serve to supplement each other.


BOOK I.

HISTORY
OF THE
GREEK SCHOOL
PHILOSOPHY,
WITH REFERENCE TO
PHYSICAL SCIENCE.


Tίς γὰρ ἀρχὰ δέξατο ναυτιλίας;
Τίς δὲ κίνδυνος κρατεροῖς ἀδάμαντος δῆσεν
ἄλοις;
.  .  .  .  .  . 
Ἐπεὶ δ’ ἐμβόλου
Κρέμασαν ἀγκύρας ὕπερθεν
Χρυσέαν χείρεσσι λαβὼν φιάλαν
Ἀρχὸς ἐν πρύμνᾳ πατέρ Οὐρανιδᾶν
Ἐγχεικέραυνον Ζῆνα, καὶ ὠκυπόρους
Κυμάτων ῥίπας, ἀνέμων τ’ ἐκάλει,
Νύκτας τε, καὶ πόντου κελεύθους,
Ἀματά τ’ εὔφρονα, καὶ
Φιλίαν νόστοιο μοῖραν.
Pindar.
Pyth. iv. 124, 349.

Whence came their voyage? them what peril
held
With adamantine rivets firmly bound?
*  *  *  *  * 
 *  *  
But soon as on the vessel’s bow
The anchor was hung up,
Then took the Leader on the prow
In hands a golden cup,
And on great Father Jove did call,
And on the Winds and Waters all,
Swept by the hurrying blast;
And on the Nights, and Ocean Ways,
And on the fair auspicious Days,
And loved return at last.



BOOK I.

HISTORY OF THE GREEK SCHOOL PHILOSOPHY, WITH
REFERENCE TO PHYSICAL SCIENCE.
</div></body></text></TEI>