<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="11">FURTHER VIEW OF THE SAME SUBJECT.
 Before entering on the main argument of the last Chapter, it may be remarked,
 that the plainest and most natural view of the language employed by the sacred
 historian is, that his expressions ought to be received by us in the sense in
 which they were understood by the people to whom he addressed himself. If, when
 speaking of the creation, instead of using the terms light and water, he had
 spoken of the former as a wave, and of the latter as the union of two invisible
 airs, he would assuredly have been perfectly unintelligible to his country-
[page] 73
 men:—at the distance of above three thousand years his writings would just
 have begun to be comprehended; and possibly three thousand years hence those
 views may be as inapplicable to the then existing state of human knowledge as
 they would have been when the first chapter of Genesis was written. Those, however,
 who attempt to disprove the facts presented by observation, by placing them
 in opposition to revelation, have mistaken the very groundwork of the question.
 The revelation of Moses itself rests, and must necessarily rest, on testimony. Moses, the author of the oldest of the sacred books, lived about fifteen
 hundred years before the Christian era, or about three thousand three hundred 
 years ago. The oldest manuscripts of the Pentateuch at present known, appear
 to have been written about 900 years ago.* These were copied from
 * Mr. Home, in the Introduction to the Critical Study of the Holy Scriptures, states, that the total number of Hebrew MSS. collated by Dr. Kennicott,
 for his critical
[page] 74
 others of older date, and those again might probably, if their history were
 known, be traced up through a few transcripts to the original author; but no
 part of this history is revelation; it is testimony. Although the matter edition
 of the Hebrew Bible, was about 630. In that work, Mr. Home gives an account
 of ten of the most ancient of these MSS.: four of which contain the first chapter
 of Genesis, viz.:— No. 4. Codex Caesense, in the Malatesta Library at Bologna,
 written about the end of the eleventh century. No. 6. Codex Mediolanensis, written
 towards the close of the twelfth century. "The beginning of the book of "Genesis,
 and the end of Leviticus and Deuteronomy, "have been written by a later hand."
 No. 8. Codex Parisiensis, 27, about the commencement of the twelfth century.
 No. 10. Codex Parisiensis, 24, written at the beginning of the twelfth century.
 In the same work is an account of six of the most ancient of four hundred and
 seventy-nine MSS. collated by M. De Rossi. Two of these contain the first chapter
 of Genesis; and the date of both is about the end of the eleventh or beginning
 of the twelfth century. Of the Manuscripts of the Samaritan versions of the
 Pentateuch, cited in the same work,—one is the Codex 197, in the Ambrosian Library
 at Milan, which in the opinion of Dr. Kennicott is certainly not later than
 the tenth century.
[page] 75
 which the book contains was revealed to Moses, the fact that what we now receive
 as revelation is the same with that originally communicated revelation, is entirely
 dependent on testimony. Admitting, however, the full weight of that evidence
 above-mentioned, corroborated as it is by the Samaritan version; nay, even
 supposing that we now possessed the identical autograph of the book of Genesis
 by the hand of its author, a most important question remains,—What means do
 we possess of translating it? In similar cases we avail ourselves of the works
 of the immediate predecessors, and of the contemporaries of the writer; but
 here we are acquainted with no work of any predecessor, — with no writing of
 any contemporary; nor do we possess the works of any writers in the same language,
 even during several succeeding centuries, if we except some few of the sacred
 books. How, then, is it
[page] 76
 possible to satisfy our minds of the minute shades of meaning of words, perhaps
 employed popularly; or, if they were employed in a stricter and more philosophical
 sense, where are the contemporary philosophical writings from which their accurate
 interpretation may be gained? The extreme difficulty of such an inquiry will
 be made apparent by imagining a parallel case. Let us suppose all writings in
 the English, and indeed in all other languages previous to the time of Shakespeare,
 to have been destroyed;—let us imagine one manuscript of his plays to remain,
 but not a vestige of the works of any of his contemporaries; and further, suppose
 the whole of the succeeding works of English literature to be annihilated nearly
 up to the present time. Under such circumstances, what would be our knowledge
 of Shakespeare? We should undoubtedly understand the general tenor and the
 plots of his plays. We should read the language of all his characters;
[page] 77
 and viewing it generally, we might even be said to understand it. But how
 many words connected with the customs, habits, and manners of the time must,
 under such circumstances, necessarily remain unknown to us! Still further, if
 any question arose, requiring for its solution a knowledge of the minute shades
 of meaning of words now long obsolete, or of terms supposed to be used in a
 strict or philosophical sense, how completely unsatisfactory must our conclusions
 remain! Such I conceive to be the view which common sense bids us take of the
 interpretation of the book of Genesis. The language of the Hebrews, in times
 long subsequent to the date of that book, may not have so far changed as to
 prevent us from understanding generally the history it narrates; but there appears
 to be no reasonable ground for venturing to pronounce with confidence on the
 minute shades of meaning of allied words, and on such foundations to support
 an argument opposed to the evidence of our senses.
[page] 78
 I should have hesitated in offering these remarks respecting the right interpretation
 of the Mosaic account of the creation, had my argument depended on any acquaintance
 with the language in which the sacred volume is written, or on any refinements
 of criticism, had I possessed that knowledge; but in estimating its validity,
 or in supplying a more cogent argument, I intreat the reader to consider well
 the difficulties which it is necessary to meet. 1st. The Church of England,
 if we may judge by the writings of those placed in authority, has hitherto considered
 it to have been expressly stated in the book of Genesis, that the earth was created about six thousand years ago. 2dly. Those observers and philosophers
 who have spent their lives in the study of Geology, have arrived at the conclusion
 that there exists irresistible evidence, that the date
[page] 79
 of the earth's first formation is far anterior to the epoch supposed to be
 assigned to it by Moses; and it is now admitted by all competent persons, that
 the formation even of those strata which are nearest the surface must have occupied
 vast periods—probably millions of years—in arriving at their present state.
 3dly. Many of the most distinguished members of the Church of England now distinctly
 and formally admit the fact of such a lengthened existence of the earth we inhabit.
 It is so stated in the eighth Bridgewater Treatise, a work written by
 the Professor of Geology in the University of Oxford—himself holding an office
 of dignity in that Church, and expressly appointed to write upon that subject,
 by the Archbishop of Canterbury, and the Bishop of London. 4thly. The Professor
 of Hebrew at the same University has proposed a new interpretation of those
 passages in the Book of Genesis,
[page] 80
 which were hitherto supposed to be adverse to the now admitted facts. Such
 being the present state of the case;—it surely becomes a duty to require a
 very high degree of evidence, before we again claim authority for the opinion
 that the book of Genesis contains such a precise account of the work of the
 creation, that we may venture to appeal to it as a refutation of observed facts.
 The history of the past errors of our parent Church supplies us with a lesson
 of caution which ought not to be lost by its reformed successors. The fact that 
 the venerable Galileo was compelled publicly to deny, on bended knee, a truth
 of which he had the most convincing demonstration, remains as a beacon to all
 after time, and ought not to be without its influence on the inquiring minds
 of the present day. If the explanation offered by the Professor of Hebrew be
 admitted, those who adhere to it must still have some misgivings
[page] 81
 as to the probability that new discoveries in nature may give continual occasion
 for amended translations of various texts; whereas, should the view which has
 been advocated in this chapter be found correct, instead of fearing that the
 future progress of science may raise additional difficulties in the way of revealed
 religion, we are at once relieved from all doubt on that subject.
[page] 82</div></body></text></TEI>