<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol I</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1794</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="9">SECT. IX.
OF VOLUNTARY MOTIONS.

I. 1. Voluntary
  muscular motions are originally excited by irritations. 2. And voluntary ideas. Of reason. II. 1. Voluntary
  muscular motions are occasionally causable by sensations. 2. And voluntary ideas. III. 1. Voluntary
  muscular motions are occasionally obedient to irritations. 2. And voluntary ideas. IV. 1. Voluntary
  muscular motions are associated with other muscular motions. 2. And voluntary ideas.

When pleasure or pain affect the animal system, many of its motions
  both muscular and sensual are brought into action; as was shewn in the
  preceding section, and were called sensitive motions. The general
  tendency of these motions is to arrest and to possess the pleasure, or to
  dislodge or avoid the pain: but if this cannot immediately be
  accomplished, desire or aversion are produced, and the motions in
  consequence of this new faculty of the sensorium are called
  voluntary.
I. 1. Those muscles
  of the body that are attached to bones, have in general their principal
  connections with volition, as I move my pen or raise my body. These
  motions were originally excited by irritation, as was explained in the
  section on that subject, afterwards the sensations of pleasure or pain,
  that accompanied the motions thus excited, induced a repetition of them;
  and at length many of them were voluntarily practised in succession or in
  combination for the common purposes of life, as in learning to walk, or
  to speak; and are performed with strength and velocity in proportion to
  the energy of the volition, that excites them, and the quantity of
  sensorial power.
2. Another great class of voluntary motions
  consists of the ideas of recollection. We will to repeat a certain train
  of ideas, as of the alphabet backwards; and if any ideas, that do not
  belong to this intended train, intrude themselves by other connections,
  we will to reject them, and voluntarily persist in the determined train.
  So at my approach to a house which I have but once visited, and that at
  the distance of many months, I will to recollect the names of the
  numerous family I expect to see there, and I do recollect them.
On this voluntary recollection of ideas our faculty of reason depends,
  as it enables us to acquire an idea of the dissimilitude of any two
  ideas. Thus if you voluntarily produce the idea of a right-angled
  triangle, and then of a square; and after having excited these ideas
  repeatedly, you excite the idea of their difference, which is that of
  another right-angled triangle inverted over the former; you are said to
  reason upon this subject, or to compare your ideas.
These ideas of recollection, like the muscular motions above
  mentioned, were originally excited by the irritation of external bodies,
  and were termed ideas of perception: afterwards the pleasure or pain,
  that accompanied these motions, induced a repetition of them in the
  absence of the external body, by which they were first excited; and then
  they were termed ideas of imagination. At length they become voluntarily
  practised in succession or in combination for the common purposes of
  life; as when we make ourselves masters of the history of mankind, or of
  the sciences they have investigated; and are then called ideas of
  recollection; and are performed with strength and velocity in proportion
  to the energy of the volition that excites them, and the quantity of
  sensorial power.
II. 1. The muscular
  motions above described, that are most frequently obedient to the will
  are nevertheless occasionally causable by painful or pleasurable
  sensation, as in the starting from fear, and the contraction of the calf
  of the leg in the cramp.
2. In like manner the sensual motions, or
  ideas, that are most frequently connected with volition, are nevertheless
  occasionally causable by painful or pleasurable sensation. As the
  histories of men, or the description of places, which we have voluntarily
  taken pains to remember, sometimes occur to us in our dreams.
III. 1. The muscular
  motions that are generally subservient to volition, are also occasionally
  causable by irritation, as in stretching the limbs after sleep, and
  yawning. In this manner a contraction of the arm is produced by passing
  the electric fluid from the Leyden phial along its muscles; and that even
  though the limb is paralytic. The sudden motion of the arm produces a
  disagreeable sensation in the joint, but the muscles seem to be brought
  into action simply by irritation.
2. The ideas, that are generally subservient
  to the will, are in like manner occasionally excited by irritation; as
  when we view again an object, we have before well studied, and often
  recollected.
IV. 1. Innumerable
  trains or tribes of motions are associated with these voluntary muscular
  motions above mentioned; as when I will to extend my arm to a distant
  object, some other muscles are brought into action, and preserve the
  balance of my body. And when I wish to perform any steady exertion, as in
  threading a needle, or chopping with an ax, the pectoral muscles are at
  the same time brought into action to preserve the trunk of the body
  motionless, and we cease to respire for a time.
2. In like manner the voluntary sensual
  motions, or ideas of recollection, are associated with many other trains
  or tribes of ideas. As when I voluntarily recollect a gothic window, that
  I saw some time ago, the whole front of the cathedral occurs to me at the
  same time.

</div></body></text></TEI>