<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="24">
CHAPTER VIII.
Methods of Induction depending on Resemblance.
Aphorism XLIX.
The Law of Continuity is this:—that a quantity cannot
pass from one amount to another by any change of conditions,
without passing through all intermediate magnitudes
according to the intermediate conditions. This Law may
often be employed to disprove distinctions which have no real
foundation.
Aphorism L.
The Method of Gradation consists in taking a number of
stages of a property in question, intermediate between two
extreme cases which appear to be different. This Method is
employed to determine whether the extreme cases are really
distinct or not.
Aphorism LI.
The Method of Gradation, applied to decide the question,
whether the existing geological phenomena arise from existing
causes, leads to this result:—That the phenomena do appear
to arise from Existing Causes, but that the action of existing
causes may, in past times, have transgressed, to any extent,
their recorded limits of intensity.
Aphorism LII.
The Method of Natural Classification consists in classing
cases, not according to any assumed Definition, but according
to the connexion of the facts themselves, so as to make them
the means of asserting general truths. 221
Sect. I.—The Law of Continuity.
1. THE
Law of Continuity is applicable to quantity
primarily, and therefore might be associated
with the methods treated of in the last chapter: but
inasmuch as its inferences are made by a transition from
one degree to another among contiguous cases, it will
be found to belong more properly to the Methods of
Induction of which we have now to speak.
The Law of Continuity consists in this proposition,—That
a quantity cannot pass from one amount to
another by any change of conditions, without passing
through all intermediate degrees of magnitude according
to the intermediate conditions. And this law may
often be employed to correct inaccurate inductions,
and to reject distinctions which have no real foundation
in nature. For example, the Aristotelians made
a distinction between motions according to nature, (as
that of a body falling vertically downwards,) and motions
contrary to nature, (as that of a body moving
along a horizontal plane:) the former, they held, became
naturally quicker and quicker, the latter naturally
slower and slower. But to this it might be replied,
that a horizontal line may pass, by gradual motion,
through various inclined positions, to a vertical
position: and thus the retarded motion may pass into the
accelerated; and hence there must be some inclined
plane on which the motion downwards is naturally
uniform: which is false, and therefore the distinction
of such kinds of motion is unfounded. Again, the
proof of the First Law of Motion depends upon the
Law of Continuity: for since, by diminishing the
resistance to a body moving on a horizontal plane, we
diminish the retardation, and this without limit, the
law of continuity will bring us at the same time to
the case of no resistance and to the case of no retardation.
2. The Law of Continuity is asserted by Galileo
in a particular application; and the assertion which it 222
suggests is by him referred to
Plato;—namely36 that a
moveable body cannot pass from rest to a determinate
degree of velocity without passing through all smaller
degrees of velocity. This law, however, was first asserted
in a more general and abstract form by
Leibnitz37:
and was employed by him to show that the laws
of motion propounded by Descartes must be false. The
Third Cartesian Law of Motion was
this38: that when
one moving body meets another, if the first body have
a less momentum than the second, it will be reflected
with its whole motion: but if the first have a greater
momentum than the second, it will lose a part of its
motion, which it will transfer to the second. Now
each of these cases leads, by the Law of Continuity, to
the case in which the two bodies have equal momentums:
but in this case, by the first part of the law the
body would retain all its motion; and by the second
part of the law it would lose a portion of it: hence the
Cartesian Law is false.
36
 Dialog. iii. 150. iv. 32.
37
 Opera, i. 366.
38
 Cartes, Prin. p. 35.
3. I shall take another example of the application
of this Law from Professor Playfair’s Dissertation on
the History of Mathematical and Physical
Science39.
‘The Academy of Sciences at Paris having (in 1724)
proposed, as a Prize Question, the Investigation of the
Laws of the Communication of Motion, John Bernoulli
presented an Essay on the subject very ingenious and
profound; in which, however, he denied the existence
of hard bodies, because in the collision of such bodies,
a finite change of motion must take place in an instant:
an event which, on the principle just explained, he
maintained to be impossible.’ And this reasoning
was justifiable: for we can form a continuous
transition from cases in which the impact manifestly
occupies a finite time, (as when we strike a large soft
body) to cases in which it is apparently instantaneous.
Maclaurin and others are disposed, in order to avoid
the conclusion of Bernoulli, to reject the Law of 223
Continuity. This, however, would not only be, as Playfair
says, to deprive ourselves of an auxiliary, commonly
useful though sometimes deceptive; but what is much
worse, to acquiesce in false propositions, from the want
of clear and patient thinking. For the Law of Continuity,
when rightly interpreted, is never violated in
actual fact. There are not really any such bodies as
have been termed perfectly hard: and if we approach
towards such cases, we must learn the laws of motion
which rule them by attending to the Law of Continuity,
not by rejecting it.
39
 In the Encyc. Brit. p. 537.
4. Newton used the Law of Continuity to suggest,
but not to prove, the doctrine of universal gravitation.
Let, he said, a terrestrial body be carried as high as
the moon: will it not still fall to the earth? and does
not the moon fall by the same force40?
Again: if any
one says that there is a material ether which does not
gravitate41,
this kind of matter, by condensation, may
be gradually transmuted to the density of the most
intensely gravitating bodies: and these gravitating
bodies, by taking the internal texture of the condensed
ether, may cease to gravitate; and thus the weight of
bodies depends, not on their quantity of matter, but
on their texture; which doctrine Newton conceived he
had disproved by experiment.
40
 Principia, lib. iii. prop. 6.
41
 Ib. cor. 2.
5. The evidence of the Law of Continuity resides
in the universality of those Ideas, which enter into
our apprehension of Laws of Nature. When, of two
quantities, one depends upon the other, the Law of
Continuity necessarily governs this dependence. Every
philosopher has the power of applying this law, in
proportion as he has the faculty of apprehending the Ideas
which he employs in his induction, with the same
clearness and steadiness which belong to the fundamental
ideas of Quantity, Space and Number. To those
who possess this faculty, the Law is a Rule of very wide
and decisive application. Its use, as has appeared in the
above examples, is seen rather in the disproof of erroneous
views, and in the correction of false propositions, 224
than in the invention of new truths. It is a test of
truth, rather than an instrument of discovery.
Methods, however, approaching very near to the
Law of Continuity may be employed as positive means
of obtaining new truths; and these I shall now describe.
Sect. II.—The Method of Gradation.
6. To gather together the cases which resemble
each other, and to separate those which are essentially
distinct, has often been described as the main business
of science; and may, in a certain loose and vague
manner of speaking, pass for a description of some of
the leading procedures in the acquirement of knowledge.
The selection of instances which agree, and of
instances which differ, in some prominent point or
property, are important steps in the formation of
science. But when classes of things and properties
have been established in virtue of such comparisons, it
may still be doubtful whether these classes are separated
by distinctions of opposites, or by differences of
degree. And to settle such questions, the Method of
Gradation is employed; which consists in taking
intermediate stages of the properties in question, so as to
ascertain by experiment whether, in the transition
from one class to another, we have to leap over a
manifest gap, or to follow a continuous road.
7. Thus for instance, one of the early Divisions
established by electrical philosophers was that of Electrics
and Conductors. But this division Dr. Faraday
has overturned as an essential opposition. He
takes42 a
Gradation which carries him from Conductors to
Non-conductors. Sulphur, or Lac, he says, are held to be
non-conductors, but are not rigorously so. Spermaceti
is a bad conductor: ice or water better than spermaceti:
metals so much better that they are put in a
different class. But even in metals the transit of the
electricity is not instantaneous: we have in them proof
of a retardation of the electric current: ‘and what 225
reason,” Mr. Faraday asks, “why this retardation
should not be of the same kind as that in spermaceti,
or in lac, or sulphur? But as, in them, retardation is
insulation, [and insulation is
induction43] why should
we refuse the same relation to the same exhibitions of
force in the metals?”
42
 Researches, 12th series, art. 1328.
43
 These words refer to another proposition,
also established by the Method of Gradation.
The process employed by the same sagacious philosopher
to show the identity of Voltaic and Franklinic
electricity, is another example of the same kind44.
Machine [Franklinic] electricity was made to exhibit the
same phenomena as Voltaic electricity, by causing the
discharge to pass through a bad conductor, into a very
extensive discharging train: and thus it was clearly
shown that Franklinic electricity, not so conducted,
differs from the other kinds, only in being in a state
of successive tension and explosion instead of a state
of continued current.
44
 Hist. Ind. Sc. b. xiv. c. ix. sect. 2.
Again; to show that the decomposition of bodies in
the Voltaic circuit was not due to the Attraction of the
Poles45,
Mr. Faraday devised a beautiful series of
experiments, in which these supposed Poles were made to
assume all possible electrical conditions:—in some cases
the decomposition took place against air, which according
to common language is not a conductor, nor is decomposed;—in
others, against the metallic poles, which
are excellent conductors but undecomposable;—and so
on: and hence he infers that the decomposition cannot
justly be considered as due to the Attraction, or Attractive
Powers, of the Poles.
45
 Ibid. Researches, art. 497.
8. The reader of the Novum Organon may perhaps,
in looking at such examples of the Rule, be reminded
of some of Bacon’s Classes of Instances, as his instantiæ
absentiæ in proximo, and his instantiæ migrantes.
But we may remark that Instances classed
and treated as Bacon recommends in those parts of
his work, could hardly lead to scientific truth. His 226
processes are vitiated by his proposing to himself the
form or cause of the property before him, as the object
of his inquiry; instead of being content to obtain, in
the first place, the law of phenomena. Thus his
example46
of a Migrating Instance is thus given. “Let
the Nature inquired into be that of Whiteness;
an Instance Migrating to the production of this property is
glass, first whole, and then pulverized; or plain water,
and water agitated into a foam; for glass and water
are transparent, and not white; but glass powder and
foam are white, and not transparent. Hence we must
inquire what has happened to the glass or water in
that Migration. For it is plain that the Form of
Whiteness is conveyed and induced by the crushing
of the glass and shaking of the water.” No real
knowledge has resulted from this line of reasoning:—from
taking the Natures and Forms of things and of
their qualities for the primary subject of our researches.
46
 Nov. Org. lib. ii. Aph. 28.
9. We may easily give examples from other subjects in
which the Method of Gradation has been used
to establish, or to endeavour to establish, very extensive
propositions. Thus Laplace’s Nebular Hypothesis,—that
systems like our solar system are formed by
gradual condensation from diffused masses, such as the
nebulæ among the stars,—is founded by him upon an
application of this Method of Gradation. We see, he
conceives, among these nebulæ, instances of all degrees
of condensation, from the most loosely diffused fluid,
to that separation and solidification of parts by which
suns, and satellites, and planets are formed: and thus
we have before us instances of systems in all their
stages; as in a forest we see trees in every period of
growth. How far the examples in this case satisfy the
demands of the Method of Gradation, it remains for
astronomers and philosophers to examine.
Again; this method was used with great success by
Macculloch and others to refute the opinion, put in
currency by the Wernerian school of geologists, that 227
the rocks called trap rocks must be classed with those
to which a sedimentary origin is ascribed. For it was
shown that a gradual transition might be traced from
those examples in which trap rocks most resembled
stratified rocks, to the lavas which have been recently
ejected from volcanoes: and that it was impossible to
assign a different origin to one portion, and to the
other, of this kind of mineral masses; and as the
volcanic rocks were certainly not sedimentary, it followed,
that the trap rocks were not of that nature.
Again; we have an attempt of a still larger kind
made by Sir C. Lyell, to apply this Method of Gradation
so as to disprove all distinction between the causes by
which geological phenomena have been produced, and
the causes which are now acting at the earth’s surface.
He has collected a very remarkable series of changes
which have taken place, and are still taking place, by
the action of water, volcanoes, earthquakes, and other
terrestrial operations; and he conceives he has shown
in these a gradation which leads, with no wide chasm
or violent leap, to the state of things of which geological
researches have supplied the evidence.
10. Of the value of this Method in geological speculations,
no doubt can be entertained. Yet it must still
require a grave and profound consideration, in so vast
an application of the Method as that attempted by
Sir C. Lyell, to determine what extent we may allow to
the steps of our gradation; and to decide how far the
changes which have taken place in distant parts of the
series may exceed those of which we have historical
knowledge, without ceasing to be of the same kind.
Those who, dwelling in a city, see, from time to time,
one house built and another pulled down, may say that
such existing causes, operating through past time,
sufficiently explain the existing condition of the city. Yet
we arrive at important political and historical truths,
by considering the origin of a city as an event of a
different order from those daily changes. The causes
which are now working to produce geological results,
may be supposed to have been, at some former epoch,
so far exaggerated in their operation, that the changes 228
should be paroxysms, not degrees;—that they should
violate, not continue, the gradual series. And we
have no kind of evidence whether the duration of our
historical times is sufficient to give us a just measure
of the limits of such degrees;—whether the terms
which we have under our notice enable us to ascertain
the average rate of progression.
11. The result of such considerations seems to be
this:—that we may apply the Method of Gradation in
the investigation of geological causes, provided we
leave the Limits of the Gradation undefined. But,
then, this is equivalent to the admission of the opposite
hypothesis: for a continuity of which the successive
intervals are not limited, is not distinguishable from
discontinuity. The geological sects of recent times
have been distinguished as uniformitarians and catastrophists:
the Method of Gradation seems to prove the
doctrine of the uniformitarians; but then, at the same
time that it does this, it breaks down the distinction
between them and the catastrophists.
There are other exemplifications of the use of gradations
in Science which well deserve notice: but some
of them are of a kind somewhat different, and may be
considered under a separate head.
Sect. III. The Method of Natural Classification.
12. The Method of Natural Classification consists, as
we have seen, in grouping together objects, not according
to any selected properties, but according to their
most important resemblances; and in combining such
grouping with the assignation of certain marks of the
classes thus formed. The examples of the successful
application of this method are to be found in the
Classificatory Sciences through their whole extent; as,
for example, in framing the Genera of plants and animals.
The same method, however, may often be extended to other
sciences. Thus the classification of
Crystalline Forms, according to their Degree of Symmetry,
(which is really an important distinction,) as introduced
by Mohs and Weiss, was a great improvement 229
upon Haüy’s arbitrary division according to certain
assumed primary forms. Sir David Brewster was led
to the same distinction of crystals by the study of
their optical properties; and the scientific value of the
classification was thus strongly exhibited. Mr. Howard’s
classification of Clouds appears to be founded in
their real nature, since it enables him to express the
laws of their changes and successions. As we have
elsewhere said, the criterion of a true classification is,
that it makes general propositions possible. One of
the most prominent examples of the beneficial influence
of a right classification, is to be seen in the
impulse given to geology by the distinction of strata
according to the organic fossils which they
contain47:
which, ever since its general adoption, has been a
leading principle in the speculations of geologists.
47
 Hist. Ind. Sc. b. xviii. c. ii. sect. 3.
13. The mode in which, in this and in other cases,
the Method of Natural Classification directs the researches
of the philosopher, is this:—his arrangement
being adopted, at least as an instrument of inquiry and
trial, he follows the course of the different members of
the classification, according to the guidance which Nature
herself offers; not prescribing beforehand the
marks of each part, but distributing the facts according
to the total resemblances, or according to those
resemblances which he finds to be most important.
Thus, in tracing the course of a series of strata from
place to place, we identify each stratum, not by any
single character, but by all taken together;—texture,
colour, fossils, position, and any other circumstances
which offer themselves. And if, by this means, we
come to ambiguous cases, where different indications
appear to point different ways, we decide so as best to
preserve undamaged those general relations and truths
which constitute the value of our system. Thus
although we consider the organic fossils in each stratum
as its most important characteristic, we are not
prevented, by the disappearance of some fossils, or the
addition of others, or by the total absence of fossils, 230
from identifying strata in distant countries, if the
position and other circumstances authorize us to do so.
And by this Method of Classification, the doctrine of
Geological Equivalents48
has been applied to a great
part of Europe.
48
 Hist. Ind. Sc. b. xviii. c. iii. sect. 4.
14. We may further observe, that the same method
of natural classification which thus enables us to
identify strata in remote situations, notwithstanding that
there may be great differences in their material and
contents, also forbids us to assume the identity of the
series of rocks which occur in different countries, when
this identity has not been verified by such a continuous
exploration of the component members of the
series. It would be in the highest degree unphilosophical
to apply the special names of the English or
German strata to the rocks of India, or America, or
even of southern Europe, till it has appeared that in
those countries the geological series of northern Europe
really exists. In each separate country, the divisions
of the formations which compose the crust of the
earth must be made out, by applying the Method of
Natural Arrangement to that particular case, and not
by arbitrarily extending to it the nomenclature
belonging to another case. It is only by such precautions,
that we can ever succeed in obtaining geological
propositions, at the same time true and comprehensive; or
can obtain any sound general views respecting the
physical history of the earth.
15. The Method of Natural Classification, which
we thus recommend, falls in with those mental habits
which we formerly described as resulting from the
study of Natural History. The method was then termed
the Method of Type, and was put in opposition to the
Method of Definition.
The Method of Natural Classification is directly
opposed to the process in which we assume and apply
arbitrary definitions; for in the former Method, we
find our classes in nature, and do not make them by
marks of our own imposition. Nor can any advantage 231
to the progress of knowledge be procured, by laying
down our characters when our arrangements are as yet
quite loose and unformed. Nothing was gained by
the attempts to define Metals by their weight, their
hardness, their ductility, their colour; for to all these
marks, as fast as they were proposed, exceptions were
found, among bodies which still could not be excluded
from the list of Metals. It was only when
elementary substances were divided into Natural
Classes, of which classes Metals were one, that a true
view of their distinctive characters was obtained.
Definitions in the outset of our examination of nature are
almost always, not only useless, but prejudicial.
16. When we obtain a Law of Nature by induction
from phenomena, it commonly happens, as we have
already seen, that we introduce, at the same time, a
Proposition and a Definition. In this case, the two
are correlative, each giving a real value to the other.
In such cases, also, the Definition, as well as the
Proposition, may become the basis of rigorous reasoning,
and may lead to a series of deductive truths. We have
examples of such Definitions and Propositions in the
Laws of Motion, and in many other cases.
17. When we have established Natural Classes of
objects, we seek for Characters of our classes; and
these Characters may, to a certain extent, be called the
Definitions of our classes. This is to be understood,
however, only in a limited sense: for these Definitions
are not absolute and permanent. They are liable to
be modified and superseded. If we find a case which
manifestly belongs to our Natural Class, though violating
our Definition, we do not shut out the case, but
alter our definition. Thus, when we have made it
part of our Definition of the Rose family, that they
have alternate stipulate leaves, we do not, therefore,
exclude from the family the genus Lowæa, which has
no stipulæ. In Natural Classifications, our
Definitions are to be considered as temporary and
provisional only. When Sir C. Lyell established the
distinctions of the tertiary strata, which he termed Eocene,
Miocene, and Pliocene, he took a numerical criterion 232
(the proportion of recent species of shells contained in
those strata) as the basis of his division. But now
that those kinds of strata have become, by their
application to a great variety of cases, a series of Natural
Classes, we must, in our researches, keep in view the
natural connexion of the formations themselves in different
places; and must by no means allow ourselves
to be governed by the numerical proportions which
were originally contemplated; or even by any amended
numerical criterion equally arbitrary; for however
amended, Definitions in natural history are never immortal.
The etymologies of Pliocene and Miocene
may, hereafter, come to have merely an historical interest;
and such a state of things will be no more inconvenient,
provided the natural connexions of each class
are retained, than it is to call a rock oolite or
porphyry, when it has no roelike structure and no fiery
spots.
The Methods of Induction which are treated of in
this and the preceding chapter, and which are specially
applicable to causes governed by relations of Quantity
or of Resemblance, commonly lead us to Laws of Phenomena
only. Inductions founded upon other ideas,
those of Substance and Cause for example, appear to
conduct us somewhat further into a knowledge of the
essential nature and real connexions of things. But
before we speak of these, we shall say a few words
respecting the way in which inductive propositions,
once obtained, may be verified and carried into effect
by their application.
</div></body></text></TEI>