<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="129">CHAPTER VII.
Progress of Animal Morphology.

Sect. 1.—Rise of Comparative
Anatomy.
THE most general and constant
relations of the form of the organs, both in plants and animals, are
the most natural grounds of classification. Hence the first scientific
classifications of animals are the first steps in animal morphology.
At first, a zoology was constructed by arranging animals, as
plants were at first arranged, according to their external parts. But
in the course of the researches of the anatomists of the seventeenth
century, it was seen that the internal structure of animals offered
resemblances and transitions of a far more coherent and philosophical
kind, and the Science of Comparative Anatomy rose into favor
and importance. Among the main cultivators of this science91 at the period just mentioned, we find
Francis Redi, of Arezzo; Guichard-Joseph Duvernay, who was for sixty
years Professor of Anatomy at the Jardin du Roi at Paris, and during
this lapse of time had for his pupils almost all the greatest
anatomists of the greater part of the eighteenth century; Nehemiah
Grew, secretary to the Royal Society of London, whose Anatomy of
Plants we have already noticed.
91 Cuv. Leçons sur l’Hist. des Sc.
Nat. 414, 420.
But Comparative Anatomy, which had been cultivated with ardor 476 to the end of the
seventeenth century, was, in some measure, neglected during the first
two-thirds of the eighteenth. The progress of botany was, Cuvier
sagaciously suggests,92 one cause of this; for that science had
made its advances by confining itself to external characters, and
rejecting anatomy; and though Linnæus acknowledged the dependence of
zoology upon anatomy93 so far as to make the number of teeth
his characters, even this was felt, in his method, as a bold step. But
his influence was soon opposed by that of Buffon, Daubenton, and
Pallas; who again brought into view the importance of comparative
anatomy in Zoology; at the same time that Haller proved how much might
be learnt from it in Physiology. John Hunter in England, the two
Monros in Scotland, Camper in Holland, and Vicq d’Azyr in France, were
the first to follow the path thus pointed out. Camper threw the glance
of genius on a host of interesting objects, but almost all that he
produced was a number of sketches; Vicq d’Azyr, more assiduous, was
stopt in the midst of a most brilliant career by a premature
death.
92 Cuv. Hist. Sc. Nat. i.
301.
93 Ib.
Such is Cuvier’s outline of the earlier history of comparative
anatomy. We shall not go into detail upon this subject; but we may
observe that such studies had fixed in the minds of naturalists the
conviction of the possibility and the propriety of considering large
divisions of the animal kingdom as modifications of one common
type. Belon, as early as 1555, had placed the skeleton of a man
and a bird side by side, and shown the correspondence of parts. So far
as the case of vertebrated animals extends, this correspondence is
generally allowed; although it required some ingenuity to detect its
details in some cases; for instance, to see the analogy of parts
between the head of a man and a fish.
In tracing these less obvious correspondencies, some curious steps
have been made in recent times. And here we must, I conceive, again
ascribe no small merit to the same remarkable man who, as we have
already had to point out, gave so great an impulse to vegetable
morphology. Göthe, whose talent and disposition for speculating on all
parts of nature were truly admirable, was excited to the study of
anatomy by his propinquity to the Duke of Weimar’s cabinet of natural
history. In 1786, he published a little essay, the object of which was
to show that in man, as well as in beasts, the upper jaw contains an
intermaxillary bone, although the sutures are obliterated. After
1790,94 animated and impelled by the same
passion for natural 477 observation and for general views, which
had produced his Metamorphosis of Plants, he pursued his speculations
on these subjects eagerly and successfully. And in 1795, he published
a Sketch of a Universal Introduction into Comparative Anatomy,
beginning with Osteology; in which he attempts to establish an
“osteological type,” to which skeletons of all animals may be
referred. I do not pretend that Göthe’s anatomical works have had any
influence on the progress of the science comparable with that which
has been exercised by the labors of professional anatomists; but the
ingenuity and value of the views which they contained was acknowledged
by the best authorities; and the clearer introduction and application
of the principle of developed and metamorphosed symmetry may be dated
from about this time. Göthe declares that, at an early period of these
speculations, he was convinced95 that the bony
head of beasts is to be derived from six vertebræ. In 1807, Oken
published a “Program” On the Signification of the Bones of the
Skull, in which he maintained that these bones are equivalent to
four vertebræ); and Meckel, in his Comparative Anatomy, in
1811, also resolved the skull into vertebræ. But Spix, in his
elaborate work Cephalogenesis, in 1815, reduced the vertebræ of
the head to three. “Oken,” he says,96 “published
opinions merely theoretical, and consequently contrary to those
maintained in this work, which are drawn from observation.” This
resolution of the head into vertebræ is assented to by many of the
best physiologists, as explaining the distribution of the nerves, and
other phenomena. Spix further extended the application of the
vertebral theory to the heads of all classes of vertebrate animals;
and Bojanus published a Memoir expressly on the vertebral structure of
the skulls of fishes in Oken’s Isis for 1818. Geoffroy
Saint-Hilaire presented a lithographic plate to the French Academy in
February 1824, entitled Composition de la Tête osseuse chez
l’Homme et les Animaux, and developed his views of the vertebral
composition of the skull in two Memoirs published in the Annales
des Sciences Naturelles for 1824. We cannot fail to recognize here
the attempt to apply to the skeleton of animals the principle which
leads botanists to consider all the parts of a flower as
transformations of the same organs. How far the application of the
principle, as here proposed, is just, I must leave philosophical
physiologists to decide.
94 Zur Morphologie, i.
234.
95 Zur Morphologie, 250.
96  Spix,
Cephalogenesis.
By these and similar researches, it is held by the best
physiologists 478
that the skull of all vertebrate animals is pretty well reduced to a
uniform structure, and the laws of its variations nearly determined.97
97 Cuv. Hist. Sc. Nat. iii.
442.
The vertebrate animals being thus reduced to a single type, the
question arises how far this can be done with regard to other animals,
and how many such types there are. And here we come to one of the
important services which Cuvier rendered to natural history.
Sect. 2.—Distinction of the General
Types of the Forms of Animals.—Cuvier.
Animals were divided by
Lamarck into vertebrate and invertebrate; and the general analogies of
all vertebrate animals are easily made manifest. But with regard to
other animals, the point is far from clear. Cuvier was the first to
give a really philosophical view of the animal world in reference to
the plan on which each animal is constructed. There are,98 he says, four such plans;—four
forms on which animals appear to have been modelled; and of which the
ulterior divisions, with whatever titles naturalists have decorated
them, are only very slight modifications, founded on the development
or addition of some parts which do not produce any essential change in
the plan.
98 Règne Animal, p. 57.
These four great branches of the animal world are the
vertebrata, mollusca, articulata, radiata;
and the differences of these are so important that a slight
explanation of them may be permitted.
The vertebrata are those animals which (as man and other
sucklers, birds, fishes, lizards, frogs, serpents) have a backbone and
a skull with lateral appendages, within which the viscera are
included, and to which the muscles are attached.
The mollusca, or soft animals, have no bony skeleton; the
muscles are attached to the skin, which often includes stony plates
called shells; such molluscs are shell-fish; others are
cuttle-fish, and many pulpy sea-animals.
The articulata consist of crustacea (lobsters,
&c.), insects, spiders, and annulose worms,
which consist of a head and a number of successive annular portions of
the body jointed together (to the interior of which the muscles
are attached), whence the name.
Finally, the radiata include the animals known under the
name of zoophytes. In the preceding three branches the organs
of motion and of sense were distributed symmetrically on the two sides
of an axis, 479 so
that the animal has a right and a left side. In the radiata the
similar members radiate from the axis in a circular manner, like the
petals of a regular flower.
The whole value of such a classification cannot be understood
without explaining its use in enabling us to give general
descriptions, and general laws of the animal functions of the classes
which it includes; but in the present part of our work our business is
to exhibit it as an exemplification of the reduction of animals to
laws of Symmetry. The bipartite Symmetry of the form of vertebrate and
articulate animals is obvious; and the reduction of the various forms
of such animals to a common type has been effected, by attention to
their anatomy, in a manner which has satisfied those who have best
studied the subject. The molluscs, especially those in which the head
disappears, as oysters, or those which are rolled into a spiral, as
snails, have a less obvious Symmetry, but here also we can apply
certain general types. And the Symmetry of the radiated zoophytes is
of a nature quite different from all the rest, and approaching, as we
have suggested, to the kind of Symmetry found in plants. Some
naturalists have doubted whether99 these zoophytes
are not referrible to two types (acrita or polypes, and true
radiata,) rather than to one.
99 Brit. Assoc. Rep. iv.
227.
This fourfold division was introduced by Cuvier.100 Before him, naturalists followed
Linnæus, and divided non-vertebrate animals into two classes, insects
and worms. “I began,” says Cuvier, “to attack this view of the
subject, and offered another division, in a Memoir read at the Society
of Natural History of Paris, the 21st of Floreal, in the year III. of
the Republic (May 10, 1795,) printed in the Décade
Philosophique: in this, I mark the characters and the limits of
molluscs, insects, worms, echinoderms, and zoophytes. I distinguish
the red-blooded worms or annelides, in a Memoir read to the Institute,
the 11th Nivose, year X. (December 31, 1801.) I afterwards distributed
these different classes into three branches, each co-ordinate to the
branch formed by the vertebrate animals, in a Memoir read to the
Institute in July, 1812, printed in the Annales du Muséum
d’Histoire Naturelle, tom. xix.” His great systematic work, the
Règne Animal, founded on this distribution, was published in
1817; and since that time the division has been commonly accepted
among naturalists.
100 Règne A. 61.
[2nd Ed.] [The question of the Classification of Animals is
discussed in the first of Prof. Owen’s Lectures on the
Invertebrate 480 Animals (1843). Mr. Owen observes
that the arrangement of animals into Vertebrate and
Invertebrate which prevailed before Cuvier, was necessarily
bad, inasmuch as no negative character in Zoology gives true
natural groups. Hence the establishment of the sub-kingdoms,
Mollusca, Articulata, Radiata, as co-ordinate
with Vertebrata, according to the arrangement of the nervous
system, was a most important advance. But Mr. Owen has seen reason to
separate the Radiata of Cuvier into two divisions; the
Nematoneura, in which the nervous system can be traced in a
filamentary form (including Echinoderma, Ciliobrachiata,
Cœlelmintha, Rotifera,) and the Acrita or lowest
division of the animal kingdom, including Acalepha,
Nudibrachiata, Sterelmintha, Polygastria.]
~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~
Sect. 3.—Attempts to establish the
Identity of the Types of Animal Forms.
Supposing this great step in
Zoology, of which we have given an account,—the reduction of all
animals to four types or plans,—to be quite secure, we are then
led to ask whether any further advance is possible;—whether
several of these types can be referred to one common form by any wider
effort of generalization. On this question there has been a
considerable difference of opinion. Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire,101 who had previously endeavored to show
that all vertebrate animals were constructed so exactly upon the same
plan as to preserve the strictest analogy of parts in respect to their
osteology, thought to extend this unity of plan by demonstrating, that
the hard parts of crustaceans and insects are still only modifications
of the skeleton of higher animals, and that therefore the type of
vertebrata must be made to include them also:—the segments of
the articulata are held to be strictly analogous to the vertebras of
the higher animals, and thus the former live within their
vertebral column in the same manner as the latter live
without it. Attempts have even been made to reduce molluscous
and vertebrate animals to a community of type, as we shall see
shortly.
101 Mr. Jenyns, Brit. Assoc.
Rep. iv. 150.
Another application of the principle, according to which creatures
the most different are developments of the same original type, may be
discerned102 in the doctrine, that the embryo of
the higher forms of animal life passes by gradations through those
forms which are 481
permanent in inferior animals. Thus, according to this view, the human
fœtus assumes successively the plan of the zoophyte, the worm, the
fish, the turtle, the bird, the beast. But it has been well observed,
that “in these analogies we look in vain for the precision which can
alone support the inference that has been deduced;”103 and that at each step, the higher
embryo and the lower animal which it is supposed to resemble, differ
in having each different organs suited to their respective
destinations.
102 Dr. Clark, Report, Ib.
iv. 113.
103 Dr. Clark, p. 114.
Cuvier104 never assented to this view, nor to
the attempts to refer the different divisions of his system to a
common type. “He could not admit,” says his biographer, “that the
lungs or gills of the vertebrates are in the same connexion as the
branchiæ of molluscs and crustaceans, which in the one are situated at
the base of the feet, or fixed on the feet themselves, and in the
other often on the back or about the arms. He did not admit the
analogy between the skeleton of the vertebrates and the skin of the
articulates; he could not believe that the tænia and the sepia were
constructed on the same plan; that there was a similarity of
composition between the bird and the echinus, the whale and the snail;
in spite of the skill with which some persons sought gradually to
efface their discrepancies.”
104 Laurillard, Elog. de
Cuvier, p. 66.
Whether it may be possible to establish, among the four great
divisions of the “Animal Kingdom,” some analogies of a higher order
than those which prevail within each division, I do not pretend to
conjecture. If this can be done, it is clear that it must be by
comparing the types of these divisions under their most general forms:
and thus Cuvier’s arrangement, so far as it is itself rightly founded
on the unity of composition of each branch, is the surest step to the
discovery of a unity pervading and uniting these branches. But those
who generalize surely, and those who generalize rapidly, may travel in
the same direction, they soon separate so widely, that they appear to
move from each other. The partisans of a universal “unity of
composition” of animals, accused Cuvier of being too inert in
following the progress of physiological and zoological science.
Borrowing their illustration from the political parties of the times,
they asserted that he belonged to the science of resistance,
not to the science of the movement. Such a charge was highly
honorable to him; for no one acquainted with the history of zoology
can doubt that he had a great share in the impulse by which the
“movement” was occasioned; or that he 482 himself made a large advance with it;
and it was because he was so poised by the vast mass of his knowledge,
so temperate in his love of doubtful generalizations, that he was not
swept on in the wilder part of the stream. To such a charge, moderate
reformers, who appreciate the value of the good which exists, though
they try to make it better, and who know the knowledge,
thoughtfulness, and caution, which are needful in such a task, are
naturally exposed. For us, who can only decide on such a subject by
the general analogies of the history of science, it may suffice to
say, that it appears doubtful whether the fundamental conceptions of
affinity, analogy, transition, and developement, have yet been fixed
in the minds of physiologists with sufficient firmness and clearness,
or unfolded with sufficient consistency and generality, to make it
likely that any great additional step of this kind can for some time
be made.
We have here considered the doctrine of the identity of the
seemingly various types of animal structure, as an attempt to extend
the correspondencies which were the basis of Cuvier’s division of the
animal kingdom. But this doctrine has been put forward in another
point of view, as the antithesis to the doctrine of final causes. This
question is so important a one, that we cannot help attempting to give
some view of its state and bearings.
</div></body></text></TEI>