<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="45">CHAPTER XLV.
INCLOSING OF FOSSILS IN PEAT, BROWN SAND, AND VOLCANIC
EJECTIONS.
Division of the subject—Imbedding of organic remains in deposits on emerged
land—Growth of peat—Site of ancient forests in Europe now occupied by
peat—Bog iron-ore—Preservation of animal substances in peat—Miring of
quadrupeds—Bursting of the Solway moss—Great Dismal Swamp—Imbedding
of organic bodies and human remains in blown sand—Moving sands of
African deserts—De Luc on their recent origin—Buried temple of Ipsambul—Dried
carcases in the sands—Towns overwhelmed by sand-floods—Imbedding
of organic and other remains in volcanic formations on the land.
Division of the subject.—The next subject of inquiry is the mode in
which the remains of animals and plants become fossil, or are buried
in the earth by natural causes. M. Constant Prevost has observed,
that the effects of geological causes are divisible into two great classes;
those produced during the submersion of land beneath the waters,
and those which take place after its emersion. Agreeably to this classification,
I shall consider, first, in what manner animal and vegetable
remains become included and preserved in deposits on emerged land, or
that part of the surface which is not permanently covered by water,
whether of seas or lakes; secondly, the manner in which organic remains
become imbedded in subaqueous deposits.
Under the first division, I shall treat of the following topics:—1st, the
growth of peat, and the preservation of vegetable and animal remains
therein;—2dly, the burying of organic remains in blown sand;—3dly,
of the same in the ejections and alluviums of volcanoes;—4thly, in
alluviums generally, and in the ruins of landslips;—5thly, in the mud
and stalagmite of caves and fissures.
Growth of Peat, and Preservation of Vegetable and Animal Remains
therein.
The generation of peat, when not completely under water, is confined
to moist situations, where the temperature is low, and where vegetables
may decompose without putrefying. It may consist of any of the
numerous plants which are capable of growing in such stations; but a
species of moss (Sphagnum) constitutes a considerable part of the peat
found in marshes of the north of Europe; this plant having the property
of throwing up new shoots in its upper part, while its lower
extremities are decaying.1003 Reeds, rushes, and other aquatic plants
may usually be traced in peat; and their organization is often so entire
that there is no difficulty in discriminating the distinct species.
719
Analysis of peat.—In general, says Sir H. Davy, one hundred parts
of dry peat contain from sixty to ninety-nine parts of matter destructible
by fire; and the residuum consists of earths usually of the same
kind as the substratum of clay, marl, gravel, or rock, on which they are
found, together with oxide of iron. "The peat of the chalk counties
of England," observes the same writer, "contains much gypsum: but I
have found very little in any specimens from Ireland or Scotland, and
in general these peats contain very little saline matter."1004 From the
researches of Dr. MacCulloch, it appears that peat is intermediate
between simple vegetable matter and lignite, the conversion of peat to
lignite being gradual, and being brought about by a prolonged action
of water.1005
Peat abundant in cold and humid climates.—Peat is sometimes
formed on a declivity in mountainous regions, where there is much
moisture; but in such situations it rarely, if ever, exceeds four feet in
thickness. In bogs, and in low grounds into which alluvial peat is
drifted, it is found forty feet thick, and upwards; but in such cases it
generally owes one half of its volume to the water which it contains.
It has seldom, if ever, been discovered within the tropics; and it rarely
occurs in the valleys, even in the south of France and Spain. It
abounds more and more, in proportion as we advance farther from the
equator, and becomes not only more frequent but more inflammable in
northern latitudes.1006
The same phenomenon is repeated in the southern hemisphere. No
peat is found in Brazil, nor even in the swampy parts of the country
drained by the La Plata on the east side of South America, or in the
island of Chiloe on the west; yet when we reach the 45th degree of
latitude and examine the Chonos Archipelago or the Falkland Islands,
and Tierra del Fuego, we meet with an abundant growth of this substance.
Almost all plants contribute here by their decay to the production
of peat, even the grasses; but it is a singular fact, says Mr.
Darwin, as contrasted with what occurs in Europe, that no kind of
moss enters into the composition of the South American peat, which
is formed by many plants, but chiefly by that called by Brown Astelia
pumila.1007
I learn from Dr. Forchhammer (1849) that water charged with vegetable
matter in solution does not throw down a deposit of peat in
countries where the mean temperature of the year is above 43° or 44°
Fahrenheit. Frost causes the precipitation of such peaty matter, but
in warm climates the attraction of the carbon for the oxygen of the air
mechanically mixed with the water increases with the increasing temperature,
and the dissolved vegetable matter or humic acid (which is
organic matter in a progressive state of decomposition) being converted
into carbonic acid, rises and is absorbed into the atmosphere, and thus
disappears.
720
Extent of surface covered by peat.—There is a vast extent of surface
in Europe covered with peat, which, in Ireland, is said to extend over a
tenth of the whole island. One of the mosses on the Shannon is
described as being fifty miles long, by two or three broad; and the great
marsh of Montoire, near the mouth of the Loire, is mentioned, by
Blavier, as being more than fifty leagues in circumference. It is a
curious and well-ascertained fact, that many of these mosses of the north
of Europe occupy the place of forests of pine and oak, which have, many
of them, disappeared within the historical era. Such changes are
brought about by the fall of trees and the stagnation of water, caused
by their trunks and branches obstructing the free drainage of the
atmospheric waters, and giving rise to a marsh. In a warm climate,
such decayed timber would immediately be removed by insects, or by
putrefaction; but, in the cold temperature now prevailing in our
latitudes, many examples are recorded of marshes originating in this
source. Thus, in Mar forest, in Aberdeenshire, large trunks of Scotch
fir, which had fallen from age and decay, were soon immured in peat,
formed partly out of their perishing leaves and branches, and in part
from the growth of other plants. We also learn, that the overthrow of
a forest by a storm, about the middle of the seventeenth century, gave
rise to a peat-moss near Lochbroom, in Ross-shire, where, in less than
half a century after the fall of the trees, the inhabitants dug peat.1008 Dr.
Walker mentions a similar change, when, in the year 1756, the whole
wood of Drumlaurig in Dumfries-shire was overset by the wind. Such
events explain the occurrence, both in Britain and on the Continent, of
mosses where the trees are all broken within two or three feet of the
original surface, and where their trunks all lie in the same direction.1009
It may however be suggested in these cases, that the soil had become
exhausted for trees, and that, on the principle of that natural rotation
which prevails in the vegetable world, one set of plants died out and
another succeeded. It is certainly a remarkable fact that in the
Danish islands, and in Jutland and Holstein, fir wood of various species,
especially Scotch fir, is found at the bottom of the peat-mosses, although
it is well ascertained that for the last five centuries no Coniferæ have
grown wild in these countries; the coniferous trees which now flourish
there having been all planted towards the close of the last century.
Nothing is more common than the occurrence of buried trees at the
bottom of the Irish peat-mosses, as also in most of those of England,
France, and Holland; and they have been so often observed with parts
of their trunks standing erect, and with their roots fixed to the subsoil,
that no doubt can be entertained of their having generally grown on
the spot. They consist, for the most part, of the fir, the oak, and the
birch: where the subsoil is clay, the remains of oak are the most abundant;
where sand is the substratum, fir prevails. In the marsh of
Curragh, in the Isle of Man, vast trees are discovered standing firm on
721
their roots, though at the depth of eighteen or twenty feet below the
surface. Some naturalists have desired to refer the imbedding of timber
in peat-mosses to aqueous transportation, since rivers are well known
to float wood into lakes; but the facts above mentioned show that, in
numerous instances, such an hypothesis is inadmissible. It has, moreover,
been observed, that in Scotland, as also in many parts of the Continent,
the largest trees are found in those peat-mosses which lie in the
least elevated regions, and that the trees are proportionally smaller in
those which lie at higher levels; from which fact De Luc and Walker
have both inferred that the trees grew on the spot, for they would
naturally attain a greater size in lower and warmer levels. The leaves,
also, and fruits of each species, are continually found immersed in the
moss along with the parent trees; as, for example, the leaves and acorns
of the oak, the cones and leaves of the fir, and the nuts of the hazel.
Recent origin of some peat-mosses.—In Hatfield moss, in Yorkshire,
which appears clearly to have been a forest eighteen hundred years
ago, fir-trees have been found ninety feet long, and sold for masts and
keels of ships; oaks have also been discovered there above one hundred
feet long. The dimensions of an oak from this moss are given in the
Philosophical Transactions, No. 275, which must have been larger than
any tree now existing in the British dominions.
In the same moss of Hatfield, as well as in that of Kincardine, in
Scotland, and several others, Roman roads have been found covered to the
depth of eight feet by peat. All the coins, axes, arms, and other utensils
found in British and French mosses, are also Roman; so that a
considerable portion of the peat in European peat-bogs is evidently not
more ancient than the age of Julius Cæsar. Nor can any vestiges of
the ancient forests described by that general, along the line of the great
Roman way in Britain, be discovered, except in the ruined trunks of
trees in peat.
De Luc ascertained that the very sites of the aboriginal forests of Hercinia,
Semana, Ardennes, and several others, are now occupied by mosses
and fens; and a great part of these changes have, with much probability,
been attributed to the strict orders given by Severus, and other emperors,
to destroy all the wood in the conquered provinces. Several of the
British forests, however, which are now mosses, were cut at different
periods, by order of the English parliament, because they harbored wolves
or outlaws. Thus the Welsh woods were cut and burned, in the reign
of Edward I.; as were many of those in Ireland, by Henry II., to prevent
the natives from harboring in them, and harassing his troops.
It is curious to reflect that considerable tracts have, by these accidents,
been permanently sterilized, and that, during a period when civilization
has been making great progress, large areas in Europe have, by
human agency, been rendered less capable of administering to the
wants of man. Rennie observes,1010 with truth, that in those regions
722
alone which the Roman eagle never reached—in the remote circles of
the German empire, in Poland and Prussia, and still more in Norway,
Sweden, and the vast empire of Russia—can we see what Europe was
before it yielded to the power of Rome. Desolation now reigns where
stately forests of pine and oak once flourished, such as might now have
supplied all the navies of Europe with timber.
Sources of bog iron-ore.—At the bottom of peat-mosses there is
sometimes found a cake, or "pan," as it is termed, of oxide of iron,
and the frequency of bog iron-ore is familiar to the mineralogist. The
oak, which is so often dyed black in peat, owes its color to the same
metal. From what source the iron is derived has often been a subject
of discussion, until the discoveries of Ehrenberg seem at length to
have removed the difficulty. He had observed in the marshes about
Berlin a substance of a deep ochre yellow passing into red, which
covered the bottom of the ditches, and which, where it had become dry
after the evaporation of the water, appeared exactly

Fig. 101.
Gaillonella ferruginea.
a. 2000 times magnified.

like oxide of iron. But under the microscope it was
found to consist of slender articulated threads or
plates, partly siliceous and partly ferruginous, of
what he considered an animalcule, Gaillonella ferruginea,
but which most naturalists now regard as
a plant.1011 There can be little doubt, therefore, that
bog iron-ore consists of an aggregate of millions of these organic bodies
invisible to the naked eye.1012
Preservation of animal substances in peat.—One interesting circumstance
attending the history of peat mosses is the high state of preservation
of animal substances buried in them for periods of many years.
In June, 1747, the body of a woman was found six feet deep, in a peat-moor
in the Isle of Axholm, in Lincolnshire. The antique sandals on
her feet afforded evidence of her having been buried there for many ages:
yet her nails, hair, and skin, are described as having shown hardly any
marks of decay. On the estate of the Earl of Moira, in Ireland, a human
body was dug up, a foot deep in gravel, covered with eleven feet of
moss; the body was completely clothed and the garments seemed all to
be made of hair. Before the use of wool was known in that country
the clothing of the inhabitants was made of hair, so that it would appear
that this body had been buried at that early period; yet it was fresh and
unimpaired.1013 In the Philosophical Transactions we find an example
recorded of the bodies of two persons having been buried in moist peat,
in Derbyshire, in 1674, about a yard deep, which were examined twenty-eight
years and nine months afterwards; "the color of their skin was
fair and natural, their flesh soft as that of persons newly dead."1014
Among other analogous facts we may mention, that in digging a pit
723
for a well near Dulverton, in Somersetshire, many pigs were found in
various postures, still entire. Their shape was well preserved, the skin,
which retained the hair, having assumed a dry, membranous appearance.
Their whole substance was converted into a white, friable, laminated,
inodorous, and tasteless substance; but which, when exposed to heat,
emitted an odor precisely similar to broiled bacon.1015
Cause of the antiseptic property of peat.—We naturally ask whence
peat derives this antiseptic property? It has been attributed by some to
the carbonic and gallic acids which issue from decayed wood, as also to
the presence of charred wood in the lowest strata of many peat-mosses,
for charcoal is a powerful antiseptic, and capable of purifying water
already putrid. Vegetable gums and resins also may operate in the
same way.1016
The tannin occasionally present in peat is the produce, says Dr. MacCulloch,
of tormentilla, and some other plants; but the quantity he
thinks too small, and its occurrence too casual, to give rise to effects of
any importance. He hints that the soft parts of animal bodies, preserved
in peat-bogs, may have been converted into adipocire by the action of
water merely; an explanation which appears clearly applicable to some
of the cases above enumerated.1017
Miring of quadrupeds.—The manner, however, in which peat contributes
to preserve, for indefinite periods, the harder parts of terrestrial
animals, is a subject of more immediate interest to the geologist. There
are two ways in which animals become occasionally buried in the peat
of marshy grounds; they either sink down into the semifluid mud, underlying
a turfy surface upon which they have rashly ventured, or, at
other times, as we shall see in the sequel, a bog "bursts," and animals
may be involved in the peaty alluvium.
In the extensive bogs of Newfoundland, cattle are sometimes found
buried with only their heads and necks above ground; and after having
remained for days in this situation, they have been drawn out by ropes
and saved. In Scotland, also, cattle venturing on the "quaking moss"
are often mired, or "laired," as it is termed; and in Ireland, Mr. King
asserts that the number of cattle which are lost in sloughs is quite
incredible.1018
Solway moss.—The description given of the Solway moss will serve
to illustrate the general character of these boggy grounds. That moss,
observes Gilpin, is a flat area, about seven miles in circumference, situated
on the western confines of England and Scotland. Its surface is covered
with grass and rushes, presenting a dry crust and a fair appearance;
but it shakes under the least pressure, the bottom being unsound and
semifluid. The adventurous passenger, therefore, who sometimes in dry
seasons traverses this perilous waste, to save a few miles, picks his cautious
way over the rushy tussocks as they appear before him, for here the soil
724
is firmest. If his foot slip, or if he venture to desert this mark of security,
it is possible he may never more be heard of.
"At the battle of Solway, in the time of Henry VIII. (1542), when
the Scotch army, commanded by Oliver Sinclair, was routed, an unfortunate
troop of horse, driven by their fears, plunged into this morass, which
instantly closed upon them. The tale was traditional, but it is now
authenticated; a man and horse, in complete armor, having been
found by peat-diggers, in the place where it was always supposed the
affair had happened. The skeleton of each was well preserved, and the
different parts of the armor easily distinguished."1019
The same moss, on the 16th of December, 1772, having been filled
like a great sponge with water during heavy rains, swelled to an unusual
height above the surrounding country, and then burst. The turfy covering
seemed for a time to act like the skin of a bladder retaining the
fluid within, till it forced a passage for itself, when a stream of black
half-consolidated mud began at first to creep over the plain, resembling,
in the rate of its progress, an ordinary lava-current. No lives were lost,
but the deluge totally overwhelmed some cottages, and covered 400 acres.
The highest parts of the original moss subsided to the depth of about
twenty-five feet; and the height of the moss, on the lowest parts of the
country which it invaded, was at least fifteen feet.
Bursting of a peat-moss in Ireland.—A recent inundation in Sligo
(January, 1831), affords another example of this phenomenon. After a
sudden thaw of snow, the bog between Bloomfield and Geevah gave way;
and a black deluge, carrying with it the contents of a hundred acres of
bog, took the direction of a small stream and rolled on with the violence
of a torrent, sweeping along heath, timber, mud, and stones, and overwhelming
many meadows and arable land. On passing through some
boggy land, the flood swept out a wide and deep ravine, and part of the
road leading from Bloomfield to St. James's Well was completely
carried away from below the foundation for the breadth of 200 yards.
Great Dismal Swamp.—I have described, in my Travels in North
America,1020 an extensive swamp or morass, forty miles long from north
to south, and twenty-five wide, between the towns of Norfolk in Virginia,
and Weldon in North Carolina. It is called the "Great Dismal," and
has somewhat the appearance of an inundated river-plain covered with
aquatic trees and shrubs, the soil being as black as that of a peat bog.
It is higher on all sides except one than the surrounding country, towards
which it sends forth streams of water to the north, east, and south, receiving
a supply from the west only. In its centre it rises 12 feet above
the flat region which bounds it. The soil, to the depth of 15 feet, is
formed of vegetable matter without any admixture, of earthy particles,
and offers an exception to a general rule before alluded to, namely, that
such peaty accumulations scarcely ever occur so far south as lat. 36°, or
in any region where the summer heat is so great as in Virginia. In digging
725
canals through the morass for the purpose of obtaining timber,
much of the black soil has been thrown out from time to time, and exposed
to the sun and air, in which case it soon rots away so that
nothing remains behind, showing clearly that it owes its preservation to
the shade afforded by a luxuriant vegetation and to the constant evaporation
of the spongy soil by which the air is cooled during the hot
months. The surface of the bog is carpeted with mosses, and densely
covered with ferns and reeds, above which many evergreen shrubs and
trees flourish, especially the White Cedar (Cupressus thyoides), which
stands firmly supported by its long tap roots in the softest parts of the
quagmire. Over the whole the deciduous cypress (Taxodium distichum)
is seen to tower with its spreading top, in full leaf in the season when
the sun's rays are hottest, and when, if not intercepted by a screen of
foliage, they might soon cause the fallen leaves and dead plants of the
preceding autumn to decompose, instead of adding their contributions to
the peaty mass. On the surface of the wide morass lie innumerable trunks
of large and tall trees, while thousands of others, blown down by the
winds, are buried at various depths in the black mire below. They remind
the geologist of the prostrate position of large stems of Sigillaria
and Lepidodendron, converted into coal in ancient carboniferous rocks.
Bones of herbivorous quadrupeds in peat.—The antlers of large and
full-grown stags are amongst the most common and conspicuous remains
of animals in peat. They are not horns which have been shed; for
portions of the skull are found attached, proving that the whole animal
perished. Bones of the ox, hog, horse, sheep, and other herbivorous
animals, also occur. M. Morren has discovered in the peat of Flanders
the bones of otters and beavers1021; but no remains have been met with
belonging to those extinct quadrupeds, of which the living congeners
inhabit warmer latitudes, such as the elephant, rhinoceros, hippopotamus,
hyæna, and tiger, though these are so common in superficial
deposits of silt, mud, sand, or stalactite, in various districts throughout
Great Britain. Their absence seems to imply that they had ceased to
live before the atmosphere of this part of the world acquired that cold
and humid character which favors the growth of peat.
Remains of ships, &c., in peat mosses.—From the facts before mentioned,
that mosses occasionally burst, and descend in a fluid state to
lower levels, it will readily be seen that lakes and arms of the sea may
occasionally become the receptacles of drift peat. Of this, accordingly,
there are numerous examples; and hence the alternations of clay and
sand with different deposits of peat so frequent on some coasts, as on
those of the Baltic and German Ocean. We are informed by Deguer,
that remains of ships, nautical instruments, and oars, have been found
in many of the Dutch mosses; and Gerard, in his History of the Valley
of the Somme, mentions that in the lowest tier of that moss was found
a boat loaded with bricks, proving that these mosses were at one period
726
navigable lakes and arms of the sea, as were also many mosses on the
coast of Picardy, Zealand, and Friesland, from which soda and salt are
procured.1022 The canoes, stone hatchets, and stone arrow-heads found
in peat in different parts of Great Britain, lead to similar conclusions.
Imbedding of human and other remains, and works of Art, in
Blown Sand.
The drifting of sand may next be considered among the causes
capable of preserving organic remains and works of art on the emerged
land.
African Sands.—The sands of the African deserts have been driven
by the west winds over part of the arable land of Egypt, on the western
bank of the Nile, in those places where valleys open into the plain,
or where there are gorges through the Libyan mountains. By similar
sand-drifts the ruins of ancient cities have been buried between the
temple of Jupiter Ammon and Nubia. M. G. A. De Luc attempted to
infer the recent origin of our continents, from the fact that these moving
sands have arrived only in modern times at the fertile plains of the Nile.
The same scourge, he said, would have afflicted Egypt for ages anterior
to the times of history, had the continents risen above the level of the
sea several hundred centuries before our era.1023 But the author proceeded
in this, as in all his other chronological computations, on a multitude of
gratuitous assumptions. He ought, in the first place, to have demonstrated
that the whole continent of Africa was raised above the level of
the sea at one period; for unless this point was established, the region
from whence the sands began to move might have been the last addition
made to Africa, and the commencement of the sand-flood might have
been long posterior to the laying dry of the greater portion of that continent.
That the different parts of Europe were not all elevated at one
time is now generally admitted. De Luc should also have pointed out
the depth of drift sand in various parts of the great Libyan deserts, and
have shown whether any valleys of large dimensions had been filled up—how
long these may have arrested the progress of the sands, and how far
the flood had upon the whole advanced since the times of history.
We have seen that Sir J. G. Wilkinson is of opinion that, while the
sand-drift is making aggressions at certain points upon the fertile soil of
Egypt, the alluvial deposit of the Nile is advancing very generally upon
the desert; and that, upon the whole, the balance is greatly in favor of
the fertilizing mud.1024
No mode of interment can be conceived, more favorable to the conservation
of monuments for indefinite periods than that now so common in
the region immediately westward of the Nile. The sand which surrounded
and filled the great temple of Ipsambul, first discovered by
727
Burckhardt, and afterwards partially uncovered by Belzoni and Beechey,
was so fine as to resemble a fluid when put in motion. Neither the
features of the colossal figures, nor the color of the stucco with which
some were covered, nor the paintings on the walls, had received any
injury from being enveloped for ages in this dry impalpable dust.1025
At some future period, perhaps when the pyramids shall have perished,
the action of the sea, or an earthquake, may lay open to the day some of
these buried temples. Or we may suppose the desert to remain undisturbed,
and changes in the surrounding sea and land to modify the
climate and the direction of the prevailing winds, so that these may then
waft away the Libyan sands as gradually as they once brought them to
those regions. Thus, many a town and temple of higher antiquity than
Thebes or Memphis may reappear in their original antiquity, and a
part of the gloom which overhangs the history of the earlier nations be
dispelled.
Whole caravans are said to have been overwhelmed by the Libyan
sands; and Burckhardt informs us that "after passing the Akaba near
the head of the Red Sea, the bones of dead camels are the only guides of
the pilgrim through the wastes of sand."—"We did not see," says Captain
Lyon, speaking of a plain near the Soudah mountains, in Northern
Africa, "the least appearance of vegetation; but observed many skeletons
of animals, which had died of fatigue on the desert, and occasionally
the grave of some human being. All these bodies were so dried by the
heat of the sun, that putrefaction appears not to have taken place after
death. In recently expired animals I could not perceive the slightest
offensive smell; and in those long dead, the skin with the hair on it
remained unbroken and perfect, although so brittle as to break with a
slight blow. The sand-winds never cause these carcases to change their
places; for, in a short time, a slight mound is formed round them, and
they become stationary."1026
Towns overwhelmed by sand floods.—The burying of several towns and
villages in England, France, and Jutland, by blown sand, is on record;
thus, for example, near St. Pol de Leon, in Brittany, a whole village was
completely buried beneath drift sand, so that nothing was seen but the
spire of the church.1027 In Jutland marine shells adhering to sea-weed are
sometimes blown by the violence of the wind to the height of 100 feet,
and buried in similar hills of sand.
In Suffolk, in the year 1688, part of Downham was overwhelmed by
sands which had broken loose about 100 years before, from a warren
five miles to the south-west. This sand had, in the course of a century,
travelled five miles, and covered more than 1000 acres of land.1028 A considerable
tract of cultivated land on the north coast of Cornwall has been
inundated by drift sand, forming hills several hundred feet above the
728
level of the sea, and composed of comminuted marine shells, in which some
terrestrial shells are enclosed entire. By the shifting of these sands the
ruins of ancient buildings have been discovered; and in some cases where
wells have been bored to a great depth, distinct strata, separated by a
vegetable crust, are visible. In some places, as at New Quay, large masses
have become sufficiently indurated to be used for architectural purposes.
The lapidification, which is still in progress, appears to be due to oxide of
iron held in solution by the water which percolates the sand.1029
Imbedding of Organic and other Remains in Volcanic Formations on
the Land.
I have in some degree anticipated the subject of this section in former
chapters, when speaking of the buried cities around Naples, and those
on the flanks of Etna (pp. 385. 400.). From the facts referred to, it
appeared that the preservation of human remains and works of art is
frequently due to the descent of floods caused by the copious rains which
accompany eruptions. These aqueous lavas, as they are called in Campania,
flow with great rapidity, and in 1822 surprised and suffocated, as
was stated, seven persons in the villages of St. Sebastian and Massa, on
the flanks of Vesuvius.
In the tuffs, moreover, or solidified mud, deposited by these aqueous
lavas, impressions of leaves and of trees have been observed. Some of
those, formed after the eruption of Vesuvius in 1822, are now preserved
in the museum at Naples.
Lava itself may become indirectly the means of preserving terrestrial
remains, by overflowing beds of ashes, pumice, and ejected matter, which
may have been showered down upon animals and plants, or upon human
remains. Few substances are better non-conductors of heat than volcanic
dust and scoriæ, so that a bed of such materials is rarely melted by a
superimposed lava-current. After consolidation, the lava affords secure
protection to the lighter and more removable mass below, in which the
organic relics may be enveloped. The Herculanean tuffs containing the
rolls of papyrus, of which the characters are still legible, have, as was
before remarked, been for ages covered by lava.
Another mode by which lava may tend to the conservation of imbedded
remains, at least of works of human art, is by its overflowing them when
it is not intensely heated, in which case they sometimes suffer little or no
injury.
Thus when the Etnean lava-current of 1669 covered fourteen towns
and villages, and part of the city of Catania, it did not melt down a great
number of statues and other articles in the vaults of Catania; and at the
depth of thirty-five feet in the same current, on the site of Mompiliere, one
of the buried towns, the bell of a church and some statues were found
uninjured (p. 401.).
729
We read of several buried cities in Central India, and among others
of Oujein (or Oojain) which about fifty years before the Christian era
was the seat of empire, of art, and of learning; but which in the time
of the Rajah Vicramaditya, was overwhelmed, according to tradition,
together with more than eighty other large towns in the provinces of
Malwa and Bagur, "by a shower of earth." The city which now bears
the name is situated a mile to the southward of the ancient town. On
digging on the spot where the latter is supposed to have stood, to the
depth of fifteen or eighteen feet, there are frequently discovered, says Mr.
Hunter, entire brick walls, pillars of stone, and pieces of wood of an
extraordinary hardness, besides utensils of various kinds, ancient coins,
and occasionally buried wheat in a state resembling charcoal.1030
The soil which covers Oujein is described as "being of an ash-gray
color, with minute specks of black sand."1031 And the "shower of earth,"
said to have "fallen from heaven," has been attributed by some travellers
to volcanic agency. There are, however, no active volcanoes in Central
India, the nearest to Oujein being Denodur hill near Bhooj, the capital
of Cutch, 300 geographical miles distant, if indeed that hill has ever
poured out lava in historical times, which is doubted by many.1032 The
latest writers on Oujein avow their suspicion that the supposed "catastrophe"
was nothing more than the political decline and final abandonment
of a great city which, like Nineveh or Babylon, and many an
ancient seat of empire in the East, after losing its importance as a metropolis,
became a heap of ruins. The rapidity with which the sun-dried
bricks, of which even the most splendid oriental palaces are often constructed,
crumble down when exposed to rain and sun, and are converted
into mounds of ordinary earth and clay, is well known. According to
Captain Dangerfield, trap tuff and columnar basalt constitute the rocks
in the environs of Oujein1033, and the volcanic nature of these formations,
from which the materials of the bricks were originally derived, may
have led to the idea of the city having been overwhelmed by a volcanic
eruption.

730</div></body></text></TEI>