<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="27">CHAPTER XXVII.
EARTHQUAKES AND THEIR EFFECTS.
Earthquakes and their effects—Deficiency of ancient accounts—Ordinary atmospheric
phenomena—Changes produced by earthquakes in modern times considered
in chronological order—Earthquake in Syria, 1837—Earthquakes in Chili
in 1837 and 1835—Isle of Santa Maria raised ten feet—Chili, 1822—Extent of
country elevated—Aleppo and Ionian Isles—Earthquake of Cutch in 1819—Subsidence
in the Delta of the Indus—Island of Sumbawa in 1815—Earthquake
of Caraccas in 1812—Shocks at New Madrid in 1811 in the valley of the Mississippi—Aleutian
Islands in 1806—Reflections on the earthquakes of the nineteenth
century—Earthquake in Quito, Quebec, &c.—Java, 1786—Sinking down
of large tracts.
In the sketch before given of the geographical boundaries of volcanic
regions, I stated, that although the points of eruption are but thinly
scattered, constituting mere spots on the surface of those vast districts,
yet the subterranean movements extend simultaneously over immense
areas. We may now proceed to consider the changes which these
movements produce on the surface, and in the internal structure of the
earth's crust.
452
Deficiency of ancient accounts.—It is only within the last century and
a half, since Hooke first promulgated, in 1688, his views respecting the
connection between geological phenomena and earthquakes, that the
permanent changes affected by these convulsions have excited attention.
Before that time, the narrative of the historian was almost exclusively
confined to the number of human beings who perished, the number of
cities laid in ruins, the value of property destroyed, or certain atmospheric
appearances which dazzled or terrified the observers. The creation
of a new lake, the engulfing of a new city, or the raising of a new
island, are sometimes, it is true, adverted to, as being too obvious, or of
too much geographical or political interest to be passed over in silence.
But no researches were made expressly with a view of ascertaining the
amount of depression or elevation of the ground, or any particular alterations
in the relative position of sea and land; and very little distinction
was made between the raising of soil by volcanic ejections, and the upheaving
of it by forces acting from below. The same remark applies to
a very large proportion of modern accounts: and how much reason we
have to regret this deficiency of information appears from this, that in
every instance where a spirit of scientific inquiry has animated the eyewitnesses
of these events, facts calculated to throw light on former modifications
of the earth's structure are recorded.
Phenomena attending earthquakes.—As I shall confine myself almost
entirely, in the following notice of earthquakes, to the changes brought
about by them in the configuration of the earth's crust, I may mention,
generally, some accompaniments of these terrible events which are
almost uniformly commemorated in history, that it may be unnecessary
to advert to them again. Irregularities in the seasons preceding or following
the shocks; sudden gusts of wind, interrupted by dead calms;
violent rains at unusual seasons, or in countries where such phenomena
are almost unknown; a reddening of the sun's disk, and a haziness in
the air, often continued for months; an evolution of electric matter, or
of inflammable gas from the soil, with sulphurous and mephitic vapors;
noises underground, like the running of carriages, or the discharge of
artillery, or distant thunder; animals uttering cries of distress, and
evincing extraordinary alarm, being more sensitive than men of the
slightest movement; a sensation like sea-sickness, and a dizziness in the
head, experienced by men:—these, and other phenomena, less connected
with our present subject as geologists, have recurred again and
again at distant ages, and in all parts of the globe.
I shall now begin the enumeration of earthquakes with the latest
authentic narratives, and so carry back the survey retrospectively, that
I may bring before the reader, in the first place, the minute and circumstantial
details of modern times, and thus enable him, by observing the
extraordinary amount of change within the last 150 years, to perceive
how great must be the deficiency in the meager annals of earlier eras.
453
EARTHQUAKES OF THE NINETEENTH CENTURY.622
Syria, January, 1837.—It has been remarked that earthquakes
affect elongated areas. The violent shock which devastated Syria in
1837 was felt on a line 500 miles in length by 90 in breadth:623 more
than 6000 persons perished; deep rents were caused in solid rocks, and
new hot springs burst out at Tabereah.
Chili—Valdivia, 1837.—One of the latest earthquakes by which the
position of solid land is known to have been permanently altered is that
which occurred in Chili, on November 7th, 1837. On that day Valdivia
was destroyed by an earthquake, and a whaler, commanded by Captain
Coste, was violently shaken at sea, and lost her masts, in lat. 43° 38' S.
in sight of the land. The captain went on the 11th of December following
to a spot near the island of Lemus, one of the Chonos archipelago,
where he had anchored two years before, and found that the bottom of
the sea had been raised more than eight feet. Some rocks formerly
covered at all times by the sea were now constantly exposed, and an
enormous quantity of shells and fish in a decaying state, which had been
thrown there by the waves, or suddenly laid dry during the earthquake,
attested the recent date of the occurrence. The whole coast was strewed
with uprooted trees.624
Chili—Conception, 1835.—Fortunately we have a still more detailed
account of the geographical changes produced in the same country on
the 20th of February, 1835. An earthquake was then felt at all places
between Copiapo and Chiloe, from north to south, and from Mendoza
to Juan Fernandez, from east to west. "Vessels," says Mr. Caldcleugh,
"navigating the Pacific, within 100 miles of the coast, experienced the
shock with considerable force."625 Conception, Talcahuano, Chillan, and
other towns were thrown down. From the account of Captain Fitz Roy,
R. N., who was then employed in surveying the coast, we learn that after
the shock the sea retired in the Bay of Conception, and the vessels
grounded, even those which had been lying in seven fathoms water: all
the shoals were visible, and soon afterwards a wave rushed in and then
retreated, and was followed by two other waves. The vertical height of
these waves does not appear to have been much greater than from sixteen
to twenty feet, although they rose to much greater heights when
they broke upon a sloping beach.
Fig. 69.

According to Mr. Caldcleugh and Mr. Darwin, the whole volcanic
454
chain of the Chilian Andes, a range 150 miles in length, was in a state
of unusual activity, both during the shocks and for some time preceding
and after the convulsion, and lava was seen to flow from the crater of
Osorno. (See Map, fig. 69.) The island of Juan Fernandez, distant
365 geographical miles from Chili, was violently shaken at the same
time, and devastated by a great wave. A submarine volcano broke out
455
there near Bacalao Head, about a mile from the shore, in sixty-nine
fathoms water, and illumined the whole island during the night.626
"At Conception," says Captain Fitz Roy, "the earth opened and
closed rapidly in numerous places. The direction of the cracks was not
uniform, though generally from southeast to northwest. The earth was
not quiet for three days after the great shock, and more than 300
shocks were counted between the 20th February and the 4th of March.
The loose earth of the valley of the Biobio was everywhere parted from
the solid rocks which bound the plain, there being an opening between
them from an inch to a foot in width.
Fig. 70.

"For some days after the 20th of February, the sea at Talcahuano,"
says Captain Fitz Roy, "did not rise to the usual marks by four or five
feet vertically. When walking on the shore, even at high water, beds
of dead mussels, numerous chitons, and limpets, and withered seaweed,
still adhering, though lifeless, to the rocks on which they had
lived, everywhere met the eye." But this difference in the relative level
of the land and sea gradually diminished, till in the middle of April the
water rose again to within two feet of the former high-water mark. It
might be supposed that these changes of level merely indicated a temporary
disturbance in the set of the currents or in the height of the tides
at Talcahuano; but, on considering what occurred in the neighboring
island of Santa Maria, Captain Fitz Roy concluded that the land had
456
been raised four or five feet in February, and that it had returned in
April to within two or three feet of its former level.
Santa Maria, the island just alluded to, is about seven miles long and
two broad, and about twenty-five miles southwest of Conception. (See
Map, fig. 70.) The phenomena observed there are most important. "It
appeared," says Captain Fitz Roy, who visited Santa Maria twice, the
first time at the end of March, and afterwards in the beginning of April,
"that the southern extremity of the island had been raised eight feet,
the middle nine, and the northern end upwards of ten feet. On steep
rocks, where vertical measures could be correctly taken, beds of dead
mussels were found ten feet above high-water mark. One foot lower
than the highest bed of mussels, a few limpets and chitons were seen
adhering to the rock where they had grown. Two feet lower than the
same, dead mussels, chitons, and limpets were abundant.
"An extensive rocky flat lies around the northern parts of Santa
Maria. Before the earthquake this flat was covered by the sea, some
projecting rocks only showing themselves. Now, the whole flat is exposed,
and square acres of it are covered with dead shell-fish, the stench
arising from which is abominable. By this elevation of the land the
southern port of Santa Maria has been almost destroyed; little shelter
remaining there, and very bad landing." The surrounding sea is also
stated to have become shallower in exactly the same proportion as the
land had risen; the soundings having diminished a fathom and a half
everywhere around the island.
At Tubal, also, to the southeast of Santa Maria, the land was raised six
feet, at Mocha two feet, but no elevation could be ascertained at Valdivia.
Among other effects of the catastrophe, it is stated that cattle standing
on a steep slope, near the shore, were rolled down into the sea, and
many others were washed off by the great wave from low land and
drowned.627
In November of the same year (1835), Conception was shaken by
a severe earthquake, and on the same day Osorno, at the distance of
400 miles, renewed its activity. These facts prove not only the connection
of earthquakes with volcanic eruptions in this region, but also the
vast extent of the subterranean areas over which the disturbing cause
acts simultaneously.
Ischia, 1828.—On the 2d of February the whole island of Ischia
was shaken by an earthquake, and in the October following I found all
the houses in Casamicciol still without their roofs. On the sides of a
ravine between that town and Forio, I saw masses of greenish tuff
which had been thrown down. The hot-spring of Rita, which was
nearest the centre of the movement, was ascertained by M. Covelli to
have increased in temperature, showing, as he observes, that the explosion
took place below the reservoirs which heat the thermal waters.628
457
Bogota, 1827.—On the 16th of November, 1827, the plain of Bogota,
in New Granada, or Colombia, was convulsed by an earthquake, and a
great number of towns were thrown down. Torrents of rain swelled
the Magdalena, sweeping along vast quantities of mud and other substances,
which emitted a sulphurous vapor and destroyed the fish.
Popayan, which is distant 200 geographical miles S. S. W. of Bogota,
suffered greatly. Wide crevices appeared in the road of Guanacas,
leaving no doubt that the whole of the Cordilleras sustained a powerful
shock. Other fissures opened near Costa, in the plains of Bogota, into
which the river Tunza immediately began to flow.629 It is worthy of
remark, that in all such cases the ancient gravel bed of a river is deserted
and a new one formed at a lower level; so that a want of relation
in the position of alluvial beds of the existing water-courses may
be no test of the high antiquity of such deposits, at least in countries
habitually convulsed by earthquakes. Extraordinary rains accompanied
the shocks before mentioned; and two volcanoes are said to have been
in eruption in the mountain-chain nearest to Bogota.
Chili, 1822.—On the 19th of November, 1822, the coast of Chili
was visited by a most destructive earthquake. The shock was felt simultaneously
throughout a space of 1200 miles from north to south.
St. Jago, Valparaiso, and some other places, were greatly injured.
When the district round Valparaiso was examined on the morning after
the shock, it was found that the coast for a considerable distance was
raised above its former level.630 At Valparaiso the elevation was three
feet, and at Quintero about four feet. Part of the bed of the sea, says
Mrs. Graham, remained bare and dry at high water, "with beds of
oysters, mussels, and other shells adhering to the rocks on which they
grew, the fish being all dead, and exhaling most offensive effluvia.631
An old wreck of a ship, which before could not be approached,
became accessible from the land, although its distance from the original
sea-shore had not altered. It was observed that the water-course of a
mill, at the distance of about a mile from the sea, gained a fall of fourteen
inches, in little more than one hundred yards; and from this fact
it is inferred that the rise in some parts of the inland country was far
more considerable than on the borders of the ocean.632 Part of the coast
thus elevated consisted of granite, in which parallel fissures were caused,
some of which were traced for a mile and a half inland. Cones of earth
about four feet high were thrown up in several districts, by the forcing
up of water mixed with sand through funnel-shaped hollows,—a phenomenon
very common in Calabria, and the explanation of which will hereafter
be considered. Those houses in Chili of which the foundations
were on rock were less damaged than such as were built on alluvial
soil.
Mr. Cruickshanks, an English botanist, who resided in the country
458
during the earthquake, has informed me that some rocks of greenstone
at Quintero, a few hundred yards from the beach, which had always
been under water till the shock of 1822, have since been uncovered
when the tide is at half-ebb: and he states that, after the earthquake,
it was the general belief of the fishermen and inhabitants of the Chilian
coast, not that the land had risen, but that the ocean had permanently
retreated.
Dr. Meyen, a Prussian traveller, who visited Valparaiso in 1831, says
that on examining the rocks both north and south of the town, nine years
after the event, he found, in corroboration of Mrs. Graham's account,
that remains of animals and sea-weed, the Lessonia of Bory de St. Vincent,
which has a firm ligneous stem, still adhered to those rocks which
in 1822 had been elevated above high-water mark.633 According to the
same author, the whole coast of Central Chili was raised about four feet,
and banks of marine shells were laid dry on many parts of the coast.
He observed similar banks, elevated at unknown periods, in several
places, especially at Copiapo, where the species all agree with those now
living in the ocean. Mr. Freyer also, who resided some years in South
America, has confirmed these statements;634 and Mr. Darwin obtained
evidence that the remains of an ancient wall, formerly washed by the
sea, and now 11½ feet above high-water mark, acquired several feet of
this additional elevation during the earthquake of 1822.635
The shocks continued up to the end of September, 1823; even then,
forty-eight hours seldom passed without one, and sometimes two or
three were felt during twenty-four hours. Mrs. Graham observed, after
the earthquake of 1822, that besides a beach newly raised above highwater
mark, there were several older elevated lines of beach, one above
the other, consisting of shingle mixed with shells extending in a parallel
direction to the shore, to the height of fifty feet above the sea.636
Extent of country elevated.—By some observers it has been supposed
that the whole country from the foot of the Andes to a great distance
under the sea was upraised in 1822, the greatest rise being at the distance
of about two miles from the shore. "The rise upon the coast was
from two to four feet:—at the distance of a mile inland it must have
been from five to six or seven feet."637 It has also been conjectured by
the same eye-witnesses to the convulsion, that the area over which this
permanent alteration of level extended may have been equal to 100,000
square miles. Although the increased fall of certain water-courses may
have afforded some ground for this conjecture, it must be considered as
very hypothetical, and the estimate may have exceeded or greatly fallen
short of the truth. It may nevertheless be useful to reflect on the enormous
amount of change which this single convulsion occasioned, if the
459
extent of country moved upward really amounted to 100,000 square
miles,—an extent just equal to half the area of France, or about five-sixths
of the area of Great Britain and Ireland. If we suppose the
elevation to have been only three feet on an average, it will be seen that
the mass of rock added to the continent of America by the movement,
or, in other words, the mass previously below the level of the sea, and
after the shocks permanently above it, must have contained fifty-seven
cubic miles in bulk; which would be sufficient to form a conical mountain
two miles high (or about as high as Etna), with a circumference at
the base of nearly thirty-three miles. We may take the mean specific
gravity of the rock at 2·655,—a fair average, and a convenient one in
such computations, because at such a rate a cubic yard weighs two tons.
Then, assuming the great pyramid of Egypt, if solid, to weigh, in accordance
with an estimate before given, six million tons, we may state the
rock added to the continent by the Chilian earthquake to have more than
equalled 100,000 pyramids.
But it must always be borne in mind that the weight of rock here alluded
to constituted but an insignificant part of the whole amount which
the volcanic forces had to overcome. The whole thickness of rock between
the surface of Chili and the subterranean foci of volcanic action
may be many miles or leagues deep. Say that the thickness was only
two miles, even then the mass which changed place and rose three feet
being 200,000 cubic miles in volume, must have exceeded in weight
363 million pyramids.
It may be instructing to consider these results in connection with
others already obtained from a different source, and to compare the
working of two antagonistic forces—the levelling power of running
water, and the expansive energy of subterranean heat. How long, it
may be asked, would the Ganges require, according to data before explained
(p. 283), to transport to the sea a quantity of solid matter equal
to that which may have been added to the land by the Chilian earthquake?
The discharge of mud in one year by the Ganges was estimated
at 20,000 million cubic feet. According to that estimate it would
require about four centuries (or 418 years) before the river could bear
down from the continent into the sea a mass equal to that gained by the
Chilian earthquake. In about half that time, perhaps, the united waters
of the Ganges and Burrampooter might accomplish the operation.
Cutch, 1819.—A violent earthquake occurred at Cutch, in the delta
of the Indus, on the 16th of June, 1819. (See Map, fig. 71.) The
principal town, Bhooj, was converted into a heap of ruins, and its stone
buildings were thrown down. The movement was felt over an area
having a radius of 1000 miles from Bhooj, and extending to Kbatmandoo,
Calcutta, and Pondicherry.638 The vibrations were felt in Northwest
India, at a distance of 800 miles, after an interval of about fifteen
minutes after the earthquake at Bhooj. At Ahmedabad the great
460
mosque, erected by Sultan Ahmed nearly 450 years before, fell to the
ground, attesting how long a period had elapsed since a shock of similar
violence had visited that point. At Anjar, the fort, with its tower
and guns, was hurled to the ground in one common mass of ruin. The
shocks continued until the 20th; when, thirty miles northwest from
Bhooj, the volcano called Denodur is said by some to have sent forth
flames, but Capt. Grant was unable to authenticate this statement.
Fig. 71.

Subsidence in the delta of the Indus.—Although the ruin of towns was
great, the face of nature in the inland country, says Captain Macmurdo,
was not visibly altered. In the hills some large masses only of rock
and soil were detached from the precipices; but the eastern and almost
deserted channel of the Indus, which bounds the province of Cutch, was
greatly changed. This estuary, or inlet of the sea, was, before the
earthquake, fordable at Luckput, being only about a foot deep when
the tide was at ebb, and at flood-tide never more than six feet; but it
was deepened at the fort of Luckput, after the shock, to more than
eighteen feet at low water.639 On sounding other parts of the channel, it
was found, that where previously the depth of the water at flood never
exceeded one or two feet, it had become from four to ten feet deep.
By these and other remarkable changes of level, a part of the inland
navigation of that country, which had been closed for centuries, became
again practicable.
461
Fig. 72.
Fort of Sindree, on the eastern branch of the Indus, before it was submerged by the earthquake
of 1819, from a sketch of Capt. Grindlay, made in 1808.
Fort and village submerged.640—The fort and village of Sindree, on the
eastern arm of the Indus, above Luckput, are stated by the same writer
to have been overflowed; and, after the shock, the tops of the houses
and wall were alone to be seen above the water, for the houses, although
submerged, were not cast down. Had they been situated, therefore, in
the interior, where so many forts were levelled to the ground, their site
would, perhaps, have been regarded as having remained comparatively
unmoved. Hence we may suspect that great permanent upheavings
and depressions of soil may be the result of earthquakes, without the
inhabitants being in the least degree conscious of any change of level.
A more recent survey of Cutch, by Sir A. Burnes, who was not in
communication with Capt. Macmurdo, confirms the facts above enumerated,
and adds many important details.641 That officer examined the
delta of the Indus in 1826 and 1828, and from his account it appears
that, when Sindree subsided in June, 1819, the sea flowed in by the
eastern mouth of the Indus, and in a few hours converted a tract of
land, 2000 square miles in area, into an inland sea, or lagoon. Neither
the rush of the sea into this new depression, nor the movement of the
earthquake, threw down entirely the small fort of Sindree, one of the
four towers, the northwestern, still continuing to stand; and, the day after
the earthquake, the inhabitants who had ascended to the top of this
tower, saved themselves in boats.642
462
Elevation of the Ullah Bund.—Immediately after the shock, the inhabitants
of Sindree saw, at the distance of five miles and a half from
their village, a long elevated mound, where previously there had been a
low and perfectly level plain. (See Map, fig. 71.) To this uplifted
tract they gave the name of "Ullah Bund," or the "Mound of God,"
to distinguish it from several artificial dams previously thrown across
the eastern arm of the Indus.
Extent of country raised.—It has been ascertained that this new-raised
country is upwards of fifty miles in length from east to west,
running parallel to that line of subsidence before mentioned, which
caused the grounds around Sindree to be flooded. The range of this
elevation extends from Puchum Island towards Gharee; its breadth
from north to south is conjectured to be in some parts sixteen miles, and
its greatest ascertained height above the original level of the delta is
ten feet,—an elevation which appears to the eye to be very uniform
throughout.
For several years after the convulsion of 1819, the course of the Indus
was very unsettled, and at length, in 1826, the river threw a vast
body of water into its eastern arm, that called the Phurraun, above
Sindree; and forcing its way in a more direct course to the sea, burst
through all the artificial dams which had been thrown across its channel,
and at length cut right through the "Ullah Bund," whereby a
natural section was obtained. In the perpendicular cliffs thus laid open
Sir A. Burnes found that the upraised lands consisted of clay filled with
shells. The new channel of the river where it intersected the "bund"
was eighteen feet deep, and forty yards in width; but in 1828 the
channel was still farther enlarged. The Indus, when it first opened this
new passage, threw such a body of water into the new mere, or salt
lagoon, of Sindree, that it became fresh for many months; but it had
recovered its saltness in 1828, when the supply of river-water was less
copious, and finally it became more salt than the sea, in consequence, as
the natives suggested to Sir A. Burnes, of the saline particles with
which the "Runn of Cutch" is impregnated.
In 1828 Sir A. Burnes went in a boat to the ruins of Sindree, where
a single remaining tower was seen in the midst of a wide expanse of sea.
The tops of the ruined walls still rose two or three feet above the level
of the water; and standing on one of these, he could behold nothing in
the horizon but water, except in one direction, where a blue streak of
land to the north indicated the Ullah Bund. This scene presents to the
imagination a lively picture of the revolutions now in progress on the
earth—a waste of waters where a few years before all was land, and
the only land visible consisting of ground uplifted by a recent earthquake.
Ten years after the visit of Sir A. Burnes above alluded to, my friend,
Captain Grant, F. G. S., of the Bombay Engineers, had the kindness
to send at my request a native surveyor to make a plan of Sindree and
Ullah Bund, in March, 1838. From his description it appears that, at
463
that season, the driest of the whole year, he found the channel traversing
the Bund to be 100 yards wide, without water, and incrusted with
salt. He was told that it has now only four or five feet of water in it
after rains. The sides or banks were nearly perpendicular, and nine
feet in height. The lagoon has diminished both in area and depth, and
part near the fort was dry land. The annexed drawing, made by Captain
Grant from the surveyor's plan, shows the appearance of the fort
in the midst of the lake, as seen in 1838 from the west, or from the
same point as that from which Captain Grindlay's sketch (see fig. 72)
was taken in 1808, before the earthquake.
Fig. 73.
View of the Fort of Sindree, from the west, in March, 1838.
The Runn of Cutch is a flat region of a very peculiar character, and no
less than 7000 square miles in area: a greater superficial extent than
Yorkshire, or about one-fourth the area of Ireland. It is not a desert
of moving sand, nor a marsh, but evidently the dried-up bed of an inland
sea, which for a great part of every year has a hard and dry bottom
uncovered by weeds or grass, and only supporting here and there a
few tamarisks. But during the monsoons, when the sea runs high, the
salt-water driven up from the Gulf of Cutch and the creeks at Luckput
overflows a large part of the Runn, especially after rains, when the soaked
ground permits the sea-water to spread rapidly. The Runn is also liable
to be overflowed occasionally in some parts by river-water: and it is remarkable
that the only portion which was ever highly cultivated (that
anciently called Sayra) is now permanently submerged. The surface of
the Runn is sometimes incrusted with salt about an inch in depth, in consequence
of the evaporation of the sea-water. Islands rise up in some parts
of the waste, and the boundary lands form bays and promontories. The
natives have various traditions respecting the former separation of Cutch
and Sinde by a bay of the sea, and the drying up of the district called
the Runn. But these tales, besides the usual uncertainty of oral tradition,
are farther obscured by mythological fictions. The conversion of
the Runn into land is chiefly ascribed to the miraculous powers of a Hindoo
saint, by name Damorath (or Dhoorunnath), who had previously done
penance for twelve years on the summit of Denodur hill. Captain Grant
infers, on various grounds, that this saint flourished about the eleventh
464
or twelfth century of our era. In proof of the drying up of the Runn,
some towns far inland are still pointed out as having once been ancient
ports. It has, moreover, been always said that ships were wrecked and
engulphed by the great catastrophe; and in the jets of black muddy
water thrown out of fissures in that region, in 1819, there were cast up
numerous pieces of wrought-iron and ship nails.643 Cones of sand six or
eight feet in height were at the same time thrown up on these lands.644
We must not conclude without alluding to a moral phenomenon
connected with this tremendous catastrophe, which we regard as highly
deserving the attention of geologists. It is stated by Sir A. Burnes, that
"these wonderful events passed unheeded by the inhabitants of Cutch;"
for the region convulsed, though once fertile, had for a long period been
reduced to sterility by want of irrigation, so that the natives were indifferent
as to its fate. Now it is to this profound apathy which all but
highly civilized nations feel, in regard to physical events not having an
immediate influence on their worldly fortunes, that we must ascribe the
extraordinary dearth of historical information concerning changes of the
earth's surface, which modern observations show to be by no means of
rare occurrence in the ordinary course of nature.
Since the above account was written, a description has been published
of more recent geographical changes in the district of Cutch, near the
mouth of the Koree, or eastern branch of the Indus, which happened
in June, 1845. A large area seems to have subsided, and the Sindree
lake had become a salt marsh.645
Island of Sumbawa, 1815.—In April, 1815, one of the most frightful
eruptions recorded in history occurred in the province of Tomboro, in the
island of Sumbawa (see Map, fig. 39, p. 351), about 200 miles from
the eastern extremity of Java. In April of the year preceding the
volcano had been observed in a state of considerable activity, ashes having
fallen upon the decks of vessels which sailed past the coast.646 The
eruption of 1815 began on the 5th of April, but was most violent on the
11th and 12th, and did not entirely cease till July. The sound of the
explosions was heard in Sumatra, at the distance of 970 geographical
miles in a direct line; and at Ternate, in an opposite direction, at the
distance of 720 miles. Out of a population of 12,000, in the province
of Tomboro, only twenty-six individuals survived. Violent whirlwinds
carried up men, horses, cattle, and whatever else came within their influence
into the air; tore up the largest trees by the roots, and covered the
whole sea with floating timber.647 Great tracts of land were covered by
lava, several streams of which, issuing from the crater of the Tomboro
mountain, reached the sea: So heavy was the fall of ashes, that they
broke into the Resident's house at Bima, forty miles east of the volcano,
and rendered it as well as many other dwellings in the town uninhabitable.
On the side of Java the ashes were carried to the distance of 300
465
miles, and 217 towards Celebes, in sufficient quantity to darken the air.
The floating cinders to the westward of Sumatra formed, on the 12th of
April, a mass two feet thick, and several miles in extent, through which
ships with difficulty forced their way.
The darkness occasioned in the daytime by the ashes in Java was so
profound, that nothing equal to it was ever witnessed in the darkest
night. Although this volcanic dust when it fell was an impalpable
powder, it was of considerable weight when compressed, a pint of it
weighing twelve ounces and three quarters. "Some of the finest particles,"
says Mr. Crawfurd, "were transported to the islands of Amboyna
and Banda, which last is about 800 miles east from the site of the volcano,
although the southeast monsoon was then at its height." They
must have been projected, therefore, into the upper regions of the
atmosphere, where a counter-current prevailed.
Along the sea-coast of Sumbawa and the adjacent isles, the sea rose
suddenly to the height of from two to twelve feet, a great wave rushing
up the estuaries, and then suddenly subsiding. Although the wind at
Bima was still during the whole time, the sea rolled in upon the shore,
and filled the lower parts of the houses with water a foot deep. Every
prow and boat was forced from the anchorage, and driven on shore.
The town called Tomboro, on the west side of Sumbawa, was overflowed
by the sea, which encroached upon the shore so that the water
remained permanently eighteen feet deep in places where there was land
before. Here we may observe, that the amount of subsidence of land
was apparent, in spite of the ashes, which would naturally have caused
the limits of the coast to be extended.
The area over which tremulous noises and other volcanic effects extended,
was 1000 English miles in circumference, including the whole
of the Molucca Islands, Java, a considerable portion of Celebes, Sumatra,
and Borneo. In the island of Amboyna, in the same month and
year, the ground opened, threw out water, and then closed again.648
In conclusion, I may remind the reader, that but for the accidental
presence of Sir Stamford Raffles, then Governor of Java, we should
scarcely have heard in Europe of this tremendous catastrophe. He
required all the residents in the various districts under his authority to
send in a statement of the circumstances which occurred within their own
knowledge; but, valuable as were their communications, they are often
calculated to excite rather than to satisfy the curiosity of the geologist.
They mention that similar effects, though in a less degree, had, about
seven years before, accompanied an eruption of Carang Assam, a volcano
in the island of Bali, west of Sumatra; but no particulars of that great
catastrophe are recorded.649
Caraccas, 1812.—On the 26th of March, 1812, several violent shocks
of an earthquake were felt in Caraccas. The surface undulated like a
boiling liquid, and terrific sounds were heard underground. The whole
466
city with its splendid churches was in an instant a heap of ruins, under
which 10,000 of the inhabitants were buried. On the 5th of April,
enormous rocks were detached from the mountains. It was believed
that the mountain Silla lost from 300 to 360 feet of its height by subsidence;
but this was an opinion not founded on any measurement. On
the 27th of April, a volcano in St. Vincent's threw out ashes; and, on
the 30th, lava flowed from its crater into the sea, while its explosions
were heard at a distance equal to that between Vesuvius and Switzerland,
the sound being transmitted, as Humboldt supposes, through the
ground. During the earthquake which destroyed Caraccas, an immense
quantity of water was thrown out at Valecillo, near Valencia, as also at
Porto Cabello, through openings in the earth; and in the Lake Maracaybo
the water sank. Humboldt observed that the Cordilleras, composed
of gneiss and mica slate, and the country immediately at their feet,
were more violently shaken than the plains.650
South Carolina and New Madrid, Missouri, 1811-12.—Previous to
the destruction of La Guayra and Caraccas, in 1812, earthquakes were
felt in South Carolina; and the shocks continued till those cities were
destroyed. The valley also of the Mississippi, from the village of New
Madrid to the mouth of the Ohio in one direction, and to the St. Francis
in another, was convulsed in such a degree as to create new lakes and
islands. It has been remarked by Humboldt in his Cosmos, that the
earthquake of New Madrid presents one of the few examples on record
of the incessant quaking of the ground for several successive months far
from any volcano. Flint, the geographer, who visited the country seven
years after the event, informs us, that a tract of many miles in extent,
near the Little Prairie, became covered with water three or four feet
deep; and when the water disappeared a stratum of sand was left in its
place. Large lakes of twenty miles in extent were formed in the course
of an hour, and others were drained. The grave-yard at New Madrid
was precipitated into the bed of the Mississippi; and it is stated that the
ground whereon the town is built, and the river-bank for fifteen miles
above, sank eight feet below their former level.651 The neighboring forest
presented for some years afterwards "a singular scene of confusion; the
trees standing inclined in every direction, and many having their trunks
and branches broken."652
The inhabitants relate that the earth rose in great undulations; and
when these reached a certain fearful height, the soil burst, and vast volumes
of water, sand, and pit-coal were discharged as high as the tops
of the trees. Flint saw hundreds of these deep chasms remaining in an
alluvial soil, seven years after. The people in the country, although
inexperienced in such convulsions, had remarked that the chasms in the
earth were in a direction from S. W. to N. E.; and they accordingly
felled the tallest trees, and laying them at right angles to the chasms,
467
stationed themselves upon them. By this invention, when chasms opened
more than once under these trees, several persons were prevented
from being swallowed up.653 At one period during this earthquake, the
ground not far below New Madrid swelled up so as to arrest the Mississippi
in its course, and to cause a temporary reflux of its waves. The
motion of some of the shocks is described as having been horizontal, and
of others perpendicular; and the vertical movement is said to have been
much less desolating than the horizontal.
The above account has been reprinted exactly as it appeared in
former editions of this work, compiled from the authorities which I have
cited; but having more recently (March, 1846) had an opportunity
myself of visiting the disturbed region of the Mississippi, and conversing
with many eye-witnesses of the catastrophe, I am able to confirm
the truth of those statements, and to add some remarks on the present
face and features of the country. I skirted, as was before related (p.
270), part of the territory immediately west of New Madrid, called
"the sunk country," which was for the first time permanently submerged
during the earthquake of 1811-12. It is said to extend along
the course of the White Water and its tributaries for a distance of between
70 and 80 miles north and south, and 30 miles east and west. I
saw on its borders many full-grown trees still standing leafless, the bottoms
of their trunks several feet under water, and a still greater number
lying prostrate. An active vegetation of aquatic plants is already
beginning to fill up some of the shallows, and the sediment washed in
by occasional floods when the Mississippi rises to an extraordinary
height contributes to convert the sunk region into marsh and forest
land. Even on the dry ground along the confines of the submerged
area, I observed in some places that all the trees of prior date to 1811
were dead and leafless, though standing erect and entire. They are
supposed to have been killed by the loosening of their roots during the
repeated undulations which passed through the ground for three months
in succession.
Mr. Bringier, an experienced engineer of New Orleans, who was on
horseback near New Madrid when some of the severest shocks were experienced,
related to me (in 1846), that "as the waves advanced the
trees bent down, and the instant afterwards, while recovering their position,
they often met those of other trees similarly inclined, so that their
branches becoming interlocked, they were prevented from righting themselves
again. The transit of the wave through the woods was marked
by the crashing noise of countless boughs, first heard on one side and
then on the other. At the same time powerful jets of water, mixed
with sand, mud, and fragments of coaly matter, were cast up, endangering
the lives of both horse and rider."
I was curious, to ascertain whether any vestiges still remained of
these fountains of mud and water, and carefully examined between New
468
Madrid and the Little Prairie several "sink holes," as they are termed.
They consist of cavities from 10 to 30 yards in width, and 20 feet or
more in depth, and are very conspicuous, interrupting the level surface
of a flat alluvial plain. I saw abundance of sand, which some of the
present inhabitants saw spouting from these deep holes, also fragments
of decayed wood and black bituminous shale, probably drifted down at
some former period in the main channel of the Mississippi, from the
coal-fields farther north. I also found numerous rents in the soil left
by the earthquake, some of them still several feet wide, and a yard or
two in depth, although the action of rains, frost, and occasional inundations,
and especially the leaves of trees blown into them in countless
numbers every autumn, have done much to fill them up. I measured
the direction of some of the fissures, which usually varied from 10 to
45 degrees W. of north, and were often parallel to each other; I found,
however, a considerable diversity in their direction. Many of them are
traceable for half a mile and upwards, but they might easily be mistaken
for artificial trenches if resident settlers were not there to assure
us that within their recollection they were "as deep as wells." Fragments
of coaly shale were strewed along the edges of some of these
open fissures, together with white sand, in the same manner as round
the "sink holes."654
Among other monuments of the changes wrought in 1811-12, I explored
the bed of the lake called Eulalie, near New Madrid, 300 yards
long by 100 yards in width, which was suddenly drained during the
earthquake. The parallel fissures by which the waters escaped are not
yet entirely closed, and all the trees growing on its bottom were at the
time of my visit less than 34 years old. They consisted of cotton-wood,
willows, and honey-locust, and other species, differing from those clothing
the surrounding higher grounds, which are more elevated by 12 or
15 feet. On them the hickory, the black and white oak, the gum and
other trees, many of them of ancient date, were flourishing.
Aleutian Islands, 1806.—In the year 1806, a new island, in the form
of a peak, with some low conical hills upon it, is said to have risen from
the sea among the Aleutian Islands, east of Kamtschatka. According to
Langsdorf,655 it was four geographical miles in circumference; and Von
Buch infers from its magnitude, and from its not having again subsided
below the level of the sea, that it did not consist merely of ejected matter,
but of a solid rock of trachyte upheaved.656 Another extraordinary
eruption happened in the spring of the year 1814, in the sea near Unalaschka,
in the same archipelago. A new isle was then produced of
considerable size, and with a peak three thousand feet high, which remained
standing for a year afterwards, though with somewhat diminished
height.
Although it is not improbable that earthquakes accompanying these
469
tremendous eruptions may have heaved up part of the bed of the sea,
yet the circumstance of the islands not having disappeared like Sabrina
(see p. 416), may have arisen from the emission of lava. If Jorullo, for
example, in 1759, had risen from a shallow sea to the height of 1600
feet, instead of attaining that elevation above the Mexican plateau, the
massive current of basaltic lava which poured out from its crater would
have enabled it to withstand, for a long period, the action of a turbulent
sea.
Reflections on the earthquakes of the nineteenth century.—We are now
about to pass on to the events of the eighteenth century; but before we
leave the consideration of those already enumerated, let us pause for a
moment, and reflect how many remarkable facts of geological interest
are afforded by the earthquakes above described, though they constitute
but a small part of the convulsions even of the last forty years. New
rocks have risen from the waters; new hot springs have burst out, and
the temperature of others has been raised; the coast of Chili has been
thrice permanently elevated; a considerable tract in the delta of the
Indus has sunk down, and some of its shallow channels have become
navigable; an adjoining part of the same district, upwards of fifty miles
in length and sixteen in breadth, has been raised about ten feet above its
former level; part of the great plain of the Mississippi, for a distance of
eighty miles in length by thirty in breadth, has sunk down several feet;
the town of Tomboro has been submerged, and twelve thousand of the
inhabitants of Sumbawa have been destroyed. Yet, with a knowledge
of these terrific catastrophes, witnessed during so brief a period by the
present generation, will the geologist declare with perfect composure
that the earth has at length settled into a state of repose? Will he
continue to assert that the changes of relative level of land and sea, so
common in former ages of the world, have now ceased? If, in the face
of so many striking facts, he persists in maintaining this favorite dogma,
it is in vain to hope that, by accumulating the proofs of similar convulsions
during a series of antecedent ages, we shall shake his tenacity of
purpose:—


Si fractus illabatur orbis
Impavidum ferient ruinæ.


EARTHQUAKES OF THE EIGHTEENTH CENTURY.
Quito, 1797.—On the morning of February 4th, 1797, the volcano
of Tunguragua in Quito, and the surrounding district, for forty leagues
from south to north, and twenty leagues from west to east, experienced
an undulating movement, which lasted four minutes. The same shock
was felt over a tract of 170 leagues from south to north, from Piura to
Popayan; and 140 from west to east, from the sea to the river Napo.
In the smaller district first mentioned, where the movement was more
intense, every town was levelled to the ground; and Riobamba, Quero,
and other places, were buried under masses detached from the mountains.
470
At the foot of Tunguragua the earth was rent open in several
places; and streams of water and fetid mud, called "moya," poured
out, overflowing and wasting every thing. In valleys 1000 feet broad,
the water of these floods reached to the height of 600 feet; and the
mud deposit barred up the course of the river, so as to form lakes,
which in some places continued for more than eighty days. Flames and
suffocating vapors escaped from the lake Quilotoa, and killed all the
cattle on its shores. The shocks continued all February and March;
and on the 5th of April they recurred with almost as much violence as
at first. We are told that the form of the surface in the district most
shaken was entirely altered, but no exact measurements are given
whereby we may estimate the degree of elevation or subsidence.657 Indeed
it would be difficult, except in the immediate neighborhood of the
sea, to obtain any certain standard of comparison if the levels were really
as much altered as the narrations imply.
Cumana, 1797.—In the same year, on the 14th of December, the
small Antilles experienced subterranean movements, and four-fifths of
the town of Cumana was shaken down by a vertical shock. The form
of the shoal of Mornerouge, at the mouth of the river Bourdones, was
changed by an upheaving of the ground.658
Canada—Quebec, 1791.—We learn from Captain Bayfield's memoirs,
that earthquakes are very frequent on the shore of the estuary of the
St. Lawrence, of force sufficient at times to split walls and throw down
chimneys. Such were the effects experienced in December, 1721, in St.
Paul's Bay, about fifty miles N. E. from Quebec; and the inhabitants
say, that about every twenty-five years a violent earthquake returns,
which lasts forty days. In the History of Canada, it is stated that, in
1663, a tremendous convulsion lasted six months, extending from Quebec
to Tadeausac,—a distance of about 130 miles. The ice on the
river was broken up, and many landslips caused.659
Caraccas, 1790.—In the Caraccas, near where the Caura joins the
Orinoco, between the towns San Pedro de Alcantara and San Francisco
de Aripao, an earthquake, on St. Matthew's day 1790, caused a sinking
in of the granitic soil, and left a lake 800 yards in diameter, and from
eighty to one hundred in depth. It was a portion of the forest of Aripao
which subsided, and the trees remained green for several months
under water.660
Sicily, 1790.—On the 18th of March in the same year, at S. Maria
di Niscemi, some miles from Terranuova, near the south coast of Sicily,
the ground gradually sunk down for a circumference of three Italian
miles, during seven shocks; and, in one place, to the depth of thirty
feet. It continued to subside to the end of the month. Several fissures
sent forth sulphur, petroleum, steam, and hot water, and a stream of
471
mud, which flowed for two hours, and covered a space sixty feet long
and thirty broad. This happened far from both the ancient and modern
volcanic district, in a group of strata consisting chiefly of blue clay.661
Java, 1786.—About the year 1786, an earthquake was felt at intervals,
for the period of four months, in the neighborhood of Batur, in
Java, and an eruption followed. Various rents were formed, which
emitted a sulphurous vapor; separate tracts sunk away, and were
swallowed by the earth. Into one of these the rivulet Dotog entered,
and afterwards continued to follow a subterraneous course. The village
of Jampang was buried in the ground, with thirty-eight of its inhabitants,
who had not time to escape. We are indebted to Dr. Horsfield
for having verified the above-mentioned facts.662
</div></body></text></TEI>