<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="32">CHAPTER XXXII.
CAUSES OF EARTHQUAKES AND VOLCANOES—continued.
Review of the proofs of internal heat—Theory of an unoxidated metallic nucleus—Whether
the decomposition of water may be a source of volcanic heat—Geysers
of Iceland—Causes of earthquakes—Wavelike motion—Expansive
power of liquid gases—Connection between the state of the atmosphere and
earthquakes—Permanent upheaval and subsidence of land—Expansion of rocks
by heat—The balance of dry land how preserved—Subsidence in excess—Conclusion.
When we reflect that the largest mountains are but insignificant protuberances
upon the surface of the earth, and that these mountains are
nevertheless composed of different parts which have been formed in succession,
we may well feel surprise that the central fluidity of the planet
should have been called in to account for volcanic phenomena. To suppose
the entire globe to be in a state of igneous fusion, with the exception
of a solid shell, not more than from thirty to one hundred miles
thick, and to imagine that the central heat of this fluid spheroid exceeds
by more than two hundred times that of liquid lava, is to introduce a
force altogether disproportionate to the effects which it is required to
explain.
The ordinary repose of the surface implies, on the contrary, an inertness
in the internal mass which is truly wonderful. When we consider
the combustible nature of the elements of the earth, so far as they are
known to us,—the facility with which their compounds may be decomposed
and made to enter into new combinations,—the quantity of heat
which they evolve during these processes; when we recollect the expansive
power of steam, and that water itself is composed of two gases which,
by their union, produce intense heat; when we call to mind the number
of explosive and detonating compounds which have been already discovered,
we may be allowed to share the astonishment of Pliny, that a single
546
day should pass without a general conflagration:—"Excedit profectò
omnia miracula, ullum diem fuisse quo non cuncta conflagrarent."759
The signs of internal heat observable on the surface of the earth do
not necessarily indicate the permanent existence of subterranean heated
masses, whether fluid or solid, by any means so vast as our continents
and seas; yet how insignificant would these appear if distributed through
an external shell of the globe one or two hundred miles in depth! The
principal facts in proof of the accumulation of heat below the surface
may be summed up in a few words. Several volcanoes are constantly
in eruption, as Stromboli and Nicaragua; others are known to have been
active for periods of 60, or even 150 years, as those of Sangay in Quito,
Popocatepetl in Mexico, and the volcano of the Isle of Bourbon. Many
craters emit hot vapors in the intervals between eruptions, and solfataras
evolve incessantly the same gases as volcanoes. Steam of high temperature
has continued for more than twenty centuries to issue from the
"stufas," as the Italians call them; thermal springs abound not only
in regions of earthquakes, but are found in almost all countries, however
distant from active vents; and, lastly, the temperature in the mines of
various parts of the world is found to increase in proportion as we descend.
The diagram (fig. 93) in the next page, may convey some idea of the
proportion which our continents and the ocean bear to the radius of the
earth.760 If all the land were about as high as the Himalaya mountains,
and the ocean everywhere as deep as the Pacific, the whole of both
might be contained within a space expressed by the thickness of the line
a b; and masses of nearly equal volume might be placed in the space
marked by the line c d, in the interior. Seas of lava, therefore, of the
size of the Mediterranean, or even of the Atlantic, would be as nothing
if distributed through such an outer shell of the globe as is represented
by the shaded portion of the figure a b c d. If throughout that space
we imagine electro-chemical causes to be continually in operation, even
of very feeble power, they might give rise to heat which, if accumulated
at certain points, might melt or render red-hot entire mountains, or sustain
the temperature of stufas and hot springs for ages.
Theory of an unoxidated metallic nucleus.—When Sir H. Davy first
discovered the metallic basis of the earths and alkalies, he threw out the
idea that those metals might abound in an unoxidized state in the subterranean
regions to which water must occasionally penetrate. Whenever
this happened, gaseous matter would be set free, the metals would
combine with the oxygen of the water, and sufficient heat might be
evolved to melt the surrounding rocks. This hypothesis, although afterwards
abandoned by its author, was at first very favorably received
both by the chemist and the geologist: for silica, alumina, lime, soda, and
oxide of iron,—substances of which lavas are principally composed,—would
547
all result from the contact of the inflammable metals alluded to
with water. But whence this abundant store of unsaturated metals in
the interior? It was assumed that, in the beginning of things, the
nucleus of the earth was mainly composed of inflammable metals, and
that oxidation went on with intense energy at first; till at length, when
a superficial crust of oxides had been formed, the chemical action became
more and more languid.
Fig. 93.
Centre of the earth.
This speculation, like all others respecting the primitive state of the
earth's nucleus, rests unavoidably on arbitrary assumptions. But we
548
may fairly inquire whether any existing causes may have the power of
deoxidating the earthy and alkaline compounds formed from time to
time by the action of water upon the metallic bases. If so, and if the
original crust or nucleus of the planet contained distributed through it
here and there some partial stores of potassium, sodium, and other metallic
bases, these might be oxidated and again deoxidated, so as to sustain
for ages a permanent chemical action. Yet even then we should
be unable to explain why such a continuous circle of operations, after
having been kept up for thousands of years in one district, should entirely
cease, and why another region, which had enjoyed a respite from
volcanic action for one or many geological periods, should become a theatre
for the development of subterranean heat.
It is well known to chemists, that the metallization of oxides, the
most difficult to reduce, may be effected by hydrogen brought into contact
with them at a red heat; and it is more than probable that the
production of potassium itself, in the common gun-barrel process, is due
to the power of nascent hydrogen derived from the water which the
hydrated oxide contains. According to the recent experiments, also, of
Faraday, it would appear that every case of metallic reduction by voltaic
agency, from saline solutions, in which water is present, is due to
the secondary action of hydrogen upon the oxide; both of these being
determined to the negative pole and then reacting upon one another.
It is admitted that intense heat would be produced by the occasional
contact of water with the metallic bases; and it is certain that, during
the process of saturation, vast volumes of hydrogen must be evolved.
The hydrogen, thus generated, might permeate the crust of the earth
in different directions, and become stored up for ages in fissures and
caverns, sometimes in a liquid form, under the necessary pressure.
Whenever, at any subsequent period, in consequence of the changes
effected by earthquakes in the shell of the earth, this gas happened to
come in contact with metallic oxides at a high temperature, the reduction
of these oxides might be the result.
No theory seems at first more startling than that which represents
water as affording an inexhaustible supply of fuel to the volcanic fires;
yet is it by no means visionary. It is a fact that must not be overlooked,
that while a great number of volcanoes are entirely submarine, the remainder
occur for the most part in islands or maritime tracts. There
are a few exceptions; but some of these, observes Dr. Daubeny, are near
inland salt lakes, as in Central Tartary; while others form part of a
train of volcanoes, the extremities of which are near the sea.
Sir H. Davy suggested that, when the sea is distant, as in the case of
some of the South American volcanoes, they may still be supplied with
water from subterranean lakes; since, according to Humboldt, large
quantities of fish are often thrown out during eruptions.761 Mr. Dana
also, in his valuable and original observations on the volcanoes of the
549
Sandwich Islands, reminds us of the prodigious volume of atmospheric
water which must be absorbed into the interior of such large and lofty
domes, composed as they are entirely of porous lava. To this source
alone he refers the production of the steam by which the melted matter
is propelled upwards, even to the summit of cones three miles in height.762
When treating of springs and overflowing wells, I have stated that
porous rocks are percolated by fresh water to great depths, and that
sea-water probably penetrates in the same manner through the rocks
which form the bed of the ocean. But, besides this universal circulation
in regions not far from the surface, it must be supposed that,
wherever earthquakes prevail, much larger bodies of water will be
forced by the pressure of the ocean into fissures at great depths, or
swallowed up in chasms; in the same manner as on the land, towns,
houses, cattle, and trees are sometimes engulfed. It will be remembered,
that these chasms often close again after houses have fallen into
them; and for the same reason, when water has penetrated to a mass
of melted lava, the steam into which it is converted may often rush out
at a different aperture from that by which the water entered.
The gases, it is said, exhaled from volcanoes, together with steam, are
such as would result from the decomposition of salt water, and the
fumes which escape from the Vesuvian lava have been observed to deposit
common salt.763 The emission of free muriatic acid gas in great
quantities is also thought by many to favor the theory of the decomposition
of the salt contained in sea-water. It has been objected, however,
that M. Boussingault did not meet with this gas in his examination of the
elastic fluids evolved from the volcanoes of equatorial America; which
only give out aqueous vapor (in very large quantity), carbonic acid gas,
sulphurous acid gas, and sometimes fumes of sulphur.764 In reply, Dr.
Daubeny has remarked, that muriatic acid may have ceased to be disengaged,
because the volcanic action has become languid in equatorial
America, and sea-water may no longer obtain admission.
M. Gay Lussac, while he avows his opinion that the decomposition
of water contributes largely to volcanic action, called attention, nevertheless,
to the supposed fact, that hydrogen had not been detected in
a separate form among the gaseous products of volcanoes; nor can it,
he says, be present; for, in that case, it would be inflamed in the air
by the red-hot stones thrown out during an eruption. Dr. Davy, in
his account of Graham Island, says, "I watched when the lightning was
most vivid, and the eruption of the greatest degree of violence, to see if
there was any inflammation occasioned by this natural electric spark—any
indication of the presence of inflammable gas; but in vain."765
May not the hydrogen, Gay Lussac inquires, be combined with chlorine,
and produce muriatic acid? for this gas has been observed to be
evolved from Vesuvius—and the chlorine may have been derived from
550
sea salt; which was, in fact, extracted by simple washing from the
Vesuvian lava of 1822, in the proportion of nine per cent.766 But it
was answered, that Sir H. Davy's experiments had shown, that hydrogen
is not combustible when mixed with muriatic acid gas; so that if
muriatic gas was evolved in large quantities, the hydrogen might be
present without inflammation.767 M. Abich, on the other hand, assures
us, "that although it be true that vapor illuminated by incandescent
lava has often been mistaken for flame," yet he clearly detected in the
eruption of Vesuvius in 1834 the flame of hydrogen.768
M. Gay Lussac, in the memoir just alluded to, expressed doubt as to
the presence of sulphurous acid; but the abundant disengagement of
this gas during eruptions has been since ascertained: and thus all difficulty
in regard to the general absence of hydrogen in an inflammable
state is removed; for, as Dr. Daubeny suggests, the hydrogen of decomposed
water may unite with sulphur to form sulphuretted hydrogen
gas, and this gas will then be mingled with the sulphurous acid as it
rises to the crater. It is shown by experiment, that these gases mutually
decompose each other when mixed where steam is present; the
hydrogen of the one immediately uniting with the oxygen of the other
to form water, while the excess of sulphurous acid alone escapes into
the atmosphere. Sulphur is at the same time precipitated.
This explanation is sufficient; but it may also be observed that the
flame of hydrogen would rarely be visible during an eruption; as that
gas, when inflamed in a pure state, burns with a very faint blue flame,
which even in the night could hardly be perceptible by the side of redhot
and incandescent cinders. Its immediate, conversion into water
when inflamed in the atmosphere, might also account for its not appearing
in a separate form.
Dr. Daubeny is of opinion that water containing atmospheric air may
descend from the surface of the earth to the volcanic foci, and that the
same process of combustion by which water is decomposed may deprive
such subterranean air of its oxygen. In this manner he explains the
great quantities of nitrogen evolved from volcanic vents and thermal
waters, and the fact that air disengaged from the earth in volcanic regions
is either wholly or in part deprived of its oxygen.
Sir H. Davy, in his memoir on the "Phenomena of Volcanoes," remarks,
that there was every reason to suppose in Vesuvius the existence
of a descending current of air; and he imagined that subterranean
cavities which threw out large volumes of steam during the eruption,
might afterwards, in the quiet state of the volcano, become filled with
atmospheric air.769 The presence of ammoniacal salts in volcanic emanations,
and of ammonia (which is in part composed of nitrogen) in lava,
favors greatly the notion of air as well as water being deoxidated in the
interior of the earth.770
551
It has been alleged by Professor Bischoff that the slight specific gravity
of the metals of the alkalies is fatal to Davy's hypothesis, for if the
mean density of the earth, as determined by astronomers, surpass that
of all kinds of rocks, these metals cannot exist, at least not in great
quantities in the interior of the earth.771 But Dr. Daubeny has shown,
that if we take the united specific gravity of potassium, sodium, silicon,
iron, and all the materials which, when united with oxygen, constitute
ordinary lava, and then compare their weight with lava of equal bulk,
the difference is not very material, the specific gravity of the lava only
exceeding by about one-fourth that of the unoxidized metals. Besides,
at great depths, the metallic bases of the earths and alkalies may very
probably be rendered heavier by pressure.772 Nor is it fair to embarrass
the chemical theory of volcanoes with a doctrine so purely gratuitous,
as that which supposes the entire nucleus of the planet to have been at
first composed of unoxidated metals.
Professor Bunsen of Marburg, after analyzing the gases which escape
from the volcanic fumeroles and solfataras of Iceland, and after calculating
the quantity of hydrogen evolved between two eruptions, affirms,
in contradiction of opinions previously entertained, that the hydrogen
bears a perfect relation in quantity to the magnitude of the streams of
lava, assuming the fusion of these last to have been the result of the
heat evolved during the oxidation of alkaline and earthy metals, and this
to have been brought about by the decomposition of water. Yet after
having thus succeeded in removing the principal objection once so
triumphantly urged against Davy's hypothesis, Bunsen concludes by
declaring that the hydrogen evolved in volcanic regions cannot have
been generated by the decomposition of water coming in contact with
alkaline and earthy metallic bases. For, says the Professor, this process
presupposes the prevalence of a temperature in which carbonic acid cannot
exist in contact with hydrogen without suffering a partial reduction
to carbonic oxide; "and not a trace of carbonic oxide is ever found in
volcanic exhalations."773 At the same time it will be seen, by consulting
the able memoirs of the Marburg chemist, that he supposes many energetic
kinds of chemical action to be continually going on in the interior
of the earth, capable of causing the disengagement of hydrogen; and
there can be no doubt that this gas may be a source of innumerable new
changes, capable of producing the local development of internal heat.
Cause of volcanic eruptions.—The most probable causes of a volcanic
outburst at the surface have been in a great degree anticipated in the
preceding speculations on the liquefaction of rocks and the generation of
gases. When a minute hole is bored in a tube filled with gas condensed
into a liquid, the whole becomes instantly aeriform, or, as some writers
have expressed it, "flashes into vapor," and often bursts the tube. Such
552
an experiment may represent the mode in which gaseous matter may
rush through a rent in the rocks, and continue to escape for days or
weeks through a small orifice, with an explosive power sufficient to reduce
every substance which opposes its passage into small fragments or
even dust. Lava may be propelled upwards at the same time, and ejected
in the form of scoriæ. In some places, where the fluid lava lies at the
bottom of a deep fissure, communicating on the one hand with the surface,
and on the other with a cavern in which a considerable body of
vapor has been formed, there may be an efflux of lava, followed by the
escape of gas. Eruptions often commence and close with the discharge
of vapor; and, when this is the case, the next outburst may be expected
to take place by the same vent, for the concluding evolution of elastic
fluids will keep open the duct, and leave it unobstructed.
The breaking out of lava from the side or base of a lofty cone, rather
than from the summit, may be attributed to the hydrostatic pressure to
which the flanks of the mountain are exposed, when the column of lava
has risen to a great height. Or if, before it has reached the top, there
should happen to be any stoppage in the main duct, the upward pressure
of the ascending column of gas and lava may burst a lateral opening.
In the case however of Mount Loa, in the Sandwich Islands, there
appears to be a singular want of connection or sympathy between the
eruptions of the central and the great lateral vent. The great volcanic
cone alluded to rises to the height of 13,760 feet above the level of the
sea, having a crater at its summit, from which powerful streams of lava
have flowed in recent times, and having another still larger crater, called
Kilauea, on its southeastern slope, about 4000 feet above the sea. This
lateral cavity resembles a huge quarry cut in the mountain's side, being
about 1000 feet deep when in its ordinary state. It is seven miles and
a half in circuit, and scattered over its bottom, at different levels, are
lakes and pools of lava, always in a state of ebullition. The liquid in one
of these will sometimes sink 100 or 150 feet, while it is overflowing in
another at a higher elevation, there being, it should seem, no communication
between them. In like manner, lava overflows in the summit
crater of Mount Loa, nearly 14,000 feet high, while the great lateral
cauldron just alluded to (of Kilauea) continues as tranquil as usual, affording
no relief to any part of the gases or melted matter which are forcing
their way upwards in the centre of the mountain. "How," asks Mr.
Dana, "if there were any subterranean channel connecting the two great
vents, could this want of sympathy exist? How, according to the laws
of hydrostatic pressure, can a column of fluid stand 10,000 feet higher
in one leg of the siphon than in the other?" The eruptions, he observes,
are not paroxysmal; on the contrary, the lava rises slowly and gradually
to the summit of the lofty cone, and then escapes there without any
commotion manifesting itself in Kilauea, a gulf always open on the flanks
of the same mountain. One conclusion, he says, is certain, namely, that
volcanoes are no safety valves as they have been called; for here two
independent and apparently isolated centres of volcanic activity, only
553
sixteen miles distant from each other, are sustained in one and the same
cone.774
Without pretending to solve this enigma, I cannot refrain from remarking,
that the supposed independence of several orifices of eruption
in one crater like Kilauea, when adduced in confirmation of the doctrine
of two distinct sources of volcanic action underneath one mountain,
proves too much. No one can doubt, that the pools of lava in Kilauea
have been derived from some common reservoir, and have resulted from
a combination of causes commonly called volcanic, which are at work in
the interior at some unknown distance below. These causes have given
rise in Mount Loa to eruptions from many points, but principally from
one centre, so that a vast dome of ejected matter has been piled up.
The subsidiary crater has evidently never given much relief to the imprisoned,
heated, and liquefied matter, for Kilauea does not form a lateral
protuberance interfering with the general shape or uniform outline
of Mount Loa.
Geysers of Iceland.—As aqueous vapor constitutes the most abundant
of the aeriform products of volcanoes in eruption, it may be well to consider
attentively a case in which steam is exclusively the moving power—that
of the Geysers of Iceland. These intermittent hot springs occur
in a district situated in the southwestern division of Iceland, where
nearly one hundred of them are said to break out within a circle of two
miles. That the water is of atmospheric origin, derived from rain and
melted snow, is proved, says Professor Bunsen, by the nitrogen which
rises from them either pure or mixed with other gases. The springs
rise through a thick current of lava, which may perhaps have flowed
from Mount Hecla, the summit of that volcano being seen from the spot
at the distance of more than thirty miles. In this district the rushing
of water is sometimes heard in chasms beneath the surface; for here,
as on Etna, rivers flow in subterranean channels through the porous and
cavernous lavas. It has more than once happened, after earthquakes,
that some of the boiling fountains have increased or diminished in violence
and volume, or entirely ceased, or that new ones have made their
appearance—changes which may be explained by the opening of new
rents and the closing of pre-existing fissures.
Few of the Geysers play longer than five or six minutes at a time,
although sometimes half an hour. The intervals between their eruptions
are for the most part very irregular. The Great Geyser rises out
of a spacious basin at the summit of a circular mound composed of siliceous
incrustations deposited from the spray of its waters. The diameter
of this basin, in one direction, is fifty-six feet, and forty-six in another.
(See fig. 94.) In the centre is a pipe seventy-eight feet in perpendicular
depth, and from eight to ten feet in diameter, but gradually widening,
as it rises into the basin. The inside of the basin is whitish, consisting
of a siliceous crust, and perfectly smooth, as are likewise two small
554
channels on the sides of the mound, down which the water escapes
when the bowl is filled to the margin. The circular basin is sometimes
empty, as represented in the following sketch; but is usually filled with
beautifully transparent water in a state of ebullition. During the rise
of the boiling water in the pipe, especially when the ebullition is most
violent, and when the water is thrown up in jets, subterranean noises
are heard, like the distant firing of cannon, and the earth is slightly
shaken. The sound then increases and the motion becomes more violent,
till at length a column of water is thrown up, with loud explosions, to
the height of one or two hundred feet. After playing for a time like
an artificial fountain, and giving off great clouds of vapor, the pipe or
tube is emptied; and a column of steam, rushing up with amazing force
and a thundering noise, terminates the eruption.
Fig. 94.
View of the Crater of the Great Geyser in Iceland.775
If stones are thrown into the crater, they are instantly ejected; and
such is the explosive force, that very hard rocks are sometimes shivered
by it into small pieces. Henderson found that by throwing a great
quantity of large stones into the pipe of Strockr, one of the Geysers, he
could bring on an eruption in a few minutes.776 The fragments of stone,
as well as the boiling water, were thrown in that case to a much greater
height than usual. After the water had been ejected, a column of steam
continued to rush up with a deafening roar for nearly an hour; but the
Geyser, as if exhausted by this effort, did not send out a fresh eruption
when its usual interval of rest had elapsed. The account given by Sir
George Mackenzie of a Geyser which he saw in eruption in 1810 (see
fig. 95), agrees perfectly with the above description by Henderson. The
555
steam and water rose for half an hour to the height of 70 feet, and the
white column remained perpendicular notwithstanding a brisk gale of
wind which was blowing against it. Stones thrown into the pipe were
projected to a greater height than the water. To leeward of the vapor
a heavy shower of rain was seen to fall.777
Fig. 95.
Eruption of the New Geyser in 1810. (Mackenzie.)
Among the different theories proposed to account for these phenomena,
I shall first mention one suggested by Sir. J. Herschel. An imitation
of these jets, he says, may be produced on a small scale, by heating
red hot the stem of a tobacco pipe, filling the bowl with water, and
so inclining the pipe as to let the water run through the stem. Its escape,
instead of taking place in a continued stream, is then performed by
a succession of violent explosions, at first of steam alone, then of water
mixed with steam; and, as the pipe cools, almost wholly of water. At
every such paroxysmal escape of the water, a portion is driven back, accompanied
with steam, into the bowl. The intervals between the explosions
depend on the heat, length, and inclination of the pipe; their continuance,
on its thickness and conducting power.778
The application of
556
this experiment to the Geysers merely requires that a subterranean
stream, flowing through the pores and crevices of lava, should suddenly
reach a fissure in which the rock is red hot or nearly so. Steam would
immediately be formed, which, rushing up the fissure, might force up
water along with it to the surface, while, at the same time, part of the
steam might drive back the water of the supply for a certain distance
towards its source. And when, after the space of some minutes, the
steam was all condensed, the water would return, and a repetition of the
phenomena take place.
Fig. 96.
Supposed reservoir and pipe of a Geyser in Iceland.779
There is, however, another mode of explaining the action of the Geyser,
perhaps more probable than that above described. Suppose water
percolating from the surface of the earth to penetrate into the subterranean
cavity A D (fig. 96) by the fissures F F, while, at the same time,
steam at an extremely high temperature, such as is commonly given out
from the rents of lava currents during congelation, emanates from the
fissures C. A portion of the steam is at first condensed into water,
while the temperature of the water is raised by the latent heat thus
evolved, till, at last, the lower part of the cavity is filled with boiling
water and the upper with steam under high pressure. The expansive
force of the steam becomes, at length, so great, that the water is forced
up the fissure or pipe E B, and runs over the rim of the basin. When
the pressure is thus diminished, the steam in the upper part of the cavity
A expands, until all the water D is driven into the pipe; and when this
557
happens, the steam, being the lighter of the two fluids, rushes up
through the water with great velocity. If the pipe be choked up artificially,
even for a few minutes, a great increase of heat must take place;
for it is prevented from escaping in a latent form in steam; so that the
water is made to boil more violently, and this brings on an eruption.
Professor Bunsen, before cited, adopts this theory to account for the
play of the "Little Geyser," but says it will not explain the phenomena
of the Great one. He considers this, like the others, to be a thermal
spring, having a narrow funnel-shaped tube in the upper part of its
course, where the walls of the channel have become coated over with
siliceous incrustations. At the mouth of this tube the water has a
temperature, corresponding to the pressure of the atmosphere, of about
212° Fahr., but at a certain depth below it is much hotter. This the
professor succeeded in proving by experiment; a thermometer suspended
by a string in the pipe rising to 266° Fahr., or no less than 48
degrees above the boiling point. After the column of water has been
expelled, what remains in the basin and pipe is found to be much cooled.
Previously to these experiments of Bunsen and Descloizeaux, made in
Iceland in 1846, it would scarcely have been supposed possible that the
lower part of a free and open column of water could be raised so much
in temperature without causing a circulation of ascending and descending
currents, followed by an almost immediate equalization of heat.
Such circulation is no doubt impeded greatly by the sides of the well
not being vertical, and by numerous contractions of its diameter, but
the phenomenon may be chiefly due to another cause. According to
recent experiments on the cohesion of liquids by Mr. Donny of Ghent,
it appears that when water is freed from all admixture of air, its temperature
can be raised, even under ordinary atmospheric pressure, to
275° Fahr., so much does the cohesion of its molecules increase780 when
they are not separated by particles of air. As water long boiled becomes
more and more deprived of air, it is probably very free from such
intermixture at the bottom of the Geysers.
Among other results of the experiments of Bunsen and his companion,
they convinced themselves that the column of fluid filling the
tube is constantly receiving accessions of hot water from below, while it
becomes cooler above by evaporation on the broad surface of the basin.
They also came to a conclusion of no small interest, as bearing on the
probable mechanism of ordinary volcanic eruptions, namely that the
tube itself is the main seat or focus of mechanical force. This was
proved by letting down stones suspended by strings to various depths.
Those which were sunk to considerable distances from the surface were
not cast up again, whereas those nearer the mouth of the tube were ejected
to great heights. Other experiments also were made tending to demonstrate
the singular fact, that there is often scarce any motion below,
when a violent rush of steam and water is taking place above. It seems
558
that when a lofty column of water possesses a temperature increasing
with the depth, any slight ebullition or disturbance of equilibrium in the
upper portion may first force up water into the basin, and then cause it
to flow over the edge. A lower portion, thus suddenly relieved of part
of its pressure, expands and is converted into vapor more rapidly than
the first, owing to its greater heat. This allows the next subjacent
stratum, which is much hotter, to rise and flash into a gaseous form;
and this process goes on till the ebullition has descended from the
middle to near the bottom of the funnel.781
In speculating, therefore, on the mechanism of an ordinary volcanic
eruption, we may suppose that large subterranean cavities exist at the
depth of some miles below the surface of the earth, in which melted
lava accumulates; and when water containing the usual mixture of air
penetrates into these, the steam thus generated may press upon the
lava and force it up the duct of a volcano, in the same manner as a
column of water is driven up the pipe of a Geyser. In other cases we
may suppose a continuous column of liquid lava mixed with red-hot
water (for water may exist in that state, as Professor Bunsen reminds
us, under pressure), and this column may have a temperature regularly
increasing downwards. A disturbance of equilibrium may first bring on
an eruption near the surface, by the expansion and conversion into gas
of entangled water and other constituents of what we call lava, so as to
occasion a diminution of pressure. More steam would then be liberated,
carrying up with it jets of melted rock, which being hurled up into the
air may fall in showers of ashes on the surrounding country, and at
length, by the arrival of lava and water more and more heated at the
orifice of the duct or the crater of the volcano, expansive power may be
acquired sufficient to expel a massive current of lava. After the eruption
has ceased, a period of tranquillity succeeds, during which fresh
accessions of heat are communicated from below, and additional masses
of rock fused by degrees, while at the same time atmospheric or sea
water is descending from the surface. At length the conditions required
for a new outburst are obtained, and another cycle of similar
changes is renewed.
Causes of earthquakes—wave-like motion.—I shall now proceed to
examine the manner in which the heat of the interior may give rise to
earthquakes. One of the most common phenomena attending subterranean
movements, is the undulatory motion of the ground. And this,
says Michell, will seem less extraordinary, if we call to mind the extreme
elasticity of the earth and the compressibility of even the most solid
materials. Large districts, he suggests, may rest on fluid lava; and,
when this is disturbed, its motions may be propagated through the incumbent
rocks. He also adds the following ingenious speculation:—"As
a small quantity of vapor almost instantly generated at some considerable
559
depth below the surface of the earth will produce a vibratory
motion, so a very large quantity (whether it be generated almost instantly,
or in any small portion of time) will produce a wave-like motion.
The manner in which this wave-like motion will be propagated
may, in some measure, be represented by the following experiment:—Suppose
a large cloth, or carpet (spread upon a floor), to be raised at
one edge, and then suddenly brought down again to the floor; the air
under it, being by this means propelled, will pass along till it escapes
at the opposite side, raising the cloth in a wave all the way as it goes.
In like manner, a large quantity of vapor may be conceived to raise the
earth in a wave, as it passes along between the strata, which it may
easily separate in a horizontal direction, there being little or no cohesion
between one stratum and another. The part of the earth that is first
raised being bent from its natural form, will endeavor to restore itself
by its elasticity; and the parts next to it being to have their weight
supported by the vapor, which will insinuate itself under them, will be
raised in their turn, till it either finds some vent, or is again condensed
by the cold into water, and by that means prevented from proceeding
any farther."782 In a memoir published in 1843, on the structure of the
Appalachian chain, by the Professors Rogers,783 the following hypothesis
is proposed as "simpler and more in accordance with dynamical considerations,
and the recorded observations on earthquakes."—"In
place," say they, "of supposing it possible for a body of vapor or gaseous
matter to pass horizontally between the strata, or even between the
crust and the fluid lava upon which it floats, and with which it must
be closely entangled, we are inclined to attribute the movement to an
actual pulsation, engendered in the molten matter itself, by a linear disruption
under enormous tension, giving vent explosively to elastic vapors,
escaping either to the surface, or into cavernous spaces beneath. According
to this supposition, the movement of the subterranean vapors
would be towards, and not from, the disrupted belt, and the oscillation
of the crust would originate in the tremendous and sudden disturbance
of the previous pressure on the surface of the lava mass below, brought
about by the instantaneous and violent rending of the overlying strata."
This theory requires us to admit that the crust of the earth is so
flexible, that it can assume the form, and follow the motion of an undulation
in the fluid below. Even if we grant this, says Mr. Mallet, another
more serious objection presents itself, viz. the great velocity attributed
to the transit of the wave in the subterranean sea of lava. We are called
upon to admit that the speed of the wave below equals that of the true
earthquake shock at the surface, which is so immense, that it is not inferior
to the velocity of sound in the same solids. But the undulation
in the fluid below must follow the laws of a tidal wave, or of the great
sea-wave already spoken of. "Its velocity, like that of the tidal wave
560
of our seas, will be a function of its length and of the depth of the fluid,
diminished in this case by certain considerations as to the density and
degree of viscidity of the liquid; and although it would be at present
impossible, for want of data, to calculate the exact velocity with which
this subterraneous lava-wave could move, it may be certainly affirmed
that its velocity would be immeasurably short of the observed or theoretic
velocity of the great earth-wave, or true shock in earthquakes."784
Liquid gases.—The rending and upheaving of continental masses are
operations which are not difficult to explain, when we are once convinced
that heat, of sufficient power, not only to melt but to reduce to a gaseous
form a great variety of substances, is accumulated in certain parts
of the interior. We see that elastic fluids are capable of projecting solid
masses to immense heights in the air; and the volcano of Cotopaxi has
been known to throw out, to the distance of eight or nine miles, a mass
of rock about one hundred cubic yards in volume. When we observe
these aeriform fluids rushing out from particular vents for months, or
even years, continuously, what power may we not expect them to exert
in other places, where they happen to be confined under an enormous
weight of rock?
The experiments of Faraday and others have shown, within the last
twelve years, that many of the gases, including all those which are most
copiously disengaged from volcanic vents, as the carbonic, sulphurous,
and muriatic acids, may be condensed into liquids by pressure. At
temperatures of from 30° to 50° F., the pressure required for this purpose
varies from fifteen to fifty atmospheres; and this amount of pressure
we may regard as very insignificant in the operations of nature. A
column of Vesuvian lava that would reach from the lip of the crater to
the level of the sea, must be equal to about three hundred atmospheres;
so that, at depths which may be termed moderate in the interior of the
crust of the earth, the gases may be condensed into liquids, even at very
high temperatures. The method employed to reduce some of these
gases to a liquid state is, to confine the materials, from the mutual action
of which they are evolved, in tubes hermetically sealed, so that the accumulated
pressure of the vapor, as it rises and expands, may force
some part of it to assume the liquid state. A similar process may, and
indeed must, frequently take place in subterranean caverns and fissures,
or even in the pores and cells of many rocks; by which means, a much
greater store of expansive power may be packed into a small space than
could happen if these vapors had not the property of becoming liquid.
For, although the gas occupies much less room in a liquid state, yet it
exerts exactly the same pressure upon the sides of the containing cavity
as if it remained in the form of vapor.
If a tube, whether of glass or other materials, filled with condensed
gas, have its temperature slightly raised, it will often burst; for a slight
increment of heat causes the elasticity of the gas to increase in a very
561
high ratio. We have only to suppose certain rocks, permeated by these
liquid gases (as porous strata are sometimes filled with water), to have
their temperature raised some hundred degrees, and we obtain a power
capable of lifting superincumbent masses of almost any conceivable thickness;
while, if the depth at which the gas is confined be great, there is
no reason to suppose that any other appearances would be witnessed by
the inhabitants of the surface than vibratory movements and rents, from
which no vapor might escape. In making their way through fissures a
very few miles only in length, or in forcing a passage through soft yielding
strata, the vapors may be cooled and absorbed by water. For water
has a strong affinity to several of the gases, and will absorb large quantities,
with a very slight increase of volume. In this manner, the heat
or the volume of springs may be augmented, and their mineral properties
made to vary.
Connection between the state of the atmosphere and earthquakes.—The
inhabitants of Stromboli, who are mostly fishermen, are said to make
use of that volcano as a weather-glass, the eruptions being comparatively
feeble when the sky is serene, but increasing in turbulence during
tempestuous weather, so that in winter the island often seems to shake
from its foundations. Mr. P. Scrope, after calling attention to these
and other analogous facts, first started the idea (as long ago as the year
1825) that the diminished pressure of the atmosphere, the concomitant
of stormy weather, may modify the intensity of the volcanic action. He
suggests that where liquid lava communicates with the surface, as in
the crater of Stromboli, it may rise or fall in the vent on the same principle
as mercury in a barometer; because the ebullition or expansive
power of the steam contained in the lava would be checked by every
increase, and augmented by every diminution of weight. In like manner,
if a bed of liquid lava be confined at an immense depth below the
surface, its expansive force may be counteracted partly by the weight
of the incumbent rocks, and also in part by atmospheric pressure acting
contemporaneously on a vast superficial area. In that case, if the upheaving
force increase gradually in energy, it will at length be restrained
by only the slightest degree of superiority in the antagonist or repressive
power, and then the equilibrium may be suddenly destroyed by
any cause, such as an ascending draught of air, which is capable of
depressing the barometer. In this manner we may account for the
remarkable coincidence so frequently observed between the state of the
weather and subterranean commotions, although it must be admitted
that earthquakes and volcanic eruptions react in their turn upon the
atmosphere, so that disturbances of the latter are generally the consequences
rather than the forerunners of volcanic disturbances.785
From an elaborate catalogue of the earthquakes experienced in Europe
and Syria during the last fifteen centuries, M. Alexis Perrey has
deduced the conclusion that the number which happen in the winter
562
season preponderates over those which occur in any one of the other
seasons of the year, there being, however, some exceptions to this rule,
as in the Pyrenees. Curious and valuable as are these data, M. d'Archiac
justly remarks, in commenting upon them, that they are not as
yet sufficiently extensive or accordant in different regions, to entitle us
to deduce any general conclusions from them respecting the laws of
subterranean movements throughout the globe.786
Permanent elevation and subsidence.—It is easy to conceive that the
shattered rocks may assume an arched form during a convulsion, so
that the country above may remain permanently upheaved. In other
cases gas may drive before it masses of liquid lava, which may thus be
injected into newly opened fissures. The gas having then obtained
more room, by the forcing up of the incumbent rocks, may remain at
rest; while the lava congealing in the rents may afford a solid foundation
for the newly raised district.
Experiments have recently been made in America, by Colonel Totten,
to ascertain the ratio according to which some of the stones commonly
used in architecture expand with given increments of heat.787 It was
found impossible, in a country where the annual variation of temperature
was more than 90° F., to make a coping of stones, five feet in
length, in which the joints should fit so tightly as not to admit water
between the stone and the cement; the annual contraction and expansion
of the stones causing, at the junctions, small crevices, the width of
which varied with the nature of the rock. It was ascertained that fine-grained
granite expanded with 1° F. at the rate of ·000004825; while
crystalline marble ·000005668; and red sandstone ·000009532, or
about twice as much as granite.
Now, according to this law of expansion, a mass of sandstone a mile
in thickness, which should have its temperature raised 200° F., would
lift a superimposed layer of rock to the height of ten feet above its
former level. But, suppose a part of the earth's crust, one hundred
miles in thickness and equally expansive, to have its temperature raised
600° or 800°, this might produce an elevation of between two and
three thousand feet. The cooling of the same mass might afterwards
cause the overlying rocks to sink down again and resume their original
position. By such agency we might explain the gradual rise of Scandinavia
or the subsidence of Greenland, if this last phenomenon should
also be established as a fact on farther inquiry.
It is also possible that as the clay in Wedgwood's pyrometer contracts,
by giving off its water, and then, by incipient vitrification; so,
large masses of argillaceous strata on the earth's interior may shrink,
when subjected to heat and chemical changes, and allow the incumbent
rocks to subside gradually.
Moreover, if we suppose that lava cooling slowly at great depths
563
may be converted into various granitic rocks, we obtain another source
of depression; for, according to the experiments of Deville and the
calculations of Bischoff, the contraction of granite when passing from a
melted or plastic to a solid and crystalline state must be more than ten
per cent.788 The sudden subsidence of land may also be occasioned by
subterranean caverns giving way, when gases are condensed, or when
they escape through newly-formed crevices. The subtraction, moreover,
of matter from certain parts of the interior, by the flowing of lava
and of mineral springs, must, in the course of ages, cause vacuities
below, so that the undermined surface may at length fall in.
The balance of dry land, how preserved.—In the present state of our
knowledge, we cannot pretend to estimate the average number of earthquakes
which may happen in the course of a single year. As the area of
the ocean is nearly three times that of the land, it is probable that about
three submarine earthquakes may occur for one exclusively continental;
and when we consider the great frequency of slight movements in certain
districts, we can hardly suppose that a day, if, indeed, an hour, ever
passes without one or more shocks being experienced in some part of
the globe. We have also seen that in Sweden, and other countries,
changes in the relative level of sea and land may take place without
commotion, and these perhaps produce the most important geographical
and geological changes; for the position of land may be altered to a
greater amount by an elevation or depression of one inch over a vast
area, than by the sinking of a more limited tract, such as the forest of
Aripao, to the depth of many fathoms at once.789
It must be evident, from the historical details above given, that the
force of subterranean movement, whether intermittent or continuous,
whether with or without disturbance, does not operate at random, but is
developed in certain regions only; and although the alterations produced
during the time required for the occurrence of a few volcanic eruptions
may be inconsiderable, we can hardly doubt that, during the ages
necessary for the formation of large volcanic cones, composed of thousands
of lava currents, shoals might be converted into lofty mountains,
and low lands into deep seas.
In a former chapter (p. 198), I have stated that aqueous and igneous
agents may be regarded as antagonist forces; the aqueous laboring incessantly
to reduce the inequalities of the earth's surface to a level,
while the igneous are equally active in renewing the unevenness of the
surface. By some geologists it has been thought that the levelling power
of running water was opposed rather to the elevating force of earthquakes
than to their action generally. This opinion is, however, untenable;
for the sinking down of the bed of the ocean is one of the
means by which the gradual submersion of land is prevented. The depth
of the sea cannot be increased at any one point without a universal fall
of the waters, nor can any partial deposition of sediment occur without
564
the displacement of a quantity of water of equal volume, which will
raise the sea, though in an imperceptible degree, even to the antipodes.
The preservation, therefore, of the dry land may sometimes be effected
by the subsidence of part of the earth's crust (that part, namely, which
is covered by the ocean), and in like manner an upheaving movement
must often tend to destroy land; for if it render the bed of the sea more
shallow, it will displace a certain quantity of water, and thus tend to
submerge low tracts.
Astronomers having proved (see above, p. 129) that there has been
no change in the diameter of the earth during the last two thousand
years, we may assume it as probable, that the dimensions of the planet
remain uniform. If, then, we inquire in what manner the force of earthquakes
must be regulated, in order to restore perpetually the inequalities
of the surface which the levelling power of water tends to efface, it will
be found, that the amount of depression must exceed that of elevation.
It would be otherwise if the action of volcanoes and mineral springs were
suspended; for then the forcing outwards of the earth's envelope ought
to be no more than equal to its sinking in.
To understand this proposition more clearly, it must be borne in mind,
that the deposits of rivers and currents probably add as much to the
height of lands which are rising, as they take from those which have
risen. Suppose a large river to bring down sediment to a part of the
ocean two thousand feet deep, and that the depth of this part is gradually
reduced by the accumulation of sediment till only a shoal remains,
covered by water at high tides; if now an upheaving force should uplift
this shoal to the height of 2000 feet, the result would be a mountain
2000 feet high. But had the movement raised the same part of the
bottom of the sea before the sediment of the river had filled it up; then,
instead of changing a shoal into a mountain 2000 feet high, it would
only have converted a deep sea into a shoal.
It appears, then, that the operations of the earthquake are often such
as to cause the levelling power of water to counteract itself; and,
although the idea may appear paradoxical, we may be sure, wherever
we find hills and mountains composed of stratified deposits, that such
inequalities of the surface would have had no existence if water, at some
former period, had not been laboring to reduce the earth's surface to
one level.
But, besides the transfer of matter by running water from the continents
to the ocean, there is a constant transportation from below upwards,
by mineral springs and volcanic vents. As mountain masses are,
in the course of ages, created by the pouring forth of successive streams
of lava, so stratified rocks, of great extent, originate from the deposition
of carbonate of lime, and other mineral ingredients, with which springs
are impregnated. The surface of the land, and portions of the bottom
of the sea, being thus raised, the external accessions due to these operations
would cause the dimensions of the planet to enlarge continually, if
the amount of depression of the earth's crust were no more than equal
565
to the elevation. In order, therefore, that the mean diameter of the
earth should remain uniform, and the unevenness of the surface be preserved,
it is necessary that the amount of subsidence should be in excess.
And such a predominance of depression is far from improbable,
on mechanical principles, since every upheaving movement must be
expected either to produce caverns in the mass below, or to cause some
diminution of its density. Vacuities must, also, arise from the subtraction
of the matter poured out from volcanoes and mineral springs,
or from the contraction of argillaceous masses by subterranean heat;
and the foundations having been thus weakened, the earth's crust, shaken
and rent by reiterated convulsions, must, in the course of time, fall in.
If we embrace these views, important geological consequences will
follow; since, if there be, upon the whole, more subsidence than elevation,
the average depth to which former surfaces have sunk beneath
their original level must exceed the height which ancient marine strata
have attained above the sea. If, for example, marine strata, about the
age of our chalk and greensand, have been lifted up in Europe to an extreme
height of more than eleven thousand feet, and a mean elevation of
some hundreds, we may conclude that certain parts of the surface, which
existed when those strata were deposited, have sunk to an extreme depth
of more than eleven thousand feet below their original level, and to a
mean depth of more than a few hundreds.
In regard to faults, also, we must infer, according to the hypothesis
now proposed, that a greater number have arisen from the sinking down
than from the elevation of rocks.
To conclude: it seems to be rendered probable, by the views above
explained, that the constant repair of the land, and the subserviency of
our planet to the support of terrestrial as well as aquatic species, are secured
by the elevating and depressing power of causes acting in the
interior of the earth; which, although so often the source of death and
terror to the inhabitants of the globe—visiting in succession every zone,
and filling the earth with monuments of ruin and disorder—are nevertheless
the agents of a conservative principle above all others essential to
the stability of the system.

566
BOOK III.</div></body></text></TEI>