<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="14"> 

CHAPTER IV.
Of Methods of acquiring clear Scientific Ideas,
continued.—Of the Discussion of Ideas.


Aphorism XXXIII.
The conception involved in scientific truths have attained
the requisite degree of clearness by means of the Discussions
respecting ideas which have taken place among discoverers
and their followers. Such discussions are very far from
being unprofitable to science. They are metaphysical, and
must be so: the difference between discoverers and barren
reasoners is, that the former employ good, and the latter bad
metaphysics.

1. IT
is easily seen that in every part of science, the
establishment of a new set of ideas has been accompanied
with much of doubt and dissent. And by
means of discussions so occasioned, the new conceptions,
and the opinions which involve them, have gradually become
definite and clear. The authors and
asserters of the new opinions, in order to make them
defensible, have been compelled to make them consistent:
in order to recommend them to others, they have
been obliged to make them more entirely intelligible
to themselves. And thus the Terms which formed the
main points of the controversy, although applied in a
loose and vacillating manner at first, have in the end
become perfectly definite and exact. The opinions discussed
have been, in their main features, the same
throughout the debate; but they have at first been
dimly, and at last clearly apprehended: like the objects
of a landscape, at which we look through a telescope
ill adjusted, till, by sliding the tube backwards and 181
forwards, we at last bring it into focus, and perceive
every feature of the prospect sharp and bright.
2. We have in the last
Book21 fully exemplified
this gradual progress of conceptions from obscurity
to clearness by means of Discussion. We have
seen, too, that this mode of treating the subject has
never been successful, except when it has been associated
with an appeal to facts as well as to reasonings.
A combination of experiment with argument, of observation
with demonstration, has always been found
requisite in order that men should arrive at those
distinct conceptions which give them substantial truths.
The arguments used led to the rejection of undefined,
ambiguous, self-contradictory notions; but the reference
to facts led to the selection, or at least to the
retention, of the conceptions which were both true and
useful. The two correlative processes, definition and
true assertion, the formation of clear ideas and the
induction of laws, went on together.</div></body></text></TEI>