<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="118">CHAPTER IV.
The Reform of Linnæus.

Sect. 1.—Introduction of the
Reform.
ALTHOUGH, perhaps, no man of
science ever exercised a greater sway than Linnæus, or had more
enthusiastic admirers, the most intelligent botanists always speak of
him, not as a great discoverer, but as a judicious and strenuous
Reformer. Indeed, in his own lists of botanical writers, he
places himself among the “Reformatores;” and it is apparent that this
is the nature of his real claim to admiration; for the doctrine of the
sexes of plants, even if he had been the first to establish it, was a
point of botanical physiology, a province of the 388 science which no one
would select as the peculiar field of Linnæus’s glory; and the
formation of a system of arrangement on the basis of this doctrine,
though attended with many advantages, was not an improvement of any
higher order than those introduced by Ray and Tournefort. But as a
Reformer of the state of Natural History in his time, Linnæus was
admirable for his skill, and unparalleled in his success. And we have
already seen, in the instance of the reform of mineralogy, as
attempted by Mohs and Berzelius, that men of great talents and
knowledge may fail in such an undertaking.
It is, however, only by means of the knowledge which he displays,
and of the beauty and convenience of the improvements which he
proposes, that any one can acquire such an influence as to procure his
suggestions to be adopted. And even if original circumstances of birth
or position could invest any one with peculiar prerogatives and powers
in the republic of science, Karl Linné began his career with no such
advantages. His father was a poor curate in Smaland, a province of
Sweden; his boyhood was spent in poverty and privation; it was with
great difficulty that, at the age of twenty-one, he contrived to
subsist at the University of Upsal, whither a strong passion for
natural history had urged him. Here, however, he was so far fortunate,
that Olaus Rudbeck, the professor of botany, committed to him the care
of the Botanic Garden.86 The perusal of the works of Vaillant
and Patrick Blair suggested to him the idea of an arrangement of
plants, formed upon the sexual organs, the stamens and pistils; and of
such an arrangement he published a sketch in 1731, at the age of
twenty-four.
86 Sprengel, ii. 232.
But we must go forwards a few years in his life, to come to the
period to which his most important works belong. University and family
quarrels induced him to travel; and, after various changes of scene,
he was settled in Holland, as the curator of the splendid botanical
garden of George Clifford, an opulent banker. Here it was87 that he laid the foundation of his
future greatness. In the two years of his residence at Hartecamp, he published nine works. The first, the
Systema Naturæ, which contained a comprehensive sketch of the
whole domain of Natural History, excited general astonishment, by the
acuteness of the observations, the happy talent of combination, and
the clearness of the systematic views. Such a work could not fail to
procure considerable respect for its author. His Hortus
Cliffortiana 389 and Musa Cliffortiana added to
this impression. The weight which he had thus acquired, he proceeded
to use for the improvement of botany. His Fundamenta Botanica
and Bibliotheca Botanica appeared in 1736; his Critica
Botanica and Genera Plantarum in 1737; his Classes
Plantarum in 1738; his Species Plantarum was not published
till 1753; and all these works appeared in many successive editions,
materially modified.
87 Ibid. 234.
This circulation of his works showed that his labors were producing
their effect. His reputation grew; and he was soon enabled to exert a
personal, as well as a literary, influence, on students of natural
history. He became Botanist Royal, President of the Academy of
Sciences at Stockholm, and Professor in the University of Upsal; and
this office he held for thirty-six years with unrivalled credit;
exercising, by means of his lectures, his constant publications, and
his conversation, an extraordinary power over a multitude of zealous
naturalists, belonging to every part of the world.
In order to understand more clearly the nature and effect of the
reforms introduced by Linnæus into botany, I shall consider them under
the four following heads;—Terminology,
Nomenclature, Artificial System, and Natural
System.
Sect. 2.—Linnæan Reform of Botanical
Terminology.
It must be recollected that I
designate as Terminology, the system of terms employed
in the description of objects of natural history; while by
Nomenclature, I mean the collection of the names of
species. The reform of the descriptive part of botany was one
of the tasks first attempted by Linnæus; and his terminology was the
instrument by which his other improvements were effected.
Though most readers, probably, entertain, at first, a persuasion
that a writer ought to content himself with the use of common words in
their common sense, and feel a repugnance to technical terms and
arbitrary rules of phraseology, as pedantic and troublesome; it is
soon found, by the student of any branch of science that, without
technical terms and fixed rules, there can be no certain or
progressive knowledge. The loose and infantine grasp of common
language cannot hold objects steadily enough for scientific
examination, or lift them from one stage of generalization to another.
They must be secured by the rigid mechanism of a scientific
phraseology. This necessity had been felt in all the sciences, from
the earliest periods of their progress. But the 390 conviction had never
been acted upon so as to produce a distinct and adequate descriptive
botanical language. Jung, indeed,88 had already
attempted to give rules and precepts which should answer this purpose;
but it was not till the Fundamenta Botanica appeared, that the
science could be said to possess a fixed and complete terminology.
88 Isagoge Phytoscopica,
1679.
To give an account of such a terminology, is, in fact, to give a
description of a dictionary and grammar, and is therefore what cannot
here be done in detail. Linnæus’s work contains about a thousand terms
of which the meaning and application are distinctly explained; and
rules are given, by which, in the use of such terms, the botanist may
avoid all obscurity, ambiguity, unnecessary prolixity and complexity,
and even inelegance and barbarism. Of course the greater part of the
words which Linnæus thus recognized had previously existed in
botanical writers; and many of them had been defined with technical
precision. Thus Jung89 had already explained what was a
composite, what a pinnate leaf; what kind of a bunch of
flowers is a spike, a panicle, an umbel, a
corymb, respectively. Linnæus extended such distinctions,
retaining complete clearness in their separation. Thus, with him,
composite leaves are further distinguished as digitate,
pinnate, bipinnate, pedate, and so on; pinnate
leaves are abruptly so, or with an odd one, or with a
tendril; they are pinnate oppositely, alternately,
interruptedly, articulately, decursively. Again,
the inflorescence, as the mode of assemblage of the flowers is
called, may be a tuft (fasciculus), a head (capitulum),
a cluster (racemus), a bunch (thyrsus), a
panicle, a spike, a catkin (amentum), a
corymb, an umbel, a cyme, a whorl
(verticillus). And the rules which he gives, though often apparently
arbitrary and needless, are found, in practice, to be of great service
by their fixity and connexion. By the good fortune of having had a
teacher with so much delicacy of taste as Linnæus, in a situation of
so much influence, Botany possesses a descriptive language which will
long stand as a model for all other subjects.
89 Sprengel, ii. 28.
It may, perhaps, appear to some persons, that such a terminology as
we have here described must be enormously cumbrous; and that, since
the terms are arbitrarily invested with their meaning, the invention
of them requires no knowledge of nature. With respect to the former
doubt, we may observe, that technical description is, in reality, the
only description which is clearly intelligible; but that technical
language cannot be understood without being learnt as any other 391 language is learnt;
that is, the reader must connect the terms immediately with his own
sensations and notions, and not mediately, through a verbal
explanation; he must not have to guess their meaning, or to discover
it by a separate act of interpretation into more familiar language as
often as they occur. The language of botany must be the botanist’s
most familiar tongue. When the student has thus learnt to
think in botanical language, it is no idle distinction to
tell him that a bunch of grapes is not a cluster;
that is, a thyrsus not a raceme. And the terminology
of botany is then felt to be a useful implement, not an oppressive
burden. It is only the schoolboy that complains of the irksomeness of
his grammar and vocabulary. The accomplished student possesses them
without effort or inconvenience.
As to the other question, whether the construction of such a
botanical grammar and vocabulary implies an extensive and accurate
acquaintance with the facts of nature, no one can doubt who is
familiar with any descriptive science. It is true, that a person might
construct an arbitrary scheme of distinctions and appellations, with
no attention to natural objects; and this is what shallow and
self-confident persons often set about doing, in some branch of
knowledge with which they are imperfectly acquainted. But the
slightest attempt to use such a phraseology leads to confusion; and
any continued use of it leads to its demolition. Like a garment which
does not fit us, if we attempt to work in it we tear it in pieces.
The formation of a good descriptive language is, in fact, an
inductive process of the same kind as those which we have already
noticed in the progress of natural history. It requires the
discovery of fixed characters, which discovery is to be marked
and fixed, like other inductive steps, by appropriate technical
terms. The characters must be so far fixed, that the things which
they connect must have a more permanent and real association than the
things which they leave unconnected. If one bunch of grapes were
really a racemus, and another a thyrsus, according to the definition
of these terms, this part of the Linnæan language would lose its
value; because it would no longer enable us to assert a general
proposition with respect to one kind of plants.
Sect. 3.—Linnæan Reform of Botanical
Nomenclature.
In the ancient writers each
recognized kind of plants had a distinct name. The establishment of
Genera led to the practice of designating 392 Species by the name of the genus, with
the addition of a “phrase” to distinguish the species. These phrases,
(expressed in Latin in the ablative case,) were such as not only to
mark, but to describe the species, and were intended to contain such
features of the plant as were sufficient to distinguish it from others
of the same genus. But in this way the designation of a plant often
became a long and inconvenient assemblage of words. Thus different
kinds of Rose were described as,

Rosa campestris, spinis carens, biflora (Rosa alpina.)
Rosa aculeata, foliis odoratis subtus rubiginosis (R.
eglanteria.)
Rosa carolina fragrans, foliis medio tenus serratis (R.
carolina.)
Rosa sylvestris vulgaris, flore odorato incarnato (R.
canina.)
And several others. The prolixity of these
appellations, their variety in every different author, the
insufficiency and confusion of the distinctions which they contained,
were felt as extreme inconveniences. The attempt of Bauhin to remedy
this evil by a Synonymy, had, as we have seen, failed at the time, for want of any
directing principle; and was become still more defective by the lapse
of years and the accumulation of fresh knowledge and new books. Haller
had proposed to distinguish the species of each genus by the numbers
1, 2, 3, and so on; but botanists found that their memory could not
deal with such arbitrary abstractions. The need of some better
nomenclature was severely felt.
The remedy which Linnæus finally introduced was the use of
trivial names; that is, the designation of each species by the
name of the genus along with a single conventional word,
imposed without any general rule. Such names are added above in
parentheses, to the specimens of the names previously in use. But
though this remedy was found to be complete and satisfactory, and is
now universally adopted in every branch of natural history, it was not
one of the reforms which Linnæus at first proposed. Perhaps he did not
at first see its full value; or, if he did, we may suppose that it
required more self-confidence than he possessed, to set himself to
introduce and establish ten thousand new names in the botanical world.
Accordingly, the first attempts of Linnæus at the improvement of the
nomenclature of botany were, the proposal of fixed and careful rules
for the generic name, and for the descriptive phrase. Thus, in his
Critica Botanica, he gives many precepts concerning the
selection of the names of 393 genera, intended to secure convenience
or elegance. For instance, that they are to be single words;90 he substitutes atropa for
bella donna, and leontodon for dens leonis; that
they are not to depend upon the name of another genus,91 as acriviola,
agrimonoides; that they are not92 to be
“sesquipedalia;” and, says he, any word is sesquipedalian to me, which
has more than twelve letters, as kalophyllodendron, for which
he substitutes calophyllon. Though some of these rules may seem
pedantic, there is no doubt that, taken altogether, they tend
exceedingly, like the labors of purists in other languages, to exclude
extravagance, caprice, and barbarism in botanical speech.
90 Phil. Bot. 224.
91 Ib. 228, 229.
92 Ib. 252.
The precepts which he gives for the matter of the “descriptive
phrase,” or, as it is termed in the language of the Aristotelian
logicians, the “differentia,” are, for the most part, results of the
general rule, that the most fixed characters which can be found are to
be used; this rule being interpreted according to all the knowledge of
plants which had then been acquired. The language of the rules was, of
course, to be regulated by the terminology, of which we have already
spoken.
Thus, in the Critica Botanica, the name of a plant is
considered as consisting of a generic word and a specific phrase; and
these are, he says,93 the right and left hands of the plant.
But he then speaks of another kind of name; the trivial name,
which is opposed to the scientific. Such names were, he says,94 those of his predecessors, and
especially of the most ancient of them. Hitherto95 no rules had
been given for their use. He manifestly, at this period, has small
regard for them. “Yet,” he says, “trivial names may, perhaps, be used
on this account,—that the differentia often turns out too
long to be convenient in common use, and may require change as new
species are discovered. However,” he continues, “in this work we set
such names aside altogether, and attend only to the
differentiæ.”
93 Ib. 266.
94 Ib. 261.
95 Ib. 260.
Even in the Species Plantarum, the work which gave general
currency to these trivial names, he does not seem to have yet dared to
propose so great a novelty. They only stand in the margin of the work.
“I have placed them there,” he says in his Preface, “that, without
circumlocution, we may call every herb by a single name; I have done
this without selection, which would require more time. And I beseech
all sane botanists to avoid most religiously ever 394 proposing a trivial
name without a sufficient specific distinction, lest the science
should fall into its former barbarism.”
It cannot be doubted, that the general reception of these trivial
names of Linnæus, as the current language among botanists, was due, in
a very great degree, to the knowledge, care, and skill with which his
characters, both of genera and of species, were constructed. The
rigorous rules of selection and expression which are proposed in the
Fundamenta Botanica and Critica Botanica, he himself
conformed to; and this scrupulosity was employed upon the results of
immense labor. “In order that I might make myself acquainted with the
species of plants,” he says, in the preface to his work upon them, “I
have explored the Alps of Lapland, the whole of Sweden, a part of
Norway, Denmark, Germany, Belgium, England, France: I have examined
the Botanical Gardens of Paris, Oxford, Chelsea, Hartecamp, Leyden, Utrecht, Amsterdam, Upsal, and
others: I have turned over the Herbals of Burser, Hermann, Clifford,
Burmann, Oldenland, Gronovius, Royer, Sloane, Sherard, Bobart, Miller,
Tournefort, Vaillant, Jussieu, Surian, Beck, Brown, &c.: my dear disciples
have gone to distant lands, and sent me plants from thence;  Kalm to Canada, Hasselquist to Egypt,  Osbeck to China, Toren to Surat, Solander to
England, Alstrœmer to Southern Europe, Martin to Spitzbergen, Pontin
to Malabar, Kœhler to Italy, Forskähl to the East, Lœfling to Spain,
Montin to Lapland: my botanical friends have sent me many seeds and
dried plants from various countries: Lagerström many from the East
Indies; Gronovius most of the Virginian; Gmelin all the Siberian;
Burmann those of the Cape.” And in consistency with this habit of
immense collection of materials, is his maxim,96 that “a person
is a better botanist in proportion as he knows more species.” It will
easily be seen that this maxim, like Newton’s declaration that
discovery requires patient thought alone, refers only to the exertions
of which the man of genius is conscious; and leaves out of sight his
peculiar endowments, which he does not see because they are part of
his power of vision. With the taste for symmetry which dictated the
Critica Botanica, and the talent for classification which
appears in the Genera Plantarum, and the Systema Naturæ,
a person must undoubtedly rise to higher steps of classificatory
knowledge and skill, as he became acquainted with a greater number of
facts.
96 Phil. Bot. 259.
The acknowledged superiority of Linnæus in the knowledge of the
395 matter of his
science, induced other persons to defer to him in what concerned its
form; especially when his precepts were, for the most part,
recommended strongly both by convenience and elegance. The trivial
names of the Species Plantarum were generally received; and
though some of the details may have been altered, the immense
advantage of the scheme ensures its permanence.
Sect. 4.—Linnæus’s Artificial System.
We have already seen, that,
from the time of Cæsalpinus, botanists had been endeavoring to frame a
systematic arrangement of plants. All such arrangements were
necessarily both artificial and natural: they were artificial,
inasmuch as they depended upon assumed principles, the number, form,
and position of certain parts, by the application of which the whole
vegetable kingdom was imperatively subdivided; they were
natural, inasmuch as the justification of this division was,
that it brought together those plants which were naturally related. No
system of arrangement, for instance, would have been tolerated which,
in a great proportion of cases, separated into distant parts of the
plan the different species of the same genus. As far as the main body
of the genera, at least, all systems are natural.
But beginning from this line, we may construct our systems with two
opposite purposes, according as we endeavor to carry our assumed
principle of division rigorously and consistently through the system,
or as we wish to associate natural families of a wider kind than
genera. The former propensity leads to an artificial, the latter to a
natural method. Each is a System of Plants; but in the first,
the emphasis is thrown on the former word of the title, in the other,
on the latter.
The strongest recommendation of an artificial system, (besides its
approaching to a natural method,) is, that it shall be capable of easy
use; for which purpose, the facts on which it depends must be apparent
in their relations, and universal in their occurrence. The system of
Linnæus, founded upon the number, position, and other circumstances of
the stamina and pistils, the reproductive organs of the plants,
possessed this merit in an eminent degree, as far as these characters
are concerned; that is, as far as the classes and orders. In its
further subdivision into genera, its superiority was mainly due to the
exact observation and description, which we have already had to notice
as talents which Linnæus peculiarly possessed.
The Linnæan system of plants was more definite than that of 396 Tournefort, which was
governed by the corolla; for number is more definite than irregular
form. It was more readily employed than any of those which depend on
the fruit, for the flower is a more obvious object, and more easily
examined. Still, it can hardly be doubted, that the circumstance which
gave the main currency to the system of Linnæus was its physiological
signification: it was the Sexual System. The relation of the
parts to which it directed the attention, interested both the
philosophical faculty and the imagination. And when, soon after the
system had become familiar in our own country, the poet of The
Botanic Garden peopled the bell of every flower with “Nymphs” and
“Swains,” his imagery was felt to be by no means forced and
far-fetched.
The history of the doctrine of the sexes of plants, as a point of
physiology, does not belong to this place; and the Linnæan system of
classification need not be longer dwelt upon for our present purpose.
I will only explain a little further what has been said, that it is,
up to a certain point, a natural system. Several of Linnæus’s classes
are, in a great measure, natural associations, kept together in
violation of his own artificial rules. Thus the class
Diadelphia, in which, by the system, the filaments of the
stamina should be bound together in two parcels, does, in fact,
contain many genera which are monadelphous, the filaments of
the stamina all cohering so as to form one bundle only; as in
Genista, Spartium, Anthyllis, Lupinus,
&c. And why is this violation of rule? Precisely because these
genera all belong to the natural tribe of Papilionaceous plants, which
the author of the system could not prevail upon himself to tear
asunder. Yet in other cases Linnæus was true to his system, to the
injury of natural alliances, as he was, for instance, in another
portion of this very tribe of Papilionaceæ; for there are
plants which undoubtedly belong to the tribe, but which have ten
separate stamens; and these he placed in the order Decandria.
Upon the whole, however, he inclines rather to admit transgression of
art than of nature.
The reason of this inclination was, that he rightly considered an
artificial method as instrumental to the investigation of a natural
one; and to this part of his views we now proceed.
Sect. 5.—Linnæus’s Views on a Natural
Method.
The admirers of Linnæus, the
English especially, were for some time in the habit of putting his
Sexual System in opposition to the Natural Method, which about the
same time was attempted in France. And 397 as they often appear to have imagined
that the ultimate object of botanical methods was to know the name of
plants, they naturally preferred the Swedish method, which is
excellent as a finder. No person, however, who wishes to know
botany as a science, that is, as a body of general truths, can be
content with making names his ultimate object. Such a person will be
constantly and irresistibly led on to attempt to catch sight of the
natural arrangement of plants, even before he discovers, as he will
discover by pursuing such a course of study, that the knowledge of the
natural arrangement is the knowledge of the essential construction and
vital mechanism of plants. He will consider an artificial method as a
means of arriving at a natural method. Accordingly, however much some
of his followers may have overlooked this, it is what Linnæus himself
always held and taught. And though what he executed with regard to
this object was but little,97 the distinct
manner in which he presented the relations of an artificial and
natural method, may justly be looked upon as one of the great
improvements which he introduced into the study of his science.
97 The natural orders which he
proposed are a bare enumeration of genera, and have not been generally
followed.
Thus in the Classes Plantarum (1747), he speaks of the
difficulty of the task of discovering the natural orders, and of the
attempts made by others. “Yet,” he adds, “I too have labored at this,
have done something, have much still to do, and shall labor at the
object as long as I live.” He afterwards proposed sixty-seven orders,
as the fragments of a natural method, always professing their
imperfection.98 And in others of his works99 he lays down some antitheses on the
subject after his manner. “The natural orders teach us the nature of
plants; the artificial orders enable us to recognize plants. The
natural orders, without a key, do not constitute a Method; the Method
ought to be available without a master.”
98 Phil. Bot. p. 80.
99 Genera Plantarum, 1764. See
Prælect. in Ord. Nat. p. xlviii.
That extreme difficulty must attend the formation of a Natural
Method, may be seen from the very indefinite nature of the Aphorisms
upon this subject which Linnæus has delivered, and which the best
botanists of succeeding times have assented to. Such are
these;—the Natural Orders must be formed by attention, not to
one or two, but to all the parts of plants;—the same
organs are of great importance in regulating the divisions of one part
of the system, and 398 of small importance in another part;100—the Character does not
constitute the Genus, but the Genus the Character;—the Character
is necessary, not to make the Genus, but to recognize it. The
vagueness of these maxims is easily seen; the rule of attending to all
the parts, implies, that we are to estimate their relative importance,
either by physiological considerations (and these again lead to
arbitrary rules, as, for instance, the superiority of the function of
nutrition to that of reproduction), or by a sort of latent naturalist
instinct, which Linnæus in some passages seems to recognize. “The
Habit of a plant,” he says,101 “must be
secretly consulted. A practised botanist will distinguish, at the
first glance, the plants of different quarters of the globe, and yet
will be at a loss to tell by what mark he detects them. There is, I
know not what look,—sinister, dry, obscure in African plants;
superb and elevated, in the Asiatic; smooth and cheerful, in the
American; stunted and indurated, in the Alpine.”
100 Phil. Bot. p. 172.
101 Ib. p. 171.
Again, the rule that the same parts are of very different value in
different Orders, not only leaves us in want of rules or reasons which
may enable us to compare the marks of different Orders, but destroys
the systematic completeness of the natural arrangement. If some of the
Orders be regulated by the flower and others by the fruit, we may have
plants, of which the flower would place them in one Order, and the
fruit in another. The answer to this difficulty is the maxim already
stated;—that no Character makes the Order; and that if a
Character do not enable us to recognize the Order, it does not answer
its purpose, and ought to be changed for another.
This doctrine, that the Character is to be employed as a servant
and not as a master, was a stumbling-block in the way of those
disciples who looked only for dogmatical and universal rules. One of
Linnæus’s pupils, Paul Dietrich Giseke, has given us a very lively
account of his own perplexity on having this view propounded to him,
and of the way in which he struggled with it. He had complained of the
want of intelligible grounds, in the collection of natural orders
given by Linnæus. Linnæus102 wrote in
answer, “You ask me for the characters of the Natural Orders: I
confess I cannot give them.” Such a reply naturally increased Giseke’s
difficulties. But afterwards, in 1771, he had the good fortune to
spend some time at Upsal; and he narrates a conversation which he held
with the great 399
teacher on this subject, and which I think may serve to show the
nature of the difficulty;—one by no means easily removed, and by
the general reader, not even readily comprehended with distinctness.
Giseke began by conceiving that an Order must have that
attribute from which its name is derived;—that the
Umbellatæ must have their flower disposed in an umbel. The
“mighty master” smiled,103 and told him not to look at names, but
at nature. “But” (said the pupil) “what is the use of the name, if it
does not mean what it professes to mean?” “It is of small import”
(replied Linnæus) “what you call the Order, if you
take a proper series of plants and give it some name, which is clearly
understood to apply to the plants which you have associated. In such
cases as you refer to, I followed the logical rule, of borrowing a
name a potiori, from the principal member. Can you” (he added)
“give me the character of any single Order?” Giseke. “Surely,
the character of the Umbellatæ is, that they have an umbel?”
Linnæus. “Good; but there are plants which have an umbel, and
are not of the Umbellatæ.” G. “I remember. We must
therefore add, that they have two naked seeds.” L. “Then,
Echinophora, which has only one seed, and Eryngium,
which has not an umbel, will not be Umbellatæ; and yet they are
of the Order.” G. “I would place Eryngium among the
Aggregatæ. L. “No; both are beyond dispute
Umbellatæ. Eryngium has an involucrum, five stamina, two
pistils, &c. Try again for your Character.” G. “I would
transfer such plants to the end of the Order, and make them form the
transition to the next Order. Eryngium would connect the
Umbellatæ with the Aggregatæ.” L. “Ah! my good
friend, the Transition from Order to Order is one thing; the
Character of an Order is another. The Transitions I could
indicate; but a Character of a Natural Order is impossible. I will not
give my reasons for the distribution of Natural Orders which I have
published. You or some other person, after twenty or after fifty
years, will discover them, and see I was in the right.”
102 Linnæi Prælectiones,
Pref. p. xv.
103 “Subrisit ὁ πανυ.”
I have given a portion of this curious conversation in order to
show that the attempt to establish Natural Orders leads to convictions
which are out of the domain of the systematic grounds on which they
profess to proceed. I believe the real state of the case to be that
the systematist, in such instances, is guided by an unformed and
undeveloped apprehension of physiological functions. The ideas of the
form, 400 number,
and figure of parts are, in some measure, overshadowed and superseded
by the rising perception of organic and vital relations; and the
philosopher who aims at a Natural Method, while he is endeavoring
merely to explore the apartment in which he had placed himself, that
of Arrangement, is led beyond it, to a point where another light
begins, though dimly, to be seen; he is brought within the influence
of the ideas of Organization and Life.
The sciences which depend on these ideas will be the subject of our
consideration hereafter. But what has been said may perhaps serve to
explain the acknowledged and inevitable imperfection of the
unphysiological Linnæan attempts towards a natural method. “Artificial
Glasses are,” Linnæus says, “a substitute for Natural, till Natural
are detected.” But we have not yet a Natural Method. “Nor,” he says,
in the conversation above cited, “can we have a Natural Method; for a
Natural Method implies Natural Classes and Orders; and these Orders
must have Characters.” “And they,” he adds in another place,104 “who, though they cannot obtain a
complete Natural Method, arrange plants according to the fragments of
such a method, to the rejection of the Artificial, seem to me like
persons who pull down a convenient vaulted room, and set about
building another, though they cannot turn the vault which is to cover
it.”
104 Gen. Plant. in Prælect.
p. xii.
How far these considerations deterred other persons from turning
their main attention to a natural method, we shall shortly see; but in
the mean time, we must complete the history of the Linnæan Reform.
Sect. 6.—Reception and Diffusion of the Linnæan
Reform.
We have already seen that
Linnæus received, from his own country, honors and emoluments which
mark his reputation as established, as early as 1740; and by his
publications, his lectures, and his personal communications, he soon
drew round him many disciples, whom he impressed strongly with his own
doctrines and methods. It would seem that the sciences of
classification tend, at least in modern times more than other
sciences, to collect about the chair of the teacher a large body of
zealous and obedient pupils; Linnæus and Werner were by far the most
powerful heads of schools of any men who appeared in the course of the
last century. Perhaps one reason of this is, that in these sciences,
consisting of such an enormous multitude of species, of descriptive
401 particulars,
and of previous classifications, the learner is dependent upon the
teacher more completely, and for a longer time than in other subjects
of speculation: he cannot so soon or so easily cast off the aid and
influence of the master, to pursue reasonings and hypotheses of his
own. Whatever the cause may be, the fact is, that the reputation and
authority of Linnæus, in the latter part of his life, were immense. He
enjoyed also royal favor, for the King and Queen of Sweden were both
fond of natural history. In 1753, Linnæus received from the hand of
his sovereign the knighthood of the Polar Star, an honor which had
never before been conferred for literary merit; and in 1756, was
raised to the rank of Swedish nobility by the title of Von Linné; and
this distinction was confirmed by the Diet in 1762. He lived, honored
and courted, to the age of seventy-one; and in 1778 was buried in the
cathedral of Upsal, with many testimonials of public respect and
veneration.
De Candolle105 assigns, as the causes of the
successes of the Linnæan system,—the specific names,—the
characteristic phrase,—the fixation of descriptive
language,—the distinction of varieties and species,—the
extension of the method to all the kingdoms of nature,—and the
practice of introducing into it the species most recently discovered.
This last course Linnæus constantly pursued; thus making his works the
most valuable for matter, as they were the most convenient in form.
The general diffusion of his methods over Europe may be dated,
perhaps, a few years after 1760, when the tenth and the succeeding
editions of the Systema Naturæ were in circulation, professing
to include every species of organized beings. But his pupils and
correspondents effected no less than his books, in giving currency to
his system. In Germany,106 it was defended by Ludwig, Gesner,
Fabricius. But Haller, whose reputation in physiology was as great as
that of Linnæus in methodology, rejected it as too merely artificial.
In France, it did not make any rapid or extensive progress: the best
French botanists were at this time occupied with the solution of the
great problem of the construction of a Natural Method. And though the
rhetorician Rousseau charmed, we may suppose, with the elegant
precision of the Philosophia Botanica, declared it to be the
most philosophical work he had ever read in his life, Buffon and
Andanson, describers and philosophers of a more ambitious school, felt
a repugnance to the rigorous rules, and limited, but finished,
undertakings of the Swedish naturalist. To resist his 402 criticism and his
influence, they armed themselves with dislike and contempt.
105 Théor. Elém. p. 40.
106 Sprengel, ii. 244.
In England the Linnæan system was very favorably
received:—perhaps the more favorably, for being a strictly
artificial system. For the indefinite and unfinished form which almost
inevitably clings to a natural method, appears to be peculiarly
distasteful to our countrymen. It might seem as if the suspense and
craving which comes with knowledge confessedly incomplete were so
disagreeable to them, that they were willing to avoid it, at any rate
whatever; either by rejecting system altogether, or by accepting a
dogmatical system without reserve. The former has been their course in
recent times with regard to Mineralogy; the latter was their
proceeding with respect to the Linnæan Botany. It is in this country
alone, I believe, that Wernerian and Linnæan Societies have been
instituted. Such appellations somewhat remind us of the Aristotelian
and Platonic schools of ancient Greece. In the same spirit it was,
that the Artificial System was at one time here considered, not as
subsidiary and preparatory to the Natural Orders, but as opposed to
them. This was much as if the disposition of an army in a review
should be considered as inconsistent with another arrangement of it in
a battle.
When Linnæus visited England in 1736, Sloane, then the patron of
natural history in this country, is said to have given him a cool
reception, such as was perhaps most natural from an old man to a young
innovator; and Dillenius, the Professor at Oxford, did not accept the
sexual system. But as Pulteney, the historian of English Botany, says,
when his works became known, “the simplicity of the classical
characters, the uniformity of the generic notes, all confined to the
parts of the fructification, and the precision which marked the
specific distinctions, merits so new, soon commanded the assent of the
unprejudiced.”
Perhaps the progress of the introduction of the Linnæan System into
England will be best understood from the statement of T. Martyn, who
was Professor of Botany in the University of Cambridge, from 1761 to
1825. “About the year 1750,” he says,107 “I was a
pupil of the school of our great countryman Ray; but the rich vein of
knowledge, the profoundness and precision, which I remarked everywhere
in the Philosophia Botanica, (published in 1751,) withdrew me
from my first master, and I became a decided convert to that system of
botany which has since been generally received. In 1753, the
Species 403
Plantarum, which first introduced the specific names, made me a
Linnæan completely.” In 1763, he introduced the system in his lectures
at Cambridge, and these were the first Linnæan lectures in England.
Stillingfleet had already, in 1757, and Lee, in 1760, called the
attention of English readers to Linnæus. Sir J. Hill, (the king’s
gardener at Kew,) in his Flora Britannica, published in 1760,
had employed the classes and generic characters, but not the
nomenclature; but the latter was adopted by Hudson, in 1762, in the
Flora Anglica.
107 Pref. to Language of
Botany, 3rd edit. 1807.
Two young Swedes, pupils of Linnæus, Dryander and Solander, settled
in England, and were in intimate intercourse with the most active
naturalists, especially with Sir Joseph Banks, of whom the former was
librarian, and the latter a fellow-traveller in Cook’s celebrated
voyage. James Edward Smith was also one of the most zealous disciples
of the Linnæan school; and, after the death of Linnæus, purchased his
Herbariums and Collections. It is related,108 as a curious
proof of the high estimation in which Linnæus was held, that when the
Swedish government heard of this bargain, they tried, though too late,
to prevent these monuments of their countryman’s labor and glory being
carried from his native land, and even went so far as to send a
frigate in pursuit of the ship which conveyed them to England. Smith
had, however, the triumph of bringing them home in safety. On his
death they were purchased by the Linnæan Society. Such relics serve,
as will easily be imagined, not only to warm the reverence of his
admirers, but to illustrate his writings: and since they have been in
this country, they have been the object of the pilgrimage of many a
botanist, from every part of Europe.
108 Trapp’s Transl. of Stower’s
Life of Linnæus, p. 314.
I have purposely confined myself to the history of the Linnæan
system in the cases in which it is most easily applicable, omitting
all consideration of more obscure and disputed kinds of vegetables, as
ferns, mosses, fungi, lichens, sea-weeds, and the like. The nature and
progress of a classificatory science, which it is our main purpose to
bring into view, will best be understood by attending, in the first
place, to the cases in which such a science has been pursued with the
most decided success; and the advances which have been made in the
knowledge of the more obscure vegetables, are, in fact, advances in
artificial classification, only in as far as they are advances in
natural classification, and in physiology.
To these subjects we now proceed. 404</div></body></text></TEI>