<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="4"> 

CHAPTER V.
Of Certain Characteristics of Scientific Induction.


Aphorism X.
The process of scientific discovery is cautious and rigorous,
not by abstaining from hypotheses, but by rigorously comparing
hypotheses with facts, and by resolutely rejecting all
which the comparison does not confirm.
Aphorism XI.
Hypotheses may be useful, though involving much that is
superfluous, and even erroneous: for they may supply the
true bond of connexion of the facts; and the superfluity and
errour may afterwards be pared away.
Aphorism XII.
It is a test of true theories not only to account for, but to
predict phenomena.
Aphorism XIII.
Induction is a term applied to describe the process of a
true Colligation of Facts by means of an exact and appropriate
Conception. An Induction is also employed to denote
the proposition which results from this process.
Aphorism XIV.
The Consilience of Inductions takes place when an
Induction, obtained from one class of facts, coincides with
an Induction, obtained from another different class. This 71
Consilience is a test of the truth of the Theory in which it
occurs.
Aphorism XV.
An Induction is not the mere sum of the Facts which are
colligated. The Facts are not only brought together, but seen
in a new point of view. A new mental Element is superinduced;
and a peculiar constitution and discipline of mind
are requisite in order to make this Induction.
Aphorism XVI.
Although in Every Induction a new conception is superinduced
upon the Facts; yet this once effectually done, the
novelty of the conception is overlooked, and the conception is
considered as a part of the fact.
Sect. I.—Invention a part of Induction.

1. THE
two operations spoken of in the preceding
chapters,—the Explication of the Conceptions
of our own minds, and the Colligation of observed Facts
by the aid of such Conceptions,—are, as we have just
said, inseparably connected with each other. When
united, and employed in collecting knowledge from the
phenomena which the world presents to us, they constitute
the mental process of Induction; which is usually and
justly spoken of as the genuine source of all
our real general knowledge respecting the external
world. And we see, from the preceding analysis of
this process into its two constituents, from what origin
it derives each of its characters. It is real, because it
arises from the combination of Real Facts, but it is
general, because it implies the possession of General
Ideas. Without the former, it would not be knowledge of the
External World; without the latter, it
would not be Knowledge at all. When Ideas and
Facts are separated from each other, the neglect of
Facts gives rise to empty speculations, idle subtleties,
visionary inventions, false opinions concerning the laws
of phenomena, disregard of the true aspect of nature: 72
while the want of Ideas leaves the mind overwhelmed,
bewildered, and stupified by particular sensations, with
no means of connecting the past with the future, the
absent with the present, the example with the rule;
open to the impression of all appearances, but capable
of appropriating none. Ideas are the Form, facts the
Material, of our structure. Knowledge does not
consist in the empty mould, or in the brute mass of matter,
but in the rightly-moulded substance. Induction
gathers general truths from particular facts;—and in
her harvest, the corn and the reaper, the solid ears and
the binding band, are alike requisite. All our knowledge
of nature is obtained by Induction; the term
being understood according to the explanation we have
now given. And our knowledge is then most complete, then
most truly deserves the name of Science,
when both its elements are most perfect;—when the
Ideas which have been concerned in its formation have,
at every step, been clear and consistent; and when
they have, at every step also, been employed in binding
together real and certain Facts. Of such Induction,
I have already given so many examples and illustrations
in the two preceding chapters, that I need not
now dwell further upon the subject.
2. Induction is familiarly spoken of as the process
by which we collect a General Proposition from a number
of Particular Cases: and it appears to be frequently
imagined that the general proposition results
from a mere juxta-position of the cases, or at most, from
merely conjoining and extending them. But if we
consider the process more closely, as exhibited in the
cases lately spoken of, we shall perceive that this is an
inadequate account of the matter. The particular
facts are not merely brought together, but there is a
New Element added to the combination by the very
act of thought by which they are combined. There is
a Conception of the mind introduced in the general
proposition, which did not exist in any of the observed
facts. When the Greeks, after long observing the
motions of the planets, saw that these motions might
be rightly considered as produced by the motion of one 73
wheel revolving in the inside of another wheel, these
Wheels were Creations of their minds, added to the
Facts which they perceived by sense. And even if the
wheels were no longer supposed to be material, but
were reduced to mere geometrical spheres or circles,
they were not the less products of the mind alone,—something
additional to the facts observed. The same
is the case in all other discoveries. The facts are
known, but they are insulated and unconnected, till
the discoverer supplies from his own stores a Principle
of Connexion. The pearls are there, but they will not
hang together till some one provides the String. The
distances and periods of the planets were all so many
separate facts; by Kepler’s Third Law they are connected
into a single truth: but the Conceptions which
this law involves were supplied by Kepler’s mind, and
without these, the facts were of no avail. The planets
described ellipses round the sun, in the contemplation
of others as well as of Newton; but Newton conceived
the deflection from the tangent in these elliptical
motions in a new light,—as the effect of a Central Force
following a certain law; and then it was, that such a
force was discovered truly to exist.
Thus5
in each inference made by Induction, there is
introduced some General Conception, which is given,
not by the phenomena, but by the mind. The conclusion
is not contained in the premises, but includes
them by the introduction of a New Generality. In
order to obtain our inference, we travel beyond the
cases which we have before us; we consider them as
mere exemplifications of some Ideal Case in which the
relations are complete and intelligible. We take a
Standard, and measure the facts by it; and this
Standard is constructed by us, not offered by Nature.
We assert, for example, that a body left to itself will
move on with unaltered velocity; not because our
senses ever disclosed to us a body doing this, but
because (taking this as our Ideal Case) we find that all 74
actual cases are intelligible and explicable by means of
the Conception of Forces, causing change and motion,
and exerted by surrounding bodies. In like manner,
we see bodies striking each other, and thus moving and
stopping, accelerating and retarding each other: but
in all this, we do not perceive by our senses that
abstract quantity, Momentum, which is always lost by
one body as it is gained by another. This Momentum
is a creation of the mind, brought in among the facts,
in order to convert their apparent confusion into order,
their seeming chance into certainty, their perplexing
variety into simplicity. This the Conception of Momentum
gained and lost does: and in like manner, in
any other case in which a truth is established by Induction,
some Conception is introduced, some Idea is
applied, as the means of binding together the facts,
and thus producing the truth.</div></body></text></TEI>