<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 165, folios 128-131</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 165, folios 128-131.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1838">undated [July 1838]</date>
          <note type="place">[no place]</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 165, folios 128-131</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_165_folios_128-131.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Weddy. Morg.</p>
      <p>It is a great relief to me that you approve of all I have done, for I was very anxious about it.-- I did not expect much that you could come up before Thursday.--</p>
      <p>I think Anne should come certainly, as I have requested Green to take our housekeeping at Ashley, making of tea, coffee &amp;c, &amp; she cannot do this unless she has a nursery assistant.</p>
      <p>Besides this, I think Anne with the help of the cook, should act as housemaid.--</p>
      <p>But perhaps it is on account of the small-pox, that you question the propriety of her going. If so, you had better talk to Green about it.--</p>
      <p>Whatever you decide about the riding horses, I shall think best. I do not know if I quite like the idea of those steep stony hills on a horse only used to plain roads.--</p>
      <p>I hope you will not think I have done wrong in engaging</p>
      <p>a pair of horses for today.-- As I was to pay a guinea at any rate, I determined to make the most of the money, &amp; mean to go to Fordhook, see the De Morgans &amp; get the things I wanted from there. The drive will be a nice wholesome one, &amp; besides this I shall be able to make use of the beasts for Town today.--</p>
      <p>Are you aware that Mrs Cattermole set out for Ockham at 3 o'clock in the morning of yesterday. I am glad of it, for she will be the most comfortable nurse for her</p>
      <p>husband. Some one kindly lent her a gig, &amp; I heard on its return yesterday that the coachman was much better &amp; doing most favorably. This is exactly what Dr Locock expected to hear, &amp; I think it seems probable that the man caught the disease from John, but that the vaccination delayed its appearance. You know he says he has been unwell the last 3 weeks or more.-- Do ask Mrs Cattermole about John, for I have heard through her that he is quite out of danger, &amp; eating enormously. Mrs Cattermole has been sending things to him, which are now</p>
      <p>requisite, &amp; not furnished at the hospital. Had you made any arrangements about this? If not, we ought to do so, for after such a desperate illness he will no doubt require excellent feeding.--</p>
      <p>My vaccinated arm does not trouble me in the least at present. I believe before tomorrow it is hardly likely to show much, but there is a little red circle round each of the two places, which I think indicates it was done effectually.-- The child was a little merry healthy boy of 5 months old, who kept laughing &amp; rocking his body backwards</p>
      <p>&amp; forwards, so that Dr L had great difficulty in taking the matter from him.-- I am extremely comfortable in my little suite of rooms.</p>
      <p>Will you say I wish my old parasol, the one lined with white silk, to be brought. Also a small parcel containing bottles, which was taken to Ockham by the coachman who went down on Monday, &amp; which is of some consequence to me, as it contains things for my teeth.-- Likewise please tell Green to bring me</p>
      <p>a night-shift for tomorrow night with her, &amp; indeed she had best likewise bring a day-shift &amp; a pari of trowsers for Friday, in case the carrier should not come in time.--</p>
      <p>Take a stock of letter-wax pray, both for here &amp; Ashley.</p>
      <p>Do have your 6 shirts from the school, enquired for &amp; brought, if they have not already come, &amp; let them have the marking undone, for that can be added at any time.--</p>
      <p>I shall answer the enclosed,</p>
      <p>after you come.</p>
      <p>I have got three orders for the Zoological Gardens, &amp; the regulations &amp; list of members. If I am to be a member, I must be proposed now or soon, to be elected for next year. It is done by ballot, 3 members proposing the candidate, &amp; many ladies are members. I shall I think ask Mr Philip Coxe to manage it for me, if I decide to be a member, he is one. It is only necessary for one of the proposing members to be acquainted with the candidate.</p>
      <p>All this I got at the office in Leicester Sqre today, &amp; my 3 orders, gratis. I want to take B.</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
