<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 165, folios 68-69</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 165, folios 68-69.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1836">9 December [1836]</date>
          <note type="place">Ockham</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 165, folios 68-69</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_165_folios_68-69.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Ockham Thursday Evg. Decr 9</p>
      <p>My Dearest Mate. A sad disappointment this morning, when I had certainly reckoned on a letter from Exeter!--</p>
      <p>The house is very vacant without you, though I have no business to complain when the dear kind Hen is here.--</p>
      <p>There is an enclosure of this morning written on smart pink paper for your mother,</p>
      <p>and I think the hand is Emily's, but there is not a line for you. I strongly suspect she is affronted.--</p>
      <p>I am delighted with the progress of the hot-house. miss D'Espourria &amp; I stood in admiration of it today.--</p>
      <p>The Hen has just brought down a letter for you, which she (naughty bird!) won't let me (poor little thing!) read.-- Do not believe any bad she may have said of me, for I assure you I am a very dear little thing!--</p>
      <p>The Hen is charmed with</p>
      <p>Rickman's Architecture, which came by the Cab. She cuts open all the new books she can find.-- I have sent my dressing case to Town to be done the best with which the case admits of.--</p>
      <p>A leg has just come off one of the hideous screens in the sitting room, and the generous Hen insists on giving me some instead. I am only afraid you may have ordered some.-- I mean to give her a clock for Fordhood Chimney Piece for mine has left a sad</p>
      <p>gap behind it.--</p>
      <p>On Sunday we have no general post at Fordhook, but on Monday I expect to hear from you there. How I long to see your hand- writing! I am afraid I am but a silly little bird.</p>
      <p>Lady George Murray offers to come here on Tuesday or Wednesday next. I have told her I shall then be away, but hope she can come later.-- The little Bird, with its young, chirps at ou, &amp; says Good Bye.</p>
      <p>Your most affecte A. A. K.</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
