<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Sketch of the Analytical Engine with Notes by the Translator</title><author>Menabrea, Luigi; Lovelace, Ada</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1843</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="9">
NOTE G.—Page 24.
It is desirable to guard against the possibility of exaggerated
ideas that might arise as to the powers of the Analytical Engine. In
considering any new subject, there is frequently a tendency, first, to
overrate what we find to be already interesting or remarkable;
and, secondly, by a sort of natural reaction, to undervalue
the true state of the case, when we do discover that our notions have
surpassed those that were really tenable.
The Analytical Engine has no pretensions whatever to originate
any thing. It can do whatever we know how to order it to
perform. It can follow analysis; but it has no power of
anticipating any analytical relations or truths. Its province
is to assist us in making available what we are already
acquainted with. This it is calculated to effect primarily and chiefly
of course, through its executive faculties; but it is likely to exert
an indirect and reciprocal influence on science itself in
another manner. For, in so distributing and combining the truths and
the formulæ of analysis, that they may become most easily and rapidly
amenable to the mechanical combinations of the engine, the relations
and the nature of many subjects in that science are necessarily thrown
into new lights, and more profoundly investigated. This is a decidedly
indirect, and a somewhat speculative, consequence of such an
invention. It is however pretty evident, on general principles, that
in devising for mathematical truths a new form in which to record and
throw themselves out for actual use, views are likely to be induced,
which should again react on the more theoretical phase of the subject.
There are in all extensions of human power, or additions to human
[Pg 57]
knowledge, various collateral influences, besides the main and
primary object attained.
To return to the executive faculties of this engine: the question must
arise in every mind, are they really even able to follow
analysis in its whole extent? No reply, entirely satisfactory to all
minds, can be given to this query, excepting the actual existence of
the engine, and actual experience of its practical results. We will
however sum up for each reader’s consideration the chief elements with
which the engine works:—
1. It performs the four operations of simple arithmetic upon any
numbers whatever.
2. By means of certain artifices and arrangements (upon which we
cannot enter within the restricted space which such a publication
as the present may admit of), there is no limit either to the
magnitude of the numbers used, or to the number of
quantities (either variables or constants) that may be employed.
3. It can combine these numbers and these quantities either
algebraically or arithmetically, in relations unlimited as to variety,
extent, or complexity.
4. It uses algebraic signs according to their proper laws, and
developes the logical consequences of these laws.
5. It can arbitrarily substitute any formula for any other; effacing
the first from the columns on which it is represented, and making the
second appear in its stead.
6. It can provide for singular values. Its power of doing this is
referred to in M. Menabrea’s memoir, page 20, where he mentions the
passage of values through zero and infinity. The practicability of
causing it arbitrarily to change its processes at any moment, on the
occurrence of any specified contingency (of which its substitution of

for () explained in Note E.,
is in some degree an illustration), at once secures this point.
The subject of integration and of differentiation demands some notice.
The engine can effect these processes in either of two ways:—
First. We may order it, by means of the Operation and of the
Variable-cards, to go through the various steps by which the required
limit can be worked out for whatever function is under
consideration.
Secondly. It may (if we know the form of the limit for the function
in question) effect the integration or differentiation by direct[28]
substitution. We remarked in Note B., that any set of columns
[Pg 58]
on which numbers are inscribed, represents merely a general
function of the several quantities, until the special function
have been impressed by means of the Operation and Variable-cards.
Consequently, if instead of requiring the value of the function, we
require that of its integral, or of its differential coefficient, we
have merely to order whatever particular combination of the ingredient
quantities may constitute that integral or that coefficient. In
, for instance, instead of the quantities













being ordered to appear on  in the combination
, they would be ordered to appear in that of


They would then stand thus:—












Similarly, we might have , the integral of
.
An interesting example for following out the processes of the engine
would be such a form as

or any other cases of integration by successive reductions, where an
integral which contains an operation repeated  times can be made
to depend upon another which contains the same  or 
times, and so on until by continued reduction we arrive at a certain
ultimate form, whose value has then to be determined.
The methods in Arbogat’s Calcul des Dérivations are peculiarly
fitted for the notation and the processes of the engine. Likewise the
whole of the Combinatorial Analysis, which consists first in a purely
numerical calculation of indices, and secondly in the distribution and
combination of the quantities according to laws prescribed by these
indices.
We will terminate these Notes by following up in detail the steps
through which the engine could compute the Numbers of Bernoulli, this
being (in the form in which we shall deduce it) a rather complicated
example of its powers. The simplest manner of computing those numbers
would be from the direct expansion of
[Pg 59]
which is in fact a particular case of the development of

mentioned in Note E. Or again, we might compute them from the
well-known form

or from the form

or from many others. As however our object is not simplicity or
facility of computation, but the illustration of the powers of the
engine, we prefer selecting the formula below, marked (8.). This is
derived in the following manner:—
If in the equation

(in which ,  ..., &c. are the
Numbers of Bernoulli), we expand the denominator of the first side in
powers of , and then divide both numerator and denominator by
, we shall derive

If this latter multiplication be actually performed, we shall have a
series of the general form

in which we see, first, that all the coefficients of the powers of
 are severally equal to zero; and secondly, that the general form
for  the coefficient of the 2()th term
(that is of  even any power of ), is the
following:—

[Pg 60]
Multiplying every term by () we have

which it may be convenient to write under the general form:—

, , &c. being those functions of  which respectively belong to
, , &c.
We might have derived a form nearly similar to (8.), from
 the coefficient of any odd power of
 in (6.); but the general form is a little different for the
coefficients of the odd powers, and not quite so convenient.
On examining (7.) and (8.), we perceive that, when these formulæ
are isolated from (6.) whence they are derived, and considered in
themselves separately and independently,  may be any whole
number whatever; although when (7.) occurs as one of the
’s in (6.), it is obvious that  is then not
arbitrary, but is always a certain function of the distance of
that  from the beginning. If that distance be
= , then

It is with the independent formula (8.) that we have to do.
Therefore it must be remembered that the conditions for the value of
 are now modified, and that  is a perfectly arbitrary
whole number. This circumstance, combined with the fact (which we may
easily perceive) that whatever  is, every term of (8.) after the
()th is = 0, and that the ()th term itself is always
 enables us
to find the value (either numerical or algebraical) of any th
Number of Bernoulli , in terms of all the
preceding ones, if we but know the values of ,
 ... . We append to this Note
a Diagram and Table, containing the details of the computation for
, (, , 
being supposed given).
On attentively considering (8.), we shall likewise perceive that we
may derive from it the numerical value of every Number of Bernoulli
in succession, from the very beginning, ad infinitum, by the
following series of computations:—
1st Series.—Let , and calculate (8.) for this value of .
The result is .
2nd Series.—Let . Calculate (8.) for this value of 
substituting the value of , just obtained. The result
is .
3rd Series.—Let . Calculate (8.) for this value of ,
substituting the values of ,  before
obtained. The result is . And so on, to any extent.
The diagram[30] represents the columns of the engine when just
[Pg 61]
prepared for computing , (in the case of );
while the table beneath them presents a complete simultaneous
view of all the successive changes which these columns then severally
pass through in order to perform the computation. (The reader is
referred to Note D, for explanations respecting the nature and notation
of such tables.)
Six numerical data are in this case necessary for making
the requisite combinations. These data are 1, 2,  (= 4),
, , . Were  = 5,
the additional datum , would be needed. Were  = 6,
the datum , would be needed; and so on. Thus the
actual number of data needed will always be , for ;
and out of these  data, () of them
are successive Numbers of Bernoulli. The reason why the Bernoulli
Numbers used as data, are nevertheless placed on Result-columns
in the diagram, is because they may properly be supposed to have
been previously computed in succession by the engine itself;
under which circumstances each  will appear as a
result, previous to being used as a datum for computing
the succeeding . Here then is an instance (of the kind
alluded to in Note D.) of the same Variables filling more than one
office in turn. It is true that if we consider our computation of
, as a perfectly isolated calculation, we may
conclude , , , to have
been arbitrarily placed on the columns; and it would then perhaps be
more consistent to put them on , ,
 as data and not results. But we are not taking
this view. On the contrary, we suppose the engine to be in the
course of computing the Numbers to an indefinite extent, from the
very beginning; and that we merely single out, by way of example,
one amongst the successive but distinct series of computations
it is thus performing. Where the ’s are fractional, it
must be understood that they are computed and appear in the notation
of decimal fractions. Indeed this is a circumstance that
should be noticed with reference to all calculations. In any of the
examples already given in the translation and in the Notes, some of
the data, or of the temporary or permanent results, might be
fractional, quite as probably as whole numbers. But the arrangements
are so made, that the nature of the processes would be the same as for
whole numbers.
In the above table and diagram we are not considering the signs of any
of the ’s, merely their numerical magnitude. The engine
would bring out the sign for each of them correctly of course, but we
cannot enter on every additional detail of this kind, as we
might wish to do. The circles for the signs are therefore intentionally
left blank in the diagram.
Operation-cards 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 prepare are

Thus, Card 1 multiplies two into , and the three
Receiving Variable-cards belonging respectively to
, , , allow the result
 to be placed on each of these latter columns (this being a
case in which a triple receipt of the result is needed for subsequent
purposes); we see that the upper indices of the two Variables used,
during Operation 1, remain unaltered.
We shall not go through the details of every operation singly, since
the table and diagram sufficiently indicate them; we shall merely
notice some few peculiar cases.
By Operation 6, a positive quantity is turned into a
negative quantity, by simply subtracting the quantity from
a column which has only zero upon it. (The sign at the top of
[Pg 62]
 would become—during this process.)
Operation 7 will be unintelligible, unless it be remembered that if
we were calculating for  instead of , Operation 6
would have completed the computation of  itself; in
which case the engine, instead of continuing its processes, would
have to put  on ; and then either
to stop altogether, or to begin Operations 1, 2 ... 7 all over again
for value of  (= 2), in order to enter on the computation of
; (having however taken care, previous to this
recommencement, to make the number on , equal to
two, by the addition of unity to the former  on that
column). Now Operation 7 must either bring out a result equal to
zero (if ); or a result greater than zero, as
in the present case; and the engine follows the one or the other of
the two courses just explained, contingently on the one or the other
result of Operation 7. In order fully to perceive the necessity of
this experimental operation, it is important to keep in mind
what was pointed out, that we are not treating a perfectly isolated
and independent computation, but one out of a series of antecedent and
prospective computations.
Cards 8, 9, 10 produce
.
In Operation 9 we see an example of an upper index which again
becomes a value after having passed front preceding values to zero.
 has successively been ,
, , ,
; and, from the nature of the office which
, performs in the calculation, its index will
continue to go through further changes of the same description, which,
if examined, will be found to be regular and periodic.
Card 12 has to perform the same office as Card 7 did in the preceding
section; since, if  had been = 2, the 11th operation would have
completed the computation of .
Cards 13 to 20 make . Since 
always consists of  factors,  has three
factors; and it will be seen that Cards 13, 14, 15, 16 make the second
of these factors, and then multiply it with the first; and that 17, 18,
19, 20 make the third factor, and then multiply this with the product
of the two former factors.
Card 23 has the office of Cards 11 and 7 to perform, since if 
were = 3, the 21st and 22nd operations would complete the computation
of . As our case is , the computation
will continue one more stage; and we must now direct attention to the
fact, that in order to compute  it is merely necessary
precisely to repeat the group of Operations 13 to 20; and then, in
order to complete the computation of , to repeat
Operations 21, 22.
[Pg 63]
It will be perceived that every unit added to  in
, entails an additional repetition of operations
(13 ... 23) for the computation of . Not only
are all the operations precisely the same however for every
such repetition, but they require to be respectively supplied with
numbers from the very same pairs of columns; with only the one
exception of Operation 21, which will of course need 
(from ) instead of  (from
). This identity in the columns which supply
the requisite numbers, must not be confounded with identity in the
values these columns have upon them and give out to the mill.
Most of those values undergo alterations during a performance of the
operations (13 ... 23), and consequently the columns present a new set
of values for the next performance of (13 ... 23) to work on.
At the termination of the repetition of operations (13 ... 23) in computing
, the alterations in the values on the Variables are, that


In this state the only remaining processes are first: to transfer
the value which is on , to ;
and secondly to reduce , ,
 to zero, and to add[30] one to
, in order that the engine may be ready to commence
computing . Operations 24 and 25 accomplish these
purposes. It may be thought anomalous that Operation 25 is represented
as leaving the upper index of  still = unity. But it
must be remembered that these indices always begin anew for a separate
calculation, and that Operation 25 places upon , the
first value for the new calculation.
It should be remarked, that when the group (13 ... 23) is repeated,
changes occur in some of the upper indices during the course
of the repetition: for example, , would become
, and .
We thus see that when , nine Operation-cards are used; that
when , fourteen Operation-cards are used; and that when
, twenty-five Operation-cards are used; but that no more
are needed, however great  may be; and not only this, but that
these same twenty-five cards suffice for the successive computation
of all the Numbers from , to ,
inclusive. With respect to the number of Variable-cards,
it will be remembered, from the explanations in previous Notes,
that an average of three such cards to each operation
(not however to each Operation-card) is the estimate.
According to this the computation of  will require
twenty-seven Variable-cards;  forty-two such cards;
 seventy-five; and for every succeeding 
after , there would be thirty-three additional
Variable-cards (since each repetition of the group (13 ... 23) adds
eleven to the number of operations required for computing the previous
). But we must now explain, that whenever there is a
cycle of operations, and if these merely require to be supplied
with numbers from the same pairs of columns and likewise each
operation to place its result on the same column for
every repetition of the whole group, the process then admits of a
cycle of Variable-cards for effecting its purposes. There is
obviously much more symmetry and simplicity in the arrangements,
when cases do admit of repeating the Variable as well as the
Operation-cards. Our present example is of this nature. The only
exception to a perfect identity in all the processes and
columns used, for every repetition of Operations (13 ... 23) is, that
Operation 21 always requires one of its factors from a new column, and
Operation 24 always puts its result on a new column. But as these
[Pg 64]
variations follow the same law at each repetition, (Operation 21 always
requiring its factor from a column one in advance of that which it
used the previous time, and Operation 24 always putting its result on
the column one in advance of that which received the previous
result), they are easily provided for in arranging the recurring group
(or cycle) of Variable-cards.
We may here remark that the average estimate of three Variable-cards
coming into use to each operation, is not to be taken as an absolutely
and literally correct amount for all cases and circumstances. Many
special circumstances, either in the nature of a problem, or in the
arrangements of the engine under certain contingencies, influence and
modify this average to a greater or less extent. But it is a very safe
and correct general rule to go upon. In the preceding case it
will give us seventy-five Variable-cards as the total number which will
be necessary for computing any  after .
This is very nearly the precise amount really used, but we cannot here
enter into the minutiæ of the few particular circumstances which occur
in this example (as indeed at some one stage or other of probably most
computations) to modify slightly this number.
It will be obvious that the very same seventy-five
Variable-cards may be repeated for the computation of every succeeding
Number, just on the same principle as admits of the repetition of
the thirty-three Variable-cards of Operations (13 ... 23) in the
computation of any one Number. Thus there will be a cycle of
a cycle of Variable-cards.
If we now apply the notation for cycles, as explained in Note E, we may
express the operations for computing the Numbers of Bernoulli in the
following manner:—

Again,

represents the total operations for computing every number in
succession, from  to  inclusive.
In this formula we see a varying cycle of the first
order, and an ordinary cycle of the second order. The latter
cycle in this case includes in it the varying cycle.
[Pg 65]
On inspecting the ten Working-Variables of the diagram, it will be
perceived, that although the value on any one of them (excepting
, and ) goes through a series of
changes, the office which each performs is in this calculation
fixed and invariable. Thus  always
prepares the numerators of the factors of any ;
 the denominators.  always
receives the ()th factor of , and
 the ()th.  always decides
which of two courses the succeeding processes are to follow, by feeling
for the value of  through means of a subtraction; and so on; but
we shall not enumerate further. It is desirable in all calculations,
so to arrange the processes, that the offices performed by the
Variables may be as uniform and fixed as possible.

Diagram for the computation by the Engine of the Numbers of Bernoulli.
See Note G. (page 67 et seq.)
[Pg 66]



Number of operation.
Nature of operation.
Variables acted upon.
Variables receiving results.
Indication of change in the value of any Variable.
Statement of Results.
Data.
Working variables.





























0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0

0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0

1
2
4
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0















1



















2





1













3





1













4








0
0









5






2












6















0



7





1













8



















9



















10



















11
















0


12



















13





















14



















15



















16












0






17




















18



















19



















20













0





21
















0



22

















0


23




















Here follows a repetition of Operations thirteen to twenty-three

24



















25






by a Variable-card.





0
0











Number of operation.
Result Variables.

















0

0

0






1





2





3





4





5





6





7





8





9





10





11





12





13





14





15





16





17





18





19





20





21





22





23







24





25







[Pg 67]
Supposing that it was desired not only to tabulate ,
, &c., but , ,
&c.; we have only then to appoint another series of Variables,
, , &c., for receiving
these latter results as they are successively produced upon
. Or again, we may, instead of this, or in addition
to this second series of results, wish to tabulate the value of each
successive total term of the series (8), viz: ,
, , &c. We have
then merely to multiply each  with each corresponding
, as produced; and to place these successive products on
Result-columns appointed for the purpose.
The formula (8.) is interesting in another point of view. It is one
particular case of the general Integral of the following Equation of
Mixed Differences:—

for certain special suppositions respecting ,  and .
The general integral itself is of the form,

and it is worthy of remark, that the engine might (in a manner more or
less similar to the preceding) calculate the value of this formula upon
most other hypotheses for the functions in the integral, with as
much, or (in many cases) with more, ease than it can formula (8.).
A. A. L.
[Pg 68]
FOOTNOTES:


[16]
We do not mean to imply that the only use
made of the Jacquard cards is that of regulating the algebraical
operations. But we mean to explain that those cards and
portions of mechanism which regulate these operations, are
wholly independent of those which are used for other purposes. M.
Menabrea explains that there are three classes of cards used in
the engine for three distinct sets of objects, viz. Cards of the
Operations, Cards of the Variables, and certain Cards of
Numbers. (See pages 13 and 22.)



[17]
In fact such an extension as we allude to, would merely
constitute a further and more perfected development of any system
introduced for making the proper combinations of the signs plus and
minus. How ably M. Menabrea has touched on this restricted case is
pointed out in Note B.



[18]
The machine might have been constructed so as to tabulate
for a higher value of  than seven. Since, however, every unit
added to the value of  increases the extent of the mechanism
requisite, there would on this account be a limit beyond which it
could not be practically carried. Seven is sufficiently high for the
calculation of all ordinary tables.

The fact that, in the Analytical Engine, the same extent of mechanism
suffices for the solution of , whether ,
, or  = any number whatever, at once suggests how
entirely distinct must be the nnature of the principles through
whose application matter has been enabled to become the working agent
of abstract mental operations in each of these engines respectively;
and it affords an equally obvious presumption, that in the case of
the Analytical Engine, not only are those principles in themselves of
a higher and more comprehensive description, but also such as must
vastly extend the practical value of the engine whose basis they
constitute.



[19]
This subject is further noticed in Note F.



[20]
A fuller account of the manner in which the signs
are regulated, is given on in Mons. Menabrea’s Memoir, pages 17, 18.
He himself expresses doubts (in a note of his own at the bottom of
the latter page) as to his having been likely to hit on the precise
methods really adopted; his explanation In being merely a conjectural
one. That it does accord precisely with the fact is a remarkable
circumstance, and affords a convincing proof how completely Mons.
Menabrea has been imbued with the true spirit of the invention.
Indeed the whole of the above Memoir is a striking production, when
we consider that Mons. Menabrea had had but very slight means for
obtaining any adequate ideas respecting the Analytical Engine. It
requires however a considerable acquaintance with the abstruse and
complicated nature of such a subject, in order fully to appreciate the
penetration of the writer who could take so just and comprehensive a
view of it upon such limited opportunity.



[21]
This adjustment is done by hand merely.



[22]
It is convenient to omit the circles whenever the signs +
or — can be actually represented.



[23]
See the diagram of page 46.



[24]
We recommend the reader to trace the successive
substitutions backwards from (1.) to (4.), in Mons. Menabrea’s Table.
This he will easily do by means of the upper and lower indices, and it
is interesting to observe how each  successively ramifies
(so to speak) into two other ’s in some other column of
the Table; until at length the ’s of the original data
are arrived at.



[25]
This division would be managed by ordering the number
two to appear on any separate new column which should be conveniently
situated for the purpose, and then directing this column (which is
in the strictest sense a Working-Variable) to divide itself
successively with , , &c.



[26]
It should be observed, that were the rest of the factor
() taken into account,
instead of four terms only,  would have
the additional term ; and
, the two additional terms, ,
. This would indeed have been
the case had even six terms been multiplied.



[27]
A cycle that includes  other cycles, successively
contained one within another, is called a cycle of the th
order. A cycle may simply include many other cycles, and yet only
be of the second order. If a series follows a certain law for a certain
number of terms, and then another law for another number of terms,
there will be a cycle of operations for every new law; but these cycles
will not be contained one within another,—they merely follow
each other. Therefore their number may be infinite without
influencing the order of a cycle that includes a repetition of
such a series.



[28]
The engine cannot of course compute limits for perfectly
simple and uncompounded functions, except in this manner.
It is obvious that it has no power of representing or of manipulating
with any but finite increments or decrements; and consequently
that wherever the computation of limits (or of any other functions)
depends upon the direct introduction of quantities which either
increase or decrease indefinitely, we are absolutely beyond
the sphere of its powers. Its nature and arrangements are remarkably
adapted for taking into account all finite increments or
decrements (however small or large), and for developing the true and
logical modifications of form or value dependent upon differences of
this nature. The engine may indeed be considered as including the
whole Calculus of Finite Differences; many of whose theorems would be
especially and beautifully fitted for development by its processes, and
would offer peculiarly interesting considerations. We may mention, as
an example, the calculation of the Numbers of Bernoulli by means of the
Differences of Nothing.



[29]
See the diagram at the end of these Notes.



[30]
It is interesting to observe, that so complicated a
case as this calculation of the Bernoullian Numbers, nevertheless,
presents a remarkable simplicity in one respect; viz., that during the
processes for the computation of millions of these Numbers, no
other arbitrary modification would be requisite in the arrangements,
excepting the above simple and uniform provision for causing one of the
data periodically to receive the finite increment unity.




Transcriber’s Notes
“Article XXIX,” extracted from Scientific memoirs, Vol. 3, 1843.
Translated, with notes, from the Italian original by Ada King, Countess
of Lovelace, daughter of Byron. She is identified on page 35 as “A. A.
L.” It was originally published by Luigi Federico Menabrea as ‘Notions
sur la machine analytique de M. Charles Babbage,’ pp. 352-376 in:
Bibliothèque Universelle de Génève. Nouvelle Série, Tome 41.



</div></body></text></TEI>