<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="83">CHAPTER I.
Discovery of Laws of Magnetic Phenomena.
THE history of Magnetism is in
a great degree similar to that of Electricity, and many of the same
persons were employed in the two trains of research. The general fact,
that the magnet attracts iron, was nearly all that was known to the
ancients, and is frequently mentioned and referred to; for instance,
by Pliny, who wonders and declaims concerning it, in his usual
exaggerated style.1 The writers of the Stationary Period, in
this subject as in others, employed themselves in collecting and
adorning a number of extravagant tales, which the slightest reference
to experiment would have disproved; as, for example, that a magnet,
when it has lost its virtue, has it restored by goat’s blood. Gilbert,
whose work De Magnete we have already
mentioned, speaks with becoming indignation and pity of this bookish
folly, and repeatedly asserts the paramount value of experiments. He
himself, no doubt, acted up to his own precepts; for his work contains
all the fundamental facts of the science, so fully examined indeed,
that even at this day we have little to add to them. Thus, in his
first Book, the subjects of the third, fourth, and fifth Chapters
are,—that the magnet has poles,—that we may call these
poles the north and the south pole,—that in two magnets the
north pole of each attracts the south pole and repels the north pole
of the other. This is, indeed, the cardinal fact on which our
generalizations rest; and the reader will perceive at once its
resemblance to the leading phenomena of statical electricity.
1 Hist. Nat. lib. xxxvi. c.
25.
But the doctrines of magnetism, like those of heat, have an
additional claim on our notice from the manner in which they are
exemplified in the globe of the earth. The subject of terrestrial
magnetism forms a very important addition to the general facts of
magnetic attraction and repulsion. The property of the magnet by which
it directs its poles exactly or nearly north and south, when once
discovered, was of immense importance to the mariner. It does not
218 appear easy to
trace with certainty the period of this discovery. Passing over
certain legends of the Chinese, as at any rate not bearing upon the
progress of European science,2 the earliest
notice of this property appears to be contained in the Poem of Guyot
de Provence, who describes the needle as being magnetized, and then
placed in or on a straw, (floating on water, as I presume:)

Puis se torne la pointe toute
Contre l’estoile sans doute;
that is, it turns towards the pole-star. This account
would make the knowledge of this property in Europe anterior to 1200.
It was afterwards found3 that the needle does not point exactly
towards the north. Gilbert was aware of this deviation, which he calls
the variation, and also, that it is different in different
places.4 He maintained on theoretical principles
also,5 that at the same place the variation is
constant; probably in his time there were not any recorded
observations by which the truth of this assertion could be tested; it
was afterwards found to be false. The alteration of the variation in
proceeding from one place to another was, it will be recollected, one
of the circumstances which most alarmed the companions of Columbus in
1492. Gilbert says,6 “Other learned men have, in long
navigations, observed the differences of magnetic variations, as
Thomas Hariot, Robert Hues, Edward Wright, Abraham Kendall, all
Englishmen: others have invented magnetic instruments and convenient
modes of observation, such as are requisite for those who take long
voyages, as William Borough in his Book concerning the variation of
the compass, William Barlo in his supplement, William Norman in his
New Attractive. This is that Robert Norman (a good seaman and
an ingenious artificer,) who first discovered the dip of
magnetic iron.” This important discovery was made7 in 1576. From the
time when the difference of the variation of the compass in different
places became known, it was important to mariners to register the
variation in all parts of the world. Halley was appointed to the
command of a ship in the Royal Navy by the Government of William and
Mary, with orders “to seek by observation the discovery of the rule
for the variation of the compass.” He published Magnetic Charts, which
219 have been since
corrected and improved by various persons. The most recent are those
of Mr. Yates in 1817, and of M. Hansteen. The dip, as well as the
variation, was found to be different in different places. M. Humboldt,
in the course of his travels, collected many such observations. And
both the observations of variation and of dip seemed to indicate that
the earth, as to its effect on the magnetic needle, may, approximately
at least, be considered as a magnet, the poles of which are not far
removed from the earth’s poles of rotation. Thus we have a magnetic
equator, in which the needle has no dip, and which does not
deviate far from the earth’s equator; although, from the best
observations, it appears to be by no means a regular circle. And the
phenomena, both of the dip and of the variation, in high northern
latitudes, appear to indicate the existence of a pole below the
surface of the earth to the north of Hudson’s Bay. In his second
remarkable expedition into those regions, Captain Ross is supposed to
have reached the place of this pole; the dipping-needle there pointing
vertically downwards, and the variation-compass turning towards this
point in the adjacent regions. We shall hereafter have to consider the more complete
and connected views which have been taken of terrestrial
magnetism.
2 Enc. Met. art.
Magnetism, p. 736.
3 Before 1269. Enc. Met. p.
737.
4 De Magnete, lib. iv. c.
1.
5 c. 3.
6 Lib. i. c. 1.
7 Enc. Met. p. 738.
In 1633, Gellibrand discovered that the variation is not constant,
as Gilbert imagined, but that at London it had diminished from eleven
degrees east in 1580, to four degrees in 1633. Since that time the
variation has become more and more westerly; it is now about
twenty-five degrees west, and the needle is supposed to have begun to
travel eastward again.
The next important fact which appeared with respect to terrestrial
magnetism was, that the position of the needle is subject to a small
diurnal variation: this was discovered in 1722, by Graham, a
philosophical instrument-maker, of London. The daily variation was
established by one thousand observations of Graham, and confirmed by
four thousand more made by Canton, and is now considered to be out of
dispute. It appeared also, by Canton’s researches, that the diurnal
variation undergoes an annual inequality, being nearly a quarter of a
degree in June and July, and only half that quantity in December and
January.
Having thus noticed the principal facts which belong to terrestrial
magnetism, we must return to the consideration of those phenomena
which gradually led to a consistent magnetic theory. Gilbert observed
that both smelted iron and hammered iron have the magnetic virtue,
220 though in a
weaker degree than the magnet itself,8 and he asserted
distinctly that the magnet is merely an ore of iron, (lib. i. c. 16,
Quod magnes et vena ferri idem sunt.) He also noted the increased
energy which magnets acquire by being armed; that is, fitted
with a cap of polished iron at each pole.9 But we do not
find till a later period any notice of the distinction which exists
between the magnetical properties of soft iron and of hard
steel;—the latter being susceptible of being formed into
artificial magnets, with permanent poles; while soft iron is
only passively magnetic, receiving a temporary polarity from
the action of a magnet near it, but losing this property when the
magnet is removed. About the middle of the last century, various
methods were devised of making artificial magnets, which exceeded in
power all magnetic bodies previously known.
8 Lib. i. c. 9–13.
9 Lib. ii. c. 17.
The remaining experimental researches had so close an historical
connexion with the theory, that they will be best considered along
with it, and to that, therefore, we now proceed.
</div></body></text></TEI>