<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="15">CHAPTER XV.
TRANSPORTATION OF SOLID MATTER BY ICE.
Carrying power of river-ice—Rocks annually conveyed into the St. Lawrence by
its tributaries—Ground-ice; its origin and transporting
power—Glaciers—Theory
of their downward movement—Smoothed and grooved rocks—The
moraine unstratified—Icebergs covered with mud and stones—Limits of glaciers
and icebergs—Their effects on the bottom when they run
aground—Packing
of coast-ice—Boulders drifted by ice on coast of Labrador—Blocks moved by
ice in the Baltic.
The power of running water to carry sand, gravel, and fragments
of rock to considerable distances is greatly augmented in those regions
where, during some part of the year, the frost is of sufficient intensity
to convert the water, either at the surface or bottom of rivers, into ice.
This subject may be considered under three different heads:—first,
the effect of surface-ice and ground-ice in enabling streams to remove
gravel and stones to a distance; secondly, the action of glaciers in the
transport of boulders, and in the polishing and scratching of rocks;
thirdly, the floating off of glaciers charged with solid matter into the
sea, and the drifting of icebergs and coast-ice.
River-ice.—Pebbles and small pieces of rock may be seen entangled
in ice, and floating annually down the Tay in Scotland, as far as the
mouth of that river. Similar observations might doubtless be made
respecting almost all the larger rivers of England and Scotland; but
there seems reason to suspect that the principal transfer from place
to place of pebbles and stones adhering to ice goes on unseen by us
under water. For although the specific gravity of the compound
mass may cause it to sink, it may still be very buoyant, and easily borne
along by a feeble current. The ice, moreover, melts very slowly at the
bottom of running streams in winter, as the water there is often nearly
at the freezing point, as will be seen from what will be said in the
sequel of ground-ice.
As we traverse Europe in the latitudes of Great Britain, we find the
winters more severe, and the rivers more regularly frozen over. M.
Lariviere relates that, being at Memel on the Baltic in 1821, when the
ice of the river Niemen broke up, he saw a mass of ice thirty feet long
which had descended the stream, and had been thrown ashore. In the
middle of it was a triangular piece of granite, about a yard in diameter,
resembling in composition the red granite of Finland.283
220
When rivers in the northern hemisphere flow from south to north,
the ice first breaks up in the higher part of their course, and the flooded
waters, bearing along large icy fragments, often arrive at parts of the
stream which are still firmly frozen over. Great inundations are thus
frequently occasioned by the obstructions thrown in the way of the descending
waters, as in the case of the Mackenzie in North America, and
the Irtish, Obi, Yenesei, Lena, and other rivers of Siberia. (See map,
fig. 1, p. 79.) A partial stoppage of this kind lately occurred (Jan. 31,
1840) in the Vistula, about a mile and a half above the city of Dantzic,
where the river, choked up by packed ice, was made to take a new
course over its right bank, so that it hollowed out in a few days a
deep and broad channel, many leagues in length, through a tract of
sand-hills which were from 40 to 60 feet high.
In Canada, where the winter's cold is intense, in a latitude corresponding
to that of central France, several tributaries of the St. Lawrence
begin to thaw in their upper course, while they remain frozen
over lower down, and thus large slabs of ice are set free and thrown
upon the unbroken sheet of ice below. Then begins what is called the
packing of the drifted fragments; that is to say, one slab is made to
slide over another, until a vast pile is built up, and the whole being
frozen together, is urged onwards by the force of the dammed up
waters and drift-ice. Thus propelled, it not only forces along boulders,
but breaks off from cliffs, which border the rivers, huge pieces of
projecting rock. By this means several buttresses of solid masonry,
which, up to the year 1836, supported a wooden bridge on the St.
Maurice, which falls into the St. Lawrence, near the town of Trois
Rivières, lat. 46° 20', were thrown down, and conveyed by the ice
into the main river; and instances have occurred at Montreal of wharfs
and stone-buildings, from 30 to 50 feet square, having been removed in
a similar manner. We learn from Captain Bayfield that anchors laid
down within high-water mark, to secure vessels hauled on shore for the
winter, must be cut out of the ice on the approach of spring, or they
would be carried away. In 1834, the Gulnare's bower-anchor, weighing
half a ton, was transported some yards by the ice, and so firmly
was it fixed, that the force of the moving ice broke a chain-cable suited
for a 10-gun brig, and which had rode the Gulnare during the heaviest
gales in the gulf. Had not this anchor been cut out of the ice, it would
have been earned into deep water and lost.284
PLATE II.

BOULDERS DRIFTED BY ICE ON SHORES OF THE ST. LAWRENCE
View taken by Lieut. Bowen, from the N. E., in the Spring of 1835, at Richelieu Rapid, lat. 46° N.
The scene represented in the annexed plate (pl. 2), from a drawing
by Lieutenant Bowen, R. N., will enable the reader to comprehend the
incessant changes which the transport of boulders produces annually
on the low islands, shores, and bed of the St. Lawrence above Quebec.
The fundamental rocks at Richelieu Rapid, situated in lat. 46° N., are
limestone and slate, which are seen at low-water to be covered with
boulders of granite. These boulders owe their spheroidal form chiefly to
221
weathering, or action of frost, which causes the surface to exfoliate in
concentric plates, so that all the more prominent angles are removed.
At the point a is a cavity in the mud or sand of the beach, now filled
with water, which was occupied during the preceding winter (1835) by
the huge erratic b, a mass of granite, 70 tons' weight, found in the
spring following (1836) at a distance of several feet from its former
position. Many small islands are seen on the river, such as c d, which
afford still more striking proofs of the carrying and propelling power of
ice. These islets are never under water, yet every winter ice is thrown
upon them in such abundance, that it packs to the height of 20, and
even 30 feet, bringing with it a continual supply of large stones or
boulders, and carrying away others; the greatest number being deposited,
according to Lieutenant Bowen, on the edge of deep water. On
the island d, on the left of the accompanying view, a lighthouse is represented,
consisting of a square wooden building, which having no other
foundation than the boulders, requires to be taken down every winter,
and rebuilt on the reopening of the river.
These effects of frost, which are so striking on the St. Lawrence
above Quebec, are by no means displayed on a smaller scale below that
city, where the gulf rises and falls with the tide. On the contrary; it
is in the estuary, between the latitudes 47° and 49°, that the greatest
quantity of gravel and boulders of large dimensions are carried down
annually towards the sea. Here the frost is so intense, that a dense
sheet of ice is formed at low water, which, on the rise of the tide, is
lifted up, broken, and thrown in heaps on the extensive shoals which
border the estuary. When the tide recedes, this packed ice is exposed
to a temperature sometimes 30° below zero, which freezes together all
the loose pieces of ice, as well as the granitic and other boulders. The
whole of these are often swept away by a high tide, or when the river
is swollen by the melting of the snow in Spring. One huge block of
granite, 15 feet long by 10 feet both in width and height, and estimated
to contain 1500 cubic feet, was conveyed in this manner to some distance
in the year 1837, its previous position being well known, as up
to that time it had been used by Captain Bayfield as a mark for the
surveying station.
Ground-ice.—When a current of cold air passes over the surface of
a lake or stream it abstracts from it a quantity of heat, and the specific
gravity of the water being thereby increased, the cooled portion sinks.
This circulation may continue until the whole body of fluid has been
cooled down to the temperature of 40° F., after which, if the cold increase,
the vertical movement ceases, the water which is uppermost
expands and floats over the heavier fluid below, and when it has attained
a temperature of 32° Fahr. it sets into a sheet of ice. It should seem
therefore impossible, according to this law of congelation, that ice
should ever form at the bottom of a river; and yet such is the fact, and
many speculations have been hazarded to account for so singular a phenomenon.
M. Arago is of opinion that the mechanical action of a running
222
stream produces a circulation by which the entire body of water is
mixed up together, and cooled alike, and the whole being thus reduced
to the freezing point, ice begins to form at the bottom for two reasons,
first, because there is less motion there, and secondly, because the
water is in contact with solid rock or pebbles which have a cold surface.285
Whatever explanation we adopt, there is no doubt of the fact,
that in countries where the intensity and duration of the cold is great,
rivers and torrents acquire an increase of carrying power by the formation
of what is called ground-ice. Even in the Thames we learn from
Dr. Plott that pieces of this kind of ice, having gravel frozen on to their
under side, rise up from the bottom in winter, and float on the surface.
In the Siberian rivers, Weitz describes large stones as having been
brought up from the river's bed in the same manner, and made to
float.286
Glaciers.—In the temperate zone, the snow lies for months in winter
on the summit of every high mountain, while in the arctic regions, a
long summer's day of half a year's duration is insufficient to melt the
snow, even on land just raised above the level of the sea. It is therefore
not surprising, since the atmosphere becomes colder in proportion
as we ascend in it, that there should be heights, even in tropical countries,
where the snow never melts. The lowest limit to which the perpetual
snow extends downwards, from the tops of mountains at the
equator, is an elevation of not less than 16,000 feet above the sea;
while in the Swiss Alps, in lat. 46° N. it reaches as low as 8,500 feet
above the same level, the loftier peaks of the Alpine chain being from
12,000 to 15,000 feet high. The frozen mass augmenting from year to
year would add indefinitely to the altitude of alpine summits, were it
not relieved by its descent through the larger and deeper valleys to
regions far below the general snow-line. To these it slowly finds its
way in the form of rivers of ice, called glaciers, the consolidation of
which is produced by pressure, and by the congelation of water infiltered
into the porous mass, which is always undergoing partial liquefaction,
and receiving in summer occasional showers of rain on its surface.
In a day of hot sunshine, or mild rain, innumerable rills of pure and
sparkling water run in icy channels along the surface of the glaciers,
which in the night shrink, and come to nothing. They are often precipitated
in bold cascades into deep fissures in the ice, and contribute together
with springs to form torrents, which flow in tunnels at the bottom
of the glaciers for many a league, and at length issue at their
extremities, from beneath beautiful caverns or arches. The waters of
these streams are always densely charged with the finest mud, produced
by the grinding of rock and sand under the weight of the moving
mass. (See fig. 18.)
223
Fig. 18.
Glacier with medial and lateral moraines and with terminal cave
The length of the Swiss glaciers is sometimes twenty miles, their
width in the middle portion, where they are broadest, occasionally two
or three miles; their depth or thickness sometimes more than 600 feet.
When they descend steep slopes, and precipices, or are forced through
narrow gorges, the ice is broken up, and assumes the most fantastic and
picturesque forms, with lofty peaks and pinnacles, projecting above the
general level. These snow-white masses are often relieved by a dark
background of pines, as in the valley of Chamouni; and are not only
surrounded with abundance of the wild rhododendron in full flower,
but encroach still lower into the region of cultivation, and trespass on
fields where the tobacco-plant is flourishing by the side of the peasant's
hut.
The cause of glacier motion has of late been a subject of careful
investigation and much keen controversy. Although a question of
physics, rather than of geology, it is too interesting to allow me to pass
it by without some brief mention. De Saussure, whose travels in the
Alps are full of original observations, as well as sound and comprehensive
general views, conceived that the weight of the ice might be sufficient
to urge it down the slope of the valley, if the sliding motion were
aided by the water flowing at the bottom. For this "gravitation
theory" Charpentier, followed by Agassiz, substituted the hypothesis of
dilatation. The most solid ice is always permeable to water, and penetrated224
by innumerable fissures and capillary tubes, often extremely
minute. These tubes imbibe the aqueous fluid during the day, which
freezes, it is said, in the cold of the night, and expands while in the act
of congelation. The distension of the whole mass exerts an immense
force, tending to propel the glacier in the direction of least resistance—"in
other words, down the valley." This theory was opposed by
Mr. Hopkins on mathematical and mechanical grounds, in several able
papers. Among other objections, he pointed out that the friction of
so enormous a body as a glacier on its bed is so great, that the vertical
direction would always be that of least resistance, and if a considerable
distension of the mass should take place, by the action of freezing, it
would tend to increase its thickness, rather than accelerate its downward
progress. He also contended (and his arguments were illustrated
by many ingenious experiments), that a glacier can move along an
extremely slight slope, solely by the influence of gravitation, owing to
the constant dissolution of ice in contact with the rocky bottom, and
the number of separate fragments into which the glacier is divided by
fissures, so that freedom of motion is imparted to its several parts
somewhat resembling that of an imperfect fluid. To this view Professor
James Forbes objected, that gravitation would not supply an adequate
cause for the sliding of solid ice down slopes having an inclination
of no more than four or five degrees, still less would it explain
how the glacier advances where the channel expands and contracts.
The Mer de Glace in Chamouni, for example, after being 2000 yards
wide, passes through a strait only 900 yards in width. Such a gorge,
it is contended, would be choked up by the advance of any solid
mass, even if it be broken up into numerous fragments. The same
acute observer remarked, that water in the fissures and pores of glaciers
cannot, and does not part with its latent heat, so as to freeze
every night to a great depth, or far in the interior of the mass. Had
the dilatation theory been true, the chief motion of the glacier would
have occurred about sunset, when the freezing of the water must be
greatest, and it had, in fact, been at first assumed by those who favored
that hypothesis, that the mass moved faster at the sides, where the
melting of ice was promoted by the sun's heat, reflected from boundary
precipices.
Agassiz appears to have been the first to commence, in 1841, aided
by a skilful engineer, M. Escher de la Linth, a series of exact measurements
to ascertain the laws of glacier motion, and he soon discovered,
contrary to his preconceived notions, that the stream of ice moved more
slowly at the sides than at the centre, and faster in the middle region
of the glacier than at its extremity.287 Professor James Forbes, who
had joined Mr. Agassiz during his earlier investigations in the Alps,
225
undertook himself an independent series of experiments, which he followed
up with great perseverance, to determine the laws of glacier
motion. These he found to agree very closely with the laws governing
the course of rivers, their progress being greater in the centre than
at the sides, and more rapid at the surface than at the bottom. This
fact was verified by carefully fixing a great number of marks in the
ice, arranged in a straight line, which gradually assumed a beautiful
curve, the middle part pointing down the glacier, and showing a velocity
there, double or treble that of the lateral parts.288 He ascertained
that the rate of advance by night was nearly the same as by day, and
that even the hourly march of the icy stream could be detected, although
the progress might not amount to more than six or seven inches
in twelve hours. By the incessant though invisible advance of the
marks placed on the ice, "time," says Mr. Forbes, "was marked out
as by a shadow on a dial, and the unequivocal evidence which I obtained,
that even while walking on a glacier we are, day by day, and
hour by hour, imperceptibly carried on by the resistless flow of the icy
stream, filled me with admiration." (Travels in the Alps, p. 133.) In
order to explain this remarkable regularity of motion, and its obedience
to laws so strictly analogous to those of fluids, the same writer proposed
the theory that the ice, instead of being solid and compact, is a
viscous or plastic body, capable of yielding to great pressure, and the
more so in proportion as its temperature is higher, and as it approaches
more nearly to the melting point. He endeavors to show that this
hypothesis will account for many complicated phenomena, especially
for a ribboned or veined structure which is everywhere observable
in the ice, and might be produced by lines of discontinuity, arising
from the different rates at which the various portions of the semi-rigid
glacier advance and pass each other. Many examples are adduced to
prove that a glacier can model itself to the form of the ground over
which it is forced, exactly as would happen if it possessed a certain
ductility, and this power of yielding under intense pressure, is shown
not to be irreconcilable with the idea of the ice being sufficiently compact
to break into fragments, when the strain upon its parts is excessive;
as where the glacier turns a sharp angle, or descends upon a
rapid or convex slope. The increased velocity in summer is attributed
partly to the greater plasticity of the ice, when not exposed to intense
cold, and partly to the hydrostatic pressure of the water in the
capillary tubes, which imbibe more of this liquid in the hot season.
On the assumption of the ice being a rigid mass, Mr. Hopkins attributed
the more rapid motions in the centre to the unequal rate at which
the broad stripes of ice, intervening between longitudinal fissures, advance;
but besides that there are parts of the glacier where no such
fissures exist, such a mode of progression, says Mr. Forbes, would cause
the borders of large transverse rents or "crevasses," to be jagged like a
226
saw, instead of being perfectly even and straight-edged.289 An experiment
recently made by Mr. Christie, secretary to the Royal Society, appears
to demonstrate that ice, under great pressure, possesses a sufficient degree
of moulding and self-adapting power to allow it to be acted upon,
as if it were a pasty substance. A hollow shell of iron an inch and a
half thick, the interior being ten inches in diameter, was filled with water,
in the course of a severe winter, and exposed to the frost, with the fuze-hole
uppermost. A portion of the water expanded in freezing, so as to
protrude a cylinder of ice from the fuze-hole; and this cylinder continued
to grow inch by inch in proportion as the central nucleus of water
froze. As we cannot doubt that an outer shell of ice is first formed,
and then another within, the continued rise of the column through the
fuze-hole must proceed from the squeezing of successive shells of ice
concentrically formed, through the narrow orifice; and yet the protruded
cylinder consisted of entire, and not fragmentary ice.290
The agency of glaciers in producing permanent geological changes consists
partly in their power of transporting gravel, sand, and huge stones
to great distances, and partly in the smoothing, polishing, and scoring
of their rocky channels, and the boundary walls of the valleys through
which they pass. At the foot of every steep cliff or precipice in high
Alpine regions, a talus is seen of rocky fragments detached by the alternate
action of frost and thaw. If these loose masses, instead of accumulating
on a stationary base, happen to fall upon a glacier, they will
move along with it, and, in place of a single heap, they will form in the
course of years a long stream of blocks. If a glacier be 20 miles long,
and its annual progression about 500 feet, it will require about two centuries
for a block thus lodged upon its surface to travel down from the
higher to the lower regions, or to the extremity of the icy mass. This
terminal point remains usually unchanged from year to year, although
every part of the ice is in motion, because the liquefaction by heat is just
sufficient to balance the onward movement of the glacier, which may be
compared to an endless file of soldiers, pouring into a breach, and shot
down as fast as they advance.
The stones carried along on the ice are called in Switzerland the
"moraines" of the glacier. There is always one line of blocks on each
side or edge of the icy stream, and often several in the middle, where they
are arranged in long ridges or mounds, often several yards high. (See
fig. 18, p. 223.) The cause of these "medial moraines" was first explained
by Agassiz, who referred them to the confluence of tributary
glaciers.291 Upon the union of two streams of ice, the right lateral moraine
227
of one of the streams comes in contact with the left lateral moraine of
the other, and they afterwards move on together, in the centre, if the
confluent glaciers are equal in size, or nearer to one side if unequal.
All sand and fragments of soft stone which fall through fissures and
reach the bottom of the glaciers, or which are interposed between the
glacier and the steep sides of the valley, are pushed along, and ground
down into mud, while the larger and harder fragments have their angles
worn off. At the same time the fundamental and boundary rocks are
smoothed and polished, and often scored with parallel furrows, or with
lines and scratches produced by hard minerals, such as crystals of quartz,
which act like the diamond upon glass.292 This effect is perfectly different
from that caused by the action of water, or a muddy torrent forcing
along heavy fragments; for when stones are fixed firmly in the ice, and
pushed along by it under great pressure, in straight lines, they scoop out
long rectilinear furrows or grooves parallel to each other.293 The discovery
of such markings at various heights far above the surface of the
existing glaciers and for miles beyond their present terminations, affords
geological evidence of the former extension of the ice beyond its present
limits in Switzerland and other countries.
The moraine of the glacier, observes Charpentier, is entirely devoid of
stratification, for there has been no sorting of the materials, as in the case
of sand, mud, and pebbles, when deposited by running water. The ice
transports indifferently, and to the same spots, the heaviest blocks and
the finest particles, mingling all together, and leaving them in one confused
and promiscuous heap wherever it melts.294
Icebergs.—In countries situated in high northern latitudes, like Spitzbergen,
between 70° and 80° N., glaciers, loaded with mud and rock,
descend to the sea, and there huge fragments of them float off and become
icebergs. Scoresby counted 500 of these bergs drifting along
in latitudes 69° and 70° N., which rose above the surface from the
height of 100 to 200 feet, and measured from a few yards to a mile in
circumference.295 Many of them were loaded with beds of earth and rock
of such thickness, that the weight was conjectured to be from 50,000 to
100,000 tons. Specimens of the rocks were obtained, and among them
were granite, gneiss, mica-schist, clay-slate, granular felspar, and greenstone.
Such bergs must be of great magnitude; because the mass of
ice below the level of the water is about eight times greater than that
above. Wherever they are dissolved, it is evident that the "moraine"
will fall to the bottom of the sea. In this manner may submarine valleys,
mountains, and platforms become strewed over with gravel, sand,
mud, and scattered blocks of foreign rock, of a nature perfectly dissimilar
from all in the vicinity, and which may have been transported across
unfathomable abysses. If the bergs happen to melt in still water, so
that the earthy and stony materials may fall tranquilly to the bottom,
228
the deposit will probably be unstratified, like the terminal moraine of a
glacier; but whenever the materials are under the influence of a current
of water as they fall, they will be sorted and arranged according to their
relative weight and size, and therefore more or less perfectly stratified.
In a former chapter it was stated that some ice islands have been
known to drift from Baffin's Bay to the Azores, and from the South Pole
to the immediate neighborhood of the Cape of Good Hope, so that the
area over which the effects of moving ice may be experienced, comprehends
a large portion of the globe.
We learn from Von Buch that the most southern point on the continent
of Europe at which a glacier comes down to the sea is in Norway,
in lat. 67° N.296 But Mr. Darwin has shown, that they extend to the
sea, in South America, in latitudes more than 20° nearer the equator
than in Europe; as, for example, in Chili, where, in the Gulf of Penas,
lat. 46° 40' S., or the latitude of central France; and in Sir George
Eyre's Sound, in the latitude of Paris, they give origin to icebergs, which
were seen in 1834 carrying angular pieces of granite, and stranding them
in fiords, where the shores were composed of clay-slate.297 A large proportion,
however, of the ice-islands seen floating both in the northern
and southern hemispheres, are probably not generated by glaciers, but
rather by the accumulation of coast ice. When the sea freezes at the
base of a lofty precipice, the sheet of ice is prevented from adhering to
the land by the rise and fall of the tide. Nevertheless, it often continues
on the shore at the foot of the cliff, and receives accessions of
drift snow blown from the land. Under the weight of this snow the ice
sinks slowly if the water be deep, and the snow is gradually converted
into ice by partial liquefaction and re-congelation. In this manner, islands
of ice of great thickness and many leagues in length, originate, and are
eventually blown out to sea by off-shore winds. In their interior are inclosed
many fragments of stone which had fallen upon them from overhanging
cliffs during their formation. Such floating icebergs are commonly
flat-topped, but their lower portions are liable to melt in latitudes
where the ocean at a moderate depth is usually warmer than the surface
water and the air. Hence their centre of gravity changes continually,
and they turn over and assume very irregular shapes.
In a voyage of discovery made in the antarctic regions in 1839, a dark-colored
angular mass of rock was seen imbedded in an iceberg, drifting
along in mid-ocean in lat. 61° S. That part of the rock which was visible
was about 12 feet in height, and from 5 to 6 in width, but the dark
color of the surrounding ice indicated that much more of the stone was
concealed. A sketch made by Mr. Macnab, when the vessel was within
a quarter of a mile of it, is now published.298 This iceberg, one of many
observed at sea on the same day, was between 250 and 300 feet high,
and was no less than 1400 miles from any certainly known land. It is
exceedingly improbable, says Mr. Darwin, in his notice of this phenomenon,
229
that any land will hereafter be discovered within 100 miles of the
spot, and it must be remembered that the erratic was still firmly fixed
in the ice, and may have sailed for many a league farther before it
dropped to the bottom.299
Captain Sir James Ross, in his antarctic voyage in 1841, 42, and 43,
saw multitudes of icebergs transporting stones and rocks of various
sizes, with frozen mud, in high southern latitudes. His companion,
Dr. J. Hooker, informs me that he came to the conclusion that most
of the southern icebergs have stones in them, although they are usually
concealed from view by the quantity of snow which falls upon them.
In the account given by Messrs. Dease and Simpson, of their recent
arctic discoveries, we learn that in lat. 71° N., long. 156° W., they
found "a long low spit, named Point Barrow, composed of gravel and
coarse sand, in some parts more than a quarter of a mile broad, which
the pressure of the ice had forced up into numerous mounds, that,
viewed from a distance, assumed the appearance of huge boulder
rocks."300
This fact is important, as showing how masses of drift ice, when
stranding on submarine banks, may exert a lateral pressure capable of
bending and dislocating any yielding strata of gravel, sand, or mud.
The banks on which icebergs occasionally run aground between Baffin's
Bay and Newfoundland, are many hundred feet under water, and the
force with which they are struck will depend not so much on the velocity
as the momentum of the floating ice-islands. The same berg is
often carried away by a change of wind, and then driven back again
upon the same bank, or it is made to rise and fall by the waves of the
ocean, so that it may alternately strike the bottom with its whole
weight, and then be lifted up again until it has deranged the superficial
beds over a wide area. In this manner the geologist may account, perhaps,
for the circumstance that in Scandinavia, Scotland, and other
countries where erratics are met with, the beds of sand, loam, and
gravel are often vertical, bent, and contorted into the most complicated
folds, while the underlying strata, although composed of equally pliant
materials, are horizontal. But some of these curvatures of loose strata
may also have been due to repeated alternations of layers of gravel and
sand, ice and snow, the melting of the latter having caused the intercalated
beds of indestructible matter to assume their present anomalous
position.
There can be little doubt that icebergs must often break off the peaks
and projecting points of submarine mountains, and must grate upon and
polish their surface, furrowing or scratching them in precisely the same
way as we have seen that glaciers act on the solid rocks over which
they are propelled.301
230
To conclude: it appears that large stones, mud, and gravel are carried
down by the ice of rivers, estuaries, and glaciers, into the sea,
where the tides and currents of the ocean, aided by the wind, cause
them to drift for hundreds of miles from the place of their origin. Although
it will belong more properly to the seventh and eighth chapters
to treat of the transportation of solid matter by the movements of the
ocean, I shall add here what I have farther to say on this subject in
connection with ice.
The saline matter which sea-water holds in solution, prevents its congelation,
except where the most intense cold prevails. But the drifting
of the snow from the land often renders the surface-water brackish near
the coast, so that a sheet of ice is readily formed there, and by this
means a large quantity of gravel is frequently conveyed from place to
place, and heavy boulders also, when the coast-ice is packed into dense
masses. Both the large and small stones thus conveyed usually travel
in one direction like shingle-beaches, and this was observed to take
place on the coast of Labrador and Gulf of St. Lawrence, between the
latitudes 50° and 60° N., by Capt. Bayfield, during his late survey.
The line of coast alluded to is strewed over for a distance of 700 miles
with ice-borne boulders, often 6 feet in diameter, which are for the most
part on their way from north to south, or in the direction of the prevailing
current. Some points on this coast have been observed to be occasionally
deserted, and then again at another season thickly bestrewed
with erratics.
Fig. 19.
Boulders, chiefly of granite, stranded by ice on the coast of Labrador, between lat. 50° and 60° N.
(Lieut. Bowen, R. N.)
The accompanying drawing (fig. 19), for which I am indebted to
Lieut. Bowen, R. N., represents the ordinary appearance of the Labrador
coast, between the latitudes of 50° and 60° N. Countless blocks, chiefly
granitic, and of various sizes, are seen lying between high and low-water
231
mark. Capt. Bayfield saw similar masses carried by ice through the
Straits of Belle Isle, between Newfoundland and the American continent,
which he conceives may have travelled in the course of years
from Baffin's Bay, a distance which may be compared in our hemisphere
to the drifting of erratics from Lapland and Iceland as far south as Germany,
France, and England.
It may be asked in what manner have these blocks been originally
detached? We may answer that some have fallen from precipitous
cliffs, others have been lifted up from the bottom of the sea, adhering
by their tops to the ice, while others have been brought down by rivers
and glaciers.
The erratics of North America are sometimes angular, but most of
them have been rounded either by friction or decomposition. The
granite of Canada, as before remarked (p. 221 ), has a tendency to concentric
exfoliation, and scales off in spheroidal coats when exposed to
the spray of the sea during severe frosts. The range of the thermometer
in that country usually exceeds, in the course of the year, 100°, and
sometimes 120° F.; and, to prevent the granite used in the buildings
of Quebec from peeling off in winter, it is necessary to oil and paint the
squared stones.
In parts of the Baltic, such as the Gulf of Bothnia, where the quantity
of salt in the water amounts in general to one fourth only of that in
the ocean, the entire surface freezes over in winter to the depth of 5 or
6 feet. Stones are thus frozen in, and afterwards lifted up about 3 feet
perpendicularly on the melting of the snow in summer, and then carried
by floating ice-islands to great distances. Professor Von Baer states, in
a communication on this subject to the Academy of St. Petersburg, that
a block of granite, weighing a million of pounds, was carried by ice during
the winter of 1837-8 from Finland to the island of Hockland, and
two other huge blocks were transported about the years 1806 and 1814
by packed ice on the south coast of Finland, according to the testimony
of the pilots and inhabitants, one block having travelled about a quarter
of a mile, and lying about 18 feet above the level of the sea.302
More recently Dr. Forchhammer has shown that in the Sound, the
Great Belt, and other places near the entrance of the Baltic, ground-ice
forms plentifully at the bottom and then rises to the surface, charged
with sand and gravel, stones and sea-weed. Sheets of ice, also, with
included boulders, are driven up on the coast during storms, and "packed"
to a height of 50 feet. To the motion of such masses, but still
more to that of the ground-ice, the Danish professor attributes the striation
of rocky surfaces, forming the shores and bed of the sea, and he relates
a striking fact to prove that large quantities of rocky fragments
are annually carried by ice out of the Baltic. "In the year 1807," he
says, "at the time of the bombardment of the Danish fleet, an English
sloop-of-war, riding at anchor in the roads at Copenhagen, blew up. In
232
1844, or thirty-seven years afterwards, one of our divers, known to be a
trustworthy man, went down to save whatever might yet remain in the
shipwrecked vessel. He found the space between decks entire, but
covered with blocks from 6 to 8 cubic feet in size, and some of them
heaped one upon the other. He also affirmed, that all the sunk ships
which he had visited in the Sound, were in like manner strewed over
with blocks."
Dr. Forchhammer also informs us, that during an intense frost in
February, 1844, the Sound was suddenly frozen over, and sheets of ice,
driven by a storm, were heaped up at the bottom of the Bay of Täarbeijk,
threatening to destroy a fishing-village on the shore. The whole
was soon frozen together into one mass, and forced up on the beach,
forming a mound more than 16 feet high, which threw down the walls
of several buildings. "When I visited the spot next day, I saw ridges
of ice, sand, and pebbles, not only on the shore, but extending far out
into the bottom of the sea, showing how greatly its bed had been changed,
and how easily, where it is composed of rock, it may be furrowed and
streaked by stones firmly fixed in the moving ice."303
</div></body></text></TEI>