<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="7">

CHAPTER VII.
Of the Philosophy of the Sciences.


WE
proceed, in the ensuing Books, to the closer examination
of a considerable number of those Fundamental Ideas on which
the sciences, hitherto most successfully cultivated, are
founded. In this task, our objects will be to explain and
analyze such Ideas so as to bring into view the Definitions
and Axioms, or other forms, in which we may clothe the
conditions to which our speculative knowledge is subjected.
I shall also try to prove, for some of these Ideas in
particular, what has been already urged respecting them in
general, that they are not derived from observation, but
necessarily impose their conditions upon that knowledge of
which observation supplies the materials. I shall further,
in some cases, endeavour to trace the history of these Ideas
as they have successively come into notice in the progress
of science; the gradual development by which they have
arrived at their due purity and clearness; and, as a
necessary part of such a history, I shall give a view of
some of the principal controversies which have taken place
with regard to each portion of knowledge.
An exposition and discussion of the Fundamental Ideas of
each Science may, with great propriety, be termed the
Philosophy of such Science. These ideas contain in
themselves the elements of those truths which the science
discovers and enunciates; and in the progress of the
sciences, both in the world at large and in the mind of each
individual student, the most important steps consist in
apprehending these ideas clearly, and in bringing them into
accordance with the observed facts. I shall, therefore, in a
series of Books, 82 treat of the Philosophy of the Pure
Sciences, the Philosophy of the Mechanical
Sciences, the Philosophy of Chemistry, and the
like, and shall analyze and examine the ideas which these
sciences respectively involve.
In this undertaking, inevitably somewhat long, and involving
many deep and subtle discussions, I shall take, as a chart
of the country before me, by which my course is to be
guided, the scheme of the sciences which I was led to form
by travelling over the history of each in order8. Each
of the sciences of which I then narrated the progress,
depends upon several of the Fundamental Ideas of which I
have to speak: some of these Ideas are peculiar to one field
of speculation, others are common to more. A previous
enumeration of Ideas thus collected may serve both to show
the course and limits of this part of our plan, and the
variety of interest which it offers.</div></body></text></TEI>