<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="38">CHAPTER XXXVI.
Yet, thus surrounded, and regaled with this animated
praise, I was not content; I wanted a friend. I was alone
amidst the innumerable multitudes of those I had blessed.
I knew no cordiality; I could repose no confidence; I
could find no equal. I was like a God, who dispenses his
bounties profusely through twenty climates, but who at the
same time sits, separate, elevated, and alone, in the highest
heaven. The reader may, if he pleases, despise me for the
confession; but I felt that I was not formed for the happiness
of a God.
I was not however long sufficiently at leisure, thus to[378]
refine upon the deficiencies of my situation. I had engaged
in a task of extreme delicacy, in which the smallest failure
would draw along with it the most serious consequences.
Mine was not an undertaking that had for its object, to
supply those around me with luxuries, or to augment the
stock of their cheerful relaxations and amusements; the
very existence of my beneficiaries depended on its success.
I had put myself in a considerable degree, with whatever
diffidence and caution, in the room of the course of nature,
and had taken the administration of the common benefits
of human society into my hands. The populace are ever
ready to construe this delegation in the strictest sense:
unqualified to trace the wheels and combinations of the
great machine, if prosperity is their lot, they willingly ascribe
it to their protectors and governors; and if they
are unfortunate, it is against them that the storm of their
resentment is directed. The moment they are thus irritated,
their impatience is too great to admit of correctives
and remedies; in the fury of their disappointment, they
disturb every thing, and render that irreparable and fatal,
which was at first only doubtful and unpromising.
My proceedings, as I have already said, bore in the commencement
the most benignant face, and seemed a revival
of this despairing and unfortunate nation little less than
miraculous. The regular labours in which the inhabitants
became engaged, restored a healthful tone to their minds;
the payments they duly received seemed to discharge them
from all anxious solicitude; and, as by my own efforts and
the enterprises of others, the market was supplied with provisions,
they had no difficulty in exchanging these payments
for the necessaries of life. The supply of the market at
first was easy; the universal dejection that preceded, though
it had not prevented all exertions for that purpose, had
rendered those exertions too feeble for extensive success.
The strenuous efforts that were now made were productive
of a copious supply; but they rendered each importation
more difficult than the importation before. The demand
continued the same; the relief was every day more diminutive
and precarious. The harvest was however advancing
with the happiest auspices: and, though some time must[379]
yet be consumed in expectation, it was probable frugality
and fortitude might enable the inhabitants to hold out till
the season of plenty should arrive.
But fortitude is not the virtue of a populace. The
higher had been their hopes, and the more unexpected their
deliverance, with so much the more blank and melancholy
a countenance they beheld this unexpected delay and retrogression.
Not understanding the powers by which I acted,
they blindly ascribed to me the faculty of doing whatever I
pleased. As long as every thing went on prosperously,
they were grateful; the moment a reverse occurred, they
were inclined to murmur. They made no allowance for the
limited capacities of a human creature: they imputed
whatever was unpleasing to indifference or ill will. The
price of commodities, after having for a while become
moderate, now rapidly rose again: this was partly the consequence
of the increased quantity of the precious metals,
by means of which any assignable sum bore a less proportion
to the provisions of the market than it had done
before. Bread was at a very high price; and it occasionally
happened to buyers who did not come early enough,
that there was no bread to be purchased. The doors of the
houses where it was sold, were besieged; the industrious
poor appeared before them with the first faint dawn of the
morning’s light. Here they consumed hours of painful
expectation, in grievous addition to the hours of their customary
fatigue. The whole was a scene of anguish and
calamity; the passions of those who composed it, mingled
with the distress, and rendered it too heavy to be borne.
Anticipating famine, they felt the mischiefs of it before
it arrived. Never was the demand so urgent; it seemed as
if the capacity of men’s appetites was enlarged, and the
cravings of hunger became more insatiable, in proportion to
the smallness of the supply. To people thus circumstanced,
it would have been vain to recommend frugality and moderation.
They devoured the food with their eyes, while
it was yet beyond the reach of their hands; and the lesson
you read them, would have sounded in their ears as if you
had bid them die to-day, to escape the danger of dying to-morrow.
[380]
The crowds which the necessity of purchasing bread
brought together at certain hours, when assembled, naturally
entered into the discussion of their present discontents.
They were not satisfied with the discourse and jostling of
the morning; the habits produced by these noisy assemblies
had a secret charm with them, and drew them together at
seasons of less urgent demand. They patroled the streets:
they were loud in the expressions of their dissatisfaction.
With the inconsequence incident to the lower orders of
mankind, they threatened to destroy the mills, the markets,
the places of sale, the means and materials by which their
wants were to be supplied.
In the midst of these scenes of tumult and confusion, it
is not to be imagined that I escaped uncensured. Far
otherwise: in proportion to the gratitude and adoration
with which they had lately regarded me, were their detestation
and abhorrence now. My interference was spoken
of with contempt and execration. For what purpose had
I, a foreigner, come into their country, and intruded myself
into their affairs? Why had I impiously taken them out
of the hands of their heavenly Father, whose care was so
constant, and whose relief so certain? It was on my part a
despicable vanity and presumption, which the justice of
Providence could not fail to avenge; and they must now
suffer the punishment of my blasphemy. But they did not
stop here. There was no horrible calumny which they did
not invent, or give credit to, against me. They imputed to
me the basest personal motives for what I had done. Under
the hypocritical pretence, they cried, of being their benefactor
and saviour, I was using them only for my private ends.
I had become a purchaser and vender of corn, for the single
purpose of increasing my fortune. The present scarcity,
they were well assured, was artificial, and of my own contriving.
I had magazines in different stations on the borders,
which, when the price was risen to the standard of my
avarice, and when half the people had fallen victims to my
inhumanity, I purposed to dispose of to an immense profit.
Such were the aspersions to which my character became
generally exposed. By the populace, who now experienced
the unsatisfied cravings of hunger, and in whom my proceedings[381]
had excited hope, only to be followed by a more
cruel disappointment, they were greedily credited. Many
who knew their falsehood, were yet zealous to propagate
them. Short as had been my residence in Hungary, I had
made many enemies. It is to be feared that no man can
be assiduous and indefatigable in the service of others,
without incurring that consequence. I employed a great
number of workmen; every one whom for whatever reason
I refused to employ, every one who, being unqualified for
the service I required, looked with an envious eye on the
better fortune of his neighbour, was well disposed to be my
enemy. Persons of no contemptible account in the community
had been excited by expectations of profit to
engage in the importation of corn: these persons viewed
my efforts in the same department with a suspicious eye,
and regarded a man who, however cautious in his proceedings,
was not regulated by the same motive, as a most pernicious
rival. My sudden elevation and importance in the
country were viewed with not more astonishment than
aversion by those whose importance I obscured. They could
not hear with patience of an upstart, a boy, a stranger,
one universally unknown, elbowing out the influence of
all that was most illustrious and venerable in the community,
and robbing them daily of their adherents and
retainers. All these persons left no effort untried to defame
my character.
The impulse once given, the turbulent disposition of the
populace became every day more formidable. It is much
easier to disseminate a temper of this sort than to quell it:
my opulent foes might take alarm at its excesses, and desire
to undo what they had done; but it was beyond their
power. Every day I feared lest, from threats and invectives,
the populace should proceed to violence: every night
I thought I had reason to congratulate myself, that the day
had passed without waste and spoil committed by them on
the means of their subsistence, or was not marked with the
destruction of their champion and benefactor. In some
places a sort of petty sedition broke out among the labourers
I employed: in the morning they refused to work: why
should a man work, they muttered, when after all he may[382]
starve with the wages of his labour in his possession? At
night they became impatient and furious, and demanded
from my superintendents and storehouse-men the food,
which in the morning they had refused to earn, and were
therefore now unable to purchase. I had already had some
experience in the nature of popular tumults; I had now no
marchese Filosanto at hand to persuade me of their inefficacy;
and, if I had, I should no longer have lent an ear
to his serene and unsuspicious generosity. I felt the reality
of the danger; I saw the storm as it blackened in my horizon,
and was deeply convinced what it would be if it burst
upon my head.
It may be imagined with what feelings I viewed my
whole design on the point to be subverted, by the unruliness
of those for whose benefit it had been planned. It is true
I had now no darling relations to be involved in my fate,
no incomparable wife, no daughters illustrious in innocence
and beauty; yet my feelings were scarcely less pungent
than they had been at the period of my catastrophe at Pisa.
I had blamed myself in review, that, in my experiments at
Constance, at Dresden, at Pisa, and at Madrid, I had not
commenced upon a sufficiently ample scale, but had suffered
myself to be frustrated by the ingloriousness of my precautions.
That had not been my error in the present
instance; yet my success now promised to be scarcely more
flattering than upon former occasions. I had looked for
happiness as the result of the benevolence and philanthropy
I was exerting; I found only anxiety and a well grounded
fear even for my personal safety. Let no man build on the
expected gratitude of those he spends his strength to serve!
Let him be beneficent if he will; but let him not depend
for his happiness on the conviction of his rectitude and
virtue that is to be impressed on the minds of others!
There is a principle in the human breast, that easily induces
them to regard every thing that can be done for them,
as no more than their due, and speedily discharges them
from the oppressive consciousness of obligation. There is
a levity in the generality of men, that entails on them a
continual oblivion of past benefits, and makes one recent
disappointment of more importance in their eyes than an[383]
eternity of kindnesses and condescension. I shall have
other instances of ingratitude to display in what yet remains
to be related of my story.
My nights were restless; my thoughts were in arms.
What was it that it became me to do in the present emergency?
Sometimes, in the bitterness of my heart, hating
myself, hating the endowments of the stranger, hating a
race of beings who denied all credit to the most unheard-of
exertions for their advantage, I determined to withdraw
unobserved from my attendants and clients, and bid adieu
to Hungary for ever. But whither was I to fly? What
was I to do next? What experiment could I make of the
purposes to which to apply the philosopher’s stone, that I
had not already made? These questions, to none of which
I could give a satisfactory answer, checked the career of my
passion, and gave pause to my thoughts.
Whatever I did, I was determined to do nothing rashly,
nor to quit a great experiment without its having been fully
tried. It was no light concern, no trivial child’s-play, in
which I had embarked. I had taken the welfare, perhaps
the existence, of a great and heroic nation under my protection.
In this glorious vocation it did not become me to
be lightly discouraged. What if those I served and saved
did not show themselves sufficiently sensible to the exertions
I made for them? I ought to purify my bosom, on an
occasion like this, from base and ignoble motives, and to
deem myself sufficiently recompensed by my conscious virtue.
What if the service in which I had engaged now
appeared to be a service of hazard and peril? Is there
any great undertaking that can be separated from this condition?
If hastily, from cowardice, from pique, or from
any other motive, I deserted the business on which I had
entered, what was to become of my mistaken indeed, but
in that case most unfortunate clients? The greater was
the crisis to which they were exposed, the more were unremitted
vigilance and uncommon powers necessary to guide
them amidst its rocks and its quicksands. I saw thousands
of men who for several weeks had fed, as it were, from the
stores of my bounty. By a propensity inseparable from the
human heart, I became attached to the work of my meditations,[384]
and the labour of my thoughts. All their fickleness,
their injustice, even the atrocious calumnies they admitted
and propagated against me, could not wean my
attachment from beings, a great portion of whom, but for
my interference, would, I believed, long ere this have expired
of hunger.
In the peculiar and urgent circumstances in which I
found myself, no expedient was so obvious as that of calling
in the interference of the government under which I lived.
It was necessary that the resources of national subsistence
should be defended from the wanton spoil of those who,
when they were annihilated, must inevitably perish. It
was necessary that the benefactor of Hungary, who, I flattered
myself, was still able to watch effectively for her
advantage, should be protected from her misguided resentment.
The alternative was singularly painful to my feelings.
The pride with which my unparalleled endowments inspired
me, was deeply wounded, when I was compelled to confess
that I was not alone equal to the task I had undertaken,
and that I must submit to call in a foreign auxiliary. I
augured little favourable from the interference of government,
which, if I implored, I could scarcely expect to
guide, which was not likely to submit to my principle of
rendering its interference the mildest and smallest that the
nature of the case would admit; but, puffed up with presumption,
and intoxicated with authority, would probably
leave no concern of the public welfare uninvaded. Least
of all, could I anticipate much of good from a Turkish government.
But what could I do? I could discover no
other expedient. Influenced by the views I have recited,
I had hitherto kept myself as far from the observation of
the political directors of the state as I could. But my
cautiousness and reserve were now at an end. With my
eyes open I exposed myself to all the evils that might attend
on my proceeding.
I determined to apply to the bashaw of the province.
Previously to my taking this step, I had the precaution to
enquire his character. He was the genuine offspring of the
Turkish system of government. His name was Muzaffer
Bey. He was originally a Circassian slave; then a Janissary;[385]
and, rising by insensible gradation, had at length been
appointed bashaw of Buda, which, as being the immediate
frontier between Austria and the Porte, was at this time
the most arduous situation in the gift of the sultan. He
was esteemed a good soldier; he had been early distinguished
by his dexterity in military exercises; he had since
seen much service; and, in every situation in which he was
placed, had earned commendation and honour. He was
abstemious and hardy; for himself, he neither pampered
his appetites nor shrunk from severity; and he had as little
indulgence for those under his command as for his own person.
Yet he was indebted for his present eminence more to
the arts of the courtier, than to his merits in the field. His
chief care had ever been to recommend himself to those
above him, and to obtain the good will of his equals; for
the opinion of his inferiors he gave himself little concern.
With considerable ability, he laboured under no check from
either principle or ingenuous pride; and therefore was
extremely successful in his attacks on the inclination of
those he sought. The habits of his mind had modified the
lines of his countenance and the tones of his voice. Except
to his dependants and the poor he almost always spoke with
a smile upon his face, and his enunciation was silver-tongued,
oily, copious, and insinuating. If he ever adopted
a different manner, the variation was only in the means
not the end; and, when he seemed to travel by an opposite
road, the goal at which he aimed was the same. He never
consulted any oracle but that of his apparent interest; if he
had any insolence in his nature, he regarded his slaves and
those under his military command as affording a sufficient
sphere for its exercise; he had no affections to disturb him
from his bent; he had no passions but the self-complacency
of superior cunning, and the sordid love of pelf.
This account of the man with whom I had to deal was
far from encouraging; but I had no alternative. I sent to
signify my desire to confer with him; or, to speak more
accurately, to ask, in the Eastern manner when it would be
agreeable to him to receive a present of which I requested
his acceptance. He appointed the morning of the following
day. I prepared a gift, such as might tend to conciliate his[386]
favour, without marking in the donor the possession of
immoderate wealth. It consisted of silks and muslins, with
a small piece of plate of exquisite workmanship. My
present was borne by two of my servants. We were
ushered to the bashaw in his private apartment; there were
two or three persons in attendance upon him. They examined
my present together; and, without condescending
to express much approbation, I could nevertheless discern
that the bashaw was pleased with it. This ceremony concluded;
Muzaffer ordered what I had brought to be taken
into a different apartment; and, every other person withdrawing,
we were left alone.
While the bashaw was examining my gift, I took the
opportunity of considering his person. He appeared to be
about sixty years of age; his complexion dark and muddy;
his features coarse and distorted; his mustachoes remarkably
large; his person, though bony and muscular, considerably
below the middle size; and his figure ungainly and
ungraceful. I felt surprised that such a man should ever
have been an excellent soldier, or have risen from a low
rank to one of the first situations of the empire. To look
at him, he seemed better formed for the vice of a comedy,
than the ruler of a nation. He raised his eyes towards me
askance, as he sat leaning on his elbow, and said,
“You call yourself—?”
“The sieur de Chatillon.”
“And your age—?”
“Is two and twenty.”
“I am glad you are come to me. I intended to have
sent for you, and you have saved me the trouble.”
I made many apologies for my intrusion, but added
that I had a petition to prefer, and I hoped he would favour
me with a hearing.
“Not at all, not at all; do not call it an intrusion: it
is necessary I should be acquainted with you.” He proceeded:—
“You have undertaken to confer great benefits on the
subjects of the grand signior, my master; to rescue them
from famine. Young, rich, a stranger, unknown to my
master, unknown to his subjects, I understand that you[387]
have spared no labour or expense to bring about their welfare.
This is really a very extraordinary case; your merit
is unprecedented; I do not feel myself competent to reward
it.”
I answered that I laid no claim to uncommon merit;
that every temper had its particular gratifications; and that
I found as real a luxury in the proceedings he had remarked,
as other men did in the excesses of the table, or
the promiscuous enjoyments of the harem.
“It is out of my power,” continued he, “to remunerate
you as you deserve; I must send you to Constantinople.”
I perceived that this was the first essay of his artifice.
I informed him which I have no doubt he knew well enough
before, that I had no desire to go to Constantinople. I
wished to remain where I was, and to finish what I had
begun.
“What, you have not done then?” suddenly and with
an abrupt voice exclaimed the bashaw. “By Mahomet, a
man of a reasonable appetite in your place might be satisfied.
Have not you filled the streets with riots, and the
country with rebellion? Do not the populace assemble in
crowds, insulting every one they meet, and talking of nothing
but fire and devastation, the bowstring and the
cimeter? Be so good, my dear sir; as to inform me what
further you may have in view?”
“Reverend bashaw,” cried I with submission, yet with
firmness, “I have none of these things in view. But a
moment ago you did justice to my intentions. They are
those of beneficence, and beneficence only.”
“I know nothing about that. I have nothing to do
with honest men’s blunders; I look to the effects they produce.”
“These effects, most mighty sir, are temporary; they
are the clouds that will often obscure for an instant the
brightest sunshine. Condescend to lend me your generous
assistance, and all will be well.”
“Do not tell me of clouds and sunshine. This is, to
my thinking, not an April shower, but an earthquake and
a hurricane. If we are all to be swallowed up or whirled
into the air, it is no consolation to me, that the day after[388]
we are gone, every thing shall be as fair and serene as
paradise itself.”
“Remember, sir, that when I came into Hungary, I
found its inhabitants in the most desperate condition, miserable,
wasted and starving. Have I not already suspended
this evil for months?”
“Yes, I do remember. You are one of those busy-bodies,
who never see an evil without imagining they are
the persons to correct it, intruding into every thing, and
subverting every thing. The superintendence of the public
welfare is a mystery to which none are competent, but those
whom Mahomet has raised to the situation of statesmen.
Your interference is blasphemy against the spirit of our
religion, and deserves to be encountered with the most
exemplary punishment.”
“Good God! then, is it in this country a crime to feed
the hungry, to clothe the naked, and shelter the houseless?”
“Sieur de Chatillon,” retorted the bashaw, “you appear
to be unacquainted with the maxims of Turkish policy, the
wisest and most beneficent in the world. If none of the
disturbances had happened at which I have so much reason
to be alarmed, still, in relieving the people in the manner
you have done, you have incurred the guilt of high treason
against the sultan. Know, sir, that, through the whole
extent of his dominions, there is but one proprietor,
and that is our illustrious monarch. You say, that you
wish to be the benefactor of his subjects, and the judge of
your own proceedings: such sentiments are direct rebellion
against the glorious constitution of Ottoman. The sovereign
of Constantinople will have no benefactor in the
countries he presides over, but himself. Like the invisible
ruler of the universe, he acts by second causes; he allows
his ministers to be the instruments of his beneficence; but
all must be ascribed to him, must flow from his will, and
be placed under his control. You, who have formed a plan
of public benefit without consulting him, and have presumed,
like a luminary of the world, to move in an orbit
of your own, have in strictness of construction forfeited your
life to his justice; and I consult rather the clemency of his[389]
nature than the maxims of his policy, if I suffer you to go
from this palace with your head upon your shoulders.”
Without permitting myself to be too much moved by the
imperious language addressed to me, I complained to the
bashaw of the rigorous and arbitrary character of what he
stated to be the maxims of the Turkish government. I
solemnly protested that I had no private or personal object
in view. The effect of my operations would be to give
new strength and energy to his master’s dominions. By
diffusing happiness among his subjects, by reviving industry,
and scattering plenty, prosperity, and ease, all disaffection
would be rooted out; and the people, who are never
minute in scanning the cause of their enjoyments, would
bless the sceptre under which they were made to participate
such manifold benefits. If the policy of the divan led them
in any degree to interfere, they ought rather to crown my
measures with their applause, than wantonly to throw obstacles
in the way of what I purposed. I asked however
no reward, I demanded no favour for myself; all I desired
was that the sultan would assist me in securing to his people
those benefits, the dissemination of which I had so
auspiciously begun.
The bashaw, without taking any direct notice of this
expostulation, answered, that I was not aware of the maxims
of his government, to which, in consideration of my seeming
generosity and rectitude, he was willing to give the mildest
interpretation. “It is however,” continued he, “to the
last degree idle in you to imagine, that you can be permitted
to go on unobserved, and that the sultan and his representatives
are to take no account of your proceeding. The great
instrument for ruling mankind is by their passions and
their opinions. The man from whom they believe they
have the most to fear and the most to hope, will always be
their master. Whatever be your secret or your professed
designs, you go on from day to day making yourself partisans,
and enlisting the subjects of the sultan among your
personal retainers. What security has he for your submission
and loyalty? How shall he know that, when you
have acquired the advantages of a powerful leader, you will
not go over to the enemy, or, in the present distracted condition[390]
of the province, even have the audacity to set up for
yourself? If therefore, by an unexampled clemency of
construction, I decline to reduce you into the passive machine
of my master’s will, it is at least incumbent on me,
that I should take account of your powers, and possess myself
of the schedule of your property. By this means only
can I watch your progress, and take care that you do not
suddenly become too powerful for a subject. Are you prepared
to satisfy me on this head?”
On this question I hesitated for a moment; I had not
exactly anticipated the enquiry; at length I requested the
delay of a few days, and then I promised that all his demands
should be satisfied. The bashaw resumed:—
“Sieur de Chatillon, I remark your hesitation, and I
draw from it no favourable augury. These indirect and
involuntary indications are more worthy of my attention
than all the studied and elaborate information you shall
think proper to give me. Sir, you are a man of darkness,
and every thing that relates to you is enveloped in mystery.
You come hither with no apparent motive; you have no
connections of blood in Hungary; you have no acquaintance
with any eminent person of the Hungarian nation. I
have had my spies on you, though I have not hitherto
thought proper to summon you to my presence. You have
purchased no property in the province; I cannot learn that
you have any correspondences or resources from abroad. I
have been at the pains to procure an account of your expenditure
during the three months you have resided among
us; much of that expenditure has been obscure, clandestine,
and indirect; but I believe you will find my estimate,
which you are at liberty to inspect and remark upon, tolerably
correct. Your disbursements for three months,
exceed the amount of two years’ income of the richest subject
that even the credulous monarchs of Christendom suffer
within their dominions. What am I to think of this? How
can I be sufficiently vigilant respecting a man, whose expenditure
is immense, and whose wealth can neither be
traced to its source, nor ascertained in its amount?”
I was not slow in conjecturing the result which the
bashaw proposed to himself from our present conference. I[391]
was confirmed in my conjecture by the circumstance of his
choosing that the discussion between us should be apart
from all witnesses. He regarded me as a boy, and had
therefore practised upon me all those arts which might
most effectually excite in me fear and alarm. He found
however that, under the external indications of youth and
inexperience, I possessed the wariness that added years most
powerfully inculcate, and the self-possession of a mind thoroughly
awake to its situation and its resources. This
must have been to the minister before whom I stood a
memorable phenomenon. But curiosity is not a Turkish
passion; and the single object of the bashaw in the present
instance, was to make the mysteriousness of my circumstances
a pretext for extorting money. I submitted with
as little seeming reluctance as possible to the necessity of
the case; I requested the good offices of Muzaffer to protect
my benefactions; and begged permission to make him
the compliment of a handsome sum of money, by way of
convincing him that I was worthy of his friendship.
This business was easily adjusted between us. I found
him perfectly skilled in the duties of a public office, and
by no means under the dominion of visionary scruples. He
told me he was now convinced that I was a well meaning
man, and a good subject; he said, that nothing could tend
more effectually to demonstrate my innocence, than my
showing that I understood the duties and concerns of a
minister of state; and that for his own part he was never
so happy, as when he was thus able to reconcile his private
interests with the good and faithful service of his master.
There was nothing that demanded a more unremitted vigilance,
or a more skilful management, than such a situation
as his; and it would be most unreasonable, either in the
sovereign that appointed him, or the subjects over whom he
was placed, to expect him to be indifferent to the emoluments
and perquisites of his function. He complimented
me warmly upon the disinterestedness and liberality of my
exertions. He thought himself particularly fortunate in
having so public-spirited an individual within the circuit
of his jurisdiction. In fine, he hoped he should be honoured
with my personal acquaintance, and assured me that[392]
nothing could make him more happy than the frequent repetition
of my visits.
We now perfectly understood one another; and it was
apparent that I had to do with a man, who, for what he
deemed an adequate consideration, would willingly lend me
the authority and countenance of his office, and suffer me
to guide him in any of the functions I might conceive necessary
for the execution of my projects. Guards were
agreed to be placed upon the magazines where corn was
still contained, and from place to place on the banks of
the rivers, where the depredations of a misguided populace
were most to be apprehended. Finding the bashaw so
perfectly willing to comply with my requisitions, I further
obtained from him the direction of several squadrons of
cavalry for the protection of the crops, which from the consequences
of my interference now began on all sides to
variegate the scene. This was a most important service.
When the corn was first committed to the earth, it was out
of the reach of military devastation. But, as time glided
silently on, the case became materially altered; the enemy
might from forecast desire to reap the harvest of what he
had not sown, or from malice to destroy that without which
the Turk would perhaps be unable to retain his newly acquired
territory. This had in reality been the principal
cause, before my arrival in Hungary, of the very general
neglect into which agriculture had fallen. Muzaffer, than
whom no person could now be more polite and condescending,
allowed me to determine the number and nature of the
troops I required; and added that, though he could not
openly put them under my direction, the slightest intimation
I might think proper to convey to him, should at any
time decide their march, and regulate their quarters.
</div></body></text></TEI>