<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="1">ADVERTISEMENT.
The Publishers of the Collection of “Standard
Novels” are extremely desirous that I should furnish
them with a few lines, by way of introduction to the
appearance of St. Leon in its present form. I am
however at a loss how to oblige them. In the original
Preface I frankly stated the sources upon which I had
drawn for the idea and conduct of the work. I have
therefore no remarks to offer, but these which follow:—
In 1794 I produced the novel of Caleb Williams. I
believed myself fortunate in the selection I had made
of the ground-plot of that work. An atrocious
crime committed by a man previously of the most
exemplary habits, the annoyance he suffers from the
immeasurable and ever-wakeful curiosity of a raw youth
who is placed about his person, the state of doubt in
which the reader might for a time be as to the truth
of the charges, and the consequences growing out of
these causes, seemed to me to afford scope for a narrative
of no common interest. I was not disappointed.
Caleb Williams was honoured with the public favour.
The consequence was that I was solicited to try my
hand again in a work of fiction. I hesitated long. I
despaired of finding again a topic so rich of interest
and passion. In those days it was deemed a most
daring thought to attempt to write a novel, with the
hope that it might hereafter rank among the classics
of a language. The most successful English writers[vi]
in that province of literature had scarcely gone
beyond three. It had not then been conceived that the
same author might produce twenty or thirty, at the
rate of two or three per annum, and might still at least
retain his hold upon the partiality of his contemporaries.
To Sir Walter Scott we are indebted for this
discovery.
At length, after having passed some years in a
state of diffidence and irresolution, I ventured on the
task. It struck me that if I could “mix human feelings
and passions with incredible situations,” I might
thus attain a sort of novelty that would conciliate the
patience, at least, even of some of the severest judges.
To this way of thinking St. Leon was indebted for a
“local habitation, and a name.”
One of my most valued friends [Mr. Northcote]
has often told me, that the public may sometimes be
interested in the perusal of a book, but that they never
give themselves any trouble about the author. He
therefore kindly advised me on no occasion to say any
thing in print about myself. The present race of
readers seem scarcely disposed to verify this maxim.
They are understood to be desirous to learn something
of the peculiarities, the “life, character, and behaviour,”
of an author, before they consign him to the
gulph of oblivion, and are willing to learn from his own
testimony what train of thoughts induced him to adopt
the particular subject and plan of the work, upon the
perusal of which they are engaged.
June, 1831.

[vii]</div></body></text></TEI>