<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="5">
NOVUM ORGANON RENOVATUM.

BOOK I.
APHORISMS CONCERNING IDEAS DERIVED FROM
THE HISTORY OF IDEAS.
I.
MAN is the Interpreter of Nature, Science the right
interpretation. (History of Scientific Ideas:
Book i. Chapter 1.)
II.
The Senses place before us the Characters of the Book
of Nature; but these convey no knowledge to us, till we
have discovered the Alphabet by which they are to be read.
(Ibid. i. 2.)
III.
The Alphabet, by means of which we interpret Phenomena,
consists of the Ideas existing in our own minds; for
these give to the phenomena that coherence and significance
which is not an object of sense. (i. 2.)
IV.
The antithesis of Sense and Ideas is the foundation of
the Philosophy of Science. No knowledge can exist without
the union, no philosophy without the separation, of these two
elements. (i. 2.)
6
V.
Fact and Theory correspond to Sense on the one hand,
and to Ideas on the other, so far as we are conscious of our
Ideas: but all facts involve ideas unconsciously; and thus
the distinction of Facts and Theories is not tenable, as that
of Sense and Ideas is. (i. 2.)
VI.
Sensations and Ideas in our knowledge are like Matter
and Form in bodies. Matter cannot exist without Form,
nor Form without Matter: yet the two are altogether distinct
and opposite. There is no possibility either of separating,
or of confounding them. The same is the case with
Sensations and Ideas. (i. 2.)
VII.
Ideas are not transformed, but informed Sensations; for
without ideas, sensations have no form. (i. 2.)
VIII.
The Sensations are the Objective, the Ideas the Subjective
part of every act of perception or knowledge. (i. 2.)
IX.
General Terms denote Ideal Conceptions, as a circle, an
orbit, a rose. These are not Images of real things, as was
held by the Realists, but Conceptions: yet they are conceptions, not bound
together by mere Name, as the Nominalists
held, but by an Idea. (i. 2.)
X.
It has been said by some, that all Conceptions are merely
states or feelings of the mind, but this assertion only tends
to confound what it is our business to distinguish. (i. 2.)
XI.
Observed Facts are connected so as to produce new truths,
by superinducing upon them an Idea: and such truths are
obtained by Induction. (i. 2.)
7
XII.
Truths once obtained by legitimate Induction are Facts:
these Facts may be again connected, so as to produce higher
truths: and thus we advance to Successive Generalizations.
(i. 2.)
XIII.
Truths obtained by Induction are made compact and
permanent by being expressed in Technical Terms. (i. 3.)
XIV.
Experience cannot conduct us to universal and necessary
truths:—Not to universal, because she has not tried all
cases:—Not to necessary, because necessity is not a matter
to which experience can testify. (i. 5.)
XV.
Necessary truths derive their necessity from the Ideas
which they involve; and the existence of necessary truths
proves the existence of Ideas not generated by experience.
(i. 5.)
XVI.
In Deductive Reasoning, we cannot have any truth in
the conclusion which is not virtually contained in the
premises. (i. 6.)
XVII.
In order to acquire any exact and solid knowledge, the
student must possess with perfect precision the ideas
appropriate to that part of knowledge: and this precision is
tested by the student’s perceiving the axiomatic evidence of
the axioms belonging to each Fundamental Idea. (i. 6.)
XVIII.
The Fundamental Ideas which it is most important to
consider, as being the Bases of the Material Sciences, are the
Ideas of Space, Time (including Number), Cause
(including Force and Matter), Outness of Objects, and Media of
Perception of Secondary Qualities, Polarity (Contrariety),
8
Chemical Composition and Affinity, Substance, Likeness
and Natural Affinity, Means and Ends (whence the Notion
of Organization), Symmetry, and the Ideas of Vital Powers.
(i. 8.)
XIX.
The Sciences which depend upon the Ideas of Space and
Number are Pure Sciences, not Inductive Sciences: they do
not infer special Theories from Facts, but deduce the conditions
of all theory from Ideas. The Elementary Pure
Sciences, or Elementary Mathematics, are Geometry, Theoretical
Arithmetic and Algebra. (ii. 1.)
XX.
The Ideas on which the Pure Sciences depend, are those
of Space and Number; but Number is a modification of
the conception of Repetition, which belongs to the Idea of
Time. (ii. 1.)
XXI.
The Idea of Space is not derived from experience, for
experience of external objects presupposes bodies to exist in
Space, Space is a condition under which the mind receives
the impressions of sense, and therefore the relations of space
are necessarily and universally true of all perceived objects.
Space is a form of our perceptions, and regulates them,
whatever the matter of them may be. (ii. 2.)
XXII.
Space is not a General Notion collected by abstraction
from particular cases; for we do not speak of Spaces in
general, but of universal or absolute Space. Absolute Space
is infinite. All special spaces are in absolute space, and are
parts of it. (ii. 3.)
XXIII.
Space is not a real object or thing, distinct from the
objects which exist in it; but it is a real condition of the
existence of external objects. (ii. 3.)
9
XXIV.
We have an Intuition of objects in space; that is, we
contemplate objects as made up of spatial parts, and
apprehend their spatial relations by the same act by which we
apprehend the objects themselves. (ii. 3.)
XXV.
Form or Figure is space limited by boundaries. Space
has necessarily three dimensions, length, breadth, depth; and
no others which cannot be resolved into these. (ii. 3.)
XXVI.
The Idea of Space is exhibited for scientific purposes, by
the Definitions and Axioms of Geometry; such, for instance,
as these:—the Definition of a Right Angle, and of a Circle;—the
Definition of Parallel Lines, and the Axiom concerning them;—the
Axiom that two straight lines cannot
inclose a space. These Definitions are necessary, not arbitrary;
and the Axioms are needed as well as the Definitions,
in order to express the necessary conditions which the Idea of
Space imposes. (ii. 4.)
XXVII.
The Definitions and Axioms of Elementary Geometry do
not completely exhibit the Idea of Space. In proceeding
to the Higher Geometry, we may introduce other additional
and independent Axioms; such as that of Archimedes, that
a curve line which joins two points is less than any
broken line joining the same points and including the
curve line. (ii. 4.)
XXVIII.
The perception of a solid object by sight requires that act
of mind by which, from figure and shade, we infer distance
and position in space. The perception of figure by sight
requires that act of mind by which we give an outline
to each object. (ii. 6.)
10
XXIX.
The perception of Form by touch is not an impression on
the passive sense, but requires an act of our muscular frame
by which we become aware of the position of our own limbs.
The perceptive faculty involved in this act has been called
the muscular sense. (ii. 6.)
XXX.
The Idea of Time is not derived from experience, for
experience of changes presupposes occurrences to take place in
Time. Time is a condition under which the mind receives
the impressions of sense, and therefore the relations of time
are necessarily and universally true of all perceived occurrences.
Time is a form of our perceptions, and regulates
them, whatever the matter of them may be. (ii. 7.)
XXXI.
Time is not a General Notion collected by abstraction
from particular cases. For we do not speak of particular
Times as examples of time in general, but as parts of a
single and infinite Time. (ii. 8.)
XXXII.
Time, like Space, is a form, not only of perception, but
of Intuition. We consider the whole of any time as equal
to the sum of the parts; and an occurrence as coinciding
with the portion of time which it occupies. (ii. 8.)
XXXIII.
Time is analogous to Space of one dimension: portions
of both have a beginning and an end, are long or short.
There is nothing in Time which is analogous to Space of
two, or of three, dimensions, and thus nothing which corresponds
to Figure. (ii. 8.)
XXXIV.
The Repetition of a set of occurrences, as, for example,
strong and weak, or long and short sounds, according
to a 11
steadfast order, produces Rhythm, which is a conception
peculiar to Time, as Figure is to Space. (ii. 8.)
XXXV.
The simplest form of Repetition is that in which there is
no variety, and thus gives rise to the conception of Number.
(ii. 8.)
XXXVI.
The simplest numerical truths are seen by Intuition; when
we endeavour to deduce the more complex from these simplest,
we employ such maxims as these:—If equals be added
to equals the wholes are equal:—If equals be subtracted
from equals the remainders are equal:—The whole is
equal to the sum of all its parts. (ii. 9.)
XXXVII.
The Perception of Time involves a constant and latent
kind of memory, which may be termed a Sense of Succession.
The Perception of Number also involves this Sense of
Succession, although in small numbers we appear to apprehend
the units simultaneously and not successively. (ii. 10.)
XXXVIII.
The Perception of Rhythm is not an impression on the
passive sense, but requires an act of thought by which we
connect and group the strokes which form the Rhythm.
(ii. 10.)
XXXIX.
Intuitive is opposed to Discursive reason. In intuition,
we obtain our conclusions by dwelling upon one aspect of
the fundamental Idea; in discursive reasoning, we combine
several aspects of the Idea, (that is, several axioms,) and
reason from the combination. (ii. 11.)
XL.
Geometrical deduction (and deduction in general) is called
Synthesis, because we introduce, at successive steps,
the 12
results of new principles. But in reasoning on the relations
of space, we sometimes go on separating truths into their
component truths, and these into other component truths; and
so on: and this is geometrical Analysis. (ii. 11.)
XLI.
Among the foundations of the Higher Mathematics, is the
Idea of Symbols considered as general Signs of Quantity.
This idea of a Sign is distinct from, and independent of
other ideas. The Axiom to which we refer in reasoning by
means of Symbols of quantity is this:—The interpretation
of such symbols must be perfectly general. This Idea
and
Axiom are the bases of Algebra in its most general form.
(ii. 12.)
XLII.
Among the foundations of the Higher Mathematics is
also the Idea of a Limit. The Idea of a Limit cannot be
superseded by any other definitions or Hypotheses, The
Axiom which we employ in introducing this Idea into our
reasoning is this:—What is true up to the Limit is true
at the Limit. This Idea and Axiom are the bases of all
Methods of Limits, Fluxions, Differentials, Variations, and
the like. (ii. 12.)
XLIII.
There is a pure Science of Motion, which does not depend
upon observed facts, but upon the Idea of motion. It may
also be termed Pure Mechanism, in opposition to Mechanics
Proper, or Machinery, which involves the mechanical conceptions of
force and matter. It has been proposed to name
this Pure Science of Motion, Kinematics. (ii. 13.)
XLIV.
The pure Mathematical Sciences must be successfully cultivated,
in order that the progress of the principal Inductive
Sciences may take place. This appears in the case of Astronomy,
in which Science, both in ancient and in modern
times, each advance of the theory has depended upon
the 13 previous
solution of problems in pure mathematics. It appears
also inversely in the Science of the Tides, in which, at present,
we cannot advance in the theory, because we cannot
solve the requisite problems in the Integral Calculus. (ii. 14.)
XLV.
The Idea of Cause, modified into the conceptions of
mechanical cause, or Force, and resistance to force, or Matter,
is the foundation of the Mechanical Sciences; that is, Mechanics,
(including Statics and Dynamics,) Hydrostatics,
and Physical Astronomy. (iii. 1.)
XLVI.
The Idea of Cause is not derived from experience; for in
judging of occurrences which we contemplate, we consider
them as being, universally and necessarily, Causes and Effects,
which a finite experience could not authorize us to do.
The Axiom, that every event must have a cause, is true
independently of experience, and beyond the limits of
experience. (iii. 2.)
XLVII.
The Idea of Cause is expressed for purposes of science by
these three Axioms:—Every Event must have a Cause:—Causes
are measured by their Effects:—Reaction is equal
and opposite to Action. (iii. 4.)
XLVIII.
The Conception of Force involves the Idea of Cause, as
applied to the motion and rest of bodies. The conception of
force is suggested by muscular action exerted: the conception
of matter arises from muscular action resisted. We necessarily
ascribe to all bodies solidity and inertia, since we
conceive Matter as that which cannot be compressed or moved
without resistance. (iii. 5.)
XLIX.
Mechanical Science depends on the Conception of Force;
and is divided into Statics, the doctrine of Force preventing
14 motion, and
Dynamics, the doctrine of Force producing
motion. (iii. 6.)
L.
The Science of Statics depends upon the Axiom, that Action and
Reaction are equal, which in Statics assumes this
form:—When two equal weights are supported on the
middle point between them, the pressure on the fulcrum
is equal to the sum of the weights. (iii. 6.)
LI.
The Science of Hydrostatics depends upon the Fundamental
Principle that fluids press equally in all directions.
This principle necessarily results from the conception of a
Fluid, as a body of which the parts are perfectly moveable
in all directions. For since the Fluid is a body, it can
transmit pressure; and the transmitted pressure is equal to
the original pressure, in virtue of the Axiom that Reaction
is equal to Action. That the Fundamental Principle is not
derived from experience, is plain both from its evidence and
from its history. (iii. 6.)
LII.
The Science of Dynamics depends upon the three Axioms
above stated respecting Cause. The First Axiom,—that every
change must have a Cause,—gives rise to the First Law of
Motion,—that a body not acted upon by a force will move
with a uniform velocity in a straight line. The Second
Axiom,—that Causes are measured by their Effects,—gives
rise to the Second Law of Motion,—that when a force acts
upon a body in motion, the effect of the force is compounded
with the previously existing motion. The Third
Axiom,—that Reaction is equal and opposite to Action,—gives
rise to the Third Law of Motion, which is expressed
in the same terms as the Axiom; Action and Reaction
being understood to signify momentum gained and lost.
(iii. 7.) 15
LIII.
The above Laws of Motion, historically speaking, were
established by means of experiment: but since they have been
discovered and reduced to their simplest form, they have been
considered by many philosophers as self-evident. This result
is principally due to the introduction and establishment of
terms and definitions, which enable us to express the Laws in
a very simple manner. (iii. 7.)
LIV.
In the establishment of the Laws of Motion, it happened,
in several instances, that Principles were assumed as self-evident
which do not now appear evident, but which have
since been demonstrated from the simplest and most evident
principles. Thus it was assumed that a perpetual motion
is impossible;—that the velocities of bodies acquired by
falling down planes or curves of the same vertical height
are equal;—that the actual descent of the center of gravity
is equal to its potential ascent. But we are not hence
to suppose that these assumptions were made without ground:
for since they really follow from the laws of motion, they
were probably, in the minds of the discoverers, the results of
undeveloped demonstrations which their sagacity led them to
divine. (iii. 7.)
LV.
It is a Paradox that Experience should lead us to truths
confessedly universal, and apparently necessary, such as the
Laws of Motion are. The Solution of this paradox is,
that these laws are interpretations of the Axioms of Causation.
The axioms are universally and necessarily true, but
the right interpretation of the terms which they involve, is
learnt by experience. Our Idea of Cause supplies the Form,
Experience, the Matter, of these Laws. (iii. 8.)
LVI.
Primary Qualities of Bodies are those which we can conceive
as directly perceived; Secondary Qualities are
those 16
which we conceive as perceived by means of a
Medium. (iv. 1.)
LVII.
We necessarily perceive bodies as without us; the Idea of
Externality is one of the conditions of perception. (iv. 1.)
LVIII.
We necessarily assume a Medium for the perceptions of
Light, Colour, Sound, Heat, Odours, Tastes; and this Medium must convey
impressions by means of its mechanical attributes. (iv. 1.)
LIX.
Secondary Qualities are not extended but intensive:
their effects are not augmented by addition of parts, but by
increased operation of the medium. Hence they are not
measured directly, but by scales; not by units, but by
degrees. (iv. 4.)
LX.
In the Scales of Secondary Qualities, it is a condition
(in order that the scale may be complete,) that every example
of the quality must either agree with one of the degrees of
the Scale, or lie between two contiguous degrees. (iv. 4.)
LXI.
We perceive by means of a medium and by means of
impressions on the nerves: but we do not (by our senses) perceive
either the medium or the impressions on the nerves. (iv. 1.)
LXII.
The Prerogatives of the Sight are, that by this sense we
necessarily and immediately apprehend the position of its
objects: and that from visible circumstances, we infer the
distance of objects from us, so readily that we seem to perceive
and not to infer. (iv. 2.)
17
LXIII.
The Prerogatives of the Hearing are, that by this sense
we perceive relations perfectly precise and definite between
two notes, namely, Musical Intervals (as an Octave, a
Fifth); and that when two notes are perceived together, they
are comprehended as distinct, (a Chord,) and as having a
certain relation, (Concord or Discord.) (iv. 2.)
LXIV.
The Sight cannot decompose a compound colour into
simple colours, or distinguish a compound from a simple
colour. The Hearing cannot directly perceive the place, still
less the distance, of its objects: we infer these obscurely and
vaguely from audible circumstances. (iv. 2.)
LXV.
The First Paradox of Vision is, that we see objects upright,
though the images on the retina are inverted. The
solution is, that we do not see the image on the retina at all,
we only see by means of it. (iv. 2.)
LXVI.
The Second Paradox of Vision is, that we see objects
single, though there are two images on the retinas, one in
each eye. The explanation is, that it is a Law of Vision
that we see (small or distant) objects single, when their images
fall on corresponding points of the two retinas. (iv. 2.)
LXVII.
The law of single vision for near objects is this:—When
the two images in the two eyes are situated, part for part,
nearly but not exactly, upon corresponding points, the object
is apprehended as single and solid if the two objects are such
as would be produced by a single solid object seen by the eyes
separately. (iv. 2.)
LXVIII.
The ultimate object of each of the Secondary Mechanical
Sciences is, to determine the nature and laws of the
processes 18
by which the impression of the Secondary Quality treated of
is conveyed: but before we discover the cause, it may be
necessary to determine the laws of the phenomena; and for
this purpose a Measure or Scale of each quality is necessary.
(iv. 4.)
LXIX.
Secondary qualities are measured by means of such effects
as can be estimated in number or space. (iv. 4.)
LXX.
The Measure of Sounds, as high or low, is the Musical
Scale, or Harmonic Canon. (iv. 4.)
LXXI.
The Measures of Pure Colours are the Prismatic Scale;
the same, including Fraunhofer’s Lines; and Newton’s
Scale of Colours. The principal Scales of Impure Colours
are Werner’s Nomenclature of Colours, and Merimée’s
Nomenclature of Colours. (iv. 4.)
LXXII.
The Idea of Polarity involves the conception of contrary
properties in contrary directions:—the properties being, for
example, attraction and repulsion, darkness and light, synthesis and
analysis; and the contrary directions being those
which are directly opposite, or, in some cases, those which are
at right angles. (v. 1.)
LXXIII. (Doubtful.)
Coexistent polarities are fundamentally identical. (v. 2.)
LXXIV.
The Idea of Chemical Affinity, as implied in Elementary
Composition, involves peculiar conceptions. It is not properly
expressed by assuming the qualities of bodies to resemble
those of the elements, or to depend on the figure of the elements,
or on their attractions. (vi. 1.)
19
LXXV.
Attractions take place between bodies, Affinities between
the particles of a body. The former may be compared to the
alliances of states, the latter to the ties of family. (vi. 2.)
LXXVI.
The governing principles of Chemical Affinity are, that it
is elective; that it is definite; that it determines the properties
of the compound; and that analysis is possible. (vi. 2.)
LXXVII.
We have an idea of Substance: and an axiom involved
in this Idea is, that the weight of a body is the sum of the
weights of all its elements. (vi. 3.)
LXXVIII.
Hence Imponderable Fluids are not to be admitted as
chemical elements. (vi. 4.)
LXXIX.
The Doctrine of Atoms is admissible as a mode of expressing
and calculating laws of nature; but is not proved by any
fact, chemical or physical, as a philosophical truth. (vi. 5.)
LXXX.
We have an Idea of Symmetry; and an axiom involved
in this Idea is, that in a symmetrical natural body, if there
be a tendency to modify any member in any manner, there is
a tendency to modify all the corresponding members in the
same manner. (vii. 1.)
LXXXI.
All hypotheses respecting the manner in which the elements
of inorganic bodies are arranged in space, must be constructed
with regard to the general facts of crystallization.
(vii. 3.) 20
LXXXII.
When we consider any object as One, we give unity to it
by an act of thought. The condition which determines what
this unity shall include, and what it shall exclude, is this;—that
assertions concerning the one thing shall be possible. (viii. 1.)
LXXXIII.
We collect individuals into Kinds by applying to them
the Idea of Likeness. Kinds of things are not determined
by definitions, but by this condition:—that general assertions
concerning such kinds of things shall be possible. (viii. 1.)
LXXXIV.
The Names of kinds of things are governed by their use;
and that may be a right name in one use which is not so in
another. A whale is not a fish in natural history, but it is
a fish in commerce and law. (viii. 1.)
LXXXV.
We take for granted that each kind of things has a special
character which may be expressed by a Definition. The
ground of our assumption is this;—that reasoning must be
possible. (viii. 1.)
LXXXVI.
The “Five Words,” Genus, Species, Difference, Property, Accident,
were used by the Aristotelians, in order to
express the subordination of Kinds, and to describe the nature
of Definitions and Propositions. In modern times, these
technical expressions have been more referred to by Natural
Historians than by Metaphysicians. (viii. 1.)
LXXXVII.
The construction of a Classificatory Science includes
Terminology, the formation of a descriptive language;—Diataxis,
the Plan of the System of Classification, called
21
also the Systematick;—Diagnosis, the Scheme of the Characters
by which the different Classes are known, called also
the Characteristick. Physiography is the knowledge which
the System is employed to convey. Diataxis includes Nomenclature.
(viii. 2.)
LXXXVIII.
Terminology must be conventional, precise, constant;
copious in words, and minute in distinctions, according to
the needs of the science. The student must understand the
terms, directly according to the convention, not through the
medium of explanation or comparison. (viii. 2.)
LXXXIX.
The Diataxis, or Plan of the System, may aim at a
Natural or at an Artificial System. But no classes can be
absolutely artificial, for if they were, no assertions could be
made concerning them. (viii. 2.)
XC.
An Artificial System is one in which the smaller groups
(the Genera) are natural; and in which the wider divisions
(Classes, Orders) are constructed by the peremptory application
of selected Characters; (selected, however, so as not to
break up the smaller groups.) (viii. 2.)
XCI.
A Natural System is one which attempts to make all the
divisions natural, the widest as well as the narrowest; and
therefore applies no characters peremptorily. (viii. 2.)
XCII.
Natural Groups are best described, not by any Definition
which marks their boundaries, but by a Type which marks
their center. The Type of any natural group is an example
which possesses in a marked degree all the leading characters
of the class. (viii. 2.)
22
XCIII.
A Natural Group is steadily fixed, though not precisely
limited; it is given in position, though not circumscribed; it
is determined, not by a boundary without, but by a central
point within;—not by what it strictly excludes, but by what
it eminently includes;—by a Type, not by a Definition.
(viii. 2.)
XCIV.
The prevalence of Mathematics as an element of education
has made us think Definition the philosophical mode
of fixing the meaning of a word: if (Scientific) Natural
History were introduced into education, men might become
familiar with the fixation of the signification of words by
Types; and this process agrees more nearly with the common
processes by which words acquire their significations.
(viii. 2.)
XCV.
The attempts at Natural Classification are of three sorts;
according as they are made by the process of blind trial, of
general comparison, or of subordination of characters.
The process of Blind Trial professes to make its classes by
attention to all the characters, but without proceeding methodically.
The process of General Comparison professes to
enumerate all the characters, and forms its classes by the
majority. Neither of these methods can really be carried
into effect. The method of Subordination of Characters
considers some characters as more important than others;
and this method gives more consistent results than the others.
This method, however, does not depend upon the Idea of
Likeness only, but introduces the Idea of Organization or
Function. (viii. 2.)
XCVI.
A Species is a collection of individuals, which are descended
from a common stock, or which resemble such a
collection as much as these resemble each other: the resemblance
being opposed to a definite difference.
(viii. 2.) 23
XCVII.
A Genus is a collection of species which resemble each
other more than they resemble other species: the resemblance
being opposed to a definite difference. (viii. 2.)
XCVIII.
The Nomenclature of a Classificatory Science is the collection
of the names of the Species, Genera, and other divisions.
The binary nomenclature, which denotes a species by
the generic and specific name, is now commonly adopted in
Natural History. (viii. 2.)
XCIX.
The Diagnosis, or Scheme of the Characters, comes, in
the order of philosophy, after the Classification. The characters
do not make the classes, they only enable us to recognize them.
The Diagnosis is an Artificial Key to a Natural
System. (viii. 2.)
C.
The basis of all Natural Systems of Classification is the
Idea of Natural Affinity. The Principle which this Idea
involves is this:—Natural arrangements, obtained from
different sets of characters, must coincide with each other.
(viii. 4.)
CI.
In order to obtain a Science of Biology, we must analyse
the Idea of Life. It has been proved by the biological speculations
of past time, that Organic Life cannot rightly be
solved into Mechanical or Chemical Forces, or the operation
of a Vital Fluid, or of a Soul. (ix. 2.)
CII.
Life is a System of Vital Forces; and the conception of
such Forces involves a peculiar Fundamental Idea.
(ix. 3.) 24
CIII.
Mechanical, chemical, and vital Forces form an ascending
progression, each including the preceding. Chemical Affinity
includes in its nature Mechanical Force, and may often be
practically resolved into Mechanical Force. (Thus the ingredients
of gunpowder, liberated from their chemical union,
exert great mechanical Force: a galvanic battery acting by
chemical process does the like.) Vital Forces include in
their nature both chemical Affinities and mechanical Forces:
for Vital Powers produce both chemical changes, (as digestion,)
and motions which imply considerable mechanical
force, (as the motion of the sap and of the blood.) (ix. 4.)
CIV.
In voluntary motions, Sensations produce Actions, and
the connexion is made by means of Ideas: in reflected
motions, the connexion neither seems to be nor is made by
means of Ideas: in instinctive motions, the connexion is
such as requires Ideas, but we cannot believe the Ideas to
exist. (ix. 5.)
CV.
The Assumption of a Final Cause in the structure of each
part of animals and plants is as inevitable as the assumption
of an Efficient Cause for every event. The maxim that in
organized bodies nothing is in vain, is as necessarily true as
the maxim that nothing happens by chance. (ix. 6.)
CVI.
The Idea of living beings as subject to disease includes a
recognition of a Final Cause in organization; for disease is
a state in which the vital forces do not attain their proper
ends. (ix. 7.)
CVII.
The Palætiological Sciences depend upon the Idea of
Cause: but the leading conception which they involve is that
of historical cause, not mechanical cause.
(x. 1.) 25
CVIII.
Each Palætiological Science, when complete, must possess
three members: the Phenomenology, the Ætiology, and the
Theory. (x. 2.)
CIX.
There are, in the Palætiological Sciences, two antagonist
doctrines: Catastrophes and Uniformity. The doctrine
of a uniform course of nature is tenable only when we
extend the nation of Uniformity so far that it shall include Catastrophes.
(x. 3.)
CX.
The Catastrophist constructs Theories, the Uniformitarian
demolishes them. The former adduces evidence of an Origin,
the latter explains the evidence away. The Catastrophist’s
dogmatism is undermined by the Uniformitarian’s skeptical
hypotheses. But when these hypotheses are asserted dogmatically
they cease to be consistent with the doctrine of Uniformity. (x. 3.)
CXI.
In each of the Palætiological Sciences, we can ascend to
remote periods by a chain of causes, but in none can we
ascend to a beginning of the chain. (x. 3.)
CXII.
Since the Palætiological sciences deal with the conceptions
of historical cause, History, including Tradition, is
an important source of materials for such sciences. (x. 4.)
CXIII.
The history and tradition which present to us the providential
course of the world form a Sacred Narrative; and
in reconciling the Sacred Narrative with the results of science,
arise inevitable difficulties which disturb the minds of
those who reverence the Sacred Narrative.
(x. 4.) 26
CXIV.
The disturbance of reverent minds, arising from scientific
views, ceases when such views become familiar, the Sacred
Narrative being then interpreted anew in accordance with
such views. (x. 4.)
CXV.
A new interpretation of the Sacred Narrative, made for
the purpose of reconciling it with doctrines of science, should
not be insisted on till such doctrines are clearly proved; and
when they are so proved, should be frankly accepted, in the
confidence that a reverence for the Sacred Narrative is consistent
with a reverence for the Truth. (x. 4.)
CXVI.
In contemplating the series of causes and effects which
constitutes the world, we necessarily assume a First Cause
of the whole series. (x. 5.)
CXVII.
The Palætiological Sciences point backwards with lines
which are broken, but which all converge to the same invisible
point: and this point is the Origin of the Moral and
Spiritual, as well as of the Natural World. (x. 5.)
</div></body></text></TEI>