<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="16">CHAPTER XVI.
PHENOMENA OF SPRINGS.
Origin of Springs—Artesian wells—Borings at Paris—Distinct causes by which
mineral and thermal waters may be raised to the surface—Their connection with
volcanic agency—Calcareous springs—Travertin of the Elsa—Baths of San
Vignone and of San Filippo, near Radicofani—Spheroidal structure in travertin—Lake
of the Solfatara, near Rome—Travertin at Cascade of Tivoli—Gypseous,
siliceous, and ferruginous springs—Brine springs—Carbonated springs—Disintegration
of granite in Auvergne—Petroleum springs—Pitch lake of Trinidad.
Origin of springs.—The action of running water on the surface of the
land having been considered, we may next turn our attention to what
may be termed "the subterranean drainage," or the phenomena of
springs. Every one is familiar with the fact, that certain porous soils,
such as loose sand and gravel, absorb water with rapidity, and that the
ground composed of them soon dries up after heavy showers. If a well
be sunk in such soils, we often penetrate to considerable depths before
we meet with water; but this is usually found on our approaching the
lower parts of the formation, where it rests on some impervious bed; for
here the water, unable to make its way downwards in a direct line,
accumulates as in a reservoir, and is ready to ooze out into any opening
which may be made, in the same manner as we see the salt water flow
into, and fill, any hollow which we dig in the sands of the shore at low tide.
233
The facility with which water can percolate loose and gravelly soils
is clearly illustrated by the effect of the tides in the Thames between
Richmond and London. The river, in this part of its course, flows
through a bed of gravel overlying clay, and the porous superstratum
is alternately saturated by the water of the Thames as the tide rises,
and then drained again to the distance of several hundred feet from the
banks when the tide falls, so that the wells in this tract regularly ebb
and flow.
If the transmission of water through a porous medium be so rapid,
we cannot be surprised that springs should be thrown out on the side
of a hill, where the upper set of strata consist of chalk, sand, or other
permeable substances, while the subjacent are composed of clay or
other retentive soils. The only difficulty, indeed, is to explain why the
water does not ooze out everywhere along the line of junction of the
two formations, so as to form one continuous land-soak, instead of a
few springs only, and these far distant from each other. The principal
cause of this concentration of the waters at a few points is, first, the
frequency of rents and fissures, which act as natural drains; secondly,
the existence of inequalities in the upper surface of the impermeable
stratum, which lead the water, as valleys do on the external surface of
a country, into certain low levels and channels.
That the generality of springs owe their supply to the atmosphere is
evident from this, that they become languid, or entirely cease to flow,
after long droughts, and are again replenished after a continuance of
rain. Many of them are probably indebted for the constancy and uniformity
of their volume to the great extent of the subterranean reservoirs
with which they communicate, and the time required for these to
empty themselves by percolation. Such a gradual and regulated discharge
is exhibited, though in a less perfect degree, in every great lake
which is not sensibly affected in its level by sudden showers, but only
slightly raised; so that its channel of efflux, instead of being swollen
suddenly like the bed of a torrent, is enabled to carry off the surplus
water gradually.
Much light has been thrown, of late years, on the theory of springs,
by the boring of what are called by the French "Artesian wells," because
the method has long been known and practised in Artois; and it
is now demonstrated that there are sheets, and in some places currents
of fresh water, at various depths in the earth. The instrument employed
in excavating these wells is a large augur, and the cavity bored
is usually from three to four inches in diameter. If a hard rock is met
with, it is first triturated by an iron rod, and the materials being thus
reduced to small fragments or powder, are readily extracted. To hinder
the sides of the well from falling in, as also to prevent the spreading of
the ascending water in the surrounding soil, a jointed pipe is introduced,
formed of wood in Artois, but in other countries more commonly of
metal. It frequently happens that, after passing through hundreds of
feet of retentive soils, a water-bearing stratum is at length pierced,
234
when the fluid immediately ascends to the surface, and flows over.
The first rush of the water up the tube is often violent, so that for a time
the water plays like a fountain, and then, sinking, continues to flow over
tranquilly, or sometimes remains stationary at a certain depth below the
orifice of the well. This spouting of the water in the first instance is
probably owing to the disengagement of air and carbonic acid gas, for
both of these have been seen to bubble up with the water.304
At Sheerness, at the mouth of the Thames, a well was bored on a
low tongue of land near the sea, through 300 feet of the blue clay of
London, below which a bed of sand and pebbles was entered, belonging,
doubtless, to the plastic clay formation; when this stratum was pierced,
the water burst up with impetuosity, and filled the well. By another
perforation at the same place, the water was found at the depth of 328
feet below the surface clay; it first rose rapidly to the height of 189 feet,
and then, in the course of a few hours, ascended to an elevation of
eight feet above the level of the ground. In 1824 a well was dug at
Fulham, near the Thames, at the Bishop of London's, to the depth of
317 feet, which, after traversing the tertiary strata, was continued
through 67 feet of chalk. The water immediately rose to the surface,
and the discharge was about 50 gallons per minute. In the garden of
the Horticultural Society at Chiswick, the borings passed through 19
feet of gravel, 242½ feet of clay and loam, and 67½ feet of chalk, and
the water then rose to the surface from a depth of 329 feet.305 At the
Duke of Northumberland's, above Chiswick, the borings were carried to
the extraordinary depth of 620 feet, so as to enter the chalk, when a
considerable volume of water was obtained, which rose four feet above
the surface of the ground. In a well of Mr. Brooks, at Hammersmith,
the rush of water from a depth of 360 feet was so great, as to inundate
several buildings and do considerable damage; and at Tooting, a sufficient
stream was obtained to turn a wheel, and raise the water to the
upper stories of the houses.306 In 1838, the total supply obtained from
the chalk near London was estimated at six million gallons a day, and,
in 1851, at nearly double that amount, the increase being accompanied
by an average fall of no less than two feet a year in the level to which
the water rose. The water stood commonly, in 1822, at high-water
mark, and had sunk in 1851 to 45, and in some wells to 65 feet below
high-water mark.307 This fact shows the limited capacity of the subterranean
reservoir. In the last of three wells bored through the chalk
at Tours, to the depth of several hundred feet, the water rose 32 feet
above the level of the soil, and the discharge amounted to 300 cubic
yards of water every twenty-four hours.308
By way of experiment, the sinking of a well was commenced at Paris
235
in 1834, which had reached, in November, 1839, a depth of more than
1600 English feet, and yet no water ascended to the surface. The
government were persuaded by M. Arago to persevere, if necessary, to
the depth of more than 2000 feet; but when they had descended
above 1800 English feet below the surface, the water rose through
the tube (which was about ten inches in diameter), so as to discharge
half a million of gallons of limpid water every twenty-four hours. The
temperature of the water increased at the rate of 1·8° F. for every 101
English feet, as they went down, the result agreeing very closely with
the anticipations of the scientific advisers of this most spirited undertaking.
Mr. Briggs, the British consul in Egypt, obtained water between
Cairo and Suez, in a calcareous sand, at the depth of thirty feet; but
it did not rise in the well.309 But other borings in the same desert, of
variable depth, between 50 and 300 feet, and which passed through
alternations of sand, clay, and siliceous rock, yielded water at the
surface.310
The rise and overflow of the water in Artesian wells is generally
referred, and apparently with reason, to the same principle as the play
of an artificial fountain. Let the porous stratum or set of strata, a a,
rest on the impermeable rock d, and be covered by another mass of an
impermeable nature. The whole mass a a may easily, in such a position,
become saturated with water, which may descend from its higher
and exposed parts—a hilly region to which clouds are attracted, and
where rain falls in abundance. Suppose that at some point, as at b,
an opening be made, which gives a free passage upwards to the waters
confined in a a, at so low a level that they are subjected to the pressure
of a considerable column of water collected in the more elevated
portion of the same stratum. The water will then rush out, just as the
liquid from a large barrel which is tapped, and it will rise to a height
corresponding to the level of its point of departure, or, rather, to a
height which balances the pressure previously exerted by the confined
waters against the roof and sides of the stratum or reservoir a a. In
like manner, if there happen to be a natural fissure c, a spring will be
produced at the surface on precisely the same principle.
Fig. 20.
Among the causes of the failure of Artesian wells, we may mention
those numerous rents and faults which abound in some rocks, and the
236
deep ravines and valleys by which many countries are traversed; for,
when these natural lines of drainage exist, there remains a small quantity
only of water to escape by artificial issues. We are also liable to
be baffled by the great thickness either of porous or impervious strata,
or by the dip of the beds, which may carry off the waters from the adjoining
high lands to some trough in an opposite direction, as when the
borings are made at the foot of an escarpment where the strata incline
inwards, or in a direction opposite to the face of the cliffs.
The mere distance of hills or mountains need not discourage us from
making trials; for the waters which fall on these higher lands readily
penetrate to great depths through highly inclined or vertical strata, or
through the fissures of shattered rocks, and after flowing for a great
distance, must often reascend and be brought up again by other fissures,
so as to approach the surface in the lower country. Here they may
be concealed beneath the covering of undisturbed horizontal beds, which
it may be necessary to pierce in order to reach them. It should be
remembered, that the course of waters flowing under ground bears
but a remote resemblance to that of rivers on the surface, there being,
in the one case, a constant descent from a higher to a lower level from
the source of the stream to the sea; whereas, in the other, the water
may at one time sink far below the level of the ocean, and afterwards
rise again high above it.
Among other curious facts ascertained by aid of the borer, it is
proved that in strata of different ages and compositions, there are often
open passages by which the subterranean waters circulate. Thus, at
St. Ouen, in France, five distinct sheets of water were intersected in a
well, and from each of these a supply obtained. In the third waterbearing
stratum, at the depth of 150 feet, a cavity was found in which
the borer fell suddenly about a foot, and thence the water ascended in
great volume.311 The same falling of the instrument, as in a hollow
space, has been remarked in England and other countries. At Tours,
in 1830, a well was perforated quite through the chalk, when the
water suddenly brought up, from a depth of 364 feet, a great quantity
of fine sand, with much vegetable matter and shells. Branches of a
thorn several inches long, much blackened by their stay in the water,
were recognized, as also the stems of marsh plants, and some of their
roots, which were still white, together with the seeds of the same in a
state of preservation, which showed that they had not remained more
than three or four months in the water. Among the seeds were those
of the marsh plant Galium uliginosum; and among the shells, a freshwater
species (Planorbis marginatus), and some land species, as Helix
rotundata, and H. striata. M. Dujardin, who, with others, observed
this phenomenon, supposes that the waters had flowed from some valleys
of Auvergne or the Vivarais since the preceding autumn.312
An analogous phenomenon is recorded at Reimke, near Bochum in
237
Westphalia, where the water of an Artesian well brought up, from a
depth of 156 feet, several small fish, three or four inches long, the
nearest streams in the country being at a distance of some leagues.313
In both cases it is evident that water had penetrated to great
depths, not simply by filtering through a porous mass, for then it
would have left behind the shells, fish, and fragments of plants, but by
flowing through some open channels in the earth. Such examples
may suggest the idea that the leaky beds of rivers are often the feeders
of springs.
MINERAL AND THERMAL SPRINGS.
Almost all springs, even those which we consider the purest, are
impregnated with some foreign ingredients, which, being in a state of
chemical solution, are so intimately blended with the water as not to
affect its clearness, while they render it, in general, more agreeable to
our taste, and more nutritious than simple rain-water. But the springs
called mineral contain an unusual abundance of earthy matter in solution,
and the substances with which they are impregnated correspond remarkably
with those evolved in a gaseous form by volcanoes. Many of these
springs are thermal, i. e., their temperature is above the mean temperature
of the place, and they rise up through all kinds of rock; as, for
example, through granite, gneiss, limestone, or lava, but are most frequent
in volcanic regions, or where violent earthquakes have occurred
at eras comparatively modern.
The water given out by hot springs is generally more voluminous and
less variable in quantity at different seasons than that proceeding from
any others. In many volcanic regions, jets of steam, called by the
Italians "stufas," issue from fissures, at a temperature high above the
boiling point, as in the neighborhood of Naples, and in the Lipari Isles,
and are disengaged unceasingly for ages. Now, if such columns of
steam, which are often mixed with other gases, should be condensed
before reaching the surface by coming in contact with strata filled with
cold water, they may give rise to thermal and mineral springs of every
degree of temperature. It is, indeed, by this means only, and not by
hydrostatic pressure, that we can account for the rise of such bodies of
water from great depths; nor can we hesitate to admit the adequacy of
the cause, if we suppose the expansion of the same elastic fluids to be
sufficient to raise columns of lava to the lofty summits of volcanic mountains.
Several gases, the carbonic acid in particular, are disengaged in
a free state from the soil in many districts, especially in the regions of
active or extinct volcanoes; and the same are found more or less intimately
combined with the waters of all mineral springs, both cold and
thermal. Dr. Daubeny and other writers have remarked, not only that
these springs are most abundant in volcanic regions, but that when
remote from them, their site usually coincides with the position of some
238
great derangement in the strata; a fault, for example, or great fissure,
indicating that a channel of communication has been opened with the
interior of the earth at some former period of local convulsion. It is
also ascertained that at great heights in the Pyrenees and Himalaya
mountains hot springs burst out from granitic rocks, and they are abundant
in the Alps also, these chains having all been disturbed and dislocated
at times comparatively modern, as can be shown by independent
geological evidence.
The small area of volcanic regions may appear, at first view, to present
an objection to these views, but not so when we include earthquakes
among the effects of igneous agency. A large proportion of
the land hitherto explored by geologists can be shown to have been
rent or shaken by subterranean movements since the oldest tertiary
strata were formed. It will also be seen, in the sequel, that new
springs have burst out, and others have had the volume of their waters
augmented, and their temperature suddenly raised after earthquakes, so
that the description of these springs might almost with equal propriety
have been given under the head of "igneous causes," as they are agents
of a mixed nature, being at once igneous and aqueous.
But how, it will be asked, can the regions of volcanic heat send forth
such inexhaustible supplies of water? The difficulty of solving this
problem would, in truth, be insurmountable, if we believed that all the
atmospheric waters found their way into the basin of the ocean; but in
boring near the shore we often meet with streams of fresh water at the
depth of several hundred feet below the sea level; and these probably
descend, in many cases, far beneath the bottom of the sea, when not
artificially intercepted in their course. Yet, how much greater may be
the quantity of salt water which sinks beneath the floor of the ocean,
through the porous strata of which it is often composed, or through
fissures rent in it by earthquakes. After penetrating to a considerable
depth, this water may encounter a heat of sufficient intensity to convert
it into vapor, even under the high pressure to which it would then be
subjected. This heat would probably be nearest the surface in volcanic
countries, and farthest from it in those districts which have been longest
free from eruptions or earthquakes.
It would follow from the views above explained, that there must be
a twofold circulation of terrestrial waters; one caused by solar heat,
and the other by heat generated in the interior of our planet. We
know that the land would be unfit for vegetation, if deprived of the
waters raised into the atmosphere by the sun; but it is also true that
mineral springs are powerful instruments in rendering the surface subservient
to the support of animal and vegetable life. Their heat is said
to promote the development of the aquatic tribes in many parts of the
ocean, and the substances which they carry up from the bowels of the
earth to the habitable surface, are of a nature and in a form which
adapts them peculiarly for the nutrition of animals and plants.
As these springs derive their chief importance to the geologist from
239
the quantity and quality of the earthy materials which, like volcanoes,
they convey from below upwards, they may properly be considered in
reference to the ingredients which they hold in solution. These consist
of a great variety of substances; but chiefly salts with bases of lime,
magnesia, alumine, and iron, combined with carbonic, sulphuric, and muriatic
acids. Muriate of soda, silica, and free carbonic acid are frequently
present; also springs of petroleum, or liquid bitumen, and of naphtha.
Calcareous springs.—Our first attention is naturally directed to springs
which are highly charged with calcareous matter, for these produce a
variety of phenomena of much interest in geology. It is known that
rain-water collecting carbonic acid from the atmosphere has the property
of dissolving the calcareous rocks over which it flows, and thus, in the
smallest ponds and rivulets, matter is often supplied for the earthy secretions
of testacea, and for the growth of certain plants on which they
feed. But many springs hold so much carbonic acid in solution, that
they are enabled to dissolve a much larger quantity of calcareous matter
than rain-water; and when the acid is dissipated in the atmosphere, the
mineral ingredients are thrown down, in the form of porous tufa or of
more compact travertin.314
Auvergne.—Calcareous springs, although most abundant in limestone
districts, are by no means confined to them, but flow out indiscriminately
from all rock formations. In central France, a district where the primary
rocks are unusually destitute of limestone, springs copiously
charged with carbonate of lime rise up through the granite and gneiss.
Some of these are thermal, and probably derive their origin from the
deep source of volcanic heat, once so active in that region. One of these
springs, at the northern base of the hill upon which Claremont is built,
issues from volcanic peperino, which rests on granite. It has formed,
by its incrustations, an elevated mound of travertin, or white concretionary
limestone, 240 feet in length, and, at its termination, sixteen feet
high and twelve wide. Another encrusting spring in the same department,
situated at Chaluzet, near Pont Gibaud, rises in a gneiss country,
at the foot of a regular volcanic cone, at least twenty miles from any
calcareous rock. Some masses of tufaceous deposit, produced by this
spring, have an oolitic texture.
Valley of the Elsa.—If we pass from the volcanic district of France
to that which skirts the Apennines in the Italian peninsula, we meet
with innumerable springs which have precipitated so much calcareous
matter, that the whole ground in some parts of Tuscany is coated over
with tufa and travertin, and sounds hollow beneath the foot.
In other places in the same country, compact rocks are seen descending
the slanting sides of hills, very much in the manner of lava currents,
except that they are of a white color and terminate abruptly when they
reach the course of a river. These consist of a calcareous precipitate
from springs, some of which are still flowing, while others have disappeared
240
or changed their position. Such masses are frequent on the
slope of the hills which bound the valley of the Elsa, one of the tributaries
of the Arno, which flows near Colle, through a valley several hundred
feet deep, shaped out of a lacustrine formation, containing fossil
shells of existing species. I observed here that the travertin was unconformable
to the lacustrine beds, its inclination according with the
slope of the sides of the valley. One of the finest examples which I
saw was at the Molino delle Caldane, near Colle. The Senà, and several
other small rivulets which feed the Elsa, have the property of encrusting
wood and herbs with calcareous stone. In the bed of the Elsa itself,
aquatic plants, such as Charæ, which absorb large quantities of carbonate
of lime, are very abundant.
Fig. 21.
Section of travertin, San Vignone.
Baths of San Vignone.—Those persons who have merely seen the
action of petrifying waters in England, will not easily form an adequate
conception of the scale on which the same process is exhibited in those
regions which lie nearer to the active centres of volcanic disturbance.
One of the most striking examples of the rapid precipitation of carbonate
of lime from thermal waters, occurs in the hill of San Vignone in Tuscany,
at a short distance from Radicofani, and only a few hundred yards
from the high road between Sienna and Rome. The spring issues from
near the summit of a rocky hill, about 100 feet in height. The top of
the hill stretches in a gently inclined platform to the foot of Mount
Amiata, a lofty eminence, which consists in great part of volcanic products.
The fundamental rock, from which the spring issues, is a black
slate, with serpentine (b b, fig. 21), belonging to the older Apennine formation.
The water is hot, has a strong taste, and, when not in very
small quantity, is of a bright green color. So rapid is the deposition
near the source, that in the bottom of a conduit-pipe for carrying off
the water to the baths, and which is inclined at an angle of 30°, half a
foot of solid travertin is formed every year. A more compact rock is
produced where the water flows slowly; and the precipitation in winter,
when there is least evaporation, is said to be more solid, but less in
quantity by one-fourth, than in summer. The rock is generally white;
some parts of it are compact, and ring to the hammer; others are cellular,
241
and with such cavities as are seen in the carious part of bone or
the siliceous millstone of the Paris basin. A portion of it also below
the village of San Vignone consists of incrustations of long vegetable
tubes, and may be called tufa. Sometimes the travertin assumes precisely
the botryoidal and mammillary forms, common to similar deposits
in Auvergne, of a much older date; and, like them, it often scales off
in thin, slightly undulating layers.
A large mass of travertin (c, fig. 21) descends the hill from the
point where the spring issues, and reaches to the distance of about half
a mile east of San Vignone. The beds take the slope of the hill at
about an angle of 6°, and the planes of stratification are perfectly parallel.
One stratum, composed of many layers, is of a compact nature,
and fifteen feet thick; it serves as an excellent building stone, and a
mass of fifteen feet in length was, in 1828, cut out for the new bridge
over the Orcia. Another branch of it (a, fig. 21) descends to the west,
for 250 feet in length, of varying thickness, but sometimes 200 feet
deep; it is then cut off by the small river Orcia, as some glaciers in
Switzerland descend into a valley till their progress is suddenly arrested
by a transverse stream of water.
The abrupt termination of the mass of rock at the river, where its
thickness is undiminished, clearly shows that it would proceed much
farther if not arrested by the stream, over which it impends slightly.
But it cannot encroach upon the channel of the Orcia, being constantly
undermined, so that its solid fragments are seen strewed amongst the
alluvial gravel. However enormous, therefore, the mass of solid rock
may appear which has been given out by this single spring, we may
feel assured that it is insignificant in volume when compared to that
which has been carried to the sea since the time when it began to flow.
What may have been the length of that period of time we have no
data for conjecturing. In quarrying the travertin, Roman tiles have
been sometimes found at the depth of five or six feet.
Baths of San Filippo.—On another hill, not many miles from that
last mentioned, and also connected with Mount Amiata, the summit of
which is about three miles distant, are the celebrated baths of San
Filippo. The subjacent rocks consist of alternations of black slate, limestone,
and serpentine. There are three warm springs containing carbonate
and sulphate of lime, and sulphate of magnesia. The water
which supplies the baths falls into a pond, where it has been known to
deposit a solid mass thirty feet thick in about twenty years.315 A manufactory
of medallions in basso-relievo is carried on at these baths. The
water is conducted by canals into several pits, in which it deposits travertin
and crystals of sulphate of lime. After being thus freed from its
grosser parts, it is conveyed by a tube to the summit of a small chamber,
and made to fall through a space of ten or twelve feet. The current
is broken in its descent by numerous crossed sticks, by which the
242
spray is dispersed around upon certain moulds, which are rubbed
lightly over with a solution of soap, and a deposition of solid matter
like marble is the result, yielding a beautiful cast of the figures formed
in the mould. The geologist may derive from these experiments considerable
light, in regard to the high slope of the strata at which some
semi-crystalline precipitations can be formed; for some of the moulds
are disposed almost perpendicularly, yet the deposition is nearly equal
in all parts.
A hard stratum of stone, about a foot in thickness, is obtained from
the waters of San Filippo in four months; and, as the springs are
powerful, and almost uniform in the quantity given out, we are at no
loss to comprehend the magnitude of the mass which descends the
hill, which is a mile and a quarter in length and the third of a mile in
breadth, in some places attaining a thickness of 250 feet at least. To
what length it might have reached it is impossible to conjecture, as it is
cut off, like the travertin of San Vignone, by a small stream, where it
terminates abruptly. The remainder of the matter held in solution is
carried on probably to the sea.
Spheroidal structure in travertin.—But what renders this recent
limestone of peculiar interest to the geologist, is the spheroidal form
which it assumes, analogous to that of the cascade of Tivoli, afterwards
to be described. (See fig. 22, p. 244.) The lamination of some of the
concentric masses is so minute that sixty may be counted in the thickness
of an inch, yet, notwithstanding these marks of gradual and successive
deposition, sections are sometimes exhibited of what might seem
to be perfect spheres. This tendency to a mammillary and globular
structure arises from the facility with which the calcareous matter is
precipitated in nearly equal quantities on all sides of any fragment of
shell or wood or any inequality of the surface over which the mineral
water flows, the form of the nucleus being readily transmitted through
any number of successive envelopes. But these masses can never be
perfect spheres, although they often appear such when a transverse
section is made in any line not in the direction of the point of attachment.
There are, indeed, occasionally seen small oolitic and pisolitic
grains, of which the form is globular; for the nucleus, having been for
a time in motion in the water, has received fresh accessions of matter on
all sides.
In the same manner I have seen, on the vertical walls of large steam-boilers,
the heads of nails or rivets covered by a series of enveloping
crusts of calcareous matter, usually sulphate of lime; so that a concretionary
nodule is formed, preserving a nearly globular shape, when increased
to a mass several inches in diameter. In these, as in many travertins,
there is often a combination of the concentric and radiated structure.
Campagna di Roma.—The country around Rome, like many parts of
the Tuscan States already referred to, has been at some former period
the site of numerous volcanic eruptions; and the springs are still
copiously impregnated with lime, carbonic acid, and sulphuretted hydrogen.
243
A hot spring was discovered about 1827, near Civita Vecchia,
by Signor Riccioli, which deposits alternate beds of a yellowish travertin,
and a white granular rock, not distinguishable, in hand specimens,
either in grain, color, or composition, from statuary marble. There
is a passage between this and ordinary travertin. The mass accumulated
near the spring is in some places about six feet thick.
Lake of the Solfatara.—In the Campagna, between Rome and Tivoli,
is the Lake of the Solfatara, called also Lago di Zolfo (lacus albula),
into which flows continually a stream of tepid water from a smaller
lake, situated a few yards above it. The water is a saturated solution
of carbonic acid gas, which escapes from it in such quantities in some
parts of its surface, that it has the appearance of being actually in ebullition.
"I have found by experiment," says Sir Humphry Davy, "that
the water taken from the most tranquil part of the lake, even after being
agitated and exposed to the air, contained in solution more than its
own volume of carbonic acid gas, with a very small quantity of sulphuretted
hydrogen. Its high temperature, which is pretty constant at 80°
of Fahr., and the quantity of carbonic acid that it contains, render it
peculiarly fitted to afford nourishment to vegetable life. The banks of
travertin are everywhere covered with reeds, lichen, confervæ, and
various kinds of aquatic vegetables; and at the same time that the process
of vegetable life is going on, the crystallizations of the calcareous
matter, which is everywhere deposited, in consequence of the escape
of carbonic acid, likewise proceed. There is, I believe, no place in the
world where there is a more striking example of the opposition or contrast
of the laws of animate and inanimate nature, of the forces of inorganic
chemical affinity, and those of the powers of life."316
The same observer informs us that he fixed a stick in a mass of
travertin covered by the water in the month of May, and in April following
he had some difficulty in breaking, with a sharp-pointed hammer,
the mass which adhered to the stick, and which was several inches in
thickness. The upper part was a mixture of light tufa and the leaves
of confervæ; below this was a darker and more solid travertin, containing
black and decomposed masses of confervæ; in the inferior part the
travertin was more solid, and of a gray color, but with cavities probably
produced by the decomposition of vegetable matter.317
The stream which flows out of this lake fills a canal about nine feet
broad and four deep, and is conspicuous in the landscape by a line of
vapor which rises from it. It deposits calcareous tufa in this channel,
and the Tiber probably receives from it, as well as from numerous other
streams, much carbonate of lime in solution, which may contribute to
the rapid growth of its delta. A large proportion of the most splendid
edifices of ancient and modern Rome are built of travertin, derived from
the quarries of Ponte Lucano, where there has evidently been a lake at
a remote period, on the same plain as that already described.
Fig. 22.
Section of spheroidal concretionary Travertin under the Cascade of Tivoli.
244
Travertin of Tivoli.—In the same neighborhood the calcareous
waters of the Anio incrust the reeds which grow on its banks, and the
foam of the cataract of Tivoli forms beautiful pendant stalactites. On
the sides of the deep chasm into which the cascade throws itself, there
is seen an extraordinary accumulation of horizontal beds of tufa and
travertin, from four to five hundred feet in thickness. The section
immediately under the temples of Vesta and the Sibyl, displays, in a
precipice about four hundred feet high, some spheroids which are from
six to eight feet in diameter, each concentric layer being about the eighth
of an inch in thickness. The preceding diagram exhibits about fourteen
feet of this immense mass, as seen in the path cut out of the rock in descending
from the temple of Vesta to the Grotto di Nettuno. I have
not attempted to express in this drawing the innumerable thin layers of
which these magnificent spheroids are composed, but the lines given
mark some of the natural divisions into which they are separated by
minute variations in the size or color of the laminæ. The undulations
245
also are much smaller in proportion to the whole circumference than in
the drawing. The beds (a a) are of hard travertin and soft tufa; below
them is a pisolite (b), the globules being of different sizes: underneath
this appears a mass of concretionary travertin (c c), some of the
spheroids being of the above-mentioned extraordinary size. In some
places (as at d) there is a mass of amorphous limestone, or tufa, surrounded
by concentric layers. At the bottom is another bed of
pisolite (b), in which the small nodules are about the size and shape
of beans, and some of them of filberts, intermixed with some smaller
oolitic grains. In the tufaceous strata, wood is seen converted into a
light tufa.
There can be little doubt that the whole of this deposit was formed
in an extensive lake which existed when the external configuration of
this country varied greatly from that now observed. The Anio throws
itself into a ravine excavated in the ancient travertin, and its waters
give rise to masses of calcareous stone, scarcely if at all distinguishable
from the older rock. I was shown, in 1828, in the upper part of the
travertin, the hollow left by a cart-wheel, in which the outer circle and
the spokes had been decomposed, and the spaces which they filled left
void. It seemed to me at the time impossible to explain the position
of this mould without supposing that the wheel was imbedded before
the lake was drained; but Sir R. Murchison suggests that it may have
been washed down by a flood into the gorge in modern times, and then
incrusted with calcareous tufa in the same manner as the wooden beam
of the church of St. Lucia was swept down in 1826, and stuck fast in
the Grotto of the Syren, where it still remains, and will eventually be
quite imbedded in travertin.
I have already endeavored to explain (p. 241), when speaking of
the travertin of San Filippo, how the spheroidal masses represented in
figure 22 may have been formed.
Sulphureous and gypseus springs.—The quantity of other mineral
ingredients wherewith springs in general are impregnated, is insignificant
in comparison to lime, and this earth is most frequently combined
with carbonic acid. But as sulphuric acid, and sulphuretted hydrogen
are very frequently supplied by springs, gypsum may, perhaps, be deposited
largely in certain seas and lakes. Among other gypseous
precipitates at present known on the land, I may mention those of
Baden, near Vienna, which feed the public bath. Some of these supply
singly from 600 to 1000 cubic feet of water per hour, and deposit
a fine powder, composed of a mixture of sulphate of lime with sulphur
and muriate of lime.318 The thermal waters of Aix, in Savoy, in passing
through strata of Jurassic limestone, turn them into gypsum or sulphate
of lime. In the Andes, at the Puenta del Inca, Lieutenant Brand
found a thermal spring at the temperature of 91° Fahr., containing a
large proportion of gypsum with carbonate of lime and other ingredients.
246
319
Many of the mineral springs of Iceland, says Mr. R. Bunsen,
deposit gypsum.320 and sulphureous acid gas escapes plentifully from
them as from the volcanoes of the same island. It may, indeed, be laid
down as a general rule, that the mineral substances dissolved in hot
springs agree very closely with those which are disengaged in a gaseous
form from the craters of active volcanoes.
Siliceous springs.—Azores.—In order that water should hold a very
large quantity of silica in solution, it seems necessary that it should be
raised to a high temperature.321 The hot springs of the Valle das
Fernas, in the island of St. Michael, rising through volcanic rocks, precipitate
vast quantities of siliceous sinter. Around the circular basin of
the largest spring, which is between twenty and thirty feet in diameter,
alternate layers are seen of a coarser variety of sinter mixed with clay,
including grass, ferns, and reeds, in different states of petrifaction. In
some instances, alumina, which is likewise deposited from the hot
waters, is the mineralizing material. Branches of the same ferns which
now flourish in the island are found completely petrified, preserving the
same appearance as when vegetating, except that they acquire an ash-gray
color. Fragments of wood, and one entire bed from three to five
feet in depth, composed of reeds now common in the island, have become
completely mineralized.
The most abundant variety of siliceous sinter occurs in layers, from a
quarter to half an inch in thickness, accumulated on each other often
to the height of a foot and upwards, and constituting parallel, and for
the most part horizontal, strata many yards in extent. This sinter has
often a beautiful semi-opalescent lustre. A recent breccia is also in
the act of forming, composed of obsidian, pumice, and scoriæ, cemented
by siliceous sinter.322
Geysers of Iceland.—But the hot springs in various parts of Iceland,
particularly the celebrated geysers, afford the most remarkable example
of the deposition of silex.323 The circular reservoirs into which the geysers
fall, are lined in the interior with a variety of opal, and round the
edges with sinter. The plants incrusted with the latter substance have
much the same appearance as those incrusted with calcareous tufa in
our own country. They consist of various grasses, the horse-tail
(Equisetum), and leaves of the birch-tree, which are the most common
of all, though no trees of this species now exist in the surrounding
country. The petrified stems also of the birch occur in a state much
resembling agatized wood.324
By analysis of the water, Mr. Faraday has ascertained that the solution
of the silex is promoted by the presence of the alkali, soda. He
suggests that the deposition of silica in an insoluble state takes place
partly because the water when cooled by exposure to the air is unable
247
to retain as much silica as when it issues from the earth at a temperature
of 180° or 190° Fahr.; and partly because the evaporation of the
water decomposes the compound of silica and soda which previously
existed. This last change is probably hastened by the carbonic acid
of the atmosphere uniting with the soda. The alkali, when disunited
from the silica, would readily be dissolved in and removed by running
water.325
Mineral waters, even when charged with a small proportion of silica,
as those of Ischia, may supply certain species of corals, sponges, and infusoria,
with matter for their siliceous secretions; but there is little doubt
that rivers obtain silex in solution from another and far more general
source, namely, the decomposition of felspar. When this mineral,
which is so abundant an ingredient in the hypogene and trappean rocks,
has disintegrated, it is found that the residue, called porcelain clay, contains
a small proportion only of the silica which existed in the original
felspar, the other part having been dissolved and removed by water.326
Ferruginous springs.—The waters of almost all springs contain some
iron in solution; and it is a fact familiar to all, that many of them are
so copiously impregnated with this metal, as to stain the rocks or herbage
through which they pass, and to bind together sand and gravel into
solid masses. We may naturally, then, conclude that this iron, which
is constantly conveyed from the interior of the earth into lakes and seas,
and which does not escape again from them into the atmosphere by
evaporation, must act as a coloring and cementing principle in the subaqueous
deposits now in progress. Geologists are aware that many
ancient sandstones and conglomerates are bound together or colored
by iron.
Brine springs.—So great is the quantity of muriate of soda in some
springs, that they yield one-fourth of their weight in salt. They are
rarely, however, so saturated, and generally contain, intermixed with
salt, carbonate and sulphate of lime, magnesia, and other mineral ingredients.
The brine springs of Cheshire are the richest in our country;
those of Northwich being almost saturated. Those of Barton also, in
Lancashire, and Droitwich in Worcestershire, are extremely rich.327 They
are known to have flowed for more than 1000 years, and the quantity
of salt which they have carried into the Severn and Mersey must be
enormous. These brine springs rise up through strata of sandstone and
red marl, which contain large beds of rock salt. The origin of the brine,
therefore, may be derived in this and many other instances from beds of
fossil salt; but as muriate of soda is one of the products of volcanic
emanations and of springs in volcanic regions, the original source of salt
may be as deep seated as that of lava.
Many springs in Sicily contain muriate of soda, and the "fiume salso,"
248
in particular, is impregnated with so large a quantity, that cattle refuse
to drink of it. A hot spring, rising through granite, at Saint Nectaire,
in Auvergne, may be mentioned as one of many, containing a large proportion
of muriate of soda, together with magnesia and other ingredients.328
Carbonated springs.—Auvergne.—Carbonic acid gas is very plentifully
disengaged from springs in almost all countries, but particularly near
active or extinct volcanoes. This elastic fluid has the property of decomposing
many of the hardest rocks with which it comes in contact, particularly
that numerous class in whose composition felspar is an ingredient.
It renders the oxide of iron soluble in water, and contributes, as was
before stated, to the solution of calcareous matter. In volcanic districts
these gaseous emanations are not confined to springs, but rise up in the
state of pure gas from the soil in various places. The Grotto del Cane,
near Naples, affords an example, and prodigious quantities are now
annually disengaged from every part of the Limagne d'Auvergne, where
it appears to have been developed in equal quantity from time immemorial.
As the acid is invisible, it is not observed, except an excavation
be made, wherein it immediately accumulates, so that it will extinguish
a candle. There are some springs in this district, where the water is
seen bubbling and boiling up with much noise, in consequence of the
abundant disengagement of this gas. In the environs of Pont-Gibaud,
not far from Clermont, a rock belonging to the gneiss formation, in which
lead-mines are worked, has been found to be quite saturated with carbonic
acid gas, which is constantly disengaged. The carbonates of iron,
lime, and manganese are so dissolved, that the rock is rendered soft, and
the quartz alone remains unattacked.329 Not far off is the small volcanic
cone of Chaluzet, which once broke up through the gneiss, and sent
forth a lava stream.
Supposed atmosphere of carbonic acid.—Prof. Bischoff in his history
of volcanoes,330 has shown what enormous quantities of carbonic acid gas
are exhaled in the vicinity of the extinct craters of the Rhine (in the
neighborhood of the Laacher-see, for example, and the Eifel), and also
in the mineral springs of Nassau and other countries, where there are no
immediate traces of volcanic action. It would be easy to calculate in
how short a period the solid carbon, thus emitted from the interior of the
earth in an invisible form, would amount to a quantity as great as could
be obtained from the trees of a large forest, and how many thousand
years would be required to supply the materials of a dense seam of pure
coal from the same source. Geologists who favor the doctrine of the
former existence of an atmosphere highly charged with carbonic acid, at
the period of the ancient coal-plants, have not sufficiently reflected on
the continual disengagement of carbon, which is taking place in a gaseous
form from springs, as also in a free state from the ground and from
249
volcanic craters into the air. We know that all plants are now engaged
in secreting carbon, and many thousands of large trees are annually
floated down by great rivers, and buried in their alluvial deposits; but
before we can assume that the quantity of carbon which becomes permanently
locked up in the earth by such agency will bring about an
essential change in the chemical composition of the atmosphere, we must
be sure that the trees annually buried contain more carbon than is given
out from the interior of the earth in the same lapse of time. Every large
area covered by a dense mass of peat, bears ample testimony to the fact,
that several million tons of carbon have been taken from the air, by the
powers of vegetable life, and stored up in the earth's crust, a large
quantity of oxygen having been at the same time set free; but we cannot
infer from these circumstances, that the constitution of the atmosphere
has been materially deranged, until we have data for estimating
the rate at which dead animal and vegetable substances are daily putrefying,—organic
remains and various calcareous rocks decomposing, and
volcanic regions emitting fresh volumes of carbonic acid gas. That the
ancient carboniferous period was one of vast duration all geologists are
agreed; instead, therefore, of supposing an excess of carbonic acid in
the air at that epoch, for the support of a peculiar flora, we may imagine
Time to have multiplied the quantity of carbon given out annually by
mineral springs, volcanic craters, and other sources, until the component
elements of any given number of coal-seams had been evolved from below,
without any variation taking place in the constitution of the atmosphere.
It has been too common, in reasoning on this question, to compute
the loss of carbon by the volume of coal stored up in the ancient
strata, and to take no account of the annual gain, by the restoration of
carbonic acid to the atmosphere, through the machinery above alluded to.331
Disintegrating effects of carbonic acid.—The disintegration of granite
is a striking feature of large districts in Auvergne, especially in the
neighborhood of Clermont. This decay was called by Dolomieu, "la
maladie du granite;" and the rock may with propriety be said to have
the rot, for it crumbles to pieces in the hand. The phenomenon may,
without doubt, be ascribed to the continual disengagement of carbonic
acid gas from numerous fissures.
In the plains of the Po, between Verona and Parma, especially at
Villa Franca, south of Mantua, I observed great beds of alluvium, consisting
chiefly of primary pebbles, percolated by spring-water, charged
with carbonate of lime and carbonic acid in great abundance. They are
for the most part incrusted with calc-sinter; and the rounded blocks of
gneiss, which have all the outward appearance of solidity, have been so
disintegrated by the carbonic acid as readily to fall to pieces.
The subtraction of many of the elements of rocks by the solvent power
of carbonic acid, ascending both in a gaseous state and mixed with
spring-water in the crevices of rocks, must be one of the most powerful
250
sources of those internal changes and rearrangements of particles so
often observed in strata of every age. The calcareous matter, for example,
of shells, is often entirely removed and replaced by carbonate of
iron, pyrites, silex, or some other ingredient, such as mineral waters
usually contain in solution. It rarely happens, except in limestone
rocks, that the carbonic acid can dissolve all the constituent parts of the
mass; and for this reason, probably, calcareous rocks are almost the
only ones in which great caverns and long winding passages are found.
Petroleum springs.—Springs of which the waters contain a mixture
of petroleum and the various minerals allied to it, as bitumen, naphtha,
asphaltum, and pitch, are very numerous, and are, in many cases, undoubtedly
connected with subterranean fires, which raise or sublime the
more subtle parts of the bituminous matters contained in rocks. Many
springs in the territory of Modena and Parma, in Italy, produce petroleum
in abundance; but the most powerful, perhaps, yet known, are
those on the Irawadi, in the Burman empire. In one locality there are
said to be 520 wells, which yield annually 400,000 hogsheads of petroleum.332
Pitch lake of Trinidad.—Fluid bitumen is seen to ooze from the
bottom of the sea, on both sides of the island of Trinidad, and to rise
up to the surface of the water. Near Cape La Braye there is a vortex
which, in stormy weather, according to Captain Mallet, gushes out,
raising the water five or six feet, and covers the surface for a considerable
space with petroleum, or tar; and the same author quotes Gumilla,
as stating, in his "Description of the Orinoco," that about seventy years
ago, a spot of land on the western coast of Trinidad, near half-way between
the capital and an Indian village, sank suddenly, and was immediately
replaced by a small lake of pitch, to the great terror of the
inhabitants.333
It is probable that the great pitch lake of Trinidad owes its origin to
a similar cause; and Dr. Nugent has justly remarked, that in that district
all the circumstances are now combined from which deposits of
pitch may have originated. The Orinoco has for ages been rolling
down great quantities of woody and vegetable bodies into the surrounding
sea, where, by the influence of currents and eddies, they may be
arrested and accumulated in particular places. The frequent occurrence
of earthquakes and other indications of volcanic action in those parts
lend countenance to the opinion, that these vegetable substances may
have undergone, by the agency of subterranean fire, those transformations
and chemical changes which produce petroleum; and this may,
by the same causes, be forced up to the surface, where, by exposure to
the air, it becomes inspissated, and forms the different varieties of pure
and earthy pitch, or asphaltum, so abundant in the island.334
251
It may be stated generally, that a large portion of the finer particles
and the more crystalline substances, found in sedimentary rocks of different
ages, are composed of the same elements as are now held in solution
by springs, while the coarser materials bear an equally strong
resemblance to the pebbles and sedimentary matter carried down by
torrents and rivers. It should also be remembered, that it is not only
during inundations, when the muddy sediment is apparent, that rivers
are busy in conveying solid matter to the sea, but that even when their
waters are perfectly transparent, they are annually bearing along vast
masses of carbon, lime, and silica to the ocean.
</div></body></text></TEI>