<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="70">CHAPTER IX.
Discovery of the Laws of Phenomena of Dipolarized
Light.
BESIDES the above-mentioned
perplexing cases of colors produced by common light, cases of
periodical colors produced by polarized light began to be
discovered, and soon became numerous. In August, 1811, M. Arago
communicated to the Institute of France an account of colors seen by
passing polarized light through mica, and analysing57 it with a prism of Iceland spar. It is
remarkable that the light which produced the colors in this case was
the light polarized by the sky, a cause of polarization not previously
known. The effect which the mica thus produced was termed
depolarization;—not a very happy term, since the effect
is not the destruction of the polarization, but the combination of a
new polarizing influence with the former. The word
dipolarization, which has since been proposed, is a much more
appropriate expression. Several other curious phenomena of the same
kind were observed in quartz, and in flint-glass. M. Arago was not
able to reduce these phenomena to laws, but he had a full conviction
of their value, and ventures to class them with the great steps in
81 this part of
optics. “To Bartholin we owe the knowledge of double refraction; to
Huyghens, that of the accompanying polarization; to Malus,
polarization by reflection; to Arago, depolarization.” Sir D. Brewster
was at the same time engaged in a similar train of research; and made
discoveries of the same nature, which, though not published till some
time after those of Arago, were obtained without a knowledge of what
had been done by him. Sir D. Brewster’s Treatise on New
Philosophical Instruments, published in 1813, contains many
curious experiments on the “depolarizing” properties of minerals. Both
these observers noticed the changes of color which are produced by
changes in the position of the ray, and the alternations of color in
the two oppositely polarized images; and Sir D. Brewster discovered
that, in topaz, the phenomena had a certain reference to lines which
he called the neutral and depolarizing axes. M. Biot had
endeavored to reduce the phenomena to a law; and had succeeded so far,
that he found that in the plates of sulphate of lime, the place of the
tint, estimated in Newton’s scale (see ante, chap. vii.), was as the square of the sine of the
inclination. But the laws of these phenomena became much more obvious
when they were observed by Sir D. Brewster with a larger field of
view.58 He found that the colors of topaz,
under the circumstances now described, exhibited themselves in the
form of elliptical rings, crossed by a black bar, “the most brilliant
class of phenomena,” as he justly says, “in the whole range of
optics.” In 1814, also, Wollaston observed the circular rings with a
black cross, produced by similar means in calc-spar; and M. Biot, in
1815, made the same observation. The rings in several of these cases
were carefully measured by M. Biot and Sir D. Brewster, and a great
mass of similar phenomena was discovered. These were added to by
various persons, as M. Seebeck, and Sir John Herschel.
57 The prism of Iceland spar produces
the colors by separating the transmitted rays according to the laws of
double refraction. Hence it is said to analyse the light.
58 Phil. Trans. 1814.
Sir D. Brewster, in 1818, discovered a general relation between the
crystalline form and the optical properties, which gave an
incalculable impulse and a new clearness to these researches. He found
that there was a correspondence between the degree of symmetry of the
optical phenomena and the crystalline form; those crystals which are
uniaxal in the crystallographical sense, are also uniaxal in their
optical properties, and give circular rings; those which are of other
forms are, generally speaking, biaxal; they give oval and knotted
isochromatic lines, with two poles. He also discovered a
rule for the tint at each point 82 in such cases; and thus explained, so far
as an empirical law of phenomena went, the curious and various forms
of the colored curves. This law, when simplified by M. Biot,59 made the tint proportional to the
product of the distances of the point from the two poles. In the
following year, Sir J. Herschel confirmed this law by showing, from
actual measurement, that the curve of the isochromatic lines in these
cases was the curve termed the lemniscata, which has, for each
point, the product of the distances from two fixed poles equal to a
constant quantity.60 He also reduced to rule some other
apparent anomalies in phenomena of the same class.
59 Mém. Inst. 1818, p.
192.
60 Phil. Trans. 1819.
M. Biot, too, gave a rule for the directions of the planes of
polarization of the two rays produced by double refraction in biaxal
crystals, a circumstance which has a close bearing upon the phenomena
of dipolarization. His rule was, that the one plane of polarization
bisects the dihedral angle formed by the two planes which pass through
the optic axes, and that the other is perpendicular to such a plane.
When, however, Fresnel had discovered from the theory the true laws of
double refraction, it appeared that the above rule is inaccurate,
although in a degree which observation could hardly detect without the
aid of theory.61
61  Fresnel, Mém. Inst. 1827,
p. 162.
There were still other classes of optical phenomena which attracted
notice; especially those which are exhibited by plates of quartz cut
perpendicular to the axis. M. Arago had observed, in 1811, that this
substance produced a twist of the plane of polarization to the
right or left hand, the amount of this twist being different for
different colors; a result which was afterwards traced to a
modification of light different both from common and from polarized
light, and subsequently known as circular polarization. Sir J.
Herschel had the good fortune and sagacity to discover that this
peculiar kind of polarization in quartz was connected with an equally
peculiar modification of crystallization, the plagihedral faces
which are seen, on some crystals, obliquely disposed, and, as it were,
following each other round the crystal from left to right, or from
right to left. Sir J. Herschel found that the right-handed or
left-handed character of the circular polarization
corresponded, in all cases, to that of the crystal.
In 1815, M. Biot, in his researches on the subject of circular
polarization, was led to the unexpected and curious discovery, that
this 83 property
which seemed to require for its very conception a crystalline
structure in the body, belonged nevertheless to several fluids, and in
different directions for different fluids. Oil of turpentine, and an
essential oil of laurel, gave the plane of polarization a rotation to
the left hand; oil of citron, syrup of sugar, and a solution of
camphor, gave a rotation to the right hand. Soon after, the like
discovery was made independently by Dr. Seebeck, of Berlin.
It will easily be supposed that all those brilliant phenomena could
not be observed, and the laws of many of the phenomena discovered,
without attempts on the part of philosophers to combine them all under
the dominion of some wide and profound theory. Endeavors to ascend
from such knowledge as we have spoken of, to the general theory of
light, were, in fact, made at every stage of the subject, and with a
success which at last won almost all suffrages. We are now arrived at
the point at which we are called upon to trace the history of this
theory; to pass from the laws of phenomena to their causes;—from
Formal to Physical Optics. The undulatory theory of light, the only
discovery which can stand by the side of the theory of universal
gravitation, as a doctrine belonging to the same order, for its
generality, its fertility, and its certainty, may properly be treated
of with that ceremony which we have hitherto bestowed only on the
great advances of astronomy; and I shall therefore now proceed to
speak of the Prelude to this epoch, the Epoch itself, and its Sequel,
according to the form of the preceding Book which treats of
astronomy.
[2nd Ed.] [I ought to have stated, in the beginning of this
chapter, that Malus discovered the depolarization of white
light in 1811. He found that a pencil of light which, being
polarized, refused to be reflected by a surface properly placed,
recovered its power of being reflected after being transmitted through
certain crystals and other transparent bodies. Malus intended to
pursue this subject, when his researches were terminated by his death,
Feb. 7, 1812. M. Arago, about the same time, announced his important
discovery of the depolarization of colors by crystals.
I may add, to what is above said of M.
Biot’s discoveries respecting the circular polarizing power of fluids,
that he pursued his researches so as to bring into view some most
curious relations among the elements of bodies. It appeared that
certain substances, as sugar of canes, had a right-handed effect, and
certain other substances, as gum, a left-handed effect; and that the
molecular value of this effect was not altered by dilution. It
appeared also that a certain element of the 84 substance of fruits, which had been
supposed to be gum, and which is changed into sugar by the operation
of acids, is not gum, and has a very energetic right-handed effect.
This substance M. Biot called dextrine, and he has since traced
its effects into many highly curious and important results.]


PHYSICAL OPTICS.
</div></body></text></TEI>