<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="95">CHAPTER II.
Doctrine of Acid and
Alkali.—Sylvius.
AMONG the results of mixture
observed by chemists, were many instances in which two ingredients,
each in itself pungent or destructive, being put together, became mild
and inoperative; each 263 counteracting and neutralizing the
activity of the other. The notion of such opposition and neutrality is
applicable to a very wide range of chemical processes. The person who
appears first to have steadily seized and generally applied this
notion is Francis de la Boé Sylvius; who was born in 1614, and
practised medicine at Amsterdam, with a success and reputation which
gave great currency to his opinions on that art.2 His chemical
theories were propounded as subordinate to his medical doctrines; and
from being thus presented under a most important practical aspect,
excited far more attention than mere theoretical opinions on the
composition of bodies could have done. Sylvius is spoken of by
historians of science, as the founder of the iatro-chemical
sect among physicians; that is, the sect which considers the disorders
in the human frame as the effects of chemical relations of the fluids,
and applies to them modes of cure founded upon this doctrine. We have
here to speak, not of his physiological, but of his chemical
views.
2 Sprengel. Geschichte der
Arzneykunde, vol. iv. Thomson’s History of Chemistry in the
corresponding part is translated from Sprengel.
The distinction of acid and alkaline bodies
(acidum, lixivum) was familiar before the time of
Sylvius; but he framed a system, by considering them both as eminently
acrid and yet opposite, and by applying this notion to the human
frame. Thus3 the lymph contains an acid, the bile an
alkaline salt. These two opposite acrid substances, when they are
brought together, neutralize each other (infringunt),
and are changed into an intermediate and milder substance.
3 De Methodo Medendi, Amst.
1679. Lib. ii. cap. 28, sects. 8 and 53.
The progress of this doctrine, as a physiological one, is an
important part of the history of medical science in the seventeenth
century; but with that we are not here concerned. But as a chemical
doctrine, this notion of the opposition of acid and alkali, and of its
very general applicability, struck deep root, and has not been
eradicated up to our own time. Boyle, indeed, whose disposition led
him to suspect all generalities, expressed doubts with regard to this
view;4 and argued that the supposition of acid
and alkaline parts in all bodies was precarious, their offices
arbitrary, and the notion of them unsettled. Indeed it was not
difficult to show, that there was no one certain criterion to which
all supposed acids conformed. Yet the general conception of such a
combination as that of acid and alkali was supposed to 264 be, served so well to
express many chemical facts, that it kept its ground. It is found, for
instance, in Lemery’s Chemistry, which was one of those in most
general use before the introduction of the phlogistic theory. In this
work (which was translated into English by Keill, in 1698) we find
alkalies defined by their effervescing with acids.5 They were
distinguished as the mineral alkali (soda), the
vegetable alkali (potassa), and the volatile alkali
(ammonia). Again, in Macquer’s Chemistry, which was long the
text-book in Europe during the reign of phlogiston, we find acids and
alkalies, and their union, in which they rob each other of their
characteristic properties, and form neutral salts, stated among the
leading principles of the science.6
4 Shaw’s Boyle, iii. p.
432.
5 Lemery, p. 25.
6 Macquer, p. 19.
In truth, the mutual relation of acids to alkalies was the most
essential part of the knowledge which chemists possessed concerning
them. The importance of this relation arose from its being the first
distinct form in which the notion of chemical attraction or affinity
appeared. For the acrid or caustic character of acids and alkalies is,
in fact, a tendency to alter the bodies they touch, and thus to alter
themselves; and the neutral character of the compounds is the absence of
any such proclivity to change. Acids and alkalies have a strong
disposition to unite. They combine, often with vehemence, and produce
neutral salts; they exhibit, in short, a prominent example of the
chemical attraction, or affinity, by which two ingredients are formed
into a compound. The relation of acid and base in a salt
is, to this day, one of the main grounds of all theoretical
reasonings.
The more distinct development of the notion of such chemical
attraction, gradually made its way among the chemists of the latter
part of the seventeenth and the beginning of the eighteenth century,
as we may see in the writings of Boyle, Newton, and their followers.
Beecher speaks of this attraction as a magnetism; but I do not
know that any writer in particular, can be pointed out as the person
who firmly established the general notion of chemical
attraction.
But this idea of chemical attraction became both more clear and
more extensively applicable, when it assumed the form of the doctrine
of elective attractions, in which shape we must now speak of
it. 265</div></body></text></TEI>