<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="13">CHAPTER IV.
Sequel to the Inductive Epoch of
Hipparchus.

Sect. 1.—Researches which verified
the Theory.
THE discovery of the leading
Laws of the Solar and Lunar Motions, and the detection of the
Precession, may be considered as the great positive steps in the
Hipparchian astronomy;—the parent discoveries, from which many
minor improvements proceeded. The task of pursuing the collateral and
consequent researches which now offered themselves,—of bringing
the other parts of astronomy up to the level of its most improved
portions,—was prosecuted by a succession of zealous observers
and calculators, first, in the school of Alexandria, and afterwards in
other parts of the world. We must notice the various labors of this
series of astronomers; but we shall do so very briefly; for the
ulterior development of doctrines once established is not so important
an object of contemplation for our present purpose, as the first
conception and proof of those fundamental truths on which systematic
doctrines are founded. Yet Periods of Verification, as well as Epochs
of Induction, deserve to be attended to; and they can nowhere be
studied with so much advantage as in the history of astronomy.
In truth, however, Hipparchus did not leave to his successors the
task of pursuing into detail those views of the heavens to which his
discoveries led him. He examined with scrupulous care almost every
part of the subject. We must briefly mention some of the principal
points which were thus settled by him.
The verification of the laws of the changes which he assigned to
the skies, implied that the condition of the heavens was constant,
except so far as it was affected by those changes. Thus, the doctrine
that the changes of position of the stars were rightly represented by
the precession of the equinoxes, supposed that the stars were fixed
with regard to each other; and the doctrine that the unequal number of
days, in certain subdivisions of months and years, was adequately
explained by the theory of epicycles, assumed that years and days were
always of constant lengths. But Hipparchus was not content with
assuming these bases of his theory, he endeavored to prove them. 158
1. Fixity of the Stars.—The question necessarily arose
after the discovery of the precession, even if such a question had
never suggested itself before, whether the stars which were called
fixed, and to which the motions of the other luminaries are
referred, do really retain constantly the same relative position. In
order to determine this fundamental question, Hipparchus undertook to
construct a Map of the heavens; for though the result of his
survey was expressed in words, we may give this name to his Catalogue
of the positions of the most conspicuous stars. These positions are
described by means of alineations; that is, three or more such
stars are selected as can be touched by an apparent straight line
drawn in the heavens. Thus Hipparchus observed that the southern claw
of Cancer, the bright star in the same constellation which precedes
the head of the Hydra, and the bright star Procyon, were nearly in the
same line. Ptolemy quotes this and many other of the configurations
which Hipparchus had noted, in order to show that the positions of the
stars had not changed in the intermediate time; a truth which the
catalogue of Hipparchus thus gave astronomers the means of
ascertaining. It contained 1080 stars.
The construction of this catalogue of the stars by Hipparchus is an
event of great celebrity in the history of astronomy. Pliny,77 who speaks of it with admiration as a
wonderful and superhuman task (“ausus rem etiam Deo improbam,
annumerare posteris stellas”), asserts the undertaking to have been
suggested by a remarkable astronomical event, the appearance of a new
star; “novam stellam et alium in ævo suo genitam deprehendit; ejusque
motu, qua die fulsit, ad dubitationem est adductus anne hoc sæpius
fieret, moverenturque et eæ quas putamus affixas.” There is nothing
inherently improbable in this tradition, but we may observe, with
Delambre,78 that we are not informed whether this
new star remained in the sky, or soon disappeared again. Ptolemy makes
no mention of the star or the story; and his catalogue contains no
bright star which is not found in the “Catasterisms” of
Eratosthenes. These Catasterisms were an enumeration of 475 of the
principal stars, according to the constellations in which they are,
and were published about sixty years before Hipparchus.
77 Nat. Hist. lib. ii.
(xxvi.)
78 A. A. i. 290.
2. Constant Length of Years.—Hipparchus also attempted
to ascertain whether successive years are all of the same length; and
though, with his scrupulous love of accuracy,79 he does not
appear to have 159
thought himself justified in asserting that the years were always
exactly equal, he showed, both by observations of the time when the
sun passed the equinoxes, and by eclipses, that the difference of
successive years, if there were any difference, must be extremely
slight. The observations of succeeding astronomers, and especially of
Ptolemy, confirmed this opinion, and proved, with certainty, that
there is no progressive increase or diminution in the duration of the
year.
79 Ptolem. Synt. iii. 2.
3. Constant Length of Days. Equation of Time.—The
equality of days was more difficult to ascertain than that of years;
for the year is measured, as on a natural scale, by the number of days
which it contains; but the day can be subdivided into hours only by
artificial means; and the mechanical skill of the ancients did not
enable them to attain any considerable accuracy in the measure of such
portions of time; though clepsydras and similar instruments were used
by astronomers. The equality of days could only be proved, therefore,
by the consequences of such a supposition; and in this manner it
appears to have been assumed, as the fact really is, that the apparent
revolution of the stars is accurately uniform, never becoming either
quicker or slower. It followed, as a consequence of this, that the
solar days (or rather the nycthemers, compounded of a night and
a day) would be unequal, in consequence of the sun’s unequal motion,
thus giving rise to what we now call the Equation of
Time,—the interval by which the time, as marked on a dial,
is before or after the time, as indicated by the accurate timepieces
which modern skill can produce. This inequality was fully taken
account of by the ancient astronomers; and they thus in fact assumed
the equality of the sidereal days.
Sect. 2.—Researches which did not verify the
Theory.
Some of the researches of Hipparchus and
his followers fell upon the weak parts of his theory; and if the
observations had been sufficiently exact, must have led to its being
corrected or rejected.
Among these we may notice the researches which were made concerning
the Parallax of the heavenly bodies, that is, their apparent
displacement by the alteration of position of the observer from one
part of the earth’s surface to the other. This subject is treated of
at length by Ptolemy; and there can be no doubt that it was well
examined by Hipparchus, who invented a parallactic instrument
for that purpose. The idea of parallax, as a geometrical possibility,
was indeed too obvious to be overlooked by geometers at any time; and
when the doctrine of the sphere was established, it must have appeared
strange 160 to the
student, that every place on the earth’s surface might alike be
considered as the centre of the celestial motions. But if this was
true with respect to the motions of the fixed stars, was it also true
with regard to those of the sun and moon? The displacement of the sun
by parallax is so small, that the best observers among the ancients
could never be sure of its existence; but with respect to the moon,
the case is different. She may be displaced by this cause to the
amount of twice her own breadth, a quantity easily noticed by the
rudest process of instrumental observation. The law of the
displacement thus produced is easily obtained by theory, the globular
form of the earth being supposed known; but the amount of the
displacement depends upon the distance of the moon from the earth, and
requires at least one good observation to determine it. Ptolemy has
given a table of the effects of parallax, calculated according to the
apparent altitude of the moon, assuming certain supposed distances;
these distances, however, do not follow the real law of the moon’s
distances, in consequence of their being founded upon the Hypothesis
of the Eccentric and Epicycle.
In fact this Hypothesis, though a very close representation of the
truth, so far as the positions of the luminaries are
concerned, fails altogether when we apply it to their
distances. The radius of the epicycle, or the eccentricity of
the eccentric, are determined so as to satisfy the observations of the
apparent motions of the bodies; but, inasmuch as the
hypothetical motions are different altogether from the real motions,
the Hypothesis does not, at the same time, satisfy the observations of
the distances of the bodies, if we are able to make any such
observations.
Parallax is one method by which the distances of the moon, at
different times, may be compared; her Apparent Diameters afford
another method. Neither of these modes, however, is easily capable of
such accuracy as to overturn at once the Hypothesis of epicycles; and,
accordingly, the Hypothesis continued to be entertained in spite of
such measures; the measures being, indeed, in some degree falsified in
consequence of the reigning opinion. In fact, however, the
imperfection of the methods of measuring parallax and magnitude, which
were in use at this period, was such, their results could not lead to
any degree of conviction deserving to be set in opposition to a theory
which was so satisfactory with regard to the more certain
observations, namely, those of the motions.
The Eccentricity, or the Radius of the Epicycle, which would
satisfy 161 the
inequality of the motions of the moon, would, in fact, double
the inequality of the distances. The Eccentricity of the
moon’s orbit is determined by Ptolemy as 1⁄12 of the radius of the
orbit; but its real amount is only half as great; this difference is a
necessary consequence of the supposition of uniform circular motions,
on which the Epicyclic Hypothesis proceeds.
We see, therefore, that this part of the Hipparchian theory carries
in itself the germ of its own destruction. As soon as the art of
celestial measurement was so far perfected, that astronomers could be
sure of the apparent diameter of the moon within 1⁄30 or
1⁄40
of the whole, the inconsistency of the theory with itself would become
manifest. We shall see, hereafter, the way in which this inconsistency
operated; in reality a very long period elapsed before the methods of
observing were sufficiently good to bring it clearly into view.
Sect. 3.—Methods of Observation of the Greek
Astronomers.
We must now say a word concerning the
Methods above spoken of. Since one of the most important tasks of
verification is to ascertain with accuracy the magnitude of the
quantities which enter, as elements, into the theory which occupies
men during the period; the improvement of instruments, and the methods
of observing and experimenting, are principal features in such
periods. We shall, therefore, mention some of the facts which bear
upon this point.
The estimation of distances among the stars by the eye, is an
extremely inexact process. In some of the ancient observations,
however, this appears to have been the method employed; and stars are
described as being a cubit or two cubits from other
stars. We may form some notion of the scale of this kind of
measurement, from what Cleomedes remarks,80 that the sun
appears to be about a foot broad; an opinion which he confutes at
length.
80 Del. A. A. i. 222.
A method of determining the positions of the stars, susceptible of
a little more exactness than the former, is the use of
alineations, already noticed in
speaking of Hipparchus’s catalogue. Thus, a straight line passing
through two stars of the Great Bear passes also through the pole-star;
this is, indeed, even now a method usually employed to enable us
readily to fix on the pole-star; and the two stars β and α of Ursa
Major, are hence often called “the pointers.” 162
But nothing like accurate measurements of any portions of the sky
were obtained, till astronomers adopted the method of making visual
coincidences of the objects with the instruments, either by means of
shadows or of sights.
Probably the oldest and most obvious measurements of the positions
of the heavenly bodies were those in which the elevation of the sun
was determined by comparing the length of the shadow of an upright
staff or gnomon, with the length of the staff itself. It
appears,81 from a memoir of Gautil, first printed
in the Connaissance des Temps for 1809, that, at the lower town
of Loyang, now called Hon-anfou, Tchon-kong found the length of the
shadow of the gnomon, at the summer solstice, equal to one foot and a
half, the gnomon itself being eight feet in length. This was about
1100 b. c. The Greeks, at an early period,
used the same method. Strabo says82 that “Byzantium
and Marseilles are on the same parallel of latitude, because the
shadows at those places have the same proportion to the gnomon,
according to the statement of Hipparchus, who follows Pytheas.”
81 Lib. U. K. Hist. Ast. p.
5.
82 Del. A. A. i. 257.
But the relations of position which astronomy considers, are, for
the most part, angular distances; and these are most simply expressed
by the intercepted portion of a circumference described about the
angular point. The use of the gnomon might lead to the determination
of the angle by the graphical methods of geometry; but the numerical
expression of the circumference required some progress in
trigonometry; for instance, a table of the tangents of angles.
Instruments were soon invented for measuring angles, by means of
circles, which had a border or limb, divided into equal parts.
The whole circumference was divided into 360 degrees: perhaps
because the circles, first so divided, were those which represented
the sun’s annual path; one such degree would be the sun’s daily
advance, more nearly than any other convenient aliquot part which
could be taken. The position of the sun was determined by means of the
shadow of one part of the instrument upon the other. The most ancient
instrument of this kind appears to be the Hemisphere of
Berosus. A hollow hemisphere was placed with its rim horizontal,
and a style was erected in such a manner that the extremity of the
style was exactly at the centre of the sphere. The shadow of this
extremity, on the concave surface, had the same position with regard
to the lowest point of the sphere which the sun had with regard to the
highest point of the heavens. 163 But this instrument was in fact used
rather for dividing the day into portions of time than for determining
position.
Eratosthenes83 observed the amount of the obliquity of
the sun’s path to the equator: we are not informed what instruments he
used for this purpose; but he is said to have obtained, from the
munificence of Ptolemy Euergetes, two Armils, or instruments
composed of circles, which were placed in the portico at Alexandria,
and long used for observations. If a circular rim or hoop were placed
so as to coincide with the plane of the equator, the inner concave
edge would be enlightened by the sun’s rays which came under the front
edge, when the sun was south of the equator, and by the rays which
came over the front edge, when the sun was north of the equator: the
moment of the transition would be the time of the equinox. Such an
instrument appears to be referred to by Hipparchus, as quoted by
Ptolemy.84 “The circle of copper, which stands at
Alexandria in what is called the Square Porch, appears to mark, as the
day of the equinox, that on which the concave surface begins to be
enlightened from the other side.” Such an instrument was called an
equinoctial armil.
83 Delambre, A. A. i. 86.
84 Ptol. Synt. iii. 2.
A solstitial armil is described by Ptolemy, consisting of
two circular rims, one sliding round within the other, and the inner
one furnished with two pegs standing out from its surface at right
angles, and diametrically opposite to each other. These circles being
fixed in the plane of the meridian, and the inner one turned, till, at
noon, the shadow of the peg in front falls upon the peg behind, the
position of the sun at noon would be determined by the degrees on the
outer circle.
In calculation, the degree was conceived to be divided into 60
minutes, the minute into 60 seconds, and so on. But in
practice it was impossible to divide the limb of the instrument into
parts so small. The armils of Alexandria were divided into no parts
smaller than sixths of degrees, or divisions of 10 minutes.
The angles, observed by means of these divisions, were expressed as
a fraction of the circumference. Thus Eratosthenes stated the interval
between the tropics to be  11⁄83 of the circumference.85
85 Delambre, A. A. i. 87. It is
probable that his observation gave him 47⅔ degrees. The fraction 47⅔⁄360 =
143⁄1080 = 11∙13⁄1080  = 11⁄831⁄13,
which is very nearly  11⁄83.
It was soon remarked that the whole circumference of the circle
164 was not wanted
for such observations. Ptolemy86 says that he
found it more convenient to observe altitudes by means of a square
flat piece of stone or wood, with a quadrant of a circle
described on one of its flat faces, about a centre near one of the
angles. A peg was placed at the centre, and one of the extreme radii
of the quadrant being perpendicular to the horizon, the elevation of
the sun above the horizon was determined by observing the point of the
arc of the quadrant on which the shadow of the peg fell.
86 Synt. i. 1.
As the necessity of accuracy in the observations was more and more
felt, various adjustments of such instruments were practised. The
instruments were placed in the meridian by means of a meridian
line drawn by astronomical methods on the floor on which they
stood. The plane of the instrument was made vertical by means of a
plumb-line: the bounding radius, from which angles were measured, was
also adjusted by the plumb-line.87
87 The curvature of the plane of the
circle, by warping, was noticed. Ptol. iii. 2. p. 155, observes that
his equatorial circle was illuminated on the hollow side twice in the
same day. (He did not know that this might arise from
refraction.)
In this manner, the places of the sun and of the moon could be
observed by means of the shadows which they cast. In order to observe
the stars,88 the observer looked along the face of
the circle of the armil, so as to see its two edges apparently brought
together, and the star apparently touching them.89
88 Delamb. A. A. i. 185.
89 Ptol. Synt. i. 1. Ὥσπερ
κεκολλήμενος ἀμφοτέραις αὐτῶν ταῖς ἐπιφανείαις ὁ ἀστὴρ ἐν τῷ δι’ αὐτῶν
ἐπιπέδῳ διοπτεύηται.
It was afterwards found important to ascertain the position of the
sun with regard to the ecliptic: and, for this purpose, an instrument,
called an astrolabe, was invented, of which we have a
description in Ptolemy.90 This also consisted of circular rims,
movable within one another, or about poles; and contained circles
which were to be brought into the position of the ecliptic, and of a
plane passing through the sun and the poles of the ecliptic. The
position of the moon with regard to the ecliptic, and its position in
longitude with regard to the sun or a star, were thus determined.
90 Synt. v. 1.
The astrolabe continued long in use, but not so long as the
quadrant described by Ptolemy; this, in a larger form, is the mural
quadrant, which has been used up to the most recent times.
It may be considered surprising,91 that Hipparchus,
after having 165
observed, for some time, right ascensions and declinations, quitted
equatorial armils for the astrolabe, which immediately refers the
stars to the ecliptic. He probably did this because, after the
discovery of precession, he found the latitudes of the stars constant,
and wanted to ascertain their motion in longitude.
91 Del. A. A. 181.
To the above instruments, may be added the dioptra, and the
parallactic instrument of Hipparchus and Ptolemy. In the
latter, the distance of a star from the zenith was observed by looking
through two sights fixed in a rule, this being annexed to another
rule, which was kept in a vertical position by a plumb-line; and the
angle between the two rules was measured.
The following example of an observation, taken from Ptolemy, may
serve to show the form in which the results of the instruments, just
described, were usually stated.92
92 Del. A. A. ii. 248.
“In the 2d year of Antoninus, the 9th day of Pharmouthi, the sun
being near setting, the last division of Taurus being on the meridian
(that is, 5½ equinoctial hours after noon), the moon was in 3 degrees
of Pisces, by her distance from the sun (which was 92 degrees, 8
minutes); and half an hour after, the sun being set, and the quarter
of Gemini on the meridian, Regulus appeared, by the other circle of
the astrolabe, 57½ degrees more forwards than the moon in longitude.”
From these data the longitude of Regulus is calculated.
From what has been said respecting the observations of the
Alexandrian astronomers, it will have been seen that their
instrumental observations could not be depended on for any close
accuracy. This defect, after the general reception of the Hipparchian
theory, operated very unfavorably on the progress of the science. If
they could have traced the moon’s place distinctly from day to day,
they must soon have discovered all the inequalities which were known
to Tycho Brahe; and if they could have measured her parallax or her
diameter with any considerable accuracy, they must have obtained a
confutation of the epicycloidal form of her orbit. By the badness of
their observations, and the imperfect agreement of these with
calculation, they not only were prevented making such steps, but were
led to receive the theory with a servile assent and an indistinct
apprehension, instead of that rational conviction and intuitive
clearness which would have given a progressive impulse to their
knowledge. 166
Sect. 4.—Period from Hipparchus to
Ptolemy.
We have now to speak of the cultivators of
astronomy from the time of Hipparchus to that of Ptolemy, the next
great name which occurs in the history of this science; though even he
holds place only among those who verified, developed, and extended the
theory of Hipparchus. The astronomers who lived in the intermediate
time, indeed, did little, even in this way; though it might have been
supposed that their studies were carried on under considerable
advantages, inasmuch as they all enjoyed the liberal patronage of the
kings of Egypt.93 The “divine school of Alexandria,” as
it is called by Synesius, in the fourth century, appears to have
produced few persons capable of carrying forwards, or even of
verifying, the labors of its great astronomical teacher. The
mathematicians of the school wrote much, and apparently they observed
sometimes; but their observations are of little value; and their books
are expositions of the theory and its geometrical consequences,
without any attempt to compare it with observation. For instance, it
does not appear that any one verified the remarkable discovery of the
precession, till the time of Ptolemy, 250 years after; nor does the
statement of this motion of the heavens appear in the treatises of the
intermediate writers; nor does Ptolemy quote a single observation of
any person made in this long interval of time; while his references to
those of Hipparchus are perpetual; and to those of Aristyllus and
Timocharis, and of others, as Conon, who preceded Hipparchus, are not
unfrequent.
93 Delamb. A. A. ii. 240.
This Alexandrian period, so inactive and barren in the history of
science, was prosperous, civilized, and literary; and many of the
works which belong to it are come down to us, though those of
Hipparchus are lost. We have the “Uranologion” of Geminus,94 a systematic treatise on Astronomy,
expounding correctly the Hipparchian Theories and their consequences,
and containing a good account of the use of the various Cycles, which
ended in the adoption of the Calippic Period. We have likewise “The
Circular Theory of the Celestial Bodies” of Cleomedes,95 of which the principal part is a
development of the doctrine of the sphere, including the consequences
of the globular form of the earth. We have also another work on
“Spherics” by Theodosius of Bithynia,96 which contains
some of the most important propositions of the subject, and has been
used as a book of 167 instruction even in modern times.
Another writer on the same subject is Menelaus, who lived somewhat
later, and whose Three Books on Spherics still remain.
94 b. c.
70.
95 b. c.
60.
96 b. c.
50.
One of the most important kinds of deduction from a geometrical
theory, such as that of the doctrine of the sphere, or that of
epicycles, is the calculation of its numerical results in particular
cases. With regard to the latter theory, this was done in the
construction of Solar and Lunar Tables, as we have already seen; and
this process required the formation of a Trigonometry, or
system of rules for calculating the relations between the sides and
angles of triangles. Such a science had been formed by Hipparchus, who
appears to be the author of every great step in ancient astronomy.97 He wrote a work in twelve books, “On
the Construction of the Tables of Chords of Arcs;” such a table being
the means by which the Greeks solved their triangles. The Doctrine of
the Sphere required, in like manner, a Spherical Trigonometry,
in order to enable mathematicians to calculate its results; and this
branch of science also appears to have been formed by Hipparchus,98 who gives results that imply the
possession of such a method. Hypsicles, who was a contemporary of
Ptolemy, also made some attempts at the solution of such problems: but
it is extraordinary that the writers whom we have mentioned as coming
after Hipparchus, namely, Theodosius, Cleomedes, and Menelaus, do not
even mention the calculation of triangles,99 either plain or
spherical; though the latter writer100 is said to
have written on “the Table of Chords,” a work which is now lost.
97 Delamb. A. A. ii. 37.
98 A. A. i. 117.
99 A. A. i. 249.
100 A. A. ii. 37.
We shall see, hereafter, how prevalent a disposition in literary
ages is that which induces authors to become commentators. This
tendency showed itself at an early period in the school of Alexandria.
Aratus,101 who lived 270 b.
c. at the court of Antigonus, king of Macedonia, described the
celestial constellations in two poems, entitled “Phænomena,” and
“Prognostics.” These poems were little more than a versification of
the treatise of Eudoxus on the acronycal and heliacal risings and
settings of the stars. The work was the subject of a comment by
Hipparchus, who perhaps found this the easiest way of giving
connection and circulation to his knowledge. Three Latin translations
of this poem gave the Romans the means of becoming acquainted with it:
the first is by Cicero, of which we have numerous fragments 168 extant;102 Germanicus Cæsar, one of the
sons-in-law of Augustus, also translated the poem, and this
translation remains almost entire. Finally, we have a complete
translation by Avienus.103 The “Astronomica” of Manilius, the
“Poeticon Astronomicon” of Hyginus, both belonging to the time of
Augustus, are, like the work of Aratus, poems which combine
mythological ornament with elementary astronomical exposition; but
have no value in the history of science. We may pass nearly the same
judgment upon the explanations and declamations of Cicero, Seneca, and
Pliny, for they do not apprise us of any additions to astronomical
knowledge; and they do not always indicate a very clear apprehension
of the doctrines which the writers adopt.
101 A. A. i. 74.
102 Two copies of this translation,
illustrated by drawings of different ages, one set Roman, and the
other Saxon, according to Mr. Ottley, are described in the
Archæologia, vol. xviii.
103 Montucla, i. 221.
Perhaps the most remarkable feature in the two last-named writers,
is the declamatory expression of their admiration for the discoverers
of physical knowledge; and in one of them, Seneca, the persuasion of a
boundless progress in science to which man was destined. Though this
belief was no more than a vague and arbitrary conjecture, it suggested
other conjectures in detail, some of which, having been verified, have
attracted much notice. For instance, in speaking of comets,104 Seneca says, “The time will come when
those things which are now hidden shall be brought to light by time
and persevering diligence. Our posterity will wonder that we should be
ignorant of what is so obvious.” “The motions of the planets,” he
adds, “complex and seemingly confused, have been reduced to rule; and
some one will come hereafter, who will reveal to us the paths of
comets.” Such convictions and conjectures are not to be admired for
their wisdom; for Seneca was led rather by enthusiasm, than by any
solid reasons, to entertain this opinion; nor, again, are they to be
considered as merely lucky guesses, implying no merit; they are
remarkable as showing how the persuasion of the universality of law,
and the belief of the probability of its discovery by man, grow up in
men’s minds, when speculative knowledge becomes a prominent object of
attention.
104 Seneca, Qu. N. vii.
25.
An important practical application of astronomical knowledge was
made by Julius Cæsar, in his correction of the calendar, which we have
already noticed; and this was strictly due
to the Alexandrian School: Sosigenes, an astronomer belonging to that
school, came from Egypt to Rome for the purpose. 169
Sect. 5.—Measures of the Earth.
There were, as we have said, few attempts
made, at the period of which we are speaking, to improve the accuracy
of any of the determinations of the early Alexandrian astronomers. One
question naturally excited much attention at all times, the
magnitude of the earth, its figure being universally
acknowledged to be a globe. The Chaldeans, at an earlier period, had
asserted that a man, walking without stopping, might go round the
circuit of the earth in a year; but this might be a mere fancy, or a
mere guess. The attempt of Eratosthenes to decide this question went
upon principles entirely correct. Syene was situated on the tropic;
for there, on the day of the solstice, at noon, objects cast no
shadow; and a well was enlightened to the bottom by the sun’s rays. At
Alexandria, on the same day, the sun was, at noon, distant from the
zenith by a fiftieth part of the circumference. Those two cities were
north and south from each other: and the distance had been determined,
by the royal overseers of the roads, to be 5000 stadia. This gave a
circumference of 250,000 stadia to the earth, and a radius of about
40,000. Aristotle105 says that the mathematicians make the
circumference 400,000 stadia. Hipparchus conceived that the measure of
Eratosthenes ought to be increased by about one-tenth.106 Posidonius, the friend of Cicero, made
another attempt of the same kind. At Rhodes, the star Canopus but just
appeared above the horizon; at Alexandria, the same star rose to an
altitude of  1⁄48th of the circumference;
the direct distance on the meridian was 5000 stadia, which gave
240,000 for the whole circuit. We cannot look upon these measures as
very precise; the stadium employed is not certainly known; and no
peculiar care appears to have been bestowed on the measure of the
direct distance.
105 De Cœlo, ii. ad fin.
106 Plin. ii. (cviii.)
When the Arabians, in the ninth century, came to be the principal
cultivators of astronomy, they repeated this observation in a manner
more suited to its real importance and capacity of exactness. Under
the Caliph Almamon,107 the vast plain of Singiar, in
Mesopotamia, was the scene of this undertaking. The Arabian
astronomers there divided themselves into two bands, one under the
direction of Chalid ben Abdolmalic, and the other having at its head
Alis ben Isa. These two parties proceeded, the one north, the other
south, determining the distance by the actual application of their
measuring-rods to the ground, 170 till each was found, by astronomical
observation, to be a degree from the place at which they started. It
then appeared that these terrestrial degrees were respectively 56
miles, and 56 miles and two-thirds, the mile being 4000 cubits. In
order to remove all doubt concerning the scale of this measure, we are
informed that the cubit is that called the black cubit, which consists
of 27 inches, each inch being the thickness of six grains of
barley.
107 Montu. 357.
Sect. 6.—Ptolemy’s Discovery of Evection.
By referring, in this place, to the
last-mentioned measure of the earth, we include the labors of the
Arabian as well as the Alexandrian astronomers, in the period of mere
detail, which forms the sequel to the great astronomical revolution of
the Hipparchian epoch. And this period of verification is rightly
extended to those later times; not merely because astronomers were
then still employed in determining the magnitude of the earth, and the
amount of other elements of the theory,—for these are some of
their employments to the present day,—but because no great
intervening discovery marks a new epoch, and begins a new
period;—because no great revolution in the theory added to the
objects of investigation, or presented them in a new point of view.
This being the case, it will be more instructive for our purpose to
consider the general character and broad intellectual features of this
period, than to offer a useless catalogue of obscure and worthless
writers, and of opinions either borrowed or unsound. But before we do
this, there is one writer whom we cannot leave undistinguished in the
crowd; since his name is more celebrated even than that of Hipparchus;
his works contain ninety-nine hundredths of what we know of the Greek
astronomy; and though he was not the author of a new theory, he made
some very remarkable steps in the verification, correction, and
extension of the theory which he received. I speak of Ptolemy, whose
work, “The Mathematical Construction” (of the heavens), contains a
complete exposition of the state of astronomy in his time, the reigns
of Adrian and Antonine. This book is familiarly known to us by a term
which contains the record of our having received our first knowledge
of it from the Arabic writers. The “Megiste Syntaxis,” or Great
Construction, gave rise, among them, to the title Al Magisti,
or Almagest, by which the work is commonly described. As a
mathematical exposition of the Theory of Epicycles and Eccentrics, of
the observations and calculations which were employed in 171 order to apply this
theory to the sun, moon, and planets, and of the other calculations
which are requisite, in order to deduce the consequences of this
theory, the work is a splendid and lasting monument of diligence,
skill, and judgment. Indeed, all the other astronomical works of the
ancients hardly add any thing whatever to the information we obtain
from the Almagest; and the knowledge which the student possesses of
the ancient astronomy must depend mainly upon his acquaintance with
Ptolemy. Among other merits, Ptolemy has that of giving us a very
copious account of the manner in which Hipparchus established the main
points of his theories; an account the more agreeable, in consequence
of the admiration and enthusiasm with which this author everywhere
speaks of the great master of the astronomical school.
In our present survey of the writings of Ptolemy, we are concerned
less with his exposition of what had been done before him, than with
his own original labors. In most of the branches of the subject, he
gave additional exactness to what Hipparchus had done; but our main
business, at present, is with those parts of the Almagest which
contain new steps in the application of the Hipparchian hypothesis.
There are two such cases, both very remarkable,—that of the
moon’s Evection, and that of the Planetary Motions.
The law of the moon’s anomaly, that is, of the leading and obvious
inequality of her motion, could be represented, as we have seen,
either by an eccentric or an epicycle; and the amount of this
inequality had been collected by observations of eclipses. But though
the hypothesis of an epicycle, for instance, would bring the moon to
her proper place, so far as eclipses could show it, that is, at new
and full moon, this hypothesis did not rightly represent her motions
at other points of her course. This appeared, when Ptolemy set about
measuring her distances from the sun at different times. “These,” he108 says, “sometimes agreed, and sometimes
disagreed.” But by further attention to the facts, a rule was detected
in these differences. “As my knowledge became more complete and more
connected, so as to show the order of this new inequality, I perceived
that this difference was small, or nothing, at new and full moon; and
that at both the dichotomies (when the moon is half
illuminated) it was small, or nothing, if the moon was at the apogee
or perigee of the epicycle, and was greatest when she was in the
middle of the interval, and therefore when the first 172 inequality was
greatest also.” He then adds some further remarks on the circumstances
according to which the moon’s place, as affected by this new
inequality, is before or behind the place, as given by the epicyclical
hypothesis.
108 Synth. v. 2.
Such is the announcement of the celebrated discovery of the moon’s
second inequality, afterwards called (by Bullialdus) the
Evection. Ptolemy soon proceeded to represent this inequality
by a combination of circular motions, uniting, for this purpose, the
hypothesis of an epicycle, already employed to explain the first
inequality, with the hypothesis of an eccentric, in the circumference
of which the centre of the epicycle was supposed to move. The mode of
combining these was somewhat complex; more complex we may, perhaps,
say, than was absolutely requisite;109 the apogee of
the eccentric moved backwards, or contrary to the order of the signs,
and the centre of the epicycle moved forwards nearly twice as fast
upon the circumference of the eccentric, so as to reach a place
nearly, but not exactly, the same, as if it had moved in a concentric
instead of an eccentric path. Thus the centre of the epicycle went
twice round the eccentric in the course of one month: and in this
manner it satisfied the condition that it should vanish at new and
full moon, and be greatest when the moon was in the quarters of her
monthly course.110
109 If Ptolemy had used the
hypothesis of an eccentric instead of an epicycle for the first
inequality of the moon, an epicycle would have represented the second
inequality more simply than his method did.
110 I will insert here the
explanation which my German translator, the late distinguished
astronomer Littrow, has given of this point. The Rule of this
Inequality, the Evection, may be most simply expressed thus. If
a denote the excess of the Moon’s Longitude over the Sun’s, and
b the Anomaly of the Moon reckoned from her Perigee, the
Evection is equal to 1°. 3.sin
(2a − b). At New and Full Moon, a is
0 or 180°, and thus the Evection is − 1°.3.sin b. At both quarters, or
dichotomies, a is 90° or 270°, and consequently the Evection is
+ 1°.3.sin b. The
Moon’s Elliptical Equation of the centre is at all points of her orbit
equal to 6°.3.sin b.
The Greek Astronomers before Ptolemy observed the moon only at the
time of eclipses; and hence they necessarily found for the sum of
these two greatest inequalities of the moon’s motion the quantity
6°.3.sin b − 1°.3.sin
b, or 5°.sin
b: and as they took this for the moon’s equation of the
centre, which depends upon the eccentricity of the moon’s orbit, we
obtain from this too small equation of the centre, an eccentricity
also smaller than the truth. Ptolemy, who first observed the moon in
her quarters, found for the sum of those Inequalities at those points
the quantity 6°.3.sin b
+ 1°.3.sin b, or 7°.6.sin b; and thus made the eccentricity of
the moon as much too great at the quarters as the observers of
eclipses had made it too small. He hence concluded that the
eccentricity of the Moon’s orbit is variable, which is not the
case.
The discovery of the Evection, and the reduction of it to the
173 epicyclical
theory, was, for several reasons, an important step in astronomy; some
of these reasons may be stated.
1. It obviously suggested, or confirmed, the suspicion that the
motions of the heavenly bodies might be subject to many
inequalities:—that when one set of anomalies had been discovered
and reduced to rule, another set might come into view;—that the
discovery of a rule was a step to the discovery of deviations from the
rule, which would require to be expressed in other rules;—that
in the application of theory to observation, we find, not only the
stated phenomena, for which the theory does account, but also
residual phenomena, which remain unaccounted for, and stand
out beyond the calculation;—that thus nature is not simple and
regular, by conforming to the simplicity and regularity of our
hypotheses, but leads us forwards to apparent complexity, and to an
accumulation of rules and relations. A fact like the Evection,
explained by an Hypothesis like Ptolemy’s, tended altogether to
discourage any disposition to guess at the laws of nature from mere
ideal views, or from a few phenomena.
2. The discovery of Evection had an importance which did not come
into view till long afterwards, in being the first of a numerous
series of inequalities of the moon, which results from the
Disturbing Force of the sun. These inequalities were
successfully discovered; and led finally to the establishment of the
law of universal gravitation. The moon’s first inequality arises from
a different cause;—from the same cause as the inequality of the
sun’s motion;—from the motion in an ellipse, so far as the
central attraction is undisturbed by any other. This first inequality
is called the Elliptic Inequality, or, more usually, the Equation
of the Centre.111 All the planets have such
inequalities, but the Evection is peculiar to the moon. The discovery
of other inequalities of the moon’s motion, the Variation and Annual
Equation, made an immediate sequel in the order of the subject to
174 the discoveries
of Ptolemy, although separated by a long interval of time; for these
discoveries were only made by Tycho Brahe in the sixteenth century.
The imperfection of astronomical instruments was the great cause of
this long delay.
111 The Equation of the Centre is the
difference between the place of the Planet in its elliptical orbit,
and that place which a Planet would have, which revolved uniformly
round the Sun as a centre in a circular orbit in the same time. An
imaginary Planet moving in the manner last described, is called the
mean Planet, while the actual Planet which moves in the ellipse
is called the true Planet. The Longitude of the mean Planet at
a given time is easily found, because its motion is uniform. By adding
to it the Equation of the Centre, we find the Longitude of the true
Planet, and thus, its place in its orbit.—Littrow’s
Note.
 I may add that the word Equation, used in such cases,
denotes in general a quantity which must be added to or subtracted
from a mean quantity, to make it equal to the true quantity;
or rather, a quantity which must be added to or subtracted from a
variably increasing quantity to make it increase
equably.
3. The Epicyclical Hypothesis was found capable of accommodating
itself to such new discoveries. These new inequalities could be
represented by new combinations of eccentrics and epicycles: all the
real and imaginary discoveries by astronomers, up to Copernicus, were
actually embodied in these hypotheses; Copernicus, as we have said,
did not reject such hypotheses; the lunar inequalities which Tycho
detected might have been similarly exhibited; and even Newton112 represents the motion of the moon’s
apogee by means of an epicycle. As a mode of expressing the law of the
irregularity, and of calculating its results in particular cases, the
epicyclical theory was capable of continuing to render great service
to astronomy, however extensive the progress of the science might be.
It was, in fact, as we have already said, the modern process of
representing the motion by means of a series of circular
functions.
112 Principia, lib. iii. prop.
xxxv.
4. But though the doctrine of eccentrics and epicycles was thus
admissible as an Hypothesis, and convenient as a means of expressing
the laws of the heavenly motions, the successive occasions on which it
was called into use, gave no countenance to it as a Theory; that is,
as a true view of the nature of these motions, and their causes. By
the steps of the progress of this Hypothesis, it became more and more
complex, instead of becoming more simple, which, as we shall see, was
the course of the true Theory. The notions concerning the position and
connection of the heavenly bodies, which were suggested by one set of
phenomena, were not confirmed by the indications of another set of
phenomena; for instance, those relations of the epicycles which were
adopted to account for the Motions of the heavenly bodies, were not
found to fall in with the consequences of their apparent Diameters and
Parallaxes. In reality, as we have said, if the relative distances of
the sun and moon at different times could have been accurately
determined, the Theory of Epicycles must have been forthwith
overturned. The insecurity of such measurements alone maintained the
theory to later times.113
113 The alteration of the apparent
diameter of the moon is so great that it cannot escape us, even with
very moderate instruments. This apparent diameter contains, when the
moon is nearest the earth, 2010 seconds; when she is furthest off 1762
seconds; that is, 248 seconds, or 4 minutes 8 seconds, less than in
the former case. [The two quantities are in the proportion of 8 to 7,
nearly.]—Littrow’s Note. 175
Sect. 7.—Conclusion of the History of
Greek Astronomy.
I might now proceed to give an account of
Ptolemy’s other great step, the determination of the Planetary Orbits;
but as this, though in itself very curious, would not illustrate any
point beyond those already noticed, I shall refer to it very briefly.
The planets all move in ellipses about the sun, as the moon moves
about the earth; and as the sun apparently moves about the earth. They
will therefore each have an Elliptic Inequality or Equation of the
centre, for the same reason that the sun and moon have such
inequalities. And this inequality may be represented, in the cases of
the planets, just as in the other two, by means of an eccentric; the
epicycle, it will be recollected, had already been used in order to
represent the more obvious changes of the planetary motions. To
determine the amount of the Eccentricities and the places of the
Apogees of the planetary orbits, was the task which Ptolemy undertook;
Hipparchus, as we have seen, having been destitute of the observations
which such a process required. The determination of the Eccentricities
in these cases involved some peculiarities which might not at first
sight occur to the reader. The elliptical motion of the planets takes place
about the sun; but Ptolemy considered their movements as altogether
independent of the sun, and referred them to the earth alone; and thus
the apparent eccentricities which he had to account for, were the
compound result of the Eccentricity of the earth’s orbit, and of the
proper eccentricity of the orbit of the Planet. He explained this
result by the received mechanism of an eccentric Deferent,
carrying an Epicycle; but the motion in the Deferent is uniform, not
about the centre of the circle, but about another point, the
Equant. Without going further into detail, it may be sufficient
to state that, by a combination of Eccentrics and Epicycles, he did
account for the leading features of these motions; and by using his
own observations, compared with more ancient ones (for instance, those
of Timocharis for Venus), he was able to determine the Dimensions and
Positions of the orbits.114
114 Ptolemy determined the Radius and
the Periodic Time of his two circles for each Planet in the following
manner: For the inferior Planets, that is, Mercury and Venus,
he took the Radius of the Deferent equal to the Radius of the Earth’s
orbit, and the Radius of the Epicycle equal to that of the Planet’s
orbit. For these Planets, according to his assumption, the Periodic
Time of the Planet in its Epicycle was to the Periodic Time of the
Epicyclical Centre on the Deferent, as the synodical Revolution
of the Planet to the tropical Revolution of the Earth above the
Sun. For the three superior Planets, Mars, Jupiter, and Saturn,
the Radius of the Deferent was equal to the Radius of the Planet’s
orbit, and the Radius of the Epicycle was equal to the Radius of the
Earth’s orbit; the Periodic Time on the Planet in its Epicycle was to
the Periodic Time of the Epicyclical Centre on the Deferent, as the
synodical Revolution of the Planet to the tropical
Revolution of the same Planet.
 Ptolemy might obviously have made the geometrical motions of all
the Planets correspond with the observations by one of these two modes
of construction; but he appears to have adopted this double form of
the theory, in order that in the inferior, as well as in the superior
Planets, he might give the smaller of the two Radii to the Epicycle:
that is, in order that he might make the smaller circle move round the
larger, not vice versâ.—Littrow’s Notes.
176 I shall here
close my account of the astronomical progress of the Greek School. My
purpose is only to illustrate the principles on which the progress of
science depends, and therefore I have not at all pretended to touch
upon every part of the subject. Some portion of the ancient theories,
as, for instance, the mode of accounting for the motions of the moon
and planets in latitude, are sufficiently analogous to what has been
explained, not to require any more especial notice. Other parts of
Greek astronomical knowledge, as, for instance, their acquaintance
with refraction, did not assume any clear or definite form, and can
only be considered as the prelude to modern discoveries on the same
subject. And before we can with propriety pass on to these, there is a
long and remarkable, though unproductive interval, of which some
account must be given.
Sect. 8.—Arabian Astronomy.
The interval to which I have just alluded
may be considered as extending from Ptolemy to Copernicus; we have no
advance in Greek astronomy after the former; no signs of a revival of
the power of discovery till the latter. During this interval of 1350
years,115 the principal cultivators of astronomy
were the Arabians, who adopted this science from the Greeks whom they
conquered, and from whom the conquerors of western Europe again
received back their treasure, when the love of science and the
capacity for it had been awakened in their minds. In the intervening
time, the precious deposit had undergone little change. The Arab
astronomer had been the scrupulous but unprofitable servant, who kept
his talent without apparent danger of loss, but also without prospect
of increase. There is little in 177 Arabic literature which bears upon the
progress of astronomy; but as the little that there is must
be considered as a sequel to the Greek science, I shall notice one or
two points before I treat of the stationary period in general.
115 Ptolemy died about a. d. 150. Copernicus was living a.
d. 1500.
When the sceptre of western Asia had passed into the hands of the
Abasside caliphs,116 Bagdad, “the city of peace,” rose to
splendor and refinement, and became the metropolis of science under
the successors of Almansor the Victorious, as Alexandria had been
under the successors of Alexander the Great. Astronomy attracted
peculiarly the favor of the powerful as well as the learned; and
almost all the culture which was bestowed upon the science, appears to
have had its source in the patronage, often also in the personal
studies, of Saracen princes. Under such encouragement, much was done,
in those scientific labors which money and rank can command.
Translations of Greek works were made, large instruments were erected,
observers were maintained; and accordingly as observation showed the
defects and imperfection of the extant tables of the celestial
motions, new ones were constructed. Thus under Almansor, the Grecian
works of science were collected from all quarters, and many of them
translated into Arabic.117 The translation of the “Megiste
Syntaxis” of Ptolemy, which thus became the Almagest, is ascribed to
Isaac ben Homain in this reign.
116 Gibbon, x. 31.
117 Id. x. 36.
The greatest of the Arabian Astronomers comes half a century later.
This is Albategnius, as he is commonly called; or more exactly,
Mohammed ben Geber Albatani, the last appellation indicating that he
was born at Batan, a city of Mesopotamia.118 He was a
Syrian prince, whose residence was at Aracte or Racha in Mesopotamia:
a part of his observations were made at Antioch. His work still
remains to us in Latin. “After having read,” he says, “the Syntaxis of
Ptolemy, and learnt the methods of calculation employed by the Greeks,
his observations led him to conceive that some improvements might be
made in their results. He found it necessary to add to Ptolemy’s
observations as Ptolemy had added to those of Abrachis” (Hipparchus).
He then published Tables of the motions of the sun, moon, and planets,
which long maintained a high reputation.
118 Del. Astronomie du Moyen
Age, 4.
These, however, did not prevent the publication of others. Under
the Caliph Hakem (about a. d. 1000) Ebon
Iounis published Tables of the Sun, Moon, and Planets, which were
hence called the Hakemite Tables. Not long after, Arzachel of
Toledo published the Toletan 178 Tables. In the 13th century, Nasir Eddin
published Tables of the Stars, dedicated to Ilchan, a Tartar prince,
and hence termed the Ilchanic Tables. Two centuries later,
Ulugh Beigh, the grandson of Tamerlane, and prince of the countries
beyond the Oxus, was a zealous practical astronomer; and his Tables,
which were published in Europe by Hyde in 1665, are referred to as
important authority by modern astronomers. The series of Astronomical
Tables which we have thus noticed, in which, however, many are
omitted, leads us to the Alphonsine Tables, which were put
forth in 1488, and in succeeding years, under the auspices of
Alphonso, king of Castile; and thus brings us to the verge of modern
astronomy.
For all these Tables, the Ptolemaic hypotheses were employed; and,
for the most part, without alteration. The Arabs sometimes felt the
extreme complexity and difficulty of the doctrine which they studied;
but their minds did not possess that kind of invention and energy by
which the philosophers of Europe, at a later period, won their way
into a simpler and better system.
Thus Alpetragius states, in the outset of his “Planetarum
Theorica,” that he was at first astonished and stupefied with this
complexity, but that afterwards “God was pleased to open to him the
occult secret in the theory of his orbs, and to make known to him the
truth of their essence and the rectitude of the quality of their
motion.” His system consists, according to Delambre,119 in attributing to the planets a spiral
motion from east to west, an idea already refuted by Ptolemy. Geber of
Seville criticises Ptolemy very severely,120 but without
introducing any essential alteration into his system. The Arabian
observations are in many cases valuable; both because they were made
with more skill and with better instruments than those of the Greeks;
and also because they illustrate the permanence or variability of
important elements, such as the obliquity of the ecliptic and the
inclination of the moon’s orbit.
119 Delambre, M. A. p.
7.
120 M. A. p. 180,
&c.
We must, however, notice one or two peculiar Arabian doctrines. The
most important of these is the discovery of the Motion of the Son’s
Apogee by Albategnius. He found the Apogee to be in longitude 82
degrees; Ptolemy had placed it in longitude 65 degrees. The difference
of 17 degrees was beyond all limit of probable error of calculation,
though the process is not capable of great precision; and the
inference of the Motion of the Apogee was so obvious, that we cannot
179 agree with
Delambre, in doubting or extenuating the claim of Albategnius to this
discovery, on the ground of his not having expressly stated it.
In detecting this motion, the Arabian astronomers reasoned rightly
from facts well observed: they were not always so fortunate. Arzachel,
in the 11th century, found the apogee of the sun to be less advanced
than Albategnius had found it, by some degrees; he inferred that it
had receded in the intermediate time; but we now know, from an
acquaintance with its real rate of moving, that the true inference
would have been, that Albategnius, whose method was less trustworthy
than that of Arzachel, had made an error to the amount of the
difference thus arising. A curious, but utterly false hypothesis was
founded on observations thus erroneously appreciated; namely, the
Trepidation of the fixed stars. Arzachel conceived that a
uniform Precession of the equinoctial points would not account for the
apparent changes of position of the stars, and that for this purpose,
it was necessary to conceive two circles of about eight degrees radius
described round the equinoctial points of the immovable sphere, and to
suppose the first points of Aries and Libra to describe the
circumference of these circles in about 800 years. This would produce,
at one time a progression, and at another a regression, of the
apparent equinoxes, and would moreover change the latitude of the
stars. Such a motion is entirely visionary; but the doctrine made a
sect among astronomers, and was adopted in the first edition of the
Alphonsine Tables, though afterwards rejected.
An important exception to the general unprogressive character of
Arabian science has been pointed out recently by M. Sedillot.121 It appears that Mohammed-Aboul
Wefa-al-Bouzdjani, an Arabian astronomer of the tenth century, who
resided at Cairo, and observed at Bagdad in 975, discovered a third
inequality of the moon, in addition to the two expounded by Ptolemy,
the Equation of the Centre, and the Evection. This third inequality,
the Variation, is usually supposed to have been discovered by
Tycho Brahe, six centuries later. It is an inequality of the moon’s
motion, in virtue of which she moves quickest when she is at new or
full, and slowest at the first and third quarter; in consequence of
this, from the first quarter to the full, she is behind her mean
place; at the full, she does not differ from her mean place; from the
full to the third quarter, she is before her true 180 place; and so on; and
the greatest effect of the inequality is in the octants, or
points half-way between the four quarters. In an Almagest of Aboul
Wefa, a part of which exists in the Royal Library at Paris, after
describing the two inequalities of the moon, he has a Section ix., “Of
the Third Anomaly of the moon called Muhazal or
Prosneusis.” He there says, that taking cases when the moon was
in apogee or perigee, and when, consequently, the effect of the two
first inequalities vanishes, he found, by observation of the
moon, when she was nearly in trine and in sextile
with the sun, that she was a degree and a quarter from her calculated
place. “And hence,” he adds, “I perceived that this anomaly exists
independently of the two first: and this can only take place by a
declination of the diameter of the epicycle with respect to the centre
of the zodiac.”
121 Sedillot, Nouvelles Rech. sur
l’Hist. de l’Astron. chez les Arabes. Nouveau Journal
Asiatique. 1836.
We may remark that we have here this inequality of the moon made
out in a really philosophical manner; a residual quantity in the
moon’s longitude being detected by observation, and the cases in which
it occurs selected and grouped by an inductive effort of the mind. The
advance is not great; for Aboul Wefa appears only to have detected the
existence, and not to have fixed the law or the exact quantity of the
inequality; but still it places the scientific capacity of the Arabs
in a more favorable point of view than any circumstance with which we
were previously acquainted.
But this discovery of Aboul Wefa appears to have excited no notice
among his contemporaries and followers: at least it had been long
quite forgotten when Tycho Brahe rediscovered the same lunar
inequality. We can hardly help looking upon this circumstance as an
evidence of a servility of intellect belonging to the Arabian period.
The learned Arabians were so little in the habit of considering
science as progressive, and looking with pride and confidence at
examples of its progress, that they had not the courage to believe in
a discovery which they themselves had made, and were dragged back by
the chain of authority, even when they had advanced beyond their Greek
masters.
As the Arabians took the whole of their theory (with such slight
exceptions as we have been noticing) from the Greeks, they took from
them also the mathematical processes by which the consequences of the
theory were obtained. Arithmetic and Trigonometry, two main branches
of these processes, received considerable improvements at their hands.
In the former, especially, they rendered a service to the world which
it is difficult to estimate too highly, in abolishing the 181 cumbrous Sexagesimal
Arithmetic of the Greeks, and introducing the notation by means of the
digits 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 0, which we now employ.122 These numerals appear to be of Indian
origin, as is acknowledged by the Arabs themselves; and thus form no
exception to the sterility of the Arabian genius as to great
scientific inventions. Another improvement, of a subordinate kind, but
of great utility, was Arabian, being made by Albategnius. He
introduced into calculation the sine, or half-chord of the
double arc, instead of the chord of the arc itself, which had been
employed by the Greek astronomers. There have been various conjectures
concerning the origin of the word sine; the most probable
appears to be that sinus is the Latin translation of the Arabic
word gib, which signifies a fold, the two halves of the chord
being conceived to be folded together.
122 Mont. i. 376.
The great obligation which Science owes to the Arabians, is to have
preserved it during a period of darkness and desolation, so that
Europe might receive it back again when the evil days were past. We
shall see hereafter how differently the European intellect dealt with
this hereditary treasure when once recovered.
Before quitting the subject, we may observe that Astronomy brought
back, from her sojourn among the Arabs, a few terms which may still be
perceived in her phraseology. Such are the zenith, and the
opposite imaginary point, the nadir;—the circles of the
sphere termed almacantars and azimuth circles. The
alidad of an instrument is its index, which possesses an
angular motion. Some of the stars still retain their Arabic names;
Aldebran, Rigel, Fomalhaut; many others were
known by such appellations a little while ago. Perhaps the word
almanac is the most familiar vestige of the Arabian period of
astronomy.

It is foreign to my purpose to note any efforts of the intellectual
faculties among other nations, which may have taken place
independently of the great system of progressive European culture,
from which all our existing science is derived. Otherwise I might
speak of the astronomy of some of the Orientals, for example, the
Chinese, who are said, by Montucla (i. 465), to have discovered the
first equation of the moon, and the proper motion of the fixed stars
(the Precession), in the third century of our era. The Greeks had made
these discoveries 500 years earlier.


BOOK IV.


HISTORY
OF
PHYSICAL SCIENCE IN THE MIDDLE AGES;
OR,
VIEW OF THE STATIONARY PERIOD
OF
INDUCTIVE SCIENCE.


In vain, in vain! the all-composing
hour
Resistless falls  .  .  . 
.
.  .  .  . 
. . . . .
As one by one, at dread Medea’s strain,
The sickening stars fade off th’ ethereal
plain;
As Argus’ eyes, by Hermes’ wand opprest,
Closed one by one to everlasting rest;
Thus at her felt approach and secret
might,
Art after art goes out, and all is night.
See skulking Truth to her old cavern
fled,
Mountains of casuistry heaped on her
head;
Philosophy, that reached the heavens
before,
Shrinks to her hidden cause, and is no
more.
Physic of Metaphysic begs defence,
And Metaphysic calls for aid to Sense:
See Mystery to Mathematics fly!
In vain! they gaze, turn giddy, rave, and
die.
Dunciad, B. iv.  
</div></body></text></TEI>