<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="26">
[143]
CHAPTER VII.

The Nebular Hypothesis.

We have referred to Laplace, as a profound mathematician,
who has strongly expressed the opinion,
that the arrangement by which the stability of the
solar system is secured is not the result of chance;
that “a primitive cause has directed the planetary
motions.” This author, however, having arrived, as
we have done, at this conviction, does not draw from
it the conclusion which has appeared to us so irresistible,
that “the admirable arrangement of the solar
system cannot but be the work of an intelligent and
most powerful being.” He quotes these expressions,
which are those of Newton, and points at them as
instances where that great philosopher had deviated
from the method of true philosophy. He himself proposes
an hypothesis concerning the nature of the
primitive cause of which he conceives the existence
to be thus probable: and this hypothesis, on account
of the facts which it attempts to combine, the view
of the universe which it presents, and the eminence
of the person by whom it is propounded, deserves
our notice.
1. Laplace conjectures that in the original condition
of the solar system, the sun revolved upon his
axis, surrounded by an atmosphere which, in virtue
of an excessive heat, extended far beyond the orbits
of all the planets, the planets as yet having no existence.
The heat gradually diminished, and as the
solar atmosphere contracted by cooling, the rapidity
of its rotation increased by the laws of rotatory motion,
and an exterior zone of vapour was detached
from the rest, the central attraction being no longer
able to overcome the increased centrifugal force.[144]
This zone of vapour might in some cases retain its
form, as we see it in Saturn’s ring; but more usually
the ring of vapour would break into several masses,
and these would generally coalesce into one mass,
which would revolve about the sun. Such portions
of the solar atmosphere, abandoned successively at
different distances, would form “planets in the state
of vapour.” These planets, it appears from mechanical
considerations, would have each its rotatory
motion, and as the cooling of the vapour still went
on, would each produce a planet, which might have
satellites and rings, formed from the planet in the
same manner as the planets were formed from the
atmosphere of the sun.
It may easily be conceived that all the primary
motions of a system so produced would be nearly
circular, nearly in the plane of the original equator
of the solar rotation, and in the direction of that rotation.
Reasons are offered also to show that the
motions of the satellites thus produced and the motions
of rotation of the planets must be in the same
direction. And thus it is held that the hypothesis
accounts for the most remarkable circumstances in
the structure of the solar system: namely, the motions
of the planets in the same direction, and almost
in the same plane; the motions of the satellites in the
same direction as those of the planets; the motions
of rotation of these different bodies still in the same
direction as the other motions, and in planes not
much different; the small eccentricity of the orbits
of the planets, upon which condition, along with
some of the preceding ones, the stability of the system
depends; and the position of the source of light
and heat in the centre of the system.
It is not necessary for the purpose, nor suitable to
the plan of the present treatise, to examine, on physical
grounds, the probability of the above hypothesis.
It is proposed by its author, with great diffidence, as
a conjecture only. We might, therefore, very reasonably
put off all discussion of the bearings of this[145]
opinion upon our views of the government of the
world, till the opinion itself should have assumed a
less indistinct and precarious form. It can be no
charge against our doctrines, that there is a difficulty
in reconciling with them arbitrary guesses and half-formed
theories. We shall, however, make a few
observations upon this nebular hypothesis, as it may
be termed.
2. If we grant, for a moment, the hypothesis, it by
no means proves that the solar system was formed
without the intervention of intelligence and design.
It only transfers our view of the skill exercised, and
the means employed, to another part of the work.
For, how came the sun and its atmosphere to have
such materials, such motions, such a constitution,
that these consequences followed from their primordial
condition? How came the parent vapour thus
to be capable of coherence, separation, contraction,
solidification? How came the laws of its motion,
attraction, repulsion, condensation, to be so fixed, as
to lead to a beautiful and harmonious system in the
end? How came it to be neither too fluid nor too
tenacious, to contract neither too quickly nor too
slowly, for the successive formation of the several
planetary bodies? How came that substance, which
at one time was a luminous vapour, to be at a subsequent
period, solids and fluids of many various kinds?
What but design and intelligence prepared and tempered
this previously existing element, so that it
should by its natural changes produce such an orderly
system?
And if in this way we suppose a planet to be produced,
what sort of a body would it be?—something,
it may be presumed, resembling a large meteoric
stone. How comes this mass to be covered with
motion and organization, with life and happiness?
What primitive cause stocked it with plants and animals,
and produced all the wonderful and subtle contrivances
which we find in their structure, all the
wide and profound mutual dependencies which we[146]
trace in their economy? Was man, with his thought
and feeling, his powers and hopes, his will and conscience,
also produced as an ultimate result of the
condensation of the solar atmosphere? Except we
allow a prior purpose and intelligence presiding over
this material “primitive cause,” how irreconcilable
is it with the evidence which crowds in upon us from
every side!
3. In the next place, we may observe concerning
this hypothesis, that it carries us back to the beginning
of the present system of things; but that it is
impossible for our reason to stop at the point thus
presented to it. The sun, the earth, the planets, the
moons were brought into their present order out of
a previous state, and, as is supposed in the theory, by
the natural operation of laws. But how came that
previous state to exist? We are compelled to suppose
that it, in like manner, was educed from a still
prior state of things; and this, again, must have been
the result of a condition prior still. Nor is it possible
for us to find, in the tenets of the nebular hypothesis,
any resting place or satisfaction for the mind.
The same reasoning faculty, which seeks for the origin
of the present system of things, and is capable of
assenting to, or dissenting from the hypothesis propounded
by Laplace as an answer to this inquiry, is
necessarily led to seek, in the same manner, for the
origin of any previous system of things, out of which
the present may appear to have grown: and must
pursue this train of inquiries unremittingly, so long
as the answer which it receives describes a mere assemblage
of matter and motion; since it would be to
contradict the laws of matter and the nature of motion,
to suppose such an assemblage to be the first
condition.
The reflection just stated, may be illustrated by
the further consideration of the Nebular Hypothesis.
This opinion refers us, for the origin of the solar
system, to a sun surrounded with an atmosphere of
enormously elevated temperature, revolving and cooling.[147]
But as we ascend to a still earlier period, what
state of things are we to suppose?—a still higher
temperature, a still more diffused atmosphere. Laplace
conceives that, in its primitive state, the sun
consisted in a diffused luminosity so as to resemble
those nebulæ among the fixed stars, which are seen
by the aid of the telescope, and which exhibit a nucleus,
more or less brilliant, surrounded by a cloudy
brightness. “This anterior state was itself preceded
by other states, in which the nebulous matter was
more and more diffuse, the nucleus being less and
less luminous. We arrive,” Laplace says, “in this
manner, at a nebulosity so diffuse, that its existence
could scarcely be suspected.”
“Such is,” he adds, “in fact, the first state of the
nebulæ which Herschel carefully observed by means
of his powerful telescopes. He traced the progress of
condensation, not indeed on one nebula, for this progress
can only become perceptible to us in the course
of centuries; but in the assemblage of nebulæ; much
in the same manner as in a large forest we may
trace the growth of trees among the examples of
different ages which stand side by side. He saw in
the first place the nebulous matter dispersed in
patches, in the different parts of the sky. He saw in
some of these patches this matter feebly condensed
round one or more faint nuclei. In other nebulæ,
these nuclei were brighter in proportion to the surrounding
nebulosity; when by a further condensation
the atmosphere of each nucleus becomes separate
from the others, the result is multiple nebulous stars,
formed by brilliant nuclei very near each other, and
each surrounded by an atmosphere: sometimes the
nebulous matter condensing in a uniform manner
has produced nebulous systems which are called
planetary. Finally, a still greater degree of condensation
transforms all these nebulous systems into
stars. The nebulæ, classed according to this philosophical
view, indicate with extreme probability their[148]
future transformation into stars, and the anterior nebulous
condition of the stars which now exist.”
It appears then that the highest point to which this
series of conjectures can conduct us, is, “an extremely
diffused nebulosity,” attended, we may suppose, by a
far higher degree of heat, than that which, at a later
period of the hypothetical process, keeps all the materials
of our earth and planets in a state of vapour.
Now is it not impossible to avoid asking, whence was
this light, this heat, this diffusion? How came the
laws which such a state implies, to be already in existence?
Whether light and heat produce their effects
by means of fluid vehicles or otherwise, they
have complex and varied laws which indicate the
existence of some subtle machinery for their action.
When and how was this machinery constructed?
Whence too that enormous expansive power which
the nebulous matter is supposed to possess? And if,
as would seem to be supposed in this doctrine, all the
material ingredients of the earth existed in this diffuse
nebulosity, either in the state of vapour, or in
some state of still greater expansion, whence were
they and their properties? how came there to be of
each simple substance which now enters into the
composition of the universe, just so much and no
more? Do we not, far more than ever, require an
origin of this origin? an explanation of this explanation?
Whatever may be the merits of the opinion as
a physical hypothesis, with which we do not here
meddle, can it for a moment prevent our looking beyond
the hypothesis, to a First Cause, an Intelligent
Author, an origin proceeding from free volition, not
from material necessity?
But again: let us ascend to the highest point of the
hypothetical progression: let us suppose the nebulosity
diffused throughout all space, so that its course of
running into patches is not yet begun. How are we
to suppose it distributed? Is it equably diffused in
every part? clearly not; for if it were, what should[149]
cause it to gather into masses, so various in size,
form and arrangement? The separation of the nebulous
matter into distinct nebulæ implies necessarily
some original inequality of distribution; some determining
circumstances in its primitive condition.
Whence were these circumstances? this inequality?
we are still compelled to seek some ulterior agency
and power.
Why must the primeval condition be one of
change at all? Why should not the nebulous matter
be equably diffused throughout space, and continue
for ever in its state of equable diffusion, as it must
do, from the absence of all cause to determine the
time and manner of its separation? why should this
nebulous matter grow cooler and cooler? why should
it not retain for ever the same degree of heat, whatever
heat be? If heat be a fluid, if to cool be to part
with this fluid, as many philosophers suppose, what
becomes of the fluid heat of the nebulous matter, as
the matter cools down? Into what unoccupied region
does it find its way?
Innumerable questions of the same kind might be
asked, and the conclusion to be drawn is, that every
new physical theory which we include in our view of
the universe, involves us in new difficulties and perplexities,
if we try to erect it into an ultimate and
final account of the existence and arrangement of
the world in which we live. With the evidence of
such theories, considered as scientific generalizations
of ascertained facts, with their claims to a place in
our natural philosophy, we have here nothing to do.
But if they are put forwards as a disclosure of the
ultimate cause of that which occurs, and as superseding
the necessity of looking further or higher; if
they claim a place in our Natural Theology, as well
as our Natural Philosophy; we conceive that their
pretensions will not bear a moment’s examination.
Leaving then to other persons and to future ages
to decide upon the scientific merits of the nebular
hypothesis, we conceive that the final fate of this[150]
opinion cannot, in sound reason, affect at all the view
which we have been endeavouring to illustrate;—the
view of the universe as the work of a wise and
good Creator. Let it be supposed that the point to
which this hypothesis leads us, is the ultimate point
of physical science: that the farthest glimpse we can
obtain of the material universe by our natural faculties,
shows it to us occupied by a boundless abyss of
luminous matter: still we ask, how space came to be
thus occupied, how matter came to be thus luminous?
If we establish by physical proofs, that the first fact
which can be traced in the history of the world, is
that “there was light;” we shall still be led, even
by our natural reason, to suppose that before this
could occur, “God said, let there be light.”
</div></body></text></TEI>