<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="100">CHAPTER VII.
Application and Correction of the Oxygen
Theory.
SINCE a chemical theory, as
far as it is true, must enable us to obtain a true view of the
intimate composition of all bodies whatever, it will readily be
supposed that the new chemistry led to an immense number of analyses
and researches of various kinds. These it is not necessary to dwell
upon; nor will I even mention the names of any of the intelligent and
diligent men who have labored in this field. Perhaps one of the most
striking of such analyses was Davy’s decomposition of the earths and
alkalies into metallic bases and oxygen, in 1807 and 1808; thus
extending still further that analogy between the earths and the calces
of the metals, which had had so large a share in the formation of
chemical theories. This discovery, however, both in the means by which
it was made, and in the views to which it led, bears upon subjects
hereafter to be treated of.
The Lavoisierian theory also, wide as was the range of truth which
it embraced, required some limitation and correction. I do not now
283 speak of some
erroneous opinions entertained by the author of the theory; as, for
instance, that the heat produced in combustion, and even in
respiration, arose from the conversion of oxygen gas to a solid
consistence, according to the doctrine of latent heat. Such opinions
not being necessarily connected with the general idea of the theory,
need not here be considered. But the leading generalization of
Lavoisier, that acidification was always combination with
oxygen, was found untenable. The point on which the contest on this
subject took place was the constitution of the oxymuriatic and
muriatic acids;—as they had been termed by Berthollet,
from the belief that muriatic acid contained oxygen, and oxymuriatic a
still larger dose of oxygen. In opposition to this, a new doctrine was
put forward in 1809 by Gay-Lussac and Thenard in France, and by Davy
in England;—namely, that oxymuriatic acid was a simple
substance, which they termed chlorine, and that muriatic acid
was a combination of chlorine with hydrogen, which therefore was
called hydrochloric acid. It may be observed, that the point in
dispute in the controversy on this subject was nearly the same which
had been debated in the course of the establishment of the oxygen
theory; namely, whether in the formation of muriatic acid from
chlorine, oxygen is subtracted, or hydrogen added, and the water
concealed.
In the course of this dispute, it was allowed on both sides, that
the combination of dry muriatic acid and ammonia afforded an
experimentum crucis; since, if water was produced from these
elements, oxygen must have existed in the acid. Davy being at
Edinburgh in 1812, this experiment was made in the presence of several
eminent philosophers; and the result was found to be, that though a
slight dew appeared in the vessel, there was not more than might be
ascribed to unavoidable imperfection in the process, and certainly not
so much as the old theory of muriatic acid required. The new theory,
after this period, obtained a clear superiority in the minds of
philosophical chemists, and was further supported by new analogies.42
42 Paris, Life of Davy, i.
337.
For, the existence of one hydracid being thus established,
it was found that other substances gave similar combinations; and thus
chemists obtained the hydriodic, hydrofluoric, and
hydrobromic acids. These acids, it is to be observed, form
salts with bases, in the same manner as the oxygen acids do. The
analogy of the muriatic and fluoric compounds was first clearly urged
by a philosopher who was 284 not peculiarly engaged in chemical
research, but who was often distinguished by his rapid and happy
generalizations, M. Ampère. He supported this analogy by many
ingenious and original arguments, in letters written to Davy, while
that chemist was engaged in his researches on fluor spar, as Davy
himself declares.43
43 Paris, Life of Davy, i.
370.
Still further changes have been proposed, in that classification of
elementary substances to which the oxygen theory led. It has been held
by Berzelius and others, that other elements, as, for example,
sulphur, form salts with the alkaline and earthy metals,
rather than sulphurets. The character of these sulpho-salts,
however, is still questioned among chemists; and therefore it does not
become us to speak as if their place in history were settled. Of
course, it will easily be understood that, in the same manner in which
the oxygen theory introduced its own proper nomenclature, the
overthrow or material transformation of the theory would require a
change in the nomenclature; or rather, the anomalies which tended to
disturb the theory, would, as they were detected, make the theoretical
terms be felt as inappropriate, and would suggest the necessity of a
reformation in that respect. But the discussion of this point belongs
to a step of the science which is to come before us hereafter.
It may be observed, that in approaching the limits of this part of
our subject, as we are now doing, the doctrine of the combination of
acids and bases, of which we formerly traced the rise
and progress, is still assumed as a fundamental relation by which
other relations are tested. This remark connects the stage of
chemistry now under our notice with its earliest steps. But in order
to point out the chemical bearing of the next subjects of our
narrative, we may further observe, that metals, earths,
salts, are spoken of as known classes of substances; and
in like manner the newly-discovered elements, which form the last
trophies of chemistry, have been distributed into such classes
according to their analogies; thus potassium, sodium,
barium, have been asserted to be metals; iodine,
bromine, fluorine, have been arranged as analogical to
chlorine. Yet there is something vague and indefinite in the
boundaries of such classifications and analogies; and it is precisely
where this vagueness falls, that the science is still obscure or
doubtful. We are led, therefore, to see the dependence of Chemistry
upon Classification; and it is to Sciences of Classification which we
shall next proceed; as soon as we have noticed the most general views
285 which have been
given of chemical relations, namely, the views of the
electro-chemists.
But before we do this, we must look back upon a law which obtains
in the combination of elements, and which we have hitherto not stated;
although it appears, more than any other, to reveal to us the intimate
constitution of bodies, and to offer a basis for future
generalizations. I speak of the Atomic Theory, as it is usually
termed; or, as we might rather call it, the Doctrine of Definite,
Reciprocal, and Multiple Proportions.
</div></body></text></TEI>