<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="37">
[230]
CHAPTER V.

On Inductive Habits;
or, on the Impression produced
on Men’s Minds by discovering Laws of Nature.

The object of physical science is to discover such
laws and properties as those of which we have spoken
in the last chapter. In this task, undoubtedly a progress
has been made on which we may well look
with pleasure and admiration; yet we cannot hesitate
to confess that the extent of our knowledge on
such subjects bears no proportion to that of our ignorance.
Of the great and comprehensive laws which
rule over the widest provinces of natural phenomena,
few have yet been disclosed to us. And the names
of the philosophers, whose high office it has been to
detect such laws, are even yet far from numerous.
In looking back at the path by which science has
advanced to its present position, we see the names of
the great discoverers shine out like luminaries, few
and scattered along the line: by far the largest portion
of the space is occupied by those whose comparatively
humble office it was to verify, to develope,
to apply the general truths which the discoverers
brought to light.
It will readily be conceived that it is no easy matter,
if it be possible, to analyse the process of thought
by which laws of nature have thus been discovered;
a process which, as we have said, has been in so few
instances successfully performed. We shall not here
make any attempt at such an analysis. But without
this, we conceive it may be shown that the constitution
and employment of the mind on which such discoveries
depend, are friendly to that belief in a wise
and good Creator and Governor of the world, which
it has been our object to illustrate and confirm. And[231]
if it should appear that those who see further than
their fellows into the bearings and dependencies of
the material things and elements by which they are
surrounded, have also been, in almost every case,
earnest and forward in acknowledging the relation
of all things to a supreme intelligence and will; we
shall be fortified in our persuasion that the true
scientific perception of the general constitution of
the universe, and of the mode in which events are
produced and connected, is fitted to lead us to the
conception and belief of God.
Let us consider for a moment what takes place in
the mind of a student of nature when he attains to
the perception of a law previously unknown, connecting
the appearances which he has studied. A mass
of facts which before seemed incoherent and unmeaning,
assume, on a sudden, the aspect of connexion
and intelligible order. Thus, when Kepler discovered
the law which connects the periodic times with
the diameters of the planetary orbits; or, when Newton
showed how this and all other known mathematical
properties of the solar system were included in
the law of universal gravitation according to the inverse
square of the distance; particular circumstances
which, before, were merely matter of independent
record, became, from that time, indissolubly
conjoined by the laws so discovered. The separate
occurrences and facts, which might hitherto have
seemed casual and without reason, were now seen
to be all exemplifications of the same truth. The
change is like that which takes place when we attempt
to read a sentence written in difficult or imperfect
characters. For a time the separate parts
appear to be disjointed and arbitrary marks; the
suggestions of possible meanings, which succeed
each other in the mind, fail, as fast as they are tried,
in combining or accounting for these symbols: but
at last the true supposition occurs; some words are
found to coincide with the meaning thus assumed;
the whole line of letters appear to take definite[232]
shapes and to leap into their proper places; and the
truth of the happy conjecture seems to flash upon us
from every part of the inscription.
The discovery of laws of nature, truly and satisfactorily
connecting and explaining phenomena, of
which, before, the connexion and causes had been
unknown, displays much of a similar process, of obscurity
succeeded by evidence, of effort and perplexity
followed by conviction and repose. The
innumerable conjectures and failures, the glimpses
of light perpetually opening and as often clouded
over, the unwearied perseverance and inexhaustible
ingenuity exercised by Kepler in seeking for the
laws which he finally discovered, are, thanks to his
communicative disposition, curiously exhibited in his
works, and have been narrated by his biographers;
and such efforts and alternations, modified by character
and circumstances, must generally precede
the detection of any of the wider laws and dependencies
by which the events of the universe are regulated.
We may readily conceive the satisfaction
and delight with which, after this perplexity and
struggle, the discoverer finds himself in light and
tranquillity; able to look at the province of nature
which has been the subject of his study, and to read
there an intelligible connexion, a sufficing reason,
which no one before him had understood or apprehended.
This step so much resembles the mode in which
one intelligent being understands and apprehends the
conceptions of another, that we cannot be surprised
if those persons in whose minds such a process has
taken place, have been most ready to acknowledge the
existence and operation of a superintending intelligence,
whose ordinances it was their employment to
study. When they had just read a sentence of the
table of the laws of the universe, they could not
doubt whether it had had a legislator. When they
had deciphered there a comprehensive and substantial
truth, they could not believe that the letters had[233]
been thrown together by chance. They could not but
readily acknowledge that what their faculties had
enabled them to read, must have been written by
some higher and profounder mind. And accordingly,
we conceive it will be found, on examining the
works of those to whom we owe our knowledge of
the laws of nature, and especially of the wider and
more comprehensive laws, that such persons have
been strongly and habitually impressed with the persuasion
of a Divine Purpose and Power which had
regulated the events which they had attended to, and
ordained the laws which they had detected.
To those who have pursued science without reaching
the rank of discoverers;—who have possessed a
derivative knowledge of the laws of nature which
others had disclosed, and have employed themselves
in tracing the consequences of such laws, and systematizing
the body of truth thus produced, the above
description does not apply; and we have not therefore
in these cases the same ground for anticipating
the same frame of mind. If among men of science
of this class, the persuasion of a supreme Intelligence
has at some periods been less vivid and less
universal, than in that higher class of which we have
before spoken, the fact, so far as it has existed, may
perhaps be in some degree accounted for. But whether
the view which we have to give of the mental
peculiarities of men whose science is of this derivative
kind be well founded, and whether the account
we have above offered of that which takes place in
the minds of original discoverers of laws in scientific
researches be true, or not, it will probably be considered
a matter of some interest to point out historically
that in fact, such discoverers have been peculiarly
in the habit of considering the world as the
work of God. This we shall now proceed to do.
As we have already said, the names of great discoverers
are not very numerous. The sciences
which we may look upon as having reached or at
least approached their complete and finished form,[234]
are Mechanics, Hydrostatics, and Physical Astronomy.
Galileo is the father of modern Mechanics;
Copernicus, Kepler, and Newton are the great names
which mark the progress of Astronomy. Hydrostatics
shared in a great measure the fortunes of the
related science of Mechanics; Boyle and Pascal
were the persons mainly active in developing its
more peculiar principles. The other branches of
knowledge which belong to natural philosophy, as
Chemistry and Meteorology, are as yet imperfect,
and perhaps infant sciences; and it would be rash
to presume to select, in them, names of equal preeminence
with those above mentioned: but it may
not be difficult to show, with sufficient evidence, that
the effect of science upon the authors of science is,
in these subjects as in the former ones, far other
than to alienate their minds from religious trains of
thought, and a habit of considering the world as the
work of God.
We shall not dwell much on the first of the above
mentioned great names, Galileo; for his scientific
merit consisted rather in adopting the sound philosophy
of others, as in the case of the Copernican system,
and in combating prevalent errors, as in the
case of the Aristotelian doctrines concerning motion,
than in any marked and prominent discovery of new
principles. Moreover the mechanical laws which he
had a share in bringing to light, depending as they
did, rather on detached experiments and transient
facts, than on observation of the general course of
the universe, could not so clearly suggest any reflection
on the government of the world at that period,
as they did afterwards when Newton showed their
bearing on the cosmical system. Yet Galileo, as a
man of philosophical and inventive mind, who produced
a great effect on the progress of physical
knowledge, is a person whose opinions must naturally
interest us, engaged in our present course of
reasoning. There is in his writings little which bears
upon religious views, as there is in the nature of his[235]
works little to lead him to such subjects. Yet strong
expressions of piety are not wanting, both in his letters,
and in his published treatises. The persecution
which he underwent, on account of his writings in
favour of the Copernican system, was grounded, not
on his opposition to the general truths of natural religion,
which is our main concern at present, nor
even on any supposed rejection of any articles of
Christian faith, but on the alleged discrepancy between
his adopted astronomical views and the declarations
of scripture. Some of his remarks may
interest the reader.
In his third dialogue on the Copernican system he
has occasion to speak of the opinion which holds all
parts of the world to be framed for man’s use alone:
and to this he says, “I would that we should not so
shorten the arm of God in the government of human
affairs; but that we should rest in this, that we are
certain that God and nature are so occupied in the
government of human affairs, that they could not
more attend to us if they were charged with the
care of the human race alone.” In the same spirit,
when some objected to the asserted smallness of the
Medicean stars, or satellites of Jupiter, and urged
this as a reason why they were unworthy the regard
of philosophers, he replied that they are the works
of God’s power, the objects of His care, and therefore
may well be considered as sublime subjects for
man’s study.
In the Dialogues on Mechanics, there occur those
observations concerning the use of the air-bladder in
fishes, and concerning the adaptation of the size of
animals to the strength of the materials of which
they are framed, which have often since been adopted
by writers on the wisdom of Providence. The
last of the dialogues on the system of the world is
closed by a religious reflection, put in the mouth of
the interlocutor who usually expresses Galileo’s own
opinions. “While it is permitted us to speculate concerning
the constitution of the world, we are also[236]
taught (perhaps in order that the activity of the human
mind may not pause or languish) that our powers
do not enable us to comprehend the works of His
hands. May success therefore attend this intellectual
exercise, thus permitted and appointed for us;
by which we recognize and admire the greatness of
God the more, in proportion as we find ourselves the
less able to penetrate the profound abysses of his
wisdom.” And that this train of thought was habitual
to the philosopher we have abundant evidence
in many other parts of his writings. He had already
said in the same dialogue, “Nature (or God, as he
elsewhere speaks) employs means in an admirable
and inconceivable manner; admirable, that is, and
inconceivable to us, but not to her, who brings about
with consummate facility and simplicity things which
affect our intellect with infinite astonishment. That
which is to us most difficult to understand is to her
most easy to execute.”
The establishment of the Copernican and Newtonian
views of the motions of the solar system and
their causes, were probably the occasions on which
religious but unphilosophical men entertained the
strongest apprehensions that the belief in the government
of God may be weakened when we thus “thrust
some mechanic cause into his place.” It is therefore
fortunate that we can show, not only that this
ought not to occur, from the reason of the thing, but
also that in fact the persons who are the leading
characters in the progress of these opinions were
men of clear and fervent piety.
In the case of Copernicus himself it does not appear
that, originally, any apprehensions were entertained
of any dangerous discrepancy between his
doctrines and the truths of religion, either natural or
revealed. The work which contains these memorable
discoveries was addressed to Pope Paul III., the
head, at that time, (1543) of the religious world; and
was published, as the author states in the preface, at
the urgent entreaty of friends, one of whom was a[237]
cardinal, and another a bishop.[33] “I know,” he says,
“that the thoughts of a philosopher are far removed
from the judgment of the vulgar; since it is his study
to search out truth in all things, as far as that is permitted
by God to human reason.” And though the
doctrines are for the most part stated as portions of
a mathematical calculation, the explanation of the
arrangement by which the sun is placed in the centre
of the system is accompanied by a natural reflection
of a religious cast; “Who in this fair temple
would place this lamp in any other or better place
than there whence it may illuminate the whole?
We find then under this ordination an admirable
symmetry of the world, and a certain harmonious
connexion of the motion and magnitude of the orbs,
such as in any other way cannot be found. Thus
the progressions and regressions of the planets all
arise from the same cause, the motion of the earth.
And that no such movements are seen in the fixed
stars, argues their immense distance from us, which
causes the apparent magnitude of the earth’s annual
course to become evanescent. So great, in short,
is this divine fabric of the great and good God;”[34]
“this best and most regular artificer of the universe,”
as he elsewhere speaks.
Kepler was the person, who by further studying
“the connexion of the motions and magnitude of the
orbs,” to which Copernicus had thus drawn the attention
of the astronomers, detected the laws of this
connexion, and prepared the way for the discovery,
by Newton, of the mechanical laws and causes of
such motions. Kepler was a man of strong and lively
piety; and the exhortation which he addresses to[238]
his reader before entering on the exposition of some
of his discoveries, may be quoted not only for its
earnestness but its reasonableness also. “I beseech
my reader, that not unmindful of the divine goodness
bestowed on man, he do with me praise and celebrate
the wisdom and greatness of the Creator, which
I open to him from a more inward explication of the
form of the world, from a searching of causes, from
a detection of the errors of vision: and that thus, not
only in the firmness and stability of the earth he perceive
with gratitude the preservation of all living
things in nature as the gift of God, but also that in
its motion, so recondite, so admirable, he acknowledge
the wisdom of the Creator. But him who is too dull
to receive this science, or too weak to believe the
Copernican system without harm to his piety, him, I
say, I advise that, leaving the school of astronomy,
and condemning, if he please, any doctrines of the
philosophers, he follow his own path, and desist from
this wandering through the universe, and lifting up
his natural eyes, with which alone he can see, pour
himself out from his own heart in praise of God the
Creator; being certain that he gives no less worship
to God than the astronomer, to whom God has given
to see more clearly with his inward eye, and who,
for what he has himself discovered, both can and
will glorify God.”
The next great step in our knowledge of the universe,
the discovery of the mechanical causes by
which its motions are produced, and of their laws,
has in modern times sometimes been supposed, both
by the friends of religion and by others, to be unfavourable
to the impression of an intelligent first cause.
That such a supposition is founded in error we have
offered what appear to us insurmountable reasons for
believing. That in the mind of the great discoverer
of this mechanical cause, Newton, the impression of
a creating and presiding Deity was confirmed, not
shaken, by all his discoveries, is so well known that
it is almost superfluous to insist upon the fact. His[239]
views of the tendency of science invested it with no
dangers of this kind. “The business of natural philosophy
is,” he says, (Optics, Qu. 28,) “to argue from
phenomena without feigning hypotheses, and to deduce
cause from effects, till we come to the very first
cause, which is certainly not mechanical.” “Though
every true step made in this philosophy brings us not
immediately to the knowledge of the first cause, yet
it brings us nearer to it, and is on that account highly
to be valued.” The Scholium, or note, which concludes
his great work, the Principia, is a well known
and most striking evidence on this point, “This beautiful
system of sun, planets, and comets, could have
its origin in no other way than by the purpose and
command of an intelligent and powerful Being. He
governs all things, not as the soul of the world, but
as the lord of the universe. He is not only God, but
Lord or Governor. We know him only by his properties
and attributes, by the wise and admirable structure
of things around us, and by their final causes;
we admire him on account of his perfections, we
venerate and worship him on account of his government.”
Without making any further quotations, it must be
evident to the reader that the succession of great philosophers
through whom mankind have been led to
the knowledge of the greatest of scientific truths, the
law of universal gravitation, did, for their parts, see
the truths which they disclosed to men in such a light
that their religious feelings, their reference of the
world to an intelligent Creator and Preserver, their
admiration of his attributes, were exalted rather than
impaired by the insight which they obtained into the
structure of the universe.
Having shown this with regard to the most perfect
portion of human knowledge, our knowledge of the
motions of the solar system, we shall adduce a few
other passages, illustrating the prevalence of the
same fact in other departments of experimental
science; although, for reasons which have already[240]
been intimated, we conceive that sciences of experiment
do not conduct so obviously as sciences of observation
to the impression of a Divine Legislator
of the material world.
The science of Hydrostatics was constructed in a
great measure by the founders of the sister science
of Mechanics. Of those who were employed in experimentally
establishing the principles peculiarly
belonging to the doctrine of fluids, Pascal and Boyle
are two of the most eminent names. That these two
great philosophers were not only religious, but both
of them remarkable for their fervent and pervading
devotion, is too well known to be dwelt on. With
regard to Pascal, however, we ought not perhaps to
pass over an opinion of his, that the existence of
God cannot be proved from the external world. “I
do not undertake to prove this,” says he, “not only
because I do not feel myself sufficiently strong to find
in nature that which shall convince obstinate atheists,
but because such knowledge without Jesus Christ is
useless and steril.” It is obvious that such a state
of mind would prevent this writer from encouraging
or dwelling upon the grounds of natural religion;
while yet he himself is an example of that which we
wish to illustrate, that those who have obtained the
furthest insight into nature, have been in all ages
firm believers in God. “Nature,” he says, in another
place, “has perfections in order to show that she is
the image of God, and defects in order to show that
she is only his image.”[35]
Boyle was not only a most pious man as well as a
great philosopher, but he exerted himself very often
and earnestly in his writings to show the bearing
of his natural philosophy upon his views of the
Divine attributes, and of the government of the
world. Many of these dissertations convey trains of
thought and reasoning which have never been surpassed
for their combination of judicious sobriety in[241]
not pressing his arguments too far, with fervent devotion
in his conceptions of the Divine nature. As
examples of these merits, we might adduce almost
any portion of his tracts on these subjects; for instance,
his “Inquiry into the Final Causes of Natural
Things;” his “Free Inquiry into the Vulgar Notion
of Nature;” his “Christian Virtuoso;” and his essay
entitled “The High Veneration Man’s Intellect owes
to God.” It would be superfluous to quote at any
length from these works. We may observe, however,
that he notices that general fact which we are at
present employed in exemplifying, that “in almost all
ages and countries the generality of philosophers
and contemplative men were persuaded of the existence
of a Deity from the consideration of the phenomena
of the universe; whose fabric and conduct
they rationally concluded could not justly be ascribed
either to chance or to any other cause than a
Divine Being.” And in speaking of the religious
uses of science, he says: “Though I am willing to
grant that some impressions of God’s wisdom are so
conspicuous that even a superficial philosopher may
thence infer that the author of such works must be a
wise agent; yet how wise an agent he has in these
works expressed himself to be, none but an experimental
philosopher can well discern. And ’tis not by
a slight survey, but by a diligent and skilful scrutiny,
of the works of God, that a man must be, by a rational
and affective conviction, engaged to acknowledge
that the author of nature ‘is wonderful in
counsel, and excellent in working.’”
After the mechanical properties of fluids, the laws
of the operation of the chemical and physical properties
of the elements about us, offer themselves to
our notice. The relations of heat and of moisture in
particular, which play so important a part, as we
have seen, in the economy of our world, have been
the subject of various researches; and they have led
to views of the operation of such agents, some of
which we have endeavoured to present to the reader,[242]
and to point out the remarkable arrangements by
which their beneficial operation is carried on. That
the discoverers of the laws by which such operations
are regulated, were not insensible to the persuasion
of a Divine care and contrivance which those arrangements
suggest, is what we should expect, in
agreement with what we have already said, and it is
what we find. Among the names of the philosophers
to whom we owe our knowledge on these subjects,
there are none greater than those of Black, the discoverer
of the laws of latent heat, and Dalton, who
first gave us a true view of the mode in which watery
vapour exists and operates in the atmosphere. With
regard to the former of these philosophers, we shall
quote Dr. Thomson’s account of the views which the
laws of latent heat suggested to the discoverer.[36]
“Dr. Black quickly perceived the vast importance of
this discovery, and took a pleasure in laying before
his students a view of the beneficial effects of this
habitude of heat in the economy of nature. During
the summer season a vast magazine of heat is accumulated
in the water, which by gradually emerging
during congelation serves to temper the cold of winter.
Were it not for this accumulation of heat in
water and other bodies, the sun would no sooner go
a few degrees to the south of the equator than we
should feel all the horrors of winter.”
In the same spirit are Mr. Dalton’s reflections,
after pointing out the laws which regulate the balance
of evaporation and rain,[37] which he himself first
clearly explained. “It is scarcely possible,” says he,
“to contemplate without admiration the beautiful
system of nature by which the surface of the earth
is continually supplied with water, and that unceasing
circulation of a fluid so essentially necessary to
the very being of the animal and vegetable kingdom
takes place.”
[243]
Such impressions appear thus to rise irresistibly
in the breasts of men, when they obtain a sight, for
the first time, of the varied play and comprehensive
connexions of the laws by which the business of the
material world is carried on and its occurrences
brought to pass. To dwell upon or develope such
reflections is not here our business. Their general
prevalence in the minds of those to whom these first
views of new truths are granted, has been, we trust,
sufficiently illustrated. Nor are the names adduced
above, distinguished as they are, brought forwards
as authorities merely. We do not claim for the
greatest discoverers in the realms of science any
immunity from error. In their general opinions they
may, as others may, judge or reason ill. The articles
of their religious belief may be as easily and as
widely as of other men’s, imperfect, perverted, unprofitable.
But on this one point, the tendency of
our advances in scientific knowledge of the universe
to lead us up to a belief in a most wise maker and
master of the universe, we conceive that they who
make these advances, and who feel, as an original
impression, that which others feel only by receiving
their teaching, must be looked to with a peculiar
attention and respect. And what their impressions
have commonly been, we have thus endeavoured to
show.
</div></body></text></TEI>