<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="125">CHAPTER III.
Discovery of the Motion of the Chyle, and consequent
Speculations.

Sect. 1.—The Discovery of the Motion
of the Chyle.
IT may have been observed in
the previous course of this History of the Sciences, that the
discoveries in each science have a peculiar physiognomy: something of
a common type may be traced in the progress of each of the theories
belonging to the same department of knowledge. We may notice something
of this common form in the various branches of physiological
speculation. In most, or all of them, we have, as we have noticed the
case to be with respect to the circulation of the blood, clear and
certain discoveries of mechanical and chemical processes, succeeded by
speculations far more obscure, doubtful, and vague, respecting the
relation of these changes to the laws of life. This feature in the
history of physiology may be further instanced, (it shall be done very
briefly), in one or two other cases. And we may observe, that the
lesson which we are to collect from this narrative, is by no means
that we are to confine ourselves to the positive discovery, and reject
all the less clear and certain speculations. To do this, would be to
lose most of the chances of ulterior progress; for though it may be,
that our conceptions of the nature of organic life are not yet
sufficiently precise and steady to become the guides to positive
inductive truths, still the only way in which these peculiar
physiological ideas can be made more distinct and precise, and thus
brought more nearly into a scientific form, is by this struggle with
our ignorance or imperfect knowledge. This is the lesson we have
learnt from the history of physical astronomy and other sciences. We
must strive to refer facts which are known and understood, to higher
principles, of which we cannot doubt the existence, and of which, in
some degree, we can see the place; however dim and shadowy may be the
glimpses we have hitherto been able to obtain of their forms. We may
often fail in such attempts, but without the attempt we can never
succeed. 453
That the food is received into the stomach, there undergoes a
change of its consistence, and is then propelled along the intestines,
are obvious facts in the animal economy. But a discovery made in the
course of the seventeenth century brought into clearer light the
sequel of this series of processes, and its connexion with other
functions. In the year 1622, Asellius or Aselli39 discovered
certain minute vessels, termed lacteals, which absorb a white
liquid (the chyle) from the bowels, and pour it into the blood.
These vessels had, in fact, been discovered by Eristratus, in the
ancient world,40 in the time of Ptolemy; but Aselli was
the first modern who attended to them. He described them in a treatise
entitled De Venis Lacteis, cum figuris elegantissimis, printed
at Milan in 1627, the year after the death of the author. The work is
remarkable as the first which exhibits colored anatomical
figures; the arteries and veins are represented in red, the lacteals
in black.
39 Mayo, Physiology, p.
156.
40 Cuv. Hist. Sc. p. 50.
Eustachius,41 at an earlier period, had described (in
the horse) the thoracic duct by which the chyle is poured into the
subclavian vein, on the right side of the neck. But this description
did not excite so much notice as to prevent its being forgotten, and
rediscovered in 1550, after the knowledge of the circulation of the
blood had given more importance to such a discovery. Up to this
time,42 it had been supposed that the lacteals
carried the chyle to the liver, and that the blood was manufactured
there. This opinion had prevailed in all the works of the ancients and
moderns; its falsity was discovered by Pecquet, a French physician,
and published in 1651, in his New Anatomical Experiments; in
which are discovered a receptacle of the chyle, unknown till then, and
the vessel which conveys it to the subclavian vein. Pecquet himself
and other anatomists, soon connected this discovery with the doctrine,
then recently promulgated, of the circulation of the blood. In 1665,
these vessels, and the lymphatics which are connected with
them, were further illustrated by Ruysch in his exhibition of their
valves. (Dilucidatio valvularum in vasis lymphaticis et
lacteis.)
41 Cuv. Hist. p. 34.
42 Ib. p. 365.
Sect. 2.—The Consequent Speculations. Hypotheses
of Digestion.
Thus it was shown that
aliments taken into the stomach are, by its action, made to produce
chyme; from the chyme, gradually changed 454 in its progress
through the intestines, chyle is absorbed by the lacteals; and
this, poured into the blood by the thoracic duct, repairs the waste
and nourishes the growth of the animal. But by what powers is the food
made to undergo these transformations? Can we explain them on
mechanical or on chemical principles? Here we come to a part of
physiology less certain than the discovery of vessels, or of the
motion of fluids. We have a number of opinions on this subject, but no
universally acknowledged truth. We have a collection of Hypotheses
of Digestion and Nutrition.
I shall confine myself to the former class; and without dwelling
long upon these, I shall mention some of them. The philosophers of the
Academy del Cimento, and several others, having experimented on
the stomach of gallinaceous birds, and observed the astonishing force
with which it breaks and grinds substances, were led to consider the
digestion which takes place in the stomach as a kind of
trituration.43 Other writers thought it was more
properly described as fermentation; others again spoke of it as
a putrefaction. Varignon gave a merely physical account of the
first part of the process, maintaining that the division of the
aliments was the effect of the disengagement of the air introduced
into the stomach, and dilated by the heat of the body. The opinion
that digestion is a solution of the food by the gastric juice
has been more extensively entertained.
43 Bourdon, Physiol. Comp. p.
514.
Spallanzani and others made many experiments on this subject. Yet
it is denied by the best physiologists, that the changes of digestion
can be adequately represented as chemical changes only. The nerves of
the stomach (the pneumo-gastric) are said to be essential to
digestion. Dr. Wilson Philip has asserted that the influence of these
nerves, when they are destroyed, may be replaced by a galvanic
current.44 This might give rise to a supposition
that digestion depends on galvanism. Yet we cannot doubt that all
these hypotheses,—mechanical, physical, chemical,
galvanic—are altogether insufficient. “The stomach must have,”
as Dr. Prout says,45 “the power of 455 organizing and vitalizing the different
elementary substances. It is impossible to imagine that this
organizing agency of the stomach can be chemical. This agency is
vital, and its nature completely unknown.”
44 Müller (Manual of
Physiology, B. iii. Sect. 1, Chap. iii.) speaks of Dr. Wilson
Philip’s assertion that the nerves of the stomach being cut, and a
galvanic current kept up in them, digestion is still accomplished. He
states that he and other physiologists have repeated such experiments
on an extensive scale, and have found no effect of this kind.
45 Bridgewater Tr. p.
493.
</div></body></text></TEI>