<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Chambers Robert</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="9">p. 116ERA
OF THE CRETACEOUS FORMATION.
The record of this period consists
of a series of strata, in which chalk beds make a conspicuous
appearance, and which is therefore called the cretaceous system
or formation.  In England, a long stripe, extending from
Yorkshire to Kent, presents the cretaceous beds upon the surface,
generally lying conformably upon the oolite, and in many
instances rising into bold escarpments towards the west. 
The celebrated cliffs of Dover are of this formation.  It
extends into northern France, and thence north-westward into
Germany, whence it is traced into Scandinavia and Russia. 
The same system exists in North America, and probably in other
parts of the earth not yet geologically investigated.  Being
a marine deposit, it establishes that seas existed at the time of
its formation on the tracts occupied by it, while some of its
organic remains prove that, in the neighbourhood of those seas,
there were tracts of dry land.
The cretaceous formation in England presents beds chiefly
sandy in the lowest part, chiefly clayey in the middle, and
chiefly of chalk in the upper part, the chalk beds being never
absent, which some of the lower are in several places.  In
the vale of the Mississippi, again, the true chalk is wholly, or
all but wholly absent.  In the south of England, the lower
beds are, (reckoning from the lowest upwards), 1. 
Shankland or greensand, “a triple alternation
of sands and sandstones with clay;” 2.  Galt, “a
stiff blue or black clay, abounding in shells, which frequently
possess a pearly lustre;” 3.  Hard chalk;
4.  Chalk with flints; these two last being generally white,
but in some districts red, and in others yellow.  The whole
are, in England, about 1200 feet thick, shewing the considerable
depths of the ocean in which the deposits were made.
Chalk is a carbonate of lime, and the manner of its production
in such vast quantities was long a subject of speculation among
geologists.  Some light seemed to be thrown upon the subject
a few years ago, when it was observed, that the detritus of coral
reefs in the present tropical seas gave a powder,
undistinguishable, when dried, from ordinary chalk.  It then
appeared likely that the chalk beds were the detritus of the
corals which were in the oceans of that era.  Mr. Darwin,
who made some curious inquiries on this point, further suggested,
that the matter might have intermediately passed through the
bodies of worms and fish, such as feed on the corals of the
present day, and in whose stomachs he has found impure
chalk.  This, however, cannot be a full explanation of the
production of chalk, if we admit some more recent discoveries of
Professor Ehrenberg.  That master of microscopic
investigation announces, that chalk is composed partly of
“inorganic particles of irregular elliptical structure and
granular slaty disposition,” and partly of shells of
inconceivable minuteness, “varying from the one-twelfth to
the two hundred and eighty-eighth part of a line”—a
cubic inch of the substance containing above ten millions of
them!  The chalk of the north of Europe contains, he says, a
larger proportion of the inorganic matter; that of the south, a
larger proportion of the organic matter, being in some instances
almost entirely composed of it.  He has been able to
classify many of these creatures, some of them being allied to
the nautili, nummuli, cyprides, &c.  The shells of some
are calcareous, of others siliceous.  M. Ehrenberg has
likewise detected microscopic sea-plants in the chalk.
The distinctive feature of the uppermost chalk beds in
England, is the presence of flint nodules.  These are
generally disposed in layers parallel to each other.  It was
readily presumed by geologists that these masses were formed by a
chemical aggregation of particles of silica, originally held in
solution in the mass of the chalk.  But whence the silica in
a substance so different from it?  Ehrenberg suggests that
it is composed of the siliceous coverings of a portion of the
microscopic creatures, whose shells he has in other instances
detected in their original condition.  It is remarkable that
the chalk with flint abounds in the north of Europe; that
without flints in the south; while in the northern chalk
siliceous animalcules are wanting, and in the southern present in
great quantities.  The conclusion seems but natural, that in
the one case the siliceous exuviæ have been left in their
original form; in the other dissolved chemically, and aggregated
on the common principle of chemical affinity into nodules of
flint, probably concentrating, in every instance, upon a piece of
decaying organic matter, as has been the case with the nodules of
ironstone in the earlier rocks, and the spherules of the
oolite.
What is more remarkable, M. Ehrenberg has ascertained that at
least fifty-seven species of the microscopic animals of the
chalk, being infusoria and calcareous-shelled polythalamia, are
still found living in various parts of the earth.  These
species are the most abundant in the rock.  Singly they are
the most unimportant of all animals, but in the mass, forming as
they do such enormous strata over a large part of the
earth’s surface, they have an importance greatly exceeding
that of the largest and noblest of the beasts of the field. 
Moreover, these species have a peculiar interest, as the only
specific types of that early age which are reproduced in the
present day.  Species of sea mollusks, of reptiles, and of
mammifers, have been changed again and again, since the
cretaceous era; and it is not till a long subsequent age that we
find the first traces of any other of even the humblest species
which now exist; but here have these humble infusoria and
polythalamia kept their place on earth through all its
revolutions since that time,—are we to say, safe in their
very humility, which might adapt them to a greater variety of
circumstances than most other animals, or are we required to look
for some other explanation of the phenomenon?
All the ordinary and more observable orders of the inhabitants
of the sea, except the cetacea, have been found in the cretaceous
formation—zoophytes, radiaria, mollusks, crustacea, (in
great variety of species,) and fishes in smaller variety. 
In Europe, remains of the marine saurians have been found; they
may be presumed to have become extinct in that part of the globe
before this time, their place and destructive office being
perhaps supplied by cartilaginous fishes, of which the teeth are
found in great quantities.  In America, however, remains of
the plesiosaurus have been discovered in this part of the
stratified series.  The reptiles, too, so numerous in the
two preceding periods, appear to have now much diminished in
numbers.  One, entitled the mosæsaurus, seems to have
held an intermediate place between the monitor and iguana, and to
have been about twenty-five feet long, with a tail calculated to
assist it powerfully in swimming.  Crocodiles and turtles
existed, and amongst the fishes were some of a saurian
character.
Fuci abounded in the seas of this era.  Confervæ
are found enclosed in flints.  Of terrestrial vegetation, as
of terrestrial animals, the specimens in the European area are
comparatively rare, rendering it probable that there was no dry
land near.  The remains are chiefly of ferns, conifers, and
cycadeæ, but in the two former cases we have only cones and
leaves.  There have been discovered many pieces of wood,
containing holes drilled by the teredo, and thus shewing that
they had been long drifted about in the ocean before being
entombed at the bottom.
The series in America corresponding to this, entitled the
ferruginous sand formation, presents fossils generally identical
with those of Europe, not excepting the fragments of drilled
wood; shewing that, in this, as in earlier ages, there was a
parity of conditions for animal life over a vast tract of the
earth’s surface.  To European reptiles, the American
formation adds a gigantic one, styled the saurodon, from the
lizard-like character of its teeth.
We have seen that footsteps of birds are considered to have
been discovered in America, in the new red sandstone.  Some
similar isolated phenomena occur in the subsequent
formations.  Mr. Mantell discovered some bones of birds,
apparently waders, in the Wealden.  The immediate connexion
of that set of birds with land, may account, of course, for their
containing a terrestrial organic relic, which the marine beds
above and below did not possess.  In the slate of Glarus, in
Switzerland, corresponding to the English galt, in the chalk
formation, the remains of a bird have been found.  From a
chalk bed near Maidstone, have likewise been extracted some
remains of a bird, supposed to have been of the long-winged
swimmer family, and equal in size to the albatross.  These,
it must be owned, are less strong traces of the birds than we
possess of the reptiles and other tribes; but it must be
remembered, that the evidence of fossils, as to the absence of
any class of animals from a certain period of the earth’s
history, can never be considered as more than negative. 
Animals, of which we find no remains in a particular formation,
may, nevertheless, have lived at the time, and it may have only
been from unfavourable circumstances that their remains have not
been preserved for our inspection.  The single circumstance
of their being little liable to be carried down into seas, might
be the cause of their non-appearance in our quarries.  There
is at the same time a limit to uncertainty on this point. 
We see, from what remains have been found in the whole series, a
clear progress throughout, from humble to superior types of
being.  Hence we derive a light as to what animals may have
existed at particular times, which is in some measure independent
of the specialties of fossilology.  The birds are below the
mammalia in the animal scale; and therefore they may be supposed
to have existed about the time of the new red sandstone and
oolite, although we find but slight traces of them in those
formations, and, it may be said, till a considerably later
period.</div></body></text></TEI>