<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="34">
CHAPTER II.

On the Vastness of the Universe.

1. The aspect of the world, even without any of
the peculiar lights which science throws upon it, is
fitted to give us an idea of the greatness of the power
by which it is directed and governed, far exceeding
any notions of power and greatness which are suggested
by any other contemplation. The number of
human beings who surround us—the various conditions
requisite for their life, nutrition, well-being, all
fulfilled;—the way in which these conditions are
modified, as we pass in thought to other countries,
by climate, temperament, habit;—the vast amount
of the human population of the globe thus made up;—yet
man himself but one among almost endless tribes
of animals;—the forest, the field, the desert, the air,
the ocean, all teeming with creatures whose bodily
wants are as carefully provided for as his;—the sun,
the clouds, the winds, all attending, as it were, on
these organized beings;—a host of beneficent energies,
unwearied by time and succession, pervading
every corner of the earth;—this spectacle cannot
but give the contemplator a lofty and magnificent[206]
conception of the Author of so vast a work, of the
Ruler of so wide and rich an empire, of the Provider
for so many and varied wants, the Director and Adjuster
of such complex and jarring interests.
But when we take a more exact view of this spectacle,
and aid our vision by the discoveries which
have been made of the structure and extent of the
universe, the impression is incalculably increased.
The number and variety of animals, the exquisite
skill displayed in their structure, the comprehensive
and profound relations by which they are connected,
far exceed any thing which we could in any degree
have imagined. But the view of the universe expands
also on another side. The earth, the globular
body thus covered with life, is not the only globe in
the universe. There are, circling about our own sun,
six others, so far as we can judge, perfectly analogous
in their nature: besides our moon and other bodies
analogous to it. No one can resist the temptation to
conjecture, that these globes, some of them much
larger than our own, are not dead and barren;—that
they are, like ours, occupied with organization, life,
intelligence. To conjecture is all that we can do,
yet even by the perception of such a possibility, our
view of the kingdom of nature is enlarged and elevated.
The outermost of the planetary globes of
which we have spoken is so far from the sun, that
the central luminary must appear to the inhabitants
of that planet, if any there are, no larger than Venus
does to us; and the length of their year will be
eighty-two of ours.
But astronomy carries us still onwards. It teaches
us that, with the exception of the planets already
mentioned, the stars which we see have no immediate
relation to our system. The obvious supposition
is that they are of the nature and order of our
sun: the minuteness of their apparent magnitude
agrees, on this supposition, with the enormous and
almost inconceivable distance which, from all the
measurements of astronomers, we are led to attribute[207]
to them. If then these are suns, they may, like our
sun, have planets revolving round them; and these
may, like our planet, be the seats of vegetable and
animal and rational life:—we may thus have in the
universe worlds, no one knows how many, no one
can guess how varied:—but however many, however
varied, they are still but so many provinces in the
same empire, subject to common rules, governed by
a common power.
But the stars which we see with the naked eye are
but a very small portion of those which the telescope
unveils to us. The most imperfect telescope
will discover some that are invisible without it; the
very best instrument perhaps does not show us the
most remote. The number which crowds some parts
of the heavens is truly marvellous. Dr. Herschel
calculated that a portion of the milky way, about ten
degrees long and two and a half broad, contained
two hundred and fifty-eight thousand. In a sky so
occupied, the moon would eclipse two thousand of
such stars at once.
We learn too from the telescope that even in this
province the variety of nature is not exhausted. Not
only do the stars differ in colour and appearance, but
some of them grow periodically fainter and brighter,
as if they were dark on one side, and revolved on
their axes. In other cases two stars appear close to
each other, and in some of these cases it has been
clearly established, that the two have a motion of
revolution about each other; thus exhibiting an arrangement
before unguessed, and giving rise, possibly,
to new conditions of worlds. In other instances
again, the telescope shows, not luminous points, but
extended masses of dilute light, like bright clouds,
hence called nebulæ. Some have supposed (as we
have noticed in the last book) that such nebulæ by
further condensation might become suns; but for
such opinions we have nothing but conjecture. Some
stars again have undergone permanent changes, or
have absolutely disappeared, as the celebrated star
of 1572, in the constellation Cassiopea.
[208]
If we take the whole range of created objects in
our own system, from the sun down to the smallest
animalcule, and suppose such a system, or something
in some way analogous to it, to be repeated for each
of the millions of stars thus revealed to us, we have
a representation of the material part of the universe,
according to a view which many minds receive as a
probable one; and referring this aggregate of systems
to the Author of the universe, as in our own
system we have found ourselves led to do, we have
thus an estimate of the extent to which his creative
energy would thus appear to have been exercised in
the material world.
If we consider further the endless and admirable
contrivances and adaptations which philosophers
and observers have discovered in every portion of
our own system, every new step of our knowledge
showing us something new in this respect; and if we
combine this consideration with the thought how
small a portion of the universe our knowledge includes,
we shall, without being able at all to discern
the extent of the skill and wisdom thus displayed, see
something of the character of the design, and of the
copiousness and ampleness of the means which the
scheme of the world exhibits. And when we see that
the tendency of all the arrangements which we can
comprehend is to support the existence, to develope
the faculties, to promote the well-being of these countless
species of creatures; we shall have some impression
of the beneficence and love of the Creator,
as manifested in the physical government of his
creation.
2. It is extremely difficult to devise any means of
bringing before a common apprehension the scale
on which the universe is constructed, the enormous
proportion which the larger dimensions bear to the
smaller, and the amazing number of steps from large
to smaller, or from small to larger, which the consideration
of it offers. The following comparative representations[209]
may serve to give the reader to whom
the subject is new some idea of these steps.
If we suppose the earth to be represented by a
globe a foot in diameter, the distance of the sun from
the earth will be about two miles; the diameter of
the sun, on the same supposition, will be something
above one hundred feet, and consequently his bulk
such as might be made up of two hemispheres, each
about the size of the dome of St. Paul’s. The moon
will be thirty feet from us, and her diameter three
inches, about that of a cricket ball. Thus the sun
would much more than occupy all the space within
the moon’s orbit. On the same scale, Jupiter would
be above ten miles from the sun, and Uranus forty.
We see then how thinly scattered through space are
the heavenly bodies. The fixed stars would be at an
unknown distance, but, probably, if all distances were
thus diminished, no star would be nearer to such a
one-foot earth, than the moon now is to us.
On such a terrestrial globe the highest mountains
would be about an eightieth of an inch high, and
consequently only just distinguishable. We may
imagine therefore how imperceptible would be the
largest animals. The whole organized covering of
such a globe would be quite undiscoverable by the
eye, except perhaps by colour, like the bloom on a
plum.
In order to restore this earth and its inhabitants to
their true dimensions, we must magnify them forty
millions of times; and to preserve the proportions,
we must increase equally the distances of the sun
and of the stars from us. They seem thus to pass
off into infinity; yet each of them thus removed, has
its system of mechanical and perhaps of organic processes
going on upon its surface.
But the arrangements of organic life which we
can see with the naked eye are few, compared with
those which the microscope detects. We know that
we may magnify objects thousands of times, and still
discover fresh complexities of structure; if we suppose,[210]
therefore, that we increase every particle of
matter in our universe in such a proportion, in length,
breadth, and thickness, we may conceive that we
tend thus to bring before our apprehension a true
estimate of the quantity of organized adaptations
which are ready to testify the extent of the Creator’s
power.
3. The other numerical quantities which we have
to consider in the phenomena of the universe are on
as gigantic a scale as the distances and sizes. By
the rotation of the earth on its axis, the parts of the
equator move at the rate of a thousand miles an hour,
and the portions of the earth’s surface which are in
our latitude, at about six hundred. The former velocity
is nearly that with which a cannon ball is discharged
from the mouth of a gun; but, large as it is,
it is inconsiderable compared with the velocity of
the earth in its orbit about the sun. This latter velocity
is sixty-five times the former. By the rotatory
motion of the earth, a point of its surface is carried
sometimes forwards and sometimes backwards with
regard to the annual progression; but in consequence
of the great predominance of the latter velocity in
amount, the former scarcely affects it either way.
And even the latter velocity is inconsiderable compared
with that of light; which comparison, however,
we shall not make; since, according to the
theory we have considered as most probable, the
motion of light is not a transfer of matter but of motion
from one part of space to another.
The extent of the scale of density of different substances
has already been mentioned; gold is twenty
times as heavy as water; air is eight hundred and
thirty times lighter, steam eight thousand times lighter
than water; the luminiferous ether is incomparably
rarer than steam: and this is true of the matter of
light, whether we adopt the undulatory theory or
any other.
4. The above statements are vast in amount, and
almost oppressive to our faculties. They belong to[211]
the measurement of the powers which are exerted
in the universe, and of the spaces through which
their efficacy reaches (for the most distant bodies
are probably connected both by gravity and light.)
But these estimates cannot be said so much to give
us any notion of the powers of the Deity, as to correct
the errors we should fall into by supposing his
powers at all to resemble ours:—by supposing that
numbers, and spaces, and forces, and combinations,
which would overwhelm us, are any obstacle to the
arrangements which his plan requires. We can easily
understand that to an intelligence surpassing
ours in degree only, that may be easy which is impossible
to us. The child who cannot count beyond
four, the savage who has no name for any number
above five, cannot comprehend the possibility of dealing
with thousands and millions: yet a little additional
developement of the intellect makes such numbers
manageable and conceivable. The difficulty which
appears to reside in numbers and magnitudes and
stages of subordination, is one produced by judging
from ourselves—by measuring with our own sounding
line; when that reaches no bottom, the ocean
appears unfathomable. Yet in fact, how is a hundred
millions of miles a great distance? how is a
hundred millions of times a great ratio? Not in itself:
this greatness is no quality of the numbers which
can be proved like their mathematical properties; on
the contrary, all that absolutely belongs to number,
space, and ratio, must, we know demonstrably, be
equally true of the largest and the smallest. It is
clear that the greatness of these expressions of measure
has reference to our faculties only. Our astonishment
and embarrassment take for granted the
limits of our own nature. We have a tendency to treat
a difference of degree and of addition, as if it were
a difference of kind and of transformation. The existence
of the attributes, design, power, goodness, is
a matter depending on obvious grounds: about these
qualities there can be no mistake: if we can know[212]
any thing, we can know these attributes when we
see them. But the extent, the limits of such attributes
must be determined by their effects; our knowledge
of their limits by what we see of the effects.
Nor is any extent, any amount of power and goodness
improbable beforehand: we know that these
must be great, we cannot tell how great. We should
not expect beforehand to find them bounded; and
therefore when the boundless prospect opens before
us, we may be bewildered, but we have no reason to
be shaken in our conviction of the reality of the cause
from which their effects proceed: we may feel ourselves
incapable of following the train of thought,
and may stop, but we have no rational motive for
quitting the point which we have thus attained in
tracing the Divine Perfections.
On the contrary, those magnitudes and proportions
which leave our powers of conception far behind;—that
ever-expanding view which is brought
before us, of the scale and mechanism, the riches
and magnificence, the population and activity of the
universe;—may reasonably serve, not to disturb,
but to enlarge and elevate our conceptions of the
Maker and Master of all; to feed an ever-growing
admiration of His wonderful nature; and to excite
a desire to be able to contemplate more steadily and
conceive less inadequately the scheme of his government
and the operation of his power.
</div></body></text></TEI>