<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="31">CHAPTER XXXI.
CAUSES OF EARTHQUAKES AND VOLCANOES.
Intimate connection between the causes of volcanoes and earthquakes—Supposed
original state of fusion of the planet—Universal fluidity not proved by spheroidal
figure of the earth—Attempt to calculate the thickness of the solid crust
of the earth by precessional motion—Heat in mines increasing with the depth—Objections
to the supposed intense heat of a central fluid—Whether chemical
changes may produce volcanic heat—Currents of electricity circulating in the
earth's crust.
It will hardly be questioned, after the description before given of the
phenomena of earthquakes and volcanoes, that both of these agents have,
to a certain extent, a common origin; and I may now, therefore, proceed
to inquire into their probable causes. But first, it may be well to
recapitulate some of those points of relation and analogy which lead
naturally to the conclusion that they spring from a common source.
The regions convulsed by violent earthquakes include within them
the site of all the active volcanoes. Earthquakes, sometimes local, sometimes
extending over vast areas, often precede volcanic eruptions. The
subterranean movement and the eruption return again and again, at
irregular intervals of time, and with unequal degrees of force, to the
same spots. The action of either may continue for a few hours, or for
several consecutive years. Paroxysmal convulsions are usually followed,
in both cases, by long periods of tranquillity. Thermal and mineral
springs are abundant in countries of earthquakes and active volcanoes.
Lastly, hot springs situated in districts considerably distant from volcanic
vents have been observed to have their temperature suddenly
raised, and the volume of their water augmented, by subterranean movements.
All these appearances are evidently more or less connected with the
passage of heat from the interior of the earth to the surface; and where
there are active volcanoes, there must exist, at some unknown depth below,
enormous masses of matter intensely heated, and, in many instances,
in a constant state of fusion. We have first, then, to inquire, whence is
this heat derived?
It has long been a favorite conjecture, that the whole of our planet
was originally in a state of igneous fusion, and that the central parts
still retain a great portion of their primitive heat. Some have imagined,
with the late Sir W. Herschel, that the elementary matter of the earth
may have been first in a gaseous state, resembling those nebulæ which
we behold in the heavens, and which are of dimensions so vast, that some
of them would fill the orbits of the remotest planets of our system. The
increased power of the telescope has of late years resolved the greater
number of these nebulous appearances into clusters of stars, but so long
534
as they were confidently supposed to consist of aeriform matter it was a
favorite conjecture that they might, if concentrated, form solid spheres;
and it was also imagined that the evolution of heat, attendant on condensation,
might retain the materials of the new globes in a state of
igneous fusion.
Without dwelling on such speculations, which can only have a distant
bearing on geology, we may consider how far the spheroidal form
of the earth affords sufficient ground for presuming that its primitive
condition was one of universal fluidity. The discussion of this question
would be superfluous, were the doctrine of original fluidity less popular;
for it may well be asked, why the globe should be supposed to have
had a pristine shape different from the present one?—why the terrestrial
materials, when first called into existence, or assembled together
in one place, should not have been subject to rotation, so as to
assume at once that form which alone could retain their several parts in
a state of equilibrium?
Let us, however, concede that the statical figure may be a modification
of some other pre-existing form, and suppose the globe to have been
at first a perfect and quiescent sphere, covered with a uniform ocean—what
would happen when it was made to turn round on its axis with its
present velocity? This problem has been considered by Playfair in his
Illustrations, and he has decided, that if the surface of the earth, as laid
down in Hutton's theory, has been repeatedly changed by the transportation
of the detritus of the land to the bottom of the sea, the figure of
the planet must in that case, whatever it may have been originally, be
brought at length to coincide with the spheroid of equilibrium.742 Sir
John Herschel also, in reference to the same hypothesis, observes, "a
centrifugal force would in that case be generated, whose general tendency
would be to urge the water at every point of the surface to recede
from the axis. A rotation might indeed be conceived so swift as to flirt
the whole ocean from the surface, like water from a mop. But this would
require a far greater velocity than what we now speak of. In the case
supposed, the weight of the water would still keep it on the earth; and
the tendency to recede from the axis could only be satisfied therefore by
the water leaving the poles, and flowing towards the equator; there
heaping itself up in a ridge, and being retained in opposition to its weight
or natural tendency towards the centre by the pressure thus caused.
This, however, could not take place without laying dry the polar regions,
so that protuberant land would appear at the poles, and a zone of ocean
be disposed around the equator. This would be the first or immediate
effect. Let us now see what would afterwards happen if things were
allowed to take their natural course.
"The sea is constantly beating on the land, grinding it down, and
scattering its worn-off particles and fragments, in the state of sand and
pebbles, over its bed. Geological facts afford abundant proof that the
535
existing continents have all of them undergone this process even more
than once, and been entirely torn in fragments, or reduced to powder,
and submerged and reconstructed. Land, in this view of the subject,
loses its attribute of fixity. As a mass it might hold together in opposition
to forces which the water freely obeys; but in its state of successive
or simultaneous degradation, when disseminated through the water,
in the state of sand or mud, it is subject to all the impulses of that fluid.
In the lapse of time, then, the protuberant land would be destroyed, and
spread over the bottom of the ocean, filling up the lower parts, and tending
continually to remodel the surface of the solid nucleus, in correspondence
with the form of equilibrium. Thus after a sufficient lapse of
time, in the case of an earth in rotation, the polar protuberances would
gradually be cut down and disappear, being transferred to the equator
(as being then the deepest sea), till the earth would assume by degrees
the form we observe it to have—that of a flattened or oblate
ellipsoid.
"We are far from meaning here to trace the process by which the
earth really assumed its actual form; all we intend is to show that this
is the form to which, under a condition of a rotation on its axis, it must
tend, and which it would attain even if originally and (so to speak) perversely
constituted otherwise."743
In this passage, the author has contemplated the superficial effects of
aqueous causes only; but neither he nor Playfair seem to have followed
out the same inquiry with reference to another part of Hutton's system;
namely, that which assumes the successive fusion by heat of different
parts of the solid earth. Yet the progress of geology has continually
strengthened the evidence in favor of the doctrine that local variations of
temperature have melted one part after another of the earth's crust, and
this influence has perhaps extended downwards to the very centre. If,
therefore, before the globe had assumed its present form, it was made
to revolve on its axis, all matter to which freedom of motion was given
by fusion, must before consolidating have been impelled towards the
equatorial regions in obedience to the centrifugal force. Thus lava flowing
out in superficial streams would have its motion retarded when its
direction was towards the pole, accelerated when towards the equator;
or if lakes and seas of lava existed beneath the earth's crust in equatorial
regions, as probably now beneath the Peruvian Andes, the imprisoned
fluid would force outwards and permanently upheave the overlying
rocks. The statical figure, therefore, of the terrestrial spheroid
(of which the longest diameter exceeds the shortest by about twenty-five
miles), may have been the result of gradual and even of existing causes,
and not of a primitive, universal, and simultaneous fluidity.744
Experiments made with the pendulum, and observations on the manner
in which the earth attracts the moon, have shown that our planet is
536
not an empty sphere, but, on the contrary, that its interior, whether
solid or fluid, has a higher specific gravity than the exterior. It has
also been inferred, that there is a regular increase in density from the
surface towards the centre, and that the equatorial protuberance is continued
inwards; that is to say, that layers of equal density are arranged
elliptically, and symmetrically, from the exterior to the centre. These
conclusions, however, have been deduced rather as a consequence of
the hypothesis of primitive and simultaneous fluidity than proved by
experiment. The inequalities in the moon's motion, by which some have
endeavored to confirm them, are so extremely slight, that the opinion
can be regarded as little more than a probable conjecture.
The mean density of the earth has been computed by Laplace to be
about 5½, or more than five times that of water. Now the specific
gravity of many of our rocks is from 2½ to 3, and the greater part of
the metals range between that density and 21. Hence some have
imagined that the terrestrial nucleus may be metallic—that it may correspond,
for example, with the specific gravity of iron, which is about 7.
But here a curious question arises in regard to the form which materials,
whether fluid or solid, might assume, if subjected to the enormous
pressure which must obtain at the earth's centre. Water, if it continued
to decrease in volume according to the rate of compressibility deduced
from experiment, would have its density doubled at the depth of ninety-three
miles, and be as heavy as mercury at the depth of 362 miles.
Dr. Young computed that, at the earth's centre, steel would be compressed
into one-fourth, and stone into one-eighth of its bulk.745 It is
more than probable, however, that after a certain degree of condensation,
the compressibility of bodies may be governed by laws altogether
different from those which we can put to the test of experiment; but
the limit is still undetermined, and the subject is involved in such obscurity,
that we cannot wonder at the variety of notions which have
been entertained respecting the nature and conditions of the central nucleus.
Some have conceived it to be fluid, others solid; some have
imagined it to have a cavernous structure, and have even endeavored to
confirm this opinion by appealing to observed irregularities in the vibrations
of the pendulum in certain countries.
An attempt has recently been made by Mr. Hopkins to determine
the least thickness which can be assigned to the solid crust of the globe,
if we assume the whole to have been once perfectly fluid, and a certain
portion of the exterior to have acquired solidity by gradual refrigeration.
This result he has endeavored to obtain by a new solution of the delicate
problem of the processional motion of the pole of the earth. It is
well known that while the earth revolves round the sun the direction of
its axis remains very nearly the same, i. e. its different positions in space
are all nearly parallel to each other. This parallelism, however, is not
537
accurately preserved, so that the axis, instead of coming exactly into
the position which it occupied a year before, becomes inclined to it at a
very small angle, but always retaining very nearly the same inclination
to the plane of the earth's orbit. This motion of the pole changes the
position of the equinoxes by about fifty seconds annually, and always
in the same direction. Thus the pole-star, after a certain time, will
entirely lose its claim to that appellation, until in the course of somewhat
more than 25,000 years the earth's axis shall again occupy its present
angular position, and again point very nearly as now to the pole-star.
This motion of the axis is called precession. It is caused by the attraction
of the sun and moon, and principally the moon, on the protuberant
parts of the earth's equator; and if these parts were solid to a great
depth, the motion thus produced would differ considerably from that
which would exist if they were perfectly fluid, and incrusted over with
a thin shell only a few miles thick. In other words, the disturbing action
of the moon will not be the same upon a globe all solid and upon
one nearly all fluid, or it will not be the same upon a globe in which
the solid shell forms one-half of the mass, and another in which it forms
only one-tenth.
Mr. Hopkins has, therefore, calculated the amount of precessional motion
which would result if we assume the earth to be constituted as
above stated; i. e. fluid internally, and enveloped by a solid shell; and
he finds that the amount will not agree with the observed motion, unless
the crust of the earth be of a certain thickness. In calculating the exact
amount some ambiguity arises in consequence of our ignorance of the
effect of pressure in promoting the solidification of matter at high temperatures.
The hypothesis least favorable for a great thickness is found
to be that which assumes the pressure to produce no effect on the process
of solidification. Even on this extreme assumption the thickness of
the solid crust must be nearly four hundred miles, and this would lead
to the remarkable result that the proportion of the solid to the fluid part
would be as 49 to 51, or, to speak in round numbers, there would be
nearly as much solid as fluid matter in the globe. The conclusion, however,
which Mr. Hopkins announces as that to which his researches
have finally conducted him, is thus expressed: "Upon the whole, then,
we may venture to assert that the minimum thickness of the crust of the
globe, which can be deemed consistent with the observed amount of precession,
cannot be less than one-fourth or one-fifth of the earth's radius."
That is from 800 to 1000 miles.746
It will be remarked, that this is a minimum, and any still greater
amount would be quite consistent with the actual phenomena; the calculations
not being opposed to the supposition of the general solidity of the
entire globe. Nor do they preclude us from imagining that great lakes
or seas of melted matter may be distributed through a shell 400 or 800
538
miles thick, provided they be so inclosed as to move with it, whatever
motion of rotation may be communicated by the disturbing forces of the
sun and moon.
Central heat.—The hypothesis of internal fluidity calls for the more
attentive consideration, as it has been found that the heat in mines augments
in proportion as we descend. Observations have been made, not
only on the temperature of the air in mines, but on that of the rocks,
and on the water issuing from them. The mean rate of increase, calculated
from results obtained in six of the deepest coal mines in Durham
and Northumberland, is 1° Fahr. for a descent of forty-four English
feet.747 A series of observations, made in several of the principal lead
and silver mines in Saxony, gave 1° Fahr. for every sixty-five feet. In
this case, the bulb of the thermometer was introduced into cavities purposely
cut in the solid rock at depths varying from 200 to above 900 feet.
But in other mines of the same country, it was necessary to descend
thrice as far for each degree of temperature.748
A thermometer was fixed in the rock of the Dolcoath mine, in Cornwall,
by Mr. Fox, at the great depth of 1380 feet, and frequently observed
during eighteen months; the mean temperature was 68° Fahr.,
that of the surface being 50°, which gives 1° for every seventy-five feet.
Kupffer, after an extensive comparison of the results in different countries,
makes the increase 1° F. for about every thirty-seven English feet.749
M. Cordier announces, as the result of his experiments and observations
on the temperature of the interior of the earth, that the heat increases
rapidly with the depth; but the increase does not follow the same law
over the whole earth, being twice or three times as much in one country
as in another, and these differences are not in constant relation either
with the latitudes or longitudes of places.750 He is of opinion, however,
that the increase would not be overstated at 1° Cent. for every twenty-five
metres, or about 1° F. for every forty-five feet.751 The experimental
well bored at Grenelle, near Paris, gave about 1° F. for every sixty
English feet, when they had reached a depth of 1312 feet.
Some writers have endeavored to refer these phenomena (which, however
discordant as to the ratio of increasing heat, appear all to point one
way) to the condensation of air constantly descending from the surface
into the mines. For the air under pressure would give out latent heat,
on the same principle as it becomes colder when rarefied in the higher
regions of the atmosphere. But, besides that the quantity of heat is
greater than could be supposed to flow from this source, the argument
has been answered in a satisfactory manner by Mr. Fox, who has shown,
that in the mines of Cornwall the ascending have generally a higher
539
temperature than the descending aerial currents. The difference between
them was found to vary from 9° to 17° F.; a proof that, instead
of imparting heat, these currents actually carry off a large quantity from
the mines.752
If we adopt M. Cordier's estimate of 1° F. for every 45 feet of depth
as the mean result, and assume, with the advocates of central fluidity,
that the increasing temperature is continued downwards, we should
reach the ordinary boiling point of water at about two miles below the
surface, and at the depth of about twenty-four miles should arrive at
the melting point of iron, a heat sufficient to fuse almost every known
substance. The temperature of melted iron was estimated at 21,000°
F., by Wedgwood; but his pyrometer gives, as is now demonstrated,
very erroneous results. Professor Daniell ascertained that the point of
fusion is 2,786° F.753
Fig. 92.
Section of the earth, in which the breadth of the outer boundary line represents a thickness of
25 miles; the space between the circles, including the breadth of the lines, 200 miles.
According to Mr. Daniell's scale, we ought to encounter the internal
540
melted matter before penetrating through a thickness represented by
that of the outer circular line in the annexed diagram (fig. 92); whereas,
if the other or less correct scale be adopted, we should meet with it at
some point between the two circles; the space between them, together
with the lines themselves, representing a crust of 200 miles in depth.
In either case, we must be prepared to maintain that a temperature
many times greater than that sufficient to melt the most refractory substances
known to us, is sustained at the centre of the globe; while a
comparatively thin crust, resting upon the fluid, remains unmelted; or
is even, according to M. Cordier, increasing in thickness, by the continual
addition of new internal layers solidified during the process of refrigeration.
The mathematical calculations of Fourier, on the passage of heat
through conducting bodies, have been since appealed to in support of
these views; for he has shown that it is compatible with theory that
the present temperature of the surface might coexist with an intense
heat at a certain depth below. But his reasoning seems to be confined
to the conduction of heat through solid bodies; and the conditions of
the problem are wholly altered when we reason about a fluid nucleus, as
we must do if it be assumed that the heat augments from the surface
to the interior, according to the rate observed in mines. For when the
heat of the lower portion of a fluid is increased, a circulation begins
throughout the mass, by the ascent of hotter, and the descent of colder
currents. And this circulation, which is quite distinct from the mode
in which heat is propagated through solid bodies, must evidently occur
in the supposed central ocean, if the laws of fluids and of heat are the
same there as upon the surface.
In Mr. Daniell's experiments for obtaining a measure of the heat of
bodies at their point of fusion, he invariably found that it was impossible
to raise the heat of a large crucible of melted iron, gold, or silver, a single
degree beyond the melting point, so long as a bar of the respective
metals was kept immersed in the fluid portions. So in regard to other
substances, however great the quantities fused, their temperature could
not be raised while any solid pieces immersed in them remained unmelted;
every accession of heat being instantly absorbed during their
liquefaction. These results are, in fact, no more than the extension of a
principle previously established, that so long as a fragment of ice remains
in water, we cannot raise the temperature of the water above
32° F.
If, then, the heat of the earth's centre amount to 450,000° F., as M.
Cordier deems highly probable, that is to say, about twenty times the
heat of melted iron, even according to Wedgwood's scale, and upwards
of 160 times according to the improved pyrometer, it is clear that the
upper parts of the fluid mass could not long have a temperature only
just sufficient to melt rocks. There must be a continual tendency towards
a uniform heat; and until this were accomplished, by the interchange
of portions of fluid of different densities, the surface could not
541
begin to consolidate. Nor, on the hypothesis of primitive fluidity, can
we conceive any crust to have been formed until the whole planet had
cooled down to about the temperature of incipient fusion.
It cannot be objected that hydrostatic pressure would prevent a tendency
to equalization of temperature; for, as far as observations have
yet been made, it is found that the waters of deep lakes and seas are
governed by the same laws as a shallow pool; and no experiments indicate
that solids resist fusion under high pressure. The arguments, indeed,
now controverted, always proceed on the admission that the internal
nucleus is in a state of fusion.
It may be said that we may stand upon the hardened surface of a lava-current
while it is still in motion,—nay, may descend into the crater of
Vesuvius after an eruption, and stand on the scoriæ while every crevice
shows that the rock is red-hot two or three feet below us; and at a
somewhat greater depth, all is, perhaps, in a state of fusion. May not,
then, a much more intense heat be expected at the depth of several
hundred yards, or miles? The answer is,—that until a great quantity
of heat has been given off, either by the emission of lava, or in a latent
form by the evolution of steam and gas, the melted matter continues to
boil in the crater of a volcano. But ebullition ceases when there is no
longer a sufficient supply of heat from below, and then a crust of lava
may form on the top, and showers of scoriæ may then descend upon
the surface, and remain unmelted. If the internal heat be raised again,
ebullition will recommence, and soon fuse the superficial crust. So in
the case of the moving current, we may safely assume that no part of
the liquid beneath the hardened surface is much above the temperature
sufficient to retain it in a state of fluidity.
It may assist us in forming a clearer view of the doctrine now controverted,
if we consider what would happen were a globe of homogeneous
composition placed under circumstances analogous, in regard to
the distribution of heat, to those above stated. If the whole planet, for
example, were composed of water covered with a spheroidal crust of ice
fifty miles thick, and with an interior ocean having a central heat about
two hundred times that of the melting point of ice, or 6400° F.; and if,
between the surface and the centre, there was every intermediate degree
of temperature between that of melting ice and that of the central nucleus—could
such a state of things last for a moment? If it must be
conceded, in this case, that the whole spheroid would be instantly in a
state of violent ebullition, that the ice (instead of being strengthened
annually by new internal layers) would soon melt, and form part of an
atmosphere of steam—on what principle can it he maintained that analogous
effects would not follow, in regard to the earth, under the conditions
assumed in the theory of central heat?754
542M. Cordier admits that there must be tides in the internal melted
ocean; but their effect, he says, has become feeble, although originally,
when the fluidity of the globe was perfect, "the rise and fall of these
ancient land tides could not have been less than from thirteen to sixteen
feet." Now, granting for a moment, that these tides have become so
feeble as to be incapable of causing the fissured shell of the earth to be
first uplifted and then depressed every six hours, still may we not ask
whether, during eruptions, the lava, which is supposed to communicate
with a great central ocean, would not rise and fall sensibly in a crater
such as Stromboli, where there is always melted matter in a state of
ebullition?
Whether chemical changes may produce volcanic heat.—Having now
explained the reasons which have induced me to question the hypothesis
of central heat as the primary source of volcanic action, it remains to
consider what has been termed the chemical theory of volcanoes. It is
well known that many, perhaps all, of the substances of which the earth
is composed are continually undergoing chemical changes. To what
depth these processes may be continued downwards must, in a great
degree, be matter of conjecture; but there is no reason to suspect that,
if we could descend to a great distance from the surface, we should find
elementary substances differing essentially from those with which we are
acquainted.
All the solid, fluid, and gaseous bodies known to us consist of a very
small number of these elementary substances variously combined: the
total number of elements at present known is less than sixty; and not
half of these enter into the composition of the more abundant inorganic
productions. Some portions of such compounds are daily undergoing
decomposition, and their constituent parts being set free are passing into
new combinations. These processes are by no means confined to minerals
at the earth's surface, and are very often accompanied by the evolution
of heat, which is intense in proportion to the rapidity of the combinations.
At the same time there is a development of electricity.
The spontaneous combustion of beds of bituminous shale, and of refuse
coal thrown out of mines, is generally due to the decomposition of pyrites;
and it is the contact of air and water which brings about the change.
Heat results from the oxidation of the sulphur and iron, though on what
principle heat is generated, when two or more bodies having a strong
affinity for each other unite suddenly, is wholly unexplained.
Electricity a source of volcanic heat.—It has already been stated, that
chemical changes develop electricity; which, in its turn, becomes a
powerful disturbing cause. As a chemical agent, says Davy, its silent
and slow operation in the economy of nature is much more important
than its grand and impressive operation in lightning and thunder. It
may be considered, not only as directly producing an infinite variety of
543
changes, but as influencing almost all which take place; it would seem,
indeed, that chemical attraction itself is only a peculiar form of the exhibition
of electrical attraction.755
Now that it has been demonstrated that magnetism and electricity
are always associated, and are perhaps only different conditions of the
same power, the phenomena of terrestrial magnetism have become of
no ordinary interest to the geologist. Soon after the first great discoveries
of Oersted in electro-magnetism, Ampère suggested that all
the phenomena of the magnetic needle might be explained by supposing
currents of electricity to circulate constantly in the shell of the
globe in directions parallel to the magnetic equator. This theory has
acquired additional consistency the farther we have advanced in science;
and according to the experiments of Mr. Fox, on the electro-magnetic
properties of metalliferous veins, some trace of electric currents seems to
have been detected in the interior of the earth.756
Some philosophers ascribe these currents to the chemical action going
on in the superficial parts of the globe to which air and water have the
readiest access; while others refer them, in part at least, to thermo-electricity
excited by the solar rays on the surface of the earth during
its rotation; successive parts of the atmosphere, land, and sea being
exposed to the influence of the sun, and then cooled again in the night.
That this idea is not a mere speculation, is proved by the correspondence
of the diurnal variations of the magnet with the apparent motion
of the sun; and by the greater amount of variation in summer than in
winter, and during the day than in the night. M. de la Rive, although
conceding that such minor variations of the needle may be due to
thermo-electricity, contends that the general phenomena of terrestrial
magnetism must be attributed to currents far more intense; which,
though liable to secular fluctuations, act with much greater constancy
and regularity than the causes which produce the diurnal variations.757
The remark seems just; yet it is difficult to assign limits to the accumulated
influence even of a very feeble force constantly acting on the
whole surface of the earth. This subject, however, must evidently
remain obscure, until we become acquainted with the causes which give
a determinate direction to the supposed electric currents. Already the
experiments of Faraday on the rotation of magnets have led him to
speculate on the manner in which the earth, when once it had become
magnetic, might produce electric currents within itself, in consequence
of its diurnal rotation.758 We have seen also in a former chapter (p. 129)
that the recent observations of Schwabe, 1852, have led Col. Sabine to
the discovery of a connection between certain periodical changes, which
take place in the spots on the sun, and a certain cycle of variations in
terrestrial magnetism. These seem to point to the existence of a solar
544
magnetic period, and suggest the idea of the sun's magnetism exerting
an influence on the mass of our planet.
In regard to thermo-electricity, I may remark, that it may be generated
by great inequalities of temperature, arising from a partial distribution
of volcanic heat. Wherever, for example, masses of rock occur
of great horizontal extent, and of considerable depth, which are at one
point in a state of fusion (as beneath some active volcano); at another,
red-hot; and at a third, comparatively cold—strong thermo-electric
action may be excited.
Some, perhaps, may object, that this is reasoning in a circle; first to
introduce electricity as one of the primary causes of volcanic heat, and
then to derive the same heat from thermo-electric currents. But there
must, in truth, be much reciprocal action between the agents now under
consideration; and it is very difficult to decide which should be regarded
as the prime mover, or to see where the train of changes, once
begun, would terminate. Whether subterranean electric currents if
once excited might sometimes possess the decomposing power of the
voltaic pile, is a question not perhaps easily answered in the present
state of science; but such a power, if developed, would at once supply
us with a never-failing source of chemical action from which volcanic
heat might be derived.
Recapitulation.—Before entering, in the next chapter, still farther
into the inquiry, how far the phenomena of volcanoes and earthquakes
accord with the hypothesis of a continued generation of heat by chemical
action, it may be desirable to recapitulate, in a few words, the conclusions
already obtained.
1st. The primary causes of the volcano and the earthquake are, to a
great extent, the same, and must be connected with the passage of heat
from the interior to the surface.
2dly. This heat has been referred, by many, to a supposed state of
igneous fusion of the central parts of the planet when it was first
created, of which a part still remains in the interior, but is always
diminishing in intensity.
3dly. The spheroidal figure of the earth, adduced in support of this
theory, does not of necessity imply a universal and simultaneous
fluidity, in the beginning; for supposing the original figure of our planet
had been strictly spherical—which, however, is a gratuitous assumption,
resting on no established analogy—still the statical figure must have
been assumed, if sufficient time be allowed, by the gradual operation of
the centrifugal force, acting on the materials brought successively within
its action by aqueous and igneous causes.
4thly. It appears, from experiment, that the heat in mines increases
progressively with their depth; and if the ratio of increase be continued
uniformly from the surface to the interior, the whole globe, with the
exception of a small external shell, must be fluid, and the central parts
must have a temperature many times higher than that of melted iron.
5thly. But the theory adopted by M. Cordier and others, which
545
maintains the actual existence of such a state of things, seems wholly
inconsistent with the laws which regulate the circulation of heat through
fluid bodies. For, if the central heat were as intense as is represented,
there must be a circulation of currents, tending to equalize the temperature
of the resulting fluids, and the solid crust itself would be melted.
6thly. Instead of an original central heat, we may, perhaps, refer the
heat of the interior to chemical changes constantly going on in the earth's
crust; for the general effect of chemical combination is the evolution of
heat and electricity, which in their turn become sources of new chemical
changes.
</div></body></text></TEI>