<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="9">INTRODUCTION.
THE earliest and fundamental
conceptions of men respecting the objects with which Astronomy is
concerned, are formed by familiar processes of thought, without
appearing to have in them any thing technical or scientific. Days,
Years, Months, the Sky, the Constellations, are notions which the most
uncultured and incurious minds possess. Yet these are elements of the
Science of Astronomy. The reasons why, in this case alone, of all the
provinces of human knowledge, men were able, at an early and
unenlightened period, to construct a science out of the obvious facts
of observation, with the help of the common furniture of their minds,
will be more apparent in the course of the philosophy of science: but
I may here barely mention two of these reasons. They are, first, that
the familiar act of thought, exercised for the common purposes of
life, by which we give to an assemblage of our impressions such a
unity as is implied in the above notions and terms, a Month, a Year,
the Sky, and the like, is, in reality, an inductive act, and
shares the nature of the processes by which all sciences are formed;
and, in the next place, that the ideas appropriate to the induction in
this case, are those which, even in the least cultivated minds, are
very clear and definite; namely, the ideas of Space and Figure, Time
and Number, Motion and Recurrence. Hence, from their first origin, the
modifications of those ideas assume a scientific form.
We must now trace in detail the peculiar course which, in
consequence of these causes, the knowledge of man respecting the
heavenly bodies took, from the earliest period of his history. 112</div></body></text></TEI>