<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="135">CHAPTER IV.
Attempts to Discover General Laws in
Geology.

Sect. 1.—General Geological
Phenomena.
BESIDES thus noticing such
features in the rocks of each country as were necessary to the
identification of the strata, geologists have had many other phenomena
of the earth’s surface and materials presented to their notice; and
these they have, to a certain extent, attempted to generalize, so as
to obtain on this subject what we have elsewhere termed the Laws of
Phenomena, which are the best materials for physical theory. Without
dwelling long upon these, we may briefly note some of the most
obvious. Thus it has been observed that mountain ranges often consist
of a ridge of subjacent rock, on which lie, on each side, strata
sloping from the ridge. Such a ridge is an Anticlinal Line, a
Mineralogical Axis. The sloping strata present their
Escarpements, or steep edges, to this axis. Again, in mining
countries, the Veins which contain the ore are usually a system
of parallel and nearly vertical partitions in the rock; and
these are, in very many cases, intersected by another system of veins
parallel to each other and nearly perpendicular to the former.
Rocky regions are often intersected by Faults, or fissures
interrupting the strata, in which the rock on one side the fissure
appears to have been at first continuous with that on the other, and
shoved aside or up or down after the fracture. Again, besides these
larger fractures, rocks have Joints,—separations, or
tendencies to separate in some directions rather than in others; and a
slaty Cleavage, in which the parallel subdivisions may be
carried on, so as to produce laminæ of indefinite thinness. As an
example of those laws of phenomena of which we have spoken, we may
instance the general law asserted by Prof. 538 Sedgwick (not, however, as free from
exception), that in one particular class of rocks the slaty Cleavage
never coincides with the Direction of the strata.
The phenomena of metalliferous veins may be referred to, as another
large class of facts which demand the notice of the geologist. It
would be difficult to point out briefly any general laws which prevail
in such cases; but in order to show the curious and complex nature of
the facts, it may be sufficient to refer to the description of the
metallic veins of Cornwall by Mr. Carne;56 in which the
author maintains that their various contents, and the manner in which
they cut across, and stop, or shift, each other, leads
naturally to the assumption of veins of no less than six or eight
different ages in one kind of rock.
56 Transactions of the Geol. Soc.
of Cornwall, vol. ii.
Again, as important characters belonging to the physical history of
the earth, and therefore to geology, we may notice all the general
laws which refer to its temperature;—both the laws of climate,
as determined by the isothermal lines, which Humboldt has
drawn, by the aid of very numerous observations made in all parts of
the world; and also those still more curious facts, of the increase of
temperature which takes place as we descend in the solid mass. The
latter circumstance, after being for a while rejected as a fable, or
explained away as an accident, is now generally acknowledged to be the
true state of things in many distant parts of the globe, and probably
in all.
Again, to turn to cases of another kind: some writers have
endeavored to state in a general manner laws according to which the
members of the geological series succeed each other; and to reduce
apparent anomalies to order of a wider kind. Among those who have
written with such views, we may notice Alexander von Humboldt, always,
and in all sciences, foremost in the race of generalization. In his
attempt to extend the doctrine of geological equivalents from the
rocks of Europe57 to those of the Andes, he has marked by
appropriate terms the general modes of geological succession. “I have
insisted,” he says58 “principally upon the phenomena of
alternation, oscillation, and local suppression,
and on those presented by the passages of formations from one
to another, by the effect of an interior developement.”
57 Gissement des Roches dans les
deux Hemisphères, 1823.
58 Pref. p. vi.
The phenomena of alternation to which M. de Humboldt here refers
are, in fact, very curious: as exhibiting a mode in which the
transitions from one formation to another may become gradual and
insensible, 539
instead of sudden and abrupt. Thus the coal measures in the south of
England are above the mountain limestone; and the distinction of the
formations is of the most marked kind. But as we advance northward
into the coal-field of Yorkshire and Durham, the subjacent limestone
begins to be subdivided by thick masses of sandstone and carbonaceous
strata, and passes into a complex deposit, not distinguishable from
the overlying coal measures; and in this manner the transition from
the limestone to the coal is made by alternation. Thus, to use another
expression of M. de Humboldt’s in ascending from the limestone, the
coal, before we quit the subjacent stratum, preludes to its
fuller exhibition in the superior beds.
Again, as to another point: geologists have gone on up to the
present time endeavoring to discover general laws and facts, with
regard to the position of mountain and mineral masses upon the surface
of the earth. Thus M. Von Buch, in his physical description of the
Canaries, has given a masterly description of the lines of volcanic
action and volcanic products, all over the globe. And, more recently,
M. Elie de Beaumont has offered some generalizations of a still wider
kind. In this new doctrine, those mountain ranges, even in distant
parts of the world, which are of the same age, according to the
classifications already spoken of, are asserted to be parallel59 to each other, while those ranges which
are of different ages lie in different directions. This very wide and
striking proposition may be considered as being at present upon its
trial among the geologists of Europe.60
59 We may observe that the notion of
parallelism, when applied to lines drawn on remote portions
of a globular surface, requires to be interpreted in so arbitrary a
manner, that we can hardly imagine it to express a physical law.
60 Mr. Lyell, in the sixth edition of
his Principles, B. i. c. xii., has combated the hypothesis of
M. Elie de Beaumont, stated in the text. He has argued both against
the catastrophic character of the elevation of mountain chains, and
the parallelism of the contemporaneous ridges. It is evident that the
former doctrine may be true, though the latter be shown to be
false.
Among the organic phenomena, also, which have been the subject of
geological study, general laws of a very wide and comprehensive kind
have been suggested, and in a greater or less degree confirmed by
adequate assemblages of facts. Thus M. Adolphe Brongniart has not
only, in his Fossil Flora, represented and skilfully restored a
vast number of the plants of the ancient world; but he has also, in
the Prodromus of the work, presented various important and
striking views of the general character of the vegetation of former
periods, as 540
insular or continental, tropical or temperate. And M. Agassiz, by the
examination of an incredible number of specimens and collections of
fossil fish, has been led to results which, expressed in terms of his
own ichthyological classification, form remarkable general laws. Thus,
according to him,61 when we go below the lias, we lose all
traces of two of the four orders under which he comprehends all known
kinds of fish; namely, the Cycloïdean and the
Ctenoïdean; while the other two orders, the Ganoïdean
and Placoïdean, rare in our days, suddenly appear in great
numbers, together with large sauroid and carnivorous fishes. Cuvier,
in constructing his great work on ichthyology, transferred to M.
Agassiz the whole subject of fossil fishes, thus showing how highly he
esteemed his talents as a naturalist. And M. Agassiz has shown himself
worthy of his great predecessor in geological natural history, not
only by his acuteness and activity, but by the comprehensive character
of his zoological philosophy, and by the courage with which he has
addressed himself to the vast labors which lie before him. In his
Report on the Fossil Fish discovered in England, published in
1835, he briefly sketches some of the large questions which his
researches have suggested; and then adds,62 “Such is the
meagre outline of a history of the highest interest, full of curious
episodes, but most difficult to relate. To unfold the details which it
contains will be the business of my life.”
61 Greenough, Address to Geol.
Soc. 1835, p. 19.
62 Brit. Assoc. Report, p.
72.
[2nd Ed.] [In proceeding downwards through the series of formations
into which geologists have distributed the rocks of the earth, one
class of organic forms after another is found to disappear. In the
Tertiary Period we find all the classes of the present world: Mammals,
Birds, Reptiles, Fishes, Crustaceans, Mollusks, Zoophytes. In the
Secondary Period, from the Chalk down to the New Red Sandstone,
Mammals are not found, with the minute exception of the marsupial
amphitherium and phascolotherium in the Stonesfield
slate. In the Carboniferous and Devonian period we have no large
Reptiles, with, again, a minute amount of exception. In the lower part
of the Silurian rocks, Fishes vanish, and we have no animal forms but
Mollusks, Crustaceans and Zoophytes.
The Carboniferous, Devonian and Silurian formations, thus
containing the oldest forms of life, have been termed
palæozoic. The boundaries of the life-bearing series have not
yet been determined; but the series in which vertebrated animals do
not appear has been 541 provisionally termed protozoic,
and the lower Silurian rocks may probably be looked upon as its upper
members. Below this, geologists place a hypozoic or
azoic series of rocks.
Geologists differ as to the question whether these changes in the
inhabitants of the globe were made by determinate steps or by
insensible gradations. M. Agassiz has been led to the conviction that
the organized population of the globe was renewed in the interval of
each principal member of its formations.63 Mr. Lyell, on
the other hand, conceives that the change in the collection of
organized beings was gradual, and has proposed on this subject an
hypothesis which I shall hereafter
consider.]
63 Brit. Assoc. Report 1842,
p. 83.
Sect. 2.—Transition to Geological
Dynamics.
While we have been giving this account of
the objects with which Descriptive Geology is occupied, it must have
been felt how difficult it is, in contemplating such facts, to confine
ourselves to description and classification. Conjectures and
reasonings respecting the causes of the phenomena force themselves
upon us at every step; and even influence our classification and
nomenclature. Our Descriptive Geology impels us to endeavor to
construct a Physical Geology. This close connexion of the two branches
of the subject by no means invalidates the necessity of distinguishing
them: as in Botany, although the formation of a Natural System
necessarily brings us to physiological relations, we still distinguish
Systematic from Physiological Botany.
Supposing, however, our Descriptive Geology to be completed, as far
as can be done without considering closely the causes by which the
strata have been produced, we have now to enter upon the other
province of the science, which treats of those causes, and of which we
have already spoken, as Physical Geology. But before we can treat this
department of speculation in a manner suitable to the conditions of
science, and to the analogy of other parts of our knowledge, a certain
intermediate and preparatory science must be formed, of which we shall
now consider the origin and progress.


GEOLOGICAL DYNAMICS.
</div></body></text></TEI>