<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="62">CHAPTER I.
Primary Induction of Optics.—Rays of Light and
Laws of Reflection.
IN speaking of the Ancient
History of Physics, we have already noticed
that the optical philosophers of antiquity had satisfied themselves
that vision is performed in straight lines;—that they had fixed
their attention upon those straight lines, or rays, as the
proper object of the science;—they had ascertained that rays
reflected from a bright surface make the angle of reflection
equal to the angle of incidence;—and they had drawn
several consequences from these principles.
We may add to the consequences already mentioned, the art of
perspective, which is merely a corollary from the doctrine of
rectilinear visual rays; for if we suppose objects to be referred by
such rays to a plane interposed between them and the eye, all the
rules of perspective follow directly. The ancients practised this art,
as we see in the pictures which remain to us and we learn from
Vitruvius,1 that they also wrote upon it.
Agatharchus, who had been instructed by Eschylus in the art of making
decorations for the theatre, was the first author on this subject, and
Anaxagoras, who was a pupil of Agatharchus, also wrote an
Actinographia, or doctrine of drawing by rays: but none of
these treatises are come down to us. The moderns re-invented the art
in the flourishing times of the art of painting, that is, about the
end of the fifteenth century; and, belonging to that period also, we
have treatises2 upon it.
1 De Arch. ix. Mont. i.
707.
2 Gauricus, 1504.
But these are only deductive applications of the most elementary
optical doctrines; we must proceed to the inductions by which further
discoveries were made. 54</div></body></text></TEI>