<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="126">CHAPTER IV.
Examination of the Process of Reproduction in Animals
and Plants, and Consequent Speculations.
Sect. 1.—The Examination of the
Process of Reproduction in Animals.
IT would not, perhaps, be
necessary to give any more examples of what has hitherto been the
general process of investigations on each branch of physiology; or to
illustrate further the combination which such researches present, of
certain with uncertain knowledge;—of solid discoveries of organs
and processes, succeeded by indefinite and doubtful speculation
concerning vital forces. But the reproduction of organized beings is
not only a subject of so much interest as to require some notice, but
also offers to us laws and principles which include both the vegetable
and the animal kingdom; and which, therefore, are requisite to render
intelligible the most general views to which we can attain, respecting
the world of organization.
The facts and laws of reproduction were first studied in detail in
animals. The subject appears to have attracted the attention of some
of the philosophers of antiquity in an extraordinary degree: and
indeed we may easily imagine that they hoped, by following this path,
if any, to solve the mystery of creation. Aristotle appears to have
pursued it with peculiar complacency; and his great work On
animals contains46 an extraordinary collection of curious
observations relative to this subject. He had learnt the modes of
reproduction of most of the animals with which he was acquainted; and
his work is still, as a writer of our own times has said,47 “original after so many copies, and
young after two thousand years.” His observations referred principally
to the external circumstances of generation: the anatomical
examination was 456
left to his successors. Without dwelling on the intermediate labors,
we come to modern times, and find that this examination owes its
greatest advance to those who had the greatest share in the discovery
of the circulation of the blood;—Fabricius of Acquapendente, and
Harvey. The former48 published a valuable work on the Egg
and the Chick. In this are given, for the first time, figures
representing the developement of the chick, from its almost
imperceptible beginning, to the moment when it breaks the shell.
Harvey pursued the researches of his teacher. Charles49 the First had supplied him with the
means of making the experiments which his purpose required, by
sacrificing a great number of the deer in Windsor Park in the state of
gestation: but his principal researches were those respecting the egg,
in which he followed out the views of Fabricius. In the troubles which
succeeded the death of the unfortunate Charles the house of Harvey was
pillaged; and he lost the whole of the labors he had bestowed on the
generation of insects. His work, Exercitationes de Generatione
Animalium, was published at London in 1651; it is more detailed
and perfect than that of Fabricius; but the author was prevented by
the unsettled condition of the country from getting figures engraved
to accompany his descriptions.
46 Bourdon, p. 161.
47 Ib. p. 101.
48 Cuv. Hist. Sc. Nat. p.
46.
49 Ib. p. 53.
Many succeeding anatomists pursued the examination of the series of
changes in generation, and of the organs which are concerned in them,
especially Malpighi, who employed the microscope in this
investigation, and whose work on the Chick was published in 1673. It
is impossible to give here any general view of the result of these
laborious series of researches: but we may observe, that they led to
an extremely minute and exact survey of all the parts of the fœtus,
its envelopes and appendages, and, of course, to a designation of
these by appropriate names. These names afterwards served to mark the
attempts which were made to carry the analogy of animal generation
into the vegetable kingdom.
There is one generalization of Harvey which deserves notice.50 He was led by his researches to the
conclusion, that all living things may be properly said to come from
eggs: “Omne vivum ex ovo.” Thus not only do oviparous animals produce
by means of eggs, but in those which are viviparous, the process of
generation begins with the developement of a small vesicle, which
comes from the ovary, and which exists before the embryo: and thus
viviparous or suckling-beasts, 457 notwithstanding their name, are born
from eggs, as well as birds, fishes, and reptiles.51 This principle also excludes that
supposed production of organized beings without parents (of worms in
corrupted matter, for instance,) which was formerly called
spontaneous generation; and the best physiologists of modern
times agree in denying the reality of such a mode of generation.52
50 Exerc. lxiii.
51 Bourdon, p. 221.
52 Ib. p. 49.
Sect. 2.—The Examination of the Process of
Reproduction in Vegetables.
The extension of the
analogies of animal generation to the vegetable world was far from
obvious. This extension was however made;—with reference to the
embryo plant, principally by the microscopic observers, Nehemiah Grew,
Marcello Malpighi, and Antony Leeuwenhoek;—with respect to the
existence of the sexes, by Linnæus and his predecessors.
The microscopic labors of Grew and Malpighi were patronized by the
Royal Society of London in its earliest youth. Grew’s book, The
Anatomy of Plants, was ordered to be printed in 1670. It contains
plates representing extremely well the process of germination in
various seeds, and the author’s observations exhibit a very clear
conception of the relation and analogies of different portions of the
seed. On the day on which the copy of this work was laid before the
Society, a communication from Malpighi of Bologna, Anatomes
Plantarum Idea, stated his researches, and promised figures which
should illustrate them. Both authors afterwards went on with a long
train of valuable observations, which they published at various times,
and which contain much that has since become a permanent portion of
the science.
Both Grew and Malpighi were, as we have remarked, led to apply to
vegetable generation many terms which imply an analogy with the
generation of animals. Thus, Grew terms the innermost coat of the
seed, the secundine; speaks of the navel-fibres, &c.
Many more such terms have been added by other writers. And, as has
been observed by a modern physiologist,53 the resemblance
is striking. Both in the vegetable seed and in the fertilized animal
egg, we have an embryo, chalazæ, a placenta, an
umbilical cord, a cicatricula, an amnios,
membranes, nourishing vessels. The cotyledons of
the seed are the equivalent of the vitellus of birds, or of the
umbilical vesicle of suckling-beasts: 458 the albumen or perisperm
of the grain is analogous to the white of the egg of birds, or
the allantoid of viviparous animals.
53 Ib. p. 384.
Sexes of Plants.—The attribution of sexes to plants,
is a notion which was very early adopted; but only gradually unfolded
into distinctness and generality.54 The ancients
were acquainted with the fecundation of vegetables. Empedocles,
Aristotle, Theophrastus, Pliny, and some of the poets, make mention of
it; but their notions were very incomplete, and the conception was
again lost in the general shipwreck of human knowledge. A Latin poem,
composed in the fifteenth century by Jovianus Pontanus, the preceptor
of Alphonso, King of Naples, is the first modern work in which mention
is made of the sex of plants. Pontanus sings the loves of two
date-palms, which grew at the distance of fifteen leagues from each
other: the male at Brundusium, the female at Otranto. The distance did
not prevent the female from becoming fruitful, as soon as the palms
had raised their heads above the surrounding trees, so that nothing
intervened directly between them, or, to speak with the poet, so that
they were able to see each other.
54 Mirbel, El. ii. 538.
Zaluzian, a botanist who lived at the end of the fifteenth century,
says that the greater part of the species of plants are
androgynes, that is, have the properties of the male and of the
female united in the same plant; but that some species have the two
sexes in separate individuals; and he adduces a passage of Pliny
relative to the fecundation of the date-palm. John Bauhin, in the
middle of the seventeenth century, cites the expressions of Zaluzian;
and forty years later, a professor of Tübingen, Rudolph Jacob
Camerarius, pointed out clearly the organs of generation, and proved
by experiments on the mulberry, on maize, and on the plant called
Mercury (mercurialis), that when by any means the action of the
stamina upon the pistils is intercepted, the seeds are barren.
Camerarius, therefore, a philosopher in other respects of little note,
has the honor assigned him of being the author of the discovery of the
sexes of plants in modern times.55
55 Mirbel, ii. 539.
The merit of this discovery will, perhaps, appear more considerable
when it is recollected that it was rejected at first by very eminent
botanists. Thus Tournefort, misled by insufficient experiments,
maintained that the stamina are excretory organs; and Reaumur, at the
beginning of the eighteenth century, inclined to the same doctrine.
459 Upon this,
Geoffroy, an apothecary at Paris, scrutinized afresh the sexual
organs; he examined the various forms of the pollen, already observed
by Grew and Malpighi; he pointed out the excretory canal, which
descends through the style, and the micropyle, or minute
orifice in the coats of the ovule, which is opposite to the extremity
of this canal; though he committed some mistakes with regard to the
nature of the pollen. Soon afterwards, Sebastian Vaillant, the pupil
of Tournefort, but the corrector of his error on this subject,
explained in his public lectures the phenomenon of the fecundation of
plants, described the explosion of the anthers, and showed that the
florets of composite flowers, though formed on the type of an
androgynous flower, are sometimes male, sometimes female, and
sometimes neuter.
But though the sexes of plants had thus been noticed, the subject
drew far more attention when Linnæus made the sexual parts the basis
of his classification. Camerarius and Burkard had already entertained
such a thought, but it was Linnæus who carried into effect, and thus
made the notion of the sexes of vegetables almost as familiar to us as
that of the sexes of animals.
Sect. 3.—The Consequent
Speculations.—Hypotheses of Generation.
The views of the processes of
generation, and of their analogies throughout the whole of the organic
world, which were thus established and diffused, form an important and
substantial part of our physiological knowledge. That a number of
curious but doubtful hypotheses should be put forward, for the purpose
of giving further significance and connexion to these discoveries, was
to be expected. We must content ourselves with speaking of these very
briefly. We have such hypotheses in the earliest antiquity of Greece;
for as we have already said, the speculations of cosmogony were the
source of the Greek philosophy; and the laws of generation appeared to
offer the best promise of knowledge respecting the mystery of
creation. Hippocrates explained the production of a new animal by the
mixture of seed of the parents; and the offspring was male or
female as the seminal principle of the father or of the mother was the
more powerful. According to Aristotle, the mother supplied the
matter, and the father the form. Harvey’s doctrine was,
that the ovary of the female is fertilized by a seminal
contagion produced by the seed of the male. But an opinion which
obtained far more general reception was, that 460 the embryo pre-existed in the
mother, before any union of the sexes.56 It is easy to
see that this doctrine is accompanied with great difficulties;57 for if the mother, at the beginning of
life, contain in her the embryos of all her future children; these
embryos again must contain the children which they are capable of
producing; and so on indefinitely; and thus each female of each
species contains in herself the germs of infinite future generations.
The perplexity which is involved in this notion of an endless series
of creatures, thus encased one within another, has naturally driven
inquirers to attempt other suppositions. The microscopic researches of
Leeuwenhoek and others led them to the belief that there are certain
animalcules contained in the seed of the male, which are the main
agents in the work of reproduction. This system ascribes almost
everything to the male, as the one last mentioned does to the female.
Finally, we have the system of Buffon;—the famous hypothesis of
organic molecules. That philosopher asserted that he found, by
the aid of the microscope, all nature full of moving globules, which
he conceived to be, not animals as Leeuwenhoek imagined, but bodies
capable of producing, by their combination, either animals or
vegetables, in short, all organized bodies. These globules he called
organic molecules.58 And if we inquire how these organic
molecules, proceeding from all parts of the two parents, unite into a
whole, as perfect as either of the progenitors, Buffon answers, that
this is the effect of the interior mould; that is, of a system
of internal laws and tendencies which determine the form of the result
as an external mould determines the shape of the cast.
56 Bourdon, p. 204.
57 Ib. p. 209.
58 Ib. p. 219.
An admirer of Buffon, who has well shown the untenable character of
this system, has urged, as a kind of apology for the promulgation of
the hypothesis,59 that at the period when its author
wrote, he could not present his facts with any hope of being attended
to, if he did not connect them by some common tie, some dominant idea
which might gratify the mind; and that, acting under this necessity,
he did well to substitute for the extant theories, already
superannuated and confessedly imperfect, conjectures more original and
more probable. Without dissenting from this view, we may observe, that
Buffon’s theory, like those which preceded it, is excusable, and even
deserving of admiration, so far as it groups the facts consistently;
because in doing this, it exhibits the necessity, which the
physiological speculator ought to feel, of aspiring to definite and
solid general principles; and that thus, though 461 the theory may not be
established as true, it may be useful by bringing into view the real
nature and application of such principles.
59 Ib. p. 221.
It is, therefore, according to our views, unphilosophical to derive
despair, instead of hope, from the imperfect success of Buffon and his
predecessors. Yet this is what is done by the writer to whom we refer.
“For me,” says he,60 “I vow that, after having long
meditated on the system of Buffon,—a system so remarkable, so
ingenious, so well matured, so wonderfully connected in all its parts,
at first sight so probable;—I confess that, after this long
study, and the researches which it requires, I have conceived in
consequence, a distrust of myself a skepticism, a disdain of
hypothetical systems, a decided predilection and exclusive taste for
pure and rational observation, in short, a disheartening, which I had
never felt before.”
60 Bourdon, p. 274.
The best remedy of such feelings is to be found in the history of
science. Kepler, when he had been driven to reject the solid epicycles
of the ancients, or a person who had admired Kepler as M. Bourdon
admires Buffon, but who saw that his magnetic virtue was an untenable
fiction, might, in the same manner, have thrown up all hope of a sound
theory of the causes of the celestial motions. But astronomers were
too wise and too fortunate to yield to such despondency. The
predecessors of Newton substituted a solid science of Mechanics for
the vague notions of Kepler; and the time soon came when Newton
himself reduced the motions of the heavens to a Law as distinctly
conceived as the Motions had been before.
</div></body></text></TEI>