<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="59">

CHAPTER III.
Application of the Natural History Method to Mineralogy.



1. THE
philosophy of the Sciences of Classification has had great light thrown upon it by
discussions concerning the methods which are used in
Botany: for that science is one of the most complete
examples which can be conceived of the consistent and
successful application of the principles and ideas of
Classification; and this application has been made in
general without giving rise to any very startling paradoxes, or disclosing any insurmountable difficulties.
But the discussions concerning methods of Mineralogical Classification have been instructive for quite a
different reason: they have brought into view the
boundaries and the difficulties of the process of Classification; and have presented examples in which every
possible mode of classifying appeared to involve inextricable contradictions. I will notice some of the points
of this kind which demand our attention, referring to
the works published recently by several mineralogists.
In the History of Mineralogy we noticed the attempt made by Mohs and other Germans to apply to
minerals a method of arrangement similar to that
which has been so successfully employed for plants.
The survey which we have now taken of the grounds
of that method will point out some of the reasons of
the very imperfect success of this attempt. We have
already said that the Terminology of Mineralogy was
materially reformed by Werner; and including in this
branch of the subject (as we must do) the Crystallography of later writers, it may be considered as to a
great extent complete. Of the attempts at a Natural
arrangement, that of Mohs appears to proceed by the 139 method of blind trial, the undefinable perception of
relationship, by which the earliest attempts at a Natural Arrangement of plants were made. Breithaupt
however, has made (though I do not know that he has
published) an essay in a mode which corresponds very
nearly to Adanson’s process of multiplied comparisons.
Having ascertained the specific gravity and hardness
of all the species of minerals, he arranged them in a
table, representing by two lines at right angles to each
other these two numerical quantities. Thus all minerals were distributed according to two co-ordinates
representing specific gravity and hardness. He conceived that the groups which were thus brought together were natural groups. On both these methods, and
on all similar ones, we might observe, that in minerals
as in plants, the mere general notion of Likeness cannot lead us to a real arrangement: this notion requires
to have precision and aim given it by some other relation;—by the relation of Chemical Composition in
minerals, as by the relation of Organic Function in
vegetables. The physical and crystallographical properties of minerals must be studied with reference to
their constitution; and they must be arranged into
Groups which have some common Chemical Character,
before we can consider any advance as made towards a
Natural Arrangement.
In reality, it happens in Mineralogy as it happened
in Botany, that those speculators are regulated by
an obscure perception of this ulterior relation, who
do not profess to be regulated by it. Several of the
Orders of Mohs have really great unity of chemical
character, and thus have good evidence of their being
really Natural Orders.
2. Supposing the Diataxis of minerals thus obtained, Mohs attempted the Diagnosis; and his Characteristick of the Mineral Kingdom, published in
Dresden, in 1820, was the first public indication of his
having constructed a system. From the nature of a
Characteristick, it is necessarily brief, and without any
ostensible principle; but its importance was duly appreciated by the author’s countrymen. Since that 140 time, many attempts have been made at improved
arrangements of minerals, but none, I think, (except
perhaps that of Breithaupt,) professing to proceed
rigorously on the principles of Natural History;—to
arrange by means of external characters, neglecting
altogether, or rather postponing, the consideration of
chemical properties. By relaxing from this rigour,
however, and by combining physical and chemical considerations, arrangements have been obtained (for
example, that of Naumann,) which appear more likely
than the one of Mohs to be approximations to an ultimate really natural system. Naumann’s Classes are
Hydrolytes, Haloides, Silicides, Metal Oxides, Metals,
Sulphurides, Anthracides, with subdivisions of Orders,
as Anhydrous unmetallic Silicides. It may be remarked
that the designations of these are mostly chemical. As
we have observed already, Chemistry, and Mineralogy
in its largest sense, are each the necessary supplement
of the other. If Chemistry furnish the Nomenclature,
Mineralogy must supply the Physiography: if the
Arrangement be founded on External Characters and
the Names be independent of Chemistry, the chemical
composition of each species is an important scientific
Truth respecting it.
3. The inquiry may actually occur, whether any
subordination of groups in the mineral kingdom has
really been made out. The ancient chemical arrangements, for instance, that of Haüy, though professing
to distribute minerals according to Classes, Orders,
Genera, and Species, were not only arbitrary, but inapplicable; for the first postulate of any method, that
the species should have constant characters of unity
and difference, was not satisfied. It was not ascertained
that carbonate of lime was really distinguishable in all
cases from carbonate of magnesia, or of iron; yet these
species were placed in remote parts of the system: and
the above carbonates made just so many species; although, if they were distinct from one another at all,
they were further distinguishable into additional species. Even now, we may, perhaps, say that the limits
of mineralogical species, and their laws of fixity, are 141 not yet clearly seen. For the discoveries of the isomorphous relations and of the optical properties of
minerals have rather shown us in what direction the
object lies, than led us to the goal. It is clear that, in
the mineral kingdom, the Definition of Species, borrowed from the laws of the continuation of the kind,
which holds throughout the organic world, fails us
altogether, and must be replaced by some other condition: nor is it difficult to see that the definite atomic
relations of the chemical constituents, and the definite
crystalline angle, must supply the principles of the
Specific Identity for minerals. Yet the exact limits of
definiteness in both these cases (when we admit the
effect of mechanical mixtures, &c.) have not yet been
completely disentangled. Moreover, any arbitrary assumption (as the allowance of a certain per-centage of
mixture, or a certain small deviation in the angle,) is
altogether contrary to the philosophy of the Natural
System, and can lead to no stable views. It is only
by laborious, extensive, and minute research, that we
can hope to attain to any solid basis of arrangement.
4. Still, though there are many doubts respecting
mineralogical species, a large number of such species
are so far fixed that they may be supposed capable of
being united under the higher divisions of a system
with approximate truth. Of these higher divisions,
those which have been termed Orders appear to tend
to something like a fixed chemical character. Thus
the Haloids of Naumann, and mostly those of Mohs,
are combinations of an oxide with an acid, and thus
resemble Salts, whence their name. The Silicides
contain most of Mohs’s Spaths: and the Orders Pyrites, Glance, and Blende, are common to Naumann
and Mohs; being established by the latter on a difference of external character, which difference is, indeed,
very manifest; and being included by the former in
one chemical Class, Sulphurides. The distinctions of
Hydrous and Anhydrous, Metallic and Unmetallic,
are, of course, chemical distinctions, but occur as the
differences of Orders in Naumann’s mixed system. 142
We may observe that some French writers, following Haüy’s last edition, use, instead of metallic and
unmetallic, autopside metallic and heteropside metallic;
meaning by this phraseology to acknowledge the discovery that earths, etc., are metallic, though they do
not appear to be so, while metals both are and appear
metallic. But this seems to be a refinement not only
useless but absurd. For what is gained by adding the
word metallic, which is common to all, and therefore
makes no distinction? If certain metals are distinguished by their appearing to be metals, this appearance is a reason for giving them the peculiar name,
metals. Nothing is gained by first bringing earths and
metals together, and then immediately separating
them again by new and inconvenient names. No proposition can be expressed better by calling earths, heteropside metallic substances, and therefore such nomenclature is to be rejected.
Granting, then, that the Orders of the best recent
mineralogical systems approximate to natural groups,
we are led to ask whether the same can be said of the
Genera of the Natural History systems, such as those
of Mohs and Breithaupt. And here I must confess
that I see no principle in these Genera; I have failed
to apprehend the conceptions by the application of
which they have been constructed: I shall therefore
not pass any further judgment upon them. The subordination of Mineralogical Species to Orders is a
manifest gain to science: in the interposition of Genera
I see nothing but a source of confusion.
5. In Mineralogy, as in other branches of natural
history, a reformed arrangement ought to give rise to
a reformed Nomenclature; and for this, there is more
occasion at present in Mineralogy than there was in
Botany at the worst period, at least as far as the extent of the subject allows. The characters of minerals
are much more dimly and unfrequently developed
than those of plants; hence arbitrary chemical arrangements, which could not lead to any natural groups,
and therefore not to any good names, prevailed till
recently; and this state of things produced an anarchy 143 in which every man did what seemed right in his own
eyes,—proposed species without any ascertained distinction, and without a thought of subordination, and
gave them arbitrary names; and thus with only about
two or three hundred known species, we have thousands upon thousands of names, of anomalous form
and uncertain application.
Mohs has attempted to reform the Nomenclature of
the subject in a mode consistent with his attempt to
reform the System. In doing this, he has fatally transgressed a rule always insisted upon by the legislators
of Botany, of altering usual names as little as possible;
and his names are both so novel and so cumbrous,
that they appear to have little chance of permanent
currency. They are, perhaps, more unwieldy than
they need to be, by referring, as we have said, to three
of the steps of his classification, the Species, Genus,
and Order. We may, however, assert confidently, from
the whole analogy of natural history, that no good
names can be found which do not refer to at least two
terms of the arrangement. This rule has been practically adopted to a great extent by Naumann, who
gives to most of his Haloids the name Spar, as Calc
spar, Iron spar, &c.; to all his Oxides the terminal
word Erz (Ore); and to the species of the orders Kies
(Pyrites), Glance, and Blende, these names. It has
also been theoretically assented to by Beudant, who
proposes that we should say silicate stilbite, silicate
chabasie; carbonate calcaire, carbonate witherite; sulphate couperose, &c. One great difficulty in this case
would arise from the great number of silicides; it is
not likely that any names would obtain a footing which
tacked the term silicide to another word for each of
these species. The artifice which I have proposed, in
order to obviate this difficulty, is that we should
make the names of the silicides, and those alone, end
in ite or lite, which a large proportion of them do
already.
By this and a few similar contrivances, we might,
I conceive, without any inconvenient change, introduce
into Mineralogy a systematic nomenclature. 144
6. I shall now proceed to make a few remarks on
a work on Mineralogy more recent than those which I
have above noticed, and written with express reference
to such difficulties as I have been discussing. I allude
to the treatise of M. Necker, Le Règne Mineral ramené
aux Methods d’Histoire Naturelle44, which also contains various dissertations on the Philosophy of Classification in general, and its application to Mineralogy
in particular.</div></body></text></TEI>