<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="85">CHAPTER I.
Discovery of Voltaic Electricity.
WE have given the name of
mechanico-chemical to the class of sciences now under our
consideration; for these sciences are concerned with cases in which
mechanical effects, that is, attractions and repulsions, are produced;
while the conditions under which these effects occur, depend, as we
shall hereafter see, on chemical relations. In that branch of these
sciences which we have just treated of, Magnetism, the mechanical
phenomena were obvious, but their connexion with chemical causes was
by no means apparent, and, indeed, has not yet come under our
notice.
The subject to which we now proceed, Galvanism, belongs to the same
group, but, at first sight, exhibits only the other, the chemical,
portion of the features of the class; for the connexion of galvanic
phenomena with chemical action was soon made out, but the mechanical
effects which accompany them were not examined till the examination
was required by a new train of discovery. It is to be observed, that I
do not include in the class of mechanical effects the convulsive
motions in the limbs of animals which are occasioned by galvanic
action; for these movements are produced, not by attraction and
repulsion, but by muscular irritability; and though they indicate the
existence of a peculiar agency, cannot be used to measure its
intensity and law.
The various examples of the class of agents which we here
consider,—magnetism, electricity, galvanism, electro-magnetism,
thermo-electricity,—differ from each other principally in the
circumstances by which they are called into action; and these
differences are in reality of a chemical nature, and will have to be
considered when we come to treat of the inductive steps by which the
general principles of chemical theory are established. In the present
part of our task, therefore, we must take for granted the chemical
conditions on which the excitation of these various kinds of action
depends, and trace the history of the discovery of their mechanical
laws only. This rule will much abridge the account we have here to
give of the progress of discovery in the provinces to which I have
just referred. 238
The first step in this career of discovery was that made by
Galvani, Professor of Anatomy at Bologna. In 1790, electricity, as an
experimental science, was nearly stationary. The impulse given to its
progress by the splendid phenomena of the Leyden phial had almost died
away; Coulomb was employed in systematizing the theory of the electric
fluid, as shown by its statical effects; but in all the other parts of
the subject, no great principle or new result had for some time been
detected. The first announcement of Galvani’s discovery in 1791
excited great notice, for it was given forth as a manifestation of
electricity under a new and remarkable character; namely, as residing
in the muscles of animals.1 The limbs of a dissected frog were
observed to move, when touched with pieces of two different metals;
the agent which produced these motions was conceived to be identified
with electricity, and was termed animal electricity; and
Galvani’s experiments were repeated, with various modifications, in
all parts of Europe, exciting much curiosity, and giving rise to many
speculations.
1 De Viribus Electricis in Motu
Musculari, Comm. Bonon. t. vii. 1792.
It is our business to determine the character of each great
discovery which appears in the progress of science. Men are fond of
repeating that such discoveries are most commonly the result of
accident; and we have seen reason to reject this opinion, since that
preparation of thought by which the accident produces discovery is the
most important of the conditions on which the successful event
depends. Such accidents are like a spark which discharges a gun
already loaded and pointed. In the case of Galvani, indeed, the
discovery may, with more propriety than usual, be said to have been
casual; but in the form in which it was first noted, it exhibited no
important novelty. His frog was lying on a table near the conductor of
an electrical machine, and the convulsions appeared only when a spark
was taken from the machine. If Galvani had been as good a physicist as
he was an anatomist, he would probably have seen that the movements so
occasioned proved only that the muscles or nerves, or the two
together, formed a very sensitive indicator of electrical action. It
was when he produced such motions by contact of metals alone, that he
obtained an important and fundamental fact in science.
The analysis of this fact into its real and essential conditions
was the work of Alexander Volta, another Italian professor. Volta,
indeed, possessed that knowledge of the subject of electricity which
made a hint like that of Galvani the basis of a new science. Galvani
appears 239 never
to have acquired much general knowledge of electricity: Volta, on the
other hand, had labored at this branch of knowledge from the age of
eighteen, through a period of nearly thirty years; and had invented an
electrophorus and an electrical condenser, which showed
great experimental skill. When he turned his attention to the
experiments made by Galvani, he observed that the author of them had
been far more surprised than he needed to be, at those results in
which an electrical spark was produced; and that it was only in the
cases in which no such apparatus was employed, that the observations
could justly be considered as indicating a new law, or a new kind of
electricity.2 He soon satisfied himself3
(about 1794) that the essential conditions of this kind of action
depended on the metals; that it is brought into play most decidedly
when two different metals touch each other, and are connected by any
moist body;—and that the parts of animals which had been used
discharged the office both of such moist bodies, and of very sensitive
electrometers. The animal electricity of Galvani might, he
observed, be with more propriety called metallic
electricity.
2 Phil. Trans. 1793, p.
21.
3 See Fischer, viii. 625.
The recognition of this agency as a peculiar kind of
electricity, arose in part perhaps, at first, from the
confusion made by Galvani between the cases in which his electrical
machine was, and those in which it was not employed. But the identity
was confirmed by its being found that the known difference of
electrical conductors and non-conductors regulated the conduction of
the new influence. The more exact determination of the new facts to
those of electricity was a succeeding step of the progress of the
subject.
The term “animal electricity” has been superseded by others, of
which galvanism is perhaps the most familiar. I think it will
appear from what has been said, that Volta’s office in this discovery
is of a much higher and more philosophical kind than that of Galvani;
and it would, on this account, be more fitting to employ the term
voltaic electricity; which, indeed, is very commonly used,
especially by our most recent and comprehensive writers.
Volta more fully still established his claim as the main originator
of this science by his next step. When some of those who repeated the
experiments of Galvani had expressed a wish that there was some method
of multiplying the effect of this electricity, such as the
Leyden phial supplies for common electricity, they probably thought
their wishes far from a realization. But the voltaic pile,
which Volta 240
described in the Philosophical Transactions for 1800,
completely satisfies this aspiration; and was, in fact, a more
important step in the history of electricity than the Leyden jar had
been. It has since undergone various modifications, of which the most
important was that introduced by Cruickshanks, who4
substituted a trough for a pile. But in all cases the principle of the
instrument was the same;—a continued repetition of the triple
combination of two metals and a fluid in contact, so as to form a
circuit which returns into itself.
4 Fischer, viii. p. 683.
Such an instrument is capable of causing effects of great
intensity; as seen both in the production of light and heat, and in
chemical changes. But the discovery with which we are here concerned,
is not the details and consequences of the effects, (which belong to
chemistry,) but the analysis of the conditions under which such
effects take place; and this we may consider as completed by Volta at
the epoch of which we speak.
</div></body></text></TEI>