<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="19">
CHAPTER III.
Of Methods of acquiring clear Scientific Ideas;
and first of Intellectual Education.
Aphorism XXIX.
The Methods by which the acquisition of clear Scientific
Ideas is promoted, are mainly two; Intellectual Education
and Discussion of Ideas.
Aphorism XXX.
The Idea of Space becomes more clear by studying Geometry;
the Idea of Force, by studying Mechanics; the Ideas
of Likeness, of Kind, of Subordination of Classes, by studying
Natural History.
Aphorism XXXI.
Elementary Mechanics should now form a part of intellectual
education, in order that the student may understand
the Theory of Universal Gravitation: for an intellectual
education should cultivate such ideas as enable the student to
understand the most complete and admirable portions of the
knowledge which the human race has attained to.
Aphorism XXXII.
Natural History ought to form a part of intellectual education,
in order to correct certain prejudices which arise from
cultivating the intellect by means of mathematics alone; and
in order to lead the student to see that the division of things
into Kinds, and the attribution and use of Names, are processes
susceptible of great precision. 165
THE
ways in which men become masters of those
clear and yet comprehensive conceptions which
the formation and reception of science require, are
mainly two; which, although we cannot reduce them
to any exact scheme, we may still, in a loose use of
the term, call Methods of acquiring clear Ideas. These
two ways are Education and Discussion.
1. (I.) Idea of Space.—It is easily seen that
Education may do at least something to render our ideas
distinct and precise. To learn Geometry in youth,
tends, manifestly, to render our idea of space clear and
exact. By such an education, all the relations, and all
the consequences of this idea, come to be readily and
steadily apprehended; and thus it becomes easy for us
to understand portions of science which otherwise we
should by no means be able to comprehend. The conception
of similar triangles was to be mastered, before
the disciples of Thales could see the validity of his
method of determining the height of lofty objects by
the length of their shadows. The conception of the
sphere with its circles had to become familiar, before
the annual motion of the sun and its influence upon
the lengths of days could be rightly traced. The
properties of circles, combined with the
pure13
doctrine of
motion, were required as an introduction to the theory
of Epicycles: the properties of conic sections were
needed, as a preparation for the discoveries of Kepler.
And not only was it necessary that men should possess
a knowledge of certain figures and their properties; but
it was equally necessary that they should have the
habit of reasoning with perfect steadiness, precision,
and conclusiveness concerning the relations of space.
No small discipline of the mind is requisite, in most
cases, to accustom it to go, with complete insight and
security, through the demonstrations respecting intersecting
planes and lines, dihedral and trihedral angles,
which occur in solid geometry. Yet how absolutely
necessary is a perfect mastery of such reasonings, to
him who is to explain the motions of the moon in 166
latitude and longitude! How necessary, again, is the
same faculty to the student of crystallography! Without
mathematical habits of conception and of thinking,
these portions of science are perfectly inaccessible. But
the early study of plane and solid geometry gives to
all tolerably gifted persons, the habits which are thus
needed. The discipline of following the reasonings of
didactic works on this subject, till we are quite familiar
with them, and of devising for ourselves reasonings of
the same kind, (as, for instance, the solutions of problems
proposed,) soon gives the mind the power of discoursing
with perfect facility concerning the most
complex and multiplied relations of space, and enables
us to refer to the properties of all plane and solid
figures as surely as to the visible forms of objects.
Thus we have here a signal instance of the efficacy of
education in giving to our Conceptions that clearness,
which the formation and existence of science indispensably require.
13
 See Hist. Sc. Ideas, b. ii. c. xiii.
2. It is not my intention here to enter into the
details of the form which should be given to education,
in order that it may answer the purposes now contemplated.
But I may make a remark, which the above
examples naturally suggest, that in a mathematical
education, considered as a preparation for furthering
or understanding physical science, Geometry is to be
cultivated, far rather than Algebra:—the properties of
space are to be studied and reasoned upon as they are
in themselves, not as they are replaced and disguised
by symbolical representations. It is true, that when
the student is become quite familiar with elementary
geometry, he may often enable himself to deal in a
more rapid and comprehensive manner with the relations
of space, by using the language of symbols and
the principles of symbolical calculation: but this is an
ulterior step, which may be added to, but can never be
substituted for, the direct cultivation of geometry.
The method of symbolical reasoning employed upon
subjects of geometry and mechanics, has certainly
achieved some remarkable triumphs in the treatment
of the theory of the universe. These successful 167
applications of symbols in the highest problems of physical
astronomy appear to have made some teachers of mathematics
imagine that it is best to begin the pupil’s course
with such symbolical generalities. But this mode of
proceeding will be so far from giving the student clear
ideas of mathematical relations, that it will involve
him in utter confusion, and probably prevent his ever
obtaining a firm footing in geometry. To commence
mathematics in such a way, would be much as if we
should begin the study of a language by reading the
highest strains of its lyrical poetry.
3. (II.) Idea of Number, &c.—The study of
mathematics, as I need hardly observe, developes and renders
exact, our conceptions of the relations of number, as
well as of space. And although, as we have already
noticed, even in their original form the conceptions of
number are for the most part very distinct, they may
be still further improved by such discipline. In complex
cases, a methodical cultivation of the mind in such
subjects is needed: for instance, questions concerning
Cycles, and Intercalations, and Epacts, and the like,
require very great steadiness of arithmetical apprehension
in order that the reasoner may deal with them
rightly. In the same manner, a mastery of problems
belonging to the science of Pure Motion, or, as I have
termed it, Mechanism, requires either great natural
aptitude in the student, or a mind properly disciplined
by suitable branches of mathematical study.
4. Arithmetic and Geometry have long been standard
portions of the education of cultured persons throughout
the civilized world; and hence all such persons have
been able to accept and comprehend those portions of
science which depend upon the idea of space: for instance,
the doctrine of the globular form of the earth,
with its consequences, such as the measures of latitude
and longitude;—the heliocentric system of the universe
in modern, or the geocentric in ancient times;—the
explanation of the rainbow; and the like. In nations
where there is no such education, these portions of
science cannot exist as a part of the general stock of
the knowledge of society, however intelligently they 168
may be pursued by single philosophers dispersed here
and there in the community.
5. (III.) Idea of Force.—As the idea of Space is
brought out in its full evidence by the study of Geometry,
so the idea of Force is called up and developed
by the study of the science of Mechanics. It has
already been shown, in our scrutiny of the Ideas of the
Mechanical Sciences, that Force, the Cause of motion
or of equilibrium, involves an independent Fundamental
Idea, and is quite incapable of being resolved into any
mere modification of our conceptions of space, time,
and motion. And in order that the student may possess
this idea in a precise and manifest shape, he must
pursue the science of Mechanics in the mode which
this view of its nature demands;—that is, he must
study it as an independent science, resting on solid
elementary principles of its own, and not built upon
some other unmechanical science as its substructure.
He must trace the truths of Mechanics from their own
axioms and definitions; these axioms and definitions
being considered as merely means of bringing into
play the Idea on which the science depends. The conceptions
of force and matter, of action and reaction, of
momentum and inertia, with the reasonings in which
they are involved, cannot be evaded by any substitution
of lines or symbols for the conceptions. Any attempts
at such substitution would render the study of
Mechanics useless as a preparation of the mind for
physical science; and would, indeed, except counteracted
by great natural clearness of thought on such
subjects, fill the mind with confused and vague notions,
quite unavailing for any purposes of sound reasoning.
But, on the other hand, the study of Mechanics, in its
genuine form, as a branch of education, is fitted to give
a most useful and valuable precision of thought on
such subjects; and is the more to be recommended,
since, in the general habits of most men’s minds, the
mechanical conceptions are tainted with far greater
obscurity and perplexity than belongs to the conceptions
of number, space, and motion.
6. As habitually distinct conceptions of space and 169
motion were requisite for the reception of the doctrines
of formal astronomy, (the Ptolemaic and Copernican
system,) so a clear and steady conception of force
is indispensably necessary for understanding the Newtonian
system of physical astronomy. It may be objected
that the study of Mechanics as a science has not
commonly formed part of a liberal education in Europe,
and yet that educated persons have commonly accepted
the Newtonian system. But to this we reply, that although
most persons of good intellectual culture have
professed to assent to the Newtonian system of the universe,
yet they have, in fact, entertained it in so vague
and perplexed a manner as to show very clearly that a
better mental preparation than the usual one is necessary,
in order that such persons may really understand
the doctrine of universal attraction. I have elsewhere
spoken of the prevalent indistinctness of mechanical
conceptions14;
and need not here dwell upon the
indications, constantly occurring in conversation and in
literature, of the utter inaccuracy of thought on such
subjects which may often be detected; for instance, in
the mode in which many men speak of centrifugal and
centripetal forces;—of projectile and central forces;—of
the effect of the moon upon the waters of the ocean;
and the like. The incoherence of ideas which we
frequently witness on such points, shows us clearly
that, in the minds of a great number of men, well
educated according to the present standard, the
acceptance of the doctrine of Universal Gravitation is a result
of traditional prejudice, not of rational conviction.
And those who are Newtonians on such grounds, are
not at all more intellectually advanced by being
Newtonians in the nineteenth century, than they would
have been by being Ptolemaics in the fifteenth.
14
 Hist. Sc. Ideas, b. iii. c. x.
7. It is undoubtedly in the highest degree desirable
that all great advances in science should become the
common property of all cultivated men. And this can
only be done by introducing into the course of a liberal
education such studies as unfold and fix in men’s minds 170
the fundamental ideas upon which the new-discovered
truths rest. The progress made by the ancients in
geography, astronomy, and other sciences, led them to
assign, wisely and well, a place to arithmetic and
geometry among the steps of an ingenuous education. The
discoveries of modern times have rendered these steps
still more indispensable; for we cannot consider a man
as cultivated up to the standard of his times, if he is
not only ignorant of, but incapable of comprehending,
the greatest achievements of the human intellect. And
as innumerable discoveries of all ages have thus secured
to Geometry her place as a part of good education, so
the great discoveries of Newton make it proper to introduce
Elementary Mechanics as a part of the same
course. If the education deserve to be called good,
the pupil will not remain ignorant of those discoveries,
the most remarkable extensions of the field of human
knowledge which have ever occurred. Yet he cannot
by possibility comprehend them, except his mind be
previously disciplined by mechanical studies. The period
appears now to be arrived when we may venture,
or rather when we are bound to endeavour, to include
a new class of Fundamental Ideas in the elementary
discipline of the human intellect. This is indispensable,
if we wish to educe the powers which we know
that it possesses, and to enrich it with the wealth which
lies within its reach15.
15
 The University of Cambridge has, by a recent law,
made an examination in Elementary Mechanics requisite for the
Degree of B.A.
8. By the view which is thus presented to us of the
nature and objects of intellectual education, we are led
to consider the mind of man as undergoing a progress
from age to age. By the discoveries which are made,
and by the clearness and evidence which, after a time,
(not suddenly nor soon,) the truths thus discovered acquire,
one portion of knowledge after another becomes
elementary; and if we would really secure this progress,
and make men share in it, these new portions
must be treated as elementary in the constitution of a 171
liberal education. Even in the rudest forms of intelligence,
man is immeasurably elevated above the unprogressive
brute, for the idea of number is so far developed that
he can count his flock or his arrows. But
when number is contemplated in a speculative form, he
has made a vast additional progress; when he steadily
apprehends the relations of space, he has again advanced;
when in thought he carries these relations into
the vault of the sky, into the expanse of the universe,
he reaches a higher intellectual position. And when
he carries into these wide regions, not only the relations
of space and time, but of cause and effect, of
force and reaction, he has again made an intellectual
advance; which, wide as it is at first, is accessible to
all; and with which all should acquaint themselves, if
they really desire to prosecute with energy the ascending
path of truth and knowledge which lies before
them. This should be an object of exertion to all ingenuous
and hopeful minds. For, that exertion is
necessary,—that after all possible facilities have been
afforded, it is still a matter of toil and struggle to
appropriate to ourselves the acquisitions of great discoverers,
is not to be denied. Elementary mechanics,
like elementary geometry, is a study accessible to all:
but like that too, or perhaps more than that, it is a
study which requires effort and contention of mind,—a
forced steadiness of thought. It is long since one complained
of this labour in geometry; and was answered
that in that region there is no Royal Road. The same
is true of Mechanics, and must be true of all branches
of solid education. But we should express the truth
more appropriately in our days by saying that there is
no Popular Road to these sciences. In the mind, as
in the body, strenuous exercise alone can give strength
and activity. The art of exact thought can be acquired
only by the labour of close thinking.
9. (IV.) Chemical Ideas.—We appear then to have
arrived at a point of human progress in which a liberal
education of the scientific intellect should include,
besides arithmetic, elementary geometry and mechanics. 172
The question then occurs to us, whether there are any other
Fundamental Ideas, among those belonging to
other sciences, which ought also to be made part of
such an education;—whether, for example, we should
strive to develope in the minds of all cultured men
the ideas of polarity, mechanical and chemical, of which
we spoke in a former part of this work.
The views to which we have been conducted by the
previous inquiry lead us to reply that it would not be
well at present to make chemical Polarities, at any
rate, a subject of elementary instruction. For even
the most profound and acute philosophers who have
speculated upon this subject,—they who are leading
the van in the march of discovery,—do not seem yet
to have reduced their thoughts on this subject to a
consistency, or to have taken hold of this idea of Polarity
in a manner quite satisfactory to their own
minds. This part of the subject is, therefore, by no
means ready to be introduced into a course of general
elementary education; for, with a view to such a purpose,
nothing less than the most thoroughly luminous
and transparent condition of the idea will suffice. Its
whole efficacy, as a means and object of disciplinal
study, depends upon there being no obscurity, perplexity,
or indefiniteness with regard to it, beyond that
transient deficiency which at first exists in the learner’s
mind, and is to be removed by his studies. The
idea of chemical Polarity is not yet in this condition;
and therefore is not yet fit for a place in education.
Yet since this idea of Polarity is the most general idea
which enters into chemistry, and appears to be that
which includes almost all the others, it would be
unphilosophical, and inconsistent with all sound views of
science, to introduce into education some chemical
conceptions, and to omit those which depend upon this
idea: indeed such a partial adoption of the science
could hardly take place without not only omitting, but
misrepresenting, a great part of our chemical knowledge.
The conclusion to which we are necessarily
led, therefore, is this:—that at present chemistry 173
cannot with any advantage, form a portion of the general
intellectual education16.
16
 I do not here stop to prove that an education
(if it be so called) in which the memory only retains the
verbal expression of results, while the mind does not apprehend
the principles of the subject, and therefore cannot even
understand the words in which its doctrines are expressed,
is of no value whatever to the intellect, but rather, is highly
hurtful to the habits of thinking and reasoning.
10. (V.) Natural-History Ideas.—But there remains
still another class of Ideas, with regard to
which we may very properly ask whether they may
not advantageously form a portion of a liberal education:
I mean the Ideas of definite Resemblance and
Difference, and of one set of resemblances subordinate
to another, which form the bases of the classificatory
sciences. These Ideas are developed by the study of
the various branches of Natural History, as Botany,
and Zoology; and beyond all doubt, those pursuits, if
assiduously followed, very materially affect the mental
habits. There is this obvious advantage to be looked
for from the study of Natural History, considered as
a means of intellectual discipline:—that it gives us, in
a precise and scientific form, examples of the classing
and naming of objects; which operations the use of
common language leads us constantly to perform in a
loose and inexact way. In the usual habits of our
minds and tongues, things are distinguished or brought
together, and names are applied, in a manner very indefinite,
vacillating, and seemingly capricious: and we
may naturally be led to doubt whether such defects
can be avoided;—whether exact distinctions of things,
and rigorous use of words be possible. Now upon this
point we may receive the instruction of Natural History;
which proves to us, by the actual performance of
the task, that a precise classification and nomenclature
are attainable, at least for a mass of objects all of the
same kind. Further, we also learn from this study,
that there may exist, not only an exact distinction of
kinds of things, but a series of distinctions, one set
subordinate to another, and the more general including 174
the more special, so as to form a system of classification.
All these are valuable lessons. If by the study
of Natural History we evolve, in a clear and well defined form,
the conceptions of genus, species, and of
higher and lower steps of classification,
we communicate precision, clearness, and method to the intellect,
through a great range of its operations.
11. It must be observed, that in order to attain the
disciplinal benefit which the study of Natural History
is fitted to bestow, we must teach the natural not the
artificial classifications; or at least the natural as well
as the artificial. For it is important for the student to
perceive that there are classifications, not merely arbitrary,
founded upon some assumed character, but natural, recognized
by some discovered character: he ought
to see that our classes being collected according to one
mark, are confirmed by many marks not originally stated
in our scheme; and are thus found to be grouped
together, not by a single resemblance, but by a mass of
resemblances, indicating a natural affinity. That objects
may be collected into such groups, is a highly important
lesson, which Natural History alone, pursued
as the science of natural classes, can teach.
12. Natural History has not unfrequently been
made a portion of education: and has in some degree
produced such effects as we have pointed out. It
would appear, however, that its lessons have, for the
most part, been very imperfectly learnt or understood
by persons of ordinary education: and that there are
perverse intellectual habits very commonly prevalent
in the cultivated classes, which ought ere now to have
been corrected by the general teaching of Natural
History. We may detect among speculative men
many prejudices respecting the nature and rules of
reasoning, which arise from pure mathematics having
been so long and so universally the instrument of
intellectual cultivation. Pure Mathematics reasons from
definitions: whatever term is introduced into her
pages, as a circle, or a square, its definition comes along
with it: and this definition is supposed to supply all
that the reasoner needs to know, respecting the term. 175
If there be any doubt concerning the validity of the
conclusion, the doubt is resolved by recurring to the
definitions. Hence it has come to pass that in other
subjects also, men seek for and demand definitions as
the most secure foundation of reasoning. The definition
and the term defined are conceived to be so far
identical, that in all cases the one may be substituted
for the other; and such a substitution is held to be
the best mode of detecting fallacies.
13. It has already been shown that even geometry
is not founded upon definitions alone: and we shall
not here again analyse the fallacy of this belief in the
supreme value of definitions. But we may remark
that the study of Natural History appears to be the
proper remedy for this erroneous habit of thought. For
in every department of Natural History the object of
our study is kinds of things, not one of which kinds
can be rigorously defined, yet all of them are sufficiently
definite. In these cases we may indeed give a
specific description of one of the kinds, and may call it
a definition; but it is clear that such a definition does
not contain the essence of the thing. We
say17 that the
Rose Tribe are ‘Polypetalous dicotyledons, with lateral
styles, superior simple ovaria, regular perigynous stamens,
exalbuminous definite seeds, and alternate stipulate leaves.’
But no one would say that this was our
essential conception of a rose, to be substituted for it
in all cases of doubt or obscurity, by way of making
our reasonings perfectly clear. Not only so; but as
we have already seen18,
the definition does not even
apply to all the tribe. For the stipulæ are absent in
Lowea: the albumen is present in Neillia: the fruit of
Spiræa sorbifolia is capsular. If, then, we can possess
any certain knowledge in Natural History, (which no
cultivator of the subject will doubt,) it is evident that
our knowledge cannot depend on the possibility of laying
down exact definitions and reasoning from them.
17
 Lindley’s Nat. Syst. Bot. p. 81.
18
 Hist. Sc. Ideas, b. viii. c. ii. sect. 3.
14. But it may be asked, if we cannot define a 176
word, or a class of things which a word denotes, how
can we distinguish what it does mean from what it
does not mean? How can we say that it signifies one
thing rather than another, except we declare what is
its signification?
The answer to this question involves the general
principle of a natural method of classification, which
has already been stated19
and need not here be again
dwelt on. It has been shown that names of kinds of
things (genera) associate them according to total
resemblances, not partial characters. The principle
which connects a group of objects in natural history is
not a definition, but a type. Thus we take as the type
of the Rose family, it may be, the common wild rose;
all species which resemble this flower more than they
resemble any other group of species are also roses, and
form one genus. All genera which resemble Roses
more than they resemble any other group of genera
are of the same family. And thus the Rose family
is collected about some one species, which is the type
or central point of the group.
19
 Hist. Sc. Ideas, b. viii. c. ii. sect. 3.
In such an arrangement, it may readily be conceived
that though the nucleus of each group may cohere
firmly together, the outskirts of contiguous groups
may approach, and may even be intermingled, so that
some species may doubtfully adhere to one group or
another. Yet this uncertainty does not at all affect
the truths which we find ourselves enabled to assert
with regard to the general mass of each group. And
thus we are taught that there may be very important
differences between two groups of objects, although we
are unable to tell where the one group ends and where
the other begins; and that there may be propositions
of indisputable truth, in which it is impossible to give
unexceptionable definitions of the terms employed.
15. These lessons are of the highest value with
regard to all employments of the human mind; for the
mode in which words in common use acquire their
meaning, approaches far more nearly to the Method of
177 Type than
to the method of definition. The terms
which belong to our practical concerns, or to our spontaneous
and unscientific speculations, are rarely capable
of exact definition. They have been devised in order
to express assertions, often very important, yet very
vaguely conceived: and the signification of the word is
extended, as far as the assertion conveyed by it can be
extended, by apparent connexion or by analogy. And
thus, in all the attempts of man to grasp at knowledge,
we have an exemplification of that which we have
stated as the rule of induction, that Definition and
Proposition are mutually dependent, each adjusted so
as to give value and meaning to the other: and this is
so, even when both the elements of truth are defective
in precision: the Definition being replaced by an
incomplete description or a loose reference to a Type;
and the Proposition being in a corresponding degree
insecure.
16. Thus the study of Natural History, as a corrective
of the belief that definitions are essential to
substantial truth, might be of great use; and the advantage
which might thus be obtained is such as well
entitles this study to a place in a liberal education.
We may further observe, that in order that Natural
History may produce such an effect, it must be studied
by inspection of the objects themselves, and not by the
reading of books only. Its lesson is, that we must in
all cases of doubt or obscurity refer, not to words or
definitions, but to things. The Book of Nature is its
dictionary: it is there that the natural historian looks,
to find the meaning of the words which he
uses20. So
178 long as a plant,
in its most essential parts, is more like
a rose than any thing else, it is a rose. He knows no
other definition.
20
 It is a curious example of the influence of the belief
in definitions, that elementary books have been written in which
Natural History is taught in the way of question and answer, and
consequently by means of words alone. In such a scheme, of course
all objects are defined: and we may easily anticipate
the value of the knowledge thus conveyed. Thus, ‘Iron is a
well-known hard metal, of a darkish gray colour, and very elastic:’
‘Copper is an orange-coloured  metal, more sonorous than any other,
and the most elastic of any except iron.’ This is to pervert
the meaning of education, and to make it a business of mere words.
17. (VI.) Well-established Ideas alone to be used.—We
may assert in general what we have elsewhere, as
above, stated specially with reference to the fundamental
principles of chemistry:—no Ideas are suited to become
the elements of elementary education, till they have not
only become perfectly distinct and fixed in the minds
of the leading cultivators of the science to which they
belong; but till they have been so for some considerable
period. The entire clearness and steadiness of view
which is essential to sound science, must have time to
extend itself to a wide circle of disciples. The views
and principles which are detected by the most profound
and acute philosophers, are soon appropriated by all the
most intelligent and active minds of their own and of
the following generations; and when this has taken
place, (and not till then,) it is right, by a proper
constitution of our liberal education, to extend a general
knowledge of such principles to all cultivated persons.
And it follows, from this view of the matter, that we
are by no means to be in haste to adopt, into our
course of education, all new discoveries as soon as they
are made. They require some time, in order to settle
into their proper place and position in men’s minds,
and to show themselves under their true aspects; and
till this is done, we confuse and disturb, rather than
enlighten and unfold, the ideas of learners, by introducing
the discoveries into our elementary instruction.
Hence it was perhaps reasonable that a century should
elapse from the time of Galileo, before the rigorous
teaching of Mechanics became a general element of
intellectual training; and the doctrine of Universal
Gravitation was hardly ripe for such an employment till
the end of the last century. We must not direct the
unformed youthful mind to launch its little bark upon
the waters of speculation, till all the agitation of
discovery, with its consequent fluctuation and
controversy, has well subsided.
18. But it may be asked, How is it
that time 179 operates
to give distinctness and evidence to scientific
ideas? In what way does it happen that views and
principles, obscure and wavering at first, after a while
become luminous and steady? Can we point out any
process, any intermediate steps, by which this result is
produced? If we can, this process must be an important
portion of the subject now under our consideration.
To this we reply, that the transition from the hesitation
and contradiction with which true ideas are first
received, to the general assent and clear apprehension
which they afterwards obtain, takes place through
the circulation of various arguments for and against
them, and various modes of presenting and testing
them, all which we may include under the term Discussion,
which we have already mentioned as the
second of the two ways by which scientific views are
developed into full maturity.
</div></body></text></TEI>