<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="8">

CHAPTER IV.
OTHER CONSIDERATIONS CONCERNING INNATE PRINCIPLES, BOTH SPECULATIVE AND PRACTICAL.

1. Principles not innate, unless their Ideas be innate


Had those who would persuade us that there are innate principles not taken them
together in gross, but considered separately the parts out of which those
propositions are made, they would not, perhaps, have been so forward to believe
they were innate. Since, if the IDEAS which made up those truths were not, it
was impossible that the PROPOSITIONS made up of them should be innate, or our
knowledge of them be born with us. For, if the ideas be not innate, there was a
time when the mind was without those principles; and then they will not be
innate, but be derived from some other original. For, where the ideas
themselves are not, there can be no knowledge, no assent, no mental or verbal
propositions about them.


2. Ideas, especially those belonging to Principles, not born with children


If we will attentively consider new-born children, we shall have little reason
to think that they bring many ideas into the world with them. For, bating
perhaps some faint ideas of hunger, and thirst, and warmth, and some pains,
which they may have felt in the womb, there is not the least appearance of any
settled ideas at all in them; especially of IDEAS ANSWERING THE TERMS WHICH
MAKE UP THOSE UNIVERSAL PROPOSITIONS THAT ARE ESTEEMED INNATE PRINCIPLES. One
may perceive how, by degrees, afterwards, ideas come into their minds; and that
they get no more, nor other, than what experience, and the observation of
things that come in their way, furnish them with; which might be enough to
satisfy us that they are not original characters stamped on the mind.


3. Impossibility and Identity not innate ideas


“It is impossible for the same thing to be, and not to be,” is certainly (if
there be any such) an innate PRINCIPLE. But can any one think, or will any one
say, that “impossibility” and “identity” are two innate IDEAS? Are they such as
all mankind have, and bring into the world with them? And are they those which
are the first in children, and antecedent to all acquired ones? If they are
innate, they must needs be so. Hath a child an idea of impossibility and
identity, before it has of white or black, sweet or bitter? And is it from the
knowledge of this principle that it concludes, that wormwood rubbed on the
nipple hath not the same taste that it used to receive from thence? Is it the
actual knowledge of IMPOSSIBILE EST IDEM ESSE, ET NON ESSE, that makes a child
distinguish between its mother and a stranger; or that makes it fond of the one
and flee the other? Or does the mind regulate itself and its assent by ideas
that it never yet had? Or the understanding draw conclusions from principles
which it never yet knew or understood? The names IMPOSSIBILITY and IDENTITY
stand for two ideas, so far from being innate, or born with us, that I think it
requires great care and attention to form them right in our understandings.
They are so far from being brought into the world with us, so remote from the
thoughts of infancy and childhood, that I believe, upon examination it will be
found that many grown men want them.


4. Identity, an Idea not innate.


If IDENTITY (to instance that alone) be a native impression, and consequently
so clear and obvious to us that we must needs know it even from our cradles, I
would gladly be resolved by any one of seven, or seventy years old, whether a
man, being a creature consisting of soul and body, be the same man when his
body is changed? Whether Euphorbus and Pythagoras, having had the same soul,
were the same men, though they lived several ages asunder? Nay, whether the
cock too, which had the same soul, were not the same, with both of them?
Whereby, perhaps, it will appear that our idea of SAMENESS is not so settled
and clear as to deserve to be thought innate in us. For if those innate ideas
are not clear and distinct, so as to be universally known and naturally agreed
on, they cannot be subjects of universal and undoubted truths, but will be the
unavoidable occasion of perpetual uncertainty. For, I suppose every one’s idea
of identity will not be the same that Pythagoras and thousands of his followers
have. And which then shall be true? Which innate? Or are there two different
ideas of identity, both innate?


5. What makes the same man?


Nor let any one think that the questions I have here proposed about the
identity of man are bare empty speculations; which, if they were, would be
enough to show, that there was in the understandings of men no innate idea of
identity. He that shall with a little attention reflect on the resurrection,
and consider that divine justice will bring to judgment, at the last day, the
very same persons, to be happy or miserable in the other, who did well or ill
in this life, will find it perhaps not easy to resolve with himself, what makes
the same man, or wherein identity consists; and will not be forward to think
he, and every one, even children themselves, have naturally a clear idea of it.


6. Whole and Part not innate ideas.


Let us examine that principle of mathematics, viz. THAT THE WHOLE IS BIGGER
THAN A PART. This, I take it, is reckoned amongst innate principles. I am sure
it has as good a title as any to be thought so; which yet nobody can think it
to be, when he considers the ideas it comprehends in it, WHOLE and PART, are
perfectly relative; but the positive ideas to which they properly and
immediately belong are extension and number, of which alone whole and part are
relations. So that if whole and part are innate ideas, extension and number
must be so too; it being impossible to have an idea of a relation, without
having any at all of the thing to which it belongs, and in which it is founded.
Now, whether the minds of men have naturally imprinted on them the ideas of
extension and number, I leave to be considered by those who are the patrons of
innate principles.


7. Idea of Worship not innate.


That GOD IS TO BE WORSHIPPED, is, without doubt, as great a truth as any that
can enter into the mind of man, and deserves the first place amongst all
practical principles. But yet it can by no means be thought innate, unless the
ideas of GOD and WORSHIP are innate. That the idea the term worship stands for
is not in the understanding of children, and a character stamped on the mind in
its first original, I think will be easily granted, by any one that considers
how few there be amongst grown men who have a clear and distinct notion of it.
And, I suppose, there cannot be anything more ridiculous than to say, that
children have this practical principle innate, “That God is to be worshipped,”
and yet that they know not what that worship of God is, which is their duty.
But to pass by this.


8. Idea of God not innate.


If any idea can be imagined innate, the idea of GOD may, of all others, for
many reasons, be thought so; since it is hard to conceive how there should be
innate moral principles, without an innate idea of a Deity. Without a notion of
a law-maker, it is impossible to have a notion of a law, and an obligation to
observe it. Besides the atheists taken notice of amongst the ancients, and left
branded upon the records of history, hath not navigation discovered, in these
later ages, whole nations, at the bay of Soldania, in Brazil, and in the
Caribbee islands, &c., amongst whom there was to be found no notion of a
God, no religion? Nicholaus del Techo, in Literis ex Paraquaria, de Caiguarum
Conversione, has these words: Reperi eam gentem nullum nomen habere quod Deum,
et hominis animam significet; nulla sacra habet, nulla idola.


And perhaps, if we should with attention mind the lives and discourses of
people not so far off, we should have too much reason to fear, that many, in
more civilized countries, have no very strong and clear impressions of a Deity
upon their minds, and that the complaints of atheism made from the pulpit are
not without reason. And though only some profligate wretches own it too
barefacedly now; yet perhaps we should hear more than we do of it from others,
did not the fear of the magistrate’s sword, or their neighbour’s censure, tie
up people’s tongues; which, were the apprehensions of punishment or shame taken
away, would as openly proclaim their atheism as their lives do.


9. The name of God not universal or obscure in meaning.


But had all mankind everywhere a notion of a God, (whereof yet history tells us
the contrary,) it would not from thence follow, that the idea of him was
innate. For, though no nation were to be found without a name, and some few
dark notions of him, yet that would not prove them to be natural impressions on
the mind; no more than the names of fire, or the sun, heat, or number, do prove
the ideas they stand for to be innate; because the names of those things, and
the ideas of them, are so universally received and known amongst mankind. Nor,
on the contrary, is the want of such a name, or the absence of such a notion
out of men’s minds, any argument against the being of a God; any more than it
would be a proof that there was no loadstone in the world, because a great part
of mankind had neither a notion of any such thing nor a name for it; or be any
show of argument to prove that there are no distinct and various species of
angels, or intelligent beings above us, because we have no ideas of such
distinct species, or names for them. For, men being furnished with words, by
the common language of their own countries, can scarce avoid having some kind
of ideas of those things whose names those they converse with have occasion
frequently to mention to them. And if they carry with it the notion of
excellency, greatness, or something extraordinary; if apprehension and
concernment accompany it; if the fear of absolute and irresistible power set it
on upon the mind,—the idea is likely to sink the deeper, and spread the
further; especially if it be such an idea as is agreeable to the common light
of reason, and naturally deducible from every part of our knowledge, as that of
a God is. For the visible marks of extraordinary wisdom and power appear so
plainly in all the works of the creation, that a rational creature, who will
but seriously reflect on them, cannot miss the discovery of a Deity. And the
influence that the discovery of such a Being must necessarily have on the minds
of all that have but once heard of it is so great, and carries such a weight of
thought and communication with it, that it seems stranger to me that a whole
nation of men should be anywhere found so brutish as to want the notion of a
God, than that they should be without any notion of numbers, or fire.


10. Ideas of God and idea of Fire.


The name of God being once mentioned in any part of the world, to express a
superior, powerful, wise, invisible Being, the suitableness of such a notion to
the principles of common reason, and the interest men will always have to
mention it often, must necessarily spread it far and wide; and continue it down
to all generations: though yet the general reception of this name, and some
imperfect and unsteady notions conveyed thereby to the unthinking part of
mankind, prove not the idea to be innate; but only that they who made the
discovery had made a right use of their reason, thought maturely of the causes
of things, and traced them to their original; from whom other less considering
people having once received so important a notion, it could not easily be lost
again.


11. Idea of God not innate.


This is all could be inferred from the notion of a God, were it to be found
universally in all the tribes of mankind, and generally acknowledged, by men
grown to maturity in all countries. For the generality of the acknowledging of
a God, as I imagine, is extended no further than that; which, if it be
sufficient to prove the idea of God innate, will as well prove the idea of fire
innate; since I think it may be truly said, that there is not a person in the
world who has a notion of a God, who has not also the idea of fire. I doubt not
but if a colony of young children should be placed in an island where no fire
was, they would certainly neither have any notion of such a thing, nor name for
it, how generally soever it were received and known in all the world besides;
and perhaps too their apprehensions would be as far removed from any name, or
notion, of a God, till some one amongst them had employed his thoughts to
inquire into the constitution and causes of things, which would easily lead him
to the notion of a God; which having once taught to others, reason, and the
natural propensity of their own thoughts, would afterwards propagate, and
continue amongst them.


12. Suitable to God’s goodness, that all Men should have an idea of Him,
therefore naturally imprinted by Him, answered.


Indeed it is urged, that it is suitable to the goodness of God, to imprint upon
the minds of men characters and notions of himself, and not to leave them in
the dark and doubt in so grand a concernment; and also, by that means, to
secure to himself the homage and veneration due from so intelligent a creature
as man; and therefore he has done it.


This argument, if it be of any force, will prove much more than those who use
it in this case expect from it. For, if we may conclude that God hath done for
men all that men shall judge is best for them, because it is suitable to his
goodness so to do, it will prove, not only that God has imprinted on the minds
of men an idea of himself, but that he hath plainly stamped there, in fair
characters, all that men ought to know or believe of him; all that they ought
to do in obedience to his will; and that he hath given them a will and
affections conformable to it. This, no doubt, every one will think better for
men, than that they should, in the dark, grope after knowledge, as St. Paul
tells us all nations did after God (Acts xvii. 27); than that their wills
should clash with their understandings, and their appetites cross their duty.
The Romanists say it is best for men, and so suitable to the goodness of God,
that there should be an infallible judge of controversies on earth; and
therefore there is one. And I, by the same reason, say it is better for men
that every man himself should be infallible. I leave them to consider, whether,
by the force of this argument, they shall think that every man IS so. I think
it a very good argument to say,—the infinitely wise God hath made it so;
and therefore it is best. But it seems to me a little too much confidence of
our own wisdom to say,—‘I think it best; and therefore God hath made it
so.’ And in the matter in hand, it will be in vain to argue from such a topic,
that God hath done so, when certain experience shows us that he hath not. But
the goodness of God hath not been wanting to men, without such original
impressions of knowledge or ideas stamped on the mind; since he hath furnished
man with those faculties which will serve for the sufficient discovery of all
things requisite to the end of such a being; and I doubt not but to show, that
a man, by the right use of his natural abilities, may, without any innate
principles, attain a knowledge of a God, and other things that concern him. God
having endued man with those faculties of knowledge which he hath, was no more
obliged by his goodness to plant those innate notions in his mind, than that,
having given him reason, hands, and materials, he should build him bridges or
houses,—which some people in the world, however of good parts, do either
totally want, or are but ill provided of, as well as others are wholly without
ideas of God and principles of morality, or at least have but very ill ones;
the reason in both cases being, that they never employed their parts,
faculties, and powers industriously that way, but contented themselves with the
opinions, fashions, and things of their country, as they found them, without
looking any further. Had you or I been born at the Bay of Soldania, possibly
our thoughts and notions had not exceeded those brutish ones of the Hottentots
that inhabit there. And had the Virginia king Apochancana been educated in
England, he had been perhaps as knowing a divine, and as good a mathematician
as any in it; the difference between him and a more improved Englishman lying
barely in this, that the exercise of his faculties was bounded within the ways,
modes, and notions of his own country, and never directed to any other or
further inquiries. And if he had not any idea of a God, it was only because he
pursued not those thoughts that would have led him to it.


13. Ideas of God various in different Men.


I grant that if there were any ideas to be found imprinted on the minds of men,
we have reason to expect it should be the notion of his Maker, as a mark God
set on his own workmanship, to mind man of his dependence and duty; and that
herein should appear the first instances of human knowledge. But how late is it
before any such notion is discoverable in children? And when we find it there,
how much more does it resemble the opinion and notion of the teacher, than
represent the true God? He that shall observe in children the progress whereby
their minds attain the knowledge they have, will think that the objects they do
first and most familiarly converse with are those that make the first
impressions on their understandings; nor will he find the least footsteps of
any other. It is easy to take notice how their thoughts enlarge themselves,
only as they come to be acquainted with a greater variety of sensible objects;
to retain the ideas of them in their memories; and to get the skill to compound
and enlarge them, and several ways put them together. How, by these means, they
come to frame in their minds an idea men have of a Deity, I shall hereafter
show.


14. Contrary and inconsistent ideas of God under the same name.


Can it be thought that the ideas men have of God are the characters and marks
of himself, engraven in their minds by his own finger, when we see that, in the
same country, under one and the same name, men have far different, nay often
contrary and inconsistent ideas and conceptions of him? Their agreeing in a
name, or sound, will scarce prove an innate notion of him.


15. Gross ideas of God.


What true or tolerable notion of a Deity could they have, who acknowledged and
worshipped hundreds? Every deity that they owned above one was an infallible
evidence of their ignorance of Him, and a proof that they had no true notion of
God, where unity, infinity, and eternity were excluded. To which, if we add
their gross conceptions of corporeity, expressed in their images and
representations of their deities; the amours, marriages, copulations, lusts,
quarrels, and other mean qualities attributed by them to their gods; we shall
have little reason to think that the heathen world, i.e. the greatest part of
mankind, had such ideas of God in their minds as he himself, out of care that
they should not be mistaken about him, was author of. And this universality of
consent, so much argued, if it prove any native impressions, it will be only
this:—that God imprinted on the minds of all men speaking the same
language, a NAME for himself, but not any IDEA; since those people who agreed
in the name, had, at the same time, far different apprehensions about the thing
signified. If they say that the variety of deities worshipped by the heathen
world were but figurative ways of expressing the several attributes of that
incomprehensible Being, or several parts of his providence, I answer: what they
might be in the original I will not here inquire; but that they were so in the
thoughts of the vulgar I think nobody will affirm. And he that will consult the
voyage of the Bishop of Beryte, c. 13, (not to mention other testimonies,) will
find that the theology of the Siamites professedly owns a plurality of gods:
or, as the Abbe de Choisy more judiciously remarks in his Journal du Voyage de
Siam, 107/177, it consists properly in acknowledging no God at all.


16. Idea of God not innate although wise men of all nations come to have it.


If it be said, that wise men of all nations came to have true conceptions of
the unity and infinity of the Deity, I grant it. But then this,


First, excludes universality of consent in anything but the name; for those
wise men being very few, perhaps one of a thousand, this universality is very
narrow.


Secondly, it seems to me plainly to prove, that the truest and best notions men
have of God were not imprinted, but acquired by thought and meditation, and a
right use of their faculties: since the wise and considerate men of the world,
by a right and careful employment of their thoughts and reason, attained true
notions in this as well as other things; whilst the lazy and inconsiderate part
of men, making far the greater number, took up their notions by chance, from
common tradition and vulgar conceptions, without much beating their heads about
them. And if it be a reason to think the notion of God innate, because all wise
men had it, virtue too must be thought innate; for that also wise men have
always had.


17. Odd, low, and pitiful ideas of God common among men.


This was evidently the case of all Gentilism. Nor hath even amongst Jews,
Christians, and Mahometans, who acknowledged but one God, this doctrine, and
the care taken in those nations to teach men to have true notions of a God,
prevailed so far as to make men to have the same and the true ideas of him. How
many even amongst us, will be found upon inquiry to fancy him in the shape of a
man sitting in heaven; and to have many other absurd and unfit conceptions of
him? Christians as well as Turks have had whole sects owning and contending
earnestly for it,—that the Deity was corporeal, and of human shape: and
though we find few now amongst us who profess themselves Anthropomorphites,
(though some I have met with that own it,) yet I believe he that will make it
his business may find amongst the ignorant and uninstructed Christians many of
that opinion. Talk but with country people, almost of any age, or young people
almost of any condition, and you shall find that, though the name of God be
frequently in their mouths, yet the notions they apply this name to are so odd,
low, and pitiful, that nobody can imagine they were taught by a rational man;
much less that they were characters written by the finger of God himself. Nor
do I see how it derogates more from the goodness of God, that he has given us
minds unfurnished with these ideas of himself, than that he hath sent us into
the world with bodies unclothed; and that there is no art or skill born with
us. For, being fitted with faculties to attain these, it is want of industry
and consideration in us, and not of bounty in him, if we have them not. It is
as certain that there is a God, as that the opposite angles made by the
intersection of two straight lines are equal. There was never any rational
creature that set himself sincerely to examine the truth of these propositions
that could fail to assent to them; though yet it be past doubt that there are
many men, who, having not applied their thoughts that way, are ignorant both of
the one and the other. If any one think fit to call this (which is the utmost
of its extent) UNIVERSAL CONSENT, such an one I easily allow; but such an
universal consent as this proves not the idea of God, any more than it does the
idea of such angles, innate.


18. If the Idea of God be not innate, no other can be supposed innate.


Since then though the knowledge of a God be the most natural discovery of human
reason, yet the idea of him is not innate, as I think is evident from what has
been said; I imagine there will be scarce any other idea found that can pretend
to it. Since if God hath set any impression, any character, on the
understanding of men, it is most reasonable to expect it should have been some
clear and uniform idea of Himself; as far as our weak capacities were capable
to receive so incomprehensible and infinite an object. But our minds being at
first void of that idea which we are most concerned to have, it is a strong
presumption against all other innate characters. I must own, as far as I can
observe, I can find none, and would be glad to be informed by any other.


19. Idea of Substance not innate.


I confess there is another idea which would be of general use for mankind to
have, as it is of general talk as if they had it; and that is the idea of
SUBSTANCE; which we neither have nor can have by sensation or reflection. If
nature took care to provide us any ideas, we might well expect they should be
such as by our own faculties we cannot procure to ourselves; but we see, on the
contrary, that since, by those ways whereby other ideas are brought into our
minds, this is not, we have no such clear idea at all; and therefore signify
nothing by the word SUBSTANCE but only an uncertain supposition of we know not
what, i. e. of something whereof we have no idea, which we take to be the
substratum, or support, of those ideas we do know.


20. No Propositions can be innate, since no Ideas are innate.


Whatever then we talk of innate, either speculative or practical, principles,
it may with as much probability be said, that a man hath 100 pounds sterling in
his pocket, and yet denied that he hath there either penny, shilling, crown, or
other coin out of which the sum is to be made up; as to think that certain
PROPOSITIONS are innate when the IDEAS about which they are can by no means be
supposed to be so. The general reception and assent that is given doth not at
all prove, that the ideas expressed in them are innate; for in many cases,
however the ideas came there, the assent to words expressing the agreement or
disagreement of such ideas, will necessarily follow. Every one that hath a true
idea of GOD and WORSHIP, will assent to this proposition, ‘That God is to be
worshipped,’ when expressed in a language he understands; and every rational
man that hath not thought on it to-day, may be ready to assent to this
proposition to-morrow; and yet millions of men may be well supposed to want one
or both those ideas to-day. For, if we will allow savages, and most country
people, to have ideas of God and worship, (which conversation with them will
not make one forward to believe,) yet I think few children can be supposed to
have those ideas, which therefore they must begin to have some time or other;
and then they will also begin to assent to that proposition, and make very
little question of it ever after. But such an assent upon hearing, no more
proves the IDEAS to be innate, than it does that one born blind (with cataracts
which will be couched to-morrow) had the innate ideas of the sun, or light, or
saffron, or yellow; because, when his sight is cleared, he will certainly
assent to this proposition, “That the sun is lucid, or that saffron is yellow.”
And therefore, if such an assent upon hearing cannot prove the ideas innate, it
can much less the PROPOSITIONS made up of those ideas. If they have any innate
ideas, I would be glad to be told what, and how many, they are.


21. No innate Ideas in the Memory.


To which let me add: if there be any innate ideas, any ideas in the mind which
the mind does not actually think on, they must be lodged in the memory; and
from thence must be brought into view by remembrance; i. e. must be known, when
they are remembered, to have been perceptions in the mind before; unless
remembrance can be without remembrance. For, to remember is to perceive
anything with memory, or with a consciousness that it was perceived or known
before. Without this, whatever idea comes into the mind is new, and not
remembered; this consciousness of its having been in the mind before, being
that which distinguishes remembering from all other ways of thinking. Whatever
idea was never PERCEIVED by the mind was never in the mind. Whatever idea is in
the mind, is, either an actual perception, or else, having been an actual
perception, is so in the mind that, by the memory, it can be made an actual
perception again. Whenever there is the actual perception of any idea without
memory, the idea appears perfectly new and unknown before to the understanding.
Whenever the memory brings any idea into actual view, it is with a
consciousness that it had been there before, and was not wholly a stranger to
the mind. Whether this be not so, I appeal to every one’s observation. And then
I desire an instance of an idea, pretended to be innate, which (before any
impression of it by ways hereafter to be mentioned) any one could revive and
remember, as an idea he had formerly known; without which consciousness of a
former perception there is no remembrance; and whatever idea comes into the
mind without THAT consciousness is not remembered, or comes not out of the
memory, nor can be said to be in the mind before that appearance. For what is
not either actually in view or in the memory, is in the mind no way at all, and
is all one as if it had never been there. Suppose a child had the use of his
eyes till he knows and distinguishes colours; but then cataracts shut the
windows, and he is forty or fifty years perfectly in the dark; and in that time
perfectly loses all memory of the ideas of colours he once had. This was the
case of a blind man I once talked with, who lost his sight by the small-pox
when he was a child, and had no more notion of colours than one born blind. I
ask whether any one can say this man had then any ideas of colours in his mind,
any more than one born blind? And I think nobody will say that either of them
had in his mind any ideas of colours at all. His cataracts are couched, and
then he has the ideas (which he remembers not) of colours, DE NOVO, by his
restored sight, conveyed to his mind, and that without any consciousness of a
former acquaintance. And these now he can revive and call to mind in the dark.
In this case all these ideas of colours which, when out of view, can be revived
with a consciousness of a former acquaintance, being thus in the memory, are
said to be in the mind. The use I make of this is,—that whatever idea,
being not actually in view, is in the mind, is there only by being in the
memory; and if it be not in the memory, it is not in the mind; and if it be in
the memory, it cannot by the memory be brought into actual view without a
perception that it comes out of the memory; which is this, that it had been
known before, and is now remembered. If therefore there be any innate ideas,
they must be in the memory, or else nowhere in the mind; and if they be in the
memory, they can be revived without any impression from without; and whenever
they are brought into the mind they are remembered, i. e. they bring with them
a perception of their not being wholly new to it. This being a constant and
distinguishing difference between what is, and what is not in the memory, or in
the mind;—that what is not in the memory, whenever it appears there,
appears perfectly new and unknown before; and what is in the memory, or in the
mind, whenever it is suggested by the memory, appears not to be new, but the
mind finds it in itself, and knows it was there before. By this it may be tried
whether there be any innate ideas in the mind before impression from sensation
or reflection. I would fain meet with the man who, when he came to the use of
reason, or at any other time, remembered any of them; and to whom, after he was
born, they were never new. If any one will say, there are ideas in the mind
that are NOT in the memory, I desire him to explain himself, and make what he
says intelligible.


22. Principles not innate, because of little use or little certainty.


Besides what I have already said, there is another reason why I doubt that
neither these nor any other principles are innate. I that am fully persuaded
that the infinitely wise God made all things in perfect wisdom, cannot satisfy
myself why he should be supposed to print upon the minds of men some universal
principles; whereof those that are pretended innate, and concern SPECULATION,
are of no great use; and those that concern PRACTICE, not self-evident; and
neither of them distinguishable from some other truths not allowed to be
innate. For, to what purpose should characters be graven on the mind by the
finger of God, which are not clearer there than those which are afterwards
introduced, or cannot be distinguished from them? If any one thinks there are
such innate ideas and propositions, which by their clearness and usefulness are
distinguishable from all that is adventitious in the mind and acquired, it will
not be a hard matter for him to tell us WHICH THEY ARE; and then every one will
be a fit judge whether they be so or no. Since if there be such innate ideas
and impressions, plainly different from all other perceptions and knowledge,
every one will find it true in himself. Of the evidence of these supposed
innate maxims, I have spoken already: of their usefulness I shall have occasion
to speak more hereafter.


23. Difference of Men’s Discoveries depends upon the different Application of
their Faculties.


To conclude: some ideas forwardly offer themselves to all men’s understanding;
and some sorts of truths result from any ideas, as soon as the mind puts them
into propositions: other truths require a train of ideas placed in order, a due
comparing of them, and deductions made with attention, before they can be
discovered and assented to. Some of the first sort, because of their general
and easy reception, have been mistaken for innate: but the truth is, ideas and
notions are no more born with us than arts and sciences; though some of them
indeed offer themselves to our faculties more readily than others; and
therefore are more generally received: though that too be according as the
organs of our bodies and powers of our minds happen to be employed; God having
fitted men with faculties and means to discover, receive, and retain truths,
according as they are employed. The great difference that is to be found in the
notions of mankind is, from the different use they put their faculties to.
Whilst some (and those the most) taking things upon trust, misemploy their
power of assent, by lazily enslaving their minds to the dictates and dominion
of others, in doctrines which it is their duty carefully to examine, and not
blindly, with an implicit faith, to swallow; others, employing their thoughts
only about some few things, grow acquainted sufficiently with them, attain
great degrees of knowledge in them, and are ignorant of all other, having never
let their thoughts loose in the search of other inquiries. Thus, that the three
angles of a triangle are quite equal to two right ones is a truth as certain as
anything can be, and I think more evident than many of those propositions that
go for principles; and yet there are millions, however expert in other things,
who know not this at all, because they never set their thoughts on work about
such angles. And he that certainly knows this proposition may yet be utterly
ignorant of the truth of other propositions, in mathematics itself, which are
as clear and evident as this; because, in his search of those mathematical
truths, he stopped his thoughts short and went not so far. The same may happen
concerning the notions we have of the being of a Deity. For, though there be no
truth which a man may more evidently make out to himself than the existence of
a God, yet he that shall content himself with things as he finds them in this
world, as they minister to his pleasures and passions, and not make inquiry a
little further into their causes, ends, and admirable contrivances, and pursue
the thoughts thereof with diligence and attention, may live long without any
notion of such a Being. And if any person hath by talk put such a notion into
his head, he may perhaps believe it; but if he hath never examined it, his
knowledge of it will be no perfecter than his, who having been told, that the
three angles of a triangle are equal to two right ones, takes it upon trust,
without examining the demonstration; and may yield his assent as a probable
opinion, but hath no knowledge of the truth of it; which yet his faculties, if
carefully employed, were able to make clear and evident to him. But this only,
by the by, to show how much OUR KNOWLEDGE DEPENDS UPON THE RIGHT USE OF THOSE
POWERS NATURE HATH BESTOWED UPON US, and how little upon SUCH INNATE PRINCIPLES
AS ARE IN VAIN SUPPOSED TO BE IN ALL MANKIND FOR THEIR DIRECTION; which all men
could not but know if they were there, or else they would be there to no
purpose. And which since all men do not know, nor can distinguish from other
adventitious truths, we may well conclude there are no such.


24. Men must think and know for themselves.


What censure doubting thus of innate principles may deserve from men, who will
be apt to call it pulling up the old foundations of knowledge and certainty, I
cannot tell;—I persuade myself at least that the way I have pursued,
being conformable to truth, lays those foundations surer. This I am certain, I
have not made it my business either to quit or follow any authority in the
ensuing Discourse. Truth has been my only aim; and wherever that has appeared
to lead, my thoughts have impartially followed, without minding whether the
footsteps of any other lay that way or not. Not that I want a due respect to
other men’s opinions; but, after all, the greatest reverence is due to truth:
and I hope it will not be thought arrogance to say, that perhaps we should make
greater progress in the discovery of rational and contemplative knowledge, if
we sought it in the fountain, IN THE CONSIDERATION OF THINGS THEMSELVES; and
made use rather of our own thoughts than other men’s to find it. For I think we
may as rationally hope to see with other men’s eyes, as to know by other men’s
understandings. So much as we ourselves consider and comprehend of truth and
reason, so much we possess of real and true knowledge. The floating of other
men’s opinions in our brains, makes us not one jot the more knowing, though
they happen to be true. What in them was science, is in us but opiniatrety;
whilst we give up our assent only to reverend names, and do not, as they did,
employ our own reason to understand those truths which gave them reputation.
Aristotle was certainly a knowing man, but nobody ever thought him so because
he blindly embraced, and confidently vented the opinions of another. And if the
taking up of another’s principles, without examining them, made not him a
philosopher, I suppose it will hardly make anybody else so. In the sciences,
every one has so much as he really knows and comprehends. What he believes
only, and takes upon trust, are but shreds; which, however well in the whole
piece, make no considerable addition to his stock who gathers them. Such
borrowed wealth, like fairy money, though it were gold in the hand from which
he received it, will be but leaves and dust when it comes to use.


25. Whence the Opinion of Innate Principles.


When men have found some general propositions that could not be doubted of as
soon as understood, it was, I know, a short and easy way to conclude them
innate. This being once received, it eased the lazy from the pains of search,
and stopped the inquiry of the doubtful concerning all that was once styled
innate. And it was of no small advantage to those who affected to be masters
and teachers, to make this the principle of principles,—THAT PRINCIPLES
MUST NOT BE QUESTIONED. For, having once established this tenet,—that
there are innate principles, it put their followers upon a necessity of
receiving SOME doctrines as such; which was to take them off from the use of
their own reason and judgment, and put them on believing and taking them upon
trust without further examination: in which posture of blind credulity, they
might be more easily governed by, and made useful to some sort of men, who had
the skill and office to principle and guide them. Nor is it a small power it
gives one man over another, to have the authority to be the dictator of
principles, and teacher of unquestionable truths; and to make a man swallow
that for an innate principle which may serve to his purpose who teacheth them.
Whereas had they examined the ways whereby men came to the knowledge of many
universal truths, they would have found them to result in the minds of men from
the being of things themselves, when duly considered; and that they were
discovered by the application of those faculties that were fitted by nature to
receive and judge of them, when duly employed about them.


26. Conclusion.


To show HOW the understanding proceeds herein is the design of the following
Discourse; which I shall proceed to when I have first premised, that
hitherto,—to clear my way to those foundations which I conceive are the
only true ones, whereon to establish those notions we can have of our own
knowledge,—it hath been necessary for me to give an account of the
reasons I had to doubt of innate principles. And since the arguments which are
against them do, some of them, rise from common received opinions, I have been
forced to take several things for granted; which is hardly avoidable to any
one, whose task is to show the falsehood or improbability of any
tenet;—it happening in controversial discourses as it does in assaulting
of towns; where, if the ground be but firm whereon the batteries are erected,
there is no further inquiry of whom it is borrowed, nor whom it belongs to, so
it affords but a fit rise for the present purpose. But in the future part of
this Discourse, designing to raise an edifice uniform and consistent with
itself, as far as my own experience and observation will assist me, I hope to
erect it on such a basis that I shall not need to shore it up with props and
buttresses, leaning on borrowed or begged foundations: or at least, if mine
prove a castle in the air, I will endeavour it shall be all of a piece and hang
together. Wherein I warn the reader not to expect undeniable cogent
demonstrations, unless I may be allowed the privilege, not seldom assumed by
others, to take my principles for granted; and then, I doubt not, but I can
demonstrate too. All that I shall say for the principles I proceed on is, that
I can only appeal to men’s own unprejudiced experience and observation whether
they be true or not; and this is enough for a man who professes no more than to
lay down candidly and freely his own conjectures, concerning a subject lying
somewhat in the dark, without any other design than an unbiassed inquiry after
truth.


</div></body></text></TEI>