<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="26">
CHAPTER X.
Of the Induction of Causes.
Aphorism LX.
In the Induction of Causes the principal Maxim is, that
we must be careful to possess, and to apply, with perfect
clearness, the Fundamental Idea on which the Induction depends.
Aphorism LXI.
The Induction of Substance, of Force, of Polarity, go
beyond mere laws of phenomena, and may be considered as
the Induction of Causes.
Aphorism LXII.
The Cause of certain phenomena being inferred, we are
led to inquire into the Cause of this Cause, which inquiry
must be conducted in the same manner as the previous one;
and thus we have the Induction of Ulterior Causes.
Aphorism LXIII.
In contemplating the series of Causes which are themselves
the effects of other causes, we are necessarily led to assume a
Supreme Cause in the Order of Causation, as we assume a
First Cause in Order of Succession.
1. WE
formerly53
stated the objects of the researches
of Science to be Laws of Phenomena and
Causes; and showed the propriety and the necessity of
not resting in the former object, but extending our 248
inquiries to the latter also. Inductions, in which phenomena
are connected by relations of Space, Time,
Number and Resemblance, belong to the former class;
and of the Methods applicable to such Inductions we
have treated already. In proceeding to Inductions
governed by any ulterior Ideas, we can no longer lay
down any Special Methods by which our procedure
may be directed. A few general remarks are all that
we shall offer.
53
 B. ii. c. vii.
The principal Maxim in such cases of Induction is
the obvious one:—that we must be careful to possess
and to apply, with perfect clearness and precision, the
Fundamental Idea on which the Induction depends.
We may illustrate this in a few cases.
2. Induction of Substance.—The
Idea of Substance54
involves this axiom, that the weight of the whole compound
must be equal to the weights of the separate
elements, whatever changes the composition or separation
of the elements may have occasioned. The application
of this Maxim we may term the Method of the
Balance. We have seen55
elsewhere how the memorable
revolution in Chemistry, the overthrow of Phlogiston,
and the establishment of the Oxygen Theory,
was produced by the application of this Method. We
have seen too56
that the same Idea leads us to this
Maxim;—that Imponderable Fluids are not to be
admitted as chemical elements of bodies.
54
 Hist. Sc. Ideas, Book vi. c. iii.
55
 Ibid. b. vi. c. iv.
56
 Ibid.
Whether those which have been termed Imponderable
Fluids,—the supposed fluids which produce the
phenomena of Light, Heat, Electricity, Galvanism,
Magnetism,—really exist or no, is a question, not
merely of the Laws, but of the Causes of Phenomena.
It is, as has already been shown, a question which we
cannot help discussing, but which is at present involved
in great obscurity. Nor does it appear at all likely that
we shall obtain a true view of the cause of Light,
Heat, and Electricity, till we have discovered precise
and general laws connecting optical, thermotical, and 249
electrical phenomena with those chemical doctrines to
which the Idea of Substance is necessarily applied.
3. Induction of Force.—The inference of Mechanical
Forces from phenomena has been so abundantly
practised, that it is perfectly familiar among scientific
inquirers. From the time of Newton, it has been the
most common aim of mathematicians; and a persuasion
has grown up among them, that mechanical forces,—attraction
and repulsion,—are the only modes of
action of the particles of bodies which we shall ultimately
have to consider. I have attempted to show
that this mode of conception is inadequate to the purposes
of sound philosophy;—that the Particles of
crystals, and the Elements of chemical compounds,
must be supposed to be combined in some other way
than by mere mechanical attraction and repulsion.
Dr. Faraday has gone further in shaking the usual
conceptions of the force exerted, in well-known cases.
Among the most noted and conspicuous instances of
attraction and repulsion exerted at a distance, were
those which take place between electrized bodies. But
the eminent electrician just mentioned has endeavoured
to establish, by experiments of which it is very difficult
to elude the weight, that the action in these cases
does not take place at a distance, but is the result of
a chain of intermediate particles connected at every
point by forces of another kind.
4. Induction of Polarity.—The forces to which
Dr. Faraday ascribes the action in these cases are
Polar Forces57.
We have already endeavoured
to explain the Idea of Polar Forces; which
implies58 that at
every point forces exactly equal act in opposite directions;
and thus, in the greater part of their course,
neutralize and conceal each other; while at the extremities
of the line, being by some cause liberated, they
are manifested, still equal and opposite. And the
criterion by which this polar character of forces is
recognized, is implied in the reasoning of Faraday, on
the question of one or two electricities, of which we 250
formerly spoke59.
The maxim is this:—that in the
action of polar forces, along with every manifestation
of force or property, there exists a corresponding and
simultaneous manifestation of an equal and opposite
force or property.
57
 Researches, 12th series.
58
 B. v. c. i. [For this and the following note, please
see the Transcriber’s Notes.]
59
 Book v. c. i.
5. As it was the habit of the last age to reduce all
action to mechanical forces, the present race of physical
speculators appears inclined to reduce all forces to
polar forces. Mosotti has endeavoured to show that the
positive and negative electricities pervade all bodies,
and that gravity is only an apparent excess of one of
the kinds over the other. As we have seen, Faraday
has given strong experimental grounds for believing
that the supposed remote actions of electrized bodies
are really the effects of polar forces among contiguous
particles. If this doctrine were established with regard
to all electrical, magnetical, and chemical forces,
we might ask, whether, while all other forces are
polar, gravity really affords a single exception to the
universal rule? Is not the universe pervaded by an
omnipresent antagonism, a fundamental conjunction of
contraries, everywhere opposite, nowhere independent?
We are, as yet, far from the position in which Inductive
Science can enable us to answer such inquiries.
6. Induction of Ulterior Causes.—The first Induction
of a Cause does not close the business of scientific
inquiry. Behind proximate causes, there are ulterior
causes, perhaps a succession of such. Gravity is the
cause of the motions of the planets; but what is the
cause of gravity? This is a question which has occupied
men’s minds from the time of Newton to the present day.
Earthquakes and volcanoes are the causes
of many geological phenomena; but what is the cause
of those subterraneous operations? This inquiry after
ulterior causes is an inevitable result from the intellectual
constitution of man. He discovers mechanical
causes, but he cannot rest in them. He must needs
ask, whence it is that matter has its universal power of
attracting matter. He discovers polar forces: but even 251
if these be universal, he still desires a further insight
into the cause of this polarity. He sees, in organic
structures, convincing marks of adaptation to an end:
whence, he asks, is this adaptation? He traces in the
history of the earth a chain of causes and effects
operating through time: but what, he inquires, is the
power which holds the end of this chain?
Thus we are referred back from step to step in the
order of causation, in the same, manner as, in the palætiological
sciences, we were referred back in the order
of time. We make discovery after discovery in the
various regions of science; each, it may be, satisfactory,
and in itself complete, but none final. Something
always remains undone. The last question answered,
the answer suggests still another question. The strain
of music from the lyre of Science flows on, rich and
sweet, full and harmonious, but never reaches a close:
no cadence is heard with which the intellectual ear can
feel satisfied.
Of the Supreme Cause.—In the utterance of Science,
no cadence is heard with which the human mind can
feel satisfied. Yet we cannot but go on listening for
and expecting a satisfactory close. The notion of a
cadence appears to be essential to our relish of the
music. The idea of some closing strain seems to lurk
among our own thoughts, waiting to be articulated in
the notes which flow from the knowledge of external
nature. The idea of something ultimate in our philosophical
researches, something in which the mind can
acquiesce, and which will leave us no further questions
to ask, of whence, and why, and by what power, seems
as if it belongs to us:—as if we could not have it
withheld from us by any imperfection or incompleteness
in the actual performances of science. What is
the meaning of this conviction? What is the reality
thus anticipated? Whither does the developement of
this Idea conduct us?
We have already seen that a difficulty of the same
kind, which arises in the contemplation of causes and
effects considered as forming an historical series, drives
us to the assumption of a First Cause, as an Axiom 252
to which our Idea of Causation in time necessarily
leads. And as we were thus guided to a First Cause,
in order of Succession, the same kind of necessity
directs us to a Supreme Cause in order of Causation.
On this most weighty subject it is difficult to speak
fitly; and the present is not the proper occasion, even
for most of that which may be said. But there are
one or two remarks which flow from the general train
of the contemplations we have been engaged in, and
with which this Work must conclude.
We have seen how different are the kinds of cause
to which we are led by scientific researches. Mechanical
Forces are insufficient without Chemical Affinities;
Chemical Agencies fail us, and we are compelled
to have recourse to Vital Powers; Vital Powers cannot
be merely physical, and we must believe in something
hyperphysical, something of the nature of a Soul.
Not only do biological inquiries lead us to assume an
animal soul, but they drive us much further; they
bring before us Perception, and Will evoked
by Perception. Still more, these inquiries disclose to us Ideas
as the necessary forms of Perception, in the actions
of which we ourselves are conscious. We are aware,
we cannot help being aware, of our Ideas and our
Volitions as belonging to us, and thus we pass from
things to persons; we have the idea of Personality
awakened. And the idea of Design and Purpose, of
which we are conscious in our own minds, we find
reflected back to us, with a distinctness which we
cannot overlook, in all the arrangements which constitute
the frame of organized beings.
We cannot but reflect how widely diverse are the
kinds of principles thus set before us;—by what vast
strides we mount from the lower to the higher, as we
proceed through that series of causes which the range
of the sciences thus brings under our notice. Yet
we know how narrow is the range of these sciences
when compared with the whole extent of human knowledge.
We cannot doubt that on many other subjects,
besides those included in physical speculation, man has
made out solid and satisfactory trains of 253 connexion;—has
discovered clear and indisputable evidence of causation.
It is manifest, therefore, that, if we are to
attempt to ascend to the Supreme Cause—if we are
to try to frame an idea of the Cause of all these subordinate
causes;—we must conceive it as more different from any
of them, than the most diverse are
from each other;—more elevated above the highest,
than the highest is above the lowest.
But further;—though the Supreme Cause must thus
be inconceivably different from all subordinate causes,
and immeasurably elevated above them all, it must
still include in itself all that is essential to each of
them, by virtue of that very circumstance that it is
the Cause of their Causality. Time and Space,—Infinite
Time and Infinite Space,—must be among its
attributes; for we cannot but conceive Infinite Time
and Space as attributes of the Infinite Cause of the
universe. Force and Matter must depend upon it
for their efficacy; for we cannot conceive the activity
of Force, or the resistance of Matter, to be independent
powers. But these are its lower attributes. The Vital
Powers, the Animal Soul, which are the Causes of the
actions of living things, are only the Effects of the
Supreme Cause of Life. And this Cause, even in the
lowest forms of organized bodies, and still more in
those which stand higher in the scale, involves a
reference to Ends and Purposes, in short, to manifest
Final Causes. Since this is so, and since, even when
we contemplate ourselves in a view studiously narrowed,
we still find that we have Ideas, and Will and
Personality, it would render our philosophy utterly
incoherent and inconsistent with itself, to suppose that
Personality, and Ideas, and Will, and Purpose, do not
belong to the Supreme Cause from which we derive
all that we have and all that we are.
But we may go a step further;—though, in our
present field of speculation, we confine ourselves
to knowledge founded on the facts which the external
world presents to us, we cannot forget, in speaking of
such a theme as that to which we have thus been led,
that these are but a small, and the least significant 254
portion of the facts which bear upon it. We cannot
fail to recollect that there are facts belonging to the
world within us, which more readily and strongly
direct our thoughts to the Supreme Cause of all
things. We can plainly discern that we have Ideas
elevated above the region of mechanical causation, of
animal existence, even of mere choice and will, which
still have a clear and definite significance, a permanent
and indestructible validity. We perceive as a fact,
that we have a Conscience, judging of Right and
Wrong; that we have Ideas of Moral Good and Evil,
that we are compelled to conceive the organization
of the moral world, as well as of the vital frame, to
be directed to an end and governed by a purpose.
And since the Supreme Cause is the cause of these
facts, the Origin of these Ideas, we cannot refuse to
recognize Him as not only the Maker, but the Governor
of the World; as not only a Creative, but a Providential
Power; as not only a Universal Father, but
an Ultimate Judge.
We have already passed beyond the boundary of
those speculations which we proposed to ourselves as
the basis of our conclusions. Yet we may be allowed
to add one other reflection. If we find in ourselves
Ideas of Good and Evil, manifestly bestowed upon us
to be the guides of our conduct, which guides we yet
find it impossible consistently to obey;—if we find
ourselves directed, even by our natural light, to aim at a
perfection of our moral nature from which we are constantly
deviating through weakness and perverseness;
if, when we thus lapse and err, we can find, in the
region of human philosophy, no power which can efface
our aberrations, or reconcile our actual with our ideal
being, or give us any steady hope and trust with regard
to our actions, after we have thus discovered their
incongruity with their genuine standard;—if we discern
that this is our condition, how can we fail to see
that it is in the highest degree consistent with all the
indications supplied by such a philosophy as that of
which we have been attempting to lay the foundations,
that the Supreme Cause, through whom man exists as 255
a moral being of vast capacities and infinite Hopes,
should have Himself provided a teaching for our ignorance,
a propitiation for our sin, a support for our
weakness, a purification and sanctification of our
nature?
And thus, in concluding our long survey of the
grounds and structure of science, and of the lessons
which the study of it teaches us, we find ourselves
brought to a point of view in which we can cordially
sympathize, and more than sympathize, with all the
loftiest expressions of admiration and reverence and
hope and trust, which have been uttered by those who
in former times have spoken of the elevated thoughts
to which the contemplation of the nature and progress
of human knowledge gives rise. We can not only hold
with Galen, and Harvey, and all the great physiologists,
that the organs of animals give evidence of a
purpose;—not only assert with Cuvier that this conviction
of a purpose can alone enable us to understand
every part of every living thing;—not only say with
Newton that ‘every true step made in philosophy
brings us nearer to the First Cause, and is on that
account highly to be valued;’—and that ‘the business
of natural philosophy is to deduce causes from effects,
till we come to the very First Cause, which certainly is
not mechanical;’—but we can go much farther, and
declare, still with Newton, that ‘this beautiful system
could have its origin no other way than by the purpose
and command of an intelligent and powerful Being,
who governs all things, not as the soul of the world,
but as the Lord of the Universe; who is not only God,
but Lord and Governor.’
When we have advanced so far, there yet remains
one step. We may recollect the prayer of one, the
master in this school of the philosophy of science:
‘This also we humbly and earnestly beg;—that human things
may not prejudice such as are divine;—neither that from
the unlocking of the gates of sense, and
the kindling of a greater natural light, anything may
arise of incredulity or intellectual night towards divine
mysteries; but rather that by our minds thoroughly 256
purged and cleansed from fancy and vanity, and yet
subject and perfectly given up to the divine oracles,
there may be given unto faith the things that are
faith’s.’ When we are thus prepared for a higher
teaching, we may be ready to listen to a greater than
Bacon, when he says to those who have sought their
God in the material universe, ‘Whom ye ignorantly
worship, him declare I unto you.’ And when we recollect
how utterly inadequate all human language has
been shown to be, to express the nature of that Supreme
Cause of the Natural, and Rational, and Moral,
and Spiritual world, to which our Philosophy points
with trembling finger and shaded eyes, we may receive,
with the less wonder but with the more reverence,
the declaration which has been vouchsafed to us:
ΕΝ ΑΡΧΗ ΗΝ Ὁ ΛΟΓΟΣ,
ΚΑI Ὁ ΛΟΓΟΣ ΗΝ ΠΡΟΣ ΤΟΝ ΘΕΟΝ, ΚΑI ΘΕΟΣ ΗΝ Ὁ ΛΟΓΟΣ.
</div></body></text></TEI>