<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="8">CHAPTER VIII.
ON FORMER CHANGES IN PHYSICAL GEOGRAPHY AND CLIMATE.
Geographical features of the northern hemisphere, at the period of the oldest fossiliferous
strata—State of the surface when the mountain limestone and coal
were deposited—Changes in physical geography, between the carboniferous
period and the chalk—Abrupt transition from the secondary to the tertiary fossils—Accession
of land, and elevation of mountain chains, after the consolidation
of the secondary rocks—Explanation of Map, showing the area covered by
sea, since the commencement of the tertiary period—Astronomical theories of
the causes of variations in climate—Theory of the diminution of the supposed
primitive heat of the globe.
In the sixth chapter, I stated the arguments derived from organic remains
for concluding that in the period when the carboniferous strata
were deposited, the temperature of the ocean and the air was more uniform
in the different seasons of the year, and in different latitudes, than
at present, and that there was a remarkable absence of cold as well as
great moisture in the atmosphere. It was also shown that the climate
had been modified more than once since that epoch, and that it had been
reduced, by successive changes, more and more nearly to that now prevailing
in the same latitudes. Farther, I endeavored, in the last chapter,
to prove that vicissitudes in climate of no less importance may be
expected to recur in future, if it be admitted that causes now active in
nature have power, in the lapse of ages, to produce considerable variations
in the relative position of land and sea. It remains to inquire
whether the alterations, which the geologist can prove to have actually
taken place at former periods, in the geographical features of the northern
hemisphere, coincide in their nature, and in the time of their occurrence,
with such revolutions in climate as might naturally have resulted, according
to the meteorological principles already explained.
Period of the primary fossiliferous rocks.—The oldest system of strata
which afford by their organic remains any evidence as to climate, or the
former position of land and sea, are those formerly known as the transition
rocks, or what have since been termed Lower Silurian or "primary
fossiliferous" formations. These have been found in England,
France, Germany, Sweden, Russia, and other parts of central and northern
Europe, as also in the great Lake district of Canada and the United
States. The multilocular or chambered univalves, including the Nautilus,
and the corals, obtained from the limestones of these ancient groups,
have been compared to forms now most largely developed in tropical
seas. The corals, however, have been shown by M. Milne Edwards to
differ generally from all living zoophytes; so that conclusions as to a
warmer climate drawn from such remote analogies must be received with
115
caution. Hitherto, few, if any, contemporaneous vegetable remains have
been noticed; but such as are mentioned agree more nearly with the
plants of the carboniferous era than any other, and would therefore
imply a warm and humid atmosphere entirely free from intense cold
throughout the year.
This absence or great scarcity of plants as well as of freshwater shells
and other indications of neighboring land, coupled with the wide extent
of marine strata of this age in Europe and North America, are facts
which imply such a state of physical geography (so far at least as regards
the northern hemisphere) as would, according to the principles
before explained, give rise to such a moist and equable climate. (See p.
109, and fig. 5, p. 111.)
Carboniferous group.—This group comes next in the order of succession;
and one of its principal members, the mountain limestone, was
evidently a marine formation, as is shown by the shells and corals which
it contains. That the ocean of that period was of considerable extent in
our latitudes, we may infer from the continuity of these calcareous strata
over large areas in Europe, Canada, and the United States. The same
group has also been traced in North America, towards the borders of
the arctic sea.196
There are also several regions in Scotland, and in the central and
northern parts of England, as well as in the United States, where marine
carboniferous limestones alternate with strata containing coal, in such
a manner as to imply the drifting down of plants by rivers into the sea,
and the alternate occupation of the same space by fresh and salt water.
Since the time of the earlier writers, no strata have been more extensively
investigated, both in Europe and North America, than those of
the ancient carboniferous group, and the progress of science has led to
a general belief that a large portion of the purest coal has been formed,
not, as was once imagined, by vegetable matter floated from a distance,
but by plants which grew on the spot, and somewhat in the manner of
peat on the spaces now covered by the beds of coal. The former existence
of land in some of these spaces has been proved, as already
stated, by the occurrence of numerous upright fossil trees, with their
roots terminating downwards in seams of coal; and still more generally
by the roots of trees (stigmariæ) remaining in their natural position in
the clays which underlie almost every layer of coal.
As some nearly continuous beds of such coal have of late years been
traced in North America, over areas 100 or 200 miles and upwards in
diameter, it may be asked whether the large tracts of ancient land implied
by this fact are not inconsistent with the hypothesis of the general
prevalence of islands at the period under consideration? In reply, I
may observe that the coal-fields must originally have been low alluvial
grounds, resembling in situation the cypress-swamps of the Mississippi,
or the sunderbunds of the Ganges, being liable like them to be inundated
116
at certain periods by a river or by the sea, if the land should be
depressed a few feet. All the phenomena, organic and inorganic, imply
conditions nowhere to be met with except in the deltas of large rivers.
We have to account for an abundant supply of fluviatile sediment, carried
for ages towards one and the same region, and capable of forming
strata of mud and sand thousands of feet, or even fathoms, in thickness,
many of them consisting of laminated shale, inclosing the leaves of ferns
and other terrestrial plants. We have also to explain the frequent intercalations
of root-beds, and the interposition here and there of brackish
and marine deposits, demonstrating the occasional presence of the
neighboring sea. But these forest-covered deltas could only have been
formed at the termination of large hydrographical basins, each drained
by a great river and its tributaries; and the accumulation of sediment
bears testimony to contemporaneous denudation on a large scale, and,
therefore, to a wide area of land, probably containing within it one or
more mountain chains.
In the case of the great Ohio or Appalachian coal-field, the largest
in the world, it seems clear that the uplands drained by one or more
great rivers were chiefly to the eastward, or they occupied a space now
filled by part of the Atlantic Ocean, for the mechanical deposits of mud
and sand increase greatly in thickness and coarseness of material as we
approach the eastern borders of the coal-field, or the southeast flanks
of the Alleghany mountains, near Philadelphia. In that region numerous
beds of pebbles, often of the size of a hen's egg, are seen to alternate
with beds of pure coal.
But the American coal-fields are all comprised within the 30th and
50th degrees of north latitude; and there is no reason to presume that
the lands at the borders of which they originated ever penetrated so far
or in such masses into the colder and arctic regions, so as to generate a
cold climate. In the southern hemisphere, where the predominance of
sea over land is now the distinguishing geographical feature, we nevertheless
find a large part of the continent of Australia, as well as New
Zealand, placed between the 30th and 50th degrees of S. latitude. The
two islands of New Zealand taken together, are between 800 and 900
miles in length, with a breadth in some parts of ninety miles, and they
stretch as far south as the 46th degree of latitude. They afford, therefore,
a wide area for the growth of a terrestrial vegetation, and the botany
of this region is characterized by abundance of ferns, one hundred
and forty species of which are already known, some of them attaining
the size of trees. In this respect the southern shores of New Zealand
in the 46th degree of latitude almost vie with tropical islands. Another
point of resemblance between the Flora of New Zealand and that of the
ancient carboniferous period is the prevalence of the fir tribe or of
coniferous wood.
An argument of some weight in corroboration of the theory above
explained respecting the geographical condition of the temperate and
arctic latitudes of the northern hemisphere in the carboniferous period117
may also be derived from ah examination of those groups of strata which
immediately preceded the coal. The fossils of the Devonian and Silurian
strata in Europe and North America have led to the conclusion,
that they were formed for the most part in deep seas, far from land.
In those older strata land plants are almost as rare as they are abundant
or universal in the coal measures. Those ancient deposits, therefore,
may be supposed to have belonged to an epoch when dry land had
only just begun to be upraised from the deep; a theory which would
imply the existence during the carboniferous epoch of islands, instead of
an extensive continent, in the area where the coal was formed.
Such a state of things prevailing in the north, from the pole to the
30th parallel of latitude, if not neutralized by circumstances of a contrary
tendency in corresponding regions south of the line, would give
rise to a general warmth and uniformity of climate throughout the globe.
Changes in physical geography between the formation of the carboniferous
strata and the chalk.—We have evidence in England that the
strata of the ancient carboniferous group, already adverted to, were, in
many instances, fractured and contorted, and often thrown into a vertical
position, before the deposition of some even of the oldest known secondary
rocks, such as the new red sandstone.
Fragments of the older formations are sometimes included in the conglomerates
of the more modern; and some of these fragments still retain
their fossil shells and corals, so as to enable us to determine the parent
rocks from whence they were derived. There are other proofs of the
disturbance at successive epochs of different secondary rocks before the
deposition of others; and satisfactory evidence that, during these reiterated
convulsions, the geographical features of the northern hemisphere
were frequently modified, and that from time to time new lands
emerged from the deep. The vegetation, during some parts of the period
in question (from the lias to the chalk inclusive), when genera allied
to Cycas and Zamia were abundant, appears to have approached to that
of the larger islands of the equatorial zone; such, for example, as we
now find in the West Indian archipelago.197 These islands appear to
have been drained by rivers of considerable size, which were inhabited
by crocodiles and gigantic oviparous reptiles, both herbivorous and carnivorous,
belonging for the most part to extinct genera. Of the contemporary
inhabitants of the land we have as yet acquired but scanty
information, but we know that there were flying reptiles, insects, and
small mammifers, allied to the marsupial tribes.
A freshwater deposit, called the Wealden, occurs in the upper part
of the secondary series of the south of England, which, by its extent
and fossils, attests the existence in that region of a large river draining
a continent or island of considerable dimensions. We know that this
land was clothed with wood, and inhabited by huge terrestrial reptiles
and birds. Its position so far to the north as the counties of Surrey and
118Sussex, at a time when the mean temperature of the climate is supposed
to have been much hotter than at present, may at first sight appear inconsistent
with the theory before explained, that the heat was caused
by the gathering together of all the great masses of land in low latitudes,
while the northern regions were almost entirely sea. But it must not
be taken for granted that the geographical conditions already described
(p. 109, and fig. 5, p. 111) as capable of producing the extreme of heat
were ever combined at any geological period of which we have yet obtained
information. It is more probable, from what has been stated in
the preceding chapters, that a slight approximation to such an extreme
state of things would be sufficient; in other words, if most of the dry
land were tropical, and scarcely any of it arctic or antarctic, a prodigious
elevation of temperature must ensue, even though a part of some continents
should penetrate far into the temperate zones.
Changes during the tertiary periods.—The secondary and tertiary formations
of Europe, when considered separately, may be contrasted as
having very different characters; the secondary appearing to have been
deposited in open seas, the tertiary in regions where dry land, lakes,
bays, and perhaps inland seas, abounded. The secondary series is almost
exclusively marine; the tertiary, even the oldest part, contains lacustrine
strata, and not unfrequently freshwater and marine beds alternating.
In fact there is evidence of important geographical changes
having occurred between the deposition of the cretaceous system, or
uppermost of the secondary series, and that of the oldest tertiary group,
and still more between the era of the latter and that of the newer tertiary
formations. This change in the physical geography of Europe
and North America was accompanied by an alteration no less remarkable
in organic life, scarcely any species being common both to the secondary
and tertiary rocks, and the fossils of the latter affording evidence
of a different climate.
On the other hand, when we compare the tertiary formations of successive
ages, we trace a gradual approximation in the imbedded fossils,
from an assemblage in which extinct species predominate, to one where
the species agree for the most part with those now existing. In other
words, we find a gradual increase of animals and plants fitted for our
present climates, in proportion as the strata which we examine are more
modern. Now, during all these successive tertiary periods, there are
signs of a great increase of land in European and North American latitudes.
By reference to the map (Pl. 1), and its description, p. 121.
the reader will see that about two-thirds of the present European lands
have emerged since the earliest tertiary group originated. Nor is this
the only revolution which the same region has undergone within the
period alluded to, some tracts which were previously land having gained
in altitude, others, on the contrary, having sunk below their former level.
That the existing lands were not all upheaved at once into their
present position is proved by the most striking evidence. Several Italian
geologists, even before the time of Brocchi, had justly inferred that119
the Apennines were elevated several thousand feet above the level of
the Mediterranean before the deposition of the modern Subapennine
beds which flank them on either side. What now constitutes the central
calcareous chain of the Apennines must for a long time have been a
narrow ridgy peninsula, branching off, at its northern extremity, from
the Alps near Savona. This peninsula has since been raised from one
to two thousand feet, by which movement the ancient shores, and, for a
certain extent, the bed of the contiguous sea, have been laid dry, both
on the side of the Mediterranean and the Adriatic.
Fig. 7.
The nature of these vicissitudes will be explained by the accompanying
diagram, which represents a transverse section across the Italian
peninsula. The inclined strata A are the disturbed formations of the
Apennines, into which the ancient igneous rocks a are supposed to have
intruded themselves. At a lower level on each flank of the chain are
the more recent shelly beds b b, which often contain rounded pebbles
derived from the waste of contiguous parts of the older Apennine limestone.
These, it will be seen, are horizontal, and lie in what is termed
"unconformable stratification" on the more ancient series. They now
constitute a line of hills of moderate elevation between the sea and the
Apennines, but never penetrate to the higher and more ancient valleys
of that chain.
The same phenomena are exhibited in the Alps on a much grander
scale; those mountains being composed in some even of their higher regions
of the newer secondary and oldest tertiary formations, while they
are encircled by a great zone of more modern tertiary rocks both on
their southern flank towards the plains of the Po, and on the side of
Switzerland and Austria, and at their eastern termination towards Styria
and Hungary.198 This newer tertiary zone marks the position of former
seas or gulfs, like the Adriatic, wherein masses of strata accumulated,
some single groups of which are not inferior in thickness to the most
voluminous of our secondary formations in England. Some even of
these newer groups have been raised to the height of three or four thousand
feet, and in proportion to their antiquity, they generally rise to
greater heights, the older of them forming interior zones nearest to the
central ridges of the Alps. We have already ascertained that the Alps
gained accessions to their height and width at several successive peri120ods,
and that the last series of improvements occurred when the seas
were inhabited by many existing species of animals.
We may imagine some future series of convulsions once more to heave
up this stupendous chain, together with the adjoining bed of the sea, so
that the mountains of Europe may rival the Andes in elevation; in
which case the deltas of the Po, Adige, and Brenta, now encroaching
upon the Adriatic, might be uplifted so as to form another exterior belt
of considerable height around the southeastern flank of the Alps.
The Pyrenees, also, have acquired their present altitude, which in
Mont Perdu exceeds eleven thousand feet, since the deposition of the
nummulitic or Eocene division of the tertiary series. Some of the tertiary
strata at the base of the chain are raised to the height of only a
few hundred feet above the sea, and retain a horizontal position, without
partaking in general in the disturbance to which the older series
has been subjected; so that the great barrier between France and Spain
was almost entirely upheaved in the interval between the deposition of
certain groups of tertiary strata.
The remarkable break between the most modern of the known secondary
rocks and the oldest tertiary, may be apparent only, and ascribable
to the present deficiency of our information. Already the marles and
green sand of Heers near Tongres, in Belgium, observed by M. Dumont,
and the "pisolitic limestone" of the neighborhood of Paris, both intermediate
in age between the Maestricht chalk and the lower Eocene
strata, begin to afford us signs of a passage from one state of things to
another. Nevertheless, it is far from impossible that the interval between
the chalk and tertiary formations constituted an era in the earth's
history, when the transition from one class of organic beings to another
was, comparatively speaking, rapid. For if the doctrines above explained
in regard to vicissitudes of temperature are sound, it will follow
that changes of equal magnitude in the geographical features of the
globe may at different periods produce very unequal effects on climate;
and, so far as the existence of certain animals and plants depends
on climate, the duration of species would be shortened or protracted,
according to the rate at which the change of temperature
proceeded.
For even if we assume that the intensity of the subterranean disturbing
forces is uniform and capable of producing nearly equal amounts of
alteration on the surface of the planet, during equal periods of time, still
the rate of alteration in climate would be by no means uniform. Let us
imagine the quantity of land between the equator and the tropic in one
hemisphere to be to that in the other as thirteen to one, which, as before
stated, represents the unequal proportion of the extra-tropical lands in
the two hemispheres at present. (See figs. 3 and 4, p. 110.) Then
let the first geographical change consist in the shifting of this preponderance
of land from one side of the line to the other; from the southern
hemisphere, for example, to the northern. Now this need not affect the
general temperature of the earth. But if, at another epoch, we suppose
121
a continuance of the same agency to transfer an equal volume of land
from the torrid zone to the temperate and arctic regions of the northern
and southern hemispheres, or into one of them, there might be so great
a refrigeration of the mean temperature in all latitudes, that scarcely
any of the pre-existing races of animals would survive; and, unless it
pleased the Author of Nature that the planet should be uninhabited,
new species, and probably of widely different forms, would then be substituted
in the room of the extinct. We ought not, therefore, to infer
that equal periods of time are always attended by an equal amount of
change in organic life, since a great fluctuation in the mean temperature
of the earth, the most influential cause which can be conceived in exterminating
whole races of animals and plants, must, in different epochs,
require unequal portions of time for its completion.
Plate I. Map showing the extent of surface in Europe which has at one period or
another been covered by the sea since the commencement of the deposition of the
older or Eocene Tertiary strata.

This map will enable the reader to perceive at a glance the great extent
of change in the physical geography of Europe, which can be proved
to have taken place since some of the older tertiary strata began to be
deposited. The proofs of submergence, during some part or other of
this period, in all the districts distinguished by ruled lines, are of a most
unequivocal character; for the area thus described is now covered by
deposits containing the fossil remains of animals which could only have
lived in salt water. The most ancient part of the period referred to cannot
be deemed very remote, considered geologically; because the deposits
of the Paris and London basins, and many other districts belonging
to the older tertiary epoch, are newer than the greater part of the
sedimentary rocks (those commonly called secondary and primary fossiliferous
or paleozoic) of which the crust of the globe is composed.
The species, moreover, of marine testacea, of which the remains are
found in these older tertiary formations, are not entirely distinct from
such as now live. Yet, notwithstanding the comparatively recent epoch
to which this retrospect is carried, the variations in the distribution of
land and sea depicted on the map form only a part of those which must
have taken place during the period under consideration. Some approximation
has merely been made to an estimate of the amount of sea converted
into land in parts of Europe best known to geologists; but we
cannot determine how much land has become sea during the same period;
and there may have been repeated interchanges of land and water in the
same places, changes of which no account is taken in the map, and respecting
the amount of which little accurate information can ever be obtained.
I have extended the sea in some instances beyond the limits of the
land now covered by tertiary formations, and marine drift, because other
geological data have been obtained for inferring the submergence of these
122
tracts after the deposition of the Eocene strata had begun. Thus, for
example, there are good reasons for concluding that part of the chalk of
England (the North and South Downs, for example, together with the
intervening secondary tracts) continued beneath the sea until the oldest
tertiary beds had begun to accumulate.
A strait of the sea separating England and Wales has also been introduced,
on the evidence afforded by shells of existing species found in
a deposit of gravel, sand, loam, and clay, called the northern drift, by
Sir R. Murchison.199 And Mr. Trimmer has discovered similar recent
marine shells on the northern coast of North Wales, and on Moel Tryfane,
near the Menai Straits, at the height of 1392 feet above the level
of the sea!
Some raised sea-beaches, and drift containing marine shells, which I
examined in 1843, between Limerick and Dublin, and which have been
traced over other parts of Ireland by different geologists, have required
an extension of the dark lines so as to divide that island into several.
In improving this part of my map I have been especially indebted to
the assistance of Mr. Oldham, who in 1843 announced to the British Association
at Cork the fact that at the period when the drift or glacial beds
were deposited, Ireland must have formed an archipelago such as is here
depicted. A considerable part of Scotland might also have been represented
in a similar manner as under water when the drift originated.
A portion of Brittany is divided into islands, because it is known to
be covered with patches of marine tertiary strata chiefly miocene. When
I examined these in 1830 and 1843, I convinced myself that the sea
must have covered much larger areas than are now occupied by these
small and detached deposits. The former connection of the White Sea
and the Gulf of Finland is proved by the fact that a multitude of huge
erratic blocks extend over the intervening space, and a large portion of
Norway, Sweden, and Denmark, as well as Germany and Russia, are
represented as sea, on the same evidence, strengthened by the actual
occurrence of fossil sea-shells, of recent species, in the drift of various
portions of those countries. The submergence of considerable areas
under large bodies of fresh water, during the tertiary period, of which
there are many striking geological proofs in Auvergne, and elsewhere,
has not been expressed by ruled lines. They bear testimony to the
former existence of neighboring lands, and a certain elevation of the
areas where they occur above the level of the ocean; they are therefore
left blank, together with all the space that cannot be demonstrated
to have been part of the sea at some time or other, since the commencement
of the Eocene epoch.
In compiling this map, which has been entirely recast since the first
edition, I have availed myself of the latest geological maps of the British
isles, and north of Europe; also of those published by the government
surveyors of France, MM. de Beaumont and Dufresnoy; the map of
123
Germany and part of Europe, by Von Dechen, and that of Italy by
M. Tchihatchoff (Berlin, 1842). Lastly, Sir R. Murchison's important
map of Russia, and the adjoining countries, has enabled me to mark out
not only a considerable area, previously little known, in which tertiary
formations occur; but also a still wider expanse, over which the northern
drift, and erratic blocks with occasional marine shells, are traceable.
The southern limits of these glacial deposits in Russia and Germany indicate
the boundary, so far as we can now determine it, of the northern
ocean, at a period immediately antecedent to that of the human race.
I was anxious, even in the title of this map, to guard the reader against
the supposition that it was intended to represent the state of the physical
geography of part of Europe at any one point of time. The difficulty,
or rather the impossibility, of restoring the geography of the globe as it
may have existed at any former period, especially a remote one, consists
in this, that we can only point out where part of the sea has been turned
into land, and are almost always unable to determine what land may
have become sea. All maps, therefore, pretending to represent the
geography of remote geological epochs must be ideal. The map under
consideration is not a restoration of a former state of things, at any particular
moment of time, but a synoptical view of a certain amount of one
kind of change (the conversion of sea into land) known to have been
brought about within a given period.
It may be proper to remark that the vertical movements to which the
land is subject in certain regions, occasion alternately the subsidence and
the uprising of the surface; and that, by such oscillations at successive
periods, a great area may have been entirely covered with marine deposits,
although the whole may never have been beneath the waters at
one time; nay, even though the relative proportion of land and sea may
have continued unaltered throughout the whole period. I believe, however,
that since the commencement of the tertiary period, the dry land
in the northern hemisphere has been continually on the increase, both
because it is now greatly in excess beyond the average proportion which
land generally bears to water on the globe, and because a comparison
of the secondary and tertiary strata affords indications, as I have already
shown, of a passage from the condition of an ocean interspersed with
islands to that of a large continent.
But supposing it were possible to represent all the vicissitudes in the
distribution of land and sea that have occurred during the tertiary period,
and to exhibit not only the actual existence of land where there
was once sea, but also the extent of surface now submerged which may
once have been land, the map would still fail to express all the important
revolutions in physical geography which have taken place within the
epoch under consideration. For the oscillations of level, as was before
stated, have not merely been such as to lift up the land from below the
water, but in some cases to occasion a rise of many thousand feet above
the sea. Thus the Alps have acquired an additional altitude of 4000,
and even in some places 10,000 feet; and the Apennines owe a considerable
124
part of their present height to subterranean convulsions which
have happened within the tertiary epoch.
On the other hand, some mountain chains may have been lowered
during the same series of ages, in an equal degree, and shoals may have
been converted into deep abysses.200 Since this map was recast in 1847,
geologists have very generally come to the conclusion that the nummulitic
limestone, together with the overlying fucoidal grit and shale, called
"Flysch," in the Alps, belongs to the older tertiary or Eocene group.
As these nummulitic rocks enter into the structure of some of the most
lofty and disturbed parts of the Alps, Apennines, Carpathians, Pyrenees,
and other mountain chains, and form many of the elevated lands of Africa
and Asia, their position almost implies the ubiquity of the
post-Eocene ocean, not, indeed, by the simultaneous, but by the successive,
occupancy of the whole ground by its waters.201
Concluding remarks on changes in physical geography.—The foregoing
observations, it may be said, are confined chiefly to Europe, and therefore
merely establish the increase of dry land in a space which constitutes
but a small portion of the northern hemisphere; but it was stated
in the preceding chapter, that the great Lowland of Siberia, lying chiefly
between the latitudes 55° and 75° N. (an area nearly equal to all Europe),
is covered for the most part by marine strata, which, from the
account given by Pallas, and more recently by Sir R. Murchison, belongs
to a period when all or nearly all the shells were of a species still living
in the north. The emergence, therefore, of this area from the deep is,
comparatively speaking, a very modern event, and must, as before remarked,
have caused a great increase of cold throughout the globe.
Upon a review, then, of all the facts above enumerated, respecting
the ancient geography of the globe as attested by geological monuments,
there appear good grounds for inferring that changes of climate coincided
with remarkable revolutions in the former position of sea and land. A
wide expanse of ocean, interspersed with islands, seems to have pervaded
the northern hemisphere at the periods when the Silurian and carboniferous
rocks were formed, and a warm and very uniform temperature
then prevailed. Subsequent modifications in climate accompanied the
deposition of the secondary formations, when repeated changes were effected
in the physical geography of our northern latitudes. Lastly, the
refrigeration became most decided, and the climate most nearly assimilated
to that now enjoyed, when the lands in Europe and northern Asia had
attained their full extension, and the mountain chains their actual height.
Soon after the first publication of this theory of climate, an objection
was made by an anonymous German critic in 1833 that there are no
geological proofs of the prevalence at any former period of a temperature
125lower than that now enjoyed; whereas, if the causes above assigned
were the true ones, it might reasonably have been expected that fossil
remains would sometimes indicate colder as well as hotter climates than
those now established.202 In answer to this objection, I may suggest,
that our present climates are probably far more distant from the extreme
of possible heat than from its opposite extreme of cold. A glance at
the map (fig. 6, p. 111) will show that all the existing lands might be
placed between the 30th parallels of latitude on each side of the equator,
and that even then they would by no means fill that space. In no other
position would they give rise to so high a temperature. But the present
geographical condition of the earth is so far removed from such a state
of things, that the land lying between the poles and the parallels of 30,
is in great excess; so much so that, instead of being to the sea in the
proportion of 1 to 3, which is as near as possible the average general
ratio throughout the globe, it is 9 to 23.203 Hence it ought not to surprise
us if, in our geological retrospect, embracing perhaps a small part
only of a complete cycle of change in the terrestrial climates, we should
happen to discover everywhere the signs of a higher temperature. The
strata hitherto examined may have originated when the quantity of equatorial
land was always decreasing and the land in regions nearer the
poles augmenting in height and area, until at length it attained its present
excess in high latitudes. There is nothing improbable in supposing
that the geographical revolutions of which we have hitherto obtained
proofs had this general tendency; and in that case the refrigeration must
have been constant, although, for reasons before explained, the rate of
cooling may not have been uniform.
It may, however, be as well to recall the reader's attention to what
was before said of the indication brought to light of late years, of a considerable
oscillation of temperature, in the period immediately preceding
the human era. We have seen that on examining some of the most
northern deposits, those commonly called the northern drift in Scotland,
Ireland, and Canada, in which nearly all, in some cases, perhaps all, the
fossil shells are of recent species, we discover the signs of a climate colder
than that now prevailing in corresponding latitudes on both sides the
Atlantic. It appears that an arctic fauna specifically resembling that
of the present seas, extended farther to the south than now. This opinion
is derived partly from the known habitations of the corresponding
living species, and partly from the abundance of certain genera of shells
126
and the absence of others.204 The date of the refrigeration thus inferred
appears to coincide very nearly with the era of the dispersion of erratic
blocks over Europe and North America, a phenomenon which will be ascribed
in the sequel (ch. 16) to the cold then prevailing in the northern
hemisphere. The force, moreover, of the German critic's objection has
been since in a great measure destroyed, by the larger and more profound
knowledge acquired in the last few years of the ancient carboniferous flora,
which has led the ablest botanists to adopt the opinion, that the climate
of the coal period was remarkable for its warmth, moisture, equability,
and freedom from cold, rather than the intensity of its tropical heat. We
are therefore no longer entitled to assume that there has been a constant
and gradual decline in the absolute amount of heat formerly contained
in the atmosphere and waters of the ocean, such as it was conjectured
might have emanated from the incandescent central nucleus of a new
and nearly fluid planet, before the interior had lost, by radiation into
surrounding space, a great part of its original high temperature.
Astronomical causes of fluctuations in climate.—Sir John Herschel
has lately inquired, whether there are any astronomical causes which
may offer a possible explanation of the difference between the actual
climate of the earth's surface, and those which formerly appear to have
prevailed. He has entered upon this subject, he says, "impressed with
the magnificence of that view of geological revolutions, which regards
them rather as regular and necessary effects of great and general causes,
than as resulting from a series of convulsions and catastrophes, regulated
by no laws, and reducible to no fixed principles." Geometers, he adds,
have demonstrated the absolute invariability of the mean distance of the
earth from the sun; whence it would at first seem to follow, that the
mean annual supply of light and heat derived from that luminary would
be alike invariable: but a closer consideration of the subject will show,
that this would not be a legitimate conclusion; but that on the contrary,
the mean amount of solar radiation is dependent on the eccentricity of
the earth's orbit, and therefore liable to variation.205
Now the eccentricity of the orbit, he continues, is actually diminishing,
and has been so for ages beyond the records of history. In consequence,
the ellipse is in a state of approach to a circle, and the annual
average of solar heat radiated to the earth is actually on the decrease. So
far this is in accordance with geological evidence, which indicates a general
refrigeration of climate; but the question remains, whether the amount
of diminution which the eccentricity may have ever undergone can be supposed
sufficient to account for any sensible refrigeration. The calculations
127
necessary to determine this point, though practicable, have never
yet been made, and would be extremely laborious; for they must embrace
all the perturbations which the most influential planets, Venus,
Mars, Jupiter, and Saturn, would cause in the earth's orbit, and in each
other's movements round the sun.
The problem is also very complicated, inasmuch as it depends not
merely on the ellipticity of the earth's orbit, but on the assumed temperature
of the celestial spaces beyond the earth's atmosphere; a matter
still open to discussion, and on which M. Fourier and Sir J. Herschel
have arrived at very different opinions. But if, says Herschel, we suppose
an extreme case, as if the earth's orbit should ever become as eccentric
as that of the planet Juno or Pallas, a great change of climate
might be conceived to result, the winter and summer temperatures
being sometimes mitigated, and at others exaggerated, in the same latitudes.
It is much to be desired that the calculations alluded to were executed,
as even if they should demonstrate, as M. Arago thinks highly
probable,206 that the mean amount of solar radiation can never be materially
affected by irregularities in the earth's motion, it would still be
satisfactory to ascertain the point. Such inquiries, however, can never
supersede the necessity of investigating the consequences of the varying
position of continents, shifted as we know them to have been during
successive epochs, from one part of the globe to the other.
Another astronomical hypothesis respecting the possible cause of secular
variations in climate, has been proposed by a distinguished mathematician
and philosopher, M. Poisson. He begins by assuming, 1st,
that the sun and our planetary system are not stationary, but carried
onward by a common movement through space; 2dly, that every point
in space receives heat as well as light from innumerable stars surrounding
it on all sides, so that if a right line of indefinite length be produced
in any direction from such a point, it must encounter a star either visible
or invisible to us. 3dly, He then goes on to assume, that the different
regions of space, which in the course of millions of years are traversed
by our system, must be of very unequal temperature, inasmuch as some
of them must receive a greater, others a less, quantity of radiant heat
from the great stellary inclosure. If the earth, he continues, or any
other large body, pass from a hotter to a colder region, it would not
readily lose in the second all the heat which it has imbibed in the first
region, but retain a temperature increasing downwards from the surface,
as in the actual condition of our planet.207
Now the opinion originally suggested by Sir W. Herschel, that our
sun and its attendant planets were all moving onward through space,
in the direction of the constellation Hercules, is very generally thought
by eminent astronomers to be confirmed. But even if its reality be
128
no longer matter of doubt, conjectures as to its amount are still vague
and uncertain; and great, indeed, must be the extent of the movement
before this cause alone can work any material alteration in the terrestrial
climates. Mr. Hopkins, when treating of this theory, remarked, that so
far as we were acquainted with the position of the stars not very remote
from the sun, they seem to be so distant from each other, that there are
no points in space among them, where the intensity of radiating heat
would be comparable to that which the earth derives from the sun, except
at points very near to each star. Thus, in order that the earth
should derive a degree of heat from stellar radiation comparable to that
now derived from the sun, she must be in close proximity to some particular
star, leaving the aggregate effect of radiation from the other stars
nearly the same as at present. This approximation, however, to a single
star could not take place consistently with the preservation of the
motion of the earth about the sun, according to its present laws.
Suppose our sun should approach a star within the present distance
of Neptune. That planet could no longer remain a member of the solar
system, and the motions of the other planets would be disturbed in a
degree which no one has ever contemplated as probable since the existence
of the solar system. But such a star, supposing it to be no larger
than the sun, and to emit the same quantity of heat, would not send to
the earth much more than one-thousandth part of the heat which she
derives from the sun, and would therefore produce only a very small
change in terrestrial temperature.208
Variable splendor of stars.—There is still another astronomical suggestion
respecting the possible causes of secular variations in the terrestrial
climates which deserves notice. It has long been known that certain
stars are liable to great and periodical fluctuations in splendor, and
Sir J. Herschel has lately ascertained (Jan. 1840), that a large and
brilliant star, called alpha Orionis, sustained, in the course of six weeks,
a loss of nearly half its light. "This phenomenon," he remarks, "cannot
fail to awaken attention, and revive those speculations which were
first put forth by my father Sir W. Herschel, respecting the possibility
of a change in the lustre of our sun itself. If there really be a community
of nature between the sun and fixed stars, every proof that we obtain
of the extensive prevalence of such periodical changes in those remote
bodies, adds to the probability of finding something of the kind
nearer home." Referring then to the possible bearing of such facts on
ancient revolutions, in terrestrial climates, he says, that "it is a matter
of observed fact, that many stars have undergone, in past ages, within
the records of astronomical history, very extensive changes in apparent
lustre, without a change of distance adequate to producing such an effect.
If our sun were even intrinsically much brighter than at present,
the mean temperature of the surface of our globe would, of course, be
proportionally greater. I speak now not of periodical, but of secular
129
changes. But the argument is complicated with the consideration of
the possibly imperfect transparency of the celestial spaces, and with the
cause of that imperfect transparency, which may be due to material
non-luminous particles diffused irregularly in patches analogous to nebulæ,
but of greater extent—to cosmical clouds, in short—of whose existence
we have, I think, some indication in the singular and apparently
capricious phenomena of temporary stars, and perhaps in the recent
extraordinary sudden increase and hardly less sudden diminution of
η Argus."209
More recently (1852) Schwabe has observed that the spots on the
sun alternately increase and decrease in the course of every ten years,
and Captain Sabine has pointed out that this variable obscuration coincides
in time both as to its maximum and minimum with changes in all
those terrestrial magnetic variations which are caused by the sun.
Hence he infers that the period of alteration in the spots is a solar magnetic
period. Assuming such to be the case, the variable light of some
stars may indicate a similar phenomenon, or they may be stellar magnetic
periods, differing only in the degree of obscuration and its duration.
And as hitherto we have perceived no fluctuation in the heat
received by the earth from the sun coincident with the solar magnetic
period, so the fluctuations in the brilliancy of the stars may not perhaps
be attended with any perceptible alteration in their power of radiating
heat. But before we can speculate with advantage in this new
and interesting field of inquiry, we require more facts and observations.
Supposed gradual diminution of the earth's primitive
heat.—The gradual diminution of the supposed primitive heat of the globe has been
resorted to by many geologists as the principal cause of alterations of
climate. The matter of our planet is imagined, in accordance with the
conjectures of Leibnitz, to have been originally in an intensely heated
state, and to have been parting ever since with portions of its heat, and
at the same time contracting its dimensions. There are, undoubtedly,
good grounds for inferring from recent observation and experiment, that
the temperature of the earth increases as we descend from the surface
to that slight depth to which man can penetrate: but there are no
positive proofs of a secular decrease of internal heat accompanied by
contraction. On the contrary, La Place has shown, by reference to
astronomical observations made in the time of Hipparchus, that in the
last two thousand years at least there has been no sensible contraction
of the globe by cooling; for had this been the case, even to an extremely
small amount, the day would have been shortened, whereas its
length has certainly not diminished during that period by 1/300th of a
second.
Baron Fourier, after making a curious series of experiments on the
cooling of incandescent bodies, considers it to be proved mathematically,
that the actual distribution of heat in the earth's envelope is precisely
130
that which would have taken place if the globe had been formed in a
medium of a very high temperature, and had afterwards been constantly
cooled.210 He contends, that although no contraction can be demonstrated
to have taken place within the historical period (the operation
being slow and the time of observation limited), yet it is no less certain
that heat is annually passing out by radiation from the interior of the
globe into the planetary spaces. He even undertook to demonstrate
that the quantity of heat thus transmitted into space in the course of
every century, through every square metre of the earth's surface, would
suffice to melt a column of ice having a square metre for its base, and
being three metres (or 9 feet 10 inches) high.
It is at the same time denied, that there is any assignable mode in
which the heat thus lost by radiation can be again restored to the earth,
and consequently the interior of our planet must, from the moment of
its creation, have been subject to refrigeration, and is destined together
with the sun and stars forever to grow colder. But I shall point out
in the sequel (chapter 31) many objections to these views, and to the
theory of the intense heat of the earth's central nucleus, and shall then
inquire how far the observed augmentation of temperature, as we descend
below the surface, may be referable to other causes unconnected
with the supposed pristine fluidity of the entire globe.
</div></body></text></TEI>