<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="12">CHAPTER III.
Inductive Epoch of Hipparchus.

Sect. 1.—Establishment of the Theory
of Epicycles and Eccentrics.
ALTHOUGH, as we have already
seen, at the time of Plato, the Idea of Epicycles had been suggested,
and the problem of its general application proposed, and solutions of
this problem offered by his followers; we still consider Hipparchus as
the real discoverer and founder of that theory; inasmuch as he not
only guessed that it might, but showed that it must,
account for the phenomena, both as to their nature and as to their
quantity. The assertion that “he only discovers who proves,” is just;
not only because, until a theory is proved to be the true one, it has
no pre-eminence over the numerous other guesses among which it
circulates, and above which the proof alone elevates it; but also
because he who takes hold of the theory so as to apply calculation to
it, possesses it with a distinctness of conception which makes it
peculiarly his.
In order to establish the Theory of Epicycles, it was necessary to
assign the magnitudes, distances, and positions of the circles or
spheres in which the heavenly bodies were moved, in such a manner as
to account for their apparently irregular motions. We may best
understand what was the problem to be solved, by calling to mind what
we now know to be the real motions of the heavens. The true motion of
the earth round the sun, and therefore the apparent annual motion of
the sun, is performed, not in a circle of which the earth is the
centre, but in an ellipse or oval, the earth being nearer to one end
than to the other; and the motion is most rapid when the sun is at the
nearer end of this oval. But instead of an oval, we may suppose the
sun to move uniformly in a circle, the earth being now, not in the
centre, but nearer to one side; for on this supposition, the sun will
appear to move most quickly when he is nearest to the earth, or in his
Perigee, as that point is called. Such an orbit is called an
Eccentric, and the distance of the earth from the centre of the
circle is called the Eccentricity. It may easily be shown by
geometrical reasoning, that the inequality of apparent motion so
produced, is exactly the same in 146 detail, as the inequality which follows
from the hypothesis of a small Epicycle, turning uniformly on
its axis, and carrying the sun in its circumference, while the centre
of this epicycle moves uniformly in a circle of which the earth is the
centre. This identity of the results of the hypothesis of the
Eccentric and the Epicycle is proved by Ptolemy in the third book of
the “Almagest.”
The Sun’s Eccentric.—When Hipparchus had clearly
conceived these hypotheses, as possible ways of accounting
for the sun’s motion, the task which he had to perform, in order to
show that they deserved to be adopted, was to assign a place to the
Perigee, a magnitude to the Eccentricity, and an
Epoch at which the sun was at the perigee; and to show that, in
this way, he had produced a true representation of the motions of the
sun. This, accordingly, he did; and having thus determined, with
considerable exactness, both the law of the solar irregularities, and
the numbers on which their amount depends, he was able to assign the
motions and places of the sun for any moment of future time with
corresponding exactness; he was able, in short, to construct Solar
Tables, by means of which the sun’s place with respect to the
stars could be correctly found at any time. These tables (as they are
given by Ptolemy)63 give the Anomaly, or inequality
of the sun’s motion; and this they exhibit by means of the
Prosthapheresis, the quantity of which, at any distance of the
sun from the Apogee, it is requisite to add to or subtract from
the arc, which he would have described if his motion had been
equable.
63 Syntax. 1. iii.
The reader might perhaps expect that the calculations which thus
exhibited the motions of the sun for an indefinite future period must
depend upon a considerable number of observations made at all seasons
of the year. That, however, was not the case; and the genius of the
discoverer appeared, as such genius usually does appear, in his
perceiving how small a number of facts, rightly considered, were
sufficient to form a foundation for the theory. The number of days
contained in two seasons of the year sufficed for this purpose to
Hipparchus. “Having ascertained,” says Ptolemy, “that the time from
the vernal equinox to the summer tropic is 94½ days, and the time from
the summer tropic to the autumnal equinox 92½ days, from these
phenomena alone he demonstrates that the straight line joining the
centre of the sun’s eccentric path with the centre of the zodiac (the
spectator’s eye) is nearly the 24th part of the radius of the
eccentric path; and that 147 its apogee precedes the summer
solstice by 24½ degrees nearly, the zodiac containing 360.”
The exactness of the Solar Tables, or Canon, which was
founded on these data, was manifested, not only by the coincidence of
the sun’s calculated place with such observations as the Greek
astronomers of this period were able to make (which were indeed very
rude), but by its enabling them to calculate solar and lunar eclipses;
phenomena which are a very precise and severe trial of the accuracy of
such tables, inasmuch as a very minute change in the apparent place of
the sun or moon would completely alter the obvious features of the
eclipse. Though the tables of this period were by no means perfect,
they bore with tolerable credit this trying and perpetually recurring
test; and thus proved the soundness of the theory on which the tables
were calculated.
The Moon’s Eccentric.—The moon’s motions have many
irregularities; but when the hypothesis of an Eccentric or an Epicycle
had sufficed in the case of the sun, it was natural to try to explain,
in the same way, the motions of the moon; and it was shown by
Hipparchus that such hypotheses would account for the more obvious
anomalies. It is not very easy to describe the several ways in which
these hypotheses were applied, for it is, in truth, very difficult to
explain in words even the mere facts of the moon’s motion. If she were
to leave a visible bright line behind her in the heavens wherever she
moved, the path thus exhibited would be of an extremely complex
nature; the circle of each revolution slipping away from the
preceding, and the traces of successive revolutions forming a sort of
band of net-work running round the middle of the sky.64 In each revolution, the motion in
longitude is affected by an anomaly of the same nature as the sun’s
anomaly already spoken of; but besides this, the path of the moon
deviates from the ecliptic to the north and to the south of the
ecliptic, and thus she has a motion in latitude. This motion in
latitude would be sufficiently known if we knew the period of its
restoration, that is, the time which the moon occupies in
moving from any latitude till she is restored to the same latitude;
as, for instance, from the ecliptic on one side of the heavens to the
ecliptic on the same side of the heavens again. But it is found that
the period of the restoration of the latitude is not the same as the
period of the restoration of the longitude, that is, as the period of
the moon’s revolution among the 148 stars; and thus the moon describes a
different path among the stars in every successive revolution, and her
path, as well as her velocity, is constantly variable.
64 The reader will find an attempt to
make the nature of this path generally intelligible in the
Companion to the British Almanac for 1814.
Hipparchus, however, reduced the motions of the moon to rule and to
Tables, as he did those of the sun, and in the same manner. He
determined, with much greater accuracy than any preceding astronomer,
the mean or average equable motions of the moon in longitude and in
latitude; and he then represented the anomaly of the motion in
longitude by means of an eccentric, in the same manner as he had done
for the sun.
But here there occurred still an additional change, besides those
of which we have spoken. The Apogee of the Sun was always in the same
place in the heavens; or at least so nearly so, that Ptolemy could
detect no error in the place assigned to it by Hipparchus 250 years
before. But the Apogee of the Moon was found to have a motion among
the stars. It had been observed before the time of Hipparchus, that in
6585⅓ days, there are 241 revolutions of the moon with regard to the
stars, but only 239 revolutions with regard to the anomaly. This
difference could be suitably represented by supposing the eccentric,
in which the moon moves, to have itself an angular motion, perpetually
carrying its apogee in the same direction in which the moon travels;
but this supposition being made, it was necessary to determine, not
only the eccentricity of the orbit, and place of the apogee at a
certain time, but also the rate of motion of the apogee itself, in
order to form tables of the moon.
This task, as we have said, Hipparchus executed; and in this
instance, as in the problem of the reduction of the sun’s motion to
tables, the data which he found it necessary to employ were very few.
He deduced all his conclusions from six eclipses of the moon.65 Three of these, the records of which
were brought from Babylon, where a register of such occurrences was
kept, happened in the 366th and 367th years from the era of
Nabonassar, and enabled Hipparchus to determine the eccentricity and
apogee of the moon’s orbit at that time. The three others were
observed at Alexandria, in the 547th year of Nabonassar, which gave
him another position of the orbit at an interval of 180 years; and he
thus became acquainted with the motion of the orbit itself, as well as
its form.66
65 Ptol. Syn. iv. 10.
66 Ptolemy uses the hypothesis of an
epicycle for the moon’s first inequality; but Hipparchus employs an
eccentric.
149 The moon’s
motions are really affected by several other inequalities, of very
considerable amount, besides those which were thus considered by
Hipparchus; but the lunar paths, constructed on the above data,
possessed a considerable degree of correctness, and especially when
applied, as they were principally, to the calculation of eclipses; for
the greatest of the additional irregularities which we have mentioned
disappear at new and full moon, which are the only times when eclipses
take place.
The numerical explanation of the motions of the sun and moon, by
means of the Hypothesis of Eccentrics, and the consequent construction
of tables, was one of the great achievements of Hipparchus. The
general explanation of the motions of the planets, by means of the
hypothesis of epicycles, was in circulation previously, as we have
seen. But the special motions of the planets, in their epicycles, are,
in reality, affected by anomalies of the same kind as those which
render it necessary to introduce eccentrics in the cases of the sun
and moon.
Hipparchus determined, with great exactness, the Mean
Motions of the Planets; but he was not able, from want of data, to
explain the planetary Irregularities by means of Eccentrics.
The whole mass of good observations of the planets which he received
from preceding ages, did not contain so many, says Ptolemy, as those
which he has transmitted to us of his own. “Hence67 it was,” he
adds, “that while he labored, in the most assiduous manner to
represent the motions of the sun and moon by means of equable circular
motions; with respect to the planets, so far as his works show, he did
not even make the attempt, but merely put the extant observations in
order, added to them himself more than the whole of what he received
from preceding ages, and showed the insufficiency of the hypothesis
current among astronomers to explain the phenomena.” It appears that
preceding mathematicians had already pretended to construct “a
Perpetual Canon,” that is, Tables which should give the places of the
planets at any future time; but these being constructed without regard
to the eccentricity of the orbits, must have been very erroneous.
67 Synt. ix. 2.
Ptolemy declares, with great reason, that Hipparchus showed his
usual love of truth, and his right sense of the responsibility of his
task, in leaving this part of it to future ages. The Theories of the
Sun and Moon, which we have already described, constitute him a great
astronomical discoverer, and justify the reputation he has always
150 possessed.
There is, indeed, no philosopher who is so uniformly spoken of in
terms of admiration. Ptolemy, to whom we owe our principal knowledge
of him, perpetually couples with his name epithets of praise: he is
not only an excellent and careful observer, but “a68 most
truth-loving and labor-loving person,” one who had shown extraordinary
sagacity and remarkable desire of truth in every part of science.
Pliny, after mentioning him and Thales, breaks out into one of his
passages of declamatory vehemence: “Great men! elevated above the
common standard of human nature, by discovering the laws which
celestial occurrences obey, and by freeing the wretched mind of man
from the fears which eclipses inspired—Hail to you and to your
genius, interpreters of heaven, worthy recipients of the laws of the
universe, authors of principles which connect gods and men!” Modern
writers have spoken of Hipparchus with the same admiration; and even
the exact but severe historian of astronomy, Delambre, who bestows his
praise so sparingly, and his sarcasm so generally;—who says69 that it is unfortunate for the memory
of Aristarchus that his work has come to us entire, and who cannot
refer70 to the statement of an eclipse rightly
predicted by Halicon of Cyzicus without adding, that if the story be
true, Halicon was more lucky than prudent;—loses all his
bitterness when he comes to Hipparchus.71 “In Hipparchus,”
says he, “we find one of the most extraordinary men of antiquity; the
very greatest, in the sciences which require a combination of
observation with geometry.” Delambre adds, apparently in the wish to
reconcile this eulogium with the depreciating manner in which he
habitually speaks of all astronomers whose observations are inexact,
“a long period and the continued efforts of many industrious men are
requisite to produce good instruments, but energy and assiduity depend
on the man himself.”
68 Synt. ix. 2.
69 Astronomie Ancienne, i.
75.
70 Ib. i. 17.
71 Ib. i. 186.
Hipparchus was the author of other great discoveries and
improvements in astronomy, besides the establishment of the Doctrine
of Eccentrics and Epicycles; but this, being the greatest advance in
the theory of the celestial motions which was made by the
ancients, must be the leading subject of our attention in the present
work; our object being to discover in what the progress of real
theoretical knowledge consists, and under what circumstances it has
gone on. 151
Sect. 2.—Estimate of the Value of the Theory of
Eccentrics and Epicycles.
It may be useful here to explain the value
of the theoretical step which Hipparchus thus made; and the more so,
as there are, perhaps, opinions in popular circulation, which might
lead men to think lightly of the merit of introducing or establishing
the Doctrine of Epicycles. For, in the first place, this doctrine is
now acknowledged to be false; and some of the greatest men in the more
modern history of astronomy owe the brightest part of their fame to
their having been instrumental in overturning this hypothesis. And,
moreover, in the next place, the theory is not only false, but
extremely perplexed and entangled, so that it is usually looked upon
as a mass of arbitrary and absurd complication. Most persons are
familiar with passages in which it is thus spoken of.72


.  .  .  .  .   He his
fabric of the heavens
Hath left to their disputes, perhaps to
move
His laughter at their quaint opinions wide;
Hereafter, when they come to model heaven
And calculate the stars, how will they
wield
The mighty frame! how build, unbuild,
contrive,
To save appearances! how gird the sphere
With centric and eccentric scribbled o’er,
Cycle in epicycle, orb in orb!

And every one will recollect the celebrated saying of
Alphonso X., king of Castile,73 when this
complex system was explained to him; that “if God had consulted him at
the creation, the universe should have been on a better and simpler
plan.” In addition to this, the system is represented as involving an
extravagant conception of the nature of the orbs which it introduces;
that they are crystalline spheres, and that the vast spaces which
intervene between the celestial luminaries are a solid mass, formed by
the fitting together of many masses perpetually in motion; an
imagination which is presumed to be incredible and monstrous.
72 Paradise Lost, viii.
73a. d.
1252.
We must endeavor to correct or remove these prejudices, not only in
order that we may do justice to the Hipparchian, or, as it is usually
called, Ptolemaic system of astronomy, and to its founder; but for
another reason, much more important to the purpose of this work; 152 namely, that we may
see how theories may be highly estimable, though they contain false
representations of the real state of things, and may be extremely
useful, though they involve unnecessary complexity. In the advance of
knowledge, the value of the true part of a theory may much outweigh
the accompanying error, and the use of a rule may be little impaired
by its want of simplicity. The first steps of our progress do not lose
their importance because they are not the last; and the outset of the
journey may require no less vigor and activity than its close.
That which is true in the Hipparchian theory, and which no
succeeding discoveries have deprived of its value, is the
Resolution of the apparent motions of the heavenly bodies
into an assemblage of circular motions. The test of the truth and
reality of this Resolution is, that it leads to the construction of
theoretical Tables of the motions of the luminaries, by which their
places are given at any time, agreeing nearly with their places as
actually observed. The assumption that these circular motions, thus
introduced, are all exactly uniform, is the fundamental principle of
the whole process. This assumption is, it may be said, false; and we
have seen how fantastic some of the arguments were, which were
originally urged in its favor. But some assumption is
necessary, in order that the motions, at different points of a
revolution, may be somehow connected, that is, in order that we may
have any theory of the motions; and no assumption more simple than the
one now mentioned can be selected. The merit of the theory is
this;—that obtaining the amount of the eccentricity, the place
of the apogee, and, it may be, other elements, from few
observations, it deduces from these, results agreeing with
all observations, however numerous and distant. To express an
inequality by means of an epicycle, implies, not only that there is an
inequality, but further,—that the inequality is at its greatest
value at a certain known place,—diminishes in proceeding from
that place by a known law,—continues its diminution for a known
portion of the revolution of the luminary,—then increases again;
and so on: that is, the introduction of the epicycle represents the
inequality of motion, as completely as it can be represented with
respect to its quantity.
We may further illustrate this, by remarking that such a Resolution
of the unequal motions of the heavenly bodies into equable circular
motions, is, in fact, equivalent to the most recent and improved
processes by which modern astronomers deal with such motions. Their
universal method is to resolve all unequal motions into a series of
153 terms,
or expressions of partial motions; and these terms involve
sines and cosines, that is, certain technical modes of
measuring circular motion, the circular motion having some constant
relation to the time. And thus the problem of the resolution of the
celestial motions into equable circular ones, which was propounded
above two thousand years ago in the school of Plato, is still the
great object of the study of modern astronomers, whether observers or
calculators.
That Hipparchus should have succeeded in the first great steps of
this resolution for the sun and moon, and should have seen its
applicability in other cases, is a circumstance which gives him one of
the most distinguished places in the roll of great astronomers. As to
the charges or the sneers against the complexity of his system, to
which we have referred, it is easy to see that they are of no force.
As a system of calculation, his is not only good, but, as we
have just said, in many cases no better has yet been discovered. If,
when the actual motions of the heavens are calculated in the best
possible way, the process is complex and difficult, and if we are
discontented at this, nature, and not the astronomer, must be the
object of our displeasure. This plea of the astronomers must be
allowed to be reasonable. “We must not be repelled,” says Ptolemy,74 “by the complexity of the hypotheses,
but explain the phenomena as well as we can. If the hypotheses satisfy
each apparent inequality separately, the combination of them will
represent the truth; and why should it appear wonderful to any that
such a complexity should exist in the heavens, when we know nothing of
their nature which entitles us to suppose that any inconsistency will
result?”
74 Synt. xiii. 2.
But it may be said, we now know that the motions are more simple
than they were thus represented, and that the Theory of Epicycles was
false, as a conception of the real construction of the heavens. And to
this we may reply, that it does not appear that the best astronomers
of antiquity conceived the cycles and epicycles to have a material
existence. Though the dogmatic philosophers, as the Aristotelians,
appear to have taught that the celestial spheres were real solid
bodies, they are spoken of by Ptolemy as imaginary;75 and it is clear, from his proof of the
identity of the results of the hypothesis of an eccentric and an
epicycle, that they are intended to pass for no more than geometrical
conceptions, in which view they are true representations of the
apparent motions.
75 Ibid. iii. 3.
154 It is true,
that the real motions of the heavenly bodies are simpler than the
apparent motions; and that we, who are in the habit of representing to
our minds their real arrangement, become impatient of the seeming
confusion and disorder of the ancient hypotheses. But this real
arrangement never could have been detected by philosophers, if the
apparent motions had not been strictly examined and successfully
analyzed. How far the connection between the facts and the true theory
is from being obvious or easily traced, any one may satisfy himself by
endeavoring, from a general conception of the moon’s real motions, to
discover the rules which regulate the occurrences of eclipses; or even
to explain to a learner, of what nature the apparent motions of the
moon among the stars will be.
The unquestionable evidence of the merit and value of the Theory of
Epicycles is to be found in this circumstance;—that it served to
embody all the most exact knowledge then extant, to direct astronomers
to the proper methods of making it more exact and complete, to point
out new objects of attention and research; and that, after doing this
at first, it was also able to take in, and preserve, all the new
results of the active and persevering labors of a long series of
Greek, Latin, Arabian, and modern European astronomers, till a new
theory arose which could discharge this office. It may, perhaps,
surprise some readers to be told, that the author of this next
great step in astronomical theory, Copernicus, adopted the
theory of epicycles; that is, he employed that which we have spoken of
as its really valuable characteristic. “We76 must confess,”
he says, “that the celestial motions are circular, or compounded of
several circles, since their inequalities observe a fixed law and
recur in value at certain intervals, which could not be, except that
they were circular; for a circle alone can make that which has been,
recur again.”
76 Copernicus. De Rev. 1. i. c.
4.
In this sense, therefore, the Hipparchian theory was a real and
indestructible truth, which was not rejected, and replaced by
different truths, but was adopted and incorporated into every
succeeding astronomical theory; and which can never cease to be one of
the most important and fundamental parts of our astronomical
knowledge.
A moment’s reflection will show that, in the events just spoken of,
the introduction and establishment of the Theory of Epicycles, those
characteristics were strictly exemplified, which we have asserted to
be the conditions of every real advance in progressive science;
namely, 155 the
application of distinct and appropriate Ideas to a real series of
Facts. The distinctness of the geometrical conceptions which enabled
Hipparchus to assign the Orbits of the Sun and Moon, requires no
illustration; and we have just explained how these ideas combined into
a connected whole the various motions and places of those luminaries.
To make this step in astronomy, required diligence and care, exerted
in collecting observations, and mathematical clearness and steadiness
of view, exercised in seeing and showing that the theory was a
successful analysis of them.
Sect. 3.—Discovery of the Precession of the
Equinoxes.
The same qualities which we trace in the
researches of Hipparchus already examined,—diligence in
collecting observations, and clearness of idea in representing
them,—appear also in other discoveries of his, which we must not
pass unnoticed. The Precession of the Equinoxes, in particular, is one
of the most important of these discoveries.
The circumstance here brought into notice was a Change of Longitude
of the Fixed Stars. The longitudes of the heavenly bodies, being
measured from the point where the sun’s annual path cuts the equator,
will change if that path changes. Whether this happens, however, is
not very easy to decide; for the sun’s path among the stars is made
out, not by merely looking at the heavens, but by a series of
inferences from other observable facts. Hipparchus used for this
purpose eclipses of the moon; for these, being exactly opposite to the
sun, afford data in marking out his path. By comparing the eclipses of
his own time with those observed at an earlier period by Timocharis,
he found that the bright star, Spica Virginis, was six degrees behind
the equinoctial point in his own time, and had been eight degrees
behind the same point at an earlier epoch. The suspicion was thus
suggested, that the longitudes of all the stars increase perpetually;
but Hipparchus had too truly philosophical a spirit to take this for
granted. He examined the places of Regulus, and those of other stars,
as he had done those of Spica; and he found, in all these instances, a
change of place which could be explained by a certain alteration of
position in the circles to which the stars are referred, which
alteration is described as the Precession of the Equinoxes.
The distinctness with which Hipparchus conceived this change of
relation of the heavens, is manifested by the question which, as we
are told by Ptolemy, he examined and decided;—that this motion
of the 156 heavens
takes place about the poles of the ecliptic, and not about those of
the equator. The care with which he collected this motion from the
stars themselves, may be judged of from this, that having made his
first observations for this purpose on Spica and Regulus, zodiacal
stars, his first suspicion was that the stars of the zodiac alone
changed their longitude, which suspicion he disproved by the
examination of other stars. By his processes, the idea of the nature
of the motion, and the evidence of its existence, the two conditions
of a discovery, were fully brought into view. The scale of the facts
which Hipparchus was thus able to reduce to law, may be in some
measure judged of by recollecting that the precession, from his time
to ours, has only carried the stars through one sign of the zodiac;
and that, to complete one revolution of the sky by the motion thus
discovered, would require a period of 25,000 years. Thus this
discovery connected the various aspects of the heavens at the most
remote periods of human history; and, accordingly, the novel and
ingenious views which Newton published in his chronology, are founded
on this single astronomical fact, the Precession of the Equinoxes.
The two discoveries which have been described, the mode of
constructing Solar and Lunar Tables, and the Precession, were advances
of the greatest importance in astronomy, not only in themselves, but
in the new objects and undertakings which they suggested to
astronomers. The one discovery detected a constant law and order in
the midst of perpetual change and apparent disorder; the other
disclosed mutation and movement perpetually operating where every
thing had been supposed fixed and stationary. Such discoveries were
well adapted to call up many questionings in the minds of speculative
men; for, after this, nothing could be supposed constant till it had
been ascertained to be so by close examination; and no apparent
complexity or confusion could justify the philosopher in turning away
in despair from the task of simplification. To answer the inquiries
thus suggested, new methods of observing the facts were requisite,
more exact and uniform than those hitherto employed. Moreover, the
discoveries which were made, and others which could not fail to follow
in their train, led to many consequences, required to be reasoned
upon, systematized, completed, enlarged. In short, the Epoch of
Induction led, as we have stated that such epochs must always
lead, to a Period of Development, of Verification,
Application, and Extension. 157</div></body></text></TEI>