<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="34">

GEOLOGICAL DYNAMICS.

CHAPTER V.
Inorganic Geological Dynamics.

Sect. 1.—Necessity and Object of a
Science of Geological Dynamics.
WHEN the structure and
arrangement which men observed in the materials of the earth
instigated them to speculate concerning the past changes and
revolutions by which such results had been produced, they at first
supposed themselves sufficiently able to judge what would be the
effects of any of the obvious agents of change, as water or volcanic
fire. It did not at once occur to them to suspect, that their common
and extemporaneous judgment on such points was far from sufficient for
sound knowledge;—they did not foresee that they must create a
special science, whose object should be to estimate the general laws
and effects of assumed causes, before they could pronounce whether
such causes had actually produced the particular facts which their
survey of the earth had disclosed to them.
Yet the analogy of the progress of knowledge on other subjects
points out very clearly the necessity of such a science. When
phenomenal astronomy had arrived at a high point of completeness, by
the labors of ages, and especially by the discovery of Kepler’s laws,
astronomers were vehemently desirous of knowing the causes of these
motions; and sanguine men, such as Kepler, readily conjectured that
the motions were the effects of certain virtues and influences, by
which the heavenly bodies acted upon each other. But it did not at
first occur to him and his fellow-speculators, that they had not
ascertained what motions the influences of one body upon another could
produce: and that, therefore, they were not prepared to judge whether
such causes as they spoke of, did really regulate the motions of the
planets. Yet such was found to be the necessary course of sound
inference. Men needed a science of motion, in order to arrive at a
science of the 543
heavenly motions: they could not advance in the study of the Mechanics
of the heavens, till they had learned the Mechanics of terrestrial
bodies. And thus they were, in such speculations, at a stand for
nearly a century, from the time of Kepler to the time of Newton, while
the science of Mechanics was formed by Galileo and his successors.
Till that task was executed, all the attempts to assign the causes of
cosmical phenomena were fanciful guesses and vague assertions; after
that was done, they became demonstrations. The science of
Dynamics enabled philosophers to pass securely and completely
from Phenomenal Astronomy to Physical Astronomy.
In like manner, in order that we may advance from Phenomenal
Geology to Physical Geology, we need a science of Geological
Dynamics;—that is, a science which shall investigate and
determine the laws and consequences of the known causes of changes
such as those which Geology considers:—and which shall do this,
not in an occasional, imperfect, and unconnected manner, but by
systematic, complete, and conclusive methods;—shall, in short,
be a Science, and not a promiscuous assemblage of desultory
essays.
The necessity of such a study, as a distinct branch of geology, is
perhaps hardly yet formally recognized, although the researches which
belong to it have, of late years, assumed a much more methodical and
scientific character than they before possessed. Mr. Lyell’s work
(Principles of Geology), in particular, has eminently
contributed to place Geological Dynamics in its proper prominent
position. Of the four books of his Treatise, the second and third are
upon this division of the subject; the second book treating of aqueous
and igneous causes of change, and the third, of changes in the organic
world.
There is no difficulty in separating this auxiliary geological
science from theoretical Geology itself, in which we apply our
principles to the explanation of the actual facts of the earth’s
surface. The former, if perfected, would be a demonstrative science
dealing with general cases; the latter is an ætiological view having
reference to special facts; the one attempts to determine what always
must be under given conditions; the other is satisfied with knowing
what is and has been, and why it has been; the first study has a
strong resemblance to Mechanics, the other to philosophical
Archæology.
Since this portion of science is still so new, it is scarcely
possible to give any historical account of its progress, or any
complete survey of its shape and component parts. I can only attempt a
few notices, 544
which may enable us in some measure to judge to what point this
division of our subject is tending.
We may remark, in this as in former cases, that since we have here
to consider the formation and progress of a science, we must
treat as unimportant preludes to its history, the detached and casual
observations of the effects of causes of change which we find in older
writers. It is only when we come to systematic collections of
information, such as may afford the means of drawing general
conclusions; or to rigorous deductions from known laws of
nature;—that we can recognise the separate existence of
geological dynamics, as a path of scientific research.
The following may perhaps suffice, for the present, as a sketch of
the subjects of which this science treats:—the aqueous causes of
change, or those in which water adds to, takes from, or transfers, the
materials of the land:—the igneous causes; volcanoes, and,
closely connected with them, earthquakes, and the forces by which they
are produced;—the calculations which determine, on physical
principles, the effects of assumed mechanical causes acting upon large
portions of the crust of the earth;—the effect of the forces,
whatever they be, which produce the crystalline texture of rocks,
their fissile structure, and the separation of materials, of which we
see the results in metalliferous veins. Again, the estimation of the
results of changes of temperature in the earth, whether operating by
pressure, expansion, or in any other way;—the effects of assumed
changes in the superficial condition, extent, and elevation, of
terrestrial continents upon the climates of the earth;—the
effect of assumed cosmical changes upon the temperature of this
planet;—and researches of the same nature as these.
These researches are concerned with the causes of change in the
inorganic world; but the subject requires no less that we should
investigate the causes which may modify the forms and conditions of
organic things; and in the large sense in which we have to use the
phrase, we may include researches on such subjects also as parts of
Geological Dynamics; although, in truth, this department of physiology
has been cultivated, as it well deserves to be, independently of its
bearing upon geological theories. The great problem which offers
itself here, in reference to Geology, is, to examine the value of any
hypotheses by which it may be attempted to explain the succession of
different races of animals and plants in different strata; and though
it may be difficult, in this inquiry, to arrive at any positive
result, we 545 may
at least be able to show the improbability of some conjectures which
have been propounded.
I shall now give a very brief account of some of the attempts made
in these various departments of this province of our knowledge; and in
the present chapter, of Inorganic Changes.
Sect. 2.—Aqueous Causes of Change.
The controversies to which
the various theories of geologists gave rise, proceeding in various
ways upon the effects of the existing causes of change, led men to
observe, with some attention and perseverance, the actual operation of
such causes. In this way, the known effect of the Rhine, in filling up
the Lake of Geneva at its upper extremity, was referred to by De Luc,
Kirwan, and others, in their dispute with the Huttonians; and attempts
were even made to calculate how distant the period was, when this
alluvial deposit first began. Other modern observers have attended to
similar facts in the natural history of rivers and seas. But the
subject may be considered as having first assumed its proper form,
when taken up by Mr. Von Hoff; of whose History of the Natural
Changes of the Earth’s surface which are proved by Tradition, the
first part, treating of aqueous changes, appeared in 1822. This work
was occasioned by a Prize Question of the Royal Society of Göttingen,
promulgated in 1818; in which these changes were proposed as the
subject of inquiry, with a special reference to geology. Although Von
Hoff does not attempt to establish any general inductions upon the
facts which his book contains, the collection of such a body of facts
gave almost a new aspect to the subject, by showing that changes in
the relative extent of land and water were going on at every time, and
almost at every place; and that mutability and fluctuation in the form
of the solid parts of the earth, which had been supposed by most
persons to be a rare exception to the common course of events, was, in
fact, the universal rule. But it was Mr. Lyell’s Principles of
Geology, being an attempt to explain the former Changes of the Earth’s
Surface by the Causes now in action (of which the first volume was
published in 1830), which disclosed the full effect of such researches
on geology; and which attempted to present such assemblages of special
facts, as examples of general laws. Thus this work may, as we have
said, be looked upon as the beginning of Geological Dynamics, at least
among us. Such generalizations and applications as it contains give
the most lively 546
interest to a thousand observations respecting rivers and floods,
mountains and morasses, which otherwise appear without aim or meaning;
and thus this department of science cannot fail to be constantly
augmented by contributions from every side. At the same time it is
clear, that these contributions, voluminous as they must become, must,
from time to time, be resolved into laws of greater and greater
generality; and that thus alone the progress of this, as of all other
sciences, can be furthered.
I need not attempt any detailed enumeration of the modes of aqueous
action which are here to be considered. Some are destructive, as when
the rivers erode the channels in which they flow; or when the waves,
by their perpetual assault, shatter the shores, and carry the ruins of
them into the abyss of the ocean. Some operations of the water, on the
other hand, add to the land; as when deltas are formed at the
mouths of rivers or when calcareous springs form deposits of
travertin. Even when bound in icy fetters, water is by no mean
deprived of its active power; the glacier carries into the
valley masses of its native mountain, and often, becoming ice-bergs,
float with a lading of such materials far into the seas of the
temperate zone. It is indisputable that vast beds of worn down
fragments of the existing land are now forming into strata at the
bottom of the ocean; and that many other effects are constantly
produced by existing aqueous causes, which resemble some, at least, of
the facts which geology has to explain.
[2nd Ed.] [The effects of glaciers above mentioned are obvious; but
the mechanism of these bodies,—the mechanical cause of their
motions,—was an unsolved problem till within a very few years.
That they slide as rigid masses;—that they advance by the
expansion of their mass;—that they advance as a collection of
rigid fragments; were doctrines which were held by eminent physicists;
though a very slight attention to the subject shows these opinions to
be untenable. In Professor James Forbes’s theory on the subject
(published in his Travels through the Alps, 1843,) we find a
solution of the problem, so simple, and yet so exact, as to produce
the most entire conviction. In this theory, the ice of a glacier is,
on a great scale, supposed to be a plastic or viscous mass, though
small portions of it are sensibly rigid. It advances down the slope of
the valley in which it lies as a plastic mass would do, accommodating
itself to the varying shape and size of its bed, and showing by its
crevasses its mixed character between fluid and rigid. It shows this
character still more curiously by a ribboned 547 structure on a
small scale, which is common in the solid ice of the glacier. The
planes of these ribbons are, for the most part, at right angles
to the crevasses, near the sides of the glacier, while, near its
central line, they dip towards the upper part of the glacier.
This structure appears to arise from the difference of velocities of
contiguous moving filaments of the icy mass, as the crevasses
themselves arise from the tension of larger portions. Mr. Forbes has,
in successive publications, removed the objections which have been
urged against this theory. In the last of them, a Memoir in the
Phil. Trans., 1846, (Illustrations of the Viscous Theory of
Glacier Motion,) he very naturally expresses astonishment at the
opposition which has been made to the theory on the ground of the
rigidity of small pieces of ice. He has himself shown that the ice of
glaciers has a plastic flexibility, by marking forty-five points in a
transverse straight line upon the Mer de Glace, and observing them for
several days. The straight line in that time not only became oblique
to the side, but also became visibly curved.
Both Mr. Forbes and other philosophers have made it in the highest
degree probable that glaciers have existed in many places in which
they now exist no longer, and have exercised great powers in
transporting large blocks of rock, furrowing and polishing the rocks
along which they slide, and leaving lines and masses of detritus or
moraine which they had carried along with them or pushed before
them. It cannot be doubted that extinct glaciers have produced some of
the effects which the geologist has to endeavor to explain. But this
part of the machinery of nature has been worked by some theorists into
an exaggerated form, in which it cannot, as I conceive, have any place
in an account of Geological Dynamics which aims at being
permanent.
The great problem of the diffusion of drift and erratic blocks from
their parent rocks to great distances, has driven geologists to the
consideration of other hypothetical machinery by which the effects may
be accounted for: especially the great northern drift and
boulders,—the rocks from the Scandinavian chain which
cover the north of Europe on a vast area, having a length of 2000 and
breadth of from 400 to 800 miles. The diffusion of these blocks has
been accounted for by supposing them to be imbedded in icebergs,
detached from the shore, and floated into oceanic spaces, where they
have grounded and been deposited by the melting of the ice. And this
mode of action may to some extent be safely admitted into geological
speculation. For it is a matter of fact, that our navigators in arctic
and antarctic regions have 548 repeatedly seen icebergs and icefloes
sailing along laden with such materials.
The above explanation of the phenomena of drift supposes the land
on which the travelled materials are found to have been the bottom of
a sea where they were deposited. But it does not, even granting the
conditions, account for some of the facts observed;—that the
drift and the boulders are deposited in “trainées” or streaks, which,
in direction, diverge from the parent rock;—and that the
boulders are of smaller and smaller size, as they are found more
remote from that centre. These phenomena rather suggest the notion of
currents of water as the cause of the distribution of the materials
into their present situations. And though the supposition that the
whole area occupied by drift and boulders was a sea-bottom when they
were scattered over it much reduces the amount of violence which it is
necessary to assume in order to distribute the loose masses, yet still
the work appears to be beyond the possible effect of ordinary marine
currents, or any movements which would be occasioned by a slow and
gradual rising of the centre of distribution.
It has been suggested that a sudden rise of the centre of
distribution would cause a motion in the surrounding ocean sufficient
to produce such an effect: and in confirmation of this reference has
been made to Mr. Scott Russell’s investigations with respect to waves,
already referred to. (Book viii.) The wave in this case would be the wave
of translation, in which the motion of the water is as great at the
bottom as at the top; and it has hence been asserted that by
paroxysmal elevations of 100 or 200 feet, a current of 25 or 30 miles
an hour might be accounted for. But I think it has not been
sufficiently noted that at each point this “current” is transient: it
lasts only while the wave is passing over the point, and therefore it
would only either carry a single mass the whole way with its own
velocity, or move through a short distance a series of masses over
which it successively passed. It does not appear, therefore, that we
have here a complete account of the transport of a collection of
materials, in which each part is transferred through great
distances:—except, indeed, we were to suppose a numerous
succession of paroxysmal elevations. Such a battery might, by
successive shocks, transmitting their force through the water, diffuse
the fragments of the central mass over any area, however wide.
The fact that the erratic blocks are found to rest on the lower
drift, is well explained by supposing the latter to have been spread
on the 549 sea
bottom while rock-bearing ice-masses floated on the surface till they
deposited their lading.
Sir R. Murchison has pointed out another operation of ice in
producing mounds of rocky masses; namely, the effects of rivers and
lakes, in climates where, as in Russia, the waters carry rocky
fragments entangled in the winter ice, and leave them in heaps at the
highest level which the waters attain.
The extent to which the effects of glaciers, now vanished, are
apparent in many places, especially in Switzerland and in England, and
other phenomena of the like tendency, have led some of the most
eminent geologists to the conviction that, interior to the period of
our present temperature, there was a Glacial Period, at which
the temperature of Europe was lower than it now is.]
Although the study of the common operations of water may give the
geologist such an acquaintance with the laws of his subject as may
much aid his judgment respecting the extent to which such effects may
proceed, a long course of observation and thought must be requisite
before such operations can be analysed into their fundamental
principles, and become the subjects of calculation, or of rigorous
reasoning in any manner which is as precise and certain as
calculation. Various portions of Hydraulics have an important bearing
upon these subjects, including some researches which have been pursued
with no small labor by engineers and mathematicians; as the effects of
currents and waves, the laws of tides and of rivers, and many similar
problems. In truth, however, such subjects have not hitherto been
treated by mathematicians with much success; and probably several
generations must elapse before this portion of geological dynamics can
become an exact science.
Sect. 3.—Igneous Causes of Change.—Motions
of the Earth’s Surface.
The effects of volcanoes have
long been noted as important and striking features in the physical
history of our globe; and the probability of their connexion with many
geological phenomena, had not escaped notice at an early period. But
it was not till more recent times, that the full import of these
phenomena was apprehended. The person who first looked at such
operations with that commanding general view which showed their
extensive connexion with physical geology, was Alexander von Humboldt,
who explored the volcanic phenomena 550 of the New World, from 1799 to 1804. He
remarked64 the linear distribution of volcanic
domes, considering them as vents placed along the edge of vast
fissures communicating with reservoirs of igneous matter, and
extending across whole continents. He observed, also, the frequent
sympathy of volcanic and terremotive action in remote districts of the
earth’s surface, thus showing how deeply seated must be the cause of
these convulsions. These views strongly excited and influenced the
speculations of geologists; and since then, phenomena of this kind
have been collected into a general view as parts of a
natural-historical science. Von Hoff, in the second volume of the work
already mentioned, was one of the first who
did this; “At least,” he himself says,65 (1824,) “it was
not known to him that any one before him had endeavored to combine so
large a mass of facts with the general ideas of the natural
philosopher, so as to form a whole.” Other attempts were, however,
soon made. In 1825, M. von Ungern-Sternberg published his book On
the Nature and Origin of Volcanoes,66 in which, he
says, his object is, to give an empirical representation of these
phenomena. In the same year, Mr. Poulett Scrope published a work in
which he described the known facts of volcanic action; not, however,
confining himself to description; his purpose being, as his title
states, to consider “the probable causes of their phenomena, the laws
which determine their march, the disposition of their products, and
their connexion with the present state and past history of the globe;
leading to the establishment of a new theory of the earth.” And in
1826, Dr. Daubeny, of Oxford, produced A Description of Active
and Extinct Volcanoes, including in the latter phrase the
volcanic rocks of central France, of the Rhine, of northern and
central Italy, and many other countries. Indeed, the near connexion
between the volcanic effects now going on, and those by which the
basaltic rocks of Auvergne and many other places had been produced,
was, by this time, no longer doubted by any; and therefore the line
which here separates the study of existing causes from that of past
effects may seem to melt away. But yet it is manifest that the
assumption of an identity of scale and mechanism between volcanoes now
active, and the igneous catastrophes of which the products have 551 survived great
revolutions on the earth’s surface, is hypothetical; and all which
depends on this assumption belongs to theoretical geology.</div></body></text></TEI>