<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="38">CHAPTER XXXVIII.
LAWS WHICH REGULATE THE GEOGRAPHICAL DISTRIBUTION OF
SPECIES—continued.
Geographical distribution of animals—Buffon on specific distinctness of quadrupeds
of Old and New World—Doctrine of "natural barriers"—Different
regions of indigenous mammalia—Europe—Africa—India, and Indian Archipelago—Australia—North
and South America—Quadrupeds in islands—Range
of the Cetacea—Dispersion of quadrupeds—Their powers of swimming—Migratory
instincts—Drifting of animals on ice-floes—On floating
islands of drift-timber—Migrations of Cetacea—Habitations of birds—Their
migrations and facilities of diffusion—Distribution of reptiles, and their
power of dissemination.
Geographical distribution of animals.—Although in speculating
on "philosophical possibilities," said Buffon, "the same temperature
might have been expected, all other circumstances being equal, to
produce the same beings in different parts of the globe, both in the
animal and vegetable kingdoms, yet it is an undoubted fact, that when
America was discovered, its indigenous quadrupeds were all dissimilar
to those previously known in the Old World. The elephant, the
rhinoceros, the hippopotamus, the camelopard, the camel, the dromedary,
the buffalo, the horse, the ass, the lion, the tiger, the apes, the
baboons, and a number of other mammalia, were nowhere to be met
with on the new continent; while in the old, the American species,
of the same great class, were nowhere to be seen—the tapir, the lama,
the pecari, the jaguar, the couguar, the agouti, the paca, the coati, and
the sloth."
These phenomena, although few in number relatively to the whole
animate creation, were so striking and so positive in their nature, that
the great French naturalist caught sight at once of a general law in
the geographical distribution of organic beings, namely, the limitation
of groups of distinct species to regions separated from the rest of the
globe by certain natural barriers. It was, therefore, in a truly philosophical
spirit that, relying on the clearness of the evidence obtained
respecting the larger quadrupeds, he ventured to call in question the
identifications announced by some contemporary naturalists of species
of animals said to be common to the southern extremities of America
and Africa.871
The migration of quadrupeds from one part of the globe to another,
observes Dr. Prichard, is prevented by uncongenial climates and the
branches of the ocean which intersect continents. "Hence, by a
630
reference to the geographical site of countries, we may divide the
earth into a certain number of regions fitted to become the abodes of
particular groups of animals, and we shall find, on inquiry, that each
of these provinces, thus conjecturally marked out, is actually inhabited
by a distinct nation of quadrupeds."872 It will be observed that the
language of Buffon respecting "natural barriers," which has since
been so popular, would be wholly without meaning if the geographical
distribution of organic beings had not led naturalists to adopt very
generally the doctrine of specific centres, or, in other words, to believe
that each species, whether of plant or animal, originated in a single
birth-place. Reject this view, and the fact that not a single native
quadruped is common to Australia, the Cape of Good Hope, and
South America, can in no ways be explained by adverting to the
wide extent of intervening ocean, or to the sterile deserts, or the great
heat or cold of the climates, through which each species must have
passed, before it could migrate from one of those distant regions to
another. It might fairly be asked of one who talked of impassable
barriers, why the same kangaroos, rhinoceroses, or lamas, should not
have been created simultaneously in Australia, Africa, and South
America! The horse, the ox, and the dog, although foreign to these
countries until introduced by man, are now able to support themselves
there in a wild state, and we can scarcely doubt that many of
the quadrupeds at present peculiar to Australia, Africa, and South
America, might have continued in like manner to inhabit each of the
three continents had they been indigenous or could they once have got
a footing there as new colonists.
At the same time every zoologist will be willing to concede, that
even if the departure of each species from a single centre had not
appeared to be part of the plan of Nature, the range of species in
general must have become limited, under the influence of a variety of
causes, especially in the class of terrestrial mammalia. Scarcely any
one of these could be expected to retain as fair a claim to the title of
cosmopolite as man, although even the human race, fitted as it is by
its bodily constitution and intellectual resources to spread very widely
over the earth, is far from being strictly cosmopolite. It is excluded
both from the arctic and antarctic circles, from many a wide desert
and the summits of many mountain-chains; and lastly, from
three-fourths
of the globe covered by water, where there are large areas
very prolific in animal life, even in the highest order of the vertebrate
class. But the habitations of species are, as before stated, in reference
to plants (see above, p. 614), circumscribed by causes different
from those which determine their stations, and these causes are clearly
connected with the time and place of the original creation of each
species.
As the names and characters of land quadrupeds are much better
631
known to the general reader than those of other great families of the
animal kingdom, I shall select this class to exemplify the zoological
provinces into which species are divisible, confining myself, however,
to those facts which may help to elucidate some principle, or rule
apparently followed by the Author of Nature, in regard to that
"mystery of mysteries," the first peopling of the earth with living
beings.873 First, then, the European region comprehends, besides Europe,
the borders of the Mediterranean, and even the north of Africa, and
extends into Asia, beyond the Oural mountains and the Caspian. Although
the species are almost all peculiar, the number of characteristic
genera is remarkably small. The bear, the fox, the hare, the rabbit,
the deer, and almost every European form is found equally in several
of the other large provinces of mammalia, where the species are
distinct. Even the mole (Talpa), although confined to the northern
parts of the old world, ranges eastwards, as far as the Himalaya
mountains.
2dly. The African Fauna, on the other hand, is singularly rich in
generic forms, not met with in a living state in any other region. The
hippopotamus, for example, of which two very distinct species are known,
the giraffe, the Chimpanzee, the blue-faced baboon, the four-fingered
monkeys (Colubus), many carnivora, such as Proteles, allied to the
hyæna, and a multitude of other forms, are exclusively African. A few
of the species inhabiting the northern confines of this continent, such as
the dromedary, lion, and jackall, are also common to Asia; and a much
larger number of forms belong equally to the great Asiatic province,
the species being distinct. The elephant, for example, of Africa is
smaller, has a rounder head, and larger ears than the Indian one, and
has only three instead of four nails on each hind foot. In like manner,
not one of three African species of Rhinoceros agrees with one of the
three Indian kinds.
3dly. The Southern region of Africa, where that continent extends
into the temperate zone, constitutes another separate zoological province,
surrounded as it is on three sides by the ocean, and cut off from the
countries of milder climate in the northern hemisphere, by the intervening
torrid zone. In many instances, this region contains the same
genera which are found in temperate climates to the northward of the
line: but then the southern are different from the northern species.
Thus, in the south we find the quagga and the zebra; in the north, the
horse, the ass, and the jiggetai of Asia.
The south of Africa is spread out into fine level plains from the tropic
to the Cape. In this region, says Pennant, besides the horse genus, of
which five species have been found, there are also peculiar species of
632
rhinoceros, the hog, and the hyrax, among pachydermatous races; and
amongst the ruminating, the Cape buffalo, and a variety of remarkable
antelopes, as the springbok, the oryx, the gnou, the leucophoë, the
pygarga, and several others.874
4thly. The assemblage of quadrupeds in Madagascar affords a striking
illustration of the laws before alluded to, as governing the distribution
of species in islands. Separated from Africa by the Mozambique
channel, which is 300 miles wide, Madagascar forms, with two or three
small islands in its immediate vicinity, a zoological province by itself,
all the species except one, and nearly all the genera, being peculiar.
The only exception consists of a small insectivorous quadruped (Centetes),
found also in the Mauritius, to which place it is supposed to have been
taken in ships. The most characteristic feature of this remarkable fauna
consists in the number of quadrumana of the Lemur family, no less than
six genera of these monkeys being exclusively met with in this island,
and a seventh genus of the same, called Galago, which alone has any
foreign representative, being found, as we might from analogy have
anticipated, in the nearest main land. Had the species of quadrupeds
in Madagascar agreed with those of the contiguous parts of Africa, as
do those of England with the rest of Europe, the naturalist would have
inferred that there had been a land communication since the period of
the coming in of the existing quadrupeds, whereas we may now conclude
that the Mozambique channel has constituted an insuperable barrier to
the fusion of the continental fauna with that of the great island during
the whole period that has elapsed since the living species were created.
5thly. Another of the great nations of terrestrial mammalia is that
of India, containing a great variety of peculiar forms, such as the sloth-bear
(Prochilus), the musk-deer (Moscus), the nylghau, the gibbon or
long-armed ape, and many others.
6thly. A portion of the islands of
the Indian archipelago might, perhaps, be considered by some geologists
as an appendage of the same province. In fact, we find in the large
islands of Java, Sumatra, and Borneo, the same genera, for the most
part, as on the continent of India, and some of the same species, e. g.
the tapir (Tapirus Malayanus), the rhinoceros of Sumatra, and some
others. Most of the species, however, are distinct, and each island has
many, and even a few genera, peculiar to itself. Between eighty and
ninety species are known to inhabit Java, and nearly the same number
occur in Sumatra. Of these, more than half are common to the two
islands. Borneo, which is much less explored, has yielded already
upwards of sixty species, more than half of which are met with either
in Java or Sumatra. Of the species inhabiting Sumatra and not found
in Java, Borneo contains the greater portion. Upon the whole, if these
three large islands were united, and a fusion of their respective indigenous
mammalia should take place, they would present a fauna related
to that of continental India, and comprising about as many species as
633
we might expect from analogy to discover in an area of equal extent.
The Philippine Islands are peopled with another assemblage of species
generically related to the great Indian type.
7thly. But the islands of Celebes, Amboina, Timor, and New Guinea,
constitute a different region of mammalia more allied to the Australian
type, as having an intermixture of marsupial quadrupeds, yet showing
an affinity also to the Indian in such forms as the deer (Cervus), the
weasel (Viverra), the pig (Sus), the Macaque monkey (Cercopithecus),
and others. As we proceed in a south-westerly direction, from Celebes
to Amboina and thence to New Guinea, we find the Indian types
diminishing in number, and the Australian (i. e. marsupial forms)
increasing. Thus in New Guinea seven species of pouched quadrupeds
have been detected, and among them two singular tree-kangaroos; yet
only one species of the whole seven, viz. the flying opossum (Petauris
ariel), is common to the Indian archipelago and the main land of Australia.
The greater the zoological affinity, therefore, between the latter
and the New Guinea fauna, although it seems in some way connected
with geographical proximity, is not to be explained simply by the
mutual migration of species from the one to the other.
8thly. When Australia was discovered, its land quadrupeds, belonging
almost exclusively to the marsupial or pouched tribe, such as the
kangaroos, wombats, flying opossums, kangaroo-rats, and others, some
feeding on herbs and fruits, others carnivorous, were so novel in their
structure and aspect, that they appeared to the naturalist almost as
strange as if they were the inhabitants of some other planet. We learn
from the recent investigations of Mr. Waterhouse,875 that no less than
170 species of marsupial quadrupeds have now been determined, and of
the whole number all but thirty-two are exclusively restricted to Australia.
Of these thirty-two, nine belong to the islands in the Indian
archipelago before mentioned, and the other twenty-three are all species
of opossum inhabiting the tropical parts of South America, or a few of
them extending into Mexico and California, and one, the Virginian
opossum, into the United States.
9thly. It only remains for me to say something of the mammiferous
fauna of North and South America. It has often been said that,
where the three continents of Asia, Europe, and North America, approach
very near to each other towards the pole, the whole arctic region
forms one zoological and botanical province. The narrow straits which
separate the old and new world are frozen over in winter, and the distance
is farther lessened by intervening islands. Many plants and animals
of various classes have accordingly spread over all the arctic lands,
being sometimes carried in the same manner as the polar bear, when it
is drifted on floating ice from Greenland to Iceland. But on a close
inspection of the arctic mammalia, it has been found of late years that
a very small number of the American species are identical with those of
634
Europe or Asia. The genera are, in great part, the same or nearly
allied; but the species are rarely identical, and are often very unlike,
as in the case of the American badger and that of Europe. Some of the
genera of arctic America, such as the musk ox (Ovibos), are quite peculiar,
and the distinctness of the fauna of the great continents goes on
increasing in proportion as we trace them southwards, or as they recede
farther from each other, and become more and more separated by the
ocean. At length we find that the three groups of tropical mammalia,
belonging severally to America, Africa, and India, have not a single
species in common.
The predominant influence of climate over all the other causes which
limit the range of species in the mammalia is perhaps nowhere so conspicuously
displayed as in North America. The arctic fauna, so admirably
described by Sir John Richardson, has scarcely any species in common
with the fauna of the state of New York, which is 600 miles farther
south, and comprises about forty distinct mammifers. If again we travel
farther south about 600 miles, and enter another zone, running east and
west, in South Carolina, Georgia, Alabama, and the contiguous states,
we again meet with a new assemblage of land quadrupeds, and this
again differs from the fauna of Texas, where frosts are unknown. It will
be observed that on this continent there are no great geographical
barriers running east and west, such as high snow-clad mountains, barren
deserts, or wide arms of the sea, capable of checking the free migration
of species from north to south. But notwithstanding the distinctness
of those zones of indigenous mammalia, there are some species, such as
the buffalo (Bison Americanus), the racoon (Procyon lotor), and the
Virginian opossum (Didelphis Virginiana), which have a wider habitation,
ranging almost from Canada to the Gulf of Mexico; but they form
exceptions to the general rule. The opossum of Texas (Didelphis
carnivora) is different from that of Virginia, and other species of the
same genus inhabit westward of the Rocky Mountains, in California, for
example, where almost all the mammalia differ from those of the United
States.
10thly. The West Indian land quadrupeds are not numerous, but
several of them are peculiar; and 11thly, South America is the most
distinct, with the exception of Australia, of all the provinces into which
the mammalia can be classed geographically. The various genera of
monkeys, for example, belong to the family Platyrrhini, a large natural
division of the quadrumana, so named from their widely separated nostrils.
They have a peculiar dentition, and many of them prehensile
tails, and are entirely unknown in other quarters of the globe. The
sloths and armadillos, the true blood-sucking bats or vampyres (Phyllostomidæ),
the capybara, the largest of the rodents, the carnivorous coatimondi
(Nasua), and a great many other forms, are also exclusively
characteristic of South America.
"In Peru and Chili," says Humboldt, "the region of the grasses,
which is at an elevation of from 12,300 to 15,400 feet, is inhabited by
635
crowds of lama, guanaco, and alpaca. These quadrupeds, which here
represent the genus camel of the ancient continent, have not extended
themselves either to Brazil or Mexico; because, during their journey,
they must necessarily have descended into regions that were too hot for
them."876 In this passage it will be seen that the doctrine of "specific
centres" is tacitly assumed.
Quadrupeds in Islands.—Islands remote from continents, especially
those of small size, are either destitute of quadrupeds, except such as
have been conveyed to them by man, or contain species peculiar to
them. In the Galapagos archipelago no indigenous quadrupeds were
found except one mouse, which is supposed to be distinct from any
hitherto found elsewhere. A peculiar species of fox is indigenous in
the Falkland Islands, and a rat in New Zealand, which last country,
notwithstanding its magnitude, is destitute of other mammalia, except
bats, and these, says Dr. Prichard, may have made their way along
the chain of islands which extend from the shores of New Guinea far
into the Southern Pacific. The same author remarks, that among the
various groups of fertile islands in the Pacific, no quadrupeds have
been met with except the rat and a few bats as above mentioned, and
the dog and hog, which appear to have been conveyed thither by the
natives from New Guinea. "Rats are to be found even on some
desert islands, whither they may have been conveyed by canoes which
have occasionally approached the shore. It is known, also, that rats
occasionally swim in large numbers to considerable distances."877
Geographical range of the Cetacea.—It is natural to suppose that
the geographical range of the different species of Cetacea should be
less correctly ascertained than that of the terrestrial mammifers. It
is, however, well known that the whales which are obtained by our
fishers in the South Seas are distinct from those of the North; and
the same dissimilarity has been found in all the other marine animals,
of the same class, so far as they have yet been studied by naturalists.
Dispersion of quadrupeds.—Let us now inquire what facilities the
various land quadrupeds enjoy of spreading themselves over the surface
of the earth. In the first place, as their numbers multiply, all of them,
whether they feed on plants, or prey on other animals, are disposed to
scatter themselves gradually over as wide an area as is accessible to
them. But before they have extended their migrations over a large
space, they are usually arrested either by the sea, or a zone of uncongenial
climate, or some lofty and unbroken chain of mountains, or a
tract already occupied by a hostile and more powerful species.
Their powers of swimming.—Rivers and narrow friths can seldom
interfere with their progress; for the greater part of them swim well,
and few are without this power when urged by danger and pressing
want. Thus, amongst beasts of prey, the tiger is seen swimming about
636
among the islands and creeks in the delta of the Ganges, and the
jaguar traverses with ease the largest streams in South America.878
The bear, also, and the bison, cross the current of the Mississippi.
The popular error, that the common swine cannot escape by swimming
when thrown into the water, has been contradicted by several curious
and well-authenticated instances during the floods in Scotland of 1829.
One pig, only six months old, after having been carried down from
Garmouth to the bar at the mouth of the Spey, a distance of a quarter
of a mile, swam four miles eastward to Port Gordon, and landed safe.
Three others, of the same age and litter, swam, at the same time, five
miles to the west, and landed at Blackhill.879
In an adult and wild state, these animals would doubtless have been
more strong and active, and might, when hard pressed, have performed
a much longer voyage. Hence islands remote from the continent may
obtain inhabitants by casualties which, like the late storms in Morayshire,
may only occur once in many centuries, or thousands of years,
under all the same circumstances. It is obvious that powerful tides,
winds, and currents may sometimes carry along quadrupeds capable,
in like manner, of preserving themselves for hours in the sea, to very
considerable distances; and in this way, perhaps, the tapir (Tapir
Indicus) may have become common to Sumatra and the Malayan
peninsula.
To the elephant, in particular, the power of crossing rivers is essential
in a wild state, for the quantity of food which a herd of these animals
consumes renders it necessary that they should be constantly moving
from place to place. The elephant crosses the stream in two ways.
If the bed of the river be hard, and the water not of too great a depth,
he fords it. But when he crosses great rivers, such as the Ganges and
the Niger, the elephant swims deep, so deep, that the end of his trunk
only is out of the water; for it is a matter of indifference to him
whether his body be completely immersed, provided he can bring the
tip of his trunk to the surface, so as to breathe the external air.
Animals of the deer kind frequently take to the water, especially in
the rutting season, when the stags are seen, swimming for several leagues
at a time, from island to island, in search of the does, especially in the
Canadian lakes; and in some countries where there are islands near the
sea-shore, they fearlessly enter the sea and swim to them. In hunting
excursions, in North America, the elk of that country is frequently
pursued for great distances through the water.
The large herbivorous animals, which are gregarious, can never
remain long in a confined region, as they consume so much vegetable
food. The immense herds of bisons (Bos Americanus) which often,
in the great valleys of the Mississippi and its tributaries blacken the
637
surface of the prairie lands, are continually shifting their quarters,
followed by wolves, which prowl about in their rear. "It is no exaggeration,"
says Mr. James, "to assert, that in one place, on the banks
of the Platte, at least ten thousand bisons burst on our sight in an
instant. In the morning, we again sought the living picture; but
upon all the plain, which last evening was so teeming with noble
animals, not one remained."880
Migratory instincts.—Besides the disposition common to the individuals
of every species slowly to extend their range in search of food,
in proportion as their numbers augment, a migratory instinct often
developes itself in an extraordinary manner, when, after an unusually
prolific season, or upon a sudden scarcity of provisions, great multitudes
are threatened by famine. It may be useful to enumerate some
examples of these migrations, because they may put us upon our
guard against attributing a high antiquity to a particular species merely
because it is diffused over a great space; they show clearly how soon,
in a state of nature, a newly created species might spread itself, in every
direction, from a single point.
In very severe winters, great numbers of the black bears of America
migrate from Canada into the United States; but in milder seasons,
when they have been well fed, they remain and hybernate in the north.881
The rein-deer, which, in Scandinavia, can scarcely exist to the south of
the sixty-fifth parallel, descends, in consequence of the greater coldness
of the climate, to the fiftieth degree in Chinese Tartary, and often roves
into a country of more southern latitude than any part of England.
In Lapland, and other high latitudes, the common squirrels, whenever
they are compelled, by want of provisions, to quit their usual abodes,
migrate in amazing numbers, and travel directly forwards, allowing
neither rocks nor forests, nor the broadest waters, to turn them from their
course. Great numbers are often drowned in attempting to pass friths
and rivers. In like manner the small Norway rat sometimes pursues
its migrations in a straight line across rivers and lakes; and Pennant
informs us, that when the rats, in Kamtschatka, become too numerous,
they gather together in the spring, and proceed in great bodies westward,
swimming over rivers, lakes, and arms of the sea. Many are
drowned or destroyed by water-fowl or fish. As soon as they have
crossed the river Penginsk, at the head of the gulf of the same name,
they turn southward, and reach the rivers Judoma and Okotsk by the
middle of July; a district more than 800 miles distant from their point
of departure.
The lemings, also, a small kind of rat, are described as natives of the
mountains of Kolen, in Lapland; and once or twice in a quarter of a
century they appear in vast numbers, advancing along the ground, and
"devouring every green thing." Innumerable bands march from the
638
Kolen, through Nordland and Finmark, to the Western Ocean, which
they immediately enter; and after swimming about for some time, perish.
Other bands take their route through Swedish Lapland, to the Bothnian
Gulf, where they are drowned in the same manner. They are followed
in their journeys by bears, wolves, and foxes, which prey upon them incessantly.
They generally move in lines, which are about three feet
from each other, and exactly parallel, going directly forward through
rivers and lakes; and when they meet with stacks of hay or corn, gnawing
their way through them instead of passing round.882 These excursions
usually precede a rigorous winter, of which the lemings seem in
some way forewarned.
Fig. 97.
The Leming, or Lapland Marmot (Mus Lemmus, Linn.)
Vast troops of the wild ass, or onager of the ancients, which inhabit
the mountainous deserts of Great Tartary, feed, during the summer, in
the tracts east and north of Lake Aral. In the autumn they collect in
herds of hundreds, and even thousands, and direct their course towards
Persia, to enjoy a warm retreat during winter.883 Bands of two or three
hundred quaggas, a species of wild ass, are sometimes seen to migrate
from the tropical plains of southern Africa to the vicinity of the Malaleveen
River. During their migrations they are followed by lions, who
slaughter them night by night.884
The migratory swarms of the springbok, or Cape antelope, afford
another illustration of the rapidity with which a species under certain
circumstances may be diffused over a continent. When the stagnant
pools of the immense deserts south of the Orange River dry up, which
often happens after intervals of three or four years, myriads of these animals
desert the parched soil, and pour down like a deluge on the cultivated
regions near the Cape. The havoc committed by them resembles
that of the African locusts; and so crowded are the herds, that "the
lion has been seen to walk in the midst of the compressed phalanx with
only as much room between him and his victims as the fears of those
immediately around could procure by pressing outwards."885
639
Fig. 98.

Mydaus meliceps, or badger-headed Mydaus. Length, including the tail, 16 inches.
Dr. Horsfield mentions a singular fact in regard to the geographical
distribution of the Mydaus meliceps, an animal intermediate between
the polecat and badger. It inhabits Java, and is "confined exclusively
to those mountains which have an elevation of more than seven thousand
feet above the level of the ocean; on these it occurs with the same regularity
as many plants. The long extended surface of Java, abounding
with conical points which exceed this elevation, affords many places
favorable for its resort. On ascending these mountains, the traveller
scarcely fails to meet with this animal, which, from its peculiarities, is
universally known to the inhabitants of these elevated tracts, while to
those of the plains it is as strange to an animal from a foreign county.
In my visits to the mountainous districts, I uniformly met with it; and,
as far as the information of the natives can be relied on, it is found on
all the mountains."886
Now, if asked to conjecture how the Mydaus arrived at the elevated
regions of each of these isolated mountains, we might say that, before
the island was peopled by man, by whom their numbers are now
thinned, they may occasionally have multiplied so as to be forced to
collect together and migrate: in which case notwithstanding the slowness
of their motions, some few would succeed in reaching another
mountain, some twenty, or even, perhaps, fifty miles distant; for although
the climate of the hot intervening plains would be unfavourable to them,
they might support it for a time, and would find there abundance of
insects on which they feed. Volcanic eruptions, which, at different
times have covered the summits of some of those lofty cones with sterile
sand and ashes, may have occasionally contributed to force on these
migrations.
Drifting of animals on ice-floes.—The power of the terrestrial mammalia
to cross the sea is very limited, and it was before stated that the
same species is scarcely ever common to districts widely separated by
the ocean. If there be some exceptions to this rule, they generally
admit of explanation; for there are natural means whereby some animals
may be floated across the water, and the sea may in the course of ages
640
wear a wide passage through a neck of land, leaving individuals of a
species on each side of the new channel. Polar bears are known to
have been frequently drifted on the ice from Greenland to Iceland; they
can also swim to considerable distances, for Captain Parry, on the return
of his ships through Barrow's Straits, met with a bear swimming in the
water about midway between the shores, which were about forty miles
apart, and where no ice was in sight.887 "Near the east coast of Greenland,"
observes Scoresby, "they have been seen on the ice in such
quantities, that they were compared to flocks of sheep on a common;
and they are often found on field-ice, above two hundred miles from the
shore."888 Wolves, in the arctic regions, often venture upon the ice near
the shore, for the purpose of preying upon young seals which they surprise
when asleep. When these ice-floes get detached, the wolves are
often carried out to sea; and though some may be drifted to islands or
continents, the greater part of them perish, and have been often heard
in this situation howling dreadfully, as they die by famine.889
During the short summer which visits Melville Island, various plants
push forth their leaves and flowers the moment the snow is off the
ground, and form a carpet spangled with the most lively colours. These
secluded spots are reached annually by herds of musk-oxen and reindeer,
which travel immense distances over dreary and desolate regions,
to graze undisturbed on these luxuriant pastures.890 The rein-deer often
pass along in the same manner, by the chain of the Aleutian Islands,
from Behring's Straits to Kamtschatka, subsisting on the moss found in
these islands during their passage.891 But the musk-ox, notwithstanding
its migratory habits, and its long journeys over the ice, does not exist,
either in Asia or Greenland.892
On floating islands of drift-wood.—Within the tropics there are no
ice-floes; but, as if to compensate for that mode of transportation, there
are floating islets of matted trees, which are often borne along through
considerable spaces. These are sometimes seen sailing at the distance
of fifty or one hundred miles from the mouth of the Ganges, with living
trees standing erect upon them. The Amazon, the Congo, and the
Orinoco, also produce these verdant rafts, which are formed in the
manner already described when speaking of the great raft of the Atchafalaya,
an arm of the Mississippi, where a natural bridge of timber, ten
miles long, and more than two hundred yards wide, existed for more
than forty years, supporting a luxuriant vegetation, and rising and
sinking with the water which flowed beneath it.
On these green islets of the Mississippi, observes Malte-Brun, young
trees take root, and the pistia and nenuphar display their yellow
641
flowers: serpents, birds, and the cayman alligator, come to repose
there, and all are sometimes carried to the sea and engulphed in its
waters.893
Spix and Martius relate that, during their travels in Brazil, they were
exposed to great danger while ascending the Amazon in a canoe, from
the vast quantity of drift-wood constantly propelled against them by
the current; so much so, that their safety depended on the crew being
always on the alert to turn aside the trunks of trees with long poles.
The tops alone of some trees appeared above water, others had their
roots attached to them with so much soil that they might be compared
to floating islets. On these, say the travellers, we saw some very
singular assemblages of animals, pursuing peacefully their uncertain
way in strange companionship. On one raft were several grave-looking
storks, perched by the side of a party of monkeys, who made comical
gestures, and burst into loud cries, on seeing the canoe. On another
was seen a number of ducks and divers, sitting by a group of squirrels.
Next came down upon the stem of a large rotten cedar tree, an enormous
crocodile, by the side of a tiger-cat, both animals regarding each other
with hostility and mistrust, but the saurian being evidently most at his
ease, as conscious of his superior strength.894
Similar green rafts, principally composed of canes and brushwood,
are called "camelotes" on the Parana in South America; and they are
occasionally carried down by inundations, bearing on them the tiger,
cayman, squirrels, and other quadrupeds, which are said to be always
terror-stricken on their floating habitation. No less than four tigers
(pumas) were landed in this manner in one night at Monte Video, lat.
35° S., to the great alarm of the inhabitants, who found them prowling
about the streets in the morning.895
In a memoir lately published, a naval officer relates that, as he
returned from China by the eastern passage, he fell in, among the Moluccas,
with several small floating islands of this kind, covered with mangrove
trees interwoven with underwood. The trees and shrubs retained
their verdure, receiving nourishment from a stratum of soil which formed
a white beach round the margin of each raft, where it was exposed to
the washing of the waves and the rays of the sun.896 The occurrence
of soil in such situations may easily be explained; for all the natural
bridges of timber which occasionally connect the islands of the Ganges,
Mississippi, and other rivers, with their banks, are exposed to floods of
water, densely charged with sediment.
Captain W. H. Smyth informs me, that, when cruising in the Cornwallis
amidst the Philippine Islands, he has more than once seen, after
those dreadful hurricanes called typhoons, floating masses of wood, with
642
trees growing upon them, and ships have sometimes been in imminent
peril, as often as these islands were mistaken for terra firma, when, in
fact, they were in rapid motion.
It is highly interesting to trace, in imagination, the effects of the
passage of these rafts from the mouth of a large river to some archipelago,
such as those in the South Pacific, raised from the deep, in comparatively
modern times, by the operations of the volcano and the earthquake,
and the joint labours of coral animals and testacea. If a storm
arise, and the frail vessel be wrecked, still many a bird and insect may
succeed in gaining, by flight, some island of the newly formed group,
while the seeds and berries of herbs and shrubs, which fall into the
waves, may be thrown upon the strand. But if the surface of the deep
be calm, and the rafts are carried along by a current, or wafted by some
slight breath of air fanning the foliage of the green trees, it may arrive,
after a passage of several weeks, at the bay of an island, into which its
plants and animals may be poured out as from an ark, and thus a colony
of several hundred new species may at once be naturalized.
The reader should be reminded, that I merely advert to the transportation
of these rafts as of extremely rare and accidental occurrence; but
it may account, in tropical countries, for some of the rare exceptions to
the general law of the confined range of mammiferous species.
Migrations of the Cetacea.—Many of the Cetacea, the whales of the
northern seas for example, are found to desert one tract of the sea, and
to visit another very distant, when they are urged by want of food, or
danger. The seals also retire from the coast of Greenland in July, return
again in September, and depart again in March, to return in June. They
proceed in great droves northwards, directing their course where the sea
is most free from ice, and are observed to be extremely fat when they
set out on this expedition, and very lean when they come home again.897
Species of the Mediterranean, Black Sea, and Caspian identical.—Some
naturalists have wondered that the sea-calves, dolphins, and other
marine mammalia of the Mediterranean and Black Sea, should be identical
with those found in the Caspian: and among other fanciful theories,
they have suggested that they may dive through subterranean conduits,
and thus pass from one sea into the other. But as the occurrence of
wolves and other noxious animals, on both sides of the British Channel,
was adduced, by Verstegan and Desmarest, as one of many arguments
to prove that England and France were once united; so the correspondence
of the aquatic species of the inland seas of Asia with those of the
Black Sea tend to confirm the hypothesis, for which there are abundance
of independent geological data, that those seas were connected together
by straits at no remote period of the earth's history.
Geographical Distribution and Migrations of Birds.
I shall now offer a few observations on some of the other divisions of
643
the animal kingdom. Birds, notwithstanding their great locomotive
powers, form no exception to the general rules already laid down; but,
in this class, as in plants and terrestrial quadrupeds, different groups of
species are circumscribed within definite limits. We find, for example,
one assemblage in the Brazils, another in the same latitudes in Central
Africa, another in India, and a fourth in New Holland. Of twenty-six
different species of land birds found in the Galapagos archipelago, all,
with the exception of one, are distinct from those inhabiting other parts
of the globe;898 and in other archipelagos a single island sometimes contains
a species found in no other spot on the whole earth; as is exemplified
in some of the parrot tribes. In this extensive family, which are,
with few exceptions, inhabitants of tropical regions, the American group
has not one in common with the African, nor either of these with the
parrots of India.899
Another illustration is afforded by that minute and beautiful tribe,
the humming-birds. The whole of them are, in the first place, peculiar
to the new world; but some species are confined to Mexico, while
others exist only in some of the West India Islands, and have not
been found elsewhere in the western hemisphere. Yet there are species
of this family which have a vast range, as the Trochilus flammifrons
(or Mellisuga Kingii), which is found over a space of 2500
miles on the west coast of South America, from the hot dry country
of Lima to the humid forests of Tierra del Fuego. Captain King,
during his survey in the years 1826-30, found this bird at the Straits
of Magellan, in the month of May—the depth of winter—sucking the
flowers of a large species of fuchsia, then in bloom, in the midst of a
shower of snow.
The ornithology of our own country affords one well-known and
striking exemplification of the law of a limited specific range; for the
common grouse (Tetra scoticus) occurs nowhere in the known world
except in the British isles.
Some species of the vulture tribe are said to be cosmopolites; and
the common wild goose (Anas anser, Linn.), if we may believe some
ornithologists, is a general inhabitant of the globe, being met with from
Lapland to the Cape of Good Hope, frequent in Arabia, Persia, China,
and Japan, and in the American continent from Hudson's Bay to South
Carolina.900 An extraordinary range has also been attributed to the
nightingale, which extends from western Europe to Persia, and still farther.
In a work entitled Specchio Comparativo,901 by Charles Bonaparte,
many species of birds are enumerated as common to Rome and Philadelphia:
the greater part of these are migratory, but some of them,
such as the long-eared owl (Strix otus), are permanent in both countries.
The correspondence of the ornithological fauna of the eastern and
644
western hemispheres increases considerably, as might have been anticipated,
in high northern latitudes.902
Their facilities of diffusion.—In parallel zones of the northern and
southern hemispheres, a great general correspondence of form is
observable, both in the aquatic and terrestrial birds; but there is rarely
any specific identity; and this phenomenon is truly remarkable, when
we recollect the readiness with which some birds, not gifted with great
powers of flight, shift their quarters to different regions, and the facility
with which others, possessing great strength of wing, perform their
aërial voyage. Some migrate periodically from high latitudes, to avoid
the cold of winter, and the accompaniments of cold,—scarcity of insects
and vegetable food; others, it is said, for some particular kinds of nutriment
required for rearing their young: for this purpose they often traverse
the ocean for thousands of miles, and recross it at other periods,
with equal security.
Periodical migrations, no less regular, are mentioned by Humboldt,
of many American water-fowl, from one part of the tropics to another,
in a zone where there is the same temperature throughout the year.
Immense flights of ducks leave the valley of the Orinoco, when the
increasing depth of its waters and the flooding of its shores prevent
them from catching fish, insects, and aquatic worms. They then betake
themselves to the Rio Negro and Amazon, having passed from the
eighth and third degrees of north latitude to the first and fourth of south
latitude, directing their course south-south-east. In September, when
the Orinoco decreases and re-enters its channel, these birds return northwards.903
The insectivorous swallows which visit our island would perish during
winter, if they did not annually repair to warmer climes. It is supposed
that in these aerial excursions the average rapidity of their flight is not
less than fifty miles an hour; so that, when aided by the wind, they
soon reach warmer latitudes. Spallanzani calculated that the swallow
can fly at the rate of ninety-two miles an hour, and conceived that the
rapidity of the swift might be three times greater.904 The rate of flight
of the eider duck (Anas mollissima) is said to be ninety miles an hour;
and Bachman says that the hawk, wild pigeon (Columba migratoria),
and several species of wild ducks, in North America, fly at the rate of
forty miles an hour, or nearly a thousand miles in twenty-four hours.905
When we reflect how easily different species, in a great lapse of ages,
may be each overtaken by gales and hurricanes, and, abandoning themselves
to the tempest, be scattered at random through various regions
of the earth's surface, where the temperature of the atmosphere, the
vegetation, and the animal productions, might be suited to their wants,
we shall be prepared to find some species capriciously distributed, and
645
to be sometimes unable to determine the native countries of each.
Captain Smyth informs me, that, when engaged in his survey of the
Mediterranean, he encountered a gale in the Gulf of Lyons, at the distance
of between twenty and thirty leagues from the coast of France,
which bore along many land birds of various species, some of which
alighted on the ship, while others were thrown with violence against the
sails. In this manner islands become tenanted by species of birds
inhabiting the nearest mainland.
Geographical Distribution and Dissemination of Reptiles.
A few facts respecting the third great class of vertebrated animals
will suffice to show that the plan of nature in regard to their location
on the globe is perfectly analogous to that already exemplified in other
parts of the organic creation, and has probably been determined by
similar causes.
Habitations of reptiles.—Of the great saurians, the gavials which
inhabit the Ganges differ from the cayman of America, or the crocodile
of the Nile. The monitor of New Holland is specifically distinct from
the Indian species; these latter, again, from the African, and all from
their congeners in the new world. So in regard to snakes; we find the
boa of America represented by the python, a different though nearly
allied genus in India. America is the country of the rattlesnake;
Africa, of the cerastes; and Asia, of the hooded snake, or cobra di
capello. The amphibious genera Siren and Menopoma belong to North
America, possessing both lungs and gills, and respiring at pleasure
either air or water. The only analogous animal of the old world is
the Proteus anguinus of the lakes of Lower Carniola, and the grotto of
Adelsberg between Trieste and Vienna.906
There is a legend that St. Patrick expelled all reptiles from Ireland;
and certain it is that none of the three species of snakes common in
England, nor the toad, have been observed there by naturalists. They
have our common frog, and our water-newt, and according to Ray
(Quad. 264.), the green lizard (Lacerta viridis).
Migrations of the larger reptiles.—The range of the large reptiles is,
in general, quite as limited as that of some orders of the terrestrial
mammalia. The great saurians sometimes cross a considerable tract in
order to pass from one river to another; but their motions by land are
generally slower than those of quadrupeds. By water, however, they
may transport themselves to distant situations more easily. The larger
alligator of the Ganges sometimes descends beyond the brackish water
of the delta into the sea; and in such cases it might chance to be
drifted away by a current, and survive till it reached a shore at some
distance; but such casualties are probably very rare.
Turtles migrate in large droves from one part of the ocean to another
646
during the ovipositing season; and they find their way annually to the
island of Ascension, from which the nearest land is about 800 miles
distant. Dr. Fleming mentions, that an individual of the hawk's bill
turtle (Chelonia imbricata), so common in the American seas, has been
taken at Papa Stour, one of the West Zetland Islands;907 and, according
to Sibbald, "the same animal came into Orkney." Another was taken,
in 1774, in the Severn, according to Turton. Two instances, also, of
the occurrence of the leathern tortoise (C. coriacea), on the coast of
Cornwall, in 1756, are mentioned by Borlase. These animals of more
southern seas can be considered only as stragglers, attracted to our
shores during uncommonly warm seasons by an abundant supply of food,
or carried by the Gulf stream, or driven by storms to high latitudes.
Some of the smaller reptiles lay their eggs on aquatic plants; and
these must often be borne rapidly by rivers, and conveyed to distant
regions in a manner similar to the dispersion of seeds before adverted to.
But that the larger ophidians may be themselves transported across the
seas, is evident from the following most interesting account of the arrival
of one at the island of St. Vincent. It is worthy of being recorded, says
Mr. Guilding, "that a noble specimen of the Boa constrictor was lately
conveyed to us by the currents, twisted round the trunk of a large sound
cedar tree, which had probably been washed out of the bank by the
floods of some great South American river, while its huge folds hung on
the branches, as it waited for its prey. The monster was fortunately
destroyed after killing a few sheep, and his skeleton now hangs before
me in my study, putting me in mind how much reason I might have had
to fear in my future rambles through the forests of St. Vincent, had this
formidable reptile been a pregnant female, and escaped to a safe retreat."908
</div></body></text></TEI>