<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="30">
      SECTION 6. ORDER OF MERIT.
    

      Amongst the various proposals for encouraging science, the institution of
      an order of merit has been suggested. It is somewhat singular, that whilst
      in most of the other kingdoms of Europe, such orders exist for the purpose
      of rewarding, by honorary distinctions, the improvers of the arts of life,
      or successful discoverers in science, nothing of the kind has been
      established in England. [At the great meeting of the philosophers at
      Berlin, in 1828, of which an account is given in the Appendix; the respect
      in which Berzelius, Oersted, Gauss, and Humboldt were held in their
      respective countries was apparent in the orders bestowed on them by the
      Sovereigns of Sweden, of Denmark, of Hanover, and of Prussia; and there
      were present many other philosophers, whose decorations sufficiently
      attested the respect in which science was held in the countries from which
      they came.]
    

      Our orders of knighthood are favourable only to military distinction. It
      has been urged, as an argument for such institutions, that they are a
      cheap mode of rewarding science, whilst, on the other hand, it has been
      objected, that they would diminish the value of such honorary distinctions
      by making them common. The latter objection is of little weight, because
      the numbers who pursue science are few, and, probably, will long continue
      so. It would also be easily avoided, by restricting the number of the
      order or of the class, if it were to form a peculiar class of another
      order. Another objection, however, appears to me to possess far greater
      weight; and, however strong the disposition of the Government might be (if
      such an order existed) to fill it properly, I do not believe that, in the
      present state of public opinion respecting science, it could be done, and,
      in all probability, it would be filled up through the channels of
      patronage, and by mere jobbers in science.
    

      Another proposal, of a similar kind, has also been talked of, one which it
      may appear almost ridiculous to suggest in England, but which would be
      considered so in no other country. It is, to ennoble some of the greatest
      scientific benefactors of their country. Not to mention political causes,
      the ranks of the nobility are constantly recruited from the army, the
      navy, and the bar; why should not the family of that man, whose name is
      imperishably connected with the steam-engine, be enrolled amongst the
      nobility of his country? In utility and profit, not merely to that
      country, but to the human race, his deeds may proudly claim comparison
      even with the most splendid of those achieved by classes so rich in
      glorious recollections. An objection, in most cases fatal to such a
      course, arises from the impolicy of conferring a title, unless a
      considerable fortune exists to support it; a circumstance very rarely
      occurring to the philosopher. It might in some measure be removed, by
      creating such titles only for life. But here, again, until there existed
      some knowledge of science amongst the higher classes, and a sound state of
      public opinion relative to science, the execution of the plan could only
      be injurious.
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>