<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="75">INTRODUCTION.
Of Thermotics and Atmology.
I EMPLOY the term
Thermotics to include all the doctrines respecting Heat, which
have hitherto been established on proper scientific grounds. Our
survey of the history of this branch of science must be more rapid and
less detailed than it has been in those subjects of which we have
hitherto treated: for our knowledge is, in this case, more vague and
uncertain than in the others, and has made less progress towards a
general and certain theory. Still, the narrative is too important and
too instructive to be passed over.
The distinction of Formal Thermotics and Physical
Thermotics,—of the discovery of the mere Laws of Phenomena, and
the discovery of their causes,—is applicable here, as in other
departments of our knowledge. But we cannot exhibit, in any prominent
manner, the latter division of the science now before us; since no
general theory of heat has yet been propounded, which affords the
means of calculating the circumstances of the phenomena of conduction,
radiation, expansion, and change of solid, liquid, and gaseous form.
Still, on each of these subjects there have been proposed, and
extensively assented to, certain general views, each of which explains
its appropriate class of phenomena; and, in some cases, these
principles have been clothed in precise and mathematical conditions,
and thus made bases of calculation.
These principles, thus possessing a generality of a limited kind,
connecting several observed laws of phenomena, but yet not connecting
all the observed classes of facts which relate to heat, will require
our separate attention. They may be described as the Doctrine of
Conduction, the Doctrine of Radiation, the Doctrine of Specific Heat,
and the Doctrine of Latent Heat; and these, and similar doctrines
respecting heat, make up the science which we may call Thermotics
proper.
But besides these collections of principles which regard heat by
itself, the relations of heat and moisture give rise to another and
important collection of laws and principles, which I shall treat of in
connexion with Thermotics, and shall term Atmology, borrowing
138 the term from
the Greek word (ἄτμος,) which signifies vapor. The
Atmosphere was so named by the Greeks, as being a sphere of
vapor; and, undoubtedly, the most general and important of the
phenomena which take place in the air, by which the earth is
surrounded, are those in which water, of one consistence or
other (ice, water, or steam,) is concerned. The knowledge which
relates to what takes place in the atmosphere has been called
Meteorology, in its collective form: but such knowledge is, in
fact, composed of parts of many different sciences. And it is useful
for our purpose to consider separately those portions of Meteorology
which have reference to the laws of aqueous vapor, and these we may
include under the term Atmology.
The instruments which have been invented for the purpose of
measuring the moisture of the air, that is, the quantity of vapor
which exists in it, have been termed Hygrometers; and the
doctrines on which these instruments depend, and to which they lead,
have been called Hygrometry; but this term has not been used in
quite so extensive a sense as that which we intend to affix to
Atmology.
In treating of Thermotics, we shall first describe the earlier
progress of men’s views concerning Conduction, Radiation, and the
like, and shall then speak of the more recent corrections and
extensions, by which they have been brought nearer to theoretical
generality.


THERMOTICS PROPER.
</div></body></text></TEI>