<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="25">CHAPTER V.
Sequel to the epoch of Kepler. Reception,
Verification, and Extension of the Elliptical Theory.

Sect. 1.—Application of the
Elliptical Theory to the Planets.
THE extension of Kepler’s
discoveries concerning the orbit of Mars to the other planets,
obviously offered itself as a strong probability, and was confirmed by
trial. This was made in the first place upon the orbit of Mercury;
which planet, in consequence of the largeness of its eccentricity,
exhibits more clearly than the others the circumstances of the
elliptical motion. These and various other supplementary portions of
the views to which Kepler’s discoveries had led, appeared in the
latter part of his Epitome Astronomiæ Copernicanæ, published in
1622.
The real verification of the new doctrine concerning the orbits and
motions of the heavenly bodies was, of course, to be found in the
construction of tables of those motions, and in the continued
comparison of such tables with observation. Kepler’s discoveries had
been founded, as we have seen, principally on Tycho’s observations.
Longomontanus (so called as being a native of Langberg in Denmark),
published in 1621, in his Astronomia Danica, tables founded
upon the theories as well as the observations of his countryman.
Kepler44 in 1627 published his tables of the
planets, which he called Rudolphine Tables, the result and
application of his own theory. In 1633, Lansberg, a Belgian, published
also Tabulæ Perpetuæ, a work which was ushered into the world
with considerable pomp and pretension, and in which the author cavils
very keenly at Kepler and Brahe. We may judge of the impression made
upon the astronomical world in general by these rival works, from the
account which our countryman Jeremy Horrox has given of their effect
on him. He had been seduced by the magnificent promises of Lansberg,
and the praises of his admirers, which are prefixed to the work, and
was persuaded that the common opinion which preferred Tycho and Kepler
to him was a prejudice. In 1636, however, he became acquainted with
Crabtree, another young 303 astronomer, who lived in the same part
of Lancashire. By him Horrox was warned that Lansberg was not to be
depended on; that his hypotheses were vicious, and his observations
falsified or forced into agreement with his theories. He then read the
works and adopted the opinions of Kepler; and after some hesitation
which he felt at the thought of attacking the object of his former
idolatry, he wrote a dissertation on the points of difference between
them. It appears that, at one time, he intended to offer himself as
the umpire who was to adjudge the prize of excellence among the three
rival theories of Longomontanus, Kepler, and Lansberg; and, in
allusion to the story of ancient mythology, his work was to have been
called Paris Astronomicus; we easily see that he would have
given the golden apple to the Keplerian goddess. Succeeding
observations confirmed his judgment: and the Rudolphine Tables,
thus published seventy-six years after the Prutenic, which were
founded on the doctrines of Copernicus, were for a long time those
universally used.
44 Rheticus, Narratio, p.
98.
Sect. 2.—Application of the Elliptical Theory to
the Moon.
The reduction of the Moon’s motions to rule
was a harder task than the formation of planetary tables, if accuracy
was required; for the Moon’s motion is affected by an incredible
number of different and complex inequalities, which, till their law is
detected, appear to defy all theory. Still, however, progress was made
in this work. The most important advances were due to Tycho Brahe. In
addition to the first and second inequalities of the moon (the
Equation of the Centre, known very early, and the
Evection, which Ptolemy had discovered), Tycho proved that
there was another inequality, which he termed the Variation,45 which depended on the moon’s position
with respect to the sun, and which at its maximum was forty minutes
and a half, about a quarter of the evection. He also perceived, though
not very distinctly, the necessity of another correction of the moon’s
place depending on the sun’s longitude, which has since been termed
the Annual Equation.
45  We have seen (chap. iii.), that Aboul-Wefa, in the tenth
century, had already noticed this inequality; but his discovery had
been entirely forgotten long before the time of Tycho, and has only
recently been brought again into notice.
These steps concerned the Longitude of the Moon; Tycho also made
important advances in the knowledge of the Latitude. The Inclination
of the Orbit had hitherto been assumed to be the same at all 304 times; and the motion
of the Node had been supposed uniform. He found that the inclination
increased and diminished by twenty minutes, according to the position
of the line of nodes; and that the nodes, though they regress upon the
whole, sometimes go forwards and sometimes go backwards.
Tycho’s discoveries concerning the moon are given in his
Progymnasmata, which was published in 1603, two years after the
author’s death. He represents the Moon’s motion in longitude by means
of certain combinations of epicycles and eccentrics. But after Kepler
had shown that such devices are to be banished from the planetary
system, it was impossible not to think of extending the elliptical
theory to the moon. Horrox succeeded in doing this; and in 1638 sent
this essay to his friend Crabtree. It was published in 1673, with the
numerical elements requisite for its application added by Flamsteed.
Flamsteed had also (in 1671–2) compared this theory with
observation, and found that it agreed far more nearly than the
Philolaic Tables of Bullialdus, or the Carolinian Tables
of Street (Epilogus ad Tabulas). Moreover Horrox, by making the
centre of the ellipse revolve in an epicycle, gave an explanation of
the evection, as well as of the equation of the centre.46
46 Horrox (Horrockes as he
himself spelt his name) gave a first sketch of his theory in letters
to his friend Crabtree in 1638: in which the variation of the
eccentricity is not alluded to. But in Crabtree’s letter to Gascoigne
in 1642, he gives Horrox’s rule concerning it; and Flamsteed in his
Epilogue to the Tables, published by Wallis along with Horrox’s
works in 1673, gave an explanation of the theory which made it amount
very nearly to a revolution of the centre of the ellipse in an
epicycle. Halley afterwards made a slight alteration; but hardly, I
think, enough to justify Newton’s assertion (Princip. Lib. iii.
Prop. 35, Schol.), “Halleius centrum ellipseos in epicyclo locavit.”
See Baily’s Flamsteed, p. 683.
Modern astronomers, by calculating the effects of the perturbing
forces of the solar system, and comparing their calculations with
observation, have added many new corrections or equations to those
known at the time of Horrox; and since the Motions of the heavenly
bodies were even then affected by these variations as yet undetected,
it is clear that the Tables of that time must have shown some errors
when compared with observation. These errors much perplexed
astronomers, and naturally gave rise to the question whether the
motions of the heavenly bodies really were exactly regular, or whether
they were not affected by accidents as little reducible to rule as
wind and weather. Kepler had held the opinion of the casualty
of such errors; but Horrox, far more philosophically, argues against
this opinion, though he 305 allows that he is much embarrassed by
the deviations. His arguments show a singularly clear and strong
apprehension of the features of the case, and their real import. He
says,47 “these errors of the tables are
alternately in excess and defect; how could this constant compensation
happen if they were casual? Moreover, the alternation from excess to
defect is most rapid in the Moon, most slow in Jupiter and Saturn, in
which planets the error continues sometimes for years. If the errors
were casual, why should they not last as long in the Moon as in
Saturn? But if we suppose the tables to be right in the mean motions,
but wrong in the equations, these facts are just what must happen;
since Saturn’s inequalities are of long period, while those of the
Moon are numerous, and rapidly changing.” It would be impossible, at
the present moment, to reason better on this subject; and the
doctrine, that all the apparent irregularities of the celestial
motions are really regular, was one of great consequence to establish
at this period of the science.
47 Astron. Kepler. Proleg. p.
17.
Sect. 3.—Causes of the further Progress of
Astronomy.
We are now arrived at the time when theory
and observation sprang forwards with emulous energy. The physical
theories of Kepler, and the reasonings of other defenders of the
Copernican theory, led inevitably, after some vagueness and
perplexity, to a sound science of Mechanics; and this science in time
gave a new face to Astronomy. But in the mean time, while mechanical
mathematicians were generalizing from the astronomy already
established, astronomers were accumulating new facts, which pointed
the way to new theories and new generalizations. Copernicus, while he
had established the permanent length of the year, had confirmed the
motion of the sun’s apogee, and had shown that the eccentricity of the
earth’s orbit, and the obliquity of the ecliptic, were gradually,
though slowly, diminishing. Tycho had accumulated a store of excellent
observations. These, as well as the laws of the motions of the moon
and planets already explained, were materials on which the Mechanics
of the Universe was afterwards to employ its most matured powers. In
the mean time, the telescope had opened other new subjects of notice
and speculation; not only confirming the Copernican doctrine by the
phases of Venus, and the analogical examples of Jupiter and Saturn,
which with their Satellites 306 appeared like models of the Solar
System; but disclosing unexpected objects, as the Ring of Saturn, and
the Spots of the Sun. The art of observing made rapid advances, both
by the use of the telescope, and by the sounder notions of the
construction of instruments which Tycho introduced. Copernicus had
laughed at Rheticus, when he was disturbed about single minutes; and
declared that if he could be sure to ten minutes of space, he should
be as much delighted as Pythagoras was when he discovered the property
of the right-angled triangle. But Kepler founded the revolution which
he introduced on a quantity less than this. “Since,” he says,48 “the Divine Goodness has given us in
Tycho an observer so exact that this error of eight minutes is
impossible, we must be thankful to God for this, and turn it to
account. And these eight minutes, which we must not neglect, will, of
themselves, enable us to reconstruct the whole of astronomy.” In
addition to other improvements, the art of numerical calculation made
an inestimable advance by means of Napier’s invention of Logarithms;
and the progress of other parts of pure mathematics was proportional
to the calls which astronomy and physics made upon them.
48 De Stellâ Martis, c.
19.
The exactness which observation had attained enabled astronomers
both to verify and improve the existing theories, and to study the yet
unsystematized facts. The science was, therefore, forced along by a
strong impulse on all sides, and its career assumed a new character.
Up to this point, the history of European Astronomy was only the
sequel of the history of Greek Astronomy; for the heliocentric system,
as we have seen, had had a place among the guesses, at least, of the
inventive and acute intellects of the Greek philosophers. But the
discovery of Kepler’s Laws, accompanied, as from the first they were,
with a conviction that the relations thus brought to light were the
effects and exponents of physical causes, led rapidly and irresistibly
to the Mechanical Science of the skies, and collaterally, to the
Mechanical Science of the other parts of Nature: Sound, and Light, and
Heat; and Magnetism, and Electricity, and Chemistry. The history of
these Sciences, thus treated, forms the sequel of the present work,
and will be the subject of the succeeding volumes. And since, as I
have said, our main object in this work is to deduce, from the history
of science, the philosophy of scientific discovery, it may be regarded
as fortunate for our purpose that the history, after this point, so
far changes its aspect as to offer new materials for such
speculations. The details of 307 a history of astronomy, such as the
history of astronomy since Newton has been, though interesting to the
special lovers of that science, would be too technical, and the
features of the narrative too monotonous and unimpressive, to interest
the general reader, or to suggest a comprehensive philosophy of
science. But when we pass from the Ideas of Space and Time to the
Ideas of Force and Matter, of Mediums by which action and sensation
are produced, and of the Intimate Constitution of material bodies, we
have new fields of inquiry opened to us. And when we find that in
these fields, as well as in astronomy, there are large and striking
trains of unquestioned discovery to be narrated, we may gird ourselves
afresh to the task of writing, and I hope, of reading, the remaining
part of the History of the Inductive Sciences, in the trust that it
will in some measure help us to answer the important questions, What
is Truth? and, How is it to be discovered?


BOOK VI.

THE MECHANICAL SCIENCES.

HISTORY OF
MECHANICS,
INCLUDING
FLUID MECHANICS.


ΚΡΑΤΟΣ ΒIΑ ΤΕ, σφῷν μὲν ἐντολὴ Διὸς
Ἔχει Τέλος δὴ, κ’ οὐδὲν ἐμποδῶν ἔτι
Æschylus. Prom.
Vinct. 13.  

You, FORCE and POWER, have done your destined
task:
And naught impedes the work of other hands.

</div></body></text></TEI>