<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Reflections on the Decline of Science in England</title><author>Babbage, Charles (1791-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>B. Fellowes</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="13">
      SECTION 6. OF THE FUNDS OF THE SOCIETY.
    

      Although the Society is not in a state approaching to poverty, it may be
      useful to offer a few remarks respecting the distribution of its money.
    

      EXPENSE OF ENGRAVINGS FOR SIR E. HOME'S PAPERS.—The great expense of
      the engravings which adorn the volumes of the Philosophical Transactions,
      is not sufficiently known. That many of those engravings are quite
      essential for the papers they illustrate, and that those papers are fit
      for the Transactions, I do not doubt; but, some inquiry is necessary, when
      such large sums are expended. I shall endeavour, therefore, to approximate
      to the sum these engravings have cost the Royal Society.
    

      Previous to 1810, there are upwards of seventy plates to papers of Sir E.
      Home's; in many of these, which I have purposely separated, the
      workmanship is not so minute as in the succeeding ones. Since 1810, there
      have occurred 187 plates attached to papers of the same author. Many of
      these have cost from twelve to twenty guineas each plate; but I shall take
      five pounds as the average cost of the first portion, and twelve as that
      of the latter. This would produce,
    

      70 X  5 =  350
     187 X 12 = 2244
     ......    ——-......    L2594


      As this is only proposed as a rough approximation, let us omit the odd
      hundreds, and we have two thousand pounds expended in plates only on ONE
      branch of science, and for one person! Without calling in question the
      importance of the discoveries contained in those papers, it may be
      permitted to doubt whether such a large sum might not have been expended
      in a manner more beneficial to science. Not being myself conversant with
      those subjects, I can only form an opinion of the value from extraneous
      circumstances. Had their importance been at all equal to their number, I
      should have expected to have heard amongst the learned of other countries
      much more frequent mention of them than I have done, and even the Council
      of the Royal Society would scarcely have excluded from their Transactions
      one of those productions which they had paid for as a lecture.
    

      It might also have been more delicate not to have placed on the Council so
      repeatedly a gentleman, for whose engravings they were annually expending,
      during the last twenty years, about an hundred pounds. On the other hand,
      when the Council lent Sir E. Home the whole of those valuable plates to
      take off impressions for his large work on Comparative Anatomy, of which
      they constitute almost the whole, it might have been as well not to have
      obliterated from each plate all indication of the source to which he was
      indebted for them.
    

      THE PRESIDENT'S DISCOURSES.—I shall mention this circumstance,
      because it fell under my own observation.
    

      Observing in the annual accounts a charge of 381L 5s. for the President's
      Speeches, I thought it right to inquire into the nature of this item.
      Happening to be on the Council the next year, I took an opportunity, at an
      early meeting of that Council, to ask publicly for an explanation of the
      following resolution, which stands in the Council-books for Dec. 21, 1828.
    

      "Resolved, That 500 copies of the President's Discourses, about to be
      printed by Mr. Murray, be purchased by the Society, at the usual trade
      price."
    

      The answer given to that question was, "THAT THE COUNCIL HAD AGREED TO
      PURCHASE THESE VOLUMES AT THAT PRICE, IN ORDER TO INDUCE MR. MURRAY TO
      PRINT THE PRESIDENT'S SPEECHES."
    

      I remarked at the time that such an answer was quite unsatisfactory, as
      the following statement will prove.
    

      The volume consists of 160 pages, or twenty sheets, and the following
      prices are very liberal:
    

                                                   L  s. d.
     To composing and printing twenty sheets, at
          3L. per sheet...............             60  0  0
     Twenty reams of paper, at 3L. per ream.....   60  0  0
     Corrections, alterations, &c..........        30  0  0

     Total cost of 500 copies......               150  0  0


      Now upon the subject of the expense of printing, the Council could not
      plead ignorance. The Society are engaged in printing, and in paying
      printers' bills, too frequently to admit of such an excuse; and several of
      the individual members must have known, from their own private experience,
      that the cost of printing such a volume was widely different from that
      they were about to pay, as an inducement to a bookseller to print it on
      his own account. Here, then, was a sum of above two hundred pounds beyond
      what was necessary for the object, taken from the funds of the Royal
      Society; and for what purpose? Did the President and his officers ever
      condescend to explain this transaction to the Council; or were they
      expected, as a matter of course, to sanction any thing proposed to them?
      Could they have been so weak, or so obedient, as to order the payment of
      above three hundred and eighty pounds, to induce a bookseller to do what
      they might have done themselves for less than half the sum? Or did they
      wish to make Mr. Murray a present of two hundred pounds? If so, he must
      have had powerful friends in the Council, and it is fit the Society should
      know who they were; for they were not friends, either to its interests or
      to its honour.
    

      The copies, so purchased, were ordered by the Council to be sold to
      members of the Society at 15s. each: (the trade price is 15s. 3d.) and out
      of the five hundred copies twenty-seven only have been sold: the remainder
      encumber our shelves. Thus, after four years, the Society are still losers
      of three hundred and sixty Pounds on this transaction.
    

      ON THE CONVERSION OF THE GREENWICH OBSERVATIONS INTO PASTEBOARD.—Although
      the printing of these observations is not paid for out of the funds of the
      Royal Society, yet as the Council of that body are the visitors of the
      Royal Observatory, it may not be misplaced to introduce the subject here.
    

      Some years since, a member of the Royal Society accidentally learned, that
      there was, at an old store-shop in Thames Street, a large quantity of the
      volumes of the Greenwich Observations on sale as waste paper. On making
      inquiry, he ascertained that there were two tons and a half to be disposed
      of, and that an equal quantity had already been sold, for the purpose of
      converting it into pasteboard. The vendor said he could get fourpence a
      pound for the whole, and that it made capital Bristol board. The fact was
      mentioned by a member of the Council of the Royal Society, and they
      thought it necessary to inquire into the circumstances.
    

      Now, the Observations made at the Royal Observatory are printed with every
      regard to typographical luxury, with large margins, on thick paper,
      hotpressed, and with no sort of regard to economy. This magnificence is
      advocated by some who maintain, that the volumes ought to be worthy of a
      great nation; whilst others, seeing how little that nation spends on
      science, regret that the sums allotted to it should not be applied with
      the strictest economy. If the Astronomer Royal really has a right to these
      volumes, printed by the government at a large expense, it is, perhaps, the
      most extravagant mode which was ever yet invented of paying a public
      servant. When that right was given to him,—let us suppose somebody
      had suggested the impolicy of it, lest he should sell the costly volumes
      for waste paper,—who would have listened for one moment to such a
      supposition? He would have been told that it was impossible to suppose a
      person in that high and responsible situation, could be so indifferent to
      his own reputation.
    

      A short time since, I applied to the President and Council of the Royal
      Society, for copies of the Greenwich Observations, which were necessary
      for an inquiry on which I was at that time engaged. Being naturally
      anxious to economize the small funds I can devote to science, the request
      appeared to me a reasonable one. It was, however, refused; and I was at
      the same time informed that the Observations could be purchased at the
      bookseller's. [This was a mistake; Mr. Murray has not copies of the
      Greenwich Observations prior to 1823.] When I consider that practical
      astronomy has not occupied a very prominent place in my pursuits, I feel
      disposed, on that ground, to acquiesce in the propriety of the refusal.
      This excuse can, however, be of no avail for similar refusals to other
      gentlemen, who applied nearly at the same time with myself, and whose time
      had been successfully devoted to the cultivation of that science. [M.
      Bessel, at the wish of the Royal Academy of Berlin, projected a plan for
      making a very extensive map of the heavens. Too vast for any individual to
      attempt, it was proposed that a portion should be executed by the
      astronomers of various countries, and invitations to this effect were
      widely circulated. One only of the divisions of this map was applied for
      by any English astronomer; and, after completing the portion of the map
      assigned to him, he undertook another, which had remained unprovided for.
      This gentleman, the Rev. Mr. Hussey, was one of the rejected applicants
      for the Greenwich Observations.]
    

      There was, however, another ground on which I had weakly anticipated a
      different result;—but those who occupy official situations, rendered
      remarkable by the illustrious names of their predecessors, are placed in
      no enviable station; and, if their own acquirements are confessedly
      insufficient to keep up the high authority of their office, they must
      submit to the mortifications of their false position. I am sure,
      therefore, that the President and officers of the Royal Society must have
      sympathized MOST DEEPLY with me, when they felt it their duty to propose
      that the Society over which Newton once presided, should refuse so
      trifling an assistance to the unworthy possessor of the chair he once
      filled.
    

      In reply to my application to the President and Council, to be allowed a
      copy of the Greenwich Observations, I was informed that, "The number of
      copies placed by government at the disposal of the Royal Society, was
      insufficient to supply the demands made on them by various learned bodies
      in Europe; and, consequently, they were unable, however great their
      inclination, to satisfy the wishes of individual applicants." Now I have
      spent some time in searching the numerous proceedings in the council-books
      of the Royal Society, and I believe the following is the real state of the
      case:—
    

      In 1785, Lord Sidney, one of His Majesty's principal Secretaries of State,
      wrote to the Council a letter, dated Whitehall, March 8, 1785, from which
      the following is extracted:—
    

      "The King has been pleased to consent, that any copies of the Astronomical
      Observations, made at the Observatory of Greenwich, (and paid for by the
      Board of Ordnance, pursuant to His Majesty's command, of July 21, 1767,)
      which may at any time remain in the hands of the printer, shall, after you
      have reserved such copies as you may think proper as presents, be given to
      the said Nevil Maskelyne, in consideration of his trouble in the
      superintending the printing thereof. I am to signify His Majesty's
      pleasure, that you do, from time to time, give the necessary orders for
      that purpose, until His Majesty's further commands shall be communicated
      to you.
    

      Soon after this letter, I find on the council-books:—
    

      "Ordered, That sixty copies of the Greenwich Observations, last published,
      be retained as presents, and that the rest be delivered to the Astronomer
      Royal."
    

      It is difficult to be sure of a negative fact, but in searching many
      volumes of the Proceedings of the Council, I have not discovered any
      revocation of this order, and I believe none exists. This is confirmed by
      the circumstance of the Council at the present day receiving precisely the
      same number of copies as their predecessors, and I believe that in fact
      they do not know the authority on which the right to those sixty rests.
    

      Supposing this order unrevoked, it was clearly meant to be left to the
      discretion of the Council, to order such a number to be reserved, "from
      time to time," as the demands of science might require. When, therefore,
      they found that the number of sixty copies was insufficient, they ought to
      have directed the printer to send them a larger number; but when they
      found out the purpose to which the Astronomer Royal applied them, they
      ought immediately to have ordered nearly the whole impression, in order to
      prevent this destruction of public property. If, on the other hand, the
      above order is revoked, and we really have no right to more than sixty
      copies; then, on discovering the Observations in their progress towards
      pasteboard, it was the duty of the Council of the Royal Society, as
      visitors of the Royal Observatory, immediately to have represented to
      Government the evil of the arrangement, and to have suggested, that if the
      Astronomer Royal have the right, it would be expedient to commute it for a
      liberal compensation.
    

      Whichever be the true view of the case, they have taken no steps on the
      subject; and I cannot help expressing my belief, that the President and
      Council were induced to be thus negligent of the interests of science,
      from the fear of interfering with the perquisites of the Astronomer Royal.
    

      It is, however, but justice to observe, that the injury already done to
      science, by the conversion of these Observations into pasteboard, is not
      so great as the public might have feared. Mr. Pond, than whom no one can
      be supposed better acquainted with their value, and whose right to judge
      no man can question, has shown his own opinion to be, that his reputation
      will be best consulted by diminishing the extent of their circulation.
    

      Before I quit the subject of the Royal Observatory, on which much might be
      said, I will just refer to the report by a Committee of the Royal Society
      that was made relative to it, some years since, and which, it is imagined,
      is a subject by no means grateful to the memory of any of the parties
      concerned in it. My object is to ascertain, whether any amendments have
      taken place in consequence. To one fact of considerable importance, I was
      myself a witness, when I was present officially at a visitation. At that
      time, no original observations made at the transit instrument were ever
      preserved. Had I not been an eye witness of the process of an observation,
      I should not have credited the fact.
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>