<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="63">

CHAPTER II.
Successive Biological Hypotheses.


Sect. I.—The Mystical School.
IN order to abbreviate as much as can conveniently
be done the historical view which I have now to
take, I shall altogether pass over the physiological
speculations of the ancients, and begin my survey with
the general revival of science in modern times.
We need not dwell long on the fantastical and unsubstantial doctrines concerning physiology which prevailed in the sixteenth century, and which flowed in a
great measure from the fertile but ill-regulated imaginations of the cultivators of Alchemy and Magic. One
of the prominent doctors of this school is the celebrated
Paracelsus, whose doctrines contained a combination
of biblical interpretations, visionary religious notions,
fanciful analogies, and bold experiments in practical
medicine. The opinion of a close but mystical resemblance of parts between the universe and the human
body,—the Macrocosm and the Microcosm,—as these
two things, thus compared, were termed, had probably
come down from the Neoplatonists; it was adopted by
the Paracelsists1, and connected with various astrological dreams and cabbalistic riddles. A succession
of later Paracelsists2, Rosicrucians, and other fanatics
of the same kind, continued into the seventeenth century. Upon their notions was founded the pretension
of curing wounds by a sympathetic powder, which Sir
Kenelm Digby, among others, asserted; while animal
magnetism, and the transfer of diseases from one person to another3, were maintained by others of this 175 school. They held, too, the doctrines of astral bodies
corresponding to each terrestrial body; and of the signatures of plants, that is, certain features in their external form by which their virtues might be known.
How little advantage or progress real physiology could
derive from speculations of this kind may be seen from
this, that their tendency was to obliterate the distinction between living and lifeless things: according to
Paracelsus, all things are alive, eat, drink, and excrete;
even minerals and fluids4. According to him and his
school, besides material and immaterial beings, there
are elementary Spirits which hold an intermediate place,
Sylvans, Nymphs, Gnomes, Salamanders, &c. by whose
agency various processes of enchantment may be
achieved, and things apparently supernatural explained.
Thus this spiritualist scheme dealt with a world of its
own by means of fanciful inventions and mystical visions, instead of making any step in the study of nature.</div></body></text></TEI>