<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="142">CHAPTER III.
The Relation of Vapour and Air.

Sect. 4.—Force of Steam.
THE experiments on the elastic
force of steam made by the French Academy are fitted in an especial
manner to decide the question between rival formulæ, in consequence of
the great amount of force to which they extend; namely, 60 feet of
mercury, or 24 atmospheres: for formulæ which give results almost
indistinguishable in the lower part of the scale diverge widely at
those elevated points. Mr. Waterston10 has reduced both
these and other experiments to a rule in the following
manner:—He takes the zero of gaseous tension, determined by
other experimenters (Rudberg, Magnus, and Regnault,) to be 461° below
the zero of Fahrenheit, or 274° below the zero of the centigrade
scale: and temperatures reckoned from this zero he calls “G
temperatures.” The square root of the G temperatures is the element to
which the elastic force is referred (for certain theoretical reasons),
and it is found that the density of steam is as the sixth power
of this element. The agreement of this rule with the special results
is strikingly close. A like rule was found by him to apply generally
to many other gases in contact with their liquids.
10 Phil. Trans. 1852.
But M. Regnault has recently investigated the subject in the most
complete and ample manner, and has obtained results somewhat
different.11 He is led to the conclusion that no
formula proceeding by 607 a power of the temperature can represent
the experiments. He also finds that the rule of Dalton (that as the
temperatures increase in arithmetical progression, the elastic force
increases in geometric progression) deviates from the observations,
especially at high temperatures. Dalton’s rule would be expressed by
saying that the variable part of the elastic force is as
at, where t is the temperature. This failing,
M. Regnault makes trial of a formula suggested by M. Biot, consisting
of a sum of two terms, one of which is as at, and
the other is bt: and in this way satisfies the
experiments very closely. But this can only be considered as a formula
of interpolation, and has no theoretical basis. M. Roche had proposed
a formula in which the force is as az, z
depending upon the temperature by an equation12 to which he had
been led by theoretical considerations. This agrees better with
observation than any other formula which includes only the same number
of coefficients.
11 Mém. de l’Institut, vol.
xxi. (1847). M. Regnault’s Memoir occupies 767 pages.
12 The equation z =  t⁄1 +
mt.
Among the experimental thermotical laws referred to by M. Regnault
are, the Law of Watt,13 that “the quantity of heat which is
required to convert a pint of water at a temperature of zero into
steam, is the same whatever be the pressure.” Also, the Law of
Southern, that “the latent heat of vaporization, that is the heat
absorbed in the passage from the liquid to the gaseous consistence, is
constant for all purposes: and that we obtain the total heat in adding
to the constant latent heat the number which represents the latent
heat of steam.” Southern found the latent heat of the steam of water
to be represented by about 950 degrees of Fahrenheit.14
13 See Robison’s Mechanical
Philosophy, vol. ii. p. 8.
14 Ib. p. 160.
Sect. 5.—Temperature of the
Atmosphere.
I may notice, as important
additions to our knowledge on this subject, the results of four
balloon ascents made in 1852,15 by the Committee
of the Meteorological Observatory established at Kew by the British
Association for the Advancement of Science. In these ascents the
observers mounted to more than 13,000, 18,000, and 19,000 feet, and in
the last to 22,370; by which ascent the temperature fell from 49
degrees to nearly 10 degrees below zero; and the dew-point fell from
37° to 12°. Perhaps the most marked result of these observations is
the 608
following:—The temperature of the air decreases uniformly as we
ascend above the earth’s surface; but this decrease does not go on
continuously. At a certain elevation, varying on different days, the
decrease is arrested: and for a depth of two or three thousand feet of
air, the temperature decreases little, or even increases in ascending.
Above this, the diminution again takes place at nearly the same rate
as in the lower regions. This intermediate region of undecreasing
temperature extended in the various ascents, from about altitude 4000
to 6000 feet, 6500 to 10,000, 2000 to 4500, and 4000 to 8000. This
interruption in the decrease of temperature is accompanied by a large
and abrupt fall in the temperature of the dew-point, or by an actual
condensation of vapor. Thus, this region is the region of the
clouds, and the increase of heat appears to arise from the latent
heat liberated when aqueous vapor is formed into clouds.
15 Phil. Trans. 1853.
</div></body></text></TEI>