<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="9">CHAPTER VII.
It was not long before the unhappy partner of my fortunes
was informed of what had passed. The wretches who had
stripped me of my all soon made their appearance to claim
what was no longer mine. What would have been their
reception, if I had sufficiently possessed myself to parley
with them on the subject, I am unable to determine. I
could not have preserved the wreck of my property from
their grasp, but at the expense of an indelible stain upon
my honour; yet my desperation would probably have led[72]
me to a conduct equally extravagant and useless. In the
condition in which I was, the whole direction of the business
devolved upon Marguerite; and never did human
creature demean herself with greater magnanimity and propriety.
She saw at once that she could not resist their
claims but at the expense of my reputation; for herself
she valued not riches, and had no dread of poverty; and,
thus circumstanced, she had the courage herself to bring to
me the papers they offered, the object of which I scarcely
understood, and to cause me to annex that signature which
was to strip her and her children of all earthly fortune.
Her purpose was, as soon as this business was over, to
cause us to quit France, and retire into some scene of virtuous
obscurity. But she would not leave behind her for the
last descendants of the counts de St. Leon any avoidable
disgrace. Her mode of reasoning upon the subject was extremely
simple. Obscurity she regarded as no misfortune;
and eminent situation, where it fairly presented itself, as a
responsibility it would be base to shrink from: ignominy
alone she considered as the proper theme of abhorrence.
For the fickleness and inconstancy of fortune it is impossible
to answer; by one of those reverses in which she
appears to delight, she might yet restore us to the lustre of
our former condition; but, if the name of St. Leon was
henceforth to disappear from the annals of France, she was
desirous at least, as far as depended on her, that it should
expire, like the far famed bird of Arabia, in the midst of
perfumes.
When the whole situation of Marguerite is taken into
consideration, the reader, like myself, will stand astonished
at the fortitude of her conduct. She had come to Paris,
unable any longer to tranquillise the agitation of her mind,
and exhausted with fears, suspicions, and alarms. When
she arrived, she experienced indeed one delusive moment
of transport and joy. But that was soon over. It was
succeeded by reflections and conjectures respecting the
mysteriousness of my behaviour; it was succeeded by my
unexpected departure, and the hourly expectation of my
return. After the lapse of a night and a day, I returned
indeed, but in what a condition! Drenched with rain,[73]
trembling with inanition, speechless and alone. Scarcely
had she received notice of my arrival, and come forward to
meet me, than she saw me fall, motionless and insensible,
at her feet. She watched my recovery, and hung with indescribable
expectation over my couch. She was only
called away by the wretches, who came to advance their
accursed claims, and to visit her with the intelligence of
our ruin, as with a thunderbolt. Already enfeebled and
alarmed by all the preceding circumstances, they spoke
with no consideration to her weakness, they stooped to no
qualifications and palliatives, but disclosed the whole in the
most abrupt and shocking manner. Any other woman
would have sunk under this accumulation of ill. Marguerite
only borrowed vigour from her situation, and rose in proportion
to the pressure of the calamity. She took her resolution
at once, and answered them in the most firm and
decisive language.
The period of inactivity and stupor that at first seized
me was succeeded by a period of frenzy. It was in this
condition that Marguerite conducted me and my children to
an obscure retreat in the canton of Soleure, in the republic
of Switzerland. Cheapness was the first object; for the
most miserable pittance was all she had saved from the
wreck of our fortune. She had not chosen for beauty of
situation, or magnificence of prospects. The shock her
mind had sustained was not so great as to destroy her activity
and fortitude, but it left her little leisure for the wantonness
of studied indulgence. The scene was remote and
somewhat sterile. She conceived that, when I recovered
my senses, an event which she did not cease to promise
herself, solitude would be most grateful, at least to the first
stage of my returning reason.
Hither then it was that she led me, our son, and three
daughters. Immediately upon our arrival she purchased
a small and obscure, but neat, cottage, and attired herself
and her children in habits similar to those of the
neighbouring peasants. My paternal estates, as well as
those which had fallen to me by marriage, had all been
swallowed up in the gulf, which my accursed conduct had
prepared. Marguerite made a general sale of our moveables,[74]
our ornaments, and even our clothes. A few books, guided
by the attachment to literature which had always attended
me, were all that she saved from the wreck. A considerable
part of the sum thus produced was appropriated by my
creditors. Marguerite had the prudence and skill to satisfy
them all, and was contented to retain that only which remained
when their demands were discharged. This was
the last dictate of her pride and the high-born integrity of
her nature, at the time that she thus departed a voluntary
exile from her native country. Two servants accompanied
us in our flight, whose attachment was so great, that even
if their attendance had not been necessary, it would have
been found somewhat difficult to shake them off. Marguerite,
however, was governed by the strictest principles of
economy; and, whatever the struggle might have been with
the importunity of humble affection in dismissing these last
remains of our profuse and luxurious household, she would
have thought herself obliged to proceed even to this extreme,
if judicious parsimony had demanded it from her. But it
did not. Our youngest daughter was at this time only
twelve months old, and it would have been scarcely possible
for the mother, however resolute in her exertions, to have
discharged the cares due to such a family, at a time when
the father of it was suffering under so heavy an affliction.
One female servant she retained to assist her in these offices.
She could not dispense herself from a very assiduous attention
to me. She could never otherwise have been satisfied,
that every thing was done that ought to be done, that every
tenderness was exercised that might be demanded by my
humiliating situation, or that sufficient sagacity and skill were
employed in watching and encouraging the gleams of returning
reason. The violence of my paroxysms, however,
was frequently such as to render a manual force greater than
hers necessary to prevent me from effecting some desperate
mischief. Bernardin, a trusty servant, nearly of my own
age, and who had attended upon my person almost from
infancy, was retained by Marguerite for this purpose. I
was greatly indebted for the recovery which speedily followed
to the affectionate anxiety and enlightened care of
this incomparable woman. It is inconceivable to those[75]
who have never been led to a practical examination of the
subject, how much may be effected in this respect by an
attachment ever on the watch, and an understanding judicious
to combine, where hired attendance would sleep, and
the coarseness of a blunt insensibility would irritate, nay,
perhaps, mortally injure.
It is scarcely possible to imagine a wife more interesting
and admirable than Marguerite appeared upon the present
occasion. Fallen from the highest rank to the lowest
poverty, she did not allow herself a mean and pitiful regret.
No reverse could be more complete and abrupt, but she did
not sink under it. She proved, in the most convincing
manner, that her elevation was not the offspring of wealth
or rank, but was properly her own. She gave a grace, even
a lustre, to poverty, which it can only receive from the
emanations of a cultivated mind. Her children were reconciled
and encouraged by her example, and soon forgot those
indulgences which had not yet had time to emasculate their
spirits. The deplorable situation to which the father of
the family was reduced was far from inducing her to cease
from her efforts in the bitterness of despair. She determined
for the present to be both a father and a mother to her
children. She looked forward with confidence to my speedy
recovery. Though I was the author of her calamities, she
did not permit this consideration to subtract from the purity
of her affection, or the tenderness of her anxiety. She resolved
that no word or look of hers should ever reproach
me with my misconduct. She had been accustomed to desire
rank, and affluence, and indulgence for her children;
that her son might run the career of glory which his forefathers
ran, and that her daughters might unite their fates
with what was most illustrious and honourable in their
native country. But, if she were disappointed in this, she
determined, as far as it should be in her power, to give
them virtue and cheerfulness and content, a mind that should
find resources within itself, and call forth regard and esteem
from the rest of mankind.
My recovery was fitful and precarious, sometimes appearing
to be rapidly on the advance, and at others to threaten
a total relapse. Among the expedients that Marguerite[76]
employed to re-excite the slumbering spark of reason was
that of paternal affection. Ever on the watch for a favourable
opportunity, she sometimes brought to me her own
little namesake, who, though only twelve months old, did
not fail to discover unequivocal marks of that playfulness
and gaiety which made so considerable a part of her constitutional
character. Her innocent smiles, her frolic and
careless laughter, produced a responsive vibration that
reached to my inmost heart. They were, not unfrequently,
powerful enough to check the career of my fury, or to raise
me from the lowest pitch of despondence. Julia wept for
me, and Louisa endeavoured to copy the offices of kindness
she was accustomed to see her mother perform: Charles,
who conceived more fully than the rest the nature of my
indisposition, was upon all occasions solicitous to be admitted
into my presence, and attended me for the most part
with speechless anxiety, while his watchful, glistening eye
uttered volumes, without the assistance of words. His
mother at length yielded to his importunity, and he became
established the regular assistant of Bernardin in the care of
my person. The restlessness and impetuosity he had hitherto
manifested seemed upon this occasion entirely to subside:
hour after hour he willingly continued shut up in my chamber,
eager for every opportunity of usefulness, and gratified
with that complaisance with which the human mind never
fails to be impressed, when it regards its actions as beneficent,
or approves its temper as compassionate.
The restoration of my health was greatly retarded by
the melancholy impressions which necessarily offered themselves
to my mind when recollection resumed her seat.
It was fortunate for me that this sort of retrospection appears
not to be the first thing that occurs after a paroxysm
of insanity. When the tide of incoherent ideas subsides,
the soul is left in a state of exhaustion; and seems, by a
sort of instinct, to shun the influx of tumultuous emotions,
and to dwell upon such feelings as are mild, tranquil, and
restorative. Once, however, when I was nearly recovered,
the thought of what I had been, and the recollection of what
I was, violently suggesting themselves to my mind, brought
on a relapse, attended with more alarming and discouraging[77]
symptoms than my original alienation. At that moment
Marguerite was, for the first time, irresistibly struck
with the conception that mine was an incurable lunacy;
and, as she afterwards assured me, at no period down to
that instant had she felt herself so truly inconsolable. But
even a sentiment of the last despair was incapable of superseding
the active beneficence of Marguerite. Her assiduities,
so far as related to this fatal calamity, were at
length crowned with success. Her gloomy prognostics
were not realised, and the distemper of my understanding
quitted me for ever.
Wretched, however, as I have already remarked, beyond
all common notions of wretchedness, were my thoughts,
when my soul returned to its proper bias, and I fully surveyed
the nature of my present situation. Marguerite,
who, by her sagacity and patience, had recovered me from
a state of the most dreadful disease, now exerted herself to
effect the more arduous task of reconciling me to myself.
She assured me that she forgave me from her inmost heart;
nay, that she was thankful to Providence, which, in the
midst of what the world calls great calamities, had preserved
to her what she most valued, my affection, entire.
She contrasted what had been the subject of her apprehensions
before she came to Paris, with what had proved
to be the state of the case afterwards. She averred, that
the worst that had happened was trivial and tolerable,
compared with the image that her fears had delineated.
She had feared to find my heart alienated from her, and
herself a widowed mother to orphan children. She dreaded
lest I should have proved myself worthless in her eyes, lest
I should have been found to have committed to oblivion
the most sacred of all duties; and, for the gratification of
a low and contemptible caprice, to have sacrificed all pretensions
to honour and character. For that, indeed, her
heart would have bled; against that, all the pride she derived
from her ancestry and my own would have revolted;
that would have produced a revulsion of her frame, snapping
the chain of all her habits, and putting a violent close
upon all the sentiments she had most fondly nourished.
She dreaded, indeed, that she should not have survived it.[78]
But the mistake I had committed was of a very different
nature. I had neither forgotten that I was a husband nor
a father; I had only made an injudicious and unfortunate
choice of the way of discharging what was due to these
characters. What had passed was incapable of impeaching
either the constancy of my affections or the integrity of
my principles. She forgave me, and it was incumbent
upon me to forgive myself.
She assured me that poverty, in her apprehension, was
a very slight evil; and she appealed to my own understanding
for the soundness of her judgment. She bid me
look round upon the peasantry of the neighbourhood, upon
a footing with whom we were now placed, and ask my
own heart whether they were not happy. One disadvantage,
indeed, they were subjected to,—the absence of cultivation
and learning. She could never bring herself to
believe that ignorance was a benefit; she saw the contrary
of this practically illustrated in her own case, in mine, and
in that of all the persons to whom, through life, she had
been most ardently attached. She wished her children to
attain intellectual refinement, possess fully the attributes of
a rational nature, and to be as far removed as possible from
the condition of stocks and stones, by accumulating a magazine
of thoughts, and by a rich and cultivated sensibility.
But the want of fortune did not in our case, as in the case
of so many others, shut them out from this advantage: it
was in our own power to bestow it upon them.
It was the part of a reasonable man, she told me, not to
waste his strength in useless regrets for what was past, and
had already eluded his grasp; but to advert to the blessings
he had still in possession. If we did this in our present
situation, we should find every reason for contentment and
joy. Our pleasure in each other, and the constancy of our
attachment, was unassailed and unimpaired. Where were
there two married persons, she would venture to ask, who
had more reason to applaud their connection, or to whom
their connection was pregnant with so various gratifications?
From ourselves we had only to turn our thoughts to our
children; and we were surely as singularly fortunate in
this respect as in each other. Charles, who had always[79]
been the subject of our pride, had lately exhibited such an
example of patient sympathy and filial affection, as perhaps
had never been equalled in a child so young. The sensibility
of Julia, the understanding of Louisa, and the vivacity
of Marguerite, were all of them so many growing
sources of inexhaustible delight. Our children were intelligent,
affectionate, and virtuous. Thus circumstanced,
she entreated me not to indulge that jaundice of the imagination,
which should create to itself a sentiment of melancholy
and discontent in the midst of this terrestrial
paradise.
Most virtuous of women, now perhaps the purest and
the brightest among the saints in heaven! why was I deaf
to the soundness of your exhortations, and the generosity
of your sentiments? Deaf, indeed, I was! A prey to the
deepest dejection, they appeared to me the offspring of
misapprehension and paradox! Supposing, in the mean
time, that they were reasonable and just in the mouth of
her who uttered them, I felt them as totally foreign to my
own situation. The language, as they were, of innocence;
it was not wonderful that to an innocent heart they spoke
tranquillity and peace. Marguerite looked round upon the
present rusticity and plainness of our condition, and every
thing that she saw talked to her of her merit and her worth.
If we were reduced, she was in no way accountable for
that reduction; it had been the test of her magnanimity,
her patience, and the immutableness of her virtue. She
smiled at the assaults of adversity, and felt a merit in
her smiles. How different was my situation! Every
thing that I saw reminded me of my guilt, and upbraided
me with crimes that it was hell to recollect. My own
garb, and that of my wife and children, the desertion in
which we lived, the simple benches, the unhewn rafters, the
naked walls, all told me what it was I had done, and were
so many echoes to my conscience, repeating, without intermission
and without end, its heart-breaking reproaches.
Sleep was almost a stranger to me; these incessant monitors
confounded my senses in a degree scarcely short of madness
itself. It is the property of vice to convert every thing
that should be consolation into an additional source of anguish.[80]
The beauty, the capacity, and the virtue of my
children, the affection with which they regarded me, the
patience and attentiveness and forbearance of their excellent
mother, were all so many aggravations of the mischief I had
perpetrated. I could almost have wished to have been the
object of their taunts and execration. I could have wished
to have been disengaged from the dearest charities of our
nature, and to have borne the weight of my crimes alone.
It would have been a relief to me if my children had been
covered with the most loathsome diseases, deformed and
monstrous. It would have been a relief to me, if they had
been abortive in understanding, and odious in propensities,
if their hearts had teemed with every vice, and every day
had marked them the predestined victims of infamy. The
guilt of having stripped them of every external advantage
would then have sat light upon me. But thus to have
ruined the most lovely family perhaps that existed on the
face of the earth, the most exemplary of women, and
children in whom I distinctly marked the bud of every excellence
and every virtue, was a conduct that I could never
forgive even to myself. Oh, Damville, Damville! best of
men! truest of friends! why didst thou put thy trust in
such a wretch as I am! Hadst thou no presentiment of the
fatal consequences? Wert thou empowered to commit
thy only child and all her possible offspring to so dreadful
a risk? Indeed, it was not well done! It was meant in
kindness; but it was the cruellest mischief that could have
been inflicted on me. I was not a creature qualified for
such dear and tender connections. I was destined by
nature to wander a solitary outcast on the face of the earth.
For that only, that fearful misery, was I fitted. Why,
misguided, misjudging man! didst thou not leave me to
my fate? Even that would have been less dreadful than
what I have experienced!—Wretch that I am! Why
do I reproach my best benefactor? No, let me turn the
whole current of my invective upon myself! Damville was
actuated by the noblest and most generous sentiment that
ever entered the human mind. What a return then have
I made, and to what a benefit!
All the previous habits of my mind had taught me to[81]
feel my present circumstances with the utmost acuteness.
Marguerite, the generous Marguerite, stood, with a soul
almost indifferent, between the opposite ideas of riches and
poverty. Not so her husband. I had been formed, by
every accident of my life, to the love of splendour. High
heroic feats, and not the tranquillity of rural retirement, or
the pursuits of a character professedly literary, had been the
food of my imagination, ever since the faculty of imagination
was unfolded in my mind. The field of the cloth of
gold, the siege and the battle of Pavia, were for ever present
to my recollection. Francis the First, Bayard, and Bourbon,
eternally formed the subject of my visions and reveries.
These propensities had indeed degenerated into an infantine
taste for magnificence and expense; but the roots did not
embrace their soil the less forcibly, because the branches
were pressed down and diverted from their genuine perpendicular.
That from a lord, descended from some of the
most illustrious houses in France, and myself amply imbued
with the high and disdainful spirit incident to my
rank, I should become a peasant, was itself a sufficient degradation.
But I call the heavens to witness that I could
have endured this with patience, if I had endured it alone.
I should have regarded it as the just retribution of my
follies, and submitted with the most exemplary resignation.
But I could not, with an equal mind, behold my wife and
children involved in my punishment. I turned my eyes upon
the partner of my life, and recalled with genuine anguish
the magnificence to which she was accustomed, and the
hopes to which she was born. I looked upon my children,
the fruit of my loins, and once the pride of my heart, and
recollected that they were paupers, rustics, exiles. I could
foresee no return to rank, but for them and their posterity
an interminable succession of obscurity and meanness. A
real parent can support the calamity of personal degradation,
but he cannot bear to witness and anticipate this corruption
of his blood. At some times I honoured Marguerite for
her equanimity. At others I almost despised her for this
integrity of her virtues. I accused her in my heart of being
destitute of the spark of true nobility. Her patience I considered
as little less than meanness and vulgarity of spirit.[82]
It would have become her better, I thought, like me, to
have cursed her fate, and the author of that fate; like me,
to have spurned indignant at the slavery to which we were
condemned; to have refused to be pacified; and to have
wasted the last dregs of existence in impatience and regret.
I could act that which had involved us in this dire reverse;
but I could not encounter the consequences of my act.
The state of my mind was in the utmost degree dejected
and forlorn. I carried an arrow in my heart, which the
kindness of my wife and children proved inadequate to extract,
and the ranklings of which time itself had not the
power to assuage. The wound was not mortal; but, like the
wound of Philoctetes, poisoned with the blood of the Lernean
hydra, I dragged it about with me from year to year, and
it rendered my existence a galling burden hardly to be
supported. A great portion of my time was passed in a
deep and mournful silence, which all the soothings that
were addressed to me could not prevail on me to break.
Not that in this silence there was the least particle of ill
humour or sullenness. It was a mild and passive situation
of the mind; affectionate, as far as it was any thing,
to the persons around me; but it was a species of disability;
my soul had not force enough to give motion to the
organs of speech, or scarcely to raise a finger. My eye
only, and that only for a moment at a time, pleaded for forbearance
and pardon. I seemed like a man in that species
of distemper, in which the patient suffers a wasting of the
bones, and at length presents to us the shadow, without the
powers, of a human body.
This was at some times my condition. But my stupor
would at others suddenly subside. Mechanically, and in a
moment, as it were, I shook off my supineness, and sought
the mountains. The wildness of an untamed and savage
scene best accorded with the temper of my mind. I sprung
from cliff to cliff among the points of the rock. I rushed
down precipices that to my sobered sense appeared in a
manner perpendicular, and only preserved my life, with a
sort of inborn and unelective care, by catching at the roots
and shrubs which occasionally broke the steepness of the
descent. I hung over the tops of rocks still more fearful[83]
in their declivities, and courted the giddiness and whirl of
spirit which such spectacles are accustomed to produce. I
could not resolve to die: death had too many charms to suit
the self-condemnation that pursued me. I found a horrible
satisfaction in determining to live, and to avenge upon
myself the guilt I had incurred. I was far from imagining
that the evils I had yet suffered were a mere sport and
ostentation of misery, compared with those that were in reserve
for me.
The state of mind I am here describing was not madness,
nor such as could be mistaken for madness. I never
forgot myself, and what I was. I was never in that delirium
of thought, in which the patient is restless and active
without knowing what it is that he does, and from which,
when roused, he suddenly starts, shakes off the dream that
engaged him, and stands astonished at himself. Mine was
a rage, guided and methodised by the discipline of despair.
I burst into no fits of raving; I attempted no injury to any
one. Marguerite therefore could not reconcile herself to
the placing me under any restraint. I frequently returned
home, with my clothes smeared with the soil, and torn by
the briars. But my family soon became accustomed to my
returning in personal safety; and therefore, whatever was
the uneasiness my wife felt from my excursions, she preferred
the enduring it, to the idea of imposing on me any
species of violence.
The state of my family presented a singular contrast
with that of its head. Marguerite was certainly not insensible
to the opposition between her former and her present
mode of life; but she submitted to the change with such an
unaffected cheerfulness and composure, as might have extorted
admiration from malignity itself. She would perhaps
have dismissed from her thoughts all retrospect to our former
grandeur, had not the dejection and despair that
seemed to have taken possession of my mind forcibly and
continually recalled it to her memory. For my sufferings
I am well assured she felt the truest sympathy; but there
was one consideration attending them that imperiously compelled
her to task her fortitude. They deprived me of the[84]
ability of in any degree providing for and superintending
my family; it became therefore incumbent upon her to
exert herself for the welfare of all. Had we never fallen
under this astonishing reverse, I might have spent my whole
life in daily intercourse with this admirable woman, without
becoming acquainted with half the treasures of her
mind. She was my steward; and from the result of her
own reflections made the most judicious disposition of my
property. She was my physician; not by administering
medicines to my body, but by carefully studying and exerting
herself to remove the distemper of mind. Unfortunately
no distempers are so obstinate as mental ones; yet,
had my distemper had any lighter source than an upbraiding
conscience, I am persuaded the wisdom of Marguerite
would have banished it. She was the instructor of my
children; her daughters felt no want of a governess; and
I am even ready to doubt whether the lessons of his mother
did not amply supply to Charles his loss of an education in
the university of Paris. The love of order, the activity,
the industry, the cheerfulness of, let me say, this illustrious
matron, became contagious to all the inhabitants of my
roof. Once and again have I stolen a glance at them, or
viewed them from a distance busied, sometimes gravely,
sometimes gaily, in the plain, and have whispered to my
bursting heart, “How miserable am I! how happy they!
So insurmountable is the barrier that divides innocence
from guilt. They may breathe the same air; they may
dwell under the same roof; they may be of one family and
one blood; they may associate with each other every day
and every hour; but they can never assimilate, never have
any genuine contact. Is there a happier family than mine
in all the valley of this far-famed republic? Is there a
family more virtuous, or more cultivated with all the refinements
that conduce to the true dignity of man? I, I
only am its burden and its stain! The pleasure with
which I am surrounded on every side finds a repellent
quality in my heart that will not suffer its approach. To
whatever is connected with me I communicate misfortune.
Whenever I make my appearance, those countenances that
at all other times spoke contentment and hilarity fall into[85]
sadness. Like a pestilential wind, I appear to breathe
blast to the fruits of nature, and sickliness to its aspect.”
Marguerite expostulated with me in the most soothing
manner upon the obstinacy of my malady. “My Reginald!
my love!” said she, “cease to be unhappy, or to
reproach yourself! You were rash in the experiment you
made upon the resources of your family. But have you
done us mischief, or have you conferred a benefit? I more
than half incline to the latter opinion. Let us at length
dismiss artificial tastes, and idle and visionary pursuits,
that do not flow in a direct line from any of the genuine
principles of our nature! Here we are surrounded with
sources of happiness. Here we may live in true patriarchal
simplicity. What is chivalry, what are military prowess and
glory? Believe me, they are the passions of a mind depraved,
that with ambitious refinement seeks to be wise beyond
the dictates of sentiment or reason! There is no happiness
so solid, or so perfect, as that which disdains these
refinements. You, like me, are fond of the luxuriant and
romantic scenes of nature. Here we are placed in the midst
of them. How idle it would be, to wish to change our
arbours, our verdant lanes and thickets, for vaulted roofs,
and gloomy halls, and massy plate! Alas, Reginald! it is,
I fear, too true, that the splendour in which we lately lived
has its basis in oppression; and that the superfluities of
the rich are a boon extorted from the hunger and misery
of the poor! Here we see a peasantry more peaceful and
less oppressed than perhaps any other tract of the earth
can exhibit. They are erect and independent, at once
friendly and fearless. Is not this a refreshing spectacle?
I now begin practically to perceive that the cultivators of
the fields and the vineyards are my brethren and my
sisters; and my heart bounds with joy, as I feel my relations
to society multiply. How cumbrous is magnificence!
The moderate man is the only free. He who reduces all
beneath him to a state of servitude becomes himself the
slave of his establishment, and of all his domestics. To
diminish the cases in which the assistance of others is felt
absolutely necessary is the only genuine road to independence.
We can now move wherever we please without[86]
waiting the leisure of others. Our simple repasts require
no tedious preparation, and do not imprison us in saloons
and eating rooms. Yet we partake of them with a more
genuine appetite, and rise from them more truly refreshed,
than from the most sumptuous feast. I prepare for my
meal by industry and exercise; and when it is over, amuse
myself with my children in the fields and the shade.—Though
I love the sight of the peasants, I would not be a
peasant. I would have a larger stock of ideas, and a
wider field of activity. I love the sight of peasants only
for their accessories, or by comparison. They are comparatively
more secure than any other large masses of men,
and the scenes in the midst of which they are placed are
delightful to sense. But I would not sacrifice in prone
oblivion the best characteristics of my nature. I put in my
claim for refinements and luxuries; but they are the refinements
and purifying of intellect, and the luxuries of
uncostly, simple taste. I would incite the whole world, if
I knew how to do it, to put in a similar claim. I would
improve my mind; I would enlarge my understanding; I
would contribute to the instruction of all connected with
me, and to the mass of human knowledge. The pleasures
I would pursue and disseminate, though not dependent on
a large property, are such as could not be understood by
the rustic and the savage.—Our son, bred in these fields,
indeed, will probably never become a preux chevalier, or
figure in the roll of military heroes; but he may become
something happier and better. He may improve his mind,
and cultivate his taste. He may be the counsellor and protector
of his sisters. He may be the ornament of the district
in which he resides. He may institute in his adoptive
country new defences for liberty, new systems of public
benefit, and new improvements of life. There is no character
more admirable than the patriot-yeoman, who unites
with the utmost simplicity of garb and manners an understanding
fraught with information and sentiment and a
heart burning with the love of mankind. Such were Fabricius
and Regulus among the ancients, and such was
Tell, the founder of the Helvetic liberty. For my part,
I am inclined to be thankful, that this unexpected reverse[87]
in our circumstances has made me acquainted with new
pleasures, and opened to my mind an invaluable lesson.
If you could but be prevailed on to enter into our pleasures,
to dismiss idle reproaches and pernicious propensities, our
happiness would then be complete.”
The expostulations of Marguerite often excited my attention,
often my respect, and sometimes produced a sort
of imperfect conviction. But the conviction was transient,
and the feelings I have already described as properly my
own returned, when the fresh and vivid impression of what
I had heard was gone. It was in vain that I heard the
praises of simplicity and innocence. I was well pleased to
see those who were nearest to me not affecting contentment,
but really contented with these things. But I could
not be contented for them. The lessons of my education
had left too deep an impression. I could myself have surrendered
my claim to admiration and homage, as a penance
for my misdeeds; but I could not figure to myself a genuine
satisfaction unaccompanied by these accessories:
and this satisfaction I obstinately and impatiently coveted
for those I loved.
</div></body></text></TEI>