<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 165, folios 74-75</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 165, folios 74-75.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1837">12 September [1837]</date>
          <note type="place">[no place]</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 165, folios 74-75</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_165_folios_74-75.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Tuesday. 12th Sepr 1/2 pst 11 o'clock.</p>
      <p>Dearest Mate. How very mischievous of you to begin your letter by telling the poor Avis that the nasty chesnut mare jumped about.-- I hope I shall behave better than Lady Fletcher, &amp; wait dutifully for your return. A very kind letter from Dr Locock, which I enclose, has set the whole matter of doctors at rest in the most satisfactory manner. By his advice, I shall of course</p>
      <p>abide precisely, &amp; I have his enclosure for Dr Ferguson in safe keeping.-- I do not think myself at all likely to be taken ill before you return.--</p>
      <p>I am much pleased with Green &amp; the arrangements she is making, which promise greatly for my comfort.--</p>
      <p>Today Mr Wharton is to come at 1/2 pst 2 o'clock with the master-in-chancery. As I find that my part of the business must be conducted without the husband's presence, I think it is just as well this opportunity is taken.--</p>
      <p>Yesterday I went to the Hen's between</p>
      <p>1 &amp; 2, &amp; was agreeably surprised to find there Mrs Dahoury, whom I brought back here with me for an hour, &amp; have engaged to dine with us tomorrow. She was delighted with Byron, who behaved himself very well--</p>
      <p>By the bye he is greatly charmed with his cart, especially the horse, so I think you were certainly wrong in thinking the latter should have been omitted.</p>
      <p>I was rather sorry this morning to see a voluminous letter arrive for Hester from Charlotte, very little of which was imparted to me.-- They are certainly the Inseparables.--</p>
      <p>Mrs. L. K continues very prosperous.</p>
      <p>I take great care of the horses, &amp; am in every respect a very nice Avis or Bird.--</p>
      <p>Mr Lauzelle is going on, slowly with my teeth, &amp; I think he will stop all further annoyance.</p>
      <p>This is another reason I have for wishing to defer any accouchement.--</p>
      <p>Yesterday evening it rained torrents, &amp; I believe in the night also, but you have nice weather on the whole.--</p>
      <p>Most affecly The Little Bird Ada</p>
      <p>Return Me Dr Locock's letter.--</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
