<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 165, folios 105-108</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 165, folios 105-108.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1838">11 March [1838]</date>
          <note type="place">[no place]</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 165, folios 105-108</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_165_folios_105-108.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Sunday 1/2 pst 6 o'clock 11th March</p>
      <p>Dearest Mate. I was so pleased with ou sweet letter this morning, having expected none from .-- I shall be anxious to hear the results of Mr Dymond's survey. If you resided there, you might no doubt make a fine thing of it.-- Last night I saw Kayes, who I believe means to write to you himself on Wednesday.-- I made particular enquiries about the irrigation. Until Friday morning it went on , but</p>
      <p>the sharp frost then lessened the quantity of water very much, as also yesterday morning. However it did go on a little, &amp; this morning I do not think there has been any frost. It has been a most delicious day,-- a fine breeze, &amp; sparkling sunshine, infusing life &amp; brightness into everything.</p>
      <p>I spoke to Kayes about the colt, which you were mistaken in supposing had been brought here handled. It is at Blackmore Heath, &amp; nothing whatever has been yet done with it.-- It is 3 years old, &amp; the coachman tells me no time must be lost, or it will be too old to break</p>
      <p>properly, &amp; the more as it is supposed to be promising for a lady, &amp; likely to suit Annabella, or perhaps myself if it is tall enough to please me.-- Both Kayes &amp; coachman agree in saying that a professional breaker must be employed. It is a very dark brown, &amp; they say a most beautiful animal, with a head &amp; neck that are lovely.--</p>
      <p>I also consulted Kayes about a plan of mine for having one of our cows up when we go to Town to remain. He highly opposes it, &amp; says she would do very well in the stables. We should have to engage, some one to come daily for an hour</p>
      <p>or two morning &amp; evening to see after her &amp; the milk &amp; cream, since I &amp; Hester have fully considered that none of our servants could be spared.-- But this could be easily arranged.--</p>
      <p>I have been writing today about the leather sofa cover, though not positively ordering it till I get Minter's answer; It will be very expensive, but Hester says the wear is eternal, if we have morocco, &amp; certainly her suggestion that the canvas would be shockingly incongruous amidst all the silks &amp; gilding &amp; rose-wood, is very true.</p>
      <p>She tells me that two arm-chairs which have been in constant use in Dover St for 17 years, are still quite good, being covered with red moroccco.--</p>
      <p>Another thing I have been writing about, to Miles &amp; , is a border to the Alhambra carpet. I find you have ordered it not to go close round the walls, but if that is the case it must have a border, for they look very bad indeed without &amp; quite shabby as if one had not had stuff enough.-- And have you</p>
      <p>yet given any order about the floors being polished &amp; painted in my rooms, with a view to the empty space to be left round the carpet?-- If not, it should be done immediately, for they cannot put down the carpet till it is.--</p>
      <p>I must ask you to re=consider about the hot closets in the laundry, which I find you desired not to be put. I assure you it is quite necessary, &amp; that without it one cannot have our clothes dried, since they must not be hung out of doors in</p>
      <p>London.-- So long ago as when they were building the house, you may remember my mentioning this as a sine qua [diacritical mark above the a] non.</p>
      <p>I looked at many colours &amp; stuffs for the curtains of my rooms, &amp; have nearly decided on a bright light green, &amp; the silky stuff they call .-- There was a most beautiful satin with embroidered coloured roses &amp; flowers all over, on which I cast my eyes thinking it very suitable to the room.-- But it was unluckily 2..0..0 a yard!-- I have made</p>
      <p>several small arrangements about rugs for the doors, &amp; various little things, of which I am sure you will highly approve when you see them, &amp; I assure you that I have taken durability as well as elegance into account in all my decisions. My zebra wood very much diminished on seeing more of it, &amp; enquiring more.--</p>
      <p>I do not send you the Sunday papers, for fear of your losing them, as I now put them by. Hester sent some letters &amp; papers to Ashley, before I came down, by mistake.</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
