<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="49">CHAPTER III.
Principles and Problems.

Significance of Analytical Mechanics.
IN the text, page 372, I have stated that Lagrange, near the
end of his life, expressed his sorrow that the methods of
approximation employed in Physical Astronomy rested on arbitrary
processes, and not on any insight into the results of mechanical
action. From the recent biography of Gauss, the greatest physical
mathematician of modern times, we learn that he congratulated himself
on having escaped this error. He remarked35 that many of the
most celebrated mathematicians, Euler very often, Lagrange sometimes,
had trusted too much to the symbolical calculation of their problems,
and would not have been able to give an account of the meaning of each
successive step of their investigation. He said that he himself, on
the other hand, could assert that at every step which he took, he
always had the aim and purpose of his operations before his eyes
without ever turning aside from the way. The same, he remarked, might
be said of Newton.
35 Gauss, Zum Gedächtniss, von W.
Sartorius v. Waltershausen, p. 80.
Engineering Mechanics.
The principles of the science of Mechanics were discovered by
observations made upon bodies within the reach of men; as we have seen
in speaking of the discoveries of Stevinus, Galileo, and others, up to
the time of Newton. And when there arose the controversy about vis
viva (Chap. v. Sect. 2 of this
Book);—namely, whether the “living force” of a body is measured
by the product of the weight into the 537 velocity, or of the weight into the
square of the velocity;—still the examples taken were cases of
action in machines and the like terrestrial objects. But Newton’s
discoveries identified celestial with terrestrial mechanics; and from
that time the mechanical problems of the heavens became more important
and attractive to mathematicians than the problems about earthly
machines. And thus the generalizations of the problems, principles,
and methods of the mathematical science of Mechanics from this period
are principally those which have reference to the motions of the
heavenly bodies: such as the Problem of Three Bodies, the Principles
of the Conservation of Areas, and of the Immovable Plane, the Method
of Variation of Parameters, and the like (Chap. vi. Sect. 7 and 14). And
the same is the case in the more recent progress of that subject, in
the hands of Gauss, Bessel, Hansen, and others.
But yet the science of Mechanics as applied to terrestrial
machines—Industrial Mechanics, as it has been
termed—has made some steps which it may be worth while to
notice, even in a general history of science. For the most part, all
the most general laws of mechanical action being already finally
established, in the way which we have had to narrate, the
determination of the results and conditions of any combination of
materials and movements becomes really a mathematical deduction from
known principles. But such deductions may be made much more easy and
much more luminous by the establishment of general terms and general
propositions suited to their special conditions. Among these I may
mention a new abstract term, introduced because a general mechanical
principle can be expressed by means of it, which has lately been much
employed by the mathematical engineers of France, MM. Poncelet,
Navier, Morin, &c. The abstract term is Travail, which has
been translated Laboring Force; and the principle which gives
it its value, and makes it useful in the solution of problems, is
this;—that the work done (in overcoming resistance or
producing any other effect) is equal to the Laboring Force, by
whatever contrivances the force be applied. This is not a new
principle, being in fact mathematically equivalent to the conservation
of Vis Viva; but it has been employed by the mathematicians of whom I
have spoken with a fertility and simplicity which make it the mark of
a new school of The Mechanics of Engineering.
The Laboring Force expended and the work done have been described
by various terms, as Theoretical Effect and Practical
Effect, and the like. The usual term among English engineers for
the work 538 which
an Engine usually does, is Duty; but as this word naturally
signifies what the engine ought to do, rather than what it
does, we should at least distinguish between the Theoretical and the
Actual Duty.
The difference between the Theoretical and Actual Duty of a Machine
arises from this: that a portion of the Laboring Force is absorbed in
producing effects, that is, in doing work which is not reckoned as
Duty: for instance, overcoming the resistance and waste of the machine
itself. And so long as this resistance and waste are not rightly
estimated, no correspondence can be established between the
theoretical and the practical Duty. Though much had been written
previously upon the theory of the steam-engine, the correspondence
between the Force expended and the Work done was not clearly made out
till Comte De Pambour published his Treatise on Locomotive
Engines in 1835, and his Theory of the Steam-Engine in
1839.
Strength of Materials.
Among the subjects which have specially engaged the attention of
those who have applied the science of Mechanics to practical matters,
is the strength of materials: for example, the strength of a
horizontal beam to resist being broken by a weight pressing upon it.
This was one of the problems which Galileo took up. He was led to his
study of it by a visit which he made to the arsenal and dockyards of
Venice, and the conclusions which he drew were published in his
Dialogues, in 1633. In his mode of regarding the problem, he
considers the section at which the beam breaks as the short arm of a
bent lever which resists fracture, and the part of the beam which is
broken off as the longer arm of the lever, the lever turning about the
fracture as a hinge. So far this is true; and from this principle he
obtained results which are also true  as, that the strength of a
rectangular beam is proportional to the breadth multiplied into the
square of the depth:—that a hollow beam is stronger than a solid
beam of the same mass; and the like.
But he erred in this, that he supposed the hinge about which the
breaking beam turns, to be exactly at the unrent surface, that surface
resisting all change, and the beam being rent all the way across.
Whereas the fact is, that the unrent surface yields to compression,
while the opposite surface is rent; and the hinge about which the
breaking beam turns is at an intermediate point, where the extension
539 and rupture
end, and the compression and crushing begin: a point which has been
called the neutral axis. This was pointed out by Mariotte; and
the notion, once suggested, was so manifestly true that it was adopted
by mathematicians in general. James Bernoulli,36 in 1705,
investigated the strength of beams on this view; and several eminent
mathematicians pursued the subject; as Varignon, Parent, and
Bulfinger; and at a later period, Dr. Robison in our own country.
36 Opera, ii. p. 976.
But along with the fracture of beams, the mathematicians considered
also another subject, the flexure of beams, which they undergo before
they break, in virtue of their elasticity. What is the elastic
curve?—the curve into which an elastic line forms itself
under the pressure of a weight—is a problem which had been
proposed by Galileo, and was fully solved, as a mathematical problem,
by Euler and others.
But beams in practice are not mere lines: they are solids. And
their resistance to flexure, and the amount of it, depends upon the
resistance of their internal parts to extension and compression, and
is different for different substances. To measure these differences,
Dr. Thomas Young introduced the notion of the Modulus of
Elasticity:37 meaning thereby a column of the
substance of the same diameter, such as would by its weight produce a
compression equal to the whole length of the beam, the rate of
compression being supposed to continue the same throughout. Thus if a
rod of any kind, 100 inches long, were compressed 1 inch by a weight
1000 pounds, the weight of its modulus of elasticity would be 100,000
pounds. This notion assumes Hooke’s law that the extension of a
substance is as its tension; and extends this law to compression
also.
37 Lecture xiii. The height of the
modulus is the same for the same substance, whatever its breadth and
thickness may be; for atmospheric air it is about five miles, and for
steel nearly 1500 miles.
There is this great advantage in introducing the definition of the
Modulus of Elasticity,—that it applies equally to the flexure of
a substance and to the minute vibrations which propagate sound, and
the like. And the notion was applied so as to lead to curious and
important results with regard to the power of beams to resist flexure,
not only when loaded transversely, but when pressed in the direction
of their length, and in any oblique direction.
But in the fracture of beams, the resistance to extension and to
compression are not practically equal; and it was necessary to
determine 540 the
difference of these two forces by experiments. Several persons pursued
researches on this subject; especially Mr. Barlow, of the Royal
Military Academy,38 who investigated the subject with great
labor and skill, so far as wood is concerned. But the difference
between the resistance to tension and to compression requires more
special study in the case of iron; and has been especially attended to
in recent times, in consequence of the vast increase in the number of
iron structures, and in particular, railways. It appears that wrought
iron yields to compressive somewhat more easily than to tensile force,
while cast iron yields far more easily to tensile than to compressive
strains. In all cases the power of a beam to resist fracture resides
mainly in the upper and the under side, for there the tenacity of the
material acts at the greatest leverage round the hinge of fracture.
Hence the practice was introduced of making iron beams with a broad
flange at the upper and another flange at the under side,
connected by a vertical plate or web, of which the office was
to keep the two flanges asunder. Mr. Hodgkinson made many valuable
experiments, on a large scale, to determine the forms and properties
of such beams.
38 An Essay on the Strength and
Shape of Timber. 3d edition, 1826.
But though engineers were, by such experiments and reasonings,
enabled to calculate the strength of a given iron beam, and the
dimensions of a beam which should bear a given load, it would hardly
have occurred to the boldest speculator, a few years ago, to predict
that there might be constructed beams nearly 500 feet long, resting
merely on their two extremities, of which it could be known
beforehand, that they would sustain, without bending or yielding in
any perceptible degree, the weight of a railroad train, and the jar of
its unchecked motion. Yet of such beams, constructed beforehand with
the most perfect confidence, crowned with the most complete success,
is composed the great tubular bridge which that consummate engineer,
Mr. Robert Stephenson, has thrown across the Menai Strait, joining
Wales with the island of Anglesey. The upper and under surfaces of
this quadrangular tube are the flanges of the beam, and the two sides
are the webs which connect them. In planning this wonderful structure,
the point which required especial care was to make the upper surface
strong enough to resist the compressive force which it has to sustain;
and this was done by constructing the upper part of the beam of a
series of cells, made of iron plate. The application of the arch, of
the dome, and of groined vaulting, to the widest space over which they
have ever been thrown, 541 are achievements which have, in the ages
in which they occurred, been received with great admiration and
applause; but in those cases the principle of the structure had been
tried and verified for ages upon a smaller scale. Here not only was
the space thus spanned wider than any ever spanned before, but the
principle of such a beam with a cellular structure of its parts, was
invented for this very purpose, experimentally verified with care, and
applied with the most exact calculation of its results.
Roofs—Arches—Vaults.
The calculations of the mechanical conditions of structures
consisting of several beams, as for instance, the frames of roofs,
depends upon elementary principles of mechanics; and was a subject of
investigation at an early period of the science. Such frames may be
regarded as assemblages of levers. The parts of which they consist are
rigid beams which sustain and convey force, and Ties which
resist such force by their tension. The former parts must be made
rigid in the way just spoken of with regard to iron beams; but ties
may be rods merely. The wide structures of many of the roofs of
railway stations, compared with the massive wooden roofs of ancient
buildings, may show us how boldly and how successfully this
distinction has been carried out in modern times. The investigation of
the conditions and strength of structures consisting of wooden beams
has been cultivated by Mathematicians and Engineers, and is often
entitled Carpentry in our Mechanical Treatises. In our own
time, Dr. Robison and Dr. Thomas Young have been two of the most
eminent mathematicians who have written upon this subject.
The properties of the simple machines have been known, as we have
narrated, from the time of the Ancient Greeks. But it is plain that
such machines are prevented from producing their full effect by
various causes. Among the rest, the rubbing of one part of the machine
upon another produces an obstacle to the effectiveness of a machine:
for instance, the rubbing of the axle of a wheel in the hole in which
it rests, the rubbing of a screw against the sides of its hollow
screw; the rubbing of a wedge against the sides of its notch; the
rubbing of a cord against its pulley. In all these cases, the effect
of the machine to produce motion is diminished by the friction. And
this Friction may be measured and its effects calculated; and
thus we have a new branch of mechanics, which has been much
cultivated. 542
Among the effects of friction, we may notice the standing of a
stone arch. For each of the vaulting stones of an arch is a truncated
wedge; and though a collection of such stones might be so proportioned
in their weights as to balance exactly, yet this balance would be a
tottering equilibrium, which the slightest shock would throw down, and
which would not practically subsist. But the friction of the vaulting
stones against one another prevents this instability from being a
practical inconvenience; and makes an equilibrated arch to be an arch
strong for practical purposes. The Theory of Arches is a
portion of Mechanics which has been much cultivated, and which has led
to conclusions of practical use, as well as of theoretical beauty.
I have already spoken of the invention of the Arch, the Dome, and
Groined Vaulting, as marked steps in building. In all these cases the
invention was devised by practical builders; and mechanical theory,
though it can afterwards justify these structures, did not originally
suggest them. They are not part of the result, nor even of the
application of theory, but only of its exemplification. The authors of
all these inventions are unknown; and the inventions themselves may be
regarded as a part of the Prelude of the science of mechanics, because
they indicate that the ideas of mechanical pressure and support, in
various forms, are acquiring clearness and fixity.
In this point of view, I spoke (Book iv. chap. v. sect. 5) of the Architecture of the Middle Ages
as indicating a progress of thought which led men towards the
formation of Statics as a science.
As particular instances of the operation of such ideas, we have the
Flying Buttresses which support stone vaults; and especially,
as already noted, the various contrivances by which stone vaults are
made to intersect one another, so as to cover a complex pillared space
below with Groined Vaulting. This invention, executed as it was
by the builders of the twelfth and succeeding centuries, is the most
remarkable advance in the mechanics of building, after the invention
of the Arch itself.
It is curious that it has been the fortune of our times, among its
many inventions, to have produced one in this department, of which we
may say that it is the most remarkable step in the mechanics of arches
which has been made since the introduction of pointed groined vaults.
I speak of what are called Skew Arches, in which the courses of
stone or brick of which the bridge is built run obliquely to the walls
of the bridge. Such bridges have become very common in the works of
railroads; for they save space and material, and the 543 invention once made,
the cost of the ingenuity is nothing. Of course, the mechanical
principles involved in such structures are obvious to the
mathematician, when the problem has been practically solved. And in
this case, as in the previous cardinal inventions in structure, though
the event has taken place within a few years, no single person, so far
as I am aware, can be named as the inventor.39
39 Since this was written, I have been
referred to Rees’s Cyclopædia, Article Oblique Arches,
where this invention is correctly explained, and is claimed for an
engineer named Chapman. It is there said, that the first arch of this
kind was erected in 1787 at Naas, near Kildare in Ireland.


BOOK VII.

PHYSICAL ASTRONOMY.
</div></body></text></TEI>