<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 166, folios 39-40</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 166, folios 39-40.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1842">undated [July 1842]</date>
          <note type="place">Cambridge</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 166, folios 39-40</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_166_folios_39-40.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>Cambridge Friday</p>
      <p>Dearest W. I will write a line, tho' I am rather hurried, because tomorrow I cannot. From the enclosed, I expect the Hen here tomorrow.</p>
      <p>Charlotte, I rejoice to say, is much better; gaining rapidly &amp; satisfactorily.--</p>
      <p>I forgot to tell you how very nice &amp; remarkable a little thing her son is. You know</p>
      <p>I am not very prone to admire little babies. But I never saw one so beautifully made, or so intelligent at that age.</p>
      <p>I have been a little vexed with what I call a stupidity of the Hen's yesterday. She sent her man over all the way from Brampton, merely to bring me a note. It could have come perfectly alone, without such a chaperon, by a parcel. It has cost her much expense, &amp; me much</p>
      <p>trouble; for I could not get the man away from here. He wanted to stay &amp; amuse himself; &amp; declared there was no way of getting back before tomorrow. Whereas found he could have returned last night, or early this morning perfectly.</p>
      <p>And Calliphronas actually had to go &amp; take a place for him, before I could get him off today.</p>
      <p>I have been sight-seeing; &amp; also introduced to</p>
      <p>Sedgwick, Dr Carus, &amp; Dr Clarke.</p>
      <p>I have been a little plagued with Tooth-ache again; quite in a new &amp; uncomeatable place; &amp; must go to Lauzelle about it the moment I leave the Hen. I fear too it is a very bad job; as indeed all my concerns of this sort usually are.</p>
      <p>I am a little disappointed to have no letter from you today.</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
