<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Temple of Nature</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1803</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="15">(p. 018) ADDITIONAL NOTE. V.

AMPHIBIOUS ANIMALS.

  So still the Diodons, amphibious tribe,
  With twofold lungs the sea and air imbibe.
Cant. I. l. 331.
D. D. Garden dissected the amphibious creature called diodon by
Linneus, and was amazed to find that it possessed both external gills
and internal lungs, which he described and prepared and sent to
Linneus; who thence put this animal into the order nantes of his class
amphibia. He adds also, in his account of polymorpha before the class
amphibia, that some of this class breathe by lungs only, and others by
both lungs and gills.
Some amphibious quadrupeds, as the beaver, water rat, and otter, are
said to have the foramen ovale of the heart open, which communicates
from one cavity of it to the other; and that, during their continuance
under water, the blood can thus for a time circulate without passing
through the lungs; but as it cannot by these means acquire oxygen
either from the air or water, these creatures find it frequently
necessary to rise to the surface to respire. As this foramen ovale is
always open in the fœtus of quadrupeds, till after its birth that
it begins to respire, it has been proposed by some to keep young
puppies three or four times a day for a minute or two under warm water
to prevent this communication from one cavity of the heart to the
other from growing up; whence it has been thought such dogs might
become amphibious. It is also believed that this circumstance has
existed in some divers for pearl; whose children are said to have been
thus kept under water in their early infancy to enable them afterwards
to succeed in their employment.
But the most frequent distinction of the amphibious animals, that live
much in the water, is, that their heart consists but of one cell; and
as they are pale creatures with but little blood, and that colder
(p. 019) and darker coloured, as frogs and lizards, they require less
oxygen than the warmer animals with a greater quantity and more
scarlet blood; and thence, though they have only lungs, they can stay
long under water without great inconvenience; but are all of them,
like frogs, and crocodiles, and whales, necessitated frequently to
rise above the surface for air.
In this circumstance of their possessing a one-celled heart, and
colder and darker blood, they approach to the state of fish; which
thus appear not to acquire so much oxygen by their gills from the
water as terrestrial animals do by their lungs from the atmosphere;
whence it may be concluded that the gills of fish do not decompose the
water which passes through them, and which contains so much more
oxygen than the air, but that they only procure a small quantity of
oxygen from the air which is diffused in the water; which also is
further confirmed by an experiment with the air-pump, as fish soon die
when put in a glass of water into the exhausted receiver, which they
would not do if their gills had power to decompose the water and
obtain the oxygen from it.
The lamprey, petromyzon, is put by Linneus amongst the nantes, which
are defined to possess both gills and lungs. It has seven spiracula,
or breathing holes, on each side of the neck, and by its more perfect
lungs approaches to the serpent kind; Syst. Nat. The means by which it
adheres to stones, even in rapid streams, is probably owing to a
partial vacuum made by its respiring organs like sucking, and may be
compared to the ingenious method by which boys are seen to lift large
stones in the street, by applying to them a piece of strong moist
leather with a string through the centre of it; which, when it is
forcibly drawn upwards, produces a partial vacuum under it, and thus
the stone is supported by the pressure of the atmosphere.
The leech, hirudo, and the remora, echeneis, adhere strongly to
objects probably by a similar method. I once saw ten or twelve leeches
adhere to each foot of an old horse a little above his hoofs, who was
grazing in a morass, and which did not lose their hold when he moved
about. The bare-legged travellers in Ceylon are said to be much
infested by leeches; and the sea-leech, hirudo muricata, is said
(p. 020) to adhere to fish, and the remora is said to adhere to ships
in such numbers as to retard their progress.
The respiratory organ of the whale, I suppose, is pulmonary in part,
as he is obliged to come frequently to the surface, whence he can be
pursued after he is struck with the harpoon; and may nevertheless be
in part like the gills of other fish, as he seems to draw in water
when he is below the surface, and emits it again when he rises above
it.
</div></body></text></TEI>