<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Chambers Robert</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1844</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="4">p.
54COMMENCEMENT OF ORGANIC LIFE—
SEA PLANTS, CORALS, ETC.
We can scarcely be said to have
passed out of these rocks, when we begin to find new conditions
in the earth.  It is here to be observed that the subsequent
rocks are formed, in a great measure, of matters derived from the
substance of those which went before, but contain also beds of
limestone, which is to no small extent composed of an ingredient
which has not hitherto appeared.  Limestone is a carbonate
of lime, a secondary compound, of which one of the ingredients,
carbonic acid gas, presents the element carbon, a perfect
novelty in our progress.  Whence this substance?  The
question is the more interesting, from our knowing that carbon is
the main ingredient in organic things.  There is reason to
believe that its primeval condition was that of a gas, confined
in the interior of the earth, and diffused in the
atmosphere.  The atmosphere still contains about a
two-thousandth part of carbonic acid gas, forming the grand store
from which the substance of each year’s crop of herbage and
grain is derived, passing from herbage and grain into animal
substance, and from animals again rendered back to the atmosphere
in their expired breath, so that its amount is never
impaired.  Knowing this, when we hear of carbon beginning to
appear in the ascending series of rocks, we are unavoidably led
to consider it as marking a time of some importance in the
earth’s history, a new era of natural conditions, one in
which organic life has probably played a part.
It is not easy to suppose that, at this period, carbon was
adopted directly in its gaseous form into rocks; for, if so, why
should it not have been taken into earlier ones also?  But
we know that plants take it in, and transform it into substance;
and we also know that there are classes of animals (marine
polypes) which are capable of appropriating it, in connexion with
lime, (carbonate of lime,) from the waters of the ocean, provided
it be there in solution; and this substance do these animals
deposit in masses (coral reefs) equal in extent to many
strata.  It has even been suggested, on strong grounds of
probability, that a class of limestone beds are simply these
reefs subjected to subsequent heat and pressure.
The appearance, then, of limestone beds in the early part of
the stratified series, may be presumed to be connected with the
fact of the commencement of organic life upon our planet, and,
indeed, a consequent and a symptom of it.
It may not be out of place here to remark, that carbon is
presumed to exist largely in the interior of the earth, from the
fact of such considerable quantities of it issuing at this day,
in the form of carbonic acid gas, from fissures and
springs.  The primeval and subsequent history of this
element is worthy of much attention, and we shall have to revert
to it as a matter greatly concerning our subject.  Delabeche
estimates the quantity of carbonic acid gas locked up in every
cubic yard of limestone, at 16,000 cubic feet.  The quantity
locked up in coal, in which it forms from 64 to 75 per cent.,
must also be enormous.  If all this were disengaged in a
gaseous form, the constitution of the atmosphere would undergo a
change, of which the first effect would be the extinction of life
in all land animals.  But a large proportion of it must have
at one time been in the atmosphere.  The atmosphere would
then, of course, be incapable of supporting life in land
animals.  It is important, however, to observe that such an
atmosphere would not be inconsistent with a luxuriant land
vegetation; for experiment has proved that plants will flourish
in air containing one-twelfth of this gas, or 166 times
more than the present charge of our atmosphere.  The results
which we observe are perfectly consistent with, and may be said
to presuppose an atmosphere highly charged with this gas, from
about the close of the primary non-fossiliferous rocks to the
termination of the carboniferous series, for there we see vast
deposits (coal) containing carbon as a large ingredient, while at
the same time the leaves of the Stone Book present no
record of the contemporaneous existence of land animals.
The hypothesis of the connexion of the first limestone beds
with the commencement of organic life upon our planet is
supported by the fact, that in these beds we find the first
remains of the bodies of animated creatures.  My hypothesis
may indeed be unsound; but, whether or not, it is clear, taking
organic remains as upon the whole a faithful chronicle, that the
deposition of these limestone beds was coeval with the existence
of the earliest, or all but the earliest, living creatures upon
earth.
And what were those creatures?  It might well be with a
kind of awe that the uninstructed inquirer would wait for an
answer to this question.  But nature is simpler than
man’s wit would make her, and behold, the interrogation
only brings before us the unpretending forms of various zoophytes
and polypes, together with a few single and double-valved
shell-fish (mollusks), all of them creatures of the sea.  It
is rather surprising to find these before any vegetable forms,
considering that vegetables appear to us as forming the necessary
first link in the chain of nutrition; but it is probable that
there were sea plants, and also some simpler forms of animal
life, before this period, although of too slight a substance to
leave any fossil trace of their existence.
The exact point in the ascending stratified series at which
the first traces of organic life are to be found is not clearly
determined.  Dr. M’Culloch states that he found fossil
orthocerata (a kind of shell-fish) so early as the gneiss tract
of Loch Eribol, in Sutherland; but Messrs. Sedgwick and
Murchison, on a subsequent search, could not verify the
discovery.  It has also been stated, that the gneiss and
mica tract of Bohemia contains some seams of grawacke, in which
are organic remains; but British geologists have not as yet
attached much importance to this statement.  We have to look
a little higher in the series for indubitable traces of organic
life.
Above the gneiss and mica slate system, or group of strata, is
the Clay Slate and Grawacke Slate System; that is to say,
it is higher in the order of supraposition, though very
often it rests immediately on the primitive granite.  The
sub-groups of this system are in the following succession
upwards:—1, hornblende slate; 2, chiastolite slate; 3, clay
slate; 4, Snowdon rocks, (grawacke and conglomerates;) 5, Bala
limestone; 6, Plynlymmon rocks, (grawacke and grawacke slates,
with beds of conglomerates.)  This system is largely
developed in the west and north of England, and it has been well
examined, partly because some of the slate beds are extensively
quarried for domestic purposes.  If we overlook the dubious
statements respecting Sutherland and Bohemia, we have in this
“system” the first appearances of life upon our
planet.  The animal remains are chiefly confined to the
slate beds, those named from Bala, in Wales, being the most
prolific.  Zoophyta, polyparia,
crinoidea, conchifera, and crustacea, [60] are the orders of the animal kingdom
thus found in the earliest of earth’s sepulchres.  The
orders are distinguished without difficulty, from the
general characters of the creatures whose remains are found; but
it is only in this general character that they bear a general
resemblance to any creatures now existing.  When we come to
consider specific characters, we see that a difference
exists—that, in short, the species and even genera are no
longer represented upon earth.  More than this, it will be
found that the earliest species comparatively soon gave place to
others, and that they are not represented even in the next higher
group of rocks.  One important remark has been made, that a
comparatively small variety of species is found in the older
rocks, although of some particular ones the remains are very
abundant; as, for instance, of a species of asaphus, which is
found between the laminæ of some of the slate rocks of
Wales, and the corresponding rocks of Normandy and Germany in
enormous quantities.
Ascending to the next group of rocks, we find the traces of
life become more abundant, the number of species extended, and
important additions made in certain vestiges of fuci, or
sea-plants, and of fishes.  This group of rocks has been
called by English geologists, the Silurian System, because
largely developed at the surface of a district of western
England, formerly occupied by a people whom the Roman historians
call Silures.  It is a series of sandstones, limestones, and
beds of shale (hardened mud), which are classed in the following
sub-groups, beginning with the undermost:—1, Llandillo
rocks, (darkish calcareous flagstones;) 2 and 3, two groups
called Caradoc rocks; 4, Wenlock shale; 5, Wenlock limestone; 6,
Lower Ludlow rocks, (shales and limestones;) 7, Aymestry
limestone; 8, Upper Ludlow rocks, (shales and limestone, chiefly
micaceous.)  From the lowest beds upwards, there are
polypiaria, though most prevalent in the Wenlock limestone;
conchifera, a vast number of genera, but all of the order
brachiopoda, (including terebratula, pentamerus, spirifer,
orthis, leptæna;) mollusca, of several orders and many
genera, (including turritella, orthoceras, nautilus,
bellerophon;) crustacea, all of them trilobites, (including
trinucleus, asaphus, calamene.)  A little above the
Llandillo rocks, there have been discovered certain convoluted
forms, which are now established as annelids, or sea-worms, a
tribe of creatures still existing, (nereidina and serpulina,) and
which may often be found beneath stones on a sea-beach.  One
of these, figured by Mr. Murchison, is furnished with feet in
vast numbers all along its body, like a centipede.  The
occurrence of annelids is important, on account of their
character and status in the animal kingdom.  They are
red-blooded and hermaphrodite, and form a link of connexion
between the annulosa (white-blooded worms) and a humble class of
the vertebrata. [62]  The Wenlock limestone is most
remarkable amongst all the rocks of the Silurian system, for
organic remains.  Many slabs of it are wholly composed of
corals, shells, and trilobites, held together by shale.  It
contains many genera of crinoidea and polypiaria, and it is
thought that some beds of it are wholly the production of the
latter creatures, or are, in other words, coral reefs transformed
by heat and pressure into rocks.  Remains of fishes, of a
very minute size, have been detected by Mr. Philips in the
Aymestry limestone, being apparently the first examples of
vertebrated animals which breathed upon our planet.  In the
upper Ludlow rocks, remains of six genera of fish have been for a
longer period known; they belong to the order of cartilaginous
fishes, an order of mean organization and ferocious habits, of
which the shark and sturgeon are living specimens. 
“Some were furnished with long palates, and squat,
firmly-based teeth, well adapted for crushing the strong-cased
zoophytes and shells of the period, fragments of which occur in
the fœcal remains; some with teeth that, like the fossil
sharks of the later formations, resemble lines of miniature
pyramids, larger and smaller alternating; some with teeth sharp,
thin, and so deeply serrated, that every individual tooth
resembles a row of poniards set up against the walls of an
armory; and these last, says Agassiz, furnished with weapons so
murderous, must have been the pirates of the period.  Some
had their fins guarded with long spines, hooked like the beak of
an eagle; some with spines of straighter and more slender form,
and ribbed and furrowed longitudinally like columns; some were
shielded by an armour of bony points, and some thickly covered
with glistening scales.” [64]
The traces of fuci in this system are all but sufficient to
allow of a distinction of genera.  In some parts of North
America, extensive though thin beds of them have been
found.  A distinguished French geologist, M. Brogniart, has
shewn that all existing marine plants are classifiable with
regard to the zones of climate; some being fitted for the torrid
zone, some for the temperate, some for the frigid.  And he
establishes that the fuci of these early rocks speak of a torrid
climate, although they may be found in what are now temperate
regions; he also states that those of the higher rocks betoken,
as we ascend, a gradually diminishing temperature.
We thus early begin to find proofs of the general uniformity
of organic life over the surface of the earth, at the time when
each particular system of rocks was formed.  Species
identical with the remains in the Wenlock limestone occur in the
corresponding class of rocks in the Eifel, and partially in the
Harz, Norway, Russia, and Brittany.  The situations of the
remains in Russia are fifteen hundred miles from the Wenlock
beds; but at the distance of between six and seven thousand from
those,—namely, in the vale of Mississippi, the same species
are discovered.  Uniformity in animal life over large
geographical areas argues uniformity in the conditions of animal
life; and hence arise some curious inferences.  Species, in
the same low class of animals, are now much more limited; for
instance, the Red Sea gives different polypiaria, zoophytes, and
shell-fish, from the Mediterranean.  It is the opinion of M.
Brogniart, that the uniformity which existed in the primeval
times can only be attributed to the temperature arising from the
internal heat, which had yet, as he supposes, been sufficiently
great to overpower the ordinary meteorological influences, and
spread a tropical clime all over the globe.</div></body></text></TEI>