<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="46">

BOOK VI.

THE PHILOSOPHY OF CHEMISTRY.

CHAPTER I.
Attempts to conceive Elementary Composition.



1. WE have now to bring into view, if possible, the
Ideas and General Principles which are involved in Chemistry,—the science of the composition
of bodies. For in this as in other parts of human
knowledge, we shall find that there are certain Ideas,
deeply seated in the mind, though shaped and unfolded
by external observation, which are necessary conditions
of the existence of such a science. These Ideas it is,
which impel man to such a knowledge of the Composition of bodies, which give meaning to facts exhibiting
this composition, and universality to special truths
discovered by experience. These are the Ideas of
Element and of Substance.
Unlike the Idea of Polarity, of which we treated in
the last Book, these Ideas have been current in men’s
minds from very early times, and formed the subject
of some of the first speculations of philosophers. It
happened however, as might have been expected, that
in the first attempts they were not clearly distinguished
from other notions, and were apprehended and applied
in an obscure and confused manner. We cannot better
exhibit the peculiar character and meaning of these
Ideas than by tracing the form which they have assumed 4
and the efficacy which they have exerted in these successive essays. This, therefore, I shall endeavour to
do, beginning with the Idea of Element.
2. That bodies are composed or made up of certain
parts, elements, or principles, is a conception which
has existed in men’s minds from the beginning of the
first attempts at speculative knowledge. The doctrine
of the Four Elements, Earth, Air, Fire and Water, of
which all things in the universe were supposed to be
constituted, is one of the earliest forms in which this
conception was systematized; and this doctrine is
stated by various authors to have existed as early as
the times of the ancient Egyptians1. The words usually
employed by Greek writers to express these elements
are ἀρχὴ a principle or beginning, and στοιχεῖον,
which probably meant a letter (of a word) before it
meant an element of a compound. For the resolution
of a word into its letters is undoubtedly a remarkable
instance of a successful analysis performed at an early
stage of man’s history; and might very naturally
supply a metaphor to denote the analysis of substances
into their intimate parts, when men began to contemplate such an analysis as a subject of speculation. The
Latin word elementum itself, though by its form it
appears to be a derivative abstract term, comes from
some root now obsolete; probably2 from a word signifying to grow or spring up.</div></body></text></TEI>