<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Principles of Geology</title><author>Lyell, Charles (1797-1875)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="39">CHAPTER XXXIX.
LAWS WHICH REGULATE THE GEOGRAPHICAL DISTRIBUTION OF
SPECIES—continued.
Geographical distribution and migration of Fish—of Testaoea—of Zoophytes—Distribution
of Insects—Migratory instincts of some species—Certain types
characterize particular countries—Their means of dissemination—Geographical
distribution and diffusion of man—Speculations as to the birth-place of
the human species—Progress of human population—Drifting of canoes to vast
distances—On the involuntary influence of man in extending the range of
many other species.
Geographical Distribution and Migrations of Fish.
Although we are less acquainted with the habitations of marine animals
than with the grouping of the terrestrial species before described, yet it
647
is well ascertained that their distribution is governed by the same general
laws. The testimony borne by MM. Péron and Lesueur to this important
fact is remarkably strong. These eminent naturalists, after collecting and
describing many thousand species of marine animals which they brought
to Europe from the southern hemisphere, insist most emphatically on
their distinctness from those north of the equator; and this remark they
extend to animals of all classes, from those of a more simple to those of
a more complex organization—from the sponges and Medusæ to the
Cetacea. "Among all those which we have been able to examine," say
they, "with our own eyes, or with regard to which it has appeared to us
possible to pronounce with certainty, there is not a single animal of the
southern regions which is not distinguished by essential characters from
the analogous species in the northern seas."909
On comparing the freshwater fish of Europe and North America, Sir
John Richardson remarks, that the only species which is unequivocally
common to the two continents is the pike (Esox lucius); and it is curious
that this fish is unknown to the westward of the Rocky Mountains, the
very coast which approaches nearest to the old continent.910 According
to the same author the genera of freshwater fish in China agree closely
with those of the peninsula of India, but the species are not the same.
"As in the distribution," he adds, "of marine fish, the interposition of a
continent stretching from the tropics far into the temperate or colder
parts of the ocean, separate different ichthyological groups; so with respect
to the freshwater species, the intrusion of arms of the sea running far to
the northwards, or the interposition of a lofty mountain-chain, effects the
same thing. The freshwater fish of the Cape of Good Hope and the
South American ones, are different from those of India and China, &c."911
Cuvier and Valenciennes, in their "Histoire des Poissons," observe,
that very few species of fish cross the Atlantic. Although their statement
is correct, it is found that a great many species are common to the
opposite sides of the Indian Ocean, inhabiting alike the Red Sea, the
eastern coast of Africa, Madagascar, the Mauritius, the Indian Ocean,
the southern seas of China, the Malay archipelago, the northern coasts
of Australia, and the whole of Polynesia!912 This very wide diffusion,
says Sir J. Richardson, may have been promoted by chains of islands
running east and west, which are wanting in the deep Atlantic. An
archipelago extending far in longitude, favours the migration of fish by
multiplying the places of deposit for spawn along the shores of islands,
and on intervening coral banks; and in such places, also, fish find their
appropriate food.
The flying fish are found (some stragglers excepted) only between the
tropics: in receding from the line, they never approach a higher latitude
648
than the fortieth parallel. The course of the Gulf stream, however, and
the warmth of its water, enable some tropical fish to extend their habitations
far into the temperate zone; thus the chætodons which abound in
the seas of hot climates, are found among the Bermudas on the thirty-second
parallel, where they are preserved in basins inclosed from the sea,
as an important article of food for the garrison and inhabitants. Other
fish, following the direction of the same great current, range from the
coast of Brazil to the banks of Newfoundland.913
All are aware that there are certain fish of passage which have their
periodical migrations, like some tribes of birds. The salmon, towards
the season of spawning, ascends the rivers for hundreds of miles, leaping
up the cataracts which it meets in its course, and then retreats again
into the depths of the ocean. The herring and the haddock, after frequenting
certain shores, in vast shoals, for a series of years, desert them
again, and resort to other stations, followed by the species which prey on
them. Eels are said to descend into the sea for the purpose of producing
their young, which are seen returning into the fresh water by myriads,
extremely small in size, but possessing the power of surmounting every
obstacle which occurs in the course of a river, by applying their slimy
and glutinous bodies to the surface of rocks, or the gates of a lock, even
when dry, and so climbing over it.914 Before the year 1800 there were no
eels in Lake Wener, the largest inland lake in Sweden, which discharges
its waters by the celebrated cataracts of Trolhättan. But I am informed
by Professor Nilsson, that since the canal was opened uniting the river
Gotha with the lake by a series of nine locks, each of great height, eels
have been observed in abundance in the lake. It appears, therefore, that
though they were unable to ascend the falls, they have made their way
by the locks, by which in a very short space a difference of level of 114
feet is overcome.
Gmelin says, that the Anseres (wild geese, ducks, and others) subsist,
in their migrations, on the spawn of fish; and that oftentimes, when
they void the spawn, two or three days afterwards, the eggs retain their
vitality unimpaired.915 When there are many disconnected freshwater
lakes in a mountainous region, at various elevations, each remote from
the other, it has often been deemed inconceivable how they could all
become stocked with fish from one common source; but it has been suggested,
that the minute eggs of these animals may sometimes be entangled
in the feathers of water-fowl. These, when they alight to wash
and plume themselves in the water, may often unconsciously contribute
to propagate swarms of fish, which, in due season, will supply
them with food. Some of the water-beetles, also, as the Dyticidæ, are
amphibious, and in the evening quit their lakes and pools, and, flying in
the air, transport the minute ova of fishes to distant waters. In this
manner some naturalists account for the fry of fish appearing occasionally
649
in small pools caused by heavy rains; but the showers of small fish,
stated in so many accounts to have fallen from the atmosphere, require
farther investigation.
Geographical Distribution and Migrations of Testacea.
The Testacea, of which so great a variety of species occurs in the sea,
are a class of animals of peculiar importance to the geologist; because
their remains are found in strata of all ages, and generally in a higher
state of preservation than those of other organic beings. Climate has
a decided influence on the geographical distribution of species in this
class; but as there is much greater uniformity of temperature in the
waters of the ocean, than in the atmosphere which invests the land, the
diffusion of marine mollusks is on the whole more extensive.
Some forms attain their fullest development in warm latitudes; and
are often exclusively confined to the torrid zone, as Nautilus, Harpa,
Terebellum, Pyramidella, Delphinula, Aspergillum, Tridacna, Cucullæa,
Crassatella, Corbis, Perna, and Plicatula. Other forms are limited to
one region of the sea, as the Trigonia to parts of Australia, and the
Concholepas to the western coast of South America. The marine species
inhabiting the ocean on the opposite sides of the narrow isthmus of
Panama, are found to differ almost entirely, as we might have anticipated,
since a West Indian mollusk cannot enter the Pacific without
coasting round South America, and passing through the inclement climate
of Cape Horn. The continuity of the existing lines of continent
from north to south, prevents any one species from belting the globe, or
from following the direction of the isothermal lines.
Currents also flowing permanently in certain directions, and the influx
at certain points of great bodies of fresh water, limit the extension of
many species. Those which love deep water are arrested by shoals;
others, fitted for shallow seas, cannot migrate across unfathomable abysses.
The nature also of the ground has an important influence on the
testaceous fauna, both on the land and beneath the waters. Certain
species prefer a sandy, others a gravelly, and some a muddy sea-bottom.
On the land, limestone is of all rocks the most favourable to the number
and propagation of species of the genera Helix, Clausilia, Bulimus, and
others. Professor E. Forbes has shown as the result of his labours in
dredging in the Ægean Sea, that there are eight well-marked regions of
depth, each characterized by its peculiar testaceous fauna. The first of
these, called the littoral zone, extends to a depth of two fathoms only;
but this narrow belt is inhabited by more than one hundred species.
The second region, of which ten fathoms is the inferior limit, is almost
equally populous; and a copious list of species is given as characteristic
of each region down to the seventh, which lies between the depths
of 80 and 105 fathoms, all the inhabited space below this being included
in the eighth province, where no less than 65 species of Testacea have
been taken. The majority of the shells in this lowest zone are white or
650
transparent. Only two species of Mollusca are common to all the eight
regions, namely, Arca lactea and Cerithium lima.916
Great range of some provinces and species.—In Europe conchologists
distinguish between the arctic fauna, the southern boundary of which
corresponds with the isothermal line of 32° F., and the Celtic, which,
commencing with that limit as its northern frontier, extends southwards
to the mouth of the English Channel and Cape Finisterre, in France.
From that point begins the Lusitanian fauna, which, according to the
recent observations of Mr. M'Andrew (1852), ranges to the Canary
Islands. The Mediterranean province is distinct from all those above
enumerated, although it has some species in common with each.
The Indo-Pacific region is by far the most extensive of all. It reaches
from the Red Sea and the eastern coast of Africa, to the Indian Archipelago,
and adjoining parts of the Pacific Ocean. To the geologist it
furnishes a fact of no small interest, by teaching us that one group of
living species of mollusca may prevail throughout an area exceeding in
magnitude the utmost limits we can as yet assign to any assemblage of
contemporaneous fossil species. Mr. Cuming obtained more than a
hundred species of shells from the eastern coast of Africa identical with
those collected by himself at the Philippines and in the eastern coral
islands of the Pacific Ocean, a distance equal to that from pole to pole.917
Certain species of the genus Ianthina have a very wide range, being
common to seas north and south of the equator. They are all provided
with a beautifully contrived float, which renders them buoyant, facilitating
their dispersion, and enabling them to become active agents in disseminating
other species. Captain King took a specimen of Ianthina fragilis,
alive, a little north of the equator, so loaded with barnacles (Pentelasmis)
and their ova that the upper part of its shell was invisible. The "Rock
Whelk" (Purpura lapillus), a well-known British univalve, inhabits
both the North Atlantic and North Pacific.
Helix putris (Succinea putris, Lam.), so common in Europe, where it
reaches from Norway to Italy, is also said to occur in the United States
and in Newfoundland. As this animal inhabits constantly the borders of
pools and streams where there is much moisture, it is not impossible that
different water-fowl have been the agents of spreading some of its
minute eggs, which may have been entangled in their feathers. The
freshwater snail, Lymneus palustris, so abundant in English ponds,
ranges uninterruptedly from Europe to Cashmere, and thence to the
eastern parts of Asia. Helix aspersa, one of the commonest of our
larger land-shells, is found in St. Helena and other distant countries.
Some conchologists have conjectured that it was accidentally imported into
St. Helena in some ship; for it is an eatable species, and these animals are
capable of retaining life during long voyages, without air or nourishment.918
651
Perhaps no species has a better claim to be called cosmopolite than
one of our British bivalves, Saxicava rugosa. It is spread over all the
north-polar seas, and ranges in one direction through Europe to Senegal,
occurring on both sides of the Atlantic; while in another it finds its way
into the North Pacific, and thence to the Indian Ocean. Nor do its
migrations cease till it reaches the Australian seas.
A British brachiopod, named Terebratula caput-serpentis, is common,
according to Professor E. Forbes, to both sides of the North Atlantic,
and to the South African and Chinese seas.
Confined range of other species.—Mr. Lowe, in a memoir published
in the Cambridge Transactions in 1834, enumerates seventy-one species
of land Mollusca, collected by him in the islands of Madeira and Porto
Santo, sixty of which belonged to the genus Helix alone, including as
sub-genera Bulimus and Achatina, and excluding Vitrina and Clausilia;
forty-four of these are new. It is remarkable that very few of the
above-mentioned species are common to the neighbouring archipelago of
the Canaries; but it is a still more striking fact, that of the sixty species
of the three genera above mentioned, thirty-one are natives of Porto
Santo; whereas, in Madeira, which contains ten times the superficies,
were found but twenty-nine. Of these only four were common to the
two islands, which are separated by a distance of only twelve leagues;
and two even of these four (namely Helix rhodostoma and H. ventrosa)
are species of general diffusion, common to Madeira, the Canaries, and
the south of Europe.919
The confined range of these mollusks may easily be explained, if we
admit that species have only one birth-place; and the only problem to be
solved would relate to the exceptions—to account for the dissemination
of some species throughout several islands, and the European continent.
May not the eggs, when washed into the sea by the undermining of
cliffs, or blown by a storm from the land, float uninjured to a distant shore?
Their mode of diffusion.—Notwithstanding the proverbially slow
motion of snails and mollusks in general, and although many aquatic
species adhere constantly to the same rock for their whole lives, they are
by no means destitute of provision for disseminating themselves rapidly
over a wide area. "Some Mollusca," says Professor E. Forbes, "migrate
in their larva state, for all of them undergo a metamorphosis either in the
egg or out of the egg. The gasteropoda commence life under the form
of a small spiral shell, and an animal furnished with ciliated wings, or
lobes, like a pteropod, by means of which it can swim freely, and in this
form can migrate with ease through the sea."920
652
We are accustomed to associate in our minds the idea of the greatest
locomotive powers with the most mature and perfect state of each
species of invertebrate animal, especially when they undergo a series of
transformations; but in all the Mollusca the reverse is true. The young
fry of the cockle, for example (Cardium), possess, when young or in the
larva state, an apparatus which enables them both to swim and to be
carried along easily by a marine current. (See fig. 99.)
Fig. 99.
Tne young fry of a cockle (Cardium pygmæum,) from Loven's Kongl. Vetenskaps. Akadem.
Handling, 1848.

A, The young just hatched, magnified 100 diameters.      B, the same farther advanced.
a, The ciliated organ of locomotion with its filamentous appendage b.
c, The rudimentary intestine.
d, The rudimentary shell.
These small bodies here represented, which bear a considerable
resemblance to the fry of the univalve, or gasteropodous shells above
mentioned, are so minute at first as to be just visible to the naked eye.
They begin to move about from the moment they are hatched, by means
of the long cilia, a, a, placed on the edges of the locomotive disk or
velum. This disk shrinks up as they increase in size, and gradually
disappears, no trace of it being visible in the perfect animal.
Some species of shell-bearing Mollusca lay their eggs in a sponge-like
nidus, wherein the young remain enveloped for a time after their birth;
and this buoyant substance floats far and wide as readily as sea-weed.
The young of other viviparous tribes are often borne along entangled in
sea-weed. Sometimes they are so light, that, like grains of sand, they
can be easily moved by currents. Balani and Serpulæ are sometimes
found adhering to floating cocoa-nuts, and even to fragments of pumice.
In rivers and lakes, on the other hand, aquatic univalves usually attach
their eggs to leaves and sticks which have fallen into the water, and
which are liable to be swept away during floods, from tributaries to the
main streams, and from thence to all parts of the same basins. Particular
species may thus migrate during one season from the head waters
of the Mississippi, or any other great river, to countries bordering the
sea, at the distance of many thousand miles.
An illustration of the mode of attachment of these eggs will be seen
in the annexed cut. (Fig. 100.)
The habit of some Testacea to adhere to floating wood is proved by
their fixing themselves to the bottoms of ships. By this mode of conveyance
Mytilus polymorphus, previously known only in the Danube and
653
Wolga, may have been brought to the Commercial Docks in the Thames,
and to Hamburgh, where the species is now domiciled. But Mr. Gray
suggests that as the animal is known to have the faculty of living for a
very long time out of water, it is more probable that it was brought in
Russian timber, than borne uninjured through the salt water at the
bottom of a vessel.921
A lobster (Astacus marinus) was lately taken alive covered with living
mussels (Mytilus edulis)922; and a large female crab (Cancer pagurus),
covered with oysters, and bearing also Anomia ephippium, and Actiniæ,
was taken in April, 1832, off the English coast. The oysters, seven in number,
include individuals of six years' growth, and the two largest are four
inches long and three inches and a half broad. Both the crab and
the oysters were seen alive by Mr. Robert Brown.923
Fig. 100.
Eggs of Freshwater mollusks.

Fig. 1. Eggs of Ampullaria ovata (a fluviatile species) fixed to a small sprig which had fallen into
the water.
Fig. 2. Eggs of Planorbis albus, attached to a dead leaf lying under water.
Fig. 3. Eggs of the common Limneus (L. vulgaris), adhering to a dead stick under water.

From this example we learn the manner in which oysters may be
diffused over every part of the sea where the crab wanders; and if they
are at length carried to a spot where there is nothing but fine mud, the
foundation of a new oyster-bank may be laid on the death of the crab.
In this instance the oysters survived the crab many days, and were
killed at last only by long exposure to the air.
654
Geographical Distribution and Migrations of Zoophytes.
Zoophytes are very imperfectly known; but there can be little doubt
that each maritime region possesses species peculiar to itself. The
Madrepores, or lamelliferous Polyparia, are found in their fullest development
only in the tropical seas of Polynesia and the East and West
Indies; and this family is represented only by a few species in our seas.
The zoophytes of the Mediterranean, according to Ehrenberg, differ
almost entirely from those of the Red Sea, although only seventy miles
distant. Out of 120 species of Anthozoa, only two are common to both
seas.924 Péron and Lesueur, after studying the Holothuriæ, Medusæ,
and other congeners of delicate and changeable forms, came to the conclusion
that each kind has its place of residence determined by the
temperature necessary to support its existence. Thus, for example,
they found the abode of Pyrosoma Atlantica to be confined to one
particular region of the Atlantic Ocean.925
Let us now inquire how the transportation of zoophytes from one
part of the globe to another is effected. Many of them, as in the
families Flustra and Sertularia, attach themselves to sea-weed, and are
occasionally drifted along with it. Many fix themselves to the shells of
Mollusca, and are thus borne along by them to short distances. Others,
like some species of sea-pens, float about in the ocean, and are usually
believed to possess powers of spontaneous motion. But the most frequent
mode of transportation consists in the buoyancy of their eggs,
or certain small vesicles, which are detached, and are capable of becoming
the foundation of a new colony. These gems, as they are called,
have, in many instances, a locomotive power of their own, by which
they proceed in a determinate direction for several days after separation
from the parent. They are propelled by means of numerous short
threads or ciliæ, which are in constant and rapid vibration; and, when
thus supported in the water, they may be borne along by currents to a
great distance.
That some zoophytes adhere to floating bodies, is proved by their
being found attached to the bottoms of ships, like certain Testacea
before alluded to.
Geographical Distribution and Migrations of Insects.
Before I conclude this sketch of the manner in which the habitable
parts of the earth are shared out among particular assemblages of
organic beings, I must offer a few remarks on insects, which, by their
numbers and the variety of their powers and instincts, exert a prodigious
influence in the economy of animate nature. As a large portion
of these minute creatures are strictly dependent for their subsistence on
certain species of vegetables, the entomological provinces must coincide
in considerable degree with the botanical.
655
All the insects, says Latreille, brought from the eastern parts of Asia
and China, whatever be their latitude and temperature, are distinct from
those of Europe and of Africa. The insects of the United States,
although often approaching very close to our own, are, with very few
exceptions, specifically distinguishable by some characters. In South
America, the equinoctial lands of New Granada and Peru on the one
side, and of Guiana on the other, contain for the most part distinct
groups; the Andes forming the division, and interposing a narrow
line of severe cold between climates otherwise very similar.926
Migratory instincts.—Nearly all the insects of the United States
and Canada, differ specifically from the European; while those of Greenland
appear to be in a great measure identical with our own. Some
insects are very local; while a few, on the contrary, are common to
remote countries, between which the torrid zone and the ocean intervene.
Thus our painted lady butterfly (Vanessa cardui) re-appears at
the Cape of Good Hope and in New Holland and Japan with scarcely
a varying streak.927 The same species is said to be one of the few
insects which are universally dispersed over the earth, being found
in Europe, Asia, Africa, and America; and its wide range is the more
interesting, because it seems explained by its migratory instinct,
seconded, no doubt, by a capacity, enjoyed by few species, of enduring
a great diversity of temperature.
A vast swarm of this species, forming a column from ten to fifteen
feet broad, was, a few years since, observed in the Canton de Vaud;
they traversed the country with great rapidity from north to south, all
flying onwards in regular order, close together, and not turning from
their course on the approach of other objects. Professor Bonelli, of
Turin, observed, in March of the same year, a similar swarm of the
same species, also directing their flight from north to south, in Piedmont,
in such immense numbers that at night the flowers were literally
covered with them. They had been traced from Coni, Raconi, Susa, &c.
A similar flight at the end of the last century is recorded by M. Louch in
the Memoirs of the Academy of Turin. The fact is the more worthy of
notice, because the caterpillars of this butterfly are not gregarious, but
solitary from the moment that they are hatched; and this instinct remains
dormant, while generation after generation passes away, till it suddenly
displays itself in full energy when their numbers happen to be in excess.
Not only peculiar species, but certain types, distinguish particular
countries; and there are groups, observes Kirby, which represent each
other in distant regions, whether in their form, their functions, or in
both. Thus the honey and wax of Europe, Asia, and Africa, are in each
case prepared by bees congenerous with our common hive-bee (Apis,
Latr.); while, in America, this genus is nowhere indigenous, but is
replaced by Melipona, Trigona, and Euglossa; and in New Holland by
656
a still different but undescribed type.928 The European bee (Apis mellifica),
although not a native of the new world, is now established both
in North and South America. It was introduced into the United States
by some of the early settlers, and has since overspread the vast forests
of the interior, building hives in the decayed trunks of trees. "The
Indians," says Irving, "consider them as the harbinger of the white
man, as the buffalo is of the red man, and say that in proportion as the
bee advances the Indian and the buffalo retire. It is said," continues
the same writer, "that the wild bee is seldom to be met with at any
great distance from the frontier, and that they have always been the
heralds of civilization, preceding it as it advanced from the Atlantic
borders. Some of the ancient settlers of the west even pretend to give
the very year when the honey-bee first crossed the Mississippi."929 The
same species is now also naturalized in Van Diemen's Land and New
Zealand.
As almost all insects are winged, they can readily spread themselves
wherever their progress is not opposed by uncongenial climates, or by
seas, mountains, and other physical impediments; and these barriers
they can sometimes surmount by abandoning themselves to violent
winds, which, as I before stated, when speaking of the dispersion of
seeds (p. 618.), may in a few hours carry them to very considerable
distances. On the Andes some sphinxes and flies have been observed
by Humboldt, at the height of 19,180 feet above the sea, and which
appeared to him to have been involuntarily carried into these regions
by ascending currents of air.930
White mentions a remarkable shower of aphides which seem to have
emigrated, with an east wind, from the great hop plantations of Kent
and Sussex, and blackened the shrubs and vegetables where they alighted
at Selbourne, spreading at the same time in great clouds all along the
vale from Farnham to Alton. These aphides are sometimes accompanied
by vast numbers of the common lady-bird (Coccinella septempunctata),
which feed upon them.931
It is remarkable, says Kirby, that many of the insects which are
occasionally observed to emigrate, as, for instance, the Libellulæ, Coccinellæ,
Carabi, Cicadæ, &c. are not usually social insects; but seem to
congregate, like swallows, merely for the purpose of emigration.932
Here, therefore, we have an example of an instinct developing itself on
certain rare emergencies, causing unsocial species to become gregarious
and to venture sometimes even to cross the ocean.
The armies of locusts which darken the air in Africa, and traverse
the globe from Turkey to our southern counties in England, are well
known to all. When the western gales sweep over the Pampas they
657
bear along with them myriads of insects of various kinds. As a proof
of the manner in which species may be thus diffused, I may mention
that when the Creole frigate was lying in the outer roads off Buenos
Ayres, in 1819, at the distance of six miles from the land, her decks and
rigging were suddenly covered by thousands of flies and grains of sand.
The sides of the vessel had just received a fresh coat of paint, to which
the insects adhered in such numbers as to spot and disfigure the vessel,
and to render it necessary partially to renew the paint.933 Captain W.
H. Smyth was obliged to repaint his vessel, the Adventure, in the Mediterranean,
from the same cause. He was on his way from Malta to
Tripoli, when a southern wind blowing from the coast of Africa, then
one hundred miles distant, drove such myriads of flies upon the fresh
paint, that not the smallest point was left unoccupied by insects.
To the southward of the river Plate, off Cape St. Antonio, and at the
distance of fifty miles from land, several large dragon-flies alighted on the
Adventure frigate, during Captain King's late expedition to the Straits of
Magellan. If the wind abates when insects are thus crossing the sea, the
most delicate species are not necessarily drowned; for many can repose
without sinking on the water. The slender long-legged tipulæ have been
seen standing on the surface of the sea, when driven out far from our
coast, and took wing immediately on being approached.934 Exotic beetles
are sometimes thrown on our shore, which revive after having been long
drenched in salt water; and the periodical appearance of some conspicuous
butterflies amongst us, after being unseen some for five others for fifty
years, has been ascribed, not without probability, to the agency of the
winds.
Inundations of rivers, observes Kirby, if they happen at any season except
in the depths of winter, always carry down a number of insects,
floating on the surface of bits of stick, weeds, &c.; so that when the waters
subside, the entomologist may generally reap a plentiful harvest. In the
dissemination, moreover, of these minute beings, as in that of plants, the
larger animals play their part. Insects are, in numberless instances, borne
along in the coats of animals, or the feathers of birds; and the eggs of
some species are capable, like seeds, of resisting the digestive powers of
the stomach, and after they are swallowed with herbage, may be ejected
again unharmed in the dung.
Geographical Distribution and Diffusion of Man.
I have reserved for the last some observations on the range and diffusion
of the human species over the earth, and the influence of man in
spreading other animals and plants, especially the terrestrial.
Many naturalists have amused themselves in speculating on the probable
birth-place of mankind, the point from which, if we assume the whole
human race to have descended from a single pair, the tide of emigration
658
must originally have proceeded. It has been always a favorite conjecture,
that this birth-place was situated within or near the tropics, where
perpetual summer reigns, and where fruits, herbs, and roots are plentifully
supplied throughout the year. The climate of these regions, it has been
said, is suited to a being born without any covering, and who had not yet
acquired the arts of building habitations or providing clothes.
Progress of Human Population.—"The hunter state," it has been argued,
"which Montesquieu placed the first, was probably only the second
stage to which mankind arrived; since so many arts must have been invented
to catch a salmon, or a deer, that society could no longer have
been in its infancy when they came into use."935 When regions where the
spontaneous fruits of the earth abound became overpeopled, men would
naturally diffuse themselves over the neighboring parts of the temperate
zone; but a considerable time would probably elapse before this event took
place; and it is possible, as a writer before cited observes, that in the
interval before the multiplication of their numbers and their increasing
wants had compelled them to emigrate, some arts to take animals were
invented, but far inferior to what we see practised at this day among
savages. As their habitations gradually advanced into the temperate
zone, the new difficulties they had to encounter would call forth by
degrees the spirit of invention, and the probability of such inventions
always rises with the number of people involved in the same necessity.936
A distinguished modern writer, who coincides for the most part in the
views above mentioned, has introduced one of the persons in his second
dialogue, as objecting to the theory of the human race having gradually
advanced from a savage to a civilized state, on the ground that "the first
man must have inevitably been destroyed by the elements or devoured by
savage beasts, so infinitely his superiors in physical force."937 He then
contends against the difficulty here started by various arguments, all of
which were, perhaps, superfluous; for if a philosopher is pleased to indulge
in conjectures on this subject, why should he not assign, as the original
seat of man, some one of those large islands within the tropics, which are
as free from large beasts of prey as Van Diemen's Land or Australia?
Here man may have remained for a period, peculiar to a single island,
just as some of the large anthropomorphous species are now limited to
one island within the tropics. In such a situation, the new-born race
might have lived in security, though far more helpless than the New Holland
savages, and might have found abundance of vegetable food. Colonies
may afterwards have been sent forth from this mother country,
and then the peopling of the earth may have proceeded according to the
hypothesis before alluded to.
To form a probable conjecture respecting the country from whence the
early civilization of India was derived, has been found almost as difficult
as to determine the original birth-place of the human race. That the
dawn of oriental civilization did not arise within the limits of the tropics,
659
is the conclusion to which Baron William von Humboldt has come after
much patient research into "the diversities of the structure of language
and their influence on the mental development of the human race." According
to him the ancient Zend country from whence the spread of
knowledge and the arts has been traced in a south-easterly direction, lay
to the north-west of the upper Indus.938
As to the time of the first appearance of man upon the earth, if we
are to judge from the discordance of opinion amongst celebrated chronologers,
not even a rude approximation has yet been made towards
determining a point of so much interest. The problem seems hitherto to
have baffled the curiosity of the antiquary, if possible, more completely
than the fixing on a geographical site for the original habitation of the
ancestors of the human race. The Chevalier Bunsen, in his elaborate
and philosophical work on Ancient Egypt,939 has satisfied not a few of the
learned, by an appeal to monumental inscriptions still extant, that the
successive dynasties of kings may be traced back without a break, to
Menes, and that the date of his reign would correspond with the year
3640 B. C. He supposes at the same time, what is most reasonable, that
the Egyptian people must have existed for a long period (probably at
least for five centuries), in their earlier and less settled state, before they
reached the point of civilization at which Menes consolidated them into
a great and united empire. This would carry us back to upwards of
4000 years B. C., or to an epoch coincident with that commonly set down
for the creation of the world in accordance with computations founded on
the combined ages of the successive antediluvian patriarchs. It follows
that the same epoch of Menes is anterior by a great many centuries to
the most ancient of the dates usually fixed upon for the Mosaic deluge.
The fact that no record or tradition of any great and overwhelming flood
has been detected in the mythology, or monumental annals of the Egyptians,
will suggest many reflections to a geologist who has weighed well
the evidence we possess of a variety of partial deluges which have happened
in districts not free like Egypt, for the last 3000 years, from earthquakes
and other causes of great aqueous catastrophes. The tales and
legends of calamitous floods preserved in Greece, Asia Minor, the southern
shores of the Baltic, China, Peru, and Chili, have, as we have seen, been
all of them handed down to us by the inhabitants of regions in which
the operation of natural causes in modern times, and the recurrence of a
succession of disastrous floods, afford us data for interpreting the meaning
of the obscure traditions of an illiterate age.940
In his learned treatise on ancient chronology, Dr. Hales has selected,
from a much greater number, a list of no less than 120 authors, all of
whom give a different period for the epoch of the creation of the world,
660
the extreme range of difference between them amounting to no less than
3268 years. It appears that even amongst authorities, who in England
are generally regarded, as orthodox, there is a variance, not of years or
of one or two centuries, but of upwards of a millennium, according as they
have preferred to follow the Hebrew, or the Samaritan, or the Greek versions
of the Mosaic writings. Can we then wonder that they who decipher
the monuments of Egypt, or the geologist who interprets the
earth's autobiography, should arrive at views respecting the date of an
ancient empire, or the age of our planet, irreconcilable with every one
of these numerous and conflicting chronologies? The want of agreement
amongst the learned in regard to the probable date of the deluge
of Noah is a source of far greater perplexity and confusion than our extreme
uncertainty as to the epoch of the creation,—the deluge being a
comparatively modern event, from which the repeopling of the earth and
the history of the present races of mankind is made to begin.
Naturalists have long felt that to render probable the received opinion
that all the leading varieties of the human family have originally sprung
from a single pair, (a doctrine against which there appears to me to be
no sound objection,) a much greater lapse of time is required for the
slow and gradual formation of races, (such as the Caucasian, Mongolian,
and Negro,) than is embraced in any of the popular systems of chronology.
The existence of two of those marked varieties above mentioned
can be traced back 3000 years before the present time, or to the painting
of pictures, preserved in the tombs or on the walls of buried temples in
Egypt. In these we behold the Negro and Caucasian physiognomies
portrayed as faithfully and in as strong contrast as if the likenesses of those
races had been taken yesterday. When we consider therefore the extreme
slowness of the changes, which climate and other modifying
causes have produced in modern times, we must allow for a vast series of
antecedent ages, in the course of which the long-continued influence of similar
external circumstances gave rise to peculiarities, probably increased in
many successive generations, until they were fixed by hereditary transmission.
The characteristic forms and features thus acquired by certain
tribes, may have been afterwards diffused by migration from a few centres
over wide continental spaces. The theory, therefore, that all the
races of man have come from one common stock receives support from
every investigation which forces us to expand our ideas of the duration
of past time, or which multiplies the number of years that have passed
away since the origin of man. Hitherto, geology has neither enlarged
nor circumscribed the "human period;" but simply proved that in the
history of animated nature it is comparatively modern, or the last of a
long series of antecedent epochs, in each of which the earth has been
successively peopled by distinct species of animals and plants.
In an early stage of society the necessity of hunting acts as a principle
of repulsion, causing men to spread with the greatest rapidity over a
country, until the whole is covered with scattered settlements. It has
been calculated that eight hundred acres of hunting-ground produce only
661
as much food as half an acre of arable land. When the game has been
in a great measure exhausted, and a state of pasturage succeeds, the
several hunter tribes, being already scattered, may multiply in a short
time into the greatest number which the pastoral state is capable of sustaining.
The necessity, says Brand, thus imposed upon the two savage
states, of dispersing themselves far and wide over the country, affords a
reason why, at a very early period, the worst parts of the earth may have
become inhabited.
But this reason, it may be said, is only applicable in as far as regards
the peopling of a continuous continent; whereas the smallest islands,
however remote from continents, have almost always been found inhabited
by man. St. Helena, it is true, afforded an exception; for when
that island was discovered in 1501, it was only inhabited by sea-fowl,
and occasionally by seals and turtles, and was covered with a forest of
trees and shrubs, all of species peculiar to it, with one or two exceptions,
and which seem to have been expressly created for this remote and
insulated spot.941
The islands also of Mauritius, Bourbon, Pitcairns, and Juan Fernandez,
and those of the Galapagos archipelago, one of which is seventy
miles long, were inhabited when first discovered, and, what is more
remarkable than all, the Falkland Islands, which together are 120 miles
in length by 60 in breadth, and abounding in food fit for the support
of man.
Drifting of canoes to vast distances.—But very few of the numerous
coral islets and volcanoes of the vast Pacific, capable of sustaining a
few families of men, have been found untenanted; and we have, therefore,
to inquire whence and by what means, if all the members of the
great human family have had one common source, could those savages
have migrated. Cook, Forster, and others, have remarked that parties
of savages in their canoes must have often lost their way, and must
have been driven on distant shores, where they were forced to remain,
deprived both of the means and of the requisite intelligence for returning
to their own country. Thus Captain Cook found on the island of
Wateoo three inhabitants of Otaheite, who had been drifted thither in
a canoe, although the distance between the two isles is 550 miles. In
1696, two canoes, containing thirty persons, who had left Ancorso, were
thrown by contrary winds and storms on the island of Samar, one of
the Philippines, at a distance of 800 miles. In 1721, two canoes, one
of which contained twenty-four, and the other six persons, men, women,
and children, were drifted from an island called Farroilep to the island
of Guaham, one of the Marians, a distance of 200 miles.942
Kotzebue, when investigating the Coral Isles of Radack, at the eastern
extremity of the Caroline Isles, became acquainted with a person of
the name of Kadu, who was a native of Ulea, an isle 1500 miles distant,
from which he had been drifted with a party. Kadu and three of his
662
countrymen one day left Ulea in a sailing boat, when a violent storm
arose, and drove them out of their course: they drifted about the open
sea for eight months, according to their reckoning by the moon, making
a knot on a cord at every new moon. Being expert fishermen, they
subsisted entirely on the produce of the sea; and when the rain fell, laid
in as much fresh water as they had vessels to contain it. "Kadu,"
says Kotzebue, "who was the best diver, frequently went down to the
bottom of the sea, where it is well known that the water is not so salt,
with a cocoa-nut shell, with only a small opening."943 When these
unfortunate men reached the isles of Radack, every hope and almost
every feeling had died within them; their sail had long been destroyed,
their canoe had long been the sport of winds and waves, and they
were picked up by the inhabitants of Aur in a state of insensibility;
but by the hospitable care of those islanders they soon recovered, and
were restored to perfect health.944
Captain Beechey, in his voyage to the Pacific, fell in with some natives
of the Coral Islands, who had in a similar manner been carried to a
great distance from their native country. They had embarked, to the
number of 150 souls, in three double canoes, from Anaa, or Chain
Island, situated about three hundred miles to the eastward of Otaheite.
They were overtaken by the monsoon, which dispersed the canoes; and
after driving them about the ocean, left them becalmed, so that a great
number of persons perished. Two of the canoes were never heard of;
but the other was drifted from one uninhabited island to another, at
each of which the voyagers obtained a few provisions; and at length,
after having wandered for a distance of 600 miles, they were found and
carried to their home in the Blossom.945
Mr. Crawfurd informs me that there are several well-authenticated
accounts of canoes having been drifted from Sumatra to Madagascar,
and by such causes a portion of the Malayan language, with some
useful plants, have been transferred to that island, which is principally
peopled by negroes.
The space traversed in some of these instances was so great, that
similar accidents might suffice to transport canoes from various parts of
Africa to the shores of South America, or from Spain to the Azores,
and thence to North America; so that man, even in a rude state of
society, is liable to be scattered involuntarily by the winds and waves
over the globe, in a manner singularly analogous to that in which many
plants and animals are diffused. We ought not, then, to wonder, that
during the ages required for some tribes of the human race to attain
that advanced stage of civilization which empowers the navigator to
cross the ocean in all directions with security, the whole earth should
663
have become the abode of rude tribes of hunters and fishers. Were
the whole of mankind now cut off, with the exception of one family,
inhabiting the old or new continent, or Australia, or even some coral
islet of the Pacific, we might expect their descendants, though they
should never become more enlightened than the South Sea Islanders or
the Esquimaux, to spread in the course of ages over the whole earth,
diffused partly by the tendency of population to increase, in a limited
district, beyond the means of subsistence, and partly by the accidental
drifting of canoes by tides and currents to distant shores.
Involuntary Influence of Man in diffusing Animals and Plants.
Many of the general remarks which have been made respecting the
influence of man in spreading or in checking the diffusion of plants
apply equally to his relations with the animal kingdom. On a future
occasion I shall be led to speak of the instrumentality of our species in
naturalizing useful animals and plants in new regions, when explaining
my views of the effects which the spreading and increase of certain
species exert in the extirpation of others. At present I shall confine
myself to a few remarks on the involuntary aid which man lends to the
dissemination of species.
In the mammiferous class our influence is chiefly displayed in increasing
the number of quadrupeds which are serviceable to us, and in
exterminating or reducing the number of those which are noxious.
Sometimes, however, we unintentionally promote the multiplication of
inimical species, as when we introduced the rat, which was not indigenous
in the new world, into all parts of America. They have been conveyed
over in ships, and now infest a great multitude of islands and parts of
that continent. In like manner the Norway rat (Mus decumanus)
has been imported into England, where it plunders our property in ships
and houses.
Among birds, the house sparrow may be cited as a species known to
have extended its range with the tillage of the soil. During the last
century it has spread gradually over Asiatic Russia towards the north
and east, always following the progress of cultivation. It made its first
appearance on the Irtisch in Tobolsk, soon after the Russians had
ploughed the land. It came in 1735 up the Obi to Beresow, and four
years after to Naryn, about fifteen degrees of longitude farther east. In
1710, it had been seen in the higher parts of the coast of the Lena, in the
government of Irkutzk. In all these places it is now common, but is not
yet found in the uncultivated regions of Kamtschatka.946
The great viper (Fer de lance), a species no less venomous than the
rattlesnake, which now ravages Martinique and St. Lucia, was accidentally
introduced by man, and exists in no other part of the West Indies.
Many parasitic insects which attack our persons, and some of which
are supposed to be peculiar to our species, have been carried into all parts
664
of the earth, and have as high a claim as man to a universal geographical
distribution.
A great variety of insects have been transported in ships from one
country to another, especially in warmer latitudes. The European house-fly
has been introduced in this way into all the South Sea Islands.
Notwithstanding the coldness of our climate in England we have been
unable to prevent the cockroach (Blatta orientalis) from entering and
diffusing itself in our ovens and kneading troughs, and availing itself
of the artificial warmth which we afford. It is well known also, that
beetles, and many other kinds of ligniperdous insects, have been introduced
into Great Britain in timber; especially several North American
species. "The commercial relations," says Malte-Brun947, "between France
and India have transported from the latter country the aphis, which
destroys the apple tree, and two sorts of Neuroptera, the Lucifuga and
Flavicola, mostly confined to Provence and the neighbourhood of Bourdeaux,
where they devour the timber in the houses and naval arsenals."
Among mollusks we may mention the Teredo navalis, which is a
native of equatorial seas, but which, by adhering to the bottom of ships,
was transported to Holland, where it has been most destructive to vessels
and piles. The same species has also become naturalized in England,
and other countries enjoying an extensive commerce. Bulimus undatus,
a land species of considerable size, native of Jamaica and other West Indian
islands, has been imported, adhering to tropical timber, into Liverpool;
and, as I learn from Mr. Broderip, is now naturalized in the woods
near that town.
In all these and innumerable other instances we may regard the involuntary
agency of man as strictly analogous to that of the inferior animals.
Like them, we unconsciously contribute to extend or limit the
geographical range and numbers of certain species, in obedience to general
rules in the economy of nature, which are for the most part beyond
our control.

665</div></body></text></TEI>