<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="123">CHAPTER I.
Discovery of the Organs of Voluntary
Motion.
Sect. 1.—Knowledge of Galen and his
Predecessors.
IN the earliest conceptions
which men entertained of their power of moving their own members, they
probably had no thought of any mechanism or organization by which this
was effected. The foot and the hand, no less than the head, were seen
to be endowed with life; and this pervading life seemed sufficiently
to explain the power of motion in each part of the frame, without its
being held necessary to seek out a special seat of the will, or
instruments by which its impulses were made effective. But the
slightest inspection of dissected animals showed that their limbs were
formed of a curious and complex collection of cordage, and
communications of various kinds, running along and connecting the
bones of the skeleton. These cords and communications we now
distinguish as muscles, nerves, veins, arteries, &c.; and among
these, we assign to the muscles the office of moving the parts to
which they are attached, as cords move the parts of a machine. Though
this action of the muscles on the bones may now appear very obvious,
it was, probably, not at first discerned. It is observed that Homer,
who describes the wounds which are inflicted in his battles with so
much apparent anatomical precision, nowhere employs the word
muscle. And even Hippocrates of Cos, the most celebrated
physician of antiquity, is held to have had no distinct conception of
such an organ.1 He always employs the word flesh
when he means muscle, and the first explanation of the latter
word (μῦς) occurs in a spurious work ascribed to him. For nerves,
sinews, ligaments,2 he used indiscriminately the same terms;
(τόνος or νεῦρον;) and of these nerves (νεῦρα) he asserts that they
contract the limbs. Nor do we find much more distinctness on this
subject even in Aristotle, a generation or two later. “The origin of
the νεῦρα,” he says,3 “is from the heart; they connect 439 the bones, and
surround the joints.” It is clear that he means here the muscles, and
therefore it is with injustice that he has been accused of the gross
error of deriving the nerves from the heart. And he is held to have
really had the merit4 of discovering the nerves of sensation,
which he calls the “canals of the brain” (πόροι τοῦ ἐγκεφάλου); but
the analysis of the mechanism of motion is left by him almost
untouched. Perhaps his want of sound mechanical notions, and his
constant straining after verbal generalities, and systematic
classifications of the widest kind, supply the true account of his
thus missing the solution of one of the simplest problems of
Anatomy.
1 Sprengel, Geschichte der
Arzneikunde, i. 382.
2 Sprengel, Gesch. Arz. i.
385.
3 Hist. Anim. iii. 5.
4 Ib. i. 456.
In this, however, as in other subjects, his immediate predecessors
were far from remedying the deficiencies of his doctrines. Those who
professed to study physiology and medicine were, for the most part,
studious only to frame some general system of abstract principles,
which might give an appearance of connexion and profundity to their
tenets. In this manner the successors of Hippocrates became a medical
school, of great note in its day, designated as the Dogmatic
school;5 in opposition to which arose an
Empiric sect, who professed to deduce their modes of cure, not
from theoretical dogmas, but from experience. These rival parties
prevailed principally in Asia Minor and Egypt, during the time of
Alexander’s successors,—a period rich in names, but poor in
discoveries; and we find no clear evidence of any decided advance in
anatomy, such as we are here attempting to trace.
5 Sprengel, Gesch. Arz. i.
583.
The victories of Lucullus and Pompeius, in Greece and Asia, made
the Romans acquainted with the Greek philosophy; and the consequence
soon was, that shoals of philosophers, rhetoricians, poets, and
physicians6 streamed from Greece, Asia Minor, and
Egypt, to Rome and Italy, to traffic their knowledge and their arts
for Roman wealth. Among these, was one person whose name makes a great
figure in the history of medicine, Asclepiades of Prusa in Bithynia.
This man appears to have been a quack, with the usual endowments of
his class;—boldness, singularity, a contemptuous rejection of
all previously esteemed opinions, a new classification of diseases, a
new list of medicines, and the assertion of some wonderful cures. He
would not, on such accounts, deserve a place in the history of
science, but that he became the founder of a new school, the
Methodic, which professed to hold itself separate both from the
Dogmatics and the Empirics.
6 Sprengel, Gesch. Arz. ii.
5.
440 I have
noticed these schools of medicine, because, though I am not able to
state distinctly their respective merits in the cultivation of
anatomy, a great progress in that science was undoubtedly made during
their domination, of which the praise must, I conceive, be in some way
divided among them. The amount of this progress we are able to
estimate, when we come to the works of Galen, who flourished under the
Antonines, and died about a.d. 203. The
following passage from his works will show that this progress in
knowledge was not made without the usual condition of laborious and
careful experiment, while it implies the curious fact of such
experiment being conducted by means of family tradition and
instruction, so as to give rise to a caste of dissectors. In
the opening of his Second Book On Anatomical Manipulations, he
speaks thus of his predecessors: “I do not blame the ancients, who did
not write books on anatomical manipulation; though I praise Marinus,
who did. For it was superfluous for them to compose such records for
themselves or others, while they were, from their childhood, exercised
by their parents in dissecting, just as familiarly as in writing and
reading; so that there was no more fear of their forgetting their
anatomy, than of forgetting their alphabet. But when grown men, as
well as children, were taught, this thorough discipline fell off; and,
the art being carried out of the family of the Asclepiads, and
declining by repeated transmission, books became necessary for the
student.”
That the general structure of the animal frame, as composed of
bones and muscles, was known with great accuracy before the time of
Galen, is manifest from the nature of the mistakes and deficiencies of
his predecessors which he finds it necessary to notice. Thus he
observes, that some anatomists have made one muscle into two, from its
having two heads;—that they have overlooked some of the muscles
in the face of an ape, in consequence of not skinning the animal with
their own hands;—and the like. Such remarks imply that the
current knowledge of this kind was tolerably complete. Galen’s own
views of the general mechanical structure of an animal are very clear
and sound. The skeleton, he observes, discharges7 the office of the
pole of a tent, or the walls of a house. With respect to the action of
the muscles, his views were anatomically and mechanically correct; in
some instances, he showed what this action was, by severing the
muscle.8 He himself added considerably to the
existing knowledge of 441 this subject; and his discoveries and
descriptions, even of very minute parts of the muscular system, are
spoken of with praise by modern anatomists.9
7 De Anatom. Administ. i.
2.
8 Sprengel, ii. 157.
9 Sprengel, ii. 150.
We may consider, therefore, that the doctrine of the muscular
system, as a collection of cords and sheets, by the contraction of
which the parts of the body are moved and supported, was firmly
established, and completely followed into detail, by Galen and his
predecessors. But there is another class of organs connected with
voluntary motion, the nerves, and we must for a moment trace the
opinions which prevailed respecting these. Aristotle, as we have said,
noticed some of the nerves of sensation. But Herophilus, who lived in
Egypt in the time of the first Ptolemy, distinguished nerves as the
organs of the will,10 and Rufus, who lived in the time of
Trajan,11 divides the nerves into sensitive and
motive, and derives them all from the brain. But this did not imply
that men had yet distinguished the nerves from the muscles. Even Galen
maintained that every muscle consists of a bundle of nerves and
sinews.12 But the important points, the necessity
of the nerve, and the origination of all this apparatus of motion from
the brain, he insists upon with great clearness and force. Thus he
proved the necessity experimentally, by cutting through some of the
bundles of nerves,13 and thus preventing the corresponding
motions. And it is, he says,14 allowed by all,
both physicians and philosophers, that where the origin of the nerve
is, there the seat of the soul (ἡγημονικὸν τῆς ψυχῆς) must be: now
this, he adds, is in the brain, and not in the heart.
10 Ib. i. 534.
11 Ib. ii. 67.
12 Ibid. ii. 152. Galen, De Motu
Musc., p. 553.
13 Ib. 157.
14 De Hippocr. et Plat. Dog.
viii. 1.
Thus the general construction and arrangement of the organization
by which voluntary motion is effected, was well made out at the time
of Galen, and is found distinctly delivered in his works. We cannot,
perhaps, justly ascribe any large portion of the general discovery to
him: indeed, the conception of the mechanism of the skeleton and
muscles was probably so gradually unfolded in the minds of anatomical
students, that it would be difficult, even if we knew the labors of
each person, to select one, as peculiarly the author of the discovery.
But it is clear that all those who did materially contribute to the
establishment of this doctrine, must have possessed the qualifications
which we find in Galen for such a task; namely, clear mechanical views
of what the 442
tensions of collections of strings could do, and an exact practical
acquaintance with the muscular cordage which exists in the animal
frame;—in short, in this as in other instances of real advance
in science, there must have been clear ideas and real facts, unity of
thought and extent of observation, brought into contact.
Sect. 2.—Recognition of Final Causes in
Physiology. Galen.
There is one idea which the
researches of the physiologist and the anatomist so constantly force
upon him, that he cannot help assuming it as one of the guides of his
speculations; I mean, the idea of a purpose, or, as it is
called in Aristotelian phrase, a final cause, in the
arrangements of the animal frame. It is impossible to doubt that the
motive nerves run along the limbs, in order that they may
convey to the muscles the impulses of the will; and that the muscles
are attached to the bones, in order that they may move and
support them. This conviction prevails so steadily among anatomists,
that even when the use of any part is altogether unknown, it is still
taken for granted that it has some use. The developement of this
conviction,—of a purpose in the parts of animals,—of a
function to which each portion of the organization is
subservient,—contributed greatly to the progress of physiology;
for it constantly urged men forwards in their researches respecting
each organ, till some definite view of its purpose was obtained. The
assumption of hypothetical final causes in Physics may have been, as
Bacon asserts it to have been, prejudicial to science; but the
assumption of unknown final causes in Physiology, has given rise to
the science. The two branches of speculation, Physics and Physiology,
were equally led, by every new phenomenon, to ask their question,
“Why?” But, in the former case, “why” meant “through what cause?” in
the latter, “for what end?” And though it may be possible to introduce
into physiology the doctrine of efficient causes, such a step can
never obliterate the obligations which the science owes to the
pervading conception of a purpose contained in all organization.
This conception makes its appearance very early. Indeed, without
any special study of our structure, the thought, that we are fearfully
and wonderfully made, forces itself upon men, with a mysterious
impressiveness, as a suggestion of our Maker. In this bearing, the
thought is developed to a considerable extent in the well-known
passage in Xenophon’s Conversations of Socrates. Nor did it
ever lose its hold on sober-minded and instructed men. The Epicureans,
indeed, 443 held
that the eye was not made for seeing, nor the ear for hearing; and
Asclepiades, whom we have already mentioned as an impudent pretender,
adopted this wild dogma.15 Such assertions required no labor. “It
is easy,” says Galen,16 “for people like Asclepiades, when they
come to any difficulty, to say that Nature has worked to no purpose.”
The great anatomist himself pursues his subject in a very different
temper. In a well-known passage, he breaks out into an enthusiastic
scorn of the folly of the atheistical notions.17 “Try,” he says,
“if you can imagine a shoe made with half the skill which appears in
the skin of the foot.” Some one had spoken of a structure of the human
body which he would have preferred to that which it now has. “See,”
Galen exclaims, after pointing out the absurdity of the imaginary
scheme, “see what brutishness there is in this wish. But if I were to
spend more words on such cattle, reasonable men might blame me for
desecrating my work, which I regard as a religious hymn in honor of
the Creator.”
15 Sprengel, ii. 15.
16 De Usu Part. v. 5, (on the
kidneys.)
17 De Usu Part. iii. 10.
Galen was from the first highly esteemed as an anatomist. He was
originally of Pergamus; and after receiving the instructions of many
medical and philosophical professors, and especially of those of
Alexandria, which was then the metropolis of the learned and
scientific world, he came to Rome, where his reputation was soon so
great as to excite the envy and hatred of the Roman physicians. The
emperors Marcus Aurelius and Lucius Verus would have retained him near
them; but he preferred pursuing his travels, directed principally by
curiosity. When he died, he left behind him numerous works, all of
them of great value for the light they throw on the history of anatomy
and medicine; and these were for a long period the storehouse of all
the most important anatomical knowledge which the world possessed. In
the time of intellectual barrenness and servility, among the Arabians
and the Europeans of the dark ages, the writings of Galen had almost
unquestioned authority;18 and it was only by an uncommon effort
of independent thinking that Abdollatif ventured to assert, that even
Galen’s assertions must give way to the evidence of the senses. In
more modern times, when Vesalius, in the sixteenth century, accused
Galen of mistakes, he drew upon himself the hostility of the whole
body of physicians. Yet the mistakes were such as might have 444 been pointed out and
confessed19 without acrimony, if, in times of
revolution, mildness and moderation were possible; but an impatience
of the superstition of tradition on the part of the innovators, and an
alarm of the subversion of all recognized truths on the part of the
established teachers, inflame and pervert all such discussions.
Vesalius’s main charge against Galen is, that his dissections were
performed upon animals, and not upon the human body. Galen himself
speaks of the dissection of apes as a very familiar employment, and
states that he killed them by drowning. The natural difficulties
which, in various ages, have prevented the unlimited prosecution of
human dissection, operated strongly among the ancients, and it would
have been difficult, under such circumstances, to proceed more
judiciously than Galen did.
18 Sprengel, ii. 359.
19 Cuv. Leçons sur l’Hist. des Sc.
Nat. p. 25.
I shall now proceed to the history of the discovery of another and
less obvious function, the circulation of the blood, which belongs to
modern times.
</div></body></text></TEI>