<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="3"> 

CHAPTER IV.
Of the Colligation of Facts.


Aphorism VII.
Science begins with common observation of facts; but
even at this stage, requires that the observations be precise.
Hence the sciences which depend upon space and number
were the earliest formed. After common observation, come
Scientific Observation and Experiment.
Aphorism VIII.
The Conceptions by which Facts are bound together, are
suggested by the sagacity of discoverers. This sagacity cannot
be taught. It commonly succeeds by guessing; and this
success seems to consist in framing several tentative
hypotheses and selecting the right one. But a supply of
appropriate hypotheses cannot be constructed by rule, nor without
inventive talent.
Aphorism IX.
The truth of tentative hypotheses must be tested by their
application to facts. The discoverer must be ready, carefully
to try his hypotheses in this manner, and to reject
them if they will not bear the test, in spite of indolence and
vanity.

1. FACTS
such as the last Chapter speaks of are, by
means of such Conceptions as are described in
the preceding Chapter, bound together so as to give
rise to those general Propositions of which Science
consists. Thus the Facts that the planets revolve 60
about the sun in certain periodic times and at certain
distances, are included and connected in Kepler’s Law,
by means of such Conceptions as the squares of numbers,
the cubes of distances, and the proportionality of
these quantities. Again the existence of this proportion
in the motions of any two planets, forms a set of
Facts which may all be combined by means of the
Conception of a certain central accelerating force, as
was proved by Newton. The whole of our physical
knowledge consists in the establishment of such
propositions; and in all such cases, Facts are bound
together by the aid of suitable Conceptions. This part
of the formation of our knowledge I have called the
Colligation of Facts: and we may apply this term to
every case in which, by an act of the intellect, we
establish a precise connexion among the phenomena
which are presented to our senses. The knowledge of
such connexions, accumulated and systematized, is
Science. On the steps by which science is thus collected
from phenomena we shall proceed now to make
a few remarks.
2. Science begins with Common Observation of
facts, in which we are not conscious of any peculiar
discipline or habit of thought exercised in observing.
Thus the common perceptions of the appearances and
recurrences of the celestial luminaries, were the first
steps of Astronomy: the obvious cases in which bodies
fall or are supported, were the beginning of Mechanics;
the familiar aspects of visible things, were the origin
of Optics; the usual distinctions of well-known plants,
first gave rise to Botany. Facts belonging to such
parts of our knowledge are noticed by us, and accumulated
in our memories, in the common course of our
habits, almost without our being aware that we are
observing and collecting facts. Yet such facts may
lead to many scientific truths; for instance, in the first
stages of Astronomy (as we have shown in the History)
such facts led to Methods of Intercalation and Rules
of the Recurrence of Eclipses. In succeeding stages
of science, more especial attention and preparation on
the part of the observer, and a selection of certain 61
kinds of facts, becomes necessary; but there is an early
period in the progress of knowledge at which man is
a physical philosopher, without seeking to be so, or
being aware that he is so.
3. But in all stages of the progress, even in that
early one of which we have just spoken, it is necessary,
in order that the facts may be fit materials of
any knowledge, that they should be decomposed into
Elementary Facts, and that these should be observed
with precision. Thus, in the first infancy of astronomy,
the recurrence of phases of the moon, of places
of the sun’s rising and setting, of planets, of eclipses,
was observed to take place at intervals of certain definite
numbers of days, and in a certain exact order;
and thus it was, that the observations became portions
of astronomical science. In other cases, although the
facts were equally numerous, and their general aspect
equally familiar, they led to no science, because their
exact circumstances were not apprehended. A vague
and loose mode of looking at facts very easily observable,
left men for a long time under the belief that a
body, ten times as heavy as another, falls ten times as
fast;—that objects immersed in water are always magnified,
without regard to the form of the surface;—that
the magnet exerts an irresistible force;—that
crystal is always found associated with ice;—and the
like. These and many others are examples how blind
and careless men can be, even in observation of the
plainest and commonest appearances; and they show
us that the mere faculties of perception, although
constantly exercised upon innumerable objects, may long
fail in leading to any exact knowledge.
4. If we further inquire what was the favourable
condition through which some special classes of facts
were, from the first, fitted to become portions of science,
we shall find it to have been principally this;—that
these facts were considered with reference to the
Ideas of Time, Number, and Space, which are Ideas
possessing peculiar definiteness and precision; so that
with regard to them, confusion and indistinctness are
hardly possible. The interval from new moon to new 62
moon was always a particular number of days: the
sun in his yearly course rose and set near to a known
succession of distant objects: the moon’s path passed
among the stars in a certain order:—these are observations
in which mistake and obscurity are not likely
to occur, if the smallest degree of attention is bestowed
upon the task. To count a number is, from the first
opening of man’s mental faculties, an operation which
no science can render more precise. The relations of
space are nearest to those of number in obvious and
universal evidence. Sciences depending upon these
Ideas arise with the first dawn of intellectual civilization.
But few of the other Ideas which man employs
in the acquisition of knowledge possess this clearness
in their common use. The Idea of Resemblance may
be noticed, as coming next to those of Space and Number
in original precision; and the Idea of Cause, in a
certain vague and general mode of application, sufficient
for the purposes of common life, but not for the
ends of science, exercises a very extensive influence
over men’s thoughts. But the other Ideas on which
science depends, with the Conceptions which arise out
of them, are not unfolded till a much later period of
intellectual progress; and therefore, except in such
limited cases as I have noticed, the observations of
common spectators and uncultivated nations, however
numerous or varied, are of little or no effect in giving
rise to Science.
5. Let us now suppose that, besides common everyday
perception of facts, we turn our attention to some
other occurrences and appearances, with a design of
obtaining from them speculative knowledge. This
process is more peculiarly called Observation, or, when
we ourselves occasion the facts, Experiment. But the
same remark which we have already made, still holds
good here. These facts can be of no value, except
they are resolved into those exact Conceptions which
contain the essential circumstances of the case. They
must be determined, not indeed necessarily, as has
sometimes been said, ‘according to Number, Weight,
and Measure;’ for, as we have endeavoured to show 63
in the preceding Books4,
there are many other
Conceptions to which phenomena may be subordinated,
quite different from these, and yet not at all less
definite and precise. But in order that the facts obtained
by observation and experiment may be capable of
being used in furtherance of our exact and solid knowledge,
they must be apprehended and analysed according to some
Conceptions which, applied for this purpose, give distinct
and definite results, such as can be
steadily taken hold of and reasoned from; that is, the
facts must be referred to Clear and Appropriate Ideas,
according to the manner in which we have already explained
this condition of the derivation of our knowledge. The
phenomena of light, when they are such
as to indicate sides in the ray, must be referred to the
Conception of polarization; the phenomena of mixture,
when there is an alteration of qualities as well
as quantities, must be combined by a Conception of
elementary composition. And thus, when mere position,
and number, and resemblance, will no longer answer the
purpose of enabling us to connect the facts,
we call in other Ideas, in such cases more efficacious,
though less obvious.</div></body></text></TEI>