<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zoonomia Vol I</title><author>Darwin, Erasmus (1731-1802)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1794</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="section" n="25">SECT. XXV.
OF THE STOMACH AND INTESTINES.

1. Of swallowing our food. Ruminating
  animals. 2. Action of the stomach.
3. Action of the intestines. Irritative
  motions connected with these. 4. Effects
  of repletion. 5. Stronger action of the
  stomach and intestines from more stimulating food. 6. Their action inverted by still greater
  stimuli. Or by disgustful ideas. Or by volition. 7. Other glands strengthen or invert their
  motions by sympathy. 8. Vomiting
  performed by intervals. 9. Inversion of
  the cutaneous absorbents. 10. Increased
  secretion of bile and pancreatic juice. 11. Inversion of the lacteals. 12. And of the bile-ducts. 13. Case of a cholera. 14. Further account of the inversion of
  lacteals. 15. Iliac passions. Valve of
  the colon. 16. Cure of the iliac
  passion. 17. Pain of gall-stone
  distinguished from pain of the stomach. Gout of the stomach from torpor,
  from inflammation. Intermitting pulse owing to indigestion. To overdose
  of foxglove. Weak pulse from emetics. Death from a blow on the stomach.
  From gout of the stomach.

1. The throat, stomach, and intestines, may
  be considered as one great gland; which like the lacrymal sack above
  mentioned, neither begins nor ends in the circulation. Though the act of
  masticating our aliment belongs to the sensitive class of motions, for
  the pleasure of its taste induces the muscles of the jaw into action; yet
  the deglutition of it when masticated is generally, if not always, an
  irritative motion, occasioned by the application of the food already
  masticated to the origin of the pharinx; in the same manner as we often
  swallow our spittle without attending to it.
The ruminating class of animals have the power to invert the motion of
  their gullet, and of their first stomach, from the stimulus of this
  aliment, when it is a little further prepared; as is their daily practice
  in chewing the cud; and appears to the eye of any one, who attends to
  them, whilst they are employed in this second mastication of their
  food.
2. When our natural aliment arrives into the
  stomach, this organ is simulated into its proper vermicular action; which
  beginning at the upper orifice of it, and terminating at the lower one,
  gradually mixes together and pushes forwards the digesting materials into
  the intestine beneath it.
At the same time the glands, that supply the gastric juices, which are
  necessary to promote the chemical part of the process of digestion, are
  stimulated to discharge their contained fluids, and to separate a further
  supply from the blood-vessels: and the lacteals or lymphatics, which open
  their mouths into the stomach, are stimulated into action, and take up
  some part of the digesting materials.
3. The remainder of these digesting materials
  is carried forwards into the upper intestines, and stimulates them into
  their peristaltic motion similar to that of the stomach; which continues
  gradually to mix the changing materials, and pass them along through the
  valve of the colon to the excretory end of this great gland, the
  sphincter ani.
The digesting materials produce a flow of bile, and of pancreatic
  juice, as they pass along the duodenum, by stimulating the excretory
  ducts of the liver and pancreas, which terminate in that intestine: and
  other branches of the absorbent or lymphatic system, called lacteals, are
  excited to drink up, as it passes, those parts of the digesting
  materials, that are proper for their purpose, by its stimulus on their
  mouths.
4. When the stomach and intestines are thus
  filled with their proper food, not only the motions of the gastric
  glands, the pancreas, liver, and lacteal vessels, are excited into
  action; but at the same time the whole tribe of irritative motions are
  exerted with greater energy, a greater degree of warmth, colour,
  plumpness, and moisture, is given to the skin from the increased action
  of those glands called capillary vessels; pleasurable sensation is
  excited, the voluntary motions are less easily exerted, and at length
  suspended; and sleep succeeds, unless it be prevented by the stimulus of
  surrounding objects, or by voluntary exertion, or by an acquired habit,
  which was originally produced by one or other of these circumstances, as
  is explained in Sect. XXI. on Drunkenness.
At this time also, as the blood-vessels become replete with chyle,
  more urine is separated into the bladder, and less of it is reabsorbed;
  more mucus poured into the cellular membranes, and less of it reabsorbed;
  the pulse becomes fuller, and softer, and in general quicker. The reason
  why less urine and cellular mucus is absorbed after a full meal with
  sufficient drink is owing to the blood-vessels being fuller: hence one
  means to promote absorption is to decrease the resistance by emptying the
  vessels by venesection. From this decreased absorption the urine becomes
  pale as well as copious, and the skin appears plump as well as
  florid.
By daily repetition of these movements they all become connected
  together, and make a diurnal circle of irritative action, and if one of
  this chain be disturbed, the whole is liable to be put into disorder. See
  Sect. XX. on Vertigo.
5. When the stomach and intestines receive a
  quantity of food, whose stimulus is greater than usual, all their
  motions, and those of the glands and lymphatics, are stimulated into
  stronger action than usual, and perform their offices with greater vigour
  and in less time: such are the effects of certain quantities of spice or
  of vinous spirit.
6. But if the quantity or duration of these
  stimuli are still further increased, the stomach and throat are
  stimulated into a motion, whose direction is contrary to the natural one
  above described; and they regurgitate the materials, which they contain,
  instead of carrying them forwards. This retrograde motion of the stomach
  may be compared to the stretchings of wearied limbs the contrary way, and
  is well elucidated by the following experiment. Look earnestly for a
  minute or two on an area an inch square of pink silk, placed in a strong
  light, the eye becomes fatigued, the colour becomes faint, and at length
  vanishes, for the fatigued eye can no longer be stimulated into direct
  motions; then on closing the eye a green spectrum will appear in it,
  which is a colour directly contrary to pink, and which will appear and
  disappear repeatedly, like the efforts in vomiting. See Section XXIX. 11.
Hence all those drugs, which by their bitter or astringent stimulus
  increase the action of the stomach, as camomile and white vitriol, if
  their quantity is increased above a certain dose become emetics.
These inverted motions of the stomach and throat are generally
  produced from the stimulus of unnatural food, and are attended with the
  sensation of nausea or sickness: but as this sensation is again connected
  with an idea of the distasteful food, which induced it; so an idea of
  nauseous food will also sometimes excite the action of nausea; and that
  give rise by association to the inversion of the motions of the stomach
  and throat. As some, who have had horse-flesh or dogs-flesh given them
  for beef or mutton, are said to have vomited many hours afterwards, when
  they have been told of the imposition.
I have been told of a person, who had gained a voluntary command over
  these inverted motions of the stomach and throat, and supported himself
  by exhibiting this curiosity to the public. At these exhibitions he
  swallowed a pint of red rough gooseberries, and a pint of white smooth
  ones, brought them up in small parcels into his mouth, and restored them
  separately to the spectators, who called for red or white as they
  pleased, till the whole were redelivered.
7. At the same time that these motions of the
  stomach and throat are stimulated into inversion, some of the other
  irritative motions, that had acquired more immediate connexions with the
  stomach, as those of the gastric glands, are excited into stronger action
  by this association; and some other of these motions, which are more
  easily excited, as those of the gastric lymphatics, are inverted by their
  association with the retrograde motions of the stomach, and regurgitate
  their contents, and thus a greater quantity of mucus, and of lymph, or
  chyle, is poured into the stomach, and thrown up along with its
  contents.
8. These inversions of the motion of the
  stomach in vomiting are performed by intervals, for the same reason that
  many other motions are reciprocally exerted and relaxed; for during the
  time of exertion the stimulus, or sensation, which caused this exertion,
  is not perceived; but begins to be perceived again, as soon as the
  exertion ceases, and is some time in again producing its effect. As
  explained in Sect. XXXIV. on Volition, where it
  is shewn, that the contractions of the fibres, and the sensation of pain,
  which occasioned that exertion, cannot exist at the same time. The
  exertion ceases from another cause also, which is the exhaustion of the
  sensorial power of the part, and these two causes frequently operate
  together.
9. At the times of these inverted efforts of
  the stomach not only the lymphatics, which open their mouths into the
  stomach, but those of the skin also, are for a time inverted; for sweats
  are sometimes pushed out during the efforts of vomiting without an
  increase of heat.
10. But if by a greater stimulus the motions
  of the stomach are inverted still more violently or more permanently, the
  duodenum has its peristaltic motions inverted at the same time by their
  association with those of the stomach; and the bile and pancreatic juice,
  which it contains, are by the inverted motions brought up into the
  stomach, and discharged along with its contents; while a greater quantity
  of bile and pancreatic juice is poured into this intestine; as the
  glands, that secrete them, are by their association with the motions of
  the intestine excited into stronger action than usual.
11. The other intestines are by association
  excited into more powerful action, while the lymphatics, that open their
  mouths into them, suffer an inversion of their motions corresponding with
  the lymphatics of the stomach, and duodenum; which with a part of the
  abundant secretion of bile is carried downwards, and contributes both to
  stimulate the bowels, and to increase the quantity of the evacuations.
  This inversion of the motion of the lymphatics appears from the quantity
  of chyle, which comes away by stools; which is otherwise absorbed as soon
  as produced, and by the immense quantity of thin fluid, which is
  evacuated along with it.
12. But if the stimulus, which inverts the
  stomach, be still more powerful, or more permanent, it sometimes happens,
  that the motions of the biliary glands, and of their excretory ducts, are
  at the same time inverted, and regurgitate their contained bile into the
  blood-vessels, as appears by the yellow colour of the skin, and of the
  urine; and it is probable the pancreatic secretion may suffer an
  inversion at the same time, though we have yet no mark by which this can
  be ascertained.
13. Mr. —— eat two putrid
  pigeons out of a cold pigeon-pye, and drank about a pint of beer and ale
  along with them, and immediately rode about five miles. He was then
  seized with vomiting, which was after a few periods succeeded by purging;
  these continued alternately for two hours; and the purging continued by
  intervals for six or eight hours longer. During this time he could not
  force himself to drink more than one pint in the whole; this great
  inability to drink was owing to the nausea, or inverted motions of the
  stomach, which the voluntary exertion of swallowing could seldom and with
  difficulty overcome; yet he discharged in the whole at least six quarts;
  whence came this quantity of liquid? First, the contents of the stomach
  were emitted, then of the duodenum, gall-bladder, and pancreas, by
  vomiting. After this the contents of the lower bowels, then the chyle,
  that was in the lacteal vessels, and in the receptacle of chyle, was
  regurgitated into the intestines by a retrograde motion of these vessels.
  And afterwards the mucus deposited in the cellular membrane, and on the
  surface of all the other membranes, seems to have been absorbed; and with
  the fluid absorbed from the air to have been carried up their respective
  lymphatic branches by the increased energy of their natural motions, and
  down the visceral lymphatics, or lacteals, by the inversion of their
  motions.
14. It may be difficult to invent
  experiments to demonstrate the truth of this inversion of some branches
  of the absorbent system, and increased absorption of others, but the
  analogy of these vessels to the intestinal canal, and the symptoms of
  many diseases, render this opinion more probable than many other received
  opinions of the animal œconomy.
In the above instance, after the yellow excrement was voided, the
  fluid ceased to have any smell, and appeared like curdled milk, and then
  a thinner fluid, and some mucus, were evacuated; did not these seem to
  partake of the chyle, of the mucous fluid from all the cells of the body,
  and lastly, of the atmospheric moisture? All these facts may be easily
  observed by any one, who takes a brisk purge.
15. Where the stimulus on the stomach, or on
  some other part of the intestinal canal, is still more permanent, not
  only the lacteal vessels, but the whole canal itself, becomes inverted
  from its associations: this is the iliac passion, in which all the fluids
  mentioned above are thrown up by the mouth. At this time the valve in the
  colon, from the inverted motions of that bowel, and the inverted action
  of this living valve, does not prevent the regurgitation of its
  contents.
The structure of this valve may be represented by a flexile leathern
  pipe standing up from the bottom of a vessel of water: its sides collapse
  by the pressure of the ambient fluid, as a small part of that fluid
  passes through it; but if it has a living power, and by its inverted
  action keeps itself open, it becomes like a rigid pipe, and will admit
  the whole liquid to pass. See Sect. XXIX. 2.
  5.
In this case the patient is averse to drink, from the constant
  inversion of the motions of the stomach, and yet many quarts are daily
  ejected from the stomach, which at length smell of excrement, and at last
  seem to be only a thin mucilaginous or aqueous liquor.
From whence is it possible, that this great quantity of fluid for many
  successive days can be supplied, after the cells of the body have given
  up their fluids, but from the atmosphere? When the cutaneous branch of
  absorbents acts with unnatural strength, it is probable the intestinal
  branch has its motions inverted, and thus a fluid is supplied without
  entering the arterial system. Could oiling or painting the skin give a
  check to this disease?
So when the stomach has its motions inverted, the lymphatics of the
  stomach, which are most strictly associated with it, invert their motions
  at the same time. But the more distant branches of lymphatics, which are
  less strictly associated with it, act with increased energy; as the
  cutaneous lymphatics in the cholera, or iliac passion, above described.
  And other irritative motions become decreased, as the pulsations of the
  arteries, from the extra-derivation or exhaustion of the sensorial
  power.
Sometimes when stronger vomiting takes place the more distant branches
  of the lymphatic system invert their motions with those of the stomach,
  and loose stools are produced, and cold sweats.
So when the lacteals have their motions inverted, as during the
  operation of strong purges, the urinary and cutaneous absorbents have
  their motions increased to supply the want of fluid in the blood, as in
  great thirst; but after a meal with sufficient potation the urine is
  pale, that is, the urinary absorbents act weakly, no supply of water
  being wanted for the blood. And when the intestinal absorbents act too
  violently, as when too great quantities of fluid have been drank, the
  urinary absorbents invert their motions to carry off the superfluity,
  which is a new circumstance of association, and a temporary diabetes
  supervenes.
16. I have had the opportunity of seeing
  four patients in the iliac passion, where the ejected material smelled
  and looked like excrement. Two of these were so exhausted at the time I
  saw them, that more blood could not be taken from them, and as their pain
  had ceased, and they continued to vomit up every thing which they drank,
  I suspected that a mortification of the bowel had already taken place,
  and as they were both women advanced in life, and a mortification is
  produced with less preceding pain in old and weak people, these both
  died. The other two, who were both young men, had still pain and strength
  sufficient for further venesection, and they neither of them had any
  appearance of hernia, both recovered by repeated bleeding, and a scruple
  of calomel given to one, and half a dram to the other, in very small
  pills: the usual means of clysters, and purges joined with opiates, had
  been in vain attempted. I have thought an ounce or two of crude mercury
  in less violent diseases of this kind has been of use, by contributing to
  restore its natural motion to some part of the intestinal canal, either
  by its weight or stimulus; and that hence the whole tube recovered its
  usual associations of progressive peristaltic motion. I have in three
  cases seen crude mercury given in small doses, as one or two ounces twice
  a day, have great effect in stopping pertinacious vomitings.
17. Besides the affections above described,
  the stomach is liable, like many other membranes of the body, to torpor
  without consequent inflammation: as happens to the membranes about the
  head in some cases of hemicrania, or in general head-ach. This torpor of
  the stomach is attended with indigestion, and consequent flatulency, and
  with pain, which is usually called the cramp of the stomach, and is
  relievable by aromatics, essential oils, alcohol, or opium.
The intrusion of a gall-stone into the common bile-duct from the
  gall-bladder is sometimes mistaken for a pain of the stomach, as neither
  of them are attended with fever; but in the passage of a gall-stone, the
  pain is confined to a less space, which is exactly where the common
  bile-duct enters the duodenum, as explained in Section XXX. 1. 3. Whereas in this gastrodynia the pain
  is diffused over the whole stomach; and, like other diseases from torpor,
  the pulse is weaker, and the extremities colder, and the general debility
  greater, than in the passage of a gall-stone; for in the former the
  debility is the consequence of the pain, in the latter it is the cause of
  it.
Though the first fits of the gout, I believe, commence with a torpor
  of the liver; and the ball of the toe becomes inflamed instead of the
  membranes of the liver in consequence of this torpor, as a coryza or
  catarrh frequently succeeds a long exposure of the feet to cold, as in
  snow, or on a moist brick-floor; yet in old or exhausted constitutions,
  which have been long habituated to its attacks, it sometimes commences
  with a torpor of the stomach, and is transferable to every membrane of
  the body. When the gout begins with torpor of the stomach, a painful
  sensation of cold occurs, which the patient compares to ice, with weak
  pulse, cold extremities, and sickness; this in its slighter degree is
  relievable by spice, wine, or opium; in its greater degree it is
  succeeded by sudden death, which is owing to the sympathy of the stomach
  with the heart, as explained below.
If the stomach becomes inflamed in consequence of this gouty torpor of
  it, or in consequence of its sympathy with some other part, the danger is
  less. A sickness and vomiting continues many days, or even weeks, the
  stomach rejecting every thing stimulant, even opium or alcohol, together
  with much viscid mucus; till the inflammation at length ceases, as
  happens when other membranes, as those of the joints, are the seat of
  gouty inflammation; as observed in Sect. XXIV.
  2. 8.
The sympathy, or association of motions, between those of the stomach
  and those of the heart, are evinced in many diseases. First, many people
  are occasionally affected with an intermission of their pulse for a few
  days, which then ceases again. In this case there is a stop of the motion
  of the heart, and at the same time a tendency to eructation from the
  stomach. As soon as the patient feels a tendency to the intermission of
  the motion of his heart, if he voluntarily brings up wind from his
  stomach, the stop of the heart does not occur. From hence I conclude that
  the stop of digestion is the primary disease; and that air is instantly
  generated from the aliment, which begins to ferment, if the digestive
  process is impeded for a moment, (see Sect. XXIII. 4.); and that the stop of the heart is in
  consequence of the association of the motions of these viscera, as
  explained in Sect. XXXV. 1. 4.; but if the
  little air, which is instantly generated during the temporary torpor of
  the stomach, be evacuated, the digestion recommences, and the temporary
  torpor of the heart does not follow. One patient, whom I lately saw, and
  who had been five or six days much troubled with this intermission of a
  pulsation of his heart, and who had hemicrania with some fever, was
  immediately relieved from them all by losing ten ounces of blood, which
  had what is termed an inflammatory crust on it.
Another instance of this association between the motions of the
  stomach and heart is evinced by the exhibition of an over dose of
  foxglove, which induces an incessant vomiting, which is attended with
  very slow, and sometimes intermitting pulse.—Which continues in
  spite of the exhibition of wine and opium for two or three days. To the
  same association must be ascribed the weak pulse, which constantly
  attends the exhibition of emetics during their operation. And also the
  sudden deaths, which have been occasioned in boxing by a blow on the
  stomach; and lastly, the sudden death of those, who have been long
  debilitated by the gout, from the torpor of the stomach. See Sect. XXXV. 1. 4.

</div></body></text></TEI>