<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="124">CHAPTER II.
Discovery of the Circulation of the
Blood.

Sect. 1.—Prelude to the
Discovery.
THE blood-vessels, the veins
and arteries, are as evident and peculiar in their appearance as the
muscles; but their function is by no means so obvious. Hippocrates20 did not discriminate Veins and
Arteries; both are called by the same name (φλέβες) and the word from
which artery comes (ἀρτηρίη) means, in his works, the windpipe.
Aristotle, scanty as was his knowledge of the vessels of the body, has
yet the merit of having traced the origin of all the veins to the
heart. He expressly contradicts those of his predecessors who had
derived the veins from the head;21 and refers to
dissection for the proof. If the book On the Breath be genuine
(which is doubted), Aristotle was aware of the distinction between
veins and arteries. “Every artery,” 445 it is there asserted, “is accompanied by
a vein; the former are filled only with breath or air.”22 But whether or no this passage be
Aristotle’s, he held opinions equally erroneous; as, that the windpipe
conveys air into the heart.23 Galen24 was far from having views respecting
the blood-vessels, as sound as those which he entertained concerning
the muscles. He held the liver to be the origin of the veins, and the
heart of the arteries. He was, however, acquainted with their
junctions, or anastomoses. But we find no material advance in
the knowledge of this subject, till we overleap the blank of the
middle ages, and reach the dawn of modern science.
20 Sprengel, i. 383.
21 Hist. Animal. iii. 3.
22 De Spiritu, v. 1078.
23 Spr. i. 501.
24 Ib. ii. 152.
The father of modern anatomy is held to be Mondino,25 who dissected and taught at Bologna in
1315. Some writers have traced in him the rudiments of the doctrine of
the circulation of the blood; for he says that the heart transmits
blood to the lungs. But it is allowed, that he afterwards destroys the
merit of his remark, by repeating the old assertion that the left
ventricle ought to contain spirit or air, which it generates from the
blood.
25 Encyc. Brit. 692.
Anatomy.
Anatomy was cultivated with great diligence and talent in Italy by
Achillini, Carpa, and Messa, and in France by Sylvius and Stephanus
(Dubois and Etienne). Yet still these empty assumptions respecting the
heart and blood-vessels kept their ground. Vesalius, a native of
Brussels, has been termed the founder of human anatomy, and his great
work De Humani Corporis Fabricâ is, even yet, a splendid
monument of art, as well as science. It is said that his figures were
designed by Titian; and if this be not exactly true, says Cuvier,26 they must, at least, be from the pencil
of one of the most distinguished pupils of the great painter; for to
this day, though we have more finished drawings, we have no designs
that are more artist-like. Fallopius, who succeeded Vesalius at Padua,
made some additions to the researches of his predecessor; but in his
treatise De Principio Venarum, it is clearly seen27 that the circulation of the blood was
unknown to him. Eustachius also, whom Cuvier groups with Vesalius and
Fallopius, as the three great founders of modern anatomy, wrote a
treatise on the vein azygos28 which is a
little treatise on comparative anatomy; but the discovery of the
functions of the veins came from a different quarter.
26 Leçons sur l’Hist. des Sc.
Nat. p. 21.
27 Cuv. Sc. Nat. p. 32.
28 Ib. p. 34.
446 The
unfortunate Servetus, who was burnt at Geneva as a heretic in 1553, is
the first person who speaks distinctly of the small circulation, or
that which carries the blood from the heart to the lungs, and back
again to the heart. His work entitled Christianismi Restitutio
was also burnt; and only two copies are known to have escaped the
flames. It is in this work that he asserts the doctrine in question,
as a collateral argument or illustration of his subject. “The
communication between the right and left ventricle of the heart, is
made,” he says, “not as is commonly believed, through the partition of
the heart, but by a remarkable artifice (magno artificio) the
blood is carried from the right ventricle by a long circuit through
the lungs; is elaborated by the lungs, made yellow, and transfused
from the vena arteriosa into the arteria venosa.” This
truth is, however, mixed with various of the traditional fancies
concerning the “vital spirit, which has its origin in the left
ventricle.” It may be doubted, also, how far Servetus formed his
opinion upon conjecture, and on a hypothetical view of the formation
of this vital spirit. And we may, perhaps, more justly ascribe the
real establishment of the pulmonary circulation as an inductive truth,
to Realdus Columbus, a pupil and successor of Vesalius at Padua, who
published a work De Re Anatomicâ in 1559, in which he claims
this discovery as his own.29
29 Encyc. Brit.
Andrew Cæsalpinus, who has already come under our notice as one of
the fathers of modern inductive science, both by his metaphysical and
his physical speculations, described the pulmonary circulation still
more completely in his Quæstiones Peripateticæ, and even seemed
to be on the eve of discovering the great circulation; for he remarked
the swelling of veins below ligatures, and inferred from it a refluent
motion of blood in these vessels.30 But another
discovery of structure was needed, to prepare the way for this
discovery of function; and this was made by Fabricius of
Acquapendente, who succeeded in the grand list of great professors at
Padua, and taught there for fifty years.31 Sylvius had
discovered the existence of the valves of the veins; but Fabricius
remarked that they are all turned towards the heart. Combining this
disposition with that of the valves of the heart, and with the absence
of valves in the arteries, he might have come to the conclusion32 that the blood moves in a different
direction in the arteries and in the veins, and might thus have
discovered the circulation: but this glory was reserved for William
Harvey: so true 447
is it, observes Cuvier, that we are often on the brink of a discovery
without suspecting that we are so;—so true is it, we may add,
that a certain succession of time and of persons is generally
necessary to familiarize men with one thought, before they can advance
to that which is the next in order.
30 Ib.
31 Cuv. p. 44.
32 p. 45.
Sect. 2.—The Discovery of the Circulation made by
Harvey.
William Harvey was born in
1578, at Folkestone in Kent.33 He first
studied at Cambridge: he afterwards went to Padua, where the celebrity
of Fabricius of Acquapendente attracted from all parts those who
wished to be instructed in anatomy and physiology. In this city,
excited by the discovery of the valves of the veins, which his master
had recently made, and reflecting on the direction of the valves which
are at the entrance of the veins into the heart, and at the exit of
the arteries from it, he conceived the idea of making experiments, in
order to determine what is the course of the blood in its vessels. He
found that when he tied up veins in various animals, they swelled
below the ligature, or in the part furthest from the heart; while
arteries, with a like ligature, swelled on the side next the heart.
Combining these facts with the direction of the valves, he came to the
conclusion that the blood is impelled, by the left side of the heart,
in the arteries to the extremities, and thence returns by the veins
into the right side of the heart. He showed, too, how this was
confirmed by the phenomena of the pulse, and by the results of opening
the vessels. He proved, also, that the circulation of the lungs is a
continuation of the larger circulation; and thus the whole doctrine of
the double circulation was established.
33 Cuv. p. 51.
Harvey’s experiments had been made in 1616 and 1618; it is commonly
said that he first promulgated his opinion in 1619; but the manuscript
of the lectures, delivered by him as lecturer to the College of
Physicians, is extant in the British Museum, and, containing the
propositions on which the doctrine is founded, refers them to April,
1616. It was not till 1628 that he published, at Frankfort, his
Exercitatio Anatomica de Motu Cordis et Sanguinis; but he there
observes that he had for above nine years confirmed and illustrated
his opinion in his lectures, by arguments grounded upon ocular
demonstrations. 448
Sect. 3.—Reception of the Discovery.
Without dwelling long upon
the circumstances of the general reception of this doctrine, we may
observe that it was, for the most part, readily accepted by his
countrymen, but that abroad it had to encounter considerable
opposition. Although, as we have seen, his predecessors had approached
so near to the discovery, men’s minds were by no means as yet prepared
to receive it. Several physicians denied the truth of the opinion,
among whom the most eminent was Riolan, professor at the Collège de
France. Other writers, as usually happens in the case of great
discoveries, asserted that the doctrine was ancient, and even that it
was known to Hippocrates. Harvey defended his opinion with spirit and
temper; yet he appears to have retained a lively recollection of the
disagreeable nature of the struggles in which he was thus involved. At
a later period of his life, Ent,34 one of his
admirers, who visited him, and urged him to publish the researches on
generation, on which he had long been engaged, gives this account of
the manner in which he received the proposal: “And would you then
advise me, (smilingly replies the doctor,) to quit the tranquillity of
this haven, wherein I now calmly spend my days, and again commit
myself to the unfaithful ocean? You are not ignorant how great
troubles my lucubrations, formerly published, have raised. Better it
is, certainly, at some time, to endeavor to grow wise at home in
private, than by the hasty divulgation of such things to the knowledge
whereof you have attained with vast labor, to stir up tempests that
may deprive you of your leisure and quiet for the future.”
34 Epist. Dedic. to Anatom.
Exercit.
His merits were, however, soon generally recognized. He was35 made physician to James the First, and
afterwards to Charles the First, and attended that unfortunate monarch
in the civil war. He had the permission of the parliament to accompany
the king on his leaving London; but this did not protect him from
having his house plundered in his absence, not only of its furniture,
but, which he felt more, of the records of his experiments. In 1652,
his brethren of the College of Physicians placed a marble bust of him
in their hall, with an inscription recording his discoveries; and two
years later, he was nominated to the office of President of the
College, which however he 449 declined in consequence of his age and
infirmities. His doctrine soon acquired popular currency; it was, for
instance, taken by Descartes36 as the basis of
his physiology in his work On Man; and Harvey had the pleasure,
which is often denied to discoverers, of seeing his discovery
generally adopted during his lifetime.
35 Biog. Brit.
36 Cuv. 53.
Sect. 4.—Bearing of the Discovery on the Progress
of Physiology.
In considering the
intellectual processes by which Harvey’s discoveries were made, it is
impossible not to notice, that the recognition of a creative purpose,
which, as we have said, appears in all sound physiological reasonings,
prevails eminently here. “I remember,” says Boyle, “that when I asked
our famous Harvey what were the things that induced him to think of a
circulation of the blood, he answered me, that when he took notice
that the valves in the veins of so many parts of the body were so
placed, that they gave a free passage to the blood towards the heart,
but opposed the passage of the venal blood the contrary way; he was
incited to imagine that so provident a cause as Nature had not placed
so many valves without design; and no design seemed more probable than
that the blood should be sent through the arteries, and return through
the veins, whose valves did not oppose its course that way.”
We may notice further, that this discovery implied the usual
conditions, distinct general notions, careful observation of many
facts, and the mental act of bringing together these elements of
truth. Harvey must have possessed clear views of the motions and
pressures of a fluid circulating in ramifying tubes, to enable him to
see how the position of valves, the pulsation of the heart, the
effects of ligatures, of bleeding, and of other circumstances, ought
to manifest themselves in order to confirm his view. That he referred
to a multiplied and varied experience for the evidence that it was so
confirmed, we have already said. Like all the best philosophers of his
time, he insists rigidly upon the necessity of such experience. “In
every science,” he says,37 “be it what it will, a diligent
observation is requisite, and sense itself must be frequently
consulted. We must not rely upon other men’s experience, but our own,
without which no man is a proper disciple of any part of natural
knowledge.” And by publishing his experiments, he trusts, he adds,
that he has enabled his reader “to be an equitable 450 umpire between
Aristotle and Galen;” or rather, he might have said, to see how, in
the promotion of science, sense and reason, observation and invention,
have a mutual need of each other.
37 Generation of Animals,
Pref.
We may observe further, that though Harvey’s glory, in the case now
before us, rested upon his having proved the reality of certain
mechanical movements and actions in the blood, this discovery, and all
other physiological truths, necessarily involved the assumption of
some peculiar agency belonging to living things, different both from
mechanical agency, and from chemical; and in short, something
vital, and not physical merely. For when it was seen that the
pulsation of the heart, its systole and diastole, caused
the circulation of the blood, it might still be asked, what force
caused this constantly-recurring contraction and expansion. And again,
circulation is closely connected with respiration; the blood is, by
the circulation, carried to the lungs, and is there, according to the
expression of Columbus and Harvey, mixed with air. But by what
mechanism does this mixture take place, and what is the real
nature of it? And when succeeding researches had enabled physiologists
to give an answer to this question, as far as chemical relations go,
and to say, that the change consists in the abstraction of the carbon
from the blood by means of the oxygen of the atmosphere; they were
still only led to ask further, how this chemical change was effected,
and how such a change of the blood fitted it for its uses. Every
function of which we explain the course, the mechanism, or the
chemistry, is connected with other functions,—is subservient to
them, and they to it; and all together are parts of the general vital
system of the animal, ministering to its life, but deriving their
activity from the life. Life is not a collection of forces, or
polarities, or affinities, such as any of the physical or chemical
sciences contemplate; it has powers of its own, which often supersede
those subordinate relations; and in the cases where men have traced
such agents in the animal frame, they have always seen, and usually
acknowledged, that these agents were ministerial to some higher
agency, more difficult to trace than these, but more truly the cause
of the phenomena.
The discovery of the mechanical and chemical conditions of the
vital functions, as a step in physiology, may be compared to the
discovery of the laws of phenomena in the heavens by Kepler and his
predecessors, while the discovery of the force by which they were
produced was still reserved in mystery for Newton to bring to light.
The subordinate relation of the facts, their dependence on space and time,
their reduction to order and cycle, had been fully performed; but the
451 reference of
them to distinct ideas of causation, their interpretation as the
results of mechanical force, was omitted or attempted in vain. The
very notion of such Force, and of the manner in which motions were
determined by it, was in the highest degree vague and vacillating; and
a century was requisite, as we have seen, to give to the notion that
clearness and fixity which made the Mechanics of the Heavens a
possible science. In like manner, the notion of Life, and of Vital
Forces, is still too obscure to be steadily held. We cannot connect it
distinctly with severe inductions from facts. We can trace the motions
of the animal fluids as Kepler traced the motions of the planets; but
when we seek to render a reason for these motions, like him, we recur
to terms of a wide and profound, but mysterious import; to Virtues,
Influences, undefined Powers. Yet we are not on this account to
despair. The very instance to which I am referring shows us how rich
is the promise of the future. Why, says Cuvier,38 may not Natural
History one day have its Newton? The idea of the vital forces may
gradually become so clear and definite as to be available in science;
and future generations may include, in their physiology, propositions
elevated as far above the circulation of the blood, as the doctrine of
universal gravitation goes beyond the explanation of the heavenly
motions by epicycles.
38 Ossem. Foss. Introd.
If, by what has been said, I have exemplified sufficiently the
nature of those steps in physiology, which, like the discovery of the
Circulation, give an explanation of the process of some of the animal
functions, it is not necessary for me to dwell longer on the subject;
for to write a history, or even a sketch of the history of Physiology,
would suit neither my powers nor my purpose. Some further analysis of
the general views which have been promulgated by the most eminent
physiologists, may perhaps be attempted in treating of the Philosophy
of Inductive Science; but the estimation of the value of recent
speculations and investigations must be left to those who have made
this vast subject the study of their lives. A few brief notices may,
however, be here introduced. 452</div></body></text></TEI>