<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="6">CHAPTER VI.
DOCTRINE OF THE DISCORDANCE OF THE ANCIENT AND MODERN
CAUSES OF CHANGE CONTROVERTED.
Climate of the Northern Hemisphere formerly different—Direct proofs from the
organic remains of the Italian strata—Proofs from analogy derived from extinct
quadrupeds—Imbedding of animals in icebergs—Siberian
mammoths—Evidence in regard to temperature, from the fossils of tertiary and secondary
rocks—From the plants of the coal formation—Northern limit of these fossils—Whether
such plants could endure the long continuance of an arctic night.
Climate of the Northern hemisphere formerly different.—Proofs of
former revolutions in climate, as deduced from fossil remains, have afforded
one of the most popular objections to the theory which endeavors
to explain all geological changes by reference to those now in
progress on the earth. The probable causes, therefore, of fluctuations
in climate, may first be treated of.
That the climate of the Northern hemisphere has undergone an important
change, and that its mean annual temperature must once have
more nearly resembled that now experienced within the tropics, was the
opinion of some of the first naturalists who investigated the contents of
the ancient strata. Their conjecture became more probable when the
shells and corals of the older tertiary and many secondary rocks were
carefully examined; for the organic remains of these formations were
found to be intimately connected by generic affinity with species now
living in warmer latitudes. At a later period, many reptiles, such as
turtles, tortoises, and large saurian animals, were discovered in European
formations in great abundance; and they supplied new and powerful
arguments, from analogy, in support of the doctrine, that the heat
of the climate had been great when our secondary strata were deposited.
Lastly, when the botanist turned his attention to the specific determination
of fossil plants, the evidence acquired still fuller confirmation; for
the flora of a country is peculiarly influenced by temperature: and the
ancient vegetation of the earth might have been expected more readily
than the forms of animals, to have afforded conflicting proofs, had the
popular theory been without foundation. When the examination of fossil
remains was extended to rocks in the most northern parts of Europe
and North America, and even to the Arctic regions, indications of the
same revolution in climate were discovered.
It cannot be said, that in this, as in many other departments of
geology, we have investigated the phenomena of former eras, and neglected
those of the present state of things. On the contrary, since the
first agitation of this interesting question, the accessions to our knowledge
of living animals and plants have been immense, and have far74
surpassed all the data previously obtained for generalizing on the relation
of certain types of organization to particular climates. The tropical
and temperate zones of South America and of Australia have been explored;
and, on close comparison, it has been found that scarcely any
of the species of the animate creation in these extensive continents are
identical with those inhabiting the old world. Yet the zoologist and
botanist, well acquainted with the geographical distribution of organic
beings in other parts of the globe, would have been able, if distinct
groups of species had been presented to them from these regions, to
recognize those which had been collected from latitudes within, and
those which were brought from without the tropics.
Before I attempt to explain the probable causes of great vicissitudes
of temperature on the earth's surface, I shall take a rapid view of some
of the principal data which appear to support the popular opinions now
entertained on the subject. To insist on the soundness of these inferences,
is the more necessary, because some zoologists have undertaken to
vindicate the uniformity of the laws of nature, not by accounting for
former fluctuations in climate, but by denying the value of the evidence
in their favor.126
Proofs from fossil shells in tertiary strata.—In Sicily, Calabria, and
in the neighborhood of Naples, the fossil testacea of the most modern
tertiary formations belong almost entirely to species now inhabiting the
Mediterranean; but as we proceed northwards in the Italian peninsula
we find in the strata called Subapennine an assemblage of fossil shells
departing somewhat more widely from the type of the neighboring
seas. The proportion of species identifiable with those now living in
the Mediterranean is still considerable; but it no longer predominates,
as in the South of Italy and part of Sicily, over the unknown species.
Although occurring in localities which are removed several degrees farther
from the equator (as at Sienna, Parma, Asti, &c.), the shells yield
clear indications of a warmer climate. This evidence is of great weight,
and is not neutralized by any facts of a conflicting character; such, for
instance, as the association, in the same group, of individuals referable
to species now confined to arctic regions. Whenever any of the fossil
shells are identified with living species foreign to the Mediterranean, it
is not in the Northern Ocean, but nearer the tropics, that they must be
sought: on the other hand, the associated unknown species belong, for
the most part, to genera which are now most largely developed in equinoctial
regions, as, for example, the genera Cancellaria, Cassidaria,
Pleurotoma, Conus, and Cypræa.
On comparing the fossils of the tertiary deposits of Paris and London
with those of Bourdeaux, and these again with the more modern strata
of Sicily, we should at first expect that they would each indicate a
higher temperature in proportion as they are situated farther to the
75south. But the contrary is true; of the shells belonging to these several
groups, whether freshwater or marine, some are of extinct, others of
living species. Those found in the older, or Eocene, deposits of Paris
and London, although six or seven degrees to the north of the Miocene
strata at Bourdeaux, afford evidence of a warmer climate; while those
of Bourdeaux imply that the sea in which they lived was of a higher
temperature than that of Sicily, where the shelly strata were formed six
or seven degrees nearer to the equator. In these cases the greater antiquity
of the several formations (the Parisian being the oldest and the
Sicilian the newest) has more than counterbalanced the influence which
latitude would otherwise exert, and this phenomenon clearly points to a
gradual and successive refrigeration of climate.
Siberian Mammoths.—It will naturally be asked, whether some recent
geological discoveries bringing evidence to light of a colder, or as it has
been termed "glacial epoch," towards the close of the tertiary periods
throughout the northern hemisphere, does not conflict with the theory
above alluded to, of a warmer temperature having prevailed in the eras
of the Eocene, Miocene, and Pliocene formations. In answer to this inquiry,
it may certainly be affirmed, that an oscillation of climate has occurred
in times immediately antecedent to the peopling of the earth by
man; but proof of the intercalation of a less genial climate at an era
when nearly all the marine and terrestrial testacea had already become
specifically the same as those now living, by no means rebuts the conclusion
previously drawn, in favor of a warmer condition of the globe,
during the ages which elapsed while the tertiary strata were deposited.
In some of the most superficial patches of sand, gravel, and loam, scattered
very generally over Europe, and containing recent shells, the remains
of extinct species of land quadrupeds have been found, especially
in places where the alluvial matter appears to have been washed into
small lakes, or into depressions in the plains bordering ancient rivers.
Similar deposits have also been lodged in rents and caverns of rocks,
where they may have been swept in by land floods, or introduced by
engulphed rivers during changes in the physical geography of these
countries. The various circumstances under which the bones of animals
have been thus preserved, will be more fully considered
hereafter;127 I shall only state here, that among the extinct mammalia thus entombed,
we find species of the elephant, rhinoceros, hippopotamus, bear, hyæna,
lion, tiger, monkey (macacus128), and many others; consisting partly of
genera now confined to warmer regions.
It is certainly probable that when some of these quadrupeds abounded
in Europe, the climate was milder than that now experienced. The
hippopotamus, for example, is now only met with where the temperature
of the water is warm and nearly uniform throughout the year, and
76where the rivers are never frozen over. Yet when the great fossil species
(Hippopotamus major, Cuv.) inhabited England, the testacea of our
country were nearly the same as those now existing, and the climate
cannot be supposed to have been very hot. The bones of this animal
have lately been found by Mr. Strickland, together with those of a bear
and other mammalia, at Cropthorn, near Evesham, in Worcestershire, in
alluvial sand, together with twenty-three species of terrestrial and freshwater
shells, all, with two exceptions, of British species. The bed of
sand, containing the shells and bones, reposes on lias, and is covered with
alternating strata of gravel, sand, and loam.129
The mammoth also appears to have existed in England when the
temperature of our latitudes could not have been very different from
that which now prevails; for remains of this animal have been found at
North Cliff, in the county of York, in a lacustrine formation, in which
all the land and freshwater shells, thirteen in number, can be identified
with species and varieties now existing in that county. Bones of the
bison, also, an animal now inhabiting a cold or temperate climate, have
been found in the same place. That these quadrupeds, and the indigenous
species of testacea associated with them, were all contemporary
inhabitants of Yorkshire, has been established by unequivocal proof.
The Rev. W. V. Vernon Harcourt caused a pit to be sunk to the depth
of twenty-two feet through undisturbed strata, in which the remains of
the mammoth were found imbedded, together with the shells, in a deposit
which had evidently resulted from tranquil waters.130
In the valley of the Thames, as at Ilford and Grays, in Essex, bones
of the elephant and rhinoceros occur in strata abounding in freshwater
shells of the genera Unio, Cyclas, Paludina, Valvata, Ancylus, and
others. These fossil shells belong for the most part to species now living
in the same district, yet some few of them are extinct, as, for example,
a species of Cyrena, a genus no longer inhabiting Europe, and now
entirely restricted to warmer latitudes.
When reasoning on such phenomena, the reader must always bear in
mind that the fossil individuals belonged to species of elephant, rhinoceros,
hippopotamus, bear, tiger, and hyæna, distinct from those which
now dwell within or near the tropics. Dr. Fleming, in a discussion on
this subject, has well remarked that a near resemblance in form and osteological
structure is not always followed, in the existing creation, by
a similarity of geographical distribution; and we must therefore be on
our guard against deciding too confidently, from mere analogy of anatomical
structure, respecting the habits and physiological peculiarities of
species now no more. "The zebra delights to roam over the tropical
plains, while the horse can maintain its existence throughout an Iceland
winter. The buffalo, like the zebra, prefers a high temperature, and
cannot thrive even where the common ox prospers. The musk-ox, on
the other hand, though nearly resembling the buffalo, prefers the stinted
77herbage of the arctic regions, and is able, by its periodical migrations,
to outlive a northern winter. The jackal (Canis aureus) inhabits Africa,
the warmer parts of Asia, and Greece; while the isatis (Canis lagopus)
resides in the arctic regions. The African hare and the polar hare have
their geographical distribution expressed in their trivial names;"131 and
different species of bears thrive in tropical, temperate, and arctic latitudes.
Recent investigations have placed beyond all doubt the important fact
that a species of tiger, identical with that of Bengal, is common in the
neighborhood of Lake Aral, near Sussac, in the forty-fifth degree of
north latitude; and from time to time this animal is now seen in Siberia,
in a latitude as far north as the parallel of Berlin and Hamburgh.132
Humboldt remarks that the part of Southern Asia now inhabited by this
Indian species of tiger is separated from the Himalaya by two great
chains of mountains, each covered with perpetual snow,—the chain of
Kuenlun, lat. 35° N., and that of Mouztagh, lat. 42°,—so that it is impossible
that these animals should merely have made excursions from
India, so as to have penetrated in summer to the forty-eighth and fifty-third
degrees of north latitude. They must remain all the winter north
of the Mouztagh, or Celestial Mountains. The last tiger killed, in 1828,
on the Lena, in lat. 52-1/4°, was in a climate colder than that of Petersburg
and Stockholm.133
We learn from Mr. Hodgson's account of the mammalia of Nepal,
that the tiger is sometimes found at the very edge of perpetual snow in
the Himalaya;134 and Pennant mentions that it is found among the snows
of Mount Ararat in Armenia. The jaguar, also, has been seen in America,
wandering from Mexico, as far north as Kentucky, lat. 37° N.,135 and
even as far as 42° S. in South America,—a latitude which corresponds
to that of the Pyrenees in the northern hemisphere.136 The range of the
puma is still wider, for it roams from the equator to the Straits of Magellan,
being often seen at Port Famine, in lat. 53° 38' S.
A new species of panther (Felis irbis), covered with long hair, has
been discovered in Siberia, evidently inhabiting, like the tiger, a region
north of the Celestial Mountains, which are in lat. 42°.137
The two-horned African rhinoceros occurs without the tropics at the
Cape of Good Hope, in lat. 34° 29' S., where it is accompanied by the
elephant, hippopotamus, and hyæna. Here the migration of all these
species towards the south is arrested by the ocean; but if the continent
had been prolonged still farther, and the land had been of moderate elevation,
78
it is very probable that they might have extended their range to
a greater distance from the tropics.
Now, if the Indian tiger can range in our own times to the southern
borders of Siberia, or skirt the snows of the Himalaya, and if the puma
can reach the fifty-third degree of latitude in South America, we may
easily understand how large species of the same genera may once have
inhabited our temperate climates. The mammoth (E. primigenius), already
alluded to, as occurring fossil in England, was decidedly different
from the two existing species of elephants, one of which is limited to
Asia, south of the 31° of N. lat., the other to Africa, where it extends,
as before stated, as far south as the Cape of Good Hope. The bones
of the great fossil species are very widely spread over Europe and North
America; but are nowhere in such profusion as in Siberia, particularly
near the shores of the Frozen Ocean. Are we, then, to conclude that this
animal preferred a polar climate? If so, it may well be asked, by what
food was it sustained, and why does it not still survive near the arctic
circle?138
Pallas and other writers describe the bones of the mammoth as abounding
throughout all the Lowlands of Siberia, stretching in a direction west
and east, from the borders of Europe to the extreme point nearest America,
and south and north, from the base of the mountains of Central Asia
to the shores of the Arctic Sea. (See map, fig. 1.) Within this space,
scarcely inferior in area to the whole of Europe, fossil ivory has been
collected almost everywhere, on the banks of the Irtish, Obi, Yenesei,
Lena, and other rivers. The elephantine remains do not occur in the
marshes and low plains, but where the banks of the rivers present lofty
precipices of sand and clay, from which circumstance Pallas very justly
inferred that, if sections could be obtained, similar bones might be found
in all the elevated lands intervening between the great rivers. Strahlenberg,
indeed, had stated, before the time of Pallas, that wherever any of
the great rivers overflowed and cut out fresh channels during floods, more
fossil remains of the same kind were invariably disclosed.
MAP OF SIBERIA.
Fig. 1. Map showing the course of the Siberian rivers from south to north, from temperate to arctic regions, in the country where the
fossil bones of the Mammoth abound.
As to the position of the bones, Pallas found them in some places imbedded
together with marine remains; in others, simply with fossil wood,
or lignite, such as, he says, might have been derived from carbonized
peat. On the banks of the Yenesei, below the city of Krasnojarsk, in
lat. 56°, he observed grinders, and bones of elephants, in strata of yellow
79
and red loam, alternating with coarse sand and gravel, in which was
also much petrified wood of the willow and other trees. Neither here
nor in the neighboring country were there any marine shells, but merely
layers of black coal.139 But grinders of the mammoth were collected
much farther down the same river, near the sea, in lat. 70°, mixed with
marine petrifactions.140 Many other places in Siberia are cited by Pallas,
80
where sea shells and fishes' teeth accompany the bones of the mammoth,
rhinoceros, and Siberian buffalo, or bison (Bos priscus). But it is not
on the Obi nor the Yenesei, but on the Lena, farther to the east, where,
in the same parallels of latitude, the cold is far more intense, that fossil
remains have been found in the most wonderful state of preservation.
In 1772, Pallas obtained from Wiljuiskoi, in lat. 64°, from the banks of
the Wiljui, a tributary of the Lena, the carcass of a rhinoceros (R.
tichorhinus), taken from the sand in which it must have remained congealed
for ages, the soil of that region being always frozen to within a
slight depth of the surface. This carcass was compared to a natural
mummy, and emitted an odor like putrid flesh, part of the skin being
still covered with black and gray hairs. So great, indeed, was the
quantity of hair on the foot and head conveyed to St. Petersburg, that
Pallas asked whether the rhinoceros of the Lena might not have been
an inhabitant of the temperate regions of middle Asia, its clothing being
so much warmer than that of the African rhinoceros.141
Professor Brandt, of St. Petersburg, in a letter to Baron Alex. Von
Humboldt, dated 1846, adds the following particulars respecting this
wonderful fossil relic:—"I have been so fortunate as to extract from
cavities in the molar teeth of the Wiljui rhinoceros a small quantity of
its half-chewed food, among which fragments of pine leaves, one-half of
the seed of a polygonaceous plant, and very minute portions of wood
with porous cells (or small fragments of coniferous wood), were still
recognizable. It was also remarkable, on a close investigation of the
head, that the blood-vessels discovered in the interior of the mass
appeared filled, even to the capillary vessels, with a brown mass
(coagulated blood), which in many places still showed the red color of
blood."142
After more than thirty years, the entire carcass of a mammoth (or
extinct species of elephant) was obtained in 1803, by Mr. Adams, much
farther to the north. It fell from a mass of ice, in which it had been
encased, on the banks of the Lena, in lat. 70°; and so perfectly had the
soft parts of the carcass been preserved, that the flesh, as it lay, was
devoured by wolves and bears. This skeleton is still in the museum of
St. Petersburg, the head retaining its integument and many of the ligaments
entire. The skin of the animal was covered, first, with black
bristles, thicker than horse hair, from twelve to sixteen inches in length;
secondly, with hair of a reddish brown color, about four inches long;
and thirdly, with wool of the same color as the hair, about an inch in
length. Of the fur, upwards of thirty pounds' weight were gathered
from the wet sand-bank. The individual was nine feet high and sixteen
feet long, without reckoning the large curved tusks: a size rarely surpassed
by the largest living male elephants.143
It is evident, then, that the mammoth, instead of being naked, like the
81living Indian and African elephants, was enveloped in a thick shaggy
covering of fur, probably as impenetrable to rain and cold as that of the
musk ox.144 The species may have been fitted by nature to withstand
the vicissitudes of a northern climate; and it is certain that, from the
moment when the carcasses, both of the rhinoceros and elephant, above
described, were buried in Siberia, in latitudes 64° and 70° N., the soil
must have remained frozen, and the atmosphere nearly as cold as at
this day.
The most recent discoveries made in 1843 by Mr. Middendorf, a distinguished
Russian naturalist, and which he communicated to me in
September, 1846, afford more precise information as to the climate of
the Siberian lowlands, at the period when the extinct quadrupeds were
entombed. One elephant was found on the Tas, between the Obi and
Yenesei, near the arctic circle, about lat. 66° 30' N., with some parts
of the flesh in so perfect a state that the bulb of the eye is now preserved
in the museum at Moscow. Another carcass, together with a
young individual of the same species, was met with in the same year,
1843, in lat. 75° 15' N., near the river Taimyr, with the flesh decayed.
It was imbedded in strata of clay and sand, with erratic blocks, at about
15 feet above the level of the sea. In the same deposit Mr. Middendorf
observed the trunk of a larch tree (Pinus larix), the same wood
as that now carried down in abundance by the Taimyr to the Arctic
Sea. There were also associated fossil shells of living northern species,
and which are moreover characteristic of the drift or glacial deposits of
Europe. Among these Nucula pygmæa, Tellina calcarea, Mya truncata,
and Saxicava rugosa were conspicuous.
So fresh is the ivory throughout northern Russia, that, according to
Tilesius, thousands of fossil tusks have been collected and used in turning;
yet others are still procured and sold in great plenty. He declares
his belief that the bones still left in northern Russia must greatly exceed
in number all the elephants now living on the globe.
82
We are as yet ignorant of the entire geographical range of the mammoth;
but its remains have been recently collected from the cliffs of
frozen mud and ice on the east side of Behring's Straits, in Eschscholtz's
Bay, in Russian America, lat. 66° N. As the cliffs waste
away by the thawing of the ice, tusks and bones fall out, and a strong
odor of animal matter is exhaled from the mud.145
On considering all the facts above enumerated, it seems reasonable to
imagine that a large region in central Asia, including, perhaps, the
southern half of Siberia, enjoyed, at no very remote period in the earth's
history, a temperate climate, sufficiently mild to afford food for numerous
herds of elephants and rhinoceroses, of species distinct from those
now living. It has usually been taken for granted that herbivorous
animals of large size require a very luxuriant vegetation for their support;
but this opinion is, according to Mr. Darwin, completely erroneous:—"It
has been derived," he says, "from our acquaintance with
India and the Indian islands, where the mind has been accustomed to
associate troops of elephants with noble forests and impenetrable jungles.
But the southern parts of Africa, from the tropic of Capricorn to
the Cape of Good Hope, although sterile and desert, are remarkable for
the number and great bulk of the indigenous quadrupeds. We there
meet with an elephant, five species of rhinoceros, a hippopotamus, a
giraffe, the bos caffer, the elan, two zebras, the quagga, two gnus, and
several antelopes. Nor must we suppose, that while the species are
numerous, the individuals of each kind are few. Dr. Andrew Smith
saw, in one day's march, in lat. 24° S., without wandering to any great
distance on either side, about 150 rhinoceroses, with several herds of
giraffes, and his party had killed, on the previous night, eight hippopotamuses.
Yet the country which they inhabited was thinly covered
with grass and bushes about four feet high, and still more thinly with
mimosa-trees, so that the wagons of the travellers were not prevented
from proceeding in a nearly direct line."146
In order to explain how so many animals can find support in this region,
it is suggested that the underwood, of which their food chiefly
consists, may contain much nutriment in a small bulk, and also that the
vegetation has a rapid growth; for no sooner is a part consumed than
its place, says Dr. Smith, is supplied by a fresh stock. Nevertheless,
after making every allowance for this successive production and consumption,
it is clear, from the facts above cited, that the quantity of
food required by the larger herbivora is much less than we have usually
imagined. Mr. Darwin conceives that the amount of vegetation supported
at any one time by Great Britain may exceed, in a ten-fold ratio,
the quantity existing on an equal area in the interior parts of Southern
Africa.147 It is remarked, moreover, in illustration of the small connec83tion
discoverable between abundance of food and the magnitude of indigenous
mammalia, that while in the desert part of Southern Africa
there are so many huge animals; in Brazil, where the splendor and exuberance
of the vegetation are unrivalled, there is not a single wild
quadruped of large size.148
It would doubtless be impossible for herds of mammoths and rhinoceroses
to subsist, at present, throughout the year, even in the southern
part of Siberia, covered as it is with snow during winter; but there is
no difficulty in supposing a vegetation capable of nourishing these great
quadrupeds to have once flourished between the latitudes 40° and
60° N.
Dr. Fleming has hinted, that "the kind of food which the existing
species of elephant prefers, will not enable us to determine, or even to
offer a probable conjecture, concerning that of the extinct species. No
one acquainted with the gramineous character of the food of our fallow-deer,
stag, or roe, would have assigned a lichen to the reindeer."
Travellers mention that, even now, when the climate of eastern Asia
is so much colder than the same parallels of latitude farther west, there
are woods not only of fir, but of birch, poplar, and alder, on the banks
of the Lena, as far north as latitude 60°.
It has, moreover, been suggested, that as, in our own times, the
northern animals migrate, so the Siberian elephant and rhinoceros may
have wandered towards the north in summer. The musk oxen annually
desert their winter quarters in the south, and cross the sea upon the ice,
to graze for four months, from May to September, on the rich pasturage
of Melville Island, in lat. 75°. The mammoths, without passing so
far beyond the arctic circle, may nevertheless have made excursions,
during the heat of a brief northern summer, from the central or temperate
parts of Asia to the sixtieth parallel of latitude.
Now, in this case, the preservation of their bones, or even occasionally
of their entire carcasses, in ice or frozen soil, may be accounted for,
without resorting to speculations concerning sudden revolutions in the
former state and climate of the earth's surface. We are entitled to assume,
that, in the time of the extinct elephant and rhinoceros, the Lowland
of Siberia was less extensive towards the north than now; for we
have seen (p. 80) that the strata of this Lowland, in which the fossil
bones lie buried, were originally deposited beneath the sea; and we
know, from the facts brought to light in Wrangle's Voyage, in the years
1821, 1822, and 1823, that a slow upheaval of the land along the borders
of the Icy Sea is now constantly taking place, similar to that experienced
in part of Sweden. In the same manner, then, as the shores
of the Gulf of Bothnia are extended, not only by the influx of sediment
brought down by rivers, but also by the elevation and consequent drying
up of the bed of the sea, so a like combination of causes may, in
modern times, have been extending the low tract of land where marine
84shells and fossil bones occur in Siberia.149 Such a change in the physical
geography of that region, implying a constant augmentation in the
quantity of arctic land, would, according to principles to be explained
in the next chapter, tend to increase the severity of the winters. We
may conclude, therefore, that, before the land reached so far to the
north, the temperature of the Siberian winter and summer was more
nearly equalized; and a greater degree of winter's cold may, even more
than a general diminution of the mean annual temperature, have finally
contributed to the extermination of the mammoth and its contemporaries.
On referring to the map (p. 79), the reader will see how all the
great rivers of Siberia flow at present from south to north, from temperate
to arctic regions, and they are all liable, like the Mackenzie, in
North America, to remarkable floods, in consequence of flowing in this
direction. For they are filled with running water in their upper or
southern course when completely frozen over for several hundred miles
near their mouths, where they remain blocked up by ice for six months
in every year. The descending waters, therefore, finding no open channel,
rush over the ice, often changing their direction, and sweeping along
forests and prodigious quantities of soil and gravel mixed with ice.
Now the rivers of Siberia are among the largest in the world, the
Yenesei having a course of 2500, the Lena of 2000 miles; so that we
may easily conceive that the bodies of animals which fall into their
waters may be transported to vast distances towards the Arctic Sea,
and, before arriving there, may be stranded upon and often frozen into
thick ice. Afterwards, when the ice breaks up, they may be floated
still farther towards the ocean, until at length they become buried in
fluviatile and submarine deposits near the mouths of rivers.
Humboldt remarks that near the mouths of the Lena a considerable
thickness of frozen soil may be found at all seasons at the depth of a
few feet; so that if a carcass be once imbedded in mud and ice in such
a region and in such a climate, its putrefaction may be arrested for indefinite
ages.150 According to Prof. Von Baer of St. Petersburg, the
ground is now frozen permanently to the depth of 400 feet, at the town
of Yakutzt, on the western bank of the Lena, in lat. 62° N., 600 miles
distant from the polar sea. Mr. Hedenstrom tells us that, throughout
a wide area in Siberia, the boundary cliffs of the lakes and rivers consist
of alternate layers of earthy materials and ice, in horizontal stratification;151
and Mr. Middendorf informed us, in 1846, that, in his tour there
three years before, he had bored in Siberia to the depth of seventy feet,
and, after passing through much frozen soil mixed with ice, had come
85down upon a solid mass of pure transparent ice, the thickness of which,
after penetrating two or three yards, they did not ascertain. We may
conceive, therefore, that even at the period of the mammoth, when the
Lowland of Siberia was less extensive towards the north, and consequently
the climate more temperate than now, the cold may still have
been sufficiently intense to cause the rivers flowing in their present
direction to sweep down from south to north the bodies of drowned
animals, and there bury them in drift ice and frozen mud.
If it be true that the carcass of the mammoth was imbedded in pure
ice, there are two ways in which it may have been frozen in. We may
suppose the animal to have been overwhelmed by drift snow. I have
been informed by Dr. Richardson, that, in the northern parts of America,
comprising regions now inhabited by many herbivorous quadrupeds,
the drift snow is often converted into permanent glaciers. It is
commonly blown over the edges of steep cliffs, so as to form an inclined
talus hundreds of feet high; and when a thaw commences, torrents
rush from the land, and throw down from the top of the cliff alluvial
soil and gravel. This new soil soon becomes covered with vegetation,
and protects the foundation of snow from the rays of the sun. Water
occasionally penetrates into the crevices and pores of the snow; but,
as it soon freezes again, it serves the more rapidly to consolidate the
mass into a compact iceberg. It may sometimes happen that cattle
grazing in a valley at the base of such cliffs, on the borders of a sea or
river, may be overwhelmed, and at length inclosed in solid ice, and
then transported towards the polar regions. Or a herd of mammoths
returning from their summer pastures in the north, may have been surprised,
while crossing a stream, by the sudden congelation of the waters.
The missionary Huc relates, in his travels in Thibet in 1846, that, after
many of his party had been frozen to death, they pitched their tents
on the banks of the Mouroui-Ousson (which lower down becomes the
famous Blue River), and saw from their encampment "some black
shapeless objects ranged in file across the stream. As they advanced
nearer no change either in form or distinctness was apparent; nor was
it till they were quite close, that they recognized in them a troop of the
wild oxen, called Yak by the Thibetans.152 There were more than fifty
of them incrusted in the ice. No doubt they had tried to swim across
at the moment of congelation, and had been unable to disengage themselves.
Their beautiful heads, surmounted by huge horns, were still
above the surface, but their bodies were held fast in the ice, which was
so transparent that the position of the imprudent beasts was easily distinguishable;
they looked as if still swimming, but the eagles and
ravens had pecked out their eyes."153
The foregoing investigations, therefore, lead us to infer that the mammoth,
and some other extinct quadrupeds fitted to live in high latitudes,
86were inhabitants of Northern Asia at a time when the geographical
conditions and climate of that continent were different from the present.
But the age of this fauna was comparatively modern in the earth's history.
It appears that when the oldest or eocene tertiary deposits were
formed, a warm temperature pervaded the European seas and lands.
Shells of the genus Nautilus and other forms characteristic of tropical
latitudes; fossil reptiles, such as the crocodile, turtle, and tortoise;
plants, such as palms, some of them allied to the cocoa-nut, the screw-pine,
the custard-apple, and the acacia, all lead to this conclusion. This
flora and fauna were followed by those of the miocene formation, in
which indications of a southern, but less tropical climate are detected.
Finally, the pliocene deposits, which come next in succession, exhibit
in their organic remains a much nearer approach to the state of things
now prevailing in corresponding latitudes. It was towards the close of
this period that the seas of the northern hemisphere became more and
more filled with floating icebergs often charged with erratic blocks, so
that the waters and the atmosphere were chilled by the melting ice, and
an arctic fauna enabled, for a time, to invade the temperate latitudes
both of N. America and Europe. The extinction of a considerable
number of land quadrupeds and aquatic mollusca was gradually brought
about by the increasing severity of the cold; but many species survived
this revolution in climate, either by their capacity of living under a variety
of conditions, or by migrating for a time to more southern lands
and seas. At length, by modifications in the physical geography of the
northern regions, and the cessation of floating ice on the eastern side of
the Atlantic, the cold was moderated, and a milder climate ensued,
such as we now enjoy in Europe.154
Proofs from fossils in secondary and still older strata.—A great interval
of time appears to have elapsed between the formation of the
secondary strata, which constitute the principal portion of the elevated
land in Europe, and the origin of the eocene deposits. If we examine
the rocks from the chalk to the new red sandstone inclusive, we find
many distinct assemblages of fossils entombed in them, all of unknown
species, and many of them referable to genera and families now most
abundant between the tropics. Among the most remarkable are reptiles
of gigantic size; some of them herbivorous, others carnivorous,
and far exceeding in size any now known even in the torrid zone. The
genera are for the most part extinct, but some of them, as the crocodile
and monitor, have still representatives in the warmer parts of the
earth. Coral reefs also were evidently numerous in the seas of the
same periods, composed of species often belonging to genera now characteristic
of a tropical climate. The number of large chambered shells
87also, including the nautilus, leads us to infer an elevated temperature;
and the associated fossil plants, although imperfectly known, tend to
the same conclusion, the Cycadeæ constituting the most numerous
family.
But it is from the more ancient coal-deposits that the most extraordinary
evidence has been supplied in proof of the former existence of a
very different climate—a climate which seems to have been moist, warm,
and extremely uniform, in those very latitudes which are now the colder,
and in regard to temperature, the most variable regions of the globe.
We learn from the researches of Adolphe Brongniart, Goeppert, and
other botanists, that in the flora of the carboniferous era there was a
great predominance of ferns, some of which were arborescent; as, for
example, Caulopteris, Protopteris, and Psarronius; nor can this be accounted
for, as some have supposed, by the greater power which ferns
possess of resisting maceration in water.155 This prevalence of ferns indicates
a moist, equable, and temperate climate, and the absence of any
severe cold; for such are the conditions which, at the present day, are
found to be most favorable to that tribe of plants. It is only in the
islands of the tropical oceans, and of the southern temperate zone, such
as Norfolk Island, Otaheite, the Sandwich Islands, Tristan d'Acunha, and
New Zealand, that we find any near approach to that remarkable preponderance
of ferns which is characteristic of the Carboniferous flora.
It has been observed that tree ferns and other forms of vegetation which
flourished most luxuriantly within the tropics, extend to a much greater
distance from the equator in the southern hemisphere than in the northern,
being found even as far as 46° S. latitude in New Zealand.
There is little doubt that this is owing to the more uniform and moist
climate occasioned by the greater proportional area of sea. Next to
ferns and pines, the most abundant vegetable forms in the coal formation
are the Calamites, Lepidodendra, Sigillariæ, and Stigmariæ. These
were formerly considered to be so closely allied to tropical genera, and
to be so much greater in size than the corresponding tribes now inhabiting
equatorial latitudes, that they were thought to imply an extremely
hot, as well as humid and equable climate. But recent discoveries respecting
the structure and relations of these fossil plants, have shown
that they deviated so widely from all existing types in the vegetable
world, that we have more reason to infer from this evidence a widely
different climate in the Carboniferous era, as compared to that now prevailing,
than a temperature extremely elevated.156 Palms, if not entirely
88wanting when the strata of the carboniferous group were deposited, appear
to have been exceedingly rare.157 The Coniferæ, on the other hand,
so abundantly met with in the coal, resemble Araucariæ in structure, a
family of the fir tribe, characteristic at present of the milder regions of
the southern hemisphere, such as Chili, Brazil, New Holland, and Norfolk
Island.
"In regard to the geographical extent of the ancient vegetation, it
was not confined," says M. Brongniart, "to a small space, as to Europe,
for example; for the same forms are met with again at great distances.
Thus, the coal-plants of North America are, for the most part, identical
with those of Europe, and all belong to the same genera. Some specimens,
also, from Greenland, are referable to ferns, analogous to those
of our European coal-mines."158 The fossil plants brought from Melville
Island, although in a very imperfect state, have been supposed to warrant
similar conclusions;159 and assuming that they agree with those of
Baffin's Bay, mentioned by M. Brongniart, how shall we explain the
manner in which such a vegetation lived through an arctic night of several
months' duration?160
It may seem premature to discuss this question until the true nature
of the fossil flora of the arctic regions has been more accurately determined;
yet, as the question has attracted some attention, let us assume
for a moment that the coal-plants of Melville Island are strictly analogous
to those of the strata of Northumberland—would such a fact present
an inexplicable enigma to the vegetable physiologist?
89Plants, it is affirmed, cannot remain in darkness, even for a week,
without serious injury, unless in a torpid state; and if exposed to heat
and moisture they cannot remain torpid, but will grow, and must therefore
perish. If, then, in the latitude of Melville Island, 75° N., a high
temperature, and consequent humidity, prevailed at that period when
we know the arctic seas were filled with corals and large multilocular
shells, how could plants of tropical forms have flourished? Is not the
bright light of equatorial regions as indispensable a condition of their
well-being as the sultry heat of the same countries? and how could
they annually endure a night prolonged for three months?161
Now, in reply to this objection, we must bear in mind, in the first
place, that, so far as experiments have been made, there is every reason
to conclude, that the range of intensity of light to which living plants
can accommodate themselves is far wider than that of heat. No palms
or tree ferns can live in our temperate latitudes without protection from
the cold; but when placed in hot-houses they grow luxuriantly, even
under a cloudy sky, and where much light is intercepted by the glass
and frame-work. At St. Petersburg, in lat. 60° N., these plants have
been successfully cultivated in hot-houses, although there they must exchange
the perpetual equinox of their native regions, for days and nights
which are alternately protracted to nineteen hours and shortened to
five. How much farther towards the pole they might continue to live,
provided a due quantity of heat and moisture were supplied, has not
yet been determined; but St. Petersburg is probably not the utmost
limit, and we should expect that in lat. 65° at least, where they would
never remain twenty-four hours without enjoying the sun's light, they
might still exist.
It should also be borne in mind, in regard to tree ferns, that they
grow in the gloomiest and darkest parts of the forests of warm and
temperate regions, even extending to nearly the 46th degree of south
latitude in New Zealand. In equatorial countries, says Humboldt, they
abound chiefly in the temperate, humid, and shady parts of mountains.
As we know, therefore, that elevation often compensates for the effect
of latitude in the geographical distribution of plants, we may easily understand
that a class of vegetables, which grows at a certain height in
the torrid zone, would flourish on the plains at greater distances from
the equator, if the temperature, moisture, and other necessary conditions,
were equally uniform throughout the year.
Nor must we forget that in all the examples above alluded to, we
have been speaking of living species; but the coal-plants were of perfectly
distinct species, nay, few of them except the ferns and pines can
be referred to genera or even families of the existing vegetable kingdom.
Having a structure, therefore, and often a form which appears to the
botanist so anomalous, they may also have been endowed with a
differ90ent constitution, enabling them to bear a greater variation of circumstances
in regard to light. We find that particular species of plants
and tree ferns require at present different degrees of heat; and that
some species can thrive only in the immediate neighborhood of the
equator, others only a distance from it. In the same manner the minimum
of light, sufficient for the now existing species, cannot be taken
as the standard for all analogous tribes that may ever have flourished
on the globe.
But granting that the extreme northern point to which a flora like
that of the Carboniferous era could ever reach, may be somewhere between
the latitudes of 65° and 70°, we should still have to inquire
whether the vegetable remains might not have been drifted from thence,
by rivers and currents, to the parallel of Melville Island, or still farther.
In the northern hemisphere, at present, we see that the materials for
future beds of lignite and coal are becoming amassed in high latitudes,
far from the districts where the forests grew, and on shores where
scarcely a stunted shrub can now exist. The Mackenzie, and other
rivers of North America, carry pines with their roots attached for many
hundred miles towards the north, into the Arctic Sea, where they are
imbedded in deltas, and some of them drifted still farther by currents
towards the pole.
Before we can decide on this question of transportation, we must
know whether the fossil coal-plants occurring in high latitudes bear the
marks of friction and of having decayed previously to fossilization.
Many appearances in our English coal-fields certainly prove that the
plants were not floated from great distances; for the outline of the
stems of succulent species preserve their sharp angles, and others have
their surfaces marked with the most delicate lines and streaks. Long
leaves, also, are attached in many instances to the trunks or branches;162
and leaves, we know, in general, are soon destroyed when steeped in
water, although ferns will retain their forms after an immersion of many
months.163 It seems fair to presume, that most of the coal-plants grew
upon the same land which supplied materials for the sandstones and
conglomerates of the strata in which they are imbedded. The coarseness
of the particles of many of these rocks attests that they were not
borne from very remote localities, and that there was land therefore in
the vicinity wasting away by the action of moving waters. The progress
also of modern discovery has led to the very general admission of
the doctrine that beds of coal have for the most part been formed of
the remains of trees and plants that grew on the spot where the coal
now exists; the land having been successively submerged, so that a
covering of mud and sand was deposited upon accumulations of
vegetable mater. That such has been the origin of some coal-seams
is proved by the upright position of fossil trees, both in
91Europe and America, in which the roots terminate downwards in beds
of coal.164
To return, therefore, from this digression,—the flora of the coal appears
to indicate a uniform and mild temperature in the air, while the
fossils of the contemporaneous mountain-limestone, comprising abundance
of lamelliferous corals, large chambered cephalopods, and crinoidea,
naturally lead us to infer a considerable warmth in the waters of the
northern sea of the Carboniferous period. So also in regard to strata
older than the coal, they contain in high northern latitudes mountain
masses of corals which must have lived and grown on the spot, and large
chambered univalves, such as Orthocerata and Nautilus, all seeming to
indicate, even in regions bordering on the arctic circle, the former prevalence
of a temperature more elevated than that now prevailing.
The warmth and humidity of the air, and the uniformity of climate,
both in the different seasons of the year, and in different latitudes, appears
to have been most remarkable when some of the oldest of the fossiliferous
strata were formed. The approximation to a climate similar to
that now enjoyed in these latitudes does not commence till the era of the
formations termed tertiary; and while the different tertiary rocks were
deposited in succession, from the eocene to the pliocene, the temperature
seems to have been lowered, and to have continued to diminish even after
the appearance upon the earth of a considerable number of the existing
species, the cold reaching its maximum of intensity in European latitudes
during the glacial epoch, or the epoch immediately antecedent to that in
which all the species now contemporary with man were in being.
92</div></body></text></TEI>