<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="27">CHAPTER I.
Prelude to the Epoch of Galileo.

Sect. 1.—Prelude to the Science of
Statics.
SOME steps in the science of
Motion, or rather in the science of Equilibrium, had been made by the
ancients, as we have seen. Archimedes established satisfactorily the
doctrine of the Lever, some important properties of the Centre of
Gravity, and the fundamental proposition of Hydrostatics. But this
beginning led to no permanent progress. Whether the distinction
between the principles of the doctrine of Equilibrium and of Motion
was clearly seen by Archimedes, we do not know; but it never was
caught hold of by any of the other writers of antiquity, or by those
of the Stationary Period. What was still worse, the point which
Archimedes had won was not steadily maintained.
We have given some examples of the general
ignorance of the Greek philosophers on such subjects, in noticing the
strange manner in which Aristotle refers to mathematical properties,
in order to account for the equilibrium of a lever, and the attitude
of a man rising from a chair. And we have seen, in speaking of the indistinct ideas of the
Stationary Period, that the attempts which were made to extend the
statical doctrine of Archimedes, failed, in such a manner as to show
that his followers had not clearly apprehended the idea on which his
reasoning altogether depended. The clouds which he had, for a moment,
cloven in his advance, closed after him, and the former dimness and
confusion settled again on the land.
This dimness and confusion, with respect to all subjects of
mechanical reasoning, prevailed still, at the period we now have to
consider; namely, the period of the first promulgation of the
Copernican opinions. This is so important a point that I must
illustrate it further.
Certain general notions of the connection of cause and effect in
motion, exist in the human mind at all periods of its development, and
are implied in the formation of language and in the most familiar
employments of men’s thoughts. But these do not constitute a
science of 313 Mechanics, any more than the notions of
square and round make a Geometry, or the notions of
months and years make an Astronomy. The unfolding these
Notions into distinct Ideas, on which can be founded principles and
reasonings, is further requisite, in order to produce a science; and,
with respect to the doctrines of Motion, this was long in coming to
pass; men’s thoughts remained long entangled in their primitive and
unscientific confusion.
We may mention one or two features of this confusion, such as we
find in authors belonging to the period now under review.
We have already, in speaking of the Greek
School Philosophy, noticed the attempt to explain some of the
differences among Motions, by classifying them into Natural Motions
and Violent Motions; and we have spoken of the assertion that heavy
bodies fall quicker in proportion to their greater weight. These
doctrines were still retained: yet the views which they implied were
essentially erroneous and unsound; for they did not refer distinctly
to a measurable Force as the cause of all motion or change of motion;
and they confounded the causes which produce and those which
preserve, motion. Hence such principles did not lead
immediately to any advance of knowledge, though efforts were made to
apply them, in the cases both of terrestrial Mechanics and of the
motions of the heavenly bodies.
The effect of the Inclined Plane was one of the first, as it was
one of the most important, propositions, on which modern writers
employed themselves. It was found that a body, when supported on a
sloping surface, might be sustained or raised by a force or exertion
which would not have been able to sustain or raise it without such
support. And hence, The Inclined Plane was placed in the list
of Mechanical Powers, or simple machines by which the efficacy of
forces is increased: the question was, in what proportion this
increase of efficiency takes place. It is easily seen that the force
requisite to sustain a body is smaller, as the slope on which it rests
is smaller; Cardan (whose work, De Proportionibus Numerorum,
Motuum, Ponderum, &c., was published in 1545) asserts that the
force is double when the angle of inclination is double, and so on for
other proportions; this is probably a guess, and is an erroneous one.
Guido Ubaldi, of Marchmont, published at Pesaro, in 1577, a work which
he called Mechanicorum Liber, in which he endeavors to prove
that an acute wedge will produce a greater mechanical effect than an
obtuse one, without determining in what proportion. There is, he
observes, “a certain repugnance” between the direction in which the
side of the wedge tends to 314 move the obstacle, and the direction in
which it really does move. Thus the Wedge and the Inclined Plane are
connected in principle. He also refers the Screw to the Inclined Plane
and the Wedge, in a manner which shows a just apprehension of the
question. Benedetti (1585) treats the Wedge in a different manner; not
exact, but still showing some powers of thought on mechanical
subjects. Michael Varro, whose Tractatus de Motu was published
at Geneva in 1584, deduces the wedge from the composition of
hypothetical motions, in a way which may appear to some persons an
anticipation of the doctrine of the Composition of Forces.
There is another work on subjects of this kind, of which several
editions were published in the sixteenth century, and which treats
this matter in nearly the same way as Varro, and in favour of which a
claim has been made2 (I think an unfounded one), as if it
contained the true principle of this problem. The work is “Jordanus
Nemorarius De Ponderositate.” The date and history of this
author were probably even then unknown; for in 1599, Benedetti,
correcting some of the errors of Tartalea, says they are taken “a
Jordano quodam antiquo.” The book was probably a kind of school-book,
and much used; for an edition printed at Frankfort, in 1533, is stated
to be Cum gratia et privilegio Imperiali, Petro Apiano mathematico
Ingolstadiano ad xxx annos concesso. But this edition does not
contain the Inclined Plane. Though those who compiled the work assert
in words something like the inverse proportion of Weights and their
Velocities, they had not learnt at that time how to apply this maxim
to the Inclined Plane; nor were they ever able to render a sound
reason for it. In the edition of Venice, 1565, however, such an
application is attempted. The reasonings are founded on the
Aristotelian assumption, “that bodies descend more quickly in
proportion as they are heavier.” To this principle are added some
others; as, that “a body is heavier in proportion as it descends more
directly to the centre,” and that, in proportion as a body descends
more obliquely, the intercepted part of the direct descent is smaller.
By means of these principles, the “descending force” of bodies, on
inclined planes, was compared, by a process, which, so far as it forms
a line of proof at all, is a somewhat curious example of confused and
vicious reasoning. When two bodies are supported on two inclined
planes, and are connected by a string passing over the junction of the
planes, so that when one descends the other ascends, 315 they must move
through equal spaces on the planes; but on the plane which is more
oblique (that is, more nearly horizontal), the vertical descent will
be smaller in the same proportion in which the plane is longer. Hence,
by the Aristotelian principle, the weight of the body on the longer
plane is less; and, to produce an equality of effect, the body must be
greater in the same proportion. We may observe that the Aristotelian
principle is not only false, but is here misapplied; for its genuine
meaning is, that when bodies fall freely by gravity, they
move quicker in proportion as they are heavier; but the rule is here
applied to the motions which bodies would have, if they were
moved by a force extraneous to their gravity. The proposition was
supposed by the Aristotelians to be true of actual
velocities; it is applied by Jordanus to virtual velocities,
without his being aware what he was doing. This confusion being made,
the result is got at by taking for granted that bodies thus
proved to be equally heavy, have equal powers of descent on
the inclined planes; whereas, in the previous part of the reasoning,
the weight was supposed to be proportional to the descent in the
vertical direction. It is obvious, in all this, that though the author
had adopted the false Aristotelian principle, he had not settled in
his own mind whether the motions of which it spoke were actual or
virtual motions;—motions in the direction of the inclined plane,
or of the intercepted parts of the vertical, corresponding to these;
nor whether the “descending force” of a body was something different
from its weight. We cannot doubt that, if he had been required to
point out, with any exactness, the cases to which his reasoning
applied, he would have been unable to do so; not possessing any of
those clear fundamental Ideas of Pressure and Force, on which alone
any real knowledge on such subjects must depend. The whole of
Jordanus’s reasoning is an example of the confusion of thought of his
period, and of nothing more. It no more supplied the want of some man
of genius, who should give the subject a real scientific foundation,
than Aristotle’s knowledge of the proportion of the weights on the
lever superseded the necessity of Archimedes’s proof of it.
2 Mr. Drinkwater’s Life of
Galileo, in the Lib. Usef. Kn. p. 83.
We are not, therefore, to wonder that, though this pretended
theorem was copied by other writers, as by Tartalea, in his Quesiti
et Inventioni Diversi, published in 1554, no progress was made in
the real solution of any one mechanical problem by means of it. Guido
Ubaldi, who, in 1577, writes in such a manner as to show that he had
taken a good hold of his subject for his time, refers to Pappus’s
solution of the problem of the Inclined Plane,  but makes no mention
of that of 316
Jordanus and Tartalea.3 No progress was likely to occur, till
the mathematicians had distinctly recovered the genuine Idea of
Pressure, as a Force producing equilibrium, which Archimedes had
possessed, and which was soon to reappear in Stevinus.
3 Ubaldi mentions and blames Jordanus’s
way of treating the Lever. (See his Preface.)
The properties of the Lever had always continued known to
mathematicians, although, in the dark period, the superiority of the
proof given by Archimedes had not been recognized. We are not to be
surprised, if reasonings like those of Jordanus were applied to
demonstrate the theories of the Lever with apparent success. Writers
on Mechanics were, as we have seen, so vacillating in their mode of
dealing with words and propositions, that their maxims could be made
to prove any thing which was already known to be true.
We proceed to speak of the beginning of the real progress of
Mechanics in modern times.
Sect. 2.—Revival of the Scientific Idea of
Pressure.—Stevinus.—Equilibrium of Oblique
Forces.
The doctrine of the Centre of Gravity was
the part of the mechanical speculations of Archimedes which was most
diligently prosecuted after his time. Pappus and others, among the
ancients, had solved some new problems on this subject, and
Commandinus, in 1565, published De Centro Gravitatis Solidorum.
Such treatises contained, for the most part, only mathematical
consequences of the doctrines of Archimedes; but the mathematicians
also retained a steady conviction of the mechanical property of the
Centre of Gravity, namely, that all the weight of the body might be
collected there, without any change in the mechanical results; a
conviction which is closely connected with our fundamental conceptions
of mechanical action. Such a principle, also, will enable us to
determine the result of many simple mechanical arrangements; for
instance, if a mathematician of those days had been asked whether a
solid ball could be made of such a form, that, when placed on a
horizontal plane, it should go on rolling forwards without limit
merely by the effect of its own weight, he would probably have
answered, that it could not; for that the centre of gravity of the
ball would seek the lowest position it could find, and that, when it
had found this, the ball could have no tendency to roll any further.
And, in making this assertion, the supposed reasoner would not be
317 anticipating
any wider proof of the impossibility of a perpetual motion
drawn from principles subsequently discovered, but would be referring
the question to certain fundamental convictions, which, whether put
into Axioms or not, inevitably accompany our mechanical
conceptions.
In the same way, Stevinus of Bruges, in 1586, when he published his
Beghinselen der Waaghconst (Principles of Equilibrium), had
been asked why a loop of chain, hung over a triangular beam, could
not, as he asserted it could not, go on moving round and round
perpetually, by the action of its own weight, he would probably have
answered, that the weight of the chain, if it produced motion at all,
must have a tendency to bring it into some certain position, and that
when the chain had reached this position, it would have no tendency to
go any further; and thus he would have reduced the impossibility of
such a perpetual motion, to the conception of gravity, as a force
tending to produce equilibrium; a principle perfectly sound and
correct.
Upon this principle thus applied, Stevinus did establish the
fundamental property of the Inclined Plane. He supposed a loop of
string, loaded with fourteen equal balls at equal distances, to hang
over a triangular support which was composed of two inclined planes
with a horizontal base, and whose sides, being unequal in the
proportion of two to one, supported four and two balls respectively.
He showed that this loop must hang at rest, because any motion would
only bring it into the same condition in which it was at first; and
that the festoon of eight balls which hung down below the triangle
might be removed without disturbing the equilibrium; so that four
balls on the longer plane would balance two balls on the shorter
plane; or in other words, the weights would be as the lengths of the
planes intercepted by the horizontal line.
Stevinus showed his firm possession of the truth contained in this
principle, by deducing from it the properties of forces acting in
oblique directions under all kinds of conditions; in short, he showed
his entire ability to found upon it a complete doctrine of
equilibrium; and upon his foundations, and without any additional
support, the mathematical doctrines of Statics might have been carried
to the highest pitch of perfection they have yet reached. The
formation of the science was finished; the mathematical development
and exposition of it were alone open to extension and change.
[2d Ed.] [“Simon Stevin of Bruges,” as he usually designates
himself in the title-page of his work, has lately become an object of
general interest in his own country, and it has been resolved to erect
a 318 statue in
honor of him in one of the public places of his native city. He was
born in 1548, as I learn from M. Quetelet’s notice of him, and died in
1620. Montucla says that he died in 1633; misled apparently by the
preface to Albert Girard’s edition of Stevin’s works, which was
published in 1634, and which speaks of a death which took place in the
preceding year; but on examination it will be seen that this refers to
Girard, not to Stevin.
I ought to have mentioned, in consideration of the importance of
the proposition, that Stevin distinctly states the triangle of
forces; namely, that three forces which act upon a point are in
equilibrium when they are parallel and proportional to the three sides
of any plane triangle. This includes the principle of the
Composition of Statical Forces. Stevin also applies his
principle of equilibrium to cordage, pulleys, funicular polygons, and
especially to the bits of bridles; a branch of mechanics which he
calls Chalinothlipsis.
He has also the merit of having seen very clearly, the distinction
of statical and dynamical problems. He remarks that the question,
“What force will support a loaded wagon on an inclined plane?
is a statical question, depending on simple conditions; but that the
question, What force will move the wagon? requires additional
considerations to be introduced.
In Chapter iv. of this Book, I have noticed
Stevin’s share in the rediscovery of the Laws of the Equilibrium of
Fluids. He distinctly explains the hydrostatic paradox, of
which the discovery is generally ascribed to Pascal.
Earlier than Stevinus, Leonardo da Vinci must have a place among
the discoverers of the Conditions of Equilibrium of Oblique Forces. He
published no work on this subject; but extracts from his manuscripts
have been published by Venturi, in his Essai sur les Ouvrages
Physico-Mathematiques de Leonard da Vinci, avec des Fragmens tirés de
ses Manuscrits apportés d’Italie, Paris, 1797: and by Libri, in
his Hist. des Sc. Math. en Italie, 1839. I have also myself
examined these manuscripts in the Royal Library at Paris.
It appears that, as early as 1499, Leonardo gave a perfectly
correct statement of the proportion of the forces exerted by a cord
which acts obliquely and supports a weight on a lever. He
distinguishes between the real lever, and the potential levers,
that is, the perpendiculars drawn from the centre upon the directions
of the forces. This is quite sound and satisfactory. These views must
in all probability have been sufficiently promulgated in Italy to
influence the speculations of Galileo; 319 whose reasonings respecting the lever
much resemble those of Leonardo.—Da Vinci also anticipated
Galileo in asserting that the time of descent of a body down
an inclined plane is to the time of descent down its vertical length
in the proportion of the length of the plane to the height. But this
cannot, I think, have been more than a guess: there is no vestige of a
proof given.]
The contemporaneous progress of the other branch of mechanics, the
Doctrine of Motion, interfered with this independent advance of
Statics; and to that we must now turn. We may observe, however, that
true propositions respecting the composition of forces appear to have
rapidly diffused themselves. The Tractatus de Motu of Michael
Varro of Geneva, already noticed, printed in 1584, had asserted, that
the forces which balance each other, acting on the sides of a
right-angled triangular wedge, are in the proportion of the sides of
the triangle; and although this assertion does not appear to have been
derived from a distinct idea of pressure, the author had hence rightly
deduced the properties of the wedge and the screw. And shortly after
this time, Galileo also established the same results on different
principles. In his Treatise Delle Scienze Mecaniche (1592), he
refers the Inclined Plane to the Lever, in a sound and nearly
satisfactory manner; imagining a lever so placed, that the motion of a
body at the extremity of one of its arms should be in the same
direction as it is upon the plane. A slight modification makes this an
unexceptionable proof.
Sect. 3.—Prelude to the Science of
Dynamics.—Attempts at the First Law of Motion.
We have already seen, that Aristotle divided Motions into Natural
and Violent. Cardan endeavored to improve this division by making
three classes: Voluntary Motion, which is circular and uniform,
and which is intended to include the celestial motions; Natural
Motion, which is stronger towards the end, as the motion of a falling
body,—this is in a straight line, because it is motion to an
end, and nature seeks her ends by the shortest road; and thirdly,
Violent Motion, including in this term all kinds different from
the former two. Cardan was aware that such Violent Motion might be
produced by a very small force; thus he asserts, that a spherical body
resting on a horizontal plane may be put in motion by any force which
is sufficient to cleave the air; for which, however, he erroneously
assigns as a reason, 320 the smallness of the point of contact.4
But the most common mistake of this period was, that of supposing that
as force is requisite to move a body, so a perpetual supply of force
is requisite to keep it in motion. The whole of what Kepler called his
“physical” reasoning, depended upon this assumption. He endeavored to
discover the forces by which the motions of the planets about the sun
might be produced; but, in all cases, he considered the velocity of
the planet as produced by, and exhibiting the effect of, a force which
acted in the direction of the motion. Kepler’s essays, which are in
this respect so feeble and unmeaning, have sometimes been considered
as disclosing some distant anticipation of Newton’s discovery of the
existence and law of central forces. There is, however, in reality, no
other connection between these speculations than that which arises
from the use of the term force by the two writers in two
utterly different meanings. Kepler’s Forces were certain imaginary
qualities which appeared in the actual motion which the bodies had;
Newton’s Forces were causes which appeared by the change of motion:
Kepler’s Forces urged the bodies forwards; Newton’s deflected the
bodies from such a progress. If Kepler’s Forces were destroyed, the
body would instantly stop; if Newton’s were annihilated, the body
would go on uniformly in a straight line. Kepler compares the action
of his Forces to the way in which a body might be driven round, by
being placed among the sails of a windmill; Newton’s Forces would be
represented by a rope pulling the body to the centre. Newton’s Force
is merely mutual attraction; Kepler’s is something quite different
from this; for though he perpetually illustrates his views by the
example of a magnet, he warns us that the sun differs from the magnet
in this respect, that its force is not attractive, but directive.5
Kepler’s essays may with considerable reason be asserted to be an
anticipation of the Vortices of Descartes; but they can with no
propriety whatever be said to anticipate Newton’s Dynamical
Theory.
4 In speaking of the force which would
draw a body up an inclined plane he observes, that “per communem animi
sententiam,” when the plane becomes horizontal, the requisite force is
nothing.
5 Epitome Astron. Copern. p.
176.
The confusion of thought which prevented mathematicians from seeing
the difference between producing and preserving motion, was, indeed,
fatal to all attempts at progress on this subject. We have already  noticed the perplexity in which Aristotle
involved himself, by his endeavors to find a reason for the continued
motion of a stone 321 after the moving power had ceased to
act; and that he had ascribed it to the effect of the air or other
medium in which the stone moves. Tartalea, whose Nuova Scienza
is dated 1550, though a good pure mathematician, is still
quite in the dark on mechanical matters. One of his propositions, in
the work just mentioned, is (B. i. Prop. 3), “The more a heavy body
recedes from the beginning, or approaches the end of violent motion,
the slower and more inertly it goes;” which he applies to the
horizontal motion of projectiles. In like manner most other writers
about this period conceived that a cannon-ball goes forwards till it
loses all its projectile motion, and then falls downwards. Benedetti,
who has already been mentioned, must be considered as one of the first
enlightened opponents of this and other Aristotelian errors or
puzzles. In his Speculationum Liber (Venice, 1585), he opposes
Aristotle’s mechanical opinions, with great expressions of respect,
but in a very sweeping manner. His chapter xxiv. is headed, “Whether
this eminent man was right in his opinion concerning violent and
natural motion.” And after stating the Aristotelian opinion just
mentioned, that the body is impelled by the air, he says that the air
must impede rather than impel the body, and that6 “the motion of the
body, separated from the mover, arises by a certain natural impression
from the impetuosity (ex impetuositate) received from the
mover.” He adds, that in natural motions this impetuosity
continually increases by the continued action of the
cause,—namely, the propension of going to the place assigned it
by nature; and that thus the velocity increases as the body moves from
the beginning of its path. This statement shows a clearness of
conception with regard to the cause of accelerated motion, which
Galileo himself was long in acquiring.
6 P. 184.
Though Benedetti was thus on the way to the First Law of
Motion,—that all motion is uniform and rectilinear, except so
far as it is affected by extraneous forces;—this Law was not
likely to be either generally conceived, or satisfactorily proved,
till the other Laws of Motion, by which the action of Forces is
regulated, had come into view. Hence, though a partial apprehension of
this principle had preceded the discovery of the Laws of Motion, we
must place the establishment of the principle in the period when those
Laws were detected and established, the period of Galileo and his
followers. 322</div></body></text></TEI>