<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</title><author>Locke, John (1632-1704)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1690</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="37">

CHAPTER XXVIII.
OF OTHER RELATIONS.

1. Ideas of Proportional relations.


BESIDES the before-mentioned occasions of time, place, and causality of
comparing or referring things one to another, there are, as I have said,
infinite others, some whereof I shall mention.


First, The first I shall name is some one simple idea, which, being capable of
parts or degrees, affords an occasion of comparing the subjects wherein it is
to one another, in respect of that simple idea, v.g. whiter, sweeter, equal,
more, &c. These relations depending on the equality and excess of the same
simple idea, in several subjects, may be called, if one will, PROPORTIONAL; and
that these are only conversant about those simple ideas received from sensation
or reflection is so evident that nothing need be said to evince it.


2. Natural relation.


Secondly, Another occasion of comparing things together, or considering one
thing, so as to include in that consideration some other thing, is the
circumstances of their origin or beginning; which being not afterwards to be
altered, make the relations depending thereon as lasting as the subjects to
which they belong, v.g. father and son, brothers, cousin-germans, &c.,
which have their relations by one community of blood, wherein they partake in
several degrees: countrymen, i.e. those who were born in the same country or
tract of ground; and these I call NATURAL RELATIONS: wherein we may observe,
that mankind have fitted their notions and words to the use of common life, and
not to the truth and extent of things. For it is certain, that, in reality, the
relation is the same betwixt the begetter and the begotten, in the several
races of other animals as well as men; but yet it is seldom said, this bull is
the grandfather of such a calf, or that two pigeons are cousin-germans. It is
very convenient that, by distinct names, these relations should be observed and
marked out in mankind, there being occasion, both in laws and other
communications one with another, to mention and take notice of men under these
relations: from whence also arise the obligations of several duties amongst
men: whereas, in brutes, men having very little or no cause to mind these
relations, they have not thought fit to give them distinct and peculiar names.
This, by the way, may give us some light into the different state and growth of
languages; which being suited only to the convenience of communication, are
proportioned to the notions men have, and the commerce of thoughts familiar
amongst them; and not to the reality or extent of things, nor to the various
respects might be found among them; nor the different abstract considerations
might be framed about them. Where they had no philosophical notions, there they
had no terms to express them: and it is no wonder men should have framed no
names for those things they found no occasion to discourse of. From whence it
is easy to imagine why, as in some countries, they may have not so much as the
name for a horse; and in others, where they are more careful of the pedigrees
of their horses, than of their own, that there they may have not only names for
particular horses, but also of their several relations of kindred one to
another.


3. Ideas of Instituted or Voluntary relations.


Thirdly, Sometimes the foundation of considering things with reference to one
another, is some act whereby any one comes by a moral right, power, or
obligation to do something. Thus, a general is one that hath power to command
an army, and an army under a general is a collection of armed men obliged to
obey one man. A citizen, or a burgher, is one who has a right to certain
privileges in this or that place. All this sort depending upon men’s wills, or
agreement in society, I call INSTITUTED, or VOLUNTARY; and may be distinguished
from the natural, in that they are most, if not all of them, some way or other
alterable, and separable from the persons to whom they have sometimes belonged,
though neither of the substances, so related, be destroyed. Now, though these
are all reciprocal, as well as the rest, and contain in them a reference of two
things one to the other; yet, because one of the two things often wants a
relative name, importing that reference, men usually take no notice of it, and
the relation is commonly overlooked: v. g. a patron and client are easily
allowed to be relations, but a constable or dictator are not so readily at
first hearing considered as such. Because there is no peculiar name for those
who are under the command of a dictator or constable, expressing a relation to
either of them; though it be certain that either of them hath a certain power
over some others, and so is so far related to them, as well as a patron is to
his client, or general to his army.


4. Ideas of Moral relations.


Fourthly, There is another sort of relation, which is the conformity or
disagreement men’s VOLUNTARY ACTIONS have to a RULE to which they are referred,
and by which they are judged of; which, I think, may be called MORAL RELATION,
as being that which denominates our moral actions, and deserves well to be
examined; there being no part of knowledge wherein we should be more careful to
get determined ideas, and avoid, as much as may be, obscurity and confusion.
Human actions, when with their various ends, objects, manners, and
circumstances, they are framed into distinct complex ideas, are, as has been
shown, so many MIXED MODES, a great part whereof have names annexed to them.
Thus, supposing gratitude to be a readiness to acknowledge and return kindness
received; polygamy to be the having more wives than one at once: when we frame
these notions thus in our minds, we have there so many determined ideas of
mixed modes. But this is not all that concerns our actions: it is not enough to
have determined ideas of them, and to know what names belong to such and such
combinations of ideas. We have a further and greater concernment, and that is,
to know whether such actions, so made up, are morally good or bad.


5. Moral Good and Evil.


Good and evil, as hath been shown, (B. II. chap. xx. Section 2, and chap. xxi.
Section 43,) are nothing but pleasure or pain, or that which occasions or
procures pleasure or pain to us. MORAL GOOD AND EVIL, then, is only THE
CONFORMITY OR DISAGREEMENT OF OUR VOLUNTARY ACTIONS TO SOME LAW, WHEREBY GOOD
OR EVIL IS DRAWN ON US, FROM THE WILL AND POWER OF THE LAW-MAKER; which good
and evil, pleasure or pain, attending our observance or breach of the law by
the decree of the law-maker, is that we call REWARD and PUNISHMENT.


6. Moral Rules.


Of these moral rules or laws, to which men generally refer, and by which they
judge of the rectitude or gravity of their actions, there seem to me to be
THREE SORTS, with their three different enforcements, or rewards and
punishments. For, since it would be utterly in vain to suppose a rule set to
the free actions of men, without annexing to it some enforcement of good and
evil to determine his will, we must, wherever we suppose a law, suppose also
some reward or punishment annexed to that law. It would be in vain for one
intelligent being to set a rule to the actions of another, if he had it not in
his power to reward the compliance with, and punish deviation from his rule, by
some good and evil, that is not the natural product and consequence of the
action itself. For that, being a natural convenience or inconvenience, would
operate of itself, without a law. This, if I mistake not, is the true nature of
all law, properly so called.


7. Laws.


The laws that men generally refer their actions to, to judge of their rectitude
or obliquity, seem to me to be these three:—1. The DIVINE law. 2. The
CIVIL law. 3. The law of OPINION or REPUTATION, if I may so call it. By the
relation they bear to the first of these, men judge whether their actions are
sins or duties; by the second, whether they be criminal or innocent; and by the
third, whether they be virtues or vices.


8. Divine Law the Measure of Sin and Duty.


First, the DIVINE LAW, whereby that law which God has set to the actions of
men,—whether promulgated to them by the light of nature, or the voice of
revelation. That God has given a rule whereby men should govern themselves, I
think there is nobody so brutish as to deny. He has a right to do it; we are
his creatures: he has goodness and wisdom to direct our actions to that which
is best: and he has power to enforce it by rewards and punishments of infinite
weight and duration in another life; for nobody can take us out of his hands.
This is the only true touchstone of moral rectitude; and, by comparing them to
this law, it is that men judge of the most considerable moral good or evil of
their actions; that is, whether, as duties or sins, they are like to procure
them happiness or misery from the hands of the ALMIGHTY.


9. Civil Law the Measure of Crimes and Innocence.


Secondly, the CIVIL LAW—the rule set by the commonwealth to the actions
of those who belong to it—is another rule to which men refer their
actions; to judge whether they be criminal or no. This law nobody overlooks:
the rewards and punishments that enforce it being ready at hand, and suitable
to the power that makes it: which is the force of the Commonwealth, engaged to
protect the lives, liberties, and possessions of those who live according to
its laws, and has power to take away life, liberty, or goods, from him who
disobeys; which is the punishment of offences committed against his law.


10. Philosophical Law the Measure of Virtue and Vice.


Thirdly, the LAW OF OPINION OR REPUTATION. Virtue and vice are names pretended
and supposed everywhere to stand for actions in their own nature right and
wrong: and as far as they really are so applied, they so far are coincident
with the divine law above mentioned. But yet, whatever is pretended, this is
visible, that these names, virtue and vice, in the particular instances of
their application, through the several nations and societies of men in the
world, are constantly attributed only to such actions as in each country and
society are in reputation or discredit. Nor is it to be thought strange, that
men everywhere should give the name of virtue to those actions, which amongst
them are judged praiseworthy; and call that vice, which they account blamable:
since otherwise they would condemn themselves, if they should think anything
right, to which they allowed not commendation, anything wrong, which they let
pass without blame. Thus the measure of what is everywhere called and esteemed
virtue and vice is this approbation or dislike, praise or blame, which, by a
secret and tacit consent, establishes itself in the several societies, tribes,
and clubs of men in the world: whereby several actions come to find credit or
disgrace amongst them, according to the judgment, maxims, or fashion of that
place. For, though men uniting into politic societies, have resigned up to the
public the disposing of all their force, so that they cannot employ it against
any fellow-citizens any further than the law of the country directs: yet they
retain still the power of thinking well or ill, approving or disapproving of
the actions of those whom they live amongst, and converse with: and by this
approbation and dislike they establish amongst themselves what they will call
virtue and vice.


11. The Measure that Man commonly apply to determine what they call Virtue and
Vice.


That this is the common MEASURE of virtue and vice, will appear to any one who
considers, that, though that passes for vice in one country which is counted a
virtue, or at least not vice, in another, yet everywhere virtue and praise,
vice and blame, go together. Virtue is everywhere, that which is thought
praiseworthy; and nothing else but that which has the allowance of public
esteem is called virtue. Virtue and praise are so united, that they are called
often by the same name. Sunt sua praemia laudi, says Virgil; and so Cicero,
Nihil habet natura praestantius, quam honestatem, quam laudem, quam dignitatem,
quam decus, which he tells you are all names for the same thing. This is the
language of the heathen philosophers, who well understood wherein their notions
of virtue and vice consisted. And though perhaps, by the different temper,
education, fashion, maxims, or interest of different sorts of men, it fell out,
that what was thought praiseworthy in one place, escaped not censure in
another; and so in different societies, virtues and vices were changed; yet, as
to the main, they for the most part kept the same everywhere. For, since
nothing can be more natural than to encourage with esteem and reputation that
wherein every one finds his advantage, and to blame and discountenance the
contrary; it is no wonder that esteem and discredit, virtue and vice, should,
in a great measure, everywhere correspond with the unchangeable rule of right
and wrong, which the law of God hath established; there being nothing that so
directly and visibly secures and advances the general good of mankind in this
world, as obedience to the laws he had set them, and nothing that breeds such
mischiefs and confusion, as the neglect of them. And therefore men, without
renouncing all sense and reason, and their own interest, which they are so
constantly true to, could not generally mistake, in placing their commendation
and blame on that side that really deserved it not. Nay, even those men whose
practice was otherwise, failed not to give their approbation right, few being
depraved to that degree as not to condemn, at least in others, the faults they
themselves were guilty of; whereby, even in the corruption of manners, the true
boundaries of the law of nature, which ought to be the rule of virtue and vice,
were pretty well preferred. So that even the exhortations of inspired teachers,
have not feared to appeal to common repute: ‘Whatsoever is lovely, whatsoever
is of good report, if there be any virtue, if there be any praise,’ &c.
(Phil. iv. 8.)


12. Its Inforcement is Commendation and Discredit.


If any one shall imagine that I have forgot my own notion of a law, when I make
the law, whereby men judge of virtue and vice, to be nothing else but the
consent of private men, who have not authority enough to make a law: especially
wanting that which is so necessary and essential to a law, a power to enforce
it: I think I may say, that he who imagines commendation and disgrace not to be
strong motives to men to accommodate themselves to the opinions and rules of
those with whom they converse, seems little skilled in the nature or history of
mankind: the greatest part whereof we shall find to govern themselves chiefly,
if not solely, by this LAW OF FASHION; and so they do that which keeps them in
reputation with their company, little regard the laws of God, or the
magistrate. The penalties that attend the breach of God’s laws some, nay
perhaps most men, seldom seriously reflect on: and amongst those that do, many,
whilst they break the law, entertain thoughts of future reconciliation, and
making their peace for such breaches. And as to the punishments due from the
laws of the commonwealth, they frequently flatter themselves with the hopes of
impunity. But no man escapes the punishment of their censure and dislike, who
offends against the fashion and opinion of the company he keeps, and would
recommend himself to. Nor is there one of ten thousand, who is stiff and
insensible enough, to bear up under the constant dislike and condemnation of
his own club. He must be of a strange and unusual constitution, who can content
himself to live in constant disgrace and disrepute with his own particular
society. Solitude many men have sought, and been reconciled to: but nobody that
has the least thought or sense of a man about him, can live in society under
the constant dislike and ill opinion of his familiars, and those he converses
with. This is a burden too heavy for human sufferance: and he must be made up
of irreconcileable contradictions, who can take pleasure in company, and yet be
insensible of contempt and disgrace from his companions.


13. These three Laws the Rules of moral Good and Evil.


These three then, first, the law of God; secondly, the law of politic
societies; thirdly, the law of fashion, or private censure, are those to which
men variously compare their actions: and it is by their conformity to one of
these laws that they take their measures, when they would judge of their moral
rectitude, and denominate their actions good or bad.


14. Morality is the Relation of Voluntary Actions to these Rules.


Whether the rule to which, as to a touchstone, we bring our voluntary actions,
to examine them by, and try their goodness, and accordingly to name them, which
is, as it were, the mark of the value we set upon them: whether, I say, we take
that rule from the fashion of the country, or the will of a law-maker, the mind
is easily able to observe the relation any action hath to it, and to judge
whether the action agrees or disagrees with the rule; and so hath a notion of
moral goodness or evil, which is either conformity or not conformity of any
action to that rule: and therefore is often called moral rectitude. This rule
being nothing but a collection of several simple ideas, the conformity thereto
is but so ordering the action, that the simple ideas belonging to it may
correspond to those which the law requires. And thus we see how moral beings
and notions are founded on, and terminated in, these simple ideas we have
received from sensation or reflection. For example: let us consider the complex
idea we signify by the word murder: and when we have taken it asunder, and
examined all the particulars, we shall find them to amount to a collection of
simple ideas derived from reflection or sensation, viz. First, from REFLECTION
on the operations of our own minds, we have the ideas of willing, considering,
purposing beforehand, malice, or wishing ill to another; and also of life, or
perception, and self-motion. Secondly, from SENSATION we have the collection of
those simple sensible ideas which are to be found in a man, and of some action,
whereby we put an end to perception and motion in the man; all which simple
ideas are comprehended in the word murder. This collection of simple ideas,
being found by me to agree or disagree with the esteem of the country I have
been bred in, and to be held by most men there worthy praise or blame, I call
the action virtuous or vicious: if I have the will of a supreme invisible
Lawgiver for my rule, then, as I supposed the action commanded or forbidden by
God, I call it good or evil, sin or duty: and if I compare it to the civil law,
the rule made by the legislative power of the country, I call it lawful or
unlawful, a crime or no crime. So that whencesoever we take the rule of moral
actions; or by what standard soever we frame in our minds the ideas of virtues
or vices, they consist only, and are made up of collections of simple ideas,
which we originally received from sense or reflection: and their rectitude or
obliquity consists in the agreement or disagreement with those patterns
prescribed by some law.


15. Moral actions may be regarded either absolutely, or as ideas of relation.


To conceive rightly of moral actions, we must take notice of them under this
two-fold consideration. First, as they are in themselves, each made up of such
a collection of simple ideas. Thus drunkenness, or lying, signify such or such
a collection of simple ideas, which I call mixed modes: and in this sense they
are as much POSITIVE ABSOLUTE ideas, as the drinking of a horse, or speaking of
a parrot. Secondly, our actions are considered as good, bad, or indifferent;
and in this respect they are RELATIVE, it being their conformity to, or
disagreement with some rule that makes them to be regular or irregular, good or
bad; and so, as far as they are compared with a rule, and thereupon
denominated, they come under relation. Thus the challenging and fighting with a
man, as it is a certain positive mode, or particular sort of action, by
particular ideas, distinguished from all others, is called DUELLING: which,
when considered in relation to the law of God, will deserve the name of sin; to
the law of fashion, in some countries, valour and virtue; and to the municipal
laws of some governments, a capital crime. In this case, when the positive mode
has one name, and another name as it stands in relation to the law, the
distinction may as easily be observed as it is in substances, where one name,
v.g. MAN, is used to signify the thing; another, v.g. FATHER, to signify the
relation.


16. The Denominations of Actions often mislead us.


But because very frequently the positive idea of the action, and its moral
relation, are comprehended together under one name, and the same word made use
of to express both the mode or action, and its moral rectitude or obliquity:
therefore the relation itself is less taken notice of; and there is often no
distinction made between the positive idea of the action, and the reference it
has to a rule. By which confusion of these two distinct considerations under
one term, those who yield too easily to the impressions of sounds, and are
forward to take names for things, are often misled in their judgment of
actions. Thus, the taking from another what is his, without his knowledge or
allowance, is properly called STEALING: but that name, being commonly
understood to signify also the moral gravity of the action, and to denote its
contrariety to the law, men are apt to condemn whatever they hear called
stealing, as an ill action, disagreeing with the rule of right. And yet the
private taking away his sword from a madman, to prevent his doing mischief,
though it be properly denominated stealing, as the name of such a mixed mode;
yet when compared to the law of God, and considered in its relation to that
supreme rule, it is no sin or transgression, though the name stealing
ordinarily carries such an intimation with it.


17. Relations innumerable, and only the most considerable here mentioned.


And thus much for the relation of human actions to a law, which, therefore, I
call MORAL RELATIONS.


It would make a volume to go over all sorts of RELATIONS: it is not, therefore,
to be expected that I should here mention them all. It suffices to our present
purpose to show by these, what the ideas are we have of this comprehensive
consideration called RELATION. Which is so various, and the occasions of it so
many, (as many as there can be of comparing things one to another,) that it is
not very easy to reduce it to rules, or under just heads. Those I have
mentioned, I think, are some of the most considerable; and such as may serve to
let us see from whence we get our ideas of relations, and wherein they are
founded. But before I quit this argument, from what has been said give me leave
to observe:


18. All Relations terminate in simple Ideas.


First, That it is evident, that all relation terminates in, and is ultimately
founded on, those simple ideas we have got from sensation or reflection: so
that all we have in our thoughts ourselves, (if we think of anything, or have
any meaning,) or would signify to others, when we use words standing for
relations, is nothing but some simple ideas, or collections of simple ideas,
compared one with another. This is so manifest in that sort called
proportional, that nothing can be more. For when a man says ‘honey is sweeter
than wax,’ it is plain that his thoughts in this relation terminate in this
simple idea, sweetness; which is equally true of all the rest: though, where
they are compounded, or decompounded, the simple ideas they are made up of,
are, perhaps, seldom taken notice of: v.g. when the word father is mentioned:
first, there is meant that particular species, or collective idea, signified by
the word man; secondly, those sensible simple ideas, signified by the word
generation; and, thirdly, the effects of it, and all the simple ideas signified
by the word child. So the word friend, being taken for a man who loves and is
ready to do good to another, has all these following ideas to the making of it
up: first, all the simple ideas, comprehended in the word man, or intelligent
being; secondly, the idea of love; thirdly, the idea of readiness or
disposition; fourthly, the idea of action, which is any kind of thought or
motion; fifthly, the idea of good, which signifies anything that may advance
his happiness, and terminates at last, if examined, in particular simple ideas,
of which the word good in general signifies any one; but, if removed from all
simple ideas quite, it signifies nothing at all. And thus also all moral words
terminate at last, though perhaps more remotely, in a collection of simple
ideas: the immediate signification of relative words, being very often other
supposed known relations; which, if traced one to another, still end in simple
ideas.


19. We have ordinarily as clear a Notion of the Relation, as of the simple
ideas in things on which it is founded.


Secondly, That in relations, we have for the most part, if not always, as clear
a notion of THE RELATION as we have of THOSE SIMPLE IDEAS WHEREIN IT IS
FOUNDED: agreement or disagreement, whereon relation depends, being things
whereof we have commonly as clear ideas as of any other whatsoever; it being
but the distinguishing simple ideas, or their degrees one from another, without
which we could have no distinct knowledge at all. For, if I have a clear idea
of sweetness, light, or extension, I have, too, of equal, or more, or less, of
each of these: if I know what it is for one man to be born of a woman, viz.
Sempronia, I know what it is for another man to be born of the same woman
Sempronia; and so have as clear a notion of brothers as of births, and perhaps
clearer. For if I believed that Sempronia digged Titus out of the parsley-bed,
(as they used to tell children,) and thereby became his mother; and that
afterwards, in the same manner, she digged Caius out of the parsley-bed, I had
as clear a notion of the relation of brothers between them, as if I had all the
skill of a midwife: the notion that the same woman contributed, as mother,
equally to their births, (though I were ignorant or mistaken in the manner of
it,) being that on which I grounded the relation; and that they agreed in the
circumstance of birth, let it be what it will. The comparing them then in their
descent from the same person, without knowing the particular circumstances of
that descent, is enough to found my notion of their having, or not having, the
relation of brothers. But though the ideas of PARTICULAR RELATIONS are capable
of being as clear and distinct in the minds of those who will duly consider
them as those of mixed modes, and more determinate than those of substances:
yet the names belonging to relation are often of as doubtful and uncertain
signification as those of substances or mixed modes; and much more than those
of simple ideas. Because relative words, being the marks of this comparison,
which is made only by men’s thoughts, and is an idea only in men’s minds, men
frequently apply them to different comparisons of things, according to their
own imaginations; which do not always correspond with those of others using the
same name.


20. The Notion of Relation is the same, whether the Rule any Action is compared
to be true or false.


Thirdly, That in these I call MORAL RELATIONS, I have a true notion of
relation, by comparing the action with the rule, whether the rule be true or
false. For if I measure anything by a yard, I know whether the thing I measure
be longer or shorter than that supposed yard, though perhaps the yard I measure
by be not exactly the standard: which indeed is another inquiry. For though the
rule be erroneous, and I mistaken in it; yet the agreement or disagreement
observable in that which I compare with, makes me perceive the relation.
Though, measuring by a wrong rule, I shall thereby be brought to judge amiss of
its moral rectitude; because I have tried it by that which is not the true
rule: yet I am not mistaken in the relation which that action bears to that
rule I compare it to, which is agreement or disagreement.


</div></body></text></TEI>