<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="143">CHAPTER IV.
Theories of Heat.

The Dynamical Theory of Heat.
THAT the transmission of
radiant Heat takes place by means of the vibrations of a
medium, as the transmission of Sound certainly does, and the
transmission of Light most probably, is a theory which, as I have
endeavored to explain, has strong arguments and analogies in its
favor. But that Heat itself, in its essence and quantity, is Motion is
a hypothesis of quite another kind. This hypothesis has been recently
asserted and maintained with great ability. The doctrine thus asserted
is, that Motion may be converted into Heat, and Heat into Motion; that
Heat and Motion may produce each other, as we see in the rarefaction
and condensation of air, in steam-engines, and the like: and that in
all such cases the Motion produced and the Heat expended exactly
measure each other. The foundation of this theory is conceived to have
been laid by Mr. Joule of Manchester, in 1844: and it has since been
prosecuted by him and by Professor Thomson of Glasgow, by experimental
investigations of various kinds. It is difficult to make these
experiments so as to be quite satisfactory; for it is 609 difficult to measure
all the heat gained or lost in any of the changes here
contemplated. That friction, agitation of fluids, condensation of
gases, conversion of gases into fluids and liquids into solids,
produce heat, is undoubted: and that the quantity of such heat may be
measured by the mechanical force which produces it, or which it
produces, is a generalization which will very likely be found a
fertile source of new propositions, and probably of important
consequences.
As an example of the conclusions which Professor Thomson draws from
this doctrine of the mutual conversion of motion and heat, I may
mention his speculations concerning the cause which produces and
sustains the heat of the sun.16 He conceives
that the support of the solar heat must be meteoric matter which is
perpetually falling towards the globe of the sun, and has its motion
converted into heat. He inclines to think that the meteors containing
the stores of energy for future Sun-light must be principally within
the earth’s orbit; and that we actually see them there as the
“Zodiacal Light,” an illuminated shower, or rather tornado, of stones.
The inner parts of this tornado are always getting caught in the Sun’s
atmosphere, and drawn to his mass by gravitation.
16 On the Mechanical Energies of the
Solar System. Edinb. Trans. vol. XXI. part i. (1854), p.
67.


BOOK XI.

ELECTRICITY.
</div></body></text></TEI>