<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="74">CHAPTER XIII.
Confirmation and Extension of the Undulatory
Theory.
AFTER the undulatory theory
had been developed in all its main features, by its great authors,
Young and Fresnel, although it bore marks of truth that could hardly
be fallacious, there was still here, as in the case of other great
theories, a period in which difficulties were to be removed,
objections answered, men’s minds familiarized to the new conceptions
thus presented to them; and in which, also, it might reasonably be
expected that the theory would be extended to facts not at first
included in its domain. This period is, indeed, that in which we are
living; and we might, perhaps with propriety, avoid the task of
speaking of our living contemporaries. But it would be unjust to the
theory not to notice some of the remarkable events, characteristic of
such a period, which have already occurred; and this may be done very
simply. 119
In the case of this great theory, as in that of gravitation, by far
the most remarkable of these confirmatory researches were conducted by
the authors of the discovery, especially Fresnel. And in looking at
what he conceived and executed for this purpose, we are, it appears to
me, strongly reminded of Newton, by the wonderful inventiveness and
sagacity with which he devised experiments, and applied to them
mathematical reasonings.
1. Double Refraction of Compressed Glass.—One of these
confirmatory experiments was the production of double refraction by
the compression of glass. Fresnel observes,107 that though
Sir D. Brewster had shown that glass under compression produced colors
resembling those which are given by doubly-refracting crystals, “very
skilful physicists had not considered those experiments as a
sufficient proof of the bifurcation of the light.” In the hypothesis
of moveable polarization, it is added, there is no apparent connexion
between these phenomena of coloration and double refraction; but on
Young’s theory, that the colors arise from two rays which have
traversed the crystal with different velocities, it appears almost
unavoidable to admit also a difference of path in the two rays.
107 Ann. de Chim. 1822, tom.
xx. p. 377.
“Though,” he says, “I had long since adopted this opinion, it did
not appear to me so completely demonstrated, that it was right to
neglect an experimental verification of it;” and therefore, in 1819,
he proceeded to satisfy himself of the fact, by the phenomena of
diffraction. The trial left no doubt on the subject; but he still
thought it would be interesting actually to produce two images in
glass by compression; and by a highly-ingenious combination,
calculated to exaggerate the effect of the double refraction, which is
very feeble, even when the compression is most intense, he obtained
two distinct images. This evidence of the dependence of dipolarizing
structure upon a doubly-refracting state of particles, thus
excogitated out of the general theory, and verified by trial, may well
be considered, as he says, “as a new occasion of proving the
infallibility of the principle of interferences.”
2. Circular Polarization.—Fresnel then turned his
attention to another set of experiments, related to this indeed, but
by a tie so recondite, that nothing less than his clearness and
acuteness of view could have detected any connexion. The optical
properties of quartz had been perceived to be peculiar, from the
period of the discovery 120 of dipolarized colors by MM. Arago and
Biot. At the end of the Notice just quoted, Fresnel says,108 “As soon as my occupations permit me,
I propose to employ a pile of prisms similar to that which I have
described, in order to study the double refraction of the rays which
traverse crystals of quartz in the direction of the axis.” He then
ventures, without hesitation, to describe beforehand what the
phenomena will be. In the Bulletin des Sciences109 for December, 1822, it is stated that
experiment had confirmed what he had thus announced.
108 Ann. de Chim. 1822, tom.
xx. p. 382.
109 Ib. Ann. de Chim. 1822,
tom. xx. p. 191.
The phenomena are those which have since been spoken of as
circular polarization; and the term first occurs in this
notice.110 They are very remarkable, both by
their resemblances to, and their differences from, the phenomena of
plane-polarized light. And the manner in which Fresnel was led
to this anticipation of the facts is still more remarkable than the
facts themselves. Having ascertained by observation that two
differently-polarized rays, totally reflected at the internal surface
of glass, suffer different retardations of their undulations,
he applied the formulæ which he had obtained for the polarizing effect
of reflection to this case. But in this case the formulæ expressed an
impossibility; yet as algebraical formulæ, even in such cases, have
often some meaning, “I interpreted,” he says,111 “in the manner
which appeared to me most natural and most probable, what the analysis
indicated by this imaginary form;” and by such an interpretation he
collected the law of the difference of undulation of the two rays. He
was thus able to predict that by two internal reflections in a
rhomb, or parallelopiped of glass, of a certain form and
position, a polarized ray would acquire a circular undulation of its
particles; and this constitution of the ray, it appeared, by reasoning
further, would show itself by its possessing peculiar properties,
partly the same as those of polarized light, and partly different.
This extraordinary anticipation was exactly confirmed; and thus the
apparently bold and strange guess of the author was fully justified,
or at least assented to, even by the most cautious philosophers. “As I
cannot appreciate the mathematical evidence for the nature of circular
polarization,” says Prof. Airy,112 “I shall
mention the experimental evidence on which I receive it.” The
conception has since been universally adopted.
110 Ib. p. 194.
111 Bullet. des Sc. 1823, p.
33.
112 Camb. Trans. vol. iv. p.
81, 1831.
But Fresnel, having thus obtained circularly-polarized rays, saw
121 that he could
account for the phenomena of quartz, already observed by M. Arago, as
we have noticed in Chap. ix., by supposing two
circularly-polarized rays to pass, with different velocities, along
the axis. The curious succession of colors, following each other in
right-handed or left-handed circular order, of which we have already spoken, might thus be hypothetically
explained.
But was this hypothesis of two circularly-polarized rays,
travelling along the axis of such crystals, to be received, merely
because it accounted for the phenomena? Fresnel’s ingenuity again
enabled him to avoid such a defect in theorizing. If there were two
such rays, they might be visibly separated113 by the same
artifice, of a pile of prisms properly achromatized, which he had used
for compressed glass. The result was, that he did obtain a visible
separation of the rays; and this result has since been confirmed by
others, for instance. Professor Airy.114 The rays were
found to be in all respects identical with the circularly-polarized
rays produced by the internal reflections in Fresnel’s rhomb. This
kind of double refraction gave a hypothetical explanation of the laws
which M. Biot had obtained for the phenomena of this class; for
example,115 the rule, that the deviation of the
plane of polarization of the emergent ray is inversely as the square
of the length of an undulation for each kind of rays. And thus the
phenomena produced by light passing along the axis of quartz were
reduced into complete conformity with the theory.
113 Bull. des Sc. 1822, p.
193.
114 Cambridge Trans. iv. p.
80.
115 Bull. des Sc. 1822, p.
197.
[2nd Ed.] [I believe, however, Fresnel did not deduce the
phenomenon from the mathematical formula, without the previous
suggestion of experiment. He observed appearances which
implied a difference of retardation in the two differently-polarized
rays at total reflection; as Sir D. Brewster observed in reflection of
metals phenomena having a like character. The general fact being
observed, Fresnel used the theory to discover the law of this
retardation, and to determine a construction in which, one ray being a
quarter of an undulation retarded more than the other, circular
polarization would be produced. And this anticipation was verified by
the construction of his rhomb.
As a still more curious verification of this law, another of
Fresnel’s experiments may be mentioned. He found the proper angles for
a circularly-polarizing glass rhomb on the supposition that there were
122 four
internal reflections instead of two; two of the four taking place when
the surface of the glass was dry, and two when it was wet. The rhomb
was made; and when all the points of reflection were dry, the light
was not circularly polarized; when two points were wet, the light was
circularly polarized; and when all four were wet, it was not
circularly polarized.]
3. Elliptical Polarization in Quartz.—We now come to
one of the few additions to Fresnel’s theory which have been shown to
be necessary. He had accounted fully for the colors produced by the
rays which travel along the axis of quartz crystals; and
thus, for the colors and changes of the central spot which is produced
when polarized light passes through a transverse plate of such
crystals. But this central spot is surrounded by rings of colors. How
is the theory to be extended to these?
This extension has been successfully made by Professor Airy.116 His hypothesis is, that as rays
passing along the axis of a quartz crystal are circularly polarized,
rays which are oblique to the axis are elliptically polarized, the
amount of ellipticity depending, in some unknown manner, upon the
obliquity; and that each ray is separated by double refraction into
two rays polarized elliptically; the one right-handed, the other
left-handed. By means of these suppositions, he not only was enabled
to account for the simple phenomena of single plates of quartz; but
for many most complex and intricate appearances which arise from the
superposition of two plates, and which at first sight might appear to
defy all attempts to reduce them to law and symmetry; such as spirals,
curves approaching to a square form, curves broken in four places. “I
can hardly imagine,” he says,117 very
naturally, “that any other supposition would represent the phenomena
to such extreme accuracy. I am not so much struck with the accounting
for the continued dilatation of circles, and the general
representation of the forms of spirals, as with the explanations of
the minute deviations from symmetry; as when circles become almost
square, and crosses are inclined to the plane of polarization. And I
believe that any one who shall follow my investigation, and imitate my
experiments, will be surprised at their perfect agreement.”
116 Camb. Trans., iv. p. 83,
&c.
117 Camb. Trans., iv. p.
122.
4. Differential Equations of Elliptical
Polarization.—Although circular and elliptical polarization
can be clearly conceived, and their existence, it would seem,
irresistibly established by the phenomena, it 123 is extremely difficult to conceive any
arrangement of the particles of bodies by which such motions can
mechanically be produced; and this difficulty is the greater, because
some fluids and some gases impress a circular polarization upon light;
in which cases we cannot imagine any definite arrangement of the
particles, such as might form the mechanism requisite for the purpose.
Accordingly, it does not appear that any one has been able to suggest
even a plausible hypothesis on that subject. Yet, even here, something
has been done. Professor Mac Cullagh, of Dublin, has discovered that
by slightly modifying the analytical expressions resulting from
the common case of the propagation of light, we may obtain other
expressions which would give rise to such motions as produce circular
and elliptical polarization. And though we cannot as yet assign the
mechanical interpretation of the language of analysis thus
generalized, this generalization brings together and explains by one
common numerical supposition, two distinct classes of facts;—a
circumstance which, in all cases, entitles an hypothesis to a very
favorable consideration.
Mr. Mac Cullagh’s assumption consists in adding to the two
equations of motion which are expressed by means of second
differentials, two other terms involving third differentials in a
simple and symmetrical manner. In doing this, he introduces a
coefficient, of which the magnitude determines both the amount of
rotation of the polarization of a ray passing along the axis, as
observed and measured by Biot, and the ellipticity of the polarization
of a ray which is oblique to the axis, according to Mr. Airy’s theory,
of which ellipticity that philosopher also had obtained certain
measures. The agreement between the two sets of measures118 thus brought into connexion is such as
very strikingly to confirm Mr. Mac Cullagh’s hypothesis. It appears
probable, too, that the confirmation of this hypothesis involves,
although in an obscure and oracular form, a confirmation of the
undulatory theory, which is the starting-point of this curious
speculation.
118 Royal I. A. Trans.
1836.
5. Elliptical Polarization of Metals.—The effect of
metals upon the light which they reflect, was known from the first to
be different from that which transparent bodies produce. Sir David
Brewster, who has recently examined this subject very fully,119 has described the modification thus
produced, as elliptic polarization. In employing this term, “he
seems to have been led,” it has been observed,120 “by a 124 desire to avoid as
much as possible all reference to theory. The laws which he has
obtained, however, belong to elliptically-polarized light in the sense
in which the term was introduced by Fresnel.” And the identity of the
light produced by metallic reflection with the elliptically-polarized
light of the wave-theory, is placed beyond all doubt, by an
observation of Professor Airy, that the rings of uniaxal crystals,
produced by Fresnel’s elliptically-polarized light, are exactly the
same as those produced by Brewster’s metallic light.
119 Phil. Trans. 1830.
120 Lloyd, Report on Optics,
p. 372. (Brit. Assoc.)
6. Newton’s Rings by Polarized Light.—Other
modifications of the phenomena of thin plates by the use of polarized
light, supplied other striking confirmations of the theory. These were
in one case the more remarkable, since the result was foreseen by
means of a rigorous application of the conception of the vibratory
motion of light, and confirmed by experiment. Professor Airy, of
Cambridge, was led by his reasonings to see, that if Newton’s rings
are produced between a lens and a plate of metal, by polarized light,
then, up to the polarizing angle, the central spot will be black, and
instantly beyond this, it will be white. In a note,121 in which he announced this, he says,
“This I anticipated from Fresnel’s expressions; it is confirmatory of
them, and defies emission.” He also predicted that when the rings were
produced between two substances of very different refractive powers,
the centre would twice pass from black to white and from white to
black, by increasing the angle; which anticipation was fulfilled by
using a diamond for the higher refraction.122
121 Addressed to myself, dated May
28, 1831. I ought, however, to notice, that this experiment had been
made by M. Arago, fifteen years earlier, and published: though not
then recollected by Mr. Airy.
122 Camb. Trans. vol. ii. p.
409.
7. Conical Refraction.—In the same
manner. Professor Hamilton of Dublin pointed out that according to the
Fresnelian doctrine of double refraction, there is a certain direction
of a crystal in which a single ray of light will be refracted so as to
form a conical pencil. For the direction of the refracted ray
is determined by a plane which touches the wave surface, the rule
being that the ray must pass from the centre of the surface to the
point of contact; and though in general this contact gives a single
point only, it so happens, from the peculiar inflected form of the
wave surface, which has what is called a cusp, that in one
particular position, the plane can touch the surface in an entire
circle. Thus the general rule which assigns the path of 125 the refracted ray,
would, in this case, guide it from the centre of the surface to every
point in the circumference of the circle, and thus make it a cone.
This very curious and unexpected result, which Professor Hamilton thus
obtained from the theory, his friend Professor Lloyd verified as an
experimental fact. We may notice, also, that Professor Lloyd found the
light of the conical pencil to be polarized according to a law of an
unusual kind; but one which was easily seen to be in complete
accordance with the theory.
8. Fringes of Shadows.—The phenomena of the fringes
of shadows of small holes and groups of holes, which had been the
subject of experiment by Fraunhofer, were at a later period carefully
observed in a vast variety of cases by M. Schwerd of Spires, and
published in a separate work,123
Beugungs-erscheinungen (Phenomena of Inflection), 1836. In this
Treatise, the author has with great industry and skill calculated the
integrals which, as we have seen, are requisite in order to trace the
consequences of the theory; and the accordance which he finds between
these and the varied and brilliant results of observation is
throughout exact. “I shall,” says he, in the preface,124 “prove by the present Treatise, that
all inflection-phenomena, through openings of any form, size, and
arrangement, are not only explained by the undulation-theory, but that
they can be represented by analytical expressions, determining the
intensity of the light in any point whatever.” And he justly adds,
that the undulation-theory accounts for the phenomena of light, as
completely as the theory of gravitation does for the facts of the
solar system.
123 Die Beugungs-erscheinungen,
aus dem Fundamental-gesetz der Undulations-Theorie analytisch
entwickelt und in Bildern dargestellt, von F. M. Schwerd.
Mannheim, 1835.
124 Dated Speyer, Aug. 1835.
9. Objections to the Theory.—We have hitherto
mentioned only cases in which the undulatory theory was either
entirely successful in explaining the facts, or at least
hypothetically consistent with them and with itself. But other
objections were started, and some difficulties were long considered as
very embarrassing. Objections were made to the theory by some English
experimenters, as Mr. Potter, Mr. Barton, and others. These appeared
in scientific journals, and were afterwards answered in similar
publications. The objections depended partly on the measure of the
intensity of light in the different points of the phenomena
(a datum which it is very difficult to obtain with accuracy 126 by experiment), and
partly on misconceptions of the theory; and I believe there are none
of them which would now be insisted on.
We may mention, also, another difficulty, which it was the habit of
the opponents of the theory to urge as a reproach against it, long
after it had been satisfactorily explained: I mean the
half-undulation which Young and Fresnel had found it necessary,
in some cases, to assume as gained or lost by one of the rays. Though
they and their followers could not analyse the mechanism of reflection
with sufficient exactness to trace out all the circumstances, it was
not difficult to see, upon Fresnel’s principles, that reflection from
the interior and exterior surface of glass must be of opposite kinds,
which might be expressed by supposing one of these rays to lose half
an undulation. And thus there came into view a justification of the
step which had originally been taken upon empirical grounds alone.
10. Dispersion, on the Undulatory Theory.—A difficulty
of another kind occasioned a more serious and protracted embarrassment
to the cultivators of this theory. This was the apparent impossibility
of accounting, on the theory, for the prismatic dispersion of color.
For it had been shown by Newton that the amount of refraction is
different for every color; and the amount of refraction depends on the
velocity with which light is propagated. Yet the theory suggested no
reason why the velocity should be different for different colors: for,
by mathematical calculation, vibrations of all degrees of rapidity (in
which alone colors differ) are propagated with the same speed. Nor
does analogy lead us to expect this variety. There is no such
difference between quick and slow waves of air. The sounds of the
deepest and the highest bells of a peal are heard at any distance in
the same order. Here, therefore, the theory was at fault.
But this defect was far from being a fatal one. For though the
theory did not explain, it did not contradict, dispersion. The
suppositions on which the calculations had been conducted, and the
analogy of sound, were obviously in no small degree precarious. The
velocity of propagation might differ for different rates of
undulation, in virtue of many causes which would not affect the
general theoretical results.
Many such hypothetical causes were suggested by various eminent
mathematicians, as solutions of this conspicuous difficulty. But
without dwelling upon these conjectures, it may suffice to notice that
hypothesis upon which the attention of mathematicians was soon
concentrated. This was the hypothesis of finite intervals
between the 127
particles of the ether. The length of one of those undulations which
produce light, is a very small quantity, its mean value being 1⁄50,000th
of an inch; but in the previous investigations of the consequences of
the theory, it had been assumed that the distance from each other, of
the particles of the ether, which, by their attractions or repulsions,
caused the undulations to be propagated, is indefinitely less than
this small quantity;—so that its amount might be neglected in
the cases in which the length of the undulation was one of the
quantities which determined the result. But this assumption was made
arbitrarily, as a step of simplification, and because it was imagined
that, in this way, a nearer approach was made to the case of a
continuous fluid ether, which the supposition of distinct particles
imperfectly represented. It was still free for mathematicians to
proceed upon the opposite assumption, of particles of which the
distances were finite, either as a mathematical basis of calculation,
or as a physical hypothesis; and it remained to be seen if, when this
was done, the velocity of light would still be the same for different
lengths of undulation, that is, for different colors. M. Cauchy,
calculating, upon the most general principles, the motion of such a
collection of particles as would form an elastic medium, obtained
results which included the new extension of the previous hypothesis.
Professor Powell, of Oxford, applied himself to reduce to calculation,
and to compare with experiment, the result of these researches. And it
appeared that, on M. Cauchy’s principles, a variation in the velocity
of light is produced by a variation in the length of the wave,
provided that the interval between the molecules of the ether bears a
sensible ratio to the length of an undulation.125 Professor
Powell obtained also, from the general expressions, a formula
expressing the relation between the refractive index of a ray, and the
length of a wave, or the color of light.126 It then became
his task to ascertain whether this relation obtained experimentally;
and he found a very close agreement between the numbers which resulted
from the formula and those observed by Fraunhofer, for ten different
kinds of media, namely, certain glasses and fluids.127 To these he afterwards added ten other
cases of crystals observed by M. Rudberg.128 Mr. Kelland,
of Cambridge, also calculated, in a manner somewhat different, the
results of the same hypothesis of finite intervals;129 and, obtaining 128 formulæ not exactly
the same as Professor Powell, found also an agreement between these
and Fraunhofer’s observations.
125 Phil. Mag. vol. vi. p.
266.
126 Ib. vol. vii. 1835, p. 266.
127 Phil. Trans. 1835, p.
249.
128 Ib. 1836, p. 17.
129 Camb. Trans. vol.  vi. p.
153.
It may be observed, that the refractive indices observed and
employed in these comparisons, were not those determined by the color
of the ray, which is not capable of exact identification, but those
more accurate measures which Fraunhofer was enabled to make, in
consequence of having detected in the spectrum the black lines which
he called B, C, D, E, F, G, H. The agreement between the theoretical
formulæ and the observed numbers is remarkable, throughout all the
series of comparisons of which we have spoken. Yet we must at present
hesitate to pronounce upon the hypothesis of finite intervals, as
proved by these calculations; for though this hypothesis has given
results agreeing so closely with experiment, it is not yet clear that
other hypotheses may not produce an equal agreement. By the nature of
the case, there must be a certain gradation and continuity in the
succession of colors in the spectrum, and hence, any supposition which
will account for the general fact of the whole dispersion, may
possibly account for the amount of the intermediate dispersions,
because these must be interpolations between the extremes. The result
of this hypothetical calculation, however, shows very satisfactorily
that there is not, in the fact of dispersion, anything which is at all
formidable to the undulatory theory.
11. Conclusion.—There are several other
of the more recondite points of the theory which may be considered as,
at present, too undecided to allow us to speak historically of the
discussions which they have occasioned.130 For example,
it was conceived, for some time, that the vibrations of polarized
light are perpendicular to the plane of polarization. But this
assumption was not an essential part of the theory; and all the
phenomena would equally allow us to suppose the vibrations to be in
the polarization plane; the main requisite being, that light polarized
in planes at right angles to each other, should also have the
vibrations at right angles. Accordingly, for some time, this point was
left undecided by Young and Fresnel, and, more recently, some
mathematicians have come to the opinion that ether vibrates in the
plane of polarization. The theory of transverse vibrations is equally
stable, whichever supposition may be finally confirmed. ~Additional
material in the 3rd edition.~
130  For on account of these, see
Professor Lloyd’s Report on Physical Optics. (Brit. Assoc.
Report, 1834.)
We may speak, in the same manner, of the suppositions which, from
129 the time of
Young and Fresnel, the cultivators of this theory have been led to
make respecting the mechanical constitution of the ether, and the
forces by which transverse vibrations are produced. It was natural
that various difficulties should arise upon such points, for
transverse vibrations had not previously been made the subject of
mechanical calculation, and the forces which occasion them must act in
a different manner from those which were previously contemplated.
Still, we may venture to say, without entering into these discussions,
that it has appeared, from all the mathematical reasonings which have
been pursued, that there is not, in the conception of transverse
vibrations, anything inconsistent either with the principles of
mechanics, or with the best general views which we can form, of the
forces by which the universe is held together.
I willingly speak as briefly as the nature of my undertaking
allows, of those points of the undulatory theory which are still under
deliberation among mathematicians. With respect to these, an intimate
acquaintance with mathematics and physics is necessary to enable any
one to understand the steps which are made from day to day; and still
higher philosophical qualifications would be requisite in order to
pronounce a judgment upon them. I shall, therefore, conclude this
survey by remarking the highly promising condition of this great
department of science, in respect to the character of its cultivators.
Nothing less than profound thought and great mathematical skill can
enable any one to deal with this theory, in any way likely to promote
the interests of science. But there appears, in the horizon of the
scientific world, a considerable class of young mathematicians, who
are already bringing to these investigations the requisite talents and
zeal; and who, having acquired their knowledge of the theory since the
time when its acceptation was doubtful, possess, without effort, that
singleness and decision of view as to its fundamental doctrines, which
it is difficult for those to attain whose minds have had to go through
the hesitation, struggle, and balance of the epoch of the
establishment of the theory. In the hands of this new generation, it
is reasonable to suppose the Analytical Mechanics of light will be
improved as much as the Analytical Mechanics of the solar system was
by the successors of Newton. We have already had to notice many of
this younger race of undulationists. For besides MM. Cauchy, Poisson,
and Ampère, M. Lamé has been more recently following these researches
in France.131 In 130 Belgium, M. Quetelet has given great
attention to them; and, in our own country, Sir William Hamilton, and
Professor Lloyd, of Dublin, have been followed by Mr. Mac Cullagh.
Professor Powell, of Oxford, has continued his researches with
unremitting industry; and, at Cambridge, Professor Airy, who did much
for the establishment and diffusion of the theory before he was
removed to the post of Astronomer Royal, at Greenwich, has had the
satisfaction to see his labors continued by others, even to the most
recent time; for Mr. Kelland,132 whom we have
already mentioned, and Mr. Archibald Smith,133 the two
persons who, in 1834 and 1836, received the highest mathematical
honors which that university can bestow, have both of them published
investigations respecting the undulatory theory.
131 Prof. Lloyd’s Report, p.
392.
132 On the Dispersion of Light, as
explained by the Hypothesis of Finite Intervals. Camb. Trans. vol.
vi. p. 153.
133 Investigation of the Equation
to Fresnel’s Wave Surface, ib. p. 85. See also, in the same
volume, Mathematical Considerations on the Problem of the
Rainbow, showing it to belong to Physical Optics, by R. Potter,
Esq., of Queen’s College.
We may be permitted to add, as a reflection obviously suggested by
these facts, that the cause of the progress of science is incalculably
benefited by the existence of a body of men, trained and stimulated to
the study of the higher mathematics, such as exist in the British
universities, who are thus prepared, when an abstruse and sublime
theory comes before the world with all the characters of truth, to
appreciate its evidence, to take steady hold of its principles, to
pursue its calculations, and thus to convert into a portion of the
permanent treasure and inheritance of the civilized world, discoveries
which might otherwise expire with the great geniuses who produced
them, and be lost for ages, as, in former times, great scientific
discoveries have sometimes been.
The reader who is acquainted with the history of recent optical
discovery, will see that we have omitted much which has justly excited
admiration; as, for example, the phenomena produced by glass under
heat or pressure, noticed by MM. Lobeck, and Biot, and Brewster, and
many most curious properties of particular minerals. We have omitted,
too, all notice of the phenomena and laws of the absorption of light,
which hitherto stand unconnected with the theory. But in this we have
not materially deviated from our main design; for our end, in what we
have done, has been to trace the advances of Optics 131 towards perfection as
a theory; and this task we have now nearly executed as far as our
abilities allow.
We have been desirous of showing that the type of this
progress, in the histories of the two great sciences, Physical
Astronomy and Physical Optics, is the same. In both we have many
Laws of Phenomena detected and accumulated by acute and
inventive men; we have Preludial guesses which touch the true
theory, but which remain for a time imperfect, undeveloped,
unconfirmed: finally we have the Epoch when this true theory,
clearly apprehended by great philosophical geniuses, is recommended by
its fully explaining what it was first meant to explain, and confirmed
by its explaining what it was not meant to explain. We have then its
Progress struggling for a little while with adverse
prepossessions and difficulties; finally overcoming all these, and
moving onwards, while its triumphal procession is joined by all the
younger and more vigorous men of science.
It would, perhaps, be too fanciful to attempt to establish a
parallelism between the prominent persons who figure in these two
histories. If we were to do this, we must consider Huyghens and Hooke
as standing in the place of Copernicus, since, like him, they
announced the true theory, but left it to a future age to give it
development and mechanical confirmation; Malus and Brewster, grouping
them together, correspond to Tycho Brahe and Kepler, laborious in
accumulating observations, inventive and happy in discovering laws of
phenomena; and Young and Fresnel combined, make up the Newton of
optical science.
[2nd Ed.] [In the Report on Physical Optics, (Brit. Ass.
Reports, 1834,) by Prof. Lloyd, the progress of the mathematical
theory after Fresnel’s labors is stated more distinctly than I have
stated it, to the following effect. Ampère, in 1828, proved Fresnel’s
mathematical results directly, which Fresnel had only proved
indirectly, and derived from his proof Fresnel’s beautiful geometrical
construction. Prof. Mac Cullagh not long after gave a concise
demonstration of the same theorem, and of the other principal points
of Fresnel’s theory. He represents the elastic force by means of an
ellipsoid whose axes are inversely proportional to those of Fresnel’s
generating ellipsoid, and deduces Fresnel’s construction
geometrically. In the third Supplement to his Essay on the Theory
of Systems of Rays (Trans. R. I. Acad. vol. xvii.), Sir W.
Hamilton has presented that portion of Fresnel’s theory which relates
to the fundamental problem of the determination of the velocity and
polarization of a plane wave, in a very elegant and analytical form.
This he does by means of what he calls the 132 characteristic function of the
optical system to which the problem belongs. From this function is
deduced the surface of wave-slowness of the medium; and by
means of this surface, the direction of the rays refracted into the
medium. From this construction also Sir W. Hamilton was led to the
anticipation of conical refraction, mentioned above.
The investigations of MM. Cauchy and Lamé refer to the laws by
which the particles of the ether act upon each other and upon the
particles of other bodies;—a field of speculation which appears
to me not yet ripe for the final operations of the analyst.
Among the mathematicians who have supplied defects in Fresnel’s
reasoning on this subject, I may mention Mr. Tovey, who treated it in
several papers in the Philosophical Magazine (1837–40). Mr.
Tovey’s early death must be deemed a loss to mathematical science.
Besides investigating the motion of symmetrical systems of
particles which may be supposed to correspond to biaxal crystals, Mr.
Tovey considered the case of unsymmetrical systems, and found that the
undulations propagated would, in the general case, be elliptical; and
that in a particular case, circular undulations would take place, such
as are propagated along the axis of quartz. It appears to me, however,
that he has not given a definite meaning to those limitations of his
general hypothesis which conduct him to this result. Perhaps if the
hypothetical conditions of this result were traced into detail, they
would be found to reside in a screw-like arrangement of the
elementary particles, in some degree such as crystals of quartz
themselves exhibit in their forms, when they have plagihedral faces at
both ends.
Such crystals of quartz are, some like a right-handed and some like
a left-handed screw; and, as Sir John Herschel discovered, the
circular polarization is right-handed or left-handed according as the
plagihedral form is so. In Mr. Tovey’s hypothetical investigation it
does not appear upon what part of the hypothesis this difference of
right and left-handed depends. The definition of this part of the
hypothesis is a very desirable step.
When crystals of Quartz are right-handed at one end, they are
right-handed at the other end: but there is a different kind of
plagihedral form, which occurs in some other crystals, for instance,
in Apatite: in these the plagihedral faces are right-handed at the one
extremity and left-handed at the other. For the sake of distinction,
we may call the former homologous plagihedral faces, since, at
both ends, they have the same name; and the latter heterologous
plagihedral faces. 133
The homologous plagihedral faces of Quartz crystals are accompanied
by homologous circular polarization of the same name. I do not know
that heterologous circular polarization has been observed in any
crystal, but it has been discovered by Dr. Faraday to occur in glass,
&c., when subjected to powerful magnetic action.
Perhaps it was presumptuous in me to attempt to draw such
comparisons, especially with regard to living persons, as I have done
in the preceding pages of this Book. Having published this passage,
however, I shall not now suppress it. But I may observe that the
immense number and variety of the beautiful optical discoveries which
we owe to Sir David Brewster makes the comparison in his case a very
imperfect representation of his triumphs over nature; and that,
besides his place in the history of the Theory of Optics, he must hold
a most eminent position in the history of Optical Crystallography,
whenever the discovery of a True Optical Theory of Crystals supplies
us with the Epoch to which his labors in this field form so
rich a Prelude. I cordially assent to the expression employed
by Mr. Airy in the Phil. Trans. for 1840, in which he speaks of
Sir David Brewster as “the Father of Modern Experimental Optics.”]
~Additional material in the 3rd
edition.~


BOOK X.

SECONDARY MECHANICAL SCIENCES.
(CONTINUED.)

HISTORY
OF
THERMOTICS AND ATMOLOGY.

Et primum faciunt ignem se vortere in auras
Aëris; hinc imbrem gigni terramque creari
Ex imbri; retroque a terrâ cuncta revorti,
Humorem primum, post aëra deinde calorem;
Nec cessare hæc inter se mutare, meare,
De cœlo ad terram de terrâ ad sidera mundi.
Lucretius, i.
783.   

Water, and Air, and Fire, alternate run
Their endless circle, multiform, yet one.
For, moulded by the fervor’s latent beams,
Solids flow loose, and fluids flash to
steams,
And elemental flame, with secret force,
Pursues through earth, air, sky, its stated
course.

</div></body></text></TEI>