<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="94">CHAPTER I.
Improvement of the Notion of Chemical Analysis, and
Recognition of it as the Spagiric Art.
THE doctrine of “the four
elements” is one of the oldest monuments of man’s speculative nature;
goes back, perhaps, to times anterior to Greek philosophy; and as the
doctrine of Aristotle and Galen, reigned for fifteen hundred years
over the Gentile, Christian, and Mohammedan world. In medicine, taught
as the doctrine of the four “elementary qualities,” of which the human
body and all other substances are compounded, it had a very powerful
and extensive influence upon medical practice. But this doctrine never
led to any attempt actually to analyse bodies into their supposed
elements: for composition was inferred from the resemblance of the
qualities, not from the separate exhibition of the ingredients; the
supposed analysis was, in short, a decomposition of the body into
adjectives, not into substances.
This doctrine, therefore, may be considered as a negative state,
antecedent to the very beginning of chemistry; and some progress
beyond this mere negation was made, as soon as men began to endeavor
to compound and decompound substances by the use of fire or mixture,
however erroneous might be the opinions and expectations which they
combined with their attempts. Alchemy is a step in chemistry, so far
as it implies the recognition of the work of the cupel and the retort,
as the produce of analysis and synthesis. How perplexed and perverted
were the forms in which this recognition was clothed,—how mixed
up with mythical follies and extravagancies, we have already seen; and the share which Alchemy had in
the formation of any sounder knowledge, is not such as to justify any
further notice of that pursuit.
The result of the attempts to analyse bodies by heat, mixture, and
the like processes, was the doctrine that the first principles of
things are three, not four; namely, salt,
sulphur, and mercury; and that, of these three, all
things are compounded. In reality, the doctrine, as thus stated,
contained no truth which was of any value; for, though the chemist
could extract from most bodies portions which he called salt, 262 and sulphur, and
mercury, these names were given, rather to save the hypothesis, than
because the substances were really those usually so called: and thus
the supposed analyses proved nothing, as Boyle justly urged against
them.1
1 Shaw’s Boyle. Skeptical
Chymist, pp. 312, 313. &c.
The only real advance in chemical theory, therefore, which we can
ascribe to the school of the three principles, as compared with
those who held the ancient dogma of the four elements, is, the
acknowledgment of the changes produced by the chemist’s operations, as
being changes which were to be accounted for by the union and
separation of substantial elements, or, as they were sometimes called,
of hypostatical principles. The workmen of this school
acquired, no doubt, a considerable acquaintance with the results of
the kinds of processes which they pursued; they applied their
knowledge to the preparation of new medicines; and some of them, as
Paracelsus and Van Helmont, attained, in this way, to great fame and
distinction: but their merits, as regards theoretical chemistry,
consist only in a truer conception of the problem, and of the mode of
attempting its solution, than their predecessors had entertained.
This step is well marked by a word which, about the time of which
we speak, was introduced to denote the chemist’s employment. It was
called the Spagiric art, (often misspelt Spagyric,) from
two Greek words, (σπάω, ἀγείρω,) which mean to separate
parts, and to unite them. These two processes, or in more
modern language, analysis and synthesis, constitute the
whole business of the chemist. We are not making a fanciful
arrangement, therefore, when we mark the recognition of this object as
a step in the progress of chemistry. I now proceed to consider the
manner in which the conditions of this analysis and synthesis were
further developed.
</div></body></text></TEI>