<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="18">
CHAPTER II.
Of Methods of Observation.
Aphorism XXVIII.
The Methods of Observation of Quantity in general are,
Numeration, which is precise by the nature of Number; the
Measurement of Space and of Time, which are easily made
precise; the Conversion of Space and Time, by which each
aids the measurement of the other; the Method of Repetition;
the Method of Coincidences or Interferences. The
measurement of Weight is made precise by the Method of
Double-weighing. Secondary Qualities are measured by
means of Scales of Degrees; but in order to apply these
Scales, the student requires the Education of the Senses.
The Education of the Senses is forwarded by the practical
study of Descriptive Natural History, Chemical Manipulation,
and Astronomical Observation.
1. I
SHALL speak, in this chapter, of Methods
of exact and systematic observation, by which
such facts are collected as form the materials of precise
scientific propositions. These Methods are very various,
according to the nature of the subject inquired
into, and other circumstances: but a great portion of
them agree in being processes of measurement. These
I shall peculiarly consider: and in the first place those
referring to Number, Space, and Time, which are at
the same time objects and instruments of measurement.
2. But though we have to explain how observations
may be made as perfect as possible, we must not
forget that in most cases complete perfection is
unattainable. Observations are never perfect.
For we 146
observe phenomena by our senses, and measure their
relations in time and space; but our senses and our
measures are all, from various causes, inaccurate. If
we have to observe the exact place of the moon among
the stars, how much of instrumental apparatus is
necessary! This apparatus has been improved by
many successive generations of astronomers, yet it is
still far from being perfect. And the senses of man,
as well as his implements, are limited in their exactness.
Two different observers do not obtain precisely
the same measures of the time and place of a phenomenon;
as, for instance, of the moment at which the
moon occults a star, and the point of her limb at which
the occultation takes place. Here, then, is a source of
inaccuracy and errour, even in astronomy, where the
means of exact observation are incomparably more
complete than they are in any other department of
human research. In other cases, the task of obtaining
accurate measures is far more difficult. If we have
to observe the tides of the ocean when rippled with
waves, we can see the average level of the water first
rise and then fall; but how hard is it to select the exact
moment when it is at its greatest height, or the exact
highest point which it reaches! It is very easy, in such
a case, to err by many minutes in time, and by several
inches in space.
Still, in many cases, good Methods can remove very
much of this inaccuracy, and to these we now proceed.
3. (I.) Number.—Number is the first step of
measurement, since it measures itself, and does not, like
space and time, require an arbitrary standard. Hence
the first exact observations, and the first advances of
rigorous knowledge, appear to have been made by means
of number; as for example,—the number of days in a
month and in a year;—the cycles according to which
eclipses occur;—the number of days in the revolutions
of the planets; and the like. All these discoveries, as
we have seen in the History of Astronomy, go back to
the earliest period of the science, anterior to any
distinct tradition; and these discoveries presuppose a series,
probably a very long series, of observations, made 147
principally by means of number. Nations so rude as to
have no other means of exact measurement, have still
systems of numeration by which they can reckon to a
considerable extent. Very often, such nations have very
complex systems, which are capable of expressing numbers
of great magnitude. Number supplies the means
of measuring other quantities, by the assumption of a
unit of measure of the appropriate kind: but where
nature supplies the unit, number is applicable directly
and immediately. Number is an important element in
the Classificatory as well as in the Mathematical Sciences.
The History of those Sciences shows how the
formation of botanical systems was effected by the
adoption of number as a leading element, by Cæsalpinus;
and how afterwards the Reform of Linnæus in classification
depended in a great degree on his finding, in the
pistils and stamens, a better numerical basis than those
before employed. In like manner, the number of rays
in the membrane of the gills1,
and the number of rays
in the fins of fish, were found to be important elements
in ichthyological classification by Artedi and Linnæus.
There are innumerable instances, in all parts of Natural
History, of the importance of the observation of number.
And in this observation, no instrument, scale or
standard is needed, or can be applied; except the
scale of natural numbers, expressed either in words or
in figures, can be considered as an instrument.
1
 Hist. Ind. Sc. b. xvi. c. vii.
4. (II.) Measurement of Space.—Of quantities
admitting of continuous increase and decrease,
(for number is discontinuous,) space is the most simple in its
mode of measurement, and requires most frequently to
be measured. The obvious mode of measuring space is
by the repeated application of a material measure, as
when we take a foot-rule and measure the length of a
room. And in this case the foot-rule is the unit of
space, and the length of the room is expressed by the
number of such units which it contains: or, as it may
not contain an exact number, by a number with a
fraction. But besides this measurement of linear space, 148
there is another kind of space which, for purposes of
science, it is still more important to measure, namely,
angular space. The visible heavens being considered
as a sphere, the portions and paths of the heavenly
bodies are determined by drawing circles on the surface
of this sphere, and are expressed by means of the parts
of these circles thus intercepted: by such measures the
doctrines of astronomy were obtained in the very beginning
of the science. The arcs of circles thus measured,
are not like linear spaces, reckoned by means of an
arbitrary unit, for there is a natural unit, the total
circumference, to which all arcs may be referred. For
the sake of convenience, the whole circumference is
divided into 360 parts or degrees; and by means of
these degrees and their parts, all arcs are expressed.
The arcs are the measures of the angles at the center,
and the degrees may be considered indifferently as
measuring the one or the other of these quantities.
5. In the History of
Astronomy2,
I have described
the method of observation of celestial angles employed
by the Greeks. They determined the lines in which
the heavenly bodies were seen, by means either of
Shadows, or of Sights; and measured the angles between
such lines by arcs or rules properly applied to
them. The Armill, Astrolabe, Dioptra, and Parallactic
Instrument of the ancients, were some of the
instruments thus constructed. Tycho Brahe greatly
improved the methods of astronomical observation by
giving steadiness to the frame of his instruments,
(which were large quadrants,) and accuracy to the
divisions of the limb3.
But the application of the
telescope to the astronomical quadrant and the fixation of
the center of the field by a cross of fine wires placed in
the focus, was an immense improvement of the instrument,
since it substituted a precise visual ray, pointing
to the star, instead of the coarse coincidence of Sights.
The accuracy of observation was still further increased 149
by applying to the telescope a micrometer which might
subdivide the smaller divisions of the arc.
2
Hist. Ind. Sc.  b. iii. c. iv. sect. 3.
3
Ib. b. vii. c. vi. sect. 1.
6. By this means, the precision of astronomical observation
was made so great, that very minute angular
spaces could be measured: and it then became a question
whether discrepancies which appeared at first as
defects in the theory, might not arise sometimes from
a bending or shaking of the instrument, and from the
degrees marked on the limb being really somewhat
unequal, instead of being rigorously equal. Accordingly,
the framing and balancing of the instrument, so
as to avoid all possible tremor or flexure, and the exact
division of an arc into equal parts, became great objects
of those who wished to improve astronomical observations.
The observer no longer gazed at the stars from
a lofty tower, but placed his telescope on the solid
ground,—and braced and balanced it with various
contrivances. Instead of a quadrant, an entire circle was
introduced (by Ramsden;) and various processes were
invented for the dividing of instruments. Among
these we may notice Troughton’s method of dividing;
in which the visual ray of a microscope was substituted
for the points of a pair of compasses, and, by stepping
round the circle, the partial arcs were made to bear
their exact relation to the whole circumference.
7. Astronomy is not the only science which depends on
the measurement of angles. Crystallography
also requires exact measures of this kind; and the
goniometer, especially that devised by Wollaston,
supplies the means of obtaining such measures. The
science of Optics also, in many cases, requires the
measurement of angles.
8. In the measurement of linear space, there is no
natural standard which offers itself. Most of the common
measures appear to be taken from some part of
the human body; as a foot, a cubit, a fathom; but such
measures cannot possess any precision, and are altered
by convention: thus there were in ancient times many
kinds of cubits; and in modern Europe, there are a
great number of different standards of the foot, as the
Rhenish foot, the Paris foot, the English foot. It is 150
very desirable that, if possible, some permanent standard,
founded in nature, should be adopted; for the conventional
measures are lost in the course of ages; and
thus, dimensions expressed by means of them become
unintelligible. Two different natural standards have
been employed in modern times: the French have
referred their measures of length to the total
circumference of a meridian of the earth; a quadrant of this
meridian consists of ten million units or metres. The
English have fixed their linear measure by reference to
the length of a pendulum which employs an exact
second of time in its small oscillation. Both these
methods occasion considerable difficulties in carrying
them into effect; and are to be considered mainly as
means of recovering the standard if it should ever be
lost. For common purposes, some material standard is
adopted as authority for the time: for example, the
standard which in England possessed legal authority
up to the year 1835 was preserved in the House of
Parliament; and was lost in the conflagration which
destroyed that edifice. The standard of length now
generally referred to by men of science in England is
that which is in the possession of the Astronomical
Society of London.
9. A standard of length being established, the
artifices for applying it, and for subdividing it in the
most accurate manner, are nearly the same as in the
case of measures of arcs: as for instance, the employment
of the visual rays of microscopes instead of the
legs of compasses and the edges of rules; the use of
micrometers for minute measurements; and the like.
Many different modes of avoiding errour in such
measurements have been devised by various observers,
according to the nature of the cases with which they
had to deal4.
4 On the precautions employed in astronomical
instruments for the measure of space, see Sir J. Herschel’s
Astronomy (in the Cabinet Cyclopædia,) Arts. 103–110.
10. (III.) Measurement of Time.—The methods of
measuring Time are not so obvious as the methods of 151
measuring space; for we cannot apply one portion of
time to another, so as to test their equality. We are
obliged to begin by assuming some change as the measure
of time. Thus the motion of the sun in the sky,
or the length and position of the shadows of objects,
were the first modes of measuring the parts of the day.
But what assurance had men, or what assurance could
they have, that the motion of the sun or of the shadow
was uniform? They could have no such assurance,
till they had adopted some measure of smaller times;
which smaller times, making up larger times by repetition,
they took as the standard of uniformity;—for
example, an hour-glass, or a clepsydra which answered
the same purpose among the ancients. There is no
apparent reason why the successive periods measured
by the emptying of the hour-glass should be unequal;
they are implicitly accepted as equal; and by reference
to these, the uniformity of the sun’s motion may be
verified. But the great improvement in the measurement
of time was the use of a pendulum for the purpose by
Galileo, and the application of this device to
clocks by Huyghens in 1656. For the successive
oscillations of a pendulum are rigorously equal, and a clock
is only a train of machinery employed for the purpose
of counting these oscillations. By means of this invention,
the measure of time in astronomical observations
became as accurate as the measure of space.
11. What is the natural unit of time? It was assumed
from the first by the Greek astronomers, that
the sidereal days, measured by the revolution of a star
from any meridian to the same meridian again, are
exactly equal; and all improvements in the measure of
time tended to confirm this assumption. The sidereal
day is therefore the natural standard of time. But the
solar day, determined by the diurnal revolution of the
sun, although not rigorously invariable, as the sidereal
day is, undergoes scarcely any perceptible variation;
and since the course of daily occurrences is regulated
by the sun, it is far more convenient to seek the basis
of our unit of time in his motions. Accordingly the
solar day (the mean solar day) is divided into 24 hours, 152
and these, into minutes and seconds; and this is our
scale of time. Of such time, the sidereal day has 23
hours 56 minutes 4·09 seconds. And it is plain that
by such a statement the length of the hour is fixed,
with reference to a sidereal day. The standard of
time (and the standard of space in like manner) equally
answers its purpose, whether or not it coincides with
any whole number of units.
12. Since the sidereal day is thus the standard of
our measures of time, it becomes desirable to refer to
it, constantly and exactly, the instruments by which
time is measured, in order that we may secure ourselves
against errour. For this purpose, in astronomical
observatories, observations are constantly made of the
transit of stars across the meridian; the transit instrument
with which this is done being adjusted with
all imaginable regard to
accuracy5.
5
 On the precautions employed in the measure of
time by astronomers, see Herschel’s Astronomy, Art. 115–127.
13. When exact measures of time are required in
other than astronomical observations, the same instruments
are still used, namely, clocks and chronometers.
In chronometers, the regulating part is an oscillating
body; not, as in clocks, a pendulum oscillating by the
force of gravity, but a wheel swinging to and fro on
its center, in consequence of the vibrations of a slender
coil of elastic wire. To divide time into still
smaller portions than these vibrations, other artifices
are used; some of which will be mentioned under the
next head.
14. (IV.) Conversion of Space and Time.—Space
and time agree in being extended quantities, which are
made up and measured by the repetition of homogeneous
parts. If a body move uniformly, whether in
the way of revolving or otherwise, the space which any
point describes, is proportional to the time of its
motion; and the space and the time may each be
taken as a measure of the other. Hence in such cases,
by taking space instead of time, or time instead of 153
space, we may often obtain more convenient and precise
measures, than we can by measuring directly the
element with which we are concerned.
The most prominent example of such a conversion,
is the measurement of the Right Ascension of stars,
(that is, their angular distance from a standard
meridian6
on the celestial sphere,) by means of the time
employed in their coming to the meridian of the place
of observation. Since, as we have already stated, the
visible celestial sphere, carrying the fixed stars,
revolves with perfect uniformity about the pole; if we
observe the stars as they come in succession to a fixed
circle passing through the poles, the intervals of time
between these observations will be proportional to the
angles which the meridian circles passing through these
stars make at the poles where they meet; and hence,
if we have the means of measuring time with great
accuracy, we can, by watching the times of the transits
of successive stars across some visible mark in our own
meridian, determine the angular distances of the
meridian circles of all the stars from one another.
6
 A meridian is a circle passing through the
poles about which the celestial sphere revolves. The meridian
of any place on the earth is that  meridian which is
exactly over the place.
Accordingly, now that the pendulum clock affords
astronomers the means of determining time exactly, a
measurement of the Right Ascensions of heavenly
bodies by means of a clock and a transit instrument,
is a part of the regular business of an observatory. If
the sidereal clock be so adjusted that it marks the
beginning of its scale of time when the first point of
Right Ascension is upon the visible meridian of our
observatory, the point of the scale at which the clock
points when any other star is in our meridian, will
truly represent the Right Ascension of the star.
Thus as the motion of the stars is our measure of
time, we employ time, conversely, as our measure of
the places of the stars. The celestial machine and our
terrestrial machines correspond to each other in their
movements; and the star steals silently and steadily 154
across our meridian line, just as the pointer of the
clock steals past the mark of the hour. We may judge
of the scale of this motion by considering that the full
moon employs about two minutes of time in sailing
across any fixed line seen against the sky, transverse
to her path: and all the celestial bodies, carried along
by the revolving sphere, travel at the same rate.
15. In this case, up to a certain degree, we render
our measures of astronomical angles more exact and
convenient by substituting time for space; but when,
in the very same kind of observation, we wish to proceed
to a greater degree of accuracy, we find that it
is best done by substituting space for time. In observing
the transit of a star across the meridian, if we
have the clock within hearing, we can count the beats
of the pendulum by the noise which they make, and
tell exactly at which second of time the passage of the
star across the visible thread takes place; and thus we
measure Right Ascension by means of time. But our
perception of time does not allow us to divide a second
into ten parts, and to pronounce whether the transit
takes place three-tenths, six-tenths, or seven-tenths of
a second after the preceding beat of the clock. This,
however, can be done by the usual mode of observing
the transit of a star. The observer, listening to the
beat of his clock, fastens his attention upon the star at
each beat, and especially at the one immediately before
and the one immediately after the passage of the
thread: and by this means he has these two positions
and the position of the thread so far present to his
intuition at once, that he can judge in what proportion
the thread is nearer to one position than the other, and
can thus divide the intervening second in its due proportion.
Thus if he observe that at the beginning of
the second the star is on one side of the thread, and at
the end of the second on the other side; and that the
two distances from the thread are as two to three, he
knows that the transit took place at two-fifths (or
four-tenths) of a second after the former beat. In this
way a second of time in astronomical observations
may, by a skilful observer, be divided into ten equal 155
parts; although when time is observed as time, a tenth
of a second appears almost to escape our senses. From
the above explanation, it will be seen that the reason
why the subdivision is possible in the way thus described,
is this:—that the moment of time thus to be
divided is so small, that the eye and the mind can
retain, to the end of this moment, the impression of
position which it received at the beginning. Though
the two positions of the star, and the intermediate
thread, are seen successively, they can be contemplated
by the mind as if they were seen simultaneously: and
thus it is precisely the smallness of this portion of
time which enables us to subdivide it by means of
space.
16. There is another case, of somewhat a different
kind, in which time is employed in measuring space;
namely, when space, or the standard of space, is defined
by the length of a pendulum oscillating in a given
time. We might in this way define any space by the
time which a pendulum of such a length would take
in oscillating; and thus we might speak, as was observed
by those who suggested this device, of five
minutes of cloth, or a rope half an hour long. We
may observe, however, that in this case, the space is
not proportional to the time. And we may add, that
though we thus appear to avoid the arbitrary standard of
space (for as we have seen, the standard of
measures of time is a natural one,) we do not do so in
fact: for we assume the invariableness of gravity,
which really varies (though very slightly,) from place
to place.
17. (V.) The Method of Repetition in Measurement.—In
many cases we can give great additional
accuracy to our measurements by repeatedly adding
to itself the quantity which we wish to measure. Thus
if we wished to ascertain the exact breadth of a thread,
it might not be easy to determine whether it was one-ninetieth,
or one-ninety-fifth, or one-hundredth part of
an inch; but if we find that ninety-six such threads
placed side by side occupy exactly an inch, we have
the precise measure of the breadth of the thread. In 156
the same manner, if two clocks are going nearly at the
same rate, we may not be able to distinguish the excess
of an oscillation of one of the pendulums over an
oscillation of the other: but when the two clocks have
gone for an hour, one of them may have gained ten
seconds upon the other; thus showing that the proportion
of their times of oscillation is 3610 to 3600.
In the latter of these instances, we have the principle
of repetition truly exemplified, because (as has been
justly observed by Sir J. Herschel7,)
there is then ‘a
juxtaposition of units without errour,’—‘one vibration
commences exactly where the last terminates, no part
of time being lost or gained in the addition of the
units so counted.’ In space, this juxtaposition of units
without errour cannot be rigorously accomplished,
since the units must be added together by material
contact (as in the above case of the threads,) or in
some equivalent manner. Yet the principle of repetition
has been applied to angular measurement with
considerable success in Borda’s Repeating Circle. In
this instrument, the angle between two objects which
we have to observe, is repeated along the graduated
limb of the circle by turning the telescope from one
object to the other, alternately fastened to the circle
(by its clamp) and loose from it (by unclamping). In
this manner the errours of graduation may (theoretically)
be entirely got rid of: for if an angle repeated
nine times be found to go twice round the circle, it
must be exactly eighty degrees: and where the repetition does
not give an exact number of circumferences,
it may still be made to subdivide the errour to any
required extent.
7
 Disc. Nat. Phil. art. 121.
18. Connected with the principle of repetition, is
the Method of coincidences or interferences. If we have
two Scales, on one of which an inch is divided into 10,
and on the other into 11 equal parts; and if, these
Scales being placed side by side, it appear that the
beginning of the latter Scale is between the 2nd and
3rd division of the former, it may not be apparent 157
what fraction added to 2 determines the place of beginning
of the second Scale as measured on the first. But
if it appear also that the 3rd division of the second
Scale coincides with a certain division of the first, (the
5th,) it is certain that 2 and three-tenths is the exact
place of the beginning of the second Scale, measured
on the first Scale. The 3rd division of the 11 Scale
will coincide (or interfere with) a division of the 10
Scale, when the beginning or zero of the 11 divisions
is three-tenths of a division beyond the preceding line
of the 10 Scale; as will be plain on a little consideration.
And if we have two Scales of equal units, in
which each unit is divided into nearly, but not quite,
the same number of equal parts (as 10 and 11, 19 and
20, 29 and 30,) and one sliding on the other, it will
always happen that some one or other of the division
lines will coincide, or very nearly coincide; and thus
the exact position of the beginning of one unit, measured
on the other scale, is determined. A sliding
scale, thus divided for the purpose of subdividing the
units of that on which it slides, is called a Vernier,
from the name of its inventor.
19. The same Principle of Coincidence or Interference
is applied to the exact measurement of the length
of time occupied in the oscillation of a pendulum. If
a detached pendulum, of such a length as to swing in
little less than a second, be placed before the seconds’
pendulum of a clock, and if the two pendulums begin
to move together, the former will gain upon the latter,
and in a little while their motions will be quite discordant.
But if we go on watching, we shall find
them, after a time, to agree again exactly; namely,
when the detached pendulum has gained one complete
oscillation (back and forwards,) upon the clock pendulum,
and again coincides with it in its motion. If this
happen after 5 minutes, we know that the times of
oscillation of the two pendulums are in the proportion
of 300 to 302, and therefore the detached pendulum
oscillates in 150⁄151
of a second. The accuracy which can
be obtained in the measure of an oscillation by this
means is great; for the clock can be compared (by 158
observing transits of the stars or otherwise) with
the natural standard of time, the sidereal day. And
the moment of coincidence of the two pendulums
may, by proper arrangements, be very exactly determined.
We have hitherto spoken of methods of measuring
time and space, but other elements also may be very
precisely measured by various means.
20. (VI.) Measurement of Weight.—Weight, like
space and time, is a quantity made up by addition of
parts, and may be measured by similar methods. The
principle of repetition is applicable to the measurement
of weight; for if two bodies be simultaneously put in
the same pan of a balance, and if they balance pieces in
the other pan, their weights are exactly added.
There may be difficulties of practiced workmanship
in carrying into effect the mathematical conditions of
a perfect balance; for example, in securing an exact
equality of the effective arms of the beam in all positions.
These difficulties are evaded by the Method of
double weighing; according to which the standard
weights, and the body which is to be weighed, are
successively put in the same pan, and made to balance by
a third body in the opposite scale. By this means the
different lengths of the arms of the beam, and other
imperfections of the balance, become of no
consequence8.
8
 For other methods of measuring weights accurately,
see Faraday’s Chemical Manipulation, p. 25.
21. There is no natural Standard of weight. The
conventional weight taken as the standard, is the
weight of a given bulk of some known substance; for
instance, a cubic foot of water. But in order that this
may be definite, the water must not contain any portion
of heterogeneous substance: hence it is required
that the water be distilled water.
22. (VII.) Measurement of Secondary Qualities.—We
have already seen9 that
secondary qualities are
estimated by means of conventional Scales, which refer 159
them to space, number, or some other definite expression.
Thus the Thermometer measures heat; the
Musical Scale, with or without the aid of number, expresses
the pitch of a note; and we may have an exact
and complete Scale of Colours, pure and impure. We
may remark, however, that with regard to sound and
colour, the estimates  of the ear and the eye are not
superseded, but only assisted: for if we determine
what a note is, by comparing it with an instrument
known to be in tune, we still leave the ear to decide
when the note is in unison with one of the notes of the
instrument. And when we compare a colour with our
chromatometer, we judge by the eye which division
of the chromatometer it matches. Colour and sound
have their Natural Scales, which the eye and ear
habitually apply; what science requires is, that those
scales should be systematized. We have seen that
several conditions are requisite in such scales of
qualities: the observer’s skill and ingenuity are mainly
shown in devising such scales and methods of applying
them.
9
B. iii. c. ii. Of the Measure of Secondary Qualities.
23. The Method of Coincidences is employed in
harmonics: for if two notes are nearly, but not quite,
in unison, the coincidences of the vibrations produce
an audible undulation in the note, which is called the
howl; and the exactness of the unison is known by
this howl vanishing.
24. (VIII.) Manipulation.—The process of applying
practically methods of experiment and observation, is
termed Manipulation; and the value of observations
depends much upon the proficiency of the
observer in this art. This skill appears, as we have
said, not only in devising means and modes in measuring
results, but also in inventing and executing arrangements
by which elements are subjected to such
conditions as the investigation requires: in finding and
using some material combination by which nature shall
be asked the question which we have in our minds.
To do this in any subject may be considered as a
peculiar Art, but especially in Chemistry; where ‘many
experiments, and even whole trains of research, are 160
essentially dependent for success on mere
manipulation10.’
The changes which the chemist has to study,—compositions,
decompositions, and mutual actions,
affecting the internal structure rather than the external
form and motion of bodies,—are not familiarly
recognized by common observers, as those actions are
which operate upon the total mass of a body: and
hence it is only when the chemist has become, to a
certain degree, familiar with his science, that he has
the power of observing. He must learn to interpret
the effects of mixture, heat, and other Chemical agencies,
so as to see in them those facts which chemistry
makes the basis of her doctrines. And in learning to
interpret this language, he must also learn to call it
forth;—to place bodies under the requisite conditions,
by the apparatus of his own laboratory and the operations
of his own fingers. To do this with readiness
and precision, is, as we have said, an Art, both of the
mind and of the hand, in no small degree recondite
and difficult. A person may be well acquainted with
all the doctrines of chemistry, and may yet fail in the
simplest experiment. How many precautions and observances,
what resource and invention, what delicacy
and vigilance, are requisite in Chemical Manipulation,
may be seen by reference to Dr. Faraday’s work on
that subject.
10
Faraday’s Chemical Manipulation, p. 3.
25. The same qualities in the observer are requisite
in some other departments of science; for example,
in the researches of Optics: for in these, after the first
broad facts have been noticed, the remaining features
of the phenomena are both very complex and very
minute; and require both ingenuity in the invention
of experiments, and a keen scrutiny of their results.
We have instances of the application of these qualities
in most of the optical experimenters of recent times,
and certainly in no one more than Sir David Brewster.
Omitting here all notice of his succeeding labours, his
Treatise on New Philosophical Instruments, published
in 1813, is an excellent model of the kind of resource 161
and skill of which we now speak. I may mention as
an example of this skill, his mode of determining the
refractive power of an irregular fragment of any
transparent substance. At first this might appear an
impossible problem; for it would seem that a regular and
smooth surface are requisite, in order that we may
have any measurable refraction. But Sir David Brewster
overcame the difficulty by immersing the fragment
in a combination of fluids, so mixed, that they had the
same refractive power as the specimen. The question,
when they had this power, was answered by noticing
when the fragment became so transparent that its surface
could hardly be seen; for this happened when, the
refractive power within and without the fragment being
the same, there was no refraction at the surface. And this
condition being obtained, the refractive power of the fluid,
and therefore of the fragment, was easily ascertained.
26. (IX.) The Education of the Senses.—Colour
and Musical Tone are, as we have seen, determined by
means of the Senses, whether or not Systematical Scales
are used in expressing the observed fact. Systematical
Scales of sensible qualities, however, not only give
precision to the record, but to the observation. But for
this purpose such an Education of the Senses is requisite
as may enable us to apply the scale immediately.
The memory must retain the sensation or perception
to which the technical term or degree of the scale
refers. Thus with regard to colour, as we have said
already11,
when we find such terms as tin-white or
pinchbeck-brown, the metallic colour so denoted ought
to occur at once to our recollection without delay or
search. The observer’s senses, therefore, must be educated,
at first by an actual exhibition of the standard,
and afterwards by a familiar use of it, to understand
readily and clearly each phrase and degree of the scales
which in his observations he has to apply. This is not
only the best, but in many cases the only way in which
the observation can be expressed. Thus glassy lustre,
fatty lustre, adamantine lustre, denote
certain kinds of 162
shining in minerals, which appearances we should
endeavour in vain to describe by periphrasis; and
which the terms, if considered as terms in common
language, would by no means clearly discriminate: for
who, in common language, would say that coal has a
fatty lustre? But these terms, in their conventional
sense, are perfectly definite; and when the eye is once
familiarized with this application of them, are easily
and clearly intelligible.
11 B. viii. c. iii. Terminology.
[Please see Transcriber’s Notes.]
27. The education of the senses, which is thus
requisite in order to understand well the terminology
of any science, must be acquired by an inspection of
the objects which the science deals with; and is, perhaps,
best promoted by the practical study of Natural
History. In the different departments of Natural
History, the descriptions of species are given by means
of an extensive technical terminology: and that education
of which we now speak, ought to produce the effect
of making the observer as familiar with each of the terms
of this terminology as we are with the words of our
common language. The technical terms have a much
more precise meaning than other terms, since they are
defined by express convention, and not learnt by common
usage merely. Yet though they are thus defined,
not the definition, but the perception itself, is that
which the term suggests to the proficient.
In order to use the terminology to any good purpose,
the student must possess it, not as a dictionary,
but as a language. The terminology of his sciences
must be the natural historian’s most familiar tongue.
He must learn to think in such language. And when
this is achieved, the terminology, as I have elsewhere
said, though to an uneducated eye cumbrous and
pedantical, is felt to be a useful implement, not an
oppressive burden12.
The impatient schoolboy looks upon
his grammar and vocabulary as irksome and burdensome;
but the accomplished student who has learnt
the language by means of them, knows that they have
given him the means of expressing what he thinks, and 163
even of thinking more precisely. And as the study of
language thus gives precision to the thoughts, the study
of Natural History, and especially of the descriptive
part of it, gives precision to the senses.
12
 Hist. Ind. Sc. b. xvi. c. iv. sect. 2.
The Education of the Senses is also greatly promoted
by the practical pursuit of any science of experiment
and observation, as chemistry or astronomy.
The methods of manipulating, of which we have just
spoken, in chemistry, and the methods of measuring
extremely minute portions of space and time which are
employed in astronomy, and which are described in
the former part of this chapter, are among the best
modes of educating the senses for purposes of scientific
observation.
28. By the various Methods of precise observation
which we have thus very briefly described, facts are
collected, of an exact and definite kind; they are then
bound together in general laws, by the aid of general
ideas and of such methods as we have now to consider.
It is true, that the ideas which enable us to combine
facts into general propositions, do commonly operate in
our minds while we are still engaged in the office of
observing. Ideas of one kind or other are requisite to
connect our phenomena into facts, and to give meaning
to the terms of our descriptions: and it frequently
happens, that long before we have collected all the
facts which induction requires, the mind catches the
suggestion which some of these ideas offer, and leaps
forwards to a conjectural law while the labour of observation
is yet unfinished. But though this actually
occurs, it is easy to see that the process of combining
and generalizing facts is, in the order of nature, posterior
to, and distinct from, the process of observing
facts. Not only is this so, but there is an intermediate
step which, though inseparable from all successful
generalization, may be distinguished from it in our
survey; and may, in some degree, be assisted by peculiar
methods. To the consideration of such methods
we now proceed.
</div></body></text></TEI>