<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="27">CHAPTER XXV.
Italy may be considered as the very focus and parent of
superstitious credulity. The materials which Hector had
furnished, after all the interrogations of the donzella, were
slight compared with the superstructure which was presently
erected on them. My grotto was said to be the appropriated
haunt where a thousand devils held their infernal
sabbath. The terrified imagination of the rustics, listening
with a temper horribly distracted between curiosity and
alarm, created to itself fictitious howlings and shrieks, and
saw pale and sulphureous flames dancing upon the surface
of the stream. Poor Hector was early the victim of their
cruel and untamed ignorance; they believed that the peculiarity
of his complexion rendered him a singularly agreeable
intercessor between me and my infernal familiars.
The colour of Charon was similar to that of my confidential
attendant; and he, like Hector, fell under the calumnious
misconstructions of the affrighted villagers. Conspicuously
noble, affectionate and useful as he was, the
jaundiced eye of superstition metamorphosed him into a
devil. The storms of thunder and lightning to which the
climate in which I resided is particularly subject acquired
new terror from the ill fame which now pursued the name
of Monsieur Boismorand. At those times the shapeless
form of monsters vomiting smoke and flames were visible
to the neighbourhood, sometimes scudding along the blue
tops of the distant hills, and at others, with audaciousness
incredible, brushing even at the elbow of the almost lifeless
clowns and dairy-maids, and then suddenly dissolving into
air, their place no longer marked but by the noisome and
deadly stench they left behind. All the misfortunes of the
district were imputed to me, the mortality of cattle, the
convulsions and death of children, and the pale and lingering
decay of persons recently advanced to an age of puberty.
Innocent and blameless was my conduct to all
around us; often was I forward and eager for the relief of[268]
the poor and afflicted; never was I the author of the
slightest inconvenience or prejudice to any. Yet nothing
merely human could be hated in the degree in which I was
hated; few were daring and intrepid enough to repeat the
very name I bore; and, when it was inadvertently pronounced,
it produced through the whole extent of the
astonished circle an involuntary and supernatural shudder.
Agostino, the first lover who had made an impression on
the heart of Hector’s donzella, was, as I afterwards found,
a fellow of a gloomy and ferocious disposition, a true Italian
spadaccino, determined that none should perpetrate an affront
against him with impunity, but should expiate, in
some refined and cruel vengeance, the levity by which they
had been so unfortunate as to give birth to his hatred. He
by no means relished or approved the liberal and good-humoured
sentiments of the donzella; often had they inflicted
on him the darkest torments of jealousy; nor had he failed,
at least in one preceding instance, to make his rival the
victim of his resentment. The donzella however went on
in her career; she was light of heart, gay in temper, and
careless of consequences. She had always hitherto succeeded,
by playful blandishments, or more serious demonstrations
of contrition, in mollifying the temper of her
brute; and every pardon she received operated with her as
a new permission to offend. She did not sufficiently consider
that she was thus continually raising to a higher pitch
the frenzy of his malice. Hector in the mean time was
utterly unconscious and ignorant of the perilous situation
in which he stood; while, to the apprehension of Agostino,
the giving him a negro for a rival, whom his pride regarded
as belonging to an inferior species of beings, and his devout
ignorance likened to the leader of the infernal squadrons,
was the last and most intolerable insult.
His malice was ingenious and subtle. He disdained the
vulgar revenge of stabbing his antagonist in the dark, and
supposing that his enmity could be gorged by a blow.
When the venom of his nature was thoroughly put in motion,
nothing could restore it to quietness and tranquillity but
some mighty stroke, to excite the wonder of every bystander,
and that should leave behind it a track of desolation,[269]
never to be filled up again and erased. He heard
therefore with unsated appetite and eager joy the tale of necromancy
and infernal machination repeated to him from
Hector by the donzella. The impression which the narrative
produced upon him was a mixed sentiment of
transport at the apprehension of such an instrument of
vengeance and of palpitating hatred; superstition teaching
him to believe and to view with abhorrence that which he
desired to render tenfold more an object of faith and aversion
to his neighbours. He struck an auspicious and august
alliance between his revenge and his religion; his religion
exciting him to exterminate that, the destruction of which
would produce inexpressible gratification to his revenge.
The darkness of his spirit led him to proceed with double
caution and vigilance in his correspondence with the donzella.
He discovered nothing to her of the dark project
which was engendering in his mind; and only betrayed so
much of his superstitious feelings and fears as, by giving
new emotion, might stimulate her to gratify his curiosity
and her own by a detection of further particulars. He was
assiduous in the underhand and sinister propagation of the
tale, to which he did not fail to give his own colouring and
affix his own feelings. He was desirous that the train
should be laid in silence, and that the explosion he designed
should be free from all pre-signification of the event. Thus
an individual, of whose animosity I had no apprehension,
and the meanness of whose appearance would probably have
made me neglect all precaution against him, gave method
and direction to an evil, of which however, upon a review,
I am not inclined to doubt I should have been the victim,
if the enmity and industry of this individual had been
wholly withdrawn.
The mischief was long in preparation, before I received
in any way the slightest intimation of the predicament in
which I stood. The first circumstance at all calculated to
excite alarm in my mind, was the singular manner in which I
found myself regarded, if I entered any of the neighbouring
villages, or met the rustics and their dames, as I strayed
along the roads or the fields. They fled my approach, deserted
the streets, and carefully shut themselves up in their[270]
houses, till I had passed. Where it was impossible to
avoid me, they bowed themselves to the earth in the most
submissive guise before me, while the most lively terror
was painted in their countenances, dreading lest they should
excite the resentment of a tremendous and inexorable foe.
These tokens however were far from inspiring me with a
conception of the truth. They perplexed, they astonished,
they distressed me. Sore as I was with my recent afflictions,
my mind was but too fully prepared for anticipations of
evil. I had suffered from suspicions, I had suffered from
calumnious imputations, I had suffered from the malignant
effects of popular rumour. Had I yielded my confidence
to any person but such a one as Hector, it is probable my
suspicions would have turned on that side. But my reliance
on him was not less than that which Alexander the Great
yielded to Philip the physician: I knew his rectitude, his
simplicity, his fidelity, and the singleness of his heart; and
I could not harbour the shadow of a doubt respecting him.
My reliance was of that entire and perfect sort, which did
not express itself by a recollection of the physical possibility
and an acquittal founded in deliberation, but by a total
vacancy of doubt, or of retrospect that way directed, just
such as the state of my mind would have appeared, if the
thing had been naturally impossible.
I was not however ignorant and raw enough to be deceived
by the exterior of homage I have described; I sufficiently
knew that what I beheld was the offspring of
hatred. To feel one’s self hated is in all instances a painful
and humiliating state of the human mind. To me it was
especially so. I was not formed to retaliate this species of
injury; I could not hate in my turn. I was formed to
love. I could not look upon my species with dark and
gloomy contemplations; I was prompt to admire their
virtues, and perhaps even too prompt to extenuate their
errors. It may, I believe, be laid down as a rule, that
they who cannot hate can least endure to be made objects
of hatred. Fettered however as I now was, by the tenderest
consideration for the health and tranquillity of Marguerite,
I thought it best to temporise and submit in silence.
My principal anxiety was to hide these symptoms from the[271]
notice of my family. This I could not completely effect;
some of them were too glaring and obtrusive, entirely to
escape the observation of my daughters in their walks. But
the filial forbearance they felt towards their mother led them
implicitly and without any concerted plan to concur with
me in my exertions for her quiet.
The animosity of Agostino was restless and inextinguishable.
His plans did not terminate in exciting against
me a secret and covered abhorrence; they aimed at nothing
less than my utter destruction. The next exertion of the
conspiracy which was engendering against me was of a tragical
nature.
It happened one night, after all my family was retired
to rest, and I was myself sunk into a slumber, that I was
suddenly alarmed at the report of a musket, which seemed
to be fired almost under the window of my chamber. This
was a very singular circumstance, and calculated to convey
an impression of danger. I leaped from my bed, and ran
to the window. The night was extremely dark, and every
thing seemed perfectly quiet. Presently I discerned a
glimmering light, like that of a lantern, which however appeared
to be gradually retiring to a greater distance. I was
not thus satisfied, but determined to hasten down stairs, and
investigate the cause of the disturbance. Marguerite, who
had heard the firing of the musket as well as myself, now
called me to her, and entreated me not to expose myself to
unnecessary danger. In compliance with her remonstrances
I promised, though unwillingly, not to go out into the
court or upon the lawn, but to content myself with examining
the state of every part of the house. When I came
to the staircase and the hall, I found that the alarm had communicated
to almost every person in the family, who presently
assembled round me. We patroled the house, but
found every thing in the situation in which it had been
left, and nowhere any appearance of violence. I opened
several of the windows, but all was darkness and silence.
Having thus far satisfied myself, I listened with a degree
of amusement to the conjectures and sage remarks of several
of the servants, a rank of society who may usually be found
to derive a degree of enjoyment from incidents of this sort,[272]
which, for the moment, strikingly tend to level all artificial
distinctions, and confer on every one the liberty of uttering
his reflections without apprehension or constraint. I did not
however feel myself entirely easy; the circumstance which
had just occurred, combined with the forebodings which
had lately impressed me, had filled me with undefinable
terror and alarm. Hector would willingly have gone over
the grounds contiguous to the house, to see if he could discover
any thing that related to or could explain the incident;
but I had promised Marguerite that I would search no
further, and the temper of my mind would not suffer me
to expose another to a danger, which I abstained from encountering
in my own person. It was more than an hour
before the conclave in which we were assembled broke up,
and every one retired, fatigued with attention, and prepared
to fall into the soundest sleep. My dreams were uneasy
and disturbed; my mind was in a tumult of imaginary
calamities; and I passed the greater part of the night in a
state of singular anxiety.
In the morning I was scarcely sunk into a refreshing
slumber, before I was suddenly roused from sleep by a
repetition of shrieks of astonishment and distress. I put
on my clothes as quickly as I could, and hastened towards
the spot from which the sounds appeared to proceed. The
first object I beheld was the little boy of ten years’ old,
whom Charon had a short time before dragged out of the
river, stretched along upon the lifeless body of this faithful
and generous animal. The musket, the report of which
had alarmed us the night before, had no doubt been aimed
against Charon, and the greater part of its contents appeared
to be lodged in his body. As no further sound had succeeded
the firing, he had probably been killed on the spot.
He was at a small distance from the house, near a private
footpath, where he had been found in the morning by the
lad whose life he had recently preserved. The poor boy
had not at first understood what had happened to his benefactor,
but only thought him asleep, and, prompted by
affection for the generous creature, had quietly sat down by
him till he should awake. He had not sat long however,
before he discerned about him the marks of blood. He[273]
put his hand to the wound; the animal stirred not. He
passed to his head; he saw his eyes fiery and starting, and
his lips distorted. He endeavoured to awake him, as one
would awake a human being to whom some mischief had
happened of which he was not aware. All his efforts were
fruitless. He found his body motionless, and his joints
stiff in death. The apprehension of what had occurred
then suddenly flashed on his mind. He burst out into
shrieks of astonishment and anguish. Hector was the first
person who caught the sound, and hastened to the spot; I
immediately followed. The poor negro, who, in the innocence
of his heart was uninitiated in the proud distinctions
by which civilised man is taught to place so vast a barrier
between the human nature and the brute, was struck speechless
with sorrow and amazement. He recognised the dead
being before him for his fellow-creature. He recollected
in him his friend, his companion, his intimate acquaintance,
between whom and himself there had for some time passed
an uninterrupted reciprocation of acts of kindness and
assistance.
A morose and fastidious reader perhaps will ask me why
I lay so great a stress upon so petty and insignificant an
incident as the death of a dog. It might have been little
to other persons; it was not little to us. Let the reader
recollect his ingenuity in procuring aid for his dying master,
his gratitude to the person by whom that aid was afforded,
and his unconquerable antipathy to his master’s murderer.
These are not common traits. There are many men whose
premature fate has been the most unrelentingly avenged,
that in moral and useful qualities could not have stood the
comparison with my generous Charon. It surely was no
common cause for regret, that a creature who had distinguished
himself by a conduct so peculiarly admirable, should
have encountered so premature and unmerited a fate. His
conduct the reader may in some degree comprehend and
appreciate; but I should in vain attempt to delineate those
admirable qualities in this faithful domestic, which do not
fall within the province of narrative, and which to have
justly appreciated you must have been personally and familiarly
acquainted with him. Beside, ours was a family[274]
of love. As we were affectionately attached to each other,
so we never admitted a servant under our roof, who did not
prove himself by his conduct utterly unworthy, to whom
we did not extend a share of that friendship and affection,
which seemed to be the right of every one that dwelt in our
family. Feeling does not stay to calculate with weights
and a balance the importance and magnitude of every
object that excites it; it flows impetuously from the heart,
without consulting the cooler responses of the understanding.
There was another circumstance which rendered the
catastrophe of this generous animal of great moment to us.
It was a clear proof that there was somewhere a strong
animosity at work against his master. It was impossible
he could himself have provoked his fate. Never was a
creature more gentle and inoffensive. Though his bulk
was great, and his strength uncommon, the energies he
possessed were always employed in acts of justice and beneficence,
never in acts of aggression. But if a hatred were
at work so busy and fierce as to prompt an action like this,
how were we to estimate it? What was its source, and
whither did it tend? These were very interesting and
serious considerations. We however dwelt for some time
longer in the centre of general antipathy and abhorrence,
without being able in the smallest degree to explain to ourselves
what we saw. As we knew not in what we had
offended, we were unable to atone for our fault, or even to
guard ourselves against the repetition of it; nor were we
by any means prepared to comprehend the extent of our
danger. Happily Marguerite, whose health was now in a
rapid decline, was least exposed to the observation of this
new mischief; though she felt enough of it to confirm her
in the sentiment, that she had nothing fortunate and happy
to look forward to in the small remainder of her existence.
There was indeed one idea perpetually present to her,
which rendered the impression of ordinary occurrences
extremely feeble upon her mind:—Charles, Charles, wandering
alone in the world, unknowing and unknown, without
a friend, a relative, a counsellor, or a protector, without
money and without a name! This melancholy image followed[275]
her wherever she went, haunted her nightly in her
dreams, attended her in all her occupations, filled all her
intervals of leisure; and, though she laid it down as a law
to herself never to repeat his beloved name in my presence,
she could think of nothing else.
</div></body></text></TEI>