<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="9">

BOOK II.


THE PHILOSOPHY OF THE PURE SCIENCES.

[The principal question discussed in the last Book was this
(see chaps. v. and vi.): How are necessary and
universal truths possible? And the answer then
given was: that the necessity and universality of truths are
derived from the Fundamental Ideas which they
involve. And we proceed in this Book to exemplify this
doctrine in the case of the truths of Geometry and
Arithmetic, which derive their necessity and universality
from the Fundamental Ideas of Space, and Time, or Number.
The question thus examined is that which Kant undertook to
deal with in his celebrated work, Kritik der reinen
Vernunft (Examination of the Pure Reason): and
our solution of the Problem, so far as the Ideas of Space
and Time are concerned, agrees in the main with his. The
arguments contained in chapters ii. and vii. of this Book,
are the leading arguments respecting Space and Time, in
Kant’s Kritik. Kant, however, instead of calling
Space and Time Ideas, calls them the necessary
Forms of our experience, as I have stated in the
text.
But though I have adopted Kant’s arguments as to Space and
Time, all that follows in the succeeding Books, with regard
to other Ideas, has no resemblance to any doctrines of Kant
or his school (with the exception, perhaps, of some of the
views on the Idea of Cause). The nature and character
of the other Scientific Ideas which I have examined, in the
succeeding Books, have been established by an analysis of
the history of the several Sciences to which those Ideas are
essential, and an examination of the writings of the
principal discoverers in those Sciences.]</div></body></text></TEI>