<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="10">

INDUCTIVE TABLE OF OPTICS

First Facts. The common and obvious Phænomena of Light and Vision.
By the Idea of a Medium Light and Vision take place by means of something intermediate.
First Law of Phænomena. The effects take place in straight lines denoted by the Term Rays.



Facts of
.........
.........
.........
.........
.........
.........

.........
.........
.........
.........
.........


Rays falling on water, specula, &c.
Rays passing through water, glass, &c. Measures.Ptolemy.
Colours seen by prisms, in rainbow, &c.
Colours in diff. transp. Substances. Optical instrumts.
Two Images in Rhomb. of Calcspar.
Two Images in other crystals.
Two Rhombs of Calcspar make 4 images alternately appear and disappear.
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Fringes of shadows.Grimaldi.Hook.Newton.
Spectra of gratings. Fraunhofer.
Colours of striated surfaces. Coventry’s Micrometr. Barton’s Buttons.Young.
Colours of thick Plates.Newton.
Colours of thin Plates.Hook. Newton.


⏟
⏟




—————⏟—————

 




Euclid. Ang. Inc. equals Ang. Reflection.
Snell. Sin. Refr. to Sin. Inc. in giv. Ratio in same med.
By measures of Refraction.
Dispersion of colours is same when Refr. is diff. Measures.Dollond.
 
 
Huyghens. Rays of light have four Sides with regard to which their properties alternate.
Newton. Idea of Polarization introduced, which governs subsequent observations. Dipolarization with Colours.
 
 
 
 





—⏟—


⏞
 
 

 
 
 




 
Newt. Refr. Ro. is diff. for diff. colours, but in same med. is const. for each colour.

Measures. Huyghens.
Double Refr. in biaxal crystals.Brewster.
Rays are polarized by Calcspar, Quartz, &c. 
Rays are polarized by biaxal crystals.
Rays are polarized by Tourmaline, Agate, &c.
Rays are polarised by Refl. at glass.
Rays are polarized by transmission through glass.
Variable qy. of pol. refl. light paral. plane of Refl.Arago.
Variable qy. of pol. refl. light perp. plane of Refl.
Whole light reflected by internal Refl.
Pol. Rays through uniaxal crystals give colours. Rings. Wollaston.
Pol. Rays through biaxal crystals give colours.Arago.
Pol. Rays. through imperf. crystallized bodies give colours. (Glass strained, jellies prest.)Brewster.
Pol. Rays in axis of Quartz give a peculiar set of colours.Plane of Poln twisted diffly. for diff. colours.Biot.Arago.
Pol. Rays oblique in Quartz give peculiar rings, &c.
Pol. Rays through certain liquids give a peculiar set of colours.
The Laws of these Phænomena were never discovered till Theory had indicated them.
Newton’s Scale of Colours.Fits of Rays.Newton.



——⏟——
⏟
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 
 
 
 
 


 

Dollond. 
Propn of Ref. Rs is diff. in diff. med.Achromatism.
Huyghs.Law of Double Ref. exp. by a spheroid.
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Change of plane of pol. by Refl.Arago
Light is circularly pol. by 2 Refl. in Fresnel’s Rhomb.Fresnel.
 
 
 
+ in dirn of plagihedral faces.J. Herschel.
 
Plane of Poln. twisted.Biot
Fringes obliterated by stopping light from one edge or interposing a glass.Young.Arago.
 
 
 
 


 
 
 
 
——⏟——
⏟
⏟
⏟
⏟
⏟
 
 
 
Optical classification of crystals. Brewster.
 

 
 
 
 
 
 
 


 
 
 
Ratios not reconcilable. Irrationality.Blair.
Fresnel. 
Law exp. by surface of 4 dims.
Newt. Malus. Ray pol. in principal plane of Rhomb.; and perp. to it.
Brews. Biot. Ray pol. in plane bisecting ang.at axis; and perp. to it.
Brews. Ray pol. paral. to axis.
Malus. Ray pol. in plane of Refl. for given angle.
Malus. Ray partially pol. in plane perp. to plane of Reflection.
 
None Refld. if tan. ang. equal Refr. Ro.Brewster.

Tint is as sq. of sin.Biot.
Tint is as sin. α sin. β.Brewster.Biot.Lemniscates.J. Herschel.
 
* By interf. of resolved undulns. of 2 rays circularly pold. in opp. directions.* Fresnel.
* By interf. of resolved undulns. of 2 rays elliptically pold. in opp. directions.* Airy.

* By interf. of rays from edges.Young.
 
 
 
 


* Refl. produced by spherical undulns.
* Refr. produced by spherical undulns. of diff. vel. for diff. colour.
† Explanation imperfect.
* Refr. produced by spheroidal undulns.
* Refr. produced by curved surf. undulns.
* Poln. being prod. by resolution of transve undulns.
* Poln. being prod. by resolution of transve undulns.
† Explan. imperfect.
* Polarization being produced by resolution of transverse undulations.
* Undulns. being comd. acc. to laws of elastic bodies.
* Undulns. being comd. acc. to a certain hypothesis.
* Impossible formulæ being interpreted by analogy.
* By interf. of resolved parts of transverse undulns.
* By interf. of resolved parts of transverse undulns.
† Explan. imperfect.
* Same hypothesis explains separation of rays in axis and oblique.
† Explanation imperfect.* Maccullagh.
† Explan. wanting.
* By interf. of rays from all parts.* Young.* Fresnel.
* By interf. of undulns. from all parts.* Fraunhofer.
* By interf. of rays from striæ.* Young.
* By interf. of undulns. from two surfaces.* Young.
* By interf. of undulns. from two surfaces.* Young.


————⏟————
 
———⏟———
————⏟————
————⏟————
 
————⏟————


 
* Huyghens.
Reflection and Refraction are propagation of undulations.
 
* Young.* Fresnel.
Polarization in crystals is transverse undulations.
* Fresnel.
Polarization in Reflection and Refraction is transverse undulations.
* Fresnel.* Arago.
Dipolarized Colours are produced by interference of Rays polarized in same plane;
		length of undulation being different for different colours.

* Young.* Fresnel.
Colours of Fringes, Gratings, Striæ, thick Plates, thin Plates &c. are produced
		by interference of undulations; length of undulation being different for different colours.


* Undulations being propagated by the uniform elasticity of each medium.
* Undulns. prop. by ely. of medium diff. in 2 diff. dirns, (axis of crystal.)
* Undulns. being prop. by elasticity of med. diff. in 3 diff. directions (axes).
 


———⏟———
——⌟⌞——
—⏟—
 


 
Young. Reflection and double Refraction are propagation of undulations by crystalline elasticity.
 
* Fresnel. Double Refr. and Pol. arise from same cause.
 


—————⏟—————
—————⏟—————
—————⏟—————


 
Young.
Fresnel.
Light is transverse undulations propagated in media by elasticity dependent on axis, when crystalline.
Fresnel.
Light is transverse undulns. transmitted from one med. to another according to probable hypotheses.
Young.Fresnel.
Colours result from interferences, the lengths of undulation being different for different colours.



—————⏟—————




THE UNDULATORY THEORY OF LIGHT.


</div></body></text></TEI>