<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter: Box 165, folios 138-139</title>
        <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcribed from Bodleian Library, Lovelace Byron collection, Box 165, folios 138-139.
           Transcription by Lisa Gold (2022).
           TEI conversion for Sextant pipeline, 2026.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Lovelace, Ada Augusta (1815-1852)</author>
          <title>Letter to [William King]</title>
          <date when="1840">undated [1840]</date>
          <note type="place">St. James's Square</note>
          <note type="shelfmark">Lovelace Byron 165, folios 138-139</note>
          <note type="recipient">[William King]</note>
          <note type="transcriber">Lisa Gold</note>
          <note type="source_file">transcription_Lovelace_Byron_165_folios_138-139.txt</note>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body><div type="letter">
      <p>St. James' Sqre Saturday</p>
      <p>Dearest William. I read the enclosed, with no surprise. It is exactly what I anticipated would some time be made; &amp; shocking as it all is to reflect on, I have so long in my own mind felt the connection that such things, or something very similar, had been, in</p>
      <p>my most miserable &amp; unhappy family, that the proofs of the fact come to me as no new or startling thing.--</p>
      <p>It is tho' a most strange &amp; dreadful history! And to think that my Mother, {then we may say a young girl [double underlined]), &amp; purity &amp; innocence itself, should have been suddenly plunged into the midst of the greatest depths of depravity &amp; crimes, is almost more dreadful than the crimes themselves. I only wonder she has a particle</p>
      <p>of confidence in anybody whatever. I do indeed wonder she has!--</p>
      <p>I rather wish you could have seen what I have written to my Mother. But it would lose time to send it to you, &amp; I can repeat most of it when you come.</p>
      <p>My different affairs go on well on the whole; but the weather is very gloomy, &amp; I am rather dull than otherwise.--</p>
      <p>I have many little things to tell you when you come,</p>
      <p>&amp; I think you will approve of the arrangements I contemplate for the dispersal of my various occupations &amp; plans.--</p>
      <p>Your Birdie</p>
      <p>Very glad indeed about Parrate's Son.--</p>
    </div></body>
  </text>
</TEI>
