<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="87">CHAPTER III.
Discovery of the Laws of the Mutual Attraction and
Repulsion of Voltaic Currents.—Ampère.
IN order to show the place of
voltaic electricity among the mechanico-chemical sciences, we must
speak of its mechanical laws as separate from the laws of
electro-magnetic action; although, in fact, it was only in consequence
of the forces which conducting voltaic wires exert upon magnets, that
those forces were detected which they exert upon each 243 other. This latter
discovery was made by M. Ampère; and the extraordinary rapidity and
sagacity with which he caught the suggestion of such forces, from the
electro-magnetic experiments of M. Oersted, (of which we shall speak
in the next chapter,) well entitle him to be
considered as a great and independent discoverer. As he truly says,11 “it by no means followed, that because
a conducting wire exerted a force on a magnet, two conducting wires
must exert a force on each other; for two pieces of soft iron, both of
which affect a magnet, do not affect each other.” But immediately on
the promulgation of Oersted’s experiments, in 1820, Ampère leapt
forwards to a general theory of the facts, of which theory the mutual
attraction and repulsion of conducting voltaic wires was a fundamental
supposition. The supposition was immediately verified by direct trial;
and the laws of this attraction and repulsion were soon determined,
with great experimental ingenuity, and a very remarkable command of
the resources of analysis. But the experimental and analytical
investigation of the mutual action of voltaic or electrical currents,
was so mixed up with the examination of the laws of electro-magnetism,
which had given occasion to the investigation, that we must not treat
the two provinces of research as separate. The mention in this place,
premature as it might appear, of the labors of Ampère, arises
inevitably from his being the author of a beautiful and comprehensive
generalization, which not only included the phenomena exhibited by the
new combinations of Oersted, but also disclosed forces which existed
in arrangements already familiar, although they had never been
detected till the theory pointed out how they were to be looked
for.
11 Théorie des Phénom.
Electrodynamiques, p. 113.
</div></body></text></TEI>