<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="90">CHAPTER VI.
Theory of Electrodynamical Action.
AMPÈRE’S Theory.—Nothing
can show in a more striking manner the advanced condition of physical
speculation in 1820, than the reduction of the strange and complex
phenomena of electromagnetism to a simple and general theory as soon
as they were published. Instead of a gradual establishment of laws of
phenomena, and of theories more and more perfect, occupying ages, as
in the case of astronomy, or generations, as in the instances of
magnetism and electricity, a few months sufficed for the whole process
of generalization; and the experiments made at Copenhagen were
announced at Paris and London, almost at the same time with the
skilful analysis and comprehensive inductions of Ampère.
Yet we should err if we should suppose, from the celerity with
which the task was executed, that it was an easy one. There were
required in the author of such a theory, not only those clear
conceptions of the relations of space and force, which are the first
conditions of all sound theory, and a full possession of the
experiments; but also a masterly command of the mathematical arms by
which alone the victory could be gained, and a sagacious selection of
proper experiments which might decide the fate of the proposed
hypothesis.
It is true, that the nature of the requisite hypothesis was not
difficult to see in a certain vague and limited way. The
conducting-wire and the magnetic needle had a tendency to arrange
themselves at right angles to one another. This might be represented
by supposing the wire to be made up of transverse magnetic needles, or
by supposing the needle to be made up of transverse conducting-wires;
for it was easy to conceive forces which should bring corresponding
elements, either magnetic or voltaic, into parallel positions; and
then the 247
general phenomena above stated would be accounted for. And the choice
between the two modes of conception, appeared at first sight a matter
of indifference. The majority of philosophers at first adopted, or at
least employed, the former method, as Oersted in Germany, Berzelius in
Sweden, Wollaston in England.
Ampère adopted the other view, according to which the magnet is
made up of conducting-wires in a transverse position. But he did for
his hypothesis what no one did or could do for the other: he showed
that it was the only one which would account, without additional and
arbitrary suppositions, for the facts of continued motion in
electromagnetic cases. And he further elevated his theory to a higher
rank of generality, by showing that it explained,—not only the
action of a conducting-wire upon a magnet, but also two other classes
of facts, already spoken of in this history,—the action of magnets upon each other,—and the
action of conducting-wires upon each
other.
The deduction of such particular cases from the theory, required,
as may easily be imagined, some complex calculations: but the
deduction being satisfactory, it will be seen that Ampère’s theory
conformed to that description which we have repeatedly had to point
out as the usual character of a true and stable theory; namely, that
besides accounting for the class of phenomena which suggested it, it
supplies an unforeseen explanation of other known facts. For the
mutual action of magnets, which was supposed to be already reduced to
a satisfactory theoretical form by Coulomb, was not contemplated by
Ampère in the formation of his hypothesis; and the mutual action of
voltaic currents, though tried only in consequence of the suggestion
of the theory, was clearly a fact distinct from electromagnetic
action; yet all these facts flowed alike from the theory. And thus
Ampère brought into view a class of forces for which the term
“electromagnetic” was too limited, and which he designated14 by the appropriate term
electrodynamic; distinguishing them by this expression, as the
forces of an electric current, from the statical
effects of electricity which we had formerly to treat of. This term
has passed into common use among scientific writers, and remains the
record and stamp of the success of the Amperian induction.
14 Ann. de Chim., tom. xx. p.
60 (1822).
The first promulgation of Ampère’s views was by a communication to
the French Academy of Sciences, September the 18th, 1820; Oersted’s
discoveries having reached Paris only in the preceding July. 248 At almost every
meeting of the Academy during the remainder of that year and the
beginning of the following one, he had new developements or new
confirmations of his theory to announce. The most hypothetical part of
his theory,—the proposition that magnets might be considered in
their effects as identical with spiral voltaic wires,—he
asserted from the very first. The mutual attraction and repulsion of
voltaic wires,—the laws of this action,—the deduction of
the observed facts from it by calculation,—the determination, by
new experiments, of the constant quantities which entered into his
formulæ,—followed in rapid succession. The theory must be
briefly stated. It had already been seen that parallel voltaic
currents attracted each other; when, instead of being parallel, they
were situate in any directions, they still exerted attractive and
repulsive forces depending on the distance, and on the directions of
each element of both currents. Add to this doctrine the hypothetical
constitution of magnets, namely, that a voltaic current runs round the
axis of each particle, and we have the means of calculating a vast
variety of results which may be compared with experiment. But the laws
of the elementary forces required further fixation. What
functions are the forces of the distance and the directions
of the elements?
To extract from experiment an answer to this inquiry was far from
easy, for the elementary forces were mathematically connected with the
observed facts, by a double mathematical integration;—a long,
and, while the constant coefficients remained undefined, hardly a
possible operation. Ampère made some trials in this way, but his
happier genius suggested to him a better path. It occurred to him,
that if his integrals, without being specially found, could be shown
to vanish upon the whole, under certain conditions of the problem,
this circumstance would correspond to arrangements of his apparatus in
which a state of equilibrium was preserved, however the form of some
of the parts might be changed. He found two such cases, which were of
great importance to the theory. The first of these cases proved that
the force exerted by any element of the voltaic wire might be resolved
into other forces by a theorem resembling the well-known proposition
of the parallelogram of forces. This was proved by showing that the
action of a straight wire is the same with that of another wire which
joins the same extremities, but is bent and contorted in any way
whatever. But it still remained necessary to determine two fundamental
quantities; one which expressed the power of the distance
according to which the force varied; the other, the 249 degree in which the
force is affected by the obliquity of the elements. One of
the general causes of equilibrium, of which we have spoken, gave a
relation between these two quantities;15 and as the
power was naturally, and, as it afterwards appeared, rightly
conjectured to be the inverse square, the other quantity also was
determined; and the general problem of electrodynamical action was
fully solved.
15 Communication to the Acad. Sc.,
June 10, 1822. See Ampère, Recueil, p. 292.
If Ampère had not been an accomplished analyst, he would not have
been able to discover the condition on which the nullity of the
integral in this case depended.16 And throughout
his labors, we find reason to admire, both his mathematical skill, and
his steadiness of thought; although these excellences are by no means
accompanied throughout with corresponding clearness and elegance of
exposition in his writings.
16 Recueil, p. 314.
Reception of Ampère’s Theory.—Clear mathematical
conceptions, and some familiarity with mathematical operations, were
needed by readers also, in order to appreciate the evidence of the
theory; and, therefore, we need not feel any surprise if it was, on
its publication and establishment, hailed with far less enthusiasm
than so remarkable a triumph of generalizing power might appear to
deserve. For some time, indeed, the greater portion of the public were
naturally held in suspense by the opposing weight of rival names. The
Amperian theory did not make its way without contention and
competition. The electro-magnetic experiments, from their first
appearance, gave a clear promise of some new and wide generalization;
and held out a prize of honor and fame to him who should be first in
giving the right interpretation of the riddle. In France, the
emulation for such reputation is perhaps more vigilant and anxious
than it is elsewhere; and we see, on this as on other occasions, the
scientific host of Paris springing upon a new subject with an
impetuosity which, in a short time, runs into controversies for
priority or for victory. In this case, M. Biot, as well as Ampère,
endeavored to reduce the electro-magnetic phenomena to general laws.
The discussion between him and Ampère turned on some points which are
curious. M. Biot was disposed to consider as an elementary action, the
force which an element of a voltaic wire exerts upon a magnetic
particle, and which is, as we have seen, at right angles to their
mutual distance; and he conceived that 250 the equal reaction which necessarily
accompanies this action acts oppositely to the action, not in the same
line, but in a parallel line, at the other extremity of the distance;
thus forming a primitive couple, to use a technical expression
borrowed from mechanics. To this Ampère objected,17 that the
direct opposition of all elementary action and reaction was a
universal and necessary mechanical law. He showed too that such a
couple as had been assumed, would follow as a derivative
result from his theory. And in comparing his own theory with that in
which the voltaic wire is assimilated to a collection of transverse
magnets, he was also able to prove that no such assemblage of forces
acting to and from fixed points, as the forces of magnets do act,
could produce a continued motion like that discovered by Faraday.
This, indeed, was only the well-known demonstration of the
impossibility of a perpetual motion. If, instead of a collection of
magnets, the adverse theorists had spoken of a magnetic
current, they might probably interpret their expressions so as
to explain the facts; that is, if they considered every element of
such a current as a magnet, and consequently, every point of it as
being a north and a south point at the same instant. But to introduce
such a conception of a magnetic current was to abandon all the laws of
magnetic action hitherto established; and consequently to lose all
that gave the hypothesis its value. The idea of an electric current,
on the other hand, was so far from being a new and hazardous
assumption, that it had already been forced upon philosophers from the
time of Volta; and in this current, the relation of preceding
and succeeding, which necessarily existed between the
extremities of any element, introduced that relative polarity on which
the success of the explanations of the facts depended. And thus in
this controversy, the theory of Ampère has a great and undeniable
superiority over the rival hypotheses.
17 Ampère, Théorie, p.
154.
</div></body></text></TEI>