<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="106">CHAPTER II.
Epoch of Romé De Lisle and Haüy.—Establishment
of the Fixity of Crystalline Angles, and the Simplicity of the Laws of
Derivation.
WE have already seen that,
before 1780, several mineralogists had recognized the constancy of the
angles of crystals, and had seen (as Démeste and Werner,) that the
forms were subject to modifications of a definite kind. But neither of
these two thoughts was so apprehended and so developed, as to
supersede the occasion for a discoverer who should put forward these
principles as what they really were, the materials of a new and
complete science. The merit of this step belongs jointly to Romé de
Lisle and to Haüy. The former of these two men had already, in 1772,
published an Essai de Crystallographie, in which he had
described a number of crystals. But in this work his views are still
rude and vague; he does not establish any connected sequence of
transitions in each kind of substance, and lays little or no stress on
the angles. But in 1783, his ideas16 had reached a
maturity which, by comparison, excites our admiration. In this he
asserts, in the most distinct manner, the invariability of
the angles of crystals of each kind, under all the changes of relative
dimension which the faces may undergo;17 and he points
out that this invariability applies only to the primitive
forms, from each of which many secondary forms are derived by
various changes.18 Thus we cannot deny him the merit of
having taken steady hold on both the handles of this discovery, though
something still remained for another to do. Romé pursues his general
ideas into detail with great labor and skill. He gives drawings of
more than five hundred regular forms (in his first work he had
inserted only one hundred and ten; Linnæus only knew forty); and
assigns them to their proper substances; for instance, thirty to
calcspar, and sixteen to felspar. He also invented and used a
goniometer. We cannot doubt that he would have been 321 looked upon as a
great discoverer, if his fame had not been dimmed by the more
brilliant success of his contemporary Haüy.
16 Cristallographie, ou
Description de Formes propres à tous les Corps du Règne Minéral. 3
vols. and 1 vol. of plates.
17 p. 68.
18 p. 73.
Réné-Just Haüy is rightly looked upon as the founder of the modern
school of crystallography; for all those who have, since him, pursued
the study with success, have taken his views for their basis. Besides
publishing a system of crystallography and of mineralogy, far more
complete than any which had yet appeared, the peculiar steps in the
advance which belong to him are, the discovery of the importance of
cleavage, and the consequent expression of the laws of
derivation of secondary from primary forms, by means of the
decrements of the successive layers of integrant
molecules.
The latter of these discoveries had already been, in some measure,
anticipated by Bergman, who had, in 1773, conceived a hexagonal prism
to be built up by the juxtaposition of solid rhombs on the planes of a
rhombic nucleus.19 It is not clear20 whether Haüy
was acquainted with Bergman’s Memoir, at the time when the cleavage of
a hexagonal prism of calcspar, accidentally obtained, led him to the
same conception of its structure. But however this might be, he had
the indisputable credit of following out this conception with all the
vigor of originality, and with the most laborious and persevering
earnestness; indeed he made it the business of his life. The
hypothesis of a solid, built up of small solids, had this peculiar
advantage in reference to crystallography; it rendered a reason of
this curious fact;—that a certain series of forms occur in
crystals of the same kind, while other forms, apparently intermediate
between those which actually occur, are rigorously excluded. The
doctrine of decrements explained this; for by placing a number of
regularly-decreasing rows of equal solids, as, for instance, of
bricks, upon one another, we might form a regular equal-sided
triangle, as the gable of a house; and if the breadth of the gable
were one hundred bricks, the height of the triangle might be one
hundred, or fifty, or twenty-five; but it would be found that if the
height were an intermediate number, as fifty-seven, or forty-three,
the edge of the wall would become irregular; and such irregularity is
assumed to be inadmissible in the regular structure of crystals. Thus
this mode of conceiving crystals allows of certain definite secondary
forms, and no others.
19 De Formis Crystallorum.
Nov. Act. Reg. Soc. Sc. Ups. 1773.
20 Traité de Minér. 1822, i.
15.
The mathematical deduction of the dimensions and proportions 322 of these secondary
forms;—the invention of a notation to express them;—the
examination of the whole mineral kingdom in accordance with these
views;—the production of a work21 in which they
are explained with singular clearness and vivacity;—are services
by which Haüy richly earned the admiration which has been bestowed
upon him. The wonderful copiousness and variety of the forms and laws
to which he was led, thoroughly exercised and nourished the spirit of
deduction and calculation which his discoveries excited in him. The
reader may form some conception of the extent of his labors, by being
told—that the mere geometrical propositions which he found it
necessary to premise to his special descriptions, occupy a volume and
a half of his work;—that his diagrams are nearly a thousand in
number;—that in one single substance (calcspar) he has described
forty-seven varieties of form;—and that he has described one
kind of crystal (called by him fer sulfuré parallélique) which
has one hundred and thirty-four faces.
21 Traité de Minéralogie,
1801, 5 vols.
In the course of a long life, he examined, with considerable care,
all the forms he could procure of all kinds of mineral; and the
interpretation which he gave of the laws of those forms was, in many
cases, fixed, by means of a name applied to the mineral in which the
form occurred; thus, he introduced such names as équiaxe,
métastatique, unibinaire, perihexahèdre,
bisalterne, and others. It is not now desirable to apply
separate names to the different forms of the same mineral species, but
these terms answered the purpose, at the time, of making the subjects
of study more definite. A symbolical notation is the more convenient
mode of designating such forms, and such a notation Haüy invented; but
the symbols devised by him had many inconveniences, and have since
been superseded by the systems of other crystallographers.
Another of Haüy’s leading merits was, as we have already intimated,
to have shown, more clearly than his predecessors had done, that the
crystalline angles of substances are a criterion of the substances;
and that this is peculiarly true of the angles of
cleavage;—that is, the angles of those edges which are
obtained by cleaving a crystal in two different directions;—a
mode of division which the structure of many kinds of crystals allowed
him to execute in the most complete manner. As an instance of the
employment of this criterion, I may mention his separation of the
sulphates of baryta and strontia, which had 323 previously been confounded. Among
crystals which in the collections were ranked together as “heavy
spar,” and which were so perfect as to admit of accurate measurement,
he found that those which were brought from Sicily, and those of
Derbyshire, differed in their cleavage angle by three degrees and a
half. “I could not suppose,” he says,22 “that this
difference was the effect of any law of decrement; for it would have
been necessary to suppose so rapid and complex a law, that such an
hypothesis might have been justly regarded as an abuse of the theory.”
He was, therefore, in great perplexity. But a little while previous to
this, Klaproth had discovered that there is an earth which, though in
many respects it resembles baryta, is different from it in other
respects; and this earth, from the place where it was found (in
Scotland), had been named Strontia. The French chemists had
ascertained that the two earths had, in some cases, been mixed or
confounded; and Vauquelin, on examining the Sicilian crystals, found
that their base was strontia, and not, as in the Derbyshire ones,
baryta. The riddle was now read; all the crystals with the larger
angle belong to the one, all those with the smaller, to the other, of
these two sulphates; and crystallometry was clearly recognized as an
authorized test of the difference of substances which nearly resemble
each other.
22 Traité, ii. 320.
Enough has been said, probably, to enable the reader to judge how
much each of the two persons, now under review, contributed to
crystallography. It would be unwise to compare such contributions to
science with the great discoveries of astronomy and chemistry; and we
have seen how nearly the predecessors of Romé and Haüy had reached the
point of knowledge on which these two crystallographers took their
stand. But yet it is impossible not to allow, that in these
discoveries, which thus gave form and substance to the science of
crystallography, we have a manifestation of no common sagacity and
skill. Here, as in other discoveries, were required ideas and
facts;—clearness of geometrical conception which could deal with
most complex relations of form; a minute and extensive acquaintance
with actual crystals; and the talent and habit of referring these
facts to the general ideas. Haüy, in particular, was happily endowed
for his task. Without being a great mathematician, he was sufficiently
a geometer to solve all the problems which his undertaking demanded;
and though the mathematical reasoning might have been made more
compendious 324 by
one who was more at home in mathematical generalization, probably this
could hardly have been done without making the subject less accessible
and less attractive to persons moderately disciplined in mathematics.
In all his reasonings upon particular cases, Haüy is acute and clear;
while his general views appear to be suggested rather by a lively
fancy than by a sage inductive spirit: and though he thus misses the
character of a great philosopher, the vivacity of style, and felicity
and happiness of illustration, which grace his book, and which agree
well with the character of an Abbé of the old French monarchy, had a
great and useful influence on the progress of the subject.
Unfortunately Romé de Lisle and Haüy were not only rivals, but in
some measure enemies. The former might naturally feel some vexation at
finding himself, in his later years (he died in 1790), thrown into
shade by his more brilliant successor. In reference to Haüy’s use of
cleavage, he speaks23 of “innovators in crystallography, who
may properly be called crystalloclasts.” Yet he adopted, in
great measure, the same views of the formation of crystals by
laminæ,24 which Haüy illustrated by the
destructive process at which he thus sneers. His sensitiveness was
kept alive by the conduct of the Academy of Sciences, which took no
notice of him and his labors;25 probably
because it was led by Buffon, who disliked Linnæus, and might dislike
Romé as his follower; and who, as we have seen, despised crystallography. Haüy revenged
himself by rarely mentioning Romé in his works, though it was manifest
that his obligations to him were immense; and by recording his errors
while he corrected them. More fortunate than his rival, Haüy was, from
the first, received with favor and applause. His lectures at Paris
were eagerly listened to by persons from all quarters of the world.
His views were, in this manner, speedily diffused; and the subject was
soon pursued, in various ways, by mathematicians and mineralogists in
every country of Europe.
23 Pref. p. xxvii.
24 T. ii. p. 21.
25 Marx. Gesch. d. Cryst.
130.
</div></body></text></TEI>