<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="10">

BOOK II.

THE PHYSICAL SCIENCES IN ANCIENT
GREECE.

Plato’s Timæus and
Republic.
ALTHOUGH a great portion of
the physical speculations of the Greek philosophers was fanciful, and
consisted of doctrines which were rejected in the subsequent progress
of the Inductive Sciences; still many of these speculations must be
considered as forming a Prelude to more exact knowledge afterwards
attained; and thus, as really belonging to the Progress of knowledge.
These speculations express, as we have already said, the conviction
that the phenomena of nature are governed by laws of space and number;
and commonly, the mathematical laws which are thus asserted have some
foundation in the facts of nature. This is more especially the case in
the speculations of Plato. It has been justly stated by Professor
Thompson (A. Butler’s Lectures, Third Series, Lect. i. Note
11), that it is Plato’s merit to have discovered that the laws of the
physical universe are resolvable into numerical relations, and
therefore capable of being represented by mathematical formulæ. Of
this truth, it is there said, Aristotle does not betray the slightest
consciousness.
The Timæus of Plato contains a scheme of mathematical and
physical doctrines concerning the universe, which make it far more
analogous than any work of Aristotle to Treatises which, in modern
times, have borne the titles of Principia, System of the
World, and the like. And fortunately the work has recently been
well and carefully studied, with attention, not only to the language,
but to the doctrines and their bearing upon our real knowledge.
Stallbaum has published an edition of the Dialogue, and has compared
the opinions of Plato with those of Aristotle on the like subjects.
Professor Archer Butler of Dublin has devoted to it several of his
striking and eloquent Lectures; and these have been furnished with
valuable annotations by Professor Thompson of Cambridge; and M. The.
Henri Martin, then Professor at Rennes, published in 1841 two volumes
of Etudes sur le Timée de Platon, in 498 which the bearings of the work on
Science are very fully discussed. The Dialogue treats not only
concerning the numerical laws of harmonical sounds, of visual
appearances, and of the motions of planets and stars, but also
concerning heat, as well as light; and concerning water, ice, gold,
gems, iron, rust, and other natural objects;—concerning odors,
tastes, hearing, sight, light, colors, and the powers of sense in
general:—concerning the parts and organs of the body, as the
bones, the marrow, the brain, the flesh, muscles, tendons, ligaments,
nerves; the skin, the hair, the nails; the veins and arteries;
respiration; generation; and in short every obvious point of
physiology.
But the opinions delivered in the Timæus upon these latter
subjects have little to do with the progress of real knowledge. The
doctrines, on the other hand, which depend upon geometrical and
arithmetical relations, are portions or preludes of the sciences
which, in the fulness of time, assumed a mathematical form for the
expression of truth.
Among these may be mentioned the arithmetical relations of
harmonical sounds, to which I have referred
in the History. These occur in various parts of Plato’s writings. In
the Timæus, in which the numbers are most fully given, the
meaning of the numbers is, at first sight, least obvious. The numbers
are given as representing the proportion of the parts of the Soul
(Tim. pp. 35, 36), which does not immediately refer us to the
relations of Sounds. But in a subsequent part of the Dialogue (47,
d), we are told that music is a privilege of
the hearing given on account of Harmony; and that Harmony has Cycles
corresponding to the movements of the Soul; (referring plainly to
those already asserted.) And the numbers which are thus given by Plato
as elements of harmony, are in a great measure the same as those which
express the musical relations of the tones of the musical scale at
this day in use, as M. Henri Martin shows (Et. sur le Timée,
note xxiii.) The intervals C to D, C to F, C to G, C to C, are
expressed by the fractions  9⁄8,  4⁄3,  3⁄2,  2⁄1, and are now called a
Tone, a Fourth, a Fifth, an Octave. They were expressed by the same
fractions among the Greeks, and were called Tone,
Diatessaron, Diapente, Diapason. The Major and
Minor Third, and the Major and Minor Sixth, were however wanting, it
is conceived, in the musical scale of Plato.
The Timæus contains also a kind of theory of vision by
reflexion from a plane, and in a concave mirror; although the theory
is in this case less mathematical and less precise than that of
Euclid, referred to in chap. ii. of this
Book.
One of the most remarkable speculations in the Timæus is
that in 499 which
the Regular Solids are assigned as the forms of the Elements of which
the Universe is composed. This curious branch of mathematics, Solid
Geometry, had been pursued with great zeal by Plato and his friends,
and with remarkable success. The five Regular Solids, the Tetrahedron
or regular Triangular Pyramid, the Cube, the Octahedron, the
Dodecahedron, and the Icosahedron, had been discovered; and the
remarkable theorem, that of regular solids there can be just so many,
these and no others, was known. And in the Timæus it is
asserted that the particles of the various elements have the forms of
these solids. Fire has the Pyramid; Earth has the Cube; Water the
Octahedron; Air the Icosahedron; and the Dodecahedron is the plan of
the Universe itself. It was natural that when Plato had learnt that
other mathematical properties had a bearing upon the constitution of
the Universe, he should suppose that the singular property of space,
which the existence of this limited and varied class of solids
implied, should have some corresponding property in the Universe,
which exists in space.
We find afterwards, in Kepler and others, a recurrence to this
assumption; and we may say perhaps that Crystallography shows us that
there are properties of bodies, of the most intimate kind, which
involve such spatial relations as are exhibited in the Regular Solids.
If the distinctions of Crystalline System in bodies were hereafter to
be found to depend upon the chemical elements which predominate in
their composition, the admirers of Plato might point to his doctrine,
of the different form of the particles of the different elements of
the Universe, as a remote Prelude to such a discovery.
But the mathematical doctrines concerning the parts and elements of
the Universe are put forwards by Plato, not so much as assertions
concerning physical facts, of which the truth or falsehood is to be
determined by a reference to nature herself. They are rather
propounded as examples of a truth of a higher kind than any reference
to observation can give or can test, and as revelations of principles
such as must have prevailed in the mind of the Creator of the
Universe; or else as contemplations by which the mind of man is to be
raised above the region of sense, and brought nearer to the Divine
Mind. In the Timæus these doctrines appear rather in the former
of the two lights; as an exposition of the necessary scheme of
creation, so far as its leading features are concerned. In the seventh
Book of the Polity, the same doctrines are regarded more as a
mental discipline; as the necessary study of the true philosopher. But
in both places these mathematical 500 propositions are represented as
Realities more real than the Phenomena;—as a Natural Philosophy
of a higher kind than the study of Nature itself can teach. This is no
doubt an erroneous assumption: yet even in this there is a germ of
truth; namely, that the mathematical laws, which prevail in the
universe, involve mathematical truths  which being demonstrative, are
of a higher and more cogent kind than mere experimental truths.
Notions, such as these of Plato, respecting a truth at which
science is to aim, which is of an exact and demonstrative kind, and is
imperfectly manifested in the phenomena of nature, may help or may
mislead inquirers; they may be the impulse and the occasion to great
discoveries; or they may lead to the assertion of false and the loss
of true doctrines. Plato considers the phenomena which nature offers
to the senses as mere suggestions and rude sketches of the objects
which the philosophic mind is to contemplate. The heavenly bodies and
all the splendors of the sky, though the most beautiful of visible
objects, being only visible objects, are far inferior to the true
objects of which they are the representatives. They are merely
diagrams which may assist in the study of the higher truth  as we
might study geometry by the aid of diagrams constructed by some
consummate artist. Even then, the true object about which we reason is
the conception which we have in the mind.
We have, I conceive, an instance of the error as well as of the
truth, to which such views may lead, in the speculations of Plato
concerning Harmony, contained in that part of his writings (the
seventh Book of the Republic), in which these views are
especially urged. He there, by way of illustrating the superiority of
philosophical truth over such exactness as the senses can attest,
speaks slightingly of those who take immense pains in measuring
musical notes and intervals by the ear, as the astronomers measure the
heavenly motions by the eye. “They screw their pegs and pinch their
strings, and dispute whether two notes are the same or not.” Now, in
truth, the ear is the final and supreme judge whether two notes are
the same or not. But there is a case in which notes which are
nominally the same, are different really and to the ear; and it is
probably to disputes on this subject, which we know did prevail among
the Greek musicians, that Plato here refers. We may ascend from a note
A1 to a note C3 by two octaves and a third. We
may also ascend from the same note A1 to C3 by
fifths four times repeated. But the two notes C3 thus
arrived at are not the same: they differ by a small interval, which
the Greeks called a 501 Comma, of which the notes are in the
ratio of 80 to 81. That the ear really detects this defect of the
musical coincidence of the two notes under the proper conditions, is a
proof of the coincidence of our musical perceptions with the
mathematical relations of the notes; and is therefore an experimental
confirmation of the mathematical principles of harmony. But it seems
to be represented by Plato, that to look out for such confirmation of
mathematical principles, implies a disposition to lean on the senses,
which he regards as very unphilosophical.
Hero of Alexandria.
The other branches of mathematical science
which I have spoken of in the History as cultivated by the Greeks,
namely Mechanics and Hydrostatics, are not treated expressly by Plato;
though we know from Aristotle and others that some of the propositions
of those sciences were known about his time. Machines moved not only
by weights and springs, but by water and air, were constructed at an
early period. Ctesibius, who lived probably about b.
c. 250, under the Ptolemies, is said to have invented a
clepsydra or water-clock, and an hydraulic organ; and to have been the
first to discover the elastic power of air, and to apply it as a
moving power. Of his pupil Hero, the name is to this day familiar,
through the little pneumatic instrument called Hero’s Fountain.
He also described pumps and hydraulic machines of various kinds; and
an instrument which has been spoken of by some modern writers as a
steam-engine, but which was merely a toy made to whirl round by
the steam emitted from holes in its arms. Concerning mechanism,
besides descriptions of Automatons, Hero composed two works:
the one entitled Mechanics, or Mechanical Introductions;
the other Barulcos, the Weight-lifter. In these works
the elementary contrivances by which weights may be lifted or drawn
were spoken of as the Five Mechanical Powers, the same
enumeration of such machines as prevails to this day; namely, the
Lever, the Wheel and Axle, the Pulley, the Wedge, and the Screw. In
his Mechanics, it appears that Hero reduced all these machines to one
single machine, namely to the lever. In the Barulcos, Hero
proposed and solved the problem which it was the glory of Archimedes
to have solved: To move any object (however large) by any power
(however small). This, as may easily be conceived by any one
acquainted with the elements of Mechanics, is done by means of a
combination of the mechanical powers, and especially by means of a
train of toothed-wheels and axles. 502
The remaining writings of Hero of Alexandria have been the subject
of a special, careful, and learned examination by M. Th. H. Martin
(Paris, 1854), in which the works of this writer, Hero the Ancient, as
he is sometimes called, are distinguished from those of another writer
of the same name of later date.
Hero of Alexandria wrote also, as it appears, a treatise on
Pneumatics, in which he described machines, either useful or
amusing, moved by the force of air and vapor.
He also wrote a work called Catoptrics, which contained
proofs of properties of the rays of reflected light.
And a treatise On the Dioptra; which subject however must be
carefully distinguished from the subject entitled Dioptrics by
the moderns. This latter subject treats of the properties of refracted
light; a subject on which the ancients had little exact knowledge till
a later period; as I have shown in the
History. The Dioptra, as understood by Hero, was an instrument
for taking angles so as to measure the position and hence to determine
the distance of inaccessible objects; as is done by the
Theodolite in our times.
M. Martin is of opinion that Hero of Alexandria lived at a later
period than is generally supposed; namely, after b.
c. 81.</div></body></text></TEI>