<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="6">CHAPTER I.
Earliest Stages of Mechanics and
Hydrostatics.

Sect. 1.—Mechanics.
ASTRONOMY is a science so
ancient that we can hardly ascend to a period when it did not exist;
Mechanics, on the other hand, is a science which did not begin to be
till after the time of Aristotle; for Archimedes must be looked upon
as the author of the first sound knowledge on this subject. What is
still more curious, and shows remarkably how little the continued
progress of science follows inevitably from the nature of man, this
department of knowledge, after the right road had been fairly entered
upon, remained absolutely stationary for nearly two thousand years; no
single step was made, in addition to the propositions established by
Archimedes, till the time of Galileo and Stevinus. This extraordinary
halt will be a subject of attention hereafter; at present we must
consider the original advance.
The great step made by Archimedes in Mechanics was the
establishing, upon true grounds, the general proposition concerning a
straight lever, loaded with two heavy bodies, and resting upon a
fulcrum. The proposition is, that two bodies so circumstanced will
balance each other, when the distance of the smaller body from the
fulcrum is greater than the distance of the other, in exactly the same
proportion in which the weight of the body is less.
This proposition is proved by Archimedes in a work which is still
extant, and the proof holds its place in our treatises to this day, as
the simplest which can be given. The demonstration is made to rest on
assumptions which amount in effect to such Definitions and Axioms as
these: That those bodies are of equal weight which balance each other
at equal arms of a straight lever; and that in every heavy body there
is a definite point called a Centre of Gravity, in which point
we may suppose the weight of the body collected.
The principle, which is really the foundation of the validity of
the demonstration thus given, and which is the condition of all
experimental knowledge on the subject, is this: that when two equal
weights are supported on a lever, they act on the fulcrum of the lever
with the 97 same
effect as if they were both together supported immediately at that
point. Or more generally, we may state the principle to be this: that
the pressure by which a heavy body is supported continues the same,
however we alter the form or position of the body, so long as the
magnitude and material continue the same.
The experimental truth of this principle is a matter of obvious and
universal experience. The weight of a basket of stones is not altered
by shaking the stones into new positions. We cannot make the direct
burden of a stone less by altering its position in our hands; and if
we try the effect on a balance or a machine of any kind, we shall see
still more clearly and exactly that the altered position of one
weight, or the altered arrangement of several, produces no change in
their effect, so long as their point of support remains unchanged.
This general fact is obvious, when we possess in our minds the
ideas which are requisite to apprehend it clearly. But when we are so
prepared, the truth appears to be manifest, even independent of
experience, and is seen to be a rule to which experience must conform.
What, then, is the leading idea which thus enables us to reason
effectively upon mechanical subjects? By attention to the course of
such reasonings, we perceive that it is the idea of Pressure;
Pressure being conceived as a measurable effect of heavy bodies at
rest, distinguishable from all other effects, such as motion, change
of figure, and the like. It is not here necessary to attempt to trace
the history of this idea in our minds; but it is certain that such an
idea may be distinctly formed, and that upon it the whole science of
statics may be built. Pressure, load, weight, are
names by which this idea is denoted when the effect tends directly
downwards; but we may have pressure without motion, or dead
pull, in other cases, as at the critical instant when two
nicely-matched wrestlers are balanced by the exertion of the utmost
strength of each.
Pressure in any direction may thus exist without any motion
whatever. But the causes which produce such pressure are capable of
producing motion, and are generally seen producing motion, as in the
above instance of the wrestlers, or in a pair of scales employed in
weighing; and thus men come to consider pressure as the exception, and
motion as the rule: or perhaps they image to themselves the motion
which might or would take place; for instance, the
motion which the arms of a lever would have if they did
move. They turn away from the case really before them, which is that
of bodies at rest, and balancing each other, and pass to another case,
which is arbitrarily 98 assumed to represent the first. Now this
arbitrary and capricious evasion of the question we consider as
opposed to the introduction of the distinct and proper idea of
Pressure, by means of which the true principles of this subject can be
apprehended.
We have already seen that Aristotle was in the number of those who
thus evaded the difficulties of the problem of the lever, and
consequently lost the reward of success. He failed, as has before been
stated, in consequence of his seeking his principles in notions,
either vague and loose, as the distinction of natural and unnatural
motions, or else inappropriate, as the circle which the weight
would describe, the velocity which it would have if it
moved; circumstances which are not part of the fact under
consideration. The influence of such modes of speculation was the main
hindrance to the prosecution of the true Archimedean form of the
science of Mechanics.
The mechanical doctrine of Equilibrium, is Statics. It is to
be distinguished from the mechanical doctrine of Motion, which is
termed Dynamics, and which was not successfully treated till
the time of Galileo.
Sect. 2.—Hydrostatics.
Archimedes not only laid the foundations of
the Statics of solid bodies, but also solved the principal problem of
Hydrostatics, or the Statics of Fluids; namely, the conditions
of the floating of bodies. This is the more remarkable, since not only
did the principles which Archimedes established on this subject remain
unpursued till the revival of science in modern times, but, when they
were again put forward, the main proposition was so far from obvious
that it was termed, and is to this day called, the hydrostatic
paradox. The true doctrine of Hydrostatics, however, assuming the
Idea of Pressure, which it involves, in common with the Mechanics of
solid bodies, requires also a distinct Idea of a Fluid, as a body of
which the parts are perfectly movable among each other by the
slightest partial pressure, and in which all pressure exerted on one
part is transferred to all other parts. From this idea of Fluidity,
necessarily follows that multiplication of pressure which constitutes
the hydrostatic paradox; and the notion being seen to be verified in
nature, the consequences were also realized as facts. This notion of
Fluidity is expressed in the postulate which stands at the head of
Archimedes’ “Treatise on Floating Bodies.” And from this principle are
deduced the solutions, not only of the simple problems of the science,
but of some problems of considerable complexity. 99
The difficulty of holding fast this Idea of Fluidity so as to trace
its consequences with infallible strictness of demonstration, may be
judged of from the circumstance that, even at the present day, men of
great talents, not unfamiliar with the subject, sometimes admit into
their reasonings an oversight or fallacy with regard to this very
point. The importance of the Idea when clearly apprehended and
securely held, may be judged of from this, that the whole science of
Hydrostatics in its most modern form is only the development of the
Idea. And what kind of attempts at science would be made by persons
destitute of this Idea, we may see in the speculations of Aristotle
concerning light and heavy bodies, which we have already quoted;
where, by considering light and heavy as opposite qualities, residing
in things themselves, and by an inability to apprehend the effect of
surrounding fluids in supporting bodies, the subject was made a mass
of false or frivolous assertions, which the utmost ingenuity could not
reconcile with facts, and could still less deduce from the asserted
doctrines any new practical truths.
In the case of Statics and Hydrostatics, the most important
condition of their advance was undoubtedly the distinct apprehension
of these two appropriate Ideas—Statical Pressure,
and Hydrostatical Pressure as included in the idea of Fluidity.
For the Ideas being once clearly possessed, the experimental laws
which they served to express (that the whole pressure of a body
downwards was always the same; and that water, and the like, were
fluids according to the above idea of fluidity), were so obvious, that
there was no doubt nor difficulty about them. These two ideas lie at
the root of all mechanical science; and the firm possession of them
is, to this day, the first requisite for a student of the subject.
After being clearly awakened in the mind of Archimedes, these ideas
slept for many centuries, till they were again called up in Galileo,
and more remarkably in Stevinus. This time, they were not destined
again to slumber; and the results of their activity have been the
formation of two Sciences, which are as certain and severe in their
demonstrations as geometry itself and as copious and interesting in
their conclusions; but which, besides this recommendation, possess one
of a different order,—that they exhibit the exact impress of the
laws of the physical world, and unfold a portion of the rules
according to which the phenomena of nature take place, and must take
place, till nature herself shall alter. 100</div></body></text></TEI>