<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Reflections on the Decline of Science in England</title><author>Babbage, Charles (1791-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>B. Fellowes</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="21">
      SECTION 1. OF MINUTE PRECISION.
    

      No person will deny that the highest degree of attainable accuracy is an
      object to be desired, and it is generally found that the last advances
      towards precision require a greater devotion of time, labour, and expense,
      than those which precede them. The first steps in the path of discovery,
      and the first approximate measures, are those which add most to the
      existing knowledge of mankind.
    

      The extreme accuracy required in some of our modern inquiries has, in some
      respects, had an unfortunate influence, by favouring the opinion, that no
      experiments are valuable, unless the measures are most minute, and the
      accordance amongst them most perfect. It may, perhaps, be of some use to
      show, that even with large instruments, and most practised observers, this
      is but rarely the case. The following extract is taken from a
      representation made by the present Astronomer-Royal, to the Council of the
      Royal Society, on the advantages to be derived from the employment of two
      mural circles:—
    

      "That by observing, with two instruments, the same objects at the same
      time, and in the same manner, we should be able to estimate how much of
      that OCCASIONAL DISCORDANCE FROM THE MEAN, which attends EVEN THE MOST
      CAREFUL OBSERVATIONS, ought to be attributed to irregularity of
      refraction, and how much to THE IMPERFECTIONS OF INSTRUMENTS."
    

      In confirmation of this may be adduced the opinion of the late M.
      Delambre, which is the more important, from the statement it contains
      relative to the necessity of publishing all the observations which have
      been made.
    

      "Mais quelque soit le parti que l'on prefere, il me semble qu'on doit tout
      publier. Ces irregularites memes sont des faits qu'il importe de
      connoitre. LES SOINS LES PLUS ATTENTIFS N'EN SAUROIENT PRESERVER LES
      OBSERVATEURS LES PLUS EXERCES, et celui qui ne produiroit que des angles
      toujours parfaitment d'accord auroit ete singulierement bien servi par les
      circonstances ou ne seroit pas bien sincere."—BASE DU SYSTEME
      METRIQUE, Discours Preliminaire, p. 158.
    

      This desire for extreme accuracy has called away the attention of
      experimenters from points of far greater importance, and it seems to have
      been too much overlooked in the present day, that genius marks its tract,
      not by the observation of quantities inappreciable to any but the acutest
      senses, but by placing Nature in such circumstances, that she is forced to
      record her minutest variations on so magnified a scale, that an observer,
      possessing ordinary faculties, shall find them legibly written. He who can
      see portions of matter beyond the ken of the rest of his species, confers
      an obligation on them, by recording what he sees; but their knowledge
      depends both on his testimony and on his judgment. He who contrives a
      method of rendering such atoms visible to ordinary observers, communicates
      to mankind an instrument of discovery, and stamps his own observations
      with a character, alike independent of testimony or of judgment.
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>