<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>St. Leon</title><author>Godwin, William (1756-1836)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1799</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="13">CHAPTER XI.
It was in the evening of a summer’s day in the latter end
of the year fifteen hundred and forty-four, that a stranger
arrived at my habitation. He was feeble, emaciated, and
pale, his forehead full of wrinkles, and his hair and beard
as white as snow. Care was written in his face; it was
easy to perceive that he had suffered much from distress of
mind; yet his eye was still quick and lively, with a
strong expression of suspiciousness and anxiety. His garb,
which externally consisted of nothing more than a robe of
russet brown, with a girdle of the same, was coarse, threadbare,
and ragged. He supported his tottering steps with a
staff; and, having lost his foreteeth, his speech was indistinct
and difficult to be comprehended. His wretched appearance
excited my compassion, at the same time that I could easily
discern, beneath all its disadvantages, that he was no common
beggar or rustic. Ruined and squalid as he appeared,
I thought I could perceive traces in his countenance of what
had formerly been daring enterprise, profound meditation,
and generous humanity.
I saw that he was much fatigued, and I invited him to
rest himself upon the bench before the door. I set before
him bread and wine, and he partook of both. I asked him
his name and his country. He told me that he was a
Venetian, and that his name, as nearly as I could collect,
was signor Francesco Zampieri. He seemed however
averse to speaking, and he requested me to suffer him to
pass the night in my habitation. There was nothing singular
in the request, a hospitality of this sort being the practice
of the neighbourhood; and humanity would have prompted
my compliance, if I had not been still more strongly urged[125]
by an undefinable curiosity that began to spring up in my
bosom. I prepared for him a camp-bed in a summer-house
at the end of my garden. As soon as it was ready,
he desired to be left alone, that he might seek in rest some
relief from the fatigue he had undergone.
He retired early; and therefore, soon after daybreak the
next morning, I waited on him to enquire how he had
rested. He led me out into the fields; the morning was
genial and exhilarating. We proceeded, till we came to a
retired spot which had frequently been the scene of my
solitary meditations, and there seated ourselves upon a bank.
We had been mutually silent during the walk. As soon as
we were seated, the stranger began: “You are, I understand,
a Frenchman, and your name the count de St. Leon?”
I bowed assent.
“St. Leon,” said he, “there is something in your countenance
and manner that prepossesses me in your favour.
The only thing I have left to do in the world is to die;
and what I seek at present, is a friend who will take care
that I shall be suffered to die in peace. Shall I trust you?
Will you be that friend to me?”
I was astonished at this way of commencing his confidence
in me; but I did not hesitate to promise that he
should not find me deficient in any thing that became a man
of humanity and honour.
“You do not, I think, live alone? You have a wife and
children.”
“I have.”
“Yet none of them were at home when I arrived last
night. You brought yourself to the summer-house every
thing that was necessary for my accommodation.”
“I did so. But I have a wife to whom I have been
married seventeen years, and with whom I have no reserves.
I told her of your arrival; I spoke of your appearance; I
mentioned your name.”
“It is no matter. She has not seen me. My name is
not Zampieri; I am no Venetian.”
“Who are you then?”
“That you shall never know. It makes no part of the
confidence I design to repose in you. My name shall be[126]
buried with me in the grave; nor shall any one who has
hitherto known me, know how, at what time, or on what
spot of earth, I shall terminate my existence. The cloud of
oblivion shall shelter me from all human curiosity. What
I require of you is that you pledge your honour, and the faith
of a man, that you will never reveal to your wife, your
children, or any human being, what you may hereafter
know of me, and that no particular that relates to my history
shall be disclosed, till at least one hundred years after
my decease.”
“Upon these conditions I am sorry that I must decline
your confidence. My wife is a part of myself; for the last
six years at least I have had no thought in which she has
not participated; and these have been the most tranquil
and happy years of my life. My heart was formed by
nature for social ties; habit has confirmed their propensity;
and I will not now consent to any thing that shall infringe
on the happiness of my soul.”
While I spoke, I could perceive that my companion
grew disturbed and angry. At length, turning towards me
a look of ineffable contempt, he replied—
“Feeble and effeminate mortal! You are neither a
knight nor a Frenchman! Or rather, having been both,
you have forgotten in inglorious obscurity every thing
worthy of either! Was ever gallant action achieved
by him who was incapable of separating himself from a
woman? Was ever a great discovery prosecuted, or an
important benefit conferred upon the human race, by him
who was incapable of standing, and thinking, and feeling,
alone? Under the usurping and dishonoured name of
virtue, you have sunk into a slavery baser than that of the
enchantress Alcina. In vain might honour, worth, and
immortal renown proffer their favours to him who has
made himself the basest of all sublunary things—the puppet
of a woman, the plaything of her pleasure, wasting an
inglorious life in the gratification of her wishes and the
performance of her commands!”
I felt that I was not wholly unmoved at this expostulation.
The stranger touched upon the first and foremost
passions of my soul; passions the operation of which had[127]
long been suspended, but which were by no means extinguished
in my bosom. He proceeded:—
“But it is well! Years have passed over my head in
vain, and I have not learnt to distinguish a man of honour
from a slave. This is only one additional sorrow to those
in which my life has been spent. I have wandered through
every region of the earth, and have found only disappointment.
I have entered the courts of princes; I have accompanied
the march of armies; I have pined in the
putridity of dungeons. I have tasted every vicissitude of
splendour and meanness; five times have I been led to the
scaffold, and with difficulty escaped a public execution.
Hated by mankind, hunted from the face of the earth,
pursued by every atrocious calumny, without a country,
without a roof, without a friend; the addition that can be
made to such misfortunes scarcely deserves a thought.”
While he spoke, curiosity, resistless curiosity, presented
itself as a new motive, in aid of the sense of shame which
the stranger had just before kindled in my bosom. His
manner was inconceivably impressive; his voice, though
inarticulate from age, had an irresistible melody and
volume of sound, which awed, while it won, the heart.
His front appeared open, large, and commanding; and,
though he complained, his complaints seemed to be those
of conscious dignity and innocence. He went on:—
“Farewell, St. Leon! I go, and you shall see me and
hear of me no more. You will repent, when it is too late,
the folly of this day’s determination. I appear mean and
insignificant in your eyes. You think my secrets beneath
your curiosity, and my benefits not worth your acceptance.
Know that my benefits are such as kings would barter
their thrones to purchase, and that my wealth exceeds the
wealth of empires. You are degraded from the rank you
once held among mankind; your children are destined to
live in the inglorious condition of peasants. This day
you might have redeemed all your misfortunes, and raised
yourself to a station more illustrious than that to which
you were born. Farewell! Destiny has marked out you
and yours for obscurity and oblivion, and you do well to[128]
reject magnificence and distinction when they proffer themselves
for your acceptance.”
“Stop,” cried I, “mysterious stranger! Grant me a
moment’s leisure to reflect and determine.”
He had risen to depart, with a gesture of resolution and
contempt. At my exclamation he paused, and again turned
himself towards me. My soul was in tumults.
“Answer me, most ambiguous and impenetrable of
mortals! What is thy story? and what the secrets, the
disclosure of which is pregnant with consequences so extraordinary?”
“Do you recollect the conditions upon which only the
disclosure can be made?”
“What can I say? Shall I determine to part with that
which for years has constituted the only consolation of my
life? Shall I suppress the curiosity which now torments
me, and reject the boon you pretend to have the power to
confer?”
“I grant you the interval for reflection you demand. I
refuse to place further confidence in you, till you have maturely
examined yourself, and roused all the energies of
your spirit to encounter the task you undertake.”
“One word more. You know not, indeed you know
not, what a woman you exclude from your confidence. She
is more worthy of it than I am. Referring to my own experience
and knowledge of the world, I can safely pronounce
her the first of her sex, perhaps the first of human
beings. Indulge me in this; include her in your confidence;
and I am content.”
“Be silent! I have made my determination; do you
make yours! Know I would not if I could, and cannot
if I would, repose the secrets that press upon me in more
than a single bosom. It was upon this condition I received
the communication; upon this condition only can I impart
it. I am resolved; to die is the election of my soul—a
consummation for which I impatiently wait. Having determined
therefore to withdraw myself from the powers
committed to me, I am at liberty to impart them; upon
the same condition, and no other, you may one day, if you
desire it, seek the relief of confidence.”
[129]
Having thus spoken, the stranger rose from his seat. It
was yet early morning, nor was it likely we should meet
any one in our walk. He however employed the precaution
of causing me to explore the path, and to see that
we should return uninterrupted. We came back to the
summer-house. The window-shutters were still closed;
the stranger determined they should remain so. When I
had come to him as soon as I rose, I had found the door
secured; nor had he admitted me, till he recognised my
voice, and had ascertained that I was alone. These precautions
scarcely excited my attention at the time; but,
after the conversation that had just passed, they returned
distinctly to my memory.
The remainder of the day which had been opened by
this extraordinary scene was passed by me in great anxiety.
I ruminated with unceasing wonder and perturbation upon
the words of the stranger. Shall I shut upon myself the
gate of knowledge and information? Is it not the part of
a feeble and effeminate mind to refuse instruction, because
he is not at liberty to communicate that instruction to another—to
a wife? The stranger professes to be able to raise
me to the utmost height of wealth and distinction. Shall
I refuse the gift, which in a former instance I forfeited,
but for which, though contemplated as at an impracticable
distance, my whole soul longs? If there is any thing dishonourable
connected with the participation of this wealth,
I shall still be at liberty to refuse it. There can be no
crime in hearing what this man has to communicate. I
shall still, and always, be master of myself; nor can I have
any thing personally to fear from a man so feeble, so decrepit,
so emaciated. Yet what can be the gifts worthy of
acceptance of a man who, while he possesses them, is tired
of life, and desires to die? or what the wealth of him who
bears about him every external symptom of poverty and
desolation?
The conversation I had just held revived in my mind
the true feeling of my present situation. The wounds of
my soul had been lulled into temporary insensibility; but
they were in a state in which the slightest accident was
capable of making them bleed afresh, and with all their[130]
former violence. I had rather steeled my mind to endure
what seemed unavoidable, than reconciled myself to my
fate. The youthful passions of my soul, which my early
years had written there in characters so deep, were by no
means effaced. I could not contemplate the splendour of
rank with an impartial eye. I could not think of the
alternative of distinction or obscurity for my children with
indifference. But, most of all, the moment I had experienced
for them of hunger, and impending destruction
by famine, had produced an indelible impression. It had
destroyed all romance, I had almost said all dignity, in my
mind for ever. It had snapped, as by the touch of a red-hot
iron, all the finer and more etherialised sinews of my
frame. It had planted the sordid love of gold in my heart,
there, by its baneful vegetation, to poison every nobler and
more salubrious feeling.
When I returned to the house, Marguerite enquired of
me respecting the stranger, but my answers were short and
embarrassed. She seemed to wonder that he did not come
into the house, and partake of some refreshment in the
midst of my family. She asked, whether he were indisposed?
and whether he did not stand in need of some assistance
that she might afford him? Perceiving however that
I was desirous of saying as little as possible respecting him,
she presently became silent. I could see that she was hurt
at my incommunicativeness, yet I could not prevail upon
myself to enter into an explanation of the causes of my taciturnity.
Ours was a family of love; and I could observe
that the children sympathised with their mother, and
secretly were surprised at and lamented my reserve. There
would have been little in this, in perhaps any other family
than ours. But the last six years had been spent by us in
such primeval simplicity, that scarcely one of us had a
thought but what was known to the rest. Marguerite cherished
my frankness and unreserve with peculiar zeal; she
remembered with bitterness of soul the periods in which I
fostered conceptions only proper to myself—periods of
dreadful calamity, or of rooted melancholy and sadness.
She could not help regarding the silence into which for the
present occasion I relapsed, as a portent of evil augury.[131]
Charles, who was now sixteen years of age, recollected the
period of our ruined fortunes when he had been alone with
me at Paris, and partook of his mother’s feelings.
A trifling circumstance, at this time occasioned by the
little Marguerite, now eight years of age, rendered the
restraint under which I laboured more memorable and
striking. She had left a little book of fairy tales, in which
she had been reading the day before, in the summer-house.
At first she did not recollect what was become of it, and
employed herself in searching for it with great assiduity.
Of a sudden however she remembered where she had read
in it last; and, exclaiming with exultation, “It is in the
summer-house!” sprang forward to fetch it. I detained
her, and told her there was a sick gentleman there that she
would disturb! “Then, dear Julia!” rejoined she, “be so
good as to get it for me; you are so quiet and careful, you
never disturb any body.”
“My love,” answered I, “nobody must get it for you.
The gentleman chooses to be alone, and will not let any
body come to him. You shall have it after dinner.”
“Ah, but, papa, I want it now. I put it away, just
where the naughty giant had shut up the gentleman in the
dungeon, who came to take away the lady. I was obliged
to put it away then, because mamma called me to go to
bed; but I want so to know what will become of them,
you cannot think.”
“Well, dear Marguerite, I am sorry you must wait; but
you must learn to have patience.”
“Do you know, papa, I walked in the garden before
breakfast: and so, not thinking of any thing, I came to
the summer-house; and I tried to open the door, but I
could not. I found it was locked. So I thought Julia
was there; and I knocked, and called Julia, but nobody
answered. So then I knew Julia was not there, for I was
sure she would have opened the door. So I climbed upon
the stump of the pear-tree, and tried to look in at the window;
but the shutters were shut, and I could not get to see
over the top of them. And I walked all round the summer-house,
and all the shutters were shut. Papa, I wish
you would not let a man get into the summer-house, who[132]
shuts all the shutters, and locks the door. You always
used to let me go into every room I liked; and, do you
know, I think none but bad people lock and bolt themselves
up so. It puts mind of the giants with their drawbridges
and their pitfalls; I shall be quite afraid of this frightful old
man.”
This prattle of the child was nothing; yet it increased
the embarrassment of my situation, and made the peculiarity
of the case more conspicuous. Finding her pertinacious
in insisting upon a topic that was disagreeable to
me, her mother called her from me, and put her upon some
occupation that served to divert her attention. I felt like
a person that was guilty of some crime; and this consideration
and kindness of my wife, when I seemed to myself to
deserve her reproach, had not the power to calm my
uneasiness.
These little occurrences appeared like the beginning of
a separation of interests, and estrangement of hearts. I
tasked myself severely. I summoned the whole force of
my mind, that I might strictly consider what it was in
which I was about to engage. If this slight and casual
hint of a secret is felt by both Marguerite and myself with
so much uneasiness and embarrassment, what will be our
situation, if I go on to accept the stranger’s confidence, and
become the depository of an arcanum so important as he
represents his to be? He declares himself able to bestow
upon me the highest opulence; what will be the feelings of
my wife and children when they see my condition suddenly
changed from its present humble appearance to splendour
and wealth, without being able to assign the source of this
extraordinary accession?
It is difficult to conceive a family picture more enviable
that than to which I was now continually present, and of
which I formed a part. We had been happy on the banks
of the Garonne, and we had pictured to ourselves a plan of
happiness immediately on our arrival in the city of Constance.
But these were little and imperfect, compared with
what I now enjoyed. In the first situation my children
were infants, and in the second the eldest was but ten years
of age. The mother was now thirty-five; and she had[133]
lost, in my eyes at least, none of her personal attractions.
Her intellectual accomplishments were much greater than
ever. Her understanding was matured, her judgment decided,
her experience more comprehensive. As she had a
greater compass of materials to work upon, her fancy was
more playful, her conversation richer, and her reflections
more amusing and profound. The matron character she
had acquired, had had no other effect on her feelings, than
to render them more deep, more true and magnetical. Her
disposition was more entirely affectionate than it had been
even in the first year of our cohabitation. Her attachment
to her children was exemplary, and her vigilance uninterrupted;
and, for myself, she was accustomed, in all that
related to our mutual love, to enter into my sentiments and
inclinations with so just a tone of equality and kindness,
that we seemed to be two bodies animated by a single soul.
If the mother were improved, the children were still more
improved. In their early years we are attached to our offspring,
merely because they are ours, and in a way that has
led superficial speculators to consider the attachment, less as
the necessary operation of a sensible and conscious mind,
than as a wise provision of nature for the perpetuation of
the species. But as they grow up, the case is different.
Our partiality is then confirmed or diminished by qualities
visible to an impartial bystander as really as to ourselves.
They then cease to be merely the objects of our solicitude,
and become our companions, the partners of our sentiments,
and the counsellors of our undertakings. Such at least was
my case at the present period. Charles, who was now
sixteen, was manly beyond his years; while the native fire
of his disposition was tempered by adversity, by an humble
situation, and by the ardour of filial and fraternal affection.
Julia, who was two years younger, became daily more interesting
by the mildness of her disposition and the tenderness
of her sensibility. Louisa was only twelve; but, as
she was extremely notable, and had an uncommonly quick
and accurate spirit of imitation, she rendered herself exceedingly
useful to her mother. Marguerite, the plaything
and amusement of the family, had, as I have said, just
completed the eighth year of her age.
[134]
One exquisite source of gratification, when it is not a
source of uneasiness, to speak from my own experience,
which a parent finds in the society of his children, is their
individuality. They are not puppets, moved with wires,
and to be played on at will. Almost from the hour of their
birth they have a will of their own, to be consulted and
negotiated with. We may say to them, as Adam to the
general mother of mankind, “But now, thou wert flesh of
my flesh, and bone of my bone; and, even now, thou
standest before me vested in the prerogatives of sentiment
and reason; a living being, to be regarded with attention
and deference; to be courted, not compelled; susceptible of
the various catalogue of human passions; capable of resentment
and gratitude, of indignation and love, of perverseness
and submission. It is because thou art thus
formed that I love thee. I cannot be interested about objects
inanimate or brute. I require a somewhat that shall
exercise my judgment, and awaken my moral feelings. It
is necessary to me to approve myself, and be approved by
another. I rejoice to stand before you, at once the defendant
and the judge. I rejoice in the restraint to which your
independent character subjects me, and it will be my pride
to cultivate that independence in your mind. I would negotiate
for your affections and confidence, and not be loved
by you, but in proportion as I shall have done something
to deserve it. I could not congratulate myself upon your
correspondence to my wishes, if it had not been in your
power to withhold it.”
While I indulge this vein of reflection, I seem again to
see my family, as they surrounded me in the year fifteen
hundred and forty-four; Marguerite the partner of my life,
Charles the brother of my cares, the blooming Julia, the
sage Louisa, and the playful cadette of the family. How
richly furnished, how cheerful, how heart-reviving, appeared
to me the apartment in which they were assembled! I
dwell upon the image with fond affection and lingering delight.
Where are they now? How has all this happiness
been maliciously undermined, and irrevocably destroyed!
To look back on it, it seems like the idle fabric of a dream.
I awake, and find myself alone! Were there really such[135]
persons? Where are they dispersed? Whither are they
gone? Oh, miserable solitude and desertion, to which I
have so long been condemned! I see nothing around me
but speechless walls, or human faces that say as little to my
heart as the walls themselves! How palsied is my soul!
How withered my affections!—But I will not anticipate.
</div></body></text></TEI>