<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="97">CHAPTER IV.
Doctrine of Acidification and
Combustion.—Phlogistic Theory.
PUBLICATION of the Theory
by Beccher and Stahl.—It will be recollected that we are
tracing the history of the progress only of Chemistry, not of
its errors;—that we are concerned with doctrines only so far as
they are true, and have remained part of the received system of
chemical truths. The Phlogistic Theory was deposed and succeeded by
the Theory of Oxygen. But this circumstance must not lead us to
overlook the really sound and permanent part of the opinions which the
founders of the phlogistic theory taught. They brought together, as
processes of the same kind, a number of changes which at first
appeared to have nothing in common; as acidification, combustion,
respiration. Now this classification is true; and its importance
remains undiminished, whatever are the explanations which we adopt of
the processes themselves.
The two chemists to whom are to be ascribed the merit of this step,
and the establishment of the phlogistic theory which they
connected 268 with
it, are John Joachim Beccher and George Ernest Stahl; the former of
whom was professor at Mentz, and physician to the Elector of Bavaria
(born 1625, died 1682); the latter was professor at Halle, and
afterwards royal physician at Berlin (born 1660, died 1734). These two
men, who thus contributed to a common purpose, were very different
from each other. The first was a frank and ardent enthusiast in the
pursuit of chemistry, who speaks of himself and his employments with a
communicativeness and affection both amusing and engaging. The other
was a teacher of great talents and influence, but accused of
haughtiness and moroseness; a character which is well borne out by the
manner in which, in his writings, he anticipates an unfavorable
reception, and defies it. But it is right to add to this that he
speaks of Beccher, his predecessor, with an ungrudging acknowledgment
of obligations to him, and a vehement assertion of his merit as the
founder of the true system, which give a strong impression of Stahl’s
justice and magnanimity.
Beccher’s opinions were at first promulgated rather as a correction
than a refutation of the doctrine of the three principles, salt,
sulphur, and mercury. The main peculiarity of his views consists in
the offices which he ascribes to his sulphur, these being such
as afterwards induced Stahl to give the name of Phlogiston to
this element. Beccher had the sagacity to see that the reduction of
metals to an earthy form (calx), and the formation of sulphuric
acid from sulphur, are operations connected by a general analogy, as
being alike processes of combustion. Hence the metal was supposed to
consist of an earth, and of something which, in the process of
combustion, was separated from it; and, in like manner, sulphur was
supposed to consist of the sulphuric acid, which remained after its
combustion, and of the combustible part or true sulphur, which flew
off in the burning. Beccher insists very distinctly upon this
difference between his element sulphur and the “sulphur” of his
Paracelsian predecessors.
It must be considered as indicating great knowledge and talent in
Stahl, that he perceived so clearly what part of the views of Beccher
was of general truth and permanent value. Though he11 everywhere gives to Beccher the credit
of the theoretical opinions which he promulgates, (“Beccheriana sunt
quæ profero,”) it seems certain that he had the merit, not only of
proving them more completely, and applying them more widely than his
forerunner, but also of conceiving them 269 with a distinctness which Beccher did
not attain. In 1697, appeared Stahl’s Zymotechnia Fundamentalis
(the Doctrine of Fermentation), “simulque experimentum novum
sulphur verum arte producendi.” In this work (besides other tenets
which the author considered as very important), the opinion published
by Beccher was now maintained in a very distinct form;—namely,
that the process of forming sulphur from sulphuric acid, and of
restoring the metals from their calces, are analogous, and consist
alike in the addition of some combustible element, which Stahl termed
phlogiston (φλογίστον, combustible). The experiment most
insisted on in the work now spoken of,12 was the
formation of sulphur from sulphate of potass (or of soda) by fusing
the salt with an alkali, and throwing in coals to supply phlogiston.
This is the “experimentum novum.” Though Stahl published an account of
this process, he seems to have regretted his openness. “He denies
not,” he says, “that he should peradventure have dissembled this
experiment as the true foundation of the Beccherian assertion
concerning the nature of sulphur, if he had not been provoked by the
pretending arrogance of some of his contemporaries.”
11 Stahl, Præf. ad Specim.
Becch. 1703.
12 P. 117.
From this time, Stahl’s confidence in his theory may be traced
becoming more and more settled in his succeeding publications. It is
hardly necessary to observe here, that the explanations which his
theory gives are easily transformed into those which the more recent
theory supplies. According to modern views, the addition of oxygen
takes place in the formation of acids and of calces, and in
combustion, instead of the subtraction of phlogiston. The coal which
Stahl supposed to supply the combustible in his experiment, does in
fact absorb the liberated oxygen. In like manner, when an acid
corrodes a metal, and, according to existing theory, combines with and
oxidates it, Stahl supposed that the phlogiston separated from the
metal and combined with the acid. That the explanations of the
phlogistic theory are so generally capable of being translated into
the oxygen theory, merely by inverting the supposed transfer of the
combustible element, shows us how important a step towards the modern
doctrines the phlogistic theory really was.
The question, whether these processes were in fact addition or
subtraction, was decided by the balance, and belongs to a succeeding
period of the science. But we may observe, that both Beccher and Stahl
were aware of the increase of weight which metals undergo in 270 calcination; although
the time had not yet arrived in which this fact was to be made one of
the bases of the theory.
It has been said,13 that in the adoption of the phlogistic
theory, that is, in supposing the above-mentioned processes to be
addition rather than subtraction, “of two possible roads the wrong was
chosen, as if to prove the perversity of the human mind.” But we must
not forget how natural it was to suppose that some part of a body was
destroyed or removed by combustion; and we may
observe, that the merit of Beccher and Stahl did not consist in the
selection of one road or two, but in advancing so far as to reach this
point of separation. That, having done this, they went a little
further on the wrong line, was an error which detracted little from
the merit or value of the progress really made. It would be easy to
show, from the writings of phlogistic chemists, what important and
extensive truths their theory enabled them to express simply and
clearly.
13 Herschel’s Introd. to Nat.
Phil. p. 300.
That an enthusiastic temper is favorable to the production of great
discoveries in science, is a rule which suffers no exception in the
character of Beccher. In his preface14 addressed “to
the benevolent reader” of his Physica Subterranea, he speaks of
the chemists as a strange class of mortals, impelled by an almost
insane impulse to seek their pleasure among smoke and vapor, soot and
flame, poisons and poverty. “Yet among all these evils,” he says, “I
seem to myself to live so sweetly, that, may I die if I would change
places with the Persian king.” He is, indeed, well worthy of
admiration, as one of the first who pursued the labors of the furnace
and the laboratory, without the bribe of golden hopes. “My kingdom,”
he says, “is not of this world. I trust that I have got hold of my
pitcher by the right handle,—the true method of treating this
study. For the Pseudochymists seek gold; but the true
philosophers, science, which is more precious than any gold.”
14 Frankfort, 1681.
The Physica Subterranea made no converts. Stahl, in his
indignant manner, says,15 “No one will wonder that it never yet
obtained a physician or a chemist as a disciple, still less as an
advocate.” And again, “This work obtained very little reputation or
estimation, or, to speak ingenuously, as far as I know, none
whatever.” In 1671, Beccher published a supplement to his work, in
which he showed how metal might be extracted from mud and sand. He
offered to execute 271 this at Vienna; but found that people
there cared nothing about such novelties. He was then induced, by
Baron D’Isola, to go to Holland for similar purposes. After various
delays and quarrels, he was obliged to leave Holland for fear of his
creditors; and then, I suppose, came to Great Britain, where he
examined the Scottish and Cornish mines. He is said to have died in
London in 1682.
15 Præf. Phys. Sub.
1703.
Stahl’s publications appear to have excited more notice, and led to
controversy on the “so-called sulphur.” The success of the experiment
had been doubted, which, as he remarks, it was foolish to make a
matter of discussion, when any one might decide the point by
experiment; and finally, it had been questioned whether the substance
obtained by this process were pure sulphur. The originality of his
doctrine was also questioned, which, as he says, could not with any
justice be impugned. He published in defence and development of his
opinion at various intervals, as the Specimen Beccherianum in
1703, the Documentum Theoriæ Beecherianæ, a Dissertation De
Anatomia Sulphuris Artificialis; and finally, Casual Thoughts
on the so-called Sulphur, in 1718, in which he gave (in German)
both a historical and a systematic view of his opinions on the nature
of salts and of his Phlogiston.
Reception and Application of the Theory.—The theory
that the formation of sulphuric acid, and the restoration of metals
from their calces, are analogous processes, and consist in the
addition of phlogiston, was soon widely received; and the
Phlogistic School was thus established. From Berlin, its original
seat, it was diffused into all parts of Europe. The general reception
of the theory may be traced, not only in the use of the term
“phlogiston,” and of the explanations which it implies; but in the
adoption of a nomenclature founded on those explanations, which,
though not very extensive, is sufficient evidence of the prevalence of
the theory. Thus when Priestley, in 1774, discovered oxygen, and when
Scheele, a little later, discovered chlorine, these gases were termed
dephlogisticated air, and dephlogisticated marine acid;
while azotic acid gas, having no disposition to combustion, was
supposed to be saturated with phlogiston, and was called
phlogisticated air.
This phraseology kept its ground, till it was expelled by the
antiphlogistic, or oxygen theory. For instance. Cavendish’s papers on
the chemistry of the airs are expressed in terms of it, although his
researches led him to the confines of the new theory. We must now give
an account of such researches, and of the consequent revolution in the
science. 272</div></body></text></TEI>