<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="19">ON THE PERMANENT IMPRESSION OF OUR WORDS AND ACTIONS ON THE
 GLOBE WE INHABIT.
 The principle of the equality of action and reaction, when traced through
 all its consequences, opens views which will appear to many persons most unexpected.
 The pulsations of the air, once set in motion by the human voice, cease not
 to exist with the sounds to which they gave rise. Strong and audible as they
 may be in the immediate neighbourhood of the speaker, and at the immediate moment
 of utterance, their quickly
[page] 109
 attenuated force soon becomes inaudible to human ears. The motions they have
 impressed on the particles of one portion of our atmosphere, are communicated
 to constantly increasing numbers, but the total quantity of motion measured
 in the same direction receives no addition. Each atom loses as much as it gives,
 and regains again from other atoms a portion of those motions which they in
 turn give up. The waves of air thus raised, perambulate the earth and ocean's
 surface, and in less than twenty hours every atom of its atmosphere takes up
 the altered movement due to that infinitesimal portion of the primitive motion
 which has been conveyed to it through countless channels, and which must continue
 to influence its path throughout its future existence.*
* La courbe décrite par une simple molécule d'air ou vapeurs
 est réglée d'une manière aussi certain que les orbites
 planétaires: il n'y a de différence entre elles, que
[page] 110
 But these aerial pulses, unseen by the keenest eye, unheard by the acutest
 ear, un-perceived by human senses, are yet demonstrated to exist by human reason; and, in some few and limited instances, by calling to our aid the most refined
 and comprehensive instrument of human thought, their courses are traced and
 their intensities are measured. If man enjoyed a larger command over mathematical
 analysis, his knowledge of these motions would be more extensive; but a being
 possessed of unbounded knowledge of that science, could trace every the minutest
 consequence of that primary impulse. Such a being, however far exalted above
 our race, would still be immeasurably below even our conception of infinite
 intelligence. But supposing the original conditions of each atom of the earth's
 atmosphere, as well as all the extraneous causes acting on it to be
 celle qu'y met notre ignorance.— La Place, Théorie Analytique des
 Probabilités. Int. p. iv.
[page] 111
 given, and supposing also the interference of no new causes, such a being 
 would be able clearly to trace its future but inevitable path, and he would
 distinctly foresee and might absolutely predict for any, even the remotest period
 of time,* the circumstances and future history of every particle of that atmosphere.
 Let us imagine a being, invested with such knowledge, to examine at a distant
 epoch the coincidence of the facts with those which his profound analysis had
 enabled him to predict. If any the slightest deviation existed, he would immediately
 read in its existence the action of a new cause; and, through the aid of the
 same analysis, tracing this discordance back to its source, he would become
 aware of the time of its commencement, and the point of space at which it originated.
 Thus considered, what a strange chaos is this wide atmosphere we breathe! Every
 * See Note C in the Appendix.
[page] 112
 atom, impressed with good and with ill, retains at once the motions which
 philosophers and sages have imparted to it, mixed and combined in ten thousand
 ways with all that is worthless and base. The air itself is one vast library,
 on whose pages are for ever written all that man has ever said or woman whispered.
 There, in their mutable but unerring characters, mixed with the earliest, as
 well as with the latest sighs of mortality, stand for ever recorded, vows unredeemed,
 promises unfulfilled, perpetuating in the united movements of each particle,
 the testimony of man's changeful will. But if the air we breathe is the never-failing
 historian of the sentiments we have uttered, earth, air, and ocean, are the
 eternal witnesses of the acts we have done. The same principle of the equality
 of action and reaction applies to them: whatever movement is communicated to
 any of their particles, is transmitted to all around it, the share of each being
[page] 113
 diminished by their number, and depending jointly on the number and position
 of those acted upon by the original source of disturbance. The waves of air,
 although in many instances perceptible to the organs of hearing, are only rendered
 visible to the eye by peculiar contrivances; but those of water offer to the
 sense of sight the most beautiful illustration of transmitted motion. Every
 one who has thrown a pebble into the still waters of a sheltered pool, has seen
 the circles it has raised gradually expanding in size, and as uniformly diminishing
 in distinctness. He may have observed the reflection of those waves from the
 edges of the pool. He may have noticed also the perfect distinctness with which
 two, three, or more series of waves each pursues its own unimpeded course, when
 diverging from two, three, or more centres of disturbance. He may have seen,
 that in such cases the particles of water where the waves intersect each other,
 partake of the movements due to each series.
[page] 114
 No motion impressed by natural causes, or by human agency, is ever obliterated.
 The ripple on the ocean's surface caused by a gentle breeze, or the still water
 which marks the more immediate track of a ponderous vessel gliding with scarcely
 expanded sails over its bosom, are equally indelible. The momentary waves raised
 by the passing breeze, apparently born but to die on the spot which saw their
 birth, leave behind them an endless progeny, which, reviving with diminished
 energy in other seas, visiting a thousand shores, reflected from each and perhaps
 again partially concentrated, will pursue their ceaseless course till ocean
 be itself annihilated. The track of every canoe, of every vessel which has yet
 disturbed the surface of the ocean, whether impelled by manual force or elemental
 power, remains for ever registered in the future movement of all succeeding
 particles which may occupy its place. The furrow which it left is, indeed, instantly
 filled up by
[page] 115
 the closing waters; but they draw after them other and larger portions of
 the surrounding element, and these again once moved, communicate motion to others
 in endless succession. The solid substance of the globe itself, whether we regard
 the minutest movement of the soft clay which receives its impression from the
 foot of animals, or the concussion arising from the fall of mountains rent by
 earthquakes, equally communicates and retains, through all its countless atoms,
 their apportioned shares of the motions so impressed. Whilst the atmosphere
 we breathe is the ever-living witness of the sentiments we have uttered, the
 waters, and the more solid materials of the globe, bear equally enduring testimony
 of the acts we have committed. If the Almighty stamped on the brow of the earliest
 murderer — the indelible and visible
[page] 116
 mark of his guilt,—he has also established laws by which every succeeding
 criminal is not less irrevocably chained to the testimony of his crime; for
 every atom of his mortal frame, through whatever changes its severed particles
 may migrate, will still retain, adhering to it through every combination, some
 movement derived from that very muscular effort, by which the crime itself was
 perpetrated. The soul of the negro, whose fettered body surviving the living
 charnel-house of his infected prison, was thrown into the sea to lighten the
 ship, that his Christian master might escape the limited justice at length assigned
 by civilized man to crimes whose profit had long gilded their atrocity,—will
 need, at the last great day of human account, no living witness of his earthly
 agony.* When
 * The following extract is from a report by Captain Hayes to the Admiralty,
 of a representation made to him "respecting one of these vessels
 in 1832." The master having a large cargo of these human beings.
[page] 117
 man and all his race shall have disappeared from the face of our planet, ask
 every particle chained together, with more humanity than his fellows,
 permitted some of them to come on deck, but still chained together for the benefit of the air; when they immediately commenced jumping overboard,
 hand in hand, and drowning in couples; and, continued the person (relating
 the circumstance), ' without any cause whatever.' Now, these people were just
 brought from a situation between decks, and to which they knew they must return,
 where the scalding perspiration was running from one to the other, covered also
 with their own filth, and where it is no uncommon occurrence for women to
 be bringing forth children, and men dying at their side, with full in their 
 view living and dead bodies chained together; and the living, in addition
 to all their other torments, labouring under the most famishing thirst (being
 in very few instances allowed more than a pint of water a day);—and, let it
 not be forgotten, that these unfortunate people had just been torn from their
 country, their families, their all! Men dragged from their wives, women from
 their husbands and children, girls from their mothers, and boys from their fathers; and yet in this man's eye (for heart and soul he could have had none) there
 was no cause whatever for jumping overboard and drowning. This, in truth, is
 a rough picture; but it is not highly coloured. The men are chained in pairs; and, as a proof they are intended so to remain to the end of the voyage, their fetters are not locked, but rivetted by the blacksmith, and as
 deaths are frequently occurring lining men
[page] 118
 of air still floating over the unpeopled earth, and it will record the cruel
 mandate of the tyrant. Interrogate every wave which breaks unimpeded on ten
 thousand desolate shores, and it will give evidence of the last gurgle of the
 waters which closed over the head of his are often for a length of time confined
 to dead bodies; the living man cannot be released till the blacksmith has
 performed the operation of cutting the clench of the rivet with his chisel;
 and I have now an officer on board the Dryad, who, on examining one of
 these slave vessels, found not only living men chained to dead bodies, but
 the latter in a putrid state. And we have now a case reported here, which,
 if true, is too horrible and disgusting to be described."—Parliamentary
 Paper, 1832, B, pp. 170, 171, as quoted in the Quarterly Review, Dec.
 1835.
 When the ink was scarcely dry on the paper on which the remarks in the text,
 suggested by a former description of the atrocities of the slave trade, was
 written, the following paragraph caught my attention: " SLAVE TRADE.—His Majesty's
 ship Thalia, 31,Captain R. Wauchope, has captured on the coast of Africa,
 two slave vessels—one the Félicité, 611 slaves; the other,
 the Adalia, with 409 slaves. It appears the latter vessel had been chased
 by the boats of one of our cruizers, and to avoid being come up with she threw
 overboard upwards of 150 of the poor wretches who were on board, besides almost
 all her heavy stores."—Western Luminary, May 1837.
[page] 119
 dying victim: confront the murderer with every corporeal atom of his immolated
 slave, and in its still quivering movements he will read the prophet's denunciation
 of the prophet king.*
 * "And Nathan said unto David—Thou art the man."
[page] 120</div></body></text></TEI>