<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ninth Bridgewater Treatise</title><author>Babbage, Charles (1791-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="29">THOUGHTS ON THE NATURE OF FUTURE PUNISHMENTS.
 who has not felt the painful memory
 of departed folly? who has not at times found crowding on his recollection,
 thoughts, feelings, scenes, by all perhaps but himself forgotten, which force
 themselves involuntarily on his attention? Who has not reproached himself with
 the bitterest regret at the follies he has thought, or said, or acted? Time
 brings no alleviation to these periods of morbid memory: the weaknesses of
 our youthful days, as well as those of later life, come equally
[page] 160
 unbidden and unarranged, to mock
 our attention and claim their condemnation from our severer judgment. It is
 remarkable that those whom the world least accuses, accuse themselves the most; and that a foolish speech, which at the time of its utterance was unobserved
 as such by all who heard it, shall yet remain fixed in the memory of him who
 pronounced it, with a tenacity which he vainly seeks to communicate to more
 agreeable subjects of reflection. It is also remarkable that whilst our own
 foibles, or our imagined exposure of them to others, furnish the most frequent
 subject of almost nightly regret, yet we rarely call to recollection our acts
 of consideration for the feelings of others, or those of kindness and benevolence.
 These are not the familiar friends of our memory, ready at all times to enter
 the domicile of mind its welcome but unbidden guests. When they appear, they
 are usually summoned at the command of reason, to meet some
[page] 161
 expected ingratitude, or when the
 mind retires within its council chamber to nerve itself for the endurance or
 the resistance of injustice. If such be the pain, the penalty of thoughtless
 folly, who shall describe the punishment of real guilt? Make but the offender
 better, and he is already severely punished. Memory, that treacherous friend
 but faithful monitor, recalls the existence of the past, to a mind now imbued
 with finer feelings, with sterner notions of justice than when it enacted the
 deeds thus punished by their recollection. If additional knowledge be given
 to us, the consequences of many of our actions appear in a very altered light.
 We become acquainted with many evils they have produced, which, although quite unintentional on our part, are yet subjects of painful regret. But this unavailing
 regret is mixed with another feeling far more distressing. We reproach ourselves
 with not having sufficiently employed the faculties we
[page] 162
 possessed in acquiring that knowledge,
 which, if we had attained it, would have prevented us from committing acts we
 now discover to have been injurious to those we best loved. On the other hand,
 the good which such increased knowledge enables us to discover that we have unintentionally done, fails to produce the satisfaction always arising
 from a virtuous motive; and it is accompanied by the regret that, by a sufficient
 cultivation of our faculties, we might have enjoyed a still higher gratification,
 by a more efficient service to our fellow-creatures. Thus, on whichsoever side
 we look at the question, knowledge alone is advantageous to virtue; and
 if additional knowledge alone were given in a future life, it would cause
 the best of us to regret the errors of the present. Let us now consider the
 consequences of a higher tone of moral feeling—of a perception
[page] 163
 of excellencies of character in others, hitherto unappreciated. Without the
 torment arising from additional knowledge, we may, in such circumstances, perceive,
 that the pain we have inflicted for imagined offences was quite beyond their
 real deserts; and may feel that the justice we have done to others, has been
 quite disproportioned to the sacrifices they have made to serve us. If, without
 any addition to our intellectual faculties, increased perfection were given
 to our bodily senses, the same result would ensue. Wollaston has shown, that
 there are sounds of such a nature, that they can be heard by some individuals,
 but are inaudible to others,—a circumstance which may arise either from the
 incapacity of the parts of the ear to vibrate in the same time as those producing
 the sound, or from the force of the sounding body being insufficient to communicate
 motion through the
[page] 164
 air to those portions of the ear
 whose movement is required to produce the sensation of hearing. If we imagine
 the soul in an after stage of our existence, to be connected with a bodily organ
 of hearing so sensitive, as to vibrate with motions of the air, even of infinitesimal
 force, and if it be still within the precincts of its ancient abode, all the
 accumulated words pronounced from the creation of mankind, will fall at once
 upon that ear. Imagine, in addition, a power of directing the attention of that
 organ entirely to any one class of those vibrations: then will the apparent
 confusion vanish at once; and the punished offender may hear still vibrating
 on his ear the very words uttered, perhaps, thousands of centuries before, which
 at once caused and registered his own condemnation. It seems, then, that either
 with improved faculties or with increased knowledge, we could scarcely look
 back with any satisfaction on our
[page] 165
 past lives;—that, to the major
 part of our race, oblivion would be the greatest boon. But if, in a future state,
 we could turn from the contemplation of our own imperfections, and with increased
 powers apply our minds to the discovery of nature's laws, and to the invention
 of new methods by which our faculties might be aided in that research, pleasure
 the most unalloyed would await us at every stage of our progress. Unclogged
 by the dull corporeal load of matter which tyrannizes even over our most intellectual
 moments, and chains the ardent spirit to its unkindred clay, we should advance
 in the pursuit, stimulated instead of wearied by our past exertions, and encountering
 each new difficulty in the inquiry, with the accumulated power derived from
 the experience of the past, and the irresistible energy resulting from the confide ce
 of ultimate success. Whether, then, we regard our future prospects as connected
 with afar higher acuteness of our present senses—or, as purified by more
[page] 166
 exalted moral feelings—or, as guided
 by intellectual power surpassing all we contemplate upon earth, we equally arrive
 at the conclusion, that the mere employment of such enlarged faculties, in surveying
 our past existence, will be an ample punishment for all our errors; whilst,
 on the other hand, if that Being who assigned to us those faculties, should
 turn their application from the survey of the past, to the inquiry into the
 present and to the search into the future, the most enduring happiness would
 arise from the most inexhaustible source.
[page] 167</div></body></text></TEI>