<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="7">CHAPTER II.
Earliest Stages of Optics.
THE progress made by the
ancients in Optics was nearly proportional to that which they made in
Statics. As they discovered the true grounds of the doctrine of
Equilibrium, without obtaining any sound principles concerning Motion,
so they discovered the law of the Reflection of light, but had none
but the most indistinct notions concerning Refraction.
The extent of the principles which they really possessed is easily
stated. They knew that vision is performed by rays which
proceed in straight lines, and that these rays are reflected by
certain surfaces (mirrors) in such manner that the angles which they
make with the surface on each side are equal. They drew various
conclusions from these premises by the aid of geometry; as, for
instance, the convergence of rays which fall on a concave
speculum.
It may be observed that the Idea which is here introduced,
is that of visual rays, or lines along which vision is produced
and light carried. This idea once clearly apprehended, it was not
difficult to show that these lines are straight lines, both in the
case of light and of sight. In the beginning of Euclid’s “Treatise on
Optics,” some of the arguments are mentioned by which this was
established. We are told in the Proem, “In explaining what concerns
the sight, he adduced certain arguments from which he inferred that
all light is carried in straight lines. The greatest proof of this is
shadows, and the bright spots which are produced by light coming
through windows and cracks, and which could not be, except the rays of
the sun were carried in straight lines. So in fires, the shadows are
greater than the bodies if the fire be small, but less than the bodies
if the fire be greater.” A clear comprehension of the principle would
lead to the perception of innumerable proofs of its truth on every
side.
The Law of Equality of Angles of Incidence and Reflection was not
quite so easy to verify; but the exact resemblance of the object and
its image in a plane mirror, (as the surface of still water, for
instance), which is a consequence of this law, would afford convincing
evidence of its truth in that case, and would be confirmed by the
examination of other cases. 101
With these true principles was mixed much error and indistinctness,
even in the best writers. Euclid, and the Platonists, maintained that
vision is exercised by rays proceeding from the eye, not
to it; so that when we see objects, we learn their form as a
blind man would do, by feeling it out with his staff. This mistake,
however, though Montucla speaks severely of it, was neither very
discreditable nor very injurious; for the mathematical conclusions on
each supposition are necessarily the same. Another curious and false
assumption is, that those visual rays are not close together, but
separated by intervals, like the fingers when the hand is spread. The
motive for this invention was the wish to account for the fact, that
in looking for a small object, as a needle, we often cannot see it
when it is under our nose; which it was conceived would be impossible
if the visual rays reached to all points of the surface before us.
These errors would not have prevented the progress of the science.
But the Aristotelian physics, as usual, contained speculations more
essentially faulty. Aristotle’s views led him to try to describe the
kind of causation by which vision is produced, instead of the laws by
which it is exercised; and the attempt consisted, as in other
subjects, of indistinct principles, and ill-combined facts. According
to him, vision must be produced by a Medium,—by something
between the object and the eye,—for if we press the
object on the eye, we do not see it; this Medium is Light, or “the
transparent in action;” darkness occurs when the transparency is
potential, not actual; color is not the “absolute visible,” but
something which is on the absolute visible; color has the
power of setting the transparent in action; it is not, however, all
colors that are seen by means of light, but only the proper color of
each object; for some things, as the heads, and scales, and eyes of
fish, are seen in the dark; but they are not seen with their proper
color.1
1 De Anim. ii. 7.
In all this there is no steady adherence either to one notion, or
to one class of facts. The distinction of Power and Act is introduced
to modify the Idea of Transparency, according to the formula of the
school; then Color is made to be something unknown in addition to
Visibility; and the distinction of “proper” and “improper” colors is
assumed, as sufficient to account for a phenomenon. Such
classifications have in them nothing of which the mind can take steady
hold; nor is it difficult to see that they do not come under those
102 conditions of
successful physical speculation, which we have laid down.
It is proper to notice more distinctly the nature of the
Geometrical Propositions contained in Euclid’s work. The Optica
contains Propositions concerning Vision and Shadows, derived from the
principle that the rays of light are rectilinear: for instance, the
Proposition that the shadow is greater than the object, if the
illuminating body be less and vice versa. The Catoptrica
contains Propositions concerning the effects of Reflection, derived
from the principle that the Angles of Incidence and Reflection are
equal: as, that in a convex mirror the object appears convex, and
smaller than the object. We see here an example of the promptitude of
the Greeks in deduction. When they had once obtained a knowledge of a
principle, they followed it to its mathematical consequences with
great acuteness. The subject of concave mirrors is pursued further in
Ptolemy’s Optics.
The Greek writers also cultivated the subject of Perspective
speculatively, in mathematical treatises, as well as practically, in
pictures. The whole of this theory is a consequence of the principle
that vision takes place in straight lines drawn from the object to the
eye.
“The ancients were in some measure acquainted with
the Refraction as well as the Reflection of Light,” as I have shown in
Book ix. Chap. 2 [2d Ed.] of the
Philosophy. The current knowledge on this subject must have
been very slight and confused; for it does not appear to have enabled
them to account for one of the simplest results of Refraction, the
magnifying effect of convex transparent bodies. I have noticed in the
passage just referred to, Seneca’s crude notions on this subject; and
in like manner Ptolemy in his Optics asserts that an object
placed in water must always appear larger then when taken out.
Aristotle uses the term ἀνακλάσις (Meteorol. iii. 2), but
apparently in a very vague manner. It is not evident that he
distinguished Refraction from Reflection. His Commentators however do
distinguish these as διακλάσις and ἀνακλάσις. See Olympiodorus
in Schneider’s Eclogæ Physicæ, vol. i. p. 397. And
Refraction had been the subject of special attention among the Greek
Mathematicians. Archimedes had noticed (as we learn from the same
writer) that in certain cases, a ring which cannot be seen over the
edge of the empty vessel in which it is placed, becomes visible when
the vessel is filled with water. The same fact is stated in the
Optics of Euclid. We do not find this fact explained in that
work as we now have it; but in Ptolemy’s Optics the fact is
explained by a flexure of the visual ray: it is 103 noticed that this
flexure is different at different angles from the perpendicular, and
there is an elaborate collection of measures of the flexure at
different angles, made by means of an instrument devised for the
purpose. There is also a collection of similar measures of the
refraction when the ray passes from air to glass, and when it passes
from glass to water. This part of Ptolemy’s work is, I think, the
oldest extant example of a collection of experimental measures in any
other subject than astronomy; and in astronomy our measures are the
result of observation rather than of experiment. As
Delambre says (Astron. Anc. vol. ii. p. 427), “On y voit des
expériences de physique bien faites, ce qui est sans exemple chez les
anciens.”
Ptolemy’s Optical work was known only by Roger Bacon’s references
to it (Opus Majus, p. 286, &c.) till 1816; but copies of
Latin translations of it were known to exist in the Royal Library at
Paris, and in the Bodleian at Oxford. Delambre has given an account of
the contents of the Paris copy in his Astron. Anc. ii. 414, and
in the Connoissance des Temps for 1816; and Prof. Rigaud’s
account of the Oxford copy is given in the article Optics, in
the Encyclopædia Britannica. Ptolemy shows great sagacity in
applying the notion of Refraction to the explanation of the
displacement of astronomical objects which is produced by the
atmosphere,—Astronomical Refraction, as it is commonly
called. He represents the visual ray as refracted in passing from the
ether, which is above the air, into the air; the air being
bounded by a spherical surface which has for its centre “the centre of
all the elements, the centre of the earth;” and the refraction being a
flexure towards the line drawn perpendicular to this surface. He thus
constructs, says Delambre, the same figure on which Cassini afterwards
founded the whole of his theory; and gives a theory more complete than
that of any astronomer previous to him. Tycho, for instance, believed
that astronomical refraction was caused only by the vapors of
the atmosphere, and did not exist above the altitude of 45°.
Cleomedes, about the time of Augustus, had guessed at Refraction,
as an explanation of an eclipse in which the sun and moon are both
seen at the same time. “Is it not possible,” he says, “that the ray
which proceeds from the eye and traverses moist and cloudy air may
bend downwards to the sun, even when he is below the horizon?” And
Sextus Empiricus, a century later, says, “The air being dense, by the
refraction of the visual ray, a constellation may be seen above the
horizon when it is yet below the horizon.” But from what follows, it
104 appears
doubtful whether he clearly distinguished Refraction and
Reflection.
In order that we may not attach too much value to the vague
expressions of Cleomedes and Sextus Empiricus, we may remark that
Cleomedes conceives such an eclipse as he describes not to be
possible, though he offers an explanation of it if it be: (the fact
must really occur whenever the moon is seen in the horizon in the
middle of an eclipse:) and that Sextus Empiricus gives his suggestion
of the effect of refraction as an argument why the Chaldean astrology
cannot be true, since the constellation which appears to be rising at
the moment of a birth is not the one which is truly rising. The
Chaldeans might have answered, says Delambre, that the star begins to
shed its influence, not when it is really in the horizon, but when its
light is seen. (Ast. Anc. vol. i. p. 231, and vol. ii. p.
548.)
It has been said that Vitellio, or Vitello, whom we shall hereafter have to speak of in the history of Optics,
took his Tables of Refractions from Ptolemy. This is contrary to what
Delambre states. He says that Vitello may be accused of plagiarism
from Alhazen, and that Alhazen did not borrow his Tables from Ptolemy.
Roger Bacon had said (Opus Majus, p. 288), “Ptolemæus in libro
de Opticis, id est, de Aspectibus, seu in Perspectivâ suâ, qui prius
quam Alhazen dedit hanc sententiam, quam a Ptolemæo acceptam Alhazen
exposuit.” This refers only to the opinion that visual rays proceed
from the eye. But this also is erroneous; for Alhazen maintains the
contrary: “Visio fit radiis a visibili extrinsecus ad visum
manantibus.” (Opt. Lib. i. cap. 5.) Vitello says of his Table
of Refractions, “Acceptis instrumentaliter, prout potuimus
propinquius, angulis omnium refractionum . . . invenimus quod semper
iidem sunt anguli refractionum: . . . secundum hoc fecimus has
tabulas.” “Having measured, by means of instruments, as exactly as we
could, the whole range of the angles of refraction, we found that the
refraction is always the same for the same angle; and hence we have
constructed these Tables.”  ~Additional material in the 3rd edition.~ 105</div></body></text></TEI>