<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="16">
[104]
CHAPTER XVI.

Light.

Besides the hearing and sound there is another
mode by which we become sensible of the impressions
of external objects, namely, sight and light.
This subject also offers some observations bearing on
our present purpose.
It has been declared by writers on Natural Theology,
that the human eye exhibits such evidence of
design and skill in its construction, that no one, who
considers it attentively, can resist this impression:
nor does this appear to be saying too much. It must,
at the same time, be obvious that this construction of
the eye could not answer its purposes, except the
constitution of light corresponded to it. Light is an
element of the most peculiar kind and properties, and
such an element can hardly be conceived to have
been placed in the universe without a regard to its
operation and functions. As the eye is made for
light, so light must have been made, at least among
other ends, for the eye.
1. We must expect to comprehend imperfectly
only the mechanism of the elements. Still, we have
endeavoured to show that in some instances the arrangements
by which their purposes are effected are,
to a certain extent, intelligible. In order to explain,
however, in what manner light answers those ends
which appear to us its principal ones, we must know
something of the nature of light. There have,
hitherto, been, among men of science, two prevailing
opinions upon this subject: some considering light as
consisting in the emission of luminous particles;
others accounting for its phenomena by the propagation
of vibrations through a highly subtle and elastic[105]
ether. The former opinion has, till lately, been most
generally entertained in this country, having been
the hypothesis on which Newton made his calculations;
the latter is the one to which most of those
persons have been led, who, in recent times, have
endeavoured to deduce general conclusions from the
newly discovered phenomena of light. Among these
persons, the theory of undulations is conceived to be
established in nearly the same manner, and almost as
certainly, as the doctrine of universal gravitation;
namely, by a series of laws inferred from numerous
facts, which, proceeding from different sets of phenomena,
are found to converge to one common view;
and by calculations founded upon the theory, which,
indicating new and untried facts, are found to agree
exactly with experiment.
We cannot here introduce a sketch of the progress
by which the phenomena have thus led to the acceptance
of the theory of undulations. But this theory
appears to have such claims to our assent, that the
views which we have to offer with regard to the design
exercised in the adaptation, of light to its purposes,
will depend on the undulatory theory, so far
as they depend on theory at all.[15]
2. The impressions of sight, like those of hearing,
differ in intensity and in kind. Brightness and Colour
are the principal differences among visible things, as
loudness and pitch are among sounds. But there is
a singular distinction between these senses in one
respect: every object and part of an object seen, is
necessarily and inevitably referred to some position
in the space before us; and hence visible things have
place, magnitude, form, as well as light, shade, and
colour. There is nothing analogous to this in the
sense of hearing; for though we can, in some approximate[106]
degree, guess the situation of the point
from which a sound proceeds, this is a secondary
process, distinguishable from the perception of the
sound itself; whereas we cannot conceive visible
things without form and place.
The law according to which the sense of vision is
thus affected, appears to be this. By the properties
of light, the external scene produces, through the
transparent parts of the eye, an image or picture
exactly resembling the reality, upon the back part of
the retina: and each point which we see, is seen in
the direction of a line passing from its image on the
retina, through the centre of the pupil of the eye.[16]
In this manner we perceive by the eye the situation
of every point, at the same time that we perceive its
existence; and by combining the situations of many
points, we have forms and outlines of every sort.
That we should receive from the eye this notice
of the position of the object as well as of its other
visible qualities, appears to be absolutely necessary
for our intercourse with the external world; and the
faculty of doing so is so intimate a part of our constitution
that we cannot conceive ourselves divested
of it. Yet in order to imagine ourselves destitute of
this faculty, we have only to suppose that the eye
should receive its impressions as the ear does, and
should apprehend red and green, bright and dark,
without placing them side by side; as the ear takes
in the different sounds which compose a concert,
without attributing them to different parts of space.
The peculiar property thus belonging to vision, of
perceiving position, is so essential to us, that we may
readily believe that some particular provision has
been made for its existence. The remarkable mechanism
of the eye (precisely resembling that of a
camera obscura,) by which it produces an image on
the nervous web forming its hinder part, seems to[107]
have this effect for its main object. And this mechanism
necessarily supposes certain corresponding
properties in light itself, by means of which such an
effect becomes possible.
The main properties of light which are concerned
in this arrangement, are reflexion and refraction: reflexion
by which light is reflected and scattered by
all objects, and thus comes to the eye from all: and
refraction, by which its course is bent, when it passes
obliquely out of one transparent medium into another;
and by which, consequently, convex transparent substances,
such as the cornea and humours of the eye,
possess the power of making the light converge to a
focus or point; an assemblage of such points forming
the images on the retina, which we have mentioned.
Reflexion and refraction are therefore the essential
and indispensable properties of light; and so far as
we can understand, it appears that it was necessary
that light should possess such properties, in order that
it might form a medium of communication between
man and the external world. We may consider its
power of passing through transparent media (as air)
to be given in order that it may enlighten the earth;
its affection of reflexion, for the purpose of making
colours visible; and its refraction to be bestowed,
that it may enable us to discriminate figure and position,
by means of the lenses of the eye.
In this manner light may be considered as constituted
with a peculiar reference to the eyes of animals,
and its leading properties may be looked upon
as contrivances or adaptations to fit it for its visual
office. And in such a point of view the perfection of
the contrivance or adaptation must be allowed to be
very remarkable.
3. But besides the properties of reflexion and refraction,
the most obvious laws of light, an extraordinary
variety of phenomena have lately been discovered,
regulated by other laws of the most curious
kind, uniting great complexity with great symmetry.
We refer to the phenomena of diffraction, polarisation,[108]
and periodical colours, produced by crystals
and by thin plates. We have, in these facts, a vast
mass of properties and laws, offering a subject of
study which has been pursued with eminent skill and
intelligence. But these properties and laws, so far
as has yet been discovered, exert no agency whatever,
and have no purpose, in the general economy
of nature. Beams of light polarised in contrary directions
exhibit the most remarkable differences
when they pass through certain crystals, but manifest
no discoverable difference in their immediate
impression on the eye. We have, therefore, here, a
number of laws of light, which we cannot perceive
to be established with any design which has a reference
to the other parts of the universe.
Undoubtedly it is exceedingly possible that these
differences of light may operate in some quarter,
and in some way, which we cannot detect; and that
these laws may have purposes and may answer ends
of which we have no suspicion. All the analogy of
nature teaches us a lesson of humility, with regard to
the reliance we are to place on our discernment and
judgment as to such matters. But with our present
knowledge, we may observe, that this curious system
of phenomena appears to be a collateral result of the
mechanism by which the effects of light are produced;
and therefore a necessary consequence of the
existence of that element of which the offices are so
numerous and so beneficent.
The new properties of light, and the speculations
founded upon them, have led many persons to the
belief of the undulatory theory; which, as we have
said, is considered by some philosophers as demonstrated.
If we adopt this theory, we consider the
luminiferous ether to have no local motion; and to
produce refraction and reflexion by the operation of
its elasticity alone. We must necessarily suppose
the tenuity of the ether to be extreme; and if we
moreover suppose its tension to be very great, which
the vast velocity of light requires us to suppose, the[109]
vibrations by which light is propagated will be transverse
vibrations, that is the motion to and fro will be
athwart the line along which the undulation travels;
and from this circumstance all the laws of polarisation
necessarily follow. And the properties of transverse
vibrations, combined with the properties of vibrations
in general, give rise to all the curious and
numerous phenomena of colours of which we have
spoken.
If the vibrations be transverse, they may be resolved
into two different planes; this is polarisation:
if they fall on a medium which has different elasticity
in different directions, they will be divided into two
sets of vibrations; this is double refraction; and so on.
Some of the new properties, however, as the fringes
of shadows and the colours of thin plates, follow from
the undulatory theory, whether the vibrations be
transverse or not.
It would appear, therefore, that the propagation of
light by means of a subtle medium, leads necessarily
to the extraordinary collection of properties which
have recently been discovered; and, at any rate, its
propagation by the transverse vibrations of such a
medium does lead inevitably to these results.
Leaving it therefore to future times to point out
the other reasons (or uses if they exist) of these
newly discovered properties of light, in their bearing
on other parts of the world, we may venture to say,
that if light was to be propagated through transparent
media by the undulations of a subtle fluid, these
properties must result, as necessarily as the rainbow
results from the unequal refrangibility of different
colours. This phenomenon and those, appear alike
to be the collateral consequences of the law’s impressed
on light with a view to its principal offices.
Thus the exquisitely beautiful and symmetrical
phenomena and laws of polarisation, and of crystalline
and other effects, may be looked upon as indications
of the delicacy and subtlety of the mechanism
by which man, through his visual organs, is put in[110]
communication with the external world; is made acquainted
with the forms and qualities of objects in the
most remote regions of space; and is enabled, in
some measure, to determine his position and relation
in a universe in which he is but an atom.
4. If we suppose it clearly established that light is
produced by the vibrations of an ether, we find considerations
offer themselves, similar to those which
occurred in the case of sound. The vibrations of
this ether affect our organs with the sense of light
and colour. Why, or how do they do this? It is
only within certain limits that the effect is produced,
and these limits are comparatively narrower here
than in the case of sound. The whole scale of colour,
from violet to crimson, lies between vibrations
which are four hundred and fifty-eight million millions,
and seven hundred and twenty-seven million
millions in a second; a proportion much smaller
than the corresponding ratio for perceptible sounds.
Why should such vibrations produce perception in
the eye, and no others? There must be here some
peculiar adaptation of the sensitive powers to these
wonderfully minute and condensed mechanical motions.
What happens when the vibrations are slower
than the red, or quicker than the blue? They do not
produce vision: do they produce any effect? Have
they any thing to do with heat or with electricity?
We cannot tell. The ether must be as susceptible of
these vibrations, as of those which produce vision.
But the mechanism of the eye is adjusted to this latter
kind only; and this precise kind, (whether alone
or mixed with others,) proceeds from the sun and
from other luminaries, and thus communicates to us
the state of the visible universe. The mere material
elements then are full of properties which we can
understand no otherwise, than as the results of a refined
contrivance.
</div></body></text></TEI>