<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="131">INTRODUCTION.

Of the Palætiological Sciences.
WE now approach the last Class
of Sciences which enter into the design of the present work; and of
these, Geology is the representative, whose history we shall therefore
briefly follow. By the Class of Sciences to which I have referred it,
I mean to point out those researches in which the object is, to ascend
from the present state of things to a more ancient condition, from
which the present is derived by intelligible causes.
The sciences which treat of causes have sometimes been termed
ætiological, from αἰτία, a cause: but this term would
not sufficiently describe the speculations of which we now speak;
since it might include sciences which treat of Permanent Causality,
like Mechanics, as well as inquiries concerning Progressive Causation.
The investigations which I now wish to group together, deal, not only
with the possible, but with the actual past; and a portion of that
science on which we are about to enter, Geology, has properly been
termed Palæontology, since it treats of beings which formerly
existed.1 Hence, combining these two notions,2
Palætiology appears to be a term not inappropriate, to describe
those speculations which thus refer to actual past events, and attempt
to explain them by laws of causation.
1 Πάλαι, ὄντα
2 Πάλαι, αἰτία
Such speculations are not confined to the world of inert matter; we
have examples of them in inquiries concerning the monuments of the art
and labor of distant ages; in examinations into the origin and early
progress of states and cities, customs and languages; as well as in
researches concerning the causes and formations of mountains and
rocks, the imbedding of fossils in strata, and their elevation from
the bottom of the ocean. All these speculations are connected by this
bond,—that they endeavor to ascend to a past state of things, by
the aid of the evidence of the present. In asserting, with Cuvier,
that 500 “The
geologist is an antiquary of a new order,” we do not mark a fanciful
and superficial resemblance of employment merely, but a real and
philosophical connexion of the principles of investigation. The
organic fossils which occur in the rock, and the medals which we find
in the ruins of ancient cities, are to be studied in a similar spirit
and for a similar purpose. Indeed, it is not always easy to know where
the task of the geologist ends, and that of the antiquary begins. The
study of ancient geography may involve us in the examination of the
causes by which the forms of coasts and plains are changed; the
ancient mound or scarped rock may force upon us the problem, whether
its form is the work of nature or of man; the ruined temple may
exhibit the traces of time in its changed level, and sea-worn columns;
and thus the antiquarian of the earth may be brought into the very
middle of the domain belonging to the antiquarian of art.
Such a union of these different kinds of archæological
investigations has, in fact, repeatedly occurred. The changes which
have taken place in the temple of Jupiter Serapis, near Puzzuoli, are
of the sort which have just been described; and this is only one
example of a large class of objects;—the monuments of art
converted into records of natural events. And on a wider scale, we
find Cuvier, in his inquiries into geological changes, bringing
together historical and physical evidence. Dr. Prichard, in his
Researches into the Physical History of Man, has shown that to
execute such a design as his, we must combine the knowledge of the
physiological laws of nature with the traditions of history and the
philosophical comparison of languages. And even if we refuse to admit,
as part of the business of geology, inquiries concerning the origin
and physical history of the present population of the globe; still the
geologist is compelled to take an interest in such inquiries, in order
to understand matters which rigorously belong to his proper domain;
for the ascertained history of the present state of things offers the
best means of throwing light upon the causes of past changes.
Mr. Lyell quotes Dr. Prichard’s book more frequently than any
geological work of the same extent.
Again, we may notice another common circumstance in the studies
which we are grouping together as palætiological, diverse as they are
in their subjects. In all of them we have the same kind of
manifestations of a number of successive changes, each springing out
of a preceding state; and in all, the phenomena at each step become
more and more complicated, by involving the results of all that has
preceded, modified by supervening agencies. The general aspect of all
these 501 trains of
change is similar, and offers the same features for description. The
relics and ruins of the earlier states are preserved, mutilated and
dead, in the products of later times. The analogical figures by which
we are tempted to express this relation are philosophically true. It
is more than a mere fanciful description, to say that in languages,
customs, forms of Society, political institutions, we see a number of
formations super-imposed upon one another, each of which is, for the
most part, an assemblage of fragments and results of the preceding
condition. Though our comparison might be bold, it would be just, if
we were to assert, that the English language is a conglomerate of
Latin words, bound together in a Saxon cement; the fragments of the
Latin being partly portions introduced directly from the parent
quarry, with all their sharp edges, and partly pebbles of the same
material, obscured and shaped by long rolling in a Norman or some
other channel. Thus the study of palætiology in the materials of the
earth, is only a type of similar studies with respect to all the
elements, which, in the history of the earth’s inhabitants, have been
constantly undergoing a series of connected changes.
But, wide as is the view which such considerations give us of the
class of sciences to which geology belongs, they extend still further.
“The science of the changes which have taken place in the organic
kingdoms of nature,” (such is the description which has been given of
Geology,3) may, by following another set of
connexions, be extended beyond “the modifications of the surface of
our own planet.” For we cannot doubt that some resemblance of a closer
or looser kind, has obtained between the changes and causes of change,
on other bodies of the universe, and on our own. The appearances of
something of the kind of volcanic action on the surface of the moon,
are not to be mistaken. And the inquiries concerning the origin of our
planet and of our solar system, inquiries to which Geology
irresistibly impels her students, direct us to ask what information
the rest of the universe can supply, bearing upon this subject. It has
been thought by some, that we can trace systems, more or less like our
solar system, in the process of formation; the nebulous matter, which
is at first expansive and attenuated, condensing gradually into suns
and planets. Whether this Nebular Hypothesis be tenable or not,
I shall not here inquire; but the discussion of such a question would
be closely connected with 502 geology, both in its interests and in
its methods. If men are ever able to frame a science of the past
changes by which the universe has been brought into its present
condition, this science will be properly described as Cosmical
Palætiology.
3 Lyell, Principles of Geology,
p. 1.
These palætiological sciences might properly be called
historical, if that term were sufficiently precise: for they
are all of the nature of history, being concerned with the succession
of events: and the part of history which deals with the past causes of
events, is, in fact, a moral palætiology. But the phrase Natural
History has so accustomed us to a use of the word history
in which we have nothing to do with time, that, if we were to employ
the word historical to describe the palætiological sciences, it
would be in constant danger of being misunderstood. The fact is, as
Mohs has said, that Natural History, when systematically treated,
rigorously excludes all that is historical; for it classes
objects by their permanent and universal properties, and has nothing
to do with the narration of particular and casual facts. And this is
an inconsistency which we shall not attempt to rectify.
All palætiological sciences, since they undertake to refer changes
to their causes, assume a certain classification of the phenomena
which change brings forth, and a knowledge of the operation of the
causes of change. These phenomena, these causes, are very different,
in the branches of knowledge which I have thus classed together. The
natural features of the earth’s surface, the works of art, the
institutions of society, the forms of language, taken together, are
undoubtedly a very wide collection of subjects of speculation; and the
kinds of causation which apply to them are no less varied. Of the
causes of change in the inorganic and organic world,—the
peculiar principles of Geology—we shall hereafter have to speak.
As these must be studied by the geologist, so, in like manner, the
tendencies, instincts, faculties, principles, which direct man to
architecture and sculpture, to civil government, to rational and
grammatical speech, and which have determined the circumstances of his
progress in these paths, must be in a great degree known to the
Palætiologist of Art, of Society, and of Language, respectively, in
order that he may speculate soundly upon his peculiar subject. With
these matters we shall not here meddle, confining ourselves, in our
exemplification of the conditions and progress of such sciences, to
the case of Geology.
The journey of survey which we have attempted to perform over the
field of human knowledge, although carefully directed according to the
paths and divisions of the physical sciences, has already 503 conducted us to the
boundaries of physical science, and gives us a glimpse of the region
beyond. In following the history of Life, we found ourselves led to
notice the perceptive and active faculties of man; it appeared that
there was a ready passage from physiology to psychology, from physics
to metaphysics. In the class of sciences now under notice, we are, at
a different point, carried from the world of matter to the world of
thought and feeling,—from things to men. For, as we have already
said, the science of the causes of change includes the productions of
Man as well as of Nature. The history of the earth, and the history of
the earth’s inhabitants, as collected from phenomena, are governed by
the same principles. Thus the portions of knowledge which seek to
travel back towards the origin, whether of inert things or of the
works of man, resemble each other. Both of them treat of events as
connected by the thread of time and causation. In both we endeavor to
learn accurately what the present is, and hence what the past has
been. Both are historical sciences in the same sense.
It must be recollected that I am now speaking of history as
ætiological;—as it investigates causes, and as it does this in a
scientific, that is, in a rigorous and systematic, manner. And I may
observe here, though I cannot now dwell on the subject, that all
ætiological sciences will consist of three portions; the Description
of the facts and phenomena;—the general Theory of the causes of
change appropriate to the case;—and the Application of the
theory to the facts. Thus, taking Geology for our example, we must
have, first Descriptive or Phenomenal Geology; next, the
exposition of the general principles by which such phenomena can be
produced, which we may term Geological Dynamics; and, lastly,
doctrines hence derived, as to what have been the causes of the
existing state of things, which we may call Physical
Geology.
These three branches of geology may be found frequently or
constantly combined in the works of writers on the subject, and it may
not always be easy to discriminate exactly what belongs to each
subject.4 But the analogy of this science with
others, its present 504 condition and future fortunes, will
derive great illustration from such a distribution of its history; and
in this point of view, therefore, we shall briefly treat of it;
dividing the history of Geological Dynamics, for the sake of
convenience, into two Chapters, one referring to inorganic, and one to
organic, phenomena.
4 The Wernerians, in distinguishing
their study from Geology, and designating it as
Geognosy, the knowledge of the earth, appear to have
intended to select Descriptive Geology for their peculiar field. In
like manner, the original aim of the Geological Society of London,
which was formed (1807) “with a view to record and multiply
observations,” recognized the possibility of a Descriptive Geology
separate from the other portions of the science.


DESCRIPTIVE GEOLOGY.
</div></body></text></TEI>