<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="55">CHAPTER I.
Prelude to the Solution of Problems in
Acoustics.
IN some measure the true
theory of sound was guessed by very early speculators on the subject;
though undoubtedly conceived in a very vague and wavering manner. That
sound is caused by some motion of the sounding body, and conveyed by
some motion of the air to the ear, is an opinion which we trace to the
earliest times of physical philosophy. We may take Aristotle as the
best expounder of this stage of opinion. In his Treatise On Sound
and Hearing, he says, “Sound takes place when bodies strike the
air, not by the air having a form impressed upon it
(σχηματίζομενον), as some think, but by its being moved in a
corresponding manner; (probably he means in a manner corresponding to
the impulse;) the air being contracted, and expanded, and overtaken,
and again struck by the impulses of the breath and of the strings. For
when the breath falls upon and strikes the air which is next it, the
air is carried forwards with an impetus, and that which is contiguous
to the first is carried onwards; so that the same voice spreads every
way as far as the motion of the air takes place.”
As is the case with all such specimens of ancient physics,
different persons would find in such a statement very different
measures of truth and distinctness. The admirers of antiquity might
easily, by pressing the language closely, and using the light of
modern discovery, detect in this passage an exact account of the
production and propagation of sound: while others might maintain that
in Aristotle’s own mind, there were only vague notions, and verbal
generalizations. This 25 latter opinion is very emphatically
expressed by Bacon.1 “The collision or thrusting of air,
which they will have to be the cause of sound, neither denotes the
form nor the latent process of sound; but is a term of
ignorance and of superficial contemplation.” Nor can it be justly
denied, that an exact and distinct apprehension of the kind of motion
of the air by which sound is diffused, was beyond the reach of the
ancient philosophers, and made its way into the world long afterwards.
It was by no means easy to reconcile the nature of such motion with
obvious phenomena. For the process is not evident as motion; since, as
Bacon also observes,2 it does not visibly agitate the flame of
a candle, or a feather, or any light floating substance, by which the
slightest motions of the air are betrayed. Still, the persuasion that
sound is some motion of the air, continued to keep hold of men’s
minds, and acquired additional distinctness. The illustration employed
by Vitruvius, in the following passage, is even now one of the best we
can offer.3 “Voice is breath, flowing, and made
sensible to the hearing by striking the air. It moves in infinite
circumferences of circles, as when, by throwing a stone into still
water, you produce innumerable circles of waves, increasing from the
centre and spreading outwards, till the boundary of the space, or some
obstacle, prevents their outlines from going further. In the same
manner the voice makes its motion in circles. But in water the circle
moves breadthways upon a level plain; the voice proceeds in breadth,
and also successively ascends in height.”
1 Hist. Son. et Aud. vol. ix. p.
68.
2 Ibid.
3 De Arch. v. 3.
Both the comparison, and the notice of the difference of the two
cases, prove the architect to have had very clear notions on the
subject; which he further shows by comparing the resonance of the
walls of a building to the disturbance of the outline of the waves of
water when they meet with a boundary, and are thrown back. “Therefore,
as in the outlines of waves in water, so in the voice, if no obstacle
interrupt the foremost, it does not disturb the second and the
following ones, so that all come to the ears of persons, whether high
up or low down, without resonance. But when they strike against
obstacles, the foremost, being thrown back, disturb the lines of those
which follow.” Similar analogies were employed by the ancients in
order to explain the occurrence of Echoes. Aristotle says,4
“An Echo takes place, when the air, being as one body in consequence
of the vessel which bounds it, and being prevented from being thrust
forwards, is reflected 26 back like a ball.” Nothing material was
added to such views till modern times.
4 De Animâ, ii. 8.
Thus the first conjectures of those who philosophized concerning
sound, led them to an opinion concerning its causes and laws, which
only required to be distinctly understood, and traced to mechanical
principles, in order to form a genuine science of Acoustics. It was,
no doubt, a work which required a long time and sagacious reasoners,
to supply what was thus wanting; but still, in consequence of this
peculiar circumstance in the early condition of the prevalent doctrine
concerning sound, the history of Acoustics assumes a peculiar form.
Instead of containing, like the history of Astronomy or of Optics, a
series of generalizations, each including and rising above preceding
generalizations; in this case, the highest generalization is in view
from the first; and the object of the philosopher is to determine its
precise meaning and circumstances in each example. Instead of having a
series of inductive Truths, successively dawning on men’s minds, we
have a series of Explanations, in which certain experimental facts and
laws are reconciled, as to their mechanical principles and their
measures, with the general doctrine already in our possession. Instead
of having to travel gradually towards a great discovery, like
Universal Gravitation, or Luminiferous Undulations, we take our stand
upon acknowledged truths, the production and propagation of sound by
the motion of bodies and of air; and we connect these with other
truths, the laws of motion and the known properties of bodies, as, for
instance, their elasticity. Instead of Epochs of Discovery, we
have Solutions of Problems; and to these we must now
proceed.
We must, however, in the first place, notice that these Problems
include other subjects than the mere production and propagation of
sound generally. For such questions as these obviously
occur:—what are the laws and cause of the differences of
sounds;—of acute and grave, loud and low, continued and
instantaneous;—and, again, of the differences of articulate
sounds, and of the quality of different voices and different
instruments? The first of these questions, in particular, the real
nature of the difference of acute and grave sounds, could not help
attracting attention; since the difference of notes in this respect
was the foundation of one of the most remarkable mathematical sciences
of antiquity. Accordingly, we find attempts to explain this difference
in the ancient writers on music. In Ptolemy’s Harmonics, the
third Chapter of the first Book is entitled, “How the 27 acuteness and graveness
of notes is produced;” and in this, after noting generally the
difference of sounds, and the causes of difference (which he states to
be the force of the striking body, the physical constitution of the
body struck, and other causes), he comes to the conclusion, that “the
things which produce acuteness in sounds, are a greater density and a
smaller size; the things which produce graveness, are a greater rarity
and a bulkier form.” He afterwards explains this so as to include a
considerable portion of truth. Thus he says, “That in strings, and in
pipes, other things remaining the same, those which are stopped at the
smaller distance from the bridge give the most acute note; and in
pipes, those notes which come through holes nearest to the mouth-hole
are most acute.” He even attempts a further generalization, and says
that the greater acuteness arises, in fact, from the body being more
tense; and that thus “hardness may counteract the effect of greater
density, as we see that brass produces a more acute sound than lead.”
But this author’s notions of tension, since they were applied so
generally as to include both the tension of a string, and the tension
of a piece of solid brass, must necessarily have been very vague. And
he seems to have been destitute of any knowledge of the precise nature
of the motion or impulse by which sound is produced; and, of course,
still more ignorant of the mechanical principles by which these
motions are explained. The notion of vibrations of the parts
of sounding bodies, does not appear to have been dwelt upon as an
essential circumstance; though in some cases, as in sounding strings,
the fact is very obvious. And the notion of vibrations of the air does
not at all appear in ancient writers, except so far as it may be
conceived to be implied in the comparison of aërial and watery waves,
which we have quoted from Vitruvius. It is however, very unlikely
that, even in the case of water, the motions of the particles were
distinctly conceived, for such conception is far from obvious.
The attempts to apprehend distinctly, and to explain mechanically,
the phenomena of sound, gave rise to a series of Problems, of which we
most now give a brief history. The questions which more peculiarly
constitute the Science of Acoustics, are the questions concerning
those motions or affections of the air by which it is the medium of
hearing. But the motions of sounding bodies have both so much
connexion with those of the medium, and so much resemblance to them,
that we shall include in our survey researches on that subject also.
28</div></body></text></TEI>