<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="54">

CHAPTER II.
Application of the Idea of Symmetry to Crystals.



1. MINERALS and other bodies of definite chemical composition often exhibit that marked
regularity of form and structure which we designate
by terming them Crystals; and in such crystals, when
we duly study them, we perceive the various kinds of
symmetry of which we have spoken in the previous
chapter. And the different kinds of symmetry which
we have there described are now usually distinguished
from each other, by writers on crystallography. Indeed
it is mainly to such writers that we are indebted for
a sound and consistent classification of the kinds and
degrees of symmetry of which forms are capable. But
this classification was by no means invented as soon as
mineralogists applied themselves to the study of crystals. These first attempts to arrange crystalline forms
were very imperfect; those, for example, of Linnæus,
Werner, Romé de Lisle, and Haüy. The essays of
these writers implied a classification at once defective
and superfluous. They reduced all crystals to one or
other of certain fundamental forms; and this procedure might have been a perfectly good method of
dividing crystalline forms into classes, if the fundamental forms had been selected so as to exemplify the
different kinds of symmetry. But this was not the
case. Haüy’s fundamental or ‘primitive’ forms, were,
for instance, the following: the parallelepiped, the
octahedron, the tetrahedron, the regular hexagonal
prism, the rhombic dodecahedron, and the double hexagonal pyramid. Of these, the octahedron, the tetrahedron, the rhombic dodecahedron, all belong to the 76 same kind of symmetry (the tessular systems); also
the hexagonal prism and the hexagonal pyramid both
belong to the rhombic system; while the parallelepiped
is so employed as to include all kinds of symmetry.
It is, however, to be recollected that Haüy, in his
selection of primitive forms, not only had an eye to
the external form of the crystal and to its degree and
kind of regularity, but also made his classification
with an especial reference to the cleavage of the mineral, which he considered as a primary element in
crystalline analysis. There can be no doubt that the
cleavage of a crystal is one of its most important characters: it is a relation of form belonging to the
interior, which is to be attended to no less than the
form of the exterior. But still, the cleavage is to be
regarded only as determining the degree of geometrical
symmetry of the body, and not as defining a special
geometrical figure to which the body must be referred.
To have looked upon it in the latter light, was a mistake of the earlier crystallographic speculators, on
which we shall shortly have to remark.
2. I have said that the reference of crystals to Primitive Forms might have been well employed as a
mode of expressing a just classification of them. This
follows as a consequence from the application of the
Principle stated in the last chapter, that all symmetrical members are alike affected. Thus we may take an
upright triangular prism as the representative of the
rhombic system, and if we then suppose one of the
upper edges to be cut off, or truncated, we must, by
the Principle of Symmetry, suppose the other two
upper edges to be truncated in precisely the same
manner. By this truncation we may obtain the upper
part of a rhombohedron; and by truncations of the
same kind, symmetrically affecting all the analogous
parts of the figure, we may obtain any other form
possessing three-membered symmetry. And the same
is true of any of the other kinds of symmetry, provided we make a proper selection of a fundamental
form. And this was really the method employed
by Demeste, Werner, and Romé de Lisle. They 77 assumed a Primitive Form, and then conceived other
forms, such as they found in nature, to be derived
from the Primitive Form by truncation of the edges,
acumination of the corners, and the like processes.
This mode of conception was a perfectly just and legitimate expression of the general Idea of Symmetry.
3. The true view of the degrees of symmetry was,
as I have already said, impeded by the attempts which
Haüy and others made to arrive at primitive forms by
the light which cleavage was supposed to throw upon
the structure of minerals. At last, however, in Germany, as I have narrated in the History of Mineralogy4,
Weiss and Mohs introduced a classification of forms
implying a more philosophical principle, dividing the
forms into Systems; which, employing the terms of
the latter writer, we shall call the tessular, the pyramidal or square pyramidal, the prismatic or oblong,
and the rhombohedral systems.</div></body></text></TEI>