<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="13">
CHAPTER XIII.

The Properties of Light with regard to Vegetation.

The illuminating power of light will come under
our consideration hereafter. Its agency, with regard
to organic life, is too important not to be noticed,[95]
though this must be done briefly. Light appears to
be as necessary to the health of plants as air of moisture.
A plant may, indeed, grow without it, but it
does not appear that a species could be so continued.
Under such a privation, the parts which are usually
green, assume a white colour, as is the case with
vegetables grown in a cellar, or protected by a covering
for the sake of producing this very effect; thus,
celery, is in this manner blanched, or etiolated.
The part of the process of vegetable life for which
light is especially essential, appears to be the functions
of the leaves; these are affected by this agent
in a very remarkable manner. The moisture which
plants imbibe is, by their vital energies, carried to
their leaves; and is then brought in contact with the
atmosphere, which, besides other ingredients, contains,
in general, a portion of carbonic acid. So long
as light is present, the leaf decomposes the carbonic
acid, appropriates the carbon to the formation of its
own proper juices, and returns the disengaged oxygen
into the atmosphere; thus restoring the atmospheric
air to a condition in which it is more fitted
than it was before for the support of animal life. The
plant thus prepares the support of life for other creatures
at the same time that it absorbs its own. The
greenness of those members which affect that colour,
and the disengagement of oxygen, are the indications
that its vital powers are in healthful action: as
soon as we remove light from the plant, these indications
cease: it has no longer power to imbibe carbon
and disengage oxygen, but on the contrary, it gives
back some of the carbon already obtained, and robs
the atmosphere of oxygen for the purpose of reconverting
this into carbonic acid.
It cannot well be conceived that such effects of
light on vegetables, as we have described, should
occur, if that agent, of whatever nature it is, and
those organs, had not been adapted to each other.
But the subject is here introduced that the reader
may the more readily receive the conviction of combining[96]
purpose which must arise, on finding that an
agent possessing these very peculiar chemical properties,
is employed to produce also those effects of
illumination, vision, &c., which form the most obvious
portion of the properties of light.
</div></body></text></TEI>