<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Novum Organon Renovatum</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="9">
CHAPTER IV.
Of the Colligation of Facts.
Aphorism VII.
Science begins with common observation of facts; but
even at this stage, requires that the observations be precise.
Hence the sciences which depend upon space and number
were the earliest formed. After common observation, come
Scientific Observation and Experiment.
Aphorism VIII.
The Conceptions by which Facts are bound together, are
suggested by the sagacity of discoverers. This sagacity cannot
be taught. It commonly succeeds by guessing; and this
success seems to consist in framing several tentative
hypotheses and selecting the right one. But a supply of
appropriate hypotheses cannot be constructed by rule, nor without
inventive talent.
Aphorism IX.
The truth of tentative hypotheses must be tested by their
application to facts. The discoverer must be ready, carefully
to try his hypotheses in this manner, and to reject
them if they will not bear the test, in spite of indolence and
vanity.
1. FACTS
such as the last Chapter speaks of are, by
means of such Conceptions as are described in
the preceding Chapter, bound together so as to give
rise to those general Propositions of which Science
consists. Thus the Facts that the planets revolve 60
about the sun in certain periodic times and at certain
distances, are included and connected in Kepler’s Law,
by means of such Conceptions as the squares of numbers,
the cubes of distances, and the proportionality of
these quantities. Again the existence of this proportion
in the motions of any two planets, forms a set of
Facts which may all be combined by means of the
Conception of a certain central accelerating force, as
was proved by Newton. The whole of our physical
knowledge consists in the establishment of such
propositions; and in all such cases, Facts are bound
together by the aid of suitable Conceptions. This part
of the formation of our knowledge I have called the
Colligation of Facts: and we may apply this term to
every case in which, by an act of the intellect, we
establish a precise connexion among the phenomena
which are presented to our senses. The knowledge of
such connexions, accumulated and systematized, is
Science. On the steps by which science is thus collected
from phenomena we shall proceed now to make
a few remarks.
2. Science begins with Common Observation of
facts, in which we are not conscious of any peculiar
discipline or habit of thought exercised in observing.
Thus the common perceptions of the appearances and
recurrences of the celestial luminaries, were the first
steps of Astronomy: the obvious cases in which bodies
fall or are supported, were the beginning of Mechanics;
the familiar aspects of visible things, were the origin
of Optics; the usual distinctions of well-known plants,
first gave rise to Botany. Facts belonging to such
parts of our knowledge are noticed by us, and accumulated
in our memories, in the common course of our
habits, almost without our being aware that we are
observing and collecting facts. Yet such facts may
lead to many scientific truths; for instance, in the first
stages of Astronomy (as we have shown in the History)
such facts led to Methods of Intercalation and Rules
of the Recurrence of Eclipses. In succeeding stages
of science, more especial attention and preparation on
the part of the observer, and a selection of certain 61
kinds of facts, becomes necessary; but there is an early
period in the progress of knowledge at which man is
a physical philosopher, without seeking to be so, or
being aware that he is so.
3. But in all stages of the progress, even in that
early one of which we have just spoken, it is necessary,
in order that the facts may be fit materials of
any knowledge, that they should be decomposed into
Elementary Facts, and that these should be observed
with precision. Thus, in the first infancy of astronomy,
the recurrence of phases of the moon, of places
of the sun’s rising and setting, of planets, of eclipses,
was observed to take place at intervals of certain definite
numbers of days, and in a certain exact order;
and thus it was, that the observations became portions
of astronomical science. In other cases, although the
facts were equally numerous, and their general aspect
equally familiar, they led to no science, because their
exact circumstances were not apprehended. A vague
and loose mode of looking at facts very easily observable,
left men for a long time under the belief that a
body, ten times as heavy as another, falls ten times as
fast;—that objects immersed in water are always magnified,
without regard to the form of the surface;—that
the magnet exerts an irresistible force;—that
crystal is always found associated with ice;—and the
like. These and many others are examples how blind
and careless men can be, even in observation of the
plainest and commonest appearances; and they show
us that the mere faculties of perception, although
constantly exercised upon innumerable objects, may long
fail in leading to any exact knowledge.
4. If we further inquire what was the favourable
condition through which some special classes of facts
were, from the first, fitted to become portions of science,
we shall find it to have been principally this;—that
these facts were considered with reference to the
Ideas of Time, Number, and Space, which are Ideas
possessing peculiar definiteness and precision; so that
with regard to them, confusion and indistinctness are
hardly possible. The interval from new moon to new 62
moon was always a particular number of days: the
sun in his yearly course rose and set near to a known
succession of distant objects: the moon’s path passed
among the stars in a certain order:—these are observations
in which mistake and obscurity are not likely
to occur, if the smallest degree of attention is bestowed
upon the task. To count a number is, from the first
opening of man’s mental faculties, an operation which
no science can render more precise. The relations of
space are nearest to those of number in obvious and
universal evidence. Sciences depending upon these
Ideas arise with the first dawn of intellectual civilization.
But few of the other Ideas which man employs
in the acquisition of knowledge possess this clearness
in their common use. The Idea of Resemblance may
be noticed, as coming next to those of Space and Number
in original precision; and the Idea of Cause, in a
certain vague and general mode of application, sufficient
for the purposes of common life, but not for the
ends of science, exercises a very extensive influence
over men’s thoughts. But the other Ideas on which
science depends, with the Conceptions which arise out
of them, are not unfolded till a much later period of
intellectual progress; and therefore, except in such
limited cases as I have noticed, the observations of
common spectators and uncultivated nations, however
numerous or varied, are of little or no effect in giving
rise to Science.
5. Let us now suppose that, besides common everyday
perception of facts, we turn our attention to some
other occurrences and appearances, with a design of
obtaining from them speculative knowledge. This
process is more peculiarly called Observation, or, when
we ourselves occasion the facts, Experiment. But the
same remark which we have already made, still holds
good here. These facts can be of no value, except
they are resolved into those exact Conceptions which
contain the essential circumstances of the case. They
must be determined, not indeed necessarily, as has
sometimes been said, ‘according to Number, Weight,
and Measure;’ for, as we have endeavoured to show 63
in the preceding Books4,
there are many other
Conceptions to which phenomena may be subordinated,
quite different from these, and yet not at all less
definite and precise. But in order that the facts obtained
by observation and experiment may be capable of
being used in furtherance of our exact and solid knowledge,
they must be apprehended and analysed according to some
Conceptions which, applied for this purpose, give distinct
and definite results, such as can be
steadily taken hold of and reasoned from; that is, the
facts must be referred to Clear and Appropriate Ideas,
according to the manner in which we have already explained
this condition of the derivation of our knowledge. The
phenomena of light, when they are such
as to indicate sides in the ray, must be referred to the
Conception of polarization; the phenomena of mixture,
when there is an alteration of qualities as well
as quantities, must be combined by a Conception of
elementary composition. And thus, when mere position,
and number, and resemblance, will no longer answer the
purpose of enabling us to connect the facts,
we call in other Ideas, in such cases more efficacious,
though less obvious.
4
Hist. of Sci. Id. Bs. v. vi. vii. viii. ix. x.
6. But how are we, in these cases, to discover such
Ideas, and to judge which will be efficacious, in leading
to a scientific combination of our experimental data?
To this question, we must in the first place answer,
that the first and great instrument by which facts, so
observed with a view to the formation of exact knowledge,
are combined into important and permanent
truths, is that peculiar Sagacity which belongs to the
genius of a Discoverer; and which, while it supplies
those distinct and appropriate Conceptions which lead
to its success, cannot be limited by rules, or expressed
in definitions. It would be difficult or impossible to
describe in words the habits of thought which led Archimedes
to refer the conditions of equilibrium on the
Lever to the Conception of pressure, while Aristotle
could not see in them anything more than the results 64
of the strangeness of the properties of the circle;—or
which impelled Pascal to explain by means of the
Conception of the weight of air, the facts which his
predecessors had connected by the notion of nature’s
horrour of a vacuum;—or which caused Vitello and
Roger Bacon to refer the magnifying power of a convex lens
to the bending of the rays of light towards
the perpendicular by refraction, while others conceived
the effect to result from the matter of medium, with
no consideration of its form. These are what are commonly
spoken of as felicitous and inexplicable strokes
of inventive talent; and such, no doubt, they are. No
rules can ensure to us similar success in new cases; or
can enable men who do not possess similar endowments,
to make like advances in knowledge.
7. Yet still, we may do something in tracing the
process by which such discoveries are made; and this
it is here our business to do. We may observe that
these, and the like discoveries, are not improperly
described as happy Guesses; and that Guesses, in these
as in other instances, imply various suppositions made,
of which some one turns out to be the right one. We
may, in such cases, conceive the discoverer as inventing
and trying many conjectures, till he finds one
which answers the purpose of combining the scattered
facts into a single rule. The discovery of general
truths from special facts is performed, commonly at
least, and more commonly than at first appears, by
the use of a series of Suppositions, or Hypotheses,
which are looked at in quick succession, and of which
the one which really leads to truth is rapidly detected,
and when caught sight of, firmly held, verified, and
followed to its consequences. In the minds of most
discoverers, this process of invention, trial, and
acceptance or rejection of the hypothesis, goes on so rapidly
that we cannot trace it in its successive steps. But in
some instances, we can do so; and we can also see that
the other examples of discovery do not differ essentially
from these. The same intellectual operations
take place in other cases, although this often happens
so instantaneously that we lose the trace of the 65
progression. In the discoveries made by Kepler, we have
a curious and memorable exhibition of this process in
its details. Thanks to his communicative disposition,
we know that he made nineteen hypotheses with regard
to the motion of Mars, and calculated the results
of each, before he established the true doctrine, that
the planet’s path is an ellipse. We know, in like manner,
that Galileo made wrong suppositions respecting
the laws of falling bodies, and Mariotte, concerning
the motion of water in a siphon, before they hit upon
the correct view of these cases.
8. But it has very often happened in the history of
science, that the erroneous hypotheses which preceded
the discovery of the truth have been made, not by the
discoverer himself, but by his precursors; to whom he
thus owed the service, often an important one in such
cases, of exhausting the most tempting forms of errour.
Thus the various fruitless suppositions by which Kepler
endeavoured to discover the law of reflection, led
the way to its real detection by Snell; Kepler’s numerous
imaginations concerning the forces by which the
celestial motions are produced,—his ‘physical reasonings’
as he termed them,—were a natural prelude to
the truer physical reasonings of Newton. The various
hypotheses by which the suspension of vapour in air
had been explained, and their failure, left the field
open for Dalton with his doctrine of the mechanical
mixture of gases. In most cases, if we could truly
analyze the operation of the thoughts of those who
make, or who endeavour to make discoveries in science,
we should find that many more suppositions pass
through their minds than those which are expressed
in words; many a possible combination of conceptions
is formed and soon rejected. There is a constant
invention and activity, a perpetual creating and selecting
power at work, of which the last results only are
exhibited to us. Trains of hypotheses are called up and
pass rapidly in review; and the judgment makes its
choice from the varied group.
9. It would, however, be a great mistake to suppose
that the hypotheses, among which our choice thus 66
lies, are constructed by an enumeration of obvious
cases, or by a wanton alteration of relations which
occur in some first hypothesis. It may, indeed, sometimes
happen that the proposition which is finally
established is such as may be formed, by some slight
alteration, from those which are justly rejected. Thus
Kepler’s elliptical theory of Mars’s motions, involved
relations of lines and angles much of the same nature
as his previous false suppositions: and the true law of
refraction so much resembles those erroneous ones
which Kepler tried, that we cannot help wondering
how he chanced to miss it. But it more frequently
happens that new truths are brought into view by the
application of new Ideas, not by new modifications of
old ones. The cause of the properties of the Lever
was learnt, not by introducing any new geometrical
combination of lines and circles, but by referring the
properties to genuine mechanical Conceptions. When
the Motions of the Planets were to be explained, this
was done, not by merely improving the previous notions,
of cycles of time, but by introducing the new
conception of epicycles in space. The doctrine of the
Four Simple Elements was expelled, not by forming
any new scheme of elements which should impart,
according to new rules, their sensible qualities to their
compounds, but by considering the elements of bodies
as neutralizing each other. The Fringes of Shadows
could not be explained by ascribing new properties to
the single rays of light, but were reduced to law by
referring them to the interference of several rays.
Since the true supposition is thus very frequently
something altogether diverse from all the obvious
conjectures and combinations, we see here how far we are
from being able to reduce discovery to rule, or to give
any precepts by which the want of real invention and
sagacity shall be supplied. We may warn and encourage
these faculties when they exist, but we cannot
create them, or make great discoveries when they are
absent.
10. The Conceptions which a true theory requires
are very often clothed in a Hypothesis which connects 67
with them several superfluous and irrelevant circumstances.
Thus the Conception of the Polarization of
Light was originally represented under the image of
particles of light having their poles all turned in the
same direction. The Laws of Heat may be made out
perhaps most conveniently by conceiving Heat to be
a Fluid. The Attraction of Gravitation might have
been successfully applied to the explanation of facts, if
Newton had throughout treated Attraction as the result of
an Ether diffused through space; a supposition
which he has noticed as a possibility. The doctrine of
Definite and Multiple Proportions may be conveniently
expressed by the hypothesis of Atoms. In such cases,
the Hypothesis may serve at first to facilitate the
introduction of a new Conception. Thus a pervading
Ether might for a time remove a difficulty, which some
persons find considerable, of imagining a body to exert
force at a distance. A Particle with Poles is more
easily conceived than Polarization in the abstract.
And if hypotheses thus employed will really explain
the facts by means of a few simple assumptions, the
laws so obtained may afterwards be reduced to a simpler
form than that in which they were first suggested.
The general laws of Heat, of Attraction, of Polarization,
of Multiple Proportions, are now certain, whatever image
we may form to ourselves of their ultimate causes.
11. In order, then, to discover scientific truths,
suppositions consisting either of new Conceptions, or of
new Combinations of old ones, are to be made, till we
find one supposition which succeeds in binding together
the Facts. But how are we to find this? How is the
trial to be made? What is meant by ‘success’ in these
cases? To this we reply, that our inquiry must be,
whether the Facts have the same relation in the Hypothesis
which they have in reality;—whether the results
of our suppositions agree with the phenomena which
nature presents to us. For this purpose, we must
both carefully observe the phenomena, and steadily
trace the consequences of our assumptions, till we can 68
bring the two into comparison. The Conceptions which
our hypotheses involve, being derived from certain
Fundamental Ideas, afford a basis of rigorous reasoning,
as we have shown in the Books of the History of those
Ideas. And the results to which this reasoning leads,
will be susceptible of being verified or contradicted by
observation of the facts. Thus the Epicyclical Theory
of the Moon, once assumed, determined what the
moon’s place among the stars ought to be at any given
time, and could therefore be tested by actually observing
the moon’s places. The doctrine that musical
strings of the same length, stretched with weights of
1, 4, 9, 16, would give the musical intervals of an octave,
a fifth, a fourth, in succession, could be put to the
trial by any one whose ear was capable of appreciating
those intervals: and the inference which follows from
this doctrine by numerical reasoning,—that there must
be certain imperfections in the concords of every musical
scale,—could in like manner be confirmed by trying
various modes of Temperament. In like manner
all received theories in science, up to the present time,
have been established by taking up some supposition,
and comparing it, directly or by means of its remoter
consequences, with the facts it was intended to embrace.
Its agreement, under certain cautions and conditions,
of which we may hereafter speak, is held to be the
evidence of its truth. It answers its genuine purpose,
the Colligation of Facts.
12. When we have, in any subject, succeeded in one
attempt of this kind, and obtained some true Bond of
Unity by which the phenomena are held together, the
subject is open to further prosecution; which ulterior
process may, for the most part, be conducted in a more
formal and technical manner. The first great outline
of the subject is drawn; and the finishing of the
resemblance of nature demands a more minute pencilling,
but perhaps requires less of genius in the master. In
the pursuance of this task, rules and precepts may be
given, and features and leading circumstances pointed
out, of which it may often be useful to the inquirer to
be aware. 69
Before proceeding further, I shall speak of some
characteristic marks which belong to such scientific
processes as are now the subject of our consideration,
and which may sometimes aid us in determining when
the task has been rightly executed.
</div></body></text></TEI>