<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Babbage Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="9">
      SECTION 2. OF THE PRESIDENCY AND VICE-PRESIDENCIES.
    

      Why Mr. Davies Gilbert became President of the Royal Society I cannot
      precisely say. Let him who penned, and those who supported this resolution
      solve the enigma:
    

      "It was Resolved,
    

      "That it is the opinion of the Council that Davies Gilbert, Esq. is by far
      the most fit person to be proposed to the Society at the approaching
      anniversary as President, and that he be recommended accordingly."
    

      To resolve that he was a FIT person might have been sufficiently
      flattering: to state that he was the most fit, was a little hard upon the
      rest of the Society; but to resolve that he was "BY FAR THE MOST FIT" was
      only consistent with that strain of compliment in which his supporters
      indulge, and was a eulogy, by no means unique in its kind, I believe, even
      at that very Council.
    

      That Mr. Gilbert is a most amiable and kind-hearted man will be instantly
      admitted by all who are, in the least degree, acquainted with him: that he
      is fit for the chair of the Royal Society, will be allowed by few, except
      those who have committed themselves to the above-quoted resolution.
    

      Possessed of knowledge and of fortune more than sufficient for it, he
      might have been the restorer of its lustre. He might have called round
      him, at the council board, those most actively engaged in the pursuits of
      science, most anxious for the improvement of the Royal Society. Instead of
      himself proposing resolutions, he might have been, what a chairman ought
      to be, the organ of the body over which he presides. By the firmness of
      his own conduct he might have taught the subordinate officers of the
      Society the duties of their station. Instead of paying compliments to
      Ministers, who must have smiled at his simplicity, he might have
      maintained the dignity of his Council by the dignity of knowledge.
    

      But he has chosen a different path; with no motives of interest to allure,
      or of ambition to betray him, instead of making himself respected as the
      powerful chief of a united republic,—that of science,—he has
      grasped at despotic power, and stands the feeble occupant of its desolated
      kingdom, trembling at the force of opinions he might have directed, and
      refused even the patronage of their names by those whose energies he might
      have commanded.
    

      Mr. Gilbert told the Society he accepted the situation for a year; and
      this circumstance caused a difficulty in finding a Treasurer: an office
      which he had long held, and to which he wished to return.
    

      Another difficulty might have arisen, from the fact of the late Board of
      Longitude comprising amongst its Members the PRESIDENT of the Royal
      Society, and three of its Fellows, appointed by the President and Council.
      Of course, when Mr. Gilbert accepted the higher situation, he became, EX
      OFFICIO, a Member of the Board of Longitude; and a vacancy occurred, which
      ought to have been filled up by the President and Council. But when this
      subject was brought before them, in defiance of common sense, and the
      plain meaning of the act of parliament, which had enacted that the Board
      of Longitude should have the assistance of four persons belonging to the
      Royal Society, Mr. Gilbert refused to allow it to be filled up, on the
      ground that he should not be President next year, and had made no vacancy.
    

      Next year Mr. Gilbert wished again to be President one other year; but the
      Board of Longitude was dissolved, otherwise we might have had some LOCUM
      TENENS to retire at Mr. Gilbert's pleasure.
    

      These circumstances are in themselves of trifling importance, but they
      illustrate the character of the proceedings: and it is not becoming the
      dignity of science or of the Society that its officers should be so
      circumstanced as to have an apparent and direct interest in supporting the
      existing President, in order to retain their own places; and if such a
      system is once discovered, doubt immediately arises as to the frequency of
      such arrangements.
    


 



</div></body></text></TEI>