<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ninth Bridgewater Treatise</title><author>Babbage, Charles (1791-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="31">REFLECTIONS ON FREE WILL.
 The great question of the incompatibility
 of one of the attributes of the Creator—that of fore-knowledge, with the existence
 of the free exercise of their will in the beings he has created,—has long baffled
 human comprehension; nor is it the object of this chapter to enter upon that
 difficult question. As, however, some of the properties of the Calculating Engine
 seem, although but very remotely, to bear on a similar question, with respect
 to finite beings, it may, perhaps, not be entirely useless to state them.
[page] 168
It has already been observed, that
 it is possible so to adjust the engine, that it shall change the law it is calculating
 into another law, at any distant period which may be assigned.
 Now, by a similar adjustment, this
 change may be made to take place at a time not foreseen by the person employing
 the engine. For example: when calculating a table of squares, it may be made
 to change into a table of cubes, the first time the square number ends in the
 figures—
 269696;
 an event which only occurs at the
 99736th calculation; and whether that fact is known to the person who adjusts
 the machine or not, is immaterial to the result. But the very condition on which
 the change depends, maybe impossible. Thus, the change of the law from that
 of squares to that of cubes may be made to take place the first time
[page] 169
 the square number ends in 7. But
 it is known, that no square number can end in a 7; consequently the event,
 on the happening of which the change is determined, can itself never take place.
 Yet, the engine retains impressed on it a law, which would be called into action
 if the event on which it depends could occur in the course of the law it is
 calculating. Nay, further, if the observer of the engine is informed, that at
 certain times he can move the last figure the engine has calculated, and change
 it into any other, in consequence of which it becomes possible that some future
 term may end in 7; then, after he has so changed the last figure, whenever
 that terminal figure arrives, all future numbers calculated by the machine will
 follow the law of the cubes.
[page] 170
 These contingent changes may be
 limited to single exceptions, and the arrival of such an exception may be made
 contingent on a change which is only possible at certain rare periods. For example:
 the engine may be set to calculate square numbers, and after a certain number
 of calculations—ten million and fifty-three, for instance, it shall be possible
 to add unity to a wheel in another part of the engine, which in every other
 case is immovable. This fact being communicated to the observer, he may either
 make that addition or refrain from it: if he refrain, the law of the squares
 will continue for ever; if he make the addition, one single cube will be substituted
 for that square number, which ought to occur ten million and five terms beyond
 the point at which he made
[page] 171
the addition; and after that no
 future addition will ever become possible, and no deviation from the law of
 the squares ever can occur.
[page] 172
 CONCLUSION. 
 Reader, I have now fulfilled the task I undertook. Labouring under that imputed
 mental incapacity which the science I cultivate has been stated to produce,
 I have brought from the recesses of that science the reasonings and illustrations
 by which I have endeavoured faintly to embody the human conception of the Almighty
 mind. It is for you to determine whether the trains of thought I have excited
 have lowered or exalted your previous notions of the power and the knowledge
 of the Creator.
[page] 173
 That prejudice which I have endeavoured to expose is not a merely speculative
 opinion, it is a practical evil; and those whose writings have been supposed
 to give support to it, will, I am sure, feel grieved when they learn that it
 is used by the ignorant and the designing, for the injury of the virtuous and
 the instructed; that it is employed as a firebrand, to disturb the relations
 of social life. They will also, if the arguments I have used have the same effect
 on their minds which they have had upon my own, lament still more deeply that
 they should have contributed, in any degree, to throw discredit on that species
 of knowledge which is now found to supply some of the strongest arguments in
 favour of religion. I will, however, hope that the opinions I have combated
 are not shared or even countenanced by the higher authorities of our Protestant
 Church; and I cannot better conclude this Fragment, than by recalling to the
 reader the words of one, whose power of reasoning, and whose love of truth,
 add
[page] 174
 dignity to the high station he so deservedly fills:— " Lastly, As we must
 not dare to withhold " or disguise revealed religious truth, so, we "
 must dread the progress of no other truth. " We must not imitate the
 bigoted Romanists " who imprisoned Galileo; and step forward " Bible in hand
 (like the profane Israelites carrying the Ark of God into the field of battle)
 " to check the inquiries of the Geologist, the Astronomer, or the Political-economist,
 from " an apprehension that the cause of religion " can be endangered by them.*
 Any theory " on whatever subject, that is really sound, can " never be inimical
 to a religion founded on " truth; and any that is unsound may be refuted by
 arguments drawn from observation " and experiment, without calling in the aid
 of " revelation. If we give way to a dread of " danger from the inculcation
 of any scriptural
 * See First Lecture on Political Economy.
[page] 175
 doctrine, or from the progress of physical or "moral science, we manifest
 a want of faith in" God's power, or in his will, to maintain his own cause.
 That we shall indeed best further his cause by fearless perseverance in an "open and straight course, I am firmly persuaded; but it is not only when we perceive" the mischiefs of falsehood and disguise, and "the beneficial
 tendency of fairness and candour, that we are to be followers of truth: "the
 trial of our faith is, when we cannot perceive this: and the part of
 a lover of truth " is to follow her at all seeming hazards, after the example
 of Him who came into the world that He might bear witness to the "Truth."'*
 * Sermons by the Archbishop of Dublin.
[page 176]
[page 177]
APPENDIX. 
[page 178]
[page 179]
APPENDIX. 
 NOTE A. page 32.
ON THE GREAT LAW WHICH REGULATES MATTER.
EVER since the period
 when Newton established the great law of gravity, philosophers have occasionally
 speculated on the existence of some more comprehensive law, of which gravity
 itself is a consequence. Although some have considered it vain to search for
 a more general law, the great philosopher himself left encouragement to future
 inquirers; and the time, perhaps, has even now arrived, when such a discovery
 may be near its maturity. It would occupy too much space to introduce many illustrations
 of this opinion; there is, however, one which deserves attention, because it
 is not merely a happy conjecture, but the hypothesis on which it rests has been
 carried out by its author, through the aid of profound mathematical reasoning,
 to many of its remote consequences.
[page] 180
 M. Mosotti* has shown, that by
 supposing matter to consist of two sorts of particles, each of which repels
 similar particles, directly as the mass, and inversely as the squares of their
 distances, whilst each attracts those of the other kind, also according to the
 same law,— then the resulting attractions explain all the phenomena of electricity,
 while there remains a residual force, acting at all sensible distances, according
 to the law of gravity.
Many of the discoveries of the present day point towards
 some more general law; and many philosophers of the present time anticipate
 its near approach. Under these circumstances, it may be interesting as well
 as useful briefly to state the principles which such a law must comprehend; and to indicate, however imperfectly, the path to be pursued in the research.
If matter be supposed to consist of two sorts of particles, or rather, perhaps,
 of two sorts of centres of force, of different orders of density; and if the
 particles of each order repel their own particles, according to a given law,
 but attract particles of the other kind, according to another law,—then, if
 we conceive only one particle of the denser kind to exist, and an infinite
* Professor of Physics at the University of the Ionian Islands.—The paper of M. Mosotti has been translated, and published by Mr. R. Taylor,
 in the third number of the Scientific Memoirs; a work which it is proposed shall
 contain translations of all the most important original papers printed
 in foreign countries.
[page] 181
 number of the other kind, that
 single particle will become the centre of a system, surrounded by all the others,
 which will form around it an atmosphere denser near the central body. If we
 conceive a stream of particles, similar to those forming the atmosphere, to
 impinge upon it, so as just to overcome its resistance, they will, whilst continually
 producing undulations throughout its whole extent, gradually increase its magnitude,
 until it attains such a size, that the repulsion of the particles at the outer
 surface of this enlarged atmosphere is just balanced by the attraction of the
 central particle. If the stream continue after this point is reached, the whole
 outer layer will be pressed a little beyond the limit of attraction, and will
 fly off at right angles to the surface, which might then be said to radiate.
 If the whole of the space in which such a central particle with its atmosphere
 is placed, is itself full of atmospheric particles, then their density will
 increase in approaching the central body; and if a stream of such particles
 were directed towards the centre, they might produce throughout the atmosphere
 vibrations, which would be transmitted from it in all directions. If two such
 central particles, with their atmospheres, exist at a distance from each other,
 they will be drawn together by a force depending on the difference between
[page] 182
 the mutual repulsion of their atmospheres and central bodies respectively
 for each other, and the attraction of each central particle for its neighbour's
 atmosphere: and in order to coincide with the existing law of nature, this
 force must be directly as the mass, and inversely as the square, of the distance.
 The other conditions which such a law must satisfy, are— 1. That the juxtaposition
 of such atoms must, in some circumstances, form a solid body:— 2. In
 other circumstances, a fluid. 3. That again, in still other circumstances,
 its particles shall repel each other, or the body become gaseous. 4. In the
 first state the body must possess cohesion, tenacity, malleability, elasticity; the measure and extent of each of which must result generally from the original
 law, and in each particular case from the constants belonging to the substance
 itself. 5. In the second state, it must possess capillarity, susceptibility
 of being compressed without becoming solid, as also elasticity. But besides
 these, the central atoms must admit of a more intimate approach, so that
 their atmospheres may
[page] 183
 unite and form one atmosphere.
 This might constitute chemical union. Binary compounds might then (supposing
 the distance between the two central particles to be very small, compared with
 the diameters of the atmospheres) have atmospheres not quite spherical, and
 attracting differently in different directions; thus possessing polarity. Combinations
 of three or more atoms, as the central body of one atmosphere, might give great
 varieties of attractive forces. Each different combination would give a different
 atmosphere; and the equation of its surface might, perhaps, become the mathematical
 expression of the substance it constituted. Thus, all the phenomena produced
 by bodies, acting chemically on each other, might be deduced from the comparison
 of the characteristic surfaces of the atmospheres of their atoms. Another
 result, also, might ensue. Two or more central atoms uniting, might either not
 be able to retain the same amount of atmosphere, or they might possibly be able
 to retain a larger quantity. If the particles of such atmospheres constituted
 heat, it would in the former case be given out, and in the latter absorbed by
 chemical union. Hence the whole of chemistry, and with it crystallography, would
 become a branch of mathematical analysis, which, like astronomy, taking its
 constants from observation, would enable us to predict the character of any
 new compound, and possibly indicate the source from which its formation might
 be anticipated.
[page] 184
 For the sake of simplicity, two
 species of particles only have been mentioned above; but it seems more probable,
 that matter consists of at least three kinds. Suppose each of the three kinds
 to repel its own particles; and the central atom, whilst it repels similar particles,
 to attract those of the two other kinds; and moreover, that the latter are
 either repulsive, or indifferent to each other. We might then conceive matter
 to be made up of particles, each having a central point, with an atmosphere
 surrounding it, and this atmosphere again inclosed within another and larger
 one. Under such circumstances, the outer atmosphere might give rise to heat
 and light, to solidity and fluidity, and the gaseous condition; to capillarity,
 to elasticity, tenacity, and malleability. The more intimate union of the central
 atoms, by which two or more become enclosed in one common atmosphere of the
 second kind, might represent chemical combinations, and perhaps that atmosphere
 itself be electricity. Possibly, also, this intermediate atmosphere, acted on
 by the pressure of the external one, and by the attraction of the central atom,
 might take the liquid form. These binary or multiple-combinations of the original
 atoms, and their smaller atmospheres, would still be enclosed in an atmosphere
 of the outer kind, which might be nearly spherical. The joint action of the
 three might, at sensible distances, produce gravity.
[page] 185
 The reader should, however, bear
 in mind, that these hints are thrown out only as objects of reflection and inquiry; and that nothing but a profound mathematical investigation can establish them,
 or even give to them that temporary value which arises from any hypothesis,
 representing a large collection of facts.
[page] 186
NOTE B. page 33.
ON THE CALCULATING
 ENGINE.
THE nature of the arguments advanced in this volume having obliged me to refer,
 more frequently than I should have chosen, to the Calculating Engine, it becomes
 necessary to give the reader some brief account of its progress and present
 state.
About the year 1821, I undertook
 to superintend, for the Government, the construction of an engine for calculating
 and printing mathematical and astronomical tables. Early in the year 1833, a
 small portion of the machine was put together, and was found to perform its
 work with all the precision which had been anticipated. At that period circumstances,
 which I could not control, caused what I then considered a temporary suspension
 of its progress; and the Government, on whose
[page] 187
decision the continuance or discontinuance
 of the work depended, have not yet communicated to me their wishes on the question.
 The first illustration (p. 33 to 43) I have employed is derived from
 the calculations made by this engine.
About October, 1834, I commenced
 the design of another, and far more powerful engine. Many of the contrivances
 necessary for its performance have since been discussed and drawn according
 to various principles; and all of them have been invented in more than one
 form. I consider them, even in their present state, as susceptible of practical
 execution; but time, thought, and expense, will probably improve them. As the
 remaining illustrations are all drawn from the powers of this new engine, it
 may be right to state, that it will calculate the numerical value of any algebraical
 function—that, at any period previously fixed upon, or contingent on certain
 events, it will cease to tabulate that algebraic function, and commence the
 calculation of a different one, and that these changes may be repeated to any
 extent.
The former engine could employ about
 120 figures in its calculations; the present machine is intended to compute
 with about 4,000.
 Here I should willingly have left
 the subject; but the public having erroneously imagined, that the sums
[page] 188
 of money paid to the workmen for
 the construction of the engine, were the remuneration of my own services, for
 inventing and directing its progress; and a Committee of the House of Commons
 having incidentally led the public to believe that a sum of money was voted
 to me for that purpose,—I think it right to give to that report the most direct
 and unequivocal contradiction.
[page] 189
NOTE C. page 111.
EXTRACT FROM THE
 THEORY OF PROBABILITIES OF LAPLACE.
 "Nous devons donc envisager l'état
 présent de l'univers, comme l'effet de son état antérieur,
 et comme la cause de celui qui va suivre. " Une intelligence qui pour un instant
 donnée, connaîtrait toutes les forces dont la nature est animée,
 et la situation respective des êtres qui la composent, si d'ailleurs elle
 était assez vaste pour soumettre ces données à l'analyse,
 embrasserait, dans la même formule, les mouvemens des plus grands corps
 de l'univers et ceux du plus léger atome: rien ne serait incertain pour
 elle, et l'avenir, comme le passé, serait présent a ses yeux.
 L'esprit humain offre, dans la perfection qu'il a su donner à l'astronomie,
 une faible esquisse de cette intelli-
[page] 190
gence. Ses découvertes en
 mécanique et en géométrie, jointes à celle de la
 pesanteur universelle, l'ont mis à portée de comprendre dans les
 mêmes expressions analytiques, les états passés et futurs
 du système du monde.
"En appliquant le même méthode
 à quelques autres objets de ses connaissances, il est parvenu à
 ramener à des lois générales, les phénomènes
 observés, et à prévoir ceux que des circonstances données
 doivent faire éclore. Tous ses efforts dans la recherche de la vérité, 
 tendent à le rapprocher sans cesse à l'intelligence que nous venons
 de concevoir, mais dont il restera toujours infiniment éloigné.
 Cette tendance propre à l'espèce humaine, est ce qui la rend supérieure
 aux animaux; et ses progrès en ce genre, distinguent les nations et
 les siècles, et fondent leur véritable gloire."—Laplace, Théorie
 Analytique des Probabilités.
[page] 191
NOTE D. page 92.
NOTE TO CHAP. VIII.
 ON MIRACLES.
THE view taken of miracles in Chapter
 VIII. is the same as that contained in the work of Butler, on the Analogy of
 Religion to the Constitution and Course of Nature. Inquiries connected with
 the Calculating Engine, impressed it very forcibly on my own mind, and I have
 drawn the illustrations chiefly from that subject. 1 cannot, however, forbear
 referring the reader to the opinion of Sir J. Herschel, expressed at the beginning
 of his letter to Mr. Lyell, (see Note I. p. 225,) because it confirms
 me in the belief, that the more profoundly we inquire into the mechanism of
 nature, the more certainly we arrive at that conclusion.
[page] 192
NOTE E. page 181.
NOTE TO CHAPTER X.
 ON HUMES ARGUMENT AGAINST MIRACLES.
THE reader will observe, that throughout
 the chapter to which this note refers, as well as in the note itself, the argument
 of Hume is taken strictly according to his own interpretation of the terms he
 uses, and the calculations are founded on them; so that it is from the very
 argument itself, when fairly pursued to its full extent, that the refutation
 results.
Both our belief in the truth of
 human testimony, and our belief in the permanence of the laws of nature, are,
 according to Hume, founded on experience; we may, therefore, in the complete
 ignorance in which he assumes we are, with respect to the causes of either,
 treat the question as one of the probability of an event deduced solely from
 observations of the past.
[page] 193
 The argument of Hume asserts, that
 one improbability, namely, that of the falsehood of the testimony in favour
 of a miracle, must always be greater than another improbability, namely,
 that of the occurrence of the miracle itself; and also, that, from the very
 nature of human experience, this preponderance can never take place.
 Now the only possible mode of disproving the assertion, that one thing cannot,
 under any circumstances, be greater than another, is to measure, under all circumstances,
 the numerical value of the two things so compared, and the truth or falsehood
 of the assertion will then appear. The doctrine of chances, which has been much
 improved since the time of Hume, now enables us to apply precise measures to
 this argument; and it is the object of this Note to state the outlines of the
 calculation, and the results to which it leads. Previously to this, however,
 it may not be amiss to offer a few remarks on the principles about to be employed.
 In the great work of Laplace, " Théorie Analytique des Probabilités,"
 those principles are established, and they are not merely undisputed, but are
 admitted by other writers of the highest authority on this subject. They form
 a part of the received knowledge of the present day, and, as such, they are
 employed in the present work, in which I propose to use, not to
[page] 194
 discuss them. I state this, because
 it has occasionally been asserted by persons unacquainted with the doctrine
 of chances, that the argument respecting the probability or improbability of
 miracles does not admit of the application of numbers. The received foundations
 of science are not to be put aside by such opinions, however highly skilled
 their authors may be in other branches of knowledge, and however powerful the
 intellect by which they may have attained those acquirements. The conclusions
 arrived at by the application of pure analysis must ever rest on the truth of
 the principles assumed at the commencement of the inquiry; and although a knowledge
 of mathematics may not appear necessary for forming a right judgment of the
 accuracy of those principles, yet it is observed, that a clear apprehension
 of them is not often found in the minds of those who are unacquainted with that
 science. When, however, the grounds on which the principles employed in the
 doctrine of chances are called in question by competent authority, it will be
 time enough to examine the question; and none will more eagerly enter upon
 that examination than those best versed in it, for none are so well aware of
 the extreme difficulty and delicacy of the subject. As confusion sometimes arises
 from the difference in the meaning of the words probable and improbable in popular language and in mathematical inquiries,
[page] 195
it may be convenient to point it
 out; and to state, that in this Note it is used in the mathematical sense,
 unless the reader's attention is directly called to a question relating to its
 popular sense.
In common language, an event is
 said to be probable when it is more likely to happen than to fail: it
 is said to be improbable when it is more likely to fail than to happen.
Now, an event whose probability
 is, in mathematical language , will be called probable or improbable, in
ordinary language, according as p is less or greater than 2.
If, in mathematical language, expresses
 the probability of an event happening,  expresses the
probability of its failing, or the improbability of its happening.
It has been stated in the text,
 that two views may be taken of those extraordinary deviations from the usual
 course of nature, called miracles. According to the first of these, we have
 to calculate the probability that a white ball has been drawn from an
 urn (containing only white and black balls, out of which m balls have
 been drawn all black), as deduced from
[page] 196
 the testimony of witnesses whose
 probability of speaking truth is known:—or, of the analogous case; it having
 been observed that m persons have died without any restoration to life,
 what is the probability that such a resurrection has happened, it having been
 asserted by n independent witnesses, the probability of each of whose
 speaking false is -? The probability of the death without resurrection of the
 , and the improbability of such an
 occurrence, independently of testimony, is; which is therefore the probability
 of a contrary occurrence, or that
 of a person being raised from the dead. Now only two hypotheses can be formed,
 collusion being, by hypothesis, out of the question: either the event did happen,
 and the witnesses agree in speaking the truth, the probability of their concurrence
 being
 ,
 and of that of the hypothesis being;
 or the event did not happen, and
 the witnesses  agree in a falsehood,
 the probability of their concurrence being , and that of the hypothesis The probability
 of the witnesses speaking truth, and the event occurring, is therefore,
[page] 197

 and the probability of their falsehood
 is,

 If we interpret Hume's assertion,
 " that the falsehood of the witnesses must be more improbable than the occurrence
 of the miracle," according to the mathematical meaning of the word improbable,
 then we must
 have,

 or,

 hence,

 from which we find,

[page] 198
 are persons whose statements are
 more frequently correct than incorrect, and who give their testimony in favour
 of it without collusion,) a certain number n can always be found; so
 that it shall be a greater improbability that their unanimous statement shall
 be a falsehood, than that the miracle shall have occurred. Let us now suppose
 each witness to state one falsehood for every ten truths, or p = 11,
 and m = 1000,000,000,000;

 or twenty-five such witnesses are
 sufficient. If the witnesses only state one falsehood for every hundred truths,
 then thirteen such witnesses are sufficient. Another view of the question might
 be taken; and it might be asserted that, in order to believe in the miracle,
 the probability of its truth must be greater than the probability of its falsehood; in this case the expression (A) must be greater than (B); or,

 In this case also, under the same
 circumstances, the condition can always be fulfilled of finding a sufficient
[page] 199
number of witnesses to render the
 miracle probable, or even to give to it any required degree of probability.

 According to the second view stated
 in the text, a miracle may be assimilated to the drawing of a given number i out of an urn, containing all numbers from one to m. In this case
 the probability of the occurrence of the event is,
 and the probability of the concurrence of n witnesses in falsehood is Hence the probability that the particular number i was drawn, as deduced
 from the testimony of n witnesses, each of whose probability of falsehood
 is , is expressed by,

[page] 200
 and the probability of the number i not having been drawn, or of their falsehood, is

 Hence the improbability of the
 testimony must, according to Hume, be greater than that of the occurrence of
 the event; or,-

 If it is only required that the
 probability of the occurrence of the miracle shall be greater than its
[page] 201
 improbability, then we must make (C) greater than (D); or,

 Hence in this view, also, a sufficient
 number of witnesses of given veracity may always be found to render the
 improbability of their concurrent independent testimony being false, greater
 than the improbability of the occurrence of the miracle. There is, however,
 one other view, which it seems probable would have been that taken by Hume himself,
 had he applied numbers to his own argument. Considering the probability of the
 coincidence in falsehood of persons each having the probability
[page] 202
 in favour of his truth, which is u, that probability ought to be less than that of the occurrence
 of the miracle; or,

 This view of the question refers
 to the probability of the concurrence of the witnesses before they have
 given their testimony. The other four cases relate to the probability of the
 miracle having happened, as deduced from the fact of the testimony having been
 given. The last seems to have been that which Hume would have himself arrived
 at; the others represent the true methods of estimating the probabilities of
 the various cases: and the important conclusion follows, that, whichever be
 the interpretation given to the argument of Hume, if independent witnesses can
 be found, who speak truth more frequently than falsehood, it is always possible to assign a number of independent witnesses, the improbability of
 the falsehood of whose concurring testimony shall be greater than that of the
 improbability of the miracle itself.
[page] 203
 It is to be observed, that the
 whole of this argument applies to independent witnesses. The possibility
 of the collusion, and the degree of credit to be assigned to witnesses under
 any given circumstances, depend on facts which have not yet been sufficiently
 collected to become the subject of mathematical inquiry. Some of those considerations
 which bear on this part of the subject, the reader will find treated of in the
 work of Dr. Conyers Middleton, entitled " A Free Inquiry into the Miraculous
 Powers which are supposed to have subsisted in the Christian Church, from the
 earliest Ages through several successive Centuries." London, 1749.
[page] 204
NOTE F.
ON THE CONSEQUENCES
 OF CENTRAL HEAT.
the increase of temperature observed
 as we descend below the earth's surface, as well as other phenomena, have led
 to a very general opinion, that great heat exists in the interior of the earth,
 and that the body of our planet, having been at one time intensely heated, has
 cooled down to its present temperature. With the view of pointing out courses
 of inquiry, by which these opinions may ultimately be tested by observation,
 it may be expedient to take a cursory view of some of the consequences of such
 an hypothesis.
And first, let us imagine the exterior
 of our globe to have once been in a state of intense heat. No fluid such as
 water could then have existed on the surface: it would instantly have been
 converted into vapour; and
[page] 205
 notwithstanding the increased weight
 of atmosphere thus produced and pressing on the surface of the globe, sufficient
 heat would reduce all fluids to the gaseous state. Let us, however, inquire
 as to the possible extent of such an atmosphere. In the first place, it could
 not extend beyond that point at which the moon's attraction is equal to that
 of the earth. In the next place, much more contracted limits would be prescribed
 by the effect of centrifugal force, and of the cooling of the vapour by expansion,
 and by its distance from the source of radiant heat, which had caused its evaporation.
 It would be interesting to inquire, what would be the nature of the surface
 of the atmosphere under such circumstances. At the distance at which the centrifugal
 force is equal to that of gravity, it might happen that the temperature was
 scarcely sufficient to maintain the water in a gaseous state. Should this have
 been the case, a belt of perpetual clouds might have been formed, resembling
 those of Jupiter. If, at this limit, a still lower degree of temperature prevailed,
 instead of a belt of clouds, a ring of ice might be formed. This ring of ice,
 being exposed to different effects of radiation from variations in the radiating
 power of various parts of the earth's surface, might, by the superior heat at
 some parts, become diminished, whilst
[page] 206
 the condensation of the vapour
 might augment parts less exposed, and situated nearer to the body of the planet:
 and these conditions might continue, until at last the ring itself was melted
 or partially melted through at one or more points, and the whole might break
 up, and the fragments moving in a resisting medium, would ultimately fall down
 on the surface of the planet. The tearing up of that surface from such an event,
 would be augmented by the sudden conversion of the solid ice into steam; and
 after a time, the fragments of the ring would be absorbed again into the atmosphere
 of the planet. Let us now suppose, owing to the gradual cooling down of the
 whole globe, the limit of condensation of steam into water, to occur at a nearer
 point than that at which the centrifugal force equals that of gravity. As soon
 as the steam is condensed into water, it will descend towards the surface of
 the earth; but that surface being still very hot, will, by its radiation, again
 convert the descending shower into steam; and this will happen at different
 heights above the surface, according to the radiating power of the part below.
 We may, therefore, conceive a shell surrounding the earth, the outer surface
 of which has just been condensed into water, and the inner consists of vapour,
 just re-converted into that state by the earth's radiation. These surfaces will
 attain different heights in different places. Between these two surfaces there
 will exist a perpetual
[page] 207
 rain, descending from the upper
 as a gentle shower, becoming gradually a violent torrent, and then as it falls
 re-absorbed into another gentle shower, which is entirely converted into vapour
 in approaching the heated surface. Such being the state of things, let us imagine
 the globe to cool down uniformly. The lower surface of the descending rain,
 which is placed at irregular heights, will at length be brought down to the
 earth's surface in one or more points. The effect of this, which will in the
 first instance be a gentle shower, would be to cool that portion of the surface
 on which it falls, and hence to diminish its radiating power. This change, in
 its turn, will lower the under surface of the watery shell, so that a more violent
 rain, and ultimately an impetuous torrent will continue, perhaps, for thousands
 of years, its unremitted vertical action on the surface exposed to its force.
 The excavation of the largest valleys, or even of ocean beds, is not too much
 to expect from such forces. But let us take another view of the consequences
 of such an original state of incandescence. The whole of the fluids now on the
 surface of the earth must then have been suspended in its atmosphere. But the
 extent of that atmosphere is itself limited by various causes: the attraction
 of other bodies, the effects of centrifugal force, the decrease of temperature,
 and the
[page] 208
 distances at which the particles
 of gaseous bodies cease to repel each other, all have their influence in determining
 its form and magnitude. Let us suppose that we possessed data from which the
 approximate amount of vapour contained in the entire atmosphere were known,
 and consequently the whole quantity of water in it; then, since we know the
 area of the present seas, we might easily ascertain their average depth. If
 the result of such a computation should give a mean depth much less than that
 which we know the ocean to possess,—as, for instance, only a hundred feet,—then
 we might conclude, either that the surface of the earth had never been in such
 a state of incandescence as has been supposed, or if it had, that a new source
 of aqueous vapour had been supplied to it, subsequently to its cooling down.
[page] 209
 NOTE G. on the action
 of existing causes in producing elevations and subsidences in portions of the
 earth's surface.
 the following explanation of the
 origin of many of the changes at present going on on the earth's surface, was
 suggested in endeavouring to account for the very singular phenomena presented
 by the temple of Jupiter Serapis, at Puzzuoli, near Naples. The facts relating
 to that temple were observed by me in 1828, and the theory occurred soon after
 my return to England; but though occasionally mentioned to geological friends,
 it was not printed until it appeared in the abstract of my paper on the Temple
 of Serapis, presented to the Geological Society of London, in March 1854. The
 following positions are taken as the basis of the reasoning on this subject:—
[page] 210
 1. That, as we descend below the
 surface of the earth, the temperature increases. 2. That solid rocks expand
 by being heated; but that clay, and some other substances, contract under the
 same circumstances. 3. That different rocks and strata conduct heat differently.
 4. That the earth radiates heat differently, at different parts of its surface,
 according as it is covered with forests, with mountains, with deserts, or with
 water. 5. That existing atmospheric agents, and other causes, are constantly
 changing the condition of the surface of the globe. The only one of these propositions
 on which, in the present state of knowledge, the slightest question can be raised,
 is the first. But the observations on which it depends have latterly become
 so numerous, that the general fact of an increase of temperature, in descending
 through the crust of the earth, can scarcely be questioned; although the exact
 law of this increase, and the extent to which it penetrates, are yet undecided.
 An increase of 1 Fahrenheit's thermometer, for every 50 or 60 feet we penetrate
 below the earth's surface,
[page 211]
[page 212]

[page] 213
 seems nearly the average result
 of observations. If the rate continue, it is obvious that, at a small distance
 below the surface, we shall arrive at a heat which will keep all the substances
 with which we are acquainted in a state of fusion. Without, however, assuming
 the fluidity of the central nucleus,—a question yet unsettled, and which
 rests on very inferior evidence* to that by which the principles here employed
 are supported,—we may yet arrive at important conclusions; and these may be
 applied to the case of central fluidity, according to the opinions of the inquirer.
 If we consider the temperature of any point:—for example, G, situated two miles
 below the surface of an elevated table land, A, in the annexed wood-cut; and
 if we imagine a surface passing through all the points of equal temperature
 within t e globe; then, as this surface passes under the adjacent ocean, which
 we may suppose, on an average, to be two miles deep, it is evident that the surface of equal heat will descend towards the earth's centre; because,
 if it did not, we should have great heat nearly in contact with the bottom of
 the sea. In the first figure, B is the surface of the ocean. A D, the surface
 of the land, and of the bed of the ocean. The broken line, G F, is the isothermal
 line. Let us now
* The reader will find this question
 fully discussed in the 17th chapter of Lyell's Geology; On the Causes of Earthquakes
 and Volcanoes.
[page] 214
 suppose, by the continual wearing
 down of the continents and islands adjoining this ocean, that it becomes yearly
 filled up. The broken line C, in the second figure of the wood-cut, indicates
 the new bottom. The former bottom of the ocean being now covered with a bad
 conductor of heat, instead of with a fluid which rapidly conveyed it away, the
 surface of uniform temperature will rise, slowly but considerably, as is shown
 at G E, in the third figure. In the fourth figure, the first bed of the ocean,
 A D, and its isothermal line, G F, as well as the new bed, A C, of the ocean,
 and its corresponding isothermal line, G E, are all shown at one view. The newly
 formed strata will be consolidated by the application of heat; they may, perhaps,
 contract in bulk, and thus give space for new deposits, which will, in their
 turn, become similarly consolidated. But the surface of uniform temperature
 below the bed of the ocean cannot rise towards the earth's surface, without
 an increase in the temperature of all the beds of various rock on which it rests; and this increase must take place for a considerable depth. The consequence
 must be a gradual rise of the ancient bed of the ocean, and of all the deposits
 newly formed upon it. The shallowness of this altered ocean will, by exposing
 it to greater evaporation from the effect of the sun's heat, give increased
 force to the atmospheric causes still operating upon
[page] 215
 the inequalities of the solid surface,
 and tend more rapidly to fill up the depressions. Possibly the conducting power
 of the heated rocks may be so slow, that its total effect may not be produced
 for centuries after the sea has given place to dry land; and we can conceive,
 that in such circumstances,—the force of the sun's rays from without, and the
 increasing heat from below, so consolidating the surface, that the land may 
 again descend below the level of adjacent seas, even though its first bottom
 is still subject to the elevatory process. Thus, a series of shallow seas or
 large lakes might be formed; and these processes might even be repeated several
 times, before the full effect of the expansion from below had permanently raised
 the whole newly-formed land above . the influence of the adjacent seas. If the
 sea were originally much deeper, or, if in particular parts it were much deeper,
 as, for instance, ten or twenty miles, then a portion of the solid matter beneath
 its surface might, after the lapse of many ages, acquire a red, or even a melting
 heat, and the conversion into gases of some of the substances thus operated
 on, might give rise to earthquakes, or to subterraneous volcanoes. On the other
 hand, as the high land gradually wears away, by the removal of a portion of
 its thickness, and
[page] 216
 as the cooling down of its surface
 takes place, its contraction might give rise to enormous rents. If these cracks
 penetrate to any great reservoirs of melted matter, such as appear to subsist
 beneath volcanoes, then they will be compressed by the contraction, and the
 melted matter will rise and fill the cracks, which, when cooled down, will become
 dykes. If these rents do not reach the internal reservoir of melted matter,
 and if there exist in the neighbourhood any volcanic vents connected with it,
 the contraction of the upper strata may give rise to volcanic eruptions, through
 those vents, which might be driven by such a force to almost any height. These
 eruptions may themselves diminish the heat of the beds immediately above the
 melting cauldron from which they arise; for the conversion of some of the fluid
 substances into gases, on the removal of the enormous pressure, will rapidly
 abstract heat from the melted mass. As the removal of the upper surface of the
 high land will diminish its resistance to fracture, so the altered pressure
 arising from the removal of that weight, and its transfer to the bottom of the
 ocean, may determine the exit of the melted matter. Other consequences 'might
 arise from the different fusibility of the various strata deposited in the bed
 of the ocean. Let us imagine, in the annexed wood cut,
[page] 217
 the two beds, A and B, to melt
 at a much lower temperature than those between which they intervene. It might
 happen, by the gradual rising of the isothermal surfaces, that one or both of
 those strata should be

 melted; and thus, supposing all
 the beds originally to have contained marine remains, we might, at a distant
 period, discover two interposed beds, without any trace of such remains, but
 presenting all the appearances of former fusion, resting on, separated by, and
 existing under, other beds of demonstrably marine formation. If, during that
 former state of fusion, rents should have been formed through several of the
 strata, injection of the liquid matter might proceed from these melted beds,
 both upwards and downwards. If, on the contrary, older dykes had penetrated
 all the strata, it is possible to suppose such a degree of fusibility in the
 older dyke, or such chemical relation to the melted bed, that the portions of
 the dyke passing through that bed shall be obliterated, whilst those which traverse
[page] 218
 the less fusible beds, protected
 from r.uch action, shall remain unaltered, as in the annexed cut.

 Another consequence of this constant
 change in the position of the isothermal surfaces must be the development of
 thermo-electricity, which, acting on an immense scale, may determine the melting
 of some beds, or the combination of the melted masses of others, or cause the
 segregation of veins and crystals, in heated, though not fluid, portions of
 the strata exposed to its influence. Nor may the dykes themselves be without
 their use, either in keeping up the communication for the passage of electricity,
 if they are good conductors,—or in separating the groups of strata which produce
 it, if they are bad conductors. For the elucidation of this subject, it appears
 very important that experiment should be made on the effects of long-continued
 artificial heat in altering and obliterating the traces of organic remains existing
 in known rocks. It seems probable that by a well-planned series of such experiments,
 we might be enabled to
[page] 219
 trace the gradually disappearing
 structure of animal remains existing in rocks subjected to fire, into marks
 which, without such aid, seem utterly distinct from that origin; and that we
 might thus establish new alphabets with which to attempt the deciphering of
 some of the older rocks.* It appears, therefore, that from changes continually
 going on, by the destruction of forests, the filling up of seas, the wearing
 down of elevated lands,—the heat radiated from the earth's surface varies considerably
 at different periods. Inconsequence of this variation, and also in consequence
 of the covering up of the bottoms of seas, by the detritus of the land, the surfaces of equal temperature within the earth are continually changing
 their form, and exposing thick beds near the exterior to alterations of temperature.
 The expansion and contraction of these strata may form rents and veins, produce
 earthquakes, determine volcanic eruptions, elevate continents, and possibly
 raise mountain chains. The further consequences resulting from the working out
 of this theory would fill a volume, rather than a note.
* Some experiments, with this object in view, were undertaken at the recommendation
 of the British Association, (See Third Report,
 p. 479, and Fourth Report, p. 576.) and portions of rock, containing organic
 remains, have already (1838) been exposed, for above five years, to the heat
 of the hearth of a blast furnace, at the Elsecar iron works in Yorkshire, through
 the permission of Earl Fitzwilliam, and at the Low Moor works, by that of the
 proprietors.
[page] 220
It may, however, be remarked, that
 whilst the principles on which it is founded are really existing causes, yet
 that the sufficiency of the theory for explaining all the phenomena cannot be
 admitted until it shall have been shown, that their power is fully adequate
 to produce all the observed effects.
 NOTE H.
[page] 221
 TABLE
 Showing the Expansion of Beds
 of Granite variously heated, from One Degree to One Hundred Degrees Fahrenheit,
 and from One to Five Hundred Miles thick.


Miles.
One Degree.
Twenty Degrees.
Fifty Degrees.
One Hundred Degrees.


 
Feet.
Feet.
Feet.
Feet.I


1
.02548
.5095
1.274
2.548


5
.13
2.55
6.37
12.74


10
.25
5.10
12.74
25.48


15
.38
7'64
19.11
38.21


20
.51
10.19
25.48
50.95 i


25
.64
12.74
31.85
63.C9


30
.76
15.29
38.2J
76.43


35
.89
17.83
44.58
89.17


40
1.02
20.38
50.95
101.90


45
1.15
22.93
57.32
114.64


50
 1.27 
25.48
63.69
127.38


55
1.40
28.02
70.06
140.12


60
1.53
30'57
76.43
152.86


65
1.66
33.12
82.80
165.59


70
 1.78 
35.67
89.17
178.33


75
1.91
38.21
95.5
191.07


80
2.04
40.76
101.90
203.81


85
2.17
43.31
108.27
216.55


90
2.29
45.86
114.64
229.28


95
2.42
48.40
121.01
242.02


100
2.55
50.95
127.38
254.76


150
3.82
76.43
191.07
382.14


200
5.10
101.90
254.76
509.52


500
12.74.
254.76
636.90
1273.80


[page] 222
TABLE
Showing the Expansion of Beds
 of Granite variously heated, from Two Hundred Degrees to Three Thousand Degrees
 Fahrenheit, and from One to Five Hundred Miles thick.


Miles.
Two Hundred Degrees.
Five Hundred Degrees
One Thousand Degrees
Three Thousand Degrees.


 

Feet.
Feel.
Feet.
Feet.


1
5.095
12.738
25.476
76.428


5
25.5
63.7
127.4
382.1


10
51.0
127.4
254.8
764.3


15
76.4
191.1
382.1
1147.4


20
101.9
254.8
509.5
1528.6


25
127.4
318.5
636.9
1910.7


30
152.9
382.1
764.3
2292.8


35
178.3
445.8
891.7
2675.0


40
203.8
509.5
1019.0
3057.1


45
229.3
573.2
1146.4
3439.3


50
254.8
636.9
1273.8
3821.4


55
280.2
700.6
1401.2
4203.5


60
305.7
764.3
1528.6
4585.7


65
331.2
828.0
1655.9
4967.8


70
356.7
891.7
1783.3
5350.0


75
382.1
955.4
1910.7
5732.1


80
407.6
1019.0
2038.1
6114.2


85
433.1
1082.7
2165.5
6496.4


90
458.6
1146.4
2292.8
6878.5


95
484.0
1210.1
2420.2
7260.7


100
509.5
1273.8
2547.6
 7642.8 


150
764.3
1910.7
3821.4
 11464.2 


200
1019.0
2547.6
5095.2
 15285.6 


500
2547.5
6369.0
12738.0
 38214.0 


[page] 223
 The table was calculated from experiments
 made under the direction of Colonel Totten, by Mr. H. C. Bartlett, of the United
 States Engineers; an account of which is given in the American Journal of Science,
 Vol. XXII. p. 136. From the result of these experiments it was found that, for
 every degree of Fahrenheit,
 Granite expands ............. .000004825
 Marble.................. .000005668 Sandstone ................ .000009532
 The tables were computed by the
 Calculating Engine, from the first line, which was deduced from the experiment.
 It will be observed that the numbers given are always true to the last figure,
 a compensation which the Engine itself made. In order to find the expansion
 for marble, increase the numbers by one-sixth. To find the expansion for sandstone,
 double the numbers found in the table. Other experiments have since been made
 by Mr. Adie, of which an account is given in the thirteenth volume of the Transactions
 of the Royal Society of Edinburgh: from these I have selected the following
 list of expansions:—
 Roman Cement expands .........
 .00000750 Sicilian White Marble .......... .00000613 Carrara Marble ..............
 .00000363
[page] 224
 Sandstone, from Craigleith quarry
 .... .00000652 Slate, from Penrhyn, Wales ....... .00000576 Peterhead Red Granite
 .......... .00000498 Arbroath Pavement............ .00000499 Caithness Pavement.
 ........... .00000497 Greenstone, from Ratho ......... .00000449 Aberdeen Grey
 Granite ......... .00000438 Best Stock Brick ............. .00000306 Fire Brick
 ................. .00000274 Black Marble, Galway .......... .00000247
[page] 225
NOTE I.
 I am happy to be enabled to put
 before the reader extracts from two letters of Sir J. Herschel, which show,
 that though my early friend is extending the boundaries of our system, by his
 observations in the southern hemisphere, his active and indefatigable mind has
 yet found time to throw its comprehensive glance over some of the highest questions
 which perplex other sciences. I feel, that the almost perfect coincidence of
 his views with my own, gives additional support to the explanations I have offered; whilst the reader will perceive, from the different light in which my friend
 has viewed the subject, that we were both independently led to the same inferences
 by different courses of inquiry. I. The first of the letters to which I allude,
 and of which I shall extract the greater part, is addressed to Mr. Lyell.
" Feldhausen, Cape of Good Hope,
 Feb. 20, 1836. MY DEAR SlR,
 I am perfectly ashamed not to
 have long since acknowledged your present of the new edition of your
[page] 226
 Geology, a work which I now read
 for the third time, and every time with increased interest, as it appears
 to me one of those productions which work a complete revolution in their subject,
 by altering entirely the point of view in which it must thenceforward be
 contemplated. You have succeeded, too, in adding dignity to a subject already
 grand, by exposing to view the immense extent and complication of the problems
 it offers for solution, and by unveiling a dim glimpse of a region of speculation
 connected with it, where it seems impossible to venture without experiencing
 some degree of that mysterious awe which the sybil appeals to, in the bosom
 of AEneas, on entering the confines of the shades—or what the Maid of Avenel
 suggests to Halbert Glendinning,
'He that on such quest would go, must know nor fear nor failing; To
 coward soul or faithless heart the search were unavailing.'
 Of course I allude to that mystery
 of mysteries, the replacement of extinct species by others. Many will doubtless
 think your speculations too bold, but it is as well to face the difficulty
 at once. For my own part, I cannot but think it an inadequate conception
 of the Creator, to assume it as granted that his combinations are exhausted
 upon any one of the theatres of their former exercise, though in this, as
 in all his other works, we are led, by all analogy, to suppose that he operates
 through a series of intermediate causes, and that in consequence the origina-
[page] 227
 tion of fresh species, could
 it ever come under our cognizance, would be found to be a natural in contradistinction to a miraculous process—although we perceive no indications
 of any process actually in progress which is likely to issue in such a result."
 Now for a bit of theory. Has it ever occurred to you to speculate on the
 probable effect of the transfer of pressure from one part to another of the
 earth's surface by the degradation of existing and the formation of new
 continents—on the fluid or semi-fluid matter beneath the outer crust? Supposing
 the whole to float on a sea of lava, the effect would merely be an almost
 infinitely minute flexure of the strata; but, supposing the layer next
 below the crust to be partly solid and partly fluid, and composed of a
 mixture of fixed rock, liquid lava, and other masses, in various degrees of
 viscidity and mobility, great inequalities may subsist in the distribution
 of pressure, and the consequence maybe, local disruptions of the crust, where
 weakest, and escape to the surface of lava, &c. If the obstructions "
 to free communication among distant parts of a fluid be great, no instantaneous propagation of pressure
[page] 228
 can subsist, the hydrostatical
 law of the equality of pressure being only true of fluids in a state of undisturbed
 equilibrium. If the whole contents of the fissures, pipes, &c., into which
 we may consider the interior divided, were lava, it is true no increase of pressure
 on the bed of an ocean, from deposited matter, could force the lava up to a
 higher level than the surface, or so high. But if the contents be partly liquid,
 partly gaseous, or partly water, in a state to become steam, at a diminished
 pressure, then it may happen that the joint specific gravity of lava + gas,
 or lava+ steam occupying any given channel may be less than that of water;
 or of the joint column of water + newly deposited matter—which may be brought
 to press upon it by any sudden giving way of support, and the effect will be
 the escape of a mixture of lava and gas, either together, as froth and pumice,
 or by fits, according as they are disposed in the channel. This (taken as a
 general cause of volcanoes) would account for the great quantity of gaseous
 matter which always accompanies eruptions, and for the final blow out of
 wind and dust with which they so often terminate. It has always been my greatest
 difficulty in Geology to find a primum mobile for the volcano, taken
 as a general, not a local phenomenon. Davy's speculations about the oxidation
 of the alkaline metals seems to me a mere chemical dream, and the fermentation
 of water and pyrites as utterly insignificant on a scale of any
[page] 229
 magnitude. Poulett Scrope's notion
 of solid rocks flashing out into lava and vapour, on removal of pressure, and your statement of the probable cause of Volcanic Eruptions, in p. 385,
 vol. ii. 4th Ed. when you speak of the effect of a minute hole bored in a tube,
 in which liquefied gases are imprisoned, both appear to me wanting in explicitness,
 and as not going high enough in the inquiry, up to its true beginning, and also
 as giving, in some respects, a wrong notion of the process itself. The question
 stares us in the face—How came the gases to be so condensed? Why did they submit
 to be urged into liquefaction? If they were not originally elastic, but have
 become so by subterranean heat, whence came the heat? and why did it come
 ? How came the pressure to be removed, or what caused the crack? &c.
 &c. It seems clear that if the gases, or aqueous vapour, were once free,
 at so high a degree of elasticity as is presumed, there exists no adequate cause
 for their confinement,—the spring once uncoiled, there is nowhere a power capable
 of bending it up to the pitch. We are forced therefore to admit, that the elastic
 force has been superadded to them, during their sojourn below, by an accession
 of temperature. Now, though I cannot agree with you in your view of the subject
 of the Central heat, p. 373, vol. ii. 4th Ed. (because I see no reason why the
 heat may not
[page] 230
go on increasing to the very
 centre without necessitating such disturbance of equilibrium as to give
 rise to any circulation of currents, which you there seem to regard as the necessary
 consequence of such a state*), yet I agree entirely with what you observe in
 p. 376, that—the ordinary repose of the surface argues a wonderful inertness
 in the interior, where, in fact, I conceive that every thing is motionless.
 Under these circumstances, and debarred from that obvious means of boiling our
 pot, the invasion of a circulating current, or casual injection of intensely
 hot liquid matter from below, the question, ' Whence comes the heat T and
 ' Why did it come? remains to be answered on sound theoretical grounds.
 Now, the answer I conceive to be as follows:—
"Granting an equilibrium of temperature
 and pressure within the globe, the isothermal strata near the centre will be
 spherical, but where they approach the surface will, by degrees, conform themselves
 to the configuration of the solid portion; that is, to the bottom of
 the sea and the surface of continents. Suppose such a state of equilibrium,
 and that under
* "Heated liquids circulate not
 because the lower parts are hotter, but because they are lighter, than the upper. But in the interior of a heated globe, the density depends
 not only on the temperature, but on the pressure (i. e. the depth) of
 each stratum; so that nothing is easier than to imagine a law of increasing
 temperature which shall co-exist with increasing density.
[page] 231
 the bottom B of my great ocean
 D E, the isothermal strata are as represented by the black lines.

 Now, let that basin be filled with 
 solid matter up to A. Immediately the equilibrium of temperature will be disturbed.
 Why?—because the form of a stratum of temperature depends essentially on the
 form of the bounding surface of the solid above it, that form being one of the
 arbitrary functions which enter into its partial differential equation. Immediately,
 therefore, the temperature will begin to migrate from below upwards, and the
 isothermal strata will gradually change their forms from the black to the dotted
 lines. The lowest portions at B will then (after the lapse of ages, and when
 a fresh state of equilibrium is attained) have acquired the temperature of the
 stratum C, corresponding to their then actual depth, while a point as
 deep below B as C is below the surface, will have
[page] 232
 acquired a much higher temperature,
 and may become actually melted, and that without any bodily transfer of matter
 in a liquid state from below. But if C be already at the melting point,
 B will now be so—i. e. the lower level will attain B, and the bottom of the
 new strata will melt, water included, with which, from the circumstances
 of the case, they must be saturated. " Now, let the process of deposition go
 on, until, by accumulation of pressure on the bottom or sloping sides, or on
 some protuberance from the bottom, some support gives way—a piece of the solid
 crust breaks down, and is plunged into the liquid below, and a crack takes place
 extending upwards. Into this the liquid will rise by simple hydrostatic pressure.
 But as it gains height, it is less pressed; and if it attain such a height
 that the ignited water can become steam, the case before alluded to arises,
 the joint specific gravity of the column is suddenly diminished, and up comes
 a jet of mixed steam and lava, till so much has escaped that the deposited matter
 takes a fresh bearing, when the evacuation ceases, and the crack becomes sealed
 up. " In the analysis I have above given of the process of heating from below,
 we have, if I mistake not, a strictly theoretical account of that great desideratum
 of the Huttonian theory—' Let heat,' says he,
[page] 233
' invade a newly deposited
 stratum from below.'— But why? Not because great currents of melted matter
 are circulating in the nucleus of the globe— not because great waves of caloric
 are rushing to and fro, without a law and without a cause in the subterranean
 regions—but simply because the fact of new strata having been deposited,
 alters the conditions of the equilibrium of temperature, and they draw the heat
 to them, or, which comes to the same thing, retain it in them in its
 transit outwards (the supply from the centre being supposed inexhaustible, and
 its temperature of course invariable).
 " According to the general tenor
 of your book, we may conclude, that the greatest transfer of material to the
 bottom of the ocean, is produced at the coast line by the action of the sea; and that the quantity carried down by rivers from the surface of continents,
 is comparatively trifling. While, therefore, the greatest local accumulation
 of pressure is in the central area of deep seas, the greatest local relief takes place along the abraded coast lines. Here, then, in this view, should
 ccur the chief volcanic vents. If the view I have taken of the motionless state
 of the interior of the earth be correct, there appears no reason why any such
 influx of heat should take place under an existing continent (say Scandinavia)
 as to heat incumbent rocks (whose bases retain their level) 5 or 600 Fahr,
 for many miles in thickness. (Princ. of Geol.
[page] 234
 vol. ii. p. 384.4th Ed.) Laplace's*
 idea of the elevation of surface due to columnar expansion (which you attribute,
 in a note, to Babbage,) is in this view inadequate to explain the rise of Scandinavia,
 or of the Andes, &c. But, in the variation of local pressure due to the
 transfer of matter by the sea, on the bed of an ocean imperfectly and unequally
 supported, it seems to me an adequate cause may be found. Let A be Scandinavia,
 B the adjacent ocean (the North Sea), C a vast deposit, newly laid on the original
 bed D of the ocean; E E E a semi-fluid, or mixed

 mass, on which D D D reposes. What
 will be the effect of the enormous weight thus added to the bed DDD (rock being
 heavier than sea)? Of course,
* " Nisi Mitscherlich's. I remember
 well to have read it somewhere other."
[This was written before my friend
 had received the abstract of the paper on the Temple of Serapis, forwarded to
 him by Mr. Lyell. The reader will perceive, by Note G. of the Appendix, that isothermal sur..es form the prominent feature of both our views of this
 question.—C. B.]
[page] 235
 to depress D under it, and to force
 it down into the yielding mass E, a portion of which will be driven laterally
 under the continent A, and upheave it. Lay a weight on a surface of soft clay: you depress it below, and raise it around the weight. If the surface of the
 clay be dry and hard, it will crack in the change of figure." " I don't know
 whether I have made clear to you ray notions about the effects of the removal
 of matter from above, to below, the sea. 1st. It produces a mechanical subversion
 of the equilibrium of pressure. 2dly. It also, and by a different process
 (as above explained at large), produces a subversion of the equilibrium of temperature.
 The last is the most important. It must be an excessively slow process, and
 will depend, 1st, on the depth of matter deposited; 2dly, on the quantity of
 water retained by it under the great squeeze it has got; 3dly, on the tenacity
 of the incumbent mass—whether the influx of caloric from below, which must take
 place, acting on that water, shall either heave up the whole mass, as a continent,
 or shall crack it, and escape as a submarine volcano, or shall be suppressed
 until the mere weight of the continually accumulating mass breaks its lateral
 supports at or near the coast lines, and opens there a chain of volcanoes.
[page] 236
 " Thus the circuit is kept up—the primum mobile is the degrading power of the sea and rains (both originating
 in the sun's action) above, and the inexhaustible supply of heat from the enormous
 reservoirs below, always escaping at the surface, unless when repressed by an
 addition of fresh clothing, at any particular part. In this view of the subject,
 the tendency is outwards. Every continent deposited has a propensity
 to rise again; and the destructive principle is continually counterbalanced
 by a re-organizing principle from beneath. Nay, it may go farther—there may
 be such a tendency in the globe to swell into froth at its surface, as may maintain
 its dimensions in spite of its expense of heat; and thus preserve the uniformity
 of its rotation on its axis, in spite of the doctrines of refrigeration and
 contraction, (which, by the bye, had occurred to myself, and been rejected,
 as inadequat to give a general formula of explanation of volcanoes, &c.)
 Perhaps I shall recur to this subject on some future occasion; but really the
 stars leave me very little time to lick into form any geological theories, or
 even to examine them with any degree of scrupulous severity." II. The following
 is the copy of a letter from Sir John Herschel to Mr. Murchison, in explanation
 of the views expressed in his previous letter to Mr. Lyell.
[page] 237
 " Feldhausen, Cape of Good Hope, Nov. 15,1836.
 " In the letter you allude to as
 having been written by me to Mr. Lyell, there were some speculations about the
 effect of central heat on newly-deposited matter, which, judging from some expressions
 in his answer to that letter, I am inclined to think must have been put obscurely,
 since he appears disposed to regard the view I took of the subject as identical
 with some theory ascribed to Mr. Babbage (but, I believe, before propounded
 by Mitscherlich) about the elevation of strata by pyrometric expansion of
 the subjacent columns of rock, by an invasion of subterraneous heat. Granting
 the heat, there is no difficulty in deducing expansions, disruptions, tumefactions,
 &c.; but this was not my drift. Will it be trespassing too much
 on your patience if I here state, in brief, what I really had in view—which,
 so far as I can recollect, has not hitherto been duly, or not at all, considered
 ? If you like to call it my ' theory,' you may do so; but it is not so much
 'a theory,' as a pursuing into its consequences, according to admitted laws,
 of the hypothesis of a high central temperature, which many geologists admit,
 and all are familiar with. " Granting, then, as a postulate, a gradation of
 temperature within the globe, from the observed external temperature at the
 surface, up to a high state
[page] 238
 of incandescence at the centre: I say, that when solid matter comes to be deposited to any considerable thickness
 on any part of the bed of the ocean, by subsidence, (or even on the surface
 of a continent, by volcanic ejection, as in great volcanic plateaux and table-lands,
 or by the action of the wind,.as in sand hills,) the mere fact of such accession
 of materials, without requiring any other condition, or concomitant cause, will, of itself, in virtue of the known laws of the propagation of heat
 through a slowly-conducting mass, immediately subvert the equilibrium of temperature,
 and induce a change in the form of the isothermal surfaces (curves of equal
 temperature) in the whole region immediately beneath, and surrounding the point
 of deposition—causing all those surfaces (which, you will observe, are only
 imaginary mathematical ones, like lines of equal variation in a magnetic chart—not
 real strata) to bulge outwards, and recede from the centre in that part. The
 direct consequence of this will be, that any given point of the surface on which
 the deposit took place will, when a new state of equilibrium is attained, (supposing
 it to be so) have a temperature corresponding to an isothermal surface of
 a deeper order: i. e., it will have become hotter than it was previous
 to the new deposit; and the same is true of every point in the vertical line
 drawn from that point downwards. Supposing, as before said, a new state of equilibrium
 to be attained, (the deposition ceasing, by the filling up
[page] 239
 of the sea in that part) then the
 temperature of the lowest parts of the newly-formed strata will be that of a
 point situated beneath the surface of an old continent in the same latitude,
 at a depth equal to the thickness of the deposited matter. The thicker, therefore,
 the deposit, the hotter will its lower portions tend to grow; and, if thick
 enough, they may grow red hot,or even melt. In the latter case, their
 supports being also melted or softened, may wholly or partially yield, under
 the new circumstances of pressure, to which they were originally not adjusted;
 and the phenomena of earthquakes, volcanic explosions, &c., may arrive—while,
 on the other hand, if no cracks occur, and all goes on in quiet, the only consequence
 will be, the obliteration of organic remains, and lines of stratification, &c.—the
 formation of new combinations of a chemical nature, &c. &c.—in a word,
 the production of Lyell's ' metamorphic-' rocks. " The process described above
 is precisely that by which a man's skin grows warmer in a winter day by putting
 on an additional great coat; the flow of heat outwards is obstructed, and the
 surface of congelation carried to a distance from his person, by the accumulation
 of heat thereby caused beneath by the new covering. " You see, therefore, that
 my object is to get at a geological ' primum mobile? in the nature of
 a vera
[page] 240
causa, and to trace its working
 in a distinct and intelligible manner. In future, therefore, instead of saying,
 as heretofore, 'Let heat from below invade newly-deposited strata
 (Heaven knows how or why), then they will melt, expand,' &c. &c., we
 shall commence a step higher, and say, ' Let strata be deposited.' Then,
 as a necessary consequence, and according to known, regular, and calculable
 laws, heat will gradually invade them from below and around; and, according
 to its due degree of intensity at any assigned time, will expand, ignite, or
 melt them, as the case may be, &c. &c. &c.; and, I mistake greatly,
 if this be not a considerable reform in our geological language.
 " According to this view of the
 matter, there is nothing casual in the formation of Metamorphic Rocks. All strata,
 once buried deep enough, (and due time allowed! ! !) must assume that state,—none
 can escape. All records of former worlds must ultimately perish. " P.S.—If you
 think it worth while to read the above speculation whenever a discussion may
 arise, naturally leading to it, at any meeting of the Geological Society, (not
 as a formal communication, for I have not time to put it into shape, or work
 it out in detail, but incidentally) you are quite at liberty to do so; and
 I shall be glad to know your own opinion of it."
[page] 241
 Since the first edition of this
 work was published, Mr. Lyell has received another letter from Sir John Herschel,
 explanatory of his views on this subject; and I am happy to place before the
 reader the following extracts, not because there is any necessity to prove that
 my friend arrived independently at the same conclusions with myself, but because
 they afford additional illustrations of a view which we both think deserving
 of further inquiry. This letter was written by Sir John Herschel previously
 to the receipt of the first edition of this volume, which I had forwarded to
 him at the Cape of Good Hope.
" Feldhausen, June 12, 1837.
 " I reply to your note, however,
 immediately, " because there are points in it, and in a letter of " Murchison's
 I lately received, but especially in " yours, which call for immediate notice
 on my part, " lest I should be supposed to have willingly and " knowingly, what
 our French neighbours call, " ' emprunté des idées,'—appropriated
 the ideas of " Babbage; to which charge should any one feel " disposed to bring
 it (B. I am sure will not), I plead " not guilty. Till the arrival of Murchison's
 letter, " in fact, I was utterly unaware that Babbage had (or " any body else)
 speculated on that peculiar mutual
[page] 242
 reaction of the surface and interior
 of the globe, which consists in what, I think, we 'must now call ' the secular
 variation of the isothermal surfaces ' of the latter. The idea I considered
 as entirely my own; and I was never more taken by surprise, than when to-day,
 directed for the first time by an express mention in your letter of a paper
 of Babbage's, abstracted in the Geological Notices, I hunted up all those notices
 in my possession, and found in an uncut Number (No. 36,)—as I am sorry to say
 many of these, and other not less interesting brochures which have reached me,
 still are— an abstract of a paper on the Temple of Serapis, at the end of which
 a theory identical with mine in that leading point, undoubtedly stands printed.
 " Convinced as I feel of the great importance of this general view of geological
 revolutions, in contrast with all the arbitrary, local, and temporary expedients
 which have hitherto been resorted to to explain particular phenomena, and to
 the recourse had to ' the volcano and the earthquake,' as the great explaining
 powers; whereas in this view, these are only symptomatic phenomena, natural
 and necessary concomitants of systems of action much more extensive, which are
 constantly going forwards. ...But as I do, at all events, lay claim to absolute
 independence of speculation on the subject, it is quite right that I should
 make clear to you and to
[page] 243
 ' him the progress of my own ideas,
 and also account: for what must have appeared singular in my own; mention of his speculations in my letter to Murchison. And to take
 the last first:—The fact is, that I never was aware that Babbage had made any communication to the Geological Society on the subject, till Murchison's
 letter first led me to suppose, and yours expressly stated, by referring to
 the Proceedings for an abstract, that such was the case. The passage in your
 book and note appended, (Vol. II. p. 383, 4th Edit.) contain no allusion to
 the cause of rocks becoming heated from below. The employment of the
 pyrometric expansion of rocks as a motive power, was, I feel confident, suggested
 by some one (and the name of Mitscherlich or Laplace, has somehow
 got connected in my memory with it) many years ago, certainly before 1833. Of
 this B. must have been as ignorant as I was of his views, as he appears to have
 based his ideas on Colonel Tottens'* experiments (when made I know not). And
 I only remembered to have read Babbage's paper on the Temple of Serapis, published
 in one of the quarterly journals not long after his arrival from the Continent,
 in which, so far as I recollect, this point is not touched upon; nor is it
 in your speech from the chair, where alternate pyrometric expansion and contraction,
 without reference
* The origin of my view is stated
 in the first paragraph of this Note.
[page] 244
to the cause of the invasion or
 abstraction of heat, are alone alluded to.
" However, discussion of points
 of this sort is of little moment in itself; as, if a theory be founded in sound
 views, it matters little to the world whether A. or B. or A. and B.
 first entertained it, or whether it arose in the whole alphabet when its seeds
 were ready to germinate. As regards the course of my own ideas, it was simply
 this. When I first read your book, I was struck with your views of the metamorphic
 rocks, and I began to speculate how and why the mere fact of deep burial might
 tend to raise their temperature to the required point. Three modes occurred:—1st. Development of heat by condensation; but this cause seemed somewhat
 feeble, and not very clear in its mode of action, since at every moment an equilibrium
 of pressure and resistance is established. 2dly. Plunging down into an ignited
 pasty mass; here however, considering the excessive slowness of the process,
 it occurred to me that there would be plenty of time for the ignited matter
 below, not merely to divide its caloric with the newly superposed mass, but
 to take up fresh from below, and thus to establish a regular gradation of temperature
 from below upwards. And this led to the 3d and more general view of the matter,
 which is that of the variation of isothermal surfaces, as stated in my letters
 to Murchison and yourself.
[page] 245
 " These notions had been fermenting
 and regurgitating in the cavities of my brain, from the moment I first read
 your statement of the metamorphic doctrine in your first edition; but what
 determined the disruption of the incumbent stratum, and their final explosion,
 was the reperusal of your little 12mo. edition you were so good as to send me.
 " All things considered, however, I do not regret having written what I did: and I am still so far disposed to regard it as publici juris, as to
 wish that such passages in my letters as yourself and Murchison may think eligible
 for the purpose, might on some fitting opportunity be read at a meeting of the
 Geological Society. (All idea of my drawing up a regular paper is out of the
 question, I am so involved in other matters at present.) It will draw attention
 to the subject, and science will gain by the discussion. " When people think
 independently at different times, and excited by different original subjects
 of consideration, bearing on one more general object, if their ideas converge
 towards one view of the matter, it is a proof that there is something worthy
 of further inquiry; and if they think to any purpose, it is hardly possible
 but that many points will occur to each, which do not to the other, and that
 so a theory may branch out and acquire a body much
[page] 246
sooner than it would do by the speculations
 of one alone;—and indeed such is in some degree the case in the present instance.
 Babbage, for example, has speculated not only on the heaping on of matter in
 some parts, but on its abstraction in others, as a cause of variation in the
 isothermal surface;—and justly; it is a case of the algebraic passage from
 + to — passing through 0. In envisaging (as the French call it) the question
 algebraically, the cases could not be separated. Again, he has confined himself
 to the pyrometric changes in the solid strata, while I have left these out of
 view, and relied on what I think to be a far more energetic and widely acting
 cause—the variation of pressure, and the infirmity of supports broken by weight
 or softened by heat, to produce tilts. Both causes, however, doubtless
 act, and both must be considered in further detail: the former alone may
 account for the phenomena of the Bay of Naples; the latter must, I think, be
 called into account for those of Scandinavia and Greenland, and of the Andes.
 " I would observe that a central
 heat may or may not exist for our purposes. And it seems to be a demonstrated
 fact, that temperature does, in all parts of the earth's surface yet
 examined, increase in going down towards the centre, in what I almost
 feel disposed to call a frightfully rapid progression; and though that
 rapidity may cease, and the progression even
[page] 247
 take a contrary direction, long
 before we reach the; centre, (as it might do, for instance, had
 the earth, originally cold, been, as Poisson supposes, kept for a few billions
 or trillions of years, in a firmament full of burning suns, besetting every
 outlet of heat, and then launched into our cooler milky way) still, as all we
 want is no more than a heat sufficient to melt silex, &c. I do not think
 we need trouble ourselves with any inquiries of the sort, but take it for granted,
 that a very moderate plunge downwards, in proportion to the earth's radius,
 will do all we want. Nay, the internal heat may even be locally unequal; i.
 e. great in Europe and Asia, small under America, —as it would, for example,
 if, when roasting at Poisson's sun-fire, the great jack of the universe had
 stood still, and allowed one side of our terraqueous joint to scorch, and the
 other to remain underdone. —A hint to those who are on the look out for a cause
 (if any such there be) for the ' poles of maximum cold,' and the general inferior
 temperature of the American climate, from end to end of that continent."
[page] 248
NOTE K.
ON THE ELEVATION
 OF BEACHES BY TIDES.
if the earth were a spheroid of
 revolution, covered by one uniform ocean, two great tidal waves would follow
 each other round the globe at a distance of twelve hours.
Suppose several high narrow strips
 of land were now to encircle the globe, passing through the opposite poles,
 and dividing the earth's surface into several great unequal oceans, a separate
 tide would be raised in each. When the tidal wave had reached the farthest shore
 of one of them, conceive the causes that produce it to cease; then the wave
 thus raised would recede to the opposite shore, and continue to oscillate until
 destroyed by the friction of its bed. But if, instead of ceasing to act, the
 causes which produced the tide were to
[page] 249
 reappear at the opposite shore
 of the ocean, at the very moment when the reflected tide had returned to the
 place of its origin; then the second tide would act in augmentation of the
 first, and, if this continued, tides of great height might be produced for ages.
 The result might be, that the narrow ridge dividing the adjacent oceans would
 be broken through, and the tidal wave traverse a broader tract than in the former
 ocean. Let us imagine the new ocean to be just so much broader than the old,
 that the reflected tide would return to the origin of the tidal movement half
 a tide later than before: then, instead of two superimposed tides, we should
 have a tide arising from the subtraction of one from the other. The alterations
 of the height of the tides on shores so circumstanced, might be very small;
 and this might again continue for ages: thus causing beaches to be raised at
 very different elevations, without any real alteration in the level either of
 the sea or land. If we consider the superposition of derivative tides, similar
 effects might be found to result; and it deserves inquiry, whether it may not
 be possible to account for some remarkable and well-attested phenomena by such
 means. The gradual elevation during the past century, of one portion of the
 Swedish coast above the Baltic, is a recognised fact, and has lately been verified
 by
[page] 250
 Mr. Lyell.* It is not probable,
 from the form and position of that sea, that two tides should reach it distant
 by exactly half the interval of a tide, and thus produce a very small tide;
 nor is it likely that by the gradual but slow erosion of the longer channel,
 one tide should almost imperceptibly advance upon the other: but it becomes
 an interesting question to examine whether, in other places, under such peculiar
 circumstances, it might not be possible that a series of observations of the
 heights of tides at two distant periods, might give a different position for
 the mean level of the sea at places so situated. If we conceive two tides to
 meet at any point, one of which is twelve hours later than the other, the elevation
 of the waters will arise from the joint influence of both. Let us suppose, that
 from the abrasion of the channel, the later tide arrives each time one-hundredth
 of a second earlier than before. After about 3,150 years, the high water of
 the earlier tide will coincide in point of time with the low water of the later
 tide: and the difference of height between high and low water will be equal
 to the difference of the height of the two tides, instead of to thei sum, as
 it was at the first epoch. If, in such circumstances, the two tides were nearly
* See Phil. Trans. 1836.
[page] 251
 equal in magnitude, it might happen
 that on a coast so circumstanced, there would at one time be scarcely any perceptible
 tide; and yet, 3000 years after, the tide might rise 30 or 40 feet, or even
 higher; and this would happen without any change of relative height in the land
 and water during the intervening time. Possibly this view of the effects which
 may arise, either from the wearing down of channels, or the filling up of seas
 through which tides pass, may be applied to explain some of the phenomena of
 raised beaches, which are of frequent occurrence. Natural philosophers are at
 present not quite agreed upon the mode of determining the mean level of the
 ocean. Whether it is to be deduced from the averages between the highest and
 lowest spring tide, or from the averages of all the intermediate ones, or from
 the means of the instantaneous heights of the tide at all intervening periods—or
 by whatever other process, its true level is yet to be ascertained. It may,
 perhaps, also be useful to suggest that, besides the actual level of the sea
 at any particular place, it would be also desirable to ascertain whether the
 time of high water at given epochs is not itself a changeable quantity, These
 reflections, however, are only thrown out with the view of exciting discussion
 on a subject involved at present in great mathematical difficulties, and possessing,
 at the same time, the highest practical importance.
[page] 252
NOTE L.
ON RIPPLE-MARK.
the small waves raised on the surface
 of the water, by the passage of a slight breeze, are called Ripple; and a series
 of marks, very similar in appearance, which are sometimes seen at low water
 on the flat part of a sea-beach formed of fine sand, are called ripple-marks.
 Such marks occur in various strata of stone, and at various depths below the
 solid surface of the globe, and are regarded as evidence of their having been
 formed beneath the sea. Similar appearances occur when a strong wind drives
 over the face of a sandy plain, and are frequently seen upon the surface of
 snow.
It appears that two fluids of different
 specific gravity, the lighter passing over the surface of the former, always
 concur in the formation of ripple. It seems also
[page] 253
 that the lines of ripple-mark are
 at right angles to the direction of the current which forms them. If a fluid
 like air pass over the surface of perfectly quiescent water, in a plain absolutely
 parallel, it will have no effect; but if it impinge on the surface of the water
 with the slightest inclination, it will raise a small wave, which will be propagated
 by undulations to great distances. If the direction of the wind is very nearly
 parallel to the surface, this first wave, being raised above the general surface,
 will protect that part of the water immediately beyond it from the full effect
 of the wind, which will therefore again impinge upon the water at a little distance: and, this impact concurring with the undulation, will tend to produce another
 small wave, and thus, new waves will be produced. But the under surface of the
 air itself will also during this process assume the form of waves, and so, on
 the slightest deviation at any one point from absolute parallelism in the two
 fluids, their whole surfaces will become covered with ripples. If one of the
 fluids be water, and the lower fluid be fine sand, partially suspended in water,
 these marks do not disappear when the cause ceases to act, as they do when formed
 by movement of air over the surface of water; but they remain and form the
 ridges or ripple which we observe when the tide has receded from a flat,
 sandy shore.
[page] 254
 If, after the formation of ripple-marks
 at the bottom of a shallow sea, some adjacent river or some current deposit
 upon them the mud which it holds in suspension, then the first marks will be
 preserved, and new ripple marks may appear above them. Such is the origin of
 those marks we observe in various sand-stones, from the most recent down to
 those of the coal measures. Dr. Fitton informs me, that the sand hills on the
 south of Etapies (in France) consist of ripple-marks produced by the wind on
 a very large scale. They are crescent-shaped hillocks, many of which are more
 than a hundred feet high. The height is greatest in the middle of the crescents,
 declining towards the points; and the slope on the inner side of the crescent,
 which is remote from the prevailing direction of the winds, is much more rapid
 than that on which it strikes. Mr. Lyell has observed and described this mode
 of formation of ripple on the dunes of sand near Calais; remarking, that in
 that case there is an actual lateral transfer; the grains of sand being carried
 by the wind up the less inclined slope of the ripple, and falling over the steep
 scarp. I have observed the same fact at Swansea. A similar explanation seems
 to present itself as the origin of that form of clouds familiarly known as "a mackarel sky"—a wave-like appearance, which pro-
[page] 255
 bably arises from the passage of
 a current of air above or below a thin stratum of clouds. The air, being of
 nearly the same specific gravity as that of the cloud it acts upon, would produce
 ripple of larger size than would otherwise occur. The surface of the sun presents
 to very good telescopes a certain mottled appearance, which is not exactly ripple,
 and which it is difficult to convey by description. It may, however, be suggested,
 that wherever such appearances occur, whether in planetary or in stellar bodies,
 or in the minuter precincts of the dye-house and the engine-boiler, they indicate
 the fitness of an inquiry, whether there are not two currents of fluid or semi-fluid
 matter, one moving with a different velocity over the other, the direction of
 the motion being at right angles to the lines of waves
[page] 256
 NOTE M.
ON THE AGE OF STRATA,
 AS INFERRED FROM THE RINGS OF TREES EMBEDDED IN THEM.
 THE indelible records of past events which are preserved within the solid
 substance of our globe, may be in some measure understood without the aid of
 that refined analysis on which a complete acquaintance with them depends. The
 remains of vegetation, and of animal life, embedded in their coeval rocks, attest
 the existence of far distant times; and as science and the arts advance, we
 shall be enabled to read the minuter details of their living history. The object
 of the present note is to suggest to the reader a line of inquiry, by which
 we may still trace some small portion of the history of the past in the fossil
 woods which occur in so many of our strata. It is well known that dicotyledonous
 trees increase in size by the deposition of an additional layer annually
[page] 257
 between the wood and the bark,
 and that a transverse section of such trees presents a series of nearly concentric
 though irregular rings, the number of which indicates the age of the tree. The
 relative thickness of these rings depends on the more or less flourishing state
 of the plant during the years in which they were formed. Each ring may, in some
 trees, be observed to be subdivided into others, thus indicating successive
 periods of the same year during which its vegetation was advanced or checked.
 These rings are disturbed in certain parts by irregularities resulting from
 branches; and the year in which each branch first sprung from the parent stock
 may be ascertained by proper sections. It has been found by experiment, that
 even the motion imparted to a tree by the winds has an influence on its growth.
 Two young trees of equal size and vigour were selected and planted in similar
 circumstances, except that one was restrained from having any motion in the
 direction of the meridian, by two strong ropes fixed to it, and connecting it
 to the ground, at some distance towards the north and south. The other tree
 was by similar means prevented from having any motion in the direction of east
 and west. After several years, both trees were cut down, and the sections of
 their stems were found to be oval; but the longer axis of the oval of each was
 in the direction in which it had been capable of being moved by the winds.</div></body></text></TEI>