<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="64">CHAPTER III.
Discovery of the Law of Dispersion by
Refraction.
EARLY attempts were made to
account for the colors of the rainbow, and various other phenomena in
which colors are seen to arise from transient and unsubstantial
combinations of media. Thus Aristotle explains the colors of the
rainbow by supposing9 that it is light seen through a dark
medium: “Now,” says he, “the bright seen through the dark appears red,
as, for instance, the fire of green wood seen through the smoke, and
the sun through mist. Also10 the weaker is the light, or the visual
power, and the nearer the color approaches to the black; becoming
first red, then green, then purple. But11 the 59 vision is strongest in
the outer circle, because the periphery is greater;—thus we
shall have a gradation from red, through green, to purple, in passing
from the outer to the inner circle.” This account would hardly have
deserved much notice, if it had not been for a strange attempt to
revive it, or something very like it, in modern times. The same
doctrine is found in the work of De Dominis.12 According to
him, light is white: but if we mix with the light something dark, the
colors arise,—first red, then green, then blue or violet. He
applies this to explain the colors of the rainbow,13 by means of the
consideration that, of the rays which come to the eye from the globes
of water, some go through a larger thickness of the globe than others,
whence he obtains the gradation of colors just described.
9 Meteor. iii. 3, p. 373.
10 Ib. p. 374.
11 Ib. p. 375.
12 Cap. iii. p. 9. See also Göthe,
Farbenl. vol. ii. p. 251.
13 Göthe, p. 263.
Descartes came far nearer the true philosophy of the iridal colors.
He found that a similar series of colors was produced by refraction of
light bounded by shade, through a prism;14 and he rightly
inferred that neither the curvature of the surface of the drops of
water, nor the reflection, nor the repetition of refraction, were
necessary to the generation of such colors. In further examining the
course of the rays, he approaches very near to the true conception of
the case; and we are led to believe that he might have anticipated
Newton in his discovery of the unequal refrangibility of different
colors, if it had been possible for him to reason any otherwise than
in the terms and notions of his preconceived hypotheses. The
conclusion which he draws is,15 that “the
particles of the subtile matter which transmit the action of light,
endeavor to rotate with so great a force and impetus, that they cannot
move in a straight line (whence comes refraction): and that those
particles which endeavor to revolve much more strongly produce a red
color, those which endeavor to move only a little more strongly
produce yellow.” Here we have a clear perception that colors and
unequal refraction are connected, though the cause of refraction is
expressed by a gratuitous hypothesis. And we may add, that he applies
this notion rightly, so far as he explains himself,16 to account for the colors of the
rainbow.
14 Meteor. Sect. viii. p.
190.
15 Sect. vii. p. 192.
16 Meteor. Sect. ix.
It appears to me that Newton and others have done Descartes
injustice, in ascribing to De Dominis the true theory of the rainbow.
There are two main points of this theory, namely, the showing that a
bright circular band, of a certain definite diameter, arises
from the 60 great
intensity of the light returned at a certain angle; and the referring
the different colors to the different quantity of the
refraction; and both these steps appear indubitably to be the
discoveries of Descartes. And he informs us that these discoveries
were not made without some exertion of thought. “At first,” he says,17 “I doubted whether the iridal colors
were produced in the same way as those in the prism; but, at last,
taking my pen, and carefully calculating the course of the rays which
fell on each part of the drop, I found that many more come at an angle
of forty-one degrees, than either at a greater or a less angle. So
that there is a bright bow terminated by a shade; and hence the colors
are the same as those produced through a prism.”
17 Sect. ix. p. 193.
The subject was left nearly in the same state, in the work of
Grimaldi, Physico-Mathesis, de Lumine, Coloribus et Iride,
published at Bologna in 1665. There is in this work a constant
reference to numerous experiments, and a systematic exposition of the
science in an improved state. The author’s calculations concerning the
rainbow are put in the same form as those of Descartes; but he is
further from seizing the true principle on which its coloration
depends. He rightly groups together a number of experiments in which
colors arise from refraction;18 and explains
them by saying that the color is brighter where the light is denser:
and the light is denser on the side from which the refraction turns
the ray, because the increments of refraction are greater in the rays
that are more inclined.19 This way of treating the question might
be made to give a sort of explanation of most of the facts, but is
much more erroneous than a developement of Descartes’s view would have
been.
18 Prop. 35, p. 254.
19 Ib. p. 256.
At length, in 1672, Newton gave20 the true
explanation of the facts; namely, that light consists of rays of
different colors and different refrangibility. This now appears to us
so obvious a mode of interpreting the phenomena, that we can hardly
understand how they can be conceived in any other manner; but yet the
impression which this discovery made, both upon Newton and upon his
contemporaries, shows how remote it was from the then accepted
opinions. There appears to have been a general persuasion that the
coloration was produced, not by any peculiarity in the law of
refraction itself but by some collateral circumstance,—some
dispersion or variation of density of the light, in addition to the
refraction. Newton’s discovery consisted in 61 teaching distinctly that the law of
refraction was to be applied, not to the beam of light in general, but
to the colors in particular.
20 Phil. Trans. t. vii. p.
3075.
When Newton produced a bright spot on the wall of his chamber, by
admitting the sun’s light through a small hole in his window-shutter,
and making it pass through a prism, he expected the image to be round;
which, of course, it would have been, if the colors had been produced
by an equal dispersion in all directions; but to his surprise he saw
the image, or spectrum, five times as long as it was broad. He
found that no consideration of the different thickness of the glass,
the possible unevenness of its surface, or the different angles of
rays proceeding from the two sides of the sun, could be the cause of
this shape. He found, also, that the rays did not go from the prism to
the image in curves; he was then convinced that the different colors
were refracted separately, and at different angles; and he confirmed
this opinion by transmitting and refracting the rays of each color
separately.
The experiments are so easy and common, and Newton’s interpretation
of them so simple and evident, that we might have expected it to
receive general assent; indeed, as we have shown, Descartes had
already been led very near the same point. In fact, Newton’s opinions
were not long in obtaining general acceptance; but they met with
enough of cavil and misapprehension to annoy extremely the discoverer,
whose clear views and quiet temper made him impatient alike of
stupidity and of contentiousness.
We need not dwell long on the early objections which were made to
Newton’s doctrine. A Jesuit, of the name of Ignatius Pardies,
professor at Clermont, at first attempted to account for the
elongation of the image by the difference of the angles made by the
rays from the two edges of the sun, which would produce a difference
in the amount of refraction of the two borders; but when Newton
pointed out the calculations which showed the insufficiency of this
explanation, he withdrew his opposition. Another more pertinacious
opponent appeared in Francis Linus, a physician of Liege; who
maintained, that having tried the experiment, he found the sun’s
image, when the sky was clear, to be round and not oblong; and he
ascribed the elongation noticed by Newton, to the effect of clouds.
Newton for some time refused to reply to this contradiction of his
assertions, though obstinately persisted in; and his answer was at
last sent, just about the time of Linus’s death, in 1675. But
Gascoigne, a friend of Linus, still maintained that he and others had
seen what the Dutch physician had described; and Newton, who was
pleased with the candor of 62 Gascoigne’s letter, suggested that the
Dutch experimenters might have taken one of the images reflected from
the surfaces of the prism, of which there are several, instead of the
proper refracted one. By the aid of this hint, Lucas of Liege repeated
Newton’s experiments, and obtained Newton’s result, except that he
never could obtain a spectrum whose length was more than three and a
half times its breadth. Newton, on his side, persisted in asserting
that the image would be five times as long as it was broad, if the
experiment were properly made. It is curious that he should have been
so confident of this, as to conceive himself certain that such would
be the result in all cases. We now know that the dispersion, and
consequently the length, of the spectrum, is very different for
different kinds of glass, and it is very probable that the Dutch prism
was really less dispersive than the English one.21 The erroneous
assumption which Newton made in this instance, he held by to the last;
and was thus prevented from making the discovery of which we have next
to speak.
21 Brewster’s Newton, p.
50.
Newton was attacked by persons of more importance than those we
have yet mentioned; namely, Hooke and Huyghens. These philosophers,
however, did not object so much to the laws of refraction of different
colors, as to some expressions used by Newton, which, they conceived,
conveyed false notions respecting the composition and nature of light.
Newton had asserted that all the different colors are of distinct
kinds, and that, by their composition, they form white light. This is
true of colors as far as their analysis and composition by refraction
are concerned; but Hooke maintained that all natural colors are
produced by various combinations of two primary ones, red and
violet;22 and Huyghens held a similar doctrine,
taking, however, yellow and blue for his basis. Newton answers, that
such compositions as they speak of are not compositions of simple
colors in his sense of the expressions. These writers also had both of
them adopted an opinion that light consisted in vibrations; and
objected to Newton that his language was erroneous, as involving the
hypothesis that light was a body. Newton appears to have had a horror
of the word hypothesis, and protests against its being supposed
that his “theory” rests on such a foundation.
22 Brewster’s Newton, p. 54.
Phil. Trans. viii. 5084, 6086.
The doctrine of the unequal refrangibility of different rays is
clearly exemplified in the effects of lenses, which produce images
more or 63 less
bordered with color, in consequence of this property. The improvement
of telescopes was, in Newton’s time, the great practical motive for
aiming at the improvement of theoretical optics. Newton’s theory
showed why telescopes were imperfect, namely, in consequence of the
different refraction of different colors, which produces a
chromatic aberration: and the theory was confirmed by the
circumstances of such imperfections. The false opinion of which we
have already spoken, that the dispersion must be the same when the
refraction is the same, led him to believe that the imperfection was
insurmountable,—that achromatic refraction could not be
obtained: and this view made him turn his attention to the
construction of reflecting instead of refracting telescopes. But the
rectification of Newton’s error was a further confirmation of the
general truth of his principles in other respects; and since that
time, the soundness of the Newtonian law of refraction has hardly been
questioned among physical philosophers.
It has, however, in modern times, been very vehemently controverted
in a quarter from which we might not readily have expected a detailed
discussion on such a subject. The celebrated Göthe has written a work
on The Doctrine of Colors, (Farbenlehre; Tübingen,
1810,) one main purpose of which is, to represent Newton’s opinions,
and the work in which they are formally published, (his
Opticks,) as utterly false and mistaken, and capable of being
assented to only by the most blind and obstinate prejudice. Those who
are acquainted with the extent to which such an opinion, promulgated
by Göthe, was likely to be widely adopted in Germany, will not be
surprised that similar language is used by other writers of that
nation. Thus Schelling23 says: “Newton’s Opticks is the
greatest proof of the possibility of a whole structure of fallacies,
which, in all its parts, is founded upon observation and experiment.”
Göthe, however, does not concede even so much to Newton’s work. He
goes over a large portion of it, page by page, quarrelling with the
experiments, diagrams, reasoning, and language, without intermission;
and holds that it is not reconcileable with the most simple facts. He
declares,24 that the first time he looked through a
prism, he saw the white walls of the room still look white, “and
though alone, I pronounced, as by an instinct, that the Newtonian
doctrine is false.” We need not here point out how inconsistent with
the Newtonian doctrine it was, to expect, as Göthe expected, that the
wall should be all over colored various colors.
23 Vorlesungen, p. 270.
24 Farbenlehre, vol. ii. p.
678.
64 Göthe not only
adopted and strenuously maintained the opinion that the Newtonian
theory was false, but he framed a system of his own to explain the
phenomena of color. As a matter of curiosity, it may be worth our
while to state the nature of this system; although undoubtedly it
forms no part of the progress of physical science. Göthe’s
views are, in fact, little different from those of Aristotle and
Antonio de Dominis, though more completely and systematically
developed. According to him, colors arise when we see through a dim
medium (“ein trübes mittel”). Light in itself is colorless; but if it
be seen through a somewhat dim medium, it appears yellow; if the
dimness of the medium increases, or if its depth be augmented, we see
the light gradually assume a yellow-red color, which finally is
heightened to a ruby-red. On the other hand, if darkness is seen
through a dim medium which is illuminated by a light falling on it, a
blue color is seen, which becomes clearer and paler, the more the
dimness of the medium increases, and darker and fuller, as the medium
becomes more transparent; and when we come to “the smallest degree of
the purest dimness,” we see the most perfect violet.25 In addition to this “doctrine of the
dim medium,” we have a second principle asserted concerning
refraction. In a vast variety of cases, images are accompanied by
“accessory images,” as when we see bright objects in a
looking-glass.26 Now, when an image is displaced by
refraction, the displacement is not complete, clear and sharp, but
incomplete, so that there is an accessory image along with the
principal one.27 From these principles, the colors
produced by refraction in the image of a bright object on a dark
ground, are at once derivable. The accessory image is
semitransparent;28 and hence that border of it which is
pushed forwards, is drawn from the dark over the bright, and there the
yellow appears; on the other hand, where the clear border laps over
the dark ground, the blue is seen;29 and hence we
easily see that the image must appear red and yellow at one end, and
blue and violet at the other.
25 Farbenlehre, § 150, p.
151.
26 Ib. § 223.
27 Ib. § 227.
28 Ib. § 238.
29 Ib. § 239.
We need not explain this system further, or attempt to show how
vague and loose, as well as baseless, are the notions and modes of
conception which it introduces. Perhaps it is not difficult to point
out the peculiarities in Göthe’s intellectual character which led to
his singularly unphilosophical views on this subject. One important
65 circumstance is,
that he appears, like many persons in whom the poetical imagination is
very active, to have been destitute of the talent and the habit of
geometrical thought. In all probability, he never apprehended clearly
and steadily those relations of position on which the Newtonian
doctrine depends. Another cause of his inability to accept the
doctrine probably was, that he had conceived the “composition” of
colors in some way altogether different from that which Newton
understands by composition. What Göthe expected to see, we cannot
clearly collect; but we know, from his own statement, that his
intention of experimenting with a prism arose from his speculations on
the roles of coloring in pictures; and we can easily see that any
notion of the composition of colors which such researches would
suggest, would require to be laid aside, before he could understand
Newton’s theory of the composition of light.
Other objections to Newton’s theory, of a kind very different, have
been recently made by that eminent master of optical science, Sir
David Brewster. He contests Newton’s opinion, that the colored rays
into which light is separated by refraction are altogether simple and
homogeneous, and incapable of being further analysed and modified. For
he finds that by passing such rays through colored media (as blue
glass for instance), they are not only absorbed and transmitted in
very various degrees, but that some of them have their color altered;
which effect he conceives as a further analysis of the rays, one
component color being absorbed and the other transmitted.30 And on this subject we can only say, as
we have before said, that Newton has incontestably and completely
established his doctrine, so far as analysis and decomposition by
refraction are concerned; but that with regard to any other
analysis, which absorbing media or other agents may produce, we have
no right from his experiments to assert, that the colors of the
spectrum are incapable of such decomposition. The whole
subject of the colors of objects, both opake and transparent, is still
in obscurity. Newton’s conjectures concerning the causes of the colors
of natural bodies, appear to help us little; and his opinions on that
subject are to be separated altogether from the important step which
he made in optical science, by the establishment of the true doctrine
of refractive dispersion.
30 This latter fact has, however, been
denied by other experimenters.
[2nd Ed.] [After a careful re-consideration of Sir D. Brewster’s
asserted analysis of the solar light into three colors by means of
66 absorbing media,
I cannot consider that he has established his point as an exception to
Newton’s doctrine. In the first place, the analysis of light into
three colors appears to be quite arbitrary, granting all his
experimental facts. I do not see why, using other media, he might not
just as well have obtained other elementary colors. In the next place,
this cannot be called an analysis in the same sense as
Newton’s analysis, except the relation between the two is shown. Is it
meant that Newton’s experiments prove nothing? Or is Newton’s
conclusion allowed to be true of light which has not been analysed by
absorption? And where are we to find such light, since the atmosphere
absorbs? But, I must add, in the third place, that with a very sincere
admiration of Sir D. Brewster’s skill as an experimenter, I think his
experiment requires, not only limitation, but confirmation by other
experimenters. Mr. Airy repeated the experiments with about thirty
different absorbing substances, and could not satisfy himself that in
any case they changed the color of a ray of given refractive power.
These experiments were described by him at a meeting of the Cambridge
Philosophical Society.]
We now proceed to the corrections which the next generation
introduced into the details of this doctrine.
</div></body></text></TEI>