<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1833</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="11">
CHAPTER XI.

The Laws of Electricity.

Electricity undoubtedly exists in the atmosphere
in most states of the air; but we know very imperfectly
the laws of this agent, and are still more ignorant
of its atmospheric operation. The present state
of science does not therefore enable us to perceive
those adaptations of its laws to its uses, which we
can discover in those cases where the laws and the
uses are both of them more apparent.
We can, however, easily make out that electrical
agency plays a very considerable part among the
clouds, in their usual conditions and changes. This
may be easily shown by Franklin’s experiment of the
electrical kite. The clouds are sometimes positively,
sometimes negatively, charged, and the rain which
descends from them offers also indications of one or
other kind of electricity. The changes of wind and
alterations of the form of the clouds are generally
accompanied with changes in these electrical indications.
Every one knows that a thunder-cloud is
strongly charged with the electric fluid, (if it be a
fluid,) and that the stroke of the lightning is an electrical
discharge. We may add that it appears, by
recent experiments, that a transfer of electricity between
plants and the atmosphere is perpetually going
on during the process of vegetation.
[92]
We cannot trace very exactly the precise circumstances,
in the occurrences of the atmospheric regions,
which depend on the influence of the laws of
electricity: but we are tolerably certain, from what
has been already noticed, that if these laws did not
exist, or were very different from what they now are,
the action of the clouds and winds, and the course of
vegetation, would also be other than it now is.
It is therefore at any rate very probable that electricity
has its appointed and important purposes in
the economy of the atmosphere. And this being so,
we may see a use in the thunder-storm and the stroke
of the lightning. These violent events are, with regard
to the electricity of the atmosphere, what winds
are with regard to heat and moisture. They restore
the equilibrium where it has been dissolved, and
carry the fluid from places where it is superfluous,
to others where it is deficient.
We are so constituted, however, that these crises
impress almost every one with a feeling of awe. The
deep lowering gloom of the thunder-cloud, the overwhelming
burst of the explosion, the flash from which
the steadiest eye shrinks, and the irresistible arrow
of the lightning which no earthly substance can withstand,
speak of something fearful, even independently
of the personal danger which they may whisper.
They convey, far more than any other appearance
does, the idea of a superior and mighty power, manifesting
displeasure and threatening punishment. Yet
we find that this is not the language which they speak
to the physical inquirer: he sees these formidable
symptoms only as the means or the consequences of
good. What office the thunderbolt and the whirlwind
may have in the moral world, we cannot here discuss:
but certainly he must speculate as far beyond
the limits of philosophy as of piety, who pretends to
have learnt that there their work has more of evil
than of good. In the natural world, these apparently
destructive agents are, like all the other movements[93]
and appearances of the atmosphere, parts of a great
scheme, of which every discoverable purpose is
marked with beneficence as well as wisdom.
</div></body></text></TEI>