<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Whewell William</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1858</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="17"> 

CHAPTER VII.
Special Methods of Induction applicable to Quantity.


Aphorism XLIII.
There are special Methods of Induction applicable to
Quantity; of which the principal are, the Method of Curves,
the Method of Means, the Method of Least Squares, and
the Method of Residues.
Aphorism XLIV.
The Method of Curves consists in drawing a curve of
which the observed quantities are the Ordinates, the quantity
on which the change of these quantities depends being the
Abscissa. The efficacy of this Method depends upon the
faculty which the eye possesses, of readily detecting regularity
and irregularity in forms. The Method may be used
to detect the Laws which the observed quantities follow: and
also, when the Observations are inexact, it may be used to correct
these Observations, so as to obtain data more true than the
observed facts themselves.
Aphorism XLV.
The Method of Means gets rid of irregularities by taking
the arithmetical mean of a great number of observed quantities.
Its efficacy depends upon this; that in cases in which
observed quantities are affected by other inequalities, besides
that of which we wish to determine the law, the excesses above
and defects below the quantities which the law in question
would produce, will, in a collection of many observations,
balance each other. 203
Aphorism XLVI.
The Method of Least Squares is a Method of Means, in
which the mean is taken according to the condition, that the
sum of the squares of the errours of observation shall be the
least possible which the law of the facts allows. It appears,
by the Doctrine of Chances, that this is the most probable
mean.
Aphorism XLVII.
The Method of Residues consists in subtracting, from
the quantities given by Observation, the quantity given by any
Law already discovered; and then examining the remainder,
or Residue, in order to discover the leading Law which it
follows. When this second Law has been discovered, the
quantity given by it may be subtracted from the first Residue;
thus giving a Second Residue, which may be examined in
the same manner; and so on. The efficacy of this method
depends principally upon the circumstance of the Laws of
variation being successively smaller and smaller in amount
(or at least in their mean effect); so that the ulterior undiscovered
Laws do not prevent the Law in question from being
prominent in the observations.
Aphorism XLVIII.
The Method of Means and the Method of Least Squares
cannot be applied without our knowing the Arguments of
the Inequalities which we seek. The Method of Curves and
the Method of Residues, when the Arguments of the principal
Inequalities are known, often make it easy to find the others.
IN cases where the phenomena admit of numerical
measurement and expression, certain mathematical methods
may be employed to facilitate and give
accuracy to the determination of the formula by which
the observations are connected into laws. Among the
most usual and important of these Methods are the
following:— 204
    I. The Method of Curves.
     II. The Method of Means.
    III. The Method of Least Squares.
    IV. The Method of Residues.
Sect. I.—The Method of Curves.
1. The Method of Curves proceeds upon this basis;
that when one quantity undergoes a series of changes
depending on the progress of another quantity, (as, for
instance, the Deviation of the Moon from her equable
place depends upon the progress of Time,) this dependence
may be expressed by means of a curve. In the
language of mathematicians, the variable quantity,
whose changes we would consider, is made the ordinate
of the curve, and the quantity on which the
changes depend is made the abscissa. In this manner,
the curve will exhibit in its form a series of undulations,
rising and falling so as to correspond with the
alternate Increase and Diminution of the quantity represented,
at intervals of Space which correspond to
the intervals of Time, or other quantity by which the
changes are regulated. Thus, to take another example,
if we set up, at equal intervals, a series of ordinates
representing the Height of all the successive High Waters
brought by the tides at a given place, for a year, the
curve which connects the summits of all these ordinates
will exhibit a series of undulations, ascending
and descending once in about each Fortnight; since, in
that interval, we have, in succession, the high spring
tides and the low neap tides. The curve thus drawn
offers to the eye a picture of the order and magnitude
of the changes to which the quantity under contemplation,
(the height of high water,) is subject.
2. Now the peculiar facility and efficacy of the
Method of Curves depends upon this circumstance;—that
order and regularity are more readily and clearly
recognized, when thus exhibited to the eye in a picture,
than they are when presented to the mind in any other
manner. To detect the relations of Number considered
directly as Number, is not easy: and we might 205
contemplate for a long time a Table of recorded Numbers
without perceiving the order of their increase and
diminution, even if the law were moderately simple;
as any one may satisfy himself by looking at a Tide
Table. But if these Numbers are expressed by the
magnitude of Lines, and if these Lines are arranged in
regular order, the eye readily discovers the rule of
their changes: it follows the curve which runs along
their extremities, and takes note of the order in which
its convexities and concavities succeed each other, if
any order be readily discoverable. The separate observations
are in this manner compared and generalized
and reduced to rule by the eye alone. And the eye,
so employed, detects relations of order and succession
with a peculiar celerity and evidence. If, for example,
we thus arrive as ordinates the prices of corn in each
year for a series of years, we shall see the order,
rapidity, and amount of the increase and decrease of price,
far more clearly than in any other manner. And if
there were any recurrence of increase and decrease at
stated intervals of years, we should in this manner
perceive it. The eye, constantly active and busy, and
employed in making into shapes the hints and traces
of form which it contemplates, runs along the curve
thus offered to it; and as it travels backwards and
forwards, is ever on the watch to detect some resemblance
or contrast between one part and another. And
these resemblances and contrasts, when discovered, are
the images of Laws of Phenomena; which are made
manifest at once by this artifice, although the mind
could not easily catch the indications of their existence,
if they were not thus reflected to her in the clear
mirror of Space.
Thus when we have a series of good Observations,
and know the argument upon which their change of
magnitude depends, the Method of Curves enables us to
ascertain, almost at a glance, the law of the change; and
by further attention, may be made to give us a formula
with great accuracy. The Method enables us to perceive,
among our observations, an order, which without the
method, is concealed in obscurity and perplexity. 206
3. But the Method of Curves not only enables us
to obtain laws of nature from good Observations, but
also, in a great degree, from observations which are
very imperfect. For the imperfection of observations
may in part be corrected by this consideration;—that
though they may appear irregular, the correct facts
which they imperfectly represent, are really regular.
And the Method of Curves enables us to remedy this
apparent irregularity, at least in part. For when
Observations thus imperfect are laid down as Ordinates,
and their extremities connected by a line, we obtain,
not a smooth and flowing curve, such as we should
have if the observations contained only the rigorous
results of regular laws; but a broken and irregular
line, full of sudden and capricious twistings, and
bearing on its face marks of irregularities dependent, not
upon law, but upon chance. Yet these irregular and
abrupt deviations in the curve are, in most cases, but
small in extent, when compared with those bendings
which denote the effects of regular law. And this
circumstance is one of the great grounds of advantage
in the Method of Curves. For when the observations
thus laid down present to the eye such a broken and
irregular line, we can still see, often with great ease
and certainty, what twistings of the line are probably
due to the irregular errours of observation; and can
at once reject these, by drawing a more regular curve,
cutting off all such small and irregular sinuosities,
leaving some to the right and some to the left; and
then proceeding as if this regular curve, and not the
irregular one, expressed the observations. In this
manner, we suppose the errours of observation to
balance each other; some of our corrected measures
being too great and others too small, but with no great
preponderance either way. We draw our main regular
curve, not through the points given by our observations,
but among them: drawing it, as has been said
by one of the philosophers30
who first systematically
used this method, ‘with a bold but careful hand.’ 207
The regular curve which we thus obtain, thus freed
from the casual errours of observation, is that in which
we endeavour to discover the laws of change and succession.</div></body></text></TEI>