<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author>Lyell Charles</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher></publisher><pubPlace></pubPlace><date>1830</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="9">CHAPTER IX.
THEORY OF THE PROGRESSIVE DEVELOPMENT OF ORGANIC LIFE AT
SUCCESSIVE GEOLOGICAL PERIODS.
Theory of the progressive development of organic life—Evidence in its support
inconclusive—Vertebrated animals, and plants of the most perfect organization,
in strata of very high antiquity—Differences between the organic remains of
successive formations—Comparative modern origin of the human
race—The
popular doctrine of successive development not established by the admission
that man is of modern origin—Introduction of man, to what extent a change in
the system.
Progressive development of organic life.—In the preceding chapters I
have considered whether revolutions in the general climate of the globe
afford any just ground of opposition to the doctrine that the former
changes of the earth which are treated of in geology belong to one uninterrupted
series of physical events governed by ordinary causes.
Against this doctrine some popular arguments have been derived from
the great vicissitudes of the organic creation in times past; I shall
131
therefore proceed to the discussion of such objections, which have been
thus formally advanced by the late Sir Humphrey Davy. "It is impossible,"
he affirms, "to defend the proposition, that the present order
of things is the ancient and constant order of nature, only modified by
existing laws: in those strata which are deepest, and which must, consequently,
be supposed to be the earliest deposited, forms even of vegetable
life are rare; shells and vegetable remains are found in the next
order; the bones of fishes and oviparous reptiles exist in the following
class; the remains of birds, with those of the same genera mentioned
before, in the next order; those of quadrupeds of extinct species in a
still more recent class; and it is only in the loose and slightly consolidated
strata of gravel and sand, and which are usually called diluvian
formations, that the remains of animals such as now people the globe
are found, with others belonging to extinct species. But, in none of
these formations, whether called secondary, tertiary, or diluvial, have
the remains of man, or any of his works, been discovered; and whoever
dwells upon this subject must be convinced, that the present order
of things, and the comparatively recent existence of man as the master
of the globe, is as certain as the destruction of a former and a different
order, and the extinction of a number of living forms which have no
types in being. In the oldest secondary strata there are no remains of
such animals as now belong to the surface; and in the rocks, which
may be regarded as more recently deposited, these remains occur but
rarely, and with abundance of extinct species;—there seems, as it were,
a gradual approach to the present system of things, and a succession of
destructions and creations preparatory to the existence of man."211
In the above passages, the author deduces two important conclusions
from geological data: first, that in the successive groups of strata,
from the oldest to the most recent, there is a progressive development
of organic life, from the simplest to the most complicated forms;—secondly,
that man is of comparatively recent origin, and these conclusions
he regards as inconsistent with the doctrine, "that the present
order of things is the ancient and constant order of nature only modified
by existing laws."
With respect, then, to the first of these propositions, we may ask
whether the theory of the progressive development of animal and vegetable
life, and their successive advancement from a simple to a more
perfect state, has any secure foundation in fact? No geologists who
are in possession of all the data now established respecting fossil remains,
will for a moment contend for the doctrine in all its detail, as
laid down by the distinguished philosopher to whose opinions we have
referred: but naturalists, who are not unacquainted with recent discoveries,
continue to defend it in a modified form. They say that in the
first period of the world (by which they mean the earliest of which we
have yet brought to light any memorials), the vegetation was characterized
by a predominance of cryptogamic plants, while the animals
132
which coexisted were almost entirely confined to zoophytes, testacea,
and a few fish. Plants of a less simple structure, coniferæ and cycadeæ,
flourished largely in the next epoch, when oviparous reptiles began
also to abound. Lastly, the terrestrial flora became most diversified
and most perfect when the highest orders of animals, the mammalia
and birds, were called into existence.
Now in the first place, it may be observed, that many naturalists are
guilty of no small inconsistency in endeavoring to connect the phenomena
of the earliest vegetation with a nascent condition of organic life,
and at the same time to deduce from the numerical predominance of
certain forms, the greater heat or uniformity of the ancient climate.
The arguments in favor of the latter conclusion are without any force,
unless we can assume that the rules followed by the Author of Nature
in the creation and distribution of organic beings were the same formerly
as now; and that, as certain families of animals and plants are
now most abundant in, or exclusively confined to regions where there is
a certain temperature, a certain degree of humidity, a certain intensity
of light, and other conditions, so also analogous phenomena were exhibited
at every former era.
If this postulate be denied, and the prevalence of particular families
be declared to depend on a certain order of precedence in the introduction
of different classes into the earth, and if it be maintained that the
standard of organization was raised successively, we must then ascribe
the numerical preponderance, in the earlier ages, of plants of simpler
structure, not to the heat, or other climatal conditions, but to those different
laws which regulate organic life in newly created worlds.
Before we can infer a warm and uniform temperature in high latitudes,
from the presence of 250 species of ferns, some of them arborescent,
accompanied by lycopadiacæ of large size, and araucariæ, we
must be permitted to assume, that at all times, past, present, and
future, a heated and moist atmosphere pervading the northern hemisphere
has a tendency to produce in the vegetation a predominance of
analogous forms.
It should moreover be borne in mind, when we are considering the
question of development from a botanical point of view, that naturalists
are by no means agreed as to the existence of an ascending scale of
organization in the vegetable world corresponding to that which is very
generally recognized in animals. "From the sponge to man," in the
language of De Blainville, there may be a progressive chain of being,
although often broken and imperfect; but if we seek to classify plants
according to a linear arrangement, ascending gradually from the lichen
to the lily or the rose, we encounter incomparably greater difficulties.
Yet the doctrine of a more highly developed organization in the plants
created at successive periods presupposes the admission of such a
graduated scale.
We have as yet obtained but scanty information respecting the state
of the terrestrial flora at periods antecedent to the coal. In the carboniferous
133
epoch, about 500 species of fossil plants are enumerated by
Adolphe Brongniart, which we may safely regard as a mere fragment of
an ancient flora; since, in Europe alone, there are now no less than
11,000 living species. I have already hinted that the plants which
produced coal were not drifted from a distance, but that nearly all of
them grew on the spots where they became fossil. They appear to
have belonged, as before explained (p. 115), to a peculiar class of stations,—to
low level and swampy regions, in the deltas of large rivers,
slightly elevated above the level of the sea. From the study, therefore,
of such a vegetation, we can derive but little insight into the nature
of the contemporaneous upland flora, still less of the plants of the
mountainous or Alpine country; and if so, we are enabled to account
for the apparent monotony of the vegetation, although its uniform
character was doubtless in part owing to a greater uniformity of climate
then prevailing throughout the globe. Some of the commonest trees of
this period, such as the sigillariæ, which united the structure of ferns
and of cycadeæ, departed very widely from all known living types.
The coniferæ and ferns, on the contrary, were very closely allied to
living genera. It is remarkable that none of the exogens of Lindley
(dicotyledonous angiosperms of Brongniart), which comprise
four-fifths
of the living flora of the globe, and include all the forest trees of
Europe except the fir-tribe, have yet been discovered in the coal measures,
and a very small number—fifteen species only—of monocotyledons.
If several of these last are true plants, an opinion to which Messrs.
Lindley, Unger, Corda, and other botanists of note incline, the question
whether any of the most highly organized plants are to be met with in
ancient strata is at once answered in the affirmative. But the determination
of these palms being doubtful, we have as yet in the coal no
positive proofs either of the existence of the most perfect, or of the
most simple forms of flowering or flowerless vegetation. We have no
fungi, lichens, hepatici or mosses: yet this latter class may have been
as fully represented then as now.
In the flora of the secondary eras, all botanists agree that palms
existed, although in Europe plants of the family of zamia and cycas
together with coniferæ predominated, and must have given a peculiar
aspect to the flora. As only 200 or 300 species of plants are known
in all the rocks ranging from the Trias to the Oolite inclusive, our data
are too scanty as yet to affirm whether the vegetation of this second
epoch was or was not on the whole of a simpler organization than that
of our own times.
In the Lower Cretaceous formation, near Aix-la-Chapelle, the leaves
of a great many dicotyledonous trees have lately been discovered by
Dr. Debey, establishing the important fact of the coexistence of a large
number of angiosperms with cycadeæ, and with that rich reptilian fauna
comprising the ichthyosaur, plesiosaur, and pterodactyl, which some had
supposed to indicate a state of the atmosphere unfavorable to a dicotyledonous
vegetation.
134The number of plants hitherto obtained from tertiary strata of different
ages is very limited, but is rapidly increasing. They are referable
to a much greater variety of families and classes than an equal number
of fossil species taken from secondary or primary rocks, the angiosperms
bearing the same proportion to the gymnosperms and acrogens
as in the present flora of the globe. This greater variety may, doubtless,
be partly ascribed to the greater diversity of stations in which the plants
grew, as we have in this case an opportunity, rarely enjoyed in studying
the secondary fossils, of investigating inland or lacustrine deposits
accumulated at different heights above the sea, and containing the memorials
of plants washed down from adjoining mountains.
In regard, then, to the strata from the cretaceous to the uppermost
tertiary inclusive, we may affirm that we find in them all the principal
classes of living plants, and during this vast lapse of time four or five
complete changes in the vegetation occurred, yet no step whatever was
made in advance at any of these periods by the addition of more highly
organized species.
If we next turn to the fossils of the animal kingdom, we may inquire
whether, when they are arranged by the geologists in a chronological
series, they imply that beings of more highly developed structure and
greater intelligence entered upon the earth at successive epochs, those
of the simplest organization being the first created, and those more
highly organized being the last.
Our knowledge of the Silurian fauna is at present derived entirely
from rocks of marine origin, no fresh-water strata of such high antiquity
having yet been met with. The fossils, however, of these ancient rocks
at once reduce the theory of progressive development to within very
narrow limits, for already they comprise a very full representation of the
radiata, mollusca, and articulata proper to the sea. Thus, in the great
division of radiata, we find asteriod and helianthoid zoophytes, besides
crinoid and cystidean echinoderms. In the mollusca, between
200 and 300 species of cephalopoda are enumerated. In the articulata
we have the crustaceans represented by more than 200 species of trilobites,
besides other genera of the same class. The remains of fish are
as yet confined to the upper part of the Silurian series; but some of
these belong to placoid fish, which occupy a high grade in the scale of
organization. Some naturalists have assumed that the earliest fauna
was exclusively marine, because we have not yet found a single Silurian
helix, insect, bird, terrestrial reptile or mammifer; but when we carry
back our investigation to a period so remote from the present, we ought
not to be surprised if the only accessible strata should be limited to
deposits formed far from land, because the ocean probably occupied
then, as now, the greater part of the earth's surface. After so many
entire geographical revolutions, the chances are nearly three to one in
favor of our finding that such small portions of the existing continents
and islands as expose Silurian strata to view, should coincide in position
with the ancient ocean rather than the land. We must not, therefore,
135
too hastily infer, from the absence of fossil bones of mammalia in the
older rocks, that the highest class of vertebrated animals did not exist
in remoter ages. There are regions at present, in the Indian and Pacific
Oceans, coextensive in area with the continents of Europe and North
America, where we might dredge the bottom and draw up thousands
of shells and corals, without obtaining one bone of a land quadruped.
Suppose our mariners were to report, that, on sounding in the Indian
Ocean near some coral reefs, and at some distance from the land, they
drew up on hooks attached to their line portions of a leopard, elephant,
or tapir, should we not be skeptical as to the accuracy of their statements?
and if we had no doubt of their veracity, might we not suspect
them to be unskilful naturalists? or, if the fact were unquestioned,
should we not be disposed to believe that some vessel had been wrecked
on the spot?
The casualties must always be rare by which land quadrupeds are
swept by rivers far out into the open sea, and still rarer the contingency
of such a floating body not being devoured by sharks or other predaceous
fish, such as were those of which we find the teeth preserved in
some of the carboniferous strata. But if the carcass should escape, and
should happen to sink where sediment was in the act of accumulating,
and if the numerous causes of subsequent disintegration should not efface
all traces of the body, included for countless ages in solid rock, is
it not contrary to all calculation of chances that we should hit upon the
exact spot—that mere point in the bed of an ancient ocean, where the
precious relic was entombed? Can we expect for a moment, when we
have only succeeded, amidst several thousand fragments of corals and
shells, in finding a few bones of aquatic or amphibious animals, that we
should meet with a single skeleton of an inhabitant of the land?
Clarence, in his dream, saw, "in the slimy bottom of the deep,"


——a thousand fearful wrecks;
A thousand men, that fishes gnaw'd upon:
Wedges of gold, great anchors, heaps of pearl.


Had he also beheld, amid "the dead bones that lay scattered by," the
carcasses of lions, deer, and the other wild tenants of the forest and the
plain, the fiction would have been deemed unworthy of the genius of
Shakspeare. So daring a disregard of probability and violation of analogy
would have been condemned as unpardonable, even where the poet
was painting those incongruous images which present themselves to a
disturbed imagination during the visions of the night.
Until lately it was supposed that the old red sandstone, or Devonian
rocks, contained no vertebrate remains except those of fish, but in 1850
the footprints of a chelonian, and in 1851 the skeleton of a reptile, allied
both to the batrachians and lizards, were found in a sandstone of
that age near Elgin in Scotland.212 Up to the year 1844 it was laid
136
down as a received dogma in many works of high authority in geology,
that reptiles were not created until after the close of the carboniferous
epoch. In the course of that year, however, Hermann Von Meyer announced
the discovery, in the coal measures of Rhenish Bavaria, of a
reptile, called by him Apateon, related to the salamanders; and in
1847 three species of another genus, called archegosaurus by Goldfuss,
were obtained from the coal of Saarbrück, between Treves and Strasburg.
The footprints of a large quadruped, probably batrachian, had
also been observed by Dr. King in the carboniferous rocks of Pennsylvania
in 1844. The first example of the bones of a reptile in the Coal
of North America was detected so lately as September, 1852, by Mr.
G. W. Dawson and myself in Nova Scotia. These remains, referred by
Messrs. Wyman and Owen to a perennibranchiate batrachian, were met
with in the interior of an erect fossil tree, apparently a sigillaria. They
seem clearly to have been introduced together with sediment into the
tree, during its submergence and after it had decayed and was standing
as a hollow cylinder of bark, this bark being now converted into coal.
When Agassiz, in his great work on fossil fish, described 152 species
of ichthyolites from the Coal, he found them to consist of 94 placoids,
belonging to the families of shark and ray, and 58 ganoids. One family
of the latter he called "sauroid fish," including the megalicthys and
holoptychius, often of great size, and all predaceous. Although true
fish, and not intermediate between that class and reptiles, they seem to
have been more highly organized than any living fish, reminding us of
the skeletons of saurians by the close suture of their cranial bones, their
large conical teeth, striated longitudinally, and the articulation of the
spinous processes with the vertebræ. Among living species they are
most nearly allied to the lepidosteus, or bony pike of the North American
rivers. Before the recent progress of discovery above alluded to
had shown the fallacy of such ideas, it was imagined by some geologists
that this ichthyic type was the more highly developed, because it
took the lead at the head of nature before the class of reptiles had been
created. The confident assumption indulged in till the year 1844, that
reptiles were first introduced into the earth in the Permian period, shows
the danger of taking for granted that the date of the creation of any
family of animals or plants in past time coincides with the age of the
oldest stratified rock in which the geologist has detected its remains.
Nevertheless, after repeated disappointments, we find some naturalists
as much disposed as ever to rely on such negative evidence, and to feel
now as sure that reptiles were not introduced into the earth till after
the Silurian epoch, as they were in 1844, that they appeared for the
first time at an era subsequent to the carboniferous.
Scanty as is the information hitherto obtained in regard to the articulata
of the coal formation, we have at least ascertained that some insects
winged their way through the ancient forests. In the ironstone
of Coalbrook Dale, two species of coleoptera of the Linnæan genus curculio
have been met with: and a neuropterous insect resembling a corydalis,
137
together with another of the same order related to the phasmidæ.
As an example of the insectivorous arachnidæ, I may mention
the scorpion of the Bohemian coal, figured by Count Sternberg, in which
even the eyes, skin, and minute hairs were preserved.213 We need not
despair, therefore, of obtaining eventually fossil representatives of all
the principal orders of hexapods and arachnidæ in carboniferous strata.
Next in chronological order above the Coal comes the allied Magnesian
Limestone, or Permian group, and the secondary formations from
the Trias to the Chalk inclusive. These rocks comprise the monuments
of a long series of ages in which reptiles of every variety of size, form,
and structure peopled the earth; so that the whole period, and especially
that of the Lias and Oolite, has been sometimes called "the age of reptiles."
As there are now mammalia entirely confined to the land; others
which, like the bat and vampire, fly in the air; others, again, of amphibious
habits, frequenting rivers, like the hippopotamus, otter, and beaver;
others exclusively aquatic and marine, like the seal, whale, and narwal;
so in the early ages under consideration, there were terrestrial, winged,
and aquatic reptiles. There were iguanodons walking on the land, pterodactyls
winging their way through the air, monitors and crocodiles in
the rivers, and ichthyosaurs and plesiosaurs in the ocean. It appears
also that some of these ancient saurians approximated more nearly in
their organization to the type of living mammalia than do any of the
reptiles now existing.214
In the vast range of strata above alluded to, comprising the Permian,
the Upper New Red Sandstone and Muschelkalk, the Lias, Oolite,
Wealden, Green-sand, and Chalk, scarcely any well-authenticated instances
of the occurrence of fossil birds in Europe are on record, and
only two or three of fossil mammalia.
In regard to the absence of birds, they are usually wanting, for reasons
afterwards to be explained (see chap. 47), in deposits of all ages,
even in the tertiary periods, where we know that birds as well as land
quadrupeds abounded. Some at least of the fossil remains formerly referred
to this class in the Wealden (a great freshwater deposit below
the chalk), have been recently shown by Mr. Owen to belong to pterodactyls.215
But in North America still more ancient indications of the
existence of the feathered tribe have been detected, the fossil foot-marks
of a great variety of species, of various sizes, some larger than the ostrich,
others smaller than the plover, having been observed. These bipeds
have left marks of their footsteps on strata of an age decidedly intermediate
between the Lias and the Coal.216


Fig. 8.
Natural Size.           



Thylacotherium Prevostii (Valenciennes). Amphitherium (Owen). Lower jaw, from the
slate of Stonesfield, near Oxford.218
The examples of mammalia, above alluded to, are confined to the Trias
and the Oolite. In the former, the evidence is as yet limited to two
small molar teeth, described by Professor Plieninger in 1847, under the
138
generic name of Microlestes. They were found near Stuttgart, and possess
the double fangs so characteristic of mammalia.217 The other fossil
remains of the same class were derived from one of the inferior members
of the oolitic series in Oxfordshire, and afford more full and satisfactory
evidence, consisting of the lower jaws of three species of small quadrupeds
about the size of a mole. Cuvier, when he saw one of them (during
a visit to Oxford in 1818), referred it to the marsupial order, stating,
however, that it differed from all known carnivora in having ten molar
teeth in a row. Professor Owen afterwards pointed out that the jaw
belonged to an extinct genus, having considerable affinity to a newly
discovered Australian mammifer, the Myrmecobius of Waterhouse, which
has nine molar teeth in the lower jaw. (Fig. 9.) A more perfect specimen

Fig. 9.
Myrmecobius fasciatus (Waterhouse). Recent from Swan
River. Lower jaw of the natural size.
219

enabled Mr. Owen in 1846 to
prove that the inflection of the angular
process of the lower jaw was
not sufficiently marked to entitle
the osteologist to infer that this
quadruped was marsupial, as the
process is not bent inwards in a
greater degree than in the mole or
hedgehog. Hence the genus amphitherium, of which there are two
species from Stonesfield, must be referred to the ordinary or placental
139
type of insectivorous mammals, although it approximates in some points
of structure to the myrmecobius and allied marsupials of Australia. The
other contemporary genus, called phascolotherium, agrees much more
nearly in osteological character and precisely in the number of the teeth
with the opossums; and is believed to have been truly marsupial.
(Fig. 10.)
Fig. 10.
Natural size.

Phascolotherium Bucklandi, Owen. (Syn. Didelphis Bucklandi, Brod.)
Lower jaw, from Stonesfield.220
1. The jaw magnified twice in length.   2. The second molar tooth magnified six times.
The occurrence of these most ancient memorials of the mammiferous
type, in so low a member of the oolitic series, while no other representatives
of the same class (if we except the microlestes) have yet been
found in any other of the inferior or superior secondary strata, is a
striking fact, and should serve as a warning to us against hasty generalizations,
founded solely on negative evidence. So important an exception
to a general rule may be perfectly consistent with the conclusion,
that a small number only of mammalia inhabited European latitudes
when our secondary rocks were formed; but it seems fatal to the theory
of progressive development, or to the notion that the order of precedence
in the creation of animals, considered chronologically, has precisely
coincided with the order in which they would be ranked according
to perfection or complexity of structure.
It was for many years suggested that the marsupial order to which
the fossil animals of Stonesfield were supposed exclusively to belong
constitutes the lowest grade in the class Mammalia, and that this order,
of which the brain is of more simple form, evinces an inferior degree of
140
intelligence. If, therefore, in the oolitic period the marsupial tribes
were the only warm-blooded quadrupeds which had as yet appeared
upon our planet, the fact, it was said, confirmed the theory which
teaches that the creation of the more simple forms in each division of
the animal kingdom preceded that of the more complex. But on how
slender a support, even if the facts had continued to hold true, did such
important conclusions hang! The Australian continent, so far as it has
been hitherto explored, contains no indigenous quadrupeds save those
of the marsupial order, with the exception of a few small rodents, while
some neighboring islands to the north, and even southern Africa, in the
same latitude as Australia, abound in mammalia of every tribe except
the marsupial. We are entirely unable to explain on what physiological
or other laws this singular diversity in the habitations of living mammalia
depends; but nothing is more clear than that the causes which
stamp so peculiar a character on two different provinces of wide extent
are wholly independent of time, or of the age or maturity of the planet.
The strata of the Wealden, although of a later date than the oolite of
Stonesfield, and although filled with the remains of large reptiles, both
terrestrial and aquatic, have not yielded as yet a single marsupial bone.
Were we to assume on such scanty data that no warm-blooded quadrupeds
were then to be found throughout the northern hemisphere, there
would still remain a curious subject of speculation, whether the entire
suppression of one important class of vertebrata, such as the mammiferous,
and the great development of another, such as the reptilian, implies
a departure from fixed and uniform rules governing the fluctuations of
the animal world; such rules, for example, as appear from one century
to another to determine the growth of certain tribes of plants and animals
in arctic, and of other tribes in tropical regions.
In Australia, New Zealand, and many other parts of the southern
hemisphere, where the indigenous land quadrupeds are comparatively
few, and of small dimensions, the reptiles do not predominate in number
or size. The deposits formed at the mouth of an Australian river, within
the tropics, might contain the bones of only a few small marsupial animals,
which, like those of Stonesfield, might hereafter be discovered
with difficulty by geologists; but there would, at the same time, be no
megalosauri and other fossil remains, showing that large saurians were
plentiful on the land and in the waters at a time when mammalia were
scarce. This example, therefore, would afford a very imperfect parallel
to the state of the animal kingdom, supposed to have prevailed during
the secondary periods, when a high temperature pervaded European
latitudes.
It may nevertheless be advantageous to point to some existing anomalies
in the geographical development of distinct classes of vertebrata
which may be comparable to former conditions of the animal creation
brought to light by geology. Thus in the arctic regions, at present,
reptiles are small, and sometimes wholly wanting, where birds, large
land quadrupeds, and cetacea abound. We meet with bears, wolves,
141
foxes, musk oxen, and deer, walruses, seals, whales, and narwals, in regions
of ice and snow, where the smallest snakes, efts, and frogs are
rarely, if ever, seen.
A still more anomalous state of things presents itself in the southern
hemisphere. Even in the temperate zone, between the latitudes 52°
and 56° S., as, for example, in Tierra del Fuego, as well as in the
woody region immediately north of the Straits of Magellan, and in the
Falkland Islands, no reptiles of any kind are met with, not even a snake,
lizard, or frog; but in these same countries we find the guanaco (a kind
of llama), a deer, the puma, a large species of fox, many small rodentia,
besides the seal and otter, together with the porpoise, whale, and other
cetacea.
On what grand laws in the animal physiology these remarkable phenomena
depend, cannot in the present state of science be conjectured;
nor could we predict whether any opposite condition of the atmosphere,
in respect to heat, moisture, and other circumstances, would bring about
a state of animal life which might be called the converse of that above
described, namely, a state in which reptiles of every size and order
might abound, and mammalia disappear.
The nearest approximation to such a fauna is found in the Galapagos
Archipelago. These islands, situated under the equator, and nearly
600 miles west of the coast of Peru, have been called "the land of reptiles,"
so great is the number of snakes, large tortoises, and lizards,
which they support. Among the lizards, the first living species proper
to the ocean has been discovered. Yet, although some of these islands
are from 3000 to 4000 feet high, and one of them 75 miles long, they
contain, with the exception of one small mouse, no indigenous mammifer.
Even here, however, it is true that in the neighboring sea there
are seals, and several kinds of cetacea.221
It may be unreasonable to look for a nearer analogy between the
fauna now existing in any part of the globe, and that which we can
show to have prevailed when our secondary strata were deposited, because
we must always recollect that a climate like that now experienced
at the equator, coexisting with the unequal days and nights of European
latitudes, was a state of things to which there is now no counterpart
on the globe. Consequently, the type of animal and vegetable
existence required for such a climate might be expected to deviate
almost as widely from that now established, as do the flora and fauna
of our tropical differ from those of our arctic regions.
In the Tertiary strata.—The tertiary formations were deposited when
the physical geography of the northern hemisphere had been entirely
altered. Large inland lakes had become numerous, as in central France
and other countries. There were gulfs of the sea, into which considerable
rivers emptied themselves, and where strata like those of the Paris
basin were accumulated. There were also formations in progress, in
142
shallow seas not far from shore, such as are indicated by portions of the
Faluns of the Loire, and the English Crag.
The proximity, therefore, of large tracts of dry land to the seas and
lakes then existing, may, in a great measure, explain why the remains
of land animals, so rare in the older strata, are not uncommon in these
more modern deposits. Yet even these have sometimes proved entirely
destitute of mammiferous relics for years after they had become
celebrated for the abundance of their fossil testacea, fish, and reptiles.
Thus the calcaire grossier, a marine limestone of the district round Paris,
had afforded to collectors more than 1100 species of shells, besides
many zoophytes, echinodermata, and the teeth of fish, before the bones
of one or two land quadrupeds were met with in the same rock. The
strata called London and Plastic clay in England have been studied for
more than half a century, and about 400 species of shells, 50 or more
of fish, besides several kinds of chelonian and saurian reptiles, were
known before a single mammifer was detected. At length, in the year
1839, there were found in this formation the remains of a monkey, an
opossum, a bat,222 and a species of the extinct genus Hyracotherium,
allied to the Peccary or hog tribe.
If we examine the strata above the London clay in England, we first
meet with mammiferous remains in the Isle of Wight, in beds also belonging
to the Eocene epoch, such as the remains of the Palæotherium,
Anoplotherium, and other extinct quadrupeds, agreeing very closely
with those first found by Cuvier, near Paris, in strata of the same age,
and of similar freshwater origin.
In France we meet with another fauna, both conchological and mammalian
in the Miocene "faluns" of the Loire; above which in the
ascending series in Great Britain we arrive at the coralline crag of Suffolk,
a marine formation which has yielded three or four hundred species
of shells, very different from the Eocene testacea, and of which a large
proportion, although a minority of the whole number, are recent, besides
many corals, echini, foraminifera, and fish, but as yet no relic decidedly
mammalian except the ear-bone of a whale.
In the shelly sand, provincially termed "Red Crag," in Suffolk,
which immediately succeeds the coralline, constituting a newer member
of the same tertiary group, about 250 species of shells have been recognized,
of which a still larger proportion are recent. They are associated
with numerous teeth of fish; but no signs of a warm-blooded
quadruped had been detected until 1839, when the teeth of a leopard,
a bear, a hog, and a species of ruminant, were found at Newbourn, in
Suffolk, and since that time, several other genera of mammalia have
been met with in the same formation, or in the Red Crag.223
Of a still newer date is the Norwich Crag, a
fluvio-marine deposit of
the Pleiocene epoch, containing a mixture of marine, fluviatile, and land
143
shells, of which 90 per cent. or more are recent. These beds, since the
time of their first investigation, have yielded a supply of mammalian
bones of the genera mastodon, elephant, rhinoceros, pig, horse, deer, ox,
and others, the bodies of which may have been washed down into the
sea by rivers draining land, of which the contiguity is indicated by the
occasional presence of terrestrial and freshwater shells.
Our acquaintance with the newer Pleiocene mammalia in Europe,
South America, and Australia, is derived chiefly from cavern deposits, a
fact which we ought never to forget if we desire to appreciate the superior
facilities we enjoy for studying the more modern as compared to the
more ancient terrestrial faunas. We know nothing of the fossil bones
which must have been inclosed in the stalagmite of caverns in the older
Pleiocene, or in the Miocene or Eocene epochs, much less can we derive
any information respecting the inhabitants of the land from a similar
source, when we carry back our inquiries to the Wealden or carboniferous
epochs. We are as well assured that land and rivers then existed, as that
they exist now; but it is evident that even a slight geographical revolution,
accompanied by the submergence and denudation of land, would reduce
to an extreme improbability the chance of our hitting on those minute
points of space where caves may once have occurred in limestone rocks.
Fossil quadrumana.—Until within a few years (1836, 1837), not a
single bone of any quadrumanous animal, such as the orang, ape, baboon,
and monkey, had been discovered in a fossil state, although so much
progress had been made in bringing to light the extinct mammalia of
successive tertiary eras, both carnivorous and herbivorous. The total
absence of these anthropomorphous tribes among the records of a former
world, had led some to believe that the type of organization most nearly
resembling the human, came so late in the order of creation, as to be
scarcely, if at all, anterior to that of man. That such generalizations
were premature, I endeavored to point out in the first edition of this
work,224 in which I stated that the bones of quadrupeds hitherto met with
in tertiary deposits were chiefly those which frequent marshes, rivers, or
the borders of lakes, as the elephant, rhinoceros, hippopotamus, tapir,
hog, deer, and ox, while species which live in trees are extremely rare in
a fossil state. I also hinted, that we had as yet no data for determining
how great a number of the one kind we ought to find, before we have
a right to expect a single individual of the other. Lastly, I observed
that the climate of the more modern (or Post-Eocene) tertiary periods
in England was not tropical, and that in regard to the London clay, of
which the crocodiles, turtles, and fossil fruits implied a climate hot enough
for the quadrumana, we had as yet made too little progress in ascertaining
what were the Eocene pachydermata of England, to entitle us to expect
to have discovered any quadrumana of the same date.
Since those remarks were first written, in 1829, a great number of
extinct species have been added to our collections of tertiary mammalia
144
from Great Britain and other parts of the world. At length, between
the years 1836 and 1839, a few remains of quadrumana were found in
France and England, India and Brazil. Those of India, belonging to
more than one extinct species of monkey, were first discovered near the
Sutlej, in lat. 30° N., in tertiary strata, of which the age is not yet determined;
the Brazilian fossil, brought from the basin of the Rio das
Velhas, about lat. 18° S., is referable to a form now peculiar in America,
allied to the genus Callithrix, the species being extinct. The skull and
other bones met with in the South of France belong to a gibbon, or one
of the tailless apes, which stand next in the scale of organization to the
orang. It occurred at Sansan, about forty miles west of Toulouse, in
lat. 43° 40' N., in freshwater strata, probably of the Miocene or middle
tertiary period. Lastly, the English quadrumane first met with, occurred
in a more ancient stratum than the rest, and at a point more remote
from the equator. It belongs to the genus Macacus, is an extinct species,
and was found in Suffolk, in lat. 52°,225 in the London clay, the fossils of
which, such as crocodiles, turtles, shells of the genus Nautilus, and many
curious fruits, had already led geologists to the conclusion that the
climate of that era (the Eocene) was warm and nearly tropical.
Some years later (in 1846) the jaw of another British species of fossil
monkey, Macacus pliocenus, was announced by Mr. Owen as having
been met with in the newer Pleiocene strata, on the banks of the
Thames, at Grays, in Essex, accompanying the remains of hippopotamus,
elephant, and other quadrupeds, and associated with freshwater and
land shells, most of which are now inhabitants of the British
Isles.226
When we consider the small area of the earth's surface hitherto explored
geologically, and the new discoveries brought to light daily,
even in the environs of great European capitals, we must feel that
it would be rash to assume that the Lower Eocene deposits mark the
era of the first creation of quadrumana. It would, however, be still
145
more unphilosophical to infer, as some writers have done, from a single
extinct species of this family obtained in a latitude far from the tropics,
that the Eocene quadrumana did not attain as high a grade of organization
as they do in our own times. What would the naturalist know of
the apes and orangs now contemporary with man, if our investigations
were restricted to such northern latitudes as those where alone the geologist
has hitherto found all the fossil quadrumana of Europe?
Cetacea.—The absence of Cetacea from rocks older than the Eocene
has been frequently adduced as lending countenance to the theory of
the very late appearance of the highest class of Vertebrata on the
earth. Professor Sedgwick possesses in the Cambridge Museum a mass
of anchylosed cervical vertebræ of a whale, which he found in drift
clay near Ely, and which he has no doubt was washed out of the Kimmeridge
clay, an upper member of the Oolite. According to Professor
Owen, it exhibits well-marked specific characters, distinguishing it from
all other known recent or fossil cetacea. Dr. Leidy, of Philadelphia,
has lately described (1851) two species of cetacea of a new genus,
which he has called Priscodelphinus from the green sand of New Jersey,
which corresponds in age with the English Chalk or the cretaceous
strata above the gault. The specimens consist of dorsal and cervical
vertebræ.227 Even in the Eocene strata of Europe, the discovery of
cetaceans has never kept pace with that of land quadrupeds. The only
instance cited in Great Britain is a species of Monodon, from the London
clay, of doubtful authenticity as to its geological position. On the
other hand, the gigantic Zeuglodon of North America occurs abundantly
in the Middle Eocene strata of Georgia and Alabama, from which as
yet no bones of land quadrupeds have been obtained.
In the present imperfect state then of our information, we can scarcely
say more than that the cetacea seem to have been scarce in the secondary
and primary periods. It is quite conceivable that when aquatic saurians,
some of them carnivorous, like the Ichthyosaurus, were swarming in the
sea, and when there were large herbivorous reptiles, like the Iguanodon,
on the land, the class of reptiles may, to a certain extent, have superseded
the cetacea, and discharged their functions in the animal economy.
That mammalia had been created long before the epoch of the Kimmeridge
clay, is shown by the Microlestes of the Trias before alluded
to, and by the Stonesfield quadrupeds from the Inferior Oolite. And
we are bound to remember, whenever we infer the poverty of the flora
or fauna of any given period of the past, from the small number of fossils
occurring in ancient rocks, that it has been evidently no part of the
plan of Nature to hand down to us a complete or systematic record of
the former history of the animate world. We may have failed to discover
a single shell, marine or freshwater, or a single coral or bone in
certain sandstones, such as that of the valley of the Connecticut, where
the footprints of bipeds and quadrupeds abound; but such failure may
146
have arisen, not because the population of the land or sea was scanty at
that era, but because in general the preservation of any relics of the
animals or plants of former times is the exception to a general rule.
Time so enormous as that contemplated by the geologist may multiply
exceptional cases till they seem to constitute the rule, and so impose on
the imagination as to lead us to infer the non-existence of creatures of
which no monuments happen to remain. Professor Forbes has remarked,
that few geologists are aware how large a proportion of all
known species of fossils are founded on single specimens, while a still
greater number are founded on a few individuals discovered in one spot.
This holds true not only in regard to animals and plants inhabiting the
land, the lake, and the river, but even to a surprising number of the
marine mollusca, articulata, and radiata. Our knowledge, therefore, of
the living creation of any given period of the past may be said to depend
in a great degree on what we commonly call chance, and the casual
discovery of some new localities rich in peculiar fossils may modify
or entirely overthrow all our previous generalizations.
Upon the whole then we derive this result from a general review of
the fossils of the successive tertiary strata, namely, that since the Eocene
period, there have been several great changes in the land quadrupeds
inhabiting Europe, probably not less than five complete revolutions,
during which there has been no step whatever made in advance, no elevation
in the scale of being; so that had man been created at the commencement
of the Eocene era, he would not have constituted a greater
innovation on the state of the animal creation previously established than
now, when we believe him to have begun to exist at the close of the
Pleiocene. The views, therefore, which I proposed in the first edition
of this work, January, 1830, in opposition to the theory of progressive
development, do not seem to me to require material modification, notwithstanding
the large additions since made to our knowledge of fossil
remains.
These views may be thus briefly stated. From the earliest period at
which plants and animals can be proved to have existed, there has been
a continual change going on in the position of land and sea, accompanied
by great fluctuations of climate. To these ever-varying geographical
and climatal conditions the state of the animate world has been unceasingly
adapted. No satisfactory proof has yet been discovered of
the gradual passage of the earth from a chaotic to a more habitable
state, nor of any law of progressive development governing the extinction
and renovation of species, and causing the fauna and flora to pass
from an embryonic to a more perfect condition, from a simple to a more
complex organization.
The principle of adaptation to which I have alluded, appears to have
been analogous to that which now peoples the arctic, temperate, and
tropical regions contemporaneously with distinct assemblages of species
and genera, or which, independently of mere temperature, gives rise to
a predominance of the marsupial or didelphous tribe of quadrupeds in
147
Australia, of the placental or monodelphous tribe in Asia and Europe,
or which causes a profusion of reptiles without mammalia in the Galapagos
Archipelago, and of mammalia without reptiles in Greenland.
Recent origin of man.—If, then, the popular theory of the successive
development of the animal and vegetable world, from the simplest to
the most perfect forms, rests on a very insecure foundation; it may
be asked, whether the recent origin of man lends any support to the
same doctrine, or how far the influence of man may be considered as
such a deviation from the analogy of the order of things previously established,
as to weaken our confidence in the uniformity of the course
of nature.
Antecedently to investigation, we might reasonably have anticipated
that the vestiges of man would have been traced back at least as far as
those modern strata in which all the testacea and a certain number of
the mammalia are of existing species, for of all the mammalia the human
species is the most cosmopolite, and perhaps more capable than
any other of surviving considerable vicissitudes in climate, and in the
physical geography of the globe.
No inhabitant of the land exposes himself to so many dangers on the
waters as man, whether in a savage or a civilized state;228 and there is
no animal, therefore, whose skeleton is so liable to become imbedded in
lacustrine or submarine deposits; nor can it be said that his remains
are more perishable than those of other animals; for in ancient fields
of battle, as Cuvier has observed, the bones of men have suffered
as little decomposition as those of horses which were buried in the
same grave.229 But even if the more solid parts of our species had disappeared,
the impression of their form would have remained engraven
on the rocks, as have the traces of the tenderest leaves of plants, and
the soft integuments of many animals. Works of art, moreover, composed
of the most indestructible materials, would have outlasted almost
all the organic contents of sedimentary rocks. Edifices, and even
entire cities, have, within the times of history, been buried under volcanic
ejections, submerged beneath the sea, or engulfed by earthquakes;
and had these catastrophes been repeated throughout an indefinite
lapse of ages, the high antiquity of man would have been inscribed in
far more legible characters on the framework of the globe than are the
forms of the ancient vegetation which once covered the islands of the
northern ocean, or of those gigantic reptiles which at still later periods
peopled the seas and rivers of the northern hemisphere.230
Dr. Prichard has argued that the human race have not always existed
on the surface of the earth, because "the strata of which our continents
are composed were once a part of the ocean's bed"—"mankind
had a beginning, since we can look back to the period when the surface
on which they lived began to exist."231 This proof, however, is insufficient,
148
for many thousands of human beings now dwell in various quarters
of the globe where marine species lived within the times of history,
and, on the other hand, the sea now prevails permanently over large
districts once inhabited by thousands of human beings. Nor can this
interchange of sea and land ever cease while the present causes are in
existence. Terrestrial species, therefore, might be older than the continents
which they inhabit, and aquatic species of higher antiquity than
the lakes and seas which they now people.
But so far as our interpretation of physical movements has yet gone,
we have every reason to infer that the human race is extremely modern,
even when compared to the larger number of species now our contemporaries
on the earth, and we may, therefore, ask whether his creation
can be considered as one step in a supposed progressive system, by
which the organic world has advanced slowly from a more simple to a
more complex and perfect state? If we concede, for a moment, the
truth of the proposition, that the sponge, the cephalopod, the fish, the
reptile, the bird, and the mammifer, have followed each other in regular
chronological order, the creation of each class being separated from
the other by vast intervals of time, should we be able to recognize, in
man's entrance upon the earth, the last term of one and the same series
of progressive developments?
In reply to this question it should first be observed, that the superiority
of man depends not on those faculties and attributes which he
shares in common with the inferior animals, but on his reason, by which
he is distinguished from them. When it is said that the human race
is of far higher dignity than were any pre-existing beings on the earth,
it is the intellectual and moral attributes of our race, rather than the
physical, which are considered; and it is by no means clear that the
organization of man is such as would confer a decided pre-eminence
upon him, if, in place of his reasoning powers, he was merely provided
with such instincts as are possessed by the lower animals.
If this be admitted, it would not follow, even if there were sufficient
geological evidence in favor of the theory of progressive development,
that the creation of man was the last link in the same chain. For the
sudden passage from an irrational to a rational animal, is a phenomenon
of a distinct kind from the passage from the more simple to the
more perfect forms of animal organization and instinct. To pretend
that such a step, or rather leap, can be part of a regular series of
changes in the animal world, is to strain analogy beyond all reasonable
bounds.
Introduction of man, to what extent a change in the system.—But
setting aside the question of progressive development, another and a
far more difficult one may arise out of the admission that man is comparatively
of modern origin. Is not the interference of the human species,
it may be asked, such a deviation from the antecedent course of
physical events, that the knowledge of such a fact tends to destroy all
our confidence in the uniformity of the order of nature, both in regard
149
to time past and future? If such an innovation could take place after
the earth had been exclusively inhabited for thousands of ages by inferior
animals, why should not other changes as extraordinary and unprecedented
happen from time to time? If one new cause was permitted
to supervene, differing in kind and energy from any before in operation,
why may not others have come into action at different epochs? Or
what security have we that they may not arise hereafter? And if such
be the case, how can the experience of one period, even though we are
acquainted with all the possible effects of the then existing causes, be a
standard to which we can refer all natural phenomena of other periods?
Now these objections would be unanswerable, if adduced against one
who was contending for the absolute uniformity throughout all time of
the succession of sublunary events—if, for example, he was disposed to
indulge in the philosophical reveries of some Egyptian and Greek sects,
who represented all the changes both of the moral and material world
as repeated at distant intervals, so as to follow each other in their former
connection of place and time. For they compared the course of
events on our globe to astronomical cycles; and not only did they consider
all sublunary affairs to be under the influence of the celestial bodies,
but they taught that on the earth, as well as in the heavens, the
same identical phenomena recurred again and again in a perpetual vicissitude.
The same individual men were doomed to be re-born, and to
perform the same actions as before; the same arts were to be invented,
and the same cities built and destroyed. The Argonautic expedition
was destined to sail again with the same heroes, and Achilles with his
Myrmidons to renew, the combat before the walls of Troy.

Alter erit tum Tiphys, et altera quæ vehat Argo
Dilectos heroas; erunt etiam altera bella,
Atque iterum ad Trojam magnus mittetur Achilles.232

The geologist, however, may condemn these tenets as absurd, without
running into the opposite extreme, and denying that the order of
nature has, from the earliest periods, been uniform in the same sense in
which we believe it to be uniform at present, and expect it to remain so
in future. We have no reason to suppose, that when man first became
master of a small part of the globe, a greater change took place in its
physical condition than is now experienced when districts, never before
inhabited, become successively occupied by new settlers. When a
powerful European colony lands on the shores of Australia, and introduces
at once those arts which it has required many centuries to mature;
when it imports a multitude of plants and large animals from the
opposite extremity of the earth, and begins rapidly to extirpate many of
the indigenous species, a mightier revolution is effected in a brief period
than the first entrance of a savage horde, or their continued occupation
150
of the country for many centuries, can possibly be imagined to have
produced. If there be no impropriety in assuming that the system is
uniform when disturbances so unprecedented occur in certain localities,
we can with much greater confidence apply the same language to those
primeval ages when the aggregate number and power of the human
race, or the rate of their advancement in civilization, must be supposed
to have been far inferior. In reasoning on the state of the globe immediately
before our species was called into existence, we must be guided
by the same rules of induction as when we speculate on the state of
America in the interval that elapsed between the introduction of man
into Asia, the supposed cradle of our race, and the arrival of the first
adventurers on the shores of the New World. In that interval, we imagine
the state of things to have gone on according to the order now
observed in regions unoccupied by man. Even now, the waters of
lakes, seas, and the great ocean, which teem with life, may be said to
have no immediate relation to the human race—to be portions of the
terrestrial system of which man has never taken, nor ever can take possession;
so that the greater part of the inhabited surface of the planet
may still remain as insensible to our presence as before any isle or continent
was appointed to be our residence.
If the barren soil around Sydney had at once become fertile upon the
landing of our first settlers; if, like the happy isles whereof the poets
have given such glowing descriptions, those sandy tracts had begun to
yield spontaneously an annual supply of grain, we might then, indeed,
have fancied alterations still more remarkable in the economy of nature
to have attended the first coming of our species into the planet. Or if,
when a volcanic island like Ischia was, for the first time, brought under
cultivation by the enterprise and industry of a Greek colony, the internal
fire had become dormant, and the earthquake had remitted its destructive
violence, there would then have been some ground for speculating
on the debilitation of the subterranean forces, when the earth was
first placed under the dominion of man. But after a long interval of
rest, the volcano bursts forth again with renewed energy, annihilates
one half of the inhabitants, and compels the remainder to emigrate.
The course of nature remains evidently unchanged; and, in like manner,
we may suppose the general condition of the globe, immediately before
and after the period when our species first began to exist, to have been
the same, with the exception only of man's presence.
The modifications in the system of which man is the instrument do
not, perhaps, constitute so great a deviation from previous analogy as
we usually imagine; we often, for example, form an exaggerated estimate
of the extent of our power in extirpating some of the inferior animals,
and causing others to multiply; a power which is circumscribed
within certain limits, and which, in all likelihood, is by no means exclusively
exerted by our species.233 The growth of human population cannot
151
take place without diminishing the numbers, or causing the entire
destruction, of many animals. The larger beasts of prey, in particular,
give way before us; but other quadrupeds of smaller size, and innumerable
birds, insects, and plants, which are inimical to our interests, increase
in spite of us, some attacking our food, others our raiment and
persons, and others interfering with our agricultural and horticultural
labors. We behold the rich harvest which we have raised by the sweat
of our brow, devoured by myriads of insects, and are often as incapable
of arresting their depredations, as of staying the shock of an earthquake,
or the course of a stream of lava.
A great philosopher has observed, that we can command nature only
by obeying her laws; and this principle is true even in regard to the
astonishing changes which are superinduced in the qualities of certain
animals and plants by domestication and garden culture. I shall point
out in the third book that we can only effect such surprising alterations
by assisting the development of certain instincts, or by availing ourselves
of that mysterious law of their organization, by which individual peculiarities
are transmissible from one generation to another.234
It is probable from these and many other considerations, that as we
enlarge our knowledge of the system, we shall become more and more
convinced, that the alterations caused by the interference of man deviate
far less from the analogy of those effected by other animals than is
usually supposed.235 We are often misled, when we institute such comparisons,
by our knowledge of the wide distinction between the instincts
of animals and the reasoning power of man; and we are apt hastily to
infer, that the effects of a rational and irrational species, considered
merely as physical agents, will differ almost as much as the faculties by
which their actions are directed.
It is not, however, intended that a real departure from the antecedent
course of physical events cannot be traced in the introduction of man.
If that latitude of action which enables the brutes to accommodate
themselves in some measure to accidental circumstances could be imagined
to have been at any former period so great, that the operations
of instinct were as much diversified as are those of human reason, it
might, perhaps, be contended, that the agency of man did not constitute
an anomalous deviation from the previously established order of
things. It might then have been said, that the earth's becoming at a
particular period the residence of human beings, was an era in the
moral, not in the physical world—that our study and contemplation
of the earth, and the laws which govern its animate productions, ought
no more to be considered in the light of a disturbance or deviation from
the system, than the discovery of the satellites of Jupiter should be
regarded as a physical event affecting those heavenly bodies. Their
influence in advancing the progress of science among men, and in aiding
navigation and commerce, was accompanied by no reciprocal action
152
of the human mind upon the economy of nature in those distant planets;
and so the earth might be conceived to have become, at a certain period,
a place of moral discipline and intellectual improvement to man,
without the slightest derangement of a previously existing order of
change in its animate and inanimate productions.
The distinctness, however, of the human from all other species, considered
merely as an efficient cause in the physical world, is real; for
we stand in a relation to contemporary species of animals and plants
widely different from that which other irrational animals can ever be
supposed to have held to each other. We modify their instincts, relative
numbers, and geographical distribution, in a manner superior in
degree, and in some respects very different in kind from that in which
any other species can affect the rest. Besides, the progressive movement
of each successive generation of men causes the human species
to differ more from itself in power at two distant periods, than any
one species of the higher order of animals differs from another. The
establishment, therefore, by geological evidence, of the first intervention
of such a peculiar and unprecedented agency, long after other parts
of the animate and inanimate world existed, affords ground for concluding
that the experience during thousands of ages of all the events
which may happen on this globe, would not enable a philosopher to
speculate with confidence concerning future contingencies.
If, then, an intelligent being, after observing the order of events
for an indefinite series of ages, had witnessed at last so wonderful an
innovation as this, to what extent would his belief in the regularity of
the system be weakened?—would he cease to assume that there was
permanency in the laws of nature?—would he no longer be guided
in his speculations by the strictest rules of induction? To these questions
it may be answered, that, had he previously presumed to dogmatize
respecting the absolute uniformity of the order of nature, he
would undoubtedly be checked by witnessing this new and unexpected
event, and would form a more just estimate of the limited range of his
own knowledge, and the unbounded extent of the scheme of the universe.
But he would soon perceive that no one of the fixed and constant
laws of the animate or inanimate world was subverted by human
agency, and that the modifications now introduced for the first time
were the accompaniments of new and extraordinary circumstances,
and those not of a physical but a moral nature. The deviation permitted
would also appear to be as slight as was consistent with the
accomplishment of the new moral ends proposed, and to be in a great
degree temporary in its nature, so that, whenever the power of the
new agent was withheld, even for a brief period, a relapse would take
place to the ancient state of things; the domesticated animal, for example,
recovering in a few generations its wild instinct, and the
garden-flower and fruit-tree reverting to the likeness of the parent stock.
Now, if it would be reasonable to draw such inferences with respect
to the future, we cannot but apply the same rules of induction to the
153
past. We have no right to anticipate any modifications in the results
of existing causes in time to come, which are not conformable to analogy,
unless they be produced by the progressive development of human
power, or perhaps by some other new relations which may hereafter
spring up between the moral and material worlds. In the same manner,
when we speculate on the vicissitudes of the animate and inanimate
creation in former ages, we ought not to look for any anomalous results,
unless where man has interfered, or unless clear indications appear of
some other moral source of temporary derangement.
</div></body></text></TEI>