<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="40">

CHAPTER IV.
Of the Measure of Secondary Qualities.


Sect. I.—Scales of Qualities in general.
THE ultimate object of our investigation in each of the
Secondary Mechanical Sciences, is the nature of the
processes by which the special impressions of sound, light,
and heat, are conveyed, and the modifications of which these
processes are susceptible. And of this investigation, as we
have seen, the necessary basis is the principle, that these
impressions are transmitted by means of a medium. But before
we arrive at this ultimate object, we may find it necessary
to occupy ourselves with several intermediate objects:
before we discover the cause, it may be necessary
to determine the laws of the phenomena. Even if we
cannot immediately ascertain the mechanism of light or heat,
it may still be interesting and important to arrange and
measure the effects which we observe.
The idea of a Medium affects our proceeding in this research
also. We cannot measure Secondary qualities in the same
manner in which we measure Primary qualities, by a mere
addition of parts. There is this leading and remarkable
difference, that while both classes of qualities are
susceptible of changes of magnitude, primary qualities
increase by addition of extension, secondary, by
augmentation of intensity. A space is doubled when
another equal space is placed by its side; one weight joined
to another makes up the sum of the two. But when one degree
of warmth is combined with another, or one shade of red
colour with another, we cannot in like manner talk of the
sum. The component parts do not evidently retain
their 334 separate existence; we cannot separate a strong
green colour into two weaker ones, as we can separate a
large force into two smaller. The increase is absorbed into
the previous amount, and is no longer in evidence as a part
of the whole. And this is the difference which has given
birth to the two words extended, and intense.
That is extended which has ‘partes extra partes,’
parts outside of parts: that is intense which becomes
stronger by some indirect and unapparent increase of agency,
like the stretching of the internal springs of a machine, as
the term intense implies. Extended magnitudes can at
will be resolved into the parts of which they were
originally composed, or any other which the nature of their
extension admits; their proportion is apparent; they are
directly and at once subject to the relations of number.
Intensive magnitudes cannot be resolved into smaller
magnitudes; we can see that they differ, but we cannot tell
in what proportion; we have no direct measure of their
quantity. How many times hotter than blood is boiling water?
The answer cannot be given by the aid of our feelings of
heat alone.
The difference, as we have said, is connected with the
fundamental principle that we do not perceive Secondary
qualities directly, but through a Medium. We have no natural
apprehension of light, or sound, or heat, as they exist in
the bodies from which they proceed, but only as they affect
our organs. We can only measure them, therefore, by some
Scale supplied by their effects. And thus while
extended magnitudes, as space, time, are measurable directly
and of themselves; intensive magnitudes, as brightness,
loudness, heat, are measurable only by artificial means and
conventional scales. Space, time, measure themselves: the
repetition of a smaller space, or time, while it composes a
larger one, measures it. But for light and heat we must have
Photometers and Thermometers, which measure something which
is assumed to be an indication of the quality in question.
In the one case, the mode of applying the measure, and the
meaning of the number resulting, are seen by intuition; in
the 335 other, they are consequences of assumption and
reasoning. In the one case, they are Units, of
which the extension is made up; in the other, they are
Degrees by which the intensity ascends.
2. When we discover any property in a sensible quality,
which at once refers us to number or space, we readily take
this property as a measure; and thus we make a transition
from quality to quantity. Thus Ptolemy in the third chapter
of the First Book of his Harmonics begins thus: ‘As
to the differences which exist in sounds both in
quality and in quantity, if we consider
that difference which refers to the acuteness and graveness,
we cannot at once tell to which of the above two classes it
belongs, till we have considered the causes of such
symptoms.’ But at the end of the chapter, having satisfied
himself that grave sounds result from the magnitude of the
string or pipe, other things being equal, he infers, ‘Thus
the difference of acute and grave appears to be a difference
of quantity.’
In the same manner, in order to form Secondary Mechanical
Sciences respecting any of the other properties of bodies,
we must reduce these properties to a dependence upon
quantity, and thus make them subject to measurement. We
cannot obtain any sciential truths respecting the comparison
of sensible qualities, till we have discovered measures and
scales of the qualities which we have to consider; and
accordingly, some of the most important steps in such
sciences have been the establishment of such measures and
scales, and the invention of the requisite instruments.
The formation of the mathematical sciences which rest upon
the measures of the intensity of sensible qualities took
place mainly in the course of the last century. Perhaps we
may consider Lambert, a mathematician who resided in
Switzerland, and published about 1750, as the person who
first clearly felt the importance of establishing such
sciences. His Photometry, Pyrometry, and Hygrometry, are
examples of the systematic reduction of sensible qualities
(light, heat, moisture) to modes of numerical measurement. 336
We now proceed to speak of such modes of measurement with
regard to the most obvious properties of bodies.
Sect. II.—The Musical Scale.
3. The establishment of the Harmonic Canon, that is,
of a Scale and Measure of the musical place of notes, in the
relation of high and low, was the first
step in the science of Harmonics. The perception of the
differences and relations of musical sounds is the office of
the sense of hearing; but these relations are fixed, and
rendered accurately recognizable by artificial means.
‘Indeed, in all the senses,’ as Ptolemy truly says in the
opening of his Harmonics, ‘the sense discovers what is
approximately true, and receives accuracy from another
quarter: the reason receives the approximately-true from
another quarter, and discovers the accurate truth.’ We can
have no measures of sensible qualities which do not
ultimately refer to the sense;—whether they do this
immediately, as when we refer Colours to an assumed
Standard; or mediately, as when we measure Heat by
Expansion, having previously found by an appeal to sense
that the expansion increases with the heat. Such relations
of sensible qualities cannot be described in words, and can
only be apprehended by their appropriate faculty. The
faculty by which the relations of sounds are apprehended is
a musical ear in the largest acceptation of the term.
In this signification the faculty is nearly universal among
men; for all persons have musical ears sufficiently delicate
to understand and to imitate the modulations corresponding
to various emotions in speaking; which modulations depend
upon the succession of acuter and graver tones. These are
the relations now spoken of, and these are plainly perceived
by persons who have very imperfect musical ears, according
to the common use of the phrase. But the relations of tones
which occur in speaking are somewhat indefinite; and in
forming that musical scale which is the basis of our science
upon the subject, we 337 take the most definite and marked
of such relations of notes; such as occur, not in speaking
but in singing. Those musical relations of two sounds which
we call the octave, the fifth, the
fourth, the third, are recognized after a
short familiarity with them. These chords or
intervals are perceived to have each a peculiar
character, which separates them from the relations of two
sounds taken at random, and makes it easy to know them when
sung or played on an instrument; and for most persons, not
difficult to sing the sounds in succession exactly, or
nearly correct. These musical relations, or concords,
then, are the groundwork of our musical series of sounds.
But how are we to name these indescribable sensible
characters? how to refer, with unerring accuracy, to a type
which exists only in our own perceptions? We must have for
this purpose a Scale and a Standard.
The Musical Scale is a series of eight notes, ascending by
certain steps from the first or key-note to the octave above
it, each of the notes being fixed by such distinguishable
musical relations as we have spoken of above. We may call
these notes c, d, e, f, g, a, b, c; and we may then
say that g is determined by its being a fifth above c; d by
its being a fourth below g; e by its being a third above c;
and similarly of the rest. It will be recollected that the
terms a fifth, a fourth, a third, have
hitherto been introduced as expressing certain simple and
indescribable musical relations among sounds, which might
have been indicated by any other names. Thus we might call
the fifth the dominant, and the fourth the
subdominant, as is done in one part of musical
science. But the names we have used, which are the common
ones, are in fact derived from the number of notes which
these intervals include in the scale obtained in the above
manner. The notes, c, d, e, f, g, being five, the interval
from c to g is a fifth, and so of the rest. The fixation of
this scale gave the means of describing exactly any note
which occurs in the scale, and the method is easily
applicable to notes above and below this range; for in a
series of sounds higher or lower by an octave than 338
this standard series, the ear discovers a recurrence of the
same relations so exact, that a person may sometimes imagine
he is producing the same notes as another when he is singing
the same air an octave higher. Hence the next eight notes
may be conveniently denoted by a repetition of the same
letters, as the first; thus, c, d, e, f, g, a, b, c,
d, e, f, g, a, b;
and it is easy to devise a continuation of such cycles. And
other admissible notes are designated by a further
modification of the standard ones, as by making each note
flat or sharp; which modification it is not
necessary here to consider, since our object is only to show
how a standard is attainable, and how it serves the ends of
science.
We may observe, however, that the above is not an exact
account of the first, or early Greek scale; for that scale
was founded on a primary division of the interval of two
octaves (the extreme range which it admitted) into five
tetrachords, each tetrachord including the interval
of a fourth. All the notes of this series had different
names borrowed from this division26; thus mese
was the middle or key-note; the note below it was
lichanos mesôn, the next below was parypate
mesôn, the next lower, hypate mesôn. The fifth
above mese was nete diazeugmenôn, the octave
was nete hyperbolæôn.</div></body></text></TEI>