<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</title><author>Whewell, William (1794-1866)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John W. Parker</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1840</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="2">

CHAPTER II.
Of Technical Terms.



1. IT
has already been stated that we gather knowledge from
the external world, when we are able to apply, to the facts
which we observe, some ideal conception, which gives unity
and connexion to multiplied and separate perceptions. We
have also shown that our conceptions, thus verified by
facts, may themselves be united and connected by a new bond
of the same nature; and that man may thus have to pursue his
way from truth to truth through a long progression of
discoveries, each resting on the preceding, and rising above
it.
Each of these steps, in succession, is recorded, fixed, and
made available, by some peculiar form of words; and such
words, thus rendered precise in their meaning, and
appropriated to the service of science, we may call
Technical Terms. It is in a great measure by
inventing such Terms that men not only best express the
discoveries they have made, but also enable their followers
to become so familiar with these discoveries, and to possess
them so thoroughly, that they can readily use them in
advancing to ulterior generalizations.
Most of our ideal conceptions are described by exact and
constant words or phrases, such as those of which we here
speak. We have already had occasion to employ many of these.
Thus we have had instances of technical Terms expressing
geometrical conceptions, as Ellipsis, Radius
Vector, Axis, Plane, the Proportion of the
Inverse Square, and the like. Other Terms have
described mechanical conceptions, as Accelerating
Force and Attraction. Again, chemistry exhibits
(as do all sciences) a series of Terms which mark the steps
of our 55 progress. The views of the first real founders
of the science are recorded by the Terms which are still in
use, Neutral Salts, Affinity, and the like.
The establishment of Dalton’s theory has produced the use of
the word Atom in a peculiar sense, or of some other
word, as Proportion, in a sense equally technical.
And Mr. Faraday has found it necessary, in order to expound
his electro-chemical theory, to introduce such terms as
Anode and Cathode, Anïon and
Cathïon.
2. I need not adduce any further examples, for my object at
present is only to point out the use and influence of such
language: its rules and principles I shall hereafter try, in
some measure, to fix. But what we have here to remark is,
the extraordinary degree in which the progress of science is
facilitated, by thus investing each new discovery with a
compendious and steady form of expression. These terms soon
become part of the current language of all who take an
interest in speculation. However strange they may sound at
first, they soon grow familiar in our ears, and are used
without any effort, or any recollection of the difficulty
they once involved. They become as common as the phrases
which express our most frequent feelings and interests,
while yet they have incomparably more precision than belongs
to any terms which express feelings; and they carry with
them, in their import, the results of deep and laborious
trains of research. They convey the mental treasures of one
period to the generations that follow; and laden with this,
their precious freight, they sail safely across gulfs of
time in which empires have suffered shipwreck, and the
languages of common life have sunk into oblivion. We have
still in constant circulation among us the Terms which
belong to the geometry, the astronomy, the zoology, the
medicine of the Greeks, and the algebra and chemistry of the
Arabians. And we can in an instant, by means of a few words,
call to our own recollection, or convey to the apprehension
of another person, phenomena and relations of phenomena in
optics, mineralogy, chemistry, which are so complex and
abstruse, that it might seem to require the utmost subtlety
of the human mind to 56 grasp them, even if that were made
the sole object of its efforts. By this remarkable effect of
Technical Language, we have the results of all the labours
of past times not only always accessible, but so prepared
that we may (provided we are careful in the use of our
instrument) employ what is really useful and efficacious for
the purpose of further success, without being in any way
impeded or perplexed by the length and weight of the chain
of past connexions which we drag along with us.
By such means,—by the use of the Inductive Process, and by
the aid of Technical Terms,—man has been constantly
advancing in the path of scientific truth. In a succeeding
part of this work we shall endeavour to trace the general
rules of this advance, and to lay down the maxims by which
it may be most successfully guided and forwarded. But in
order that we may do this to the best advantage, we must
pursue still further the analysis of knowledge into its
elements; and this will be our employment in the first part
of the work.</div></body></text></TEI>