<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ninth Bridgewater Treatise</title><author>Babbage, Charles (1791-1871)</author></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>John Murray</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><date>1837</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Produced from a Project Gutenberg HTML source using gutenberg-text-splitter.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="chapter" n="23">REFLECTIONS ON THE INQUIRY IN THE PRECEDING CHAPTER.
 THOSE who have too hastily lent the credit of their authority to support the
 prejudice, that the pursuit of mathematical investigations renders the mind
 unapt for the perception of the truths of religion, must now be compelled to
 admit that they have endeavoured to discredit a science, which alone can furnish
 an exact refutation of one of the most celebrated arguments against revelation.
 Those on the other hand, who, without the knowledge which qualifies men to
 form opinions on such subjects, have obtruded their dogmatism on
[page] 133
 the world, though they may fail to learn the lessons of caution and modesty,
 may yet be disposed to abstain from scattering their misdirected darts, lest
 they should injure one of the best allies of the faith which they profess. Whilst
 those, who in humble diffidence of their own powers, rely on the opinions of
 others, and are believers from feeling rather than from reason, may learn from
 experience what they might fail to ascertain by inquiry, "that no truth in any department of knowledge " can ever be in contradiction to any other
 " truth;"—and they may after many such instances perceive, that it is no
 narrow evidence which has convinced the most enlightened men, that unlimited
 discussion is the fatal enemy of error—the most certain supporter of truth,
 In the course of this inquiry, the gradually decreasing value of human testimony,
 when transmitted from witness to witness, has been alluded to, and its bearing
 on the future
[page] 134
 reception of revelation must have
 been foreseen by some, and may, when pointed out, be feared by others, of my
 readers. It may be apprehended, that after thousands of years, the long transmitted
 testimony of revealed truth, may not have sufficient force to convince the inquirers
 of that distant time. That such a cause is in constant action must be fully
 admitted, for every statement from man to his fellow man is liable to error
 from two sources. The witness may be deceived, or he may himself be a deceiver; and however extensive his knowledge, or however high his general character
 for veracity, whilst the possibility of a failure in either direction remains,
 repeated transmission through a series of such witnesses, will ultimately reduce
 to insignificance any statement in itself highly improbable. To suppose human
 beings incapabable of being deceived and incapable of deception, is to assign
 to them attributes which we know they do not possess, and which we can scarcely
 assign to responsible and created beings.
[page] 135
 Let us examine then what reply
 reason and science can make to such forebodings. If a transmitted revelation
 contain within its pages a prophecy of events, dark and unintelligible in itself,
 and therefore unfit to cause its own fulfilment; and if from time to time facts
 occur, explaining instantly by no circuitous or lengthened process, but clearly
 and explicitly, the mystic words; if the explanation of that, which till then
 was dark and mysterious even to the learned and reflecting, flashes with spontaneous
 conviction on the minds of multitudes, who now discover for the first time the
 events to have been clearly predicted;—then a revelation, however faint from
 the lapse of time, revives with renewed energy, and claims its reception with
 a force almost equal to that which it demanded from those to whom it was originally
 delivered. If, on the other hand, an inspired writer had given an account of
 a former state of our planet, different wholly from its present con-
[page] 136
 dition, yet so distinct and minute, that if there were placed before us a
 map of the islands, continents, and rivers, with the plants and the animals
 of that ancient world, we should instantly recognise the coincidence with the
 prophet's description, and if it were impossible, from the state of knowledge
 when the revelation was delivered, that the writer could have been acquainted
 even with the relics of that former world he so well described, then it must
 be admitted, that we should have strong and irresistible evidence of his veracity.
 Let us suppose an inspired writer to describe a former constitution of our globe,
 in which a vast continent occupied the position now filled by the Pacific Ocean; that a great river with three outlets poured its waters towards the south; that these streams and their banks were peopled with animals differing as
 much from all then known races, as the plesiosaurus and the pterodactyl do from
 those which now inhabit our globe, and that he had described, it with anatomical
 precision but in popular
[page] 137
 language, the number of bones in
 the several parts of their frames, their habits, and food, as well as the plants
 which flourished on the banks of those rivers. Thousands, or perhaps hundreds
 of thousands of years hence, we may conceive an island rising from the same
 ocean, and the geologists of that distant era tracing in its then elevated strata,
 by their fossil shells of mingled fresh water and marine origin, the estuaries
 of the streams from which the strata were deposited; discovering by the depth,
 of their branches and their magnitude, that the river must have been formed
 from the drainage of some great continent; and finally, that aided by the comparative
 anatomists and botanists of that day, they should reconstruct from the fossil
 bones embedded in the strata, the very animals and plants described by the prophet,
 and ascertain even their habits and their food. If similar discoveries and reconstructions
 of animals previously unknown, have been made in our own
[page] 138
 times, almost in the infancy of
 these sciences, what advances may we not expect with the progress of time?
 What has been stated by way of illustration as resulting from some branches
 of natural science, is equally applicable under different circumstances to many
 others. Nor does this view present any thing irreconcilable with the wisdom
 and benevolence of the Creator. In the early stages of the world, before man
 had acquired knowledge to read the book of nature ever open to his view, direct
 revelation might be as necessary for his belief in a Deity, as for his moral
 government; and this might from time to time be repeated. When civilization
 and science had fixed their abode amongst mankind, and when observations and
 reason had enabled man to penetrate some little way into the mysteries of nature,
 his conviction of the existence of a first great cause would gradually acquire
 additional strength from the use of his own faculties,
[page] 139
 and when accumulating proofs had
 firmly established this great step, the recurrence of revelation might be less
 necessary for his welfare. The ancient revelation would however necessarily lose a portion of its weight from its continued transmission, and thus by
 slow but inevitable steps, tend in the lapse of ages to extinction. It is possible, 
 however, that that very revelation may contain within its pages the verification
 of its own truth, and that the advancement of man in the knowledge of the structure
 of the works of his Creator, might furnish continually increasing proofs of
 its authenticity; and that thus by the due employment of our faculties, we might
 not merely redeem revelation from the ravages of time, but give to it a degree
 of force strengthening with every accession to our knowledge, and ultimately
 forcing our understandings to assent to it even with a conviction great as that
 which had compelled
[page] 140
 the belief of those to whom it was originally delivered. It is not for the
 finite faculties of man to pronounce what has been the course chosen
 for his happiness by an all-wise Creator, but it may be permitted to him to
 meet the difficulty which necessarily arises from the fallible and fading
 nature of human testimony by pointing out one possible course in which,
 by the exertion of the highest faculties with which we have been blessed, we
 may make a nearer approach to the knowledge of the will of our Creator.
[page] 141</div></body></text></TEI>